hello everyone welcome to the
2024 dressle house
lecture it is an H
on behalf of MIT Nano for me to have a
chance to stand in front of you and on
behalf of MIT I welcome today's dress
house lecturer who I'll introduce in
just a moment my name is Vladimir
bulovic I'm the director of MIT Nano and
I have had the privilege of knowing
Millie dressle housee for many years uh
and had the privilege of being inspired
by her example many more years that
followed from the moment I met her I'm
absolutely
in all that I have a chance now to
introduce her namesake lecture in order
to carry the mission and the vision of
what Millie has indeed given to many of
us commitment to both fantastic science
and commitment to humans around us
building upon the opportunity of
building that science and human
community that will Define tomorrow
thank you for being here and allow me to
introduce the dressle house lecturer in
this 2024 edition of the lecture um we
are very lucky to be hosting today
Professor Claire gray or as I was told
by a colleague the appropriate title
would be Dame Professor Claire gray
ordinary Dame commander of the Civil
Division of the most excellent order of
the British
Empire it is truly an honor to have you
here
in many
reasons but most importantly we are
looking for inspiration that indeed we
know you
carry Professor gray is a Royal Society
research professor and uh Jeffrey
morouse Gibson professor of chemistry at
Cambridge University in
UK after receiving a ba and uh and
doctorate from Oxford University she was
a post-doctoral researcher um after
which she joined a faculty at Stony
Brook University in 1994 becoming a full
professor in 2001 and then moving to
Cambridge University in
2009 she was a director of Northeastern
chemical energy storage center a US
Department of energy energy Frontiers
Research Center and then associate
director she's currently director of the
epsrc Center for Advanced Materials for
integrated Energy Systems she's
co-founder of naalt a battery fast
charging company her current research
interests include the use of solid state
NMR and defraction bit methods to
determine structure function
relationship in materials for energy
storage conversion and carbon capture
she received many many honors most
recently these include husman
uh the corber European science price and
the ACs Central science disruptors and
innovators price it is incredible honor
to have you here with us and I would ask
you to take the stage and tell us about
your own work please
[Applause]
so it's truly wonderful to be here to
celebrate the the life and the science
of Millie dressle house and
um I I knew Millie not very well but I
worked with her particularly
particularly through a workshop in
Russell Heimer for a number of years and
this is Millie with a very diverse group
of um scientists two women Millie and
red and me
this was Millie when she we were doing
Outreach activities to some of the
scientists who'd come from various Arab
Emirates countries and this is Millie
when we went up to the top of the
mountains to watch the sunset with Shake
sa and she's there very much engaged in
a conversation with him he then responds
equally vividly so she was a wonderful
person uh in terms of interactions and
I'm people in this audience obviously
know this more than me but there were
perhaps PhD students who haven't had so
much of an opportunity to interact with
her and of course it wasn't just about
that it was the wonderful Legacy of
Science and what I've tried to do today
is I'm going to talk about some
different things I don't always talk
about particularly inspired by some of
the work of Millies and just to sort of
look at the papers that have been
instrumental to some of the thinking of
what we've been doing recently it's this
wonderful review in 1980s where she
pulled together a whole mass of
different
structural electronic properties of
graphites starting with some of her own
work in the 196 1965 and this was one of
the second papers in 66 on spin orbit
interactions a very classic work on
intercalation compounds and of course
was a very she was a very strong
advocate for women in science and this
is an article she wrote you know as
early as
1975 and if you spent a bit of time
reading it um
she's there stressing this is in the
conclusions that diversity is important
because it brings um all of the larger
Community into doing science so so I'm
honored to be here to give a lecture on
her behalf or in honor of her rather so
um with that as a link I just wanted to
start by saying I'm going to talk about
batteries and of course the battery uh
this the lithium ion rechargeable
battery was put together in sonyy in
1990 was to power their camcorder so I'm
sure that many of the PhD students in
the audience have probably no idea what
this thing even is but it was you know
it was the com that was Sony that wanted
it not for their they weren't a battery
company they were desperate to have more
energy density and of course it was the
combination of people like John good
enough and others with the lithium
Cobalt oxide chemistry but then on the
carbon side it was um people working in
carbon of which Millie was very much one
of them I like to put this paper up uh
from John goodoff where he this the
first paper on lithium cobal oxide in
Matt reses bll just to remind also the
PhD students in the audience that you
can get a Nobel Prize with the Matt res
ball paper it doesn't have to be in
nature and science so reflect on that
when you're so I'm here and I don't
again have to tell this audience that
batteries have really transformed the
way we live you know the ability to be
able to to access information on the Fly
they really have underpinned the
portable Electronics Revolution but why
we're working them on them now is
associated with climate change so these
are pictures of the icebergs in Iceland
that are melting faster this is in
Cambridge and when I say Cambridge in
this conversation I mean the
Cambridge and this is flooding uh in
grest outside Cambridge from excess rain
the other day and so it's the sort of
possibility of using um batteries to try
and reduce carbon emissions and also
pollutions so if you just think about
Transportation uh batteries are good
enough we have cars that are around and
they're cars made by people I don't want
to be political here but who have become
very important in the last few months um
but they're still too expensive and I
think uh yes and I were talking about
some of these things earlier on and
we'll continue a conversation afterwards
about some of these things but the
question we have is how do we produce
batteries at the cost that are suitable
for Mass adoption globally so it's not
just if you live in Cambridge UK or
Cambridge us and you can afford to buy
your Tesla it's how do you do this to
Electrify the planet and the biggest
challenge is really how do you make
batteries to allow more Renewables on
the grid so you need batteries for
dealing with short-term fluctuations but
you also need the ones that are much
more a bigger challenge for the long
periods of time so at the moment the sun
is shining so you're okay in the UK
sorry in the US in the UK this time of
year we have no wind and we also have no
sun and that's one of the biggest
challenges and I think just to get the
context of scale the UK has two pumped
storage locations and one of them is a
mountain inside Wales where the whole of
the Mountain's been dug out and you pump
the water up and down and that has a
storage capacity of 9.1 gwatt hours this
is the Tesla Mega Battery now there are
bigger ones than that than that but you
can see that this the challenges of
scale and so how do we do this in a
sustainable way and then we think about
the chemistry that's um out there since
the 19 um the lithium cobal oxide
battery graphite battery I was been
telling you about the energy density has
gone up by about a factor of three or
four the price has gone down by more
than a factor of 10
um but if we're going to really make
step changes we need to come up new
chemistries and come up with new
materials that are both more sustainable
and more safe and think about other
issues like secondhand use which then
mean that we have to make batteries that
last longer and then we have to do them
in a safe way so this is a little
picture of a Samsung Galaxy Notebook
those of you who fly May recognize the
the back end of an airplane seat this
was one that caught fire on a plane and
this was an incident because Samsung
tried to put the same amount of battery
in just uh 10 5% less space and so as
the battery expanded and contracted
Parts moved and it ended up short
circuiting so to think about
sustainability if we just imagine and
look up the numbers for all of the
gigafactories that are being built uh in
globally they need more tons of cobalt
than are actually being mined from the
DRC in Congo with all of its
mining issues even lithium mining has
sustainability issues these are the
salar in this particular one is in Chile
and you can see the flamingos feeding on
the algae there but as the companies are
coming in they're pumping out the the
brins they're left to evaporate so the
water's draining there there's
evaporation issues elsewhere and it's
affecting the whole ecosystem so this is
a global challenge that we have to think
about to try and increase the the
diversity of different minerals that
we're
using so in order to improve batteries
and this is I'm just preaching to the
converted here we need to understand how
they work we need to understand how they
operate and we need to understand how
they degrade and the the challenge is
that some of these processes happen in
Picos seconds to milliseconds but yet
they're going to manifest themselves in
the days to hours to years that you
might use your battery for and so how do
you think about and how do you tease
apart the relevant processes and it's
not only the time scale issue it's also
the size scale issues you have to worry
about particles uh small and what the
atoms and electrons get up to but you
also need to worry about what the
particles do and what the the pack scale
do but we're here in a university and so
it's our challenge to really understand
some of the fundamental questions that
have
impacts now but also in the next 10 to
20 years as we try and address the 2050
uh Global challenges to reduce CO2 so um
for for my sins I lead the battery
degradation project in the UK where
we're interested in what's known as a
full cell so full cell all it means is
that you have a cathode and you have an
anode and they not just lithium metal
and you work out how the the various
components interact with each other and
so for example if you charge your
cathode material up to two high voltages
oxygen can come off that oxygen can go
on the other side and it can react with
the the graphite and cause additional
mechanisms so I'll tell you a little bit
about U some of that but I want to start
by telling you about in insitum
metrologies because this is what I've
been developing over the last rather
large amount of time but then after that
I want to tell you a story about
connecting local structure and Dynamics
through to mechanisms and if I have time
I'll talk about fast charging and where
we're going
next so I don't think I need to um
belabor the point but it's much easier
to study an operating device in situ or
operando so operando means you're
actually cycling in situ just means you
don't pull it apart and it's useful
because you don't have to make lots of
different batteries and you can just
study one thing at different states of
charge but the more interesting thing is
that if you take the batteries apart
sometimes there are processes that don't
survive
disassembling and it's not so easy when
you do anmr spectroscopy just to take a
battery
and put it inside a spectrometer because
batteries have metal cans and so you've
got to get the RF through that you need
to excite the NMR so youve got to
redesign your systems and pretty much
any operando measurement has some you'd
have to have go some sort of thought
process as to how you design the setup
for the particular technique and each
will come with advantages and
disadvantages and there are other
challenges first of all sometimes the
batteries Catch Fire which is a little
bit of an issue there are big things
like you have leads coming up these
leads pick up um RF so in this room for
example um the radio frequency I I don't
know what frequency of NPR is I think
it's about 91 Point something that's the
same frequency as carbon that's sort of
what causes this noise so you've got to
do all the RF um filters to stop this
and then you've got the more interesting
challenges associated with the diversity
of different materials that have very
large shift ranges and also as you're
cycling the susceptibility change
changes so over the years we've
developed um new cells to look at it
this is a so-called plastic bag battery
where you um use the same technology
that you would to seal coffee or to seal
smoked salmon you use a food laminator
and you put your battery inside and you
can do NMR of this or we upgraded it to
plastic cells that are much easier to to
to to put together and then we um design
setups where we have p Electric Motors
inside our NMR cells so that we can tune
the components on the fly as the
materials are cycling so I just want to
give you a little flavor of the sort of
things we've learned over the years the
first study that we did was on Silicon
so graphite has a capacity of about 370
milliers per gram if you use silicon you
can react 10 times more lithium with it
and so it's been touted for many years
as the sort of Ideal replacement for
graphite but what we showed in this very
simple study was that if you took the
fully lithiated silicon and you just let
the system rest you could watch the open
circuit voltage go up which means
there's a reaction happening and by
looking at the NMR in situ you could see
the peak disappearing as this material
was being oxidized by the electrolyte
and so the the electrolyt is being
reduced itself it's being oxidized and
so this was the first study to show that
the problem with silicon was not per se
the large volume expansion of silicon as
it reacts with lithium but that it
didn't form a nice passivating layer on
the top of it and that's what forms in
graphite and it's called the SEI and
that's why all graphite materials
actually work so just to give you
another example I wanted to sort of put
carbon in as the the the the theme and
lot of what I'm talking about um in in
sodium ion batteries you can't
intercalate sodium into graphite you can
intercalate Lithium you can interpolate
potassium but sodium is the wrong size
and so if you want to go for a more
sustainable technology you've got to
form a new find a new anode replacement
and the thing that people use for um the
replacement is a material called hard
carbon which is just essentially a
carbon that's heated up that doesn't
graphitize it has enough um defects in
the structure that it doesn't form
beautiful uh layers and so what we did
was to use sodium andmr to understand
the mechanism of how you interpolate or
insert into these graphite hard carbon
graffi type structures and so the model
of a hard carbon is the so-called House
of Cards and what we showed was that you
had first of all insertion into
diamagnetic regions and then you filled
in these so-called sodium pools with
pores inside uh the hard carbon
structures so then just to um move
forward we' now we used our instit
Metrology to look at a whole variety of
different materials and so if we think
about what are the Next Generation
higher energy density mat materials that
are more sustainable we could look at
lithium sulfur we could look at lithium
air batteries so lithium air is a
reaction of lithium to an oxygen to form
peroxide the problem with um a reaction
like this it goes via superoxides
superoxides are basically the radicals
that inside eat up um cause cancer and
and will react with everything they do
the same thing in a battery they will
eat up the electrolyte and cause
degradation and so we've developed over
years auction methods to track what's
going on and similarly we use sulfur
andmr to track what goes on in Sulfur
batteries so just to sort of um give you
one more example again with carbon so
the other if you want to do a high rate
um electrochemical cell you might use a
super capacitor so super capacitors
Bridge dialectric capacitors of
batteries in that they have higher
energy density not as high as batteries
but they also can charge in principle
faster than than Battery Systems they're
used in the um they're in your mobile
phones as flashes they're also in the
emergency exits of the Airbus systems
and they work because they have these
beautiful hierarchical structures and so
you take a coconut you activate it
essentially the same coconut systems
that you'd have in an activated carbon
uh that you would use for water
filtration and you form these
hierarchical structures these strands
here are the PTFE strands to hold the
thing together and then you can store
charge by simply inserting ions and at
the Double layers um of these carbons
and what we did with our instit NMR this
is now a while ago was to look and ask
the question how do ions insert inside
carbons and so what you're watching in
real time is the Florine NMR of the
annion in this salt tetraethyl BF4 minus
in a in a aceta nitrol so this is the
signal as you're charging up and down of
the ions going in and out of the pores
and the signal is going is Shifting
backwards and forwards as you're
inserting in this case we're going
positively so we're inserting holes into
the system we're charging up the the
Carbon sheets and we're reducing the
aromaticity of the carbon and what is
happening there is you're getting um a
reduction of the the aromaticity you
have reduction of the local field on top
of it the uction of the So-Cal nuclear
independent chemical shift that you're
seeing there so you're actually able to
track the extent of whole doping in
these carbons and say something about
the mechanisms of
interpolation but that was that was nice
from a sort of theoretical perspective
but this method actually allowed us to
ask a very simple question that hadn't
been shown experimentally before so if
we imagine an activated carbon so again
these are the activated carbons that you
would have in a water filtration system
we all know that the ions will go in so
at zero volts we've got equal numbers of
negative ions and positive ions and
surprisingly it wasn't known before
whether you would store charge so let's
imagine we do an experiment we charge
something positively you could either
kick out the positive charge for charge
compensation or you could bring in the
negative ones or you could swap them so
you could do an iron expulsion ion
exchange or so on and so what we did was
to look at this and quantify the ions
charging to positive versus to negative
and we showed that if you charge
negatively you actually sorbed cats
whereas if you charged positively you
had an iron exchange mechanism and then
by doing Pulse Field gradient
spectroscopy we able to show that if you
stuff lots of catons in your material
not surprisingly the diffusivity of the
the ions inside these pores went down
and so the sort of moral of the story
was if you want to get high rate you
want to avoid these types of carbon
absorption prot you want to have an ion
exchange process so that you can still
move the
ions and so more recently we've looked
at how um how to optimize these carbons
for these processes there was a very
nice work of paty Simon a few years ago
that said you wanted pores about the
same size of the the ions the solvated
ions and that this was a descript of
capacitance our more recent work with um
my collaborator Alex Force showed that
actually you could have carbon with very
similar pores and you have very
different capacitances and actually the
better descriptor that we picked out
from these NMR signals was the degree of
coherence of the Carbon sheets and as
the system got more disordered non
intuitively the capacitance went up and
that's because if you have lots of
defects in the Carbon sheets you start
pinning charge near these defects and
then you can p pin the ions nearby this
was a paper just published very recently
and then Cara Fong who is a poster in my
lab with Angelos mades has been doing
some very beautiful um MD simulations
using machine learned um force fields to
really understand the nature of iron
pairing in these types and related
systems okay so that's my introduction
on inet dematology I want to now lead
you through a story where we're going to
connect local structure all the way
through to mechanisms for how materials
inter
and so the story starts with this
material nmc811 so this is the uh
cathode material that's in most of
today's electric vehicles it's a layered
compound like lithium cobal oxide but
you've replaced 80% of the Cobalt by
nickel and 10% by manganes so that's the
811 and we do NMR of this material and
I've studied these materials or me
collectively and my group have studied
them for many years so we know how to
interpret these quite complicated
Spectrum so we're going to do exit NMR
we're going to take different batteries
at different states of charge and try
and unpick what these sort of broad
blobs mean and the sort of main thing is
that when you take this material it's a
mix nickel 2 to Nickel 3 uh oxide that
gets oxidized to Nickel 4 plus so for
those of you who've forgotten your
inorganic chemistry nickel 4 plus is low
spin D6 it's diamagnetic and the only
paramagnetic ions that are in the system
a manganese 4 plus and when you pull
most of the lithium out the lithium
remains near these paramagnetic
manganese 4 plus ions and that's why you
get these Spectra and so the sort of
take- Home messages we can actually
interpret these Spectra the thing that
we can't interpret is in the Middle
where things get quite
sharp and when NMR signals so this is
lithium NMR so I'm looking at the local
environment around the lithium and when
I pull out 10% of the structure I see
this very broad feature I heat it up and
not much happens but if I pull out 25%
of the lithiums I now have vacancies in
the lithium layers and the ions can
start to move and this what the
signature of motion is quite clear from
when you heat this material up because
the ions are moving they're changing
their local environment and so you get
what's known as motional averaging so
the NMR only sees the average
environment of the ions moving in these
layers and you can see by the time you
got rid of 50 50% you've got very high
lithium mobility and this to a material
science audience is not that surprising
you have vacancies and so you have room
for the irons to move and you actually
need die vacancies for it really to go
fast and so what Katarina my posto did
was to um simulate these Spectra and
extract the hopping rates for transport
and so if you um go from about 20%
removal to about 70% removal you have
hopping rates of about 80 to 100 khz so
these ions are moving very fast in these
structures and we can get an activation
barrier for that transport by just
varying the
temperature so there's a there's two
points you why do you U why do you get
increased Mobility one is that the uh
layers increase and then at the end they
collapse and so that collapse is why you
actually stop moving the lithiums at the
end of charge there's another phenomena
which I worked on with a a former
collaborator who may be familiar to some
of you in the audio
um and that's associated with as G Seda
that's associated with the charge of the
ions on the layers and above and if you
oxidize your nickel from 2 plus to 4
plus you have um if I'm a lithium ion
I'm hopping from octahedral site to
tetrahedral site to octahedral site
there's a very short contact there and
that short contact gives you the
activation barrier and the higher the
oxidation the bigger the cumic repulsion
so this all makes sense so I'm going to
move now the spirit of Millie from the
anode to the from the cathode to the
anode I'm going to think about graphite
so again we all know graphite we take
graphite we have these various stages so
stage four for example this l means U
less dense it's or light or low um it
means and the stage four means it's
every four lithium is filled and you go
through stage four to three to two and
then you form the dense stages two and
one and thing about the the dilute
versus the denser stages and this was
something that Millie worked on is you
have very different uh different
conductivity and so you go from the
dilute stages that have very low
conductivity to the dense ones that are
very conducting and you can see that by
NMR so this is the uh the the dilute
stages which have a very small shift uh
once you form the dense ones you have
this large night shift which is a
measure of the density of states of the
firmy level as um measured by the lith
and then the other thing that's
interesting about it that again comes
out from the NMR is you can via
technique called a T1 row measurement is
you can quantify the diffusion the
diffusivity and it's very um easy to get
the diffusion coefficient at the
so-called T1 minimum and so the minimum
uh is is where the transport is the same
frequency as the Lal frequency and so as
you go from a dilute stage to stage one
you can see that the diff the
diffusivity here is the same but the
temperature at which you achieve that
diffusion coefficient varies and so the
diffusion coefficients in the dilute
stages are much faster than in the dense
stages but they're of the order of uh 10
to the minus 11 Cent squar per second so
the question I wanted to then ask was
how does this Mobility affect the
intercalation mechanism and to look at
this I've been working with my colleague
AE RA in the Cavendish and so if you
want to understand how particles are
inserted you typically go and find your
local synchrotron you set up very clever
mytic experiments where you focus the
synchron beam at your particle and you
watch what's going on and it's it's
great you can get beautiful information
beautiful uh spatial and temporal
resolution but you get the reality is
you often get beam damage and it's not
easy to get a lot of beam time so what
we did was to do something much more
simple we were inspired by the work of
Phil kakuru at um Oxford who developed a
lot of very good microscopy techniques
called ice scats it's a rather horrible
name um to look at fluorescent uh
fluorescent biological systems so
biologists look at they tag things and
things move around and they can watch
things very rapidly here we're just
going to use this method to look at
scattering of a particle now scattering
is proportional to polarizability and
the degree of scattering will be
dictated by the differences in the
polarizability of the two medium so if
you've got a particle it'll be the
difference between this particle and the
medium around it it it'll be lower
resolution we've got resolution of the
order of 300 nanometers it's a little
bit better now but we don't have any
direct chemical specificity so actually
and I hypothesize that we should maybe
be able to use this to follow how ions
went into material so that's the way we
went into it this was a story of 2020 or
end end of 2019 and I said let's keep it
really simple let's use a particle
that's big and we know what's happened
so we took our friend lithium cobal
oxide um the student Alice Merryweather
made some beautiful um uh experiments
where she diluted the lithium cobal
oxide in a carbon Matrix we just took a
Ramen microscope cell and so you can see
the the basil plane the top of the
lithium caral oxide and the
electrochemistry is doing its normal
thing so lithium Cal oxide has a metal
insulator transition which is this peak
here that um is shown in the dqv plot
and this process is an ordering
transition at lithium point5 that I'll
explain in a few seconds so this is the
first um Imaging of icat so what you're
seeing is the sem and these are the
pictures and you're F we're focusing on
the flat parts of these particles but
we're going down about 300 nanometers so
this is not a surface method we are
really looking at bulk phenomena and
then we got this image in March
2020 and we had all of the pandemic to
work out what was going on so this was
the one positive for the pandemic for me
was that we could actually think about
it so what you're watching is this is
now lithiation that's the li5 tra phase
transition this is a solid solution and
this is the two-phase reaction you're
going to see a nucleation across there
but now watch it in the other direction
so we're going to start fully lithiated
a particle and you're going to see that
actually things start to emerge from the
edges and you come shrinking in and then
you have a solid
solution and then this thing coming up
here is the ordering transition
li5 ripping through this particle so
what's going on so there's this
beautiful paper by um Martin bazant and
yang sha horn who had uh examined
different mechanisms and thought about
why you would get different types of
intercalation processes and they
separated these two mechanisms So-Cal
shrinking core mechanism and an
intercalation wave mechanism and if you
look at our particles this is exactly
what's Happening Here you've got a nice
shrinking core this is shown sort of in
um snapshots but on the way back you're
lithiating and you're nucleating one
thing and it's moving across so why do
you have two different mechanisms on
charge and discharge so uh what my
former postto Quinton did was to try and
model this with continum modeling and we
just think about why this might happen
so we start off again we've got this
lithium Rich phase the lithium is
stuffed the lithium isn't going to go
anywhere the diffusion coefficients are
very very low and then we have a a metal
insulator transition with a imiss
ability Gap to form this lithium por
phase that's metallic but it's also got
much higher ionic transport and so if
you think about your particle I'm
hearing my pink phase lithium isn't
moving I pull the lithiums out from the
edges and it's so much easier to keep on
pulling lithium out of the blue phases
and so the particle that gradually has
this shrinking core but I now go in the
opposite direction I nucleate somewhere
and now I've formed a pink phase that
lithium isn't going to go through the
pink phase the only way that pink phases
can grow is if it goes into the blue
phase and adds to it and so by a very
definition it's really going to have to
grow out in that direction and in sort
of uh in in reality it's the tradeoff or
the rate at which you can pull ions in
and pull them out the J versus the
relative diffusion coefficients of the
two phases that explain this and so just
for completeness this is this ordering
transition I was telling you about this
is a you form a phase li5 where you have
ordered vacancies vacancies lithium
vacancies lithiums so you've lost the
three-phase three-fold symmetry of
lithium caral oxide and you can
sometimes form three domain in a
particle and sometimes it goes with just
a single domain so that's lithium cobal
oxide so I just want to move on from
lithium cob oxide because of course this
is the material of the 1990s just to
talk about um n nmc materials uh and the
question I want to talk about was again
uh this um Discovery at least from our
hands that if you started to pull
lithium out of these materials even
though these materials in principle were
a solid solution they also had these
two-phase reactions and we said that
this was associated with a particle
level phenomena meanwhile there's a very
nice paper by um will choose group and
Martin bazant who um commented on the
fact that there was probably a electrod
level process that caused this and so we
wanted to look at this phenoma by our
ice cat method to see if we could at
least look at it at the particle level
and you can see now we've out of the
pandemic we've improved our microscope
we've got rid of some of the the
artifacts and you can see there's a lot
of heterogenity going on and if we just
look at one particle here this is a
differential image you can see there
really is a shrinking Co the particle
level and so the question then is is
this a Thermon namic process or is it a
kinetic one so lithium Coral oxide has a
two-phase reaction as a metal insulator
that's a theramic process but this one
is is a kinetic process caused by um the
the the diff differences in diffusivity
and I'll I'll show you that in a second
but the way to check that is just to
stop let the system relax and if if it
relaxes that indicates it's kinetic and
so what's going on is very similar
though to the lithium cobal oxide system
you start off your material it's stuffed
the lithium is not moving anywhere you
start pulling things lithium out from
the edges and again it's easier to pull
it out from the red phase and so it
collapses in a shrinking core mechanism
and what's nice is because now we have
the lithium diffusivity from the NMR
that's why I went through the exercise
and showed you the NMR so we had the
hopping Ates we know the we have the
hopp in frequency rather we know how
fast the the distance over which hop is
so we can then use that to calculate the
diffusivity from the NMR we can then we
know the the the voltage of the the
curve tells us the energy or the Delta G
associated with pulling the lithium out
of the structure and so we can put that
into a nice and continual modeling we're
now collaborating with Norman Fleck and
vicam dhande and Shri was the postto on
the project who built a much better
Continuum model of it with a particle
that looked like our particle and he was
nicely able to replicate the shrinking
core model of the system so okay so that
was um that was the nmc I'm now going to
go back to the anode and talk about um
graphite so this is a particle of
graphite doing its thing so this is a
stage two to stage one and you know it's
really beautiful you can see this
particle and watch the N the uh these
inter
intercalation wave mechanisms going
through it um and then you can watch the
end process now I want to just talk walk
you through this one more time so this
is the intensity there's not a lot going
on and then suddenly but you can see the
stuff going on I'm going to unpick that
in a minute and then it suddenly changes
when you go from a stage two to Stage 2
L to two um so let's just look at what
that graphite is so this is the icecat
image this is the SE M and you look at
that particle and you think it's
actually a pretty uh single grain
material but yet when you unpick it like
this there are multiple domains within
it so what can we actually do with this
ice capap for graphite so Millie in her
solidate Physics course for the MIT
undergraduates nicely explain what's
going on here so you've got uh dramatic
change in the conductivity as you go
from the dilute stage to the dense
stages so the conductivity goes up and
so the polarizability changes and you
get this very large change in the
scattering and that's exactly what
you're seeing
here um so what can you do in terms of
using this information so this movie is
a new one that never works so you can
explore nucleation so this is uh at low
temperature and if you watch you can see
that there's sort of multiple nucleation
events if you go up in temperature if I
get the movie to work there are fewer
nucle cation but actually at the highest
temperature you can see it's actually
just a single nucleation event and so
the the differences in the transport of
the lithium ions as a function of
temperature have a significant impact in
how these materials operate but the and
so this is now showing you the
differential images so this is the stage
I was talking about so this is two stage
two to one and if you just take
snapshots you can see these
intercalation waves moving across and so
this all makes sense this is this um
this been described well by particularly
some papers by Martin bant but the one
that's completely different is what's
going on here and if you look at the
individual domains you can actually see
that there's domains being lithiated R
semi randomly and continuously so if
you're epileptic please look away in the
next image because this is what's known
as a differential image and it's
flashing and so this is the domain in
the first stages and you're seeing these
events of different layers looking as if
they're almost uncorrelated as the
different layers are being filled and
you can track the correlations between
them and there's definitely
relationships of one following another
but if you look at the intensities it's
not a smooth solid solution as the
electrochemical profile would suggest is
these little series of
steps and what those little series of
steps correspond to is the individual
filling of one layer at a time which we
can actually see step by step in these
simulations and
so in retrospect like all experiments
this is obvious but actually previously
people just thought about this a sort of
uh solid solution process and it sort of
starts to resolve the questions people
have in terms of how do you go from
alternating three layers to two layers
and to four layers or vice versa and we
can model this with I won't go into
great detail but we can model it with a
very simple ising model with different
degrees of relationships between the
layers and also um defects within the
layers and this is for um reminiscence
of something called Avalanche Behavior
which you know all know what Avalanche
is something goes and it suddenly goes
and it's associated with the sort of
pinning in the layers and then once
you've overcome that activation barrier
then the whole thing goes and you get
these types of characteristic phase
transitions so it's interesting it's a
totally different mechanism for graphite
that despite this material having been
worked on for many many years hasn't
been seen
before so let's just think about why we
can't charge faster so I've talked about
uh the nmc materials and the lco
materials and as long as you're working
in the right regime uh between about 20%
and 70% actually the lithium Mobility is
pretty good so why can't we just charge
our batteries infinitely fast well uh
this is a Samsung cell that we put 10
amps through uh for one minute and this
is not a recommended experiment um heat
thing and it goes to above 60 very
quickly and the 60 is the temperature
at which the seci the passivation layer
starts to um fall a bit to fall apart
the cathode when it's oxidized is
metastable and things go horribly wrong
the other thing is something we like um
from an experimental point of view is if
you charge too fast instead of intercol
nicely into graphite you form these
dendrites these dendrites look very
beautiful but they also have caused
incidents like like the Dreamliner plane
was at least thought to be associated
with a dendr incident so we do a nice
NMR we can track our dendrites by NMR
and so the thing about NMR is that it
only has a certain depth it can go
through a metal called a skin depth and
that allows us to track the dendrites
being formed so this is the dendrites
forming this is the passivating SE
forming on top that we can track so we
can do beautiful experiments we can do
magnetic resonance imaging experiments
and we can track them as they're forming
and we can relate that to the seci
formation so that's all nice from a sort
of uh from from an experimental
perspective but it doesn't really help
us in terms of the fast charging uh this
is now more recent experiments where
we're looking at the full cells we've
got our nmc material we've got the
graphite and we're looking at charging
and we're charging at um at increasingly
low temperatures and you can see at low
temperatures you're forming lithium
plating and this lithium plating issue
is why in regenerative braking you can't
utilize all of the kinetic energy to
charge your battery because of this
worry about lithium plating so how do we
design for fast charging well we have to
find a material that operates at a high
enough voltage to avoid the lithium
plating and it has to have high lithium
mobility and the sort of prototype
material that many of us as material
scientists would think about would be a
a a proide structure or arenium trioxide
structure it's got lots of holes why
can't we use it and the problem with it
is that lithium is too small for most3
structures and so the units rotate and
they clamp the lithiums in place so
lithium arenium oxide is a Terri even
despite its price is a terrible battery
material so what you can do is to think
about how you pillar the structures to
prevent those rotations and so you can
take a material and you can conceptually
do a shearing operation so we fuse the
oct together and when you do that you
put a lithium inside you can no longer
rotate so um you can just formally
imagine that and it's stuck and you can
do it in two dimensions and that's when
you get this hnv 205 phase and you form
these blocks and again the lithium is
really there it's rigid and you get in
principle get very lith rapid lithium
mobility and so that's what my former
student Kent Griffiths did he went
through a whole series of different
compounds and the best in class he
discovered in his PhD was this nium 16
w5055 which for obvious reasons is
abbreviated NWO and so this has a block
structure of
4x5 and it has a very high rate and so
with very little optimization he was
able to get a 20c rate so 20c rate is a
a 3 minute charge and the thing that's
limiting that is not the material itself
it's the um the lithium metal that he's
charging it against and again with very
little optimization he was able to get
materials that were lasting for a very
long time and so then we can ask the
question why does it work so one way of
doing that is to do Pulse Field gradient
spectroscopy so you put a gradient
across your material you wait for the
system to move and then you quantify the
Echo and you end up getting diffusion
coefficients of about 10 to - 11 to 10
-3 M s/s so let's just reflect for a few
minutes on what that means so let's
compare our materials with the common
other conductors so if you're a liquid
electrolyte your diffusivity is about 10
to the minus 10 so if you're trying to
do a three minute charge it means you
can move about 330 microns in that 3
minutes so you can move from one side to
the other side of a battery so battery
electrodes are about 150 microns or 100
microns depending on whether you're
optimizing for power energy density but
if you're a graphite and this is the 10
the minus5 that I showed you earlier on
the talk that means that in 3 minutes
you can only move a micron and so you've
got issues again of the plating that I
was talking about and so you need to
sort of nanosiz to get the rates but if
you're an NWO you can move 33 microns
which you can means you can move make
these chunky monster particles that we
made and you don't have to Nano size
reducing cost and reducing degradation
so that was fun not only do they move
fast you also get very good electronic
conduction because you've got these
uh Edge sharing uh octahedra that go
down the material in the direction of
the tunnel and if you do DFT
calculations you end up with these the
first electron goes into these block
orbitals where you have at low
temperates antiferromagnetic coupled
electrons in in one block and the other
one but the second one forms a band and
it becomes
metallic and so then this is now the
same picture of the NWO the same um Now
battery of arm battery um and 100
seconds you can see it only goes 40 and
then it's put into a Dyson vacuum
cleaner before Dyson went off to
Singapore I wouldn't do this anymore but
anyway Second Story and now this is uh
it's in a startup company niol and this
is um little uh robot charger that can
go to your car or can go to a somewhere
in need charging and then this is a
cheaper variant that's now in a in a car
so there just an illustration of going
from from the fundamental through to
Applications I want to end with one
quick story do I have five minutes yeah
um with again to return to the sort of
theory of of the the theme of graphite
and Millie dressle Houser but this is an
even older story so I I um I've been
trying to like many people in this
audience really understand what is the
nature of the passivating layer that
grows on both graphite and lithium metal
and I thought well I could go back to
this very early experiment of Albert
overhauser so chemists may have come
across something called a nosy or a
nuclear overhouse effect and we all
imagin that this was invented for
organic chemistry and biology biology
but actually Albert overhauser many
years ago said you could actually uh zap
the uh electron spinner radiation and if
you looked at the energy levels of your
uh a couple system in lithium so you
looked at the lithium spin so the
lithium is is the um this spin here and
you looked at the electron ones if you
radiated the electron spin resonance and
you had the right relaxation mechanisms
namely this relaxation mechanism was
faster than the other ones you could
actually enhance the magnetization of um
lithium metal so this was in 53 he was
in um Illinois and his colleague down
the road or down the in the next
apartment uh replicated this experiment
um the same year so this is an
experiment by Tom Carver and Charlie
slier and what he did was he um had
little bits of lithium metal in a dilute
Matrix and he got this massive
enhancement of 110 and the signal so
he's down at um 3 millitesla so very low
frequencies and he didn't even get the
signal of lithium metal without in
radiating he worked it out based on
comparing of proton experiment so this
was sort of experiments of 1953 and I
thought well maybe we could do this in
or 2020 more accurately and so but since
then um we've upped our fields and
people like Bob Griffin in the chemistry
Department have worked a lot on this
method called Dynamic nuclear
polarization or or dnp and the challenge
has been to try and find uh gyrotrons or
mechanisms for uh radiating the
electrons at these much higher Fields
because of the the the the the um
difficulties of using microwave
technology and so here we are in 19 20
in 2020 and we've got an enhancement of
eight and it's not because we're
particularly pathetic it's because we
just don't have the same high power as
in low fuels but it's exciting we can
partially saturate it but the most
interesting thing was we could also
polarize the signal of the SEI so the
covering of that that lithium metal and
so then the question is what can we do
with this and so the first question we
had was one associated with what is so
people um better galance group is a
particular Pioneer in this area have
spent a lot of time trying to work out
what's in this SEI and they quantify
different parts and you can do XPS and
you can sort of go down to deeper levels
but what's really difficult is to really
look at that interface between the
lithium metal in the SEI but we can do
this directly and so in this experiment
we um transferred the polarization we
enhanced the lithium signal and then we
transferred it to the Florine and
surpris surprisingly there was no
lithium fluoride and lithium fluorides
has been thought to be the sort of major
critical component of the of the se but
there isn't any but if you add an
additive like FEC which is this
fluorinated carbonate then L and behold
you have some lithium
fluoride so then just a sort of end well
what about graphite so graphite because
it's conducting here's the ESR signal
without going into all the details it's
conducting it has this daian line shape
it's all very well discussed in this
beautiful review article of Millie in
uh you can separate the different line
shapes depending on the conductivity for
the different stages and
um uh sorry this my student put in this
massive image of this is a graphite and
this little arrow is meant to show you
that in there some dendrites so they're
very difficult to see but you can see
them beautifully by the ESR so here's
the signal of the lithium L I6 and
here's the dite signal and what that
means is you can irradiate selectiv
either the lic6 or the lithium dendrite
and you can enhance this passivating
layer on either the carbon or the
lithium metal and so this is an example
where we're radiating the lithium metal
and you see we're getting these massive
enhancements of that lithium metal and
smaller ones of the lithium carbon
itself and so what that then allows us
to do is to ask the question how does
the SE differ on Li I6 versus lithium
metal and the source of information we
can get out is that this is on the
lithium metal that the signal closest to
the lithium metal is a lithium oxide
there's probably saw some also some
acetylene systems there they all
resonate in this neck of the woods it's
very similar to what betters group has
seen and if you look at the um the
lithium Li I6 the lith there's lithium
hydroxides that are present in the
lithium metal but not in the LI I6 and
so we're now in the process of using
this method to really unpick uh what a
lot of the speciation is and so with
that I think I'm sort of more or less on
time um I'd like to end by just here's
the full Cell lithium cobal oxide that I
started off with the Sony rocking chair
battery with the lithium cobal oxide on
one side and the graphite on the other
side so that's for the sort of
entertainment while you're if while I
finish off the conclusions so I think I
hope I've Illustrated that we've
developed all of these different insitu
or operando metrologies from NMR to MRI
to these now Optical methods which have
allowed us to really unpick fundamental
processes at the atomistic all the way
through to the particle level and then
in the fast charging example I by
illustrat that we could then pull
through some of this understanding to
try and make some technology uh and then
more recently we've been trying to
develop these methods to actually look
at interfaces and trying to design
approaches where we can enhance specific
parts of the signal and so in this DN P
example that's one where we can radiate
specifically the electrons in one
component over the other and really use
that to try and understand the metal uh
diamagnetic interface
and obviously we can look at interfacial
processes by electron microscopy but
it's very difficult often to get the
chemical specificity and so hopefully
some of these NMR experiments allow you
to do that and of course this wouldn't
be possible without my great research
group This Is Us on a hiking trip uh a
couple of years ago um I've mentioned a
few people on the way but I want to
really highlight olle and barish who
started the insitu NMR the N nmc work
was chiao Chu and Katarina Amer and Phil
Reeves the niobates was really pioneered
by Kent Griffiths who's now on the
faculty at UC San Diego with Lauren
Mella who did a lot of the PFG she's at
um Colombia um the DFT I had a lot of um
collaborations with Andrew Morris uh
rangi and Anna and span the dendrites
the ice scat was a really a lovely
collaboration involving a raal and Alice
the former PhD student with chrish
nedman a postdoc and Norman and Shri and
Dave Hall and and Norman Fleck did the
modeling with me dnp DD wrinkle and Mike
hope and super caps um the whole large
team but largely Alex force and my
collaborator Don Franco and thank you
very much for listening to
[Applause]
me cl thank you so much um that was
extraordinary talk uh what is going to
follow uh is uh Professor yebing Chen is
going to have a brief chat with you uh
so please join him on the stage okay
thank you on the stage
now I I understand that the audience has
the ability to post questions there we
go all right wonderful and so while
you're thinking about your questions and
posting them they'll show up here uh you
know the the thing about Fireside Chats
is you have to sit down I know sorry I
felt a bit odd but you're not sitting
secondly where's the
fire uh so uh there's no battery fires
no battery fires that's right that would
have been a beautiful backdrop for our
discussion here
now um so let me kick things off and uh
ask Claire about uh the view towards
climate change in the UK today right so
as you know and we discussed earlier at
MIT we have the climate project the pan
MIT effort uh Sally corn Bluth has
doubled down on climate uh since the
last Administration Raphael r's and so
this is going to happen at MIT and we
had an election a we week or so ago uh
that's not going to affect what we do
here at MIT to any significant extent I
believe right now um what I want to ask
you is you know what's the view in the
UK you know at the student level at the
um university level uh what's the
climate on climate
change I mean I I think the the UK is I
mean I think the distinction in the UK
is pretty clearcut that it's in law
climate we have to phase out the
electric vehicles by the end of the
decade and that's now legislation now
whether it happens is another matter but
that so that has frames the conversation
very differently than particularly in
the US and now and I mean maybe that was
different two weeks ago but you have a
very act active student body and you
have these sectors in the UK Society we
have Extinction Rebellion we have these
these are the people who have been
variants of Extinction Rebellion who've
been gluing themselves to parts of the
equivalent of I95 and the train stations
and so it's a very active body I mean we
are as a university we're not um not
allowed to accept money now from fossil
fuel companies yes so that you mentioned
that earlier and that's a pretty
dramatic move and and that's coming from
the students that is not something that
the you know the academic
are there's some very disperate opinions
on it but it's the students who pushed
it and it's part of the
protests but so our students are
quite quite strong in in in in the
lobbying groups now in terms of the
University we have Cambridge zero which
is our sort of umbrella Organization for
action but it's very much policy and the
environment is headed by a woman from
the British Antarctic Survey and that's
very much shaped what she's interested
in doing and so we've been weaker on the
tech although that's something we're
trying to do at the moment because we
have a very strong track record and a
lot of energy systems but I think you
know MIT does these things well partly
because it always has more money or at
least that's the perception from the
outside that you may disagree with that
um well um you did say that that I asked
you earlier today when we met you know
so what do you see as the difference and
you said in the UK we do much of the
same thing just with less money exactly
yeah and so and also you have a and I'm
not saying that's a virtue is a reality
you know I would be very happy if it
that's right maybe you're more efficient
yes uh there there's also uh the rest of
Europe whoever what is the What is the
dynamic between the UK and the rest of
Europe on climate these days well I mean
you know the you have the election last
week as the elephant in the room of
course we have brexit as the the
elephant that sort of floats around
somewhere in the channel
um so because we've in the last few
years been part of this negotiation to
um be part of horizon 2020 which is the
funding mechanism from Europe and the EU
um link that with immigration so it was
almost used funding was used as this
sort of um thing to beat the UK over but
anyway we're back we're in hor Horizon
20 and we're very much trying to give
the impression of being outward facing
and being wanting to um collaborate and
so that's been a ma major Focus to
reestablish the networks that were
broken as part of the the whole brexit
period because there was this time where
most of the time we could be a part of
it but we couldn't lead any
collaboration so so that's that's from a
sort of um from an academic perspective
I think the whole other perspective is
the industrial one so because of brexit
you know we don't have an ability to
trade freely but yet the reality is that
a company that makes something in the UK
the EU is their major trading block and
so you have to uh in the same way that
the US if you're making something one
state you still have to obey
California's emission requirements so
there's an incentive to obey the
requirements of the whole of the US in
the UK is there's an incentive to obey
the regulations of the EU and thing we
talked about earlier on is the need to
you know manufacture as much as possible
within Europe right so that's
influencing a lot of policy influencing
the need to have materials that come
from within Europe and of course people
have been to Europe we're not a country
full of minds and there's not a lot of
Natural Resources so there are a number
of parallels here that you've pointed
out now so back to the industrial aspect
so U I may be a bit of an outlier but I
think that uh with just our election is
probably not going to change the
progress of uh climate mitigation
Technologies as much as some think for a
couple of reasons one is 2016 to 2020
there was actually a very fertile period
for both the development new technology
and creation of new companies here in
the US and here we are in 2024 and a
number of those companies now have grown
to the point where the economic benefits
are seen and those economic benefits for
instance in manufacturing are
predominantly in red States and so where
you know job creation is taking place
you what we're seeing now is that
politics are put aside and better jobs
for example more jobs better jobs are
carrying the discussion uh in the UK and
in I would say in Europe more broadly
are you starting do you see uh those
economic benefits from the energy
transition yet yeah I think it's a
really good point and I but I think the
the distinction is that the US has been
better the UK has been dragged down by
brexit and that has made a difference
the economy and Europe hasn't bounced
back with the same speed after the
pandemic as the US and so that's
dampened a lot of this and I think but
it what it's made um an issue that I
think is very relevant to the us as well
is make trying to think about how the
transition to a more sustainable um
economy is for everyone and it's not
just those who can afford their Teslas
or the equivalent and I think that and
in the UK you have talk about the red
States and the blue States we talk about
the north south divide and it was the
leveling up agenda which was the term
that was introduced by Boris Johnson who
we can discuss that with that they're
leveling up they even created an agency
for leveling up that that's been got rid
of but it doesn't it
nonetheless the labor is under even more
a political um challenge because the
labor party which was out of office for
so many years
didn't get in because the traditional
labor areas in the north of England all
voted for the conservatives and so
that's hampering them even more so it's
this balance between how do you how do
you do what's actually in law which is
to as I said to to think about removing
electric vehic sorry removing petrol
cars gasoline cars sorry um and rolling
electric vehicles and then trucks are
next yet doing this in an economy that
is is not as vibrant as this country so
I think that's it's that's what's making
labor the labor diffic um the labor
government it putting it in a very
difficult spot and they you know they
want they've wanted to be more
transparent but you know it's it's not
easy so I don't know if I answered your
question I think so I think it would be
great if there are more companies in the
U UK in the same way that start to see
this as a way of of to be blunt making
money I mean
yeah and and you had mentioned me
earlier that the rpe model for example
is being exported to the UK currently
yeah even with RP people but yeah again
as I said to you earlier on with smaller
numbers but what's interesting uh unlike
and maybe I'm wrong that because I've
now been outside the US for long that
there is also more of a model to have
rpe type projects involve Africa and
other parts of the world to think about
democratization of energy and so the and
that may be that the funding model is
different this m the UK traditionally
has put more money in Aid and some of
that Aid funding has been associated
with science and so some of that's been
folded into the um to to our RP which I
think is also interesting great thank
you for that and so uh feel free to
submit questions and you know we can go
back to some you can ask some more
technical question if You' like as well
oh vadir do we have to stop uh no we we
have a couple more minutes uh just raise
your hand if you have a question because
the is not behaving the way we expected
okay but and while we wait for that I
have I I want to ask you a little more a
somewhat more personal question here so
you know you and I met in uh almost 30
years ago and I believe that you know at
the time you had left to Pont and were
an assistant professor at Stony Brook
and you know we're now both both
considerably older and now you're U Dame
Professor Claire gray right and uh you
know I want to ask you you know what's
that like I mean when students come into
your office now uh how do they address
you do they have to bow do they have to
say they bow
bow tell us about
that oh they bow yeah
totally I mean what is there to say
about it I mean it's a slightly
embarrassing title
and I um and I went through um I did
look there's a website of people who you
were Ned right so nighted is still the
right phrase
yeah yeah it is actually it is yes it's
just that the men get men are called
their nights and they get
swords they get given a sword but the
women get off so you didn't get the
sword no sword
yeah anyway there's a website of people
who said no but I in the end I decided
you know they're not many women
scientists who get this honor so I
should just embrace it but it's okay
it's a wonderful honor and you should
embrace it I think it's wonderful so
congratulations on
that all right do we have some questions
hands one oh Lynn Professor Lyn hops
please I I just have a a very small
really drle house yeah I have a small
Millie dressle house related comment um
uh she and I and some others were
working on elect transmission electron
microscopy of of the lithium
interpolation of graphite back in 1981
which is when some of your comments were
addressed initially and um those studies
were beveled by the unavoidable but
indeterminate Electron Beam Heating in
the electron microscope and so I was
extraordinary
excited in the Imaging methods you've
dreamed up um which enable you to look
at the temperature dependence which is
clearly hugely hugely important uh in
these classes of materials and in this
kind of
technique thankk thank you thank
you
please hi uh my name is Jacob seagull um
after your work with graphine doing with
uh nitrogen do you see that if graphine
Purity increases and Manufacturing
techniques are improved that it would be
viable material for the
cathode so you're saying so do I think
nitrogen dope graphin would be good for
a cathode yeah yeah they I mean most
graphites even with nitrogen they'll be
down on the anode side so um I think
it'll be an anoe um you know the problem
you always have is that graphite is so
good
mhm and if you put nitrogen in there it
it could in the in the application I
told you of super caps where um where
you're just storing things on a double
layer and you've got solvated ions if
you start putting in defects anything
that pulls the irons closer together
gives you higher capacitance so I'd
probably look for it in that sort of
application I mean there is some you
know people do talk about nitrogen dope
Boron dop graphin and graphites but the
problem with batteries is you just want
stuff and anything that's fluffy you
know is is bad and anything that's more
fluffy of higher surface areas more
degradation so I say do a super cap okay
you know maybe I can yeah you can just
take that question and add a question on
top of your question is very graphite is
great but it's a little too close to the
lithium metal potential
fortly why is it in lithium ion battery
that we have you know lithium metal wave
graphite but then the next best thing is
lithium TI titanium oxide is all one
volt higher BT and a half higher there
and so why is this this demilitarized
zone between two what we really need is
something that's about 3/4 of a vault
off of lithium there's vanadates so
they're 0.9 Titan titanates
0.9 um I think one of the one of the
challenges if you look at the lithium
vanadates and lithium titanates is
you're having to make them lithiated to
get there and they're pain to process
you you can't do it in air so air is
about 2.9 volts or 3 volts and so you're
when you're making things you're always
making things in that ox and if you're
making it unlithiated
your so that that's half of it and yeah
I mean that's the periodic
table well we need we clearly need
another one I mean you can you know as
your suggest you can doe graphites and
but again you're you're creating
distributions of stuff and but but I do
think it's the it's the metal oxidation
states that you want that get you in
that 6. 7 you're making them lithiated
and then it's a question of how do you
scale it as well all right I think we
are out of time unfortunately and so uh
please join me and thank Claire again
for a wonderful lecture and discuss
thank you that's great there are many
materials in the world uh at MIT we have
an absolute pleasure of working with
many many of them including glass uh so
our students uh together with our
amazing staff run the glass laboratory
where glass is extruded in many
beautiful shapes including given the
fact that we are at the Thanksgiving
season and uh a pumpkin is a a symbol of
it uh we have made a glass pumpkin as a
momento of this particular day it has a
little MIT logo on it as well embedded
in the glass thank you so much uh like
give this to you as our very small token
appreciation thank you so
[Applause]
much for