So going back to uh these problems that
we defined earlier um in the first
problem um we asked how uh it would be
possible to measure all 20,000 genes in
cells um and this uh technology that we
introduced single cell RNA sequencing uh
is the answer to that. This makes it uh
possible to measure the gene expression
for all genes uh in 1 million cells.
Um and now we'll move to talk about the
second problem that we posed which was
um whether it would be possible to uh
delete individual genes in cells and see
what the effect is on uh the cells and
specifically on uh the gene expression
in those cells. And so this is part C
where we'll be talking about this uh
second technology that focuses on uh
combining these gene pertubations um
with the cell read out.
So going back to uh the scheme that we
saw earlier. Um so we spoke about how uh
from a population of cells we can uh use
single cell RNA seek uh this first
technology to um produce this gene
expression matrix.
And now um in this second technology
called uh pertabbse seek um what you can
do is introduce deletion of a specific
gene to each of these cells um and then
output a similar kind of matrix but now
where you can see how this matrix
differs from the matrix that doesn't
have uh any gene deletion or any
pertubation.
So going back to our example uh the
adiposite uh populations that we have.
Uh so we saw that in the single cell
expression matrix we could identify each
of these three populations by uh each of
these three uh clusters of genes
expressed in those clusters of cells
specifically.
And so how would this look now if we
combine this with uh the pertubations
that um the second technology permit us
to do?
So in this case for example we might
delete the gene sedd. Uh this is a gene
that's known to be important for uh
regulation of the lipogenic uh program
the lipogenic state.
And so if we delete this gene sedd, what
we'll actually um get out is a very
similar matrix uh except we'll have a
row added uh that shows um that this
gene sedd was deleted. Um and we'll have
a count to show um which cells this gene
was deleted in. Um and so this is
showing for one gene, but in theory uh
we could delete many genes uh and also
different genes in different cells.
And so what we might see is uh upon SEDD
deletion given that this is a gene that
regulates the lipogenic program that
actually um we completely lose
expression of these two genes SR BP1 and
uh fast N um which are key genes uh of
the lipogenic state and therefore we
completely um lose this cluster uh of
cell five and six that we had uh
previously
um as a result of this deletion. And uh
in this particular case, I picked a gene
that we know regulates the lipogenic
state uh or the lipogenic program. Uh
but in another case, it might be a gene
that we know nothing about. And so this
would be uh an extremely revealing uh
and interesting result. And so to dive
in a little bit more to how perturb
actually works, it relies on this gene
editing technology crisper cast 9, which
you may have heard about uh in the news.
and it won the Nobel Prize uh a few
years ago.
And uh the way it works is this protein
called the cast 9 nucleus is guided to
specific parts of uh the genome. So
specific regions of DNA or specific
genes um and at that specific location
that it's guided to, it will insert a uh
doublestranded break. uh and so what we
can do is um we can manipulate which
genes the crisper cast 9 system is
guided to by providing uh different uh
guide RNA molecules. So um we'll provide
a guide RNA molecule for a gene of
interest uh that we are interested in
deleting or knocking out the cast 9
system will be guided there and then it
will lead to this doublestranded break
therefore uh deleting the function of
that gene.
And so this is the technology that
perturbse seek uh relies on. Um and so
to remind you um of what we spoke about
perturb is the combination of two
things. Uh on the one hand using uh cast
9 to insert uh specific deletions uh in
individual cells and as I mentioned you
could have uh different genes being
deleted uh in different cells.
combining this with uh a similar readout
as we saw before which is this single
cell RNA seek matrix where for a given
cell you can count the number of RNA
molecules um but combining this with the
actual pertubation identity i.e the
specific gene that was knocked out in
that cell here denoted as A or B.
And so what's the readout? Uh there are
two readouts that you'll get. One is
this uh expression matrix uh that we're
familiar with uh hopefully by now. And
the second is this uh pertubation
identity matrix that will tell us for
each of the cells in the expression
matrix uh whether there was a
perturbation and specifically uh what
gene um was perturbed or what gene was
knocked out. So you can see here for
example that in uh cell one we have the
gene expression profile. So the uh
expression levels for every gene uh in
the genome uh in this cell. And we also
know that this expression profile um is
the result of um whatever programs were
already inside that cell uh but then
adding the deletion of MLX IPL
and likewise in cell 2 we can see the
gene expression profile uh and the gene
CBPA that was knocked out and so on.
Finally, we also have uh some cells uh
always in perturbic experiments where we
don't knock anything out so that we can
compare each of these pertubation groups
to uh the non-targeting uh it's called
control
or in other words the expectation with
no uh pertubation.
So the advantage of this is that um we
can get this very informative rich uh
transcrytoic readout uh the single cell
expression matrix. We can also as I
mentioned um do these perturbations in a
poolled format such that different cells
will receive uh different pertubations
thereby allowing us to cover more of the
uh genome. And we can use this the
combination of the cells without
perturbation and the cells uh with
specific perturbations to infer the
functions uh of these specific genes
that are perturbed.
There are however um still some
downsides. Um, one is that even uh in
spite of this pulled format that allows
us to um profile many perturbations in
parallel um it's still very time
consuming uh and would probably take one
Thiago uh doing these experiments 22
years to actually um profile cells
receiving every single of the 20,000 uh
pertubations uh in the genome.
And so this is one uh very key
motivation uh for this challenge which
is falling short of being able to
experimentally test uh in the lab every
single perturbation. What we would like
is to be able to use machine learning um
to predict pertubations, their effects
to predict this matrix, the effects of
the pertubations on individual cells and
hopefully highlight pertubations that we
um predict to be particularly important
um in uh the context of adiposite
biology and obesity.
And so we'll be talking uh more about
that in the final lecture uh on uh data
and the crunches that you'll be doing.