the migration Summit is a global
initiative dedicated to addressing
challenges and unlocking the
opportunities faced by Refugee migrant
and displaced communities the refugee
crisis won't stop unless uh we are able
to find peace since its launch in 2022
the summit has evolved from fostering
meaningful dialogue to driving
actionable outcomes in 2024 the summit
set out to achieve three key goals one
shifting mindsets two sparking action
three developing a resource platform of
tools and materials the act of of
migration uh uh where whether it's a
forc or voluntary it's like a by itself
it's an act of Entrepreneurship itself
this year the migration Summit brought
together a focused week of 12 virtual
events complemented by 15 in-person
sessions and an online campaign we
explored Innovative strategies and
solutions to unlock Pathways to
dignified work for displaced communities
as part of our online campaign we
launched an interactive map offering a
dynamic view of the hundreds of
organizations that are part of the
migration Summit
Community our new portraits of talent
page celebrates the diverse community
and talents of displaced individuals
worldwide in an animated video Maria
Valeria Akino a dedicated member of our
organizing committee shared the personal
Journey she had to take from Venezuela
to safety and new opportun unities in
Uruguay we also shared a series of blogs
that dive deeper into the personal
Journeys recruitment challenges and
innovative solutions shared by both
displaced individuals and experts in the
field from kakuma camp and Nairobi we
shared the powerful stories of Daniel
ibingo Susan and Tabitha four remarkable
individuals from South Sudan Kenya and
Congo as we continue this journey we
invite you to join us engage with our
res sources connect with our community
and be part of the change thank you for
being a part of migration Summit 2024
let's come together to turn dialogue
into action