so I will get right to it so Kart is one
of the most exciting stories in the last
decade in what happened to the cancer
therapy what it is is that you utilize
the patient's own immune cell te- cell
to be specific you harvest them from the
patient you genetically engineer them
and rein and and culture expand them and
then re inject that cell back into the
patient and mirac ously they go after
the patient cancer cell and kills them
now this is a highly expensive therapy
the single dose of this is roughly
speaking about half million dollar very
expensive but if you can cure the late
stage uncurable metastatic blood cancer
with this thing it works every single
penny of it
however uh the problem here is that this
is utilizing patient own can own te-
cell so because of that you know your
own te- cell is different from somebody
else's t- cell there is a huge variation
comes from the Doner of the cell as well
as the manufacturing processes so you
know to highlight
that here we bought a manufactured you
know car cells from the commercial
sources and tested how good they are you
know by testing it you know their you
know measuring their ability to kill the
cancer cell which is called The Killing
essay I'm not going to get into the
details of it what you can clearly see
is that even though all of these cells
are coming from the same manufacturer
and manufactur with the same protocol
it's all over the place some of them are
much better at killing cancer cell some
of them are really not it not good at so
this is a problem this is a problem not
just for the buyer of this expensive
therapy but also a big problem for the
seller and to me it is very similar
challenges that you know situation where
you walk into the grocery store and
you're not you're buying $5 watermelon
it's not a half million but $5
watermelon but still same problem we
know we have a product variation some of
them are more delicious than the other I
don't want to buy poor watermelon but
one thing that you're not allowed to do
is e them okay so you need to somehow
figure out what is the better product
than the other and what do you do you
just tap on them okay you somehow
without disrupting the
cell uh you know try to figure out the
phenotype of the cell or quality of the
cell and one thing you cannot do is that
you know traditionally the biologist try
to do this by doing what we call as a
omix study but then none of them would
be useful because you're going to end up
breaking up the cell you analyze the
genetic markup and proteomics and
everything but okay you knew that that
cell we just killed was a great t- cell
but then what's the point if the cells
are gone so this is a very interesting
Challenge and I think this is where you
know some of the new ideas coming from
the micro fluidics can be utilized and
there are a lot of ways to do the
critical quality attribute essay and
utilizing not the biochemical marker but
biophysical marker so let me tell you
how we approach this problem it's
essentially the same idea of actually
tapping the watermelon but because we
are talking about millions of te cell
that we need to qualify we cannot really
use our hand we actually use the
microfluidic devices so this is our way
of tapping the cells and te- cells so
this is a very specific iic microfluidic
devices where we actually bring in and
then you see the left hand side is all
the red blood cells but the on the right
panel we are actually designing the
pathway for these cells to be interact
with the obstacles in a very specific
Manner and this can be done in less than
10 minutes with a very small volume of
raw material and what we are trying to
do here is having these cell to interact
with these specifically designed pillars
and as a result of that interaction some
cells are ending up one location
Downstream then the other so if you have
a very rigid T Cell then you may end up
in certain location Downstream and then
the other so what you end up doing is
that at the downstream of all of these
devices we
locate where the cells end up and then
uh we have been using this as a way to
analyze these immune cells for many
different application maybe even immune
profiling and and diabetes and many
other today I'm going to just focus on
the cell therapy quality control so the
way we do is actually here this device
is really we have this uh obstacle array
or pin bur machine if you think about it
and you bring in the cell and then we
distribute the cell based on their
mechanical property or size were
combined and we started doing this work
in early 2020 we have a lab based system
and it's you know requiring grass
student and postto now after four five
years now we actually drisk this into a
building a fully integrated and and
portable systems in a manner that we can
actually now send this machine to
hospitals and you know nurses can
operate this thing in the hospital
sometimes in ICU in a very restrictive
environment so I think we actually gone
a long distance to make this thing
really
Deployable and the way we understand or
utilize these essays is quite
interesting you know just like we tap
the watermelon you know there is
no way but so some people are better at
figuring out which watermelons are
better than the other so essentially
what we are doing is sort of collect all
the data set you know after we pass
these cells through these obstacle
courses and we have a distribution and
we take that distribution for number of
different conditions a faster flow
slower sped we flow slower flow speed
and then we also change the structure so
we get a number of different
distributions and each distribution
reflects the mechanical property of
these cell
population so we generate these uh
vectors H1 H2 H3 H4 and as a
distribution of the cell at the end of
the essay and then we take this
distribution and you look at this
distribution and distribution has a lot
of interesting information hidden in
there so just like we typically do in
any type of machine learning
architecture we vectorize them we comute
them into some Matrix and we can design
many many many metrics you know more
than hundreds of them and you feed that
metric into a typical clustering
algorithm there are lot of different
ways of doing it and then try to
correlate that metric with the important
actionable outcome whether the cells are
dead whether the cells are activated
whether the cells are exhausted so
they're not really killing the cancer
cell anymore there are a lot of
interesting and important functional
outcomes that we want to predict using
this kind of
techniques
so so the very first thing we did is
actually correlating you know our data
set with you know most basic phenotype
whether the cells are healthy and or
whether they are activated or ready to
be actually start killing the cancer
cell or whe they are just came out of
the Frozen bile and they are not ready
and they are kind of you know kind of
half de and they need some more time to
recover so you see those are really
relevant phenotype that is
really you useful in the context of
delivering this C therapy and you can
see if you look at the histogram it is
very clear that depending on the
phenotype you can actually see vastly
different distribution so you know that
we can correlate these
complicated histograms with the
important phenotype that we have are
caring about so we went
further and really thinking about using
this as a way to monitor the car T cell
production process themselves and
typically these cells are harvested from
the cancer patient and then send out to
some manufacturing site and they undergo
14-day culture protocol during that
14-day the cell transforms itself into a
fully activated cart and during that
transformation processes they actually
change the morphology they change the
shape they change the distribution a lot
of things changes as you can see in the
images and we can see that without
actually doing the manual Imaging or
facts or all of these standard
biochemical essay a 10-minute pass
through our device will generate this
histogram which can be correlated with
this important transformation that is
happening to this very expensive product
so that's the kind of a value
proposition we are
proposing now after that we also think
of this as a release essay meaning that
before we sending this out to the
patient and before injecting this ctis
cell into the patient which is a really
a dire
situation is there is a need to make
sure that this product has been properly
manufactured and functional and ready to
go so here we are comparing these two
kind of a bioreactor systems people use
to generate uh kti product and and these
are all coming from the same donor and
you can see that these two different
Biore reactors systems is generating
vastly different product quality and
this was actually very obvious from our
biophysical markers and we certainly do
not understand all the nitty-gritty
molecular mechanism of it but telling
the difference in quality in itself
without knowing the mechanism is already
enough and actionable so that you can
decide what to do okay this is a good
product or not so good product or at
least repeatable produced product so
that's the goal
here and again uh we also see that these
two bio reactors are producing Better or
Worse product and both are functional
but then some bioreactors are generating
more functional product than the other
and we can monitor that quality
valuation coming from manufacturing
process using this
essay and then finally uh remember that
in the first slide I talked about the
killing essay and this is the ultimate
Way of quantifying how good the cells
are you know just take the cell and
challenge them with the actual cancer
cell and how good they are in terms of
killing the cancer cell now this is the
really a very laborious requiring armies
of grass student to do it so in the
current cart manufacturing and
administration process we cannot do that
you know these killing essay is not done
right now the K cells are blindly
injected you know without doing any kind
of a quality essay but then you know if
you look at the biophysical ESS
say that we
generate so those indexes we we generate
from these hundreds of uh features is
very strongly correlated with what we
can recover from these Robious killing
essay that we do manually so what we are
seeing here is a prospects of doing this
rapid uh quality functional quality
essay without actually going through all
these lab based in know Robious killing
assay so this is a very strong uh value
proposition what that means is that
before injecting these c t half million
dollar sales into the patient we have a
mean in 10 minute to make sure that this
is a good product to go and this is a
very important thing to have even for
the sellers of this product because it's
so expensive and so high
stake so that's all I have to say today
and I like like to show up the photo of
the person who is mostly responsible for
this great work Dr CN Jang is the main
person behind this work he's the
inventor of this technology he's
actually trying to commercialize this
technology for a lot of this application
and there are a lot of other people
helped out to make this thing happen and
the funding came from Singapore
government supporting these smart Center
research and I would be happy to answer
any questions
[Applause]
thank you very much Jay for this
interesting presentation I I love your
comparison of your essay with melon
tapping uh makes it very clear um I
noticed um I'm not sure if I saw it
correctly but you're directly working
with hospitals and I was wondering if
you provide VSA directly to the
hospitals or if you involve companies
which actually build an instrument
around your essay and then give it to
hospitals so right now we are doing uh
several clinical trials not really
necess you know related to the KT but
then more in the direction of profiling
immune state of the patient and this is
very important for things like sepsis or
even for for the kti patient one of the
big side effect is what we call as a
cyoc kind release syndrome which is sort
of same thing as a sepsis so understand
ending these kind of sudden changes in
immune system is very very critical but
it's not done currently so most of the
hospital engagement we have been doing
is actually deploying these kind of
portable you know point of care system
in ICU like environment and still do
this quick and rapid and almost real
time immune profiling to generate some
actionable information and we are
getting a lot of exciting
uh data you know maybe we can see that
oncoming CRS onset like you know half
day earlier than any other essay or
maybe you see start seeing a sudden rise
in temperature so we we are seeing a lot
of exciting o datas out of this hosp
Hospital deployment
yeah any other questions thank you so
much Professor Han so this is outside my
area my question is naive but in
addition to the physical properties of
the te- cells are there opportunities to
look at for example the magnetic
properties of te- cells stimulation of
them using magnetic field Quantum and
try to get more separation there what
are the other important properties with
respect that that's a good point I think
it's a really uh untapped and underst
studied areas of biology and we always
think of cells and and molecules it's
just a biochemical
angle right but then cells are actual
physical object and their mechanical
structure or de ability is actually a
big part of their function so I I do
believe that there are a lot of
opportunities out there to both measure
and and per perur these biological
systems physically yeah it's a good
point any other questions
sorry hi thank you very much for
interesting presentation so quick
question for the bio physics signature
for that so you mentioned that most of
your work done is a more c um uh
evaluations do you have any idea like
how can translate the
biophysical um signature towards
different immune cells or different type
of cells that was a kind of really
robust or you need to build a new model
to assess that the other type of cells
yes thank you uh so our CTI work has not
yet published it's under review right
now but we already published using this
for the whole blood okay and then as you
can see this device will immediately get
rid of the rbcs and just collect the WBC
component and then subject to this essay
so we have already published on using
this for evaluating an emergency
department patient who works into the
emergency department of the hospital
and many of them are not sick actually
they are maybe traumatized or something
and very few subset of them may have a
blood infection and finding that people
which is at the onset of systematic
inflammation is critically important and
I think we already have done a lot of
work and a much more
expanded uh clinical trial is ongoing in
Singapore
yeah any more questions s if not we'll
stop here and go into a networking break
and then we'll be back at noon for the
second part of the session so thanks
again professor H for a very interesting
presentation