All right. Thank you, Carrie. So, next
up we have Mark.
>> Hello. I've got
>> Oh, yeah.
>> I'm wired.
>> I need that, though.
>> Uh, good afternoon and last session of
the day, so I'll be quick because
everybody wants to get out of here,
right?
>> Pardon me. I have a hook.
>> Excellent. Please use it. Um
I'm going to do a a brief overview. This
has been looked at obviously a number of
times over the last two days, but um you
know this is a a milestone project in
the USA any way you look at it. Um you
know again it's Eversource Energy, you
know the owner of it. single pipe
system, ambient loop, mile distribution,
37 or 38 buildings. I thought I heard an
extra building somehow got attached. I'm
not quite sure how that worked. That's
fine. Um there's commercial buildings
and there's residential buildings. So
your upside there is you've got good
diversity. Um they're all single family
homes. A district loop would not have
made sense. So site selection was very
important. It made sense for the
residents as well as the system itself
and the owner. Excuse me. Uh 90 vertical
bore well 90 vertical and angled bore
holes. Um so I think everyone knows that
there was two configurations. Two bore
fields were vertical and then there was
another bore field that's kind of two
bore fields that are angled. So the uh
verticals were 600 feet in depth and the
angles were 720 ft approximately with
quad loops. Quad loops what I mean is
two U bends in each bore hole.
What I thought was very interesting and
looking at what was I going to be
talking about is you have some very
interesting dynamics at play here.
um have it's a unique coming together if
you think about it. Credit to Zanob Heat
being able to pursue this over all this
time and convincing a natural gas
utility that theoretically can't sell
any gas. It's kind of a interesting
concept when you think about it, right?
Um, I thought it was just absolutely
amazing because it it's a successful
project and you had two really very
disparit entities coming together. And
what I did want to do is have a bit of
an applause for uh Zay and her team
because I don't think anyone's really
recognized what they did. It was
incredible.
when you get into some of the weeds, and
I won't go too far because I know how
many minutes do I have left because I
was overtime last time. Ah, I'm good.
All right. Uh, there's a lot that goes
into it. I mean, it's not simply a
matter of, you know, sketching out a few
drawings, writing up a couple
paragraphs, and we're off to the races.
There was over,200 pages of detailed
design. It's the nuts and bolts making
it work. And you got to hammer out the
details, otherwise you have an
unsuccessful project. So, you know,
approximately 37 detailed drawings. I
looked at it again and it's actually
more because they're subsets of
drawings. That said, there was, you
know, about 37 main ones. You go through
the process once you get into
construction of clarification questions
and submissions and approvals. And it's
not it's not a straight path to success.
There's back and forth. There's going to
be, you know, let's be really candid,
there's going to be arguments because
that's the nature of the beast. You
should be doing that. No, I'm doing
this. And sometimes there's not clarity
in the written specification. As much as
you want to do it, you can't take
everything into consideration. That's
kind of life.
Some of the changes, and I was exposed
to it during the process. Um, and again,
I'm not trying to beat up here on
anything. I want everyone just to
realize what some of the challenges were
during the process. So, initially the
bore fields, the three of them were all
in a vertical configuration.
There was a change made into the angled
bore holes in one of the three bore
fields. That in and of itself causes
some some issues understanding
will the angled borer field with now
quad loops as opposed to single Ubends
perform to the level required for the
system to operate properly and support
the building loads anticipated. So you
can probably imagine there was a lot of
back and forth. What's going on with
these angled bore holes? We had to
remodel this, remodel that. It's not
simple as okay, we're just going to
start angling them out. Doesn't work
that way.
Again, the the single Uband versus the
quad loop, you're looking what is the
capacity? What is is there an increase?
And if so, what's the impact on the
total system? Those have all got to be
calculated. And again, this is something
that doesn't happen quickly. There's a
lot of back and forth. There's a whole
hierarchy of I have a question as an
engineer. I'm not an engineer, but if
we're an engineering firm over to the um
the owner Eversource back down to a
contractor, there's a whole system of
checks and balances. That's also meaning
time consumption.
Um
what an interesting change that happened
is the North America compliant
collection vaults. Does everyone know
what I mean by a collection vault or am
I talking Greek here? That's where you
have a bunch of bore holes that come
into a collection point and that box if
you like and it's usually made from
highdensity polyethylene. There are
concrete boxes as well. They are
subterranean. They're buried and then
from there you have a supply and return
going in over to the pump house. In this
case, there was a change made between
the North American compliant vaults and
what was put in on the angled bore hole
vaults, a European spec. On the face of
it, you go, what's the difference? There
is. you end up with different pipe sizes
between a European spec, which is a DIN
spec, versus a North American spec,
which is in this particular case, we use
IPS, which is iron pipe size. Getting
those two to marry up sounds easy. It's
not. And it ends up being a potential
area of concern into the future. The
other last point on changes and impact,
those angled bore holes. Now we're going
under wetlands before they weren't. So
there's a whole regulatory process that
has to be adhered to applications,
approvals, etc. So back to what Nikki
Bruno was saying yesterday, this started
Zam, correct me if I'm wrong, 2019 is
when things really got moving.
>> Uh the initial proposal was in the fall
2019 for the Department of Public
Utility
>> till today. So you can imagine one more
step that's going to unfortunately delay
things or potentially delay things and
that's the whole communication
um component that's vital between all
parties and is it smooth? Is it
confrontational? These are all things
you have to look at when you're doing a
large project like this.
Um you've seen the picture. That's what
the angled bore holes look like. Um it's
a proven technology. It makes a whole
lot of sense. You're having a very small
footprint up top at surface and then
those bore holes spllay out and you have
the separation between the bore holes so
you're not having thermal interference
between them. It allows at the surface
to have less um
impact if you like. You're not taking up
as much room. In this particular case,
the the the project didn't have to redo
the whole um parking lot in a repave.
They had a smaller area.
Some of the areas, and they're a little
hard to see, but this is the one going
to point it out. And you've probably
seen this picture here,
uh and as well as up there. Those are
the European vaults that I was talking
about. They are substantially different
from a North American vault. Uh,
that's an area of concern moving
forward.
Um, I'm going to pick on you, Brock.
Those pipes, your best guess is is a
good idea or a bad idea on the left.
As far as
>> sounds like a traping
>> in comparison to a regular vault.
>> I Yeah, it's unconventional for what I'm
used to seeing and just the way it's
laid out.
>> Yep. Okay. And that's that's the basic
consensus. People looked at this picture
and went, "Wow, there's some some
potential concerns down the road." The
picture on the right is where those bore
holes where you can see them coming up
here. These ones here, they're all like
that. They get tied together. The
problem with there, not problem, the
issue, the concern is if you look at the
pipe on the right, you can see some of
those are basically being compressed.
That shouldn't be happening for a
long-term reliability because ultimately
this gets backfilled, gets paved, and
then you can potentially, this is a
parking lot, have big trucks on top
pushing down, pushing down. So, it's an
area of concern that again in retrospect
may have been addressed differently.
That's the vault. Um,
they're used in Europe all the time.
There's nothing wrong with them. They're
just not North America compliant. They
have components inside, particularly PCV
plastic. Uh if anyone was here this
morning, the standard in North America
says you're not using PVC in these
systems, subterranean.
So that's the below the wetlands. Um,
it's not a huge issue so long as you get
the proper uh approvals. The wetlands
are an area of concern for everybody and
you have to make sure you're dotting
eyes and crossing tees.
Um, again, just a quick uh takeaways.
Communication is key. I mean, that's in
I know we've heard that repetitively.
it came to the forefront and this one in
particular when changes happened and
they were somewhat
unconventional. We'll leave it at that.
That change from the single U bend to
the double U bend again add some
complexity to the whole issue and from a
modeling and uh performance point of
view required a lot of redoing and then
the materials used um are not North
American compliant. Not that's the end
of the world. It's just to be
recognized.
That's it. I'm Oh, good. I didn't go
over time. I'm zero minutes. Perfect.
[Applause]