hello everyone my name is Emily Nez I'm
co-founder and CEO of deline um I am a
PhD candidate in biological engineering
in seale and I have about seven years
experience Building Systems pharmacology
models at companies like fizer and
astroica my co-founder Jad ikbal is an
is an expert on digital transformation
Solutions and Ai and delineate is a
multidisciplinary team it's growing we
have about 20 plus engineers and
researchers dedicated to applying AI to
accelerate analysis
workflows so computational analysis can
be really powerful this can look
different in different fields it can be
building AI models it can be doing more
traditional statistical modeling um but
it has a really big problem in that the
workflow is really scattered it takes a
lot of manual effort to put together
structured clean data sets from very
many disperate sources um so we work a
lot in the biofarma space
um and talking with our customers it can
take teenss of scientists months to put
together a single data set so delineates
goal is to make that faster using our
custom trained models to process all of
this unstructured information into
insightful assets um so we work a lot
with research papers um specifically the
plots and graphs getting that numerical
information out um but we also process
websites and databases we use our models
to structure this to to clean it um and
deliver data sets that are fit for
purpose but also code to generate um
those models to analyze that data and we
can also generate
reports so we're building an all-in-one
research web tool um that starts from
search so AI enhanced search to help you
find uh those documents that have the
data that you need um all of that gets
put into one place and then um of course
the the meat of our of our tool our
really core competency is that
extraction of the data getting that
numerical information out but combining
that with a contextual understanding of
where that data came from and we also
have a platform where you can analyze
the data um inside that same Tool uh
using our AI assistant so the right
model with the right
data so as a case study we were able to
generate a data set for AI model
training for a top Pharma company so we
processed over 900 research papers uh
using our custom computer vision methods
we extracted the numerical information
behind all the graphs combine that with
our llm agents that gave a contextual
understanding of how that data was
collected and that was packaged into a
data set that was essentially plug-
Inplay for their AI model so we
generated uh 23,000 data points for for
them so what's really different about us
versus other Solutions you could go to
um so really we're fit for purpose data
extraction any data set that you can
think of we can help you build so the
inputs to this would be a semantic um
description of the goal of your analysis
and the data criteria so what should the
columns look like and then um The Source
the sources get processed using that so
delineate will extract the relevant
information from across the text tables
and figures um and then put it together
in this analysis ready data
set so really you know we have these
fine-tuned models for data extraction
that really is another thing that sets
us apart um we're all in one place which
simplifies the workflow saves time um
and we're also 100% auditable so you can
see exactly where every data point came
from um you know why a line of code was
created so we've made a lot of traction
to date I'm really proud of what our
team has accomplished so we have data
service contracts with two top 10 Pharma
companies and we're going to be
acknowledged in some of their upcoming
Publications um we recently became a
preferred vendor of data sets for one
top 10 Pharma company um we're going to
speak at the American Society of
clinical pharmacology and Therapeutics
soon um and we received early acceptance
to why combinators winner 2025 batch so
that will be starting
soon and we're really looking to partner
really with any companies that have
needs related to Data Mining and
structuring of complex information um
but you know we have a lot of traction
in biofarm so we would really love to uh
talk to anyone in biofarma as well um
please uh reach out to us in our email
um or you can find us on the table
outside thank you thank you so much
Emily