Thank you everyone for coming back after
the coffee break. Um our next session
our moderator is uh Kurt Newton stepping
in. uh the previous moderator is okay
but she won't be ava a available for
this session. Uh and with that I'll pass
it on to Kurt.
>> All right. Uh coming out of our our
first session we now you know where it
was I think was teed up in a really
interesting way with the kind of the
final discussion what's going on with
the sort of human side of this the the
social uh decision making the
motivations and such. we get into the
the the human landscape for these
networks and we have you know again a a
wonderful series of three uh speakers uh
starting with Nathan Phillips uh and
then uh we'll hear from Chris Rae and
last uh Kelsey Worth and then as we did
with the previous session then we'll
we'll go from the presentations into uh
into a Q&A session. So over to you
Nathan.
>> Right. Thank you, uh, Kurt. And let's
see, is this the slide advancer thingy?
Okay, great. All right. Well, I'm here
to share with you how a mildmannered
forest ecologist
ended up in a room with engineers and
law experts and policy people and
activists
uh to work on the energy transition. So,
I'm going to give you that ecological
viewpoint of this energy transition. And
it started for me as this mildmannered
uh ecologist who learned uh stumbled out
of my lane and learned that gas leaks
damage trees. So I study the plumbing of
trees and I wanted to know why what's
going on. Uh this is in Newton about
three blocks away from where I live and
seeing uh the loss of the tree canopy
was really heartbreaking as a as a
person uh but also as a scientist like
what is going on and from that moment
things started moving. I had an
accidental toolkit for understanding the
problem of methane leaks because I was
looking at how greenhouse gases are
exchanged from soils and leaves and the
same kind of equipment could be used to
document where this greenhouse gas was
leaking from the streets and sidewalks.
So we got funded to do a research study
in the city of Boston where we
documented 3,356 gas leaks across the
city. Uh that was in 2012. And this is
where as an ecologist
I started thinking about kind of
biomimicry and thinking about the eco
the city as an ecosystem. We had a grant
called urban metabolism at the time from
the National Science Foundation and it
was the lens of using living things to
think about how cities function. And as
a tree physiologist, it became clear,
you know, this gas network, this thing
that's having this kind of metabolic
problem is like a tree. It's got trunks
and it's got branches and twigs and we
we need to fix this uh problem. And
that's where the the idea of the
transition started to come in. Uh can we
prune the tree? Can the tree retract and
a new system uh grow from there? Now
things were happening at the same time
like the collapse of the gas system in
the Marramac Valley where uh system
level failures were happening and we
realized in talking with folks like Zanb
and Audrey and Heat that to solve
problems like that we need to think
bigger. We need to make the problem
bigger. And coming back to the gas leaks
problems on the streets and sidewalks of
of of Boston and the greater Boston
area, it became apparent to me that I
needed to think bigger as an ecologist.
And when I started to see things like
new trees, this is in Roslandale, being
planted into active gas leaks and the
money that was being spent and the labor
and energy that was being spent to plant
urban street trees in a place where we
knew they were going to die. So the gas
in the soil here is at about you can't
see it but it's like 15% in the soil.
That tree was not going to live. Um to
see things like uh okay the fixes made
after the problem has wre havoc on the
tree. So there's the empty tree pit and
there's the patch that fixed the gas
leak after the uh fact. So it became
apparent to me that what we call
infrastructure ecology
is about the wires and the pipes and the
streets and and all of those things. But
it's also about the knowledge networks
and the systems and the institutions
that need to communicate to actually get
the problem uh fixed. the coordination.
Uh just here's another example in what
we uh call the circle of death in Newton
which is right over the mass pike where
you can see the new pavement here. You
can see the line where the uh lighter
grade shade shade becomes darker and the
uh new pavement being cut up like two
weeks after it was put down to uh
address a gas leak. That's a 10-in cast
iron uh gas mane there. And so this
problem really I couldn't avoid as an
ecologist to think about how we need to
bring all of the stakeholders and we
need to think about the colllocated and
interdependent critical infrastructure
including the trees and everything else
as an ecosystem. That's the only way
we're going to solve this problem. And
so that's what inspired me so much about
being here and connecting with groups
like mothers out front and heat where we
weren't I was no longer being restricted
to my discipline of forest ecology. I
was connecting with people who were
thinking in a much more inclusive and
holistic uh manner about all of the
actors and entities that need to come
together. So I feel like a more holistic
uh ecologist. Uh this exemplifies to me
the way we need to see beyond the
surface and make the connections uh that
are there uh under the streets uh and
with other stakeholders. And so what
continues this work the for me is being
involved in the uh project in Framingham
that is happening and to come back to my
uh profession as a tree physiologist and
an ecoysiologist is really fulfilling
because it's like a a circle has come
back around where we are now as part of
this big project with so many different
uh academic research researchers and
others. Uh my part of this is to come
back to look at tree health. So do these
thermal networks uh have any effect on
the tree canopy? Sometimes in in science
a nonresult is actually a really great
thing to have. And after uh our research
in two years of looking at the tree
canopy where this infrastructure has
gone in, we don't see any uh negative
impact on the trees. We're going to
continue to monitor this the urban
canopy in this area because there may be
some subtle changes. If you change the
thermal environment in the soil, there
may be a change in when the leaves come
out or when the leaves drop and it may
be species dependent. So, lots of
interesting questions, but really
gratifying to to know that there's we're
not seeing any negative impact on uh the
e the actual ecosystem and and just that
you know uh there was a term that a
famous uh thinker and writer and
philosopher came up with who was not an
ecologist but came up with a very
important ecological term called
succession. And that was Henry David
Thorough in conquered succession the
change in ecosystems over time and so
it's really gratifying to be part of a
project was which is looking at that
transition from our fossilfueled
infrastructure into this new
infrastructure where we're not seeing
negative impacts on the trees here and
we're likely to see a healthier tree
canopy in places like the place where I
saw the tree uh being damaged in my own
city of Newton. So, uh, thank you and
I'll leave it at that. There's my friend
Bob Aley, colleague and Margaret
Hendrickk.
Yeah. And