Today on Chalk Radio, we're talking with
economist John Gruber, whose lecture
videos have been [music] viewed millions
of times on our channel. We talk about
the role of trade-offs in everyday life.
>> Let's say you're dating someone and
you're thinking about marriage. Well,
you basically have a opportunity cost.
>> The intersection of economics and
emotions.
>> Like I said, the standard model of
economics is no room for emotion.
>> Oh, I don't know if I belong in
economics. Then what would you say to
that? and how his interest in economics
is largely driven by his passion for
healthcare.
>> And Louis Manand really inspired me that
we need to not just think about
something of political science as an
abstract concept, but really get our
hands dirty and think about how we can
make the world a better place.
>> And we asked the question, can AI fix
the economy?
>> First of all, you should feel bad for my
students who have to read this
handwriting.
>> Okay.
>> But I wrote uh
>> find out his answer and much more on
this episode of Chalk Radio. John, thank
you for being here today.
>> Great to be here, Sarah. Thanks for
having me. Oh, you're so welcome. Uh,
you're an economist, so obviously you
looked at the opportunity costs of
joining me here today. Um, so what are
some of the trade-offs you made to be
here?
>> Uh, it's a great question because that's
how economists look at everything. Uh,
we recognize that every action has an
alternative and that's part of why they
call us the dismal science because we
say nothing's free. Um, every time you
make a decision, there's something else
you could be doing instead. So, let's
take my decision to come here today. I
could be doing economic research, which
I love. Uh, I could be back doing some
of the administrative work I have to do
as chairman of the MIT economics
department. I could be home walking my
granddog who's at my house right now.
So, those are the opportunity costs.
What are the benefits? Well, the benefit
is that I feel that uh academia today
suffers from a lack of communication
with the public that we are not doing a
good enough job as academics talking to
the public, explaining why what we do is
so important to their lives and to our
country. I mean, as a consumer in
society, I certainly have a lot of
questions about economics that I'm
hoping you can help me unravel today as
we get into this. But how did you find
your way to economics?
>> Well, actually, it's a great chance to
talk about you as ring something that
represented my journey to economics.
Now, my journey to economics started as
a freshman at MIT in 1983. Um, I was one
of those kids who was good at math but
didn't really love math. Um and I took
1401 which is the course I now teach and
uh I uh fell in love with it. I said wow
you can use math to do really
interesting and worthwhile things and
not just proofs that I found abstract
but actually as I say in 1401 you can
actually do optimization problems that
solve people's lives. Uh and that was
very exciting for me. So my object I
brought is the MIT department of
economics hat. Uh I I didn't have
anything from 1983 I could bring but
this sort of represents the key step in
my journey was taking 1401 and just
obviously what a thrill it was to come
back in 1992 and get to join and be part
of this department and now ultimately
teach the course that turned me on to
economics.
>> Yeah. Um do you have a teacher in mind
that really helped hook you on to
economics and helped you show how
powerful these applications can be in
the real world?
>> You know there were so many great
undergrad teachers I had at MIT. I
really uh many of them and then became
my colleagues Jim Purba who taught me
1430 really turned me on to statistics.
Um I had the wonderful late Rudy Dorbush
teach me international economics. Bob
Solo, Nobel Prize wing economist taught
me macroeconomics. Uh I did Europs with
uh professors Dick Eouse and Peter Teman
and Rudy Dornbush. So I just had
wonderful mentors undergraduate here and
then went on to grad school at Harvard
and had great mentors there too. So I've
just been very lucky. We have an
incredible economics community here in
Cambridge and I've been lucky to benefit
from that.
>> So, let's talk about economics and human
decision-making. Um, you've noted in one
of your lectures that economics is
sometimes called the right-wing science
and I'm wondering if you could unpack
that for me and let me know if there's
more nuance to that thing.
>> It's not really called that. It's sort
of how I introduce to students that it's
sort of a fundamentally right-wing
science. What do I mean by that?
>> Yeah. What I mean by that is economics
has a set of basic models that are
unbelievably powerful in describing much
of the world and those basic models make
a series of assumptions under which the
market knows best. So take the basic
core assumptions of economic models and
run them through. They deliver the
outcome. The best thing you can do is
just let the market run and get out of
the way. Now obviously in reality that's
wrong. And what I do in the second half
of my course is teach all the reasons
why that's wrong. And then I go on and
teach another course at MIT called 1441
public economics where I spend much more
time talking about these market failures
and the role the government has in in a
properly functioning economy. But the
point is where economics start is this
notion that Adam Smith had of the
invisible hand. The notion the market is
the best way to allocate goods across
people and allocate production across
firms which is absolutely true. the
market is a much better allocation
mechanism than is say a communist
government. That said, an unfettered
market will not get it right because
there are a lot of failures in those
markets. And that's why economists tend
to think that the right answer is sort
of a if you'll think about if you think
about an economy as bowling, think of
sort of capitalism with with gutter
guards. The idea is that there should be
freedom to bowl the ball, but there
should be some protection against really
damaging going to the gutter and and
ending a disastrous outcome.
>> That's a really interesting way to think
about it. Um, talking about models
themselves, like what are some like
tricky human behaviors that economic
models can help us make sense of those
decisions?
>> Let me give you uh a couple of examples.
Okay.
>> So, one great example is when I give in
lecture about um concert tickets.
>> Okay.
>> So, I talk in lecture about the time
that I like the band Journey. Uh Journey
wasn't really Journey. It's like a
Journey cover band. They have like the
new singer. And I bought tickets and it
was $250 for my wife and I. And then I
looked at list and I thought, you know,
I really don't want to go. I'm not that
excited to go.
>> Okay.
>> So, I'm going to sell these tickets.
Now, a common intuition would be, well,
you paid 250, you should ask 250, and
you should be upset if you get less than
250. But that would be wrong.
>> Okay, how's that?
>> Why is that wrong? Cuz the 250 is gone.
Economics, we're all about looking
forward to the next step in the
decision. The 250 is gone. The next step
is
>> how much would I be willing to pay to
still go? So, in other words, if I say,
"Look, I wouldn't go even if I I
wouldn't bend any money to go to this
concert, then I should be willing to
accept any price over a dollar for those
tickets because I get zero value from
going. So, as long as I get a dollar for
the tickets, I'm better off. The 250 is
gone. Okay, I already made that
decision. That's gone." So, really, I
should say to myself, well, if I get
less than say 100, what I say at that
point, I'd rather go.
>> Uh, and that's the way I should make
that decision. That's not very
intuitive. That's tricky, right?
>> No. And it's also like I'm not sure
that's real life. Like let's say I spend
250, I can't go for some some reason,
right? That doesn't mean I don't want
the 250 back.
>> You want the 250, but it also doesn't
mean that you should feel like the 250
is the right answer at that point. If
you literally can't go, then the right
answer is whatever the market will bear.
>> And uh but the point is, I think a lot
of people will kick themselves. Why did
I buy those tickets? I can't go. Well,
if you can't go for a reason you didn't
anticipate and you get less, that's not
your fault. That's where the market is.
>> Mhm. I mean, I find it so interesting to
think about how emotions and economics
intersect.
>> Like I said, the standard model of
economics is no room for emotion.
>> Oh, I don't know if I belong in
economics. Then what would you say to
>> you do you do because
>> here's the way I like to think about
building up economics. There's a basic
model that doesn't have room for
emotion. It hasn't room for preferences.
You can like one thing more than
another, but that's all those
preferences are all optimized. You
choose the best possible outcome. in a
calm rational way that doesn't feature
emotions.
>> Okay,
>> that model is unbelievably powerful.
>> So much of the world can be described by
that, but a lot can't.
>> Yeah.
>> So, what we do in economics, we start
with that basic core model, that
right-wing model, if you will. Okay. And
then we build on it. And when we build
on it through the field of behavioral
economics, which is bringing psychology
into economics and saying emotions
matter,
>> problems making decisions matter, people
aren't able to control their actions in
a way they'd like to. We build that in
and in some sense what I teach in 1401
is a scaffolding
>> okay
>> of a basic model that by itself does
quite well but you can build on to
really explain more and more of human
behavior.
>> You know the statistician George box
said that all models are wrong but some
are useful. The point of a model is that
it's not a description. It's not a
perfect description of reality. It was a
perfect description of reality it
wouldn't be a model. It would be
reality. So are you saying that like
those of us out in the world not in an
economics department might be kind of
using these models without thinking
about
>> Oh we are absolutely using these models.
Part of what is exciting about taking
economics is it opens your eyes to
realize the things you're already doing
>> and puts a framework to be consistent in
how you apply that.
>> So that's really what what we're doing
is sort of it really is innate human
nature in many ways that we're modeling
like I said initially without the
emotion. We add that in later.
>> Um, but basically it's it's a set of
tools that help you sort of understand
why people do what they do.
>> I can imagine that would be really
important in business.
>> It's very important in business. It's
very important in life. I'm I'm I'm an
economic imperialist. There's no
decision you can talk to me about that
can't you can't bring an economic model.
One of the most famous economists was
Gary Becker. He was at the University of
Chicago and Gary Becker developed the
economic models of love, economic models
of marriage, economic models of crime,
economic models of discrimination. All
things which really economics has a
framework to put on.
>> What? I haven't really thought about it
in that way before.
>> Well, think about an economic model of
marriage.
>> Okay,
>> let's say you're dating someone and
you're thinking about marriage. Well,
you basically have a opportunity cost
>> of that marriage and you have a
trade-off of you are gaining certain
things by being married and giving up
certain things by being married. And
economics can bring a framework to help
you evaluate that decision.
>> Hm, this is interesting. Yeah, I'm going
to have to give this some thought. Uh
you've especially thought a lot about
how economics can be applied in health
care. Yeah. Like you're basically a
healthc care economist. Would that be
the right
>> a lot of what I do for my time. Yeah.
>> So what are some ways that you're using
economics to think about the inequities
in our health care system and how models
can help us address some of those
inequities? Can you like give us some
tangible examples?
>> Yeah. So so here would be a tangible
example. Um, a tangible example would be
we have many uninsured individuals in
America. About 30 million uninsured
individuals.
>> Yeah.
>> And you might ask, well, is that worth
doing anything about? We probably have
more than 30 million people who don't
have beautiful flat screen televisions.
Are we really going to do something
about that? I don't think we should. So,
why is health insurance different from a
flat screen television? And what
economics tells is different because the
market for health care suffers from a
set of market failures that the market
for flat screen televisions doesn't.
Flat screen televisions is a basic 1401
model. You got supply, demand, the
market works. Health care, there's a
number of problems. For example, if I
don't get health insurance and as a
result I get sick and I come in here
today and I cough on you and you get
sick, then I've imposed a cost on you
that I'm not incurring. We call that an
externality. That's a problem with the
healthare market. Another problem with
the health care market is that people
might not understand the risk of getting
sick. Many people, we have what we call
the young invincibles. People who are
35, they're like, I'll never get sick.
Especially guys, you know, I can't get
pregnant. I'm never getting sick. What
do I need health insurance for? They're
wrong. They can get by a car. They can
get sick for many reasons. That's a
failure of information or a failure of
reasoning.
>> Um, we have failures on the market side.
for example, um, economic models work
best when markets are competitive, when
there's many competitors trying to
compete for your business. Well, that's
not true in healthcare. If you're a
hospital, if you're a hospital on
Nantucket, you got a monopoly because
you're the hospital. Uh, you're there's
no competition. People aren't going to
take a ferry to get their heart attack
dealt with. So, for all these reasons,
we need to bring in the tools, other
tools to help think about how we fix
problems in the healthcare markets. Can
you tell me a little bit about your
involvement in the Affordable Care Act?
>> Yeah. So, um, the proper way to make
government policy is to understand as
much as possible what affects changes,
what effects the policy will do, to not
fly by the seat of your pants, but to
really have a model,
>> yes,
>> of how it will work.
>> I developed that a model like that. So
basically I developed what was called a
giant computer micro simulation model
which essentially was a fancy way for
saying was a lot of computer code that
could basically use the best available
economic evidence to say to a policy
maker if you do policy X Y will happen.
If you do this policy this many people
gain health insurance coverage this is
what it'll cost. Um that model was um
used by Governor Romney state of
Massachusetts to help figure out the
best way to set up our healthcare reform
here in Massachusetts. Once we'd set it
up, I then got to be on the board that
actually implemented the healthcare
reform. So I got to actually go from
abstract academic to actually making
decisions like what health insurance
should people get, which was very eye
opening. I did that for a decade and
then I was able to bring that model to
bear on the national level uh working
for both President Obama and the
Congress to help them understand the
trade-offs and setting the afford
setting up the Affordable Care Act.
>> What did that feel like for you as a
person? That's like a tremendous
responsibility that affects
>> Well, I mean this is this is this is
what's wonderful about not being the
politician and being the adviser.
>> Yeah.
>> Which is [clears throat]
it's not that much responsibility
because I mean basically it's an
exciting opportunity to be involved. But
ultimately the advantage and
disadvantage of my role as an expert and
not a politician is I hand them the
numbers and then I walk away.
>> So I can say to them, look, here's the
choices you can make.
>> But ultimately they make the choices.
Now that can be very frustrating because
they can make a choice. I may have view
on those choices and it's not my choice.
On the other hand, it's also less
stressful because it's not my choice. So
in some sense my my job it's stressful
because I wanted the best possible job
right
>> but my job is to present them with a set
of options but ultimately it's the
policy makers that decide.
>> I mean all your work in healthcare it
came from somewhere you know why health
care of all the things.
>> Great question. So um as an
undergraduate at MIT uh I was very
inspired by a political science course I
took a professor who was here named
Louis Manand and Louis Manand really
inspired me that we need to not just
think about something like political
science as an abstract concept but
really get our hands dirty and think
about how we can make the world a better
place and it really inspired me to think
about making the world a better place
and I really decided when I went to
economics that's what I wanted to do
with it
>> and in 1990 when I was searching around
for what I want to work on healthcare
was a very big topic IC it was sort of
the beginning of a real movement towards
what became eventually the Clinton
healthcare reform thinking about new
models of universal healthcare and I
realized this is an area that economics
had a lot to contribute to and that I
had a lot to contribute to in trying to
make the world a better place
>> it's so central like when I think about
employment health care and health
insurance is such a huge part of it you
know it affects jobs and like what
decisions I'm going to make about where
I'll work
>> well first of all it's 18% of our
economy it's the biggest sector of our
economy Um, it's the largest single
government expenditure at both the state
and national level. So just magnitudes,
it matters. But you're right, it affects
everything. We have an employment based
health insurance system in America.
About 60% of Americans get health
insurance from their employer. That
means an important part of your job
decision is your health insurance
decision. An important part of an
employer's compensation decision is how
they're going to get how much health
insurance they're going to give their
employees. It's it's a huge sector of of
getting jobs. So healthcare jobs is one
of the main drivers of economic growth
here in Massachusetts. It it it
permeates everything, not to mention
permeating our actual physical health.
Our health is determined by many things,
primarily our genetics. Uh but a lot of
us by the health care we get and so it
it affects all aspects of our lives.
>> I know in some ways it feels a little
unfair like I make decisions about my
own health based on what my insurance
will cover.
>> You know, this is the challenge. Um the
challenge is let's go back to this
conversation started. There's no free
lunch. You can't have it all.
>> Yeah.
>> We would love a world where we all got
to get whatever care we wanted whenever
we wanted from whoever we wanted.
>> Yeah.
>> We could have that world if we only
spend a lot more on healthare.
>> The restrictions that are put in place
that cause people to hate insurance
companies also keep our premiums down.
>> If the insurance companies got rid of
those restrictions, we'd have more
choice and higher health insurance
premiums.
>> So trade-offs.
>> So there's a trade-off. So the example I
teach in my class I like is that
students in my class don't remember what
it was like to fly in the 1970s.
>> The 1970s flying in airplanes was
awesome.
>> What was it like?
>> Huge leg room, free food, real
silverware, free booze. It was in coach.
It was incredible. Um uh and
unbelievably expensive and most
Americans never flew.
>> Then we deregulated the airlines in the
late 1970s and allowed air much more
entry of airlines. prices came way down
and service got way worse.
>> Okay?
>> Now, people today complain about the
worst service, but they don't complain
about the low prices.
>> Okay?
>> And if it really is true that people
didn't like the bad service, there would
emerge an airline which would be like
the old airlines, super nice and super
expensive. Now, we have charter jets,
but the bottom line is people have
revealed they'd rather pay low prices
for mediocre flights than pay high
prices for better flights.
>> There's trade-offs in life. The the
difference with flights is it's pretty
much for the market to decide. Yeah.
With healthcare, there's a government
role in deciding that. There's a
government role in, for example,
deciding what's the minimum insurance
package people should have. The
government has a role with airlines,
too. We decide on safety.
>> Sure.
>> But we don't decide on leg room as a
government. We don't decide on food. We
don't decide on baggage fees.
>> Yes, that's clear.
>> When we go to healthare, the government
has a role in deciding, look, what's a
minimum acceptable health care package?
What's, you know, what's a reasonable
way that we pay for our healthcare
services? there's more of a role, but
ultimately you can't avoid the
trade-offs.
>> So, I have a question about models. So,
you put your professor hat on. So, I've
been hearing a lot about um preference
pricing, AI surveillance pricing.
>> So, I'd like you to explain what that
means, but then also what does that do
to basic the basic economic model of
supply and demand?
>> Yep. So, at the heart of economics is a
trade-off between equity and efficiency.
>> Okay. Okay, what do I mean by that? A
lot of basically think of it as how big
is the pie versus how you slice up the
pie.
>> Okay,
>> and what determines the size of the pie
is can we make the best match between
what people want and what gets produced.
Okay, is a key thing there. What
algorithmic pricing does is it really
improves that match because it lets me
say, well, Sarah really likes this thing
and so I'm going to make sure that she
gets it. Now, I'm going to charge her a
higher price, but if I didn't charge a
higher price, I might not make it. So
let's say
>> but that's such a benevolent way to
think about
>> No, let me finish. Let me
>> I feel like that's not true.
>> Okay, it is true. So the thing is if you
don't want it, you don't have to buy it.
>> Okay, but that's for like things that I
want. What about basic needs like buying
milk for my child? Like uh I won't I
won't name the stores, but you can do
online grocery shopping and they clearly
know what I buy and like at what price
I'm willing to buy it, right? and I went
on a site like that and they wouldn't
tell me my price until I added it to the
cart.
>> Okay, that is a great example of why you
can't just leave the free market alone.
>> Yeah,
>> here here's a different question. You go
online and they say, "Aha, I know Sarah
likes this, so I'm going to start
raising the price of that sort of thing
to her."
>> Yeah, that feels bad.
>> It feels unfair. But then that comes the
second issue, which is equity.
>> Okay. which is what happens to that
money they make from that. Now, if they
take that money and it goes to Jeff
Bezos, that is unfair.
>> Mhm.
>> But if Amazon is in a competitive
marketplace, we can go back to whether
they are. But imagine they were.
>> Okay.
>> Then that money wouldn't go to Jeff
Bezos. That would mean they'd charge
less for something else. In a really
competitive market, their profits are
limited. So, they're going to make money
off you. They're going to make less
money off someone else.
>> So, that's sort of a redistribution
issue. That's an efficiency issue. Now,
that's different if all the extra money
goes to Jeff Bezos.
>> And that's once again why we can't just
leave the market alone, right? Why you
need a government involved to make sure
that you have enough competition. But in
a standard economic model,
>> if we have algorithmic pricing and
[clears throat] people's prices better
reflect their preferences,
>> then that makes things more efficient.
>> The question is whether it makes things
more equitable
>> and and so how are economists thinking
about this? Are they grappling with it?
This is a fairly new thing.
>> It's a fairly new thing. I think we're
early to grappling with it. Okay.
>> I think we are trying to think about um
essentially what you do when this
becomes exploitative.
>> Yeah.
>> Um because of lack of information.
That's one thing we need to think hard
about
>> whether it is uh leads to increased
market failures because of
monopolization of markets and so the
money just goes to Jeff Bezos and not to
not to pick on him but you know what I
mean.
>> And also
>> the fact that there's an a fundamental
inequity. So I you're right. I made it.
I made the good case. Let me do the
opposite case.
>> Okay.
>> Let's say that
>> you're well off
>> and you can shop from lots of options.
>> Okay.
>> So, they know if they price high to
Sarah here, Sarah's going to go over
there and buy it. Now, imagine a poor
person in inner city who only has one
store they can go to.
>> Yeah.
>> That store could then say, "Aha, I've
used algorithmic determination to decide
this person has no car. They have
nowhere else to go. I'm going to charge
them a lot."
>> Yeah. Terrible.
>> That is unfair.
>> Yes. But that is has to separate
separate the efficiency from the
fairness
>> and the proper role of societies to
address both.
>> But I wanted to go back to AI for a
second
>> and just how economists are thinking
about the role of AI before we started
the podcast. I asked you a question and
you wrote an answer and you haven't
shown me the answer yet, but I asked you
um can AI fix the economy? So I'm
wondering if you could show me your
answer now. And you first of all you
feel bad for my students because they
have to read this handwriting.
>> Okay.
>> But I wrote uh it's up to us.
>> It's up to us.
>> And basically what do I mean by that?
What I mean by that is really paring a
wonderful book
>> called power and progress by my
colleagues my Nobel Prize winning
colleagues Doras Mogul and Simon
Johnson.
>> They talk about through the whole
history of technology
>> that technology can always be used for
good or for bad. And really it's up to
us to direct it to decide which
direction it's going to go in.
>> Mhm.
>> So often asked this question which is I
feel like social media has led to very
many ter tr ter tr ter tr ter tr ter tr
ter tr ter tr ter tr ter tr ter tr
terrible outcomes in our society. And I
often think 25 years ago if we knew what
we know now what would we have done
differently with social media? What
could we have done differently? I don't
really know the answer but I feel like
that's a conversation we we should be
having now about AI. We shouldn't get
behind. We know bad things are going to
come out of AI. We know good things have
come out come out of AI just like bad
and good things have come with social
media. We need to be getting ahead of
the bad things in a way we didn't with
social media.
>> So it's up to us how AI is going to
affect the economy and how it's going to
affect life.
>> It's up to whether we establish the
proper regulatory frameworks and the
proper way of thinking about it so that
we can deal with the negative effects
while capturing the positive effects.
>> Yeah. So it's sort of like the bowling
analogy that you use. We need the
gutters full.
>> Yeah.
>> We need some gutter guards.
>> We need some gutter guards. Like when
you bowl with your little kid and you
got the gutter guards, we need some
gutter guards to allow the ball to rock
around the alley, but so we don't go in
the gutters, which could be existential
destruction rather than a ball in the
alley. But the bottom line is we have
lots of hard questions that this is
raising, but it's still early days. I
know it's moving fast, but it's still
early days. I guess I'm not optimistic
that I see people engaging with with
these hard questions in a constructive
way. And I feel like we need we need
disinterested people, expert people who
aren't there to make a buck out of it to
really start thinking hard about these
things.
>> Um, you said in one of your lectures,
maybe about two years ago, which was
like pre where we are now with AI,
[laughter]
>> you said um, and I'll read you the
quote, um, any government, no matter how
large and how benevolent, cannot make
the enormous massive quantity of
billions and billions of decisions that
need to be made. Think about every good
we consume in America. a government
deciding how much of it to make and
literally who gets it. It's
overwhelming.
>> This is, you know, this is from my
introductory lecture to the class
>> where I talk about the fundamental
nature of capitalism. Capitalism has a
bad name uh right now in many circles.
But let's remember that what capitalism
is essentially about letting the market,
the invisible hand of the market make
those billions of decisions. The
opposite is a what we call a command
economy which is often in communist
societies which is where the government
would make those decisions. I don't
really see AI making it feasible to have
a command economy because ultimately
that's about people's preferences and
things. I I think AI comes to earlier
conversation AI is going to really match
people more with exactly the goods they
want and need and match the production
of that and then the question is who
benefits from that. Mhm.
>> I'd like to think there's a world where
consumers benefit, where they get goods
they wouldn't have otherwise gotten at
prices below what they were willing to
pay and get some surplus from that. But
that might not happen. Like I said, you
know, and like Jeron Stein's book
highlights, technological advancement is
a choice. We may instead end up in a
world where consumers get exploited and
a few monopolists get very rich and that
would be a bad outcome indeed. Mhm.
You've been an avid publisher on open
courseware which we've so appreciated
and I often think how can MIT justify
giving their proprietary content away
for free in this economy.
>> Uh it's a great question. Um I think
that it actually relates to another
discussion we had which is that tuition
MIT is very high. Uh now if your if your
income's below $200,000 a year it's free
but above that it's very high. And
people often say, "Well, that's unfair.
Uh, people shouldn't pay that much." But
you have to remember what's done with
that money. Part of what's done with
that money is producing things like OCW.
We have to remember that organizations
like MIT
do not break even on every transaction.
They win in some transactions, they lose
in some transactions. They're trying to
serve their broad public function. One
of those functions is educating the
public. And MIT is willing to lose money
in OCW because they know it's very
important to get that information out
there. So, John, you've shared a lot of
your thinking and a lot of your teaching
on MIT Open Courseware, which we're
really grateful for. I'm wondering if
you could tell our listeners and our
viewers what some of those offerings
are.
>> Yeah, so um 1401, the course that turned
me on to economics. Um I've now I now
have an updated version of OCW. I had a
version from 2018. There's now a version
from 2023 up on OCW. We're about to put
up uh the other course I teach at MIT,
which is 1441, which is public
economics. um which is really about the
role of the government in the economy
sort of taking as a starting point that
there are these market failures and
problems and what should the government
do about them and those are my two main
offerings on OCW there's enormous number
of offerings from the economics
department as chairman of the department
I want to also say yeah uh from the
economics department at large there's
many courses that people should look up
and take we have wonderful teachers and
great material and the last resource I'd
point out is actually um you know it's
funny Sarah you're probably too young to
remember but when I was young and you'd
fly in a plane you'd actually talk to
the person next to you before phones.
Oh, wow.
>> You'd actually talk because there was
nothing else to do. Um uh and the number
of times someone said to me, "Oh,
economics. I hated that class." And I
thought, "How can that be?" And I
realized it's really badly taught,
especially kids who take it in high
school.
>> About 80,000 kids a year take AP take
the AP microeconomics exam. And they're
typically taught by the gym teacher or
the history teacher or someone who
doesn't really understand economics. So,
I took a sobatical and made with MITx an
AP economics high school class. If you
go to MITx, it's uh microeconomics MITx.
And that's a I think a really good
resource for high schoolers and others
who really want to get started with
economics.
>> John, thank you so much for being here.
>> It's my pleasure. Thanks for having me,
Sarah.
>> You're so welcome.
[music]