the probabilistic method in
combinatorics is a powerful way to
demonstrate the existence of certain
special configurations and combinatorial
objects by introducing
Randomness in this video we will see a
one of the earliest examples of an
application of this method and it's used
to prove lower bounds to Ramsey numbers
now Ramsey numbers are interesting
objects in combinatorics and they're
defined as follows the Ramsey number
rkl is defined to be the smallest
integer n such that no matter how we
color the edges of a complete graph on N
vertices will denote such objects by KNN
so complete graph is n vertices with all
the edges all n choose two edges
uh available and if we color all such
edges each one of them either with red
or green so one of two colors then there
always exists a red KL red click on K
vertices or green click on L vertices
right so the raming number is the
smallest n such that this is possible so
to be more concrete let me
demonstrate an
example so r33
equals to six and what this means is the
following first if we have six
vertices and we color all the possible
six choose two edges each one with one
of two colors red or green so for
example maybe these edges are colored
green and the remaining edges are
colored red
then no matter how we do these colorings
there always exists a triangle which is
completely red or completely
Green in this example here you see
this is a triangle that is completely
red on the other hand if we start with
only five vertices
then it is possible to
color the
edges with one of two
colors right so color each edge with one
of two colors so that there's no
monochromatic
triangle okay so this is what it means
for r33 to be
six an important result in combinatorx
due to
Ramsey so this is known as Ramsey's
theorem and this was proved back
in the
1920s says
that this number rkl is always finite it
is always a well- defined number so as
long as n is large enough no matter how
we color the edges of a complete graph
on n vertic
there always exists a large
monochromatic either a large red K click
or a large green L
click what I want to prove in this video
is the following
theorem due to
ERS from the
1940s and ERS showed
that
rkk is bigger than 2 to the
k/2 for every integer K bigger than
three okay so this is a lower bound to
ring numbers and what it says that if
you have two few vertices namely if you
have 2 to the K over two vertices then
there is always a way to color the edges
with two colors so that there is no
monochromatic click on K
vertices a theorem is an important
foundational result and it's also one of
the earliest demonstrations of the
probabilistic method so we will see this
uh proof in this lecture in this
video in fact we will prove a slightly
more general
statement we will show that if two
integers n and
K
satisfy the following inequality n
choose K * 2 1 minus K choose 2 if this
quantity is less than
one so right now this is just some
formula it will come out of the proof so
let's not worry too much about
it
then
rkk is strictly larger than n
we will prove the second theorem and by
a calculation that is fairly
straightforward for which I will admit
one can use the second result to imply
the first
result okay so let us prove the second
theorem over here so what is it saying
if n satisfies certain inequalities so
that n is not too large then it is
possible to color the edges of a
complete graph on nver veres so that
there's no monochromatic click on K
vertices how do we find such a coloring
well let's do it
randomly so let's
color the
edges of a complete graph on K vertices
using two
colors uniformly and r
okay so meaning that for each Edge we
flip a coin if it comes up heads we
color it red if it comes up Tails we
color it
green and the goal is to find to show
that we can do this in such a way that
avoids having a monochromatic click of
size K so there are things that we want
to avoid and let us encode
bad events as follows for
every K
vertex
subset s of vertices there are n
vertices in total so for every K vertex
subset s we'll use a Subs to denote the
following bad event that we're trying to
avoid this is a
event that
s
induces
a
monochromatic
click okay it induces a monochromatic
click in this
coloring let's calculate the probability
that this occurs okay so what's the
probability that in this s which let's
say
case four for purpose of this
illustration you know of the six edges
all of them have the same color well
there are two possible colors and for
each of those colors the probability
that all of these edges are of that
color is this quantity 2 to the minus K
choose 2 so this is the probability 2 *
2 to Theus K choose 2 this is the
probability that s all the edges in s
are entirely of the same
color well
what about the probability that there is
some click of size K in the graph that
it's
monochromatic but that's really the
quantity that we care
about so let's consider the probability
that there
is
some
monochromatic click
of
size K in this
graph well if there's some monochromatic
click of size k then it must be one of
the s's so we can do what's called a
union
bound to Upper bound this probability by
the
sum of the individual event
probabilities so summing over o subsets
s of the vertices with size exactly K of
the probability that a Subs this event
occurs
okay in this summation there are n
choose K terms and each term is this
probability that we calculated
earlier and you see this expression it
was the expression in the hypothesis of
the theorem and we assume that it is
strictly less than
one and this is why we had this
expression in the
theorem okay great so the probability
that there exists some monochromatic
click of size K is strictly less than
one and
thus with positive probability
a random
coloring
has no
monochromatic
click of size
K okay and that's basically what we are
trying to do we are trying to demonst
rate the existence of a coloring with no
monochromatic click of size K and we
show that in fact by doing everything at
random the random coloring succeeds with
positive
probability and
therefore such an object must exist
right
thus such
coloring
exists and this finishes the proof of
this theorem over here that we trying to
demonstrate and as I mentioned earlier
by a more routine calculation which we
will not do here one can deduce air dous
result from this theorem and in fact by
a more careful calculation that again I
will not do one can show an even more
precise lower bound the rkk is bigger
than the following ASM totic one over
the following constant e * < tk2 so here
e is the natural constant around
2.71 plus a term that goes to zero as K
goes to
Infinity time k 2 to the k/2 so this is
a much more precise uh bound that one
can get out of analyzing the consequence
of this theorem that we just
proved in the next part of this video we
will refine or come up with additional
techniques that allows us to improve the
slower bound but for now let me make a
comment about this
technique what the stum shows is that by
doing a random coloring there is a
positive probability that this coloring
gets us what we
want and in fact the probability that
this coloring doesn't get us what we
want is this quantity here which is not
only less than one but it is actually
quite small it is very very small so if
you for example on a computer flip these
random coins and come up with this
coloring with very high probability it
will
succeed however it will be very
difficult to verify that you have
succeeded because the number of clicks
that one needs to check is n choose K
which grows very quickly as a function
of K so this is a phenomenon that is
sometimes called
finding KY in a h
stack a random coloring works with
overwhelming probability and so if you
just pick something at random it will't
work but one it is very hard to check
that what you found actually works and
two it is an active research Direction
and what seems to be a very difficult
problem to find other ways that does not
involve
Randomness but maybe even involving
Randomness in some other ways to
guarantee that what you found works and
this finding hay in a Hy stack describes
this phenomenal which is quite
counterintuitive that you know and also
demonstrates the power of the
probabilistic method that you know by
just doing everything at random it works
really really well but we don't
understand this process as much as we
would really like
to
so now you've seen a proof of A's
seminal result that gives a lower bound
to Ramsey numbers in the next two
segments of this video we will see a
couple of refinements to this technique
that allows us to get slightly better
lower bounds by introducing new ideas to
the probabilistic
method now let us introduce an
additional idea to the probabilistic
method to prove a slightly better lower
bound on Ramsey
numbers and this is a method of
alteration or the alteration
method what we will prove is the
following so let me write down the
statement it's slightly technical the
statement itself is not as important as
the ideas I will introduce so bear with
me for a
second theorem says that for any
positive integers K and
N the Ramsey number RK K is bigger than
the following quantity n minus n choose
k * 2 to the 1us k
2 okay so that's the theorem it gives
you a lower bound on Ramy numbers now by
optimizing over the value of K as a
value of n as a function of K we can
deduce the following
corollary and I will not show this
deduction here because it's a more
routine calculation so the corollary is
that rkk is bigger than the following
quantity 1/ e e is the the natural
constant 2.71 and so on plus little one
term that goes to zero as K goes to
Infinity time K * 2 the
k/2 okay so that's the ASM totic lower
bound that one obtains by taking this
theorem and optimizing the value of n as
a function of K we see that it is
slightly better than the bound that we
got previously it's slightly better by a
factor of <
tk2 okay so let us prove this theorem
here like before we
will start with a random
coloring but then make some adjustments
so in fact this construction will have
two steps construct a random coloring in
two steps
in the first
step we'll do what we did previously
just do
randomly
color each
edge with one of two
colors uniformly at random
okay so flip a coin for each Edge and
color it with one of the two
colors now this coloring might have some
monochromatic K
Clicks in which case we will delete a
Vertex from each such K click and to
destroy all the monochromatic K clicks
so the second step is to delete a vertex
from
each
mono
chromatic K
click okay so after this process you see
what we are left with is an edge
coloring of some complete
graph where there are no monochromatic K
clicks left because we've destroyed all
such monochromatic K Clicks in the
second step of this process
how many vertices are left right so we
started with initially nend vertices but
in the second step we deleted some so we
don't have as many vertices as we
started with initially so let's ask
ourselves how
many
vertices are left at the end of this
process towards the goal let me
introduce a random variable X
and X is the number of
monochromatic K
clicks at the end of the first
step well the expectation of x
can be computed as follows which is very
similar calculation to what we did
earlier there n choose K possible K
clicks and each one of them is
monochromatic with probability 2 to the
1 minus K choose 2 so that's the
expected number of monochromatic K
clicks now in the second step of this
process we delete
some number of vertices and one vertex
for each monochromatic K click although
some vertices may be used to destroy
more than one monochromatic K click so
the number of vertices that we delete is
not necessarily X but it is no more than
x so delete at
most the size of X many vertices
right and
thus the final graph that we
get at the end of this two step
process
has at least n minus the size of X
vertices let me remind you that this is
a random process the final graph and its
coloring that we get is random and X is
also a random
quantity this is a number of ver es and
this quantity here has
expectation and minus expectation of the
size of
X so X is already a size so let me don't
have to use the absolute value
bars okay so the expectation is n
minus n choose K to to the 1 - K chose
2 okay so the final graph has at least
this many vertices in
expectation well that's the average
number through this random process and
thus there must always
be with some prob positive probability
some graph that beats this average so
thus therefore
with positive
probability the remaining
graph has at least this many
vertices and furthermore
it has no
monochromatic click on K vertices
because we destroyed all such Clicks in
the second step of this
process okay this finishes the proof of
this
theorem which as you see in the
corollary gives you a slightly better
lower bound compared to what we saw last
time in the third segment of this video
we'll see yet a new another technique
that gets us even further along to prove
an even better lower bound on the Ramsey
numbers earlier we saw two different
approaches to using the probabilistic
method to lower bound Ramsey numbers the
first method was by taking a union bound
to show that the sum of all the
probabilities of bad events is fairly
small and the second method is through
alteration where we start start by
constructing some random coloring and
then fix the
blemishes so we show that by removing
the bad parts removing the vertices that
contribute to monochromatic clicks we
can get a coloring with no monochromatic
clicks now let me introduce a more
advanced method that can get us even
further so the general motivation that
we already saw a couple of times is that
we wish to avoid
a certain collection of bad
events which will denote E1 through e
l okay so these are bad events in our
case the bad events correspond to having
a monochromatic click in the random
coloring there are some extreme
situations that are easier to handle
okay and this extrem these extreme
situations are one of two types the
first is
when the events collectively have very
small probability even when they when
you just sum the probabilities of these
events so for example if the sum of the
probabilities of these bad events
is less than one then we can apply the
union
bound to deduce
that with positive probability none of
the bad events occur so that's an easy
situation to
handle another easy situation to handle
is
if all the
events all the bad events are are
independent so if they are independent
events then the
probability that none of them
occurs is equal to the product of the
probabilities that the individual events
do not occur
and this is positive provided that all
the individual event probabilities are
strictly less than
one now this situation typically does
not a it's not the case uh in a lot of
applications including the one that
we're considering for example having two
triangles if they intersect at an edge
if they overlap by an edge then them
being uh well if if you have two clicks
that intersect in uh in in some large
portion then having them individually
being monochromatic are not independent
events so what we're often dealing with
is situations where there is some
dependencies so some event dependencies
and often these are the hardest and most
interesting situations that one has to
deal with in the probabilistic
method a powerful
tool that we will see is the lowas local
Lemo
okay so let me explain what is a low
local Lum and then apply it to the
problem of lower bounds to reny number
so here is a version of the statement of
the lowas local
LMA and specifically appli to a setting
known as the random variable
model random variables
model the setting is as
follows suppose we have X1 through XV
and these are random variables
and importantly they are independent
random
variables so think of them as
independent coin tosses the outcomes of
independent random coin
tosses we'll have B1 through
b
m denote index sets so they are
subsets of numbers one through
V and for
each I ranging from one through
M
let
EI be some
event
that
depends
only
on the variables
indexed by bi
namely the variables X subj as J ranges
over the elements of
bi so this is a situation that captures
a lot of applications where you have bad
events for example clicks being
monochromatic in a coloring of a large
graph
and some of these events May have
dependencies because the events are
based on some underlying coin tosses
underlying independent random variables
and the different different events may
involve overlapping
variables so this is capturing that kind
of
setup now let me introduce some
hypotheses that captures a notion of a
weak amount of dependence a small amount
of dependence so suppose for
every
I from 1 to
M the set the index set
bi is
disjointed
from o but at
most
D other BJ
so D here is some other parameter in the
theorem so
hbi is has overlapping variables with a
small number of other
BJs and
furthermore another hypothesis is that
each bad
event occurs with some
probability which is not too large so 1/
D + 1
time constant e here e is the natural
constant 2 * 71 so on and this is true
for every I okay so let me fact just
write it a little bit more
clearly like
this okay so these are the hypothesis um
so there a lot but roughly speaking it's
saying that every bad
event is related to only a small number
of other bad events and each event
occurs with not too high probability
which depends not on the total number of
events but only on this D which is the
number of other events that it is
associated
with the
conclusion is
that the probability
that
none of the bad
events so the bad events are the indexed
are the events indexed
um okay so none of the bad events E1
[Music]
through
em
occurs is strictly positive so with
positive probability none of these bad
events occur
okay so that's the statement of the low
local
L and now let us apply this local Lama
to prove a even better lower bound than
what we saw earlier for Ramsey numbers
we will not be able to prove the local
Lama in this video so its proof is
although not long quite intricate and I
refer you to the references for a proof
so let us now see a lower bound to
ranging numbers and this is a result due
to Spencer Joel Spencer from the
70s and it says that if
if K choose 2 okay times n choose
two n minus 2 choose K minus 2 + 1 * 2
to the 1 - K CH 2 is less than 1 over
e
then the ranging number rkk
is strictly bigger than M okay so as
with earlier this is some mysterious
looking formula and I want you to not
worry too much about it it will come out
of the proof
um what may be more Illuminating is the
consequence of the
theorem so as a
corollary
rkk has the lower bound one um so lower
bound following ASM totic < tk2 / e plus
of 1 K * 2 K over
two and this yet beats the bound that we
saw earlier by another factor of root2
now this may seem like a small
Improvement and quantitatively indeed
it's only a constant Factor more whereas
the remaining astics um we do not know
how far it is away from the actual truth
but yet this result proed in the' 70s is
the best known lower bound to date for
diagonal Ramsey numbers this RK
case okay so let us now see the proof of
this theorem of spener which applies the
low vast local
Lama as earlier we will Begin by color
coloring the edges
of the complete graph on N vertices with
two
colors uniformly at
random okay and also similar to the
first proof that we saw for every
K
vertex subset
s let
us Define a bad event e Subs to
be the event
that
s
induces a monochromatic
click on the vertices in
s and we also saw earlier that the
probability of this bad event is 2 rais
to 1 minus K choose
okay let us see how this setup
corresponds to this random variable
setup
earlier the
variables correspond to
the
coloring of the
edges so in other words these are
indexed by
the N choose
two edges
of the complete graph km so there are n
choose two such
variables well what about this condition
here so B bis right so each
bi is a set
of
size K choose two corresponding to the
edges of this complete graph inside this
click of size
K so when do the bis
overlap so the uh if S and S Prime so
both K vertex
subsets of
vertices if they um so if the these are
both K vertex subsets then
their
clicks overlap in
edges if and only
if the sets of vertices S and S Prime
overlapping at least two vertices so as
an illustration if you you
have this click of size four and another
click of size four then they overlap in
at least one Edge if and only if the
vertex sets overlap in at least two
vertices so to apply the local Lama we
need to check how many other s s primes
intersect a given s in terms of their
Edge set and this is a calculation that
we can do as
follows for
each K
vertex
s the
number of K
vertex s primes
that
has intersection size at least two with
s is at most the following
well I need to pick a pair of vertices
of s where there's this overlap and then
choose and choose and then select the
remaining vertices of S Prime from the
remaining and choose two vertices of the
entire uh
click there are some possible overcount
here because some s primes may be
counted in more than one way through
this formula here um but it is certainly
an upper
bound and now we can apply the local
Lemo okay by applying the local Lama one
checks that as long as this hypothesis
inequality is satisfied
this hypothesis in the statement of the
local LMA is satisfied as well so
this inequality here corresponds
to this
inequality in hypothesis so this it is
satisfied and so we can apply the local
Lama to
deduce
that with
positive
probability none of the bad
events so none of the bad events es
occur
for ranging over all K vertex subsets s
in the
graph and
therefore with positive
probability none of the K vertex subsets
induce a monochromatic
click and that's exactly what we're
trying to show with this result over the
disclaim over here and this concludes
the proof of Spencer's
theorem so you see that this is a
demonstration of the powerful lovas lool
Lama and it is a very interesting method
that was um pioneered by lovas and has
had important applications subsequently
in the development of the probabilistic
method although we did not see the proof
of the local LMA here today I hope that
you can at least appreciate its
application and throughout this lecture
throughout this video we saw three
different approaches to lower bounding
the Ramsey number diagonal Ramsey
numbers using different ideas from the
probabilistic method um it is a powerful
method and it has lots of other
applications and many beautiful
applications to various areas of
combinatorics and Beyond