so um I'm from MIT professional
education and we partner a lot with ILP
to bring you whether it's corporate
Partnerships through education and what
we focus on is programs for engineering
and Technology
professionals uh so when you look at
folks like Philip Bola for example who
just presented he's also one of our
faculty he teaches in the machine
learning and AI professional certificate
so if you like that you get a little bit
more and if you want to learn even
related things that he talked about such
as reinforcement learning this is a
great way to bring your staff we have
open enrollment programs we work with
you to as you can see to re reward
retain Inspire employees whether it's
high potentials or people that are just
on boarding or in anywhere in between to
keep their skills up so whatever your
company goals are we work with you to
kind of help you align with that to make
sure that um the education is needed
what ever level especially around the
technical areas um we offer not just
open enrollment and in-person programs
and corporate programs but we also have
an advanced study program for example if
you want to send a senior fellow to MIT
to study for a semester or for the year
they can join our Advanced study program
uh we also come to you so whether you
want to do a corporate program here or
even overseas our International programs
we meet you where you are so wherever
that is um we will work with you to kind
of align that with how best your people
learn whether online inperson Blended we
work with you on that as well so from
renowned MIT faculty experts like Philip
is Sola later today you're going to hear
from John Hart and um Scott um Scott
James who also teaches with us and I
also put in there Regina bar who leads
our machine learning and AI
certificate um the key topic areas we
focus on um other than machine learning
and AI biotech data science
sustainability um digital transformation
Innovation um one of the underlying
things that we offer through all of our
programs is leadership and communication
um many Engineers may not have had uh a
lot of leadership training but as that
now this CH is really changing um so we
provide that as every part of our
programs is offering engineering leaders
ship whether it's persuasive
communication um effective communication
even using surveys um to be able to
bring you to the next
level so these are offered through
professional certificate programs
whether it's online in person that
people can come at MIT so we even uh a
lot of folks you'll see this is in our
certificate ceremonies many of our
online Learners come to MIT to
participate in these program
programs and we're also available
outside if you want to schedule some
time to talk we could talk about what
some of your goals are we really want to
help you to be impactful within your
organization uh these Blended programs
are offer Like Chief technology officer
programs Chief sustainability officer
programs Chief digital officer programs
where you have some residency at MIT and
you work also online or live online
online you have time to work on a
Capstone project these are year-long
programs that we offer so stop by
outside stop our table speak to me speak
to Ashley we'd be happy to talk to you
about next steps thank you
[Applause]