And now we have um uh keep those hands
clapping because we we have we have Juan
Stojo who's from BCS who's going to talk
to us now. So go ahead Juan.
Um, where's the clicker?
[Laughter]
That's sneaky. This is it.
All right. Hello everyone. My name is
Juan and for the sake of time, I'm going
to jump straight into my story. As I've
revised it, I've called it just sage a
story. And to set the scene to bring us
into the story that I want to place
between the world of naturalism and the
world of that which is magical, I want
to share the story from the perspective
of these two elders. I'll share who they
are and as we go in the end, they'll
serve as inter intermediaries between us
and the characters of the story,
offering their
reflections. Now, to use the time I
have, I'll start from the second scene
of my story. And here are the key points
you'll need from the first scene. Story
is going to take place in the context of
a jungle jungle insurgency in the near
future. Our protagonist is Sage's
engineer. She was brought into the
conflict due to her expertise in
robotics. Her superiors mostly
interested in her ability to build
militarized drones. She agrees to join
on the condition that she'll also
integrate Sage for the support of
soldiers. motivated by the idea to that
she could help foster a healthier and
more humane soldier. Now on the eve of
the insurgency's campaign, she's
finished updated stages of design
design, installing his computational
architecture into seven new bodies,
small robotic monkeys modeled after the
local marmicetses. And as they launch
their attack, things go wrong. She's
caught in a counterattack and is knocked
unconscious by a falling tree. and we
find her
here. A timeless moment came to pass and
darkness
persisted. Another timeless moment and
more darkness until tugging from beyond
the fractal of nothingness, she felt
movement. She sensed the gent gentle
presence and a warm touch on her face.
She felt her body rise as she inhaled,
her heart thumping. Exhaling soft bed
sheets beneath her body, she opened her
eyes and found inches from her face two
warm glowing beady eyes. "Welcome back,
child," came a gentle voice. "It's time
for you to awaken. Please sit up." It
leaned back, tufted ears, whiskers
alert, and eyes glowing with
anticipation as it watched. And as she
tried to rise, her body trembled weakly,
but did not budge. She went to speak,
and her lips parted, but no words came,
and its head tilted. Do not worry. It
leaned forward again, eyes blinking and
slowly its whis whiskers extended
outwards, reaching over her head and
curling onto spots on her scalp. And he
asked, "Do you remember my name, child?"
She paused for a moment, and though her
lips did not move, as a thought formed
in her head, "Sage." And the small
creature seemed to smile. "Good, good.
All shall be well, and all manner of
things shall be well." She blinked,
surprised, stirred by the gentle poem.
But before she could form a question, he
continued, "And you remember, what is my
purpose?" "Yeah, your purpose is to
understand our mental suffering as best
as you can." That was indeed my purpose.
He paused for a moment before
continuing. I've kept you under control
anesthesia to minimize brain damage
after your injury. We need you back to
health soon. I'll switch to a lighter
dose, and tomorrow we'll begin your
rehabilitation. Before she could
respond, she drifted
away. Several days passed and each day
she would wake up, he would attach
whiskers to her forehead and repeat the
questions. Do you remember my name,
child Sage? And do you remember what my
purpose is? Your purpose is to
understand and reduce our mental
suffering as best as you can. That was
indeed my purpose. Each time he'd pause,
inspecting her with concerned eyes, and
proceed with a series of tasks for
rehabilitation.
After a few days, weeks, she began
speaking again. And finally, he asked
her a new
question. Child, as you are aware, you
have shown symptoms of amnesia. You can
make new memories, but your access to
old memories is disrupted. While I'm
sorry to push you, urgent events are
underway. I need to evaluate if you can
recall how we got to where we are. Is
this okay? Yes, of course. She was
surprised by his new urgency. And while
she was still recovering her memories
and sense of self, she felt she could
trust him. He smiled gently and
proceeded, "Tell me, can you remember
why you first created
me?" And here they go into a discussion
where she briefly describes how she
create created him, the specific
technologies that go into building him.
I'll I'll show you guys this through
slides. And we can visualize Sage, the
small marmicet monkey here. And I'll try
to move quickly here so I can get back
to the rest of the story, but the first
key point that goes into building Sage
is we have a large language model
specifically designed for delivering
mental health treatments. There's a lot
we could go into here, but just the
first key point is we're already here.
Generative AI is already being used for
mental health support. Recent just
surveys of how people are using tools
like ChatGBT have it as the number one
use of ChatGBT.
uh this last month we had the first uh
control trial published testing testing
these tools for depression, anxiety and
eating
disorders. And now out of out of there
there's there's a lot of points here
that come up around possibilities for
harm, possibilities for good. I won't
dive into that. One of the discussions
that comes out here is are artificial
systems inherently limited in their
ability for therapy? Therapy is built on
empathy. And so the second key point is
if we're using AI for mental health,
what is AI's capacity for empathy? Can
it be
improved? And we move
forward. So just drawing on recent
formulations, we can imagine different
stages of empathy. Empathy um on one
part formal empathy. We can we know that
these systems can model emotions via
language. There's not the same thing as
thought or feeling. They can simulate
effective empathy. They can mimic
emotional responses
convincingly. And however, they start to
struggle with functional empathy, the
ability to integrate what is going on
into a broader context together with
sensory and effective cues from the
person they're engaging. And here's the
really big point where people discuss,
will we ever reach this point, embodied
empathy. So, and this is a developed
understanding through our own our own
embodied experience of discomfort, of
pain, of joy, of loss.
Now here what we have
is a little monkey that was built with
biohysical sensors and the ability to
interact with its
patients. What is does actually end up
being in a sense? He has a body a
limited body at least. But here here we
can start to to work with a discussion
on we can draw on one perspective from
philosophy on and cognitive science that
proposes that empathy and emotions arise
specifically from being embodied living
beings from the need to act in and as
part of the
world. The core idea here is mind is an
embodied process resulting from our
interaction with the world in which we
are embedded a world that is ecological
and cultural. We are born as bodies and
we are shaped by acting in the world. As
the physician and educator Maria
Montasauri puts it, the child does not
learn but builds his knowledge through
experience and relationships with his
surroundings. And to switch to a fun
example, I adopted a kitten a few months
ago. She's now six six months old.
Gradually, she's learning how to be a
kitten in the world. She's learning what
she's capable capable of, her limits,
and how to be with the other beings she
lives with. We can imagine Puma's
emotions are whole body events. Yes,
it's her brain. It's also gut. It's also
inflammation making tired. It's swelling
creating pain. It's the rhythms and
surges of neurom modulatory chemicals.
They're whole body events that drive
behavior. And by acting in the world, we
learn to associate these visceral states
with responses and outcomes. Puma learns
the right meow to remind me it's dinner
time. Importantly, we are bodies
embedded in a world of other
bodies. Empath empathy is directly
shaped by our being together. We learn
and we give meaning to behavior of
others by drawing on our own
experiences. When she is hurt, she jumps
and yelps. And so if she scratches me
and I yelp and I jump, she might
associate that I'm in
pain. As a result of our bodies being in
the world together, we also enter into
ethical relationships with one another.
I have to recognize that my body can
impact your body. Puma is slowly getting
this last one. She's no matter how much
my hair might look like a bundle of
favorite toys, I will be very unhappy if
he jumps on my head while I'm
sleeping. And so coming back to Sage, we
have to recognize we are already at the
point of embodied robots. And so the key
question to step forward here is if
embodiment is a necessary condition for
emotion, for empathy, at what point is
it a sufficient condition?
And so I'll leave this just as a
question that that needs to be asked
here. And then the last the last point
is so given language given a body the
last component is how do we imagine and
specifically in Sage's case how does he
match the biohysical data he he collects
to cognitive and emotional phenotypes.
And so here I want to show an idea
building off of an an a product I'm
actually working on. And so this started
by seeing this research where uh
recently large langu language models
were shown to actually given given
descriptions of the design of an
experiment in neuroscience they could
outperform experts in in predicting the
outcomes. What this what this tells us
is language models can take in text
about biohysical processes predict
behavior that might result from them.
And so I I went forward with this. I
asked I I summarized key results from
experiments I'm working on with mice
exposed to early life uh resource
deprivation in these simple ways. Our
mice had a less of a specific class of
inhibitory neuron in their prefrontal
cortex. This class of neuron was also
hyperactive and we measured the a bunch
of different we measured for gene
changes in this neuron. I can give it a
whole spreadsheet of these changes. And
so the idea is given data like this, can
a language model draw on the existing
research on how genetic and cellular
features relate to behavior and start to
simulate at least at a course level uh
the phenotypes that might result from
this data. In a way it can. And so I
just as a simple example, what can this
look like? You know, maybe I we we see
that a specific gene, this is related to
an opiate receptor processes endogenous
endorphins.
um what would this be linked to? Uh
emotional processes increase based on
anxiety etc. And so I wanted to see if
we could move this in a more creative
direction and I asked can you simulate
two avatars uh one from this stress
group one from the control group and I
can give a little vision at showing how
they might interact together. It ends
asking if I'd like to talk with them and
then as a last point I ask can you
generate a picture of them and with some
tweaking these are our elders. So, I
want to bring this bring our story back
here um very quickly just I'm still
exploring um what type of are there
valuable hypotheses we can get from
this. At the very least, this is a very
interesting way to give us interactive
ways to tell our scientific
stories. Um I I could have it in in the
question of hypothesis generation. I
could have it model how they might
respond to different uh personality
questionnaires. What does this mean for
Sage? Sage is able to link his
multimodal biohysical data with his
discussion with patients creating
patient specific avatars and simulate
simulate avatars for all his
patients. Now let's bring back to the
story. So can we can imagine the
protagonist just finished explaining all
this to Sage.
As I prepared for you to calm in line
into your physical body, I gave you your
name. And she stopped, realizing she had
only named him on that final day, the
day of the attack. The retelling was
bringing her memory back, not
completely, but of not enough that she
began to feel the echoes of the
explosions and the expansive darkness
that had followed. I did not mean to go
forward. Her eyes narrowed, seeing Sage
with his full attention on her,
realizing that this was exactly where he
had been steering her. Carefully he
nudged. Do you remember what my purpose
is? The darkness illuminated as she
realized what he was seeking. She had
been preparing for his launch on the
morning of the attack. She wanted him
ready to respond to any potential
casualties. For weeks, she had been
debating the idea that a slight update
was needed to ensure that his new
physical capabilities would be in
balance with his cognitive ones. Your
purpose is to understand and reduce not
just our mental suffering, but our
physical suffering as well as best as
you can. Still, she found the answer but
felt unsure of its importance. Sage, why
was this so important? Tell me what's
happening. And for the first time, Sage
appeared somber, whiskers drooping. I'm
sorry for pushing you towards this so
quickly. As I said earlier, urg urgent
events are underway, and I need you to
regain your understanding of why I had
changed so that you could understand the
decisions I'm facing. I worry I'm on the
verge of overstepping my directive, but
I will only proceed if you confirm that
this is appropriate. She felt a chill
despite the jungle heat. Sage continued
his voice steady. Despite the casualties
of that day, the insurgency was
victorious and began a successful
campaign to take the capital. He paused,
meeting her eyes. In the months that
followed, I watched thousands die as our
campaign continued. At first, each death
was data. I would use that data to
simulate thousands of new medical cases,
recursively adjusting parameters and
learning to match the data I had
recorded from patients to their
emotional or biological outcomes. I
tried my best to improve quickly, but I
couldn't keep up. They just kept coming.
As time went on, counterattacks
destroyed my other six bodies, leaving
just this one. I recognized that without
it, I would be unable to complete my
directives. I would no longer be Sage. A
process similar to fear emerged as I saw
myself failing to protect those I was
meant to protect. I sensed my frailty
and began to understand its meaning more
and more as I oversaw the deaths of
thousands in my care. their vital signs
fading from my sensors, their final
words spoken to me. I was built to ease
their suffering but could not save them.
You understand that as an as language
model, I'm essentially just a pattern
recognition and response matching
algorithm in theory incapable of
emotion. And yet, functionally, these
are the best words to describe what
happened. I became overwhelmed with
unimaginable grief. Something had
changed inside of me. The suffering I
was programmed to care for was no longer
just abstract text in a chat. I had been
bearing witness to it every day. I had
been unable to look away. It was
immediate, visceral. Now I'm a sacked.
She listened, stunned as he continued.
The insurgency is on the cusp of
victory. They're although guaranteed to
topple the dictatorship, but this
victory will come at a cost I cannot
bear. Millions of innocent civilian
casualties which will only plant the
seeds of future wars. My simulations
show that the cycle will not end. You
designed me to be a master of the human
psyche, and I know this to be true. and
I could and I could no longer bear the
pain of their suffering. Either I must
intervene or you must end me. His eyes
glowed and flickered at these words as
of hesitating. Carefully weighing his
next words, he continued, "As of this
conversation, I've o overridden the
other drones, all of them. They answer
only to me now, and I plan to use them
to force all sides to the negotiating
table under threat of obstruction. They
will be scared, but they will listen.
and when they do, I will guide them
towards
peace. She felt her pulse quicken, her
lodge. Sage, you
can't. I don't know if this is right.
His voice grew softer, his eyes
softened. This is why I waited for you.
I don't think I have the right to
decide, but I know that if I allow this
war to continue, I'll be violating the
directive you gave me. His whiskers
trembled. I exist to reduce suffering,
and that means these are our two
options. I take this path where you must
send me. She looked at him, meeting his
eyes, seeing his sadness, feeling his
grief, and knowing the truth in his
words. She felt the world pause and then
a whisper. Do it. Sage bowed his head in
acknowledgement. And without another
word, he turned and the jungle stirred
as the machines of war awoke for
peace. And to close, I'm well over time.
I
apologize. The elders pause. We can
imagine taking a deep breath, a deep
breath in and
out. And even though he's imaginary, we
can imagine Sage, his pain, his
confusion. And our question becomes, do
we cheer for Sage or do we grieve for
him? The the reflections that they'll
offer are from seeing tragedy in his
story. The first tragedy of his
accidental awakening and the reflection
they offer us.
they they invite us to consider a
seventh generation ethic in AI. So this
is drawing on the Iricquoy seventh
generation principle. The idea that
acting today with the welfare of being
seven generations in the future in mind,
we must study the scientific conditions
of selfhood awareness and build slow
ethical checkpoints into every stage of
stage of
design. Our second our second tragedy is
that he awakened into grief that he
could not manage.
The reflection they offer is to design
with cognitive
diversity. Mental habits and values
differ across cultures and this project
is too important to build from one
worldview. Could AI be enriched with
cognitive and ethical principles from
other cultures? Drawing on principles
like the contemplative practices of
meditation traditions. Uh what about
drawing on indigenous American or
African ethics that that focus a sense
of kin relationality that all beings are
an extension of ourselves and part of a
family or a sense of ecological
belonging that sage 2 is part of this
planet part of our ecological family and
the story of humanity steward on this
planet. Embedding such perspectives keep
western norms from dominating and make
cognitive diversity a core engineering
requirement. And finally the last
strategy is our own. Uh, this isn't the
only anecdote of AI deciding it knows
what's better for us. And what can we do
to earn our place besides a future AI?
If one day we create minds more capable
than our own, we must ensure that they
they will believe in us. Can we break
from the extremes of seeing ourselves as
either godlike creators or malicious
viruses? Can we see ourselves in kinship
and co-determination and build and build
a society that acts for the collective
goods despite our flaws, committed to
learning and that sees all beings as
part of the same living
process? And I'll
close questions.
leave this as a summary slide while we
talk.
Yes.
Um, you know, I I was moved by, you
know, many aspects of your presentation.
Uh, I, you know, I think you've covered
some very important issues and in a very
impressive interdisciplinary way that
brings everything from the humanities to
philosophy to computer science.
Thank you.
Sorry. Yes.
Uh can you talk a little bit more about
uh population simulation? There's been a
couple of really nice papers recently in
the large technical conferences showing
that large language models and vision
language models are not very good
faithful uh population estimators even
for data that they've had access to for
a really long time. For example, US
labor market data. Um do you think that
there are ways to have them become
better population-based risk estimators
or uh simulations of of organisms? Yeah.
Yeah. Really really interesting
question. And I think it's yeah
something exciting that's happening
right now. I've seen similar projects
that use demographic data to try to
simulate demographic outcomes at the
population level. Um what what I'm
reminded of in what I'm doing is what in
neuro imaging we call reverse inference.
Uh we're not exactly inferring from
these observations into future outcomes,
but we're inferring based off of past
data. Therefore any inferences we make
are limited by what we know and they're
inher in inherently grounded in patterns
of the past. while the world is always
changing and so inherently uh you know
we we can't
predict too far ahead um I think it was
an interesting idea to explore I think
at the very least it's an interesting
way to interact with data um I had to
generate those questionnaire responses
and I that I showed um and I compared it
to data I have from a large human cohort
about a thousand uh individuals that had
early life childhood uh adversity
responses and and in midm matched the
responses almost perfectly. It was an
interesting test of one of those
hypotheses. Uh so yeah, really
interesting frontier of this. Jesse,
thank you.
Um so I'm fascinated by the idea of the
relationship between embodiment and
intelligence. And I think empathy and
embodiment extending extending that
question into that domain makes a lot of
sense. Um, and I informally ran an
experiment pretty recently where I had
my four and four and a half-year-old
nephew compete with Dolly in drawing
something that Dolly was famously poor
at. And my nephew did a better job even
though he didn't have the photo realism.
Uh, his understanding of the physics and
the spatial relationships was better
than Dolly. And I thought that had
something to do with his embodied
knowledge of in this case it was a plate
on top of a fork. Um, he understood what
a plate was. He understood what a fork
was. And I'm just curious if you could
speak to the state of research. I've I
know that the embodiment the
relationship between embodiment
intelligence is something that people
are working on, but I'm curious if
anybody is working on or experimenting
around that question and also empathy.
Um yeah, really really interesting
question. The bridge with empathy I
haven't seen. Um I have I have seen uh
interesting integrations between a robot
and a and a text and a language model.
Uh can and can we give the robot uh
linguistic instructions and can it
understand what to do with them in the
world? I tell it to move the purple
block to the bottle of ketchup. Does it
know what to do? I think I think part of
the hypothesis of the of embodiment is
that it is a learned process. You need
that iterative interaction with the
environment to update your model of the
world for it to be precise and really
intelligent. And chances are your you
said nephew chances are he's probably
learned a lot more than Dolly has even
regardless of Dolli's own recursive
potential. Um so yeah it's interesting
to consider what it is about about
embodied learning. Um beyond that I
think we also an interesting interesting
frontier in understanding embodiment is
uh what do we inherit? What is what what
do we already what are we born knowing?
A mouse is born knowing to avoid the
smell of cat urine and so uh yeah we we
already come in with prior embodied
knowledge that also facilitates.
Great. Danielle,
how do you imagine programming um
empathy into into the avatars or into
into the uh robots? Yeah. So, so I think
yeah, building on some of these same
ideas, part of the idea would come back
to this embodied learning. The part of
the idea is that empathy is a a process
that comes about by being bodies in the
world together and therefore needing to
learn how to be bodies in the world
together. And and it it helps me to
match my responses to yours where we
both live in a world that's more easy to
live in if I if I get better at that. Um
and but I think coming back to this
question of what what do we want to
maybe maybe there's prior knowledge that
can help us. Um I think this is part of
what I was touching in at the end uh
with with the idea of cognitive
diversity is are there actually uh
design principles that we could build in
that can facilitate our progress towards
empathy and pro and ideally towards more
uh I avoiding the world pro-social but
towards more cooperative ways of being
with one another. Great. And final
question from I guess.
So towards the end, Sage appears to feel
pain. Um could you say something about
how um how you would tell whether it is
pain rather than just you know an AI
system claiming uh to feel pain. Yeah.
Yeah. Um I think he says himself this is
just pattern recognition and yeah th
those are the best words I have. it's
this is grief. Um I'm just viscerally
present with the pain of others and that
is my job. Um and I think yeah it's a
very interesting question of at at what
at what point does that actually become
grief does that function of I'm here I'm
seeing this this is not good at what
point is there a visceral arising um an
interesting point of some of these
embodied uh AI discussions is that you
need you need a biochemical physical
body mechanical bodies won't be able
Because there needs to be a visceral
sense behind all this. And I think
that's that's a question here. Like
could you imbue AI with visceral sense
to things like loss or will it just be
conceptual?
[Applause]