Uh, good morning. My name is Jim Flynn
and I am a program director with MIT
corporate relations and I'm delighted to
welcome you here and there's been some
question on the name of of this but it's
uh essentially
AI unleashed scaling and securing the
autonomous intelligence.
So, uh, as we've seen over the last, uh,
year or two that AI has moved from
systems that simply answer prompts and
do some interesting things. Increasingly
now, what we're seeing as the future is
that these AI systems are turning into
autonomous systems that can actually
initiate, coordinate, and complete
transactions, other tasks, making
decisions on their own. So that brings
up a whole host of questions when it
comes to security, transparency, trust,
and coordination. And that's why we
wanted to wanted to have this
conversation here this