thank you for that kind introduction
it's always a pleasure um to be here at
at MIT um I have an occasion now and I
won't say about it to to come here more
often and so maybe I will do that um I
should do two disclaimers before I start
the talk today the first is you know
this is ongoing work I'm hoping we'll
have stuff uploaded um to Archive before
the year ends it's work in control and I
figured if I want to talk about
something new in control I've never
presented this work before Lids is a
perfect place with it's eminent history
and control theory to do that so I'm
excited to do that the second
disclaimer that I want to do is you know
I'm going to do a major transgression
and not talk about machine learning in
this talk um so I'm going to apologize
to the machine learning Gods you know to
forgive me for that so there won't be
any machine learning um in my talk today
um so this is Joint work with um two of
my current PhD students Judy and Resa
um and you know we'll get into the
details in a moment but it's something
I've been thinking about for for quite
some time in terms of how we could or
how is it possible perhaps to to extend
um some techniques that are very
classical in control theory to maybe a
wider range of of applications and so
let me let me get into that um so here
is the outline um I'll briefly say a few
words about you know um convexity in
control in particular non-quadratic
conve convex costs and and issues that
come up in control when one wants to
study to go beyond quadratics I'll
introduce something called bregman
Divergence um many of you might have
heard about it but but maybe I'll I'll
present it from a slightly different
perspective I want to apply bregman
Divergence to control that's um most of
the talk I'll give some examples of the
utility of this and and then I will
conclude um so you know if you've been
in Signal processing or machine learning
or statistics you know you all know that
in the last three decades um there's
been a lot of work moving from you know
quadratics and least squares and least
means squares this kind of things to to
convex costs that are not quadratic so
when I was in grad school svds and
Subspace methods and so on were all the
rage everything was kind of quadratic
but you know you've all heard lwan loso
compressed sensing things like this low
rank Matrix recovery nuclear Norms in
machine learning then I am not
transgressing maybe um you know people
use cross entropy loss a lot um uh out
of MIT came this notion of atomic Norm
minimization so it's it's had a big
impact and it allows people when they're
looking for solutions to impose
structure or to recover models that are
or behaviors that are not easy to to
recover if all you're um focused on is
just quadratic loss um but in control I
I would like to argue that people have
not been able to do that to the same
extent largely you know if you look
especially at classical control people
focus on quadratic cost so there's the
famous you know lqr lqg criteria where
you have a quadratic cost on the state
of your system in this talk X will
always be the state a quadratic cost
perhaps on your control you and this
talk will always be the control signal
and so some expected you know um
quadratic cost of those even in h
Infiniti people still you know they look
at energy gains or quadratic cost you
have disturbances you measure as energy
and again you have your cost up here um
so things are typically quadratic and so
the question is why is that why haven't
we been able to to look at other things
um and so let me begin to slowly go into
this um so I'm going to take a very
simple example to begin with so this is
just a you know linear time invariant
State space model that's what I'll stick
through throughout this talk um X is the
state U is the control it's an
n-dimensional state in this case it's a
scalar control signal there's some
initial state which we assume we know
and so the the classical linear
quadratic regulator problem just
attempts to minimize you have two
quadratic costs defined through two PSD
matrices R and Q quadratic on the state
quadratic on on the control and you want
to minimize this over this sequence of
of control so this is clearly just a
quadratic problem there's only one
unknown in it which is the initial state
so you can certainly do that um that's
the lqr problem now if I want to like
look at this thing more generally well
clearly what I could do I can take two
general convex cost I'll use Q for the
state cost R for the control cost just
replace these quadratics by this and so
this is clearly again a quadratic cost
subject to a bunch of linear constraints
again the only unknown is X knot so this
is not a big deal you can solve this so
just to to spell it out a little bit
I'll take a very um special case this is
the lqr problem so I want to minimize
the quadratic cost subject to the state
space equations and here all I'm doing
is I'm going to replace this quadratic
cost here with an L1 so an L1 penalty on
the state and so those of you who know
L1 L1 pushes things to
sparsity um so when I do this I'll get
sparcity both in space across the um
State vectors but also across time
because you add the l1s it's essentially
the L1 Norm of an aggregated Vector so
so I expect that this will give me
somewhat sparse Solutions and so this
these are both convex optimization
problems I can solve them and here is
what you get if you just solve what I
wrote there this is for some fifth order
system the system doesn't matter the
blue curve is so I'm here writing the
magnitude the torm if you will of the
state the blue curve is what you get
from lqr it's a linear controller you
know when you have linear systems
everything decays X exponentially that's
what happens the L1 controller the one
that has the L1 on the state at the
beginning doesn't do as well but it
pushes the state absolutely to zero
after 25 steps it it wants something
that's sparse it it will do that in fact
you know if I put a weight in front of
this Matrix or excuse me in front of
this L1 norm and Crank It
Up um this happens earlier and earlier
and if you Crank It Up sufficiently at
some point it will set the state to zero
after five steps which because the
system I was looking at was controllable
is the shortest amount of time required
to push the state to zero so the point I
want to make is that you know this is
not just you know for curiosity you can
get behaviors that are very different
from what you get from lqr by just
changing that cost to an L1 this is now
something that is going to push the
state to zero earlier yes sorry what's
the control doing and that's SP driven I
I I will show you later when I add noise
I I will show you that in much more
detail this is just this is all
motivation but that's an excellent
question it will be doing more of course
but but I will show you all of that um
thank you okay so you know you can do
other crazy things and so I'll maybe go
over this quickly I can put for example
a peak bound on the
control you know so I can say if my
control is within an interval of
you know Delta I will penalize it
quadratically but if you exceed this you
you're not allowed to exceed this I'm
going to give infinite penalty to that
again this is convex I can put my L1
Norm here I can add that I can solve
this so convex
optimization um and then here is an
answer to your question um so so here
again I have the magnitude of the state
this is the second order system here the
red is the lqr
the blue is what this controller does
again it pushed it absolutely to zero
after five but because I had a
constraint on the magnitude of the
control at the beginning because the lqr
applied a pretty large control this one
couldn't the performance got a bit worse
before it you know got in better and
here you're you're it's exactly your
question you can see what the lqr
controller did and what this controller
did and so once you hit zero it doesn't
have to do anything after that um so you
can do in principle you know so why am I
even giving this talk I just showed you
you can put you know convex costs and
you can get behaviors that are
qualitatively different than what you
get with an lqr controller and there may
be reasons why you want to do this I
might have a control system where in
fact I do have a peak constraint on the
control um so these these make sense
from a from a practical point of view
certainly so what is the issue why am I
giving a talk
um so there's you know as I said you can
get these exotic controllers if you want
through convex
optimization um but there's at least two
issues the first is you know um for a
fixed Horizon if I want to solve these
problems is a convex optimization uh
there's quite a bit of complexity the
complexity grows polom in the Horizon T
typically like T
cubed um so that could be problematic
the lqr Sol solution because it has
dynamic programming built into it is
actually the complexity grows linearly
with the Horizon not not not cubically
so it's much better but in particular we
cannot solve infinite Horizon problems
this way and if you want to there's no
stability guarantees with this so people
do like you know I don't know what they
call them but they do these things in
blocks and Stitch them together and hope
that everything works and who knows if
it does um but the bigger issue
is that you know any respectable
system has noise in it okay um so
there's there's a noise there's
something also you know disturbing the
system that you're not fully aware of
and typically you know people say this
is maybe zero mean and IID and that's
what I will assume um and so this
precludes us from doing a simple
deterministic optimization because in
the previous case the only unknown was
the initial State here there's this
process constantly hitting me which is
which is unknown and so the way you have
to deal with
that
um of course is you you can no longer
Talk of the cost but you now have to
talk of the expected
cost um over you know the the randomness
in the
disturbances you also need to be very
careful about what information is
available to the controller um in the
previous case the only Known Unknown was
X notot so all the control signals at
different times could be a function of X
notot it was not a problem once you're
in this setting with noise it really
depends on what the controller knows and
for the majority of this talk to make
things simple I'll say a few words about
more General cases at the end I'm going
to assume something that's called a full
information controller which means that
the control signal at time I gets to see
the state of the system it doesn't see
the disturbance but it sees the state of
the system so it it's its control is
allowed to be a function of all the
states it's seen which are all the
states XJ up to the current time okay so
that is that is the information
available and so when you think of this
kind of setting the optimal control is
not really a signal it's really a policy
so it's really you know based on my
observations how do I you know it's
really these collections of functions F
that that that determine the control so
I'm looking for a policy now okay and so
if I just want to write it up this is
the optimization problem that we want to
solve we still have the constraints
there's noise here now and I'm looking
at minimizing over this policy the
expected value of say this convex cost
okay so that's what we like to do now I
want to convince you that even though
this looks very easy it's easy to write
it's actually very difficult to solve
and so to do this I can show the
difficulty in just a very simple toy
example so let me assume this system is
scaler X is a
scaler um control is a scaler the noise
is a scaler let's assume it's it's
gausian standard
normal um I'm going to assume the the
cost on the control is simple quadratic
and I'm going to assume the cost on the
state is the absolute value so it's the
one Norm for a scaler and you'll see
already this will become complicated now
when you're looking at this problem this
is over Horizon T the way we saw solve
this is dynamic programming you note
that the last control signal at UT it
only influences the last the state at
t+1 and so um in order to find the last
policy I just need to look at the last
terms in this um in that sum and so this
is how you find UT so I need to take the
expectation that's the absolute value
term this is the quadratic on the on the
control um and so in this expectation
because I'm sitting at time T the
controller Knows X it's going to decide
on what U is so the only Randomness here
is the noise that hits you right now
okay so this expectation is over this W
which is a standard normal now if you
sweat or you look up some book or
something it turns out you know one can
find the expectation of the absolute
value against the gaus and it has an
exponential term it has a q function Q
is the tail of a gausian this is the
formula for for it it ends up being a
function of the absolute value of this
deterministic part and here of course is
that and so I have to minimize this this
is convex so I can numerically minimize
it if I know what x is and a and b I
know um and so you minimize it you get
your U okay so I can I can numerically
compute this and I can take this U and I
can plug it in and I'll call this thing
M this is like the cost to go so if I'm
sitting at time capital t T and I
minimize this from the vantage point of
the time before me this is the optimal
cost to go it's sometimes called the
value function and as I said you can
numerically compute it but I don't know
it in closed form already you know with
with before the minimization it already
had Q functions and whatever in it um
and so the challenge is now if I go to
the next step so if I want to find the
control at UT minus one I have to take
this optimal cost to go and add it to my
current cost this is dynamic
programming um to get this expression
here and I've replaced XT in terms of UT
minus one the previous state and so on
and so here I have to do this
expectation over W UT minus one so this
part of it I know how to do it as Q
functions and everything this I don't
because the this m function I don't even
know it in closed form I have to compute
it and so the only way I can do this
expectation is through Monte Carlo so
every time you know I want to to find
out what it is either if I want the
gradient or the value to somehow
optimize this I have to generate
different realizations of w for each
realization I have to solve the problem
on the previous slide to find mome and
so this is cumbersome and you can
imagine if I do this two or three steps
I will have these nested optimizations
and it exponentially blows up in your
face and so nobody does this at best you
can do this for two three steps in
advance and sometimes people do this is
sometimes called receding Horizon
control so you make a control action
looking two steps into the future but
this is not something that you can do
okay so that's in a
nutshell um why no one does this okay
and so you might ask well what what is
going on in the quadratic case that
allows us to do everything and so let me
explain that because we will get cues
from that as we move move forward so in
the quadratic case if I look at time t
my costs are both quadratic the cost on
the uh control and on the state which I
have spelled out everything is quadratic
and so this
expectation is very easy to do because
if I take this quadratic and I expand it
out um there's a quadratic term these
are deterministic this is random and
zero mean so the deterministic terms
come
out there's cross terms involving this
random times this deterministic those in
expect a go to zero because W is zero
meain and so you're left with the
quadratic term in the random stuff which
has some expectation doesn't matter it's
not a function of you okay so so the
important thing is when things are
quadratic this expectation is Trivial
and essentially it amounts to dropping W
this is the term that
matters and so your optimization now is
just a simple quadratic
optimization um you can take derivatives
or complete squar or whatever you get a
control law which is now linear in the
state and then this you can plug this
back into here or do sure complement or
whatever your favorite method is the
important thing is this cost to go is
quadratic it's a function of a and Q and
all the parameters but there's a center
Matrix sitting here it's quadratic and
because that's the case when I go to the
next step I just have to take this
quadratic cost to go add it to the
quadratic you know Q here which is my is
the current cost and then this is the
cost on the state so everything remains
quadratic I know how to do the
expectation here uh once I replace XT
with UT minus one and XT minus1 and WT
minus one so everything remains
quadratic you know I you know the
expectation keeps quadratic the
minimization keeps things quadratic and
so tracking what happens to this Center
Matrix this uh
object is really what this rotti
recursion is for those of you who know
what it is in in control it runs
backwards in time okay so things worked
out because both the expectation and the
deterministic minimization kept
everything quadratic we never got into
like more complicated and more
complicated functions where you know
after a while we just have to throw our
hands up everything was self-contained
and easy to to do recursion on so I
would like to mimic this
if possible and um before I go into how
to do that I will just make one comment
that I'm going to focus on infinite
Horizon problem so in the infinite
Horizon case it's the same control
policy full information causal um except
that the cost will be the following I
will look at a finite Horizon cost
divide by 1 /t take the expected cost
let T run to infinite this is the object
I will try to
minimize um and again I don't know if I
should show this if if you attempt to do
this then you get What's called the
Hamilton jacobe Bellman equation which
is essentially the following thing so
you're looking for M which is a value
function or cost to go which has the
property that when you take M and you
put in ax plus bu plus W in it so like
the current state this is the cost on
the state this is the cost on the
control I have to average over W or take
expectations over W minimize over U and
I have to get the same am back yes it
seems to me in continuous time this
would look I don't know more uh you get
more Trac yes I think you would I
haven't looked at it but you but you
would
um but thank you for that anyway so this
was just a side remark what I want to do
is really to try to connect to the
quadratic thing um and I will just say
one thing because it's important the
good thing about this is if it also
comes with a guarantee of stability
because um
this M plus Q I'll call it P is a liuna
function that guarantees stability but I
won't go into that okay so what is it
that I want to do so this is all
introduction for me to get to this
concept of bregman Divergence okay so if
there's one thing I want you to take
away from this talk is that the closest
thing to quadratics is bregman
Divergence and I I'll show you why so if
you have things that work for quadratics
and you're wondering whether they can
extend to any anything else I would
always try out prman Divergence okay so
how does this thing work so you start
off with a convex differentiable
function some people insist that it be
strictly convex and I'll talk about that
um so this is called the potential s
it's it has to be differentiable or even
that can be relaxed um may or may not be
strictly convex okay and so the bregman
Divergence essentially what it is so
it's it's a function it has two inputs
in it and so the way you think of it is
this is
your say convex potential it's some
function so I look at the potential at
at the first argument and I subtract
from it the best linear approximation to
this function at the point w Prime at
the second Point okay so I'm sitting at
w Prime I draw this tangent to this
convex function and then I'm looking at
the difference between
the potential itself and its first order
approximation now since this function is
convex you know the tangents are always
below so this quantity is always non-
negative so bregman Divergence is an
immediate way where you know if if you
give me a convex function I can give you
something that's always non-
negative um through this and so this has
nice properties first of all it's clear
as I said it's not negative if you're St
L convex it's zero if and only if the
arguments
match that's why I prefer things that
are strictly convex because I I like
this
property
um so that's one thing um now there's
numerous examples of this so for example
if I take my potential to be squared
ukian distance the bregman Divergence is
just you know the difference or the
squared ukian
distance of the difference between um
the two arguments okay but you can take
anything else you want if you take
negative entropy which is convex then
you get K Divergence the bregman
Divergence for entropy is is KL
Divergence um but you know choose your
favorite convex function and so on so
these things are even though they're
non- negative they're Divergence they're
not
distances they there's no triangle
inequality so for clearly you know this
is not a distance it's the square of a
distance in this case um so that's
that's why it's a Divergence but why do
I care about this so if if you think
about what bregman Divergence is is
you're you're taking your convex
function and you're
subtracting the zeroth and first order
terms so everything that remains are
quadratics and higher and so that's why
it kind of behaves like quadratics and
let me show you some examples so we all
know hopefully from high school geometry
the law of cosines because you have a
triangle so if I'm interested in the
distance between W and W Prime and I
have this third Point here you know this
is this squared distance plus that
squared distance whatever minus the two
times the product of that so there's a
cosine I mean this is a whatever cosine
law there is a bregman Divergence
counterpart which is this so that's the
bregman Divergence that's a bregman
Divergence that's a bregman Divergence
this inner product takes this form so if
if if you take the square two Norm these
radians are just two times the weight
vector and you get that back okay so
this is
that more importantly for me there's a
completion of squares similar to what
happens for quadratics so if you have
two bregman Divergence terms there's a w
here and a w here with quadratics when
you do completion of squares what you
like to do is to bring these two
variables together under one quadratic
and then have the
leftovers so bregman Divergence there's
a formula similar to that so you get the
bregman Divergence for the sum of these
two w sits here but it's a bregman
Divergence to some W star and then you
get these two extra terms and W star is
found from this equation it's sometimes
called the normal
equation um and so it turns out when s 1
plus S 2 is strictly
convex this mapping defined through the
gradient of the potentials is invertible
and so there's a unique W star so
there's a completion of
squares so this and you know I've made
use of this but the thing that I will
make use of most is this next property
so again for quadratics let's assume V
is deterministic w Is Random okay and
let's say I want to take the expectation
of V minus W mod Square we all know the
trick we've seen this you know you add
and subtract the mean of
w um and so when you then expand things
out you get this term which is
deterministic there's no expectation the
last terms vanish because you've added
and subtracted the means you get these
zero mean terms and then the last term
is just W minus its expected value um
and you have to take this is random and
so it need some expectation okay but the
but the reason why this is important is
because this deterministic quantity got
separated out it's no longer under an
expectation okay so if I need to
optimize over it later on it's easy to
do I got rid of there is a bragman
Divergence counterpart part okay so if
I'm looking at the expected value of the
bregman Divergence between something
that's deterministic and something
that's
random the first term there's no
expectation in it it turns out it's just
the bregman Divergence between the
deterministic term and the thing that
you put here instead of being the
expected value of w you take the
expected
value of the gradient of the potential
evaluated at your random W so this
becomes deterministic after you take the
expected value and then you put it
through the inverse map of the
gradient okay and then the second term
which is kind of like this you just take
this quantity I described and you put
the bragman Divergence with the random W
so this term has Randomness in it so you
throw an expectation appr so this has no
Randomness in
it okay so this this this is this is
what essentially this is what I will use
it's the counterpart of
that okay so here is what we're going to
do um so this is the problem ideally I
would like to solve right I have um some
stochastic control problem with a convex
cost on the state a convex cost on the
control um and the problem is I don't
know how to do the expectation so I'm
going to say I'm not going to solve this
I'm going to solve this okay
so this second term I really being cous
because they're the same thing so I'm
going to take I'm going to assume my
potentials are convex let's say they're
non- Negative they hit their minimum at
zero I'm going to assume they're even
which is totally reasonable in control
there's no reason to differentiate
between positive and negative controls
or States let me assume that so this
thing here is just a bragman Divergence
between U and0 corresponding to R
because r at 0 is0 and the gradient at 0
is0 this is is just this but this term
I've changed quite a bit so rather than
minimize the convex function at this I'm
going to minimize the bregman Divergence
between this and that and note that this
is zero when you know the difference of
these which is the next state is zero so
I am penalizing the next state but I'm
penalizing it in this fashion I'm
putting all the deterministic stuff to
the left I'm putting all the random
stuff to to the right and this is really
the key so I've changed the problem on
you um and you'll see why as you can
imagine this expectation now will be
easy to do whereas the whole difficulty
with the one above was the expectation
was what you needed to bony Carlo and
all of that okay so let's do that so
again I'm going to do dynamic
programming I'm going to look at things
at time T yes can you say a few words
about how expressed that change
so so so okay so I will say this so when
the noise is small so you're looking at
the so if you look at the picture that I
had
earlier um you know so ideally you would
want to say minimize this you know
potential and I'm kind of expanding a
bit around it and so when your noise is
small when your second argument is close
to the first
argument um then this is a good the
farther way it is you you get a bit more
difference I don't know if that makes
sense to you so I mean not not not that
W Prime has to be close to W the closer
W Prime is to zero so if if your convex
potential had its minimum at zero at
zero you know the um the tangent is just
the all zero thing and so the bregman
Divergence is the potential that you
want as you move away from zero it
departs so for noise this is very close
to actually what you want um if the
noise term is bigger it's not it's
something else but but this is something
I always tell my students right I mean
we're Engineers right so we're not
mathematicians so this is a problem you
want to solve this is where the math is
if I'm really smart I move the math this
much and so the problem I bring you so
that's what I have
done um okay so this is the problem I'm
going to solve uh instead of looking at
this I'm going to insist this is what I
want to solve the bregman Divergence
between the deterministic part and the
random part for that for the potential
this is what I mean by bregman
Divergence control solving this problem
and I'm going to show you the what this
means hopefully if there's time so I
think I have to rush a little bit but
the point is if I now do the dynamic
programming if I look at time capital T
I need to do the expectation so I'll
just use the formula so this was
deterministic the only thing I have to
do is here I have to write the expected
value of the potential of Q at minus WT
and then invert it now the point is if W
is gaussian or if it has any even PDF Q
is even the gradient is odd so the
expectation of any odd function against
an even PDF is zero so this is
zero um and again because Q is even
uh the the the inverse gradient at zero
will also map to zero so this whole
thing becomes
zero and I had to put the same thing
here against minus WT so I just put zero
and again I don't even care about this
term because it's not has no u in
it and so lo and behold when I put zero
here the bregman Divergence between a
quantity and zero as I showed from the
figure is just
the um convex function that we wanted
and so my deterministic optimization is
this so it's just like the quadratic
case what happens is you just drop that
term which is what happened in the
quadratic Cas as well but an engineer
you could have made that step directly
yeah but then I would not have any
optimality I would not be able to say
what on Earth it is that I'm doing at
least I can tell you what it is I'm
doing and and there's a second step
which I as you will see is even more
critical
okay I I totally appreciate your comment
um okay so in princi I can do this
optimization now it's
deterministic maybe I can't do it in
closed form I don't know but I'll call
this thing
M and so now I want to do the next
step and so I have to take this guy
bring him here write XT in terms of UT
minus one bring in the next cost I do I
have to do expectation and I have to do
minimization so I know how to do the
expectation with this that was the whole
point of bregman Divergence to put it
here but I'm back to square one
um what do I do with that yes were you
I'm sorry um and so in order to the
expectation I need this thing to be a
bragman Divergence between the
deterministic part and the random part
that's the only way I can do the
expectation okay and there's only one
way that this can be a bragman
Divergence can anyone tell me or guess
what that is
so if I want the sum of the two things
or the difference of two things to be
the bregman
Divergence of those two things there's
only one way to do it and that's when
the thing is quadratic so if I want the
bregman Divergence between W and W Prime
to be a function of w minus W Prime the
only way that can happen is if the
function is
quadratic which means that I am going to
insist that the cost to go is quadratic
because if it's not again I'm
stuck okay so I I made two things I I
changed the problem to bregman
Divergence and I insisted that the cost
to go be quadratic because otherwise I'm
stuck okay so you might think I've
sacrificed the lot I I hope I convince
you that I haven't um okay so once you
do that the cost to go is quadratic this
is the equation and I tried to number it
and I don't know why Tech put a zero in
front of my number but um this is the
most important equation in this talk
this is the counterpart of the raati
equation um so I need I'll speak to this
equation quite a bit um and again this
quantity m + Q is a leuna function so if
you can solve this um stability is
guaranteed okay so I will say any triple
so any M that's PSD in fact I'll make it
POS positive definite in a moment and
any convex q andr that satisfy this
equation if I can find a Triple M QR
that satisfy this
equation um I can construct an optimal
stochastic prman Divergence control
yes
01ra M and M yes so so as you will see I
will not be able to willy-nilly choose Q
andr of okay what I will be able to do
is I as I'll show you many I can choose
one of them so let's say I want a uh
Peak constraint on the control I can
choose that I have a degree of Freedom
which is M because it's not as
meaningful to me and then based on that
I can see what Q's satisfy this equation
and then I'll look at them and I'll say
okay this is a reasonable Q or I might
choose a q for some reason and do this
choose M and as a function of M look at
what kind of RS I get and decide on but
I will not be able to choose them simult
things yes you're saying there are
nonquadratic
I will show you lots of them yes I will
show you lots yes yes yes so it gives
you a lot more flexibility than what you
had earlier I I'll show you many
examples Depending on time okay let me
say a few so I can parse out this
equation a little bit so you it'll it'll
be clear how I solve it and so to do
that I need to introduce this IDE of
fential duel many of you might have
heard so if I have a convex function f
its fental duel is defined in this way
you maximize over x x transpose Lambda
minus F so you're left with a function
of Lambda it's called the fenal duel I
can talk Lots about it I'm short on time
I'll only say it has certain properties
the Dual is
convex it the Dual of the Dual it's
itself so this is actually an involution
so it's appropriate to call it a
dual um for us if this F is even non-
negative with minimum at zero the same
is true for the The fential Duel this
will also be important for me the
inverse of the gradient of the function
f inverse here I mean viewing the
gradient as a mapping it's a vector um
if I view it as a mapping the inverse is
the gradient of the fenal dual
and if I look at
quadratics the fential Dual of a
quadratic is a quadratic where you
replace the center Matrix with its
inverse um so that's all I will
need and so let me now look at this
equation okay so I want to minimize over
U and I want to get back a
quadratic and so you know if if you look
at the optimality condition if I
differentiate with respect to you this
is what you get I don't expect you to
remember the equation you get this if
you differentiate with respect to X
because the equation was an identity
over X you get this doesn't matter um I
can eliminate this nasty quantity P if
you recall I had defined
as um Q + m anyway um you can eliminate
it you get
this um so it says the gradient of the
of the cost on the the control is this
quantity it's a linear function of X
depends on M but more importantly the
optimal
control you just invert this but
inverting this is just the gradient of
the fal du okay so what this shows is
significant because it shows the optimal
control
law is a nonlinear State feedback law
the control signal is a function of the
state it depends on the
um I guess Co cost on the control
through the gradient of its fental duel
it also depends on Q IND directly
through the M that satisfies the
equation that had q in it but it's a
nonlinear State
feedback um okay now I can say certain
other things so if I go back to this
equation this is the equation we wanted
to solve I'll skip if I go and I take
fental duels from both
sides uh you will end up with this
equation here so this is very nice it
says the fental Duel of this P plus the
fential Dual of the r has to be a
quadratic and so this is usually so we
usually solve these equations in the
Dual domain um so if I choose one of
these guys the other one is clear it's
just a quadratic minus the other that
that's how we will be solving these
things okay so here's the main theorem
here's your
system if you find convex functions QR
and a positive M that satisfy this
equation this is like the Hamilton
jacobe equation this was the definition
of p then this state feedback control
law which I described solves this
problem is the solution to this optimal
control problem the infinite Horizon
problem where you know my cost for
bregman
Divergence this is the
claim um and as I said the way we use
this theorem is depending on the
application you you have freedom to
choose either Q or R I'll give you many
examp examples if you choose Q then you
should find all RS and M's that satisfy
this equation which was point2 I guess
on the previous slide and then m is
really we don't really it's not as
meaningful the meaningful object is is R
the cost on the control if you've
choosen C you tune M until you find an R
that's acceptable and then you you write
down your control if you choose R you do
the same thing to find an acceptable q i
I'll show you examples of this um very
I just want to make a comment about what
happens when um so what I looked at was
the full information case in many cases
what's more reasonable is I don't have
access to the state what I have access
to is a noisy observation of the state
is sometimes called measurement
feedback and so again if you look at the
vantage point of the controller in the
measurement case if I'm sitting at time
I I don't know the State anymore but I
can construct my best estimate of the
state given the past observations that's
the conditional mean of the current
state given everything I've observed
till the current time and this is very
easy to find from the Colman filter and
it and and what this state estimate is
is kind of independent of well not the
state estimate the error is independent
of the control that I do but anyway um
so I can take the state and I can write
it as what I know and what I don't know
which is the randomness this x Tilda is
zero mean if everything is gausian it's
gusan its Co Varian is known from the
Colman filter all of that and so the
optimal control problem that I will
solve is now
this so in my bregman Divergence term I
put all the deterministic stuff to the
left I put all the random stuff to the
right so I'm looking the bregman
Divergence you know so when when you
when I take the difference of these two
things it is the state XI + one but I've
taken the state XI + one I've broken it
up into its deterministic in random
parts and I put the random Parts on the
right and again I've done this just so I
can do the expectation and so if you if
you agree with this
premise or you know agree to do this
then the solution is exactly what I
described to you earlier the equations
for pqr are all the same the only
difference is your control now is a
function of xat same function of xat and
so this is called certainty equivalence
it holds in the quadratic case which
says that if you don't know the state
the controller can kind of ignore the
estimation part and just plug in the
best estimate of the state into its
control and the estimator can ignore the
control it can just run its column and
filter whatever okay so that's all I
want to say so measurement feedback is
the same again provided you push all the
randomness to the right all the
determinism to the
left I think I'm singing a Beyonce song
or something about the left right
anyway okay let me just do some examples
and then wide up so so in these examples
because I don't want to get into rotti
equations whatever I'm going to do
everything for a simple scalar system
because I just want to demonstrate what
we get okay so the system will be
because I can do everything closed form
here um it'll be a scalar
system this scalar system okay so the
first one is I'm going to put an elastic
net on the state so the absolute value
of x plus a little bit of a quadratic
term and I'm adding this a little bit
because if I don't add it I don't have
strict convexity and so sometimes that
bothers me um so this is customary to do
this will still induce sparcity as you
will see in a moment and so if you run
through the Machinery that I just
described if you want things to work if
you choose an M for any M that you
choose m is now a scal
this is the cost on the
control okay now if you look at this
thing um you know I want this cost to be
convex and so I need the coefficient of
U sare here to be positive and so that
puts a constraint on what M's I can
choose so I cannot choose M willy nilly
there's some range of M you know so if a
is unstable any M works but if a is
stable I have to make sure that the M I
choose guarantees that this is
positive um but that's what I was saying
so you can look at this if you look for
example at the leading order terms you
know there's M's here but there's an
extra m in the numerator of both of
these so the bigger m is
the um more penalty if you will on on
the control but but typically this um
cost on the control it's piecewise
quadratic if you will but again you can
choose M to your desire now more
interesting is what the the optimal
control is again the way you find the
optimal control is you find the fental
Duel of this and you take the gradient
of the fenal duel you get a piece-wise
linear control which is
this okay so this is explicitly what the
controller is let me show you it its
performance so um again as I said you
know so I'm taking these are so it's an
unstable system in the Epsilon net I
took Epsilon very small I took a small M
so this is the cost on the state it's an
elastic net so it almost looks like you
know an absolute value function there's
a tiny bit of quadratic on top of it
which you can't see for small M we're
not putting a lot of penalty on the
controller so it's quadratic but very
barely um and so if you look at the
performance again so here I'm looking at
the absolute value of the state the red
is the lqr the blue you know um because
I'm not being very demanding of the
control the controller is not penalized
a lot it takes the state to zero after
one step and then after that it deals
with the noise okay so it's very
different behavior from the lqr you
might say well I should penalize you
know maybe the state more and so if you
up this m you get something that's more
quadratic maybe this you like more and
so again here this is not as
aggressively pushing me down to
zero um but you know it's still doing a
better job of that than than the lqr
okay so you have some flexibility in
terms of what you want through this
parameter M but the cost on the state is
kind of quadratic looking it's a
piecewise quadratic let me do another
example we can take like a peak con
constraint control so this is what we
saw
earlier
[Music]
um if I'm below a threshold t i just
quadratically penalize if I'm above T
I'm disallowing it okay so you can go
through the
Machinery again you know so you choose
an M you you do finantial dels all this
business you find the Q This Is What You
Get again it's piecewise
quadratic um if you look at this one
now um you know to get a convex Q This
coefficient has to be positive which
means that a has to be less than one it
has to be stable and this is totally
expected because
you cannot hope to stabilize an
arbitrary unstable plant if you're Peak
constrainted you know because if you're
initial state is too big it'll run away
too fast the peak constrained Guy cannot
catch up and so that's very natural that
this was the answer so what I just said
the controller again is piecewise it's
actually interesting it's linear up to a
point and after that point it just
levels off a t as you would
expect um let me show you the
performance so again again here is the
cost on the controller it's infinite
once I I guess I took t equal to 4
here and you know for this value of M we
thought this was a reasonable cost on
the
state um and you can kind of see the
performance so here I'm showing you the
absolute value of the state so here
because we are Peak constrained the lqr
isn't we do a little bit worse than the
lqr but not a whole lot because we're
Peak constrainted but here you see this
this is the actual control signal we're
constrained by four so this guy has put
in a lot less effort to get this
performance than the
lqr okay so this is the effect so we've
put in a peak
constraint um you know you might care
about safety control so now I'm going to
put a limit on the deviation of x from
zero so you might have a robot and you
want it to go you know up the stair and
not bang onto the sides so this is
supposed to be that scenario I'm giving
infinite penalty if you exceed
T um okay so I'll show you some of the
steps here so if this is q p was M plus
this thing so it's this object P star
you take the fenal duel it's this object
R star you go you know P Star Plus R
star was a quadratic so you can find R
star it's this object who cares um and
then you know if I take the gradient of
this thing well that's the r if you want
to know what the r is but um you can get
the optimal controller so this is the
controller again it's piecewise
linear I would not have guessed this
without this
Machinery um let me show you the
behavior so the red is the cost on the
state so my safety guard rails are minus
.1 to 0.1 I don't want the state to
exceed this for this value of M this
blue curve is the cost on the control
which looks reasonable to me again it's
piecewise quadratic and so this is the
behavior so these are the the I don't
know why he used green it should be red
I think for safety but anyway um these
are the margins this is where the safety
controller that I just showed you this
peie wise controller behaves and the
other one is the lqr I mean it doesn't
have the safety built into it so it
exceeds these bounds quite often okay so
we can actually build in you know a
constraint like this and construct a
controller and again these are non
obvious I
mean this is what it is okay now
everything I showed you was you know
piecewise linear doesn't have to be you
can get more exotic than that so I just
randomly chose this as my so I'm putting
exponential cost on you I don't know why
you'd want to but let's assume you
do um and if you push through this
Machinery this is the U that you you'll
get so it turns out the U the optimal
control is kind of logarithmic in this
state because this guy doesn't really
want to expand anything on on the
control so its growth with the state is
only logarithmic and for this reason it
turns out that if you insist on this
kind of penalty on the control uh your
controller will only work with a stable
a you're penalizing you're tying the
hands of the controller so much that it
can't really deal with an unstable but
you can get like some crazy
logarithmic controller and you can look
at its
Behavior again it's not as good as the
lqr because you've really constrained
what it can do but again if you look at
the control signal compared to what the
lqr does it it you know it's putting in
a lot less effort um and so maybe that
matters to you you can do quantization
you know if your say your control only
was allowed to do three things up down
or zero
how do I design an optimal controller if
this is all the controller can do right
there might be very simple controllers
where this is all you can do well this
control you can think of if it's in this
framework it'll be the gradient of the
fental Duel of the cost on the um
control and so from this you can go back
and actually figure out what the fental
duel is by just integrating this out
it's something thing and from here I
haven't done it cuz I was too tired last
night you can you know find R and Q and
M and so I just want to convince you
there's a lot that you can do with this
um so even though we insisted on bregman
Divergence and I move the random stuff
to the right and then I had to insist
that the cost to go is quadratic there's
still a lot of flexibility so to
conclude um non-quadratic convex costs
are rarely used in Su itic control
because as I said Computing this
expected cost to go is
often to put it mildly um intractable
and so the idea here was to introduce
bregman Divergence again if you want to
remember anything from this talk is that
the closest thing to quadratics is
bregman
Divergence um it allowed us to compute
the cost to go again the trick was you
put everything deterministic to the left
everything random to the right we had to
insist the cost to go is quadratic so
that it would be a bregman Divergence
itself the optimal controllers are
nonlinear State feedback
laws stability comes for free certainly
equivalence holds if you don't observe
the state and you have estimates of it
you just plug in the estimates into your
control law there's total freedom in
choosing either the cost on the state or
the cost on the controller as I showed
you but once you choose one the other
one is is you know you have some
flexibility with it but you cannot
choose I cannot say I want an L1 cost on
the state and an Infinity cost on the
control that I cannot do I can choose
one and then the other one I can play
around with the m parameter until I like
what I
see um but nonetheless it gives us a lot
more flexibility in the designer of the
controller than the standard lqr lqg
which just gives you linear controllers
and I guess I did some examples for you
so I hope I didn't rush it too much I
will stop here thank you