Okay, it is uh my pleasure to introduce
our next speaker. It is Sarab Amin. He
is a professor of civil engineering,
civil and environmental engine or the
department of civil and environmental
engineering.
And uh take it away sir.
>> Um thank you everyone. Uh thank you Jim
for inviting me. So the title here is
not mine. It's given to me by Jim.
Designing for resilience, scaling
infrastructure for environmental and
system uncertainty. So my background is
in analytics uh data science
optimization and machine learning. And
I'm going to try to address some of the
resiliency challenges in the age of data
center through a set of case studies and
uh papers that we recently completed. So
I'm going to pose this big kind of
number at you which is AI data centers
is projected uh 945 terowatt hours by
2030 is equivalent to the demand of a
whole economy such as Japan right so
when we look at these numbers in the
face of three global risks identified by
the world economic forum extreme weather
events natural resource shortages and
adverse effects of AI as a technology
what jumps out at us is the
interdependent environmental,
technological and economic risks that we
face and that we fear might get
compounded or at least changed in their
nature with the advent of this huge
demand that we are facing of data center
resulting from AI compute growth. So
here the whole presentation I want to
phrase as a dual use of AI. On one hand,
AI is helpful to us tremendously in
trying to leverage heterogeneous data
for better forecasting for better
scalable uh solution of our large scale
optimization problems and disaster
response and crisis management. But on
the other hand, it also exposes us to
these new risks because we want to we
are faced with exponential consumption
of resources and critical
interdependencies that we may have
overlooked and creating new failure
vectors. So the first kind of starting
point I want to say is that AI offers us
good tools to manage these kind of
complex interdependencies and risks on
one hand thanks to the advances in data
science and optimization but it also
creates this unprecedented
vulnerabilities that we need to address.
Right? So taking a step back now we know
that there is going to be a sustained
growth in the AI data center demand
which will impose new risks and new
demands to our energy infrastructure.
Right? So in the past years uh the uh
energy demand has increased by six uh 6%
but we are rapidly seeing between 2019
to 2026 there is more than 2x increase
in the energy demand. And what we can
say very safely is that the classical
improvements resulting from computer
architecture from how the data centers
are managed and operated they are all
very good but they are going to reach a
plateau unless we sort of take a systems
approach a broader approach in
particular we ought to think about the
multi-dimensional nature of the stresses
that these particular integration of AI
with the energy system creates in
particular strain on our energy system
our grid uh strain stain on our water
resources, strain on critical supply
chains of semiconductor devices and
semiconductor materials and also land
resources which includes sighting
conflicts. So already we are seeing
these kind of uh collocation of data
center demand which creates new stresses
in water stress regions and increased
projection of regional demand of
electricity by the independent system
operators. So what we need is a
fundamentally new way to think about
improving the resiliency of our coupled
AI infrastructure and energy systems.
Okay. So what I'm going to try to do
before we proceed is to try to tell you
three motivating aspects on why we need
to think about how we think about
resiliency and integrate in our planning
and operations. Right? So the first is
that we ought to look at past failures.
So past disasters including for example
the Texas freeze which happened in two
consecutive years. Right? So on one hand
we had a mis projection on the sudden
increase of demand because of the winter
freeze but on the other hand we also
failed to foresee the failures of
thermal generators. Right? So this
created and exposed the new ways in
which our natural gas vulnerability
infrastructure vulnerability can impact
our energy system the bulk power system
and uh resulting in cascading blackouts.
Right? So the point here is that we
cannot forget these kind of risks and
these events that we witnessed. Um and
we also need to appreciate that while AI
can help us better forecast the nature
of these risks. What is also important
is that we plan and operate under
uncertainty and the implications of AI
for AI infrastructure is that point
predictions are no longer useful. we
need to think about uh uncertainty and
we also need to think about the
interdependencies between various
infrastructures. That's my first kind of
uh starting point. The second starting
point here is that currently there are
thousands of gaw of u new generation
that is stuck in cues which is called as
interconnection cues and the decision
makers and the generators have huge
difficulty in integrating these new
assets into the uh grid because they are
facing a lots and lots of delay up to
six years of delay and they are
ultimately withdrawing. So the grid
operators have to account for these
different types of load patterns and
contingencies and and have to look at
various types of scenarios that they
need to plan for in order to integrate
these renewables and new types of loads
that are coming into the grid.
So what I want to say here is that we
need to think about new approaches to
try to try to sort of combine these kind
of integration requests right and
evaluate all these scenarios in a much
faster manner right and in doing that we
need to think about what I call as cross
center cross- sector competition between
for example the EV generated demand and
the AI data center generated demand for
example okay so that's the second point
the third point here and I'm going to
Again stress is this multi-dimensional
nature of the resources. So water stress
I already mentioned uh in particular we
see that twothird of the new data
centers are expected or are being
deployed in already water stress
regions. We are seeing land use
conflicts and we are also saying um and
this is something that we are also
working on is the supply chain
vulnerabilities because these data
centers require new kinds of
semiconductor devices for which the US
is not prepared to manufacture uh
inhouse and there are critical
interdependencies between Taiwan, China,
US and the EU that also needs to be
accounted for. So basically what I'm
trying to say here is that we need to
think about optimizing simultaneously
multiple resources across water,
minerals and land not just the energy
infrastructure. So that's my third
starting point. With that I want to say
uh that the classical way in which we
look at the operations and planning and
planning and operations is no longer
sufficient because of the reasons we
just discussed which means the classical
ways of predicting planning building and
connecting to the grid is something that
we are finding faults with already
because we these kind of modeling
approaches fail under uncertainty. uh we
need these these typically do not
account for multiple types of
interdependencies. They assume static
assumptions while we need to be more
adaptive and they typically look at
local optimization and don't look at the
systematic or system oriented approaches
that we need to look at in an integrated
manner. So what we need is uncertainty
aware planning and operations adaptation
as our new uncertainties reveal and
system level optimization which account
for cross- sector coupling across a
range of infrastructures. Okay. So with
that I'm going to present to you a new
way of thinking uh which should be
obvious for people who are in are are
aware of how to integrate uncertainty
and risks into decision problems. But
I'm going to discuss some specific
insights uh given that this is a data
center day that we are here. Right? So
I'm going to say that we need to be more
adaptive in our planning uh uh uh
planning approach. We need to sense uh
respond learn and optimize
simultaneously. But we also need to
account for the uncertainties, multiple
objectives and build in the
adaptability.
And through this I'm going to reveal a
set of resiliency principles that would
be of interest hopefully to a number of
us in the face of uh the AIdriven uh
energy systems energy growth right okay
so what I'm going to try to do in the
time that we have together is I'm going
to give four examples four concrete
examples from the research that we have
completed uh which exposes the
importance of system level thinking to
account for um uh interdependencies to
look at multiple objectives together uh
uh in the face of uncertainties and then
I'm going to think uh tell you a little
bit about how we are using generative AI
uh for the purpose of trying to um uh
look at uh scenarios which which which
are important for us in order to account
manage the risks and lastly the use of
LLMs um uh and how they can help us in
accelerating and managing this risk. So
these are the four kind of messages that
I will walk you through in the time that
we have together. Okay. So the first
case study is a paper uh with multiple
colleagues that we completed uh which
got published in cell report
sustainability which basically asks the
question that if we have a future kind
of electrification deep electrification
scenarios on the residential heating
side right how much of my
interdependencies between the natural
gas and energy infrastru electricity
infrastructure shift because the natural
gas is going to be now shifted from the
residential use of natural gas to
supplying bulk energy, right? And what
is the role of future climate change
uncertainties in demand and supply in
making this kind of shift happen? What
are the implications, right? And how do
we plan for uh for decarbonization
goals, right? In these kind of
technological shifts and under these
multiple types of uncertainties. So what
we considered here is that we considered
multiple weather variations coming from
climate models. We try to also account
for technological uncertainties uh with
electrification that we are going to
face and this fuel switching behavior
between natural gas and electric uh
infrastructure. And what we found is
that for the New England regional energy
system, the uh demand shifts to a winter
peaking system. And what we also see is
that because of the uncertainty in the
future climate scenarios, the
weatherdriven peak uncertainty becomes
much larger. Right? So this creates a
trade-off that on one hand
electrification uh heating
electrification creates lower energy and
natural gas use on the demand side but
it generates higher electricity demand.
Right? And why is it useful for data
center planning? Because when the data
center loads are integrated into the
grid, it can compound and exacerbate the
winter peaking demand, right? And
clearly in the face of future
uncertainties in the data center growth
and also the climate uncertainties, the
huge volatility that we may be facing
with needs to be planned for in terms of
citing new generation assets and
operating them. Right? So that is the
takeaway. Um and through this kind of a
cross- sector integrated analysis, we
are able to try to understand what kind
of natural gas investments that we may
be needing while maintaining strong
decarbonization goals, right? Um what
kind of flexible response capabilities
need to be exercised in order to deal
with the weather uh uncertainties and
what might be the changes in the
transmission lines and also pipeline
infrastructure natural gas pipeline
infrastructure that we may need to make
or that we would need to make in order
to account for these uncertainties. So
one of the insights that we have is that
we do need to have flexible peaking
capacities right and when we are trying
to look at data center demand growth
coupled with weatherdriven uncertainties
these kind of flexible asset deployment
and operation becomes more important.
Um overall what we find is that there
there could be some surprising takeaways
in particular when we have deep
electrification
uh coupled with u uh improvement in
building envelopes right it can result
in total system costs and also total
savings in terms of the joint demand uh
between energy and natural gas
resources. So one takeaway here that I
want us to keep in mind is that data
centers uh when they are need to be
planned the planning of this demand
needs to be accounted for while also
considering the uncertainties in the
weatherdriven uncertainties and how the
shifts in the total demand across
multiple infrastructure will occur. So
that's that's my main message for this
case study. Okay.
All right. Okay. So let's move to the
second part. Uh the second part is about
the uh renewables and uh clearly there
is a lot of interest in sighting of
renewables both solar and wind near to
the data centers in order to ensure that
the data center demand is met in a as
decarbonized way as possible. Right? And
here again what we looked at is multiple
types of resource complmentarities
across wind and solar. And one of the
key limitations that we seek to address
here is that when we talk about citing
decisions between wind and solar, they
are typically made using very coarse
resolution models. course resolution
models in the sense that we're not
really exploiting fine scale
correlations at kilometer scale between
wind and solar and integrating it with
our energy system models in order to
generate the best sighting decisions at
a micro level which will enable us to
extract the majority of gains through
spatial and temporal complimentarity
between wind and solar. Okay. So in this
paper that we completed jointly with
professor Mike Howland my colleague uh
we we uh proved that four resolution
sighting 4 kilometer resolution sighting
is possible using detailed fine grain
data as well as uh fine grained models
of energy systems and doing the joint
solar and wind optimization across
multiple weather years. And what it
essentially gives us is a significant up
to 40% cost reduction in comparison to
course resolution models. Okay. And the
key kind of insight is that through this
kind of fine grained modeling of data
integration and energy systems
optimization we are able to exploit the
resource complmentarities between wind
and solar both spatially and
temporarily. Okay. So in the sense that
we want to ensure that the wind wind
turbines are located at sites which will
be maximally compet complementing
spatial temporarily with the solar
energy resources that we have at our
disposal and this kind of spatial
temporal complimentarity can give us a
huge gains in terms of requiring lesser
total storage right when for example we
are planning for data center demand. So
the applications of data to data center
infrastructure for this kind of a
thinking is that we need to have a cost
effective matching of supply and demand.
Exploiting the complimentarities between
the different type of resources
renewable resources and here uh the high
resolution sighting can be enabled by
this deep integration of data fine
resolution data and co-optimizing across
both these resources. And what we expect
here is that this type of approach will
reduce the risks that we are facing by
creating enough geographical diversity
and making sure that multiple types of
resources are properly integrated to
meet the data center demand
fluctuations, variations and also
growth. Okay,
that's my second case study. Okay. So
the last two case studies I want to sort
of uh give a positive spin on the use of
AI and how it can help us to sort of
meet this challenge that we are talking
about. So the starting point here is
that for data center infrastructure we
need new assets right power plants,
transmission infrastructure, cooling
devices etc etc and these infrastructure
needs to operate over a multiple time
horizon 20 or 30 20 to 30 years right
and so what we need to make sure is that
we have a right amount of investment
right now while facing future
uncertainties right so if I were to plan
for worst case right if I were to plan
for worst case or scenar scenarios which
are not statistically and feasible
physically plausible then I may
overinvest in my capacity right you
agree I may overinvest so what can
generative AI do right so the idea here
is that if I'm able to sort of simulate
the supply and demand simultaneously
under future weather scenarios and I
build a generative model for the supply
demand variations that I'm encountering
or expected to encounter I sample from
this generative AI model in order to
create scenarios which are risks
sensitive which means that they are
statistically possible and physically
realistic and then plan my system
in the face of these scenarios that I
will generate. Okay, so that is the use
of generative AI and what I want to
emphasize here is that the classical
methods of trying to generate the
scenarios do not really capture this
kind of requirement of statistical and
physible physical plausibility.
Okay. And this may result in even if
it's a datadriven approach physically
unrealistic scenarios which might be
very costly leading to unnecessary or
overinvestments in the resources or
underinvestments in in the situations
where I need the most investments. Okay.
So what we find here just at a high
level is that we try to sort of train
what we call as the generative model
which is in this case a variational
autoenccoder details are not important
through uh 20 year of hourly data. So
it's a huge amount of highdimensional
data and what we see is that we are able
to learn lower dimensional
representations of these uncertainties
that we are expected and what we then do
is to sample as I mentioned in this
lower dimensional space to create new
scenarios which are risk relevant right
which are statistically and physically
plausible and what we then also do is to
emp uh is to leverage uh efficient
optimization tools in order to plan and
solve these large scale optimization
models under the uncertainty that we
just characterized.
Okay, so what this gives us here is that
it gives us a decrease in the runtime
for this large uh scale optimization
problems but more importantly a
reduction in the cost while maintaining
the robustness guarantees under future
uncertainties. So that's very important
to ensure the same level of robustness
under future uncertainties with lower
cost is a huge cane right and again this
approach avoids the over robustification
by so that because we don't have to then
consider implausible or impossible
scenarios uh this is an example try to
focus on the lower panel uh this is a
scenario example that I can actually now
generate a plausible as I said load
pattern solar capacity factor and
offshore wind pattern as well as onshore
wind pattern which I will not see in my
historical data at all. Okay, this type
of scenario will not be there in the
historical data at all but it is
statistically possible plausible and
physically realistic and it's a
high-risk scenario which means that this
scenario happens to have the highest
impact on my operations cost and that's
why I need to plan and invest for these
kind of scenarios. All right. Okay. So
what I want to express is that
generative models enable the robust
planning without building in the
overconservatism.
Okay. So that's my third case study.
Okay. Uh the final case study is the use
of large language models. So remember
that I first presented you this
challenge of interconnection cues where
various generation assets and loads are
facing this huge delays in connecting to
the grid because the grid operators need
to consider this number of scenarios and
run this complicated study reports.
Okay. So what happens is that these big
ISOs and market operators like ISO or
other other other uh independent system
operators they generate these study
reports and these are massive study
reports 200 300 pages they are you know
they are they are conducted by very
expert engineers at these uh at these uh
markets. Um so what we're doing is to
try to use large language models to
automatically extract data relevant data
uh from these uh from these uh reports
right um and then try to understand what
kind of decision-m rules these system
operators employ and which might be
revised under fork revisions right um
you know in in in more complex and you
know different ISOs interpret and
implement these rules differently so
what we want to do is to try to sort of
leverage um the LLM and optimization
framework in order to automatically
extract relevant parameters and data and
more importantly decision making
constraints from these textual
descriptions. Okay. And then integrate
it with our large scale optimization
models so that we can run these
optimization models under various
uncertainty scenarios in a
parallelizable manner for rapid scenario
analysis and decision-m support.
Okay.
So what we want to understand is how can
we leverage these messy documents which
are out there and try to conduct or try
to give very validated optimization
solvers which can be used by these
decision makers. Okay both the
generators the loads as well as the uh
system operators. Okay. So I'm going to
briefly discuss this process with you.
Uh so the first step is quite simple. It
is uh trying to understand how we can
leverage the uh spreadsheets, the
complex study reports and then parse and
chunk and embed and retrieve using
retrieval augmented generation and
create these structured data sources
right where which has the data on the
upgrade cost for various types of
upgrades you know reconductoring
transmission line upgrades etc etc delay
patterns for various types of loads and
generator request withdrawal region
reasons so when for example generators
withdraw from the interconnection cues
and other types of technical
requirements. So what we want and we're
already seeing some progress here in our
work is this kind of structured approach
to extract information that is useful
from these complex documents. Okay.
The second here is to create
mathematical constraints right from
these documents. So what we have is the
plain text data and the data or the
numerical data which is there in this
document and then try to extract what if
scenarios and then automatically
construct mathematical constraints that
we can embed in our optimization
problems. So for example you can have a
natural language description that
voltage stability requires a reactive
power reserves proportional to the
distance from the substation. It's a
it's a randomly generated constraint
which I pulled out but then it can be
mathematically already coded by the LLM
so that we can create an optimization
model and then solve it. Okay. So that's
the second kind of uh uh step and the
third step I think is the most important
and this we have a working paper called
Opihive which is available online if you
are interested. It basically says that
we can use also LLMs to generate
optimization for critical grid planning.
Okay. So what I want to say to you is
that there is a lot of approaches that
people have pursued in order to
integrate optimization and LLMs and
these are like some kind of sequential
interaction between LLM agents and
optimization right but what we are doing
here is that suppose so suppose I'm able
to create an ensemble of optimization
models right which are all consistent
with the requirements of the decision
makers and are are calibrated to the
data that I extracted from those reports
Right. And what I can do now here is
that I can now run right these multiple
optimization models and verify them for
correctness in a parallelizable manner
in order to do rapid scenario testing.
Okay. So so that's the kind of an
approach that I we have. We have uh LLM
based queries. We create solvers
instances test in parallel. We try to
sort of filter out uh you know the ones
which are mathematically incorrect and
semantically incorrect and then we build
this kind of a statistical inference
model which basically reliably tells me
what kind of model and solver are best
suited to give me the kind of results
that the decision makers would want.
Okay. Uh so basically what we already
have seen in this uh work of ours is
that we are substantively able to
improve the ability of this LLM
optimization pipeline uh to solve very
complex vehicle routing problems with
obstacles and complex combinatorial
optimization problems. And as we speak,
we are trying to extend this approach
already to develop solvers for
transmission expansion planning
decisions, right? to automatically
extract um from the ISO reports uh to
model the various tariff requirements
and then extract the model mathematical
constraint translations in an automatic
way and so that we can try to under
various policy reforms which are put out
by FIRK and other agencies conduct these
kind of scenario testing and stress
testing to provide decision support.
Okay. And the key message here is that
this aspect of statistically validated
solvers can substantively increase our
ability to leverage and integrate LLMs
into our optimization pipeline. So I'm
going to conclude in just a couple of uh
uh slides. So through this case study I
hope or case studies I hope that we
learned one the importance of having
coordinated planning right siting and
decision-m of renewables in a
complimentary spatial temporary compl
complimentary way under the
uncertainties of weather and climate
related scenarios the importance of
finding realistic worst case scenarios
through the possibly the use of
generative AI tools and the promise that
the integration of LLMs and optimization
show in accelerating these decision-m
processes. So the key message here is
that we should these tools and these
ways of thinking allow us to think about
uncertainties and interdependencies in a
in a systematic manner and in terms of
the path forward this has implications
for industry for policy and for research
but basically what I'm trying to suggest
here is that adaptation uh uncertainty
aware and cross- sector planning and
coordination is super important as we
think about planning and operating in
the age of data centerdriven energy
demand growth. All right. Okay. Thank
you.