I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob Stoner and
this is what if it
[Music]
works from the MIT energy initiative
this is what if it works a podcast
looking at the energy solutions for
climate change I'm Cara Miller you might
know me from the public radio program
Innovation Hub which I hosted and now
write the big idea column for the Boston
Globe and I'm Robert Stoner the
president of the Kendall Square project
and former director of the MIT energy
initiative and today we're talking with
Ernest munes former Secretary of Energy
under President Obama about what role
government has played in the energy
transition what role it can play and
what role it will play I think the first
thing to say without being polanish
about this is that Trump 1.0 had far
less impact on what was actually
happening in decarbonization for example
than many think and yeah you can't
really talk about decarbonization at
least not in the US if you don't look
ahead at our looming election and how a
second Trump term might unfold sure the
uh the Paris agreement was tossed out
now tossed back in by President Biden
but the Paris agreement in and of itself
does not present solutions to the carbon
challenge to the clean energy transition
mon is now the Cecil and Ida green
ameritus professor of physics and
Engineering Systems at MIT he's the
founding director of the MIT energy
initiative and the CEO of the Energy
Futures and nuclear threat initiatives I
asked him if Trump were to return to the
White House having explicitly said that
climate change is quote unquote
non-existent with the private sector
step in what would happen and what would
become of President Biden's Marquee
energy legislation the inflation
reduction act the IRA legislation that
vice president Harris where she to
become president in 2025 would
presumably build on Mon says it's not
all about the president whoever that is
frankly it's complicated the reality is
Congress has supported the clean
energy Technology Innovation agenda
pretty consistently in a bipartisan way
in a bipartisan way um especially in
areas like nuclear energy carbon capture
and sequestration Etc frankly uh you put
your finger on one of the important
Dynamics namely the private sector in
many ways kept carrying the clean energy
transition forward during Trump uh 1.0
and obviously uh with the support of the
current Administration Biden 1.0 but the
reality is private sector takes a lot of
risk uh with a lot of capital they don't
have a four-year time Horizon in the
energy business uh for sure it's a much
longer one and I believe that for many
years now the private sector has almost
entirely acknowledged that we are having
and we will continue to have a low
carbon transition the pace and the scale
are not fully understood but I think
there's a an understandable reluctance
to put a lot of money on the table for
uh carbonization when those could easily
become uh stranded assets however if
former president Trump wins the election
I think we have to distinguish between
two different Pathways one is that Trump
wins and the Republican Party takes both
chambers of Congress versus Trump wins
and the Democrats retain one chamber of
Congress or both but at least one
because the legislative options are then
quite
different however if president Trump
wins and controls if you like both
chambers of
Congress then a very important approach
to anything with budgetary implications
can come into play It's called
technically reconciliation
basically what it amounts to is any
budget related uh activity can then pass
with a simple majority in the Senate
versus the usual 60
votes the dots often aren't connected
that the last three
presidencies Obama Trump 1.0 and Biden
1.0 have all had their signature
legislative achievements accomplished
through reconciliation
Obamacare Trump tax cuts and
Ira so the difference between
controlling both Chambers and only one
chamber can be quite uh
significant if the one chamber scenario
plays out
however a trump presidency while being
very limited in its legislative
flexibility will still retain enormous
administrative
flexibility so for for example the
IRA I would find it very hard to believe
that the IRA would be
repealed in that scenario or that it
would be even modified in any very very
substantial
way however the president it's not
immediate it takes time to go through Ru
making but the ru making done in this
case by the treasury Department is very
very significant in terms of how the tax
credits in this case the IRA let's say
can be utilized there clearly will be
push back in that scenario from some
Republican Governors and and States
including members of Congress because
they have already grown to like various
aspects of this legislation like they
have wind farms and they're they have
wind farms they have they have hydrogen
hubs they have all kinds of things uh
existing or coming but nevertheless I
think in that scenario one would see
some significant administrative actions
taken by a trump presidency that would
certainly slow down although not
entirely derail in my view the low
carbon
transition you know I have a question
kind of for both of you since you've
both thought a lot about companies and
how they intersect with governments you
said something very interesting about
this idea
of that Trump 1.0 didn't send back the
clean energy agenda as much as you might
think a lot of Private Industry stepped
in are they doing that because a
consumers demand it B they've made like
ESG commitments to shareholders like why
are they doing that why are they
stepping in I think it's my sense is
that there's a social global social
movement toward decarbonizing the
economy in recognition of the importance
of addressing the climate change problem
so it's happening and and I don't think
the US is in a position to go it alone
and in the opposite direction nor is it
in our self-interest to do that okay so
they might be culturally ostracized for
not making the transition even if the
administration says well we don't care
about this think be culturally
ostracized I think they'll be investing
in stuff that's not going to have any
value in in the relatively near future
and that's a problem well OB would just
add that of course many of the large
corporations well all of the very large
corporation ations for sure are Global
in nature so they are satisfying Market
requirements in many many different
places and of course the large markets
are by definition in the developed
countries I'm not saying that they are
ignoring in any sense the developing and
emerging economies but the really big
markets the really big economies United
States Europe Japan of course you have
to add China in there which is I would
say mixed in terms of developed an
emerging emerging economy uh but China
itself of course has moved its Market in
many sectors pretty strongly towards the
energy transition not in all uh coal
plants remain obviously a very very
important part of their electricity
generation but for example right now in
the news uh it's all about electric
vehicles and what's going to happen as
they strive for the export Market we
know that they are already leader in
deployment uh and an export of of
renewable Technologies they've made
major commitments in this area and when
all is said and done I would go back to
what I said earlier even if the pace and
scale of the clean energy transition is
not understood not easily predictable I
mean we know what we would like but we
don't know what we're going to get when
the reality is We are following the
historical path of decarbonization of of
the Energy System you know we can go
into why that that's happening but but I
think it's a fact I think the private
sector understands and that's why fossil
fuel companies for example the oil and
gas companies it would be incorrect to
not think that they are genuinely
hedging their bets on the future in
terms of looking at Connected areas to
what they do like carbon capture and
sequestration and and hydrogen but you
also see some of the especially the
international oil andas gas companies
some of them going heavily into the
power sector for example with Renewables
so anyway I I just think it's a real
secular Trend just with uncertain pace
and scale I personally think that the
public interest in and pressure towards
decarbonization Will tip the political
system including in the United States
mainly through the impacts of extreme
weather the reality is and I'm not going
to get into the science of it but I
think the reality is that polling shows
that the public is more and more
certainly associating extreme weather
with global warming and climate change
uh they are seeing in many parts of the
country uh impact of things like
skyrocketing insurance rates we've had
some significant electricity outages in
various parts of the country from
extreme weather it's only going to
increase uh uh it's been predicted for a
long time it's happening and frankly I
don't want to sound uh kinly here but
the reality is the extreme weather and
the consequences of extreme weather are
more and more bringing a focus on the
impacts to the current generation as
opposed to Future
Generations we all knew the arguments
about preser serving the environment etc
for our grandchildren and uh we love our
grandchildren and our children but when
it's being felt in the pocketbook right
now I think that the attitudes are
shifting dramatically and eventually
that is what tips the political system
and my sense is that globally
governments around the world have taken
on board at some level as if their
societies that there's a problem here
and they have to address it and they've
begun to move that way and it's amazing
the degree there is inertia now in this
transition I mean large segments of the
Chinese economy for example now are
focused on becoming the renewable energy
manufacturer to the world I mean they
they did it with solar panels they've
done it with lithium ion batteries
they're trying to do it with EVS but
even even another area is steel you know
they're a huge steel producer and
they're very aware of carbon border
adjustment taxes beginning to come into
effect in Europe talk of tariffs in this
country and the use of tariffs as a
weapon very aware that their economy is
vulnerable to being too carbon intensive
in the not very far future and and in a
curious way they are the ones who are
driving the transition by enabling us
and moving very quickly themselves
there's always in the climate business
the uh the tragedy of the commons if you
like but the reality is that a place
like China for example the leadership
recognizes that the impacts of global
warming and climate change are going to
be felt very very directly in China and
there are other parts of the world the
Middle East is is an example where the
predictions of of heat and drought Etc
are really very very substantial and of
course fires the United States we've had
that but look at Canada look at many
places the exact manifestation of the
issues can be quite geographically
different but they tend to be pretty
uniform in terms of some
uh at least being very very socially
disruptive if I could go back Cara to
your original question just add one more
element of a stabilizing influence in
terms of how we go forward irrespective
of the coming
election the Ukraine war in particular
clearly put energy security onto the
front
burner and personally it's frankly it's
something that I've been saying for a
long long time
that the climate discussion the energy
security discussion and the social
Equity discussion should be viewed as
one discussion and not three separate
ones in the energy security
world after Russia's initial invasion of
Ukraine which I remind everyone was in
2014 not in
2022 the G7 in the EU I was energy
Secret at the time very explicitly came
together to kind of refresh uh how one
looked at energy security a refreshment
that really had not been done since the
oil embargos of the
1970s and one of the aspects of that
relook if you like was to explicitly
connect decarbonized energy sources with
energy security turning it around energy
insecurity is all about carbon and so I
think those conversations coming
together is also part of the reason why
we we clearly will have change depending
upon the election outcome but perhaps
not as Extreme as many think and
interestingly in in the new world of
renewable energy you can become energy
insecure by failing to have access to
critical materials by failing to have a
robust manufacturing sector by failing
to have access to cheap Capital it's an
opportunity for China to become very
energy secure where they haven't been in
the past except for coal but it's an
opportunity for the the United States if
it falls behind to become energy
insecure in in a way we really don't
want to and and so this is I think it's
a transition in the motivations and
thinking that that governments had to
undergo the third element just put put
on the table now again uh the the social
Equity part and here at MIT at the MIT
energy initiative and the Center for
Energy environment policy research we've
been doing now for six years the
so-called Roosevelt project the
Roosevelt project is all based on the
premise which I think is
incontrovertible and uh regrettably
becoming more and more clear that if we
do not address the legitimate concerns
of workers and communities about the
clean energy transition uh and have
affordable energy have a future for
these workers and communities we will
have intense headwinds in the clean
energy transition like political
opposition that's been seen the yellow
jackets in Europe for example was all
about the cost of energy we've seen it
here in the United States uh we're
seeing it in some of the major
especially again in Europe their recent
elections well let's face it have not
been pretty and the issues of what is
bubbling to the top of the priority list
was part and parcel of their drift to
the right so we have to balance clean
energy transition pace and scale with
energy security with affordability
reliability social Equity if we are
going to succeed in my view at any of
them and we need to succeed at all of
them you know I think the Europeans have
once again reinforced Kermit the Frog's
claim that it isn't easy being green and
the greens suffered a real setback in
this election and it's because I think
they're perceived to be driving the cost
of energy higher maybe not rightly but
with policies that insist on renewable
energy and investment in renewable
energy I'm not an expert on European
politics but I I think that the politics
are shifting around this as well
becoming more pragmatic in many ways so
I think this brings up an interesting
question which is if in Trump 1.0
climate policies did not get set back as
much as one might think that the private
sector no I didn't I didn't say climate
policies didn't get S back I climate
decarbonization Okay uh did not somehow
halt okay um because maybe the private
sector understands that if you're a car
company where you still have to compete
with companies around the world you you
know it doesn't necessarily ma
presidents change but there's a sort of
competitive trajectory you have to
understand then what is the right role
for government like what things should
governments be doing and what things do
governments not need to do because other
parts of society will take care of those
things
well first of all let me emphasize the
Innovation
agenda involving technology and business
models and policy those are all part of
an innovation agenda now the business
model uh Innovation is by definition
primarily obviously in the private
sector Technology Innovation side
there's no doubt that there remains a
critical role for the government at the
early stages if you like of the of the
Innovation uh road map certainly
supporting a lot of the crosscutting
basic science uh that that is needed
supporting uh some of the certainly the
early stage technology developments uh
building on that science in general but
I would posit and this becomes more and
more
controversial that the place where we
are at in terms of addressing climate
change in the technology ology
Innovation space I think needs to go to
the advanced
demonstration and early deployment
stages what is again called industrial
industrial strategy well so you're
seeing it today uh the infrastructure
law with regard to the uh energy sector
is supporting things like for example
hydrogen hubs there's going to be seven
or up to seven uh hydrogen hubs in
different parts of the country that is
trying to say that look we the
government we want to Kickstart both
hydrogen Supply and hydrogen
demand uh formation whether that will
happen uh remains to be seen but that's
a bet if you like the infrastructure law
similarly uh put forward carbon capture
and
sequestration hubs same idea to make
hubs specific locations to advance that
the government has been very very active
in uh trying to promote nuclear power
deployment in the United States we just
had uh recently the celebration of the
two new nuclear power plants uh coming
that came online in Georgia it was more
of a sigh of relief than a celebration
was um no it was a genuine celebration
uh the budget and the schedule were not
for the faint of heart but I will say
that uh um I was there these are called
the Vogal three and four units but I was
uh very happy to have a an extensive
tour of the new plants and I have to
tell you there's there was a visual
there that really impressed one namely
there was a screen showing the
instantaneous power output of the four
Vogal reactors every one of them
basically pegged at one point .2
gaw 4.8 GW of clean electrons coming out
it's pretty impressive it's similar to
the total amount of offshore wind energy
we might ever get well we'll we'll see
but um and it emphasized that it's
serving a very important function having
those almost 5 GW of firm power not
variable power but firm power like all
the time all the dispatchable ETC and in
fact so the reason I really mentioned
vogle vogle 3 and four were the two new
units the governor of Georgia Governor
Kemp Republican going back to the
earlier conversation he said publicly
surprised a lot of people when he said I
want to see Vogal 5 that means six as
well but the point is there's the the in
this case for example the department of
energy uh provided loan support to build
those reactors the department of energy
has Prov provided funding for two
so-called Generation 4 that has advanced
non-l lightwater reactors for the future
so the government is playing certainly
an important role there where the
motivations include the economy energy
security and the like but the fact is
it's clean firm power that we are going
to need a lot more of in the United
States in my view as we necessarily also
build up wind and soil
with some storage attached to it because
the reality is wind and solar very very
attractive the costs have come down
dramatically the cost of batteries have
come down dramatically for storage it
doesn't change the fact that they are
weather dependent sources and even in a
place like Texas where we have the most
Wind by far in the United States the
reality is in Texas in a typical year
there are probably 90 days 9 Z days in
that year with essentially no wind in
Texas and the Order of a week and a half
in a row of no
wind you got to have firm power to
complement the variable power and we're
going to have to find new ways of
organizing our electricity system to
Value much more The Firm power
contributions to Value the backup
contributions you can't run a system
if half or 70% of the electricity Source
may go away for over a week you're going
to have to have backup somebody has to
pay for it so we have a lot of work to
do to make this system work together but
frankly if we don't get there it won't
be because the technology isn't ready we
have a lot of Technology now we're going
to have a lot more technology in 10 15
20 years but we need the whole system to
function together including with
business model policy and Regulatory
Innovation right now we have a lot of
silos I would argue that for example
there are not very many people in
government who really understand how
large investment decisions are made by
the various players who do have very
Deep Pockets uh but are very committed
to uh using those Deep Pockets to get
them
deeper are we talking about private
sector companies here I'm talking about
corporations talking about Banks talking
about Pension funds uh there are many
many pockets of of deep Capital which
have also especially in the financial
sector as opposed to the corporate world
they have many many options as to how to
deploy those funds for maximizing return
which is the probably the highest level
priority for them they do want to
diversify and they are also hedging
their Futures etc etc but fundamentally
you have to make the Investments
investable and often policy makers don't
realize when a policy is not constructed
well to encourage the deployment of that
Capital but turning it around I would
say there aren't there aren't that many
players on Wall Street for example who
really understand how policy is made so
we need a lot of convening also of these
different sectors and of course the
Strategic investors like the corporates
for example they really need to come
together in ways that uh support the
investability of clean energy projects
they're the ones that have the trillions
maybe the tens of trillions in this
country that need to get deployed to get
these things out there yeah and and it's
they've got to have a profit motive for
doing it I think it our colleague David
Victor I think is UCSD
said the other day in a conversation
that you know clean energy Finance isn't
going to be clean energy Finance until
it's just
finance and I think that's right I mean
we've got to get these costs down there
but but that doesn't mean that policy
consistency by the federal government
and and strong signals isn't needed both
are and I and I and I do think we're at
some risk with the Trump Administration
although I don't think we're at risk of
of the the IRA or the B being canceled
or unfunded or they maybe slowed down a
bit I think we're more at risk of
inconsistency in policy that that might
cause some of that private sector money
to hang back a little bit because it's
not sure where we're going well on the
on the positive side I think one of the
very positive developments let's say in
the ira was precisely by changing the
time Horizon for the credits to 10 years
rather than the historically you know
one or twoe kinds of Horizons which
really impeded progress that's an
example of the policy world not having
really understood how to put their
incentives in place in ways that would
really incentivize but the reality is
today including in Biden Administration
has put some pretty forward-leaning
programs out there but the reality is
our approach uh in the United States I
would call carrots and
twigs uh the uh A variation on a theme
okay correct um and um and eventually
there won't be enough carrots that is if
we
succeed in this incentivization approach
eventually we don't have enough money in
the public sector to uh just keep
pouring money into clean energy programs
that are in fact scaling that's where we
have to make that transition to the
private sector and it's very unlikely
for that to happen in my view until we
get to a real carrots and sticks I mean
by Sticks what do I mean I mean for
example a carbon emissions price would
be would be an example uh and that that
resets the whole playing field it resets
how an investor makes decisions because
uh once we go to a carbon price it's
kind of assumed that um that will be in
place for a long long time and may be
growing over time and that that
influences which projects are going to
be profitable so I think that carrots
and twigs is the right policy now
frankly it's the only practical policy
uh right now but eventually and I just
can't say when I do think that the
extreme weather is going to tip the
political equation towards a real
negotiation in terms of uh how we are
going to condition the energy
Marketplace for a transition and I do
want to emphasize the word transition
because unfortunately too many of our
colleagues involved in the climate
discussion indulge themselves into
telling us how wonderful it's going to
be in
2050 but don't want to talk about the
hard work of 25 years of
transition that's what it's
about cuz if we don't have that
Viewpoint again to NE dots earlier will
never be able to address the social
Equity challenges without a real focus
on transition getting from here to there
what's the road map and so the point is
we have a lot of these pieces on the go
board but we have to start connecting
them and having a a long-term plan uh
how how that game of Go
[Music]
finishes so rnie you talked about
conditioning the marketplace which I
assume is
euphemistic way of talking about carbon
taxes at some level you mentioned carbon
taxes I said
pricing carbon how it goes in government
I I remember interviewing a couple
economists years ago I mean it had to be
10 years ago one of them being John
grber here at MIT of various stripes or
Republicans people had served in George
Bush's Administration they all agreed
there should be a carbon tax which I
just remember being the most shocking
conversation because at least economists
were in that at that time were kind of
on the same page but yes and that's late
in the game I mean Waxman Marky 2008
2009 2010 was we were so close and and
Obama made a choice it was it was he
going to spend his political capital on
that or Obamacare I think he probably
made the right choice that time but it
does beg the question are we ever going
to get to a carbon tax in the United
States or anywhere or is that just a
latent threat that the government can
sort of hang over the head of the
economy that drives the economy toward
doing the right thing for other reasons
I I personally believe that we
will that Tipping Point I mentioned I
think will end up with a an emissions
tax price whatever you want to call it I
think that something like this
eventually is going to happen where the
big tension will be in how the revenue
is
used I cannot name the name but let's
just say I not that long ago spoke with
a
prominent former Republican government
figure uh well respected in the Finance
Tax Arena and I was quite surprised when
this person said unequivocally he
supported the carbon tax
and we talked more and then we found
where there was a bit of a breakdown uh
in our views namely his view was all the
funds should go to deficit
reduction well that of course is
completely
regressive in the end that may be the
negotiation how much of this funding is
returned uh to the population in a
progressive way right how much goes to
budget balancing if I had to guess I
would guess that we may end up with that
that as the final negotiation do you
think that the US has a tendency to be
preachy in terms of you know of course
we want big economies like China and
India to try to use cleaner energy to
transition but in in a case like China
um a lot of our stuff potentially like
the stuff that we buy in the store from
Toys to bikes to blenders and whatever
is is potentially being contributing to
their emissions so do we not look at
ourself enough when we say to other
countries hey use cleaner energy buy a
fewer bikes or or
yeah obviously offshoring is an issue
but of course now what we're doing
particularly with the Biden
Administration legislative activity
where there's a lot of onshoring uh uh
going on to switch the subject slightly
not not intentionally but it it raises a
different issue as we are onshoring and
building data centers Galore especially
with AI and electrifying transportation
and electrifying space Heating and maybe
making green hydrogen electrolysis of of
water and maybe supporting a
cryptocurrency uh
uh uh world who knows we have today we
are seeing enormous growth in our own
electricity
requirements this you triggered it by
mentioning China in that context and
frankly I think the utilities are just
saying the truth that in the near term
the only way that this load can be
satisfied is by building more natural
gas plants so we have our own little
carbon load electricity load train wreck
in a certain sense but I think that uh
once again if we had some real planning
we could offset that because we
understand you know pretty well the
forcing of global warming from
greenhouse gases in the atmosphere and
uh what we need to do is uh uh not just
catch up in terms of the emissions level
but catch up in terms of the integrated
Force
of the atmosphere and the warming but
those discussions just are not happening
I think they are I don't know they they
would require some sophistication they
would require some some serious uh
analysis and modeling and everything
else and decision- making about priority
decision making about priorities I mean
AI is you know consuming a lot of energy
for things like Google Assistant uh you
know and and basically a lot of trivial
nonsense that that we could easily
dispense with but you're not going to
selectively tax it and I keep coming
back to a carbon tax as being the right
answer for a lot no I I agree with that
Rob but also I would say look the
reality is today the near-term load
growth in many parts of the United
States is driven 80 90% by data centers
that fraction will decrease as more of
the onshoring uh manufacturing plants
come online and more EVs and and and and
the like but but today it's really
driven there but I would argue that in a
digitized
world that frankly meeting the
load for data centers and AI large
language model training and the like is
frankly a national imperative for all
kinds of reasons including security so I
think that rather than arguing about it
we should just be talking about okay how
are we going to do this uh in a low
carbon world and there is a lot of
technological innovation going on to
make it possible I mean probably even
things related to this hydrogen
initiative we were talking about earlier
yeah and and by the way even in the AI
sector I think the amount of power for
example being required for these you
know gpus driving AI that can come down
by an order of magnitude now whether it
will just create 10 more cycles per
cycle we'll see but certainly Energy
Efficiency the surface has not been
scratched in that world yeah Energy
Efficiency in computer algorithms in
computer hardware in cooling hardware
and Concepts I mean I I just see this
across the board and and it is
interesting Ian but it's really got to
bear fruit correct we've covered a lot
of ground so if let's say President
Biden called you later this afternoon
which who knows could happen he never
calls me Cara okay but it might happen
later today um and and he said you know
what what's the one suggestion from both
of you what's the one suggestion you
would have that maybe like I'm not doing
Blank Slate just tell me what you think
it is but maybe something you think I
could do so like though you might
support a carbon tax you might also
think that's completely not feasible in
the current setup so but what's
something he could do that is not
currently being done and would be like
your top thing Ernie you want to say
what well first of all I would support
the carbon pricing and agree that he
can't do it right now uh the uh we're
just not ready frankly ready for that
for all the reasons we discussed earlier
but in terms of what may be doable I
would
actually say that he and his
administration should build on things
they have been starting to do in terms
of getting the whole electricity
infrastructure built out out and
straightened out this is the grit uh or
the grd uhhuh the fact is
electricity has been the lead horse and
decarbonization it is the lead horse and
decarbonization it will be the lead
horse in
decarbonization the needs are growing
dramatically we've just shifted from a
significant period where National
electricity growth was about a half% per
year to a place now where I think it's
roughly 1 and a half% per year and maybe
growing and certainly in some hotpots is
growing much faster than that having a
grid that functions and not just
regionally but inter regionally would
unlock a lot of other possibilities and
there's a lot of innovation that can be
used so if I take for example getting
very practical since you suggested
something that had to be practical uh
the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission
FK issued an order that was probably its
biggest step on transmission in over a
decade and it had some very useful
elements in it like 20-year planning for
regional grid buildout like very
importantly not discussed enough I think
is the encouragement of uh Technologies
to increase the capacity of the existing
grid new conductors and dynamic line
rating and new switching um Technologies
and modeling Etc however it also fall
short it did not consider interregional
planning it did not really consider the
permitting issues this is hard but I
think doable for example in Congress
there has been legislation it's still
kind of knocking around uh in terms of
trying to improve the permitting process
it needs a push so I would say really
addressing the
technology and Regulatory structures
needed to really build out the grid and
to
allow all the generation
Technologies to work to connect to real
loads Etc to connect faster I think
that's doable in the next four years it
it's an interesting priority because I
think it seems so like pedestrian or
unsexy you know but but in some ways
you're like well but we can't do the
cool awesome things if we have you know
the infrastructure of like what what
good is a new car if the roads are all
messed up we need a real a real push on
infrastructure uh and I agree I was
intentionally being non-sexy in that but
I would get I I will degenerate even
further and say that it's not only wires
but it's also on pipe
there's a I think terrific project in
the midwest to gather up CO2 emitted
from many many ethanol plants and bury
it sequester it except they can't get
permits to build the
pipelines so anyway so we have a a big
infrastructure challenge again I put the
electricity right up there as number one
uh and doable potentially uh but I
wouldn't ignore other parts of the
energy infrastructure as well maybe we
could make those Transmissions lines
sexier by making some of them super
conducting and Buried buried and buried
right do do you have a thought if um
President Biden called you later today
absolutely you had just one thing you
could contribute yes so I mean what I've
noticed is where we're successful and I
think of the IRA here we're operating
through the tax code and just just
changing the tax code not passing new
laws necessarily but allowing people to
deduct stuff uh or or providing rebates
in some ways or
subsidies so we got to do something
there at the same time we have very high
interest rates and it's making it hard
for people to buy houses and I can't
help thinking that somehow we could
combine these things you know allowing
them for maybe maybe using Federal money
to enable people to buy down points on
new home purchases to reduce their
interest rates if they sign up for some
sort of Energy Efficiency program
program and reduce their their
consumption of electricity natural gas
whatever it is Maybe by getting their
homes reinsulated on purchase or even as
as as a retrofit uh for people who are
refinancing their homes so I so I I
think that that's you know something
that needs obviously to be thought
through a lot more than I'm thinking it
through right now but I think we we need
to look for solutions that are
politically attractive and feasible and
where there are obvious problems that
can be solved at the same time as
solving the renewable energy problem I
mean there are programs uh particularly
for the less well-off yeah parts of the
population they tend not to subscribe to
those programs they need to be
strengthened and uh and also we I said
earlier about policy changes that can
help large private sector Financial
flows to projects there are also policy
changes needed for the other end of the
economic spectrum if you like in terms
of making
usable to them I will note that in the
current Administration the legislation
passed by Congress has a lot of elements
for addressing some of the social Equity
issues requiring things like Community
benefits plans or at least incentivizing
labor project agreements Etc the problem
is especially on the community benefits
plans uh is
that it's a new thing and there's still
a lot of figuring out uh how to do this
that's another thing which by the way a
president could also uh get some more um
energy behind really moving these
requirements for planning early with
communities in terms of what benefits
they will they will see from projects
get that really really really moving I
mean it's there but um I think there's
still a little kind of fumbling around
as people try to figure out how to make
the system work yeah well the the ones
who figure out how to make this system
work are the rich communities of course
where there's more capacity to govern
more experience more lawyers per capita
they get in there and they scoop up
these programs and and the social Equity
problems are exacerbated so I think that
there's probably a role to play perhaps
on on the government's part in
strengthening these communities in a
very deliberate way to enable them to
participate and and again we're seeing
that I think already beginning to happen
yeah finally I just wonder what your
level of optimism is I mean we've
there's a lot of uh hurdles to overcome
as we talked about ve what seems like a
very close election coming up could
easily go either
way what how do you think about not just
like the next six months but I mean the
next 10 or 20 years well first of all
you're speaking with two physicists who
are by Nature optimistic that that I can
say that about all physicists absolutely
oh okay yes all the ones I
know I do think we're going to get there
there as as usual we tend to get there a
little bit too slow and that's probably
going to be the case but uh here as well
but the reality is when all is said and
done my optimism rests on the fact that
we will
have all the technology we need
available I think at reasonable cost in
the context of what we will be paying by
not addressing the the problem there are
so many examples that I think are going
to push us over the top like the crazy
Insurance costs that are coming in
various parts of the country the real
pain and suffering that people are
experiencing from from extreme weather
literally having to move in many in many
cases and of course globally we see all
these dislocations of populations war is
part of that but so is climate change a
big part of that and and frankly those
often get intertwined as well so it may
be for for fortunate reasons uh but I
think we we are going to have the kind
of Tipping Point that I mentioned
earlier we're going to have to get the
carbon markets right we're going to have
to get policy better aligned with
finance and the technology will be there
to um hopefully save the day the
technology is coming there's no question
about it the cost reductions are coming
and I think public opinion is coming and
it's Winston Churchill famously said the
Americans can be counted on to do the
right thing after exhausting every other
possibility we're on our we're on our
normal trajectory
[Music]
here Ernest monise was Secretary of
Energy under President Obama he's now
the sisle and Ida green ameritus
professor of physics and Engineering
Systems at MIT founding director of the
MIT energy initiative thank you so much
it was a great conversation pleasure
thanks Ernie thank
you what if it works is a production of
the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend to listen and remember
to subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu SLP podcasts and
you can learn more about the work of the
energy initiative and the energy
transition at energy.
m.edu our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob ster thanks for listening
[Music]