[Music]
[Applause]
I started off by being a CIRC scholar
last year and decided that I would want
to do it again this year. And the reason
was I originally came to MIT just
knowing that there were really big
pressing challenges within the space of
computing, artificial intelligence and
all kinds of developments in society
that we need to really have a pulse on.
I found that being a circ scholar has
really given me the opportunity to work
with some of the brightest minds here on
campus and really advance a bit of
research in whatever way possible.
>> I thought that the mandate of CIRC was
so interesting and unique. The idea of
blending like social and ethical
responsibility with the accelerating
amount of computing work that we're
doing in the area was really exciting.
Um, and I also like the mentorship
aspect. You got a lot of one-on-one time
with your research adviser and got to
work in a group setting. And I thought
both of those were things I really
enjoyed this semester.
>> CIRC offers one of the few opportunities
at MIT to think very seriously about how
scientific research can be used um on
the plane of ethics and the public good.
Um so we spent you know an entire year
thinking hard about how are these
technologies that you know people are
working on very hard at universities
like MIT how can we use them responsibly
well um in a way that promotes values
like democracy and good decision-m um so
I think it really is where you can bring
some of those more fundamental human
questions um onto the science that we do
so well.
Oh, it's been wonderful. Um, every
single week we get to meet with our um,
CIRC fellow and we get to, you know,
have great conversations, read read
journal articles. Um, and and we got to
conduct our own study, design it, um,
see it through to the end and that's not
an opportunity you get so often as an
undergraduate to really um, study
exactly what you care about. So, it was
wonderful.
>> I thought it was amazing. I was lucky
that my adviser was like very very
dedicated to helping us understand every
single step. So he walked us through
papers. He had us run code ourselves and
then when we went into the part where we
started doing our independent projects,
he was there every step of the way. So I
think it's a great way to learn really
quickly and rigorously but also feel
like you're truly understanding the work
that you're doing.
[Music]
I think I would say to be open. Uh all
of the different project areas are so
different. Um and I picked one that
wasn't really a huge intersection with
the work that I do, but I feel like I
was able to grow a lot as a researcher
and do work that I'm proud of. So I
think what CIRC is about is trying new
things and trying to make the world a
better place. So I think that is
something I would recommend. I would say
for future scholars definitely
understand that coming in with a
research question is very valid but also
understand that the world changes a lot
faster than us coming in with just one
idea. Read as much as you can. Talk to
people who work in the field currently.
It's really good that you're at MIT so
you have a lot of resources available
and definitely just reflect on what you
learn. Apply that forward and really try
to see how things will evolve in the
future.