And um and now finally, last but not
least, we have Anelise Maya who's um
from MAT Hoy joint joint program. Take
it away, Anelise.
[Applause]
Who are you? Really think about that for
a
second. Now, I don't want to give anyone
an existential crisis just yet. So, I'll
give you an
answer. This is you. You're around 30
trillion human cells all stuck together.
Now add 38 trillion microbial cells to
your self-image. Those 38 trillion
microbes are spread throughout almost
every part of your body, but the vast
majority are located in your digestive
tract. Given that slightly over half the
cells in your body belong to your
microbial roommates, it perhaps isn't
surprising that keeping those roommates
happy is critical for your overall
health. Dispiosis or an imbalance in the
community composition of your gut
microbiome affects every system in your
body. It's linked to everything from
acid reflux to Crohn's disease to
cardiac disease, even depression,
schizophrenia, and
Parkinson's. These aren't tentative
correlations either. A recent reanalysis
paper showed that across multiple
disease types, significant alteration in
species richness and diversity occurred.
Now, while microbiome changes can be a
result of many things things,
environmental effects, diet, stress,
genetics, etc., we also know that these
links to disease aren't even just
correlative. Multiple studies have shown
that disease phenotypes can be induced
by replicating the disease associated
microbiome in an otherwise healthy
individual. In a notable case,
depression was induced in rats that were
grown in a micro-free environment by
inoculating them with the fecal
microbiome from depressed
humans. From acid reflux to anxiety,
Bbots are here to
help. Bots are tiny autonomous machines
that act sort of like synthetic
superpowered probiotics. These tiny
machines integrate into your gut
microbiome.
Depending on the type of Bbot, they
might set up shop in your stomach, small
intestine, or colon. There they perform
the chemical reactions that your gut
micro microbiome needs to get back on
track. Bots are inspired by nature.
These reactions are performed by
proteins just like they are by the
microbes inside you. Unlike in those
microbes, our proteins are ultra stable.
Years of testing and modifications to
the protein sequence ensures that once
you swallow the capsules containing your
Bbots, the proteins we've packed in can
do their job for
years. Though they're located in the
gut, different Bbots are curated to
perform reactions that benefit many body
systems. I'll give you a couple
examples.
In the stomach, Bbots might perform
reactions needed to synthesize vitamin
B12, release compounds that will inhibit
helicoacttor pylori, or stimulate the
growth of lactobacillus acidophilus.
Bbots can even add new functionalities
to your microbiome. One of the most
popular is a Bbot that can produce
fotadine and sissue. Fotadine is the
active ingredient in Pepsid. There's
some in my bag. It's a proven way to
control acid reflux. Vitamin B12 is
critical for many bodily functions and
statistically probably I said 20 but I
think it's going to be more like 30 uh
30 of us in this room have insufficient
levels. H pylori is the causitive act u
agent for most stomach ulcers but
lactobacillus acidophilus on the other
hand can help reduce the bloating and
nausea associated with IBS and lactose
intolerance among other things.
Now, I'm sure all the grad students in
this room want to hear what Bbots can do
for the brain because I don't think
anyone makes it through grad school
without developing crushing
anxiety. Bbots stimulate and in some
cases perform synthesis of compounds
like short chain fatty acids, indole3
propionogic acid, GABA and pilo lactose.
The role of these metabolites is
complex, but in the right amounts they
can reduce central nervous system
inflammation, increase bloodb brain
barrier integrity, prevent degradation
of neurons, and balance
neurotransmitters. These all serve to
alleviate anxiety and depression. They
can make ADHD symptoms more manageable,
prevent neurodeenerative degenerative
disease, among other
things. Okay, the biochemistry is mostly
over, I promise. So let's switch over to
the mechanics of how Bbots work. So this
is an image of some Bbots that'll take
up residence in your stomach. So note
the scale. Bbots are about the same size
as most of the other microbes in your
gut. These strings at the end are
fimbria and they allow specific
attachment to in this example the mucosa
cells that line the
stomach. This honeycomb texture prevents
other microbes from tethering to them
and interfering with their function.
Bbots are ready to go when you receive
them. Once you ingest the capsules
they're stored in, they'll find their
spots in your gut and get to
work. Let's quickly run through the
simplified BBOT diagram. So, here are
those attachment fibria we've already
discussed. In the middle is the energy
source for Bbots. Using chemical energy
like real microbes do requires too much
metabolic flexibility. Instead, we've
designed this tiny energy harvester. It
uses pzo electric energy. So that means
it gleans uh energy from vibrations.
We've designed it to be able to respond
to a large number of frequencies
enabling it to get sufficient energy
just from your natural
movement. Those cloudy shapes are the
protein catalysts. Depending on the
type, some might be docked on the BBOT
membrane, others free floating, and
still others linked to the energy
harvester. The latter proteins need an
energy input to do their job. When the
desired substrate comes in through these
transporter pores,
uh, it brings these two protein subunits
together. Proteins are conductive, so
we've keyed these to undergo the
confirmational change needed to do the
reaction when a current passes through.
The last few components are engaged only
when deactivation of a Bbot is
required. If a user decides they no
longer want a certain BBOT, they can go
into the Handy User app and trigger its
deactivation. Of course, consumer uh
customer support can also do this
remotely if
necessary. There are three simple
components needed for deactivation. The
Bluetooth receiver, a lipid vesicle
holding signal peptides, and a receptor
attached to the polar
fimria. First, the Bluetooth signal is
received from the user app that allows
an electric pulse to be transferred from
the energy harvester to the vesicle.
that then disrupts the lipid membrane
allowing the peptides inside to
escape. The signal peptides bind to the
dissolution receptor and that uh binding
lets the receptor start a cascade that
results in the dissolution of those
attachment fimria. Once the Bbot is
loose, it'll be flushed from the body
like food
waste. Okay, thanks for holding on
through that sprint introduction to
Bbots. But we here at BBOT Incorporated
aren't just here to offer you a nature
inspired single dose treatment that can
be customized to fit your needs. That's
not enough for us. We're continually
pushing the envelope. For example, due
to our recent breakthrough, we're
offering new Love Bugs Bots. They
augment your natural pherommones just to
give you that extra sparkle out there.
We've also developed uh specialized BBOT
mixes that emphasize efficient nutrient
extraction from poor quality diets and
we offer them at a subsidized rate to
low-income families. Just doing our part
to help fight food insecurity in
America. Okay, give me a sec to let me
my break
character. In my piece presubscribe, we
opened on a young scientist named Katie
as she presents Bbots to various
possible
investors. If I was trying to leave here
with all of you having in committed
money to my new BB bots venture, I'd
probably stop the presentation
here. However, that's not what I'm here
to do. I don't need to explain to this
audience that all technology comes with
drawbacks and social and ethical
complications. For example, this behind
me, uh, those are the terms and
conditions for the Amazon
Alexa. Yikes. In presubscribe, we meet
Brier, a young man from Ellensburg,
Washington. Throughout this piece, he
experiences some of the major benefits
of Bbots. Brier elected for their
balance mix to address his anxiety and
recurrent panic attacks, but then
unfortunately discovers how the
magnitude of those benefits might serve
to amplify the drawbacks of medical
technology when it's controlled by
corporate
interests. It's no secret that
privatized for-profit medical industry
in the US propate propagates systemic
inequities. Health in health outcomes
for marginalized groups for even routine
pro procedures are significantly worse
than they are for white wealthy
cisgender people and these statistics
will undoubtedly continue to worsen
given the policy changes we're seeing
today in presubscribe I touch on a few
separate factors that come into play
because of the for-profit nature of
bbots first I question how regulatory
bodies will regulate technology like
bbots that to some degree transcend
traditional
categories. Here, bubots are marketed
effectively as a supplement, so they
don't require the same level of FDA
approval. They can be put to market much
more quickly and don't require
prescription or costly doctor's
appointments. However, supplements are
rarely covered by insurance
providers. Secondly, industrial
innovation require relies on patents.
Patents provide protection and thus
safer profitability for 20 years once
initiated. and strategic modifications
to the technology can enable effective
extensions. The ethics of patents in the
medical world aside, it does mean that
in the early days of Bbots, meaningful
competition would be easily
nullified. However, the main focus of
this piece rests on the decision to
convert access to Bbots to a
subscription model. Given the meteoric
success of the subscription economy,
this probably seems like a logical
choice and one that might seem logical
to consumers given that we already pay
monthly for our prescriptions among a
myriad of other
things. Subscription services offer a
guise of affordability. What's $8.99 a
month for unlimited streaming, right?
However, incremental price increases are
a near ubiquitous practice among subs
subscription services. Even if advanced
notice is obstensively provided, these
changes are often missed by subscribers.
For example, how many of you have
Netflix? Netflix just increased. Thank
you. Uh its standard plan rate to $17.99
a month this year, and our regular
prescription drugs aren't exempt from
these sorts of cost increases.
The top 25 Medicare Part D drugs have
about doubled in price since market
launch and 21% of US adults have
foregone necessary prescriptions because
of the cost. Now, Bbots aren't Netflix
and nor are they your daily SSRI.
However, in presubscribe, the monthly
cost of Brian's Bbots follow the same
trend. And like many of us, Brian wasn't
keeping a close eye on the automatic
withdrawals for what he thought would be
a consistent monthly expense. It wasn't
until he received notice of failed
payment from the company and a warning
of imminent termination without payment
that he realized the price had rocketed
out of range of his budget. The
Bluetooth enabled termination pathway of
Bbots grants the company unfettered
ability to do just that. Terminate with
limited notice and recourse in a way
that's less like cancelling Hulu and
more akin to the bank repossessing your
house and then burning it
down. Briar's Bbots had been effective.
His baseline anxiety was minimal and
flare-ups were manageable. Like all
Bbots, they performed critical functions
within his stabilized microbiome and
were efficient producers of important
cellular
metabolites. Those Bbots may by
necessity end up being the primary
source of some of these important
metabolites.
So each circle here represents a microbe
and each line that connects them
indicates a relationship based on one or
more
metabolites. Especially if those
metabolites produced by Bbots have
widespread downstream uses, other
microbes in the ecosystem can become
dependent on Bbots for these products.
This can result in Bbots becoming a
central node in that the metabolic
network, a keystone if you will.
If you suddenly remove the keystone, you
lose the source of those products and
the functions needed to keep the e
ecosystem stable and functioning. As a
result, the ecosystem falters or might
even collapse, leaving it vulnerable to
replacement by an unhealthy disbiotic
system. This would manifest as
aggressive, long-asting withdrawal
effects. After Brier's BBOT were
deactivated, his anxiety returned worse
than ever, accompanied by depressive
symptoms, severe cramping, bloating, and
nausea. If you stop paying, no company
that I know of would offer to slowly
wean you off, connect you to a doctor to
manage the transition, and find cheaper
alternatives. Presubscribe ends with a
statement from one of the founders of
the company. Dr. Badachara severed ties
with Bbots shortly after they introduced
their subscription
model. Bbots were never going to be a
oneanddone cure. They're closer to a
prosthetic, a pacemaker for your gut. No
company should be able to suddenly turn
that off if you can't make a payment one
month. I still think that BBOT can and
will do a lot of good if they're put in
the hands of those that aren't in it for
the profit. Thank you.
[Applause]
Yeah. Uh, super interesting. So, I guess
to first to start this question, I will
divulge my medical history. So, I have
an autoimmune condition as do something
like 10% of all Americans. So, it's
actually really common. And one of the
annoying things about that is as you get
older oftentimes certain foods no longer
agree with you. Um, and it turns out
it's really hard to figure out what
exactly might be the issue because if
you think about it, you know, you like
eat a piece of pizza, you don't know
like all a sudden your stomach hurts.
You're like, "All right, is it the
cheese? Is it the gluten? Is it the
garlic? Is it the onions?" You know, you
don't know. So, um, I'm wondering if you
think Bbots instead of just being able
to use to treat something could also
have a use to diagnose as well.
Yeah, that's a great question and I
guess a great suggestion. Um, I think
there's definitely a possibility for
that. Uh I would imagine that that would
have to do with kind of characterizing
which metabolites might accumulate that
aren't being processed as they should uh
either by your microbiome that for some
reason isn't being you know maintained
by your
uh body as it is um
or you know just like by your ability of
your cells to process those ingredients.
However, I think at the moment our
understanding of the kind of
metabolic structure of the gut
microbiome isn't quite advanced enough
that we could say, "Okay, we're seeing
you that seeing that you have an
accumulation of
fructose. That means that you need to
cut out these things." Something like
that might actually be a little bit
simpler. It might be okay, you cut out
apples. Um, but for anything beyond kind
of a general intolerance, I don't know
that we're there yet. Um, but I
definitely think we could get there.
Great.
Thank you for for that. And I I sort of
share your sense of some of the the
pitfalls of technologies like this in a
for-profit health care system. But I I
wonder if you could say a bit about how
things look in a not for-profit
healthare system. So there's still going
to be limited resources and there will
be kind of decisions about in investment
in kind of speculative potentially uh
resource in startup resource intensive
technologies like this versus proven
technologies that might be distributed
more widely. So could you say
like how you see the the sort of ethical
scenario of things like this playing out
uh potentially better or maybe not in in
that kind of not for-profit uh
environment. Yeah, definitely. So, full
disclosure, uh I'm Canadian. I grew up
with universal healthcare and I think
something like this and you know, most
things would work much better in that
environment.
Um I think for this to work out the best
way it possibly could would be for it to
probably start in an academic
environment and kind of stay within that
for much of the development.
um
the at least within Canada the funding
available for research is in general
much smaller than it is in the US and
you know the venture capital is just not
there in the same way which does make
that sort of development more difficult.
Um but I think if there were you know
governmental
uh regulations in place that stipulated
if you are creating a medical technology
um first that it must
undergo rigorous classification as to
you know what we class this is. So Bbots
I think you could get through as a
supplement but they really aren't. Um,
and if you had to do uh once you've kind
of determined what it is, if you're
going to do some sort of clinical trial,
it has to be paired with multiple
academic labs that maintain a connection
throughout the entire process. Something
like that.
Great.
Thanks. I think I want to ask a question
about the economics rather than the
technology. So, oh no.
Um,
so the beat bots are developed by a
for-profit company that presumably
wouldn't have been incentivized to
develop it if there had been no prospect
of making money off of
it. And so I'm not really sure
what you're describing some some bad
thing that goes on when they increase
the price. And I agree it's bad when
prices go up,
but there's a reason. When prices go up,
it incentivizes other companies to get
into the market or develop alternative
technologies. And if there's no profits
to be made from healthcare innovations,
then things like this won't be invented
in the first place. So, I just feel like
you're being a little bit too uh
throwing too much shade on the profit
motive. You can never throw too much
shade on the profit motive. Um, no, I
mean it's a good point and the question
of um, for example, patents in the
medical
industry goes back and forth kind of on
that point. Is it giving a monopoly or
is it actually inciting competition and
iteration? And I think most schools of
thought land on the latter that, you
know, patents are important. Um, and
that's in terms of, you know,
profitability. That's kind of why I do
think it should start from an academic
setting and be linked to that throughout
development because there is motivation
that isn't just how much money can we
pump out of this and then once it
becomes
um something that is produced by a
company but regulated um and dispensed
by the
government then you know prices might
still go up but that's not landing on
the consumer.
and you're not putting consumers in a
place where they have
to see if they can make that every
month, which I know is the case with all
prescriptions in countries that have
non-universal healthcare. Um, I think BB
bots just kind of take that to a a next
level of what that would look like.
Um, I do recognize the
I think the underlying question is an
extremely debated one. So, I'm really
only offering my opinion there. Um, but
I do think it
is it's an important thing to consider
all sides and I definitely don't want to
discount that.
I disagree. Uh, I think profit is bad.
So, you know, I think you're right. Um
so my question is actually about
um not about capitalism at all. Uh it's
about um if you think about maybe
something similar which is insulin
pumps, right? Insulin pumps are a
fantastic technology um that keep lots
of people alive. There's a whole sub
community of people who hack their
insulin pumps because they don't like
the schedule that it's on, right? And
they've noticed it doesn't work well for
them, right? And so there's whole
subcommunities of patient advocates that
hack them and try to make sure that the
insulin delivery works well for them,
right? Which has dangers, right? But
there's a lot of people who are very
happy with that. Um, you could also
imagine somebody, especially if it's
Bluetooth enabled, hacking a device and
having it do something really bad to
you, right? So not the company, right?
But, you know, a person who wants to do
something bad. Um, do you have any
thoughts on how you can maybe uh make
technologies that are acting in your
body like we already have for insulin
pumps safe to this kind of sabotage
hacking? I mean, hospitals are already
held hostage by hackers, right? Yeah,
it's a great a great question.
Um, with Bbots, the way they're
currently designed, really the only
thing the user can do is turn them off.
And once they're off, they're out of
your body. Um, that's not to say that if
someone is turning them off willy-nilly,
there won't be adverse effects. Clearly,
we're seeing that when the company is
terminating them.
Um, however, I'd imagine in a case where
a user is choosing to terminate them
voluntarily,
um, there would be kind of safeguards in
place and suggestions that you contact
customer support on how best to do that.
Um, so because the Bbots that you choose
are preloaded with proteins, those
proteins can only do certain reactions.
Um, yeah. So I think the potential for
abuse in that way is is lower and the
customizability that is inherent in
having this Bluetooth
technology would actually potentially
give users the opportunity to make small
changes that benefit them in the way
that potentially slightly changing the
insulin schedule would
without giving undue harm.
Great. Nancy,
thank you. This is fantastic. Um, thank
you for presenting this one. And I say
this as a Sloan graduate student. So,
back to the business thing. Oh, no. But
as some as someone who like see, you
know, principled uh innovative leaders
underscore the principled part. So, I I
understand where we're coming from from
like the profit piece, but I can't help
think about how the revenue model could
be different here. I'm curious to get
your thoughts because I think in the US
we have a huge issue with like sick care
instead of healthare. Um and so this to
me when I was like just like reflecting
on the beginning of your presentation
comes across as like could people pay
instead of the subscription piece but
pay for like the benefits that they get
like the healing that they get as a
result of like having a healthier gut.
I'm just curious if like have you
thought about that in terms of you pay
for result as opposed to just like
access on like a monthly cadence which I
agree is a slippery slope and you know
capitalism has all these tentacles and
etc. But like I'm curious to get your
thoughts on if how we could start this
could also be a way to change the way we
think about healthcare in the US and
beyond. Thank you. Yeah, that's a
fantastic point. Um, and the kind of
subscription idea that I uh offer here
is just one example of how that could
kind of go wrong. I think the um paying
for results is really a great option.
Um, I do think I think you would kind of
need to have
uh impartial evaluators in place. And I
don't know exactly who that would be. if
it would still be your primary care
physician who then starts you on this
regimen, which I guess is kind of the
case um with uh prescriptions and
treatments nowadays. So, if something
isn't working, you change it.
Um but in that, you're not really you're
not really paying for results. Um Oops.
Yikes.
Um, I definitely see that as something
that would
um produce innovation because a company
would
be dedicated to making something that
works better and works faster and works
longer. Um, yeah, the the mechanics I'm
not exactly sure of, but I definitely
think that's a really good uh potential
route to keep
this safe and beneficial for everybody.
Great. So, the last question is from
Amanda. So what is the advantage of
these kind of approach compared to
actually using real bacteria maybe
genetically engineered to actually uh
you know do what they are that just
seems like a a much simpler technology
to to uh deploy than than something like
this uh which uh seems much more
complicated. Yeah. Um great
question.
So a lot of us already take probiotics.
If you don't you probably should.
Um,
and those definitely really can help.
And if you have a gut microbiome that is
really
disregulated, using, you know, eating a
lot of yogurt is not going to fix
everything. We do already have
treatments in place that are a little
more extreme to kind of replace an
unhealthy microbiome and that's
primarily through fecal transplants.
Um
those offer less control and
customization than something like Bbots
would. Um, it
also while you could genetically
engineer these bacteria,
um, I think having the security of the
longevity of something like Bbots and
the understanding that this is exactly
what they're doing, they are producing
just these compounds and responding in
just these ways would make them a lot
uh, easier to implement and would likely
act faster than trying to get uh,
natural bacter to establish a foothold
uh in your body.
Thank you.
Well, um thank you so much, Anelise.
Thank you. So, now it's time for the
judges to sequester in your special
room. Um,