I'm Cara Miller. And I'm Rob Stoner. And
from the MIT Energy Initiative, this is
What If It Works, a podcast looking at
the energy solutions for climate
[Music]
change. Today, we talked to a serial
entrepreneur who insists sustainable
alternatives do not have to be that
complicated. A lot of people expect
technology to be very fancy and
therefore very expensive. And so when
you see simple
solutions, people often overlook them.
That's Ariel first, a professor of
chemical engineering at MIT. She's the
co-founder of multiple startups. And so
that's one of the challenges that we
faced in our research is people say,
well, it's so easy. Is it really this
technological advance? And we say it is
because it's accomplishing what we want
to accomplish just without hundreds of
millions of dollars of infrastructure
required. In a minute, we're going to
talk about athletic wear, believe it or
not. But before we do, the key to lots
of first environmentally minded
breakthroughs is something pretty small.
Actually, it's very, very small. My
research has always been at the
intersection of engineering and biology.
And I think people often underestimate
what biology can do. So my lab looks a
lot at the natural environment and the
microbes that are there. And they can do
pretty much any chemical process that we
want to do and that chemical engineers
have been working for hundreds of years
to try to accomplish, but they can do it
more efficiently and in a living
organism that can also stay alive while
it's doing that. So if we look to those
systems that have this uh head start on
us through evolution, then we can come
up with simpler solutions. Which brings
us to athleisure and a conversation that
first had with one of her undergraduate
students. One of them was telling me
about waste in the US and the average
person in the US throws out about 80
pounds of clothes a year and almost all
of that is polyester. So, we got to
thinking, well, is there a way for us to
help with this problem? There are places
in the world now, especially in the
global south, where you can't even see
the ground because there's so much
textile waste. But the waste is not
coming from the global south. It's
coming from the global north from places
like the US. And when you donate your
clothes or when you recycle your
clothes, that's where they often end up.
And so then they're either burned, which
is releasing toxins into the air that
these people breathe, or they're left to
degrade slowly on land. And again, this
ties back into our goal of equity,
right? It's really inequitable for
people in the global north to be heavy
consumers of these products and then
ship them off when they're done to be
someone else's problem. And many of
those clothes are made out of
plasticbased fabrics like polyester,
like spandex. So if you break them down,
you encounter a new set of problems. So
one of the challenges we see with a lot
of plastic recycling is that when we do
it with current methods, we end up with
microlastics. And these generally end up
in the ocean or in drinking water or in
food systems. And the health effects of
them aren't totally known, but they're
probably not great. So, our goal was to
figure out how we can take these
polyesters, these things that they make
most of the fast fashion clothes out of,
and turn them back into things that
companies would want to use. Then we can
basically circularize the fast fashion
economy. So, you're not generating more
of these starting materials that
generally come from fossil fuels, and
you're instead recycling it from these
clothes. and Ariel first and her
students figured out a way to do it.
How? So, this was actually inspired by a
technology that we had in the lab and we
were thinking about ways we could better
use it, which is um basically our
ability to just decorate microbes with
these proteins that can do whatever we
want them to. So, we pick the right
protein and it can do whatever task we
tell it to. And the great thing is we
can basically freeze dry these microbes.
So we can turn them into astronaut ice
cream if you've had that or if you've
seen the freeze-dried fruit. It's not
that good, but but it works really well
for killing the microbes but keeping
these proteins active. So we end up with
this really light powder that is very
very active and that means we can make
kg of this stuff for dollars and so it
really decreases the cost of protein
materials which has been one of the
challenges in bioengineering. And so we
were you know thinking about what we
think these would be great for. And the
great thing is even synthetic clothes
have a lot of chemical bonds that look
like chemical bonds in our bodies. And
what that means is that there are
proteins out there that can chew up
those bonds and split them. And so we
went searching for some proteins that
can do that. We found some and we were
able to kind of decorate cells with
them. And we found that they can chew up
polyester, the synthetic material, very,
very quickly. So this is what I like
about your style. Again, you're not
solving the naive problem that would
come to mind at first. Eat this stuff,
make it go away. It's turn it into
something we can use and recycle it and
create a loop. And that's sort of the
definition of sustainability, I think.
But again, this is not coming from me.
This is coming from the high schoolers
and undergrads that we work with who say
things like, well, most people when they
do plastic recycling, if they're doing
it kind of to the end product, it ends
up as CO2. So, how are you really
solving a sustainability problem if
you're generating CO2? And so, we were
thinking about how we can kind of bypass
that step. It's really hard to change
people's behavior, right? So, instead of
asking people to potentially not shop at
their favorite stores, we're making
decisions that would allow them to do
things in a circular way. You know,
there's a lot of industries that are not
going to be able to be decarbonized,
especially in the near term. So, what
can we do to stop generating more CO2
and maybe take some of those emissions
and use them to generate starting
materials again to circularize these
economies? Okay. So, when you have that
shirt that like nobody wants anymore and
it's made of polyester and then you
unleash the microbes and they eat it and
you like hold up this test tube and
there's like a little liquid in it,
right? And it's like this is all that's
left of the shirt. What is that? What is
in that test tube? So, that is what's
called monomer. So that's the small
chemicals that they make these polymers
out of, which is just a fancy word for
the things they make the thread that
makes polyester out of. So they're just
the polyester starting
materials. So the great thing is,
especially for polyester specifically,
is those molecules look like things that
microbes in soil eat. So in addition to
being able to use these for chemical
recycling, you could also just use them
as kind of feed stock for microbial
processes. So, where's the catch? How
come we're not using this? Or maybe we
are. So, the catch right now is most of
our clothes are not just polyester. So,
what we're working on now is making more
of these astronaut ice cream materials
that have different proteins on them so
that you can throw in a mix of things to
degrade whatever mixture of waste you
have. Again, I see. So, you don't have
to sort the clothes, which would be an
expense. Exactly. You get smart. So what
is in clothes that microbes that you
don't yet have the microbes to eat? So
things like nylon is a pretty prevalent
one especially in athleisure or elastin
which is what's in all the stretchy
athleisure material. When you look at
them often they have mesh panels or
things like that that are different
materials and so you have to be able to
chew up all of it. I guess there's sort
of two things you could do. one is like
the whole cycle as you say you could
degrade a shirt and then you could have
maybe the building blocks to make a new
one so you don't have to use petroleum
as you said to like do it again but it
also seems like even if you can't sell a
company on like let's go full cycle like
let's do this you can at least say this
is better than throwing it in the trash
can than chopping it up into little bits
as you say in like microplastics and
they're wherever at least to totally
degrade it and then throw So that what
was in the test tube away is far better,
right, than what we're doing now. Yes,
definitely. And one of the things that
is really fantastic about this is you
don't need any chemicals to do this
degradation. So in addition to thinking
about chemical engineering scaled
processes where you would have this in a
large reactor or whatever, can we use
things like at home composters where you
would throw in our microbes and some
water with your clothes because that's
all we need to do this degradation. So,
if you can do that, then you could do it
at home. You wouldn't have to ship your
clothes off to be recycled. But what
happens when you get these bugs out out
all over the place in everybody's homes?
The bugs get out and they eat my
clothes. So, the the great thing is
these bugs are dead, so we're not
worried about them kind of being an
invasive species, which is a valid
consideration when you think about
engineered microbes. But because we
killed them, turn them into astronaut
ice cream, that's not an issue. And so
we've engineered them to basically turn
on at high temperatures. So at
temperatures that most people aren't
wearing clothes, you know, we're talking
almost boiling water. So unless you're
wearing your clothes in the deep sea
vent. Exactly. So then we can kind of
control when these microbes turn on. So
how do you how do you engineer something
to be that tough? Lots of talented
students. Well, as you know, I'm a total
when it comes to DNA. From our
past conversations, I've pointed out to
you that the DNA you've used in some of
your approaches is too fragile to be
used in the way you're planning to use
it, but you've pointed out to me that
it's not.
People underestimate DNA, I think. And,
you know, with a lot of the current
tools we can use for engineering
microbes, we can tune them with very
high precision. And for these proteins,
we can tune very specific pieces of the
protein as well as kind of the whole
microbe itself. So how many of these
proteins we're putting on the surface,
how stable they are is impacted by that.
Kind of how they're connected to the
microbe itself. And that impacts how hot
we can turn up the sauna on them
basically. So So give us an example if
you can of of how you've how you've done
this. What sorts of applications does
this find its way into? Yeah. So, we
think a lot about circularizing
economies and one of the main ways we
look at that is with critical materials.
So, um there's lots of things that we're
now realizing we need a lot more of to
make things like solar panels and
batteries. Um even batteries both for
your car and for your cell phone and
your smartwatch. And we're not very good
at recycling those battery materials
right now, but we're going to have to
start if we want to use batteries more.
And so we've also been able, just like
we can put proteins on microbes that
chew stuff up, we can put proteins that
specifically grab stuff from pretty
complex mixtures. So say you have a ball
pit, you only want the yellow balls. We
can put a protein on there that only
grabs the yellow ones and leaves all the
other colors. And so that's basically
what we do with these metals that are
these crit critical materials. That
sounds like it's mimicking the
biological use of DNA to to gather
together strands of proteins. Yeah. So
these are basically the DNA we're using
to tell the microbe what to do. So here
we're using DNA to basically program.
And then in some of our other work, we
do use DNA more as a material, but here
we're using that to tell the microbes to
make proteins that we then use as kind
of like the claw toy. is the idea there
that you're recycling a battery. It's
got a mixture of metals in it and you're
trying to say, well, this is this metal
and you're trying to sort them so that
you can then like take that pure thing
and say, okay, well, what are we going
to use pure lithium or whatever for
again instead of being it being a jumble
of other things. Yes. Exactly. And right
now the way people do that, people have
come up with very sophisticated chemical
tools to do that, but they're often very
energy intensive. And this is another
example of where evolution, you know,
these proteins come from these microbes
needing one specific metal and not
wanting anything else. And so they need
to be able to grab that one metal and
nothing else. And so if we take those
proteins and use them, we can get that
same specificity that it's nearly
impossible to get right now chemically.
When I think about clothes companies and
and the sort of appeal that they make to
people and the environmental impact that
they would like to have, like I would
think that if they knew anything about
what you're doing, which they might not,
but you could get companies to make,
let's say, simpler leggings that didn't
have mesh panels and saying like, if you
buy this legging, you don't have to
there other we make the ones with the
mesh panels or we do this or that, but
if you buy the like plain black
polyester something something because
it's simpler. Look at the awesomeness
that we can do with this. And people
might be like, well, they're like all
about the same price. I'll do the thing
that seems green. Yeah. I mean, that's
the goal. And at least in Europe, that's
going to be the direction everything's
heading. So, there are some mandates in
the EU that are going to make all
clothing have to be made of a single
material. Basically, they're doing it to
improve existing recycling processes so
that you can recycle more clothes. But
it would significantly help us kind of
if you could have single stream. Yeah.
Are they doing that specifically to
enable you? No. No, definitely not. That
would be fantastic. But um this is
existing recycling technologies
generally depend on very pure feed
stock. So very pure input. So you can't
have these mixed materials. You can't
have those leggings with that mesh
panel. So just to use current methods of
recycling, they're making this a mandate
that you have to use kind of single
types of fabric. Has anybody come to
you, a government or a company, and said
like this is yes, we'd like to do this.
Yes. So we've we've had some really
fantastic interactions with groups that
have made documentaries about textile
waste. They're very passionate about
solutions to that, right? They don't
want to just educate people on the
waste. They want to help solve that
problem. And so, uh, we're working with
them to get access to some of these
textile dumps in the global south. And
so that we can try once we have these
mixtures of microbes to degrade mixed
textiles and help clean up the
environment there without needing to
burn the clothes, which is what happens
now. How does that pay for itself? Does
the government have to provide the
funding to do it? Are you making a
useful product somehow? It honestly will
depend a lot on clothing/chemical
companies because if they start to see
value in these starting materials that
aren't from fossil fuel feed stocks. So
they may be a little pricier but they're
not going to be orders of magnitude
pricier. They're not going to be 100
times pricier. Then they can purchase
these and it would be useful for them
because then they and create a loop.
Exactly.
[Music]
As I mentioned at the beginning of the
show, Ariel First is not just an
entrepreneur. She's a serial
entrepreneur, and her efforts to create
a greener world extend to another
company of hers, Helix Carbon, which
also taps into her love of biology.
Helix Carbon is inspired by the DNA
Helix. Um, we talked a little bit about
how DNA is the genetic code, right? can
help cells program making proteins. But
DNA is this three-dimensional material
that has really cool properties beyond
just the letters of the bases. DNA has
two strands that unite in a specific
way. First says, and the two strands are
brought together by hydrogen bonds,
which are not particularly strong, and
that works almost like Velcro or like a
zipper coming together. these two things
that are floating separately, they come
together very tightly, but it's also
reversible. And so this allows us to use
DNA to regenerate things. What FIRST is
looking to do with this DNA is to help
facilities that generate a lot of carbon
dioxide use it in a way that's helpful
to them. And that means turning it into
all sorts of useful products, plastics,
paint, liquid aviation fuel, and these
are things that people call tough to
decarbonize industries because, you
know, it's going to be really hard to
make a plane fly on solar power alone
right now. So, these are things that are
going to take longer to fully reach an
energy transition. And so, until then,
we can at least make their process net
zero, right? because we're pulling CO2
out to be the start of that process. So,
how do you use the CO2 that facilities
emit in a more effective way than it is
currently being used? FIRS says what
Helix carbon does is it makes synthesis
gas, also known as sin gas. It's a
mixture of carbon monoxide and
hydrogen. Right now, it costs about $700
a ton if you get it from fossil fuels.
costs about $1,200 a ton minimum to get
it from electrochemical processes. So
people don't want to use it because it's
not sustainable or profitable for their
company, right? Don't want don't want to
use the electrical process. Yeah.
So, we have been able to basically stick
our catalysts onto one strand of DNA,
stick the other strand of DNA on a
carbon electrode, which decreases the
cost of our system, and that decreases
the amount of energy we need by about
30%. And it brings the overall cost per
ton of sin gas to about $350. So, it's
win-win because it will actually
incentivize companies to capture their
CO2 and convert it into something they
can actually use. I guess sin gas is the
main input to fiser tropes process for
for making hydrocarbons. Yes. So okay.
So this is a gas that's already being
used and the fisher tropes process that
would be used to make things that like
could power a big ship to go across the
ocean or something, right? So it's
there's already a need. So what you're
trying to do is just say like don't use
this, use this other way of making it.
It's better for the environment and
you're trying to make it cheaper. Yes.
And it can all be done on site. So now a
company would install our system. It
would capture CO2 that they're already
emitting and turn it into sin gas right
there in a shipping container sized
unit. Sin gas prices are pretty strongly
tied to natural gas prices. And so as
those
fluctuate, so does company costs. And so
now they know exactly what their cost
will be long term for SN gas. So you can
participate in futures markets very
efficiently. I guess that's not that is
beyond my area of expertise, but people
can with this tech. And are there many
companies that are doing both things?
They're emitting CO2, so they'd be a
good candidate for capturing it and
wanting sin gas. Yes, most kind of
chemical plants right now use sas for at
least one of their processes. And so
most conventional chemical factories
could use this technology probably for
those and they're also big emitter big
emitters. So this just sounds to me like
an incredibly valuable company. You
you've got sounds like a lock to make
all of the sustainable air fuel, all of
the e diesel, all of the e gasoline, all
of the e every fuel. And from the way
you're describing it, companies that are
in these businesses should be tripping
over themselves to license your
technology. Is that happening? Yeah. Or
do they need to hear this podcast to
know? We already do have a lot of
interest from pretty large kind of
chemical companies and it's very
exciting because um we do see a lot of
external interest from people who are
just interested in sustainability. So we
won the climate and energy prize. It was
$100,000 in non-dilutive capital plus
what was very exciting is the $5,000
audience choice award. And so that was
really gratifying for us to see that
this was impactful and meaningful to not
only the judges in the large
petrochemical companies, but also to the
general audience who were listening to
all the pitches. So without screwing up
your access to dilutive capital, the
kind of capital you're really going to
need to go big on this, where's the
catch? Actually, there there is no
catch. There's no catch. Well said.
That's that's my challenge. People ask
me that and I just uh the great thing
about the DNA we're using is it's
synthetic DNA so it's chemically made.
So it's not like we're taking DNA from
any sort of biological thing and it's
very inexpensive. It means we can use
significantly lower amounts of catalyst.
So the expensive metal parts of this and
we can use carbon electrodes that are
much more sustainable and less
expensive. So it really also decreases
the overall cost of these systems to
enable their broader use. So obviously
we're targeting these large prochemical
companies, but this could also be useful
for turning things like solar power into
chemical storage because if you can make
that solar energy go into one of these
systems to make things like ethylene,
you then have something that's
chemically stored energy. So, so what's
what's the advantage here for the
developing world where you have a lot of
interest? I mean, how do they benefit
from this uniquely or especially because
these systems are very inexpensive and
they can run off of systems that don't
require a power grid. You can set these
up pretty much wherever you want. What's
these? These is a electroly a sin gas
making machine or so s gas is our
initial target but we also have
catalysts that can make things like
ethylene and so that's good for chemical
energy storage cuz then you can use that
either for plastics or burn it directly
and so in a lot of places that don't
have grid connections so where solar or
battery storage is a challenge this
would allow them to basically capture
energy from clean systems and keep it in
chemical energy. So, so ethylene is a
fuel. Yes. Is it a useful fuel or can
you get to a useful fuel by the same
sort of logic? Yeah. So, we can take
that and make it into longer chains. So,
liquid fuels. Um, you can also use
ethylene directly and burn it. It's not
the most efficient but it is a source of
chemical energy. So, so you could
imagine one of your plants sitting in
some village in West Bengal. That is the
goal. powered by a solar panel. Cool. I
want in.
So, I mean, a lot of the stuff you're
doing that we've talked about, you're
kind of on this path to
commercialization when things come out
of the lab and then you're hoping like,
oh, you know, we can like change how we
deal with athleisure pants or whatever.
What are the biggest hurdles that you
hit? Is it like it's hard to get people
to invest? It's hard to get people to
understand the technology. I I don't
know, you know, what what's the hardest
thing about going on that path from like
the lab to the to the marketplace?
Honestly, within the MIT ecosystem, it
really hasn't been difficult. Of all the
places I've been, MIT is really very
strong for that. So for Helix Carbon, I
was actually approached by two MBAs who
were interested in commercializing this.
they had heard about it in one of their
classes and their goal in coming to
Sloan for an MBA program was to find a
sustainable tech to commercialize and so
I feel like I get a lot of support in
the areas that I'm not as comfortable
with as uh kind of engineering faculty.
So they do the business plan, they do
all the customer discovery work, they
build their network, and they're even
the ones who are going to be doing the
actual fundraising. So pitching to VCs
and all of that and so having that as a
resource I think kind of circumvents a
lot of the main challenges with
technology commercialization.
You've been involved in a program that
was set up by our former former
president the the great uh Susan
Hawkfield who's a dear friend called
female faculty entrepreneurs FFE. Is
that right? Uh I think they've changed
the name now to faculty founders but yes
it's the same program. So how does that
work and is that is that what you're
talking about when you're when you're
talking about how easy it's been? Yes.
So that is a fantastic program that was
basically set up through the school of
engineering to train female faculty on
how to be entrepreneurs because female
faculty at MIT start companies at
onetenth the rate of male faculty. So
the thought is that that leaves a lot of
tech on the table that should be
commercialized. And um the thought
between Susan Hawkfield and Sangabia
um who was one of the other people
running the program was that a lot of
this is just because of lack of exposure
and so it was to kind of train us. We
got industry mentors. It helped build a
network of other faculty on campus that
are interested in commercialization and
it's been really useful. It also
connected me to a lot of the student
entrepreneurship programs which have
helped my students um think about their
technology and also to some of these MBA
students who have helped us
commercialize. And so the the bigger
question, what do you feel like are the
challenges ahead or like how hopeful do
you feel about the trajectory we're kind
of on in terms of energy usage?
Obviously, we're really trying hard to
keep the global temperature in check.
Honestly, I feel very positive about the
way sustainability technology is moving.
And a lot of that honestly is I've
mentioned this a couple times, but it's
the high schoolers and undergrads that
work in the lab. They are incredibly
determined and missiondriven to make the
world a healthy place for everyone. And
so they are the ones driving a lot of
our motivation and you know the actual
translation of this tech and making sure
what we can do is actually usable and
cost effective and transportable,
accessible. So I really have to give
credit to them for that.
You mentioned to me that you were
thinking about ways to destroy these
so-called forever chemicals, PAS and POS
and those sorts of things. Is that
really going to be practical, do you
think, using these techniques? It has to
be right. We we need methods to degrade
these chemicals that don't also impact
the environment. A lot of the chemical
strategies to degrade forever chemicals
involve more PAS involve more of these
chemicals because that's what captures
them best. And these are chemicals that
are unleashed by like have been in
plastic and they get unleashed. Yeah.
These are things like non-stick cookware
in the Northeast. They're also on a lot
of the military bases and a lot of the
firefighter training sites because
that's what's used in firefighting foam.
Also, dental floss, like what are they
thinking? Yeah.
Stuff you put in your mouth. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. And but this stuff hangs around in
water and in the ground and stuff. And
so you're trying to We're trying to
destroy it. Yeah. With microbes. Yep.
Okay. This has become a major priority
for a lot of companies that produce
chemicals of various kinds because it's
it's just getting everywhere. So the
great thing about evolution is if you
look at a lot of these sites that have
very high levels of these chemicals,
there are microbes growing there. And
the way they're growing there is by
evolving to eat these compounds, these
chemicals. And so, you know, by pulling
out the proteins that are responsible
for that and kind of putting them on our
microbes, on our astronaut ice cream
microbes, we can at least start to
degrade these and make them either to
the point where they're no longer
potentially harmful for humans or
animals, uh, or just fully degraded.
That's amazing. It's like the upside of
the downside of like, you know, there's
these like the Pacific Garbage Patch and
all this stuff and you think, "Oh,
that's terrible." But then like I guess
somewhere there's like some little
organism that's like I could eat this.
This is pretty tasty. This is why I
think and I'm going to get a lot of
flack from my lab and my family for
saying this, but microbes are the
coolest because they have found microbes
that living in gold mines and abandoned
gold mines that have basically shifted
all of their metal usage to gold cuz
that was what was abundant. And you can
pretty much find that in any environment
that is non kind of native. The microbes
there have evolved to use what's around
them. Ariel first is a professor of
chemical engineering at MIT. She's also
the co-founder of two companies. Ariel,
thanks so much for being here. This was
great. Thank you so much. This was
really fun. Thanks, Ariel.
What if it works is a production of the
MIT Energy Initiative. If you like the
show, please leave us a review, or
invite a friend to listen. And remember
to subscribe on Apple Podcast, Spotify,
or wherever you get your
podcasts. You can find an archive of
every episode, all of our show notes,
and a lot more at
energy.mmit.edu/mpodcasts. And you can
learn more about the work of the energy
initiative and the energy transition at
energy.mmit.edu. Our original podcast
artwork is by Zitler Design. Special
thanks to all of the people at Mighty
and MIT who make this show possible. I'm
Cara Miller. And I'm Rob Silver. Thanks
for listening.