The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
So uh a lot of folks uh for instance
they'll run online poker or something
and they will say that oh we we don't
fall into the tax bracket for gambling
because we're a skill based game
and but literally agon is about you know
competition and some ways you can
consider sport but then the reason why
um why I was asking entirely um is
because the way how Ka writes it or at
least the way how uh Roger how has been
translated kind of makes it sound like
he's actually drawing hard divisions
between all these categories when really
they're all like adjectives. Uh
>> what was the original language?
>> Uh French I believe the original uh
version correct me if I'm wrong.
>> The original
>> if anyone can confirm that that would be
awesome. Write write a forum post about
it.
Yeah, I I'll I'll try to confirm that.
If it's actually French, I'll confirm it
and then write an obnoxious post about
translation errors.
>> Um, yeah, I'm sure it could have been
translated in far more interesting
language because it's kind of double
the branches going on if it actually is.
>> And then we have more reading on
Wednesday. Yay.
>> But it's it's it's an important text. Um
uh so that's uh but it but elinks will
be um I use the word vertigo a lot
because it sometimes gets get sort of
like substituted but vertigo kind of I
think people sort of have a very
specific understanding of vertigo um you
know as getting dizzy because of heights
and obviously not all games are about
heights um but you know people sure they
they use it to describe the sensation of
taking a roller coaster which literally
is about heights but it's also about
speed and you know you can use the same
thing of uh everyone played a game
called Descent uh on the PC back in the
day. Um so imagine a first person
shooter uh you're in you know you the
the game is filling up your entire
screen but there is no up um that uh
gravity that that there's no gravity
whenever you want you can turn yourself
this way and you'll just stay that way
until you want to turn it. Um otherwise
the controls work just pretty much the
same way as first person shooter. Um
that that that was that was descent. And
uh the whole the whole pleasure of that
game was that you'd be doing this all
the freaking time. I'm going down a
straight corridor. I and I never walk
and I never just go down a straight
corridor. I go down a straight corridor.
I turn into
>> Inception.
Yeah.
That's what I was saying. Imagine
playing if you ever get a chance to play
the game Prey, which is probably like
five bucks on like pre-owned nowadays.
You have that same sort of thing. And
Portal has a lot of that kind of like
loss of control, you know, physical
sensation that they're trying to get at,
but obviously real physical experiences,
you know, uh, you know, have have an
edge, right? You know, they're talking
about uh, three-legged races or um, that
coral game where you spin around on the
back with your head.
Um, I hate that game.
Um, and you think can be used to
describe any one of those things. Um,
I like to use it as describing the sort
of fun of loss of control, but that's
not necessarily even the case. It's just
the sheer physicality of of of the of
the game as part of the experience in a
way that
digital chess doesn't really have any of
that, you know? I mean, even real chess
at least has I'm moving my face. So um
actually I'm just going to write out
those words for those folks who didn't
get the chance to to read through that
that that page. So it's agon kind of
like gave the competition scale.
Uh I talked about elix which is kind of
jumping down to the last one of the user
just am I spelling this right?
>> Yeah. You know which is kind of like
physicality
kind of sucks.
Actually,
Jason, can you turn the light into
control?
Um,
other ones were
what was that again?
>> Chance, luck,
lot skill.
You guys know the phrase um aliest mean
you know
>> the have been cast.
>> Yes. Yes. The D has been cast right
before Caesar crosses and then you know
says and now they're going to attack
some
>> but uh but you know the you know Alia
meets basically
>> um match on the room.
>> Say what?
>> He matched on the room. much room.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, so the the um uh
although I've heard two translations of
the dye has been cast as a phrase
actually because on one hand you know
you can think of it as the die has been
cast so you know we'll see where fortune
takes us and you know it's not that we
can be wrong. Um, but I've also heard it
described as um the dye as in the um the
thing that you put molten metal into has
been cast. So that so whatever uh we
were making is now set and uh and and it
kind of has that same idea but it's
weird because one one one way that you
can think of this is this is now out of
a out of control and the other way that
you can think of this is and now this is
set in stone which is the two fairly
different connotations by both saying we
don't really have any control of the
situation.
>> Ya means broom
>> throat right? Yeah. Yeah. But the but
the English phrase
>> are there words
>> in English that have as a root to mean
randomly
>> in French like the word for random is
coming straight from
>> Sure. Yeah. Uh
>> which is undoubtedly why you chose that
word. I just checked he is French.
>> Oh yeah. I mean uh obviously that's why
Yeah.
>> Uh kind of want to use it.
>> Yeah. I can't think of any um English
words that use that as a root. Although
there might be some uh uh I know there's
a game company
and actually they actually make strategy
games which is kind of weird.
Um, and there's and there's one more
which is
>> memory.
Which is kind of odd because that in
English uh but not in French. Um,
mimicry is mimicry. Uh, it's, you know,
it's actually in English. So, you know,
role playing, dress up, let's pretend,
um, simulation sometimes, uh, you know,
might actually fall into that. So you
you you you can imagine you know a
tactical simulation for instance you
know being very much about competition
and skill uh but then but then if it's a
tactical simulation about
you know Russian
penet or something that then you know
and then upon the actual famous war and
then you're starting to get into into
baby territory sort of like do you it's
part of the pleasure of believing that
you are something else I suppose. to I
am this guy playing go, you know, as
opposed to I am this
17th century scholar playing go and
you're making a game about that instead.
Um
so so these are the adjectives that he
talks about um to describe games. But in
the bit where we actually asked you to
read it's more about why you know the
these words give you a clue to think
about why are people playing games. Now
um these are types of fun much in a way
that uh that that gets touched on by uh
the NBA paper that that that definitely
highly last week. You know, what are
these aesthetics that people are going
for? You know, are they going for the
thrill of competition or the thrill of
luck? Are they going for, you know,
physical motion and how that feels or
are they going for the feeling of being
someone else? And and it's not, again,
these these are not mutually exclusive
terms. These are things that you you
could have one game that has all of
this. You could have one game that that
has two in some strong composition and
the rest and and the rest all minimized.
That's fine. But understanding that this
is what people are enjoying the game for
and more importantly this is what people
are enjoying playing with each other
for. Um, one one nice thing about this
is that for the for Argon and for
Mimicry, it's really really difficult to
think about those two in particular
without thinking about the players. You
know, the competition kind of sucks if
there's no one else you're competing
against. Uh, sure you can play against a
computer nowadays. Um, but you know,
traditionally you couldn't. um at at
least you're playing against the
designer, especially when kid puzzles,
you know, it's it's really really
annoying to pretend to be somebody else
when there's no audience, you know, even
if that other person is someone
pretending along with you to play
against you. Now, luck, you can
completely play a game, you know,
flipping a coin or something like that.
uh but even when it comes to luck and it
comes to you know experiences of
physical mo emotions these things tend
to be measurable when when there's
people around that's why these part four
particular divisions that that color
picked out are really really good for
thinking about social um that game where
is is there a name for this game where
you put the bat on the ground and you go
around
>> that irritating
Wait, wait. And like someone gets picked
and then
>> so so it's like a relay race where you
like you take a baseball bat, you put
your head on it, you go around it three
times and then you you run back to your
team,
>> carry the bat, and try to hand the bat
off to somebody else.
>> Usually ending up
>> because you're not heard bats. Dizzy
bats. Dizzy bats.
>> Dizzy bats. Yeah. So, so that game, you
know, it's a lot more fun when there's
somebody yells around.
>> I do that by myself.
>> Handing it off to yourself
around
>> and even with games of chance. I mean I
mean sure you could you could play games
of chance by by yourself but the most
part also my my my enjoyment playing
games of chance are usually with a group
of four people and actually uh either
playing poker or playing something like
macho you know so so these are all very
social experiences and to think about
when someone's going to come down sit in
front of your game you know and and what
what sort of frame of mind they're going
to be in uh to to to play your your
game. What what sort of frame of mind
you want to put them in uh in order to
enjoy your game, think about why they
might want to hang out with other people
because most of because actually for
assignment one, your game has to be. So,
you know, there's this other person that
you're playing with that you may or may
not know, but try to try to think about
how you're going to construct enough
clues to sort of get them to enjoy it.
So, the game is about pretending to be
someone else. You know, I'm going to
play I I'm going to make a game where I
am playing a negotiator in a hostage
situation for a card game. Awesome. And
you know, I'm going to be negotiator and
they're going to be the uh the guy
taking hostages. Um that and then you
want to play that up and on um Friday we
had the game crunch where people were
playing
CEOs, I think. Uh yeah. And the whole
bit basic idea that you were already a
corrupt that was awesome
>> corrupt and you think about you know how
does the game even from the rules even
from the design of the box you know get
you into the mood of thinking okay I'm
going to get into I I'm going to whoever
I am in real life I'm going to take on
this persona and I'm going to enjoy
taking for a while. Yeah, they did a
really good job of that because they had
this game kind of built in where you can
actually hide cards on yourself.
>> Did you guys catch anyone doing that in
the act?
>> I got caught.
>> Yeah,
>> I got hit.
I feel like argument that's part of the
rules.
>> Yeah,
>> cuz he he'd already got it. He had
already hit him away and then the cards
were saw like way afterwards, you know.
>> And and even arguing arguing over
whether something was illegal or not,
even when there's evidence that it is,
no one caught you doing it. It's kind of
appropriate for the theme of, you know,
being a CEO of a failing bank, right?
You know, it's like, well, so we have
all of these uh CPOS, you know, that are
working. Yeah, we purchased them at some
point, but nobody caught us while we
were doing it, so now you have to help
us fix it. That's that's what the game
is about. Um
uh was there a game that was
particularly competitive uh that people
played on Friday? The game was pretty
competitive.
>> Pick one.
>> Yeah.
>> There was a competitive moment in in
Sabaturur when Alec
>> revealed himself to be a sabotur and
ruined
>> our attempts to find the gold.
>> Sabotur is a is is what I would describe
as cutthroat. Uh it's it's it's a game
that's deliberately about winning by
other people losing. You know, it's like
that's
>> it made me upset in Alec
made me proud
>> and and and um John Nash actually, you
know, a lot of it or
>> Okay. All right.
>> I keep thinking that he was involved in
MIT at some point. Anyway, um I mean Oh,
because he he he did spend some time
here at MIT. uh possibly when visiting.
Uh but he designed one game uh called
Hex which is ostensibly designed based
on the washroom tiles of one of the
building 39 or building 37 bathrooms.
But anyway, um that game and another
game called Screw You Buddy. Uh
>> are both cut games. Yeah, it's like it's
the only way that you're going to win
this game is by screwing over the the
other percentage.
>> Um, screwing in particular, it's kind of
just like boiled down diplomacy. You
know, the only way that you're going to
win this game is to betray someone else.
>> Yes.
>> Um, let's see. Games of Chance kind of
chanty on Friday.
>> It can go.
>> Yeah, it can go. That's 17
card.
>> Every threat was on the board. Two
people go in 17 drops. Oh my god.
>> It's a pressure of luck game, right? You
know, is the do you dare, you know, do
you think do you feel lucky now?
>> Um, but it's, you know, I I enjoyed the
game a lot. I I had a lot of fun. Cool.
I don't think that we had any games that
were specifically uh it's hard to get
really physical in card games. Uh
>> maybe like that game falling falling.
>> Yeah, that was hit
>> cuz it's like pit actually right two
weeks ago some of the games that we
played were really kind of kinetic.
>> So those so so even with card games you
you you already have fairly good
examples of that. I want I want you to
kind of keep uh keep in mind this one
because today we're actually going to
start the process of like getting you
folks to think about what you're you're
going to do with your first assignment
and and breaking you up in teams. Um
before we completely leave Jason here,
do do you have anything to raise
anything?
>> No. Or anybody else?
>> I was still confused about the whole
Eskimo part.
>> Agreed.
I'll have to look through
misos.
>> Take a look at the French actually.
>> Yeah, I'll take a look. He actually went
to the same one my dad did and went to
university somewhere a good friend of
ours did. So I mean we might know
someone who knows him. I'll I'll find
out tonight.
>> He's dead.
>> So why just have him like come over
chill at MIT for a little bit. Yeah,
>> we can talk to him about the Eskimos and
>> we just have to we Does anyone here know
cuz he's so we need to raise him?
>> Yeah, he he is dead but I might
>> necromancy. It's okay.
>> All right. So, so this is this is what
we're going to do. Uh we're basically
going to do brainstorming today. Uh the
the basic idea is that we're going to
hand out cards and one job to sort of
make it easier on the job of the uh of
the secretary is that you is that you'd
actually be reading out stuff that
you've written. So especially while
other people are throwing out their
ideas, you know, and you get something
and that person is still talking, you
might as well just write down your idea.
Um so we'll have a whole bunch of cards.
Um
the but uh I also like you to write
start off by writing your name right on
top. Um and the reason for this is
because I don't think every single
person in this room knows each other's
names yet. And but as we do this
process, it's more likely that you
remember, oh yeah, that guy who came up
with that idea. Uh and then oh, and that
person's name is, you know. Um so
now you want to have all the ideas from
each person on one card or have one idea
per card?
>> Uh all on one.
>> What if the professors took the notes
and we could just bounce out ideas?
Well, that's what they regarded as well.
But but the thing about writing your
ideas down is so that people can then
look at the card and say, "Yeah, that
guy, I want to follow up with this guy."
Because we're not actually going to form
the team uh uh for you by the end of
this class. The idea is so that after
this brainstorm uh this brainstorming
phase, you've got a pool of ideas of
which you guys can make games. It
actually frankly we we don't care if two
teams ended up making you know pretty
much the same game out of the same
concept because I know that two
different teams and two different people
two different sets of people are going
to end up making different games anyway
even from the same u that's that's not a
requirement you guys you folks can make
uh uh you can can take any set of ideas
from the boo today obviously if you're
the one who pitch an idea and somebody
else thinks, "Hey, that was actually
pretty cool." And, you know, take that
opportunity to talk to the person and,
you know, maybe team it.
>> Um, that pretty much is going to happen
between classes. So, by Wednesday, um, I
wanted you folks to come in. This is
basically one of the pieces of homework
is to is to tell tell me which team
you're on, who's on your team, and
what's the general oneline, you know,
uh, idea that you're working with. Now
the idea that you're giving us is what
you started with. It may not be what you
end with. That's fine. I I we're very
comfortable with that idea change while
you guys work with things. That's fine.
The team shouldn't change. So you you're
working with you know these three other
people. So for a team of four then that
should be you know be intact for the
rest of this uh for this assignment.
>> 9 10 12 13 14 15 16 perfect. So keep it
for Oh, great. Um, now the
um one more clarification about the
project. Uh, the card game for all all
the cards need to be identically sized.
Um, we do like cards that are going to
be legible, but you don't need to spend
a whole lot of time making them pretty.
Uh, I would just uh appreciate it that
by the time you actually hand in your
cards, you have them written in ink.
handies. Uh um pencil is great when
you're prototyping because you can erase
and you can make things but ink is great
for grading because it's not white. Um
your game can be uh uh playable by two,
three or four players.
It does not need to cater to any
grouping other than what you decide that
it needs to be. So if you say this is
two-player game, we will test it with
two people. If you say this is 224,
we'll test it with some number with
however many people we manage to wrestle
with two tests. Uh if you say it could
be two or four but not three, that's
fine. But you need to make that clear
because there are some games that work
really really well.
>> Um keep it keep it for uh four and under
uh or at least make it possible for us
to grade it uh with maximum of four
people. Because if you give us a game
that requires five people, we have to
find five people and get them together
in order to create your your
>> Okay. Minimum requirement.
>> Uh that's um I think there was one more
requirement for how long the game could
take.
>> I think it's probably 10 months.
>> Oh yeah, it was short.
>> Super short. Falling is really short.
>> Yeah, but crunch is not.
>> Yeah, it's about crunch is over. So when
you're brainstorming for game ideas, how
much of the game mechanism does that
come up with brainstorm?
>> Uh
>> it's a cool idea. Zombies in space.
>> I would say the game mechanic is the
thing that's that's encouraging you to
that's the thing that you about this
assignment. I have this cool game
mechanic in mind and
then that's then that's the thing that
you're throwing out. And obviously if if
if instant is you know I want to make a
game about fish I have no game mechanics
in mind but I think fish are awesome
then uh okay that's what
maybe that's the first you know the
first bad idea
I'm throwing up
if we have like several game ideas
should we take several index cards and
write one per
>> actually no I would rather see them all
on one if you can't fit them and if you
run out of space them
Um again the idea of the index cards is
not just to record the ideas down uh
because what I am going to do is I'm
just uh I'm going to try to type them
all out so that uh you can refer to them
on on forum post just to remember what
people discussed but also to find find
you you folks again. So I said yeah that
was that guy who had this idea about
fish. Who was that again? Yeah. Okay
then.
So, uh I guess I need to leave.
>> You want me to write down?
>> Um I think I think
you're not a facilitator.
>> Yeah, I'm facilitator.
>> I like better
secretary. It's almost like the
beginning
leader.
>> But I am actually wondering whether we
should divide this into two groups.
>> They would get to see the cross.
>> We did some crossation.
>> That's why it's a whole fast. Okay. So,
>> I know there were some folks who
actually started off with ideas already
on the forum. So, uh, why don't those
folks throw, uh, throw in your ideas
first because you you mentioned before?
>> Yeah, I I wasn't quite that forum.
>> Well, to start off, I mean, Jeremy and I
have been sort of discussing an idea.
You want to go ahead?
>> Sure.
>> Two ideas, I guess.
>> Well, yeah. So, I'll start with the
titles one. So the basic concept is a
game in which players are forced by some
mechanic game mechanic to refer to each
other by name uh constantly throughout
the game and at a rap very rapid pace
and that players accumulate uh their
name is generated by the game and
accumulate increasingly longer and more
wordless games as they succeed. So you
would start, you would be like lord of
something and you could accumulate extra
title son of this like bringer of flame
and you could just like have all these
modifiers that just kind of accumulate
and accumulate until your title becomes
ridiculous and then people will start
screwing up and as they say your name
and and it just hilarious.
>> Okay, I'm just going to write down like
memory jobs. Uh
>> so like procedurally generated names,
titles,
>> name
one.
>> Yeah. Can I go in the second one more uh
while we
>> Okay, so I had this idea of like sort of
like a survival horror game kind of
inspired by falling. Like the premise
is, you know, you have a group of like
player characters that are like charging
through a building and you can have like
a dealer that is putting down like
hallways as you're going through.
Occasionally threats come up and you
have to like react really quickly and be
like, "It's a zombie. We have to like go
upstairs and throw down a car to like do
that." And you have to keep doing this
until you get to the end of it and
people can like die and get eaten and
stuff.
That's good.
>> Kind of like
>> should
we be writing his ideas down?
>> No, I'm writing mine down and then
>> write on your own.
>> Yeah. Um,
>> so I have idea I thought made this up
like a year ago when I took game design.
Oh, not game design.
>> It showed video game studies. It's
actually it's like majority rule. So you
can it's kind of like a crunch where you
can just hide cars and stuff but as if
you if you get caught then you get
called out and in order to be penalized
for it you have to be you have to a
majority rule has to be by everyone
playing and so you can actually bribe
people to vote for you.
>> It's more of like a Yeah. And then the
way you get points is
depends on how we describe it.
>> Okay. Uh I'm just going to go around
this way.
>> Okay. So I had an idea of a card game
based on like having success in life. So
the beginning of the game all the
players are randomly assigned different
different goals in order which are like
wealth and uh uh adventure and love and
things like this. And then all the cards
represent different activities that take
up a different amount of time. So like
you have all these activities you can
keep in front of you and then however
much free time you have you like draw
that many cards looking for new
opportunities. So it's like you like
take opportunities and kind of leave
opportunities and things.
>> Okay. I put it right on opportunities.
>> Sure. So I have a very mechanically
oriented idea. Essentially I'm stealing
and trying to improve the draft mechanic
from um from Magic the Gathering booster
draft for those who don't know. The idea
is the idea is that you're trying to
collect a set and um so let's do it in
terms of regular card games. You're
trying to collect a straight flush as
long as possible, as high valued as
possible, but other people may be trying
to collect that same suit. So you want
to collect a different suit from other
people. And you do this by um looking at
the cards in your hand, picking one of
them, passing it the rest to the person
on your right, and then continuing to do
this. and then going back in the other
direction with a new hand and then in
the same direction again with a third
hand. And the object is collect straight
flush. Um, also guess what the person to
your right was collecting and guess what
the person to your left was collecting.
So you're trying to signal to other
people what suits are open and collect
the suit which is open.
>> Let's see who's next. Uh,
>> yeah. Um so it's going to be uh there
are different types of cards like action
cards like pickup cards or loose cards
but then so you know where they have
cards where so you have like oh from
stock pile from your friend hand from
discard pile people play different cards
in different order so the rule always
changes kind of mess up or help yourself
out.
>> How would you describe that uh the rules
are constantly changing?
>> Yeah but you get like so there's
actually an order to it. So you can
choose. So if like it's going to be your
turn that says pick a free card, you can
put down like oh from a friend's hand
like lose three cards or something like
that.
>> Makes a lot of sense in my mind.
>> So rules changing with cards.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Uh
>> all right. So uh one idea I have is a
game about uh character growth through
narrative arc. So, at the start of the
game, you're given a character, and the
idea is you want to follow a certain
narrative arc so that they grow in terms
of the hands of the game you're playing.
So, if you start out with a cocky
character, then you may want to actually
lose a couple of the hands of the game
such that your character experiences
failure and his character growth
increases. Um, and so basically, the
winner of the game is determined by who
manages to get their character to grow
the most, like emotionally.
>> Very deep.
>> Yeah.
Um, so I had this idea for like a poker
like game except it's played with more
than one deck, but the normal rules
still apply. So if you get dealt five
aces, you can't actually play that hand
because that would be cheating. So you
have an incentive to try and, you know,
like slip cards into your sleeve and
slip back and forth. So you're almost
forced to cheat at the game to be able
to actually play it.
>> So you can mix that with like
>> Yeah. and you get caught, then it's
pretty much you have to figure out how
to get out of the cab.
>> Oh, so the idea that I had was kind of
like bananagrams but with a card game.
So you have uh cards with like lines or
preset lines or shapes or something on
the cards and you have to try to connect
them all in some way on like on your
personal board so that it it forms a
closed shape and once you're done, you
know, you have to take another card from
the pile and try to fix your shape so
that it's still closed while trying to
beat everyone else. collecting cards
make shapes.
Okay.
>> So idea was just using normal poker
poker cards and doing a trading game.
You just like trading like four kinds of
pattern as four kind of stocks and you
can randomly draw the draw the card to
be your own stock and every day you
randomly draw card determine the day
price and you can trade with bank or
other players. I think you can use A to
10 as the as the stocks and the JQ and
Kas special cards and install some so
>> Okay,
>> so this one's another procedurally
generated idea. Uh the game generates
for you encounters and it's supposed to
be ridiculous and somewhat humorous. So
you'd have like a a base card like you
you know a bear and then there various
modifiers that would that you would that
you would draw to create that encounter.
So, it could be like a ninja zombie bear
in space wrapped in bacon and uh and
then and then those would all give
different attributes to that encounter
and then you'd have to find a way to
beat it. And your characters might also
maybe be procedurally generated in
similarly ridiculous ways and you'd have
to counter it with just you know
basically I like procedurally generated
ideas. Card games have never played the
same way twice. So,
>> um I need something.
>> Sorry.
with laser beams.
>> Of course.
>> So, my idea was a musical RPG in which
um players cards are musical notes and
you uh build chords. For example, to
raise your character strength, you might
make an augmented chord, etc. And then
you can chain chord progressions to
attack players.
>> Diminished your life.
>> I I just dominated yourself.
All right, I got obsessed with drafting.
I have another drafting bit. Another
drafting game uses the same drafting
mechanic except that you're drafting
tiles. You play the tiles in front of
you and they make a machine. um drafting
the same color of machine bit or same
type of machine bit and then laying it
in in consecutive blocks um
multiplicatively makes them better and
then your machines like attack other
people or do crazy
>> But but the challenge being you have to
draft the piece that fits into your
machine.
>> They can do crazy
>> They can do crazy. It has to be
pronounced like crazy.
Uh, anyone here?
>> Oh.
>> Um, so my idea is kind of like a
monarchy type thing. So it starts out as
everyone's a heir to the throne except
the king. Like everyone wants to become
the king or queen, I guess. And then um
the point is either to get the king to
really like you or to assassinate him.
But if you want to um assassinate him,
you have to kill off all the other
players first. So it's kind of like a
betrayal and deceit game and stuff.
>> So betrayal
Okay.
>> Uh, yep. So, another game is about uh
reducing your opponent's mo mobility by
placing cards that represent walls and
placing other cards to uh rotate various
walls and your opponent is doing the
same thing. So, you could sort of
envision the uh Tron life cycle game
without any hint of reflex uh removed
completely. So,
>> oh that would be really cool.
So, it's all just a strategic uh
placement of walls to reduce your
opponent's mobility. Cool.
>> Uh yeah, I think you can just make a lot
of Tetris boss and then like every time
you select one, give to the other
player, let them play some of the
Tetris. See who got the most rows
remove.
>> So, so Tetris blocks. Got it.
>> Okay.
This is kind of like Pokemon except now
it's you have you raise zombies or you
catch zombies except so you have
different types of zombies. So may like
maybe take some from like the Left 4
Dead universe or something or just
Resident Evil or something
and you have and then you could do like
a like versus like other people or
something.
>> Um I thought of having cards. I I don't
know whether there would be like words
or a few words linked together, but you
would go around and each round you would
the goal would be to build a story. So
each person would play a card face down
or something. So it' be a mechanic like
apples to apples except you're like
progressively building a story and if
people like the the your addition to the
story
>> then you get points.
>> Apple story.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Uh,
>> sure. Okay. Moving away from drafting.
>> Okay. So, I have another game idea
called Are You Asylum? Um,
>> it essentially uh
>> Are you a Sylon?
>> Are You Asylum? It essentially like
broad brush strokes steals the um skill
resolution mechanic from Battle Star
Galactic for the board game and then
strips it down to um secret sylons
sabotaging people and then people
accusing them and then everybody crying.
>> Uh so I really like Harvest Moon. So, I
was thinking that maybe there could be
like a harvest moving card, competitive
card game, and like uh I guess you have
a certain like amount of stamina each
turn and like cards are actions and
stuff and whoever has like the biggest
harvest at the end of the game would
win. I don't know how many turns it
would be, but yeah.
>> So, like farming.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> All right. So, sort of building on the
monarchy and betrayal idea. This is game
about the heir to the throne. the king
is dying. In X turns, you and the other
players are going to compete um to prove
who is the correct heir to the throne.
And you can do so through combat
directly with other players,
assassinations, or political uh
minations such as like accusing other
players of being baseorn. So
>> um actually uh just as a a favor uh when
you uh throw out your idea also throw uh
also mention your name because I'm still
learning everyone's names.
>> Okay. So I'm Ian.
>> Uh so I had this idea for a game called
Admiral Snack Bar.
So, the idea is each it's a competitive
game where each player is building up
their own sort of like snack shop and
they make a certain product, right? Um,
and the other players need that product
in some way to like enhance their own
things, but you can secretly poison
parts of your product so that when they
purchase them, they'll like get messed
up in some way. So, it's it's sort of
like a trade-off and you can like make
alliances and stuff like that.
>> You can say it's sort of like a trap.
>> Yeah, it's a trap.
>> There's the tagline right there.
Oh, no. It's a snack.
>> I don't know. Maybe. So, I was thinking
of a game, I guess, kind of like um when
like the Total Wars mixed with Nazi
Germany. And so, the point of the game
is you you want to snatch up uh
territories. And you can do this by
maybe attacking other players. Well, by
territories is like cards. And you can
do this by attacking other players or
maybe making alliances which you can
easily betray or maybe have like all the
cards in the pile and you have to every
turn you can take one and and try it and
you get points by getting certain like
combinations of lands I guess kind more
like a risk right there as well.
>> Compose
the city like compos. Okay.
Um, so I was thinking of like a trick
taking game, but uh the idea is there's
four players and you're trying to get
the second most tricks each round and
then there are cards that like allow you
to swap out other cards at the end of a
round and like other things that are
tricky.
So,
>> it's the second best
trick or second most tricks or something
like that, but yeah.
Okay.
>> So, I think sort of a I guess put
succinctly, scrabble means chicken.
So like
you have a bunch of people playing and
they play cards in the middle and you
have to make words out and then if you
make longer words you get more points
and so forth and so forth. Maybe your
letter is more rare and get more points.
But the catch is that the word is longer
you're you can't gain as much point like
your point gain like is dim is dim for
it's proportional to how long the word
is you make.
Uh, I'm Beto and I wanted to combine
like Mario Karts and Chronauts. So, like
the idea of like you're racing like
through time like somebody has some like
somebody's like the main guy that's
trying to get to some place, everyone
else is trying to stop them and your
like abilities or weapons only work in
certain time periods and stuff like
that. And so you have like the time
travel and the items from Chronauts and
then like the racing and attacking from
Mario Kart.
Michelle.
>> My name is Michelle. Um, so I was
envisioning something like ricochet
robots, but where the two people
basically, so the point is that everyone
has uh a set of like uh cards that have
pathways or grids or walls that you can
bounce off of and you build a grid with
your opponent and the there's one robot
piece that you have to try to bounce off
the walls to reach some specific goal.
You can go to the other player.
Bill Walt and Robots are
>> Patrickhead.
>> Okay.
>> Patrick and Charlie.
>> Um, so this is a game where the players
are uh owners of businesses and
depending on the nature of the business,
they might have mutual dependencies that
would be beneficial for people to get
more money. But then uh as the market
goes bad, they'll have to play cards to
uh cut off the ties between companies.
And so I call it objectivism game.
>> That that was probably a better term
than what I write down.
Uh so there's a slight variation on the
uh precision beast idea, but uh I'm now
imagining it possibly as a as a sort of
falling real time type deal. So every
turn you're getting dealt cards and you
have cards that can modify the the
dealing pattern so that can discard
other players cards or can get them to
be skipped so on and so forth. And you
also have cards that can add various
modifiers to your beast. And the goal of
the game is that by the end, like by the
time the deck has been entirely dealt,
you have the most badass um creature
that you've created and that you'd have
to figure out and there might be an
optimal way to rearrange things. So, as
you're getting cards, you have to try to
figure out how to rearrange them. And at
the same time, other players could be
discarding stuff and you have to deal
with all these things at the same time.
And then at the end of game, you have to
freeze, see who has the best one, and it
could be really bad, you know, quick
game and very hilarious.
>> Say procedural classes. kind of like
building creature plus
>> um
okay this game is monkey or Shakespeare.
>> Okay, so there are several different
several different piles of cards. Each
of them has words on them in Shakespeare
and English. Um the object of the game
so some of them
are going to be played by players. Some
of them are going to be like random
number generators essentially. So the
players that are playing as covert
Shakespeers select cards and then place
them face down in a common pool. Then
the top cards from all the other decks
get placed in the pool and then
everything gets shuffled up. And then
each of these different um piles is
going to be a different color. And so
you'll spell out sentences in the color
progressively based on the card draws.
And the object of the game for the other
players who aren't hidden Shakespearees
is trying to try and work out who is the
Shakespeare who's a Shakespeare. They're
just trying to spell the pre-arranged
sentence beforehand is and who are just
monkey piles. All right. Well, there
that was so detect the random number
generator.
Um, Beethoven. I want to take that like
tanks versus robot game that we played
before on the paper and make it into
like a card game between players and
like the tanks can like level up and
like you can change your uh specific
strategy and that kind of stuff.
>> Would the robot still be like
deterministic or something?
>> Uh, up in the air.
Um let's see who who this side hasn't
gone yet actually.
>> Um
so one mechanic is uh any game that has
a high amount of trading of cards. Uh I
mean you can imagine anything from a go
fish type thing to something more
complicated. However, you don't
mechanically enforce uh the trade of
cards. So there is basically lying in
that narrative. Um also playing off of
the uh robot tank idea a game where
basically your strategy is mitigated by
the cards you play rather than the
actual characteristics. So the cards
play dictate how another deck or another
mechanic is run rather than you directly
interfacing with that.
modification
with
an
adjusting. So I just have idea about
like your silon game. I think it's
really interesting. That's good thing
maybe it's even it will help if you can
play two characters instead of one like
if so if four people you have eight
characters that determine the identity
first and you can play either of the
character. So, two player silent
not two play two characters.
>> Two characters.
>> Sure. Uh, Andrew, so you can have
something that's sort of like a MIT
game. So, you're an MIT student and
you're going through pizzas. We'd be
doing like energy drinks to help you
along through the night. Social events
can hang out at Harvard for a night.
Career fair.
>> That would be a debug.
>> Yeah, exactly.
Sorry. You force other people to hit for
a night.
>> Uh, anything else? Second one's got
Okay, Dion, this is I guess it's so MIT
or Harvard. So this one is a you have to
decide there's some pl so let's say you
you're in design class and you're trying
to build a project but so there's some
students that some students are MIT most
of them are but then there's one or two
Harvard students and so everyone's
trying to build this project but the
Harvard students
is messing it up or maybe it could be
from MIT or Caltech and so the the other
student that's not MIT is trying to
screw up your project and so you by the
end of the game you want to figure out
who that person is or or like maybe I
don't you take turns and you make an
addition to it's something like that.
>> Uh so this came up only a few seconds
ago in my brain. I'm setting I imagine
this for this might be something like a
dark elf realm underground and there's
like various houses or various families
of dark elves and there's one that that
is not controlled by players. I guess
it's deterministic. It follows a set uh
set rules. And players every turn can
can play certain cards to influence the
behavior of this non-player entity the
next turn. And basically players are
buying for influence over this
non-player entity which can then do
benevolent or malevolent things towards
players. And it might be only
semi-obvious depending on how cards are
played who exactly took certain actions
to get the um this this like master
house to to give favor, remove favor
from one player or another. And so it'
be a game where you're trying to beat
other players at the same time trying to
figure out who's on your side, who's not
on your side, and forging alliances and
betraying each other.
>> Uh so everyone's a guy at a party and
the objective is trying to get a girl at
the end of the night.
called a fret bowl. Is that a card?
>> You could screw other people over by
like going up to them and bringing them
embarrassing stories or you would be
like really nice and like try to meet
the girls friend and based off an AI
kind of move.
>> Yeah.
Okay. Um, so Ian, uh, you have a game
where the objective is is all the
players are sort of actually trying to
build a physical house of cards out of
the cards, but each card has like, uh,
an an in-game mechanical effect as well.
And then there's like possibly the
actual structure determines something as
well. You'd have to do with like really
thick cards. Okay, so House of Cards
Jenga with the cards of cards.
>> There would be a mechanic. Actually, my
idea was building a house, but not with
a house of cards. But that's a better
idea.
Adding a mechanic would be like you can
play an action card that's like a a
storm destroys the west wall of your
opponent's house or something. In your
case, it has
>> like
your favorite.
>> Okay. Uh Jason uh Jason so the idea is
you're on a student project or corporate
project where some team doomed to fail.
Uh so your objective is to make you look
as good as you can whether by making the
project better or by making sure other
people are responsible for it being
worse.
>> A terrible microcosm for the first
design.
Don't fail too badly.
>> Brian Brian,
>> um, there's all this talk of drafting. I
started thinking about auction games. So
like an auction game where there's like
some some different points and maybe if
you collect certain types of points,
it's good. And then also like some of
the cards you can add additional
mechanics for yourself. So you can like
bid for a card that later you can play
and have everyone else bid and then you
have to go bid like after them or
something like that. But everyone has
the same amount of points at the
beginning.
>> Yeah. Points
from
>> Jason by the way. Yeah. going back to my
guys that are party one. Uh there's a
way a mechanic where people could bring
in real stories um and real
>> but you can obviously lie and make it
work for someone else but then you lose
points for lying
guy.
>> Do you see
that for people?
So, a game it's like a it's like an RPG
card game where you know you each have
your set which is like of of things you
can do and like equipment you have uh
and then there's like an encounter deck
and these keep getting flipped over and
then people have to react to this but
it's not quite coop cooperative because
at the end there's like something that
only one person can get. Um so, you
know, maybe they have to like duke it
out at the end if there's more than one
person left.
Yeah. Um, so bringing up auction
mechanics, uh, there is a bidding
mechanic that is interesting from a
theoretical standpoint that never
implemented where, uh, if you have some
or if you have a thing that's being
bidded for uh, or you have everyone
assign something that they get from some
pile and then if someone feels that they
aren't happy with what they have, they
trade it with someone else's and either
put some amount of money on the other
item or some decremental uh, type object
on their item.
The bidding system comes out of pirates
trying to spill out booty and instead of
>> making everyone happy to win.
>> So bidding bidding by by reducing other
people's bids. Is that a good
description?
>> It's a bidding system in which everyone
has something and then you trade
and add value until everyone feels it's
equal.
Uh let me
>> So my idea was like it's so you have two
team maybe like four players but and you
have it's like an RPG and so before you
start you have to draft or you have to
yeah draft like equipment and like
spells you can do and so then you you
have two like team battles against each
other and the way you determine
Like
what happens is maybe like a warlike
system where you have each opponent has
a deck and we just shuffle take the top
card of the deck with the top the
highest card wins and so that determines
damage and such done.
>> I don't like it.
Uh, so sort of taking off the RPG idea,
but adding on like a randomly generated
like board or castle that like one
player has to defend and everyone else
is trying to attack into and he has to
like set up his defenses around and like
but he's also a controlling character.
So he can move his guy around the board
to like choose one of the guys to defend
I guess. So essentially an RPG with
randomly generated board as well.
>> Defender castle.
>> Yeah.
>> Castle defense.
>> So I like so sort of building off of the
idea of pirates booty. I like the idea
that you have a bunch of items within
the game which uh the value for them is
chosen randomly so that it's unknown
what the value of the items are. So you
just have the items and various players
can make various moves like choose to
appraise an item by paying some gold.
And the idea is you want to try to get
the item that's worth the most amount of
money during any round to like get the
most amount of gold.
>> The most get the maximum value.
I'm running out of space. So, I'm gonna
be ending this soon, but
actually I'm too
interesting
factories with different products and so
you can either um so you want to b
different items, but for some people it
might be necessary to have a certain raw
bit not necessary. So, it's going to
things are going to have different
values for different people. Then you
can also get highend stuff for low-end
stuff and the randomness is going to
come in where if you have low-end stuff
a user behavior product then you kind of
lose money and stuff like that.
>> M
>> um in a bidding sort of game you could
be bidding for space and say uh for like
space to use the Hubble telescope but
before you can do this you have to pass
a couple hurdles like taking Jab or
>> use the Hubble. That's awesome.
>> One of the first hurdles
I I don't got a video for that.
>> Uh tower defense the card game.
[Music]
>> That's a lot of math.
>> Um
>> slight variation dungeon keeper the card
game. So, I' I'd imagine that there
would be several lanes down which uh uh
enemies would come and you would
collaborate with other players to create
buildings on the other of those lanes
that would then generate either traps
along the way or your own units that
would mark down the lanes to encounter
the enemies. And every turn you you run
the game yourself. So, you run your
opponent and it it automatically
advances and sends stuff at you that's
you know drawn from decks and you have
to be able to time stuff right and all
that not to get your core destroyed
basically.
Okay.
>> I'm just thinking of the idea of tower
defense, the card game. Combine that
with falling. The idea that uh turns are
happening at the same time. So, you have
one player who's playing like the
zombies invading and he's just basically
going like 1 2 3 four. That's like a
zombie advanced four steps or something
by placing cards down. Then the other
player is trying to place defenses just
as fast, but has to like discard cards
as well. So, it's really a game of how
well you are able to handle cards. But
>> I had another idea in the in the vein of
falling, but it would be like Russian
roulette. Um, so everyone's like trying
to have everyone else die and not them.
And then you can play excuse cards, be
like, "Oh, I have to go to the bathroom.
I'll be right back." Or like calling
somebody else out and calling them the
chicken or something. Maybe play with
macho points.
Uh, I think that's Russian excuses.
this.
>> So players take turns being a
prospective high schooler who wants to
go to college and the other players take
are therefore admissions officers and as
a student you're trying to get into the
college that gives you the most
>> swag anything and as admissions officers
you're trying to give them the least. So
admissions are usually like
>> admissions offic
mechanic for his idea. Um so you could
kind of have a ball where you say I'm
going to the bathroom and then someone
else will call you call you out. You
either have the bathroom card you
actually go to the bathroom.
>> So I mean that's a mechanic a bunch of
games.
>> Yeah. The full bladder card.
>> Yeah.
Uh this is a very simple mechanic but
you're try you basically place cards
down to try to create a path from some
predetermined point to another. But in
that way you can you know block other
players by placing cards.
>> So creating pass and blocking them.
>> Okay. I think it works.
>> I think we're done.
>> Yeah.
>> Because I can't I'm not tall enough to
>> All right.
at the bottom.
>> So yeah, I guess I could write down at
the bottom, but that would be a painful
for folks to look at it. So I mean these
are just, you know, memory junks what we
got up here. You know, um none of these
ideas need to be taken wholesale for
your initial idea for the team. But
those were some of the things that folks
remembered. Um, I would actually like
folks to grab one of the uh thumb tacks
over there once you've written down your
ideas on the card uh and pin them up on
the wall. Uh, you don't have to be
closely tied. In fact, spread them out a
little bit so that people can look at so
that a few people can look at the wall
at a time. Uh, and the rest of the class
basically is just time for you guys to
talk. You know, you you you talk, get to
know each other's things better. Um and
uh start discussing about you know
projects that you should work together
over there.