[RUNNING WATER]
BRIAN SCHAGEN: We're on this
bridge in Great Barrington.
This bridge has a
very large history
with repairs and maintenance.
HADEN QUINLAN: So the
problem in Massachusetts
is very significant.
There's about 2,200 bridges that
need some sort of repair to be
done in the near future.
BRIAN SCHAGEN: As you can
see, the corrosion is still
very visible in this bridge.
SIMOS GERASIMIDIS: And we're
going to try to apply a new
technology called Cold Spray,
which is sort of a 3D printing
technology of metals on a bridge
to try to repair corroded parts.
One other advantage is
that we can be very local.
We can scan the beam.
We know exactly where
it has corroded,
and we can go to these
particular places and spray.
We don't need to do
a whole big plate.
We don't have to encase
big stuff in concrete.
We can be very
localized, very precise.
HADEN QUINLAN: We accelerate
particles, so powder.
Powdered steel.
Accelerate it to a very,
very high velocity,
and then use an
applicator to spray
that metal onto a
corroded element
to restore thickness
to that element,
and also restore
structural capacities
necessary for the
bridge to operate.
SIMOS GERASIMIDIS:
This is a problem
that every state is facing.
The resources are very limited.
It's a huge thing, in
terms of efficiency.
CHENGBO ALI: We think that this
is the most cost-effective way
for repairing bridges.
And then the reality of
repairing thousands of bridges,
I think billions of
dollars will be saved.
RICHARD COOK: It's just an
exciting time in manufacturing
in the state of Massachusetts.
[AUDIO LOGO]