All right, let's jump right in. So
basically I'm going to be talking about
the motivation for developing this
blended genome exo protocol or what I'll
call BGE from now on and talk through a
couple manuscripts that delve into the
technical development of BGE and then
how we scaled and evaluated it in uh our
first large multi- ancestry cohort and
then finally talked a little bit about
some of the uh projects and resources
that we've been looking at below. is a
nice schematic picture that broad
clinical labs made that hopefully gives
you a little bit of a sense of what's
what's going on in terms of the exo
portion the low pass genome and then
blending them together to give you uh
this current product.
So prior to the development of this the
main thing that people would purchase
would be kind of a deep whole exo and
then a separate genotyping array. Mostly
this was on the global screening array
and you know that generally assayed the
things that we were most interested in
which was rare coding variation where we
think you can find the most disease
relevant rare variance um given the
sample sizes and then you've got
genotype array you add amputation on
this you get a a nice uh pretty
comprehensive overview of the common
variant landscape of things. Um but they
thought we could do better other people
were trying to do better and you know
one of the issues that we saw
particularly looking at the GSA and you
know we looked at a you know a couple of
chips this was done uh Alicia Martin's
group which really investigate a lot of
diversity and genomics I kind of wanted
to highlight this and this is you know
it's called the global screening array
but if you look at the African
population you can see compared to say
things like the multithnic array are
these more expensive chips that assay
you know on the order of millions of
variants raw genotypes versus you know
probably 5 600,000 variants you know you
see this curve is not quite the same
there's a lot of stuff at very low
frequencies where in Africa which is an
older population you should see the type
of distribution here with a lot more
convariance so you know this kind of
gives a little bit of pause is the
global screening array really assaying
uh things that we would like
particularly as we scale up to a lot of
these diverse cohorts that we were uh
you know we're going to be looking at.
And so this kind of presented this
challenge or at least this need for
something that could could overcome the
limitations of the current arrays that
that people were buying.
And so that you know the alternative
alternatives to this sort of approach is
to actually just add snips directly into
your exo array. So you could think, you
know, you have your exom capture, it
captures exxons. Why not just, you know,
create more probes, capture these
variants. You might get stuck in the
same problem if you don't pick your
probes right and your snips, right? Um,
but you could say, you know, there might
be a cheaper alternative to these two
products and just say, okay, you can
pull out more non-coding snips uh by
just, you know, adding more probes to
your exhome. The other approach is is
what I'll be talking about genering low
pass and then obviously the end the
beall end all is kind of deep whole
genome sequences where you get it all
but still the price point here is still
quite a bit higher than either of these
alternatives
and there is option one I will say here
Regeneron uh working with twist which is
kind of the main manu main manufacturer
of a lot of the exom caps we use does
have a diversity University snip panel.
This came out around 2021. So this was
in the ether around the COVID era that
you know people were moving on from
arrays and and trying to leverage
sequencing technologies to capture all
this stuff. This is out there. I don't
know too much about it. uh but uh that
this approach is being used to just
capture common variants with additional
amounts of probes in the exo
not in the exo but using kind of exom
capture technology
and then
we have the blended genome exo I have a
link here I'll click on it I will leave
but you will see what's out here broad
clinical labs not too long ago made a a
nice splash page here uh kind of giving
you the overview of this stuff. The
clinical blended genome exo, it starts
at 150. There you go. There's your price
point there. I will say the difference
between what I'm going to be talking
about, which is more for research
purposes, uh is that we don't have as
deep of a genome, so this has evolved
over time, but now you can get one that
has just as deep of a or deep of an exo,
sorry, uh as as previous stuff. Um, and
we pay on the order of I think $100 per
sample uh for for this, but as you can
see, they've they've created more
options. Um, you can see different
applications, blah blah blah, and and
get some some stuff here. If you're
interested, you can go on bro Clinical
Labs and and and see what what is here.
And uh I'll talk a little bit more about
what's provided, but I just kind of
wanted to show people that uh you know
you can learn more about this directly
from Bro Clinical Labs. So if I just go
back here,
so the first thing I'll be talking about
is the technical development of this. As
I was saying, this was right this
started probably right around the time
that everyone went on lockdown. Um so it
was a lot of zoom meetings and back and
forth um uh to do this and
you know on the other side of things
which uh I didn't have any real in-depth
knowledge of on the wet lab side of
things uh you know we would kind of be
going back and forth I would be doing
some of the concordance analysis that
I'll show but um but basically the
schematic here of this blended genome is
to create two libraries. One is the low
pass whole genomes PCR free looking at a
few different things and I'll I'll talk
a little bit more about some of the
details but then you've got a separate
exo capture library and this is all
before sequencing. So you're bl you know
you're pulling this DNA out you're
creating two separate libraries running
the exo capture on on on the PCR plus
library coming back in and then blending
at a particular ratio to run through the
sequencer. And so this is what gets you
that mix.
Um, here are some gory details. I don't
know half of what's being talked about
here. I think the thing to take away is
that during COVID when a lot of samples
were being sequenced for
uh testing and when the broad kind of
pivoted to an allout uh you know co
diagnosis testing laboratory there's a
lot of advances made a lot of increases
in throughput and in fact I learned kind
of secondhand that a you know a lot of
the ways particularly to get the price
point where it's at was in some of the
less lesons learned from doing all this
stuff. So that was really kind of
encouraging. A little bit of a silver
lining on an otherwise uh you know great
cloud of co but um it's not you know one
of the big deals with this is the fact
that we can push through quite a few
samples in per per lane of sequencing uh
with this product.
Um so I'm going to talk about I think
this is really important. You know the
exo is still the exo. Things don't
change all too much with that. The big
thing here with the low pass uh whole
genomes is that you're using imputation
to really capture all that common
variance all those common variants back
and you can you know you think about
I'll show another schematic here but how
do you how do you impute you know just
random you know on average one two reads
across the genome at any given location.
So, Glimpse had come out around this
time. These are from the same people
that made shape it and impute and you
know have a really strong track record
of this stuff and they recently came out
with some low pass stuff that looked a
lot better than some of the other stuff.
Kai really helped me out during this
development period uh in running glimpse
and getting things set up for that. This
is kind of the schematic that you can
look at and I think it it provides a
nice easy kind of detail. You go here's
what your low pass whole genome looks
like. All sorts of gaps everywhere,
right? And what we're trying to do is
we're looking at say in the reference
panel there's snips all all across here.
Sometimes there's two reads, sometimes
there's one read, sometimes there's zero
reads. If there's zero reads, your prior
is probably, you know, pretty equal. You
know, it could be a head, could be a
home alt, could be, but if you have a
couple reads, you can adjust those
priors and then you take those genotype
prior likelihoods that you get across,
say, whatever number of millions of
imputed variants that you're you're
wanting to imputee. Uh and then you kind
of run through you know what is kind of
seen as the more traditional kind of
imputation pipeline where you phase
select hllet types best guess hllet
types you run a hidden marov model
through and sample through hlet types uh
doing this and then once you get these
you get your posteriors that are
informed both by the phasing and
imputation portion of things of what
reference panel hlet types you think you
clo most closely match match, but also,
you know, informed by those priors based
on that low pass. Um, you know, there's
probably there's a lot more to this than
just this, but hopefully that gives you
a kind of a schematic of taking lowass
and doing that same hletype selection
with this and then running amputation.
So in these early iterations what we
used was just some deep hole genomes
from a quite small uh sample sets that
we pretty much ran through the entire
tubes across these iterations. So
started with 62 samples, went to 31, ran
out of all their blood, uh took 23
samples from a different cohort. And
basically what I was comparing is, you
know, taking these re read files,
phasing an amputation glimpse, comparing
to uh what we would see in GSA, running
concordance with these 30 30x whole
genomes as our quote unquote truth data
set and uh making sure that you know
seeing you know pretty strong
concordance with what what we see there.
This is kind of the final figure of
this. I would say this is probably the
most important figure and these were
different iterations that we did as we
started with different blending
operations. What you would see early on
uh as we ran through we kind of went way
too high on the exosomes. We did we did
pretty well. You know the goal was to
just not drop our exo coverage too much.
Um, but with the low pass genomes, we,
you know, we wanted to kind of hit this
sweet spot where, you know, how much
coverage do we need to do pretty well to
get strong concordance with our 30x
whole genomes. And um, and also on the
very left here, these are just the same
samples. you know, if we pull out those
just the GSA uh snips, you know, we're
we're generally doing better across the
board than we would if we uh imputed uh
using just the GSA array uh snips here,
but we kind of landed in this area. Um,
and so we're pretty keen, you know, it
was about 33% whole exom sequencing
and 67% whole genome sequencing is kind
of where we landed at as our thing. And
this is where we kind of brought it into
the next stage.
And so I'm just going to go back to what
is VGE. Um,
you've got your fragmented DNA. you've
got, you know, I just said your
one-third exo, one third, twothirds
whole genome. You're going to have a lot
more reads in the exo, but it's a much
smaller portion of the the genome.
Generally, what I've seen kind of thrown
around, you get a, you know, roughly 30x
whole exo, 4x whole genome. That's not
quite right. It's something more spread
out. Obviously, there's more variance to
this. Uh, you get somewhere around 25 to
40x. This is the research uh kind of end
of things not that clinical uh deeper
exo and then something on the order of 1
to 4x whole genome here. And one of the
things that I wanted to outline is that
you know if you if you plotted this was
an early pilot sample after the the
development what this whole genome
coverage and the and the exo coverage
here there's some winners and some
losers. Obviously these samples would
have been thrown out. This was a pilot
data, but you know, there's going to be
samples in our protocol that get, you
know, around one one X and they also get
the lowest amount of exo coverage. And
this is just how it kind of works in the
wash of high throughput. But what you
you know what we really want is to just
make sure that we get enough exom
coverage that we're we're we're
capturing enough uh reads at 10x uh at
least 10x coverage and then we kind of
get whatever you know we get whatever
else comes out and uh as long as we have
enough DNA in there you know we don't
want to get down to zero but these
lowass imputation things they'll work on
you know.1x
1x
they will do better as you go up but
they will do you know it will asmtote in
terms of imputation performance I won't
say it's it's you know it's not linear
um but I think once you get once you get
at least 1x coverage you're doing pretty
well in the amputation landscape this is
another thing just to show the
distribution of of these coverages it's
it's it's you know you get anywhere from
one to 5x this is a much larger cohort
um and then you get around that 30x
uh mean coding depth. And so really the
goals the deliverables at least from the
genotyping uh side of things or at least
the sequencing side of things is 90% of
the exom at 10x. And you know we wanted
to see that at least 45% of reads are
going into the the genome. This is a
kind of another way to look at it's a
little fuzzy, but um as you can see, you
know, when you get high coverage, you
know, a 5x coverage, a much smaller
proportion go to the exo, but you're
getting as long as we're getting 90% of
our target captured at 10x, that's kind
of the the main delivery. We're giving
you that deep enough exo uh that that
we're asking for. You're getting a hold
a low pass hold genome as well. some
samples do better than others. And if
this is something you may want to be
looking at downstream to see just how
much something like your, you know, your
lowass coverage is doing relative to say
the imputation performance. Uh something
to look at. But um but that's kind of
you know something that might be not
intuitive about uh this product but uh
this is how it works.
So after the technical development, we
scaled and evaluated this in a large
multi- ancestry cohort. Uh also looking
at um structural variance as well, which
I'll show. This was kind of our first
look at a collection we've been
gathering for quite a while at Stanley
Center. And this is the population's
underrepresented mental illness
association or pumas. And as you can see
here from from the names uh you know
most most of the samples that we were
looking at here are from the neurogap
and um you know you can see various
locations across Africa as well as South
America. The GPC in the US this is
actually uh pretty enriched for for
African-American ancestry as well. So
you know trying to test this across a a
wide diversity samples.
If you look at the uh PC plot, it's
different than what you normally see
with your canonical uh triangle of the
these different things. And you know, as
you probably look at at lower uh you
know, lower PC loadings, you you you'll
probably see separation of stuff, but
just showing this to show it's not, you
know, not your usual plot that people
like to
that also had deep hole genomes and this
was run using the GATK GCNV. So this is
this is still focusing primarily on that
exo content. I will say that you know
this doesn't in any way really turn
around the low passold genomes as much
as well are we capturing rare uh coding
structural varants well enough uh in in
this in this new product. Um and you can
see with the recall so so basically you
know how much do we we see in terms of
what's available what's seen in the deep
hole genomes as you get up to say about
you know five exxons overlapping you're
getting above that kind of point8
threshold and beyond and you can see the
distribution so you know you will say
most most of what we see is below that.
So, you could say there's there is
probably room to improve on this front.
Maybe if your your primary thing is to
look at uh SVS and and you're not happy
with this, this is knowledge that you
may want to have. Uh on the other side
of things, you're still, you know, what
you do collect is is pretty uh is pretty
pretty well captured in terms of not
calling a whole bunch of false
positives. Um so so what you do collect
is is uh pretty well identified in terms
of this positive predicted value. Um but
that's what we see in these samples as
you pull out to say that larger 50,000
sample set. We don't have this
concordance that you can look at but we
just wanted to look at say overall
distributions of deletions and
duplications in these coding regions.
And we compared that against uh Nomad V4
and largely things looked pretty good.
Um
nothing too crazy. You do see, you know,
if anything we're we're calling a little
bit more here, but you know, the main
thing we worry about is that everything
is would be on the other side of things.
If say you looked at the proportion of
samples that do carry a rare uh coding
deletion or duplication, you know, we're
right around the same area, you know, a
little bit lower, but I wouldn't look
too much into the exact numbers here.
We're roughly in the same range with
what we've seen before. So there's no
real like red flags that you know doing
this in uh using BGE over the exo
capture that was used before is going to
really hurt you in a meaningful way. You
do have a little bit less sensitivity in
those very small regions.
So when we looked at the amputation
evaluation, so what differs here in
terms of what we did before when we had
deep hole genomes, we have quite a few
samples, but uh we didn't have dirty
exhole genomes for for a lot of this
stuff. Um so what we did instead was
look at GSA array genotypes. And so kind
of subsetting that fraction of the
imputed calls to what we see in these
same samples with their arrays. There's
quite a bit of kind of back and forth QC
to kind of get things right there. But
we looked at, you know, probably on the
order of 11 12,000 individuals among
that sample set to look at this
concordance. And I I also threw this
here to give a little bit of a sense of
what the cost per sample is uh in doing
this. So on average, it's about 36
cents. That's still roughly the same. Uh
you know, there was a bit of work on
optimizing how large these batches had
to be and what sort of compute uh you're
asking for to kind of get the these
numbers as low as we can. Um, and that's
a whole another thing that I won't talk
too much about. But, uh,
during the time that we scaled up, there
was also an advance in the glimpse uh,
software
and
probably the main thing is you get large
reference panels. Things can get
expensive with low pass genomes. You
could say 280 242 pounds using say this
other option here. Um the main thing you
got a dollar in glimpse one 8 cents.
This sounds very attractive. Uh it's a
lot cheaper to do this stuff
particularly when you're using say
150,000 samples as your reference
reference panel instead of just say a
few thousand thousand genomes something
like that.
kind of the big takeaway from this
sparity, sparity, sparity, sparity. Lots
of rare variants in your reference
panel. Now, we need to handle those
differently. We got to leverage tools
and adapt to the sparity of this stuff.
Um, and as you can see, I think the main
thing with this UK bio bank is that
Glimpse 2 is doing better at those rare
variants than glimpse one. uh as you get
to those lower frequencies and up there
with that super expensive version of low
pass uh imputation.
Also, I won't go too much into this for
time sake, but um you know, having lots
of reference having a large reference
panel does really well across a pretty
wide array. you have to get pretty far
from uh that little island over there uh
in the UK before you really start seeing
things like thousand genomes and the
diversity uh stuff starting to perform
better than say a much larger reference
panel cohort. So something interesting
to think about in terms of what you
choose that probably the large reference
panel can go a long way in that sense.
So we did our implementation in Glimpse
2 with this stuff. Um we used a version
of the thousand genomes uh HTTP
uh reference panel. We did remove a lot
of the rarest variants that actually
drops down. It's there's on the order of
likeund and some odd million 150 million
snips. But if you drop out those single
tins and double tins in these in these
four case samples, you can get down to
somewhere around 67 millions. We don't
really trust the rarest variance in
these in this to impute all that well.
Anyways,
do some QC. We look at concordance with
those arrays. We see results that are
largely consistent with what we were
seeing in our pilot samples. It's very
encouraging that you know across many
different ancestries and different uh
you know um different groups that you
know we're seeing uh largely you know
we're getting above even at the lowest
frequency that we could kind of examine
using this GSA array. It's not quite as
sensitive as those whole genomes
obviously but uh you know we are still
above 90% uh in terms of our R squared u
metric. Uh so things looked good there.
Um, one of the things I I found
interesting, this is in a supplement,
but if you if you split up by coding and
non-coding snips uh that we we were able
to do that, you do see things. I mean,
there is one little outlier here, but
generally things are better. This this
is kind of what I wanted to see. I was
never quite sure about these priors and
how well that they do, but obviously
this is being tagged by a lot of this
deeper exom content, right? And so
you're going to see that when you
compare it against uh you know these
lower frequencies around. So you know
generally you're going to want to use
the exo but you are getting some
interesting kind of uh you know in terms
of imputation coding regions.
You know you've got 30x
mean sequencing depth. It is translating
into better imputation performance. So
you know you're not throwing out the exo
when you run through lowass imputation.
take whatever you can get. And on the
other side of things, we do see higher
concordance, which I I found kind of
interesting.
We did as well look at how well you
could capture structural variance in the
lowass genomes themselves. I wouldn't
say this was a particular
use case that, you know, people thought,
you know, think to do in this stuff, but
it was worth investigating as well. And
you know what you see is that as uh you
know you get to a certain length these
the the structural variants you call do
actually pretty well. In particular for
deletions you know anything even in this
0 to 500 base pair range. You know
you're doing pretty the the deletions
you're calling are deletions that we're
also seeing in deep whole genomes. You
know, the bad side of this is that your
recall is way low. So, you're not
capturing all of it. Uh, you know,
you're capturing on the order of say 30
to 40%.
Um, and as you go to that lowest one,
you're capturing a lot less. I mean,
maybe if you play around with the tuning
of these these things, you could you
could change things up, but I think as
currently stands with with the analysis
that that was run, you know, it's it's
interesting to think that, you know,
there is room to capture some, you know,
rare structural variants outside of the
coding region and say, you know, with
some confidence that even though you
you're only capturing, you know, a
fraction of this stuff, it's most likely
real. it's not just filled up with a
whole bunch of false positive calls
because of the low pass uh so that's a
little bit of a interesting side note in
these analyses
um
and so in the last uh few minutes here I
can talk about some of the current BGE
products resources you know we've given
talks uh at least the lab has rolled a
number of these BGE samples into the
larger Bipex
and schema. So bipolar and schizophrenia
exo metaanalyses.
Um I will highlight you know bipolar in
particular you know prior to the
incorporation of some of these new
samples had very few uh if any x and y
significant hits um and we're really
seeing some nice results out of that
neurogaps. It's still early days with
this stuff. African populations have a
lot more diversity. I think we're going
to be waiting on more samples to to find
stuff there. But it's really encouraging
to see uh you know downstream results
popping out. We have a lot more samples
in tow. In fact, we have probably within
our group and adjacent groups, you know,
something on the order of over 260,000
samples across uh the globe. uh making
this up probably the largest that Puma's
cohort that you know we looked at about
50,000 it's going to be growing to about
140,000 primarily schizophrenia bipolar
psychosis
um but we have number of other samples
as well and some different uh diseases
that that we're interested I know other
people out there are also starting to
look at uh BGE sample collections
um in terms of running something like
glimpse we ran ran a lot of this through
our hail batch uh system and it's a bit
more internal but there is a version of
running glimpse 2 uh right through terra
I will say if your sample size is
somewhere probably around a thousand
maybe up to a few thousand this is
actually probably the best route to run
things to once you start getting into
the 10,000 there are limitations to
running this it's not that it won't work
it's that it will take weeks to to run
through. There's quotas on the other
deep in the belly of this. I don't know
why there are quotas, but there are
quotas and that's just how it is. And we
get around it by running basically the
same thing that was developed uh in in
GP uh through the R hail batch uh
compute.
Um, but this is out there. You, you
know, if you click on on this, you can
basically see this. And one of the nice
things that that Michael did was
basically set put all the settings. You
just kind of fill in, rename this demo
into whatever you're doing and uh, you
know, select uh, how much you want the
main thing, the billing project that's
you're going to that's going to actually
pay for all this stuff. And you can do
this. So I think you know we're really
close to something that's you know
pretty accessible to people who don't
have kind of deep knowledge of kind of
the inner workings of glimpse.
Um
we are going to be getting beyond
thousand genomes http a lot of the
samples that we've we've done so far
that's been the default but there is a a
much larger uh amputation service. We're
hoping that it'll support Glimpse later
this year. I think right now they're in
kind of the pilot phase. We jump to
this. So this combines all of us and the
Anvil Centers for Common Disease
Genomics. So it's about I think on the
order of 800,000 samples. So it's big.
It's got lots of variants as many of us
are coming to learn. You know, lots of
variants are good until you have to
store them and let them sit around for a
while. But uh oh, here we go. We've got
515,000
uh uh that that came out here. Um and so
I think they're in the pilot phase right
now. So if anybody's got arrays that
they want imputed using the service,
this might be a good resource to jump
out to. not ready for glimpse yet, but
you know, we will be kind of making a
big move with a lot of our samples into
this space because we really want to
leverage uh you know, the sample size
and diversity that all of us and uh
Amble will will give us
and
also we have a BGE toolkit. It's
currently in the works. Um but in terms
of say running imputation
uh through the hail batch version and
doing things like QC and potentially say
if you're interested I mean one of the
things I didn't really talk too much
about you know things still work in the
you know impute world of things you get
your imputation you run your G-W was
meta analysis and then the exo people
run their exom stuff but you know we
really want to merge all this stuff at
the end of the day having both uh common
variants and rare variants together. Why
not? We are working on merging this in
ways that I think would be sensible and
giving analysts the ability to kind of
select just how they want to do this and
hopefully giving these sorts of tools
will will help here. And we are
developing this now as we move into kind
of the next phase of this. Uh,
and I think with that I just want to
thank a lot of those within our group
that that helped all the way from the
early days to to a lot of the scaling up
and and recent analysis out here. It's
been really an effort that spans well
beyond our units, you know, with the
help of those in in GP and
um you know, we're hoping that as
as we get here, you know, we this idea
of diversity in genomic association
studies can, you know, be realized and I
think the low pass approach really in
the long term, you know, aside from say
the inevitable
everyone has deep whole genomes. Uh if
that cost, you know, ever truly gets
down to something as competitive with
this, but that you know, you can go to
basically any population in the world
and, you know, with the right reference
panel is that you're not, you know,
systematically ignoring the sort of
variation that may exist there. where
you know with the array approach you
have the possibility that you know we
are kind of underserving what we can see
in the landscape of variation and so
really excited about this and uh thanks
all right with that let's thank Daniel
one last Time.