Um, our next speaker is, uh, Tito. Um,
sorry, Kristoff Reinhardt. Um, and I'm
gonna again let you introduce yourself.
>> Okay. I think
>> Oh, you got it. You're all set.
>> Thanks a lot, Zay. Good morning,
everybody. Uh, great pleasure to be
here. Thanks a lot to all of you for
taking the time uh to learn about this
important topic. And as Zanab said, we
all have to get involved in this and
become active. Uh I didn't learn how to
use a corkbang from Zanap. I learned
that from my uh father-in-law with whom
I've done a lot of building renovations
over the years. Uh but I'm meeting Zanab
regularly over the past year on Pi Days
and other events to eat a lot of pie. So
I think you only know me with a serious
sugar rush. And uh so let's see where I
have my remote control here. Yeah, I
think that fits really well. Basically
Jay uh talked about the whole planet and
the effects of various actions on the
planet and I tried to make the jump from
the planet to the individual building
and what this means for an individual
building owner. So uh I'm really excited
about the slides since last week a
little less so but uh what we put
together basically that as of April of
last year we had a spectacular
148 countries that represent 90% of the
world's population and 90% of the
world's GDP that had jointly said it's a
good idea to decarbonize our industry
our world and if we think about in what
kind of incredibly polarized times we
live and I guess last week shows that
there are h bumps in the road towards
this joint goal but uh that there's an
incredible buyin here uh towards this
idea of having a net zero global economy
and I would call this goal really really
radical and the reason why is because
it's so different from what we have been
doing and not a lot of people know this
I only came across that a couple of
years ago it's really worthwhile looking
this up this uh 1952 pi commission
resources for freedom that was a report
that I would say was really the moment
that defined global attitude towards
economic growth fossil fuels and so
forth. This was done uh by a set of
experts was really widely published the
paley commission was by the uh headed by
the president of the CBC paley and
basically the sentence at the bottom is
really key. It says that permanent
economic growth powered by cheap fossil
fuels of arbitrary origin is the
overarching political priority of the
20th century. And if you think about it,
it's hard to think of any policy that
has been like implemented with more
vigor over such a long period of time.
And so that in the face of this, we want
to change here is really remarkable. Of
course, we really don't want to get rid
of our energy use. We want to get rid of
the related carbon that's related to the
energy. But um it's still it's a big
change. What are the drivers between
these change? Well, in a way we heard
about it already. Uh there's lots of um
disasters happening worldwide. There's
just political momentum building and
organizations such as heat obviously
provide solutions towards this global
kind of initiative to say we want to
basically change the ways we deal with
our planet. I would say a key driver is
also that cities uh a lot of cities are
located near uh the sea and due to sea
level rise we see cities becoming so
much under pressure that they're
disappearing. I'm not you sure if you
followed that Jakarta is the first mega
city who announced that they're going to
move Jakarta. There won't be any Jakarta
anymore. The reason is sea level rise
overuse of groundwater in the city. So
they just there are some dramatic photos
out there that I didn't want to share
due to our open course reference. I'm
not even sure if I'm allowed to show
this graph here from the New York Times,
but it's very dramatic what is going on
there. And then finally, of course, uh
we hear that all the time more and more
extreme weather events are happening.
This graph put we put together a couple
of months ago that basically looks at
Noah's recorded extreme weather events.
Wow. Uh over the last um uh over the
last 70 years and 90% of these events
opened have happened in the last decade.
So it's really uh dramatic what is
happening and I've been told I have to
speed up. So now I try to make this
jump. How do we get basically from our
goal of uh these are of reducing uh the
temperature keeping global temperature
rise let's say under two degrees C
whatever our goal is then we know we
have 90 930 gigatons of CO2 left to make
the global building stock or the global
economy carbon neutral really if we are
releasing more carbon in the atmosphere
it's going to get warmer so if we now
say okay the building stock can take 40%
of this then an easy number to remember
is that we have 340 gigatons and 30
years left to make the global building
stock carbon neutral. Now this is our
budget where can we spend our budget on?
It's basically the projections are that
the global build area is going to double
by 2050. So this is our budget and this
is where we have to spend it on. This is
a simple graph that shows three
predictions of what we could do to the
global building stock. Business as usual
says 1% renovation rate globally. Uh
this is what we currently have and by
2050 we will have net zero solutions for
all buildings new and renovated. That's
is going to blow our budget
dramatically. Then the top of the orange
line shows what happens if we have in 10
years net zero new buildings for all new
construction and we increase the
retrofitting rate to five% per year.
That still doesn't get us fully there.
We also need to have by this point
embodied net zero. So all the energy
that goes into building the buildings,
we somewhat have to have net zero
technologies. We have zero ideas of how
to do that right now. But if we are
putting that together really I would say
there's a three-pronged approach of how
we're going to move the building stock
around. One is again 5% renovation rate
per year. Within 10 years we need to
have carbon neutral solutions for all
new construction and for building
retrofits. And really I would really
question this terrible notion that we
have to double the build area like in
five in 30 years we're going to build
what uh what we have built in the last
5,000 years seems a terrible idea. So
more efficient space use is very
important as well. So since I have only
two years what techn I'm now trying to
take it down right to the individual
owner. So if you have a typical building
in New England right now in
Massachusetts, the main proposal that
you get is put PV on your rooftop and
put in an airsource heat pump. That's
really what Massachusetts is pushing.
And so if we look at that, what that
means is basically if you just in
isolation put in a heat pump that in the
best case scenario, unless you do it
yourself, cost you cost you about
$25,000.
And it's going to and that's important
if you're using natural gas right now
increase your operating costs. So really
from an economic standpoint the best you
can do is put a heat pump uh use an
airsource heat pump and a PV system. But
what what that happens if you are doing
that then of course very suddenly you
have a building that puts a really
strong strain on the grid because you're
creating the electricity in the summer
but you're having a new peak due to your
heat pump in the winter and so we don't
have any big battery lying around
somewhere so that is a key problem
overall and so what we should really do
and I know I'm nearly there is we have
to have a detailed an we have to offer
every homeowner like a whole series of
different choices that they can make
with LEDs, better appliances, retrofit
their building, PV putting in a heat
pump. This type of analysis we want to
do to give to every home owner. And in
order to reach this goal, we're working
with the state of Massachusetts right
now. We build a model at two and a half
million buildings. And the way this is
going to look like in a few weeks, you
can go to your building. You can set
what have I done to my building right
now? And then we're going to give you
estimates in terms of cost, carbon
savings and so forth what you can do.
Right now in the first instances we
probably have a airsource and ground
source heat pumps not a network but
these are things that we can kind of
introduce over time if there's interest.
Thank you.
[Applause]