All
right, everybody. Uh, welcome back to
class. [clears throat] So, today we're
going to pick up where we left off. So,
remember last time we talked about the
pigeonal principle. I showed you a whole
bunch of applications of it and then we
started this longer topic that's going
to take us a couple lectures which is
probability. Um so just a quick recap of
where we left off last time. So last
time I started to introduce the basic
terminology that we need for
probability. We had these key
definitions like we had the notion of a
sample space which is really just
telling you what are all the possible
outcomes of your experiment. You could
think about something, you know, very
small and finite, like I roll a dieice
and I get a number between one and six.
Or you could even think about a sample
space as being an infinite space. For
purposes of our class, we're only going
to consider discrete sample spaces. But
you can even consider sample spaces like
what happens if I take a coin and I flip
it as many times until I get my first
heads. That's something which has an
infinite sample space. And what's
important is that to the sample space we
associate what's called a probability
measure P. So all this does is it takes
in some particular outcome from the
range of all possible outcomes. It
better assign a non- negative
probability to that. And additionally
your probability measure had better be
normalized so that the sum of P of X
over your entire sample space had better
be normalized so that it's equal to one.
Right? So that these probabilities make
sense. In fact, there are a lot of
distributions that we're going to see
over and over again. One of the simplest
and most ubiquitous distributions is
called the uniform distribution. So here
we have some finite sample space S. And
then we just look at the probability
measure that assigns the same fixed
probability to every possible outcome.
So in particular, in order for it to be
normalized, each of those probabilities
had better be one over the size of S. So
this is where we left off last time. We
also define this notion of what an event
was. You know, sometimes we're not
interested in one particular outcome,
but really a collection of outcomes.
Something like when I take a dieice and
I roll it and I get an even number.
That's not just any one atomic outcome,
but it's really three outcomes for two,
four, and six. And we talk about the
probability of an event as really just
being the sum of the probability
measured over all of the outcomes that
land in the subset t. So this is where
we left off last time. And um you know
today what we're really working towards
is we're going to talk about something
that's very important but a little bit
counterintuitive.
We're going to talk about independence
and conditioning. So what's important to
build up to this is really the idea that
you know we cannot just consider the
probabilities of individual events but
we can combine them in interesting ways.
Right? So for example if I give you two
events T1 and T2 I can think about the
union of T1 and T2. What this means is
I'm really just treating this as the set
of outcomes I'm interested in. This is
another set of possible outcomes I'm
interested in. And I'm forming a new
event that takes everything that happens
in either one of these or maybe both. So
in particular, in words, what does this
new event that I've constructed mean?
It's the event that at least
one of these events, T1 or T2, happened,
right?
So that's one way to combine events. I
could also think about combining events
by for example taking T1 intersect T2
and then what am I going to get? I'm
going to get a new event that's asking
me whether both T1 and T2 happened.
Right?
And so this now leads to a very
interesting concept which is the notion
of conditional probability.
And I promise that um [clears throat]
you know this will sound very simple but
in the examples we'll see some of them
will become pretty counterintuitive.
In fact you know when you look
conditional probability is really in the
world all around you in very important
ways. We'll talk about some real world
examples. So first let me tell you what
this means. Let me just give you the
definition.
We can also combine two events A and B
in this interesting way where we want to
assert for a fact that event B really
did happen and we want to look at if I
tell you that event B happened what's
the new probability that this other
event A happened. So you can think about
this you know in a few different ways.
So it's in words it's the probability
of event A given or conditioned on that
event
B happens
see one way to think about this is
really in terms of pictures right
so we could start off with our full
sample space S that's all of the
different possibilities
we could take one event a right here.
And what's going on is that, you know,
our probability measure really describes
a way of throwing a dart at this board.
Now, this dart always lands inside this
box S because that's the range of all
possible outcomes.
And then the probability of the event A
is just the probability that that dart
lands inside this oval that I've drawn
right here. So now when I have a pair of
events and I have A and B right here.
Well, what I can do is imagine I do this
experiment where I throw my dart at the
board and we already know it has to land
inside the set S. But then what if I
tell you that it's landed in the set B
and I promise you that event B happens.
What I want to know is given that
promise, what's the new probability that
it actually lands inside the set A? So
the only place where it could then land
an event A could happen is right here in
the intersection. And that's exactly how
we define the conditional probability,
it's literally just the probability of
the intersection of the two events
divided by the probability that I'm
conditioning on. And this part is
intuitive. You know, imagine that I have
the same chance of hitting every single
point inside this rectangle, right? Then
really what's going on is that when I
tell you that event B has happened, you
know, the probability of B is how I'm
renormalizing my space of possible
outcomes because I know that now my dart
is uniform over the set B. And what's
important is not the amount of space
that A takes up inside S, but the amount
of space that A intersect B takes up
inside B. So does this make sense? Are
there any questions about the definition
of conditional probability?
Good. All right. So, let's develop a few
different ways to think about
conditional probability. Let me actually
give one other simple example which is
related to it um which will have its own
quirks. The other crucial notion that um
I want to introduce today is the notion
of independence.
So we talked about two events you know A
and B and you know there's this very
important concept which we're going to
use all the time which is called
independence. So we say that two events
A and B are independent
if the probability of A intersect B is
equal to the probability of A times the
probability of B. So this is in some
sense the simplest way that the
probability of intersecting two events
could work is that you know whether A
happens you think of it as you know it
it contributes this P of A and whether B
happens contributes this P of B.
But in fact just as an exercise you know
um using our definition for conditional
probability we can see that you know
independence is really equivalent to a
much simpler thing which is that
probability of A given B is equal to the
probability of A. Right?
So this comes just from dividing through
by the probability of B and using my
definition for conditional independence.
So these are two completely equivalent
conditions. You can check either one.
And that's what it means for two things
to be independent. So what's going on is
that in my dartboard example, you know,
in pictures, I might have my entire
rectangle represents S. I might have
this left half represents A and maybe
this bottom half represents B. And so
what's going on is, you know, if I look
at the probability of A, that's how much
area this rectangle for A takes up out
of the entire rectangle. But then when I
condition on B, it doesn't change what
that fraction is. So this is one way to
think about what independence is. And I
want to caution you that even though
it's a very simple definition, it's
actually very counterintuitive in some
ways. there are, you know, easy pairs of
events that are natural to think about
why they're independent. And then there
are some events that are independent
that are very counterintuitive.
So let's do the simple one first. Let's
do some simple examples to get some
intuition for independence.
So imagine that uh we throw
a dice twice
and this is a fair die. So it's the
uniform distribution over all six
possibilities.
And when I look at, you know, the pair
of throws, my sample space now has 36
possibilities.
For every possibility for the first
throw X1, every possibility for the
second row X2. So I look at all
possibilities of X1, X2 that are in this
set
one, two up to six. Right? So this is my
sample space and everything is uniform
over the sample space. All of the 36
possibilities for the choice of some
number between 1 and six and some number
between 1 and six are all equally
likely. And now I can define some
events.
Let's look at events A
which is that X1 is odd.
And let's look at the event that B that
X2 is at most three.
So probably you all have very good
intuition for this. So who thinks uh
these two events A and B are
independent?
Okay. Who thinks they're not?
Who is still tired?
Okay. All right. Good honesty. All
right. So these two are independent. Now
uh one way to check independence is
literally just to follow the definition.
So when in doubt just compute the thing,
right? But we're going to see, you know,
part of the intuition for why they're
independent. We'll see in in the
computation itself, right? So what does
it mean to be independent? Let's check.
Let's look at the probability of A and
B. So in our sample space, there are 36
possibilities. How many possibilities
meet the condition that both event A and
event B hold?
Not a hard question. Yeah. A quarter of
them. Yeah. So, let me just say nine out
of 36.
Why is it nine? Because I have three
possibilities for X1 is odd, right? 1
35. I have three possibilities for X2 is
at most three one two three and every
choice of you know one of the
possibilities for A and every choice for
one of the possibilities of B defines a
possible outcome that satisfies both A
and B. So they're independent because
they have this kind of product structure
that you know whatever happens for A you
know I can choose something there and
then I can define something that happens
for B. So literally if you think about
it, it really represents this picture if
you think about it the right way. So in
any case we can check that um this
really does you know equal the
probability of A times the probability
of B because what's the probability of
A? It's just a half. A half of the rolls
are odd. What's the probability of B?
It's a half because a half of them or
three or less.
So the way to think about it is that um
you know independence is sometimes
intuitive because you know what's going
on here is I could literally think about
rolling two separate dice, right? I roll
one dice here and I care about what the
role is and then you go to another room
in building two and you roll another die
and they're independent because we
literally are not talking to each other,
right? These events are just happening
in different spaces. But independence is
a bit more counterintuitive than that
because there are other ways that events
can be independent that satisfy our
definition that aren't so easy to check.
Let me also mention that um you know a
lot of times we use the shorthands which
just means that A and B are independent
as events.
All right. So let's go a little further
with this example so that I can convince
you that independence is subtle. So
let's define a new event C which is
going to be the event X1 - X2 is equal
to 3.
Now this is a bit stranger of an event
because you know it involves both X1 and
X2. Right? Now what are the possible
outcomes in the sample space where event
C happens? Can anyone list them for me?
>> Yeah.
>> Perfect. And those are the only
possibilities. So another way to define
this event is really as the subset of
the sample space which we're interested
in which is the possibility 41. It's the
possibility 52.
And lastly we have the possibility 63.
That's the only subset of the sample
space that I'm interested in. Those are
the only things that can happen where
this event C is on is true.
And we can look at the same type of
thing. Let's look at our definition for
independence. Let's look at the
probability that A and C both happen. So
what was A? X1 is odd. And there's only
one possibility on my list where X1 is
odd and C happens. So this means the
probability of my intersection is 1 over
36.
Unfortunately, this is not equal to the
probability of A times the probability
of C. We know the probability of A is a
half and we know the probability of C is
3 over 36 just based on our description
of the event. So these two events A and
C are not independent, right? A is not
independent from C. And maybe this is
intuitive too because you know these two
events depend on the same things. They
both depend on what happens for RO one,
right? But what I claim is that there
are slight changes, you know, to event C
that actually make these things be
independent. Let's define a fourth and
final event. Let's look at this event D.
That's X1 - X2 is equal to four instead
of three. Now we have only two
possibilities. We have the possibility
51 and we have the possibility 62.
Right?
And we can just check our definition for
independence.
So the probability of A and D. Well,
there's only one thing that survives. So
my probability of the intersection is
still 1 over 36.
And you can check that this really is
equal to the probability of A which is a
half times the probability of D which is
2 over 36. Right?
So this is an example which would be a
little bit hard to guess unless you
literally did the calculation because it
doesn't look like they're independent
but they still are. So are there any
questions about independence?
Does this make sense?
Okay. All right. So let's go a little
further.
I want to tell you about um some more
powerful tools of probability that play
very nicely with conditioning and
independence.
Let me tell you about this basic fact
that we're going to use all over the
place and then I'll give you a way to
visualize it. This fact is called the
law of total probability.
Even though we already defined whatever
we need just in terms of like the sample
space and the probability measure, there
are a lot of tricks that are going to
happen where you know there are clever
ways to compute probabilities that don't
involve listing the entire sample space
and just adding things up in a boring
way. So a lot of these tools are really
a way to organize and think about the
sample space to try and make probability
more intuitive.
And the you know the basic version of
the law of total probability is that if
I have an event A and I care about its
probability right we already have a
definition for how to compute that
probability just by going over the
entire sample space. But what I claim is
that we can break it up into two
different terms. one where a and b both
happen and then I can add in the
probability that a happens and b does
not happen. Right? So this is just if
I'm interested in the probability that a
happens well you know either a happens
and b happens or a happens and b doesn't
happen. These together cover the space
of all things that could happen so that
a still occurs and they don't overlap at
all. So in particular the proof of this
is you know there really is no proof.
It's literally just we take the
definition of what the probability of A
is. It's the sum over all X in my set A
of P of X. And all I'm doing is I'm
breaking this sum up into two pieces.
It's the sum over all x in a and b of p
of x. That's literally this right here.
Plus the sum over all x in a and not b
of probability of x. Right? And so
pictorially we can go back to our you
know favorite diagram. We have this
event A that we care about. We have this
other event B. And then we can break up
this event A into two pieces. One where
A happens and B does not and one where
A happens and B does and together they
cover the space. Right? So in fact
there's an even fancier version of the
law of total probability because no one
says you have to do this with one other
event. In fact you can do this with a
ton of other events. Right? So let's
talk about the most general version.
of the law of total probability.
We can be interested in the probability
of some event A and we can write this as
the sum over a collection of other
events of the probability of A and B I
but now we need some conditions on the
BI's. We need that all of the BI's are
disjoint. So B I intersect BJ is the
empty set for I not equal to J. They're
pair-wise disjoint.
And we also need that together they
cover the entire space. The union of all
of these BIS is my sample space. So in
particular for this most general
definition for the law of total
probability really the way that I
recover that special case we already
talked about is I consider two events B1
and B2 and B2 is the complement of B1.
And that way I just get two terms in the
sum. They're definitely disjoint. B1 and
its complement don't intersect and
together they cover the space. But
instead of breaking up my entire sample
space into only two possibilities, I can
think about breaking it up into three,
four, five, how many ever is convenient.
So any questions about the law of total
probability.
Good.
All right.
So let's uh go back to visualizing these
things. I I want to try to make these
things as intuitive as possible.
So in fact there's a clever way to think
about them
using a diagram which I find very
helpful.
So we can think about
you know our random process
as really taking some sort of path in a
tree. Maybe we start off our random
process
and then we have a whole bunch of
possibilities like B1, B2,
B3.
So what I'm deciding here is really
the answer to the question which of the
BIS
happens
right because in the setup of the law of
total probability all these BIS are
pair-wise disjoint and they cover the
space so you know when I start this
process before I actually tell you what
the outcome is where the dart lands I'm
first going to tell you which region the
dart lands in. Does it land in B1? Does
it land in B2? Does it land in B3? The
assumption that these things are
pairwise disjoint just means that one
and only one of these things happens.
But I have a different probability of
traversing these edges depending on what
the probability of those events are.
Right? And then finally
I can look at conditioned on B1
happening whether the event A actually
happens. Right? So I can continue this
process
and then what I can ask is you know how
does knowing that BI happens how does
that change
the probability
of A.
So this is a nice way to visualize it,
right? Because you know what's going on
in here [snorts]
is you can write it out instead using
conditional probability like another
equivalent way to do this is it's the
sum over i of the probability of a
conditioned on bi times the probability
of bi. Literally nothing is happening
here. I'm just using the definition of
what conditional probability is. And
then you can see that you know
algebraically what's happening is first
you're telling me which BI happened that
contributes this term right here. And
then once you tell me that BI happens I
have to also take into account the
remaining conditional probability. And
when I add up over all the possibilities
that gives me the total probability of
the event. So these are very basic
algebraic manipulations but they're
powerful.
So any questions?
All makes perfect sense.
>> So what is the what are the nodes?
>> Right? So this would be these are all of
the possible outcomes in the sample
space. So what I'm doing is instead of
just telling you first where the dart
lands like which X happens first. I'm
going to tell you whether B1 happens, B2
happens or B3 happens. Once I tell you
that B1 happens, I know my dart lands in
that space. I look at all the X's that
belong to B1. And maybe I just shade in
the X's that belong to that subset that
are also in my set A. So for example,
the fraction of nodes here that are
colored is exactly the probability of A
conditioned on B1. So you can see that I
have this probability of taking D1 and
then I have a conditional probability or
I have the probability of taking this
branch and then another conditional
probability. This is pictorially what
the law of probability is telling you.
You can think about it, you know, many
different ways. This is this is tricky.
So you know don't be uh embarrassed to
ask questions. That's why I'm here. Any
other questions?
Everyone thinks this is way too easy.
Way too hard.
Just right. Okay, I'll take it. All
right. Um,
let's see.
All right. Let's check our understanding
because some of these things are a
little bit counterintuitive.
Um,
how many people have heard of the Monty
Hall problem?
Okay. How many people
feel totally comfortable with the Monty
Hall problem and think I should skip it?
Or how many people want to hear it? Who
wants me to skip it?
Okay, that's a very small number, so I'm
going to do it. So, you've all seen the
Monty Hall problem before.
What I claim is that you know a lot of
these ways of thinking about things in
terms of the law of total probability in
terms of this visual I gave you here
well they give you a nice intuitive way
to think about what's going on. So you
know I'll give you maybe an explanation
you haven't seen before. So, remember in
the Monty Hall problem, there's a game
show and there's three doors
and behind one of the doors is a nice
prize.
Maybe there's a car,
but you don't know which door has the
prize. So, the way that the game works
is that first you pick a door.
Now, whatever door you pick, if I pick
this door, there's definitely another
door that doesn't have the prize. If I
pick this door that has the prize,
there's still another door that doesn't
have the prize. So either way, the host
can always,
no matter what you picked for your first
door, reveal to you another door that
you didn't select, which als
you shouldn't pick that door. And the
basic question is, you know, do you
switch?
So this is a very famous example. I
think the first time you see it, it is a
bit hard to wrap your head around, but
it's been done in virtually every class
that covers probability so often that um
you know, maybe it's become a little bit
more intuitive. Uh you know, as you all
know, the answer is that you switch that
then you'll win this game with twothirds
probability. Now, you can you know,
figure that out by computing conditional
probabilities. You have to be very
careful about the definitions of your
events. But I think a very intuitive way
to think about it is in terms of this
tree
that I drew before, right? Because we
can think about all the things that can
happen in the game. So in the beginning
when you choose a door, remember that
the prize is put behind a door at
random. So whatever door you choose, you
have a 23 probability of selecting a
door that has no prize.
and you have a one-thirds chance of
selecting the door that has the prize.
Of course, the game isn't over then. And
we can just think about what happens
depending on your choice of strategy.
You know, you could at that juncture
decide to switch, you could decide to
not switch. And the same thing happens
here. You could decide to switch or not
switch.
And the way to think about it is that,
you know, once I select the door that
doesn't have the prize, then the host
has no choice but to reveal to me the
only other door that doesn't have the
prize. And then when I switch, I
definitely win.
So I win as soon as I select a door in
the beginning with no prize if I'm
committed to the strategy switch. And if
I don't switch, then of course I lose.
And the same thing happens here, but you
know in reverse. If I got unlucky and I
selected the door with the prize and I
committed to the strategy switch, then
the host would show me one of these two
doors without the prize and I would
switch and I would lose my prize. But
this only happens with probability 1/3
because that's the probability that this
tree associates with it and otherwise
I'd win. So you can see that once I've
committed to the fact that I'm going to
switch all I need to do is I need to get
not super lucky just I need to select a
door which doesn't have the prize and
then automatically you can see that I
will win.
So we'll do more examples of these kinds
of things later especially in recitation
like drawing out these uh diagrams to
organize the state space. Let me tell
you one more really cool tool and then
we'll do some real world applications of
it. Uh this involves again conditional
probability. It's called Baze rule
and it's a very basic formula.
So imagine that we compute something
like the probability of B given A. It
turns out there's a way to express this
in terms of
the conditional probability the other
way around. You just have to correct by
the right factors of P of B and P of A.
So this is a very powerful rule. Uh the
proof is
quite straightforward. It's just
algebraic, right? Because all we have to
do is just invoke the definitions. So by
definition,
you know, how did we define the
probability of A given B? It was just
the probability of A and B
divided by the probability of B. Right?
That's literally what our definition
was. I can take this definition and I
can just multiply by this correction
term, which is probability of B over
probability of A. And if I do this on
both sides of my equation, well, one
side I'm going to get this right hand
side. So I'll get probability of A given
B times probability of B over the
probability of A.
And on my other side, the probability of
B's are going to cancel. I'm going to
get probability of A and B over
probability of A. And I claim that this
is the same thing as the probability of
B given A. And that's because it doesn't
matter what order I intersect these two
things. Probability of A and B is the
same thing as the probability of B and
A. And then this is again literally the
definition of conditional probability.
So the proof of this B rule is very
simple. In fact, um anyone know anything
historically about, you know, why people
were interested in this? So, it's kind
of interesting historical fact. Yeah,
>> they wanted to prove God.
>> Yeah, they wanted to prove God. Uh, the
existence of God using BA's rule. I
don't think they got there and we're not
going to get there today either, but
we'll still do some fun stuff with it.
It's kind of interesting. A lot of the
um, you know, foundations of probability
have some theological component to them,
but uh, I'll leave that as a discussion
for another time. So, we've got Baze
rule. Let's do a powerful real world
example.
The numbers in this example are all
completely real.
Okay. So, let me tell you some facts.
So approximately
1%
of women
aged
40 to 50
get breast cancer.
That is a shockingly high percentage,
but it's a true fact.
And one of the ways that you can try and
screen for breast cancer is a mammogram.
So a mamogram is not a perfect test. So
it has a 10%
false positive rate.
I'll tell you what I mean by that in a
second.
And it has similarly for its false
negative rate.
So let's look at two events which we
really care about, right? Because our
test is imperfect. We can look at A is
the event that we test positive,
right? And we can look at the event B
that we really have the condition that's
being tested for in this case, you know,
breast cancer.
These are the two events
and yeah
40.
>> Yeah, it is. Yeah. So developed in that
time frame.
So here just to be clear. So what do I
mean by the false positive rate? So this
would be the probability of a given not
b. So this is the chance the test says
positive even though you don't have it.
And we can also look at the false
negative rate which is the probability
of not a given b. So you actually do
have the condition but the test doesn't
pick it up. So both of these things a
lot of these tests you know we have much
higher accuracy tests but the idea is
that you know you usually deploy some
lower accuracy test as a screening
procedure right to try and get a rough
idea but then the question is you know
how much stock should you actually put
in the test results right so you know
one of the conditional probabilities
that's you know very important is what's
the probability of B given A right. So
what does this mean? You test positive
and then you're very worried but you
want to know whether you actually have
the condition or not. Right?
Um so this you know let me take a poll
from the audience.
Let's just say approximately what do you
think the probability of B given A is?
You know after all the mammogram has um
you know 10% false positive and false
negative rate. So maybe you think you've
got a 90% chance of having the
condition.
Maybe it's 75%.
Maybe it's 25%.
Maybe it's around 10%.
Maybe it's 1%.
So you all said you understand
conditional probability. You all said uh
you're ready for a test on it, right? So
here's my test. So what do you think the
answer is? Right? And this is a very
medically important question because um
you know when you test positive for
something you have many treatment
options. Some of them are more or less
invasive than others. So how sure are
you that you have that condition? Is it
worth it to do some very invasive and
risky procedure?
Uh so who thinks the answer is one 90%.
Who thinks the answer is two? 75%.
Three, 25%. You guys have to vote. Okay,
you can't abstain. You're a doctor.
Someone's relying on you. Let's try this
again. Who thinks the answer is one?
90%.
Just take a vote. Take a chance. Don't
I'm not going to grade you on this.
Okay. Who thinks the answer is two? 75%.
Okay. Who thinks the answer's three,
25%. Who thinks the answer is four, 10%.
Who thinks the answer is five, 1%. Okay.
So, if you answered two,
then
that you're in good company because
that's the average physician's answer.
There was actually a survey of hundreds
of physicians and when you average their
scores, you get 75%. Unfortunately,
you're in a group that completely got
the wrong answer because the answer is
not at all 75%.
It's actually about 8%. So 10% is very
close. For anyone who answered four,
could you give me some kind of
intuition?
>> Yeah,
>> I guess 1% is like really low to begin
with. So 10xable.
>> Yeah, that's right. That's great
intuition is because if you think about
it already I mean this is a high
percentage but it's still in an absolute
sense low right so you can think that
the vast majority you know when you
think about a typical person who doesn't
have it 99% chance then there's still a
reasonable chance that they would still
test positive if they were tested and so
among the people who are tested positive
that's the region on the dart board I
care about still the disproport
proportionate share of them are people
who aren't going to have it. Right? So
this is actually uh from a very famous
book that I encourage you to read if you
want to be depressed.
Uh it's called thinking fast and slow by
conaman and it goes through all of these
examples about how people's and
especially doctors it kind of picks on
doctors uh make very counterintuitive
decisions. So you know when I used to
teach 042 more regularly I would still
do this example. I think it's a
beautiful example. And then in 2016, we
had our first kid uh baby girl. And I
remember that, you know, when we were
doing all these tests, not breast
cancer, but other things like testing
for the risk of Down syndrome, one of
the crazy things is that at the time,
what you do is you do an amnneoentesis
to do that. That's where you, you know,
put a needle into the belly and then you
extract fluid to try and figure out, uh,
whether, you know, various genetic
conditions are happening. The crazy
thing is that a lot of the things they
were testing for had very low
percentages of occurring. They're
terrible things when they happen like
Down syndrome, but the risk of causing
uh a miscarriage with am with an
amnocentesis when I looked it up was
something like one in 700. So I have to
say that like real world examples from
having kids makes these things feel very
differently. So if you're curious, I can
tell you all kinds of conditional
probabilities that doctors get wrong
that relate to child rearing, but that's
another topic for another time. Um, so
we have uh a little bit of time left.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to
start uh the next topic where we're
going to take these ideas even further.
So so far what we've talked about is
mostly events. We talked about ways to
reason about events. We talked about
what events were, how to combine them in
different ways. And we talked about
these fancy ways about reasoning about
their probability either through the law
of total probability or using
conditional probabilities. We talked
about how to reason about it through
this tree diagram I gave you. That's
sort of a way to organize the sample
space. We talked about some, you know,
the Monty Hall problem. We talked about
some real world examples.
Well, it turns out that um there's an
even more powerful abstraction that we
can do beyond events where things get
even more interesting. Some of the
theory goes over but it changes in in
cool ways. So let me explain this in
terms of you know how we're going to
generalize what we've seen right so last
topic for today I want to talk tell you
about is what are called random
variables.
Okay, so where are we right now? We
talked about events which are a subset
of the sample space.
We talked about a lot of properties of
events, right? We talked about the
property of independence
and how in some cases it can be
intuitive like when the experiments are
literally done separated from each
other. Other times it can be
counterintuitive and you just have to
check the definition. We talked about
you know conditioning.
We talked about unions and
intersections, right? And then you know
random variables instead of being a
subset of the sample space what they are
is they're functions
defined on the sample space.
So what they do is they take an outcome
and they ascribe to that outcome some
real value. Right? So this is the
intuitive thing. Let's do the
definition.
So a random variable
is a function
f that goes from my sample space and
ascribes to each outcome some real
value.
And in fact we'll be interested in a lot
of properties of random variables. So
one of the most useful and ubiquitous
properties is called its expectation. So
let's just define that now too. So the
associated expectation
of the random variable
as just literally the average over your
probability space of the values the
function takes. So I write it here. This
is you know a little block E
and it's defined to be equal to the sum
over all outcomes in my space of the
probability of that outcome times the
real value of the corresponding random
variable. So this is just a weighted
average of the value of the random
variable weighted by the probability of
each one of these outcomes. Right? So,
you know, random variables come up all
the time. You know, we don't just care
about events. Um, you know, one of the,
you know, simplest ways that might come
up is even in understanding something
like betting, right? Where there are a
lot of different outcomes that you could
be betting on. And then, you know,
something like the random variable would
describe the payoffs, the different
parties.
So, let's do some simple examples to get
some intuition for what the random
variable is.
Let's do one where the sample space is
infinite just for fun.
So let's toss a coin
until
you get
a heads. We'll start off with a fair
coin and then we'll we'll vary this
experiment. Right? So you know first
what is the sample space?
Well, we could have the first coin as
heads already and we stop there. We
could have tails heads could have tails
tails heads and so on. So any sequence
of ta uh tails any length from zero to
infinity with a heads appended at the
end. That's our sample space. And we
also care about what's the associated
probability measure. So furthermore,
the probability
of having I T's and then one H is equal
to a half to the I + one, right? Because
I better get my first thing is a tails.
That's a half probability. My second
thing is a tails and so on. And there I
+ one things here. So the chance of
getting exactly this string is just half
raised to the i + 1.
And now we have enough information that
we can compute the expected value. So
let's look at the random variable we'll
be interested in will be just the number
of coin tosses.
So of course this game in principle
could go on forever but the expected
value gives us some baseline of you know
what we expect it to be. We're going to
talk about a lot fancier tools later uh
in a few lectures time because when we
get back to random variables we're going
to talk about tools for arguing why
random variables in some cases are very
close to their expectation. That's very
important in things like you know
understanding the error of polling. But
for right now we just want to work with
you know what a random variable is and
get some crude idea of kind of what we
expect it to be approximately.
So you know the natural way to do this
to compute the expectation of f is
literally just to uh you know use the
expression we gave you right. So you
know there's a half probability that the
game is over instantly.
and uh you know that we get heads to
begin with. There's a quarter
probability
that this game goes on for two total
flips. There's an eighth probability
that it goes on for
three total flips and so on. And so we
can write this as a series. It's the sum
from k = 1 to infinity
of k * 1 / 2 k.
Uh already on the homework we've shown
you some examples of you know how to
evaluate sums like this. We're going to
talk about this in a lot more detail
when we get to the counting unit which
is right after the probability unit. So
we'll give you tools not only for
evaluating these sums but for thinking
about what kinds of things they count.
But in any case, we can uh evaluate this
very quickly just by um arranging things
in the right way. So from this
expression, it's not that easy to guess
what the answer is. But if we break up,
you know, this quarter, this 2 * a
quarter into the sum of two quarters, it
becomes a lot easier.
So let's write it out pictorially. We
have a half from the first term and then
we have two quarters and then we have
three
and this thing goes on right and what we
can do is we can evaluate this sum in a
different way line by line row by row
first. So if we have a half plus a
quarter plus an eighth plus a 16th and
so on. Well, this you probably all know
the answer is one for what that part of
the sum contributes. And if instead we
have a quarter plus an eighth plus a 16,
well, that's going to give us a half.
And the next thing will give us a
quarter. And now when we sum up all of
these guys along the column, we're going
to get two.
So this is very natural. The expected
number of flips for a coin until you get
your first heads is two, right? Makes
sense.
Um [clears throat]
and in fact we can do this in a more
clever way too. We'll use this in a
minute actually. So let me explain you
know the even more general setting
which leads me to something called
meanantime to failure.
This is something that comes up in a lot
of computer science applications.
Let me give you the story behind it, but
it'll really be the same kind of
exercise we just did.
Imagine we've got some computer
as a part of some giant uh computing
system and it's not a perfect computer
and it fails independently
on each day
with some probability P.
Well, one of the things you might be
interested in, what's called the
meanantime to failure,
is how many days you expect the computer
to last before you replace it. Right?
This is a very basic probabistic
statement. that shows up all the time uh
especially in things like actuarial
sciences or you know literally in
computing because you know when you're
building giant um you know computing
systems like chat GPT you know you have
to create this huge infrastructure of
computers and they often fail and you
have to have some idea for how often
that's going to happen and how much the
cost is to replace these parts to figure
out economically what you're sinking
into the system. But you know we can do
the same exercise we did the same way.
I'll do it in a slightly more clever
way. So we have this random variable t
that is the time that this computer
fails. Right? So we have some
probability p that it happens on the
first day. And then we have some
probability 1 minus p * p that it
happens on the second day. Let's just do
out one more. 1 - p^ 2 * p and it
happens on the third day.
But there's a clever trick for doing
this which is that this is equal to p
you know from this first term times 1
minus p * 1 + the expectation of t. So
this looks a bit magical right? Can
anyone give me some intuition for what
exactly I just did in this expression?
Why is this true? Yeah,
that's right. That's right. So, first,
you know, I got my P from here. I pulled
out this one minus P because
everything's got a one minus P in front
of it. But then the important thing is
that, you know, when I don't fail on the
first day, the entire process starts
over again, right? It has no memory of
what happened in the past. I've gone one
extra day, but then whatever happens to
that same identical random variable that
I care about is going to be what happens
the process there on out. Right? So in
fact, this makes it much easier. Instead
of messing around with these infinite
sums, I can just rearrange things
algebraically.
And what I'll get is that the
expectation of t is equal to 1 over p.
Okay, any questions?
Make sense? All right, so the meanantime
to failure just depends on this failure
probability in this very simple way.
So let's uh get back to expectation and
then I'm going to tell you something
unlike the Monty Hall problem that
you're definitely going to find
counterintuitive.
So, we talked about random variables. We
talked about events.
Actually, there's a way to go back and
forth between the two.
So, it turns out that we can actually
treat events
as random variables.
This will be a very important trick that
we're going to use all the time.
So this is called the indicator
function.
So in particular,
if you give me an event A,
well, I can define this function that
has this funny notation. Usually you
write it as a bold-faced one with an a
subscript, but this is just a random
variable. It takes in some outcome from
the sample space and it spits out a real
value.
It spits out the value one if
your event belong if your outcome
belongs to the event. Fine. And it
outputs a zero otherwise. Okay.
So in particular this is you know if you
give me an event this describes an
associated random variable. So this is
just a recipe for it. My random variable
takes on real values actually takes on
values just one or zero. It's one if the
event is on, it's zero otherwise.
And now the good thing is that um a lot
of what we do with uh you know random
variables we can use to reason about
events. So let's connect this back to
events. So I can look at for example the
expectation of my indicator function
over a random outcome. So let's just be
clear because we've introduced a lot of
notation already today for probability.
Remember that when I write this bold E,
I'm looking at that experiment where I
throw my dart and I get some outcome in
my space that tells me what X I have.
And remember that you know an event is
just whether or not X belongs to A. But
what's going on here is that I have this
function that just outputs one if X
belongs to A and outputs zero otherwise.
So in this case we can write out what
the definition of the expectation is.
It's the sum over all outcomes in my uh
set of the probability of the outcome
times the value of the random variable.
And this is the same thing as the sum
over all x in a of the probability of x,
right? Because the only way that this
term survives is if x belongs to a.
Otherwise, the term is zero and it goes
away. So this is really just bookkeeping
for keeping track of which p of x's
contribute to my sum. And this way I
change the subscript of my sum from
being over all outcomes to only the
outcomes in my set. So in particular the
nice thing is that we get back the
probability of the event. So you can see
that we can use random variables as a
placeholder for computing things like
the probabilities of events just by
looking at their expectation.
So this is just a bunch of bookkeeping.
Does this make sense? Any questions? All
right.
So now um one of the really powerful
things about expectation is that it
behaves really nicely in some settings.
It uh behaves as nicely as you could
want. So let me tell you a powerful
fact. Uh some of you have probably
already seen it before, but linearity of
expectation.
So it turns out [clears throat]
that when you add random variables,
computing their expectation is easy.
So in particular, I can look at a random
variable f ofx. I can look at a random
variable g of x, right? And what I'm
doing when I add them is I'm literally
creating a new random variable, right?
Because my random variable is just going
to be h of x that adds up the two values
of this function. This right here is
still a function from all of my outcomes
to a real value. And when I look at its
expectation, that's the same thing as
the sum of the expectations of the
individual functions.
So, this is a powerful tool. I think the
first time you see it, it's easy to like
nod your head and and think it looks
obvious. Uh, let's prove it, but then
I'll test your intuition to see how well
you understand this.
So, all we have to do is follow our nose
and use the definition.
We can look at this left hand side the
expectation of f ofx plus g ofx
right and by definition this is the sum
over all x in my sample space of p of x
times the value of the random variable
which is f ofx plus g ofx right and now
I can just multiply through and and
separate out the sum and this is the
same thing as the sum over all x and
of P of X * FX plus the sum over all X
and S of P of X * G ofX. And now we're
in good shape because this term right
here is literally our definition of the
expectation of F. This term right here
is literally our definition of the
expectation of G. So that proves what we
wanted, right? A lot of other things do
not behave this nicely, but expectations
always add no matter how complicated the
dependence is between f and g.
So let me test your intuition to make
sure that people are following this. I
guess I'll erase that part.
Okay,
so we know that if we have some event
A, we can look at the associated random
variable, the corresponding indicator of
that event 1 A. Can look at some other
event, you know, 1B.
And we already know from before that the
expectation
of this indicator
of a is equal to the probability of a.
Right?
Um what if I look at the expectation of
1 a of x plus 1 b of x
in some sense this looks like you know
I'm taking into account whether a or b
happened is this equal to for example
the probability that event a or b
happens
just to test your intuition.
All right. So, how many people think the
answer is yes?
How many people think the answer is no?
Okay. So, the nos have it. So, someone
who said no, can you tell me what's
wrong? I mean, it seems intuitive, but
it's not true.
>> Yeah.
A and B both happen that it gets double
counted on the left side but not on the
right.
>> That's right. That's right. So you know
what's going on here, right? Is we can
go back to our diagram. We have these
two events A and B, right?
And when I look at the expectation of,
you know, one A of X, well, I'm just
looking at this dart and throwing it in
here. And every time it lands inside A,
I'm getting a dollar. every time it
lands outside, I'm getting no dollars.
And I'm looking at the expected number
of dollars I win, right? And that's the
same thing as the probability that the
dart actually lands in that set, right?
And now, same thing is true for B. But
when I add these two things up, what's
going on is if I actually landed in the
intersection of these two, I'd be
getting $2, right? So really what's
going on is that this is not equal
because this is no longer an indicator
random variable. It doesn't just take
the value zero and one. It also takes
the value two sometimes. The only way
this would be true is if a and b were
actually disjoint.
All right. Does that make sense? All
right.
Sounds good. Um
so I'll tell you
uh one really interesting problem and
then we'll end there and we'll go on to
other topics next time.
So you all have seen the Monty Hall
problem before. That's no surprise.
It turns out that uh you know
conditional probability, conditional
expectations can still be very you know
counterintuitive
in ways that even math professors can be
totally wrong and have the wrong
intuition.
So let me tell you about uh this amazing
example that's due to my colleague
upstairs.
Uh in fact I saw him right before class.
It's called muscles dice paradox.
Elenon Muscle is a very famous
probabilist and um you know when he came
up with this his adviser told him I know
you've done a lot of great research and
he proved amazing things but this will
be what you're famous for and he was
very disappointed.
Um so here's the experiment.
You can throw a dice
until
you get a six.
Okay. And we're going to be interested
in the number of roles that you have to
take in expectation. Now, if that were
it, there would be no paradox. We
already talked about that for the
meanantime to failure, right? Because if
um my probability of rolling a six is
six, I can look at the expected number
of rolls and that would just be six.
Fine. Right? So, nothing is hard here.
But the experiment is you're going to
throw a dice until you get a six.
But now we want to compute the
conditional expectation.
So conditioned
on all the throws
being even
like what if I tell you that all the
throws are even. What is
the expected
number of rolls?
So, very simple problem. Takes a little
bit to wrap your head around it, right?
But you know the way that this
experiment goes, I'm sitting here
throwing the die until I get a six. And
you're not watching me do the
experiment. But then before I ask you
anything about the experiment, I tell
you actually while I was doing it, I
only got evens. It was the darnest
thing. And now telling you that I only
got even throws, I'm asking you how that
changes your expected number of rolls.
So it turns out that um you know there's
a very natural way to try and answer
this question. And almost everyone who
sees this the first time gets it wrong
the same way. It's it's amazing.
So there's uh one argument that leads
you to the wrong answer. So you'd claim
you'd think
that the answer
is three.
Let me tell you why you might think
that. Right? So let's go through what we
know. So we know that all roles are two,
four or six, right? because you just
promised me that all the rolls were
even. So those are the only
possibilities. Nothing else shows up
when I roll the die.
And now you know if you're rolling a
dieice and it's only got three sides,
you know, two, four, and six, then how
long do you have to go until you end up
with your first six and stop the
experiment? Well, six is a third of the
possibilities. So you'd expect just by
this argument from this meanantime to
failure that maybe the expected number
of rolls
is one over a third. So namely three
and this is actually completely wrong.
So in fact uh Elanon was teaching over
at Berkeley when he came up with this
example and uh he was doing a review for
some probability class and he wanted to
make this argument that you know
probability is very counterintuitive and
you just have to compute the darn you
know algebraic expression to do it and
he came up with this random example.
There's no special intuition behind it.
He came up with it on the fly and then
he started doing the proof out and he
got the answer three halves and he was
so convinced that somewhere in there was
like some algebraic mistake he'd made on
the board. See the truth is when you're
speaking to a large audience, you know,
your your IQ decreases by 20 points at
least. And um he told them that don't
worry, you know, I'll tell you what's
wrong with my computation and I'll email
the class and I'll tell you what I got
wrong so that you're ready for your
exam. Hey, he went home and he checked
it and um you know the darnest thing the
answer is actually three halves. It's a
very counterintuitive problem. In fact,
I remember I'll tell you I guess this is
videotaped. I'm not sure how much I
should say. Um but you know we have a
mailing list among some of the theory
faculty especially ones who teach some
of the intro uh you know proofbased math
classes. And then when this thing came
out, you know, David Carer emailed me
and told me, "This would be a great
example for, you know, 042. We should do
this." And one faculty member who shall
not be named was on the mailing list and
did not believe the answer. It was the
craziest thing. He was arguing with us
back and forth on this thread I have and
he just was convinced that the answer
was three.
And uh actually, should I cut the video
for this? Okay. So, let me tell you uh
the other part of the story. So then he
went on this debate for like uh maybe a
month or two not believing the answers
we gave him even about this very basic
statement and then he finally came into
our theory faculty lunch which I have to
go to after this and he said aha I
understand what was wrong you were all
explaining it wrong let me tell you my
explanation so he started explaining it
in this very convoluted way and Peter
was there with me at lunch uh Peter was
co-eing and Peter usually doesn't say
that much in the faculty lunches and he
Now I know why no one understands
probability when you teach it,
[laughter]
which is kind of amazing. So I'll uh
scrub the rest of the names from the
story. But um we'll do some examples in
class where we actually ask you to
compute this and uh you know you'll see
you know some tricks for doing this and
it'll be a good exercise for some of
your writing problems. So we'll stop
there a bit early and next time we will
continue with inclusion, exclusion and
other applications in probability.