Thank you so much for for inviting me.
It's really pleasure to be here and I'm
excited to tell you what we're working
on except you know especially because I
do feel that the work I do and my lab is
highly complimementaryary of the work
that you do and I think that there will
be so many opportunity to do some great
work together. So so this is a little
bit of kind of a journey of my research
and and my my lab. I really like to
do work that is highly motivated by
really important scientific question and
so I'll tell you what what is the kind
of trillion dollar question that I've
been chasing for a very long time and
what I'm doing right now in terms of joi
for our pollution exposure and the work
we are doing on the first foundation
model for climate adaptation and then I
switch on the responsible AI in terms of
thinking about the environmental impact
of AI and I think that where I am right
now in my research journey is that in
one hand I very excited about developing
this foundation model to prevent deaths
from extreme weather event and climate
and on the other side I'm also
quantifying the environmental impact of
AI and so which of the two is going to
win uh I still don't know but it's
actually is an interesting space and I
feel that's where research is is a being
on this space of always feeling
ambivalent of what is the right thing to
do. So I think that's where I'm going to
start. It's really you know are we if
you're thinking I'm going to give you an
answer in an hour. No. uh but at least I
can tell you where I am at in with in my
my research lab where literally we have
two post-docctoral fellows that they're
best friends with each other where one
is trying to you know use as many GPUs
as possible and the other one is trying
to use as less as GPUs as possible and
they're still talking to each other and
they're playing music together. So
anyway, so um here is a date kind of
trillion dollar question I'm asking uh
and you know basically does exposure to
find particular matters even a level
below the national ambient air quality
standard are still safe to human health
and is there pollution from coal fire
powered plants more toxic than air
pollution from other sources you know
how do we quantify the environmental
impact of wildfires you know this is the
type of policy relevant question which
right now actually thanks to be even
more uh more more more contentious more
contentious.
So that's are the scientific question
and then on the other side I am really
interested in causal inference and try
to go from causal inference from analyst
observational data to causal inference
and thinking about AI that can think
about causal cause and effect. I want to
mention this book and Elias Baron um I
don't know how many of you are familiar
of him. was a student of Judia Pearl. He
has published this book called causal
artificial intelligence
and I found the introduction very
helpful in terms of framing where we are
in the world of causal inference and so
uh and that's something I've been
thinking about uh very long time but I
do think it's important to frame my talk
within this framework. So first of all I
think you know uh the Judea Pearl
introduced this causal hierarchy. So
actually this is not even Elizabeth Bar
it's really Judia Pearl which he has in
included this he has introduced this um
causal hierarchy that is basically the
first level which is the red level is
just seeing right you have observational
data and you're trying to run a model to
figure out an association between X and
Y right analysis observational data then
the second layer for causal inference is
what would they call it the intervention
ional which is if I change something
right so if I which is called doing
right what if what if I do X then what's
going to be the causal effect on Y right
and then there is the third part which
is a counterfactual imaging which is
what will be the effect of acting on
something that will never see that
actually has never happened right and so
I I thought that this was a good frame
because that's how my research evolution
has been going in the context of
environmental impact from and I'm going
to show you from associational to causal
inference to now foundation model which
is counterfactual um imaging. So the
actually this is something that I wrote
before I bomb and before um Judia Pearl
framework although I really recognize
the jud framework is is really useful
and so basically just to get a narrow
down to the scientific question
basically with Cory Ziger who's a
professor at Brown we wrote this paper
where basically you know try to really
think about the question about seeing
which is basically is exposure ure to
find particular matter which are
pollutant in the air below the national
ambient air quality standard associated
with increase in mortality right that's
an associational question second
question is what if I intervene by
implementing strict international
ambient air quality standard what's
going to be the number of lives saved
and then what is imaging which is like
let's imagine an alternative world where
we have implemented the series of
strategy to cut their pollution or to
cut greenhouse gases then what will be
the positive consequence on society,
right? And so my mental framework in
terms of thinking about methodological
innovation in statistics and computer
science and AI has been following this
type of framework in in the last 15
years.
Now I you know I always say that
everything you need to start I mean one
of the premise I always work on is data.
you know without data especially if
you're trying to address an important
question you know there is there is
nothing else so I've been really
spending part of my career into
assembling a data science team that
pretty much harnessed data from the
entire US healthcare system and so and
that's where you see now the excitement
about potentially surrounding foundation
model on uh claims data from entire US
healthcare system so we we um harmonize
we buy harmonize integ great huge amount
of data engineering uh data set from
over 20 government data sources that
pretty much measure everything about
environment everything about society and
then health outcomes and so the health
outcomes come comes from the Medicare
and Medicaid claims and so basically in
the United States there is you know
there are two type of of national health
insurance Medicaid all ages for people
they have within certain lower bucket of
soio economic status and Medicaid for
everybody when you turn 65. And so for
everybody, so this is our 60 million
Americans, we know when they come into
the system, we know their zip code of
residence, we know age, gender, all
kinds of basic demographic and then we
can follow them over time for every
single hospitalization for that cause up
to that. So it's it's extremely rich.
And so the same thing for Medicaid data.
Medicaid as I mentioned is all ages but
it's not representative in terms that
you know you have to qualify to be
enrolled in Medicaid that there are
certain bucket of soio economic status.
So basically the the research of my lab
is literally seeing doing and now
imagining
in this massive amount of data right
there are three buckets. There is as I
mentioned exposure and the intervention.
So basically everything about exposure
to our pollution, wildfire exposure,
flooding, extreme weather event, right?
Chemical contaminants, right? That's one
bucket. The second bucket, as I
mentioned, all of the Medicare and
Medicaid data. And then the third
bucket, what we call confounders because
these are all other variables that can
covary with, you know, exposure to to to
environmental contaminant and health,
but that you need to to uh to account
for it, you know. And one of the major
sources of data is basically the uh the
uh census data.
So I mean what type of work we are doing
with all of this right? So just you
think about in in one hand a data
science team a massive amount of data
and the other is trying to see like do
and and imagine right and so these are
all types of challenges that we are
working on on a daily daily daily basis
one thing that in the work I do because
it's impact directory policy there are
elements that are absolutely
nonnegotiable, right? Interpretability.
We need to interpret our model. We need
to reproduce that because we're trying
to influence trillion dollar question.
And so there's going to be audits from
the industry that wanted to reproduce
our our funding. We have to act
responsibly and then we have to quantify
uncertainty across all of the different
stages in the most comprehensive way.
One thing where there is a lot of work
and probably many of you are familiar or
have done even better work than than we
did is actually on ensemble learning or
prediction to estimate exposure to our
pollution. That's is very kind of easy
and lowanging fruit. This is not about
causation. I just want to know this is
the map in the United States where there
are monitors of air pollution and you
see that there are part of the United
States where pollution is not monitored
very well right where the healthc care
data that I have is for everybody it's
for every single zip code in the United
States and so now there is this huge
literature very powerful literature
where what we try to do is we're going
to use satellite images and many other
variables that can allow to predict
localized exposure to our pollution in
in in in a very good way. So this is
something that probably is your bread
and butter right that that now has been
done and it's there is a full area of
research. So basically that could be
threebased model, narrow network model,
ensemble and hybrid models and the idea
is basically take take satellite
information which are aerosol aerosol
optical dots which is depth which is a
surrogate of our pollution. There are
many other variables and then you train
uh this model and you can you know you
can do downscaling whatever you like and
then you can estimate then 1 kilometer 1
kilometer grid the daily level of
pollution than your breed and the same
thing you can do with exposure to
wildfires the same thing you you can do
with exposure to heat right I mean this
is a very uh very simple this has been
going around for some time but I'm
telling you all this because that's has
been very helpful to us because you know
and this is actually not work I directly
do. I just you know leverage that work
because then with if I have a daily
levels of pollution a 1 kilometer to 1
kilometer grid for the last 20 years
then I can link to health data right and
so I can do an analysis for all the
continental United States and not only
for people for which air pollution data
um is is monitored. One thing though
that we need so all of these I told you
there's nothing about causality right
it's just a piece of our data science
pipe pip pi p p p p p p p p p p p p p p
p p p p p p pipeline that it's done very
well and just before I go to causal
inference allow us to really measure
exposure for everyone right in um in in
in a very good way by the way now there
are things are done even better I don't
know if you have read like the new
foundation model called Aurora I think
comes from Microsoft there are now all
of these foundation model they're
predicting hurt systems right and then
allow to estimate exposure to pollution
or to other phenomenal um extremely well
that's that's a key necessary step but
it's another part where I'm really
focusing remember what I'm really
focusing is seeing doing an imaging
because I want to look at the most
effective intervention to save life from
exposure to our pollution or from um
stressors.
So that's where I started to think about
and I want to give you the journey over
time about how you start to combine
causal inference in artificial
intelligence. And even though Elias
Bernbomb wrote an entire book about it,
I found very hard to take some of the
after chapter one [laughter] which is
the introduction and the framework which
I really like. Then after that thinking
about policym and thinking about
interpretability that's where he
completely got lost, right? I mean well
I I you know he he he lost me. maybe you
know may maybe you will be able to stick
with that and so that's what I'm
thinking in a in a much more I would say
uh practical manner of how you could
take this artificial intelligence model
and start to think about reasoning about
cause um cause and effect and so you
know remember like I come from the field
of statistics and I've been thinking
about causal inference from all my life
you know even though I know I look very
young to you, but I've been around for
quite some time, right? So, it's
actually starting to be Oh, I didn't put
the Oh, no. I put the the dates there,
right? So, some of you, you know, were
pretty young. So, first of all, I
started by thinking about, you know,
even before coausal inference, right?
When we were in the late 90s, one way of
thinking about and you see I had in red
when is about association. So like
seeing I have in orange where is about
doing which is a causal inference and
then I have in red in in green like the
new artificial intelligence framework
right and I want to show you the
trajectory of evolution of actually my
own thinking around this field so first
of all in the late 90s so when we're
thinking about association that will
think about uncertainty right and many
of you are probably very familiar was it
basically doing a Beijian
regression models and then that that's
evolved in actual invasion model
averaging. Beta vision model averaging
was a very powerful tools because will
allow you to predict what will happen in
the future averaging across the
different models which is basically now
what you call ensemble learning right so
there was nothing really about causal
inference at that point then I think in
the in the early in in the point two in
2000 then where I started to really
advance the work of the potential
outcome framework and so that is really
the causal inference under the Don the
Don Rubin work merge with Beijian
inference and I'm going to tell you a
little bit more about that and the
uncertainty piece comes what what you
call about so you call about feature
selection in machine learning in Beijian
we think about more about variable
selection under a model but also is also
called about averaging across the
different models accounting for the
uncertainty about which variable enter
in into the model. So that's the point
two and then the point three around the
2010 was about basically taking
everything that we do in the 2000 but
then making it less parametric
and that's where it gets closer to to
machine learning right because Beijian
inference originally was heavily relying
on parametric structure but now we can
do Beijian non nonparametrics and you
can do in fact Beijian machine learning
and that's a finally I'm going I'm going
to go quickly through what we're doing
right now which is AI foundation model
that can reason on cause on on cause and
effect which is start to think about
what will be the consequence on human
health if we do multiple intervention
even though we never get to observe this
multiple intervention all at the same
time and so I I just have a couple of
technical slide and this one was I think
it's important because
you know you often And um and maybe you
do and correct me if I'm wrong, but when
you're thinking about I'm sure you you
know when you're thinking about your
machine learning model or even when
you're thinking about inter
interpretability and you're thinking
about feature selection, you're always
having like one model, right? There is
an outcome model and then there is a
var, you know, series of p predictor and
what you're trying to do is to figure
out which variable is important, right?
For the prediction. But now if what you
want to do is not to predict but to
estimate a a causal effect then your
variable selection algorithm must be
different and that's where we introduce
for the first time and you know now we
are doing in the context of a linear
model but doesn't matter you can do it
in any model and I want to just give you
this idea that you should think about
and and and and and look at it where the
idea is really how you do variable
importance of feature selection
when what you want to do you want to
preserve the estimates of the causal
effect. Let me give you an example. So
basically you have to think about two
models. Generally you only think
equation two right if you're doing
prediction you only think about your
your your equation two where you want to
estimate the fact of x on y and that's
there is a a model right you have uh the
effect of x and then you you adjust for
you that is a series of coariant. Let's
assume for a moment that the the thing
you really care about is estimating the
fat of x on y. Okay, simple as that. And
what you need to figure out, you want to
know which variable u you you want to
include in the equation too, not to
predict y well, but to get an unbiased
estimate of of beta. Okay, that's the
goal. And so if you want to do that,
then you need a second equation, which
is the one on top where let me tell you
what these parameters are. Alphas are 01
variables that are unknown. that tells
you whether or not that particular
variable should be in the exposure model
which is in the first equation or alpha
y are whether or not that variable you
should be in the outcome model right so
you need to figure out which of these
variable should be turned one and zero
if you just think about pre prediction
you're going to select the use that will
best best pre predict y but if you want
to estimate the beta and the unbiased
estimates you have to take account of
that odds ratio there
which is you know let's say it's it's
omega and the omega has to be really
really large and so the criteria that
you have to show is that you want to
include a variable in your outcome model
too
only if that variable is highly
predictable of x and what does this do
is make sure that in your outcome model
you're including variables that are
strongly predicted of X and weakly
predicted of Y.
Why? Because if you omit that variable,
the estimates of beta will be biased.
Okay, so this is just a trick and you
know it's been published there are
multiple paper about but the idea would
be that if you want to select variables
in your machine learning model that get
an estimates of a causal effect you
really have to account of the
relationship between these confounders
and exposure what you're trying to
account for it to make sure that you get
unbiased um unbiased inference and then
this idea has been generalized and there
are you know multiple paper in the
context of causal inference more general
where you have to you know more general
models you know I show you the idea in
the linear model but you can have
multiple model you can have bijan on
parametric model and also in the context
of causal inference but the idea I
wanted to tell you is that when you're
doing both the seeing part and the
imaging part and when the goal is to
estimating a causal effect you cannot
rely on algorithm that are based on
principle of optimizing your
prediction but you need another model
that account the relationship between
the potential confounders and the
treatment that you're interested. Yes.
>> Um, one question I have is when you're
kind of doing this exercise and trying
to think about like what confounders
should I include in my model? Obviously,
you do your best to think about like
what are literally all the factors I
could think about that I could include.
After you construct the model, is there
like ways that you look at it to say,
okay, now I've constructed the model. I
have an estimate of my parameters. post
talk, can I maybe assess if there are
biases that I that I didn't account for?
>> Yeah, great question. So, there are
there are two two things to to think
about. Number one is that you can still
have bias if number one, you haven't
included coariant that you want to. And
so the goal here is that if you have a
good enough sample size so that will
protect you for that because you know
it's it's just engineering so that you
are going to force into your model any
variable that are related to the
exposure that you want to estimate
effect.
The other bigger one which is the
elephant in the room is that if there
are confounders that you haven't
measured right then this is not going to
save you because if you haven't measured
so now one thing that you can do there
are a lot of way of doing sensitivity
analysis for unmeasured confounding and
so there are two things you have to
think about first of all you have to
think that your unmeasured confounder to
create bias will have to be uncorrelated
with everything that you already
accounted for and second of all there
are sensitivity analysis. And basically
what they do, they allow you to estimate
how strong the relationship between this
unmeasured confounder and the exposure
will need to be to completely change
your conclusion, right? And so there are
measures that you can do about that. And
then of course the other way to overcome
a measure confounding will be not rely
on observational study, but you can do a
quas experimental you know quas
experimental studies.
So yeah and this is just to say there
has been work in my in my lab in my
group that then have been generalized
this model you know on the contest of no
no
parametric a basian um estimation and
I'll I'll skip this now all of this it's
not just like don't just like writing a
papers and getting presenting a narrow
IPS or in jazza in our statistics
community this matter right so so we
applied actually
um this work of thinking uh Beijian
causal inference in the context of
nonparametric estimation so this was a
study in 2023 where we apply to the
entire Medicare database link to
environmental exposure and societal
factor so this was a study uh where we
have 62
23 million observations
uh this was the largest uh sample size
that New England Journal of Medicine
paper published where we were able to
estimate for the first time using the
whole US healthcare system what would be
the impact of PM 2.5 on mortality and
not only for everybody but also
stratifying by people of color and and
so economic status but the most
important plot which this led to the
change of the national ambient
interquality standard under the Biden
administration. Now Trump has tried to
repeal it but has not been able to do
that yet. So it's really the doing
question. Okay, going back to causal
inference and the doing question. What
this plot shows and this was basically
what led to the change in the law. What
this plot shows is how what will be the
risk reduction in mortality rate if
instead of taking the current standard
safety standard for PM 2.5 or 12 because
originally we're at 12 and I'm going to
lower to 11 or if I take the current
standard from 12 and I'm going to lower
to 10 or I'm going to lower to nine or
I'm going to lower to eight. Right? That
is really the doing question from a
causal inference perspective and you see
that of course low you know more
stringent are the safety standard more
life you're going to save right
importantly during the Biden
administration was also the really
important element of thinking
differentially of the number you're
going to the number of life you're going
to save for the different social
economic group and it's interesting that
you see when you go from 12 to 9. You
see that actually the people of color
which are the blue bar and the white a
lower soio economic status have the much
larger reduction the number of deaths
than people of you know white of high
high soio economic status and so that
particular um paper and that figure led
to the revision of the national
amalander from 12 microgram per
kilometer to 9 microgram per kilometer
and so I show you that because it's
important when you think about even at
the most sophisticated
coal basian nonparametric ensemble AI
put whatever you want right but you it's
important then with the sophistication
of the algorithmic sophistication you
need to translate the result in a way
that policy maker wanted to to see and
you know that all the uncertainty
measure and blah blah blah so that has
been really one of the journey where we
had the disp paper, New Union Journal of
Medicine in April 2023. Then there was
um a a science article that was also
really important paper. I'm not going to
be able to tell you everything right
now, but basically the goal was to look
specifically of air pollution that comes
from coal fire power plants. And that's
so important now as I'm going to tell
you in a second with the new explosion
of AI because a lot of the AI
infrastructure is powered by coal. And
so that's where we presented the work
where uh cold fire power plants lead to
a level of pollution that is even more
toxic. And then that paper got picked up
by Senator Kerry, a COP um a COP 2028 in
Dubai where was the first time they
actually they started to really switch
from climate crisis and recognize that
is also an a health crisis and there was
a lot of seeing and doing right behind
uh behind all of this paper and then as
I mentioned uh the Biden administration
in February 2024 lowered the national
quality standard from 12 to 9. And so
cleaner hair, life saved. And the other
thing that we are doing right now using
actually um machine learning is showing
how many also less greenhouse gases you
have from implementing uh air quality
policy which actually is pretty you know
what we are finding that if you pass a
law that clean the air you actually
reducing green as gas emission more than
if you pass climate rules because the
national quality standard is a federal
law And so if you have to comply with
that law, ultimately if you try to cut
unmet exposure to our pollution, you're
gonna attack similar sources of um of
greenhouse gases. So So and then the
last piece of all of this journey, I
promise you, is that now we are getting
to have to uh building the first
foundation model for climate resilience
and climate adaptation that is strained
on the entire US healthcare system. Uh
and so basically, you know, we don't
want to do one exposure, one health
outcome at a time, but building on now
the most recent
development of foundation model to be
able to uh analyze it together. And so
the idea is that we can uh analyze
unprecedentedly massive multimodel data
to find generalizable pattern to make a
prediction more accurate than um than
traditional methods. So uh this was a
recent work that is not foundation model
yet but just to give you a sense that we
now have the ability to estimate
exposure to wildfires, burns on extreme
heat, right? All of these climate
variable are in a very like precise
matter and so that will allow to
together with health data to to train
this foundation model. So Clauddio
Clauddio but Batillaro is a
post-docctoral fellow in my lab and uh
little advertiser is on the job market
this year and he's leading this work on
uh the foundation model for healthy
climate adaptation and the idea is
basically to have a pre-train on the
entire US system plus all of the
environmental data plus all of the
societal data and basically produce
these unified embeddings that capture
the complex spatial temporary
relationship between climate stressors,
social economic variables and LTA
outcome. And so that's where you can
basically start evaluating you know
downstream benchmark task and then
that's where you start getting these
imaging where you can start thinking
about what if scenarios of forecasting
for climate
adaptation using you know synthetic
ground through data to validate
counterfactual uh counterfactual
prediction. And so uh so just to give
you some example
you know there is a lot of stuff here in
terms of
using this this model to realign
uh misalign data and then thinking about
individual level health longitudinal
trajectory because the Medicare data is
um long longitudinal and so this is
really a massive undertaking where you
know we are thinking it where the
ultimate downstream task will be to
estimate the delta effect of our
pollution and getting an exposure
response function to do downscaling to
think about what if scenarios of um uh
high uh high complex
okay so that's that's the first part and
so I you know I show you this all of
this journey and now we're saying okay
we are launching this first foundation
model a lot of GPU train all the US
healthcare system. And so then let's
look on the other side which is um you
know let's now we have solved the
problem right we have these agents that
can tell us what you should be doing to
be able to prevent deaths from extreme
weather event and is there a better
future right and so I wanted to mention
some work that we are doing on exploring
and and evaluating the environmental
impact of hyperscaler data center and
also to thinking about the health impact
um as well. So as I said you know one
part I have a team developing foundation
model another part developing a team
that quantify the harmful effect of of
this uh of this foundation model. So
this is all you know this is on the New
York Times every day right you all know
about this. So there are new data
centers you know popping up as
mushrooms. uh we're using AI you know
and I am using AI I'm developing more
powerful AI and so I think the question
is now can we start so I wanted to start
from a very data science perspective
which is I wanted to start by building
the data science pipe pipeline that
tells me in correspondence of each data
center how much carbon footprint how
much pollution what are the healthy
impact what what is the water
consumption and then if I start at least
starting with the foundation of data
then we can start reasoning and I know
that many of you thinking about decision
you're making and optimization but we
can't go there until you have the
foundation of what the data is right so
um so we have done a massive amount of
work because of course these are all
proprietary data right and the big tech
don't want to tell you really what's
going on so it's not going to be perfect
but we have done we're doing a lot of
work so there's has been we have buying
some proprietary data. There is massive
amount of web scraping. There is a lot
of remote sensing information
and so basically we have in this paper
we are focusing on the hyperscaler right
there there are many many many more data
center than 43 and actually this is
already old because this is up to April
2025th but we focus on the hyperscaler
which are the biggest one which we know
they tend to run AI uh application and
so
what you see in that map actually you
don't cannot see it very well but you
later. So the the black dots so there
are there are 403 black dots and these
are where the data center are located
and then the smaller dots of different
colors are the power plants that are
providing energy to this data center and
these low smaller dots are colorcoded
based on whether or not there are coal
or re you know or renewable sources. So
if you think about for a moment the red
one the red dots are all fossil fuel
right coal gas and oil. So you see most
of the map is red and orange right and
then the blue are um the blue are wind
or other renewable source yellow nuclear
which are very few the pink are
geothermal which are very few and so on.
Right? So you you already get a sense
that most of the AI infrastructure is
powered by uh fossil fuel uh com
combustion the majority is natural gas
but big big chunk is also on coil on
oil. So these are the the question that
we're addressing is basically what what
is electricity consumption sources and
tributable CO2 emission from these data
centers what is the full mix of the
power plants and that's where I think
your optimization expertise can help. We
have not done that yet. Uh there, you
know, right now we're just documenting
it. what is the full mix which state
have the I2 the CO2 emission and then
here I'm just going to show you the CO2
emission but we have now already
extended the pipeline that from the when
when you know the power plants that are
giving energy we know what comes out of
the smoke stack and then we have
atmospheric chemistry model that tell us
pollution where it goes and then we link
to Medicare data so we know the health
impact and we know the healthare the
healthcare cost and so then you So this
is the question ultimately we want to
get like you know uh where should I
place a data center right or where
should I intervene on the power grid or
how we can decarbonize the sector as
much as possible this are really very
hard question we are not there yet but
this is at the first step toward getting
that so just to give you a little idea
of how we are doing it and so as I
mentioned is we have validated the set
of 403 hyperscaler we actually know
whether I don't know is Amazon, Google,
we're not publishing the information but
we know where coming from so private
data web scraping satellite imaging then
we know we take the power capac you know
we we know which which power plants are
giving the electricity there are some
missing data but that actually is easy
to to deal not very much and then we
basically have make some assumption
where the annual electricity consumption
was calculated by multiplying the power
capacity hours per year and utilization
rate of 63%.
And so that utilization rate is a kind
of an average it was determined
empirically and then uh every upper
scale was assigned to is a balancing
authority and a corresponding power
plants and then the emission were
estimated using an energy generated
weighted model and APA emission factors.
If you're working on energy system, you
probably know about this 10 times more
than I do and so I'm sure there is a way
to do it better. And then we also
calculate the carbon intensity right. So
what how much CO2 emission for um
kilowatt for um for for hour. And again
the idea here is a the first data
science pipeline to do descriptive
statistics. So not even like [laughter]
um causal inference. And so but it's
it's it's actually pretty fascinating.
And so you know I'm just showing you the
data aggregate state level because we
don't want to show actually data at the
single hyperscaler but basically you see
that these are we show the data both in
terms of the balancing authority and
based on on the states at the state
level on top are the CO2 emissions and
on the bottom is the electricity
consumption. I mean, I think we all know
that Virginia is the the capital of the
data centers and um and consequentially
where you have more uh CO2 emission. But
what think is interesting and the
picture changed a little bit and I found
this picture pretty interesting is that
we also quantify the full mix, right?
what's the combination and so um for
each balancing authority so on top is on
average for the US and so you see that
the um electricity that um the um
electricity demand of these uh
hyperscalar data center is 42% natural
gas 19% coal which is a lot and 3 uh 2%
on average of nuclear and then you know
all of the rest is renewable.
[clears throat]
There are some part of the United States
I'm going to show you in a second which
of course is the one in the center where
is the coal capital where actually the
uh electricity the coal um
the sorry the fall coming from coal is
as higher as a 38 um 38% and so I think
you see you now start resonating about
if you need to you know you could
potentially transfer electricity from
one authority to other even if you don't
want to change the location of the data
center. So then you can at least try to
maximize how much is available on
renewal by the way or renewable energy.
Right now I'm in the middle of of um
actually um
doing some sort of consultation and pro
proono
analysis that will prevent for a meta
data center opening in Nebraska where in
order to do that they're going to reopen
a series of cold fire power plants that
were previously uh were previously shut
down And so basically uh right now I
mean right now already you know since
April 2025th we are dealing with 52 um
69 metaton
uh carbon emission uh which is basically
the equivalent of a major US city or or
a sizable portion of the US aviation. So
it's you know it's becoming like a
sector. Um then there has been an
increase of five times since 2018. Um
and then you know clearly Virginia is
the one that has the largest CO2
emission. This is interesting because
that show the the carbon intensity. So
how much comes from CO2 from energy
electricity and so that's really the I
would call it the coal capital of of uh
of the United States. And so you see for
example that makes no sense to build
another data center um in that um in
that particular region. So I'm going to
um end with one uh one slide which you
know doesn't give you the the answer but
I thought it was an interesting
comparison let's say and so I told you
that the total CO2 emission attributable
to the 43 hypers scale data center is
now 52 million metric tons right and so
then for curiosity
I started to think about
how much g how much CO2 emission will be
cut from the new environmental
[clears throat] reg regulation which is
all the work I'm trying to do and
actually by chance I mean this is a
little bit of a joke but if you look at
the APA 2024 regulatory analysis project
of which I've contributed for the new
standard for call they said that will
cut about 55 million metric ton per year
So we are literally at the point where
in one hand the new environmental
regulation are hoping to cut 55 million
ton and then the new data center will
generate new 55 million ton. I mean of
course the story is much more
complicated than this but I thought it
was an interesting fun fact to end.
Thank you so much for your attention.
Please don't be shy ask question and
anything. Thank you.
>> [applause]