and now to present our keynote talk I'm
privileged to introduce mit's Chancellor
for academic advancement Eric Grimson
the Bernard M Gordon professor of
medical engineering Eric
[Applause]
[Music]
good
morning let's try that again good
morning nice to have you here thank you
for joining us today for what I hope is
an informative engaging and interesting
conversation about Ai and its impact on
almost every aspect of uh mit's life
soorry not just mit's life of your life
I'm going to start um by saying what I'd
like to do in this talk is give you a
little bit of the history of AI
especially mit's role in it a little bit
of a review of what AI systems do I know
many of you know this well but it's
worth reminding you of what are the
pieces involved in it and then talk
about what MIT is doing to embed AI
throughout the research at The Institute
and to push it Forward into the future
and so that's my goal um
so AI is
everywhere in the United States if you
watch television and you look at ad adds
it looks like any company that can spell
AI says they're doing it and most of
them are but it doesn't matter what you
pick whether it's Finance it's Health
it's Transportation it's Commerce it's
security AI is here and is having an
impact and so it's worth reminding
ourselves of what is an AI
system and the standard definition from
computer science is that it's
intelligence exhibited by a machine so
it's a rational AG
that perceives this environment it
gathers information it takes actions in
order to try and maximize success at a
particular goal it's the fundamental of
what AI
does often people will say AI is
exhibited by a machine when it does
something that we would associate with a
human hopefully good things that a human
does and not mistakes that the machine
makes and so that involves problem
solving which are those three steps and
it involves machine learning and that's
in essence the definition of AI the
kinds of things that we want to
do as a consequence modern AI systems
really incorporate information from four
different areas obviously computer
science but also from Neuroscience what
goes on in our brains from cognitive
science how we think and from
mathematics especially reasoning about
uncertainty and that we're going to use
to build out an AI system
a little bit of History one can debate
how far back you want to go but most
people would point to the Dartmouth
Workshop
1956 as the founding of modern
AI I was 3 years old at the time so I'm
as old as AI or little little younger
than
AI three of the four Founders or
organizers of that Workshop were MIT
faculty members John McCarthy Marvin
Minsky and Claude Shannon um Rochester
was from IBM McCarthy eventually left to
go found AI at Stanford but we had an
early role in it and you can see the
definition that they gave they said
every aspect of learning or any other
feature of intelligence in their view
can be so precisely described that you
can get a machine to do it that was the
motivation behind the founding of
AI for 20 years early AI was basically
search if you wanted to prove a theem if
you wanted to win a game you started at
some initial position and you executed a
series of steps trying to get to the
goal and if you got to the goal great if
you didn't and you hit a dead end you
backtracked and tried the next thing and
you did that until you explored all the
space or you found a
solution I'm sure you can quickly figure
out this does not scale well it runs
into a combinatorial explosion the
number of things you have to explore
becomes huge and as a consequence for
that first period people looked at very
small examples and they made a lot of ad
hoc assumptions in order to remove
things they didn't want to think about
without any real basis on how well it
was going to work and as a consequence
after about 20 years of funding in the
US and elsewhere we hit the first AI
winter that is funding dried up because
these seen these things were seen as
just not
usable I will point out to you I started
my own work in AI in
1975 in those days it was something you
scraped off the bottom of your shoe it
was not highly respected because it had
these problems it didn't handle problems
well second wave of AI rise of expert
systems in the
1980s this was a focus on a particular
um domain and creating logical rules for
deduction so that you would basically
say given what I want to accomplish here
is the natural way in which I would get
to it there were some early commercial
successes but again one of the struggles
here was that they didn't scale well
even if I built a system to do Campbell
Soup maintenance which was the first
successful AI uh application of which
I'm aware you couldn't apply to some
other problem you had to start over
again it didn't learn it didn't
generalize and that led to the second AI
winter and now we're in the third phase
and the third phase is really driven by
bringing in solid scientific BAS from
mathematics and from
Neuroscience mathematics being able to
reason about problems under uncertainty
and come up with a principled solution
to it and Neuroscience using what we
know about how our brains work to give
us a guide to how we might build real
systems and of course began to see early
on in this phase some successes you'll
decide for yourself but IBM's Deep Blue
System beating the world's chess
champion was certainly an indication of
the power of these systems in early
commercial
successes and today as you all know this
is really then driven by three
Trends deep learning which we're going
to talk about briefly but using
sophisticated statistical methods to
reason under uncertainty about finding
solutions to problems and being driven
in part by what we know about how we
think don't have to be exactly the same
but it needs to be
similar the second one is the incredible
growth of data and this is an issue I
think all of us need to think about as
we build modern AI systems how do we get
access to enough data to train these
systems and how do we have confidence in
the quality of the data and lack of bias
in the data but as I'm sure many of you
know a current modern AI system might
have millions or hundreds of millions of
parameters and you need hundreds of
millions or billions of examples in
order to train all of those parameters
so massive data sets are
important and the third one of course is
an incredible growth in Computing
whether that's standard Computing or
that's GPU chips from Nvidia or AMD or
pick your favorite company that makes
these things the ability to do the
Computing allows you to get to it notice
two correlations though that come out of
this not everybody's going to have
access to the same data sets so there's
going to be an imbalance about who can
succeed in this
space and the climate implications if
you like are the power demands of these
systems to do the training causes other
challenges for companies and governments
to think about how do we want to balance
the advantages with the cost of it but
those are the pieces that let us build a
useful
application now today AI is mostly
machine learning not all of it but most
of it is I'll let you read the joke here
um unfortunately I think this is still
true for lots of application cases you
just throw a bunch of math and a bunch
of data stir it around if you get a good
answer great if you don't just stir it
around until you get an answer you like
not a satisfying way of dealing with
things and so we want to talk a little
bit about how one di better on it but
essentially it's machine learning and
the definition of machine learning
actually comes from the early days of AI
the first machine learning algorithm was
done by an IBM researcher named art
Samuel he wrote a program to learn to
play Checkers that simple little game
not very sophisticated but it learned
and as he said it's the field of study
that gives computers the ability to
learn without being explicitly
programmed all right great so with that
in mind this is a more modern definition
but with that in mind a quick reminder
of what goes into machine learning and
why we want to think carefully about how
we use
it traditional programming you're a
client you give a program a
specification I want my program to do
this particular task with this input I
want this output they write the program
and then you give new inputs you get
good answers
out machine
learning the programmer writes a machine
learning program and takes a collection
of input answer pairs for this input
this is the answer for this input that's
the
answer and the Machine then builds a new
program so that given new inputs it will
give you an answer and you can use it to
make a decision about is this the right
thing I want to do and you are still
involved in that but notice there's an
implicit program there you never create
the program the machine does and one of
the questions is how well does it do it
and does it do it in a manner that
actually meets my goal and notice a
problem that many people
acknowledge the quality of the input
data is going to dramatically affect the
ability of the algorithm that gets
created if you get it really good input
data that covers the space it'll do well
if you give it input data that's missing
elements of the space or has a lot of
incorrect information you're going to
have a problem
problem all right a quick
example you have a set of training data
I might say I hear a set of images that
I know are cats here a set of images
that I know are dogs I want to build a
system that will recognize cats and dogs
I convert each example into a set of
features set of numbers in this case it
might be a set of numbers that talk
about the shape of the nose a set of
numbers that say the color and the
texture the fur a set of numbers that
say the shape of the eye a collection of
pieces like that and then I want to
infer something about the process that
created that and typically here I'll
just use a neuronet I will train a
system on those examples to say how do I
wait the different features to have
something that I think actually captures
the difference between cats and
dogs and then I only use it on new data
to make sure it works so I give it a new
image it says that's a cat give it a new
image it says that's a dog and there's
still a
challenge are these cats
or dogs or very confused
animals I'll let you decide for yourself
I think the one on the left is a dog I
think the one next in is a cat I'm not
certain the one after that and I think
the one on the far right is a cat but
you get the point they're going to be
edge cases that you still need to think
about as you use this
system so that's the Paradigm for
machine learning and I want to come back
to how we use it today but also some of
those challenges in terms of um of the
performance of it um there's a range of
things we want to do most common machine
learning algorithms today are supervised
we give them those feature label Pairs
and we use them it's a whole range of
algorithms many of them dating back to
the 50s that can be used but today Le to
my experience almost everything is some
version of a neural net and of course
the Hot Topic are large language models
which everybody seems to want to use and
we'll talk about that as well but these
are all elements of what the systems
use just a tiny bit more on what those
systems
do basically we're going to use
something called logistic
regression which is going to learn a
probability of assigning a label to a
new example based on that training data
and so I'm going to skip
this tiny bit of math this is an MIT
talk there will be a quiz on the end so
you might want to take a few notes but
everybody will pass the quiz so don't
worry about it and yes by the way my
jokes are all bad but I'm a 10e
professor so you can't do a damn thing
about it all right with that in mind
just it's worth reminding you what that
system does so in logistic regression
I've got a set of feature values in a
modern system that might be tens of
thousands of feature values and the
system is going to learn weights to
assign to those features so that given
an instance it multiplies The Weight by
the feature value adds them all up and
it applies what's called a logistic
function to it and that function is
designed to assign the probability that
this is in fact an example of what I'm
looking for and it's designed to very
quickly push the probability either
towards zero or towards
one and the whole
goal is to find what are the best
weights which is what the learning
algorithms do and then set a
threshold so that when I have a new
instance if I'm above that threshold I'm
going to say this is an instance and if
it's not above that threshold I'm going
to say it's not an instance of it and I
raised the threshold because it's
actually important to think about and
unfortunately many AI systems
don't for example if I'm building a
system for autonomous driving that is
going to try and detect pedestrians I
want to set the threshold so I have very
few false negatives I don't want to not
recognize a pedestrian and have a
disaster so I want very few false
negatives that tells me how to set the
threshold
on the other hand if I'm a faculty
member and I'm running an exam and I'm
looking for cheating I hopefully don't
use this solution which I think comes
from India but I probably want very few
false positives I'd much rather accept a
few kids getting away with cheating than
accuse somebody of of cheating in that
exam so you get the idea the context
really matters here in terms of how I
set the
threshold all right almost start with a
preview so what about neuron
Nets based on our knowledge and neur
physiology how our brain works but
there're essentially a way of learning
those weights in order to set up a
logistic
classifier and so an artificial neuron
net again simplified model what goes on
in the brain I've got a set of inputs
set of feature values number bunch of
numbers I then connect each of those
features to what's called a hidden node
and it takes the product of the weights
and the feature values adds them up and
applies a function to it that gives you
an output of that internal
node the U choice of that function is
really important we'll talk briefly
about that and though those are all
connected up to an output note with an
additional set of weights and that
weighted sum is applied to the input to
the logistic function to say yes this is
a cat or yes this is a dog or I'm not
certain it's one of those confused
examples in
between in the early days artificial
neuron Nets had maybe one hidden layer
mostly because of computational costs
and lack of data today they can be huge
one of my favorite examples from an MIT
spin-off sense time the Hong Kong based
face recognition an AI company their
system has a thousand layers in their
artificial neuronet and I'm sure there
are bigger examples around but that's
basically what we want to
do all right and then deep learning just
refers to a complex neural net trying to
accomplish the this there lots of
variations but most of them and early
ones at least in computer vision go back
to the work of two Harvard
neuroscientists that won the Nobel Prize
David Hubble and Thorston weasel who
discovered cells in primate cortex that
did what we would see today as an
artificial neural net and I'm going to
skip by the examples other than just to
say that a modern neural net can do
things like face recognition character
recognition extremely
well all right
and then large large language
models I'm sure you're all aware of them
they're the current rage I think they
have a lot to to to add to the system
basically I think of these as a deep
neural net that has some interesting
properties in language it's a way of
predicting what's the next word in an
answer I'm constructing based on the
words before it notice the size though
here a word in this system is
represented presented by over 12,000
feature
values a word with a similar meaning is
very close to other ones a word that has
multiple meanings has multiple
representations so that you can deal
with the confusions in language and a
sentence is just a sequence of those
feature vectors one for each word the
magic inside of here is something called
a Transformer which is a system that
basically takes one of those words as a
representation and uses other words to
decide how to disambiguate meaning how
to use context to associate pronouns
with nouns how to use other information
to refine the words so that you can then
run the full system in order to come up
with a
solution to train
this Deep Mind who did one of the first
versions of
this or open AI which is probably the
better example of it they trained their
system on 30 billion
sentences 30
billion by the way all of you are
entitled to a little bit of revenue from
open AI because they probably used your
Facebook page or your LinkedIn page or
something else to gather that data
without your permission you can worry
about the legal ramifications of that
but they met mined massive amounts of
data in order to train this and now
given an input query the system
basically samples words from that query
to start the system and then predicts
probabilistically
what's the likely answer I want to
generate with an input as long as 3,000
words long which is actually
impressive and of course you can
generalize this if you want to create a
chatbot you take as input a sequence of
queries and responses either generated
by chat GPT or it's something that
humans did you scale them or weight them
in terms of what the quality is and then
you retrain the system in order to
create something that gives you
conversations
so probably a longer Preamble than you
needed but those are the elements of
modern Ai and I want to give you a
sense of some of the strengths and some
of the
challenges I want to remind you that a
modern large language model based on all
of this technology gives you a
probability gives you the probability of
a good answer if you run the same query
multiple times you may get slightly
different answers you may get VAR
different answers because it's a
probability if there is bias in your
training data and bias can be incorrect
data but it can also just be things
you're missing it's going to affect the
output in health care this can be a huge
problem a system trained on data from
people that look like me may be very
different than a system applied to data
from people that look like you or
somebody else because of missing data so
bias in the data is huge and these syst
systems don't have the ability to apply
common sense to their answer comes up
with a ridiculous answer you or I would
look at it and say no way system doesn't
have that ability so it's a tool it's
not a
replacement and I want to show you an
example of this I'm stealing a little
bit of Thunder From A couple of my
colleagues but I want to show you very
quickly a little bit of an example of
using an AI system and why you need to
be careful about knowing when to trust
the response it's a study out of the
Sloan School of Management at MIT I
think in collaboration with some other
people they took if I remember right 500
middle
managers HR experts uh management
experts and they divided them up into
three groups a control group a group
that had access to
gp4 and a group that had access to gp4
gp4 and a guide on how to use it and
they gave them two tasks the first task
was designed to fit very squarely in
into the expertise of chat
gp4 it was a coming up with a
description of a new product and notice
the
results the group that had access to gp4
as judged by experts their performance
both in efficiency and in quality
improved
38% and if you were in the lower half
you had less experience less capability
your improvement was 43% if you're more
experienced not surprisingly it still an
improvement of 177% you got better if
you had access to gp4 and a guide on how
to use
it you did even better in terms of
performance this is
great you notice I have blocked out part
of the slide because now you go to a
problem that was designed very
explicitly not to fit well with the
capabilities of
gp4 and there the group using
gp4 their performance decreased by
13% all right right not great and the
group that had gp4 and a guide to use
it their performance decreased even
more
why because they trusted it it's an AI
system has got to be good it must be
right not a good answer my point is it's
a tool and as a user you need to know
how to judge when it is doing something
that's acceptable and when it is not and
I think that's one of the challenges
here nonetheless it's been fascinating
to see the impact of AI and I will
simply point out to you this year's
Nobel Prize and pH physics two of the
awardees are pioneers in uh in um deep
learning Jeff Hinton and John hopfield
Nobel Prize in chemistry Demis Aus
another Pioneer in in neural
Nets hfield spent a year at MIT on
sabatical oops sorry I'll go back there
I went too fast and hbus competed his
post office at MIT so we had a little
bit of effort in in influencing these
people with that in mind where are we
today and what's MIT
doing there are a ton of areas of great
success I've just listed a bunch of my
favorites here um I'm going to show you
four examples of them but there's hardly
an area that hasn't seen an interesting
application of AI into the system
systems mostly built around software but
obviously there are Hardware boosts
certainly gpus but also specialized
chips being built to make these things
go and so success stories you all use
them speech recognition speech
translation remarkably good systems and
a range of them
available my own field is or was
computer vision I find some of these
systems really impressive face
recognition systems today actually
perform better than humans certainly on
face verification and even on face
recognition um a ious
driving should be careful as I say this
I'm not a fan of some of the shortcuts
that Tesla has taken here but there are
some impressive systems for doing
autonomous driving primarily one for me
is uh mobile eye um it does an
incredible job with it but computer
vision has been dramatically
changed
robotics I'm being biased this is an MIT
event these are four MIT spin-off
companies Mobile Life with autonomous
driving iroot and the Roomba with
household robots key are now part of
Amazon with Logistics and perhaps an
interesting one farmwise which does an
AI based Vision system to actually pick
weeds from crops without damaging the
crop in in Practical use
today and of course question answering
early version would be IBM's Watson
system but chat GPT is a great example
of the kinds of things you can do terms
of answering
questions so what's MIT doing
we're essentially embedding Ai and
machine learning across the entire
Institute and we're doing it both at the
curricular level in terms of what we
teach students but also in terms of
research and I think in interest of time
I'm going to skip over the curricular
level they'd be happy to all right sorry
I'd be happy to answer questions but
we're changing how we train and teach
students today to embed computation
throughout the curriculum every student
is learning about
Ai No matter what their major is what I
want to show you is the level of
activity and interest at MIT today in
terms of research using these
systems when we founded the MIT Stephen
a schwarzman college of computing 5
years ago one of the things we said was
we were not only going to Ed computation
throughout the Institute but we were
going to add 50 new faculty lines to The
Institute it's the largest growth at MIT
in 80 years
25 of them are in computer science 25 of
them are bridge faculty they're in
between computer science or the college
if you like and another
discipline and that both changes the
kind of faculty member we hire but it
changes the way we think about using
AI so I know this is a busy slide but
here are examples of the people that we
have hired in The Last 5 Years in these
Bridge
areas in management somebody who does
Behavior economics mechanical
engineering agriculture management
chemical engineering new synthesis
design but then some places that may
surprise you um uh music music
technology we've have an offer out in
Philosophy for somebody who does
computational ethics how do you think
about the ethical use of these
systems and then I have the pleasure
this term of actually co-sharing a
search committee to find somebody who
sits between computation and
history going to be an interesting
challenge to find somebody but there are
some interesting people there but the
idea is that we want to have faculty
that are bridges here two weeks ago MIT
did its review of Faculty members for
promotions and of the I don't know 60
cases that we saw I would say 55 of them
involved somebody using AI
in a department whether that was urban
planning or that was economics or that
was philosophy or that was political
science so there's actually a real
strong interest and let me show you some
examples of
this one of I shouldn't say my favorites
I have lots of favorites two colleagues
built a deep Learning System this is
before chat
GPT that is able to identify new drugs
to kill antibiotic resistant bacterial
infections has a lot of structural
knowledgeable chemistry built in but it
also has a deep Learning System
underneath it in their first trial the
this the sorry the molecule they
selected based on what the system gave
them as recommendations they tested on
25 known antibiotic resistant infections
and that new molecule was shown to be
have an effect on 24 out of 25 it was
one lung infection it didn't deal with
since then they've used it to designed
drugs very specifically for particular
antibiotic resistant bacterial
infections you can see two examples
here can't resist telling you because my
colleagues had discovered a new drug
they got to give it a name and they
chose to call this new drug
halison h i i
n iin that sounds like you know penic
sounds like the name of a drug and where
did HAL come from the AI computer in
2001 of Space Odyssey so they ner
they're Geeks they have a terrible sense
of humor but they have the ability to
actually build it but notice the impact
new drug
Discovery a colleague second colleague
actually a colleague in both of these is
a breast cancer survivor and she become
became fascinated with how can he do a
better job of detection she has built a
deep learning
system which tested on retrospective
data old data she has shown with 85% %
accuracy can spot the early signs of
something that is going to turn into a
tumor 5 years before the radiologist
will detect it it's now in common use at
the Harvard hospitals as a screening
mechanism incredible impact on human
health third example from Health
colleague Dina
katabi he a wireless communication
expert here's a Wi-Fi signal here as I'm
pacing back and forth I am slightly
disrupting that Wi-Fi signal and her
system which could be in the corner of
the room will not only detect that
disruption it will infer what caused it
so things she can do she can detect
vital signs of a patient remotely with
nothing attached to the patient during
Co we used her system in all of the of
the Boston b or not all most of the
Boston based hospitals so that staff
didn't have to go into the ICU
she can actually tell how well I'm
walking so if I happen to be a patient
with
Parkinson's her system can tell a
clinician how the disease is progressing
automatically um she can detect
activities the one that I find
fascinating she can detect disruptions
in sleep which are often a signal of
onset of diseases like Parkinson's all
completely
automatically Transportation obviously
we're working on a autonomous vehicles
extensively we're interested in the
traditional components of it but we're
especially interested in things like
Behavior prediction how do you predict
what a vehicle in front of you is going
to do how do you predict what a
pedestrian is going to do if I were in
Bangkok my apologies how do you predict
what all those scooters are going to do
as they going flying by you uh in the
wrong lane but it's really being able to
do reaction if you like to the
system and then things like M Last Mile
vehicle routing a great Logistics
application an area I think has really
primed for Major Impact is discovery of
new things a young colleague in chemical
engineering has built an AI system that
comes up with new models for catalysis
for building catalysts aimed at coming
up with solutions that are more
efficient less expensive and will
produce good quality
outputs design of new materials again
colleagues have built a system that will
Design or suggest Des designs for new
materials an area of particular interest
for us is things like concrete
production where the system will will
predict ways to come up with new
mixtures with lower costs lower
emissions but these are things creating
new
materials finance my colleagues will
talk about this but studies on the
economic impact of generative AI on jobs
of the future there are a number of
programs going on the one I will simply
highight highlight is work of our most
two recent Nobel Prize winners Deron
asmu and Simon Johnson looking at the
economic impact of what is going to
happen to jobs as we think about AI
there you can see a bottom example there
as well there's a whole range of
examples here of things that are going
on again it is hard to find an area
where there isn't some research going on
at
MIT and the way we think about it is
that machine learning now is the third
leg in the stool of scientific discovery
a good researcher will in at least in
science and engineering will use
mathematics to do a formal model of
something that will make predictions
which they will then gather information
on experiments that they do physically
but they then use Ai and machine
learning to add the computational
component not just to do the analysis
but also to do the simulations to look
at other things that should be tested
here and so we refer to our students in
our faculty now as being computational
bilinguals they speak the language of
chemical engineering and the language of
computation but these are the range of
things that MIT is looking at and our
goal going into the future is to embed
that notion of machine learning
throughout every department at The
Institute it means we're going to hire
new faculty members new kinds of Faculty
members we need to break down
disciplinary boundaries and of course we
have to F sorry we have to face one of
the challenges which is our data needs
our data storage needs and our computing
power needs are growing and we need to
think about how we're going to address
those things which we're actively
working
on I wanted to give you a sense of what
AI thinks about AI sorry what MIT thinks
about AI boy I need a better AI system
here what MIT thinks about AI I wanted
to give you that sense of not only the
history of how we've dealt with it but
especially how we see it moving into the
future new discovery mechanisms New
Management methods New Economic models
but even in places that you wouldn't
expect new planning for design of new
planning of design for cities use of
this in political science use of this in
economics every part of MIT is now using
AI in a different
way before we go to questions I will
simply say as somebody who started in
this field 50 years ago it's been
fascinating to see where it ended up I
hope the next 50 years aren't quite as
tumultuous but that they lead to
something different but even though
there were two AI Winters this one feels
like it's here to stay and we need to
adapt to it adjust to it and use it and
with that um Quan I'm going to let you
pick the questions I see people have um
put things in here but
um you want to where wherever qu is you
want to pull one of them up for me
ah there we go all
right people talk about artificial
general intelligence a lot can you
explain it in plain English and how can
this concept be applied in
business I'm sorry I shouldn't smile
answer to the first question
no I'm
joking the goal of people who are
pushing AGI is to say can we build an AI
system that really does behave the way
we do it's not just built for a task but
it is built to apply intelligence to
anything um as I said
earlier it's an area where to do that
you need to capture Common Sense
reasoning the kinds of things that a
2-year-old knows and an AI system
doesn't uh it's a wonderful goal to have
I will show you my bias I think it's a
long ways away um we'll get closer to it
but I think we're likely to see
successes in particular
areas more more quickly than building a
a a generative a general AI system um if
you had it it'd be great because you
could use one system to do marketing
planning to do customer service to do um
management of of of your finances all of
those sorts of things but again I think
it's much more likely that in the
shorter term you're going to build a
generative AI system for a particular
application um but that's what it's
about there are people who think it's
going to happen I'm a little skeptical
but I may be wrong all right come second
question you're an optimistic group I
like this
um since history is often a predictor of
the future I should be
careful but I think as I said this wave
feels much more real than the two
previous waves in those AI Winters and
why do I say that this wave is built on
much more solid scientific Foundation it
really is built on deep understanding of
the mathematics is built on deep
understanding of at least what we know
about how people
think and you can just see it in terms
of the commercial impact I'm sure you're
all affected in your own companies with
this so will there be another AI winter
possible could be affected by government
agencies deciding not to provide funding
for it um we've just had an interesting
event in Washington yesterday and we'll
see what happens in terms of funding
there but I don't see this having an AI
winter uh anytime really
soon having said all of that as a quick
comment I want to remind you that even
though these current systems are built
on a model of what we think goes on in
the human brain it's not a perfect model
and there may be Alternatives and I'll
give you a very quick example comes from
my college Josh tanom who raised this a
really good point these systems are
impressive but they need to be trained
on hundreds of millions of examples in
order to be
effective for those of you who have
young children or had young children
think about a
2-year-old you can show a 2-year-old a
stack of blocks on a table
and ask them what will happen if you hit
the table and with good reasonable
accuracy they'll be able to tell you
what
happens they don't have hundreds of
millions of training examples but
somehow they learn very quickly how to
predict what happens in a setting and so
there may be Alternatives that we see
that change the path of AI but to the
winter case I don't think it's coming
soon or at least I hope it is
not what's my next
question I'd like to be able to catch a
flight in a couple of days and still get
back to the United States so I'm not
certain how much I want to answer this
question but it is it is a great
question
um let me answer it this way I'm not
going to answer the particular one of is
it a wise decision I'm sorry that just
gets me in
trouble but I do think think and I think
many companies certainly in the US have
taken a role in this that we need to
think about the regulatory issues of how
you use this where are the places where
you want guard rails where are the
places where you're happy to use this
what are the standards that a a product
should meet before you allow it to be
deployed in terms of use I will point to
the European Union which I think has
done a really interesting job of this
way you can quibble with pieces of it
but they've laid out an interesting
structure for how you think about the
regulatory issues here and so I don't
know whether let's say this way I don't
know if politics should have an
influence on this but government
agencies absolutely should have it but
working with the companies and I will
point to you in the US at least my
recollection my colleagues may be able
to correct me Microsoft took the lead in
creating a Consortium of other major US
companies to begin building a framework
for what was an ethical use of AI in
different areas not to maximize their
profit it would help but to actually
make sure that it was doing what it
should which is to protect people while
building them and so absolutely there
should be government role in regulatory
components politics is a little
different I'll stay away from that one
all right Quan pick me one that doesn't
get me in trouble when I try and get
back into the
US uh yes um I've heard Masa talk about
this it's an interesting question I I'll
um you know how realistic is it I'll do
it the following way a completely
General AI I think as I said unlikely in
10 years
time but in particular domains an AI
system that outperforms humans yeah I do
think it's possible you can already see
it in some places I'll give you two
examples just ones I happen to like
again I'll go back to that face
recognition system there are ethical
issues about how you use it that's a
separate issue but the ability of modern
face recognition systems it is better
than humans and it's something that
really is going to have an impact on
Safety and Security in in places when I
flew over here in order to aboard the
flight basically was using a face
recognition system the second example I
personally find impressive is some of
the autonomous Vehicle Systems and again
I'll point to mobile ey which I think
builds a great system I'm biased it's
the name MIT spin-off but I had the
pleasure of actually riding in a car
using that system there was a person
behind the wheel he never touched the
wheel uh in the streets of Jerusalem
lots of narrow places lots of people
walking across and it was impressive how
well that system navigated merged into
traffic um you know didn't use the the
horn anywhere to honk at anybody which
in Boston you would use regularly um
it's an example of something that is
better than a human and I use that
example because think about the impact
if that could actually be brought to
bear you reduce traffic fatalities
tremendously I forget the number but
it's like Millions a year around the
world you would reduce the cost of that
tremendously so those are places where I
think um it is realistic to the I don't
know if it's 10,000 times smarter but in
specific areas you will see things that
certainly outperform humans to our
benefit I think all right Quan I got
time I think for one more
question ah great
question
um I guess short answer is I think
that's a topic of a session this
afternoon but a slightly longer answer I
would say is
um there's no one solution to this
but our experience at MIT is that if you
find ways to
encourage students faculty to explore
new
ideas find ways to connect them up with
sources of funding and find ways to
connect them up with users in the real
world you lead to interesting things
that can happen so for Thailand that is
your choice but I hope that you will
work both with your local universities
but with institutions International
to identify places where you can have an
impact and to use it to actually then
collaborate in that way I'll give you
one small piece of advice like any piece
of advice is not worth very much but
I'll give you one small piece of
advice I know for my MIT
colleagues we get many requests to
collaborate we're always interested in
listening but often the really
interesting collaborations are when
there is something about local setting
that doesn't exist in Cambridge
Massachusetts and it will draw the
faculty member here because they're
really curious to explore it you will
know what those are that could be a
particular disease that could be an
opportunity to think about
transportation in a different way it
could be something else but to the
extent that you can find those
opportunities you will draw Talent from
around the world to come and work on
it with that
I have 22 seconds left thank you
[Applause]
[Music]