It turns out that much of what accounts
for success in life is not skill or hard
work but luck.
And in that case,
it's not true that rich people are rich
because they deserve it or because they
have skills or worked hard or they're
just lucky. And why do we necessarily
want to reward luck? Indeed, can't we
think of redistribution as kind of luck
insurance?
Imagine a world where a random event's
going to happen to you. You get hit by a
car. We talked about why we want
insurance, right? Want insurance to make
sure if we get hit by the car, don't get
hit by the car, we're in the same off.
Well, same thing. Rolls talked about
behind the veil of ignorance. Imagine
before you're born, you don't know if
you were rich or poor. You would choose
a system which would ensure you against
being poor.
And that system which would involve
transfers.
So if much of success is due to luck,
we're going to want a system that shoots
the rich to the poor because the rich
got lucky, the poor didn't. That's
uncertainty we want to ensure against.
Okay. Fascinating fact. If you if you
interview people around the world and
ask them
is success mostly due to hard work or to
luck. In the US people say hard work. In
Europe people say luck. In Europe they
have much higher redistribution than we
do in the US.
because they have a view that much more
success comes from luck.