Um and I now we now have our our last
speaker and I believe we we start with a
video but she's available online. Is
that correct? Um, and I want to
introduce Hela Shakru, uh, who is the
head of the Middle East and Central
Asian division of the IFC, International
Finance Corporation, and is leading an
incredible effort um to scale uh,
geothermal networks um, in her uh, uh,
country um, group. Uh, so do we have
that live?
Hello, my name is Hela Shiru. I'm the
regional vice president for the Middle
East and Central Asia at the
International Finance Corporation. I'm
excited to speak to you about IFC's
commitment to expand geothermal energy
networks for heating and cooling across
the Middle East and Central Asia
regions.
IFC is a member of the World Bank Group
and the largest global development
institution focused on the private
sector in emerging markets. So
>> climate change is one of our strategic
pillars of action. We aim to drive a
transition towards a low emission and
climate resilient economic development
that prioritizes people, jobs and
sustainable growth. Leveraging
geothermal energy networks as a
sustainable, efficient solution to the
growing energy demands in the global
south aligns with this mission. These
are four reasons for that. First,
geothermal energy is reliable and
scalable. The substantial heat emanating
from Earth's core to its near surface
remains largely untapped. It is a
predictable source of energy that is not
weather dependent. Most geothermal
energy solutions are based on proven
technologies with long track record of
successful operating experience. It can
be utilized for various applications
including heating and cooling, our focus
today, but also in certain instances
water dissalination and electricity
generation if the geology allows for it.
Second, geothermal energy enhances
energy security because Earth's heat is
not a commodity that can be traded.
Geothermal energy offers us a free fuel
renewable with limited environmental
footprint and no emissions that is easy
to tap to. This enhances energy
independence of a country and reduces
pressure on the balance of payment for
energy. Third, geothermal energy is
truly renewable. In a world where the
majority of greenhouse gas emissions are
from the energy sector, this is both
affordable, reliable, and clean,
enabling a faster energy transition.
Emerging countries can address their
concerns about fuel price volatility,
supply chain disruptions due to
geopolitical conflicts and it offers a
free storage of excess heat and cold in
the geothermal bore holes. Hence, it's a
base load with storage bypassing the
weaknesses of intermittent renewable
electricity.
Finally, strengthening competitiveness
by offering a reliable, affordable, and
sustainable energy like geothermal
allows us to make a dent in reducing
poverty and mitigating climate change at
the same time.
This energy is available 24 hours a day,
7 days a week, making it essential for
economic development.
By supporting it through climate
finance, we can bolster local
entrepreneurship, local utilities, and
it is a job inensive solution, including
for transitioning workforce from
industries that rely on fossil fuels for
heating and and cooling into this clean
alternative. This is particularly
relevant for a just energy transition.
Heating and cooling makes up 50% of
global final energy consumption.
Harnessing surface geothermal energy
with worked ground source heat pump
working at utility scale offers us a
lowcost heating and cooling solution
that will enhance our energy security,
strengthen our economic competitiveness,
create jobs, decrease greenhouse gas
emissions, hence benefiting both
economies and societies. The emerging
markets can benefit from strategically
planning geothermal rollout. The surface
geothermal solutions like the network
ground source heat pumps can be used
anywhere. They don't have a resource
risk. They save massively on electricity
and they reduce the bills if financed
properly. Take Jordan for example. As of
2021, almost 80% of its energy needs
were met through imports of natural gas
and crude oil. Heating and cooling
consumes a large share of its
electricity, stressing an aging power
grid. Conventional cooling systems use
significant water volumes in one of the
world's most water stressed countries,
Jordan. By moving to geothermal energy
networks, we can address all of these
challenges. There is a massive
efficiency rate of five times for
heating with geothermal and six times
for cooling with geothermal.
Scaling up utility scale ground source
heat pumps is a key part of IFC's
investment program to mitigate climate
change in the region. By developing this
affordable and reliable heating and
cooling model in the immediate term, we
are providing catalytic financing for
the preparation of demonstration
projects which include the following.
First, tailored engineering design. A
suitable site is selected. The sight
specific engineering design is developed
in accordance with the country's
permitting and regulatory requirements.
Second, we engage stakeholders including
organizing study tours for decision
makers and implementers, educational
programs for and workshops for
engineers, policy makers and the
communities. Third, we address any
remaining policy gap. We do a
comprehensive review for the framework,
the regulatory environment and the
market condition for network geothermal
system. We identify barriers,
opportunities and gaps and we develop
actionable policy uh recommendations to
enable a a timely uptake. Lastly, we
mobilize the capital to finance
demonstration scale up efforts. This
would include blended finance solutions
and solutions in local currencies for
the utilities and local corporates given
that their revenues will be in local
currency.
IFC is currently rolling out
demonstration projects in seven
countries all eager to see projects move
forward. Turkey, Pakistan, Jordan and
four Central Asian nations of
Kazakhstan, Kyrgystan, Usbakistan and
Tajkistan. These projects include those
previously mentioned for areas of
support and lie the foundation for a
fifth generation district heating and
cooling network system operated by
public or private utilities. All the
demonstration projects will be
engineered using the singlepipe ambient
temperature loop to provide space
heating and cooling to residential and
commercial consumers. Each of these
projects is designed to be for at least
3,000 units equivalent with a potential
scale up for up to 30,000 units which is
the preference of most of the countries
to go big. Thank you for attending the
presentation. I'll be happy to answer
questions during the Q&A session.