I changed my title a bit but I I I I
mean first of all maybe I should
apologize to people who heard me uh talk
I think across the road uh from where
you are today in December whoops um or
November is the beginning will be
slightly
similar then will quickly diverge so
alil Taste of sort of quantitative work
we've been doing in immune repertoire
with my long-term collaborator TI mod
here in Paris and a lot of collaborators
both locally and experimental and uh
theoretical people from all over the
world so I'll I'll thank them uh to
begin with all right with that I'll
start with a who done it
so instead of being sort of in the
center of universe as youi right now
imagine you're in a ro remote location
everybody's excited this an amazing
Afterparty but the next day Joe is found
dead and next to Joe's body there are a
few drops of blood that don't belong to
them so this being scientists they cry
genetic tests for everyone and
traditionally used tests in DNA test in
forens physics reveal that the murderer
is one of two twins either Alex or Terry
and so traditionally used test and
forensics are not able to distinguish
between identical twins um of course you
being where you are you probably know
that there are signatures in the DNA
that are able to distinguish but that's
not what's being used uh but here we're
going to call in detective AIA be who is
going to use another technique based on
immune repertoire so immune
repertoire basically B cell and T Cell
repertoire are what we call a diverse
Ensemble of set of cells whose role is
to protect you against foreign pathogens
and so what these what this set of cells
is able to do and what each one of these
cells is in principle able to do is to
bind proteins uh different proteins that
presented to it that it encounters and
discriminate for perform a
discrimination task so basically figure
out whether this cell is natural to your
body your own self what we call a self
protein or if it's foreign in which case
you should get rid of it um and so if it
recognizes a a protein as foreign then
it'll proliferate it'll make many copies
of itself that will all have the same
receptor as the original cell if it
doesn't recognize anything after after a
while it'll die and the thing to realize
here is that while each cell has many
many receptors they are all of the same
kind they're all identical receptors so
if you want to protect you if you need
to protect yourself against many
different pathogens you need a diverse
set of of different cells and that's
what we call a reper and that's also why
when they proliferate they keep the same
receptor so this is the story for tea
cells I'll be jumping a little bit I'll
mostly be talking about t- cells but
I'll be jumping a little bit between B
cells and t- cells I'll tell you when
things are a little bit different and
when that's
important um but in both cases we can
now go in take blood from people
sequence it pull out the T cells or B
cells sequence them and since these are
proteins what we're going to get is
we're going to get reads that actually
encode for this protein sequence so in
principle what we have here is we have
access to your own personalized medical
record because the immun because of this
proliferation process the immune system
keeps track of every infection you had
so if we knew how to read what we get
out of these sequences in a functional
sense we knew how to relate this to
antigens or diseases we would know in
principle
every disease or at least signatures for
the diseases or conditions that you
carry still in your blood but
unfortunately we don't currently know
how to read it completely and but
basically this is what I'm interested in
doing I'm interested in figuring out how
to read this information that we carry
around in ourselves so how will this
help us find the murderer well so if we
compare the sample of blood found by
Joe's body to samples from our
suspects we can simply count the number
of shed sequences between the two
samples and based on this we can figure
out whether the two samples come from
the same person or whether they come
from two different people this is what
the data looks like so if the samples
come from the same person they are going
to share many more sequences in order of
magnitude more sequences than samples
that come from two different people even
if the two different people are
identical twins what we see here in pink
so basically you share more te- cell
receptors with yourself than with
anybody else in the world even if you
have an identical twin and so thanks to
that we'll be able to identify that the
murderer is Alex because who else could
it be in this story and additionally if
we found this rub of blood later in time
or we did the analysis later time uh we
could still find a murderer the signal
is stable here we show it Based on data
of days post vaccination we're able to
the the people look different for on the
order of days but this we use a model
this can extend up to years and and will
show you how we find these models that
are able to extend things over years but
at this point you may be asking but how
does this work in detail
so it works so I I'll explain how we can
figure it out but first I need to sort
of tell you a little bit more about how
a t- cell receptor is made so this is
the classical textbook picture a t- cell
receptor has two
arms what I called an alpha and a beta
arm uh let's just concentrate on the
beta they're made out of three segments
which are called VD andj and in your
genome you have a certain number of
templates for v d and j okay so maybe
the first thing to realize is before we
go into these details is that you have
of the order of 10 to the 9th unique or
different t- cell receptors at least now
you have a theod of 20,000 genes so
since these are proteins if they were
encoded directly in your genome simply
the DNA wouldn't fit into your nucleus
so we need a different procedure and
this procedure combines combinatorics
and Randomness to generate this
diversity so in each of your cells you
have a certain number of templates but
then the DNA in your cells gets edited
so you pick one V One D and one J in
each cell which gets you to the order of
a thousand different combinations but we
need to get to 10 to the 9th so to do
that there's enzymes that come in and
randomly insert and delete nucleotides
at the Junctions between the V and the D
and the D and the J and with these
insertions and deletions we're going to
get to this 10 to the 9th or otherwise
said a billion different
receptors okay so that seems simple but
how do we know that they're going to be
different in you and me um
so basically what we're going to do is
we're going to take
sequences that we get out
of as I described out of the sequencing
experiment this is bulk DNA sequencing
but if you get enough sequences to do
the analysis you can do it on single
cell too uh we we can talk if anybody
has questions about that I'm I'm happy
uh to talk about it I actually don't
even see the zoom bar at all so if
anybody I guess you'll tell me if I need
to pay attention I'll let you know
thanks all right so um okay so we get
sequences is out of a sequencer and the
name of the game now what we want to
understand is what is the probability
that an individual say yourself that you
generated a given t- cell receptor okay
and what is the probability of
generating any given T Cell receptor
that we see in the data and so we're
going to use a trick the so basically we
need to quantify and characterize this
process so we're going to use a trick
and the first thing we're going to do is
we're going to look at out of frame
rates so remember you have two
chromosomes one from each
parent and uh when vdj recombination
happens so this generation of diversity
first you attempt the first chromosome
if that works great that's the end of
the story but if it doesn't work you
silence it then you move on to the
second one if the second one also
doesn't work well that cell dies but if
it does work then you have a functional
receptor so you receptor that can be
expressed on the cell surface and the t-
cell Will Survive but then if you look
in and you look at the DNA in the cell
you sample the DNA you're going to find
the two receptors you're going to find
the one that was a functional one but
also the one that recombined the way
these exper recombined but was not
functional so the way these experiments
are set up is it's specific
sequencing aimed at the immune system
with primers designed for that so you
only sequence DNA that was actually uh
recombined and but if you do sequence
DNA you're going to get these two
chromosomes so what we're going to do is
we're going to use these out of frame
reads and since these reads were really
so basically the reads that come from
this receptor that got recombined but
was not functional and not expressed so
that way we're sure we don't have to
deal with
selection and um it's easy to understand
why that's the case for DNA of course
mRNA when I said it's silenced it
shouldn't be expressed in practice the
process is leaky and if we look at mRNA
data we actually do CDs out of frame
receptors too so uh we can also do this
analysis based on
cdna uh sequence okay but we're going to
use the outou of frame reads the
important thing there is that we don't
have to worry about selection and then
the second thing we're going to realize
is if we take a given sequence that we
find in the data well what we want to do
is we want to say what's the probability
with which it was generated which means
we want to say well you know we need to
say something How likely it was that it
used the given genes that it used as a
starting point but it turns out that if
we want to assign which Gene was used to
to the given sequence deterministically
that's impossible because because of
this editing of inserting and deleting
nucleotides I can assign different V
genes uh to Any Given sequence and
different de gen especially the de genes
which are quite similar and quite short
so we cannot do this deterministically
we're going to do it stast
probabilistically so we have to we we're
going to make a list of all possible
scenarios that are consistent with the
sequence we see by which I mean choice
of V Gene D Gene J Gene number of
insertions at each of the Junctions and
deletions and we do it for all
sequences and we assign weights to each
of these scenarios and then we calculate
marginals or observables depending where
you come from basically we calculate the
probability of using a given V Gene in
all of these sequences having a certain
number of deletions certain number
insertions and so on and then we have a
model which is the most General
factorizable model consistent with the
gnome biology which we use to
recalculate these weights and then we
let this convert so this is an
expectation maximization
procedure um that's basically how we
learn the parameters of these models of
of the model which are these elements
and then once we have that we're able to
calculate these weights so the
probability of each of these scenarios
and by summing up over all of these
weights we're able to calculate the
probability of generating a given
sequence so that way we can get the
sequence for every sequence we see in
the database okay so I won't tell you
about the details of these models I'll
just tell you about the final outcome
which is what it looks like this is the
probability this is a density or a
histogram if you want of the probability
of generation so basically I ask how
many T cell receptors have a probability
to be generated that's 10 Theus 10 we
put a dot here 10 the minus 8 and so on
and so there's two things to note here
one is that it spans 20 orders of
magnitude which means that you have some
sequences which are very easy to
generate given that you're generating at
least 10 to the N different receptors a
probability of 10 Theus 5 means
basically you will generate these
receptors and that means you will
generate them and I will generate them
and we'll share them but these ones over
here they're much harder to generate and
we'll still generate some but we'll be
there'll be different ones that we
generate and it's thanks to the ones
here that we're basically able to find a
murderer because what this tells you is
that each one of us is basically a
random repertoire generator we
have the same same well I'll tell you in
a second why we we have the same
generation process but we generate
different
realizations of uh the the of well of of
the process which in this case are
receptors so why am I saying that we
have the same generation process so the
spread here there red is over 20
basically over a thousand different
people so real people not genetically
Iden called mice or anything like that
and you see and this is basically 95%
variation so you see that basically this
process of generating receptors this
distribution is very very similar in all
of us so it doesn't matter where you
come from doesn't matter what you eat
basically we have the same probability
of generating given receptors
so yet because it's a random generative
process we end up with different
receptors and again these ones over here
that are have a high generation
probability will share and these ones
will be unique so there'll be some
fraction that we share with other people
and some fraction that will be unique to
us and basically this uniqueness is such
that we're able to identify any given
person out of the whole worldwide
population so it's a unique
fingerprint um that you carry around
now at this point you may ask well how
where does this distribution come from
on evolutionary terms and this is a
question I would love to know the answer
to but uh one thing we asked ourselves
is well does it depend like if receptors
that are specific and can
recognize uh known viruses are they more
skewed to the right of this distribution
do they have a higher probability of
being generated
and the answer is no so these are
receptors these are these are
distributions over receptors that are
known to recognize different viruses
that are available in databases such as
PD jdb and we plot the probability of
generation on top of the uh average that
I showed you on the previous line so
there's nothing special about these
sequences that are more likely to be
produced in terms of them being good at
recognizing bugs basically with of
course the caveat that we're talking
here about what's in
databases um going further into is
everyone the same so when we did our
murder mystery at the beginning uh you
know there's clearly a difference in
samples coming from you and your
identical twin if you happen to have one
but you the identical twin still you
know was slightly shifted compared to
unrelated individuals so if we look at
it
it uh in detail they share a little bit
more sequences than non- Twins and if we
look at the PN distribution so basically
this is the the blue and model red
unrelated individuals and the twins have
this funny little arm here
um that
uh yeah that basically that this this
longterm a tail that they Shar these
they're more likely to share these R
sequences so we looked into this in more
detail and so uh the funny thing is that
what's so special about identical twins
so identical and these are identical
twins that share a placenta and so
basically identical twins that share a
placenta are the only individuals in the
world that share blood in natural
circumstances
not just maybe blood because you share
blood with your mother but share share
immune cells in natural circumstances if
we're not talking about blood
transfusions or transplants and things
like that and so they share blood whoops
question in chat what is r in the
previous plot oh it's a correlation
coefficient
um I yeah just just the
basically um correlation I think between
uh I'm blanking out
um what is
a confidence of these points being
different from these points I
think uh ah no maybe sorry sorry sorry
sorry this is because I didn't go into
this this is the prediction of sharing
in the model and this is the what we
actually see in the data and this is the
co correlation coefficient between what
we see in the data and what the model
predicts because originally this plot
was showing two points that we're able
to predict
sharing based how many T cells are
shared or
the between the model and the data and
that's the correlation coefficients
between those sorry that was a long time
ago so um yeah that's what it is okay so
um good okay so twins share blood but
they share blood before birth they share
Blood In Utero and the other thing to
know is that in utero the enzymes that
do that make the insertions the enzyme
called tdt is severely downregulated
that means that the t- cells you produce
in utero are actually have many less
insertions than t- cells you produce
after birth so if we track the number of
te- cells with zero insertions as a
function of age they go down and we're
able to fit a Decay length to that which
gives you a clone lifetime of about 40
years 36 years okay so this is a Decay
length of clones it's not cells cells
die cells reproduce but the Clones that
would generated in NE hang around for
about 40 years so that means that if
you're about 40 you still have t- cells
that were generated before you were born
and this is not just due to the fact
that the naive pole uh contract because
that would be this Decay curve here so
it is actually an
observed decay of uh well of the
relative proportion of these uh of these
zero insertion cells which allows us to
estimate a lifetime and we'll get back
and will get back to estimating
lifetimes late okay so we already
mentioned
selection uh so the first type of
selection so after generating receptors
uh they first basically undergo an exam
which we call which is a way of thinking
about fix selection so in the Fus before
they let out into the prolifer they get
asked two questions do you bind to
anything at all if they don't bind to
anything at all uh you're going to
discard these cells because they're
probably going to be bad receptors but
if you bind too strongly to self ER
proteins you're also going to discard
them so why is the Fus a good place to
test this in principle the Fus is a pure
organ and you should only have receptors
that are specific
to that are produced sorry proteins that
are produced by your body you should
only have self proteins so by basically
being presented different proteins in
the Fus uh you the immune system
performs this discrimination tasks there
on your own self proteins and only T
cells that don't bind too strongly to
self but bind to some extent are LED out
into the periphery and then they undergo
somatic selection which we already
described this prif prepation for when
they encounter an antigen and otherwise
de so we can for any of these selection
processes we can also build a
probabilistic model and we can quantify
selection basically knowing what is the
probability of generation generating a
given sequence if we then look in the
functional repertoire for example in the
naive repertoire to quantify fic
selection uh we can say that there is
some selection factor which we we can
describe by some uh by by by a function
and then this can be an linear model
such just shown here where we basically
say that selection independently acts on
the V Gene J Gene and each of the amino
acids in between because this is this
forms the cdr3 region which is the most
variable region and often doesn't have
that's where all the insertions and
deletions happened or we can build a
neural net nwork model or any sort of
machine learning model that accounts for
nonlinear effects and so we've been done
both of
these uh and you know there's small
differences and essentially linear
models given the amounts of data that
are available usually do uh as well
there are some things we're able to pick
up with the Deep uh with the neural Nets
but it's it really depends on the on the
deepness of the data but at the end of
the day what we have is since we've
characterized generation and selection
we know the probability of giving of
seeing a given t- cell in a naive
repertoire and then uh we can talk about
the start asking questions about
functional repertoire so the plot I
showed you previously was an example of
that but we can ask it at the level of
functional repertoire we can ask how
many cells are shed by two individuals
10 individuals 100 individuals and so on
and uh we have the model prediction
which is basically the probability of
the sequence being generated in one
person and another so say in you and in
me we generate these sequences
independently so that's just P gen
squared times the probability that they
were selected in each of us again we're
independent processes so it's the
probability that was selected you and
selected in me and I can build a
separate model for you and I can build a
separate model in for me or we can build
a general model believing that fic
selection is still a somewhat Universal
process of course there are differences
for those of you that know uh about MHC
presentation for T cells and so on
either way we can build a model like
this and we can see that the model
predicts very well the sharing that we
observe in the data so the fact that you
and I share naive
sequences is still largely governed by
chance for the most part in healthy
people now we talked about I I mean we
talked about I talked about because I'm
soone talking but I mentioned MHC so t-
cells when they recognize a protein it's
presented on the major on a scaffold
which is called the MHC or major hyto
compatibility complex this is scaffold
that's encoded by the most polymorphic
Gene in the genome the hlaa so it is a
great source of diversity so we are
slightly different so if we build a
common model for people we may need to
include a sort of small selection factor
that is person dependent or group
dependent and so uh basically this will
tell us that the higher the fact
the closer it is to one one the less
stringent selection on a specific sub
subsystem or sub group of people and the
closer to zero the more stringent
selection and here we looked at how it
varies over different categories so we
can see that it looks different for
people that are CMV negative or positive
CMV is a huge influence of how immune
report was look like and we see that it
varies with age so basic basically as
you get older you have more Str you have
more signatures of more stringent
selection in in your uh
repertoire and uh so we can again go
back this is a different representation
of what I was showing you about whether
we can predict and this is related to
this um to the this r factor that I
showed before which basically was
measuring how well we could have
predicted in that set of individuals we
looked at uh which is from a different
sequencing platform than this uh but you
can see that we're doing very well at
predicting sharing in healthy
individuals with this selection factor
for t- cells same thing for B cells we
have smaller data sizes but it works
very well but if we looked at people who
recently had a sasco 2 infection and
this was a people for whom this was a
first infection we see significant
outlines we see that these people share
many more B cell receptors than
predicted by chance so this tells us
that by looking at sharing and people
we're actually able to pick up some
signal and this brings me to the second
part of my talk where I want to talk
about the fact that what we're
interested in now is basically looking
for
specific signals in the repertoire H
stack so the repertoire is a very large
system some very small fraction much
smaller than drawn here is spe is used
in a specific disease or condition
setting and an even smallest part of
that is used in uh to identify specific
antigens and we would like to know
precisely what this is or more likely
statistically what this is so can we use
this notion of
sharing and to try and
identify sequences that are specific for
given conditions and the answer is yes
so here what we're showing is a
prediction of how many TCR should be
shed between people and how many are
actually shed between people in
conditions that are diabet diabetes and
CMV infection and the red dots so this
is an inverted version of the previous
plot with the red dots being significant
outliers and the ones in a circle are
ones that were experimentally validated
to be associated with this condition um
in Pre in previous experiments so we can
actually identify disease related TCR
without having a negative cohort so
people who don't have this
condition if we go to s back to sasco V2
uh from different data sets we also have
these significant
outliers uh this is we can identify
motifs left to the linked to them and we
can connect this is for tcrs now uh
where we can also identify them we can
link tcrs that differ by at most one
Amino asset and again using vdj DB we
can link them to what sasco two epitopes
they correspond
to um and identify the logos and see
where the the variability is and if we
go back to BCS which is by doing a
simple log likelihood ratio test we can
identify whether some basically looking
at somebody's t- cells looking at the
subset of them we can say whether this
person had sasco V2 or didn't have sasco
V2 with perfect identifiability
for t- cells we need to do logistic
regression but by doing that we're also
able to do it another thing that it
allows us to do is to HLA type
individuals so in short just by looking
at the T Cell somebody has and Having
learned a model which I'll tell you
about in a second we're able to say what
HLA type that person has so what we did
is we curated a database of t- cells
that are associated
that are strongly associated with a
given HLA type so HLA type plus plus
negative donors for different HLA types
and uh from different data sets and well
we confirmed that the strong Association
goes in the way we expect meaning that
hla1 uh is mainly that that cd8 is
mainly associated with over
representation of hla1 types and CD for
with hl2 types the differences here are
not errors because we know that the same
cdr3 and cd8 and CD4 can be uh
associated with
hla1 sorry the same cdr3 can be
associated with CD4 and
cd8 uh so this is not necessarily errors
it it can be real and then we
build based on this data we build a
logistic regression model uh to figure
out basically what is the HLA type given
on presence of absence of those strongly
uh uh identified or Associated tcrs and
you can see that whether we use just one
change is the alpha or the beta or both
of them we have very good performance
now what's interesting is that this is
just used
saying that a given TC we have to see an
identical match in our database to in in
our individual to basically call an HLA
type now if we become a little bit less
strict and say what if we uh allow for a
one amino acid mismatch in the TCR with
sitting in the person from the one that
we know is associated to given HLA type
uh it turns out that we actually do
slightly better with this one mismatch
with slightly above the diagonal then we
just allow for single mismatches and so
pushing this a little bit further we can
build clusters for different this is for
different HL a groups of tcrs that
differ by at most one amino acids and we
see that they cluster into these sets
that then through again vjb we can
associate with specific known uh
epitopes so that tells us that similar
tcrs have uh the same HLA restriction
and bind similar or the same epitopes
which is a which tells us that the
information that is in a TCR repertoire
alone can help us refine presentation
models but also binding models so
basically there's a lot of information
in TCR similarity and it does seem to be
an important element which see we see
over and over again which we like to exp
exploit and so pushing with that can we
actually identify responding tcrs using
just a single
reper and so to do this and I'll show we
did this both on T cells and on B cells
I'll show you the B cell version just
for a change we can take a repertoire
which has been exposed to a given
antigen and then we can build clusters
of similar
BCR and uh then what we do is we prune
these clusters for what we expect based
on P gen basically we expect some
similarity in the data uh we expect
these clusters to be there naturally
because some BC have a higher
probability of being generated and
they're usually ones with small
insertions so the ones that are short
and with small Solutions are more likely
to be there so we need to correct for
that but once we correct for that we're
able to actually use this as a way of uh
identifying bcrs so we took data from
Steve Quakes lab from horad dool and um
for people who received the flu vaccine
at different types and if we just look
at frequencies or of count of different
VCS before and after vaccination we
don't see big differences however if we
look at
how basically how how what abundant the
neighborhoods are we see that the after
vaccination we see larger neighborhoods
which means we see bigger clusters so we
can postulate that these larger or uh um
these be pcrs that have more neighbors
are potentially
responding and so we see this clear Peak
if we look at different individuals at
day seven post infection and uh in one
individual we can build uh a network of
close by but unrated sequences meaning
they use different
V uh even if they share similar CDR
frees and we really see that they have
different
origin uh have a different origin
because they although they share this
the ones that share exactly this
specific cdf3 sequence they're encoded
by very different V that could not have
been confused by chance so we see
convergence of a response we see a
convergent response uh of clones that
were independently generated to the flu
vaccines in bcrs so I'm saying I'm out
of time here uh should I
stop are we we had some questions uh
during the talk so I think that that's
you can probably uh find a continue for
a little bit I think that's s all right
so let you have more questions I think
we can uh go as we go okay so let so
this is the last thing I want to say
sort of going back to this self versus
nonself question
um so that that HP you know that is
presumably is decided during fic
selection so the way I mean we like to
think of it following Ellen Pearson's
shapes space idea is that TCS and
pathogens live in the same abstract
space we don't know what it is it's some
sort of phenotypic space and the name of
the game for TCR and bcrs as well is to
cover the whole Space because pathogens
can be anywhere but you don't want to
put a TCR in a place where you have your
own proteins so these are sort of
forbidden regions in black but you need
to cover all of the space all all of
this space
so uh in that sense can we find features
in t- cell receptors that are able to
discriminate foreign and self peptide so
in other words can we find features in
te- cells in cell receptors that
basically tell us that this is a
forbidden region are there some sort of
features that are forbidden I mean maybe
that's the simplest way of saying that
so we already talked about fic selection
that you have to select for them being
functional so binding to anything but
self- tolerant so not binding to your
own self
proteins H and so this is a Hu process
that takes around is very fast it takes
around four to five days and so a root
check roboti back in the day did a
calculation where basically the outcome
of it is that there's not enough time
for this so given the number of self
peptides if each t- cell has to see all
possible self peptides given the number
of APC molecules so antigen presenting
molecules so the ones basically with the
scaffold that present these peptides to
t- cells uh there's no way that a T cell
can see all peptides it sees at best a
few thousands so it probes a small
fraction of possible self petti so
remember if this thing is set up in a
way that you're supposed to actually
learn make you know a list of everything
you're not supposed to recognize a t-
cell there's basically no time to make
the list and the second thing is we know
it's a leaky process so T-Rex are
examples of te- cells that bind to your
own proteins they go through this so we
know it doesn't work and of course we
know we do get autoimmune diseases so
how systematic is the TCR elimination
and again do we see signals of this
inter sequence so to investigate this we
set up an experiment with Neo freedman's
lab in mice where uh we had two markers
an activation marker basically over the
cell is responding to something and a
sellev mark
and we sequence t- cells not just in the
periphery as we usually do so functional
t- cells but throughout fic selection so
there's different cell types throughout
fic selection and at each decision of
whether the cell gets to proceed or
whether it gets
eliminated uh we sequence the ones that
passed and the ones that failed so in
you know either you care about these
different stages and you know about it
but essentially what we do is we have a
bunch of examples that passed and failed
different stages during fic selection
and specifically I'm going to really
focus on this last stage whether they're
Leed out of the periphery orever they
apoptose at this late stage so um so
what we're going to do then is we're
going to build again a Model A selection
model that takes us from generation to
the given stage of fic selection that
we're looking at to the given pass or
fail and we're going to build these
models uh and for basically the pass and
failed roups now if we just look at the
data uh even before learning a model we
don't see huge differences say this is
in V
usage uh between the different types and
again the similar colors like the pinky
color colors are the ones the the the
lighter one is the one that passed the
darker one is the one that failed same
for the orange and basically Geniuses is
really driven by the probability of
generation uh and there are definitely
not differences between the past and the
failed ones um H however if we put all
different if if we basically do a PCA
analysis on the different cell types
they do cluster in a way that we expect
so first they generate it then they go
into this double positive and they break
up separately into CD4 and cd8 but again
the ones that pass and fail are very
close together and with these models we
are able to reproduce largely again the
similarities that we expect from biology
so we are capturing something which is
not capturing some sort of Smoking Gun
so we ask the qu but what do we expect
we basically you know thinking about it
as passing and failing we basically
expect that these two subsets should be
mutually exclusive so the energy
functions that we learn from them should
be anti-correlated meaning that if I
take a property such as length and I put
a threshold here then I call some of
these t- cells long and some of them
short
and I buil a separate model for the long
ones and the short ones well a T cell is
either long or it's short so if I then
score the all the cells with the long
with the short functions the ones that
were actually short will score high but
the ones that were uh long will score
poorly with the short function but well
with the long function and vice versa so
we're going to get an
anti-correlation however even with such
a strong anti correlation we may get a
pretty weak signal of false positive
versus true positive now let's see what
we get for this sort of energy
anti-correlation on our past fail of CD4
cd8 and this is what we get so this is
CD4 here the ones that failed and the
ones that passed and were functional
same thing for the cd8 and we see that
they're completely
correlated so we it's the opposite of
what we um expect now just to show that
not everything would be correlated the
ones that die by neglect very early on
they're just a random subset of both the
cd4s and the cd8s so here we're really
seeing that they're selected they seem
to be selected for the same thing and so
maybe not surprisingly then the uh area
and the uh rck curve is close to random
so this is for the CD4 cd8 choice so
basically what does this mean it means
like if I have a bucket of cells of CD4
cells that passed fic selection and a
bucket that failed and if I put my hand
in I and pick one T cell at random and
I'm asked did I pick it from uh the the
bucket that failed or the bucket that
passed I can't really
detail
however if I now take 30 cells so I do
the same experiment I put my hand in but
now I pick out 30 unique t- cells from
the same bucket I am able to pretty well
say whether they've passed or failed and
if I pick a 100 I have perfect
discriminability
so and the the threshold is around a
thir T cells which is a similar order of
magnitude that we've previously seen for
t- cell decision making in another
context in the transition to in the
decision whether to become a memory t-
cells that was verified using
microfluidics experiment uh by mial Pon
ski News Group at the time so here they
clearly showed this some sort of
collective decision making and quum
sensing rules what we're showing with
this is not that we're just saying that
in one TCR there's not enough signal to
decide whether it should die or live but
in 30 tcrs there is and so this is
something we're trying to understand and
we don't fully understand this was so
far done on single cells we did sorry on
single chains we separately did um Alpha
and betas the signal is the same uh it's
so maybe there is more signal in
both but that doesn't explain why we
start having having signal when uh we we
go to 30 even with a single cell anyway
that's the last thing I wanted to say so
probably the most important thing I want
to say is don't kill anyone even if you
have an identical twin they seem to us
like a sort of you know fun twist but it
turns out that murderous twins is
actually a serious problem in the world
um and basically figuring out which twin
did it so people do care about that uh I
showed you how by looking at statistical
prop properties in repertoire such as
overlap between individuals or in-host
convergence were're able to identify
responding clonotypes and and will tell
you how we can do this using
longitudinal data and for fic selection
we at a point where we were unable to
find any deterministic rules for TCR
rejection so we believe there are some
again either Collective or statistical
rules that we're interested in looking
for so thank
you so it's a pleasure to give a seminar
here um okay so yeah I will I will
present some some like more details
about uh quantification of the immune
receptor
Dynamics um it's basically I will talk
about a couple three Works done in the
group of alexand I'm not the main the
main author of all of them but I'm quite
familiar with those um and so in general
okay
the kind of Alexander already talked a
lot about Rec combination and selection
but for us uh now what's important is
like after those processes so uh in our
body then we will have like a pool of t
cels or and or B cells uh with like a
lot of uh different receptors and to
give some numbers um we can have like uh
around 10 power 11 total cells in our
body and the diversity of these
receptors so in this case the number of
different colors can can it's not super
easy to estimate this number but it can
range from 10 Power 8 to 10 power
10 um and so we are interested in
understanding how this kind of
composition changes in time and which
kind of factor uh make those
changes
um okay so just to uh to list a couple
of like mechanism that can change the
repertoire composition so of course uh
uh there is cell dep as Alexander said
and there is also influx influx of new
cells through Rec combination and
selection and here I just mention
without entering too much into details
the fact that cells can also
differentiate so in in the case for
example of memory cells they can take a
decision of becoming memory cells that
keep immunological memory or to become
cells that produce plasma
antibodies but um there are also those
kind of under undergoing
processes and in addition um as also
Alexandra said if uh like one cell in
this repertoire encounter a um an
antigen a pathogen uh which is close
enough to its shape that is able to bind
to it basically this can start an
expansion an expansion of the cell and
so the cell starts to duplicate and grow
exponentially and in the specific case
of B cells uh there can also be what's
called Affinity maturation so basically
the cell that's good enough to recognize
the pathogen also starts to mutate the
receptor and the mutated receptor after
duplication uh are tested against the
antigen and selected for being good at
binding the antigen so basically there
is a really like evolutionary process
that creates better and better receptors
so we have like this this collection of
processes and we would like to better
understand like how these processes uh
happen uh in healthy conditions so
basically if we don't have any like
measure disease
we can expect that also in hetic
conditions there are cell expansions
because probably there are antigens in
our body and also Affinity mation can
happen also maybe those cells can react
to the microbiome of our
body uh so we would like to understand
how this happens in healthy conditions
and uh also what happens uh in response
to a specific stimulus and what really
uh what what really I mean is different
between responding to a specific
stimulus and from from the sort of like
uh Baseline uh kind of
Dynamics okay and um so this kind of uh
idea can be schematized as follow so you
can imagine that now in my body um I as
I told you there are a lot of receptors
and you can like just count the number
of uh cells having the same receptor so
I will call a color from now on a clone
so basically the Clone the purple clone
has abundance count three and I can
track keep track of those numbers in
time and I want to study the variation
of those numbers in
time and uh okay so the kind of question
we want to address are based on like
understanding how this variation changes
but the problem is that like what makes
this kind of inference this kind of
quantification hard is the fact that I
cannot really uh know these these
numbers because actually what I can know
are just sequencing experiments so just
subset of the of the real uh of the real
receptors and again to give some
numbers I Told You So if there are like
10 power 11 cells in a body um the the
number of cells that there will be in an
experiment can range from 10 power 5 to
10 power s so you can really see that's
it's like really an infinitesimal
fraction of the real number of
cells and in addition uh experiments can
introduce errors there are amplification
biases if there is
PCR uh so this like really makes this
this kind of U quantification
non-trivial and um so as um as a matter
of notation from now on I will call n
Prime the the experimental counts and N
without a prime the real counts and in
general I can write down uh a a given
probability of of observing an
experimental count given the real count
and I will call this the noise model and
some some I will I won't enter much into
details of how those kind of noise model
can be and how to learn them but in
general they can be like for example
aonian model so aonian model would be
like uh to model like a pure sampling I
just I'm just sampling receptors from
this
set of course the de probity
distribution is a binomial but can be
well described by a poonian because of
the big numbers uh otherwise if like the
the there are like amplification errors
people usually also use uh negative
binomials that are like broader
distributions okay and um and some some
also important fact it's important to to
like to like know is that the
distributions of those of those numbers
for T cells for B cells uh are power low
so here I draw actually a perfect power
law I don't really know if it's a
perfect power law but uh of course it's
a distribution with a very fat tail with
an exponent that's around minus two and
like studying uh experiments that like
basically are sampling from power loss
brings uh some some kind of problem s if
you want so basically if I can imagine
my experiment as a sampling from a power
low of course I I I know I can know I
pretty well I can characterize pretty
well the behavior of the common clones
because are easy to be sampled there
will be less error because they are more
abundant but I don't I I cannot know
much about rare clones and the problem
is that in my case also the majority of
my clones will be rare So basically uh
it's going to be hard to make an
inference on most the majority of of the
Clones in my
body okay so these like are mostly
General
facts
um I will like now go more into details
and divide the presentation like in
three
topics um I will try
to to cover all the three topics uh I
don't know if I have time for the third
one we will see and so what's what's
make the the topics difference is like
the conditions in which we want to study
the Dynamics of the repertoire so we
will start from healthy Dynamics then we
will go to the response to vaccinations
or infections in general and the third
one is about the coevolution with the
HIV okay
so uh considering the he Dynamic uh we
can also have like a more specific
question more practical question that
also biology are very interested in that
is the question of like how long I can
expect a clone to survive in time and of
course I mean you can imagine those
number changing in time and uh in
General on average you can expect a
clone to decrease its number in time if
it's not stimulated anymore and so the
question is how long I can expect this
this process to to happen before
Extinction and of course this is
connected also with the storage of
immunological memory so this is why like
it's an important question
uh but so like a related question and
sort of like more general question we
would like to to have a model that is
able to predict more the this kind of
variation of abundances in time in
absence of like strong
stimul so
um I will start by presenting like uh
some sort of like qualitative approach
that people already did several times in
in the in the in the past that just
allows us to say that it's true that the
actually the the repertoire the Clones
are quite stable in time so the kind of
like qualitative easy approach is the
following you can imagine that a patient
is uh sequenced two
times and then what I do is simply just
counting the number of clones I find at
time one the number of clones I find at
time two and the number of common clones
and I can easily then they find like
some sort of measure that uh that like
contains the fraction of common clones
over the uh the product of the uh number
of unique clones at the two time points
so you can already see that actually
those numbers
are uh if you want sort of surprising so
if you really think that clones are very
stable you would expect to find many
more common clones so here the fraction
of common clones is not very big
compared to the fract the the unique
clones that you have but like the reason
here is that you have power lows if you
remember and therefore when you sample
most of the time you will sample rare
clones it's very hard to sample the same
rare clone twice so that's the reason
why your signal usually will be
dominated by uh unit cles but so you
have this number here and then you can
like compare this
number in in in the second with with the
second number so basically you repeat
the same procedure but you do it with
the replicates so like
different experiments but in the same
biological conditions you will get like
again a fraction of common clones and
you can compare those two numbers in
your
uh uh and you will see that actually
doesn't change much so basically uh if
you consider samples after 10 years uh
it will be like more or less the same
fraction of common clones that they will
have uh between like replicates in the
same condition so this is really saying
that the repertoire in in this case it
was like data from memory B cells the
repertoire is quite stable so on a time
span of 10 years it's very easy that I
keep my clone
alive so but that that that's nice we
want to like uh uh improve a bit this
this kind of result we want to be more
precise more quantitative and to be more
quantitative uh we will use like a
modeling
approach and uh so what we do is like
imagine that my repertoire is evolving
like a geometric Brum motion so I will
like like motivate in a couple of slides
why I choose the geometric Bram motion
just let me describe how it is for those
of you who are not very familiar with
that so it's a stochastic process you
will have here uh this ITA is a is a
gausian noise uh and your abundance will
evolve according to this equation uh and
you have to add like an absorbing
boundary condition to like model the
fact that the Clones at some point will
get
extinct so uh for example you can try to
plot trajectories of this process for
example here on the left in a in a
logarithmic scale so basically this kind
of Cl is special because if you do like
a simple substitution of uh n being the
equal considering the variable logarithm
of n basically you get back a standard
Brum motion for which you can solve
everything so basically this makes this
process completely solvable and so
basically if You observe this like kind
of trajectory in a y logarithmic scale
basically this a normal granum motion
with drift that goes
down and so you will have this like
exponential average Decay with this time
scale
tow um and some kind of fluctuations
that whose scale is set by this this
parameter Theta
so in in on the right it's exactly the
same trajectories but on a linear scale
and you can observe like these kind of
like big fluctuations giant fluctuations
that it turns out are important also
because they are at the origin of the
power low as I will mention
briefly and
um okay so and as I told you like
everything is solvable for the for this
geometric Bram motion even we have not
we absorbing
condition um for example one can compute
the propagator so it's the probability
of observing a given experimental count
at time two given the count at time one
and uh basically if you like you see the
plot on the right if you plot this uh on
the variable Logan basically this is a
gaan far away from the boundary if you
approach the boundary it will change a
bit the shape but so in General if I'm
staying far away from the boundary this
is a simple log normal distribution for
n i I have a quick question sure um
about the N equals one boundary
condition I guess um maybe this this
model is maybe only valid for a subset
of cells like memory cells as you were
saying because I feel like in many
infections you know it's like one clone
that's really expanding so like at the
at the beginning of an infection or
something like
that can you just comment a bit on you
know what regime or like subset of cells
this kind of no I mean we here I'm I'm
really trying to model every cell in the
body and so I'm really saying like on a
very simple level I can imagine that
whatever clones in my body will follow
this
Dynamics and at some point can get
exting if he hits the boundary n equal
one but of course I mean these numbers
can go up to 10 power 6 10 power
seven but it seems that like you know
every most clones are unique to start
with and then they expand so they yeah
yeah can yeah I mean okay maybe maybe
I'm coming this in the next slide
because I have I have to pair this kind
of model with like a introdu of an
introduction of new clones with a given
rate so basically by by me meing the
fact that you have an influx of clones
so every clone will start from a number
that usually is quite
small but since I have this kind of
giant fluctuation every clones is
possible to reach some kind of big level
and then Decay later so I mean this kind
of model is not really
describing explicitly the expansions
that happening because of like
encountering the antigen of
whatever but um I mean this kind of
expansion are including in this kind of
giant fluctuation that can
happen I see so so n
Zer is is
approximately what like it's one it's
order I mean if I put exactly equal to
one it doesn't really work but it's
order one yes I see I see okay yeah then
that makes that makes more sense yeah I
guess it's just you know for my like
biologically the intuition would be you
start off with a unique clone but you're
saying that for this model to work you
kind of need something close to one but
not exactly one yeah yeah actually okay
biologically I don't really know what
what really happens close to the Border
I mean uh I guess yeah
um but yeah I mean the problem also is
that like at the end of the day we can
we can really stud study this model
through I mean we can really what we can
really say about abundances is through
sequencing experiments and I can sample
only big clones so I can really
characterize what's what happens in the
power low tail I don't really know what
happens in the rare clone regime uh as I
told you
before but yeah
okay
uh so like if I have like this model uh
that like progressively like leads to
extinction of clones because I have this
negative Decay on time this negative
exponential decay uh and I Caple it with
like introduction of clones at the end I
have a stationary distribution that's a
power L and it's like the kind of one of
main reason why I choose this model so
the power lad that's belied to be
present in in in my in my
repertoire and also like a couple of
other reason is that simple and solvable
and the third reason is that there are
also like previous works by Alexandra TI
um that were like really studying more
detailed models on how clones interact
with antigens expand and decay
and basically if you take these models
and You observe like you you you you
study this model between two time points
that are sufficiently far away in time
those model they converge to the
geometric Brum motion so basically
that's an additional reason so you can
see this model like a as a convergence
point for more detail deta detailed
models and if you look at your data uh
between sufficiently separated uh time
points and by sufficiently separate
sufficiently long separated I mean like
order a few months a
year okay so if like now we believe that
this is the kind of Baseline dynamics
that we are
assuming then we can try to include this
like in an inference
scheme and so um we imagine that uh my
my unknown real dynamic follow the
geometric brand and motion from one time
point to the
other uh but as I told you what I I can
observe our experiments so basically I
can observe this n Prime that are
generated by my by Noise by my noise uh
by by noise model and um given this
setting basically I can write down um
the probability of observing
experimental counts at time one and
experimental counts at time to for a
given clone I and this will depend on
some parameters that are the parameters
of my geometric Bram motion and the
parameters of the noise
model so it's nothing very hard here I
just have to marginalize over the hidden
variables and um and at the end of the
day given this like probability I can
write down a
likelihood so the probability uh of
observing my my my experimental counts
at the two time points and also by
assuming that every clone is like
independent in this
case and at the end I can Maxim try to
maximize my likelihood to get my best
parameter that will like fit my
geometric
BR um okay this is like in principle
doable I just want to mention like a
sort of
technical important technical Point
that's the
following uh so basic basically if I try
to to perform this inference this
likelihood maximization by using uh only
two uh experiments at different time
points basically there is a sort of like
indeterminacy problem I cannot learn at
the same time the noise model and the
geometric BR motion so basically I need
data that have this kind of structure so
I need data that are at different time
points but I Al I also need experiments
that are performed at the same time so I
need the experimental replicates and in
general I will need the experimental
replicates to learn the noise model and
then use the the the longitudinal data
to learn the dynamical model given the
noise model so this is like sort of
technical point but it will come back
later also for the inference of
responding clone it's important to State
it
out um okay so this is like just
uh to show some results
uh this was for for a from um
work of of Mariam of like a few years
ago and basically they are able to learn
these parameters for different patients
so basically this plot what is actually
saying is
that uh this line is the line that
corresponds to a power low with exponent
two which is what the people believes um
the repertoire sits in and um and you
can see that your data more or less are
around this line I don't really know
actually there is a group of points
that's not super close but um it's
probably it's probably a reasonable
exponent anyway probably a more
interesting like result is it's if we
can look is if if we look directly at
the value of to so basically we can
really here see that my tow goes from a
five years to around 15 20 years so
basically this is really saying that the
T Cel clones are extremely stable so I
remember you this St is the exponential
decay time so it really means that to
see a decrease of a factor E I have to
wait 10 years so if I start from a given
abundance after 10 years I the kind of
like number of cells in the Clone will
be decreased of a factor two or three so
it's a very very uh slow decay and also
it's interesting to see that you can
like plot this point as a function of
the age of the patient and you can
really see that this Stow increases
quite a lot with the age so young
younger patient we have a faster
Decay and uh you can basically try to
connect this Stow with the rate of rate
of reintroduction of clones so if you
believe that the total number of cell is
conserved you can basically compute
what's the toover rate so the rate at
which I introduce new clones and
basically it scales as the as one/ to
and so basically you can imagine that
like as you wage your turnover rate
slows down so you will have like clones
that live longer but you have like also
less new clones that will enters your
body so this is the kind of
interpretation you can give to this
plot
um okay so that was about this cells uh
and briefly I would like to also mention
what happens to B cells uh I just need
like a very quick digression on how the
the B cell
responds um and so again we can start
from uh like situation in which uh I
have my pool of beels I'm calling them
naive beels because they are still not
uh reacting somehow against the antigen
basically what like an antigen enters
the body there will be a good uh
receptor that is able to recognize the
antigen and what happens is that on a
time scale of of some days those naive B
cells they can differentiate into plasma
blasts and Plasma Blast they can attack
the pathogen through
antibodies uh otherwise like a sort of
different Pathways is that like after
weeks or months those naive B cells
initialize
and carry out what's called an affinity
maturation so they start to duplicate to
acquire mutations and the new receptors
are selected uh to be good at binding
the the antigen so we have like your
this this Darian process that then will
last for some weeks some months and we
release in the blood memory cells and
plasma cells so actually my focus here
will be on memory cells
so which uh like is one of the main
player for for like keeping
immunological memory and uh like one one
little difference that there is with
respect to the previous case of T cells
is that like now here uh instead of
considering my set of clones basically
my basic unit contains all the memory
cells that comes from the same Affinity
maturation process so basically with the
idea that like each Affinity mat
duration is like responding against a a
given pathogen and so all the memory
cells that comes from that process will
like somehow be in common and will be
reacting against a given pathogen so
here is exactly the same from the
mathematical point of view like it's a
set of numbers but now my numbers is the
number of cells coming from the same uh
lineage from the same Affinity
maturation and then therefore I can like
perform the inference as before and I
can get numbers as before
and I mean surprisingly enough basically
I get very similar numbers as before so
I find that like memory cells
lineages can last can have like this
time scale of decay of 16 years for one
patient and 13 years for for for the
other patient also the the age of these
two patients is quite uh old I I think
one was 70 years old the other one was
55 so again this like it's very very uh
in agreement with same with the same
result of T cells was not really um
expected from the beginning but somehow
we found similar
number I have a I have a quick uh yes
question about that um have you done
experiments to see if these estimates
are stable to sequence in depth because
i' I'd be quite interested because you
know you have the power law so I don't
really know how that yeah okay I mean in
in principle in principle all the all
the kind of framework includes the
sequencing death in the
in the picture so it shouldn't be
independent at all from for for the
sequence in that I'm pretty sure that
like in the case of Mariam for example
in this other case of thes
cels um I guess like uh each kind of
point so you can see for example you
have patient four that is like yellow
and you can see different points and
each point is a different pair so you
have multiple time points and you
perform the inference between every pair
of time points and therefore every
experiment will have also different
sequence in depth and the fact that you
obtain similar values like should Point
towards the direction that this kind of
procedure shouldn't depend on the
sequencing
dep I don't know if I answer your
question or yeah I I think I think I
think so but I guess there's also the
you know even with the same pair of
samples if you just downsampled the ah
okay in that sense in that sense I mean
I I I really think I mean I really think
nothing changes I don't know if they
tried in this
work uh what what I can tell you also is
that like those those those those
numbers have have been obtained from bu
reper
sequencing so where the sequencing that
was like I don't know I think the the
number of cells in an experiment is
around 10 10 power seven something like
that the these these numbers for B cells
have been obtained on single cell data
sets where the sequence in that is like
10 power five so it's much
smaller
uh but yeah I mean I I strongly I really
think that nothing changes just by down
sampling I I would find exactly the same
of course if you down sample too much
then you start to lose signal and
probably you will have like a larger
error bar that you inference find but uh
yeah Okay cool so it's pretty robust
yeah know I'm I'm pretty sure it's quite
robust yeah
okay
um so like to wrap up this part uh so we
have like a sort of framework that
capture the statistics of the sepor
abundance Dynamics in healthy condition
and accounting for experimental
sampling uh like we can try this kind of
framework can also like answer the
question of like about repertoire
stability which we find to be like
surprisingly long and potentially can
give us like predictions of future
experimental counts but so like to like
point out some limitations of this kind
of framework so as I tell told you
before we are trusting a geometric Brum
motion and probably this kind of model
describes well the Dynamics only if your
like experimental time points are
sufficiently far away in time so if you
look at the Dynamics after a few months
probably the the model won't be able to
capture well the the kind of statistics
and another another kind of like
limitation can be the fact that I'm
really treating every clone exactly with
the same parameters so I have a a single
geometric brand motion that describes
every clones in my body this is probably
not really realistic so realistic so
probably there will be like clones or
like um groups of clones that will die
faster group of clones that will stay
longer uh also like to to like trying to
to uh match that like the kind of
expectation we have I mean the kind of
knowledge we have about like
immunological memory we know that for
some vaccination the immunological
memory is very long for some other the
immunological memory extremely shorter
and so basically we believe that at this
point we we are not really able to
capture this kind of variation that we
have across all the different uh
lineages we have in our
body Okay so second part is about like
understanding what happens in response
to vaccinations or
infections uh so the kind of situation
now is the following so you can imagine
that when you encounter um a pathogen or
an antigen given by some vaccination uh
a few of your clones will start to
expand so through this kind of
exponential exponential
duplication uh and at some point we'll
start to contract coming back back to a
given
Baseline and the question here is trying
really trying to understand by looking
at those like trajectories so
experiments perform at multiple time
points trying to understand which are
those clone that expanded and again like
the kind of difficult part to do this
kind of task is that in experiments you
have like again experimental noise and
so you would like to disentangle between
this the real expansions and the noise
that the experiment
generates okay so like a first um a
first approach is based on um on a uh
previous work of Alexander TI is on a
data set where those two people were
like infected by covid and they
basically collected samples of the T
cell receptors starting from the 15th
day after infection up to like 3 months
after infections and there are five time
points uh basically then for for each
clone you can imagine that you can trace
like a trajectory of abundances across
these five time points so here I'm just
plotting the the very big clones because
you can imagine that a lot of clones
will be will be zero in in a few time
points so this like the top
clones and what you can do here like by
by looking at those trajectories
is to imagine those trajectories to be
like vectors in a five dimensional space
you have these five time points and you
can try to run PCA on this space so this
is very a very simple uh idea but it's
it works surprisingly well so if you do
this of course I mean you you need to
like do some sort of preprocessing on
your trajectory basically you would like
that all your trajectories the
variations of all your trajectories are
comparable so basically you have to
rescale normalize all all your
trajectories and what they do in this
work is just dividing each trajectory by
the maximum Point such that all the
trajectory uh is is like bounded between
zero and
one but like model of this kind of
processing
pre-processing uh you run PCA and you
find like really different clusters
different behaviors in the for example
here in the two principal
components and then if you like plot the
kind of average behavior of the
trajectory in the different clusters you
really observe like different Trends so
in the the the Violet ones will be the
constant trajectories so you probably
trajectories that are that are not
carrying at told of the presence of
covid then you will have like these
green ones so and after day 15 basically
you you're observing that they start
from a big count and they
Decay so they are Contracting ing so
therefore it's very likely that they
responded to the disease and now they
are just Contracting and returning to
the Baseline and then also You observe
like a third cluster that somehow it
seems to um correspond to a secondary
response uh but I mean then in in this
paper they really went more into details
and try to like um verify that the
Clones they observe in this yellow and
green cluster are effectively clones
that are able to to bind Co and it seems
so but like I would like just point out
to the fact that the method is very
simple and is able to like capture some
kind of statistics and isolate different
behaviors of your
trajectories also this um this is saying
that uh it's also capturing the fact
that like as people believe like T cell
clones typically they have like an
expansion time scale of like couple of
weeks and so if you look at the Green
Clones probably those are the really the
Clones that expanded at the maximum
point at after one two weeks and now
they are
decaying but okay this like was was like
a first approach but actually the if you
want this kind of approach is not really
is not really possible to being used
like in a systematic way because there
are like different choices that that you
can do uh a priority that are not very
well established I mean you you can take
different choices and obtain different
results I mean one one choice is the
fact that I have to normalize
trajectories is not there there are many
choices of doing this I can consider
counts or log counts but probably the
the biggest problem is that here I'm not
really taking into account uh in a
systematic way about the noise basically
what I'm doing here so in this kind of
example basically in this paper they
were selecting the top 1,000 if I
remember clones in the data set and
Performing the analysis on this top most
abundant abundant 1,000 clones if you
repeat the analysis by choosing like the
top 10,000 clone uh you stop to see any
signal because then at some point your
signal is dominated by noise so there is
not really like
a a threshold a number
that's uh uh that's valid for every
experiment that tells you to choose like
a given number of top clones to perform
your experiment so it's it doesn't
really quantitatively take care about
the the the experimental nodes so like
to include a more
um a more quantitative approach to like
uh model response in presence of
experimental noise we can use like an an
approach similar to the one we used
before so this was exactly the same
picture I show before for the geometric
Brum motion instead now of course as I
told you genetic brand and motion was
working well in healthy conditions for
very well separated time points here I'm
want to change my my model my dynamical
model by including something that models
this kind of expansions or contractions
that I'm observing in my
clones okay so let's try to look at this
model uh so uh this model is is the
following is it's quite simple so
basically it's um I I'm I'm doing this
kind of introducing this new variable
this s that is the log fold change so
basically the logarithm of the ratio
between the counts at time two and the
counts at time one and I can express of
course N2 as a function of this s and my
my my probability is depends on this s
so we will have like two
terms let's let's first focus on the
terms on the right so basically you have
this F that's the fraction of clones
that you are believing are expanding so
they are reacting to the to the disease
to the vaccination and are
expanding and this F multiplies this raw
which is a probability distribution over
the lock fold changes so it's a sort of
if you want prior on what would be the
distribution of L log fold changes that
your your data set will have uh actually
uh the kind of results of the inference
don't depend too much by the specific
choice of this
distribution um and then you you will
have a second term that's with
probability one of one minus F so the
fraction one minus F of your clones will
not expand will not
contract and basically will keep their
uh lock F
change equal to this s0 so this is a
Delta function and this s0 is a number
that's very close to zero but it's not
exactly zero because basically I I I
need to like conserve the total number
total number of cells in the body so if
some of the cells are expanding all the
others they have to contract a little
bit um so that's the model so I I will
have like one a couple of new parameter
F and S zero and typically I have like
one parameter more in my distribution of
lock fold
changes but the idea now is like exactly
to do as before so I can write down
probabilities of of observing
experimental counts uh writing a
likelihood and trying to maximize the
likelihood okay so I I can do this I can
obtain like the best parameters uh given
my
experiment and what is actually
interesting the way this kind of
framework can be used to like identify
expanding clone is the following so I
can compute a
posterior it's basically a probability
of observing a given expansion size
given some experimental counts and this
kind of posteriors can be easily
computed given the probability I showed
you
before and there and then at the end I
can use this posterior as a as a sort of
statistical tests to identify expanding
clones so basically I can compute what's
the probability of a clone not to expand
so of having a Lo F change smaller or
equal to zero given some experimental
counts and if this probability is
smaller than a given sort of statistical
confidence Alpha I can say that those
those those clones with those
experimental counts will like are likely
expanding and so I can select them and
they can be like candidates for like
future
investigations and so like as um just
like to to visualize visualize a little
bit what happens if you plot in a in
this like kind of uh diagram the counts
at time one and the counts at time two
this kind of condition with this
confidence Alpha basically we it will
trace a line on this plot and all the
points above this line so with a large
with a with a count of time to that's
much larger what would I expect if there
are no
expansion is set basically this gives me
all the Clones that are probably
expanded and uh so this kind of
procedure as has been discussed in in in
a paper of Alexan and also uh has been
like translated in in a software so
there is this open source software that
is able to perform this kind of by Asian
U analysis to identify expanding or
Contracting loans in in in
data and uh and so like to conclude this
part uh I told you that we have like
this framework that is able to
disentangle between the experimental
noise and resp and to identify like
responding clones it's a ban framework
so in principle there is also room to
play with the prior on the Lo changes
distribution um and starting from like
this this framework there is also a
software that can be downloaded and in
principle is like easy to use and can be
used on on real
analysis uh
again I would like to mention a
limitation which is which is the fact
that actually as I told you before uh
again I have a noise model entering in
my likelihood so I need to like learn
the noise model before but to learn the
noise model I need experimental
replicates so basically the main
limitation of using this kind of tools
is that I need two time points and two
experimental replicates to perform first
the inference of the noise and then the
inference of the of the expansion but
then if those are there basically all
these kind of framework should should
reliably take into account about uh all
the kind of problems that can be in the
the in the errors in the experimental
counts
Andre before you go to that part um just
a really simple question like how does
the invasion approach compared to like
the naive approach that most people use
which is just looking at clone
frequencies at time Point T1 and T2 and
if it goes up over a certain amount like
how many can you just say something like
I maybe I missed it but like like can
you just say what you think the false
positive and false negatives we're
getting when we just do a very yeah I
think I think by by learn by Better
Learning what's the kind of noise you
would
expect basically your model would like
change a little bit the threshold so it
it would shift a little bit this
line so you can say Okay I want to to
choose with confidence 1% the the
Contracting Clans if you would use like
a standard model that doesn't account
properly um of the experimental errors
you would always choose the same
threshold this kind of approach we would
move the threshold depending on the
intensity of the noise that it finds
somehow
so in in an experiment with a lot of
noise it will choose less points and
probably that that's the right way to do
because you are less confident because
that the noise is stronger