thank you very much hello everyone it's
a pleasure to be here welcome to MIT I
want to tell you about Quantum and in
particular Quantum materials for the
next you know technological Revolution
for Quantum 2.0 now I know this is a
broad audience so I'll start very simple
you know Quantum materials is the
fundamental theory that we have that
explains you know the behavior of
subatomic particles atoms molecules and
in general the physical world it was
developed over you know the past Century
by some of the greatest Minds you know
that have ever happened in human history
I'm sure you're very familiar with the
names that are listed here and it is a
very strange Theory yeah tells us that
you cannot know everything about an
object that thing is called Quantum
uncertainty objects can be in two or
more places or states exactly at the
same time that is known as Quantum
superposition objects can penetrate
through obstacles or through walls that
is known Quantum tunneling and objects
can be inextricably linked or correlated
even when infinitely apart and that is
known as quantum
entanglement now pretty much all of our
modern technology is based on quantum
mechanics and we call this Quantum 1.0
this goes from transistors and computer
phones to atomic clocks and GPS dials
LED photo voltes lasers Optical
communication superconductors for NMR
roscopy Medical Imaging and all photod
detection
Technologies and we say that this
technology is based on Quantum 1.0
because they use quantum mechanics at a
relatively simple level okay at a very
basic level as you know the countries
that have mastered Quantum 1.0 are the
most developed and you know most
powerful countries in the world today
now over the next 10 to 50 years okay
we're going to see a revolution in LED
in technology led by Quantum 2.0 this
will be the technology of the 21st
century where we're going to be able to
do things and use quantum mechanics at a
much deeper level which is going to
enable us to do many more things than we
were able to do before in particular we
will be able to use ultra secure Quantum
Communications and networks immune to
hacking we will be able to perform
Quantum simulations to discover new
types of materials new Catalyst
molecules medicis new types of superc
conductors
we will be able to use quantum computers
for factoring cryptography searching
optimization for a variety of algorithms
where we will these quantum computers
will work orders of magnitude faster
than our best super super computers
nowadays and we will be able to use use
new type of quantum sensors for and
Metrology for climate Energy Water
security space and in general basic
science
applications now in order to realize all
of the these things we're going to need
also new Quantum materials for many of
these tasks okay and MIT faculty have
played in many cases the pioneering role
in all of these Technologies and all of
these science okay and you can see here
you know people from Peter Shore you
know vented the first algorithm to of
you know we have here Noel prices Cav
price Winns Etc a lot of that basic
science and technology is happening has
happened at MIT and is happening at
MIT now traditionally for new going to
materials which is what I want to focus
on we have had two traditional platforms
to investigate Quantum materials the
first one which is the oldest is to look
at actual materials okay chunks of
crystals where you know this is for
example a high temperature Cate
superconductor the typical lens scale is
of order an anstrom the distance you
know between atoms in solids here with
this platform we have been able to
investigate hundreds of thousands of
materials but we have a relatively weak
you know you we we have very few ways in
which we can modify these materials you
know if you want to investigate a new
material you have to grow a new material
with a new composition with new
chemistry we cannot really tune very
much and control these
materials on the other hand about two
decades ago a new platform emerged it's
called ultracold atoms in Optical
latices where you know Atomic physicists
can shine lasers at each other they can
place atoms in this periodic potential
and they have Exquisite control over all
of the parameters of their system so
with just one system they can tune the
interactions between these atoms and do
plenty of things and change many things
to see if they can simulate the behavior
of quantum materials these are you know
more than Quantum simulators of
materials yeah and what I want to tell
you about today is about a new platform
it's called Mor Quantum matter the
typical lens scale here was lens scale
was a micrometer weight of light here
one Armstrong point 1 nanometers here
the typical lens scale is called the mor
length which is a order 10 nanometers so
it's very conveniently about a factor of
100 from either of these two lens scales
and this platform is also very
complementary to these two on one hand
we have a lot more control over this
platform and capability to tune you know
interactions and the system than with
traditional Quantum materials we don't
have quite as much freedom and control
ility and tunability as with the cold
atoms but on the other hand with this
platform we have been able to realize
pretty much all of the behaviors of
quantum matter and simulate them that we
know okay and in fact discovered quite a
new a few new ones that didn't exist
before which is something that this
community has been struggling because in
the ultra cold atoms field they're still
at relatively high temperatures to
realize many of the faces of cont to
matter that they would have interest in
realizing so what has enabled this more
Quantum mother platform so it's
something that you know has come to be
you know is now known as twiston which
is the fact that we can do something
with 2D materials that was impossible to
do in the history of Material Science
until recently when you have a three
dimensional material the arrangement
between the atomic planes is determined
by physics by thermodynamics you know
chemistry you get what you
get however when you have two
dimensional materials you can do the
following you can take a two-
dimensional material for example
graphine and I can put another two
dimensional material on top with any
angle of rotation that I want between
the crystalline structures okay that
thing called twiston XS when you
superimpose two periodic structures at
an angle they form a mo pattern okay the
mor pattern is this pattern that you can
see in the screen here with this white
balls there and when you do this you can
dramatically change the properties of
the header structure that you have just
assembled yeah
using this trick okay we have been able
now in the span of a few years this
development happened in 2018 and in the
span of just a few years we have been
able to create new types of correlated
insulators new unconventional
superconductors topological faes plenty
of them magnets quas crystals new fer
electrics strange metal gener V crystals
exonic insulators pneumatic systems and
the list goes on we have realized all of
the behaviors of quantum matter that we
know and quite a few new ones that we
didn't know about using this platform
just by using some simple materials and
playing with the angle between their
structure so what I want to give you
today is just a flavor so that you can
you know go home and look a little bit
more and read a bit more about three
examples of things that we've been able
to do with this type of Platform One Is
Magic Ang graphine and how you know this
can help us you know give us insight for
Quantum materials for Ultra strong
superc conductors another one is about
new type of more FCC materials for or
Quantum materials for neuromorphic you
know Computing and the last one will be
new more Quantum magnets or Quantum
materials for topological Quantum
Computing
so magicangle graphine turns out if you
put a few layers of graphine okay two or
three for example on top of each other
with a certain angle between the
structures for two layers is 1.1 de for
three layers as I'm showing here it's
1.6 de okay the material graphine which
is not a superconductor turns theer
structure into superconductor and it
turns out to be the strongest
superconductor that we know in the world
okay by far actually what do I mean a
superc conductivity is a state of matter
where current can flow without
dissipation of energy in order to do
that the electrons have to form Pairs
and these pairs are known as coupon and
Cooper pairs okay now the pairing blue
the pairing strength of electrons in
Cooper pairs is what characterizes the
strength of a superconductor and it
turns out that pairing glue in Magic
angle graphine is the strongest by far
that we have in nature this is something
which has been experimentally measured
it is not theoretically understood how
come that electrons in Magic angle
graphine are so strongly paired just to
give you an idea the superconductor
aluminum which is one that is used
nowadays in most superc conducting
quantum computers okay in super cubits
if the C pairs in aluminum had the same
pairing glue strength that they have in
Magic angle graphine aluminum could be a
superconductor at well above 1,000
Kelvin temperature okay way way way
above room temperature but aluminum CER
and aluminum are super weakly paired and
as a result they superc conduct at very
low temperatures okay so this is just
one example one example of how this
field of more superc conductors is
giving insight into strongly correlated
superconductivity superc conductivity
which is very strong now what are good
are news you know what good are new
strong superc conductors for okay this
is an image that probably many of you
have seen this is the new generation of
magnets for Fusion research you know
this is span out of MIT and you know
they're Bas you know used Now by
Commonwealth Fusion okay this latest
generation magnets for Fusion Energy are
based on high temperature
superconductors and these high
temperature superconductors they're
moderately strong superc conductors not
as strong as magic angle graphine but
quite strong and they share a similar
you know mechanism for a commcial superc
conductivity where it is not understood
which means that if with this much more
tunable platforms we're able to
understand better this only couple
superconductors we might be able to
design you know new Ultra strong
superconductors which could lead to much
more Compact and efficient magnets for
Fusion Energy but also new high
resolution Medical Imaging dissipation
less energy transport new Quantum
Computing and sensing Technologies Etc
basically all this you know would result
in energy security and efficiency which
will be critical for a sustainable
future this is just one example for more
superconductors now what about more
ferroelectrics okay so as probably many
of you know nowadays we're all
interested in AI in making AI more
efficient why don't we try to make it
work more like the brain you know and we
can learn you know and process
information with much less power like
our brain does okay so for this a
technology that is being used a lot are
actually neuromorphic devices which are
largely based on fertic materials so
with these Mor systems okay by playing
again with the structures the more
patterns and the tangles between the
structures we have been able to realize
a new type of ferroelectric device
colore ferroelectric which works
actually very similar is able to
implement operations very similar to the
way the brain does Okay so we've been
able to make new types of neuromorphic
devices which operate you know in terms
of their spiking and they have memory
based on this ferroelectric Behavior
which is completely different from
existing ferroelectrics it's a new
generation of fer electrics much more
capable than previous fedel electrics
and you can look at this paper recently
published in nature about it but not
only that this type of more devices
which can be FCC you can incorporate
them at the same time that you bring
other functionality for example superc
conductivity so last year also we were
able to realize you know the first more
superconductor which was also fed
electric material so material which is
both fed electric and superconductor so
that now you can switch between two
states but there not a high and a low
resistance state is a high and a zero
resistance state because it's a superc
conductor F Electric System yeah and you
know again what good are new more
electrics for you know there is this big
bottleneck you know in Computing the
performance bottleneck due to the fact
that now that you have to communicate
between where you operate you know you
do the operations the logic and where
you store information memory okay this
type of fed electrics and other ones
that we have discovered having actually
several types of new more electrics you
know discoveries in the past just couple
of years years and there's huge interest
in this can allow you to put the logic
and the memory exactly in the same spot
so that you don't have to waste 80% of
your time and your energy communicating
between logic and
memory now this will enable you know
Ultra fast and energy efficient
Computing you know using this type of
you know neomorphic platforms will be
critical for Next Generation Micro
Technologies and for AI
Etc the last thing that I want to tell
you about is a little bit more exotic
are into the future even that some of
these that I've mentioned which is this
Mor Quantum magnets and the fractional
Quantum anomalous H effect so the
fractional the regular fractional
Quantum H effect is an effect that
occurs in physics when you have a system
of electrons in two dimension for
example in Silicon or in Gom Maronite
and you apply a high perpendicular
magnetic
field you get a whole effect which is a
measurement of the voltage in the
perpendicular direction to the current
flow and this whole effect this voltage
happens to be the whole resistance
happens to be quantized with an accuracy
of one part in a billion actually 100
billion okay to a very precise value
yeah in this fractional qu whole effect
your electrons acquire very exotic
properties turns out the electron seems
to spit into three okay or they have
actually into quas particles we have a
fraction charge of let's say 1/3 of an
electron and they have very interesting
topological properties properties which
combine the field of mathematics
topology with physics and strong
correlations you know this was
discovered at MIT in the 80s it was
given Nobel Prize in physics in
1998 a big you know problem or a big
obstacle to use the fractional Quantum
anomal fractional quum effect in your
daily life is the fact that you have to
apply extremely high magnetic field
yeah and that's maybe some reason why
some of you may not have heard about
this
effect with the mor systems in the past
year
okay the community has discovered the
fractional Quantum anomalous whole
effect what does it mean it means the
fractional Quantum whole effect with all
this exotic physics but at zero magnetic
field this is something which was
published in nature last year and recent
you know two different Mor systems
having you know one by shadon Shu at the
University of Washington in Seattle one
by my colleague lju here at MIT we have
been able to realize as a community this
new state of matter that didn't exist
before the fractional Quantum anomos Hol
State okay now apart from being super
interesting from the physics point of
view what could this lead to okay what
good are these new Mor Quantum magnets
for turns out you heard a talk earlier
today by my colleague willber about
Quantum Computing okay Quantum Computing
is something that would be great but so
far we have not been able to realize you
know proper quantum computers because
Quantum bits are very sensitive to the
coherence it's very easy for them to
lose their Quantum coherence and hence
all the interesting properties that that
you know Quantum allows you to do for
years now theories have been
hypothesizing that if we could just
encode our Quantum bits in systems which
were robust to the coherence yeah we
would be able to make fa tolerant
Quantum Computing okay a much more
robust type of quantum Computing with
much much less orders of magnitude I'm
talking about many orders of magnitude
less number of cubits much more robust
okay the Theory's favorite platform to
realize this type of topological Quantum
bits are fractional Quantum whole states
coupled to superc conductors but
traditionally these two things are like
they go against each other superc
conductor don't like magnetic field okay
and fraction to whole effect only
happens at very high magnetic field so
it's very hard to think of how to put
this two things together okay but now
because we have fractional Quantum anous
effect fraction at zerom magnetic field
it's no problem to attach it to
superconductor so one of the biggest
perhaps biggest obstacle that people
thought would be you know to realize
topological quantum computer you know
it's gone okay and now still a lot of
research needs to be done but this is
something that plenty plenty of people
this has generated an enormous amount of
interest in the physics community and
also in some companies
so all of these things that I've told
you that we have done we have made them
with very simple materials in most cases
most of these faces you can realize it
just with carbonin and just you know do
it this okay so there is something which
is quite extraordinary you can almost
put aside the entire periodic table and
just with one or two materials work
realize all the behaviors of matter that
you have in the universe yeah now are we
there yet well not quite okay we need
there still a lot of basic research and
Engineering to solve many very difficult
problems we need a big Quantum Workforce
lots more graduate students you know
getting trained on Quantum to tackle all
these challenges and especially we need
a lot of automation okay I always tell
people that right now my grad students
are like medieval monks you know writing
a very beautiful manuscript one device
at a time is gorgeous it does all this
feny physics but it's one device at a
time it takes you know a month or more
you know and this all very manual
sometimes with Scotch tape and graphite
you may have heard about this famous
graphine that you use Scotch tape and
graphite we do use Scotch tape manually
and graphite for many of these things so
we need someone to come up and invent a
press but not just a regular press but a
Quantum press okay so this is something
that there is a lot of interest
developing in the community it is the
right moment to automate all of this
okay and we need this automation because
as you can imagine with instead of
playing with the angle and we can also
play with the number of layers and with
the different 2D materials we have
infinite possibilities actually to do
all of this and infinite possibilities
are many possibilities to explore with
gather students working by hand with SC
tape okay so we really need to develop
this Quantum press technology okay and
there are some groups that are
interested and some interest industries
that are interested but that's the
critical step now if we want to scale
this up and use this and deploy this
massively in Technologies because a lot
of the fundamental physics has already
been
done with this let me just end by saying
that what I've been telling you about
are three examples of twist Electronics
okay but actually a whole bunch of other
communities have realized that they can
also play with things you know and
rotate things so the ultra cold atoms
Community is now playing with Twisted
Optical latices to do simulators based
on you know Twisted cold atoms the trick
about electrons can be done also with
Fons or vibrations so there is also more
and twisted fonics so in twistr onics
the strict to make this strong superc
conductors at the magic angle actually
what you do there is you reduce the
electron velocity the Fring velocity to
zero turns out you can reduce the Fon
velocity to zero and realize also many
applications which are very interesting
from the point of view of sound
propagation heat propagation Etc you can
also do this with photons you can reduce
the speed of lightly to Zero by playing
with this twisting okay so this is
called Moran Twisted photonics this is
actually the largest growing field other
than the electronics and with huge
programs by the Department of Defense
because you can realize all kinds of
non-lineal optical elements and things
going to reduce the velocity of light
tremendously but why stop there you know
it turns out these Mor patterns that I
showed you have very different density
of States locally and they have local
electrochemical activity and Catal
catalytic activity so several groups are
now working on tunable electrochemistry
with more systems where they can do
chemical on the Nanos scale by looking
at these Mor patterns and you can also
do very interesting catalysis and last
but not least my high energy and coso
colleagues and cosmology colleagues they
think they can do also more gravity and
cosmology by playing you know with you
know these Twisted materials and
structures because there are analogies
of these properties in terms of the
formation of space time which map onto
their cosmological problems so with this
I want to you know thank you all thank
you my group members you know this work
is done by many groups of students and
postdocs plenty of collaborators you
know we have lots of support which we're
very thankful for and you know we're
back to these type of meetings after a
few years where it was tricky and that's
really a lot of fun and I want to thank
you all for your attention happy to take
any questions
[Applause]
do we have any questions this is the
last presentation of the
day hi there um one of your slides
mentioned high temperature
superconductors what temperature are we
talking about room temperature what what
okay thank you for the question because
very good to specify the way we
characterize in physics superconductors
is by something which is known as the
ratio of the critical temperature to the
firmy temperature basically is how high
is the critical temperature given how
much density of electrons you have in
your system okay so magic angle graphine
this Mor pattern as I mentioned at the
beginning the mor lens scale is of order
10 nanometers yeah and the super
conductivity occurs when you put two
electrons per Mo unit cell which means
two electrons in 10 by 10 nanom squ so
in 100 nanom square okay that's is a
density of el which is four of magnitude
smaller
than aluminum okay however the critical
temperature is actually above that of
aluminum it's you know about 2 Kelvin
okay so it's not that the critical
temperature is very high but the ratio
of the critical temperature to the firy
temperature okay to the of extremely
high is fours of magnitude larger than
in aluminum so if somehow we manage you
know it's amazing the magic angine
superc conducts at all at an observable
temperature because usually this pairing
glue for that density of electrons only
a few sprinkled here and there every 100
nanometer Square would Le to TCS of you
know less than 1 Melvin but it superc
conducts with a critical temperature
stronger than aluminum if we somehow
magically were able to take aluminum and
engineer the same physics the same per
glue strength okay at the metallic
densities of electrons of aluminum it
would superc conduct at more than a
th000 Kelvin yeah but we don't know how
to engineer those things yet
okay one more question and then call Dat
I think it's a very simple question
motivated by some of your last slides
where you're talking about selective
electrochemistry where you could have
different patterns both the
electrochemistry and also the
electromagnetics would mean that you
would have a lot of opportunities for
sensors you pattern electrochemical
sensors and pattering and that would be
interesting to see that area pursued it
is one is now it has been studied at
device prototype level that magic angine
for example is the best single Photon
detector at all frequencies that exist
in the world you can detect all the way
from terahertz to high energies and you
can detect single photons and it's the
fastest and the best it's a little bit
of a shame that we don't have this
Quantum press so that we you know we
don't know how to make a billion magic
Ang graphine devices fast and cheap okay
but if we knew you would have all your
satellites all your telescopes all your
Quantum C sensors based on this
technology if we can just only scale
this
up thank you Pablo thanks great
[Applause]
[Music]