All
right, welcome back to graphs. This will
be our last lecture that's fully about
graphs. Um, and we're going to move away
from what we've been talking about for
the last three lectures, simple
undirected graphs, and move to the other
kind of graph we talk about in this
class, which is directed graphs,
which we sometimes shorten to diagraph.
So, from now on, we're going to have to
be explicit. Every time we talk about a
graph, we should say directed or
undirected. Simple is implicit when we
say undirected.
But uh we should distinguish. Uh so the
motivation is uh what if your
connections only go in one direction,
right? Maybe uh you have one-way roads
like all of Boston or you have uh
one-way follow relationships instead of
friendships uh or you have network
connections you can only send in one
direction. those do exist though they're
less common and so directed graphs are
going to model that for us.
Uh so
things are going to look very similar
to the old definition uh just the edges
are different.
So you may recall we had this cross
productduct notation. I'm going to
remind you so we can compare. uh this is
a set of ordered pairs of
vertices in this case. Uh so very
similar
uh property here edges were unordered
sets of two vertices here they are
ordered pairs of two vertices. Uh the
other difference is here we forbade
having a loop.
Uh here we allow it.
So this was
not allowed over here but allowed over
here. Um
still uh we over here we forbade uh two
edges connecting the same two vertices.
Uh here we
allow uh two edges going in opposite
directions. Uh so this was a no.
uh we still forbid in this picture
having two edges going in the same
direction between the same two vertices.
Okay, that's a consequence because uh E
is a set. You're only allowed to have
one of each.
So that's the definition. Very simple.
Uh here's a little example
on
six vertices. It's a floating vertex out
here f.
Uh so you see uh you can have sometimes
you can have an edge that goes in both
directions. Sometimes you have an edge
that only goes in one direction. Uh
maybe sometimes you add a loop. I think
I wanted one here.
And I should have written it over here
that just looks like da d.
And there you go. Okay. Uh now the first
part of today is just going to be
porting over all the definitions from
last class into this model. Most of the
things we talked about behave similarly.
Some of them behave different in
interesting ways. So bear with me while
we define a few things. Um the very
first thing is what about
degrees?
So that's uh way back in the beginning
of graphs we talked about the degree of
a vertex was the number of incident
edges. But now a vertex can have two
types of incident edges. It can have
some incoming edges and it can have some
outgoing edges. So in general of a
vertex V, it's going to have some
incoming guys and some outgoing. We call
this the in degree
and we call this the outderee.
We don't define degree
because it's confusing and ambiguous. So
in degree for example of a vertex
is uh the
sorry not the sum
the cardality of the set of
uh edges uv
that are in e
where u is some vertex.
So this is just counting the number of
edges going into V and the outderee is
symmetric.
This would be like V comma U.
Before we only had one type of edge. So
uh there was only one notion. Sometimes
these are called degree plus and degree
minus or degree sub in sub out. I can
never remember which is plus and which
is minus. So I always write in degree
and outderee. Uh you can choose your own
adventure. Um a related thing to degree
is the handshaking lema.
Who remembers what the handshaking lema
was for undirected graphs?
That was ages ago before spring break.
Yeah.
Right. The sum of the degrees of the
vertices
uh
is uh twice the number of edges. I think
you said over two but close.
Um so in this world this was in some
sense because every edge
uh was getting counted twice right you
count if you sum the degrees of of this
vertex and of this vertex you count this
edge once from this side and once from
this side. Uh now we have distinguished
in some sense each end of each edge.
There's the in edge and the out edge or
I guess call this the in edge and this
is the it comes out of B and goes into
D. So if we write the sum of say in
degrees.
So this was just remembering undirected
in the directed case we have uh sum over
all vertices of inderee equals exactly
the number of edges and also equals the
sum of the outdrees
uh because now our edges are directed.
I have an arrow. And so if we sum the in
degrees, we will only count this edge
from this side when we're looking at
this vertex. If we sum the outderees,
we'll only count count this edge once
from this vertex. So these two sums are
the same and they both give you the
number of edges. So in some sense, a
little cleaner than what we had from
undirected graphs because we split each
edge and uh or we've distinguished the
two sides of the edge, I should say.
All right, let's catch up to last
lecture which is
was all about locks.
So this definition is actually it's
pretty much exactly the same. Just
repeat it so we remember.
We had a sequence of vertices
where each
uh vi
to vi + one
is an edge. But before we had curly
braces here saying the order didn't
matter because edges were undirected.
Now we have parenthesis saying this is
an ordered pair. You have to go forward
along each edge. So that's a crucial
distinction.
must
uh go forward along the edge. In other
words, you have to respect the arrows.
So, for example,
this graph uh we could start at A and go
to C and then go to E. That would be an
example of not just a walk but a path
which has no repeated vertices or edges.
Or
we could go from A to B to A to B to A
to B to D to D to D to D to D to E. That
would be an example of a walk
exciting.
I should say these structures should
look familiar. If you can remember even
farther back to lecture four which was
about state machines, these are exactly
state machines. Like the only difference
is in directed graphs we usually think
about finite graphs and with state
machines we're often thinking about
infinite machines but uh this is the
same setup. This definition mirrors
exactly um state machines and walks. The
only difference another difference is
state machine had an initial state.
There's no notion of initial state here.
But a walk is just like an execution in
a state machine. So unifying all that
terminology. We didn't have a notion of
path or anything. We just had walks.
Okay. Uh as before, a walk like this is
from v 0 to vk and k is the length.
Length always counts the number of edges
not vertices.
Uh then we had the closed notion. there
was a closed walk
uh and in particular a cycle. Closed
meant the v 0 equals vk and cycle was
essentially the closed version of a
path. So this was closed walk
of
length greater than zero
with no other repeated vertices or edges
other than the first equaling the last.
Okay. The difference is um in an
undirected graph, the shortest cycle had
length three.
We could make a cycle like this, a
triangle. Uh we weren't allowed to make
a cycle with a single edge because then
you'd necessarily repeat that edge.
Where's my red?
In an undirected graph,
this was forbidden.
But in a directed graph it's possible.
Uh if we have the edge uv and we have
the edge vu
then there is a two cycle
like that goes u vu
um there's even a one cycle right
because we can have loops. So here for
example
D to D is a length one cycle
in this notation. Okay so a little
different than what we had before a
little more general but turns out this
notion of cycle is still interesting for
directed graphs. All right let's move on
to connectivity.
Before we had a nice notion of U and V
being connected to each other and it was
symmetric. U is connected to V if and
only if V is connected to U. Now it's no
longer symmetric and we're going to use
a different term for it to make that
clear. So we'll say v is reachable
from u or u can reach v
if
uh there exists a walk
from
u to v.
Okay. So this looks like the same
definition of uv connected in the
undirected case. But now because walks
can't be reversed
because if you reverse a walk uh if I go
from VK back to V0 then I'm using all
the edges in the opposite direction and
that's not in general allowed unless you
happen to have a graph where every edge
is doubled. You won't be able to reverse
your walk.
Uh so this is no longer equivalent to
there existing a walk from V to U. But
it is still equivalent to there existing
a path from V to U from U to V sorry
that part is still true. The proof is
actually exactly the same. You take a
shortest walk from U to V and uh if it's
not a path then it has some loop in it
some cycle essentially and then you omit
that cycle and you get a shorter walk
contradiction.
Okay. So same exactly the same proof as
before still respects the edge
directions which is nice. So uh for the
purpose of reachability now uh walks and
paths are the same. So we can assume
whichever one is more convenient. Um
this relation
uh is still
this you know reachability property is
still reflexive
and transitive. Remind you what those
mean. uh reflexive means V can reach V
for any vertex V you can always get to
yourself you just don't do anything u
and it's still transitive meaning if you
can get from A to B and u B can reach if
A can reach B and B can reach C then A
can reach C you can still concatenate
paths together and that's fine okay but
uh no longer symmetric
already said this a couple times but if
you If a can a can reach b, we don't
necessarily have b can reach a. So that
makes things more interesting. In
particular, what does it mean for the
whole graph to be connected? Uh for that
it's useful to talk about
um there's a very strong notion of
connectivity.
First uh
say two vertices u and v are strongly
connected in a directed graph. if uh
they're mutually reachable.
In other words, uh U can reach V and V
can reach U.
Okay. Uh this behaves symmetrically. If
U and V are strongly connected, then V
and U are also strongly connected sort
of by definition. It's like U can reach
V and V can reach U.
uh and in particular we call the entire
graph strongly connected
if everything can reach everything.
If uh for all u all vertices u and v um
u can reach v
or in other words uh for all u and v
uh u and v are strongly connected. So
again the pairwise relation
these graphs are nice because you can
start anywhere and get anywhere else.
you never get stuck. But in general in a
directed graph, you could walk and not
be able to return. So for example, in
this graph, uh maybe you walk around
like you do take one of the walks that I
drew, but once you end up in E, you're
stuck. Or if you start in E, you can't
get anywhere except E itself. Start in
F, you also can't go anywhere.
But that's a little less exciting. So
that graph obviously is not strongly
connected. Um,
maybe I'll draw an example of one that
is
This graph is strongly connected.
It's also oileran.
So remember uh an oiler tour
was a closed walk. It visits every edge
exactly once
uh and visits every vertex
at least once.
So this graph is orarian. I drew it in
an orarian way, but I will also redraw a
path here. Uh, you can go around the
outside. Notice now I'm respecting the
edge directions. That's a little
different from the example we saw last
class.
I think I got all the edges exactly
once.
So, uh, again, you might ask when which
graphs are. We did the really long proof
last class and it turns out um
there's a very similar characterization.
So, oiler tour exists if and only if uh
your graph is strongly connected
and uh for every vertex
the in degree
equals the outderee.
And there's another there's a similar
characterization for oiler walks instead
of oiler tours. It's just a little
uglier. So I won't go into it. It's just
you allow these to differ by one for a
couple vertices in a particular way. Um
so in particular if you look at this
example it should be every vertex either
has two in two out. This one has two
coming in two going out or one in one
out. And in general, if you have k
incoming edges, you should have also k
outgoing edges in order to have an oiler
tour. Why? Uh because what goes in must
come out. Uh similar all the proofs here
are similar to what we did for
undirected graphs. Um before we are
saying the number of edges at each
vertex had to be even because every time
we enter the vertex, we also had to
leave. But this is the directed version
of that where every time you come in,
you must also exit. if you have a closed
loop, if you have a a closed walk that
visits all these edges. Uh so certainly
this is necessary. Strong connectivity
is also necessary because the oiler tour
gives you a way to get from anywhere to
anywhere. It's like a giant subway line.
You can get on whenever you want and
follow it until you get to whatever
vertex you want. Because we said the
oiler tour visits every vertex, that's a
way to get from anywhere to anywhere.
Might take a while, but you'll get
there.
Uh, and what else? Yeah, the proof again
is similar. If you want to show that
these properties are sufficient, you
take the longest possible trail that
visits every edge at most once and argue
that it's closed for the same reasons as
before and that it actually has to visit
every edge because otherwise you could
make it longer.
Okay,
I think we're pretty much through the
the main repetition from before.
There's one more related notion to
connectivity
uh which is connected components. We
talked about connected components a
little bit for undirected graphs.
They're a little more interesting for
directed graphs.
Uh
in particular they mainly make sense for
strong connectivity. We don't define any
other types. uh it's not surprising.
So strong connected component or sec
of a vertex V
is the uh graph induced. This is similar
to how we set it up before
by uh
all the vertices that are strongly
connected to V.
Okay, let's look at an example.
This example it's a little a bit
interesting. So for example, what is the
strongly connected component of A? I
haven't made this too ugly.
Redraw this a little bit.
What vertices are strongly connected to
A?
Shout them out.
B can I can definitely get to B and B
can get back to A.
C. Uh, I can get from A Oh, no. I can
get from A to C this way. And C can get
to A via B.
Anything else?
No.
Turns out if you if you follow any of
these edges any of these two edges,
you're never getting back. And also f is
neither reachable is not reachable from
a in either direction. So uh this chunk
here
is a strongly connected component. And
again when I say the graph induced by
these three vertices, so this is the
graph induced by ABC,
I mean that's my vertex set. I take
those three vertices, none of the
others, and I take all the edges that
were in my original graph among those
three vertices and throw away everything
outside. So that boxed region is the
strongly connected component of A. It's
also the strongly connected component of
B and the strongly connected component
of C.
What's the strongly connected component
of D?
Just D. So this is in a strongly
connected component by itself.
and E similarly and F similarly.
Okay. Um
in general we get a bunch of strongly
connected components and before it was
very clean, right? Everything like
anything you could possibly touch was in
one strongly connect was when one
connected component and every vertex and
every edge fell into one connected
component. That was the situation for
undirected graphs. We said that
connected components partitioned the
graph. Everything appeared exactly once
in one of the pieces. Now it's not so
clean. The vertices get partitioned.
There's some vertices in this component,
some in this, some in this, some in
this. Every vertex is in exactly one
strongly connected component. But for
directed graphs, there are also some
edges between components.
That's a little more interesting.
Uh
so let's say
every
vertex
is in
exactly
one strongly connected component. But uh
we have some
edges between
and there's a nice way to kind of
organize this which we call
condensation graph.
Okay. Uh condensation graph of a graph G
is another graph H
vertex set C and edge set F. These are
just some madeup letters
where
C is
I forgot some notation.
So the strongly connected component of
vertex V I'm going to call square
bracket V probably just for this lecture
but it's convenient to have some name
for the strongly connected component
that contains V.
And C is going to be the set of all
strongly connected components. So now I
can write it as square bracket V for all
vertices V and V.
Okay. So in this example
I
draw
a graph over here.
So this was G.
H is going to have one vertex for this
strongly connected component. One for
this one, one for this one, one for this
one. So four vertices. I'm going to
label them with the vertices that in the
original graph that they came from. Got
D up here,
E roughly over here, and F over here.
Okay. Now, what are the edges?
Well, the edges are just going to
correspond to uh whenever
uh I want to read this from right to
left. So, let me write it first.
So, whenever I have an edge UV in the
original graph, I want to draw an edge
uh between the corresponding strongly
connected components. the strongly
connected component containing U to the
strongly connected component containing
V. Uh except I don't want edges from a
strongly connected component to itself.
Uh just because it's cleaner that way.
So uh this will represent exactly the
edges between components, right? There
are some edges within components which I
kind of want to ignore because I can get
anywhere within this component. So it's
for from a connectivity standpoint, from
a reachability standpoint, I don't
really care about the distinction
between A, B, and C. They're all
essentially the same. If I'm at any of
them, I can go to any other. But then
there's these edges between components
that are interesting. Highlight them
here in bold. So we've got ABC to D.
We've got ABC to E. We've got D to E.
And that's it.
So this is the condensation graph. And
so if you want to know uh reachability
between two vertices in the original
graph, you can figure it out by looking
at reachability within H. So if
everything's strongly connected, you're
in one big component. That's easy.
Answer is always yes. Otherwise, you
have to look at walks in the cond
condensation graph.
All right,
next topic. And actually the last topic
which we'll spend a bunch of time on is
much more interesting than last time is
asyclic graphs.
So what would you call an undirected
asyclic graph?
Anyone remember
if we mentioned it
tree
what you're gonna say uh actually trees
are connected undirected as cyclic
graphs. So almost so we we may not have
even mentioned it here but we use the
word forest for the general case when
you're not necessarily connected. So in
the undirected case a forest is just any
asyclic graph. Each of its connected
components is a tree but it might have
more than one. Okay. Uh today we're
going to talk about directed as cyclic
graphs.
I feel like there should be some
nature-based pun for directed as cyclic
graphs, but instead they're just
commonly called DAGs
uh for directed as cyclic graph. So it's
kind of boring. Sometimes I've seen dog
like D- AWG. That's another type of
graph which we won't get into. So that's
nature based I guess. Um all right. So
what's an example of a directed as
cyclic graph?
Have we seen any in this class?
Yeah.
A terminating state machine. Yeah. uh
maybe not all terminating state machines
but the ones that we the method we use
to prove them. So like a state machine.
Uh
oh maybe yeah maybe all terminating
state machines actually but in
particular those with uh strictly
decreasing
uh derived variable
it's strictly decreasing then you can't
make any cycles. I think even conversely
if you made a cycle then that would be
repeating that cycle over and over would
be a non-terminating execution. So
indeed or terminating state machines
good. Um another one
is this graph the condensation graph we
just defined maybe not obvious.
These are just examples. Uh of course
there are many directed asyclic graphs
but there's no definition here. I mean
the definition is directed as cyclic and
graph or I guess as cyclic you might say
as cyclic diagramraph given the terms
we've used but it's always written d a g
so there you go uh condensation graph is
also always as cyclic because if there
was a cycle like if I could get from ABC
to D to E back to ABC well then these
three should actually all be in one
uh strongly connected component right so
there can't be any cycles in this graph
otherwise I would collapsed further.
So there we go. Uh the what makes the
condensation graph interesting in some
sense is it becomes a cyclic. You can
track all the cycles into one vertex or
each cycle into one vertex.
All right. Uh
I have a
quote practical example here. You'll see
you see why I'm laughing in a second.
So directed as cyclic graphs come up
naturally a lot. I mean you can make any
graph a cyclic by constructing the
condensation graph. But uh where they're
quite common is in a set of constraints.
Suppose you have a bunch of tasks you
need to do and there's some precedence
constraints. This has to happen before
that. This has to happen before that.
You could imagine project management or
whatever. I'm going to give a very real
world example you do every single day I
hope. uh which is getting dressed.
So suppose you have some socks you want
to put on
and you may know that socks come before
shoes. I've tried it the other way. It
doesn't work so well.
And uh usually I put one sock on at a
time. So there's your left sock and your
right sock. Uh apologies for people who
have different number of feet.
uh like dogs, it's even more annoying.
Um but uh these are examples of
precedence relations. You want to put
the left sock on before you put your
left shoe on. You want to put your right
sock on before you put your right shoe
on. But you don't really care about the
ordering between these two sides. I
could do both of these and then do both
of these. Or I could do both socks and
then both shoes. I could do left, right,
right, left. There are lots of possible
orderings that are valid here. You can
add more fun things like uh pants.
Those have to happen before your shoes.
And I don't know, you probably want to
put a shirt on. And maybe you have uh a
jacket on top of that. And you have a
belt, which you should put on before
after your pants, let's say. And maybe
like a winter coat.
Still kind of winter, maybe. We'll see.
Uh, and if you're really cold, maybe you
want a scarf. And I've heard debates
about which of these goes first, but
let's say scarf before coat. Uh,
certainly after your jacket and maybe
you want a hat on, but that could happen
pretty much anytime after your jacket.
So something like this. I think those
are all the all the annotations I had
here.
And now you'd like to find a valid
ordering. If you want to find a valid
ordering, there better not be any cycles
here because then you could never
resolve that cycle. If you have a cycle
of precedence constraints and A has to
happen before B, B has to happen before
C and C has to happen before A, then
nothing, none of A, B and C could happen
first. So that would be bad. So in any
kind of uh precedence constraint graph
like this, you want to have no cycle. So
this is practical motivation for
directed asyclic graphs. And now we'd
like to
let's define a notion of um
topological ordering
of a DAG
is
an ordering
of all the vertices.
such that each vertex
uh appears
before
all vertices it can reach.
give it a name. So I'll call it V here.
So for example, uh pants has to happen
before belt, but also pants has to
happen before your winter coat because
of these two connections.
And pants has to happen before shoe. So
pants should be listed earlier in your
sequence before your right shoe, before
your left shoe, before your winter coat,
before your belt, before uh that's
that's it for pants. Okay. Okay. And if
we can find an ordering
uh that satisfies that property, then
that would be a legitimate way to
execute this these set of tasks.
And the next thing I'd like to do is
prove that topological orderings always
exist.
Seems reasonable
in a DAG.
If, as I said before, if you have a
cyclic graph, these don't exist. That's
a little less exciting. As long as your
graph is a cyclic, you can always find a
topological order. And there's a nice
way to do it. Uh let me first define a
couple of useful terms. One is
source. This is for any directed graph.
A source is a vertex
of in degree zero.
This is going to act kind of like a leaf
for us and that we had for trees.
Remember uh directly cyclic graphs here
are sort of our analogy of trees or
forests more generally
and
degree one vertices. Well, there's no
notion of degree here anymore. We just
have inderee and outderee. So instead of
degree one vertices we're going to look
at inderee zero. So for example, left
sock is a source, right sock is a
source, pants is a source and shirt is a
source
in this graph.
Uh and the complimentary notion now is
sync
and this is a vertex
of outderee zero.
So in this graph
we have
few of them also left shoe is a sink
right shoe is a sink I have no outgoing
edges winter coat is a sink
and hat is a sink these were sinks.
Okay. And then there are some vertices
that are neither. Probably in general
most of them are neither. But uh what we
do know like the fact that every tree
with at least two vertices has at least
two leaves. We know that every
DAG has at least one source and at least
one sync.
So if you're wondering why two leaves
for a tree, this is kind of why. Maybe
this is uh distinguishing the two two
ends. And the proof is actually very
similar. So let's do lema.
Every DAG
has a source
and a sync
proof.
I don't know if you remember the proof
that every tree has at least two leaves.
Uh it was take
a longest
path or walk. Uh maybe it's worth
mentioning for DAGs, walks and paths are
the same thing because the thing we're
worried about with paths is do you ever
cycle? Do you ever repeat a vertex? But
if there's no cycles, you can't. So for
DAGs, uh
walks equal paths,
which is nice. So
for the rest of today, I don't have to
reme remember which is which, but I'll
try to be a little bit careful if I need
something.
So uh let's just take the longest or a
longest path in the DAG. So let's say it
starts at v 0
to v1
and goes up to v k
as usual. Then the claim is
Uh, V 0 is a sync
and VK
sorry
backwards.
E0 is a source
and VK is a sync
and that so then we found it.
Okay. Why? Uh, let me do a proof by
picture.
So here is our
hypothetical longest path and I want to
claim for example that v 0 is a source
meaning there is no incoming edge into v
0 in degree is zero. Well let's prove it
by contradiction. Suppose there was some
vertex here u and there was an edge from
u to v 0.
This is for contradiction.
Imagine that this happens. Well, then
that looks like a longer path in the
graph. How could it not be a longer
path? Well, maybe it cycles. Maybe this
vertex u was actually one of these other
visi.
Uh but it can't be because our graph is
as cyclic. So either
uh we get a cycle which contradicts that
we're a DAG
or we get a longer path
in the graph
which contradicts that we were longest.
So either way we get a contradiction
and that proves uh that v 0 is a source
and exactly symmetric argument proves
that vk is a sync. Cool. So these things
exist.
Now let's use them to construct
a
an order to getting dressed. I know you
you've been wondering this the answer to
this gripping question. How should I get
dressed every morning? Finally in 61200
I learned how to do it
for any graph.
Uh
the idea algorithmically is very simple.
If you want a topological order for your
graph, what should I start with? A
source seems good. Source has nothing
that has to come before it. So any one
of these would be a valid first step. So
the algorithm is just take any source,
do that first, then conceptually remove
that vertex to represent that it's been
finished and then find another source.
And because from this lema there's
always a source, you never get stuck. So
you can just keep going and eventually
you'll have done executed every task. So
for let's do it um briefly on this
example. Say we uh we do right sock
first and we up we see if there are any
new sources. Uh I think there are not.
This is still not a source because it
has an incoming edge one left. Uh then
maybe we do our pants. Put those on.
Seems like a good idea. Now we can put
on our right shoe. Finally. Been waiting
for that right shoe because there's no
more incoming edges because we've
eliminated we've finished the tasks from
before. So, if I write down the
ordering, it would be right sock,
then pants.
Uh, now I'm going to do right shoe.
Uh, then I don't know, I'm lazy. Let's
do left sock and left shoe next.
Then, uh, let's see the at this point
I've eliminated the left half of the
graph. only source is shirt. So I have
to do shirt next. I had a lot of choices
up till now but that that choice is
forced. Uh after I've eliminated these
two this becomes a source and this
becomes a source.
So I can choose belt or jacket first.
Let's do belt.
Still can't do uh winter coat because I
need to do scarf before it. Uh so jacket
is the only source at this point.
So do that.
I think you get the idea. Now I could do
hat for example both the source and a
sync. Um I can do scarf and then finally
I can do winter coat. So that was a
valid execution order or valid
topological ordering.
Cool. Let's uh prove that this always
works a little more carefully uh using
induction instead of an algorithm
because this is more of a math class
than a algorithms class though of course
we talk about both
but I think it's good to get more uh
induction practice
so
in particular induction with graphs is
still a pretty new thing. But again,
induction about graphs is always
induction or some regular induction over
natural numbers. So we're going to do
induction on the number of vertices in
the graph, which is how we normally do
it. So our uh p of n is that every dag
with n vertices has a topological order.
We're going to assume by induction that
all smaller n have this property and
prove it for n or prove it for v size of
v. So what is the smallest
that size of V can be?
Uh well I didn't put it in the
definition but I meant to say V has to
be at least one as before. We don't
allow the empty graph with no vertices.
You have to have at least one vertex. So
smallest graph has one vertex. So here
it is. Uh I guess yeah uh I mean in a
directed graph you could have a loop
here but that's that's a cycle. So not
allowed. In a DAG, there's only one
graph of one vertex. It's that one.
Let's call this A. The ordering is A. It
satisfies all the properties. Okay,
that's their topological order. So, this
is easy.
More interesting is the induction step.
So, uh now we can assume that D is at
least two bigger than the base case.
Uh
so what should we do? Well, we have this
nice lema that tells us there's a
source. So whereas the algorithm took a
source and then had to do more work to
continue, we can just take one source
and then use induction.
So uh
by the lema
there exists a source
let's call it s and the intuition is I
want to do s first.
Okay. But to figure out how to do the
rest of the graph, I can use induction.
So let's uh let G prime be G minus S.
Remember this was the graph. G minus S
was the graph induced by the subset of
vertices. That's everything except S. So
in other words, erase the vertex S and
all of its incident edges, which in this
case will only be outgoing edges. So
here we have s and there's some outgoing
edges into g prime and g is this whole
graph.
Okay so the point is um number of
vertices in g prime is one less than the
number of vertices in g. We just removed
s everyone else is there.
Uh but in particular g prime is smaller
than g was. So we can use induction
by the induction hypothesis.
Uh G prime satisfies this. I guess we
also need to check G prime is a DAG. But
if you remove a vertex, you're not going
to add any cycles. So that's cool.
Uh so G prime is a smaller DAG
according to the measure of number of
vertices. So by induction hypothesis, it
has a topological order. G prime has
topological order.
Let's call it uh vub1 v2 up to v sub I
guess number of vertices minus one.
That's how many vertices there are. So I
can you by induction I get an explicit
ordering of all those vertices. And now
I just put s first
before all of those. So we get s comma
v1 v2 and so on v sub v minus one. Uh
this is a topological order
of g and this is where I guess you have
to actually check something.
So I claim it's okay to put s before all
these other vertices and that will be a
valid ordering. uh intuitively because S
has nothing that has to happen before
it. So if you check the constraint of a
topological ordering, every vertex
that's listed must appear before all
vertices that it can reach. Well, S
definitely appears before all vertices
it can reach because it appears before
all vertices.
And the other vertices are also okay
like V2 or V1 let's say appears before
all the vertices it can reach because
all the vertices it can reach it's
inside G prime. Once you're inside G
prime, you can't escape. you can't get
back to S,
right? It's like in a different strongly
connected component. Uh any vertex down
here, which is all of the V1 through VV
minus one, cannot reach S because it
only has outgoing edges. And so they
also appear before all the vertices they
can reach because all the vertices they
can reach are within G prime.
So great. Now given a set of tasks with
precedence constraints, you can find a
valid ordering
so you can get dressed in the morning.
But uh you know we're most of us are
computer scientists and so often we're
not just one computer or one uh agent
executing a bunch of tasks but maybe we
have many computers to execute our
tasks. What if we allow parallelism? Can
we do this any faster? You imagine you
want to get dressed, but you have a
crazy uh Rube Goldberg style machine
that can put on many garments all at
once. So maybe then you can do left and
right sock in parallel. If I had four
arms, I would do that. Maybe even three
arms. I don't know. That's a good
question. Okay. So let's think about
that version where
uh we can do parallel task execution.
Then I'd like to do it as fast as
possible.
If I'm just a measly single processor
and I want to execute the tasks in this
graph, well, the number of steps it
takes me is exactly the number of
vertices. No matter how I do it, it
doesn't really matter which ordering I
choose in terms of speed, assuming, I
don't know, assuming instantaneous
switching time between different tasks.
Okay. But with parallel task scheduling,
you can do more.
So let me first define the problem a
little bit um and then we'll prove a
nice theorem.
So I want to define a schedule to say
basically what order you should do the
tasks in. But now I'm allowing multiple
tasks to be scheduled at the same time.
So a schedule is going to assign
what time
uh t of v it's going to be a natural
number
uh to each vertex
v
and
it needs to satisfy the property that uh
if u can reach V
and U does not equal V,
then uh the time that we schedule U has
to be strictly less than the time we
schedule V.
This is the analog of topological
ordering except now I can assign the
same time to multiple tasks. So maybe I
do a bunch of tasks at test at time zero
as long as none of them has to happen
before another. Then I could do a bunch
of tasks at time one, a bunch of tasks
at time two, and so on. And the um I'll
call it the span of the schedule is the
number of distinct times
t of v. So I can look at all the
different times assigned to the vertices
and if I use 17 different times, my span
is 17. span is a measure of how long it
takes to execute schedule. Uh here I'm
assuming an unlimited number of
processors. I can do all the tasks at
once if I need if I'm allowed to. If I
have no edges in my graph, I'll just do
everything in time zero and it'll be
done. And that will be a span of one.
There's only one time that value that I
needed. But in general, we're going to
need more, right? I can't do left sock
and left shoe at the same time because
left sock has to happen strictly before
left shoe. That's what this says. If one
vertex can reach another vertex that's
different, then the time assigned to the
the earlier precedent has to be strictly
less than the later one. Okay, so that's
the definition of the problem. And now
there's a nice theorem
says uh the minimum possible span of any
schedule.
So certainly a schedule like this
exists, right? We could do the one given
by the topological order. We could do
right sock in time zero, pants in time
one, right shoe in time two. Like we
could do this sequentially, one task at
a time. But if I want to minimize the
span, I want to do lots of things in
parallel. Uh this is equal to the number
of vertices
in a longest path in the graph.
So very simple characterization of how
long this takes.
Uh in this example
I think the longest path is shirt to
jacket to scarf to coat. So that was uh
that's a path of length one,
two, three.
But what I wrote there is not the length
of the path. I wrote the number of
vertices in the path and that's four. So
this is the one time when we want to
count vertices, not edges. So I write
number of vertices in the longest path.
It was shirt, jacket, scarf, winter
coat. So that's four. And so I claim
this
uh
this set of tasks can be executed in
just four steps, four rounds of parallel
execution. Namely,
I think I need another color. Let me see
what I brought.
Oh, purple.
Okay, so how I do it is actually pretty
intuitive. I just want to take all the
sources at each step. So in the
beginning I had four sources. I'm going
to do all of those at time zero. Then
what's the source? Uh this becomes a
source because both left sock and pants
were done in the previous step. This
becomes a source because right sock and
pants were done in the previous step. Uh
this becomes a source and this becomes a
source. I think that's it. So then in
the second step I'm going to do all
these everything above that purple line.
And then uh hat becomes a source, scarf
becomes a source, but winter coat is
still being annoying. So we do
everything above that line. And then in
the fourth round, we just do winter
coat.
Okay, so that's the algorithm. But let's
uh
let's prove it's not obvious that this
algorithm takes exactly the longest path
time. And there's a nice elegant proof
of it.
Let's go back here.
So um in general when we want to prove
that two numbers are equal usually we do
it in two parts. We prove that one
number is greater than equal to the
other and the one number is less than or
equal to the other. seen that a couple
of times I think and this is definitely
one of those situations. So first let's
think about why is the minimum span of a
schedule at least the number of vertices
in the longest path.
Well that makes sense because if I just
think about uh this longest path you
know it's some sequence of vertices
and let's say it has length L. So we
start at number one or it has L
different vertices in it. Well, in the
first round, uh, just looking at this
path, the first round, the only thing I
can do is the first vertex in the path.
In the second round, the only thing I
can do is the second one. Like to
execute this path clearly requires at
least L time steps, right? So, this is
just to schedule the longest path,
you certainly need the number of
vertices
of that path.
That's a bit handwavy, but pretty
intuitive. The interesting part is the
other direction. So let's suppose I
found the longest path and it has L
vertices. I claim that I can achieve I
can find a schedule that does that that
is that fast. And here it is.
Given a vertex, we're going to define
its depth
to be
uh the length
of longest path ending at V
or say I guess 2V. So it can start
anywhere, but I want the a longest path
that ends at V.
Okay. Okay. And I'm going to here I'll
use length measuring the number of edges
as usual because it doesn't really
matter. So I claim uh
that uh depth is a schedule
and that it has the right span
uh because depth assigns a natural
number 012 whatever uh to every vertex
and I claim it is a valid schedule.
Let's prove that.
Okay. So what does it mean to be a valid
schedule? It says that uh if I have two
vertices u and v where u can reach v and
u is different from v then I have to
prove that depth of u is less than depth
of v.
So uh suppose
uh u can reach
v and suppose v does not equal u.
We want to show
uh depth
of u is strictly less than depth of v.
This is what it means to be a valid
schedule.
Okay.
So, uh what does it mean that U can
reach V?
We still have the definition over here.
V is reachable from U or U can reach V
if there exists a walk from U to V or
for DAGs it's the same as or in general
it's the same as there exists a path
from U to V. So uh we know that there
exists a path
let's call it uh p uv
from u to v that's the meaning of ukv
uh and
we also know that it has length
greater than zero.
Why? Because these vertices are
different and there are no cycles.
uh I guess the only way to have a length
zero path is if you start and end at the
same vertex but if v is different from
you that path has to have uh nonzero
length this will be important in a
moment
okay let's see what else do we know we
also know uh or we know that there's a
path
uh there's a longest path
pu to uh to u
my my words are starting to sound like
numbers. Uh this to o
um right that's the definition of depth.
Depth is the length of the longest path
that ends at that vertex. So let's just
take that longest path.
Uh so this one has length
exactly depth of u. That's the
definition of depth.
It might be zero. Maybe the longest path
that ends at U. If U is a source, it's
just the path that starts at U and
doesn't do anything. But it's there is
this path.
All right. Now, my big idea is
concatenate these two paths because here
we have a path that ends at U and here
we have a path that starts at U and goes
to V. So, obvious thing to do is glue
them together. Uh, so let's concatenate
uh and I'll call this p subv is going to
be uh p sub u comma p subuv. So do
follow the path pu follow the path puv
and the length of this path.
So first of all it's a path because this
one ended at u and this one starts at u.
So you can actually concatenate them.
The length is just going to be the sum
of these two lengths.
So it's it starts with a depth of view
number of edges and then it has at least
one more. So the length is strictly
greater than depth of U because it's
just the sum of these two numbers.
Okay. Now what do I know about this
path? It is a path that ends at V.
PV ends at V, right? Because if you look
at the last vertex it visits, it's V. So
this is a path that ends at V and it's
its length is this greater than depth of
U. Now depth of V is the length of the
longest path that ends at V. And the
longest path is it greater than or equal
to any particular path. So I found a
path here. That means that uh the
longest path
is greater than or equal to this one.
And that's strictly greater than depth
of U.
And the length of the longest path here
is equal to depth of V.
So I've proved that depth of V is
strictly greater than depth of U because
I found a path that was longer than
depth of U. Therefore, depth of V is
greater than depth of U. Okay,
so
that's cool. Uh there's one last thing
to check here. So I I proved that this
is a schedule
that it it processes things in a valid
order. But we also need to check uh how
many time steps does it take?
Why is it the number of vertices in the
longest path and not the number of edges
for example?
Okay, the span
of depth
I claim is one plus uh the
number of
one plus the length
of longest path.
This is what I wanted to prove because
length counts edges. So if I add one
more, that's the number of vertices in
the path. And that's exactly what this
theorem says. Uh why? Uh because if you
look at all the possible depths, they
start at zero, right? All the sources
are going to get depth zero. Uh and they
go one, two, and so on. And I claim they
end at the length of the longest path.
Why? Because what are the depths? The
depths are the length of the longest
path ending at a particular vertex. And
we do this for all the vertices. And so
the maximum value this is going to take
on is just whatever the globally longest
path is. It ends anywhere. Okay? So
that's why we max out here. And it's
plus one because we started at zero and
we ended here. So we have one through
length of longest path. That's length of
longest path. But then we have a plus
one for zero.
Okay? So that proves this theorem and
tells us how to optimally schedule if we
have an infinite number of processors or
not infinite but enough that we could do
all the tasks at once if we wanted to.
Cool.
Let me
recast these results in a slightly
different form
that's interesting and we'll connect to
the next lecture.
So,
let me give a couple of terms that are
uh concept called partial order which
we'll talk about next time
and they let us think about these kinds
of precedence relations in a different
way. So in particular there's this idea
that okay uh left sock and left shoe
they're related. Left sock has to happen
before left shoe. Uh right shoe and
pants are also related. Right shoe has
to happen after pants. Also winter coat
has to happen after pants. But for
example pants and shirt are unrelated
either. They could happen in either
order. There's no path from pants to
shirt. There's no path from shirt to
pants. So let's define uh a notion of
comparable
meaning they are there is a precedence
relation between them in one direction
or the other.
So either U is reachable from V or V is
reachable from U. In either case, we
call U and V comparable and otherwise
they're not comparable. These are
vertices.
All right. So there's two complimentary
notions I want to define. Chain
is a set of
pair-wise
or mutually comparable
vertices.
And an anti-chain
is a set of pair-wise incomparable
vertices.
Okay, so we're thinking about sets of
vertices, subsets of the whole graph
that are either all mutually related
like they they have a defined sequence
for them or not. So for example,
uh where's my purple?
Need even more colors. Hopefully this
will still be clear. Uh so for example
if I take shirt
and jacket
and winter coat
these are three vertices and I claim
they form a chain because these two are
related. These two are related. These
two are related. All pairs of them are
related. And in fact they they have a
fixed order right? Shirt has to happen
before jacket. Jacket has to happen
before winter coat.
I happen to skip scarf but I could also
put scarf in. that would also that would
be a longer chain.
Okay, chains basically correspond to
paths except you can throw some of the
vertices away. So that's why I left a
blank line here. This is basically a
subset
of a path.
Every chain is going to be a subset of a
path. An anti-chain though is is sort of
the interesting new notion here. That's
going to be a set of vertices that are
mutually incomparable. For example, all
the sources
by definition, you can't reach any of
them for any other because you if you
start at a source, you can't get to any
sorry if you start outside you can never
get to a source. That's what I want to
say unless you started at that exact
source. So all the circled red vertices
for the sources are an anti-chain. So
are all the squared ones at the bottom.
Those are the syncs. There are four of
them. Those are form an anti-chain.
Okay. Now
I claim anti-chains are really what's
going on in the scheduling problem
in the sense that all the tasks that are
done at the same time must be an
anti-chain. So if you look at all the
things that happen at time zero those
are the sources those have to be an
anti-chain.
uh all the things done at time 53 also
have to be an anti-chain because if
there's any relation between them if one
of them had to precede another if there
was a path between two of the vertices
done at time I then that would be
invalid you're not allowed to do that if
two if things if u and v have a
reachability relationship they must be
done at different times okay so the
things you do at a particular time form
an anti-chain
and so by that exact theorem
We get this correlary.
Uh
Another
way to look at a schedule is it's
partitioning the vertices. The vertices
are all the tasks I have to do and into
the fewest number of anti-chains.
Anti-chain is a set of vertices I can do
at the same time.
So the number of steps I need the span
of that schedule is exactly the number
of anti-chains I need to cover all the
vertices to execute all the tasks. Okay,
this the theorem is this has the same
size as the size of the partition. And
the number of anti-chains you need
is uh the longest chain.
Okay, the proof is exactly you you apply
the schedule and then your anti-chains
are all the things I do at time zero,
that's one anti-chain. All the things I
do at time one, that's another
anti-chain. And so this is kind of a
neat connection between these are kind
of dual notions. one you want lots of
comparisons possible and the anti-chain
you want no comparisons possible
and this is saying that they're related
in that if I try to split into
anti-chains the number of anti-chains I
need to cover everything is equal to the
longest chain turns out the reverse is
also true the if I take if I want to
partition into the fewest chains
uh the number of chains I need is the
same as the longest anti-chain
kind of cool.
I guess this should technically be the
largest because it's a set.
Um, what else do I want to say?
You can use this to prove some fun facts
like uh
there's always a large chain or a large
anti-chain.
So for example for any t
either
there exists a chain
of length or of size
uh greater than t
or there exists an anti-chain
of size
at least n / t or size of vertices over
t.
Okay, this just follows from that
thinking about the partitions. If you if
you know that all the chains are small,
suppose all the chains have size at most
t then you know that the partition into
anti-chains
or sorry uh yeah one one way or the
other uh if I know all the chains are
small then I know I can partition into
anti-chains
uh with that number. So I can partition
into t anti-chains if all the chains
have length at most t. And that means
that uh the longest anti-chain has to be
at least v over t because all the
vertices get covered by the partition
and so the biggest one is going to be uh
bigger than the average. So you can use
it to do that. You can use it to do
other fun things like have you ever
wondered I don't know what your
calendar looks like but for me I have
lots of conflicting events. I have to be
in many places at the same time. It's
pretty annoying and partly because I
have many calendars all displayed in the
same place. And so, have you ever
wondered how do you display a calendar
like this? Well, for for one event that
appear that occurs strictly before
another, uh, I'll draw an edge.
Okay. So, uh, here's an edge there.
There's an edge there. Uh, some of these
have edges, some don't.
Then in particular if I look at two
conflicting events they will be
incomparable according to this
definition. There'll be no path from
this vertex to this vertex or this
vertex to that vertex.
And so what I'm looking at here is a
partition into chains. Each of these
chains has to be nicely ordered. And I
want to know how many different chains
do I need? Well, it turns out the answer
is exactly the size of the largest
anti-chain. In other words, the size of
the largest set of events that are
pair-wise conflicting, which is sort of
the best you could hope for, right? I
need exact I need at least one column
for each of these guys if they're all
conflicting with each other. And it
turns out you can always achieve that.
And that's how calendars draw their
events. All right, that's it.