With automation, AI and the global drive
for carbon reduction transforming
manufacturing, Hyram Saml sees capital
markets allocation remaining misaligned
with the sector's evolving needs. He
notes that the tension between
institutional investors preferences for
efficient asset light models and the
significant capital expenditures
required for transformative
manufacturing presents a substantial
challenge. He believes that engaging
capital markets early supported by
innovative business models, refined
narratives and industrial policy is
essential to mob mobilizing large
funding pools of capital that advanced
strategic priorities
require. Please welcome Hyram Samuel.
[Applause]
[Music]
Good
afternoon. So today I you know I'm
always I every time I come to an MIT
event I'm always impressed by my
colleagues because I learn so much and I
can't say I understand all of it. So,
um I thank you. I'm glad to hear that.
It makes me feel a whole lot better. Um
but I can say to you that I'm going to
talk to you today about money. Um and I
think money is something that we we all
understand. And and I have to say that I
came by this um honestly. And so I'm
looking out into the audience and I see
a bunch of you and and you know a lot of
you look to me to be mid-career. And so
actually actually I'm a second career
academic. I didn't go back to MIT to get
my PhD until I was 48. Um, and I I came
back for a variety of reasons, but a lot
of it was rooted in my own experience
and a lot of it was rooted in my
experience as an entrepreneur. And so,
uh, when I was young, I consolidated uh,
uh, industrial tool distributors,
considerably durable distributors, built
it up to a 200 billion, a $200 million
business. I I went broke doing that. I
spent five years paying the bank back.
Uh, I gave the bank my house, so I kind
of know the American entrepreneurship
story. Um, unfortunately, unlike some
folks in Europe, in the United States,
this is not a big deal. You can go and
do it again. Uh, I started a textile
manufacturing company. Uh, grew that to
what I would call mediumsiz, probably
uh, 200 people. Um, made that uh,
reasonably successful. Along the way,
owned a Dutch company, made hardwood
floors. um and came back at MIT and and
we have mid-career programs which I
encourage all of you to to look at. Um
and I participated in one called the
Sloan Fellows. It was part-time. I met a
lot of people in their 40s that were
doing interesting stuff and um I became
fascinated by the startup world and I
became a angel investor investing in
seed rounds. I've invested in about 12
companies. I can't say I've done great
but I have not done poorly. Uh I'm still
waiting for the home run. Um um but you
know there's always tomorrow. So that's
the way to think about that. But um this
sort of got me interested in in sort of
manufacturing because I love
manufacturing also in kind of American
manufacturing because I had seen the
decline of this as someone that supplied
many many companies. I we hear the
perennial Kodak punching bag story but
um I used to supply Kodak with all their
industrial and cutting tools. Um and so
when I came back to MIT um I found the
opportunity to work on a program
actually under Suzanne Burgerer that's
going to speak to you a little bit later
that's about production what's called
production in the innovation economy um
and I found this a fascinating topic for
me um because it dealt with how do young
companies scale up those that are
production based so if you think about a
productionbased company uh they have to
raise a lot of capital upfront this is
not like a digital model where you don't
have to raise so much money up front you
have to raise a lot of money up front.
And so we looked at this um and I did
this research as part of my my my uh
dissertation. Uh and we look and I
looked at this with Liz Reynolds uh was
my was was my co-author. Um Liz at the
time ran the Industrial Performance
Center which is what Ben does that Ben
does now. And Liz went on and actually
was in the Biden White House uh working
with the National Economic Council on
Advanced Manufacturing. Um and what we
found was of 250 manufacturing startups
and manufacturing based startups, the
majority of them went overseas. In other
words, they had gotten only to a certain
point. Um and then they kind of couldn't
raise enough capital, but there was
plenty of capital primarily in East Asia
where they went to build a pilot plant
and quite frankly that's where the
capabilities went. That's where the
learning went and so this sort of raised
a kind of red flag to us. I then went to
Oxford for my first academic job and um
found a similar problem and convinced
some colleagues that were in the finance
department to take a look at it and they
also teamed up with some people at
Cambridge uh and Barclays actually
financed this. Not only did they find
this was a problem for British
manufacturing production based startups
but quite frankly for all British
startups. Uh there just wasn't a whole
lot of risk capital. The pools were
really full of of of state capital. sort
of government money uh and they needed
that. Um and so I went to Oxford. I
ended up working on a whole bunch of
other stuff at Oxford. I came back to
MIT worked on a variety of stuff. I
generally do uh global strategy for
example. Um and then I sort of read this
uh you know sort of you might have seen
this report last year sort of again the
scaleup gap just never seems to go away.
It's always a a chronic problem. And so
uh when we were talking about this
conference I said this gives me an
opportunity to kind of go and do some
preliminary research how to think about
this and this comes up to raise this
problem. What is the missing middle?
Everyone's talking about the missing
middle when it comes to scaleup
financing for what we'll call deep tech
or manufacturing of basically capital
intensive companies. Um but what does it
actually mean? So let me just try to
explain it to you quickly. Um and so I
put three curves up at once but you can
imagine this. you develop a technology
um and if you just look in the y- axis
that's the investment that you've got to
make um and you start to do a little bit
of research and then you kind of get
excited you go okay we actually got to
produce this and then you kind of say
okay where am I going to get money to do
this oftentimes you've spun it out of a
university and then you kind of get you
need to raise more money um and then
slowly you'll start to commercially
expand this is in a perfect world now if
you look at the blue curve you have two
other things you need to do in One thing
that we haven't really talked a lot
about yet today is customers. What is
the demand for this product going to be
um and that's a very very important
aspect to understanding business as it's
conducted today. So you have a market
point curve and that's basically you
need to get the cost of your technology
down to where a customer is willing to
pay for it. Right? This is always the
battle between a new startup and a
company is getting willingness to pay.
Um, as all of you know, because I'm sure
all of you participate in this
environment, um, oftentimes companies
give this stuff away for free, right? Or
your $ five dollar Uber ride to the
airport in the United States is now
$57. Um, because they got to pay back
the $30 billion that they raised uh, and
have a better market position. And so
what happens here is as you get to a
point where people people were willing
to pay for it, you start to get an
adoption curve. And then at some point
you get to scale and you pay back your
investors. And so what we found happens
with scale up is oftentimes that period
of time is just too long. The venture
fund is closed. They run a five to
sevenyear cycle or even if they run a
seven or eight year cycle, they're only
in it for about five years. Um and they
close. And so this creates this problem.
Uh and this is kind of the missing
middle. So, this happens to be an
example for an energy technology where
essentially, if you think about this,
you've done the research, you've done
the innovation, um you've gone, you've
got your angel investors, you've got
your venture capital, and then you need
to go and raise another hundred million
dollars because you got to build a pilot
plant. And that becomes a challenge. Um,
and oftentimes people that have done
this, okay, you've derisked the
technology, but you've not d-risked it
enough to go to what we'll call capital
markets and particularly to if you want
to then do some sort of special special
purpose vehicle to finance this thing,
if you're doing a power generation, for
example. And so this is the missing
middle. And so we're going to talk about
this a little bit. Um, and the way that
you want to think about this often is is
there's different types of capital. And
I know this is sort of colorful, but
hopefully you can match them up. Um but
essentially if you're investing capital
you have have a high risk and you have
low risk and my assumption is everyone
in Austria you guys are all high-risisk
investors right and when I think of
Austria I think of high risk so um so
you know low risk is is you know you can
think of Norway's sovereign capital fund
uh relatively low risk but you can also
think of Abu Dhabi's sovereign small
fund and that's high risk right
investing in AI investing in a variety
of things and so Um, we're not going to
spend too much time on this, but
different countries have different
growth models, and those growth models
determine oftentimes investor
preferences, whether you realize it or
not, whether they're conscious or
unconscious. Um, this is very much true
in Europe. And then you have kind of
institutional money. This might be uh
passive money, money you put into
exchange traded funds, for example,
pension funds. Um, and then you have
kind of capital markets. That's
institutional. Could be retail
investors. I'm sure all of you are
follow following Wall Street Bets on
Reddit now. Um, and then policy driven
capital where the state then inserts
money and it's oftentimes median risk.
And then you might say, what is
production capital? Production capital
is where a company risks its own
capital. I have retained earnings. I'm
going to put my capital into it. Um,
that's often cyclical in manufacturing.
So, it's a kind of a higher risk
capital. Um, and then we have venture
capital or hedge funds that are sort of
speculative capital. And then we're not
going to talk too much about debt today,
but tomorrow in my workshop, we'll talk
a little bit more about hybrid
instruments. And so these give these are
stylized what I'm going to call stylized
capital stacks if you look at them. Um,
and I've got one for the US and I've got
one for the EU. But essentially what
happens is is is there's government
funded research that will go to
institutes like MIT for example.
Needless to say that's now changing in
the Trump era. Um, but that's very very
important to develop to to develop new
startups. I'm not sure the government
understands that. Um and then
essentially essentially uh venture
capital will come in oftentimes at
places like MIT venture capitalists walk
around labs looking for very young
inventors looking for things to do and
trying to find them early um and they'll
go and fund stuff and then what will
happen is oftentimes if they have
something promising um financial capital
will come in this might be mutual fund
companies things that are going to go
preIPO will come in and and do something
and then you're off and you're running
and you've got more you've got
institutional money you've got passive
money uh and you've got your own
production capital invested uh in the
EU. Uh if we look at the difference, one
thing that I want you to notice now is
the big basically the big red. That's
the important factor is the state never
leaves the capital stack in Europe. And
I'm going to show you a little bit later
about their European Investment Bank and
the European Investment B. You guys
just, you know, look, I'm wearing a
sweater. Take your jackets off, loosen
up. I'm going to try and convince you to
invest some money in manufacturing by
the time I'm done. So, it's important,
but because basically the problem in
Europe is is you just you're just too
riskaverse, right? There's not enough
money flowing into the sector. And what
I'm going to try to convince you is that
oftentimes people look to the state for
this problem, but the state can't offer
all the de-risking solution. You need
the competition that the marketplace
provides. You need the governance that
the marketplace provides. Um, and really
what manufacturing suffers from is part
of it's its own problem. It's actually
much more capital efficient than people
realize. It's an incredibly profitable.
I'm going to show that to you now. Um,
and that this kind of public investor
undervaluation drives capital market
behavior. It drives the capital market
behavior of manufacturers. Um, and takes
them away and out of the innovation
space. And and Ben talked a little bit
about Anderil. Um, and so you if you
have to understand the Silicon Valley
speak of today. So we we used to talk
about capital structure, now it's
capital stack. If you were vertically
integrated, now you're a full stack
company. But essentially essentially if
you get the language of Silicon Valley,
you can actually drive the multiples on
your company higher. You you need to
have a narrative. You need to have a
business model. Um and basically the
state can't be that. So I'm going to do
that very simply is I'm going to ask you
guys to make one investment decision.
I'm going to give you limited
information because that's what
investors face is limited information.
Uh, I'm going to talk to you a little
bit about the irony of capitalism
without capital. Um, and then I'm going
to try to argue close up by just
suggesting that productive speculation
is is necessary. I'm going to show you
that there is a lot of capital in just a
very few companies that I'm showing you.
And so much more than governments are
much more willing to play into this.
Okay. So, we're going to play the game
cash and control. You guys, it's your
lucky day. You've had lunch. You're
tired. But your wealthy aunt Edna who
passed away 10 years ago unbeknownst to
you was a very very good investor and
aunt Edna owned two companies. She owned
company A and company B. Now company A
has returned to her estate right now um
$ 32 billion. She was pretty wealthy on
Adenova, isn't she? It's returned $ 32
billion. Company B returned nothing for
the first seven years and then returned
15.7 billion dollars in the last two
years. Okay. Company A was very diligent
about their shares. They didn't issue
any new shares or if they issued new
shares, they bought them back. Um and on
and still owns 100% of it. Uh company B
um diluted their shares to the tune of
48%. So you actually still control. you
own about 67% of it, but uh it diluted
their shares about about 48%. Okay, I'm
going to sum it up for you on this slide
before I ask you to vote. Okay, company
A, 32 billion in return. Pretty nice.
Company B, not so bad. 15.7 billion.
Company A, you still own 100%
of Company B 48%. Now, I want you to
view this as if you're well actually 67%
but 48% diluted. So, if you I want you
to think about this as your own private
investment. Now, which one would you
rather have? Company A. All those would
rather have company A, raise your
hand. One
hand. Really? You gota you got to vote.
Okay. So, company A 32 million. Thank
you very much, Bruce, because you got
everyone behind you. Okay. And company
B. So, actually more people voting
company B. So, what why would you vote
company B?
slope is the slope looks a little bit
steeper, right? But you've waited 10
years to get that, right? So, I mean,
you didn't you missed all that return
beforehand. So, what's interesting is,
you know, you're correct if you voted
for company B. Company B has a market
cap of $285 billion. Uh, company A has a
market cap of $131 billion. Company B
trades at a price to earnings multiple
of 47. Company A trades at a price to
earnings multiple of of 21. Um, company
B is a company you may know, Salesforce.
Uh, company A is a company you may also
know, John Deere, right? Two very, very
good companies. Salesforce is a very
good company and John Deere is a very
good company. Let's take a closer look
at them, though. Okay, so the riskreward
ratio and the willingness of of of
investors to invest in companies on the
as kind of uh our colleague pointed out
is is that the steeper curve comes at
the tail end. um has got people
investing in this. I'm going to explain
this a little bit further to you, but it
gives companies more financing tools.
And so if you look at Salesforce,
Salesforce trades at a much higher
multiple than almost any manufacturing
companies. There are companies like
Danner Herur and and Haiko that trade at
high multiples. I'll talk about that
more tomorrow. It gives them capital
tools that you do not have as a
manufacturer. At least capital tools
that you don't use, you're afraid to use
as a manufacturer. So if you were to
look at this chart over here, I want you
to look at the bottom chart. So it says
additional paid in capital. Um that's
called we call that APEC. Um it has a
APE of 53 billion. That means that you
during those 10 years of
time received 53 billion of additional
paid capital just in those 10 years time
you got 53 billion investors said I
believe in you. I believe in you. I'm
going to get my return someday. Here's
another 53 billion.
Now during that whole period of time you
reported a free cash flow of about $ 37
billion but by the way 21 billion of
that is we're going to call stockbased
compensation. So that's essentially
where I go I'm going to pay you guys but
you know what I want to keep the cash.
So I'm going to come over here and sell
it to you. You guys willing to buy you
going to fund my employees because I
don't want to lose my employees. They're
very high value. I need to do this. And
so every year Salesforce goes and issues
stock to usually restricted stock units.
They vest. Employees go and sell that
stock into the capital market. Um and
Salesforce gets to keep the cash. So
basically Salesforce keeps this cash,
reports it as free cash flow. It has a
high multiple. It then goes and buys
companies for stock. Uh you can think of
Slack, Tableau, for example, Muleoft
companies that that that that Salesforce
bought. And Salesforce said, "I'm
getting a little nervous because no
one's got any money back until the last
two years. I better start returning some
money." They returned $15 billion. So,
you've given them $55 billion and you've
gotten back $15 billion. Um, and you've
paid their employees effectively $22
billion. Let's take a look at Deer. John
Deere is a much more typical what I
would call manufacturer. Um, it
generates a lot of cash, a whole lot
more than Salesforce, $51 billion. Um,
it made some small acquisitions, maybe
it made some acquisitions. It made $6
billion worth of acquisitions in in in
uh cash. Uh, issued no additional stock
or maybe some small additional stock,
which it then purchased. Um, but then
returned $10 billion in dividends and
$21 billion in in uh um stock buybacks.
So here you have two completely
different models. John Deere is paying
you back and Salesforce is taking your
money. So if we were to kind of think
about this and look at
this, John Deere, which trades at a much
lower multiple, almost half of what
Salesforce does, actually has grown its
business nicely, reasonably nicely, uh,
of all the last year. It is a cyclical
business. So you can see that in the top
line, that's the top solid line. The
dotted line is their equity. They've
grown their equity, too. um but not
quite to the same level as their
revenue. Salesforce on the other hand
has grown their revenue relatively well
um but has really bumped up their
equity. So this is a company now that
you think of as being capital light
because that's what you're trained to
think of when you think of software as a
service. It's actually capital intense.
It has Salesforce has over $60 billion
in stockholders equity. Um so it's used
a whole lot of money to do this. So I
got curious by this and I said, "Wow, is
this just these companies or is this
kind of an industry thing? How do you
how do you think about this?" So I went
and I looked at software as a service. I
just took 10 companies. Um HubSpot,
Brian Howigan and Dharmash were two of
my classmates when I was at MIT have
built a tremendous tremendous business.
Um and these are probably some brands
that you may indeed use. Palunteer that
uh Ben had talked about earlier um that
you would use. And I said, "Okay, let's
see how these companies have performed
over the last 10 years." Um, what do we
find? Okay, so basically, uh, their
additional paid in capital was
equivalent to Salesforce about $55
billion. Uh, their retained earnings is
really, uh, negative, $15 billion. Um,
so that's kind of almost the difference
between the capital increase and the and
the negative retained earnings. Um, the
revenue is pretty impressive, $40
billion.
um uh the cumulative net loss $10
billion. Um and it's free cash flow $35
billion. And this is what you'll see if
you're pitched on a SAS company as an
investment is the free cash flow of $35
billion. But by the way, all of that $35
billion plus more only shows up because
they paid it to their to their employees
and the capital markets brought that
back. So in other words, all $ 35
billion of capital that has flowed into
cash, I'm not going to say capital, cash
in capital that has flowed into SAS
companies has come through stockbased
compensation. This is a pretty nifty
tool. I'm not going to say that they're
fleecing your pocket um because these
companies are indeed very valuable. What
I want to show you is there's a lot of
tricks that you can do if you do this.
These are pretty good companies. Now
let's look at some manufacturing
companies. I took 10 manufacturing
companies. You may you may indeed uh
know them. I'm going to talk about Haiko
tomorrow. Um not surprisingly, the
market cap of these is almost twice as
high. Not quite. It's about 60%. Um the
revenue of the manufacturing companies
is is obviously higher than SAS. Um wow.
Those manufacturing companies between
the 10 of them have had a net income of
$122 billion.
Um the manufacturing company, the SAS
companies cumulative net loss of $10
billion. That seems kind of odd. They've
made 122 billion, but they have kind of
almost half the market cap. Um retained
earnings, the same thing. That was what
you would expect would follow from that.
Less redemptions. Um the total
stockbased compensation $35 billion in
in uh uh for uh SAS for manufacturers
six mill six billion. So quite a bit
lower. they are using it as a tool. Um
the cash that came back to shareholders
for manufacturers $85 billion. They
returned almost 60 69% of their cash
back to shareholders. And so now you
start to see two diverging capital
schemes. And this is where my argument
is about capital allocation.
Essentially, if you look at this, I'll
give it I'll sum it up for you on the
next slide, too. Essentially is is
manufacturers feel obligated, I guess,
to maintain their stock price. I'm not
quite 100% sure to return $85 billion to
shareholders. SAS companies because they
traded higher multiples are happy to
just take another $55 billion from
capital investors to put it in. This is
a huge amount of money and as you'll see
compared to what was invested in
manufacturing advanced manufacturing
small amount and so if you look at this
okay so they did raise some capital
manufacturers but you can see the
capital c cash return to cash return to
shareholders was quite low right $85
billion okay how do we think about this
so some of you might have seen this book
it's a well-known book I encourage you
to read it was written about 10 years
ago um by two British economists um but
essentially
SAS's model in con in concept is
capitalism of all capital. In other
words, you as a company can put your IT
in a crowd. You keep your assets light.
We can keep our assets light. We can
outsource we can outsource uh uh data
centers. We can outsource a variety of
things. We're just going to invest money
in in in our software. Turns out they
invest a lot of money in maintaining
their customer base, right? They spend a
ton of money on sales and marketing. um
their their argument at least from a
business school person would be is
they're renting their competitive
advantages. They're not really
leveraging. They have no pricing power.
At least the pricing power to me is not
that evident that they're able to
extract rent from the market. And this
is even after 10 years. Manufacturers
much more capital efficient. Stockbased
compensation is a great tool. It's also
a hidden capital. It's a way for you to
raise money. It also raises questions
though about how much you actually use
as of your revenue. Um, and there's a
big time horizon mismatch. Why is it
that manufacturers get penalized um, for
not returning cash to them when when in
essence SAS companies get 10 years of a
free ride to do that in the hopes that
you're going to make some of your money
back. I'm not going to say that. I'm not
trying to say that SAS is a bad
investment. What I'm trying to say to
you is there's a lot of money out there
that can be reallocated and that the
capital intensity of SAS, not only does
it approach manufacturing, it exceeds
it. Right? these companies have very
very capital intents. It's just that
they raise that capital in means that
are not so transparent um to an ordinary
investor to look at. Um and all of this
is reinforced by passive institutional
money at least in the United States
where you have cap weighted ETFs that
support the price of these because as
they go up in value they have a larger
share of the ETF and so they're
constantly buying stock. Now that may
also suffer on the way down. Um so how
can we explain this? So in the United
States the way that we had expansion was
not only through not only through
government surplus government stimulus
but primarily through quantitative
easing. This is a federal reserve that
increased their balance sheet from about
4 trillion to 9 trillion uh during COVID
and afterwards. And you can see that's
the NASDAQ 100 that sort of mirrors that
growth. Uh we haven't quite seen the lag
yet. We started to see a little bit of
that. I'm not telling you to short the
NASDAQ 100, but um we we haven't seen
that come back down again yet, but that
sort of really this quantitative
tightening on the Fed. They got to
figure out what they're going to do.
This has given rise to this. You might
have seen this graphic from the FT. Um
the US capital markets now account for
the majority of the world. As a matter
of fact, information technology sector
in the US markets is now larger than
pretty much the Asian and European
capital markets in total. Um the
industrial sector is not small though,
but it's uh it's small by US standards.
And so when people say there's not
enough money out there, and there's
definitely money, the trick is to get
the money where we'd like to see it go.
That's that's really the trick. And so
why is this not happening? So venture
capital is actually quite significant in
in the United States. It's also quite
significant in Europe. Uh venture
capital in in Europe is now for got
about $426 billion in assets is
invested. uh the US it's over a trillion
a trillion two um but when it comes to
manufacturing and I'm not going to say I
have everyone in here these are
pitchbook numbers um there's not a whole
lot of money that's going into it if you
look at this in the United States
advanced manufacturing um and this is
venture growth so this will be the
equivalent of scale up um last year
total in 2023 the last year I have
numbers is about $6 billion the total of
all these six years here is about $ 31
billion um lots of companies are getting
invested A lot of companies are getting
seated over 400 for example. But where
the problems start to come is with the
exits. And so when you have when you
sell a company into a public market
where multiples are low, there's not a
lot of appetite for investors to invest
in these. The only exception in the US
are defense stocks, right? Just as we
might see Rin Metal and we've seen
German defense stocks increase quite a
bit in value over the last three or four
weeks. um you need this kind of
speculation to drive to pull capital
into the market. Um and this hasn't
happened. There was one exception in
2021. Um and even that's relatively
small by standard. And so you now have
venture capital kind of looking for an
exit, can't find the exit. The exits are
pretty much through
acquisitions. Um and then you have the
large role that private equity plays.
And I know private equity is playing a
bigger role in European middle
companies, companies, families want to
sell a business. Um, and so their their
their investment activity in industrials
has gone down at least in the United
States. But the most important thing for
you to look at is and this sort of
speaks to the a little bit the
pathologies of private equity um is
close to 50% of the exits are to another
private equity company. In other words,
they can't sell them. they can't sell
them because they're not performing or
they can't sell them because they need
to create they they want to raise
liquidity for their own investors. Uh
they're now doing what are called de
dividend recapitalizations. Dividend
recapitalizations are when I go and
borrow money and use that money to pay
back my investors and I load the I load
the company with more debt. Uh very few
public listings as you can see and the
rest of them are corporate acquisitions.
And this creates a path. This creates a
a problem because if you if you if you
have this kind of behavior where you
start to add debt to your balance sheet,
how much you going to invest in research
and development? How much are you going
to invest in robotics? How much are you
going to invest in automation? And so we
have this sort of perverse problem where
venture capital is one place, private
equity is another, capital markets are
kind of left out of the game completely.
Um, and so then what you have is the
dialogue then turns to this, which is we
need the government to basically come in
and fund us. We need the government to
do this. The Biden administration did
this in a big way with the chips and
Iraq. Um, I don't think Trump is going
to do this again. Uh, certainly he's if
anything tried to claw back some of it.
Um, for those of you that don't know
venture capital, and my guess is there
probably people here that know it better
than I do. Um, you know, it's a game.
It's a portfolio game and you really do
need the you need the 50 to 100x return
to basically make the rest of your
portfolio. You don't have a lot of
information. Um and so companies
oftentimes will look for that and the
only way you get that big return is by
going public. You don't get that by
staying private. Um, and so when you
start to look at newer technologies, you
can see that I know the the the the font
is quite small here, but you know, you
start to see fusion hypersonic aircraft
coming all the way down to kind of as
we're doing now, generative AI, new
chips, whatever. Um, this is a just sort
of a a US belief that government has to
kind of fund this research. It needs to
fund the research. It needs to guarantee
loans. It needs to it needs to provide
government contracts. Um this is no
different than the uh EU. Uh this is
from that document I showed you before
at the beginning. Um interesting enough
is that even as you get to a mature fund
then European investment bank is staying
invested. They stay invested throughout
the whole process. Look if I had a
business I would take don't don't get me
wrong I would take that money. Uh but my
point to you is is that there's plenty
of private capital out there. We just
have to unleash it. We need to we need
to invest that. And so one thing I want
to show you before I end is I want to
just sort of take you show take you
through what Tesla um did and whatever
you may think of Elon Musk or anything
else. Um I will say that the way that
they financed the business was
incredibly interesting. And so one of
the things I want you to notice is is
that the blue is what I call a
traditional funding. So that's equity
and debt. And really until 2020 Tesla
didn't really have a big public equity
raise. uh they raised small amounts
periodically in the markets but 44% of
their of their funding was what I'm
going to call non-traditional so they
took advantage of government programs
but that were those government programs
were available to everybody else but
they were tradable zero emission vehicle
credits from the state of California
generated about $4 billion in revenue
for Tesla when they needed it I'm going
to show you a heat map for that
strategic investors Tesla I mean uh
Toyota Dler came in very early to to to
Tesla to give them a little bit money
when they needed it. Um, and then
government programs came in to help
round that out. And then as they they
started to have some traction with with
public stock prices, they ended up using
stockbased compensation. And so if you
to look at heat mapap, I'm not going to
say that you can read this. I know it's
very small, but I find it interesting if
you go back to its early years, you see
the money is all coming from venture
capital here. Uh, they they go public in
2010. Um, and then all of a sudden they
get a grant for $465 million. They start
to get they start to get some ZEV
credits as you kind of move through that
period when they couldn't raise a lot of
capital. And so companies that do this,
they need to piece this together. So in
many ways, governments need to work not
necessarily at odds with this, but with
companies. And one thing that people
need to realize is that when you get
venture capital, venture capital are
your best friend until they're not. um
because their goals are different than
yours as a company that as an
entrepreneur that starts a company. You
want to keep the company going. Venture
capital is going to exit as soon as they
can get a price that makes sense for
them to do that. That's what their job
is. Um I want to just put this up. I
thought this was kind of funny is only
the United States gets politicized about
everything. The reason Tesla doesn't pay
income taxes is because Elon Musk
company profits from green energy tax
breaks passed by the Democrats.
Actually, that's not true at all. As a
matter of fact, those green energy tax
breaks are the ones that generated the
capital for Tesla to actually keep
going. Um Tesla doesn't pay tax because
it has a net operating loss carry
forward. It just hasn't made enough
money to offset its losses that it has.
But only in the Wall Street Journal can
you get the political take on that on
that kind of uh on that kind of picture.
Um and then just to leave you, this was
just Stuart Kirk that wrote in the FT a
couple I don't know maybe a week ago or
two weeks ago and I'm going to talk to
you my European colleagues. It's been a
valuation game so far. This is the way
manufacturing companies have behaved.
It's time for companies to invest big.
Um, and I'll give you a statistic of
that in a second. And then to our
American colleagues, what one thing I
does concern me is a lot of the capital
going into the defense sector. There's
nothing wrong with that. Uh, it's good
that it's doing that. Uh, but we need to
get more money into more broad-based uh,
uh, uh, manufacturing like Chris's
biommanufacturing. Uh, and we need more
talent going in there. And so we need
more capital. that's actually all within
us and sort of just in a very simple
mind exercise rather than in if
institutions didn't invest $35 billion
in SAS out of their 770 market cap and
uh manufacturing companies didn't return
35 billion out of the 102 billion they
returned to shareholders but rather
invested it in startups we got $70
billion of capital that's already two
and a half almost two and a half times
what VCs invested in manufacturing over
a six-year period this is just 20
companies. There is a lot of capital out
there. We just need to find a way to get
it reallocated. A lot of that might be
education. A lot of it might be people
understanding that um and that public
investors need to move to reallocate
capital driven by political shifts.
These are strategic sectors. Now,
manufacturing, we'll start to see some
we'll start to see some rotation of
capital into that. Uh and then tomorrow
in my workshop I'll talk about uh sort
of business models, ways that you can
get multiple we call multiples
expansion, ways that you can improve the
way your business is. Um the state can
step in but it needs to act as a
partner. It can't crowd out competition.
Um and then the incumbent publics need
to believe in themselves. This is not
only in the United States but the EU.
They need to invest more money in
growth. They need to be return worry
less about returning stock to
shareholders and more about about
growing. Uh and in the EU, I see no one
took your jacket off. You guys just got
to take on some more risk. I don't know
how else to say it. Um I learned this in
the UK. Investors are very very
riskaverse here. And while the state can
act as your partner, you need to step
up. Um and that the stock 600 is is very
successful, but it returned 60% of its
of of its earnings to shareholders. And
it shouldn't have to do that. They need
to invest in growth. Okay. Thank you
very much.
All
right. Well, we have I think uh an
opportunity for some questions. Here we
go. Is the flow of talent into defense
startups not also a reflection of a lack
of risk appetite as ultimately the
customer is the state? Yeah, absolutely.
I mean that's 100% correct. I mean is is
a I mean the state you're assuming the
government's going to derisk all of that
capital by being the customer. I mean
that's the premise that I mean DARPA
which is that great US innovation thing
that was part of the department of
defense uh was very much about a a way
not only did it kind of seed a lot of
startups but it often would bring an
implicit customer that is a government
to you. Um the problem is you don't want
you don't want Anderil and Palunteer and
all these companies that have very high
private market value. challenges public
but private market valuations to suck up
all the talent uh to do that.
So I'm going to say thank you because
we're I think we have a chance for just
one more question. Uh what role should
industrial policy play in de-risisking
investments and incentivizing long-term
commitment from private capital? Uh
that's a great question and uh I'm not
sure I can give you a 100% answer for
that but I would say that um I mean in
the United States we see this now with
with the change in indirect funding for
NIH grants. Um the government needs to
fund basic research. It is it is
absolutely vital to certainly the United
States and I would argue to to Europe.
Um and I think that for for for sort of
further along scale up uh government
needs to to offer credits for example to
get private investors to stay to to stay
in there. And and I don't you know it's
kind of like you know the old the old
saw is is that markets will stay
irrational longer than I can stay in
solvent. So I mean I think that that's
probably a truth. I can't necessarily
talk down markets but I think Scott Bent
is trying to talk down markets quite
frankly. I think he's made that
statement a few times. Um, and I think
that the government can act a very
strong way to at least if anything as a
orchestrator of this and needless to say
some tax policies or even some uh even
some governmentbacked loans would become
very helpful. I know a colleague Andy
Low is working on tranched investments
that would solve that part of that
problem but we just need to get more
money into it. Well, thank you Hyram
Samo.