you've seen that there's more technical
problems than a standard class and that
means you're in the right place if
you're here for a computational class
right um this is 21m 383 computational
music theory and Analysis or I can't
remember if I call it analysis and
Theory don't hold it against me um I'm
Michael Cuthbert I'm the professor of
the class I'm a professor of Music in
music and Theater Arts and um do some
work with computational analysis so what
I want to start with oh and just that's
who I am I'm going to get to know who
you guys are on Friday and next
Wednesday um it's very important to me I
want to really quickly be able to learn
Everybody by name but on the first class
I think you're all here to figure out if
this is the place you want to be before
we get to know everybody else so that's
why I'm not going to be going around and
asking everybody today but I'm going to
I really want to know that soon so the
big question for this class the whole
semester is going to be how do computers
hear
music what does that even mean um I'm
going to give you an answer if you care
about answers like this that you can uh
read absorb pack up and go home and uh
uh you no need for this class if this is
satisfactory computers hear music by
using a microphone connected to an
analog to digital converter connected to
a microprocessor where then specialized
codec I can never remember what that
really means um to quantize the sound
into a wave file or AAC or something
else file that we store on a magnetic or
solid state disc or we store on the
cloud and store on somebody else's
magnetic solid state disc right um not a
very very useful um answer so what I
think we more want to know is the
computers are hearing music but are they
actually
listening and U these two terms hear
versus listen uh in different contexts
one of them has higher priority than the
other and implies a more deep um deep
understanding like um you know Mom or
Dad ever tell you I know you heard me
but did you listen to me right we have
that kind of distinction built in so we
want to know is um when computers hear
music what kinds of understanding might
they have might might um might be
encoded in that as if you feel
uncomfortable with the notion of
computers you know having their own
autonomy or something like that and
um the only reason I really care about
this question is that by understanding
how how a computer hears it might change
how we hear or it might open up new
pieces for us to listen to that we
didn't already know and most importantly
it might answer questions about what
it's like for us to be humans any
Androids here okay uh what it's like for
us to be humans who are listening to
music so here are any six big unknowns
for me that I want to know the answer to
I'll just say uh you turn in on Friday
the correct answer to any of these six
questions you get an A+ and you don't
have to take the class but I don't know
them so why do we listen to music I why
kind of you know we don't go around all
day you know I have my um different
scents that I smell all day or it's I we
don't you know there all kinds of things
that are enjoyable but that seem to be
different that we don't do all day long
nowadays um why do people choose what
musical styles they like how does your
musical tastes or our whole culture's
musical taste change over time and some
of us will be from different cultures
and have different musical tastes what's
the difference between a great piece of
music and a mediocre or a bad one or do
those terms even really exist um what
makes a piece of music beautiful or
ugly and let's not forget about the
physical why do I want to dance or move
move when I hear some music and other
ones I just want to sit and cry um so
these are the questions that if you
answer them I mean that would just be
astounding I think however that a one
semester twice a week um U you know
class we're not going to get the
defintive answer to them so I like to
break these questions into slightly
smaller unknowns that helped to answer
these questions and that we might be
able to start making progress
on um what particular musical
characteristics distinguish a folk song
from one part of the world from one in
another how does the look of a band its
costume age its racial composition
affect the makeup of the audience I mean
you you know I'm not about to be a heavy
metal star the way I'm currently dressed
right what what does that mean maybe
maybe I'm okay at the piano um I'm
actually better at metal than the Pian
you'll hear but that's okay I'm pretty
bad at at both um what sorts of cord
are used for relaxation for rest for
stop in music today and how is this
different in different centuries or
different parts of the world um and what
do the lyrics of top selling songs have
in common with those of worst selling
songs or don't have in common um and you
know the that's a question that um you
know I know that there are people at the
big record labels trying to answer that
um because there's money
involved what rhythms or instruments a
company texts about sadness or death
that appear less often in moments of
Happiness right that's kind of related
to the why does some music make me cry
so on so five good questions that might
help us answer a big
unknown what I'm going to do is I'm
going to leave three up and take two
off and say that these three questions
in particular musical characteristics
distinguishing X from y chords used at
certain points and change over time
rhythms about and connections to emotion
these all might be questions that having
a representation of a musical score
whether it's more modern with
handwritten ancient these are questions
that might help
answer so let's just kind of recap what
are some of the things the computer's
good at with
music I mean kind of old slides you'll
see it's pretty out but that we you know
we make a lot of music with computer we
mix it we um you know we we sort of uh
do re-editing with
it computers are absolutely changed how
we distribute music how we get it how we
access it um and then very cool you know
apps and algorithms developed at places
like this can tell you know what kind of
what song particularly is some drunken
jerk singing in a bar
that's me um
but but until about the last decade and
a half uh little had changed since the
70s and 80s in how computers could be
used to analyze scores um and so things
are changing now but let me say you know
where things were um what what people
already had for let's say text that's
that's different from
music so if you load a text you know
we're all Compu Geeks at least to a
little bit is I consider that as a term
of endearment for myself but hope that's
okay we're all computer people and um
you know so we can look at a a I can use
the term string right we can look at a
string of text like this and you can ask
various um algorithms already exist in
any programming language to be able to
identify the spaces right split or
what's a foreign diacritic cast it to
aski and see what crash is um what's
punctuation and then if you have uh you
know some kind of font rendering you'll
know what's going below the line and so
on what's a capital letter all these
things and this level of lowl
information about text really helped to
build the next level of information
about text sentence diagramming
understanding from letters to a sentence
level understanding and this kind of
builtup knowledge has helped to make to
the next level which we might be arguing
today about whether or not there there
is an actual meaning involved I'm hungry
I'm spam um so can we build these
Technologies for musical scores
maybe maybe but not yet today so this is
a class that I hope people five six 7 10
years from now hopefully less hopefully
not 30 50 um that what you do in this
class will help get to that level of of
understanding um I think put it
somewhere um this is a unique really
unique class um I think that there's
about three other classes that are
something like computational music
theory uh offered in the world today the
other ones are all doctoral seminars or
graduate
seminars this is a class that because of
mit's unique ability to merge the Arts
and programming a deep knowledge of
music and and a great culture of
collaboration in um in solving problems
we can do this at the undergraduate
level and if you're a graduate student
we can do even more uh with yall on that
so what are some of the Technologies we
need to build um well here's some simple
things that a computer has to know to do
anything with scores start off with
DFG what's the next
note
a not H right not even the Germans who
have H would would go on from that so
you need to know about these cyclic
little things um take a look at this
next
slide yeah okay we got some squirmers in
the room right right that 3 four this
does not compute um so we need to have
an idea of meter and things and then
from there building up you know which of
these two scores is more consonant and
which is more dissonant
so we need a concept of consonants
dissonance and how to bring this with
score so we're going to need to step
back from some of even the middle siize
questions and go to even smaller things
so for instance let's say this is the um
chovsky uh 1812 Overture and let's see
if um we wanted to understand how the
key relations work how we move from one
uh key to another and how this builds up
the form and the tension and the power
of the piece well in order to do this we
need to know where all the key changes
are right so we have to be able to cut
the score into smaller pieces and
identify that now how might you identify
a key change well you might say Well it
starts off with a Cadence in one key and
then it ends in a Cadence in another key
oh so now we need to be able to identify
cadences so we need something that can
do that well well this chord moves and
you know five moves to one so that's a
particular type of cadence
that term when I say five moves to one
are people hearing Roman numerals in
your head and visualizing it uh these
are the levels of musical knowledge that
we're going to be using a lot here and
so in order to figure out if a chord is
a five chord or one chord or what's in
the chord at all if it's major or minor
we need a representation of chords and
notes and pitches so some of what we're
going to be doing at the beginning of
the class is recreating some of these
tools and then we'll see what other
people have done and go further from
that so the notion that um that we don't
have all these things is kind of
surprising because there's a lot of
money a lot of work that's been out
there taking some sort of representation
musical score whether notation or midi
or something like that some sort of a
score and playing it really nicely on
speakers and things like that gr all
those things or um if you've used not
flight finale sellus Doro something that
flat IO you know that we can take a
representation of notes and turn them
into some sort of musical score so I
think of that as kind of output uh it's
like a printer and then um a lot of uh
work especially in research Labs on
taking sound in and converting it into
that kind of digital representation
that's useful for search things but once
you have a digital representation of a
score already in your computer what do
you do with it how do you analyze it how
do you work with it and there's been a
lot less research on this so it's like
we've been spending all our time
building printers and I don't know how
do we get things in Scanners and much
much less time building our actual CPUs
nobody has a CPU that looks like that
anymore time to update your slides Prof
um okay so one of the things that um
we're going to be using a lot in this
class is the toolkit that I and many
other people at MIT have used um to do
these kind of manipulations and um it's
think it's correct to say it's the most
used toolkit in the world for working
with musical scores uh it's python free
and open source and um sometime over the
next couple days you're going to be
installing it um with Pip
stall so music 21 really works from the
notion that um first we're going to
encode a lot of groundup Concepts about
music so that um when you have a chord
is that going yep we'll just generate a
chord obviously not obviously otherwise
you need this class but you're going to
have a representation of how to
represent pitches middle C E G and then
all the different things once you have
that chord that you might be able to do
you might get its lyrics I don't know
it's going by really fast um get its
volume is it is it a diminished Triad so
you can do that and hopefully any good
computer program seeing ceg for is
diminish Triad will return no no false
anything like that zero right yep
good um so in the amount of time it
takes to write computer program that can
tell whether ceg is a diminished Triad
uh you all can hear it instantly right
so why have a computer do things and
it's really so that we can listen to
music faster than we can ever listen
with our ears so this this is a
particular example of code in music 21
similar code in other toolkits that will
take uh Corral by Johan Sebastian Bach
um his 11th canata 6th movement encoded
as a file called music XML store it as a
variable get the Alto part out of it
store it as alto get measures 13 to 20
as excerpt do a particular analysis
where we're going to put all these stars
on according to how um how strongly
accented something might be metrically
and show
it and really any music analyst in the
amount of time I took to do this could
have done it herself or himself or
theirselves but what's the great three
letter is it preposition preposition
that makes computers really
powerful begins with
f oh four four yeah so we just put a for
Loop in and suddenly we're looking at
every Corral that Bach wrote getting its
alart measure 13 to 20 doing the same
thing and of course why just do that
little excerpt why just do the Alto part
let's grab every Corral four Loops
within four Loops don't over optimize
first figure out if you can do this um
in the time it takes you to get a cup of
coffee right um yeah uh we'll come back
to that theme in the class A lot um in
your computer science intro classes you
you're going to early on be thinking a
lot about is this O big O of n s is this
n cubed is this n log n all these terms
we're going to talk about that from time
to time here but for the first part
we're going to build tools that work in
an acceptable to us amount of time
you're going to hear me use this term a
lot when we have a really big research
question about oh I don't know um 15th
century musical styles and we'll say
people have waited 500 years for this
answer 10 minutes isn't so bad right um
and then then later you know you can you
can go back and make it a three minute
problem something like
that some of the questions we might ask
that come up um that these kinds of
toolkits are built to solve are higher
notes
louder we many of us perceive them as
louder are they given louder Dynamics so
we can plot um pitch everyone know
octave numbers middle C C4 is the
standard American representation today
and the cello doesn't really go up that
high I don't know is sportando really
somewhere between Forte who knows these
are kind of slightly arbitrary but
doesn't look like it to me um now this
is one little graph probably want to do
this on a couple thousand pieces run
some regression lines all the things we
can do but we can start answering those
questions how does Robert Schuman use
notes differently from Fredick
chopan and I plotted this in plotting
the pitch usage of Schuman I can see how
beautiful it's a really nice bell curve
really great uh chopan on the other hand
looks I don't know kind of like one of
these cities with no planning laws like
here's I say ABI dbby with a gigantic
skyscraper when chopan likes a gsh it's
not just any GP it's this gsh is just
going to keep playing it forever so so
these are some of the ways you can do
this uh any Robert schiman experts out
there no some some hands almost went up
some people like Robert Shuman garbage
in garbage
out this particular piece by shiman is a
string
quartet this piece by shopan is a piano
when you have a string quartet of course
you're going to have more instruments
with notes in the
middle so I did this once I thought I
had compared Apples to Apples and I
realized I compared apples to oranges so
we're going to think a lot about user
error also in how we make
things
um visualization of music is a big part
of what we're doing these kinds of
visualized graphs can make understanding
a piece very easy uh you can also use 3D
graphs which don't make it easy at all
to understand anything but they look
really cool if you need like donors and
funding and stuff so so always make them
when you when you need that but
otherwise I can't really read
that we could combine different fields
so for instance geographic information
and plotting with musical
characteristics so this is one of my fun
things I found um comparing the
distribution of large intervals these
are intervals close to what would be
Western 7ths but obviously they're not
exactly that because different cultures
use different intervals but looking at
the folk songs differing and you can see
a large difference um as we move
northward and a little bit as you move
Inland in China in the increase of large
intervals that are not octaves in folk
songs and um we'll look at certain point
over the semester at a very cool um
paper that kind of shows how a
particular mountain range divides folk
songs that are very different um on
either side of that range
if you're looking for particular
fingerprints that might tell you who a
composer was maybe there's these small
moments you might find there's one
moment in this um piece from around
1500 that is feels like it might be in a
modern composition where you just smash
your hand down on a piano was very hard
to see here but with a computer what can
do is we can take all of the notes and
put them into singular chords here
reduce them all so that they're in
closed position everyone remember that
from music theory class as close
together as you can make it annotate the
intervals and suddenly this one little
moment jumps out as very strange then
you can go back and figure out how did
the music create
this over the course of the semester we
looking at um changes in music over time
so this is um and we're also going to be
looking at various things that were done
by people either in this class or who
had worked in um the lab that um helps
create music 21 um so Beth Hadley was a
gra somebody who graduated from this
program who did this analysis and
looking at a lot of rock um popular
music songs the 1950s and 60s see the
base moves quite often by five semit
Tunes up or down which corresponds to
sort of a movement of 1 to four or 5 to
one things like that um and then
occasionally up by two semmit tones
what's that in the 1451
progression four going to five to one
and so you can see how this really
dominates at that go yeah at the time
most data set it says post 1980 it
should say 1980 to 2000 data set and you
can kind of see if we go back and forth
how it's still these fives and twos that
the main thing but
um these other
intervals are continuing to move up and
becoming more and more important love to
see an analysis we now have another full
20 years 22 and a quarter years by the
time the semester is done um worth of
music after 2000 to see if this trend
continues or stopped
uh anybody youall have taken either some
sort of a theory class so at some point
who has written a parallel fifth in this
class accidentally yes okay wow some
people have never written a parallel
fifth that's amazing or you you always
did it on purpose just to annoy your
teacher right so we can find next time
you you've given that you can generate
your own list of every single time that
Yan Sebastian Bach wrote a parallel
fifth or an octave so that you can give
it to your teacher and say yeah that was
a parallel fifth but it's exactly like
what Bach
wrote once you've written a program that
does a particular type of analysis on a
particular Corpus of Music a collection
of Music an analysis it's easy to swap
one or the other so that once you have
something that finds all parallel fifths
in Johan Sebastian Bach then we can put
it into cladium monity and find the same
analysis and do different things so each
of our tools can work on what what is it
if most of our tools I'll say not all of
them most of our tools can work on any
Corpus and any Corpus can apply to
multiple tools so this is a place where
you get sort of a squared um increase in
power by using the computer over if you
wanted to do this U by
hand I'm trained primarily as a
musicologist that is a a music historian
somebody first trained to do things um
by hand and look at history and look at
context and come to conclusion
I did a lot of computer things and um
for a little while I kind of these were
slightly separate worlds I'm trying to
move them more and more together so that
when we answer a particular question we
think about which of those big questions
what bigger answer might we have come to
so this was a particular demonstration
program I wrote early in um early in my
development that I was like oh cool I
have um you're going to see well we'll
talk about why JS spx's coming up a lot
um but I have all these pieces by Bach
let's go through and I know that Bach
when he um when he writes a piece that's
in
minor how's it going to end generally
anybody
know in the c major
chord yeah this kind of I call it picity
third so usually when he's in minor he
ends in major I TR to find every
exception to that in his uh Coral
composition great um
so pretty easy find all these places and
then I was pretty happy that I found
that there's exactly uh eight of them
and I thought that was that was kind of
neat until one day I was a little bit
bored and I started looking at what
these pieces were what pieces went with
these weird numbers and I looked at the
first one um piece 20 48 in box catalog
and I saw oh that one's wrong the
computer didn't get it I didn't expand
all the repeats so the final bar in the
piece then said Doo wait which way's
right for you yeah Dapo Aline so go back
there and the actual end was in the
middle and that one was in major so
followed that then I looked at these
other pieces I saw there something some
people call orphan Corrals there're ones
that um jsbx son CPE box said Dad wrote
and published them but we have no other
evidence that Dad wrote them and the
only time this ever happens is in those
collections so some people have been
arguing maybe these pieces aren't really
by Bach or they've been edited heavily
this seems to give us some of the
evidence that that might be true so
always remember that the computer is not
substituting for analysis it's a tool to
make the kind of analytical questions
you might already have more
efficient that's why yep that's what you
know the first couple of things that
we're going to be looking at in this
class are how we represent music what
kinds of scores are happening and so on
um and we'll get into why you might do
one representation or another um one of
the first things we'll look at is music
as a series of boxes of Russian nesting
dolls whatever you want to call it box
within a box within a box so we have a
score inside that box we have some parts
inside those boxes we might have
measures um we might have voices two
different independent voices within a
measure something like that so we'll
call those kind of part-based containers
we going even put the score into a
bigger box with like the Opus all the
works by in a
collection and then our second box we
might have um is everything that happens
at a certain point in in time so
everything that happens here everything
that happens here here and we'll be
looking at and trying to identify when
one representation might be better and
when another representation might be
better and how you might use write tools
to move from one representation to
another from a box based to a moment
based you'll see we sometimes call this
slamy spacing like you just chop the
thing like a like a slamy
a really important moment and this is I
alluded to with the the bo there is to
try to make sure that the conclusions
that we're making apply to more music
that's out there and that's only
possible if we have a lot of music and
that music is representative of people
who create
music here's some of my favorite
composers out there uh we have lud Von
bet
we have uh Joseph Buon chalier s George
Kate soer friend of this music
department uh Amy Beach fogner Rickard
Vagner jsbach uh Scott Joplin Queen Lily
ulani I spent part of my year in Hawai
very important
composer um Yamada Kos uh Wolf Gang
Mozart we got Dolly Parton and the
Beatles so these are people that I would
really love to do my work on so I go and
I start doing the work and of course um
I don't want to encode all of this music
in so I go with what other people have
encoded and that lets me work on this
subset of Music very representative
subset of of the people who were up
there
before no not at all we have Boven Bach
Vagner
Mozart um all great composers long dead
white males of copyright and then still
in copyright of white meil group The
Beatles that somehow there's just always
Beatles everywhere um you can almost
always get that so this was a state of
Music we something it's called Corpus
research work on large collections of
scores a corpus body a large body or
Repertory of scores um when I started
going into
this thankfully the situation is getting
a little little better we now have the
complete piano Rags of Scott Joplin who
wrote the Entertainer Maple Leaf Rag if
you don't think you know his name play
some we'll play some of his music and be
oh yeah I know that music so very
important composer we're starting to get
in and individuals and groups are
starting to create collections like um
this collection of a couple hundred
scores by women and non-white
composers I hope that this class at some
point we will all contribute on to
improving uh the situation uh just a bit
and try to make it so
eventually what is represented is our in
our representations looks like the world
we want to be
in so um we're going you have in front
of you somewhere uh a syllabus so I'll U
so grab grab the syllabus we're not
going to go through it line by line and
line in fact I haven't even given you
yet um the longer one that's going to
tell you day by day what we're going to
do cuz part of that depended on how many
of y'all showed up today and it's a good
good crowd uh everybody comfortable um a
little bit little bit not over there but
um but we'll we'll somehow make this
make this happen Okay um you'll be happy
that this class um there's nothing to
buy that you unless you don't happen to
have some of these things earlier we'll
use as a textbook the music 20 the sort
of standard textbook the music 21 users
guide um probably get to maybe chapter
25 I always say 1 to 30 but we might not
get there um and we can't go too much
past 30 because it just kind of trails
off it's still being written uh you can
always write some more of it if you want
as part of a project
um you're required for me to support you
for me to be a help to have a Windows or
Mac OS laptop we're going to install um
the latest version of Music 21 which is
I believe
8.1 um the hope the plan the bags under
my eyes right now was to get Version 9
released before today uh it's not out it
has some of the U near features that
we'll be using uh we'll get um I'll
probably get that out within a week or
two now you all are my focus um and then
we'll put that on so at some point we'll
I'll upgrade to that um music 21 version
8 runs on python 3.8 Version 9 runs on
310 so uh install of python 310 you'll
be very happy with that or
311 probably want to get some staff
paper and a pencil because at various
points um unless if you're using a
tablet you're probably fine but um it's
concise hard if you're taking notes on
laptop and we'll some point be using
that staff a lot there's four
recommended books I love them but
they're all ebooks but you might
consider buying them um Le Le the first
two were pretty cheap and things but we
don't really need to talk about that
more okayy we're we're making great um
time the typical week we're going to on
Wednesday um introduce a particularly
new topic this is just sort of middle of
the semester right and then you're going
to get some readings to do for IT some
of them will probably be for by Friday
we'll try to make Wednesday to Friday I
mean kind of a a time more for reading
and reflection and things on Friday so
maybe the topic is oh I let me not be
hypothetical what is topic three it's
written here somewhere uh okay
containers we just talked about this how
to represent as containers what are the
various ways working through that so
we'll just sort of introduce like we did
now a new topic and think about it a bit
on Friday we'll get to some of the
nitty-gritty difficult things um
discussion of why this representation
work why this doesn't why you might make
this choice and we'll do some inclass
work on that and then usually on Fridays
you'll get a problem set so you'll get
that on work on it but over the weekend
um you'll also be getting um a little
bit of asynchronous content so what
happened was um nobody really cares
about the history of your class but I'm
going to tell it anyway um we started
this class it was an hour and a half
twice a week and then Co hit and
suddenly a lot of things went online and
I did a lot of video Rec recording um
partially because my wife and I were
teaching at the exact same time in a one
bedroom house that had no um you know no
way for us to to teach so we did some
asynchronous things and a lot of the
asynchronous content I'm so glad you
will never have to see again it was so
you you all W live through that right
but some of it was actually better than
in class because
sometimes every once in a while there's
something that I can teach you a
particular technique and then if it was
in class I'd say great so now you know
how to do that and let's go on and
here's another technique and let's go on
and you haven't had any chance to
practice any of them so there's some
things that are useful about the Susi
street style of here's a particular
thing that takes me about five minutes
to present and then you work on it for
10 minutes then here's another 5 minutes
to work on a 10 before you know it
you've had one hour of lecture and
you've had about three hours of a
problem set you've done problem by
problem so those ones are still there
there's about uh seven of times during
the semester and and um I just guarantee
I wouldn't be doing that if I didn't
think that that was a better way to do
things so you'll do some of that work
there on Wednesday and this will be um
at least four or five hours before class
so I can do a quick spot check that's a
great part about doing um things all
online turn in the problem
set and then we'll um unlock the tools
what does that mean means if you're
working on something let's say we're
doing something with chords
I'm going to ask you to to figure out
certain of the algorithms for how to
solve some difficult problems with
chords and some of most of the things
that you're going to be doing somebody
in the world has solved I hope that's
not too disappointing most of what we do
in most of our classes instructural
engineering saying somebody has solved
it we're learning to do it
ourselves so at that point we're going
to show you some of the tools that are
already out there to do this and they
will become unlocked to you that is to
say you can keep doing using using the
tools that you built or you can use um
the standardized chord manipulation
tools and then we'll introduce the next
topic and keep going over here it does
mean that you're sometimes going to have
two topics going simultaneously and I
hope that's not too weird I'm going to
try to make that as
ready to go when when it all
loads go to runtime run
all and then stop that will probably
take like two to three minutes okay so
we'll go on from that and I'll just talk
a little bit about final projects while
that's going which way are we there we
are okay
great so what we're going to do at the
end of the semester is have final
projects we're a little bit big class
I'm probably going to let anybody who
wants to have a group of three um do
that because of the number of people
here but generally two works really
really well um solo groups are really
hard and I found that groups bigger than
three have almost always um had some
problems so we're going to do a final
project we and I used to say any Topic
in computational music U or music theory
and Analysis or composition types things
as long as it involves representations
of scores of the computer I now have one
exception I've um a lot of a AI deep
learning for composition projects have
tended not to do as well as the students
who ran them were doing in the class so
I'm going to not allow that for this
semester um to try to figure out um how
we can do that a little bit better so
that's just to um just me learning from
experience you're going to spend some
time researching um a topic that you
work on programming the tools needed to
do it reading about what what mistakes
you might have done and just think about
it then what I want from you is you're
then you're going to be making a video
about your project five minutes um I
know I'm a hard Professor I could have
made it 10 minutes and it would have
been a lot easier but five minutes you
have to you know kind of be on toes so
what I want a couple days before that is
just a draft of your script it can I
don't care how messy it is I just want
to see that um that I'm not going to get
a frantic phone call at 11:30 p.m. that
none of our software works or something
like that and then um you record and
edit a 5 minute video so let's get back
to that live
code and somewhere on here this one
we're all up
and where do I have it I have mine here
let me make this bigger in three
ways every anybody not get a note here
and maybe this one sometimes doesn't
work for a lot of people so don't worry
if that doesn't work for you but um give
me a thumbs up we got it okay cool so
let's let's start with um me finding my
script great so let's do um some of the
things we can
do if you don't care about polluting
your code base sorry I got to move this
a little bit um go ahead and import um
from music 21 import Star it should
already be in there you'll know this who
has anybody not used a Jupiter notebook
or anything like that please give who
has used one give me okay so don't need
to do too much but we can yeah we'll
enter in a new code thing move it down
so go ahead enter a new code Brank and
let's just make sure that if I type
chord and hit shift enter something like
that comes
out cool okay great so let's grab um
there's a particular piece by Bach that
we'll use quite often in this class I'm
going to use it less often this year
because we have more Alternatives now to
this and we don't want to perpetuate the
B is everything stereotype but this one
we'll use a lot so we'll assign to the
variable bo something from the music 21
Corpus calling the method parse on it
and we can just type
bwv 66.6
um I am not uh devil worshipper or
something 666 happens to be the shortest
Corral that b ever wrote so it's a nice
one for us to work with here and shift
enter and that should load um if you
ever if something doesn't work um this
is the time to cheat and look off your
neighbor and see see if maybe you
mistype something or or tap them on
we're all in class we're all here always
just to help each other right we we feel
that you're going to do that people
around you good okay so let's show it
the first time you run show it's always
a lot slower than every other time
hopefully it won't take too long you
should get a score up there
somewhere good uh right now you're only
going to get the first page of the score
um though this that's why I use this one
because it's only one page long uh soon
you'll get the whole score okay um so
let's go ahead and let's get that Alto
part so we'll say Alto equals Bach Parts
is a way of getting something out
Alto and then Alto
doow I see something
looks like this Alto part's always a
little
something like that on your page good um
you can also get a part by um doing it
numerically
so anybody know in a course what are the
four parts highest to lowest soprano
soprano Alto ten come on participation
grade let's already get our things
soprano Alto tenor base great so if we
can do it by numeric order we want to
get the alto that's what number part two
two one yes zero index python so one of
the things you'll get and so that should
be the same Part Parts one good good
guesses good wrong guesses I love I love
great wrong guess is better than great
uh than even uh getting it right on the
first time one of the things you'll find
is if something is in computer speak we
leave it alone so uh we don't tend to
number the parts in the orchestra hey
instrument 17 do this no so when we do
that we leave it in computer speak and
make it um make it sort of uh you know
zero index when we leave things that um
that musicians might know however we
tend to use the um the the musicians uh
things so let's get the soprano part
part zero here
and let's get measures 4 through six so
do measures 4 comma 6 do show and in
Python that should get you the fifth
measure through the SE through the sixth
measure because of the way zero indexed
however measure numbers measure numbers
something that human musicians talk
about yeah yeah you've you've heard of
that great we'll save time Always by
just being being Fearless at shouting
out when I ask a rhetorical question
like measureing numbers we know
musicians yeah good good that that to
save time in the class um so yeah since
musicians know what measure four is
we'll use measure four that way so
that's measure four through six um great
so let's start manipulating the score
let's say that
the 5 ah thank you that is measure that
is whatever a musician thinks measure 4
is so in this particular piece let's go
up to the beginning of the piece
um
yeah what measure is this that the mouse
is on
zero yeah pickup is what a musician
would say we got to give it a number so
what number do we like here zero so
there can be a measure zero if there's a
pickup but measure one will always be
whatever humans uh musicians think
measure one should should be so let's we
can play um some other things let's
let's just play around with the score a
little bit we'll take the soprano get
measure five you'll also see some of our
display things don't know how to display
the the right number um if you're on
mcore 4 it now displays the actual
correct number um but let's get um let's
make so this measures four through five
let's make the
formada red so what number if I'm
getting notes I'm going to get it index
by number so we're going to get measure
five and get a particular number on that
what what what note number is the
formada shout it
out two in this case musicians don't
tend to talk about I guess we do say the
second note yeah yeah that's really
confusing so in this case uh basically
when we're using the bracket square
bracket notation I'll make this a little
bit bigger does that help a bit yeah um
we'll think of it computer so we'll say
um C I should I should call it C Shar
equals but then you just get what
comments for the rest of the line so
we'll just call it C even though it's a
c c
style I think I can just check nope that
doesn't give me autocomplete equs
red and soprano
show we got the soprano I'll scroll back
up again so you can
see we already got the soprano we take a
particular note the third note indexed
by two from measure five which is
actually five and and assign it
here probably we could have made
different decisions on how we number
things right um if for version two but
whatever and then we'll set the style of
that notes color to red and then show
the entire soprano line and we get
something over
here I'm half color blind is there
actually a red note up there okay good
good good where is it it's over here
we'll emphasize that for the camera um
sh a laser on it becomes more red um
okay now um yeah that's kind of fun play
around things
um something we might actually want to
do let's take the whole piece we called
it B
right zero index yeah Bo a score object
let's analyze its
key analyze is a method so we call it
like this parentheses parth score key if
you so let me say if you're following
along at 80% but you just would I would
go a little little bit slower and then
you'd be able to have it it's going to
be fine because U most of the time we're
going to go slower than this this is
just the sort of the fun beginning of
the semester uh if you've never seen a
parenthesis or a square parentheses uh
this might be a class to take next year
or next semester uh after doing a little
bit more programming um and that's
probably more for the camera people
watching at home let's make sure that we
um that we just need a little bit
programming before we're going to go
forward okay so the piece as a whole F
minor what do we do now I've tried to
emphasize it early on but we're going to
make this a habit in the class we always
check our BS meter right says the piece
is in F
minor is that at all plausible looking
at this piece uh let's just look at the
base it's easier it looks like an a I
mean it's three Sharps Maybe
maybe the
end
f a Shar oh looks like it ends at F
major but then maybe the rest of the
piece is in minor and then this is just
the bo ending thing so it to me it
passes the smell test it might be other
things but one of the other things we
can do is let's analyze measures oops we
get Buck dot
measures zero I haven't uh spoken out
loud while I type for a while 0a 2 so
we'll just get the pickup and the first
two measures and we'll analyze the key
of this
opening ah a major that that feels more
right for the opening so we know that
the piece as a whole isn't F minor or at
least the computer thinks so if the
computer got it right and it opens an a
major a logical thing that we might play
with next is where does it change can we
do that can we analyze where key changes
are we're not going to do that well um
let's let's get some easy thing so we
said that not notes I use to get a
particular note so let's see how
many notes there are in this piece Len
um any other language would be length
but you know Len f. notes and how many
notes take a
prediction oh zero there are no notes in
this piece it is the we started with
cage 433 and we end with Bach 433 now
why are there no notes it's because B is
a score this is all about the
representation we're currently in box
within box within box there are no notes
in the score there are notes within
Parts no there are no notes within the
parts parts have measures there are
notes in measures so what we'll need to
do is we'll
say take the Bo and let's run recurse go
into every box like like a child at
Christmas open every single box and find
every single note in
there so we'll say we can take a score
we can say open up every box and to
every box get me the notes and 165 let
pass the smell test let's scroll up
don't ask anybody ever to count this but
that look like about 165 notes to you
yeah just order of magnitude if it said
1 million notes would something be wrong
if it said zero notes you knew it was
something wrong so we'll always try to
do these kind of smell tests before we
go on and the last thing I'm going to do
because I'm looking at the time and and
I I have only one good habit as a
professor I really am allergic to
keeping you over so we're not going to
do this but we'll do just for fun bu.
cify
doow now we've switched the entire thing
into salami slice
mode so these are some of the things
we're going to be
doing hopefully that was good professor
mode now here's really evil Professor
mode you're going to forget every tool
that you've just been given analyze key
is not available to you I I'll call it
locking it it's locked in this little
cabinet here when you write your own
pretty decent key analysis algorithm you
can unlock this one yours might be
better um I might ask for a license to
hey can we use that one there this is a
pretty decent one but you might write a
better one when you write your own
certification algorithm then cify will
be opened for you um we'll give you some
tools uh extracting things particular
measures um that was a lot of work but
that kind of sounds boring boring in
terms of our intellectual development
but coming up with the tools to be able
to cify a score um um we'll see how many
difficult things that come from that um
and not the time's about up so we'll
talk about that in other classes as I
said on Friday I want to get to know you
guys I want you guys to be able to talk
more but I wanted today just to blab
about what we might do in this semester
and I'm happy to have you here the
numbers look great uh you all come back
Friday you all make sure that you're
registered and I'm glad to have everyone
in this class