Next we have a short talk delivered by
Joey uh from Michael Bronston's lab from
University of Oxford on painless
simulation of multiple pre-trained
protein generative models through the
superposition principle.
All right. Uh yeah, thanks for having me
over here. So I'm super excited to talk
to you about a very recent paper that
was presented last week at Icleair as a
spotlight on how do you combine
pre-train generative models in a more
principled manner. Um to motivate this a
little bit let's talk about where we are
in terms of generative modeling and the
sciences more broadly. So far we've seen
tons of generative models. In fact you
could say it's a Cambrian explosion of
generative models and it's not
restricted to any particular domain
necessarily. For instance for images you
might have already been familiar with a
lot of existing models out there. These
frontier models like image and dolly
stable diffusion they're doing a lot of
miraculous things and just going on from
images to video. We've already seen
photorealistic videos that you can even
use as commercials if you wanted to. So
in all these spaces there are a bunch of
different models that are sort of sort
of uh in some ways experts in var
variety of different domains. But in the
case of life sciences we've also seen a
similar revolution where in proteins
we've seen Rosetta diffusion alpha 3 is
a generative model as well and so on and
so forth. But because these models are
so different and and specialist, one
natural question arises is well, how do
we get the best of all models in some
sense? So more specifically, wouldn't it
be make a lot more sense to say, can we
just train bigger and bigger models? And
and in in some ways, this is a very
poisoned question because obviously we
can't do this because a lot of the times
these models are chained on proprietary
data or data sets that we don't have
easy access to. So moreover, a lot of
these models are also available through
only API access. So you don't even know
have the internals of these models. But
at the same time, you kind of want to
get the best of all worlds. So in many
cases, it's not really easy to just
train a bigger and bigger model. So what
do we actually do? So let's taking a
step back, we can ask the question of if
we were to combine different frontier
models, what would that actually look
like? So suppose you had models one,
two, and three and up to model N. And
each of these models is in some case a
specialist or an expert in a a variety
of subdomains. And you could ask the
question, what does it mean to actually
build a mixture of expert model in the
first place? Historically in machine
learning, mixture of expert models have
actually been state-of-the-art models.
In fact, GPT4 itself was a mixture of
expert model. So in some sense, we do
want to build an expert model. But it's
unclear how to do this in a more
methodologically principled manner.
So in this talk I really want to
motivate how do we build or compose
models from first
principles. So the research question I'm
kind of want to paint towards is uh can
we combine pre-train diffusion models
specifically at inference time and why
do we want to maybe combine them in
inference time? Inference over here
means just simulating using the model
and this has the the the nice benefit
that you don't have to train a model.
Um, and this is particularly interesting
because it allows you to kind of take
existing models out there without
necessarily building a new model but but
getting the benefits of acting of having
a much larger model in the first
place. So to give a a bit more of a
picture pictorial overview, what could
this actually look like? So imagine you
have a data set as follows where you
have training data A and training data B
and different colors. If you had
diffusion models that are trained on
each respective data set, you could ask
the question, how would we compose them?
Naively, you could say, let's just
average the outputs of the models. But
if you did that, you'd get something in
the middle like this, where the orange
points over here are generated samples.
But these generated samples don't have
the benefit of either data set. So you
haven't really accomplished a whole
lot. Instead, you could instead what you
could do is maybe you could do a
sampling of the mixture of densities. In
this case, you would get a model that
kind of acts as if it was a mixture of
models. So you get samples that are from
all the different modes. Intuitively,
this is like a doing a logical or
operation between
models. Alternatively, what you could do
is you can also sample from equal
densities. That is to say that
generating samples that have equal
densities under each model. Now in this
case, the different models over here uh
green and purple don't have any shared
overlap. So an equal density region
would be a density of low region low
density region rather. So this is kind
of similar to saying this is a logical
and operation. So how do we build these
logical or and operations from existing
models. So this is going to be the focus
of this talk which is going to be the
superposition of diffusion models and
we're going to introduce an algorithm
called super diff that allows us to do
this. So to understand how to do this
from first principles we need to get a
shared understanding of what a diffusion
model is. I'm sure many of you in the
audience already know this but it's good
to recap a little bit. So a diffusion
model as you may know takes initial data
distribution P data and constructs a
forward noising process where you take a
scastic differential equation
characterized by a drift which is the
average direction you move in with a
little bit of noise which is the
brownian motion scaled by a diffusion
coefficient and you propagate this
process forward in time until you hit a
terminal distribution which is going to
be a standard normal distribution. Now,
importantly, this process that I
described over here has a very nice time
reversal in the sense that you can
characterize exactly the reverse process
that takes you from this gausian
distribution back to your data
distribution. And in this case, this
reverse process is also going to be an
SD. And in particular, the vector field
that moves you in this reverse process
is given to you in analytic form with
this expression over here. So the key
quantity of interest over here that
diffusion models end up all estimating
is this score function which tells you
the the direction of higher likelihood
the reverse process needs to navigate
until you hit the data distribution and
diffusion models typically estimate this
score function using a neural network
and they estimate the score function
everywhere in space and
time. So given a a a trained diffusion
model with access to its score function
how do we kind of build this logical or
operation? So remember our logical or
operation was essentially getting a
mixture of densities. That is to say
that you want to essentially combine or
compose existing diffusion models is
that you have one model that samples
from all different modes at inference
time. And for the ease of presentation
I'm going to focus on this setting but
similar analogies will extend to the end
setting as
well. So the or setting
uh I promise this is going to be
probably the last slide of complex math
and then we're going to go into a little
bit more pictures again. Uh so if you
give me a diffusion model, we can look
at essentially the time evolution of all
the particles. So that's the density.
This tells us how the model is changing
over time. Now because this is a
stoastic differential equation, this
this time evolution has to satisfy the
Fauler plank equation. Uh in particular,
the Fauler plank equation tells you the
first term on the first equation is
essentially the continuity equation
which tells you how the drift is
changing. Well, the second term is the
lelassian associated with adding the
noise. Now, if you had a mixture model,
what you really want to say is that QT,
which is the the time evolution of the
the mixture process, how does that
evolve over time? Well, it turns out if
you have a mixture model, it's also
going to be another stoastic
differential equation. And in
particular, the reverse SD is going to
be characterized by this new UT where UT
is your velocity. So, different
operations, you can build UT from first
principles. So, in this case, I'm
showing how to build UT as a as a
combination of different uh models
itself. So the last equation at the
bottom tells you the weighted average of
the different likelihoods assigned by
each diffusion model at everywhere in
time tells you a way to move of
combining these models. So let's intuit
it what exactly is happening a bit. So
the last equation is essentially
different weights that you multiply that
the vector field that that kind of
forces you to go in different
directions. Now this weights is
controlled by each individual diffusion
model's own density. So this qi of t. So
if I have m different models, I have m
different densities. So this immediately
poses a a potential problem. The problem
is that we need access to this q of t
and and this q of t is the density. Now
naively this is very this is very
difficult to get access to your fusion
model because to get access to the
density we would have to kind of
simulate the model in the first place
and that's a very expensive
operation. So how do we get these
densities for free if you want to build
these vector fields?
Now, naively what you would kind of do
to build these these vector fields and
these densities is to kind of integrate
the change in density over time. And
this change in density is given to you
by this term which is the log density
plus this second term over here which is
how the change happens incrementally as
I move along this
process. Now it turns out this change of
density because it satisfies the
continuity equation. You can account for
it by take just taking the time
derivative of this log function. So if I
remind you when you take the time
derivative of a function of of two
different uh variables time and space
you have to account for how it changes
in time which is the first term over
here and how it changes in position. Now
you can apply this analogy by just
differentiating this log density from
first principles and I'll spare the
derivation but what ends up happening is
that you get a couple of terms. The
first term tells you how the the the
change in time happens. The last couple
of terms tells you how this change in
space happens. Now to give a bit more
intuition for what's happening here,
this is coming from the celebrated Edo's
lema in stocastic calculus. So in some
sense it's saying how does the stocastic
process if you take the tailor
approximation for it and apply it to the
tailor approximation to this change of
density, how does that actually look
like? Now if you expand and collect
these terms, what ends up happening is
that you get this very initially
complicated looking expression, but it's
actually going to be very simple for us.
This expression has two different terms.
And what you'll notice is that none of
these terms have this very complicated
divergence operator. So this divergence
operator is kind of what you would
initially have had to use to compute the
change in density. But if you just apply
this little bit of this math uh math
lema, you get this essentially for free
a way to calculate the change in
density. So this is going to be a lot
faster for you to compute than any other
previous methods of computing density.
And what this allows us to kind of do is
say when we simulate each diffusion
model at inference, we can automatically
get the change in density associated
with each model almost for free. And one
of the main results of this paper is
this new density estimator which we call
EDOS's density estimator. And you'll
notice that you can plug in any velocity
field in this expression over here and
get the equation equivalent change of
density. So what does that actually
mean? It means that when we solve the
inference problem, we can uh essentially
paint any path for the model to follow.
And this tells you the density along
this
path. So taking a step back, what are
the benefits? The benefits of this
density estimator is that it's very
agnostic. You can apply it for any
diffusion model you have regardless of
domain, regardless of architecture and
it can work for any number of
models. But there is one uh point of
caution. The point of caution being that
because you need to compute the score
function, if you don't have access to
the learn score or essentially the
ground score, you're going to have a
bias estimate. But in certain
applications, this is not an
issue. So to motivate this even more,
let's look at some experiments and how
you could actually use this new density
estimator to build new different
composition rules. So let's look at
unconditional protein generation for a
minute.
Now the question I want to answer with
this experiment is to say I have two
different protein generative models that
are trained on maybe different data sets
and have different architectures. How do
I combine them? So if you know anything
about protein generative models uh one
common class of models are protein
backbone models which generates 3D
coordinates. So in this case what you
would have is a forward process that
takes you from a backbone to pure noise
and the reverse process which is being
learned by the diffusion model that
takes you from noise back to data. Now
two popular model choices historically
have been Proteus and frame diff where
frame diff is a diffusion model that
came out of MIT and you could ask the
question well these data these models
are trained on different datas can we
get the best of both
models so to evaluate this this new
inference process of composing models
we're going to look at a couple of
incilico metrics so designability which
tells us how likely the generated
structure can refold into another
structure which is based on a
off-the-shelf refolding
algorithm, novelty, which tells us how
similar the protein sequences are to the
training data set. And finally,
diversity, which is kind of trying to
characterize the generations and how
similar they are to each other. So, here
are the baseline numbers for the models
that exist. Now, if you naively average
the scores of these models, you get a a
model that's not particularly good at
anything.
Now if you apply these composition rules
that I've been building towards the or
and and operations, you essentially get
models that are going to be slightly
more diverse or slightly more uh
designable. And if you play with the
hyperparameters a little bit, it turns
out you can tweak the designability of
these models to a much greater uh number
than either of these models to begin
with. And this kind of really highlights
one of the benefits of composing models.
almost for free you get a a superior
model uh without actually doing any more
training. So here's an example of of the
umap structures of these models. So uh
the the the green and the orange are the
existing models while the purple ones
are the super div generated structures
only at inference time. You can kind of
get a feeling for the fact that the the
generated structures have more coverage
in some sense compared to any individual
model.
Uh so let's look at another application.
Let's look at conditional molecule
generation. So suppose you want to do
multiple property generation which is to
say that I want a molecule that let's
say inhibits this enzyme GSK3 beta and
high has high drug
likeness. Now to do this we're going to
use a pre-trained uh latent diffusion
model called LD mole and we're going to
prompt it with these following prompts
and then we're going to prompt it in
natural language. We're going to say
this molecule inhibits GSK3 beta and as
well this molecule looks like a drug.
And we're going to try to look at the
last column over here which tells us how
faithful is the generation to both
properties or the product of
properties. Now if you create a joint
prompt which essentially tells you let's
do property A and property B, you get a
model that kind of does a bit of both
but not quite well on each on either of
them. Now if you average the scores
again, you also get something that's
mediocre. However, if you do super n,
you get a model that more readily
satisfies both properties
simultaneously, again without
training. And of course, when you do
this, you get molecules that are much
more valid and unique as well. So, I'm
going to end with this final slide over
here, which gives you a visual picture
of uh of what these models look like or
the generated samples. And the last
column over here, you can see the the
generation has higher uh property scores
than either of the individual uh
composing strategies of joint prompting
or averaging the
scores. And I'll end there.
[Applause]
Yeah, thank you Joey.
So if you go back to slide 24.
When you separate the time and the space
processes.
One second. I think it was 24. It might
have been this one or Yeah, probably
this one. I believe I think it was that
one
over here. Yeah.
Down. Yeah. like well when you separate
time and the spatial variation and then
you know you s sort of go forward and
reverse these processes is that an
assumption or is that analytically true
for all that's analytically true for any
diffusion model uh the way that this
breakdown happens you have to assume one
specific property of your diffusion
model that that the drift is going to be
aphine which is generally true for all
existing diffusion models we use in ML
but if you have a more complicated SD
then this is going to be a more
complicated expression right so I mean
where do you think That's so that's the
model. You formulate the model, you fit
things into it, and then that's
analytically true, you know, for the the
optimization side of things. Where do
you think that doesn't fit reality most?
Well, well, where doesn't fit reality is
the fact that again, what this assumes
access to is the gradient of log Q. And
this assumes access to the true score.
And you will never have the true score.
In practice, you'll only have an
estimate to the score which is learned
by your model. So you're going to always
have a biased estimate of this change of
density and for applications where you
really need the exact likelihood this is
going to fail you. But for guiding
generation uh in this case that I've
shown this is totally okay even if you
have under like a bias estimate but if
you wanted to do reweing of samples or
correction through reweing then this is
going to probably fail you. Okay, cool.
Thanks,