Hello
my name is Maria Valeria
and I am honored to
share my journey with you
I was born and
raised in Venezuela
a country rich in resources
and resilient people
However, the past 24 years
have brought deep political,
economic, and social challenges
Leading to my forced migration
and leaving behind my family
and career as an agricultural engineer
In 2018
I moved to Uruguay
But first
I spent six months in Colombia
working informal jobs to save money
Upon arriving in Uruguay
I had to start over, with manual jobs
despite quickly obtaining legal status
Determined to rebuild my career
and be able to help my family
I enrolled in the MIT ReACT program
which transformed my life completely
With basic English skills
but strong determination
I earned a certificate in Data
Science and Computing from MIT
And I improved my English
through
After a year of persistent applications
I secured a position as an analyst
in a major software company
So I did it
I started my new path
What motivates me at work
is the opportunity to
learn and grow continually
I value a supportive
and inclusive environment
where teamwork and personal
development are encouraged
Working online with international
organizations can be challenging
due to the difference in regulations
time zones
and communication styles
My advice?
Is to stay organized
be proactive
and seek support networks
To shift mindsets about the positions
displaced individuals should occupy
it's crucial to recognize and promote
our diverse skills and perspectives
Companies need to see
us as a valuable asset
This includes adopting
inclusive hiring practices
and providing opportunities
for career growth
So thank you for listening to my story
and for being part of this
important conversation
at the Migration Summit 2024