So welcome.
Welcome, everyone.
My name is Bill Green.
I'm the Director of the
MIT Energy Initiative.
I thank you all for coming
for our seminar today.
MITEI is hosting
the seminar series
to try to keep the
MIT community informed
about important work happening
all over to decarbonize
the world's energy system.
In particular, in the
United States, and today
we have US Congressman
to talk about that.
The key challenge for
the energy transition
is the urgency that the climate
is changing before our eyes
and we really need to move,
but, of course, there's
still many technical aspects
that we haven't figured out
exactly what to do yet.
And in other cases,
we know what to do,
but it costs a lot of money or
it requires a lot of changes,
and so we have to figure
out how to move faster.
And so one way that
MIT can help with this
is by convening thought
leaders and discussions
about all the many,
many issues involved
in the energy transition.
And hopefully, those discussions
will lead to consensus
on how we should move
forward and maybe spark
ideas that will lead to new
innovations here at MIT.
A very important part of this--
MIT, we mostly are
engineers and scientists,
economists, business people.
And we work on trying
to solve the problems we
can in front of us.
But in the end, the
climate challenge
is a problem of
collective action.
That if everyone just follows
their own individual interests
in the short-term, we're never
going to solve the problem.
We only can solve it
when we work together.
And, of course, the
government has a key role
in helping to pull us together.
And so today we'll hear
Congressman Sean Casten
talk about that.
For the introduction, I'd like
to bring forward Professor Chris
Knittel.
Chris is the Director of the
MIT Climate Policy Project,
is that--
Climate Policy--
--Policy Center.
Climate Policy Center.
He's also the
Director of the Center
for Energy and Environmental
Policy Research.
He's also Associate
Dean of the Sloan
School for Climate and Energy--
I got that right?
Something like that.
And as you'll see, he's
quite a good speaker
and was named Professor of the
Year by the Undergraduate and--
Economics Association
at the end of last year.
[APPLAUSE]
And so he will give
an introduction
for our main speaker today.
Thanks, Bill.
Yeah, I won that award.
Two of my colleagues
won the Nobel Prize.
[LAUGHTER]
If somebody wants a
trade, let me know.
So you know you're a
big deal when you get
two people to introduce you.
So I just wanted to briefly
introduce Representative Sean
Casten from the great
6th District of Illinois?
The greatest.
In many ways, when I
was looking at his bio,
he looks a lot like
one of my colleagues
from the Martin Trust Center for
Entrepreneurship than a sitting
congressman.
So he's actually a
trained graduate--
trained biochemical engineer.
Out of grad school,
it looks like he
was an energy consultant,
and then a CEO of a company
that took waste heat and
recycled that into usable heat,
and maybe we'll learn a little
bit about that technology.
Then he started his
own company to--
sounds like to
something very similar.
And then apparently, he
got bored with industry
and thought he'd
run for Congress.
So he ran for Congress
in 2018, flipped the seat
from a Republican to Democrat.
And in many ways, climate
and energy is his focus.
I encourage you to look up the
bills that he's cosponsored
and the bills that have passed
into acts, but he has many.
He has one sitting now, which
is near and dear to many
of our hearts that would build
more transmission and to free up
some of the permitting
and siting challenges
we have with transmission
that would have
big impacts on
greenhouse gas emissions
and on costs and on efficiency.
So I'm looking forward to
hearing what he has to say.
I think the plan afterwards
is we'll both sit down,
I'll ask a couple of
questions, and at some point,
you'll have the opportunity
to ask questions yourself.
So I also encourage you
to be thinking about what
those questions might be.
So without further
ado, Sean Casten.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
You want me to stand over here?
Yeah.
OK.
You can go up there.
All right.
Well, thank you so much.
I'm hoping we can spend
most of our time on the Q&A,
but I wanted to--
let's not deny this
is a political season.
All eyes are to the election.
Any conversation about
forward energy policy
largely depends on the election.
And I don't want to
duck the politics,
but I want to just
first just frame
four macro trends,
that regardless of what
happens in this election
or the next election,
the trend lines are not
fundamentally changing.
The first is that the
United States has largely
decoupled economic growth
from fossil fuel consumption.
We're not done, we've
got a long way to go.
But if you look over
the last 15 years,
our economy has grown by 50%.
Natural gas use
has grown by 25%.
Oil use is flat.
Coal use is down by 50%
That is awesome.
We have found ways
to grow our economy
without linking to
fossil fuel use,
and that was a long time coming.
And that raises a
question going forward,
are we going to leave what's in
the United States in the ground
or are we going to export it?
That's a political question.
One of those is good for the
economy and the environment,
the other is good for producers,
but that's a political question.
But that basic trend of
decarbonization, defossilization
is going to continue.
Second big macro trend is the
combination of electrification
and renewable deployment.
We didn't reduce coal
use, reduce oil--
flattened oil use,
slow down gas use,
and not provide
access to electricity.
We now generate more power
from non-hydro renewables
than we do from coal.
That is amazing.
But we've built a
ton of it, and we've
built it because the
private sector largely
realized that it's cheaper.
We're also electrifying
huge parts of the country.
And we're electrifying in
places that don't have wires.
In the case of my
house, my garage,
where my electric vehicle
is now plugged in,
factories that are
electrifying-- this
is a larger trend.
That's also good
news because it's
much easier to decarbonize
the electric sector
than other sectors.
But building generation
in places where generation
has historically not
been, it's just there
because it's windy or sunny or
a lot of geothermal activity,
building loads in places where
loads have not historically
been, which means we have
to either build wires
way faster than we've
built wires before,
or just decide that
we love blackouts.
And that's a political question.
I have a bias, but it's
a political question.
Third big trend, and--
we are reinvesting
in manufacturing
in the United States.
And this is an inversion
of a 30-year trend.
We used to run about $70
billion a year of investments
in manufacturing.
I think we did $150
billion last year.
And a part of that
has been because
of, let's say, more
protectionist sentiments
in the United States,
but a part of it
has been because we really--
we basically ran
about as far as we
could go by getting cheap
stuff by outsourcing.
You can shut down the plant in
El Paso that pays $9 an hour
and move it to Ciudad Tavares
where they pay $0.90 an hour
and you can lower your cost, but
you only really get to do that
once.
And we ran that
gamut out, and a lot
of the hollowing out of the
middle class resulted from that.
And there's been a very
bipartisan consensus to saying,
let's bring that
manufacturing back.
We've not really--
we haven't done
that with some grand
long-term intentional plan.
And so now we're having to
have this conversation around,
would you rather have
a factory in your town
that employs people and
provides a middle-class income
or would you rather
have cheap stuff?
And I'm not laying that at the
blame of some of the Inflation,
but that's a real challenge.
There's huge conversations
right now going
on in the solar
industry of, should we
look out for the interests
of solar developers
who want to have the lowest-cost
plant so that they can sell
power to Americans at the
lowest possible price,
or should we prioritize the
interests of US solar panel
manufacturers who would like
to sell at a higher price
and bypass Chinese
supply chains?
If that question sounds like
you can argue both sides of it,
you get why that's a challenge.
But that-- again, that trend
of bringing more manufacturing
United States in the wake
of COVID, making more robust
supply chains, I don't think
that's going away regardless
of who wins.
And then the last
big macro trend
is that we are increasingly
awash in cheap energy.
It may not feel that
way in the bills,
but almost everything--
in your utility bills,
but virtually everything
we're building
has no marginal operating cost.
If you put a solar
panel on your roof,
you may or may not have
the spare cash lying around
to invest in the solar
panel on your roof,
but once you put
it on your roof,
you don't pay for
electricity anymore.
If you have the cash to
put in an electric vehicle
in your driveway, you don't
pay for gasoline anymore.
If you have the cash to insulate
your home, put a heat pump in,
you don't pay for
natural gas anymore.
Whether you get an acceptable
return on that investment
is one set of questions,
but we're building
all of this cheap energy.
And that raises a
separate question,
which starts to get into
the politics of this,
is it the goal of
US energy policy
to maximize the
benefit to US consumers
or to maximize the
benefit to US producers?
And that may sound like
there's a really obvious answer
to that question, but
it is hugely contentious
and it is hugely political.
And this now gets into
where I want to just flag,
without being overly political,
just to understand how
politics factors into all this.
In April of 2020, the price
of gasoline collapsed.
I'm sure you all
remember how sad you
were that gasoline was so cheap,
and how your heart was breaking
about what should we do
for our poor oil refiners?
Senator Cassidy from
Louisiana introduced a bill
to the Senate that said that the
United States should threaten
to withhold military
aid from Saudi Arabia
unless they curtail
oil production to raise
the prices of gasoline and
oil to protect oil producers
in his home state of Louisiana.
Donald Trump responded
to that by calling
the Saudis threatening
to withhold military aid.
The Saudis responded.
They clamped down the taps
and the price of oil went up.
If you go and you look up the
cover of Fox Business, Bloomberg
Business on April 1,
2020, you will see people
praising Donald Trump for
his negotiating skills
because he saved
the US oil industry.
Fast forward two years when the
price of oil was really high.
Myself, Susan Wild,
and Tom Malinowski,
because we're cheeky,
introduced the exact same bill,
but swapped one word and
said the US should with
withhold military aid to Saudi
Arabia unless they ramp up
production so that we
lower the cost of oil
to American consumers.
Senator Cassidy said
clearly we don't understand
how energy prices work.
At that point we had a
Democrat in the White House
and it was not deemed
appropriate to threaten
to withdraw military
aid from the Saudis,
and so we didn't do anything.
So it's hard for me
not to argue that we
have a bipartisan consensus
to prioritize energy producers
over energy consumers.
I'm not happy about that.
I'm just saying that was
arguably the lesson of those two
moments.
You can also see this
in US electric markets.
When FERC Order 1000
was passed to try
to debottleneck some of the
transmission in the country,
prior to that, we were
building about $10 billion
a year of transmission wires.
Almost instantly that
doubled to $20 billion.
Virtually all of the
wires that were built
were built to
enhance reliability,
to get power to places where
there were some shortages
and bottlenecks.
Virtually none was to lower
the price on the grid.
So if you're sitting at
two points on the grid
where one spot is paying
$90 a megawatt-hour,
another place is awash in wind
paying $30 a megawatt-hour,
you would think there would
be an economic incentive
to build that wire, except
that to build that wire,
you need the approval of the
person sitting there at $90.
There's an old saying in
the power industry, which
is patently true, that asking
a utility for permission
to interconnect
to their system is
asking a man to date his wife.
It might be in the
national interest,
but that's not going to be the
fulcrum of the conversation.
And so we've got this huge
challenge in our electric sector
as well of what happens
if you are a utility that
has a return on
equity you have to hit
and the utility regulator wants
to make sure you stay solvent,
and what you know is if
the price of electricity
falls because a bunch of cheap
solar, a bunch of cheap wind
comes onto your grid,
you're not going
to hit your return
on equity targets
and that's going to-- what
do you do in that case?
I'm not-- I'm doing my best to
argue the other side of that
equation, but this conversation
around "do we prioritize energy
producers or consumers"
is a political question.
And the reason why that's
become a political question
is because over the last 20
years, for unrelated reasons,
we went from being a
country, wherever you lived,
you were no more likely to
have Democratic or Republican
representation.
Tom Daschle out in the
Dakotas is a senior member
of the Senate.
Henry Hyde used to represent
my seat in suburban Chicago.
The way that our
country has evolved,
if you live in rural America,
you are almost certainly
represented by a
Republican today.
If you live in urban,
suburban America,
you're almost certainly
represented by a Democrat.
And the parts of
our country that
dig coal, drill
oil, drill gas tend
to be represented
by Republicans.
The parts of our
country that benefit
from having cheap
energy that they
can turn into higher-value
goods and services
tend to be represented
by Democrats.
And so if we were to actually
embrace clean energy, which
is also to embrace
cheap energy, it
would present a massive wealth
transfer from energy producers
to energy consumers, from
red America to blue America,
and that has become a huge
political lightning rod.
And I think one
of the challenges
that we've tried to
do in the Inflation
Reduction Act is to make sure
that we know that we're creating
more wealth than
we're destroying,
but how do we make sure
that everybody gets a slice?
If we follow George Bush's
advice and make the pie higher,
how do we make
sure that everybody
gets a slice of that pie?
And I think that's a
political challenge
we have to be sensitive to.
We can respect where people come
from, even as it sounds crazy,
that that's even a debate.
And the last thing I'll say on
that, and then we can hop down,
is to watch in really
very close time what
happens with the LNG pause
that's underway right now.
The Biden White House--
the Natural Gas Act says that
the Department of Energy cannot
approve a natural gas
export facility unless
it's in the national interest.
There's been this surge
of LNG export capacity
and the Biden White
House said that they
were going to go
through and review
whether the additional capacity
was in the national interest.
Those plants that are
held up by that pause
represent enough CO2 to
essentially basically
match and exceed the current
total CO2 emissions of Europe.
It is a huge carbon bomb
that's sitting there.
If we-- every time there's
been a outage at an export
facility in the United States--
the Freeport facility in Texas
is the one that's happened now
twice, once for maintenance,
once unplanned, the price of gas
in the United States has fallen.
Unsurprisingly, more domestic
supply equals lower price.
Why would you want to
build something that's
a climate disaster and
raises the price of energy
in the United States?
Well, are we doing an
energy policy that's
prioritizing the
interests of consumers
or prioritizing producers?
The White House has paused
that until after the election.
At some point in
the lame duck, they
will make a decision on that.
I have no inside information
about how that goes,
but it's a really,
really big deal.
And I don't know where
they'll sit on it,
but just understand those
to be political questions,
not fundamental policy
questions to understand
how it's going through,
and to the extent
that you choose to
be engaged on that,
understand where
the equities lie.
So I hope that's
helpful as I tried
to be very big
picture at the start,
and I'm sure we'll
get nerdy and wonky,
but look forward to the Q&A.
[APPLAUSE]
That's great.
And I will open it up soon.
I just had a couple of
questions to start with.
You hit on some
pretty big points.
I guess I'd love to hear your
perspective on the first one,
which is that we've
largely decoupled
our growth from energy.
What has led to that?
What are the main causes?
And was it policy-driven?
Was it technology-driven?
So I think the
biggest thing we did
was a commitment to
competitive markets, which
I don't think we could do in the
current political environment.
But in the 1992
Energy Policy Act,
we created wholesale markets
that said for the first time,
we will set the
price of power based
on the lowest-cost generator
that clears the market stack.
And prior to that point, it
was just a cost recovery game.
And almost instantaneously,
the nuclear fleet
went from 60% to 90%
on the same asset base.
A ton of people built
combined-cycle gas plants.
20% of the entire US power
grid was built in 10 years
after that bill was passed.
200 gigawatts of-- I mean,
just shockingly large numbers.
And most of the companies
that built those went
bankrupt because it led to
the price of power collapsing,
and then they didn't
make the money
that they had in
their pro forma,
but we were left with all
these assets that were built.
And then when fracking
happened, all of a sudden you
had a ton of underutilized
high-efficiency gas
turbines that could compete
the Dickens against the coal
industry.
And so the coal industry was
basically dead to rights by '95,
it just took them 15
years to realize it.
And so you've seen the collapse.
And yes, there have been a
lot of state issues with RPSs,
and the huge decline
in solar and wind costs
have made a difference there as
well and that surge of capacity.
But I think that was probably
the biggest single piece that
drove that along.
Were you living in that
industry at the time?
I got out of college in '93.
So I was not working
in the industry.
Full disclosure, my dad
testified before the Senate
in 1976 on what became
PURPA, and then built
the third-qualifying facility
in the country in Trenton,
New Jersey in 1979, so I kind
of grew up in this space.
A little fun fact.
The plant manager of
that plant in Trenton,
New Jersey, QF number 3, was
a guy named Don Lebowitz.
His son Jon changed his
last name to Stewart
and went into comedy.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah.
Oh, interesting.
That'll be our next guest.
Yes, yes, yes.
Backing up a little bit, I
guess one question I had is,
you did have this industry
life before Congress.
So what asset was that--
or is that in DC, having
been in this industry--
or been in energy?
I would imagine that's why
you focused a lot on energy.
Yeah.
So, I mean, let me be
philosophical for a moment.
One of the best pieces of advice
I got when I came to Congress
was Jamie Raskin said to me, "Go
around and ask your colleagues
why they ran because this
job makes you really broad,
but the reason you ran
is where your depth is.
And if you find out
where people's depth is,
then when bills come up and you
want to know what you should
work on, that's the
area to go through."
And I say that, number one,
because it's great advice,
but also because
being the guy who
has raised a couple of hundred
million dollars, deployed--
fought with all the fights
in the utility industry,
got scars in my back
from doing that,
understands how energy
markets work gives me
a depth that certainly
other members don't have.
Every member has depth
that I don't have as well.
And I think Congress
at its best has
a group of members who represent
the diversity of industries
and experiences in
America to go bring that,
and you try to be the person
who can bring that vertical,
if you will.
Yeah.
And diving a little bit
deeper into that vertical,
so one of the
things that we often
think about is, what
is the right role
of the federal
government through FERC?
And what is the right role of
the RTOs, the independent system
operators of large
wholesale markets?
And what is the right
role for states?
Which have their PUCs.
And where do you
fall in on that?
If I had a clean
sheet of paper, I
wouldn't design anything like
the balkanized system we have.
So the right role, clearly
what we're doing is not right.
I mean, the numbers are insane.
We've got about 1,300 gigawatts
of generation in this country.
There are currently 2,000
gigawatts in the queue waiting
to interconnect.
Of that 2,000 in the queue,
there's 1 gigawatt of coal,
85 gigawatts of natural gas,
and all of the rest is storage
and renewables.
It is insane that those
can't come online,
and a big part of the problem
is the RTOs and the ISOs that
have horrible
governance structures
and are captured by their
membership, essentially.
And I think we could do a
much better job of essentially
holding them to account.
Like, yes, you have
to have reliability,
but you also should be helping
your states meet their meet
their decarbonization targets.
You should be shortening
the interconnection queue,
not extending it.
You should be decongesting
those nodes in your system
that cause prices to fall.
And I think they've done a
terrible job of doing that.
FERC is arguably the only
place that can fix that,
but even at FERC, they
can't reach into the states.
And a lot of these
issues are state-level.
Ultimately state
jurisdictional issues.
As we were joking
over lunch, tell me
where your opinions
are on states' rights
and I will find another place
where you contradict yourself.
It depends on where you sit.
But we can do a--
we need to do a much better job
on putting the consumer first.
And for those who aren't as
deep as Representative Casten,
in some places you could build
a solar farm or a wind farm
and it won't be
five to seven years
before you could turn it on to
interconnect into the system.
And so how do we fix that?
We recently put a paper in
Science that we'll send you,
but on some thoughts on how
to do that, do you have--
other than FERC throwing
more weight around,
which they seem to be
reluctant to do, what is the--
Well--
Is it a bill?
Is it--
So, I mean, my general theory
of the case and the theory
that informed--
Mike Levitt and I have this bill
that CETA, the Clean Electricity
Transmission Act--
I think what it stands
for-- that fix this.
And our thesis of
the case, which
I think differs from some
other bills out there,
is that if you fix
the profit incentives,
the permitting problem is easy.
If you don't fix the
profit incentives,
the permitting
problem is a mandate
where you're
compelling people to do
something that are against
their economic interest.
And so right now in the
current rule structure--
I mean, personal story, I used
to run a utility in Upstate New
York.
I never--
When did that happen?
It was a subsidiary of ours at--
OK.
I never made as much money in
that company, or me personally
in my bonus, as when the
polar vortex hit and spiked
the price of power on that
system and all of a sudden
we could make a lot of
money selling power.
It would not have been in
my personal self-interest
to decongest that node.
And so I'm not--
I mean, trust me, I'm God's
gift to the American people,
I'm not at all selfish.
[LAUGHS] I'm also really glad
I got that bonus that year.
[LAUGHS] How do we, I
think, as regulators, how
do we change the
incentives so that if I
can lower the cost
to my consumers,
that's not a zero-sum
conversation?
And one of the things that we
did when we ran that entity was
we got New York State to
regulate us as a for-profit
cooperative so that we got a--
once we hit a target
return on capital,
we had to share $0.50 of every
dollar with our customers.
And so instead of the current
utility model where you get
a guaranteed recovery on your
capital and everything else is
a pass-through, but there are
pass-throughs at certain rates
and you can find ways
to game that system,
we had to look back at the end
of the year and say we exceeded
our target return and we're
going to exceed it by 50% beyond
that, and you keep
the other $0.50.
And it just created a
much better alignment.
We did that because
it was the only way
that we knew to have
an incentive to invest
in efficiency and conservation.
I think you could imagine
all sorts of structures
like that at the state,
local, RTO, national level.
Performance-based
rate-making, I think,
is the broad umbrella
for that idea,
but there's a lot of
different flavors of that
that could go get it done.
And it just makes the
permitting problem easier,
because now you both have
an economic incentive
to build this stuff.
Instead of saying,
well, I'm going
to fund a astroturf grassroots
operation to convince you
that wind turbines cause cancer
so that you file a NEPA ruling
and prevent people from
bringing this wire on,
we've all seen that
game played out.
Yeah.
And is that a
bipartisan issue in DC?
Fixing--
It is bipartisan to oppose
competitive markets.
[LAUGHTER]
I mean, I mean it.
Nobody comes to Washington and
says "My industry needs to be
more competitive."
And I think our
best regulation has
made industry more competitive,
but it's always hard to do it.
There's a great line--
Justice Brandeis, who is--
basically made the Sherman
Antitrust Act what it is.
The act was passed by
Congress, but then Brandeis
had these various rulings, and
he's got this great line in one
of his rulings that he said.
"When you reach points of
great wealth inequality,"
as we are right now, but
he was writing this back
in the '20s, he said, "you
basically have three choices.
You can either have government
takeover the capital,
which is to embrace communism;
you can have capital takeover
the government, which
is to embrace fascism;
or you can embrace competition
and market discipline."
And we as a country
have succeeded
when we've embraced door 3.
We have forces on both sides
of our political divide pushing
for doors 1 and
doors 2 right now.
And it's really hard to find--
I mean, again, nobody comes in.
Google does not come in and
say, "We really control too much
of the search space and we're
able to price uncompetitively."
That's not a conversation
that ever happens.
Well, I think you're seeing that
on the issue of tariffs, right?
Tariffs-- the international--
lowering international
trade seems
to be potentially
a bipartisan issue.
Well, we certainly are at
a protectionist moment.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And that pendulum
swings back and forth,
but I think there's a separate
issue than the support
for competitive markets.
That's always been, I
think, a lonely space.
Yeah.
One more question,
then I'll open it up.
You mentioned that we run this
huge risk of basically sending
money from red
areas to blue areas.
And you also mentioned
the Inflation
Reduction Act was one of the
first pieces of legislation
I saw that admitted that and
embraced it and tried to fix it.
How do you think that's going?
And will that provide
actual further support
for the Inflation--
So I want to just brag a
little bit on myself here.
I was on the Climate
Committee for four years
and we created the set of
700 policy recommendations
about what to do.
300 of those became law in
the Inflation Reduction Act.
And one of the handful of
things that I really insisted on
in our climate
report was that we
have to expand the definition
of environmental justice
communities to include
those communities that
have historically been
hurt by pollution,
but also those communities that
are going to be left behind
in the transition.
And I'm just I'm
particularly proud of that
because when you look at where
the investments in the IRA
are going right
now, they are going
to a lot of these communities.
And so as we think
about whatever happens
in a future political
cycle, it really
matters that there's a
battery manufacturing
facility in Marjorie
Taylor Greene's district
because she now has
constituents pushing for that.
One of my theories of Washington
is that losers will always
cry louder than winners cheer.
Because if you have
something to lose,
you know the stakes of
keeping that policy in place.
If you have something
to gain, you're
probably not even paying
that much attention
to the policy debate.
And so by creating a
whole lot of communities
around the country that see
clean energy as an employer,
as a provider of jobs,
as the thing that
kept the Walmart open, not as
just the thing that stealing
jobs from our
community, it matters
to build a political will.
But it also matters because
at the end of the day,
we're all Americans.
I mean, I could think of
every great political speech.
"We are not red America,
we're not blue America,
we're all Americans."
If you want to go
back behind that,
Thomas Paine said that the--
our lesser distinction
varies with the place;
our great title
is as Americans."
We've got to make sure that
we're lifting everybody up
or we're not doing it right.
Yeah.
And just to plug MIT work,
when Brian Deese, who's now--
Yeah, yeah.
--a Climate Fellow here,
and when he came here,
he created the Clean
Investment Monitor.
It's a very slick website.
You can go to the website.
He did that joint with CEEPR,
the center that I direct.
And it's showing
with actual data
that a majority of the money
is going into red districts.
Yeah, yeah.
Now we have this thing
called the Battery Belt.
Yeah, Yeah.
No, I will say,
one of the things
that is a bit of a challenge
for a lot of us is the--
if it's going to red districts
because we prioritize
going to communities that
are going to be left behind,
that's a positive if it's
going to red districts
because those are
districts that have
lower environmental permitting
standards, lower labor
standards-- because
they're also going
to a lot of
right-to-work states.
And I think there is a challenge
of we don't want to leave people
behind, but we also don't want
to have a race to the bottom
on local zoning standards.
And I think we're
going to have to see
more data to know how much
from column A and how much
from column B, but I don't
think it's 100% either.
Good point, yeah, yeah.
Well, I'm happy to
open it up for--
I have more questions, but
why don't we take a few hands.
And you want me to call on them
or do you want to call on them?
The first one I saw
is that lady there.
Hi, lady.
Do we have mics?
Or what--
I can speak loudly.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
You can hear me.
That's what matters.
OK, so three quick questions.
That's more than I asked.
Come on!
[LAUGHTER]
So [INAUDIBLE].
Not putting the--
Is it on?
Yes.
It's on.
OK, there we go.
You mentioned Brian Deese.
Your take on the clean
energy Marshall Plan
proposal, number one.
Number two, is great power
competition with China
and the domestic
content provisions
in the IRA helpful or hurtful?
And then number three, how do
we think about hyperscalers
and them opening up the
dialogue with nuclear energy?
So I'm not familiar with the
first or the third question,
so let me just take
the second one.
So there's a protectionist
moment in China.
Part of, I think, the
China conversation
relates to what I
was saying about what
is US industrial policy?
I think in hindsight, we did
a pretty good job in the IRA,
but I think in hindsight,
we should have said--
instead of saying, you
get this tax credit
only if you have 100%
domestic content,
we should have had
some phase-ins.
And if you look how we did EV
and solar, on the solar side,
it's a stacked.
On the EV side, it's
an all-or-nothing.
And I think we should
have had something
that acknowledged that--
we were speaking earlier,
how many MIT students
over the last 30 years
were foreign nationals,
got a PhD, maybe even got a
patent, applied for a visa,
and we said, no,
you can't get one?
And so they went back
to their home countries.
They learned how to
scale up over there.
And now we're saying, well, we
want this content to be here,
but we don't actually have the
skillsets to scale up here.
And I think in hindsight,
we should have said,
we'll give you a five-year
subsidy incentive,
but we got some
clawbacks, and you're
going to have to
build a factory here.
And you could have
imagined ways,
I think, to recognize that that
hollowing-out of manufacturing
in the US can't come back
immediately, so that's an issue.
There is-- I think there
are larger and very thorny
conversations about
the US and the PRC
as far as industrial espionage
and control of supply chains.
Those are very real.
There are issues about
the long-term strength
of the Chinese economy that I
think are vastly overstated.
I would much rather be
running the US economy
than the Chinese
economy right now given
some of the trajectories
of where things are going.
And I think we've I think
we've gotten very comfortable
with demonizing the threat
of the Chinese economy,
but their forward trajectory
is not very positive right now.
Would you say the
same thing about a lot
of the fear among my colleagues
that work in transportation
is China's potential
dominance of EVs and minerals,
are those things we
should guard against?
We should-- the Milton
Friedmans of the world would say
embrace it.
Let them sell us cheap EVs.
Where do you--
I mean, if I'm just a
purely economic purist,
like, I want us to
do the stuff where
we have the maximum value-add.
I'm much more
interested in us doing
the high-value-add manufacturing
than running the mine.
And yeah, the mine
is-- those mines
and the processing
cells are probably
going to be near where the
geological deposits are.
So personally, I
worry less about that.
I'm not saying that those supply
chain issues don't matter,
but I think--
there is a certain,
shall we say,
cynicism in supporters of the
fossil fuel industry saying,
I'm really concerned
about getting resources
from politically dangerous
parts of the world.
[LAUGHS] And all else
equal, I'd rather
be getting the materials
to build something
that operates in the US
for 20 years than the stuff
that we need every hour
of every day pulling out.
So I guess that's my
economic theory of the case.
Well, there's actual
support for that.
I do think that there's a--
it's easier for us than
some of our allies,
and I think there's
a lot of challenges
as far as how do we manage
inbound and outbound investment?
The German economy is hugely
tethered to the Chinese economy.
They make the machine tools that
go and manufacture over there.
And so I was in
Frankfurt last week.
All the buses in Frankfurt
are BYD Electric Buses.
To talk to the
Germans about, well,
would you put
tariffs on BYD Buses?
They're like, no,
because then we'll
get tariffs going in the back
side on exports from Germany.
And so there's a
tension in Europe
where I think we are
struggling with saying, well,
what if we export to Germany and
then that content goes through,
vice versa?
How do we--
And this is not to say we
need to decouple from China,
but where you have
concerns and controls,
I think some of the
relationships with our allies
are challenging at the moment.
I think the first hand I saw--
OK.
--sorry to make you
walk all the way back
there is in the back row there.
Maybe we turn them
on and leave them on?
Oh, is it-- OK.
Yes, there we go.
Awesome.
So first off, thank you so
much, Representative Casten,
for being here.
It's just really cool to hear
someone in the energy space
speak.
I also have multiple questions.
Just two this time, though.
So I guess the
first question is,
you talked about how
energy and clean energy
isn't a competitive
market, but if you
were to vastly oversimplify it
and say, for whatever reasons--
economic, scientific
policy, whatever,
you're going to be bullish
on one aspect of clean energy
and short one aspect, what
are you being bullish on
and what are you shorting?
And then the second question
is, I guess, sort of related.
So what would you advise a
smart, or at least a not stupid
young person to do who's
interested in clean energy
either in a policy
or a science realm?
Thank you so much.
I'm speaking to a room
of not stupid people.
[LAUGHS] We all
jump over low bars.
So to your second question--
you have to remind
me of your first one
because I've forgotten, but
I remember the second one.
My general advice
is, you're going
to get out of here and you--
you're an MIT student, which
means that you are crazy smart
and you're going to have
a ton of opportunities.
And you are really
good at learning.
You also don't
know that much yet.
And once you get out
into the world from here,
smart people are a dime a dozen.
So find yourself, whether
it's in a policy or a business
environment or whatever is
interesting, just find yourself
in a room where you feel like
the dumbest person in the room
is the single best thing
that you can happen that--
I didn't-- I'm not going to
say I made all the best life
choices, but all the choices
that I think I got right were
the ones where every day I got
into work and was sitting there
saying, these people are
so much smarter than I am,
and I'm learning from them,
and they're actually paying me
to learn, which is insane.
And then as doors
open from that,
just be brave enough
to walk through them.
Because whatever you're
doing in any sector,
being the person
who was, A, smart,
and then was like
consistently learning
is just going to
open opportunities
to 10, 20 years from now
that you can't predict,
but you don't have to do
it all in your first job.
On your first question--
I feel like this is where I
should put the disclaimer.
I am not an investment
professional,
I'm not giving
investment advice.
[LAUGHTER]
I guess I'd say that, broadly
speaking in the energy industry,
it's very easy to predict
what's going to happen,
it's very hard to
predict when because it's
such a capital-intensive
industry
and it takes a long
time to build things,
and once the things are built,
they run for a long time.
And so you can just
look at the system
and say, OK, what assets
are hitting end-of-life?
What assets are new?
What assets are in a
state of good repair?
What assets are not in
a state of good repair?
What assets have the potential
to ramp up and provide
a bunch more than they're
providing right now?
Which ones are
currently maxed out?
And I think if you just take
that in aggregate, the coal
industry is dead.
All the plants that
there are shutting down.
This huge surge of renewables
that's dominating the pipeline
is going to be what the
grid is in the future.
Electric vehicles are the
fastest-growing vehicle segment
not because we got woke,
it's because they're
crazy fun to drive.
And they have no maintenance.
And so everything
that flows from that,
I think you can make a
reasonable bet that those
are going to come through.
Is it going to go at
a predictable pace?
No.
There will be political
backlash one way or the other.
I mean, a lot of the opposition
to woke investing in Washington
is mostly because
those old industries
are getting their butt
kicked in the market.
If you just look at--
forget about the market
value of ExxonMobil, look at
their price earnings ratio.
It's sits at 8 to 9
on a consistent basis.
First solar, Tesla,
NextEra, those companies
are running 20 or 30
or 40 times multiples.
That's telling you that
capital markets are saying,
I trust company A with
my money, and company B,
you are in cash stripping mode.
And so you can see where that
investment is going to come.
And then just start
handicapping, what does it mean?
I was in Denmark over the
summer where they have--
in this little parcel of
ocean between Denmark,
the Netherlands,
and Germany, they
are bringing on-- they've got
15 gigawatts of offshore wind
tenders open right now.
That's-- what's the New England
power grid, 25 gigawatts,
I think?
This is a huge amount
of offshore wind
being built in this tiny spot.
And the Danish
government is saying,
we don't have paths
to sell that out,
which means the price of power
is going to collapse in Denmark.
And they're trying to
find a way to-- can
we attract steel mills or
hydrogen manufacturing?
Because if we don't,
some crypto knucklehead
is going to come in
here and mine Bitcoin
because it's going
to be so cheap.
What is the future?
Like, I don't know
how to predict that,
but these are real
problems that are
going to happen because you've
got so much cheap energy coming
in there.
So I'm not predicting how
that will walk through,
but I think dealing
in a world that
is awash in very cheap energy
is a really interesting world.
But there will be,
like all transitions,
some people make
a bunch of money
and some people will build
some really cool assets
and they will go bankrupt.
All right, I'm going to--
Whoa, that's a lot of hands.
I'm going to limit
to one question.
And I'll call-- we'll go here.
Is that Kurt?
Yeah, Kurt?
Boston Marathon.
Love it.
Thanks.
I have a question.
Thinking about
your constituents--
and I ask in part because I grew
up in Crystal Lake, Illinois.
I would have been
in your district
if I hadn't moved away in 1985.
It's great to see you.
I no longer have Crystal Lake.
I used to before redistricting,
but redistricting
moved a little bit south.
But it's a lovely community.
Anyway.
This space is moving so fast
and there's so much information
for people to keep up with.
And I'm wondering
what perspective
you might have on what
sort of literacies
you wish your constituents had
and constituents more broadly
in our representative
government ought
to have to just be more
effective in moving
this stuff forward?
I want to believe that we can
move in the direction of valuing
what the consumers need in a
more balanced way, for instance.
I mean, that's a deep
political philosophy question.
I think it is hard to look
at some of my colleagues
and have a very high view
of the American voter.
[LAUGHTER]
My own constituents
are exceptional.
At least 53% of them
in the last election.
[LAUGHTER]
I mean, I think my
philosophical answer
is I think that's a
give-and-take kind
of conversation.
I mean, my own
view of politics is
that you have this amazing
job where you have access
to every professional you want.
I mean, last week I'm talking--
I'm meeting with
Christine Lagarde.
Before that, I'm
with Gary Gensler.
You can get any information
you want on any subject.
And I think there's
a certain obligation
to go out and communicate
with your constituents,
help them understand.
And in so doing that,
trust their judgment.
If you agree with what I'm
saying and you like the way
I make decisions on that
and you vote for me,
then I'm now empowered
to continue doing that.
I haven't communicated,
I can't complain
if you don't vote for me.
And if you don't
vote for me and I've
told you what's really
valuable and important to me,
then I'm probably not
the right representative.
But I think that takes
like a two-way conversation
I'm hugely addicted
to town halls
and I do them all the time.
It is, frankly, been
very challenging
since the war in Gaza because
they've been disrupted so often.
And it makes me sad
because now you've
got this two-way conversation
that doesn't happen,
regardless of where
your views are,
but if we can't have rooms
where those conversations can
happen even if we
disagree with each other.
But I think democracy is weaker.
So it's a very
philosophical conversation,
but your job is not to
understand everything,
but I think we should
maximize the opportunities
for two-way conversations.
So the gentleman
in the gray shirt.
Hi.
Thanks for a great talk today.
So I come from China,
and I feel something that
is happening back in China.
So the energy storage
industry in China
is actually facing a problem
because the electricity
market in China is, let's
say, close to nothing.
So even if it was
a cheap batteries,
we need to make profits, right?
So sole driving force for
storage installation in China
is that our wind or solar farms
must come with two or four
hours of storage capacity, and
this has been removed this year.
So the energy storage industry
is facing some really serious
challenges recently.
So I guess my
question is that, do
you think with the right
upper-level policy or market
design, even if the United
States are now building
the energy system grids with
the more expensive components,
with the right policy with
the right [INAUDIBLE].
So to repeat what we'd said
in our meeting beforehand,
there's--
I've not seen any model of
how the US can decarbonize
without building more
transmission storage
and nuclear than anybody
thinks is politically possible.
That doesn't mean
we can't do it,
it just means we haven't
thought of the tools yet.
And I think from an energy
market design perspective,
I think it's an
open question, and I
can argue both sides of this,
of should we design markets such
that there is a sufficient price
spread between on- and off-peak
pricing, that you can justify
the investment in energy storage
system and we'll just have this
all captured in the system?
But at the expense of
that, have somebody
on a fixed income
suddenly saying
that they've got to turn
their air conditioner off
in the middle of a hot day
because the price of power
went so high?
Or should we have
something like described
in China that says we're just
going to mandate that you build
these systems around here,
which is basically how we built
out the US power grid, right?
We electrified
rural America, not
by saying it is economic
to provide power
to the end of the line in some
one-horse town in Nebraska.
We did it by saying we're
going to cross-subsidize
across the whole system and
you'll recover your costs
from elsewhere.
And I don't think anybody's got
the exact right balance there,
and it's always going to be a
mix of capitalism and socialism,
and sometimes
we'll get it right,
sometimes we'll get it
wrong, sometimes we'll
create massive arbitrage
opportunities across the spread.
But I don't think it's a
question of can we, it's
we don't have a choice.
We have to.
To say that we're not going to
decarbonize because we haven't
invented the right economic
model is to give up,
and I'm not willing to do that.
Oh my gosh, we have
time for one more.
But I'm going to make Tom mad
and I'm going to take two more.
So we'll do the gray sweater
there, and then Anja.
Did you have a question?
Gray sweater first?
Hello, gray sweater.
Yeah.
Thank you.
My question was about the
higher prices and the PJM grid.
And we talked a lot about how
energy is becoming cheaper,
but there's this
big spike there,
and how do we understand
what's going on there?
Should we expect that
elsewhere in the short-term?
Yeah.
So when I say that energy
is becoming cheaper,
I say that from the
perspective of a former energy
developer who--
I don't know how to get a
plant financed unless you
can say that this plant will
deliver power at a lower
cost than where the system is
and will make a spread on where
that market is.
And every renewable
generation technology
delivers a return on
investment on that thesis.
Whether or not that leads
to lower prices to consumers
is a question about the
regulatory structure.
Are you going to give
people guaranteed recovery
on their capital?
Because if you were to shift
from a totally amortized
coal-intensive grid to a
100% solar and storage grid,
you would go from a grid with
high marginal operating cost
to a grid with zero
marginal operating
cost, but all of a sudden you'd
have to amortize the capital.
And if you let people
amortize that capital,
you'd raise the price.
If you didn't let them
amortize the capital,
they'd never make
the investment.
Every market is grappling with
that in slightly different ways.
And without speaking to
PJM versus any other grid,
it does get into this tension.
This is what I
said about, are we
prioritizing consumers
or investors?
Because PJM, like every RTO,
has done a really bad job
of bringing power to those
nodes where the price is high.
To bring it down, we've
been going back and forth
now for three years
on this SOO Green Line
because Iowa is awash
in excess wind power,
Chicago has high-priced
power that the wind in Iowa
would love to sell.
They've got an HVDC line
that wants to run through.
And a lot of people
within PJM are not
really keen to have a
bunch of cheap power coming
into the grid.
I'm sympathetic to it because
if you brought it in, then
you're going to say, well,
then why would somebody build?
And it's the challenge
of clean energy.
It eats its investment thesis.
That's a really good
problem to have,
but it's a problem,
especially in a world that
has rewarded utilities
for deploying capital,
but has not necessarily
rewarded them
for lowering the cost of power.
And that's a fixable problem.
The RTOs and ISOs have some
ability to fix the problem.
The state utilities
regulators have some ability,
FERC has some ability.
No one is king.
If there's a way to run for
that job, I will take it.
But it's very balkanized.
Thanks for giving me
the last question.
I want to come back to
what you said initially
about the decoupling between
the growth of the economy
and the carbon emissions.
And I'm wondering if
part of that picture
is also the fact
that we've exported
carbon-intensive manufacturing
to other countries,
and if we bring
manufacturing back to the US,
will that reverse the trend,
at least in the short-term
and to a certain degree?
There's certainly, I think--
and I've not parsed the numbers.
Certainly there are
some things that we
don't make as much
in the US anymore
that used to be made in the
US that are carbon-intensive.
But I think if you
look at broad--
total energy use in the
United States has not slowed.
We've just shifted
to lower-carbon ways
to generate that energy.
It is unambiguously true
that the nuclear fleet
is generating a lot more
nuclear power per megawatt
of installed capacity
than it used to.
It's unambiguously
true that we're
generating a ton
of renewable power
that we didn't use to generate.
And so a lot of that
is a legitimate shift.
There is an export
problem that I
think we have to be
really sensitive to, which
is that we-- as much
as I love Norway,
I don't think we want
to become Norway where
we have a zero-carbon
economy that's
subsidized by exporting a ton
of fossil fuel to other people.
I've had somewhat
heated conversations
with some of our
Executive Branch partners
that when we say the United
States is decarbonizing,
and that US contractors
should report on their Scope 3
emissions, the US government is
not reporting on our own Scope 3
emissions as we ramp up
those exports overseas.
So I do think we need to be--
the numbers that I talked
about, about our economy
decarbonizing, I was talking
about energy consumption, not
energy production because
in that same period,
while coal use is--
oil use is flat, oil
production is growing.
Natural gas use
is growing at 25%,
natural gas exports
are up by 500%.
And so there's a
huge pressure for us
to export our carbon
emissions elsewhere.
And some of the
conversations that I've
been having, we'll see
how successfully with some
of our executive
branch colleagues,
is if you invented the cell
phone, should you export,
sell technology to
the rest of the world,
or should you export your
rotary phone technology?
If we've figured out how to
grow our economy without growing
fossil fuel use, should we
export the technologies that
have allowed us to do that?
Or should we send
them LNG tankers?
And I think one of the--
I think one of the
missed opportunities
we had after Russia invaded
Ukraine, hugely important
that we had the ability
to send LNG to Europe
to get them off Russian gas.
Number one, we didn't
sell it to them at cost.
We sold it to them because you
could make a lot more money
selling that to a Rotterdam
hub than at Henry hub
and we made money on
the spread and that
brought a bunch of money back.
Number two, why didn't we
do a Defense Production
Act for heat pumps?
Ramp up-- help get as much
efficiency in there as possible.
And looking backwards,
that makes me sad.
Looking forward, that's
an amazing opportunity.
And I think maybe that's like
my uplifting end here of we
have this opportunity
to have our cake
and eat it, too, to massively
decarbonize and grow our economy
if we make the right choices
in these next very few years.
That's the decisive
turning point.
So that's on you all.
Perfect time to stop.
That was definitely
the last word.
[LAUGHTER]
I want to thank
Congressman Casten.
Professor Knittel.
I want to thank all
of you for coming.
We have a reception downstairs.
I hope you come down, and
maybe Professor Casten,
if his voice lasts, they'll be
happy to talk a little bit more.
I also wanted to just
advertise two more events.
Tomorrow in this room at 5:00
PM, we have a discussion,
The Role of Fusion in a
Decarbonized Energy System.
So I hope to see you there.
And then on Monday in 32-123, we
have the movie Switch On, which
is a documentary about energy
access in developing countries,
followed by a discussion
with Scott Tinker,
the Founder of the Switch
Energy Alliance, and Rob Stoner,
the Founding Director of the
MIT Tata Center for Technology
and Design.
So now please join me
in thanking Professor--
I mean Congressman Casten again.
You're a professor.
[APPLAUSE]