let me introduce my colleague tiisha
dinker manager of
Partnerships engagement at
MIT startup exchange who will host the
startup lightening talks uh light
lightning talk session welcome
Tisha thank you Graham and good morning
or good afternoon or even good evening
it's an honor to be here this morning
and to introduce the MIT startup
lightning talks today you'll be hearing
from three companies and following each
presentation there will be a brief
audience L Q&A so during the
presentations you can be entering your
questions directly into the chat box all
three of the presenting startups are
part of the MIT startup
exchange the startup exchange was
created within MIT corporate relations
to support MIT connected startups as
they grow and address Global challenges
MIT startup exchange Fosters these
collaborations of Partnerships between
startups and Industry such as ILP
members and throughout the MIT
Innovation
ecosystem MIT startup exchange it
focuses on startups with a strong and
eligible connection to the Institute and
this connection could be through the
founding team the technology as well as
their affiliation to our MIT peers who
vet and support them such as start. Nano
the engine or Cale connect
plus today we have a network of about
1,000 startups virtually working in any
sector and this is possible because they
come out of any of the five schools in
one college some are created during NBAs
or other courses and many startups
graduate from other entrepreneurial
resources and there are or are over 80
here on MIT campus you can find most of
these resources at orbit. mit.edu that
our colleagues from The Martin trust
center created but another key
distinction of the MIT startup exchange
is that we typically start working with
startups when they have a technology or
a product that is ready to be tested or
used in a real
environment everything we do here at
startup exchange is to expose and
connect startups to Industry through a
highly curated approach so this includes
launching calls for startups to respond
to corporate challenges or New Market
opportunities and R&D Partnerships it's
one-on-one meetings and events such as
demo days that are virtual startup
lightning talks like today and Pitch
sessions and then the learning
opportunities are provided at workshops
that we co-organize with our MIT peers
the goal of all of these activities is
to ultimately help startups validate
pivot or scale acquire customers expand
and corporates to learn to improve the
internal processes to expand their
portfolio or to create new business
opportunities so right here this is just
a small sample of the success cases
we've had to date that include proofs of
concept uh Pilots joint development
acquis positions uh this could be you
one day on either end so we do encourage
you to to stay in touch to connect
through your program director for ILP me
Members um or to reach out to our team
here at MIT startup
exchange and now it's time to hear from
three MIT startup exchange companies
about their approach to Urban Innovation
we will have audience Le Q&A as I noted
throughout the presentation so please be
sure to enter your questions in the chat
box