Hi, welcome to Robbesity Machine
Learning Competition tackling metabolic
diseases and thank you for joining us.
My name is Chiago Batista and I'm a
senior scientist at the Broad Institute
where as part of the Bro Diabetes
Initiative, I work to apply functional
genomics to understand the genetic risk
of cardtabolic diseases. Together with
Julie Laffy, we've put together a
three-part lecture series to introduce
adipose biology, its role in metabolic
diseases, and how we may use machine
learning to better understand and treat
these complex diseases. In recent years,
our ability to perturb genes as a way to
understand their function has
dramatically expanded. Now by bringing
these approaches to disease relevant
cellar models in combination with
complex highdimensional and multimodal
data we have the unique opportunity to
convert disease biology insights into
therapeutic solutions.
However to interpret and derive
translational insights from such complex
data we also require advances in machine
learning methods. And that's where you
will have the chance to bring your
skills to really make a difference.
So let's get started.
First I'll give an overview of the crash
course. We'll have three lectures going
from the biology of adipos tissue and
its contribution to metabolic diseases.
Then we'll follow to talk about the
technologies to perturbosite biology and
we'll talk about the data that we
assemble for this competition and the
three crunches that we'll be working on
during the challenge.
So let's start with the biology of
adipose tissue and its role in metabolic
disease. In this lecture, we'll cover
three key topics.
What is adipose tissue? Edipost tissue
and metabolic diseases and how is
edipost tissue formed. So what is
adipose tissue?
Adipose tissue or most commonly known as
fat tissue is found throughout the body
either right under the skin or what we
call subcutaneous adipose tissue or in
close proximity to the internal organs.
That's what we call visceral adipost
tissue. The main cell type of adipos
tissue are the adiposytes which can be
subdivided into white adipocytes, brown
adiposytes and beige adipocytes which
will share functions with both white and
brown adipocytes.
An adipose tissue serves many functions
to support our body. It can provide
thermal insulation so we can maintain
our body temperature. It provides
mechanical protection and intraorgan
cushioning and also it provides a safe
harbor for lipid storage and handling
which is linked to the many metabolic
functions of adapost tissue. Adipost
tissue particularly white adapost tissue
it's a major site for lipid storage and
release when necessary.
After a meal, our food will be converted
into glucose, amino acids and fatty
acids which are a kind of lipids
and reach the adiposytes through the
bloodstream
which then will be converted into lipids
and stored under structures that we know
as lipid droplets.
Now under conditions of prolonged
starvation, code exposure or ex
extensive exercise,
our body will send signals to the
adipose tissue. So these stored lipids
can be released into the bloodstream and
reach distal organs to be utilized as
energy sources.
And in between cycling this storage and
release functions, adipose tissue plays
a critical role in the regulation of
energy homeostasis and maintaining blood
glucose levels.
In most cell types, including white
adiposytes, nutrients are processed in
the mitochondria by the TCA cycle which
will result in energy production in form
of ATP.
Now in brown and beige adiposytes
there's the expression of a special
protein known as uncoupling protein one
or UCP1 which can bypass this energy
producing step and generate heat
instead.
We call this energy dissipating process
thermogenesis and it's currently under
active investigation by researchers as a
tool to promote energy expenditure to
combat metabolic diseases.
In addition to energy storage and
thermogenesis, adipose tissue also
contributes to metabolism through
communication with other parts of the
body. This involved the release of
bioactive molecules which will include
peptides and hormones, metabolites,
inflammatory cytoines and others which
will enter the bloodstream reaching
distal organs such as the brain, muscle,
liver and others where will regulate
functions including appetite, energy
expenditure and others.
In addition to adiposytes, adipos tissue
also contain many other cell types that
will support its function. Recent
progress in single cell transcripttoics
which is a method that enable us to
measure gene expression patterns in
individual cells has dramatically
expanded our understanding of the cell
types that compose adapost tissue. So
here's a general workflow where we can
go from sampling
tissues from donors. We can either
process or freeze those for later uh
experiments and then we can go under
single nucleus or single cell uh
sequencing workflows.
With this data, we can map not only the
adiposytes but other many cell types
that will include endothelial and other
vascular cell types, many classes of
immune cells and also adipos adipocy
progenitors.