okay um so I'm uh Kevin O'Brien
associate professor in ECS here and I'm
going to tell you about Quantum circuits
or you can think of this as diving
deeper into the physical system that
will Oliver talked about um earlier this
this morning um and I want to talk about
some of the challenges associated with
this field and some of the solutions
that that we can um create using our our
research here so at a high level I want
to talk about how um we can go from this
stage of of quantum Computing which will
Oliver was likening to the the First
Flight of the um of the right flyer um
to the stage of commercial use
commercially useful applications and
what kinds of technological improvements
particularly what kinds of basic
research improvements uh do we need to
go uh from the current level of of
quantum computers to this commercially
useful
stage and one thing that you you know
heard this morning but I want to
emphasize is that Quantum Computing is
really happening now the current
state-of-the-art uh we have a few
hundred non-air corrected Quantum uh
cubits these are real quantum computers
they're perhaps not uh capable of doing
useful computation yet um for practical
applications it's thought that we will
need hundreds to thousands of error
corrected cubits Each of which will be
made of a number of non-error corrected
cubits and here's a couple of the uh
public commercial companies uh building
these these
chips and you might ask is is quantum
Computing physics or or is it
engineering and you know you can look
online and you can find data sheets for
quantum computers so we're seeing that
there's a there's indeed a transition to
engineering um but and another thing to
emphasize is that quantity and quality
are are both required you need a large
number of cubits and you need cubits
with a very low error rate
and small numbers of cubits with high
error rates um even with low error rates
this is something that you can
classically simulate very easily on a a
laptop as as arum was was telling you
earlier as you increase the number of
cubits um it's thought that there there
may or may not be uh near-term
applications in this so-called nisk era
but as you increase the number of cubits
as you um Implement error correction
then we can utilize the the known useful
error corrected um Quantum
algorithms uh but we have a long ways to
go to to get to this point
how far do we have to go well it depends
on your assumptions and these
assumptions are constantly changing if
you for example assume a a 2d nearest
neighbor connectivity a surface code
Gates applied at 10 MHz error rate of
10us 5 um in this 2018 uh Quantum
competing progress and uh prospects
National Academy's report it was
estimated that it would take 10 the 6 to
10 the 7 physical cubits to do something
like break RSA using uh Shores algorithm
and as you
uh as the physical cubits improve as the
quantum error correction algorithms
improve then then these assumptions may
change and the number of cubits may be
may be smaller but this is really orders
of magnitude beyond the current
state-of-the-art but not so far that
it's not in that it's infeasible so it's
so it's a really exciting time to be in
this research
field now how can we transition quantum
computers from physics experiments into
useful products it's a bit of an
electrical engineering joke do you just
sub I with minus J uh but more seriously
uh Quantum Computing really needs
engineers and their talents and experti
to to get to this level um this talk is
going to focus a lot on electrical
engineering because I'm in the
electrical engineering computer science
department but really all varieties of
of engineering experience are are
critically important in in making this
transition so I'm going to EMP I'm going
to talk about some of the the research
in my group and how that um interfaces
with superc conducting Quantum Computing
and some of the questions that um we're
really interested in is what are the
fundamental limits on system performance
imposed by quantum mechanics how can we
engineer systems to reach these limits
and can can these limits be surpassed
can are we missing some tricks in
quantum mechanics that that allow us to
do better than than
that so Ike showed you some uh Ike and
will showed you some images of of superc
conducting quantum computers um with
lots of wires going up uh up and down
the the cryostat this stage is probably
at 10 to 20 Melvin the stages are
progressively warmer in operation of
course these have metal metal canisters
like matoska d you know like a matoska
dowel um isolating each of the lower
temperature stages from the higher
temperature stages and lots of wires
going back and
forth and one one thing that I don't
know if it's it's uh clear to people
outside the field is that the quantum
processors themselves the chips they're
only a few centimeters by a few
centimeters on on a side the the rest of
this is just control and measurement
infrastructure so anything that we can
do and this is this is only for order of
hundreds of cubits um the whereas we're
going to need Millions so there are
massive improvements to the
infrastructure that that are needed um
and some of these pieces of
infrastructure they interact in in
really detrimental ways for example your
cubits are extremely sensitive to
magnetic fields whereas the circulators
and isolators required to protect uh
components from each other they have
they generate strong magnetic fields um
we also need massive infrastructure
improvements to Multiplex cubic control
and measurement develop non-magnetic
isolators and circulators cryogenic
control Hardware as as Ike was talking
about placing instead of having wires
going up and down these fridges placing
the control Hardware at one of these
lower stages um so I'm going to talk
about the measurement problem and some
of the ways in which you can develop
amplifiers to Multiplex these
measurements um to reduce the burden of
the the measurement chain so first I
want to ask how do you measure a
superconducting
cubit so as as background you may
remember this from the first talk but
I'll I'll review it um if you make an LC
resonator or LC oscillator um looking at
this Quantum mechanically it will have
discrete energy levels and this is not a
cubit this has equally spaced energy
levels well this this is not uh a cubit
in the way that we would typically use
it because these energy levels are
equally spaced so when you apply a
microwave drive you end up exciting a
bunch of different levels um and you
excite a a coherent state in this
resonator which looks like a classical
state in the in the in this resonator so
something that will um energy will
oscillate back and forth between the
electric and magnetic fields at a
certain frequency to turn this into a
cubit we use something called the Joseph
injunction which for the purpose of this
talk you can think of as a nonlinear
inductor where um the current phase
relationship
uh uh defining the inductance normally
for a linear inductor the the current is
related to the flux through the inductor
by one over the inductance in a JIS
injunction it's related by the this
Factor we call the the Jose and
inductance divided by this cosine of of
fi and that cosine of fi when when fi
gets large enough this creates
nonlinearity and this is the ingredient
that we need to to make cubits and as
we'll we'll talk about later this is
also the ingredient we use to to build
amplifiers to measure the
cubits so when we replace that linear
inductor with a josus injunction then
the level spacing becomes not equal so
notice that this level spacing is
different than this level spacing is
different than this level spacing so you
can apply a microwave drive and excite
the Cubit from 0o to one and vice versa
or excite it into super position states
of of 0o and
one and there are lots of Engineering
trade-offs in how how you design this
this and harmonicity so now we see these
two ingredients this resonator and this
Cubit now you might ask how do you how
do you measure the state of a cubit
using one of these resonators and my my
students uh nor the organizers would let
me bring a delution refrigerator uh on
stage with me but I I do have something
maybe almost as good so I brought with
me um this this aluminum beverage can um
and I'm I have connected to it something
called a nanov Vector Network analyzer
um this is sort of borrowing from a demo
of a um electromagnetic engineering
class that I teach with Luca Daniel and
um and Yelena notos previous speaker um
and what it does is it sends out uh
microwaves at different frequencies and
measures the the the reflected response
and what I'm plotting here is the
amplitude of the
response as a function of frequency from
2.1 65 GHz to 2.2 GHz as well as the
phase of the response and we see that
there's this dip here and this dip is
associated with the Resonance of the of
this resonator
and the way you measure a cubit is you
you you can actually put the Cubit
inside of this resonator and that's
actually how people did it when the
field first started they would build 3D
resonators and physically put the Cubit
inside of it and the Cubit and the
resonator they they interact through
this some of the nonlinearity of the
Cubit it's inherited by this Cubit
resonator interaction and it causes the
resonator frequency to shift depending
on the state of the Cubit so if it's in
the cubits in the in the ground state
it'll be one one frequency it's in the
excited state it'll be a different
frequency and this is really similar to
if I take this can and I just squeeze it
a little bit notice the can is Shifting
in response to my uh my squeezing it oh
okay I think I deformed the can now it's
never going back to to where it was but
you can see that this can is is a really
sensitive probe of my fingers touching
the can and this is similar to how you
measure a cubid except now it's a very
sensitive probe of the the state of a
cubit and originally the Cubit may be in
a superp position it may be in zero it
may be in one it may be in a superp
position of zero and one and that means
that your can may be in one one
frequency the other frequency or a
superposition of these frequencies
because the Cubit and the can are
entangled so typically you don't measure
this by sweeping the frequency across
typically you pick one
frequency and send that in in the form
of a pulse into your system and then
gradually you acquire more information
about the state of the the can the
resonator probably wouldn't use a can in
a real experiment um and then that
collapses the state of the Cubit
resonator system into the state of the
Canon one frequency the cubit in zero or
the canon in another frequency that
cubit in in
one but to do this you need to use a
very small amount of power because using
more than a few photons in this can um
in this resonator it disturbs the state
of the cubit in a way that um it doesn't
retain the state that it collapses to
after you measure it and this is bad for
error correction this is a you want your
uh measurement at this property of being
uh qu Quantum non-demolition
and so that means you need to use this
this really small amount of power which
creates um a lot of practical challenges
so let's um let's shift back to the
slides unless there are any questions
about this are there any questions about
this demo before we we go back to the
the
slides okay so how do you go from
the oh uh it's a good question so um so
uh from the can so we have this this
instrument called a vector Network
analyzer that's connected up to the can
with this microwave cable and it's
sending in these uh microwaves and it's
measuring the reflected response so
what's plotted in the upper left is the
uh S11 or the reflection of of from the
can on a a logarithmic uh scale the
absolute value of that uh 10 log log 10
of that absolute value squared and away
from resonance you you get about the
same amount of power back as you're
sending in but as you approach resonance
then you see that a lot of the power is
absorbed um uh but I guess uh I don't
know maybe if your question was like
operationally how you how do you do that
it's just some um some Julia code that I
wrote that um takes the data from the
vector Network analyzer processes it and
and shows it on here does that answer
your question yes okay great uh any
other
questions okay so if we shift back to
the quantum system we have the cubit
coupled to a resonator we send in
microwaves at 10 Melvin we measure the
reflective response and we see exactly
that same effect where depending on the
the Cubit State the resonator will shift
it will acquire have an amplitude and a
phase response and you can plot that
just like we were doing on the IQ plane
and you can see these these two blobs
one associated with the um with the
ground state and the other associated
with the excited state but the challenge
of doing this is that you want to do
this really really fast and you want to
do this with very high fidelity and you
want to use uh very small power levels
so measuring small power levels is not
unknown to microwave engineering your
your GPS signals are say minus 140 - 150
dbm but you can't measure your G your
can't your phone can't acquire a GPS
lock in in 100 NS so we need something
special to to do this and I'm going to
tell you what
um what what we need um but first I want
to make an analogy with the analog
measurement chain in daily life so let's
say you you want to play some music uh
play play the guitar and you want to
share it with someone else that's that's
remote um you could use an electrical
microphone to transduce this acoustic
signal into an electrical signal this
will have some noise associated with it
it's actually black body
radiation and you'll have a place a
preamplifier to increase the amplitude
of that that preamplifier will add some
of its own noise as well as amplify the
input noise then you'll you'll send this
to a uh a secondary amplifier and then
to an analog to digital converter
digitize that have it on your computer
save it maybe email it to to someone um
but this ultra low noise pre preamp is
quite critical because any noise
injected by this preamp it gets um it it
carries through the rest of the
measurement chain now to imagine how
this is with superconducting cubits
imagine that your microwave emits single
Photon level signals and your analog to
digital converter is 30,000 times hotter
than your your microphone so that's
that's similar to the Cubit measurement
uh chain where you have the Cubit and
the redout resonator you're sending in
around minus 140
dbm at 10 Melvin you have a a first
Quantum limited pre-amplifier and then a
secondary amplifier and then you measure
it at at 300 Kelvin and perform the
Cubit State
classification the the challenges of
this are first that you want to perform
these measurements very quickly you're
limited to single Photon levels and
second the the cubits are extremely
sensitive to Photon thermal photons or
other photons in the resonator for
example to get a state-of-the-art
coherence time like those that um Google
IBM Etc use you need an average number
of photons in your resonator uh nbar of
less than 0.0 uh 02 so two two parts in
a thousand of a photon on average in
your resonator you need less than that
to to achieve the coherence time and the
re the way to think about that is that
your Cubit is measured by photons in
your resonator and your Cubit doesn't
care if you're sending in those photons
intentionally or whether those photons
are from thermal fluctuations or or
something else they they all measure the
Cubit and at 4K 4 Kelvin um There are 16
photons uh in every single mode and at
room temperature they're about a
thousand so actually in this can if I
take it and I disconnect conect it from
The
Source this is a can of photons where
every mode will have about 3,000 photons
in it so people often ask you know if
there were room temperature
superconductors could you operate a a
quantum computer at room temperature and
at least if you're operating at say sub
10 GHz the answer is no you you couldn't
because the thermop photons would
completely swamp the
operation okay um so how do we actually
perform that readout you might say just
go and buy a semiconductor amplifier if
any of you work in uh RF or or something
like that you can you can go online you
can order a really good um semiconductor
amplifier but it turns out that if you
cool these down these can't achieve
Quantum limited noise performance
they're typically a factor of three
usually uh uh more uh away from the
so-called Quantum limit which is the
best an amplifier can possibly perform
and this turns out um if we um take a
look at some of the papers by by experts
in this that it results from the the
challenges of cooling down uh
dissipating the heat generated by these
transistor base amplifiers as you go to
lower temperatures because as you go to
lower temperatures there are fewer
phonons to help dissipate the heat so it
becomes more challenging but fortunately
um we can use the nonlinearity that
creates the Cubit to create amplifiers
and I I don't know if I'm brave enough
to do this like full demo uh here but I
can I can give you a little sense of it
so I
brought demo of a parametric amplifier
that's a little bit entangled with my
keys
um so you can think of this as a
parametric amplifier uh all it needs is
some oscillation and some
nonlinearity and you know if I want to
make this move I can just push it and
it'll it'll start oscillating but that's
very inconvenient to do in the base of a
dilution refrigerator but what you can
do is if you imagine this as the
microwave you want to amplify and then
you you send in a a pump wave that
changes some parameter of the system
here I'm going to change the length of
this string in the Joseph injunction
based systems you send in a strong
microwave pump that changes the
properties of the Joseph injunction and
what that does is using this this
analogy As you move the oscillator up
here you pull up on the string and then
as the mass is going down you let it out
you let that extra string out and then
every time it oscillates it falls a
little bit further effectively and that
adds energy to the um uh to the
system yeah it usually takes me a little
bit to actually do this with the the
spring and mass so I won't do it here
but maybe we can play around with it
later um but going back to the super
conducting circuits um people can make
essentially perfect amplifiers using
something called a josein parametric
amplifier which is the same physical
structure Ure as the super conducting
Cubit where it has a capacitor in
parallel with the nonlinear inductor and
then it's driven by a strong microwave
pump and this creates a gain in a in a
relatively narrow tens to hundreds of
megahertz uh bandwidth
regime but to reduce the physical
Hardware overhead we really want to um
amplify over a very broad bandwidth and
you can do this by chaining together a
bunch of these uh joses injunctions to
create a transmission line and this
doesn't have a specific frequency
associated with it so it can amplify
over a very broad bandwidth um
and but the question is can they reach
the quantum limit and this is something
that that I I find a very uh interesting
question um these amplifiers have been
demonstrated in a lot of different uh
systems but so far none of them have
really reached Quantum limited
performance and um some of these
amplifiers made using jce injunctions
through a collaboration with MIT linol
lab
these are say one of the standard
measure amplifiers for superc conducting
uh Cubit measurements the bandwidth and
dynamic range to simultaneously measure
tens of cubits and they have uh um and
hundreds of them have been um
distributed uh worldwide through these
this collaboration um here's an example
of the gain as a function of frequency
showing very Broadband uh
performance so if we look to the noise
performance uh I won't go into the
details of how this is measured but it
has about half the ideal noise
performance performance and it'd be
really great if these had uh the the
full the quantum limited noise
performance because that can lead to
obtaining all the information from the
Cubit and faster measurements
so um if we we can break down the
quantum efficiency uh budget and we can
find that uh some of the quantum
efficiency is actually unaccounted for
and some is related to things like um
lossy dialectric which can be improved
with better uh fabrication and and
engineering um maybe quick question
since we started like roughly half an
hour late should we try to finish early
or is it okay
to okay great um okay
so so in terms of the quantum efficiency
um you can view the quantum efficiency
of these amplifiers in a in a perfect
single two mode amplifier you inject a
frequency called the signal this is
Amplified this generates an idler but in
a realistic amplifier you generate all
these other sidebands all these other
frequencies and they mix in noise
um and our idea is that we can build
something called a we call a Flo mode
amplifier where we can adiabatically
change the nonlinearity of the system so
we can make it like a spring that that
responds very uh strongly to the um to
the applied field on the two or very
weakly to the applied field on the two
sides or very strongly in the middle and
then if we adiabatically vary the
strength of the this nonlinearity then
we can um we can generate all these side
bands and then coherently recombine them
into the um into the
output and maybe another way to think
about this is that um if you look at the
Dynamics of this amplifier where you
inject the signal it creates the
Amplified signal in The Idler the the
blue and the orange line and then and
this is what you want but it also
generates all this other stuff but if
you go through and you look at this in a
different basis called the basis of
floquet modes then you find that it
looks really simple and you only have
these two modes that do anything useful
so our idea was that we can
adiabatically uh interact with these
modes and it turns out that this if you
do this then um you can eliminate the
contribution of all these um noise modes
at the
output
um and when we simulate the response of
this device we see that the um Quantum
efficiency is improved by the the can
call it quantum inefficiency it's
improved by orders of magnitude when we
implement this this flow case scheme and
there's no trade-off in in
bandwidth so one one thing that I'm uh
quite passionate about in the the field
of um of super conducting circuits and
Quantum information is um analysis and
modeling Ike was mentioning how you know
it's kind of a a a Triumph of of
engineering that um the blue origin
rocket launch it it worked on the first
time and I think that's really key for
uh Quantum engineering building the
types of uh analysis software and the
types of methodologies to make these
systems work um and one of the things
that we uh contributed to this was
building open source Eda tools for
nonlinear circuit simulation uh for
these Quantum devices particular we
built this uh software package called
Joseph and circuits that's an open
source harmonic balance Simulator for
parametric processes um and it's about
10,000 times faster than the uh software
that uh people the open source software
WR spice that people are typically using
and um we also collaborated with kyite
to compare this uh with their uh ads
software and also to um help uh improve
commercial software in this in this area
um so now we want to actually build
these things so we fabricate this using
this all aluminum uh Cubit process at
MIT Lincoln Laboratories and we build
the uh device using uh coper wave guide
capacitors to uh reach near zero
dissipation and here's an image of the
wafer of these devices it was fabricated
in the um in their Foundry and here we
can look at one of the examples of these
devices it's this Meandering chain of
devices of uh this Meandering
transmission line where you inject the
signal and the microwave pump on one
side and you get the Amplified signal on
the other side and this is in one of the
packages that we developed so if we look
at the performance of this we see that
it achieves over 20 DB gain with minimal
insertion loss and um when we measure
the noise performance we see that it
reaches about 85% of the uh relative to
the quantum limit for pH preserving
amplifiers so this is uh getting quite
close to uh to being a an ideal uh
amplifier which is is really exciting
um so a lot of the the stuff that we do
it also involves um seos style process
engineering where we actually build
these things in the clean room in mit.
Nano we we characterize tens of
thousands of these jce injunctions in
order to improve the reliability so that
we can build these um quantum computers
in a in a predictable
way maybe just in the interest of time
um I'll go quickly through the last uh
section I wanted to cover is can we make
Cubit readout uh 10 times
faster
so as we were talking about uh Cubit
readout earlier
um we readout a cubit by essentially
coupling it to a resonator sending
microwaves into this resonator and
determining the state of the Cubit well
uh
to to maximize the speed at which this
happens you want to have a resonance
with a very broad bandwidth and you also
have to have the shift that the cubic
creates comparable to that bandwidth and
that shift that the cubic creates this
is something called the dispersive shift
and this is limited by how much
nonlinearity you have and it it turns
out that that amount of nonlinearity is
limited our idea was to use um a type of
Cubit that has a rather than a quadratic
potential with a bit of uh cortic
potential to it we wanted to use a type
of Cubit called a Corton that has a
purely quartic potential and this is
really weird from a physics perspective
because most things in nature are
harmonic oscillators quadratic
potentials this is something that's that
has no harmonic component and it turns
out that electrically this behaves like
a infinite inductor and when you place
this in between two cubits you can
actually turn one of the cubits into a
resonator and achieve a very strong
nonlinear interaction between these two
and we were able to using the system
experimentally demonstrate the the
strongest um nonlinear light matter
coupling of any Quant coherent system um
in you know either superc connecting
cubits photonics Etc uh which um you
know potentially has applications as we
discussed in this paper um for improving
readout speed by about an order of
magnitude um simply because this
nonlinearity is very high so that leads
to really strong
interactions um so I think I'm going to
uh wrap up here acknowledge my group and
maybe if there's time I'd be happy to
take a couple questions uh thank you
everyone
[Applause]
did I thought I might have heard you say
something about being able to measure a
c a cubit more than just whether it's a
zero or one is that is that the
case
so you can
in the in the kind of textbook picture
of quantum mechanics you have this
so-called ideal projective measurement
where you have your your Cubit say in
some superposition State and then you
measure it and it and it you know you
get a zero or you get a one in real life
measurements take a finite amount of
time so that process can't happen
infinitely quickly so what really is
this uh slow measurement or this
measurement process that that's
continuous where you gradually extract
more information about the state of the
cubit and then the Cubit gradually
decays into one of its states so you can
actually look at these trajectories uh
of the of the of the Cubit resonator
system um so yeah it's it's more
complicated than the the the textbook
the that there's a time period where the
Cubit isn't a partially ingled State
measure oh absolutely yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah you you start out with the
Cubit and the resonator fully entangled
and then you gradually uh you know
destroy that entangle going to decohere
the state of the the Cubit resonator
system and extract that useful
information and if you have a really
good amplifier then you can you know get
that information to to you if you have a
a bad amplifier then that information
may be lost to the environment well
going back
to security issues supposing Eve
comes process measuring your cubid what
happens that is an external second part
just try
the same time if a external party is
trying to measure your your Cubit then
that can
um I guess it depends that can cause
your Cubit to so normally if you if your
system is perfect and there are no EES
or no thermal photons in your
environment then your measurement rate
equals your def phasing rate um but if
there's an eve or if there are say
thermal photons then your your def
phasing rate can be faster so so it
would show up as an increase def phasing
rate
yeah can this partial measurement be
useful for
anything um it's useful for a lot of
um understanding the fundamentals of
quantum mechanics I don't know that it's
useful in the sense of like solving uh
quantum chemistry problems but maybe
that'd be a great question to ask in the
panel so I think um in a vacuum I'd love
to answer more questions but I think in
the interest of time probably we should
shift to the the panel