And with that, I'd like to present you
Altastata. Thank you.
>> Hello everyone. My name is Silvski. I'm
a former MIT link and lab researcher now
CEO of Alastata.
And we secure AI supply chain with the
encryption.
The supply chain starts with multiple
silos and collaboration with partner
sources and it ends up with inference in
production. So there are several
potential problems data set poisoning
compromising model storage rack document
poisoning
and so what are the two key security
problem for AI? First of all is data
integrity. Google report says that
attacker only needs to control 0.01%
of the data set to completely poison the
model. The other one is partners trust.
So when you use AI data center that
provides you GPUs energy, you lose the
control of your data because it's beyond
the perimeter of your organization.
The solution is autoata.
Our product is fortified data lake. It
can be established in any cloud or
private storage. It supports any file
formats. It protect the model in
training and in use. So we provide
userfriendly application
seamless integration with data platforms
like datab bricks pytor torch and if you
use confidential containers you have end
to end fully homamorphic encryption.
Additionally, we provide the tools for
compliance like GDPR, AI act, NIS, RMF
and others.
That all ensures invisible security when
data scientist can focus on their core
tasks. An auto starta handles security
transparently in the background.
Each file is encrypted with a separate
key also verified and compressed.
So while
we combine security and efficiency for
AI. So security means full control
beyond the perimeter of the of your
organization likewise inside your
organization and also data immutability.
Nobody can change this data. An
efficiency for AI means seamless
integration with AI data platforms and
also realtime performance. The solution
is based on patent that embraces
automatic key management and unique data
structure optimized for fast AI
processing. Additionally, our data
compression enables to work with
encrypted data three times faster than
even with unencrypted data and also it
provides 63% of costsaving on storage.
So let's see some particular use case.
This is Massachusetts open cloud that
supports Boston hospitals
and Boston hospital want to conduct
collaborative medical research with CR
CRO
clinical research organization
and eliminate data breaches or data
poisoning. So the solution for such
approach is data clean room and they get
it from alterata.
Uh for each partata data lake provides
secure boxes. So each party shares their
encrypted data sets with training
applications only not with humans not
with each other. uh they also
collaborate with startup which is data
partner that enables them remotely
accessing encrypted data without
duplication. When the model is trained
it goes to production and they can start
data processing on encrypted data in
real time. So what the key benefits of
this approach? It's zero trust. So by
encryption it supports uh red hot open
shift and confidential computers. It's
no data duplication and it's also cost
savings.
We are MIT based team. Our solution is
cross industry cross geography. We
partnering with AWS, Microsoft, Red Hat
and for Red Hat uh we have direct
support of their global CTO.
So what we ask if you share our vision
uh we would love to learn your use cases
and run pilots. Please connect me on
LinkedIn uh and contact via email.
>> Thank you so much Serge. Um great to
hear your presentation. We have a
question from the audience. Um how do
you deal with the data exfiltration ilk
exfiltration
>> with data exfiltration? We don't we
don't do data exfiltration. We we
partner with companies they do it but in
general in case of alterata there is no
need to do data exfiltration because we
encrypt the entire data set. So you
cannot breach it or poison.
>> Thank you. And one more question why is
Redhead so interesting partnering with
Altata and at the CTO level?
>> Yeah because we have actually similar
strategy. So we're also multicloud.
We also work with AI data centers and
Red Hat actually builds this AI data
centers and we collaborate with
confidential containers group at Red
Hat. So together with autoata it builds
full homamorphic postquantum
computation.