um today we're g to continue our sort of
application we learned so far and today
we are going to really dive in and sort
of in some sense what we could sort of
consider consider the mother of all
market failures which is externalities
the classic the single most classic
example that economists use when they
talk about market failure is
externalities and today we're going to
talk about
externalities uh what they are why they
represent market failures and what
governments can do about
them so an externality
exists whenever the actions of one party
make another party better or worse
off but the first party doesn't get the
benefits or consequence of doing so
soever my actions make you better or
worse but none of the benefits of making
you better or the cost of making you
worse accre to me
individually in that context that's an
externality okay and we will talk about
why this C is a fundamental source of
market failure and we're going to talk
about four different types of
externalities so we're going to start
with the most classic case which is a
negative
production
externality this is the most classic
example of
externalities okay so suppose that
there's a a steel plant located on a
river how many guys read The
Lorax guys go excellent good job Dr
Seuss greatest second greatest author of
history behind Shakespeare is Dr Seuss
okay so the lorax tells the story of
this plant sort of dumping crap into the
river well think about The Lorax think
about a plant on a river a steel plant
in a river dumping sludge into the river
it's a natural byproduct of the steel
they's not making sedes he's making
steel natural bipart byproduct of the
steel plant is uh this sludge and every
unit of Steel that's made produces one
unit of sludge that gets dumped by a
pipe out the back into the river just
like in The
Lorax okay however the steel plant is
not the only user of this River farther
Downstream from the steel plant is a set
of fishermen and they fish in this River
and they make their living uh fishing in
this River and it turns out that the
sludge that the steel plant's dumping in
is killing the fish and hurting the
livelihood of the fisherman down the
river now this is a classic negative
production externality it's negative
because my action as a steel plant
affects another party which is the
fisherman it's production because it's a
byproduct of the production process
we'll talk later about consumption
externals you'll see the difference
um and so this is a classic negative
production externality and the way we
Analyze That is shown in figure
241 once again from my textbook okay we
think about the market for steel the
market Standard Market diagram you got
the quantity of Steel on the xaxis
you've got the price of steel on the Y
AIS you've got um uh a demand for steel
which is the blue downward sloping line
and supply of
Steel now the key distinction we're
going to make here that we haven't drawn
before is when we've talked about what
demand and Supply represent we've talked
about them as private Concepts the
domain curve is individual's willingness
to
pay the supply curve is an individual's
firm's willingness to
supply but implicit in that and implicit
in the welfare analysis would be way
back in lecture 12 is the notion they
also represent social curves implicit in
all the analysis we've done is the
assumption that the aggregation of
individuals represents society and
therefore what's best for individuals is
best for society so implicit what we've
done is that private benefits equal
social benefits so the domain curve for
example the slope of the domain curve is
the private marginal benefit of another
unit of Steel it's also the social
marginal benefit now we haven't raised
this before because it didn't matter
before but today it will likewise the
supply curve is the private marginal
cost a producing number unit of Steel we
just called it marginal cost we didn't
call it private but that's what it is
and we also represent that as a social
marginal cost of producing steel it's
what it cost Society to produce steel is
what it cost the
producer the difference with an
externality is social costs now deviate
from private costs so if you think about
what is the cost of producing unit of
Steel well there's the marginal cost of
that steel all the stuff that goes into
it plus there's the fact that every unit
of Steel creates unit of sludge and that
kills
fish now that is not a private cost the
steel planter couldn't give a it's
a social cost because but Society is
worse off because the fish are dying
societ is comprised of everyone in
society so the cost of producing steel
the social cost is now the
manufacturer's private marginal cost
plus the marginal damage so the social
marginal cost is the manufacturer
private marginal cost plus the marginal
damage that that production does to
society in this case society's
represented just by the
fisherman the other rest of society we
are going to assume to make life easy
that marginal damage is constant you
could imagine upward or downward sloping
marginal demand curves let's leave that
alone that which makes it harder all the
math and all the intuition goes through
assume a constant assume that every
single unit of sludge dump causes a
constant marginal demand marginal damage
MD in terms of killing
fish okay what does that
imply for both private and social
welfare so for private welfare for what
the market delivers what the this is
otherwise a perfectly competitive market
it delivers the outcome at Point a the
perfectly competitive market delivers
outcome at Point a with no externalities
that is also the socially optimal
outcome we covered that that's the first
fundamental
theorem but now we say no the social
cost is not the blue line it's the red
line it's the private marginal cost plus
the marginal damage which is a shift
upwards it's a constant shift upwards
because we're assuming marginal damage
is constant so the social Optimum is not
at a it's at
C in other words from society's
perspective the steel company
overproduces
steel why does it overproduce steel
because a steel compan is saying I'm
going to produce steel until the cost to
me equals the benefits to
Consumers but from society's perspective
you should produce D the cost to society
equals the benefits to society the
benefit to society is the demand
curve but the cost Society supply curve
plus the marginal damage as a result the
steel plant is overproducing steel
because it's not accounting for the
externality it's not accounting for the
Damage Done to the other party and as a
result we get overproduction of Steel
and a dead weight
loss the dead weight loss is a New
Concept because we haven't had private
and social cost deviating before we've
seen deadweight losses before but this
is a new kind of dead weight loss that
arises because the fact that the steel
kills
fish creates an externality
which causes the steel producer to
overproduce steel and as a result of
that excess production of Steel we get a
dead weight loss dead weight losses
here's the trick are done relevant to
social marginal costs the ultimate goals
to have is to have social welfare
maximization that's at C not at a so
you've created a dead weight
loss okay questions a little
mind-blowing different concept question
about how this works yeah
no so see the thing is societ well it
depends defined Society the market can
only operate as the market the Market's
the market for steel that's what I've
drawn here Society being the government
could decide to address this and we'll
talk about later but the market itself
leads to point a so the Market's leading
us to overproduced
Steel okay so this is not a this is not
a positive analysis the positive
analysis we already know how to do posi
you get to point a this a normative
analysis which is point a is over
production producing too much course are
not accounting for the Damage Done to
the
fisherman okay let's drill this
intuition home by talking about another
case let's talk about a negative
consumption
externality let's talk about a negative
consumption externality the classic
example of which is
smoking when I
smoke I exert a negative effect on
society partly because um I raised the
cost of medical care for dealing with
with me when I'm old partly because I
create secondhand smoke but for lots of
reasons my smoking creates extra cost
for society so my smoking decision is
represented in figure
242 the cost of producing cigarettes
we're assuming no production externality
here so the supply curve is both the
private marginal cost and the social
marginal cost there's no production
externality but I choose to smoke it
point a or the market chooses smoking at
Point a which is where the so the
private marginal cost equals the private
marginal
benefit however the social marginal
benefit is lower than the private
marginal benefit the social marginal
benefit is equal to the private marginal
benefit minus the marginal damage which
once again I assume is
constant done by my
smoking in other words I over
smoke because when I decide to smoke I
just compare my benefits to the cost of
cigarettes I don't consider the fact
that I'm making you sick and making your
tax dollars go up by my
smoking as a result I smoke too much
from society's perspective think of
society as the bubble that includes
everyone whereas my decision is a bubble
that just includes me so I'm only
deciding based on me I'm ignoring the
rest of that bubble if my smoking
decisions affect the rest of that
bubble then I'm over
consuming okay and therefore we get too
many cigarettes consumed and a parallel
dead weight
loss okay this time it comes from a
shift in the demand
curve okay so that is another example uh
you note here we used a number we Ed 40
cents that's the best estimate 40 40 or
50 cents is the best estimate of what
the negative externality is from smoking
about 40 to 50 cents a pack if you add
up all the costs smokers impose on
society it's 40 to 50 cents a pack and
that's why we use that as a constant
marginal damage here so given this
there's over
consumption um of uh of
cigarettes externals can also be
positive we could have a
positive production
externality the classic example of that
so let's think about what we what we're
now you sort of are in the concept think
about what I'm going to talk about here
I'm going talk about something something
that firms
do that has benefits on others that the
firms don't
realize what's the classical example of
that research and
development when a firm does
R&D it creates new science which
benefits consumers but consumers pay for
that but other firms learn and go
further up the development curve based
on what the first firm did so if you
think about if you go go to figure
234 think about the market for R&D when
a firm's deciding how much R&D to do it
considers what's the cost of R&D R&D is
a cost you got to hire scientists and
build labs and so that's the uh
private marginal cost and there's a
benefit for R&D which is how many
patents does it deliver for the firm
that's going to drive the demand okay
what the firm is ignoring is that by
doing
R&D they are actually producing knowled
that cannot be held totally privately
eventually when the patent runs out it's
public even before that firms May learn
and that's going to benefit other firms
that's going to lower the cost of
development for other firms so there's a
social marginal
benefit which effectively lowers the
marginal cost of
R&D from society's
perspective when firms do R&D it's more
valuable than the firm at self
sees indeed the best estimates are that
the private rate of return to
firms is on the order of about 15 to 20%
pretty high rate of return because a
risky investment the social rate of
return which is accounting for the
benefits other firms get from that R&D
are something like two to three times as
large because of all the benefits of
society and one firm does it spills over
and other firms benefit as
well okay so that is a positive
production externality as a result firms
do too little
R&D just like a negative production
externality causes the steel plants to
produce too much steel a positive
production externality causes firms to
do too little
R&D okay that's one reason why in the US
we have a tax credit to promote
R&D finally we have the last example
which is a positive consumption
externality and here let me move away
from the graphs and talk about an
example okay um I have a neighbor who
I'm not fond of I may have mentioned
this before uh I do not like my neighbor
uh part of the reason I do not like my
neighbor is my neighbor has a tendency
to do big projects about halfway and
then stop because he gets bored one such
project he started about 20 years ago he
decided do a massive landscaping job on
his
yard and as part of that I produced a
giant mound of dirt that was directly
out the window of our kitchen and then
he stopped and that Dirt has sat there
for 20 years at one point my wife snuck
out and planted wild flowers on it so it
wouldn't look so bad but the bottom line
is we got this pile of dirt this guy
created so let's think about his
decision about whether to get rid of
that pile of dirt imagine that it would
cost him
$1,000 to get rid of that pile of dirt
and imagine because he doesn't mind
looking at dirt it's only worth 800
bucks to him so the marginal cost is a
th000 the marginal benefit privately is
800 you won't get rid of it but what if
it's also worth another 500 bucks to
me well in that case the social marginal
benefit is
$1,300 which is above the cost so he
should remove the dirt but he won't
because he's a jerk Okay and like he
doesn't care what I think he's just his
own and he's look he's not it he won't
not do it not just because he's jerk but
because he's considering his own private
marginal cost of medits it's not worth
it because it's an ex because removing
it would have a positive effect on me
and he's not accounting for that so he's
under he is underusing
Landscaping
okay questions about any of
this
yeah uh they're just twoo totally
different market
failures uh I think you know we could
discuss that more another time but
they're just they're really not related
in in fundamental ways I mean in
subsense you could think of information
Imes creating things that look like
externalities but they're just two
different ways the market can
fail um okay so now but my neighbor
example raises a really interesting
question okay I now hopefully have
convinced you extra NS exist they're
real they cause inefficiencies but do we
need the government to fix them I mean
after all I could go to my neighbor and
offer him 500 bucks to the Landscaping
right we don't need
government indeed there's a very famous
economist lawyer and Economist named
Ronald
Co who POS what we call the Coan
solution externalities which is just
negotiate okay
basically this
fisherman could say hey you're doing
this damage to our fishing let's
negotiate and have you produce less
steel okay so
basically theide idea is we don't really
necessarily need a government was K's
argument because we could solve some
negotiation in practice he's wrong and
he's wrong for a number of reasons the
first reason he's wrong is that the most
important externalities are not things
like me and my neighbor things like
global
warming global war is the ultimate
externality okay when you drove your car
last you were ever so incrementally
putting Bangladesh
underwater even if it's an EV Le as an
EV but even still okay did you think
about that did you think well I'm going
to drive you thought about my drive is
it worth it did you think oh but also
I'm putting Bangladesh underwater no you
didn't okay because that's an
externality you're not accounting for
that the problem is externality that's
created every day by billions of people
and affects billions of people how would
they negotiate how would the billions of
people who create carbon get to the
billions of people who are affected by
carbon negotiate they can't it's
implausible so one problem with Coast is
it's simply plausible for the most
important externalities which involve
many parties on both
sides that's the first problem with
saying we can have a private solution to
this okay the second problem is that
it's kind of socially awkward I mean you
notice I haven't in 20 years gone to my
neighbor and offered him $500 to get rid
of the Dirt Pile it's kind of socially
awkward it'd be kind of a super bizarre
thing to do right uh there's a famous
story of an economist who was on a plane
back before he had phones we used to
talk people on planes and is on a plane
trying to get some reading done and the
guy next to him wouldn't stop talking so
we offered him 10 bucks to shut up now
we laugh CU like in reality like that
can't be right no one would do that it's
just because it's not how we really
interact in society so there's both sort
of negotiating barriers and Norms that
get in the way think about a classic
classic negative production external
negative consumption
externality is when your neighbor in the
door room next to you plays their music
too
loud okay that they consumtion they are
choosing the the volume which optimizes
the Music Experience for them the
benefits and costs they're weighing off
they're not accounting for the fact it's
making it harder for you to study now do
you ever go to your neighbor and say
look I've calculated that this ladder
music will cause me to do five points
worse on my tests which will affect my
lifetime earnings by this amount pay me
this or turn down the music no you
either ignore it or tell them to stop it
you don't tell them to shut it off okay
we don't do coing negotiations in
reality okay and as a result this is why
we need to bring in Government
Solutions the government needs to step
in and solve the problem of
externalities now how can the government
solve this problem well one easy example
is they can just
regulate they can just regulate they
could say if the government knows what
the social opal production is it can
just impose it so for example let's go
back to our steel plants example okay
let's go back to figure
241 what if the government just came in
and said you know what steel plants
you're producing Q2 that's a socially
optimal amount then boom problem solved
we've produced a socially optimal amount
the government through regulation has
enforced the social
Optimum so that would be the the
theoretically sort of easiest
case the problem in practice is to
determine what Q2 is you need to know a
lot you need to know what the demand
curve looks like you need to know what
the supply curve looks like and you need
to know the size of the marginal
damage those are three hard things to
learn and in particular we've talked
before in the concept of Regulation
about why it's very hard to measure
these Curves in practice the firms will
lie to you about what the marginal cost
is it's hard to measure it it's hard to
consumers to actually reveal what
stuff's Worth to them for all the
reasons we talked about it's very hard
to actually in practice measure these
curves so there's a lot of information
need to gather to get that
right but what if there was a simpler
solution what if the government said
look I do know the marginal damage but I
don't know what demand and Supply curves
look like in fact you don't need to know
that because what the government can do
like I said it can
regulate which is sort of easy in theory
hard in practice the other thing it can
do corrective
taxation which is imagine if the
government went to the steel plant and
said I am going to Levy a tax of the
amount MD on every unit you produce all
I know is MD I don't know anything
else and it's only works MD is constant
but let's assume I know MD it's constant
then I can go to the steel plant and say
I'm going to Levy a taxing of MD what
would that do to the steel producer
decision well let's go to figure 24
44 the steel producer the former e was
at
a now the government is coming along and
saying I'm going to Levy a tax on every
unit you produce a marginal tax of MD
will that raises their marginal cost by
the amount MD therefore shifting their
private marginal cost curve up to the
point where it equals the social
marginal cost curve what the government
does through corrective taxation is
caused the firm to internalize the
externality by basically pricing the
externality it causes the firm to
incorporate that into their
decisions
thereby thereby doing so getting to the
socially optimal
outcome so the government can
essentially solve this problem with
fairly limited information knows what MD
is it can solve this so for example one
of my former colleagues Michael
greenstone served in the Obama
Administration and his main goal there
was to measure what he called the social
cost of carbon which was what is the
marginal cost of what each unit of
carbon does in terms of damage through
global warming obviously incredibly hard
calculation but we have lots of
engineering models about how carbon
affects the environment he computed the
social cost of carbon this is incredibly
important because this became a basis
for thinking about how we can tax the
use of carbon if greenstone's
calculations were right he came up at
the point time was about $50 per ton of
carbon $50 per ton of carbon is
something like I forget it's something
like 25 cents a gallon of gas maybe it's
closer to 50 cents I don't remember
exactly we could just say look that's
the tax every time you use carbon you're
going to pay this tax at a social cost
and we would cause people to internalize
the externality we could address global
warming with one
calculation that one calculation is
simply what is the damage the margin of
carbon doses does to the world to the US
or the world we have to decide what
we're optimizing and then we're done
incredibly powerful if you think about
it okay and this is the beauty of
corrective
taxation okay note that um what you have
here is a
let's go back to last
lecture last lecture we talked about the
dead weight loss of
Taxation we talked about how taxes
create dead weight loss because they
reduce the quantity produced trades that
are productive are not
made here we're saying a tax gets rid of
a dead weight loss it's exactly the
opposite why because the trades it's
getting rid of are not socially valuable
when you have a negative externality
there are socially invaluable trades
being made all the units consumed
between q1 and
Q2 are losers for society so if you go
back to figure 241 everything to the
right of
Q2 has a social marginal cost above its
private marginal benefit its social
marginal
benefit those units which are hurting
Society so by taxing the firm we are
bringing them to the social margin to
the socially optimal outcome so taxes
can create dead weight loss taxes can
also get rid of dead weight loss it
depends on your starting point if your
starting point is already the socially
optimal outcome then taxes create dead
weight loss but if you're starting from
a point of maybe too much production
taxes can reduce dead weight
loss okay and that's kind of how we uh
how we think about it okay questions
about that
okay now let's talk about government
policy in practice let's talk about what
the government does in
practice because this is one of the most
important things the government does is
regulate and address
externalities and let's talk about the
two biggest sources of negative
externalities that we have the first is
environmental
externalities and of course as I said
the mother of all externalities which is
global warming this is it this is the
most important external that exists it's
it's an existential threat to life on
Earth okay and it is a classic
externality because our use of carbon
our little use of carbon is creating
damage to the entire future of the world
okay so it's a classicality when I drive
my car I don't acknowledge the damage
that's being
done okay so basically uh and we all
know how terrible global warming is I
don't have to give you the scary facts
uh carbon dioxide in the atmosphere is
now its highest level in 400,000 years
um temperatures have risen by more than
one degree Fahrenheit in the last 70
years which is the most rapid increase
in the last 10,000 years um what you
might not know is how bad it's going to
be uh basically scientists predict that
by the end of the century uh 20 to 40%
of Bangladesh will be underwater Cape
cot will be gone much of Florida will be
gone
um and the economic D the economic
damage to Society on the order of10
trillion uh uh in terms of uh in terms
of economic damage indeed the the world
as a whole will be about 10% poor by
2100 uh if uh through the physical
damage done by global warming okay so
what could the government do well I just
described an easy answer corrective
taxation we use engineering models to
compute the social cost of carbon like
greenstone had us do and
we say okay we're going to put that into
a tax we'll basically compute for every
carbon producing activity how much
carbon it produces and we'll tax it
accordingly
indeed Europe does this a lot if you've
ever driven in Europe gas even at
today's high prices is about twice as
expensive in Europe about twice as much
per gallon of gas in Europe it's hard to
mislead if you see the signs because
it's done by leader it's all you got to
convert but it's basically about twice
as expensive why because of
taxes because European nations
significantly tax gasoline we tax
gasoline but at a much much lower
level okay they have much higher taxes
now so the easy answer is let's just tax
gas here the problem is
political Bill Clinton who was president
had a lot of controversies during his
presidency one that them talked about a
lot is he osed a 3 Cent per gallon tax
on gasoline and that was one of the most
consequentially negative things he ever
did for his electoral prospects a lot of
the reason that Republicans took
Congress in 1994 was because Bill
Clinton's 3 Cent a gallon tax proposal
gas tax
proposal so basically we know the right
answer the answer economists have pushed
for for 50 plus years which is a carbon
tax but politically it's been
challenging there therefore the
framework that's been adopted since
1992 is instead Quan
regulation and in particular a cap and
trade
system for regulating carbon what that
means is we're going to we're going to
limit each company is going to limit how
much carbon it
produces okay that's the cap part it's a
regulatory
Target okay but we're going to allow
countries to trade to take advantage of
efficient opportunities let me explain
what this means so basically um in the
US we do not it is very expensive to
convert to clean energy and the reason
is because we built an entire economy
around dirty energy think of a simple
example if I want a natural gas plant I
got to First tear down the coal plant or
retrofit the coal plant to get the
natural gas plant if you take
China they're building new plants
rapidly well it's not that much more
expensive to build a natural gas plant
than a coal plant so for them it's cheap
to convert from gold to natural gas
because they're going to build a plant
anyway they don't have to tear something
down it's a very crude description of
why it's cheaper but roughly speaking
it's cheaper for developing
countries to grow to grow in a more
environmentally sensitive way than us
for us for us to retrofit our economy
now that's great but if you go to these
countries say that they're like you you
guys got to party you put all this
carbon in the air now you want us to fix
it no way we get to have air
conditioning we get to have
refrigerators all the stuff you guys
benefited from for all these years now
we're going to get it so the challenge
is the quantity idea makes
sense but the problem is how do you get
the world to buy in and the way you get
the world to buy in is but through
trading the idea here is let's have
permits of how much carbon can be
polluted and let's make those permits
tradable so the US can say to China look
it's very expensive for us to reduce
carbon it's less expensive for you so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to buy
from
you your clean production I'm going to
essentially pay you off to the reduction
that I would otherwise have to do so in
other words instead of inefficiently the
US reducing pollution a lot and China
not much we're going to more efficiently
have the US send China a bunch of money
and have China do the pollution
reduction and you know it's the same
outcome because it's global warming a
unit of carbon in the air doesn't matter
where it came from we are totally IND
different worldwide where carbon comes
from so if we have someone who can
produce it more efficiently and some
produce it less efficiently it makes
sense for the less efficient guy to
bribe the more efficient guy and that's
how we get this system to
work okay okay now this is a brilliant
Insight that economists once again dude
Economist pioneered for many years
environmentalists were were against this
they've adopted it um and this is how we
try to regulate carbon now the problem
is it's still politically enormously
challenging because ultimately the costs
of using carbon have to one way or
another go up we will never really solve
the problem of global warming until we
make the cost of
carbon feature the damage they're doing
okay now the Biden Administration took a
somewhat different T to this they said
look economists for years have been
saying tax carbon regulate carbon
politically we're getting nowhere here's
a different idea let's subsidize green
energy remember the opposite of a tax is
a subsidy so instead of trying to tax
the bad stuff let's subsidize the good
stuff and the inflation reduction act
which was passed last year has hundreds
of billions of dollars for subsidies
things like a $7,500 tax credit if you
buy a us-made electric vehicle subsidies
for discovering new uh new sources of
green energy for carbon capture for
hydrogen development Etc basically
saying look politically it's a lot
easier to spend money than tax money so
let's spend money to try to jump start a
green economy that can move forward
politically it was
brilliant okay practically it's still
not enough ultim Ely if we're going to
truly as a world address global war
we're going to have to make people face
the true price for what they're doing
which is to make carbon more expensive
okay questions about
that all right let's talk about the
other big topic the other big source of
negative externalities which is Health
ex negative Health
externalities negative Health
externalities so much of there's a
there's a class of goods that are
sometimes called sin Goods smoking
drinking driving because it causes uh
because it causes global warming other
drugs and much of the consumption that
we do of these sin Goods imposes
negative externalities on others so for
smoking I already mentioned there's
higher medical costs we spend about 80
billion dollar a year in medical costs
due to smoking related
illness um there's secondhand smoke
there's fires thousands of people die
every year in fire started by smoke ERS
etc for drinking this drunk driving we
have 13,000 deaths a year and 400,000
injuries a year due to drunk driving
classic externality if I drive when I
decide to get behind the wheel okay I'm
weighing the benefits and cost of
driving drunk I'm not accounting for the
fact that I might ruin your life or ruin
your family's
life okay we have gasoline we talked
about that and Other Drugs indeed drug
overdose deaths are now the largest
cause of accidental death in the US
about 100,000 people
year here's the tricky
thing when are things externalities is
not obvious because
remember the definition it's when my
actions affect you but I don't bear the
consequence think about drunk driving I
do bear the consequences of getting
caught so is that really an externality
because I bear the consequences or let's
take the case the interesting case of
smoking imagine that someone Sat by
themselves on a rock in a nonflammable
part of the world and smoked themselves
to
death would there be externalities from
that
no okay or imagine that I um smoke and
uh and it does ultimately raise my
medical costs but my insurers charge me
more indeed for the first time in
history the Affordable Care Act which I
talked about in the last lecture allow
insurers to charge smokers more for
their health
insurance well if the amount I pay in
extra premiums is equal to the damage
I'm doing by smoking then there's no
more externality I've internalized it so
externalities only arise when they're
not
internalized that's a very important
thing feature to think about okay so the
key is that people don't bear the
cost okay let's talk about secondhand
smoke let's imagine the way secondhand
smoke works smoke you all cough let's
imagine way secondhand smoke worked was
I took my cigarette and stabbed you in
the arm with
it let's imagine second smoke work by
taking my cigarettes that that's the
only way second Head smoke could affect
you would that be an
externality maybe not because you could
punch me you could sue me you could make
me bear the cost of that secondhand
smoke why is secondhand smoke an next
because no one owns the air so you can't
sue me for smoking in the in in the air
unless there's a law that says I can't
so external
arise when there's not an individual
remediation that can make the person
bear the cost okay an important
distinction now when we think about Sin
consumption of sin Goods the government
has a wide variety of tools it can try
to use to address the
externalities okay the first is so what
are the government tools one tool is
information
the government can tell people
hey what you're doing uh is um is really
bad okay uh indeed um for smoking
information's played a huge role in the
US in the 1950s half of all Americans
smoked half of all Americans smoked and
of all education groups smoking rate was
pretty equal across the entire
distribution of
income then we started realizing smoking
was bad for you and about 1980 smoking
started to fall but here's what's
fascinating it fell differently by
education group smoking when the Highly
Educated has virtually
disappeared smoking on the less educated
continues to be lower but still
consequential still about 18% of
American
smoke the limitation information is only
works if people process it and use it
and account for it in their
decisions okay so the limit information
it's really created the in the
information solution has created just
sort of more inqu quity in who smokes in
America so that's one
solution the other solution is taxes we
can basically try to get smokers to
internalize the
externality by taxing
them okay and now that only works of
course if people respond to taxes by
smoking less and it turns out they do it
turns out people are somewhat price
sensitive just think price estimated
elasticity aboutus point4 that for every
10% you raise cigarette prices people
smoke about 4% less so one way to
address those your tax indeed smoking's
declined enormously it declined slowly
starting 19 due information it picked up
rapidly after 2000 due to massive
increase in taxes on cigarettes is a lot
of what drove the decline in smoking in
the US from 50% to
18% okay and that's great but while
that's an easy answer for cigarettes
it's much harder for other externalities
take drinking
the first couple drinks might actually
be good for you we don't know but
certainly you know many many people
thing is every cigarette you smoke is
bad for you there's no such thing a
cigarette's good for a harmless
cigarette every cigarette's bad whereas
drinks much of drinking is not harmful
to you indeed if you look at the big
source of externalities of drinking the
biggest source of externality is drunk
driving well most of us will drink
successfully in our lives without
driving drunk so if I deal with alcohol
by tax it it's a little bit harder
because what I'm doing is I'm collecting
a lot of the revenues people who won't
cause the
damage so that's a harder issue to deal
with politically that's a little more
challenging think about the number one
Health externality facing our society in
The Next Century
obesity okay one in every three babies
born in America today will love diabetes
before they die one and three because of
the Obesity crisis more than 30 35 % of
Americans are
obese once again huge inequality I don't
think I've taught an obese student at
MIT in 10
years okay but 35% of people your age or
30% of people your age are obese so
there's a huge amount of
inequality okay in that the trick is
address not through taxation is hard
because we all know eating is actually
pretty good for you you got to eat so
addressing obesity through taxation is
really
hard okay we can't just tax food that's
going to really hurt poor people so that
becomes a place where it's even harder
to addess through
taxation okay a third solution we can do
is
penalties for example losing your
license if you drive drunk that's great
because that targets people who are
causing the
externality if you guys drink a little
and you're fine you're not causing
externality so this T targets the person
causing the externality
the problem is it doesn't really help
penalties change in Behavior remind
relies on me making a rational decision
to say wow I better not drunk drive
because I'll get caught when you're
drunk you're not exactly making rational
decisions problem with penalties is they
sort of don't work if the sin good
itself is causing
irrationality ATT Tax Works because you
just don't buy it in the first place say
wow I can't afford that a penalty
doesn't work because it involves Forward
Thinking of the Tye that might not be
done why consuming these
Goods okay well then finally we have
illegality illegality we could just say
look it's illegal and that's in fact
what we do with hard drugs in this
country and in Most states still with
marijuana we make it illegal we say look
there's these externalities so not
people consume it the problem with that
is that is is almost certainly not
optimal because
remember even if there's externalities
unless those externalities are enormous
or
infinite some people still derive
benefits above the social
cost okay some people still right now
say cigarette taxs are close to Optimal
but people still choose to smoke does
that mean we should ban smoking not
necessarily it might mean that they just
enjoy smoking so much they're willing to
pay eight bucks a pack for cigarettes
so basically the question is whether you
should ban an activity is depend very
much on whether you think the
externality is so large that overcomes
any possible benefit of consuming the
good that's exactly the way we're having
now oh and there's one other thing
there's another wrinkle which is if you
think about it what is the largest
source of externalities for illegal
drugs the crime associated with
obtaining and distributing those drugs
which would not happen if they were
legal so not
only might the extern not be infinite
actually making the goods illegal
creates externalities in a way that
taxing them would
not and this is the argument for why
many people supported legalization of
marijuana because basically argument was
look there's externalities of marijuana
people driving High still kill people
it's less bad than drunk driving there's
still some
externalities but they are not large
enough to rule out the benefits some
people get from consuming
marijuana and we're creating new extra
Nows by making it illegal all the money
we're spending on police all the money
we spent on jails all the damage that's
done by enforcing those laws and that
was the argument for making marijuana
legal and that's an argument that's one
in some states and not one in others you
have to ask yourself why does AR going
to apply to marijuana and not cocaine or
heroin okay well if you really want to
have a co coherent argument you've got
to argue that the
externalities from cocaine or heroin are
so much larger than
marijuana that we should allow marijuana
to be legal and cocaine and heroin to
not be legal and in fact you'd be wrong
in fact the externalities from these
Goods largely arrive from the illegality
and that is why most economists think
all drugs should be legal not most
economists many economists think all
drugs should be legal
taxed that we should follow the model
that we showed in figure
244 we should have corrective taxation
account for the externality not B the
good now I hope that discussion made you
a little
uncomfortable as it does me and the
reason it made you
uncomfortable is because the framework
we're using Embraces key assumptions
that have been unstayed this whole
semester assumptions like rationality
okay what we're going to do next time is
ask how everything changes when we
question those assumptions and we're
talking about behavioral
economics but I wanted you to leave you
with this to remember absent behavioral
economics which talk about next time
it's really hard to justify making
something illegal okay on something like
externality grounds alone all right
let's stop there we'll come back next
time talk about behavioral economics