Okay. So
last time we talked about so we had a
function
or sequence of function. We had a
interval say I and we had a sequence of
function fn and a function f all defined
on this interval.
And then we uh talked about uh pointwise
convergence.
So pointwise convergence means that for
each. So this is for each
uh x
when you're looking at this. So this is
a for each x fixed this is a sequence
this is supposed to converge to f ofx.
So this was pointwise convergence and
then we also talked about uniform
convergence.
And this meant that
this meant that for all for all epsilon
greater than zero there exist a capital
n such that
if
um if little n is bigger equal to this
capital n then the difference between fn
of x and f ofx
this here is smaller than epsilon and
this here have to hold for fall in 4x
sorry
right so uniform again refer to that is
uniform in x the convergence is uniform
in x
then so we talked about that and then
one of the theorems we proved was that
if you take a sequence
uh fn and these here was integraable
uh And uh these converge
to some function f
uh then uh then then f is integral. So
this here is uniform convergence.
Then f here is integraable
and the integral is the limit of the
integrals. So the integral from a to b
of fn x dx
is equal is the limit here of this. So
the limit exist and it is equal to
the integral of f.
Okay.
Now so this is how uniform uh
convergence and
uh um and integrals interact.
Uh if we take the suppose you take a
sequence here. So this is a theorem
that suppose you take a sequence
uh fn
of functions on some interval into r.
you have uh x0
is uh is in this interval.
And then you have the following if you
have the following properties
uh that one is that this sequence here
converge to some number C.
Um sorry this sequence here converts to
some number C. two is that that these
functions here fn are differentiable.
So, so these are maybe I should say here
differentiable
and these are converge to some function
g and then three is that these functions
here sorry the derivative converge and
the I'm also requiring that the
derivative are continuous
suppose we have these three
So we have the sequence of
differentiable functions. If you just
fix this one particular point x0 then
the values of these function converge
and then the functions their derivatives
are continuous and the derivative
converge to some function
and this convergence here is uniform.
Then the claim is that then
uh um then there exist
uh f on the interval
so that uh f is uh
f
uh is differentiable.
The derivative here is continuous
and uh and you have the following two
properties
that the function here these functions
converge to f uh uniformly.
I'm going to restrict my interval.
I'm going to take it just to be some
interval from A to B. So,
and this here is a interval. I want it
to be bounded
like that.
And uh so these here converge uniformly
and true is
that uh their derivative
converts to the derivative of f
uniformly.
Okay.
So we want to prove that
and then so
so we're going to define a function f.
So G here is a proof of this.
Since this sequence here since these
here are continuous
uh and um
and these functions here converts to G
uniformly.
Then this means that uh
uh then
uh uh therefore
therefore
g here is also continuous
right. So we proved this already that if
you have a sequence of continuous
function that converges uniformly then
the limit is also continuous.
And so then we can look at so we can
define
we can therefore define
uh f as a function on this interval here
by
that's the uh that's um f of X is equal
to the integral from X0
uh so I'm defining it sorry to be um
this C constant C plus the integral from
X0 to X of G of X G of uh S
DS
right so I define this function like
this G is continuous
so this is a nice continuous function
and in fact by the fundamental theorem
of calculus
uh theorem of calculus
uh f here is differentiable
uh with
with the derivative
equal to G. Right?
We also have that um
that we also have
that uh if we're looking at f of x0 fn
of x0
right
then we know already that these convert
to c. This is the assumption one up
there. But this here is the value of f
at x0. So we have that.
I want to now prove that that not just
at this point but that this sequence
converts to f uniformly. Right? B here B
we get for free. Right? So b
follows
from
that this fn prime converts to g. Right?
And this here is this here is the
derivative of f and we have this
uniformly
by by assumption two. Right?
So all we need to show is So we just
need to show
that this fn converts to f uniform.
Right? We just need to show the a the
property a. Right?
And so we're looking at uh fn
of x we have to look at this difference
right and for a given epsilon we have to
find a little n. So we have to find a
capital n. So that if little n is bigger
than this capital n then this difference
here is smaller than epsilon for all x.
Right? But let's try to estimate this
here first. Right?
So this difference here is um
this difference is f
uh by so we can write so so we want to
estimate this difference and I can and
we can use the fundamental theorem of
calculus. I use
the fundamentality of calc
of calc
to write
uh fn
of x. We can write this as the value at
x0 plus the integral of the derivative
from this point
and then this should be s like this.
Right? We can use the fundamental the
calculus to just rewrite
fn like that. And so now I want to look
at this difference here.
And so to look at this difference fn of
x minus f ofx
now I can fill in this form of it. So I
have that this is fn of x0 plus the
integral from x0 to x fn prime sds
and then I have to subtract
uh f ofx but fx was given by by this uh
formula here and so so minus c plus this
integral here
uh g of s gs
like that
and so now I'm just rearranging terms so
I just think about this thing here as fn
n of x0 minus c. I take these two first
and then plus the integral of x0 to x f
prime n s ds minus this integral here
like that. Right? And then I use the
triangle inequality that this thing here
is less than fn of x minus c sorry fn of
x0 minus c
absolute value like this. And then I
have the second integral here. So the
absolute value or the difference here if
you do it slowly like this. So you have
this minus
this in here
of g of s ds like that.
Now I can think about this thing here as
I can find the integral. So I can write
this thing here as so this I'm just
keeping this first term here. I'm just
keeping and then the second here I can
think about this as a integral of the
difference of these function and this
here was an was an in here
like that. Right.
And now
now I can uh
now I can
so now I can uh here I can just take the
absolute value sign.
If I take the value I in under it then I
get something potentially larger. Right?
So this thing here is lesser equal to
fn of x0 minus c. That's the first term.
And now I'm replacing it by something
that is bigger equal to this. So where
I'm just integrating from x0 to x and
then of this difference here fn prime s
minus g of s gs
and now I'm using that uh that's the fn
so now using so since
fn
of y.
So
right so let me actually
let me just uh write this thing here. So
I can write this thing here. This one
here I'm keeping
this one here I'm keeping. So I'm
writing this as lesser equal to keeping
the first term
and the second term you see this thing
here is this difference between these
two. Well, the difference is at some S
is smaller than the maximum for all S,
right? But the maximum for all S, that's
what we call D F N prime G, right? That
was the maximum over all S. And so now
we just have so this this function in
here is less than this. And now we are
using this is where I want to use that
the interval is bounded. So I just get
plus b minus a. This is the length of
the interval like that. Right?
And so now you see that as
um and now there's no reference to x on
this side. Right? And so you see that as
n goes to infinity well this thing here
goes to zero and this thing here goes to
zero right. So as this go this upper
bound
goes to zero
and and and again note that there's no
reference to x. That's a reference to x0
but that's just some fixed points right?
So this is uniform in x right
so
this implies
uniform
in x convergence.
Okay. So I want to
I want to draw some uh consequences of
this.
First let me look at what will be
shortly a a particular case of more
general phenomena.
So this is
this is this example we looked at
several times
last time.
So but it's now applied in this case
here.
So suppose you're looking at the
function
uh functions e n of x. The en is where
you're summing from k = 0 to n
of x ^ k / k factorial. I looked at
those last time, these functions and I
called we called them en.
And then we also looked at the
exponential function
and the exponential function
in terms of power series that was just
this power series,
right?
And we have that uh we have that uh that
en here. So that for for all this was we
used bias stress M test to to buy bias
stress
M test
for all
L L sub positive
real number
we had that uh that we had that these
functions converge to e uniformly
on
an interval like this. They don't
necessarily in fact they don't but they
you know um they the the claim here
about uniform convergence is just on
every bounded interval right so you fix
a bounded interval like that interval
and then you have uniform convergence
it's not like uniform convergence of all
of R at the same time
okay you have that
and now if we are looking at
so Now um
if we're looking at the function
um
if we take now the derivative of the
ends. So what is the derivative of the
ens?
So the derivative of the en
is just a polomial. So you can just
differentiate each term on its own.
So this here is the sum here of uh of um
of k
x to the power k -1
/
k factorial.
And here you would be summing from k= to
zero to n right this is just the right
and now I can write this also
you see the first term because k when k
is equal to zero the first term doesn't
really count right so this thing here I
can write as I mean by it doesn't count
because it's zero right so you don't
really need to write that term. So you
can just write it from k = to 1 to n and
then you could write it again as k * uh
x ^ k -1 / k factorial.
But k factorial
k factorial
is just
is the same as k times
k minus one factorial. Right? So this
means that k factorial
over k
is just the same as k minus one
factorial.
Right? Or if you will, if I take the
inverse of this
k over k factorial, it's the same as 1 /
k minus one factorial. It's just
flipping the denominator and
denominator.
So this finite sum I can write as k = 1
to n because you see this thing here is
exactly this. So we can just replace it.
Can write it like that.
But now this thing here
I'm summing from one to n. The first
term I get
that is just this here by definition
when k is equal to one that's zero
factorial zero factorial by definition
is one right. So this thing here and
this thing here by definition is is also
one. So this here is just one. So
starting off at one when k is equal to
two then this become x this become one
factorial one factorial is just one so
this here is x right so the this here is
like this x the next one when k is equal
to three then you get x squ
sorry you get x squ and down here you
get two factorial
right and so you continue like this and
The last one you get is x ^ n -1 over n
minus one factorial right and so yeah
let let me just say uh so so you see
that this thing here is nothing but e n
minus one of x
right
so the derivative of of the e n is the
previous element en minus one. Yep.
>> Okay.
Okay. So now we have
we have that uh
like we have that dish in
If I'm
looking at the en is zero
those the value here of these guys
the only term that matters is the first
term and that's one.
So this here for each end.
So now what you have is so now we have
that you have that if you're looking at
this sequence you have we have this we
have that the e n prime
is equal to e n minus one and we already
proved that these here it doesn't matter
whether you're looking at the previous
one that they converge to e uniformly
right this is a uniform convergence
convergence
on this interval here
and then obviously three obviously the
en prime here they're polinomial
so so continuous
Right.
So now we have that um so we have so so
therefore
by the the
uh the there exists some function f. So
that these are converge to this
uniformly.
That's no great surprise.
And we also have that this thing here
the derivative converts to the
derivative of this here uniformly.
And again this is on intervals of this
form.
Right? Well, we already know that this
that it converts uniformly, right?
This is just by I mean it can only
convert to one function, right? Because
uniform convergence means that it's
converging pointwise at each x and
pointwise convergence then the limit is
is is just one thing. So we already know
that this here is e of x.
So you see that this the conclusion here
we get is now
that um that these
the and this here sorry is as we said e
n minus one. So the conclusion that we
get is that the e so this is the
conclusion from the theorem up there
that this e n minus one
converge uniformly
to the derivative
of this function.
Right?
Like the theorem said that if you have
these three condition
then there exist a function f so that is
differentiable and the derivative of it
is continuous and you have these two
properties but we already know that
these converts to this so we've already
identified what this function is so the
theorem just give us that function must
be derivative differentiable and the
derivative continuous.
But and now we try to figure out what
that derivative is. But the derivative
of these functions are the same
functions we started with but just
shifted one backwards. Right? So these
here
these here
also they converge to this. That's what
the theorem say. But but the
but the en minus one
they also converge to e right. So this
means that that these two functions here
this here
and this here must be the same
right. So this means that e is
differentiable
and the derivative is itself.
Yeah. Um so we define this for like all
n
>> this here was for all this here was this
here was defined for
any non- negative integer
right and so
I mean when I'm talking about down here
then I'm saying about n bigger equal to
one because I didn't strictly speak
define e minus one.
Okay.
So now I want to sort of do this more
generally.
So
I take a power series.
Also by the way the plan uh so after
this lectures there's two more lectures
Thursday and Tuesday next week and um
and uh right and and and the my plan is
uh it's I already updated the you know
the course plan to reflect this. So my
plan is like next time I will prove
existence of uniqueness of some OD
uh using things we have learned here you
know about metric spaces and then
Tuesday next week we'll do a review of
the class so there won't be any new
material on Tuesday. Okay.
[Applause]
also for whatever it was. I decided in
the end with a friend to turn in the
lecture notes to to turn it into a book
just because the TBB I that was like the
main reference I didn't find that great
anyway. It was also you know at thousand
pages you know who know when I reach
thousand pages right so and so the
course not here is like shorter as you
probably have seen and trying to focus
on on the uh you know the key points.
Okay. So, so eventually
there will be a book.
Um,
okay. So now,
so now, um, right. So now I want to to
do this sort of more generally. So I
take we take a power series. So we have
a as a sequence and we're looking at a
power series like this. So this is a
power series
and uh so just rem to remind you the
radius of convergence
[Applause]
of convergence
is given as as follows. So we take um we
take m and m is defined to be the lean
soup
as n go to infinity
of the n root
of
absolute value of a n right and then the
radius of convergence so r here is then
1 / m with this usual uh convention that
if m is infinity, this here is zero. If
m is zero, this here is infinity, right?
And so then we have again that we have
that. So we have that the the series
here. So if you're looking at this k = z
up to n of a n xn this here converge
to this
limit here
uh uniformly
on
each interval of this form. here where
where L here is strictly this and that.
Okay.
And this is again this here is is
biocest.
Now what I'm interested in is I'm
interested in uh so I want to be able to
calculate the derivative of this. So, so
we so we define
so we define a function
f by
that uh f ofx
is equal to the sum here from k = z to
infinity. So this is the power series x
to k like that.
And we want to uh want
a formula
for uh for the derivative and in fact I
want a formula for any derivative of uh
so say the m derivative of this function
and so uh right So now I uh look at so
we have take this power series and I'm
looking at the power series that is
given by
um
right so if I take so uh it's supposed
to looking at the power series where for
each term so you have in the original
power it's a n time x to the n then I'm
looking at n a n * x
uh -1
like this right so and here I'm summing
from um
from uh from one
uh I mean it doesn't matter sum from
zero
so zero to infinity like Yeah.
Now the radius of convergence for this.
So what is the radius of convergence? So
of convergence.
Uh the radius of convergence for this is
um
is the nth root
of n * a to the n
like this.
And this in here is the same as n to the
power 1 / n * the nth root of a n like
this. Right?
Now this thing here if you're looking at
n like this this here is you can write
this thing here as e and then it's log n
/ n. This here as n goes to infinity
converts to zero. So this thing here
converts to to one by e to the one.
And so you have that lean soup here. So
the lim soup
of the nth root of n * a n like this
this thing here is because this here
right you can write this it's the same
as li soup
n go to infinity n go to infinity it's
the same as the n root of of this in
here times the n root of like this this
here converts to one. So it really just
converts. So it's equal to the limb soup
as n go to infinity of the nth root of
a. Right? So and that was what we call m
originally.
So
this this limb soup is the same as this
limb soup. So this means that m from for
this new sequence is the same as m for
the old sequence. So this means that the
radius convergence for the new sequence
is equal to the radius of convergence
from the old sequence.
Right?
So if you take the derivative term by
term and you form this new power series
then it has the same radius of
convergence. That's the original passes.
Okay. And so now you can iterate this.
So you can iterate this.
So you can take the So this is just
taking the derivative term by term one
time.
If you now take the uh derivative
suppose you're starting with this
sequence here.
So you're starting with with sorry with
this power series and you're taking the
derivative term by term then you get as
we did up there you're getting this
power sh
now you take a derivative again term by
term.
So you're getting this right and the
thing is that each time the radius of
convergence for this same radius of
convergence
these two here same radius of
right it's because of the same principle
same radius
and and and so on. And so you can
continue.
And if you do this
um if you do this uh m time
then you're getting n
uh then so right. So if you right so if
you do this
um m times then you get that this thing
here is x
uh - m and you're getting a n and here
you're getting uh n
minus one
n minus 2 up to
uh n
min - m + 1
right this would give you so you're
getting that right
so that is after this is when you do it
m times and so again these here will
have the same radius convergence right
now
yeah now this thing here right so what
is So n if I want to write this a little
bit more compactly
if I'm thinking about this thing here n
minus 2 up to n minus m + one I can
write this thing here as n factorial
and then uh but then I getting all these
so if I wrote it as n factorial then I
would also have
Right? It would keep going like this and
the next one here would be n minus m.
Right? So if I writing so I can write
this thing here times this factorial is
equal to that. Right? Yeah. Sorry.
>> Right.
So,
>> so I think you were complaining about
one thing that I sort of uh pushed under
the rock and that is the following
that if you if you take
the way we define so if you take a power
series
again like this and you define the
radius of convergence
then you define it from this n element
right I think that's what you're
complaining about and so you take the
the coefficient to the n power that's
not exactly what I did is that what
you're complaining about yeah
>> and and that doesn't matter right and
and the thing is that so when you define
the rate of convergence
you took this n power like this right
but this was to to this it was coicient
to where this here was to the end when
I'm doing it over here I there's two
ways of dealing with it one is the one
you suggest I mean and the other one and
that was why I put it under you know I
swept it under the rock is that that the
way
the the radius this with the radius
convergence it comes from comparing it
with a geometric series and then it
really doesn't matter for this term in
terms of x whether you have shifted it
or not. Okay. But if you do it um if you
do it as you suggesting which would be
totally fine
then let's see. So then listening here
what you really should have done is that
we should have thought about this n a n
and then we should take the this here
and we should take instead of the n root
we should take the n minus one root
right but that doesn't matter either
right that's going to be the same also
yeah so either way you can check either
of these two things and I was thinking
about the first and that where it's
coming from
Okay. So,
so now um right so sorry now I lost my
thread here. So I was just observing
that if you write if you can write the n
factorial as first taking all of these
factors and then taking n minus one
right so this means that
that n factorial divided by n minus one
sorry n minus m
factorial
this is equal to n -1
n -2
down to n - m + one like that right
but you see that's exactly what we have
down here right so this thing here so so
what I conclude from this is
that if I take a power series
If I take a power s
if I take a power series like this
uh and I take the derivative term by
term
then and I do this k uh m times Then
this is what I get is n factorial
n - m factorial
and then a n x m n minus
m right.
Okay. So the and we also so this is when
we do it term by term taking the
derivative and we already have that
these here have the same radius of
conversion.
Okay.
And so now
so now we have a funny theorem
that if you take a power series so you
take a power series like this
uh r is the radius of converting
convergence.
uh and if L here is strictly less some
positive number but strictly less than
the radius of convergence
then uh then these guys here
these guys here converge to uh right so
these when you're summing when you take
a finite sum sorry these here converge
to to is uh uniformly. But not only
these
uniformly.
But not only that, but you also have
that more interestingly, you have that
um that this sequence here
uh um
k
minus
k minus k minus uh m
sorry uh k factorial
divided by k minus m factorial
a
uh k
uh x k - m
that this sequence here converge
uniformly
to the derivative
this is f ofx to the to the m derivative
of x of f.
So we have that these functions but that
we already prove that these functions
here converge and their derivative here
converge
uniformly like this
on the same.
Okay.
Now why is this the case?
So this here is again it's following so
this follows to prove
follows from the same theorem
follows
from
the theorem we proved earlier.
we showed earlier
and let's just go through that.
So let me go through it. So let's assume
assume first
that that m is equal to one.
Right? So I just take one derivative.
Well, then I'm looking at I'm getting
I'm looking at this sequence here.
Sorry. K X K
K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K
= Z to N. I'm looking at these that
converge to this
infinite this this two to two to it they
converge to f
right f again is this infinite power s
and I'm looking at the derivative of
these guys so these are this
and I know now
that these here converge
uniformly
and these This here converts uniformly
to the power series that is this
infinite series. Right? This here was
the finite part of it and this here it's
like the infinite you know the whole
thing
right. So we have that
this means in particular that so this
thing here implies of course that um
that when you're looking at the at at
zero when you're looking at zero by if
you evaluate this thing here at zero
then in this one here you get in this
this is the sequence of functions
fn of x from before. These are the fn
prime of x,
right? And so now I claim that so so the
theorem that we proved earlier is that
if you take a sequence of functions
that are
differentiable and their derivative is
continuous, these are all polinomial. So
this is definitely the case.
And we know that this that these values
here
fn in fact at zero they're equal to f of
zero. Right? So this is like so we had
three conditions. We had that the fn in
some particular point that we call x0
this is now zero that this converge. We
have that the fp prime was converging
uniformly. Well, we know that these here
converge uniformly. And then we had that
the fprime should be continuous, but
they were obviously continuous. They
were polinomials, right? Then then we
had that the derivative converge
uniformly.
Um and that the and that the function
that they converge to the the derivative
converge and also the original functions
converge,
right? And um and that the derivative
converts uniformly to the derivative of
the function that it converts to. Right?
So you see that this is just checking
that we have the tree property from the
theorem before and then we get the two
conclusion and the one conclusion that
we're interested in is that this here is
then the power series for the derivative
of f. Okay.
Now
Okay. So now the so and then you can do
the same thing with so let me just say
that you can do the same thing if you
take um if you take um
if you if you are integrating
so so here we proved so suppose you take
a sequence theorem that is converging to
f well suppose you take a power series
here
Suppose you take this power series
uh k x k=
to zero. So this is the finite this is
the power series
and suppose I'm interested in what is
the integral from a to b of
this power series
f ofx
dx right and here I'm assuming that a
and b are in the uh are um in the
interval where the power shares is
converging. So you have this right? So
this means of course that if you think
about it that you have here zero, you
have r you have here minus r and then a
and b is lying and so this means that
this whole interval is lying comfortably
inside some interval like this.
Right?
Okay. And I'm asking
what is a nice formula for this this
integral here.
And so then
well uh I can use not the theorem we
proved earlier but the theorem we proved
last time. And so what is that? So if I
define f(n) of x to be equal to the sum
here from k = to zero to n of a k x k
sorry x to power k.
These thing here, these here converge
uniformly to f ofx
on
any interval like this when l here is
strictly less than the radius of
convergence. Right? So they converge
here uniformly.
But the theorem we proved earlier was
that if you take a uniform convergence
like this and you take a and b in this
integral then the integral of these guys
here
converge to the integral
like this. Right? We have this
convergence here. But these here are
easy to integrate right
these these guys
but because they're polinomial
so the polomium so this means that the
fn
s the fns of s when you integrate this
from a to b ds these guys are the sum
here of A
uh K sorry
uh S K
K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K K
= Z to N and then the integral here
D S from A to B, right fine? Because
it's just that polomial. And so for
polomium well we can just use that it's
a sum of the of these guys a k sk
k = to zero to n right and this thing
here when we integrate this that's just
that's just um
that's just the I mean now it doesn't
get much nicer unless you make one of
them equal to zero.
So, so you have this. So, let me say
that if a here was equal to zero
and and and
b was equal to x. So if that's the case
and you're looking at this integral from
0 to x of fn
s ds, we know that this here converts to
the integral
right of the power series.
On the other hand, this integral here,
right? You know if
on the other hand
um on the other hand this integral here
if you're looking at the sum here
and then sum and now the a is zero b is
x so then is this here a k x k
now when we integrate this term here
we're getting right so we're getting the
sum here k = z to n and then this here
becomes
a
um k
+ 1
um x to the power k
+ one Right.
And so you see that if you're looking at
so you see that these guys here now
converge to the to the integral from
zero to x of f of s
gs right that's what we get from the
theorem. So the conclusion here is that
if you take a power series
um and you're looking inside the radius
of convergence then the power series is
differentiable as many times as you want
and the derivative is given by power
series and it's just the derivative of
the ter individual term by term right
and likewise if you want to integrate a
power series
then the integral So at least when
you're integrating because otherwise the
formula is not quite as nice but you get
a but you do get a formula but it does
doesn't look so nice but the integral of
a power series you can just integrate it
term by term right
okay so now the next thing we want to
talk about um and that's I'm just trying
to set up for next uh for for the next
lecture and so this is we want to talk
about uh differential equations and how
we using some of the stuff that we
proven in this class to solve
differential equation and in and it's
like an example where it may not be very
obvious
um
that you could use metric spaces to
solve a differential equation
but but this is nevertheless the case.
So, so we're looking at a differential
equation.
So, a differential equation is an
equation
is an equation
in an unknown.
in an unknown function
uh and its derivative.
So let me give you some examples of this
um that you take uh you're looking at uh
at a function f you're trying to find a
function f
so that so this is like the first
example you have you're looking for a
function f so that the derivative is x
right well we already know that this
here the solutions to This
um um f ofx
= to 1/2
x^2 plus some constant right constant
whatever the constant when you take
derivative you get zero and and the
derivative of this in here gives you x
right and those are the only solutions.
Um, another example here
is uh where you're taking something that
looks like uh f prime minus f 2. So f
ofx like this.
And if you're looking at the function
here
um f ofx = 1 - 1 /x. If you take this
function here and now you take the
derivative.
So now I'm using the chain rule. So I
get 1 - one like this squared and then I
take the derivative of this. So that's -
x
- one sorry - one.
So that's -1 * -1.
So this here is - 1 - x.
And so you see that when you take this
function here with a minus sign.
Uh
right. So,
so when you take I think it should be a
plus, right?
So, when you take
>> No, no, no. It should be minus. No,
that's right. Sorry. Yeah. Yeah. Thanks.
I did this one wrong. This here should
have been a minus like that, right?
And so, this here is now is indeed plus
and then it's this equation.
[Applause]
Okay,
the next example
um another so again if the equation is
something that involved a fun unknown
function and its derivative
uh so suppose you take something that
looks like f fprime
fprime equal to zero
if you're taking the function
f= to some constant,
this is a solution.
And if you're taking f= to say um x or
some constant times x, this is is also a
solution. They're both solutions.
And this is just because the second in
this case, the second derivative is
zero.
Okay. So now what we will be interested
in is uh we're going to be interested in
uh what's called an ordinary
differential equation. It's it's it's
and we only looked at this we only
looked as function of just one variable
if it's
so this is what the ordinary refer to.
So we want to look at ordinary
differential equation
and an ordinary
differential equation is abbreviated by
OD
and this is uh and if it's not an
ordinary then it's usually a partial uh
differential equation which involve a
function that is uh that is of more than
one variable. So it will involve the
what's called the partial derivative of
the functions.
Okay. And the the so the unknown so the
unknown function
function
uh will be denoted
by y.
And the equation that we're looking at
is that we want some particular value at
say zero.
And then we want
uh that the derivative satisfying an
equation. And the der equation that
we're looking for is that we have so we
have
um we have um so f here and g are given.
So think about those as functions that
are given. Those are two given functions
but you know they may not be super nice
and but you know that f is
differentiable
and the derivative is continuous
and g here is continuous
but in principle you know they're given
and now you're looking for a but it
might be very very complicated maybe f
is sign or you know something like that.
Uh and so you're looking for a a unknown
function y so that the derivative so y
we think about y as a function of x
and the derivative of y is supposed to
be equal to f but is now applied to this
unknown function
and then plus g of x. Right? So this
here is much more tame but this is a bit
complicated because it involved the
unknown function. Okay. And so we want
to we want to so we want to see so we
are asking
so question
does this equation
does this
OD
have a solution
and if
Um is the solution
uh unique?
Right? So by this we mean right? So
we're looking for a function. So so
here's what we're looking for.
We're looking for a function y defined
on some interval into r. This function
has to be differentiable. So this has to
exist.
A zero has to be in that interval,
right? Because we want this is a is just
a constant, right?
And so so and then we want then we want
obviously y to satisfy
uh this this equation here
right
that's what we're looking for. So this
is existence. They're saying that what
we will prove is that there exists some
interal. So, so we want so we will prove
the following.
So, we prove the following theorem of
which is has many different names and is
attributed to various people.
Um
but it's I guess
uh um in
it's
often most often
uh
named the pic lindelof theorem
and so this is that um that's um that
given
f and and g as a bound so f has to be
differentiable
and the derivative continuous g just has
to be continuous
Then there exist then
for any
a there exist
a delta greater than zero
um such that and a solution
and a solution
to this differential equation this OD
um um
on the integral from minus delta to
delta.
So we just prove we prove that there
exist a solution near the origin. The
thing is that a solution may blow up. So
it may not exist on a very long
interval. It may just exist on a smaller
interval. is all depending on f and g
but in particular will depend on f.
Okay. So it's uh and and that moreover
uh it is unique
meaning that if you take another
solution
defined on the same interval then it
must be that solution. Okay.
And so,
so now I just have a minute or two, but
but we'll prove this next time anyway,
but I just want to
um as a teaser, if you will, I will just
say that. So, the proof of this,
so the proof
the proof
uh uses
Uh the contracting mapping zoom
mapping the
I'll remind you what that is. Maybe I'll
remind you what it is. So the so recall
that the contracting mapping system
is the following
that suppose you take a metric space X
and D.
So D is a metric, X is a space.
And suppose you take a map
from X to itself.
Then X is so then T. So T here is a map
from X to itself. T is set to be
a contracting map.
If if there exists some constant that
constant and that's key it has to be
strictly less than one so that if you
measure distances
between the images
so for any X and Y in capital X
this is for all X and Y in capital X if
you look at the distance between the
images of these two points
then it's less or equal to this constant
that is strictly less than one
like this. Okay. So that's a contracting
map
and the contracting mapping theorem that
we prove I I'll remind you about it
again next time but just
the contracting mapping theorem that we
prove this that so we prove the
following theorem which is a contracting
mapping theorem that if
X here is cushy complete
Then and
and t from x to x
is a contracting map
matching map.
Then
t
has a unique
fix point.
So a there's a unique so there exist a
unique one often write like this there
exist one and only one x
so that f so that or x0
so that this map takes x0 to itself so
that's a contracting mapping theorem
okay and so now so it seems like that
what does od has to do with this
abstract concept of a metric space. So
it's it's tied together using this
and then the space X it's not. You may
think that it's it's you may think
that's close, but it's not quite the
case. You may think that it's like a
continuous function on an interval like
this. That's close. That's this here is
you may think that because that's a
space we've talked about a lot. this
here with this metric D we talked about
with this maximum distance. It's not
actually quite the case. It's a little
bit more complicated than this.
The x is but x is related to this
because x here would be a ball
around the function that is constant
um the function that is constant a
in this space
and and we have to choose this r
carefully. Okay. And so that's a space
X. And now I haven't defined the the fun
the map G, but we'll do that next time.
And I will remind you about this also.
Any questions?