Hi, my name is Graham and I wanted to
share a bit about my educational journey
with MIT open learning. I've loved doing
math since middle school, but after
learning calculus, I didn't really know
where to go next. However, a couple
summers ago, a professor that I know
recommended that I watch Gilbert
String's 18.06 linear algebra lectures
online. After seeing everything else
that open courseware had to offer, I
immediately had tons more math that I
wanted to learn about. That same
professor told me that it's important to
learn math in multiple different ways.
And so, in keeping with that, open
learning has become a very useful tool
for me to learn with in addition to
other resources like textbooks. When I
first started real analysis, the worked
examples in the 1800A lectures helped me
make sense of a subject that felt
completely new. Later, when I started
functional analysis, the intuitive
explanations in the 18102 lectures
helped me grow my understanding beyond
what textbooks could offer. Open
Learning has helped me grow my passion
for math, something I now try to share
through clubs I run at my school,
offering free tutoring, doing research,
and hopefully eventually becoming a
professor of math. Thank you, Open
Learning, for helping make this
possible.