it's great to see you all um thank you
for attending this session on space
launch and uh yeah it's always tough to
follow Dan Hastings you know I remember
Dan uh when I first came to MIT I've
been here since
1997 and uh Dan was the associate
department head he had my job and I
remember uh the open house you know
where where am I going to go where am I
going to go to grad school and Dan was
the associate Department head and talked
about the Strategic plan of the
department here and uh it was actually a
very similar speech to the one he gave
but 30 years later constellations large
scale systems a lot of the challenge a
lot of the things that at the time was
almost science fiction is really coming
to reality so it's an honor to speak to
you today my talk will follow on Dan's
remarks but I'm going to be very
narrowly focused on the launch industry
so what's happening because without
launching into orbit there is no space
Enterprise so the purpose of this talk
is to give you an update on the global
launch industry and what's been
happening there I will also say I'm the
editor-in chief of jsr the Journal of
spacecraft and Rockets which is one of
the eight journals of the aiaa so I'm
really um I have the benefit of getting
the latest research from around the
world submitted in this area so um
really have a good insight into what's
happening so let's start with a bit of
History though uh this diagram shows you
the launch history between 1957 and 2021
of course 1957 the international
geospatial year Sputnik 1 and relatively
quickly within about seven years as you
can see here we ramped up we meaning
globally we ramped up to about 120
launches a year and it stayed at roughly
that level of 120 launches per year
until the end of the Cold War right the
Berlin Wall came down 1989 1990 the
collapse of the Soviet Union and then
you can see about a decade of of
decrease fewer and fewer launches every
year and the ner the low point of the
launch industry was in about
2003 since then since then things have
been been going up quite dramatically
and um a lot of that though is driven by
the commercial uh launch industry uh the
colors show you the different propellant
types so liquid Ox oxygen liquid
hydrogen uh liquid oxygen kerosene rp1
rocket propellant one um nitrogen
tetroxide and udmh which is a form of
hydren liquid oxygen and methane and
then the solids of course like the space
shuttle and and other vehicles
and you can see on the right side which
of the vehicles use which propellant
type and you can see the different
propellants have have fallen in and out
of favor um if I could point out one of
them that is really on the ascent now
it's the use of liquid oxygen and
methane that is definitely the fuel of
the future it
seems okay so um that chart if you
notice ended in
2021 and we were basically in 202 one we
exceeded even the highest launch year
since um you know the 80s 7s and 80s
however uh things have really changed a
lot in the last three years um so and I
had to manually amend this chart so I'm
just going to go back and forth here
toggle a little bit uh last year
2023 was another record year for the
launch
industry and uh we were up um we had 222
launch attempts glob
speaking um and 210 successes so the
success rate was
94.5% we did have 11 failures launch
failures and one partial failure so a
partial failure means um you got to
space but you did not deliver the
satellite to the Target orbit that you
wanted to reach and I'm going to talk
more about failures and and where do
they come from and how what can we do
about the remaining launch failures I
hope you agree with me that for for most
systems if it's automobiles or airplanes
or trains a 95% success rate would not
be acceptable right so we are not yet uh
in a routine kind of operation in
space okay so what does it mean to get
to space so here's a a a typical launch
profile so you have uh altitude and as
many of you know the space begins at 100
kilm the Caron line um and um by by the
way uh I teach 851 16851 satellite
engineering this semester and one of the
assignments to the students was
calculate the Carmen line where space
begins from first
principles and it turns out when you do
that you cannot it actually depends on
technological assumptions the Caron line
is not a nature given border it depends
on technological assumptions it's a
essentially the point where um in order
to generate enough lift for an
aerodynamic vehicle you have to fly at
the speed of orbital velocity that's
kind of the transition Point anyway the
point is for vertical launch we have the
ascent we have the famous Max Q the
point of Maximum Dynamic pressure where
is that well di maximum Dynamic pressure
is 1 half Row the density the air time
velocity squared of course we know
density goes down exponentially veloc
vity goes up squared so there's a point
where that that expression is maximized
and it happens pretty soon after launch
like roughly 90 seconds after launch you
will hit Max Q then the ride gets
smoother the loads get less then you
have depending on the staging uh
different events and then eventually
your trajectory needs to bend over
because you need to achieve horizontal
velocity the only reason we launch
vertically is to get through the
atmosphere as as quickly as possible
here this is by the way the launch
profile for Apollo 8 which is still my
favorite Mission I was born in
1968 and this is the mission that gave
us the famous earthrise picture that
you've all seen right that was maybe the
most significant outcome of Apollo was
that picture or that set of pictures so
you saw the Saturn 5 it is right here
and for many years during those decades
that I showed you the launch industry
you know it was there it was kind of
more or less stable but there was not a
lot of innovation in the launch industry
that has changed there is a lot going on
in the launch industry uh both for heavy
or super heavy launchers as well as for
smaller launchers we'll talk about that
so here's a lineup of some of the launch
Vehicles sort of like from small medium
to large really large um so new Glenn
for example is uh under development by
Blue origin it hasn't flown yet but it's
going to happen soon I am not showing
you the STS and the SLS so the the
shuttle that was retired in 2011 and
then the derivative of the shuttle which
is the SLS rocket um but we have other
launch Vehicles so the Aran 6 which is
European the European launch vehicle um
actually a very good architecture
unfortunately a decade late Aran 6 would
have been a great launcher if it had had
its first launch in like 2013 or 2014
um it's not reusable in its current
state and then here you see the various
evolutions of you know bfr which became
Starship today so I want to uh because
this is such a Monumental uh was such a
Monumental event and I'm sure many of
you have seen bits and pieces of it I
wanted to take just those three minutes
to show you the launch video of the last
flight the last uh test flight number
five for Starship um and then I'll I'll
I'll I'll tell you what's the connection
with
MIT cre final for
operations stage one go stage two go
flight directors go for
launch we have
[Applause]
vange Max
Q Max Q I hope you heard that
start stage
separation stage
separation Z 30 seconds catch decision
confirming 30 seconds to make that
decision 10 seconds cat
decision stage separation
confirmed go boost to operator go vote
is set true we are go for catch
[Music]
booster coming in hot for booster
TCH Bo fds is
[Music]
saved 13 of those RoR engines and this
view is incredible right now I can't
wait for us to hear the sonic
boom Landing start up
[Applause]
we can see those
CH this is absolutely insan on the first
ever attempt we have successfully caught
the super heavy
[Applause]
booster theilla has caught the
booster Starship has
theere Starship isch in theing pH of
Entry start up
Is On
[Applause]
Target Starship is landed
[Music]
all right so um how exciting is that so
what's the MIT connection well many of
our our graduate students um and some
undergrads too of course who are working
on Starship are graduates of our
department um for example the lead
engineer who is responsible for the
flight back booster control Lars
Blackmore uh graduated from a asro and
here's some more recent example so matoz
did not work on Starship but he was the
Arian 6 system engineering um lead for
the requirements Katie Carroll uh
graduated in 2021 with her Masters she's
in charge of mission integration for
Falcon 9 and then Matthew maragas uh
Masters 2018 and PhD 2021 is a member of
the propulsion engineering team for
Starship that you just saw um so let me
talk a little bit about the fundamentals
here here so the fundamentals really of
Rocket Theory um date back to constanti
silovsky um it's one of the basic
equations that we all need to teach and
learn and uh 1903 is when he published
that and one of the key questions is how
much fuel do we have to burn to
accelerate accelerate a rocket from some
initial velocity to a known final
velocity and uh and this is essentially
this is an MIT conference so I got to
show you some equations right uh so this
is this is a one of the forms of the
rocket equation uh that's the one that
tells you the final mass of the rocket
so after a burn what is the mass of the
rocket well it is the um it's a function
of the initial Mass Delta V which is the
change in velocity this is the idealized
rocket equation by the way um so it does
not account for drag for example it does
not account for it's basic basically in
vacuum uh doesn't account for Gravity
losses so the Delta V velocity change um
Earth
gravity um and then ISP which is the
specific impulse so how much Delta V is
really required to reach orbit it's
quite a bit um so orbital velocity is
about 7.8 km/s but then we have to
compensate for uh the gravity losses so
when the rocket ascends like you saw on
the video right we we're fighting
gravity in a vertical sense and that's
not helping us achieve orbital velocity
so every second that the booster thrusts
in the vertical direction is a loss when
it comes to achieving orbital velocity
which has to be horizontal and then of
course we have drag losses as we go
through the atmosphere so all in all uh
that's about another 2 km/s so if if you
want a rough estimate it's kind of a
generous estimate of of how much
velocity change we need to achieve it's
about 10 kilm per second which is a lot
now um what does it mean to be an orbit
it's all about energy it's all about
energy so let's assume we're we're we're
basically entering an orbit uh a
circular orbit around the Earth uh the
height of our altitude of our orbit is H
and this would be the velocity of our
orbit so it's the square root of mu the
specific gravitational parameter divided
by r and then you can see as R increases
as you go further and further from the
earth your orbital velocity actually
goes down that's counterintuitive right
we go further away from the earth and
our velocity drops but the total energy
increases and why is that because our
potential energy increases and so this
equation on the upper right this is a
very famous equation it's the key
equation to understanding everything
about being in orbit maneuvering an
orbit refueling an orbit this is the key
equation it's called the VIS Viva
equation and shows you the energy
density or the specific energy in Jewels
per kilogram of an object in a circular
orbit or an elliptical orbit if you look
at minus mu/ 2 a a is the semi- major
axis of the orbit so um we we can plug
in different numbers for different
orbits if we could orbit the
earth um at the surface of the Earth
which we can't because of the atmosphere
we we would need about 7.9 km/s at a 500
km orbit which is um about where
starlink satellites operate they're at
550 it's 7.6 and then at geosynchronous
it's about 3
km/s why am i showing you that I'm
showing you that because we can
calculate the energy per unit mass that
we need to put into a body so that it
can orbit the earth so we can plug in
those numbers and you and and we get a
number of about 33 megga per kilogram 33
megga per kilogram the bigger part of
that is the ktic energy but the
potential energy is is is about 15% of
that so it's it's also significant so no
matter how you launch into space with a
rocket with a rail gun uh maybe with a
space elevator in the future this is the
amount of energy you're going to have to
provide that's a that's a universal law
where's that energy coming from so this
diagram shows you um the density uh by
volume and by by mass so the orbital
energy is shown here that's that
vertical line that I showed you 33 megga
per kilogram so ideally we want to use a
source of energy to the right of that
like jet fuel rp1 right um kerosene
highly refined kerosine or methane LG
liquid natural gas the biggest component
of that is methane that's what Starship
used uses that you just saw in the video
or in the lower right hydrogen the issue
with hydrogen is it gives us the best
rocket performance but it's also very
very volatile right and and if we have
it as a cryogenic fluid we do need to
deal with the boil off so you can only
really uh fuel the rocket uh minutes or
a couple hours before the launch so uh
those are the choices and
you saw in the video the staging why is
staging so important staging is so
important achieving single stage to
orbit SST launch it's been a dream for
many years we've had programs trying to
achieve single stage to orbit and
Recovery the problem with it is the mass
fractions that we would have to achieve
are still Out Of Reach therefore uh we
do staging and um I'm not going to show
you I'm not we're not going to go
through this in detail but there's some
really interesting numbers here to look
at so gamma for example that's the mass
ratio of the the payload Mass plus the
structural Mass fraction Alpha times the
amount of fuel you carry for example for
a single stage to orbit and then this
parameter beta which is essentially how
much propellant do you put into the
second stage relative to the first stage
so we can work through the math and
convince ourselves that staging is
really worth it
and it comes down to essentially proving
that this inequality here is true when
is it true well it turns out it's it's
always true um and how much benefit
really is there to staging and so here's
a a worked out example assuming that our
rocket is a uh 1 million kilogram that's
actually less than Saturn 5 Saturn 5 was
about 3 million kilograms Starship is
about 5 million kilograms but it's sort
of the same class of launch Vehicles so
we're going to keep the total launch
Mass the same and then compare our
single stage to our two-stage rocket and
the answer is the payload Advantage is
very significant in this case it's about
60% um and so we cannot do launch
without staging either two stages or
three stages then the benefit of adding
additional stages decreases so you get a
sense that designing launch Vehicles is
a real mdo problem multidisciplinary
design optimization we had actually
worked on this as an mdo problem many
years ago so you can see in this DSM all
the disciplines that are coupled the
aerodynamics the trajectory the
propellant selection the structural
design uh the cost as well and
everything is really kind of intimately
connected at the time we had predicted
that um the cost for launch so this is
cost to Launch
versus the payload launched so the two
here indicates 20 metric tons that you
couldn't do better than this blue line
which is optimized Rockets with genetic
algorithms kind of a precursor to
Ai and uh lo and behold the Falcon 9
beat our original estimate from 10 years
earlier you see it's it's below the line
so you can launch more with the same
budget or you can launch uh cheaper with
the same uh payload launch uh Target how
is that possible how is that possible
the simple answer is reusability
reusability we did not assume
reusability back in the original design
problem reusability is really the key
and it's interesting when you look at
the evolution of Falcon 9 so the version
1.0 of falcon9 which was the 2010
version and then the version
1.1 uh they were very close to that blue
parito line that we had predicted but
then ft which is the current full thrust
version of Falcon 9 beat that estimate
so here's Falcon 9 here are the specs
for Falcon 9 and we look at beta that
parameter beta that you saw uh it's
almost exactly a 3.9 almost 4:1 ratio so
the point is an optimal design of a
rocket use it but it will also change by
fuel type is for the the booster is four
times larger than the second stage or
the upper stage so this all makes sense
now Dan Hastings alluded to this um what
about emissions what about the
environmental concerns so you saw that
this is what a typical launch trajectory
looks like and we're becoming more aware
of the various forms of impact so local
impact so the local dust cloud um the
ground Cloud the plume through the uh
tropis spere and then the stratosphere
and then eventually bending over the
recovery of the the various stages and
uh even later on Rocket stages
re-entering much later rocket stages
re-entering much later uh also causing
uh emissions uh and and different
alumina and other um substances entering
uh the mesopause and the stratosphere
and there's this is actually an area of
very active research including
atmosphere chemists as well um so the
environmental impact of the launch
industry is uh becoming more um more
important and there are of course people
who will say it's such a small industry
it's not significant uh it's already
hard enough to send things up there
let's not worry about it and that's
exactly what people used to say about
the automotive industry that's exactly
what people used to say about the
airplane you know the aviation industry
so we believe now is the right time to
really think about sustainability even
for the launch industry and if you think
this is just sort of hypothetical I
pulled out this this is a new story from
the New York Times
today not like six months ago this is a
new story today in New York Times um
that launch that you saw on the video
there was an independent researcher that
measured the sound levels and they
exceeded by quite a bit what had been
advertised so the the local impacts of
um of these launches particularly for
Starship uh are quite significant and it
comes back to the question that Dan
Hastings said about regulation you know
we don't want to ground Starship because
it exceeded sound levels but we do want
to deal with it in an honest and uh
productive way uh the launch failures I
mentioned they still occur uh here's
some different so Falcon 9 of course
during its development had some launch
failures uh the Russians
um proton M this is a 2013 launch
failure and then more recently the teron
one launch failure in 2023 some of you
might know Teran um relativity space is
a very Innovative space company most of
the components on that launch vehicle
are 3D printed but they did not succeed
in that particular launch so why do we
care of course crew and payload safety
Mission success advancing the technology
and enabling
reusability and so
um so here's an analysis that we
recently published at the IAC conference
in Milan a few weeks ago on all the
launch failures that have occurred that
we know about um in in the last 20 years
and by country and also by subsystem and
so uh so here's by country and then
here's by
subsystem and so in total we have had
118 launch failures over the last 20
years
about half of them are due as you would
expect to the propulsion system so
that's your uh your turbo pumps your
nozzles um your gas generators and so
forth uh about 4% software failures uh
guidance navigation and control about
88.5% electrical structural separation
failures about
6.8% and then
unspecified uh where you know the launch
the launch reason has the the failure
reason has either not been published uh
or or it's unknown is about a quarter so
a quarter of launch failures are not
well understood and we're happy to share
that very recent paper with you on
launch analysis so in order to really
understand launch failures and even
partial failures you have to be able to
simulate these trajectories and so here
you can see an actual Falcon 9 uh launch
data uh the the blue curve is the
velocity so you see the first stage
stage separation second stage and then
the more noisy uh orange curve is the
acceleration profile and so we have the
ability to really simulate these
launches in six degrees of freedom quite
accurately and then inject synthetically
inject different failures and see
whether they match the predictions so
that's another area of Interest so let
me finish up by talking about launch
services and and figures of Merit this
is a list of how do we judge the quality
and also the the competitiveness of the
launch industry of course launch cost uh
uh then we have launch the success rate
that we've talked about uh improving
safety the launch Cadence launch rate
per year you've seen that's going up my
prediction is that by 2027 so three
years from now we're going to launch to
space every day you know we're at 220 is
launch attempts 3 years from now will
probably be around 4 00 so we'll launch
to space every day from somewhere on
Earth in about 3 years um and then of
course the payload needs an interesting
question is small launchers dedicated
small launchers versus uh launching
small satellites as secondary payloads
on the larger launches um the secondary
payloads it's a much cheaper proposition
the downside is you get not to you do
not get to choose your your target
destination orbit you have to go to the
the orbit of your primary payload uh
what about launch costs a lot of has has
been said a lot has been
promised um and uh I would say that
we've really improved a lot thanks to
Falcon 9 uh and SpaceX but also others
uh but not as much as was claimed so
this comparison this is a comparison of
the launch cost pre-ot which is uh
NASA's commercial space Transportation
Services resupplying of the ISS we're
definitely below $10,000 per kilogram uh
Falcon heavy is is if you fully utilize
that launch vehicle it's closer to
$2,000 per kilogram
today um this is just from a US
perspective active and plant launchers
we made this chart uh a couple years ago
for NASA's space um new space economy
office and I just wanted to update you
in red with what's the latest status so
Falcon 9 and Falcon heavy very
successful they've had over 400 launches
to date Starship as you saw has had five
test launches the sixth launch probably
next week um new Shepard is a suborbital
vehicle continues to operate new Glenn
we've been waiting for new Glenn uh
patiently and it looks like it is going
to have its first launch within the next
couple months um the SLS of course um
the SLS is uh a sore topic uh but it it
continues to exist as a program we'll
see in the in the new Congress now uh
whether SLS will continue or not uh
Delta 4 heavy has been retired it had
its last launch in April uh Atlas 5 a
very reliable launch vehicle um is still
active but also nearing retirement
Vulcan had its first launch this year in
January of
2024 um and then we have a couple of
smaller launchers that either were
cancelled or uh companies that went
bankrupt like virgin orbit uh launcher
one was a air launched rocket so we have
a real mix here of of success stories
and much less success as well last year
I showed this chart uh Promises by Ula
to launch Vulcan Promises by the
European Space Agency to launch Arian 6
did it
happen yes it did yes it did so Vulcan
Vulcan had its first launch on January
8th and uh and Arian 6 on July 9th so
you can see that 2024 was a really big
year in this
industry um and so the newest trend is
dedicated small launchers there's a lot
of companies competing in that my
personal opinion is uh El the electron
launch vehicle by rocket lab is probably
the most successful of all of them and
you can look at the price point here
$7.5 million for a launch that's about
uh 10% of what a falcon 9 launch costs
but of course the payload is much less
uh the payload is 300 kg to lth orbit
and then about 200 to SSO which is a sun
synchronous orbit but definitely a very
impressive small launcher company uh
they're also by the way uh developing a
launch port in the US now in Virginia
and this is my final chart I said a lot
about the US I didn't say a lot about
the global picture but here's the global
picture for 2023 by space port um so if
it was really a a a two-party race
essentially uh during the Cold War it
looks like a two-party race today China
has really impressively increased its
launch Cadence they have six launch
sites in China and achieved about uh 70
or so launches last year uh the blue bar
on the other side here is the us we also
have six launch ports I don't know if
you knew that but uh there's the Kennedy
Space Center Cape Canaveral Mars is wops
Island in Virginia psca is actually a
launchport in Alaska um and star base is
bokach chica in Texas and then
vandenbberg in California and of course
a lot of other countries are also
developing their launch capabilities uh
some of them like France have been
around for a long time but are really
very down in terms of launch rates and
then we have some new nations joining as
well so um it's it's a very exciting
time and I don't know if we have time
for questions do we have time okay so
thank you very much and I hope that was
a clear picture thank
you I think the gentleman back
to some of the ballistic or kinetic or
however you call them launch platforms
like spin launch and the rail guns where
do you think they play in this are you
positive negative ambivalent I have to
be careful how I respond to that uh SP I
actually am quite familiar with spin
launch because um they um you know they
received several Investments they've
really done some impressive work on uh
what you could say is like the first
stage right
the problem is the energetics when you
go back to that vva equation and you
actually plug in the numbers even a very
high uh initial launch velocity but you
you're doing it uh on the surface of the
Earth the the actual energy that you add
to that object uh is is still a pretty
small fraction to orbital velocity so
you still you still need a lot of extra
Delta V to get to orbit even with spin
launch and then at that point you have
to say what's more econ economical a
maintenance of a spin launch
facility or uh for example air launching
so then it becomes a bit of an economic
argument other questions comments yes
the gentleman here in the
front hi my name is Jean phip Nikolai
from France but I just have a question
um I remember long time ago maybe 20
years ago there were a lot of uh there
were launches launch pad in the on the
sea is it still operating or is it um is
it there was a commercial there was sea
launch right which was a commercial
company operating off the coast of
California off of Long Beach uh
launching I believe the zenet rocket
they are no longer in operation but
China actually has um I think it's the
Yellow Sea if you see this Yellow Sea uh
launch site that is actually sea launch
so the Chinese are doing it but the US
is no longer doing it and I think it
comes down to this economic argument you
know maintaining a um the the advantage
of sea launch is you can go exactly to
the latitude you want for example
equatorial you get the maximum Delta V
but uh the weather dependence the cost
of maintaining the ship uh the whole
logistical cost is quite significant and
so it's not clear to me that sea launch
is really worth it in general maybe for
specific applications but as a general
strategy probably
not Ron no question from you I'm
disappointed my question
answer any more
question hi Winston churn for exite um
thank you for the presentation it was
very nice uh quick question um I noticed
that you plotted uh cost per launch
versus um per kilo versus time do you
expect that Trend to continue to drop
over time and is there any physical
limitation to when that might stop and
you know how would that otherwise impact
you know kind of policy going forward
that's a great question so the question
was will the launch cost uh dollars per
kilogram continue to decrease I do
expect it will decrease um especially
once Starship becomes operational right
Starship has a capacity of over 100
metric tons the question is it's a
little bit like the A380 you know the
A380 is a great airplane but you have to
fill the airplane you have to get 500
people to buy tickets and and and sit in
the A380 to really make it economically
viable so if you have a 100 metric tonon
launch vehicle but uh On Any Given
launch only 60 or 70 of those metric
tons are actually used there's unused
capacity right in that launcher um so
we'll see I mean Starship definitely is
a GameChanger but uh filling up Starship
launch after launch once it's
operational is is going to be tricky so
to me is a similar situation to the A380
but I do expect it to continue to
decrease there probably is a lower ASM
toote first of all the cost of the fuel
itself which isn't very much
but the cost of the labor force that it
takes to operate the whole system and
then even if you can reuse that booster
stage uh 20 times or 30 times you still
have the turnaround cost the inspection
cost so there's there is a a lower
asmode what exactly that is I don't
think we know but it's it's most
certainly below
$1,000 uh per
kilogram ah there we go well you
challenged me all every time you give a
talk you show one of these equations and
I feel like I'm back in unified so thank
you for turning the clock back to 1983
you mentioned that SLS you think has an
uncertain future could you elaborate on
that a little bit and maybe comment on
the implications of a potential
cancellation um well this is a public
forum so I have to be a little careful
but I I do think this is an instance
where the election outcome actually
makes a difference
um as you know Elon Musk uh is going to
be part it looks like at least
informally of the next
Administration and um he and others have
been extremely critical of um the SLS I
mean the estimate is that a single SLS
launch costs about $1.5
billion um a falcon 9 the regular Falcon
9 not the Falcon 9 heavy is about $60
million so you can you can buy you can
pay for about
255 Falcon 9 launches for a single the
cost of a single SLS now the SLS is
human
rated um and it provides a lot of jobs
you know in certain States and that's
been the Congressional mandate for SLS
the mandated reuse of the uh rs25 you
know the space shuttle main engine the
mandated reuse of the um solid rocket
boosters uh that's that's really a
congressional mandate uh I could I could
imagine that Congress and its new
configuration plus you know the exe
executive branch will say um the three
or four billion dollars per year that
we're spending on SLS is not worth it
we're going to invest that in a
different launch vehicle I don't know
that that will happen but I think it's
much more likely now than it was a month
ago and I'm happy to if someone
disagrees with that statement I'm happy
to debate that that with you uh off
stage sorry thank you a great talk by
the way so there's been talk about
increasing um kinetic Space Warfare of
various forms taking out satellite
systems and those sorts of things which
suggests that there might be a need for
surge launch capacity to replace assets
that have been rried what's your sense
about where we are on surge capacity wow
that's a great uh that's a great
question uh there have been five
anti-satellite tests so far performed by
the way we the United States were the
first to perform anti-satellite tests so
we should just acknowledge that so there
have been five so far and um they're not
a good thing they're not a good thing
you can see the step function in the
orbital population after each of those
tests so uh for the record uh we should
be banning anti-satellite
tests you know similar to a nuclear uh
treaty nuclear test band treaty I think
it's it to me it's on the same in the
same category uh that being said um we
actually had a a doctoral thesis on uh
gain theory in space recently that that
was concluded happy to share that with
you
and and you can play out different
scenarios and it's really interesting it
comes down if there really is
large-scale conflict in space a lot of
it will come down to replacement
capacity how quickly can we replace
these failed satellites uh which means
do we have the launch sites do we the
have the launch Vehicles do we have the
satellite manufacturing capacity to
rapidly replace these uh defunct
satellites and it really reminds you of
World War II World War I right how
quickly can we make airplanes tanks and
so forth I mean I hate to bring it up
but I think the industrial capacity in
the future to launch and replace
satellites rapidly is going to be very
important okay thank you Professor okay
thank you
[Applause]