we all like to say that chemistry is the
central science and it is the central
science in fact what I'd like to say
it's the science of the familiar because
everything around us is made of
chemicals the air that we breathe is a
mixture of usually good chemicals the
food that we eat is a mixture of
chemicals the clothes that we wear are
made of chemicals our own bodies are
made of chemicals the drugs that some
people very stupidly experiment with are
chemicals ah some of you are smiling I'm
connecting with you already so complex
but it's beautiful beauty is part of
science science it's an essential part
of science I'd like to ask each one of
you right now to reach out and touch a
chemical go ahead and do it right now
somebody's tapping on somebody's
shoulder somebody's pulling somebody's
hair don't pull too long somebody's
reaching out in the air yes chemicals
are all around us and we want to learn
and enjoy the beautiful chemical world
that we live in that's why I say
chemistry is the science of the familiar
for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow