the MIT energy initiative presents
porous materials designed to trap
molecules controlling Poe openings for
maximum capture written by Nancy w
stoffer z lights are a class of minerals
used in everything from industrial
Catalyst and chemical filters to laundry
detergents and cat litter they are
mostly composed of silicon and aluminum
to Abundant inexpensive elements plus
oxygen they have a crystalline structure
and and most significantly they are
porous among the regularly repeating
Atomic patterns in them are tiny
interconnected openings or pores that
can trap molecules that just fit inside
them allow smaller ones to pass through
or block larger ones from entering a
Zite can remove unwanted molecules from
gases and liquids or trap them
temporarily and then release them or
hold them while they undergo rapid
chemical reactions some zeolites occur
naturally but they take unpredictable
forms and have variable sized pores
people synthesize artificial versions to
ensure absolute Purity and consistency
says Raphael Gomez bombelli the Jeffrey
Chuck Career Development chair in
engineering and the department of
material science and engineering
dmsc and they work hard to influence the
size of the internal pores in hopes of
matching the molecule or other particle
they're looking to capture the basic
recipe for making Zite sounds simple mix
together the raw ingredients basically
silicon dioxide and aluminum oxide and
put them in a reactor for a few days at
a high temperature and pressure
depending on the ratio between the
ingredients and the temperature pressure
and timing as the initial gel slowly
solidifies into crystalline form
different zeolites emerge but there's
one special ingredient to add to help
the system go where you want to go says
Gomez bombelli it's a molecule that
serves as a template so that the zeolite
you want will crystallize around it and
create pores of the desired size and
shape the so-called templating molecule
binds the material before it solidifies
as crystallization progresses the
molecule directs the structure or
framework that forms around it after
crystallization the temperature is
raised and the templating molecule Burns
off leaving behind a solid alumino
silicate material filled with open pores
that are given the correct templating
molecule and synthesis conditions just
the right size and shape to recognize
the targeted
molecule the zeolite
conundrum theoretical studies suggests
that there should be hundreds of
thousands of possible zeolites but
despite some 60 years of intensive
research only about 250 zeolites have
been made this is sometimes called the
zeolite conundrum why haven't more been
made especially now when they could help
ongoing efforts to decarbonize energy
and the chemical industry One Challenge
is figuring out the best recipe for
making them factors such as the best
ratio between the silicon and aluminum
what cooking temperature to use and
whether to stir the ingredients all
influence the outcome but the real key
the researchers say lies in choosing a
templating molecule that's best for
producing the intended zolly framework
making that match is difficult there are
hundreds of known templating molecules
and potentially a million zeolites and
researchers are continually designing
new molecules because Millions more
could be made and might work better for
decades the exploration of how to
synthesize a particular zeolite has been
done largely by trial and error a Time
cons uming expensive inefficient way to
go about it there's also been
considerable effort to use atomistic
atom by atom simulation to figure out
what known or novel templating molecule
to use to produce a given zeolite but
the experimental and modeling results
haven't generated reliable guidance in
many cases researchers have carefully
selected or designed a molecule to make
a particular zeolite but when they tried
their molecule in the lab the zelite
that formed wasn't what they expected or
desired so they need to start over those
experiences illustrate what Gomez
bombelli and his colleagues believe is
the problem that's been plaguing zeik
design for decades all the efforts both
experimental and theoretical have
focused on finding the templating
molecule that's best for forming a
specific zolly but what if that
templating molecule is also really good
or even better at forming some other
zeolite to determine the best molecule
for making a certain zeolite framework
and the best zeolite framework to act as
host to a a particular molecule the
researchers decided to look at both
sides of the pairing Daniel Schwab Kota
PhD 22 a former member of Gomez bom
barelli's group and now a postdoctoral
fellow at Lawrence Livermore National
Laboratory describes the process as a
sort of dance with molecules and
zeolites in a room looking for partners
each molecule wants to find a partner
zey and each zey wants to find a partner
molecule he says but it's not enough to
find a good dance partner from the
perspective of only one dance answer the
potential partner could prefer to dance
with someone else after all so it needs
to be a particularly good pairing the
upshot you need to look from the
perspective of each of them to find the
best match from both perspectives the
researchers need to try every molecule
with every zly and quantify how well the
pairings
worked a broader metric for evaluating
pairs before performing that analysis
the researchers defined a new evaluating
metric that they could use to rank each
templating molecule zeolite pair the
standard metric for measuring the
Affinity between a molecule and a
zeolite is binding energy that is how
strongly the molecule clings to the
zeolite or conversely how much energy is
required to separate the two while
recognizing the value of that metric the
MIT Le team wanted to take more
parameters into account their new
evaluating metric therefore includes not
only binding energy but also the size
shape and volume of the molecule and the
opening in in the zeolite framework and
their approach calls for tuning the
molecule to different orientations to
find the best possible fit Affinity
scores for all molecule zeolite pairs
based on that evaluating metric would
enable zeolite researchers to answer two
key questions what templating molecule
will form the zeolite that I want and if
I use that templating molecule what
other zeolites might it form instead
using the molecule zeolite Affinity
scores researchers could first identify
molecules that look good for making a
desired Z
they could then rule out the ones that
also look good for forming other
zeolites leaving a set of molecules
deemed to be highly selective for making
the desired
seite validating the approach a rich
literature but does their new metric
work better than the standard one to
find out the team needed to perform
atomistic simulations using their new
evaluating metric and then Benchmark the
results against experimental evidence
reported in the literature there are
many thousands of Journal articles
reporting on experiments involving
zeolites in many cases detailing not
only the molecule zeolite Pairs and
outcomes but also synthesis conditions
and other details fiing out articles
with the information the researchers
needed was a job for machine learning in
particular for natural language
processing for that task Gomez bombelli
and schel bota turned to their dmsc
colleague Elsa olivetti phd7 the Esther
and Herald e Edgerton associate
professor in Material Science and
Engineering using a literature mining
technique that she and a group of
collaborators had developed she and her
dmsc team processed more than 2 million
Material Science papers found some
990,000 relating to zeolites and
extracted
1,338 of them for further analysis the
yield was 549 temping molecules tested
209 zeolite Frameworks produced and
5,663 synthesis routes followed
based on those findings the researchers
used their new evaluating metric and a
novel atomistic simulation technique to
examine more than half a million
templating molecule zeolite
pairs the results reproduced
experimental outcomes reported in more
than a th000 journal articles indeed the
new metric outperformed the traditional
binding energy metric and their
simulations were orders of magnitude
faster than traditional
approaches ready for experimental
investigations
now the researchers were ready to put
their approach to the test they would
use it to design new tempting molecules
and try them out in experiments
performed by a team led by Yuri Roman
leav the Robert T Hassam 1911 professor
of chemical engineering and a team from
the Instituto de technia chem in
Valencia Spain led by Manuel mulliner
and avalino corma one set of experiments
focused on a zeolite called chabazite
which is used in catalytic converters
for vehicles
using their techniques the researchers
designed a new templating molecule for
synthesizing chabazite and the
experimental results confirmed their
approach their analyses had shown the
new templating molecule would be good
for forming chabazite and not for
forming anything else its binding
strength isn't as high as other
molecules for chabazite so people hadn't
used it says gas bombelli but it's
pretty good and it's not good for
anything else so it's selective and it's
way cheaper than the usual ones in
addition in their new molecule the
electrical charge is distributed
differently than in the traditional ones
which led to new possibilities the
researchers found that by adjusting both
the shape and charge of the molecule
they could control where the negative
charge occurs on the pore that's created
in the final zeolite the charge
placement that results can make the
chabasite a much better Catalyst than it
was before says Gomez bombelli so our
same rules for molecule design also
determine where the negative charge is
going to end up which can lead to whole
different classes of catalysts schel
Cota describes another experiment that
demonstrates the importance of molecular
shape as well as the types of new
materials made possible using the team's
approach in one striking example the
team designed a templating molecule with
a height and width that's halfway
between those of two molecules that are
now commonly used one for making
chabazite and the other for making a
zeolite called AEI every new zealite
structure is examined by the
international zeolite Association and
once approved receives a three-letter
designation experiments using that in
between templating molecule resulted in
the formation of not one zeolite or the
other but a combination of the two in a
single solid the result Blends two
different structures together in a way
that the final result is better than the
sum of its parts says schabot the
catalyst is like the one used in
catalytic converters in today's trucks
only better it's more efficient in
converting nitrogen oxides to harmless
nitrogen gases in water and because of
the two different pore es in the
aluminous silicate composition it works
well in exhaust that's fairly hot as
during normal operation and also an
exhaust that's fairly cool as during
startup putting the work into
practice as with all materials the
commercial viability of a zly will
depend in part on the cost of making it
the researcher's technique can identify
promising templating molecules but some
of them may be difficult to synthesize
in the lab as a result the overall cost
of that molecule zeolite combination may
be too high to be competitive Gomez
bombelli and his team therefore include
in their assessment process a
calculation of cost for synthesizing
each templating molecule they identified
generally the most expensive part of
making a given zeolite they use a
publicly available model devised in 2018
by Connor KY ph19 now the Henry Singer
1957 Career Development assistant
professor of chemical engineering at MIT
the model takes into account all the
starting materials and the step-by-step
chemical reactions needed to produce the
targeted templating molecule however
commercialization decisions aren't based
solely on cost sometimes there's a
trade-off between cost and performance
for instance given our chabazite
findings would customers or the
community trade a little bit of activity
for a 100 fold decrease in the cost of
the templating molecule says Gomez
bombelli the answer is likely yes so
we've made a tool that can help them
navigate that tradeoff and there are
other factors to consider for example is
this templating molecule truly novel
where of others already studied it or
perhaps even hold a patent on it while
an algorithm can guide development of
templating molecules and quantify
specific molecule zeolite matches other
types of assessments are best left to
expert judgment notes Shota we need a
partnership between computational
analysis and human intuition and
experience to that end the MIT
researchers and their colleagues decided
to share their techniques and findings
with other zeolite researchers led by
Schwab Kota they created an online
database that they made publicly
accessible and easy to use an unusual
step given the competitive industries
that rely on zeolites the interactive
website
zodb mit.edu contains the researchers
final metrics for templating molecule
zeolite pairs resulting from hundreds of
thousands of simulations all the
identified Journal articles along with
which molecules and zeolites were
examined and what synthesis conditions
were used and many more details users
are free to search and organize the data
in any way that suits them Gomez
bombelli Schwab bota and their
colleagues hope that their techniques in
the interactive website will help other
researchers explore and discover
promising new templating molecules and
zeolites some of which could have
profound impacts on efforts to
decarbonize energy and Tackle climate
change the research involved a team of
collaborators at MIT the Instituto de
technia
upv csic and Stockholm University the
work was supported in part by the MIT
energy initiative seed fund program and
by seed funds from the MIT international
science and technology initiative Daniel
schwall bota was supported by an Exon
Mobile MIT energy Fellowship in 2020
through 2021