just begin with.
So uh if we have a
a metric space here
uh then uh a cover of
of x uh is a collection
uh of subsets
u alpha so that the
uh
uh x is contained in the union of u
alpha. So that's a cover of x. And
likewise
uh likewise
if a here is a subset of x then
uh u alpha is a cover
of a if a here is in the union of the u
alpha.
So that's what it needs to cover as the
whole set or just a subset.
Then uh there are some covers that are
particularly important and those are the
open covers. So a open cover
is a cover
uh that consists
of uh open subsets.
And then finally we have uh that so if
again x comma d is a metric space a here
is a subset of x then we say that
that uh that a is compact
uh if every
A open copper
of a has a finite
uh subco.
Okay.
And one thing we proved last time was
that if you have
[Applause]
if you have a so proved last time that
if if you have a if a here is compact
then uh
then uh a is
is bound
and closed.
Okay.
Um
right. So it's a is a closed subset
meaning that the complement is is um is
open and uh a itself is contained in
some large ball centered at some point
in x.
Okay. Now the the converse is not the
case always. So uh so
in RN
uh with
the usual metric
you cleaning metric
the converse is the
But in general, not
but not in general.
Okay. And so we looked at one example
on this uh last time.
So we looked at the following example
but it was a rather trivial example that
if you take x here if you take the space
x to be say the interval from 0 to one
uh and uh the metric here this here is
the usual metric.
So the distance between two uh elements
here is is just the norm of the
difference
and then well x is the whole set. So x
so with this here x is the whole set. So
x here if you think if this here is the
metric space then x is by definition
closed because the whole set is closed
right. It's not closed as a subset of R.
But if it's if if the matrix space just
is X, you know, then then it is closed
and it's it's bounded
and bounded.
In particular, this interval here is
contained in the ball of radius 1/2
around 1/2, but it's actually equal to
that ball, if you will. Right?
So it's definitely bounded
but it's not compact. Right? So it not
compact
because you can write x here as the
union of
1 / n
to one and now you take the union over
all inte positive integers right and but
if you only take finitely many of them
then you don't get all the way down to
zero Right? So it's it's not a union.
It's union of all of these. The each of
these are is open
but you but there's no finite union of
those sets that cover X.
A more interesting example
um is that suppose you take
suppose you take um so here's another
example
that we didn't get to last time. that if
you take the continuous function on the
unit interval.
Uh and so if you take and now we use
this metric that we have looked at
before
where the
uh distance between two functions
is the max
uh over x in this interval here
uh of the norm of f ofx minus g ofx. X
right we've already seen that this here
is a nice metric right
uh and and if I now look at in this
metric I look at the the unit ball so
I'm looking at the closed unit ball so
uh which means that I'm looking at the
set
the set uh of functions there
so that the distance
of f to the function that is constant
equal to zero this distance here
is sorry is uh less or equal to one
so I'm looking here
at the subset of the continuous function
on this interval
So that the distance to the zero
function is at most one. So let me just
write this out. Right? So this means
that uh this is the function f in this
continuous function here. So that
um the max
of f ofx minus zero. So I don't really
have to write zero is
is is less or equal to one.
Right?
Now this set again this set here is what
we denote by the this is like the closed
unit ball because you have lesser equal
to here right. So and the closed unit
ball the open unit ball we have written
and this is now the the function that is
identically equal to zero
the open unit ball we wrote like this
right this is if you have strict
inequality and to to to denote that is
lesser equal to I'm just putting a bar
here
okay
and so we already know that this thing
Here if you take a metric space and
you're looking at a closed unit ball
like this we already proved that this
here is closed right because you prove
directly using the triangle inequality
that the complement is open right
okay so that's if so this is a closed
subset it's obviously bounded right
because it's actually even just a ball
right
um now
so how but I claim that it's so it's
it's closed it's bounded
but it doesn't it's not compact and and
here's a sort of interesting example uh
of a sequence of element in this form so
I will now construct for each
for each n which is a natural number
uh we construct a function
uh fn
in this
that is a continuous function on this
unit interval and the function f um will
be given as follows.
It's will be
it will be uh one
uh from
uh when
uh see let me make it uh zero.
Uh I guess doesn't matter. I I make it
one uh when uh x here is between um 1 /
n + one. No
when zero is I would make it equal to
one when x here is bigger equal to zero
and lesser equal to 1 / n + one.
Then I'll make it um when when x here is
bigger than or equal to 1 / n but lesser
equal to one then I'll set it equal to
uh to to zero
and then you see now I want it to be so
so let me just so let's look at it. So
this function here is
um
so so this function here is if you draw
this function so
I have here one here I have zero
and this function is one um up to uh 1 /
n +1. Maybe I'll draw it a little bit
further out. Uh actually make the
picture bigger.
So like that. Here I have one.
Here I have uh 1 /
n + one and here I have 1 / n.
And the function is supposed to be one
here.
And then it's supposed to uh die off
between here
and here. And I will I choose it to die
off linearly and then a zero here.
So if it's going down linearly this
means that I have right what is the
difference between two these two it's 1
/ n minus 1 / n + one this is this
distance here and so this here putting
it on a common denominator n +1 / n * n
+1 this is what you get from this and if
you put it on the common denominator for
the second one this is what you get here
and so this is just one over n
like this right
and so this is this distance here
and so if I define the function to be
uh right so I'm setting it equal to
to this and now in between when x here
is bigger equal to 1 / n +1 and lesser
equal to 1 / n. I will set it equal to 1
minus
um n * n +
uh 1
um times sorry let me make more space.
Yeah, let me make more space.
So here this here was when zero is less
or equal to x less or equal to 1 / n +
1.
This is when uh x here is between
these two numbers and this here is when
x is larger than one / n and it's
x is always in the interval between zero
and one. And here I'm I'm choosing it's
x minus
uh and then 1 /
um u n + one
right. So you see that if you take
x to be 1 / n + one then this here
contribute zero. So at this left point
this here is equal it's the function is
equal to one as it should be. And when x
here is at the other end point then this
here becomes exactly one over this. So
this whole thing becomes zero.
Right?
So if I so this function here I drew is
is uh is if you write it down precisely
this is what the function is right
and now um now if I'm looking at
um if I'm looking at the difference
between uh two such such functions. So
for the next one you see the next one
here the next one here is so this here
is fn right this is how fn look like if
I now look at fn + one right this start
off being it's zero to the right of this
thing here and then it's it's one once
you get to
n plus2 True. So the next function
looks like this. I don't know if there's
any color chalk, but this thing here
uh is
uh that's the next function, right? So
so the the the first function is this
function here. That's a graph of the
first function. The next one is like
this one here, right?
And so if you're now looking at the
distance between FN and FN + one,
right?
The distance here was the soup of the
difference of the two, right? This here
was just the max
of uh f of
like this.
it was just the max of this right and
now I know that these two numbers is
always between zero and one so this max
here is at most one right but if I now
evaluate it if I now looking at if I now
just evaluate if I'm looking at fn and
now I just evaluate it in in this point
here
in this point 1 / n + one. So if I'm
looking at this thing here,
f(n) + one 1 / n + one,
you see this value here, this was this
first function here and at this point is
one, right? This here is one,
but for the next one, you see at that
point it's zero, right?
So this means that this max here is for
all n and n + one
is actually equal to to one, right?
And so
so now
if you look at
at um if you look at at the balls
So now in particular
if I'm looking at the balls of radius
1/2
suppose I'm looking at the ball of
radius 1/2
around so this is an open ball so around
fn right because this here is an open
ball so it means that's strictly less
than a half so this means that fn plus
one
is not in that ball. Right?
So it's not in sorry it's not in that.
Right? And and so now it's easy to see
that all of these balls here are
disjoint.
So all of these balls here will be
disjoint. They're all disjoint. And so
if you're looking at if you you can
write uh this initial ball this ball
here this was this close ball that we
started with in beginning
you can write it as uh as a union
suppose you write it you can write it of
course as a union of half balls
where you take the union over all
centers. plus
all possible centers like this, right?
Because you know this clearly cover this
set because it contains all the centers,
right? But that's already the whole set,
right?
But using this here, you can see that
there is not that you can't have finite
many of these half balls that cover the
whole set. Okay. So using
the functions
fn
uh it follow follows easily
uh that finite in many
many
of these balls.
does not cover
uh and it's uh let me just cover this
here. Why why is this the case actually
sometime you you you put it uh the bar
all the way across uh but but I haven't
done that. Okay. Why is suppose that
Suppose for a second
that you have
suppose that you have a ball here
uh of a radius a half around some point
then and suppose that you have a
function
g two functions g and h that are in that
bone just ucing that it's a metric
space. So now we have that this thing
here
g is strictly less than a half and the
distance from uh f to h is strictly less
than a half. So now using the triangle
inequality, we conclude that the
distance between this pair here G and H
is less or equal to the distance where
you go over F.
And so this here is less strictly less
than a half plus a half. So this is
strictly less than one.
So you see from this in particular that
if you take such a ball here
then you can't so it's impossible
to have
that
fn
and fn plus one.
It's impossible to have that they both
are in that ball,
right? Because if they were both in this
ball, then the distance would be
strictly less than one. And we've
already seen the distance is is one,
right? And this holds not just from for
fn and the next one, but it holds for
like fn. The same argument give that
from fn and any m larger than n. this
this here would be impossible, right?
And so from this it follows that you
can't have finitely many that cover the
Yeah.
>> or how do we know that the union of all
of those
functions and like the one
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, so, so this is just and
and this is important because we're
going to use this in a minute anyway. So
again if you take if you take a set here
so if you take a metric space
and suppose you take a set subset of X
then there's always you know you can
always find a cover even an open copper
um and in particular in a minute we will
look at so if you take a here so one
example of an open cover of A is that
you're looking at at the family of
balls.
You just pick some radius. R is positive
and then you pick centers,
right? But the centers, right? You you
you take the centers, you know, X here
is now anything in A, right? If you're
looking at R is fixed, it's positive.
X is anything in A. Well, the union of
these guys, the union certainly contains
the centers, right? So this here already
cover a right and so and we will use
this in just this is like a standard
array to get a cover and then if it's
compact then finally many of those
should cover right okay so in fact let's
get to that um
so um right so the next thing I want to
prove is um
uh is um is is this volano bias version
for a metric space.
So you prove a banal bias theorem for
metric space. Remember that the banana
basis does not hold for every metric
space.
for a metric space. So, so now it the
bulan visor does not hold for every
metric space but it holds. So uh when
when this space here is compact,
right?
Okay. So that's what I want to prove and
that's like one of the motivations here
and for for the for the definition of
being compact. And so
uh let me just remind you. So on RN
on R say uh what is the bulani? So on r
the balsano
why the what did that say?
So this is that any
bounded sequence
has a convergent
subsequence,
right? That was the banana bias assume
and and so uh what we want to show here
is the following theorem for a for a
general metric space.
So we want to prove the following
theorem
that if x comma d is a matrix space
uh a here
is subset is compact
then any
Then any
sequence
in uh A has
a convergent
subsequence.
Okay,
now let me try to divide it into the poo
and let me try to divide it in into some
sub pieces.
So
I begin
with a lema.
So,
so the lema,
so I want to begin with a lema that is
the following.
So, I have uh
so I have my metric space.
I have um a here is this subset that is
uh compact.
And then I have as a a family of nested
subsets. So let me just talk about
nested subsets for a second.
So I do this on this board. And so what
do I mean by nested subsets?
So, so again I have some set and then I
have some subsets.
Um, see
it's a it's a it's a family but it's now
a family that is uh indexed by the
integers. Right? So CI here is subsets.
So this is I uh equal to one two so on
and next
I mean in this case here uh I am
thinking about that the next subset is
smaller than the previous smaller or at
most equal to the previous. So I have
this
I could also have looked at where they
were kind of increasing the subsets but
uh but this is what I have in mind.
Okay. So the sets as as I become larger
the set becomes smaller.
So I have so now back to the lema. Um I
have this metric space. I have a compact
subset and then I have a sequence here
of CIS
is a sequence.
It's a nested sequence
sequence
of subsets.
So again this means that the next
element is contained in the previous
one. Right? And this nested sequence of
subsets, it's actually a nested sequence
of closed subsets.
Closed subsets of
A. Okay, so they're closed
in X and they're contained in
in A.
And then I assuming that uh and assume
also
that the CIS that none of the CIS are
the empty sets. Right?
So I I don't want any of them to be
trivial.
uh then the claim is so the claim is
that
is that if that's the case then actually
if you take the intersection of all of
these
this here is is is is non empty so there
is something that is in all of the CIS
right okay that's what I want to prove
um and in fact this is
quite straightforward Okay.
Um
and because
since the so the proof here
since
CI is closed
this means that the complement here
is open.
Right. And now for the complements here.
So the complement let's call it
complements let's call it uh bi.
So BI is open again and BI
um + one they actually have this
property that they are because the
previous ones was nested where they
became smaller then when you're looking
at the complements then they become
larger
and uh
but uh so since this is closed then we
have is uh if
the intersection of these CR if there
was nothing in the intersection of all
of them if this here was the empty set
but then it means that
that the complement of these guys would
then cover a right it would actually
right the cover right because there's
nothing the union of the complement so
the union of the complement here
it would actually cover X but it would
in particular cover
A right. So yeah this here called BI.
So you have that.
So this mean and again this here is this
here is the same as BI.
So now since uh A is compact
since uh A is compact
this means that uh A here
A here is contained in finitely many
of these let's call them
So you have finally many like this
of the bees and I just you know I'm not
sure whether it's the first but but but
there are finitely many of these that
cover it
and so in particular but one of these
is like right one of the indices here is
the largest one of those right and so
this means that it's actually contained
in the largest of these Let's say that
that the largest of these is b right. So
you have this for some n right?
But this say but this here remember that
this here was the complement of
CN like this right. So this means that a
have nothing in CN right. So this mean
but A was a sub C was so CN intersected
with A
is empty but CN was contained in A. So
this means that since
cn was assumed to be
uh contained in a right this was subsets
of a
then this means that cn. So this here is
this means that this here then implies
that that this thing here is is cn.
Right? So you have that one of them was
empty but that we assume that none of
the sets CN was empty. Fine.
Okay. Was that clear? Sorry. Yep.
>> Okay. So that's right. So So I'm I'm
trying to prove uh this theorem here,
right? And it it's uh it's not super
complicated, but it's a little bit
involved. And so I'm trying to of course
this is always a great idea if and it's
kind of like important thing in this
class
and and and and also if you take other
math, you know, more advanced math
classes is that when you're trying to
prove something,
it's, you know, there's things that are
really easy to prove, but then there are
things that are much more complicated,
right? So one thing is that you try to
prove it. Another thing is that you try
to explain to other the proof right and
so in either case if you can divide it
into substeps right and so this here is
a substep
uh in the proof
and uh and so in a minute we will see
why this here is relevant and so this
sort of answer your question right I
mean how does how does this come up
right and and in a minute you'll see how
it comes up so So, so let me get back to
that question just a minute.
>> Are you able to explain the last remark
again?
>> Yeah.
>> So, so here so so again the BIS are open
and using compactness because all of the
BIS cover a then finally many must cover
it.
But the bis are nested in in this way
that they are increasing as subsets. So
if I'm thinking about maybe this here is
the one where the index is large this
then contain all the other. So this is
it's actually equal to in that case it
would be equal you know this really is
equal to like this.
So again, so this means that A is
contained in in the complement of CN. So
in other words, there is no elements
in uh in A that are in CN. Right? That's
what it means. So there is no elements
in A that has a CN. This is that this
thing here is empty.
But the CN remember that the CN was
assumed to be subsets of A. Right? So
this means that that there is nothing in
CN that is not in A. So this is really
just equal to CN
>> and so is that essentially just creating
a contradiction. Uh and so that's why
and that's a contradiction because now
this show that this one here this CN is
empty but they were all assumed to be
non empty right yeah okay
so so this is this is like uh yeah Sorry
question.
>> Right. Right. Okay. So if
so if the intersection of the CI
right so here sorry if they inter so I
want to prove this. So I'm assuming that
this is the case and I define the BIS to
be the complement of the CIS. So if
there is nothing
in the intersection of all of the CIS
then it means that the union of the
complements must cover the whole set
right because you know right so if you
takes anything in even in X if you take
anything in X it's not in all of the CIS
so this means that there is some I so
that it's in complement of that CI right
but that's that's exactly this
um okay so now so you're asking why is
this relevance right and and that's a
good question and uh and I'm not I'm I
will answer it in a minute but I will uh
kind of elaborate I will give you an
example where I have it and then we will
eventually see how to get to that
example okay so the next thing is
that suppose I take a
[Applause]
suppose I have the same setup
but now my sets are you know the the
then close sets so I have this setup
again so this is like a corner
of of the lema that we just pruned
so we We have x comma d. This is matrix
space.
And we have uh a here is a subset of x
uh is compact.
And now now my sets CIS
is going to be so CIS here these are
going to be balls
of radius R I
and center X I
and U there would be balls like this
and I'm assuming that they are nested
so in the Same way I'm assuming that
this thing here
the centers change the radi and the
center change is depending on I they're
all this close ball where it's like
lesser equal to the eye. So I'm assuming
that the next one is contained in the
previous one.
Okay.
And then I'm making one more assumption
is that the RA I
goes to zero.
Okay. So I have that. So so just let's
observe that these sets here they are
nested by assumption. They're closed,
right? Because it's it's it's it's this
closed ball. So they're closed subsets.
Also observe that each of these balls
contain the center. So right so this
means that each of these balls is not
empty. Right? So it's automatic that
they're not empty. Right?
Okay. So now I claim that
I claim that the intersection of all of
these balls
is is just one point.
So now
uh so now the claim here
that the uh intersection of these balls
here,
these closed balls here
is uh is a single point.
Okay. Yeah. How do we know that each of
balls contain the center?
>> Uh because you know but if you take um
if you take a ball
so if you take a ball here in any metric
space this is the y in the space in this
set. So that the distance from X to now
I take the open one but similarly with
the closed this thing here is less than
sorry this here is why saying
>> it contains its own center but not like
one single point across all
>> yeah so that's right so so I'm just
saying that so so if you plug in y x for
y right you get zero right so this is
definitely so so this here x definitely
is in here right and I'm just saying
that each of these guys is not empty
right
okay so now but and then I want to claim
that actually there's something in the
intersection of all of these balls and I
want to claim that there's only one
thing such thing there's a unique thing
that is in intersection of all these
balls right okay so now First,
first I want to prove that this thing
here
is non right
and sorry and this here should have been
the closed balls like this but you see
uh this just follows from
from the lema
because
each each
uh B, you know, because each B R I
XI is closed
and non- empty
is each is closed non- empty.
Um and and and
the family
or sequence
of of walls
is nested.
Right? By assumption, right? By
assumption, we assume that this thing
here is our i + 1 x i + 1 that this
thing here is contained in the previous
right. So by assumption by assumption so
we again we use the lema and this is the
CIS right and the CIS are closed and
they are indeed nested as they should be
and they are all non- empty just because
they each contain their own centers
right I you know yeah
>> we're making some assumption. That's
right. We're making some assumption
about um right so
we're you know and uh uh right we're
making some assumption about that we the
when you when you make this assumption
about nested there's some assumption
about the centers the the distance
between centers and there's also
something about the radi that you know
how large is one radio relative itude to
the other, right? Because if you have if
you imagine that this here is BR I
like this. This is this. So in the
picture it would be kind of contain the
boundary and then the next one but the
next one may be out here on the side but
it's supposed to be
contained in it.
Right? So you see that the center the
sender may have moved. This here was the
XI and the next center may have moved.
It may have shifted quite a bit, right?
But of course, you know, this here is
the RA I radius and this here is the RA
I + one radius, right? So you see that
there's u there's some sort of relation,
right?
But okay so so the so we have that the
it just follows from the lema that the
intersection of all these closed balls
is non empty right yeah
>> it just follows
you
>> yeah that's right so it follows now from
that I that's why we're using the r= to
zero because suppose that you have two
elements, right? Suppose that you have X
here and Y. Suppose that they are in the
intersection of these guys here.
Right?
Now look at the distance between X and
Y.
Well, they are into intersection. So
this means that for each I for each I
so for each
each eye we have that X here and Y
is in this guy here.
Right? So if it's in in this ball here
for for a a I then you can use the
triangle inequality,
right? And this thing here is bounded by
this here should have been a RA.
This here is bounded by less or equal to
because I have this bar RA I plus RA I
so 2 R I but it this here holds for all
I this here goes to zero. So this means
that this here implies as you say this
here implies that the distance
had to be zero but this is part of what
it is means to be a metric space that if
the distance is zero then the two points
are the same.
Okay so that was actually so the whole
core was really quite easy from the
demo. Okay.
And so now the question is so this is
your question is why is this relevant in
in the in this balsano vast stress right
I mean there may be not so interesting I
mean the lema and color on its own but
but it's but there are tools to prove
the banana bio
okay so let me try to first
explain the idea and then then we go to
the proof.
So we have
we have this matrix space
and we have a subset
and the subset here is compact.
subset is assumed to be compact.
Then we have a sequence
XN
and this sequence here. So this is a
sequence
contained in
in
And we want to prove that there exist.
So want to show one to
to find
a convergent
subsequent
remember that here I mean you know just
that there's no assumption you know I'm
not talking about some cushy complete
set space or something like that right
so in this case I really have to
construct the you So I have to construct
the convergence sequence but I also have
to kind of construct the limits right
and so this is where or you know like in
particular like the limit this is why we
want this thing here to have a unique
intersection
okay so that's what I want to do right
so you you have this uh space you have
the subset that's compact and and you
are given a sequence
So now I start with um so so and and and
before I actually get to the proof let
me just try to explain the idea.
So this is this is again this is sort of
uh before the proof
So I want to make an observation. So if
I am in this s iteration and suppose now
that I take so I have a here and I take
some r think of r as being really small
and then do what we did just did a
little while ago. We cover we cover
we're looking at A here is covered by A.
You can write A as a union of these
balls here where the center is anything
in A. Right? So again that cover
A and so this means that finally many
that's finally many
many
cover
a
since
a is compact.
So I can write a here
as the as uh contained in and then r
uh now I had to be careful because this
is not the x probably I should use a y
here. Sorry, just to to not confuse it
with the sequence that I have. Okay.
And so I can I can it's contained in the
union of balls like this.
YM right is contained in the union of
finitely many balls like this.
Okay. So far we haven't used our
sequence, right? But now of course I can
say that we we we were given a sequence
right we now have finally many balls
right so and there are like infinite
many elements in the sequence so it
means that there is one of these balls
finite many balls so for one of them
for one maybe more more than one maybe
all of them but for at least for one
of these sports.
There are
infinite many
elements
in the sequence.
Let me be very precise what I mean by
that.
So by that I mean of course this
sequence could be like a constant
sequence. What I mean that for
infinitely many ns xn is in one of these
balls right. So let me just write that
out just to be totally clear. So meaning
for
one of these balls.
There are
infinitely many
many ends such that
XN
is in in that ball
and let's say that this is uh Y3
whatever right so there's infin many n
okay
so now
I can just think about that one ball
right and I can just think about the
sequence instead of the original
sequence I think about a subsequence
that is contained in it. Right? So
meaning this means that there is a
therefore
there is a subsequence
a subsequent
of the given sequence
that
is contained in this
in this form.
Okay.
Now,
um,
[Applause]
okay. Now, I want to somehow repeat this
process.
I want to repeat this process and again
I'm I I haven't quite started the proof
here but I'm just trying to explain the
idea right so this is like this this is
like a step in the proof that you then
for the right sort of has to use over
and over again right
and so now
um so I want to repeat this process and
for that I I need to remind you that if
you take um metric space, if you have a
metric space, so the coin
that if um
if um x here is a metric space
uh a here is a substance
a compact subset.
A is a compact subset
and B here is a closed
set and is a closed subset
of X. Well, then A intersected with B,
right? The intersection of if it's
compact, it's also it's also closed,
right? We proved that. And so this is
the intersection of two closed sets. So
this is closed. This is contained in A.
And now we proved last time that if you
take H. So this here is a closed subset.
This is closed
and is contained in A.
Since A is compact, if you take a closed
subset of A, then this is also compact.
So this is also compact.
Okay. So now
now let's continue
that uh string of thoughts from over
there. So how do we
now we
repeat this?
So it's have I have a set I have here
maybe even bigger. I have here uh this
here is my space x. Then I have some
subset. This here is a
a is compact.
I cover it with balls here
of radius uh and I now have that
finitely many. These are balls of radius
r around some some y's,
right? Finitely many. as fin as many of
these balls and the copper eight right
then
these sets here are of course not closed
and so I'm looking at
this
ball here these finally many and I just
take the closed balls
now I want to cover right and and and I
found that for one of
there was a subsequence that was
contained in fact in the open ball so
even you know so therefore also in the
closed ball right there was a
subsequence of the original sequence
that's a ball I'm focusing on right
now this ball I can then cover by balls
of radius so I'm covering this so cover
this
by balls
of radius
uh r over 4.
So I'm going to write this thing here in
the same way. I'm going to write this
this here I now know
um
this thing here
this thing here I'm only interested in
syncs that are contained in a. So I know
that if I intersect it with A
then this here is is compact, right? I
know that this is compact. That was
because this here was closed, right? And
and Na was compact, right? So this here
is compact.
So this means that that if I can write
that set here,
I can write that set
uh as so I can write this set here.
So, so I have so
I have
so I start with a that is compact then I
find a ball
so that a subsequence is contained in
that ball right this is was that ball
then I'm looking at so this is like the
process I start with here this is step
one step two I looking at this set three
I'm Looking at now the closure of this
ball
intersected with a this here is here is
compact.
This here contains a subsequence
a subsequence
of xn.
This thing here is compact.
This means that I can cover it by balls
of radius. So cover it
by balls
of radius
um r over four. I want smaller radius as
I'm going along. Okay. So I'm covering
it with and in fact I can cover it by
finitely many balls.
Right? Why finite many? This is because
this here is compact. I'm writing this
here as the union of balls of this
radius where anything in this set is a
center. And so I have the finite many of
those cover it right by compactness.
Right?
And so now what I observe is that if I
take and now I just had to be a little
bit careful. So now I'm observing that
if I take the ball of radius
the double ball
suppose I'm taking this ball here. So I
get finite sorry no before that. So I
have that it's now finitely many balls
cover this. So this means that a
subsequence
must lie in one of these balls. Right?
So therefore, so this is the fifth step.
A subsequence
of the subsequence
lies
in one of these these
these finite many balls.
of radius
uh r
over four, right?
And now
now I take so the next thing is I do and
now I want to I want to apply the color
from before. Right. So I started with my
space X. I got this ball here of radius
R and then there was some center.
Then then the next thing is that I get a
ball of radius
uh one
quarter
ah and now this is with you know one of
these other finite many balls where a
subsequence is called it like this uh
maybe like one or something like that
right so I get that so so
The balls of radius R over four they
cover this. So a subsequence actually
would have to lie here.
Right? And so now but now I want to use
the corner. If I need the to use the
corner I need to have nested and I need
to have closed sets. Right? And so in
order to make them nested then I double
I'm I'm going to double this ball. Why
do I double this ball? Well, I double
this ball here because these guys here
cover this, right? But it means of
course that there could be something
outside, right? There could be. So this
is like a ball of radius R.
And so then you have this ball of radius
a quarter R but the quarter balls they
may have some part outside and some part
inside right so so it's not this ball
here is not contained in that ball right
but if you went to the double ball
if you went to this ball of radius 2 R
you see this this point here the center
the the the center here It would lie
right there would be some points in this
ball here that would be within it may
not be the center but there's some point
here that's within R of the center and
then by the triangle inequality any
other points is actually within R2 R
over two of that point. So everything is
comfortably. So this thing here and even
the half ball. So I I can
conclude that even the ball of radius r
over two. Even this one here
is contained
in the double ball
like that. Okay.
And and in fact if you make things less
or equal to on both things then you have
that.
Okay. Now what I have is at least here
you have
something that is nested. Right. And you
see that the radius went down. Right.
Right. So these are nested and they're
closed. Okay. And so now what we do is
so now we want to do this for a
sequence, right? And then of course we
want so now we want to construct a
sequence of closed balls like this,
right?
And so and now when you pick your
subsequence, you have to you can't wait
with picking the first element in a
subsequence. Right? Remember if you keep
waiting then you will end up getting
nothing right? So you pick at each stage
you pick one element in a subsequence
and then when you have the next ball you
pick the next element in a subsequence
and so on right and so
so we will do this with
so we're going to do this procedure here
so now we're getting back to the the
proof of the theorem right and again
remember the theorem was this maybe I
erased it now mistake but the the serum
was this bosano V theorem for a metric
space that you have a metric space you
have a compact subset and you have a
sequence in this compact subset and you
want to construct a convergent
subsequence.
So, so what you do is there's a proof
of the bulan visor
for metric spaces.
So, so what you do is so you have this
again a here is compact and you have a
sequence xn this is a sequence that is
contained in a
What you do is that first you can just
let r be equal to one
and then and then you do this you you
cover it
uh by you cover it you have here a and
you cover it by finitely many balls of
radius one
and for one of these balls you have that
there's infinite many element in the
sequence. So you're going to focus on
that ball from here on and out. And you
just pick in your subsequence. You now
pick your first element in the
subsequence to be some element in that
ball.
Then so now the picture is that you just
look at that ball, right? Forget about
the other ball and everything else.
You now cover it by uh balls of radius a
quarter,
right? And you have that again that's
finally many cover
the this this ball intersected with a
finally many cover it
right and so one of them has infinitely
many elements
in this in in in this sort of
subsequence I consider and so you just
pick one element in that right that's
the next one
and now you Repeat this process, right?
And so you see that for these balls, but
remember that. So you're starting with
radius one, but you have to double
syncs, right? So the sequence of closed
sets, the initial closed set will have
radius two, right? And the next one
won't have radius a quarter, but it will
have radius two times a quarter. So a
half, right? And the next one will then
be a ball. It will have a different
center and it will have a radius of
half. And then the next one you see at
each stage when I do it like this then
it go down with a factor of four at each
stage. Right? So this here would be 1 /
8 and so on. Right? And so you see that
this sequence these are are these closed
balls. they are nested as they should be
and the rad goes to zero. Right? So this
means that there is an element that lies
in all of these and that is now the
limit because of the subsequence if you
are from here on and out it will be like
in that ball and from later on and out
it will be in the next ball. Right? So
that intersection of all of these balls
will be your limit. Yeah.
So, right. So, really what you're
looking at that this thing here
intersected with a
right. So, it's just that these balls
here. So, the intersection here that
these are the the closed sets.
These are the compacts. they are each of
them are non- empty and and they are the
uh the closed subsets of a right so
you're really arguing on these guys here
you see what I mean
I know I stated it for balls in the call
length right but if you just think about
it right the balls play no particular
role except for saying that the
intersection of all of them contained
just one point and that was because the
rad went to zero right the important
points were that the sets were closed
subsets, right? Because then there was
the lema was just all about closed
subset. It had nothing to do with and so
you see that
that these guys here are closed subsets
of a, right? And so yeah,
it
You mean why why I went to double the
ball? No.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So I So the reason I go to the
double ball is that I want to make sure
that things are nested, right? And and
if I I just did this procedure. Suppose
so again I take this ball here. This is
the first step. I have these balls of
radius one and I find one of them so
that there's infinite many in sequence.
Then I want to have something finer,
right? And so I go to
I chose because I think you didn't quite
have to do a quarter. You could actually
have gotten away with a half, but I
thought it wasn't as clear if I I did
it. So I did it with a quarter because
then I thought it was it looked more
obvious. So if you now take this ball
here and and as you say you always have
to intersect with a right uh but just to
make things compact but so I cover it
with balls of radius
a quarter right but some of these balls
part of it may lie outside this ball
here right because you know I couldn't
cover you see if I take a ball here I
can't cover it by finally many balls if
I insist you know just if it was like
you clean if I insist that the balls had
to be these smaller ball had to be
inside this ball then there wouldn't be
finite many so I have to kind of look at
balls that where some of these balls is
kind of outside the surface right but
now of course you know so that wouldn't
really work because it's not like this
ball here let alone the double of this
ball is not contained in this So that's
why I doubled that ball. Then everything
is comfortably contained to each other.
Any other questions?
>> Yeah.
>> Isn't there since they're all closed
ball or wait no these are open balls?
>> When I cover things they are open
because I have to have when I have a
compact set I have to cover it by open
subsets. But then once I'm looking at
the nested things, I have to go to the
closure because otherwise the lema in
the corner would not apply.
>> Okay.
>> And if hypothetically though, if they
were closed though, you would be able to
cover like E1 with a
>> and and and I and I'm just saying that
if the the open balls cover it, then of
course their closure also cover it
because the closure is a larger set,
>> right? But you know it wouldn't be
approic clear that you know with you
know like it's not like you know they're
closed set so that it's not working the
definition. Yeah.
>> I'm not sure if we prove that like up
there we have like you have a compact
subset
and take the intersection with subset.
Yeah we prove that it's closed. We prove
it's compact.
>> We prove that it's compact and I can
prove it again because it's very easy.
So uh so if you take um if you take a
if you have a
if you have
you have a metric space this here is
compact
and now you take a subset here of this
here and this here is is closed. It's a
closed subset of X.
Then you look at X take away B. You take
any copper of this together with this
they cover A. But then finally many but
this here have nothing in B. So actually
finally many of the other one cover.
Any other questions?
Okay. Okay. Great. Thanks.