Good morning. My name is Athanasius
Leios. I am a posttographer at the lab
of Bred Adrius at the University of
Toronto. H. Today I'm going to tell you
a few things about how we use signal
snaps images of live cells to study
dynamic cellular phenomena at a scale.
So in the lab, we use single cell
phenomics. If you're not familiar with
the term phenomics, you can understand
it if you view it through the lens of
other omics approaches. For example, in
protoomics, our goal is to measure as
many proteins as possible. In a
biological specimen, in metabolomics, to
measure as many metabolites as possible,
in phenomics, our goal is to measure as
many phenotypes as possible. And because
almost any measurable trait can be
categorized as a phenotype, our
measurements can be diverse. We can
measure um proteins, we can measure
information about metabolites, about
subsol morphology and so on. And we do
that in single cells. So a typical
single cell phenomics pipeline entails
the use of high throughput genetics for
the construction of a large number of
cell lines or strains and then we
subject these strains to high throughput
live cell fluoresence microscopy where
we typically collect data from either
rates of 10 or hundreds of millions of
life cells and then we use computational
approaches to analyze this data and
extract systems level insights about the
function of ukarotic cells. So we are
very interested in understanding the
process of the cell division cycle which
very simply put is the process by which
a ukarotic cell gives birth to another
cell and also we're interested in
understanding how intracellular
organization emerges in ukarotic cells.
So you can understand intracellular
organization as the size and shape of
the different structures inside the cell
as well as the relative position to each
other. And it's important to mention
here that it cellular organization
emerges in a new cell during the process
of the cell division cycle. So these two
things that we study are related to each
other.
So why should we care about the cell
division cycle? Here you see a schematic
representation of the cell division
cycle of padding which is the main model
organism that we use in the lab to study
this process. Initially we start with a
single cell. As cell cycle progresses uh
the daughter cell emerges and starts
becomes larger and larger. At this part
of the cell cycle DNA replication is
taking place. Then we have the nuclear
division and eventually we end up having
two cells a mother and the new daughter
cell. And this process is essential for
the reproduction of unicellular
organisms for the growth and development
of multisellular ones as well as for
tissue repair and regeneration in them
and also the deregulation of the cell
cycle is the cause of some highly
prevalent and really devastating
diseases.
So I mentioned at the very beginning of
my talk that we use snapshot images of
life cells to study dynamic cellular
processes such as the cell cycle and by
snapshot I mean that we do not take time
series measurements and a typically
snapshot image would look something like
that where we have cells from a cell
cycle asynchronous population which
means that cells are in different phase
of the cell cycle and then we apply some
computation to segment the cells and
then we apply further computation to
extract some temporal order uh from
these images to study cell cycle
specific uh phenomena. And the question
now would be why apply computation to
extract temporal information instead of
going directly doing time series
measurements and the simple answer is
that properly done time series uh life
fluoresence imaging experiments are very
difficult to perform at scale. So this
approach allows us to do our experiments
at a really really large scale and at
the same time we can avoid some common
pitfalls associated with time series
relation microscopy such as
phototoxicity and photo blitzing.
So you can imagine that um building a
new cell is quite a challenging task for
a cell. So this process entails the
production of the synthesis of a lot of
new protein and these new newly
synthesized proteins can be used for
example as building material for the new
cell and also for regulatory purposes
and these proteins not only to be
synthesized but also need to be
distributed at different parts of the
cell at the right time of the cell
cycle. So the process of the cell
division cycle uh entails quite a bit
involves quite a bit of what I like to
describe as cellular logistics which is
nothing else than changes in proton
abadance and localization and changes in
proto abadency of the cell cycle have
been previously mapped in detail but
until very recently um we we lacked
highly resolved protomy level view of
changes in protonression during the cell
cycle in any organism.
So in the next few slides I'm going to
tell you how we used our approach to
generate the first genome scale
annotation of protein localization
changes during the cell cycle of a cell.
So initially we started by constructing
a yeast strain that express some
fluorescent proteins and by these
fluorescent proteins if we we if we
would inspect these cells via
fluorescent microscopy this these
proteins would reveal the exact cell
cycle stage that the cell was when we
took the snapshot image and then we made
use of the so-called yeast GFP
collection. So this a collection of
approximately 4,000 yeast strains and in
each of these strains a different native
protein is fused to a green fluorescent
protein or a GFP and via this fusion
again if we inspect ourselves with
fluoresence microscopy we can measure
the abundance of the respective protein
a native protein but also identify its
localization in the cell and I have to
say that um this collections
approximately 4,000 yeast strains
captures approximately spans 75% um of
the yeast proto and nearly 100% of the
so-called visible yeast proto. So the
next step was to use systematic genetics
and specifically synthetic genetic array
technology to introduce this fluorescent
mark reporters in each of the strains in
the yeast GFP collection. And we ended
up constructing a new library of 4,000
yeast strains. And now in each of these
traits we could monitor both the
abadance and localization of a native
protein but also identify the exact cell
cycle stage that the cell was at. Then
we subjected um this library in high
throughput live cell fluoresence imaging
where we collected images from a bit
more than 20 million life cells. And I
mentioned earlier that when we take a
snapshot cells are in different cell
cycle stages. So we had to somehow
automate the process of extracting cell
cycle specific information from these
images. And for that reason we developed
a supervised neural network that we call
cyclet. And what cyclet does it examines
a single cell image and based on the
fluorescent reports that we introduced
in our cells. It can tell the exact cell
cycle states um where a cell was when it
took that image. And we found out that
um cycling performed with more than 93%
accuracy. It allows us to do what we
term as incilico cell cycle
synchronization.
So once we have grouped ourselves at
different cell cycle stages using cycle
net uh we use the second convolutional
neuronet network that we applied in our
images that was previously developed in
the lab and it's called diplo and what
diplo does u it can identify the
subcellular location of a protein in a
cell with resolution of 20 distinct
subscellular localization classes. So
the essence here is that by applying two
distinct convolutional nar networks in
single snapshot images of life cells we
could extract specal information from
them at the scale and we found out that
our pipeline uh worked pretty well and
I'll show you here an example. So here
you see some cells. These are actually
cells from just taken with microscopy.
Blue denotes the cytoplas. Uh pink
denotes the nucleus and green the
proteinoperist. In this case the
protonist is vi which is a
transcriptional repressor. And we know
that at the beginning of the cell cycle
we five is localized at the nucleus. As
the cell cycle progresses, it exits the
nucleus and it goes to the cytoplasm and
it stays out of the nucleus until almost
the end of the cell cycle when it goes
back into the nucleus again. So these
are the real dynamics of W5 and in the
heat map you will see what our pipeline
predicted. So x-axis here denotes cell
cycle progression and the y-axis denotes
the different subcellular localization
classes and you can see that our
pipeline predicts that we is inside and
when the color is yellow it means that
the protein is in this localization
class. when it's dark, it's not in
there. So, our pipeline predicts that W5
is in the nucleus at the beginning of
the cell cycle. As cell cycle
progresses, it translocates to the
cytoplasm. It stays there until the end
of the cell cycle where it goes back
again into the nucleus. So, which is
exactly what WI5 does in reality. And we
found out that our pipeline could also
accurately predict um uh other
well-known but way more complex cells
cycle specific changes in protein
localization. And by applying this
pipeline to the complete visible yeast
proton and also extracting protein
abundance measurements from the very
same cell images, we could generate a
highly resolved specal map of the proton
during the cell cycle. And because this
study has been um was recently
published, I will not focus more on the
insights that we generated. I would just
like to mention that all the data
generated in the study can be accessed
in a userfriendly way from the
cellvision.org/sellcycle org/sellcycle
which is a dedicated web tool that we
built for that purpose and the tool is
also directly searchable using human
names for colleagues that might not be
so familiar with yeast biology.
Now this study was supervised by Brad
Andrew and Charles Boon and was
performed collaboration with Ben Grace
and Doran Krauss and also other
colleagues at the University of Toronto,
Harvard, Alen University and University
of Minnesota.
And now I would like to take uh the last
few minutes of my talk to discuss how
can we take this further. So how can we
use now potentially snapshot images of
live cells to reconstruct the dynamics
of subcellular structures as a function
of the cell division cycle. I mentioned
at the beginning of the talk that we're
interested in understanding how
intracellular organization emergency
during the cell cycle. So how
dracellular organization changes as a
function of the cell cycle. And to map
that ideally we would like to have some
videos like that. So here you can see a
video of a yeast cell in red you see the
cytoplasm bright red you see the
nucleus. This cell goes to the cell
division cycle. We see that the daughter
cell emerges. I hope you can see that
well enough. The cell the nucleus
positioned up properly and then we have
nuclear division and the cell division
cycle ends and it starts all over. And
the nucleus is just one structure. We
want to see more structures. Ideally
would we would have more structures on
top of them. So here you see with green
on the top another structure we see
acting patches and specifically a
protein that's called sak six. What this
protein does is it stabilizes um and
orchestrates the acting cytokeleton to
support the morphogenesis of the
daughter cell and its expansion. Uh so
while such videos would be very useful
if we would have them for all structures
in the cell to map the dynamics of adel
organization. There is a secret about
them and the secret is that they are not
real or to be more precise they are
semi-real. They are based on what we
would describe possibly as biologically
informed virtual cells and I will tell
you how we build them. Again we start
with high throughput live cell flores
microscopy. We collect a pool of tens of
millions of live cells. And then we use
our neural network cycle net to group
these cells in different cell cycle
stages. And then we start for each video
by randomly selecting a cell from the
first cell cycle stage. And then we use
a score based on three image similarity
metrics to select the next uh real cell
in the pool from the next cell cycle
stage. And we do that iteratively until
we end up having uh selected images for
each of the cell cycle positions. each
of the cell cycle stages and we and then
we use a pre-trained deep learning model
film to add motion uh in between these
frames. So essentially by generating a
backbone of real cell images at
different cell cycle stages and using
generative AI we can construct
videos of ye cells going through the
cell division cycle which can also to
our surprise remarkably um uh
recapitulate uh dynamics of subscellular
structures uh with high I will say
biological um accuracy.
So we are now at the stage that we can
generate such videos for the complete
visible yeast proto. So for 4,000
different proteins and essentially uh
that spans all major structures in the
cell. And although we can see that the
videos um what the videos show bridge
very well with known biology, we're
still looking for some ways to
systematically evaluate their accuracy.
And um you can imagine that if we have
such videos of for every possible
structure in the cell, integrating all
this information would allow us to um
build a highdetailed map of the
biogenesis of a cell during the cell
cycle. And now we're actually looking
for ways to do that. So this project is
a project that we lead together with
professor Krishnan at the CS department
of the University of Toronto the vector
institute for for AI in collaboration
with graduate student and also with
contributions from Sophisan who will be
presenting a poster here tomorrow and
with that I would like to thank you I'll
be happy to take any questions.
[Applause]
Thank you. It's a fabulous talk. Um, so
last year, uh, Mattisman published a
high resolution protein interaction
protein protein interaction in yeast. So
have you classified your uh proteins to
see whether some of the proteins are
always collocicalized throughout the
cell cycle, some of them only uh
collocicalize for a fraction of time.
Yeah, awesome question because this will
allow us to identify transit
interactions during the cell cycle. We
are now one of the things that we're
doing is uh while we um we're analyzing
these videos, we're trying to integrate
more data sets into the analysis. one of
these data sets is the data set data set
you described with the protein protein
interactions in yeast and see what we
can learn from that I don't have an
answer of what we're going to learn yet
but it's possible that we'll be able to
identify you know some trans cell cycle
specific interactions through this
process
so Jean Philippe mentioned you know
interest in perturbations um have you
started looking at perturbations and the
effect on localization That's an awesome
question because we have generated a
data set in the lab that that consists
of a bit more than 100 millions of cells
and in this data set what we have done
uh we have uh surveyed approximately 17
distinct subscellular structures and we
had applied genome scale betterations in
there. So they are working on this on a
separate project but the idea is
eventually to merge these things. Yeah.
Right, let's thank the speaker again.
[Applause]