[Music]
From the MIT Energy Initiative, this is
What If It Works, looking at the energy
solutions for climate change. I'm Tara
Miller. And I'm Rob Stoner.
[Music]
And today, the tricky but vital task of
decarbonizing all sorts of hidden
processes, things you probably never
think about. So, not the flashy stuff
like cars and airplanes, which are the
polluters we worry a lot about and talk
a lot about, but there's all these
hidden things that are around us that
are the stuff that makes up our world,
that make up the food we eat, the
pharmaceuticals we make, the chemicals
and materials that are around us, the
materials we use to build our built
world, those are also extraordinarily
carbonintensive. They lead to huge
amount of emissions that arise from the
production of those materials. That's
Yogi Serendronath, a professor of
chemistry and chemical engineering at
MIT. And he says, take something like
steel, which is probably an integral
part of most offices that you've worked
in or most schools that you've attended.
We make enormous quantities of steel
around the world. We build literally
skyscrapers with steel. Every single
atom in that steel corresponds to a
certain number of molecules of CO2 that
were emitted to make that. So as
buildings get taller and people
increasingly move from the countryside
to the city, we have to figure out how
do we accommodate all these people and
get rid of or reduce the carbonintensive
processes used to make steel. But if
that seems like a big problem, consider
what you ate today. very likely it
benefited from a process called habber
bosch which is named after two German
chemists and for about the last century
it has been helping to create huge
amounts of fertilizer fertilizer that
makes farmland around the world much
more productive and that helps feed the
8 billion people on this planet if
you're chemically inclined here's yogi
giving a quick explanation of habber
bosch it's a process uh that's been
heavily optimize an industry. But the
crux of it is pretty simple at at least
at a at an atomistic level, which is
you're taking nitrogen from the air and
you're combining it with hydrogen that
you source from fossil fuels and you're
combining that nitrogen and hydrogen to
make ammonia. And ammonia is the key
component in most fertilizers. So even
in our bodies, there's food that we eat
that has a huge carbon footprint to it.
And and even in that that amount that
that value just making the ammonia we
use to grow all the food that we do in
the world that is already about a
percent a single percent of the entire
energy budget of the planet. So if we're
going to tackle climate change we have
to do something about the processes to
make steel and fertilizer and plastics
and concrete and on and on it goes.
Basically, it's all that stuff that
makes the world modern and which
generates something like a quarter of
our carbon dioxide emissions.
Industrialization emerged out of the
ready availability and the growth and
development of large ability to extract
fossil reserves of energy. So when we
were able to extract a large amount of
that fossil energy, it spawned a huge
paniply of industries underneath it that
used that energy storehouse, that sort
of historical geological storehouse of
energy and cashed out that energy to
make all the things that we have in the
stuff of our world, right? And to really
achieve deep decarbonization, we have to
not only do the decarbonization of, you
know, what turns on the lights, um, and
what heats our homes, uh, and what
powers our cars, but also all these
other industrial processes because they
make a huge fraction of the overall
carbon budget of the planet. But as you
can imagine, there are complications. So
go back to that haberbos process, which
provides us with so much fertilizer and
in turn provides us with so much food.
Yogi says, "We're awfully good at making
that fertilizer using fossil fuels. We
have over the better part of the last 60
or 80 years, really, really heavily
optimized how we make ammonia. So much
so that it caused many, many billions of
dollars, tens of billions in some cases,
to build a new ammonia plant. So much so
that the return on investment is
actually only after decades of sort of
time, right? Um, and so simply changing
that entire infrastructure to port in a
new chemical feed stock, new feed is is
not trivial. So scientists have a couple
of choices and neither of them is easy.
They can try to fiddle with existing
effective processes to make them more
fuel efficient or they can throw them
out and say, "Look, there is a better,
more sustainable way here. Let's do this
other thing." Here is Yogi in
conversation with me and Rob. But I'm
not presenting any of this to say that
it's it's daunting. It it's it's just to
say that that we need to be cognizant of
the fact that there's still a lot of new
science and new technology that needs to
be developed to to fully appreciate what
it means to for lack of a better term
transform a large portion of our
industrial sector, right? That's not
going to happen overnight. and and just
like our current industrial sector
really developed over many many decades
of development with fossil fuels as the
input, there's going to be years and
decades of development to be able to
transition that, right? Um but if you
look at for example how far we've come
in even just the primary generation of
renewable electricity in the context of
solar and wind, if you had looked a
decade earlier or 15 years earlier, that
too would have seemed daunting.
Right? And if you if you think about
where we are in just let's take just one
technology that's going to be really
really enabling for the future which is
just water electrolysis splitting water
into hydrogen and oxygen. And of course
there are huge and we work on a lot of
this in our own lab technological
advancements that need to be made to be
able to take those technologies to
scale. But that mountain we have to
climb there is kind of on the order of
the type of mountain we climbed over the
last 15 years when it came to the cost
of solar and the scale at which we've
built out solar. And that doesn't mean
there aren't still many challenges to
climb, but I am very optimistic that we
will wheel to get there. I have a
another question kind of for both of you
because it's kind of like a
science/policy question. You know, we're
talking about this mountain to climb and
you were saying like solar and wind,
they they really have climbed a lot of
it over the last 10 or 15 years. Is this
switch to um using chemical processes
that are greener that don't as emit as
much CO2? Is this mostly an issue of we
know the chemistry, we just don't have
the money or we don't really know the
chemistry, but people are willing to
cough up the money. You know what I
mean? Is this like a policy thing or
like a resource thing or is this like we
haven't figured it out in the lab yet?
We'll let you know. I think it comes
back to in part what Yogi was saying
before about this the scale of these
these industrial processes and the
degree of optimization that we've
brought to them and how replacing them
with an alternative that we can we can
imagine and maybe we can even practice
that has different economics maybe
inferior economics means we make food
more expensive or we make building
materials more expensive we change the
economics of other parts of the economy
and well there's disruption and and you
know that's I would say that there there
is absolutely you know huge
macroeconomic consequences to these
transitions right um but I would just
say on the technical side you know I
think that there's a a little bit of a a
view that things you do in the lab and
then when they get out of the lab with
enough resources they can then go to
scale and and in fact that's really not
how most technology development happens
um uh because what really happens is you
know what you're really doing in the
laboratory is sort of setting the
foundation
It it's sort of charting a map. The more
more fine grain that map is, the faster
you'll be able to get to scale, the more
in other words, the more you know of the
lay of the land of the problems you're
going to foresee at scale. And how you
might be able to avert those is going to
allow you to cross that hurdle faster.
That's the importance of basic research
even when there's this sort of push to
run run as fast as we can. Because if
you run run as fast as you can without a
really good map, you might find that
after you're a billion dollars in and
halfway towards your first pilot plant
that you might have a real problem that
you don't know how to solve. Right?
That's why it's really important to make
the foundation as solid as you can while
we are simultaneously trying to build
with what we already know. The scale of
these things though, the amount of money
and the level of risk also means that I
think it's very hard for the private
sector to get us there alone. People
aren't willing to put billions of
dollars into a process that may or may
not work. I mean, you want to you're
going to borrow that money from a bank.
You want it to work. Governments have to
be part of it.
I think that the points that both of you
have made bring up this kind of
interesting tension. I don't know how
either of you think about it. One is
we're in this race. We've got to very
quickly try to limit, you know, how much
the temperature is is raised worldwide.
But then on the other hand, as you say,
when you think about plastics or
fertilizer or steel production, those
things didn't happen in like a month or
a year. You know, for a long time,
people have been thinking, well, you
could make plastics a little bit better
this way. You know, this doesn't work so
well. Let's tweak it. And and
fertilizer, too. And and to a point
where the the production of these things
are so good and so rock solid that
people might be a little reluctant to be
like, well, here's a totally new
process. I know you've totally got this
down, but let's do something else. But
you have this tension of like, we have
got to move really fast, but the other
processes got good because what they had
on their side is time. I don't know how
you reconcile those two things, but they
seem to be in a little bit of tension
because we kind of don't have time.
You've hit the an important nail on the
head. It's it's it's a very very
critical piece, right? And and I would
say it's a little even more than just
time, and you hinted upon this. It's
it's it's just a a fear of the
unfamiliar. I I can just make it make
the statement even from a almost human
capital standpoint, right? A lot of the
processes we think about that are going
to be really important for these
decarbonization goals that use
electricity to drive some of these
processes, they revolve around this
field that we're part of that's known as
electrochemistry. Now if you think about
it that field actually there aren't many
people who know a lot about that who
populate the chemical industries the
Exxon Mobile the Dows the duons they're
not and the reason is historically when
you had a large amount of fossil fuels
that was your raw material you didn't
need to use the economic incentive what
was the economics to hire someone who
was trying to do a process that you
would only do if you wanted to
decarbonize the process Yet now many of
these companies are looking around and
saying, "Gee, we might want to do this,
but I don't know how to develop this
in-house cuz I don't even have the
people that have expertise in this
area." Electrochemistry has not always
been cool.
It's, you know, now you're at the
epicenter of chemistry. I I joke about
it. I mean, I think that that, you know,
in many ways, you know, the modern era,
and we actually already see this in, you
know, the the the cell phones we carry
around, right? In many respects, this
century will be the century in which
that field will play such a central role
in addressing some of these problems.
But it has not historically been the
place where we have trained a lot of our
best and brightest and encouraged our
best and brightest to go and use this as
an enabling science for them to impact
the world. And I shouldn't say because
it'll go to his head, but I mean Yogi
really truly is one of the young leaders
in this very very important resurgence
of electrochemistry. And it's our way
out of trouble in in so many areas. What
do I mean how do you think about this
tension of like moving fast versus what
Yogi was saying of like well there's
like we have to refine these things.
Well, we're not going to switch off what
we have now overnight and we may even
need to intervene in ways that will only
be temporary with with measures like
carbon capture and sequestration. you
know, just keep doing these these these
processes that produce CO2, but capture
it. We'll we'll we'll continue producing
this way and and putting it into the
ground. There's a limit in how far we
can go and hopefully new processes will
become viable and competitive and we'll
we'll get there and a transition will
occur. And again, government has to be
part of it. Big companies are watching.
They're they're watching, but they're
not doing yet. you know, they're just on
the edges of the playing field. And and
that other piece is another piece that
is important, right? Is that a lot of
this has a lot to do with the fact that
there is sunk capital, right? You know,
if you think about someone who is an
ammonia producer that makes fertilizer,
you know, they've already spent billions
of dollars of capital to build that
plant, right? Right. And they may not
have even gotten a return on investment
on that depending upon when that has
been constructed. So asking them to okay
you know completely re-engineer that
plan or completely scrap it and do
something completely different is a very
very big ask given that sort of stranded
capital that's already there in that
process right and I think that's another
place where government and policy can
play a strong role to better incentivize
how you deal with the the sort of
inherent um if you will like head start
the legacy processes have simply because
they've already have all that invested
amount of capital in them. And we've
talked about that before on the show,
right? Like I think you talked about,
you know, if a coal fired power plant's
being opened in China, yeah, somebody
has, let's say, like a mortgage or
whatever on that and it it they'll be
fine if it's open for 30 years, but the
government or somebody's going to have
to come in and say, "Let me help you
out." because otherwise you're just
really in huge heap of trouble if like
we only let you run this for seven years
and then we're like no we're shutting it
down sorry you can't use it anymore to
make money. So this introduces another
very important aspect of of the of the
transition and that is to what degree
can we reuse existing facilities
repurpose them. You know maybe replace
part of the harbor bosch process with an
electrified stage. uh or the other big
process in in in thermmochemistry, the
fisser tropes process, which is the
thing you use to make carbon monoxide
and hydrogen into hydrocarbons, sort of
fuels. Fuels. Exactly. Right. But I will
say one other key thing that's a piece
that's throughout all of this is that
you know if I go and take a fossil fuel
and I use it to power a plant whether
it's fish or tropes or it's you know
habbos to make ammonia one of the things
that actually makes it easier to run
those at large scale is that they can
run 24/7 at the exact same rate at the
exact same amount of product I'm making
which means that running them in that
stable consist consistent way is a
something that makes those processes
more efficient actually and that's how
they are right now right now the problem
though is wind and solar are
intermittent right that means that when
I use wind and solar to power whether
it's even making hydrogen or directly
electrifying these processes I need to
deal with the fact that I'm going to
maybe have
fluctuations in what my fuel is the fuel
content um or the power content. If I,
for example, have a habbos plant that
I'm going to feed in hydrogen, well, the
hydrogen may be produced to some
intermittent level. And then if I need
to use electricity to power the heat,
well, that also may be intermittent. If
I'm not going to source it from fossil
fuel combustion, which means I haven't
done anything. And you're not going to
run your Fisher Tropes plant on
batteries. Exactly. So, so that's that's
the thing. We're not going to make a
bank of batteries just to make our Herb
Bosch plant run its stable operation,
right? That's a whole another
infrastructure layer that has to be
added to it. So, so, so this is why I
think things that may seem like drop in
changes still require a lot of
innovation around them, right? Yeah. I
is anyone really doing that level of
innovation at the sort of integration
level reimagining not parts of processes
but the whole thing and and trying to
build green facilities that do these
things economically as as demonstrators
to my knowledge relatively little at
this stage right be like trying to make
fertilizer right is that what you're
saying well well or I imagine trying to
make fertilizer in a green way that can
operate on an intermittent supply of the
energy or the fuel because that's what
it really would need to be down the
line, right? That's a pretty heavy lift.
Yeah. Because one reason is if if you
have to stop making when the sun sets,
your your billion-dollar plant is
sitting there doing nothing for half of
the time. And and it's even more than
that. A lot of times the catalysts, the
things that make the balls go downhill
faster, they work the best when they
have really pure inputs, really pure
outputs, and they're running at the
exact same rate all the time. But is
there something in between a completely
green plant and the way that we do
things now? Is there nothing that's like
at 50%. You know, do you know what I
mean? like where maybe you've altered
the chemistry in a way, you know, you
don't have to put as much energy into
it, but maybe at night time it does run
on fossil fuels because like, okay, the
sun's not shining. So, well, I guess I'd
point out, you know, solar power and
wind aren't the only clean options at
our disposal. We have nuclear power.
That's true, too. Which produces both
electricity and heat. And I think so
stably and very stably, they want to run
24/7. I think one of the really
interesting developments in nuclear
power that still hasn't really come to
market but will is is the development of
small modular reactors that can be sized
for industrial campuses like refineries
or Fisher Tropes plants or Harabash
plants and produce exactly the right
amount of heat and exactly the right
amount of electricity for a partially
electrified process. And and I think
we're going to see some demonstrations
of these things over the next several
years as well. Again, in part thanks to
that bipartisan infrastructure law. What
is coming to my mind is that, you know,
it's so important for us to have a grid.
We've talked about the sun setting and
rising and the wind not blowing nuclear
power plants, but we have a grid and the
grid does provide a constant source of
electricity because we have a diversity
of loads and not all on at the same
time. And so in electrifying
industry, developing that grid and and
continuing to invest in a diversity of
supply and transmission lines that move
power around the country and keep the
grid stable with a growing percentage of
renewable power is extremely important.
So electrochemistry and grid development
go hand in hand here. And the other
thing I would say that's actually really
important to bear in mind is that if you
take all the primary electricity needs
we have right now, right? And you just
take okay, what's that total amount and
you ask how much electricity do we need
to generate? if we're also going to use
electricity rather than fossil fuels to
decarbonize all this industry because
that's a significant fraction of the
carbon budget. It means we're going to
have to generate a lot more electricity
from solar and wind which means that
it's not just a question of upgrading
our grid to be able to make it stable
with intermittent supply. It also needs
to have capacity expansion, right?
Because now I have a massive sink of
electricity which is my refinery which
before wasn't that much of a sink of
electricity power because it was using
fossil fuels to power right so you don't
want your habash plant and its desire to
run stably to cause intermittency in the
energy supply to customers right there.
That is another layer that really
impacts on how critical it is for our
ability to move electricity between
places very very efficiently, right? And
and and our current infrastructure is
not by any means ready to tolerate um
what we would need to to get to uh for
for industrial and it's worth thinking
about what that infrastructure looks
like. I mean, we're talking about
industrial process electrification here,
but at the same time, we're electrifying
cars. We're trying to electrify the
heating of our homes. We're building
data centers all over the place that are
consuming enormous amounts of
electricities. In fact, they're
consuming pretty much all of the new
renewable electricity. For a while, we'd
kind of seen, you know, the electricity
demand level off and then AI came along
and like all bets were off and it's
going to get worse and we're going to
produce hydrogen from the grid. It's
huge. I can't I just heard like when you
do a query for like ChachiPT, how much
electricity use, but it's
enor Google searches. It's just the
scale is huge and when you think about
more and more people using that kind of
stuff all the time, it's it's a lot. So,
I won't say you can't get there using
just solar and wind, but you'll really
notice the solar and wind if we if we're
going to increase capacity to that
degree. It will be everywhere. And and
this is why, you know, and it's it's a
it's a complex analysis there. There are
certain chemical manufacturers or
industrial sectors that may though there
are challenges even with this have more
dedicated off-grid supplies. In other
words, like if I build a Habra Bosch
plant of the future, it may make sense
for me to have colllocated solar and
wind. I build that's not competing with
the grid, but is providing me dedicated
power for what I need, but that requires
coordinated action to be able to make a
grid that is responsive to those future
needs. So in a world where there's a lot
of decarbonization pressure on
industries, but there isn't a grid that
allows for that, in a weird way, we're
making the less efficient option to take
these resources off of the grid and make
them be sort of self-serving entities,
right? Um but that a little speaks to
how policy and and you know, I think
some um uh intentional thought about
these things can really really make a
big impact on on easing this transition.
And again, a role for government, a huge
role for government, really, really
important because it's coordination. All
these things because they couple so many
sectors, each individual sector making
decisions on their own will simply not
be able to create the most efficient
future of a decarbonized. And every time
we make any one of those decisions
that's not as efficient as it could be,
that means we need to generate even more
renewable electricity to meet that
inefficiency.
[Music]
Let's talk about what the future looks
like here. Um, are there countries, are
there companies, are there venture c I
mean, you know, where is the leadership
coming from? Where is this going to
happen first? Wow, that's a great
question. I you know when I think about
the answer to that question I think of
countries that don't have the luxury of
lowcost natural gas that we have in this
country and in some other parts of the
world that make it really really hard to
displace these fossil consuming
industrial
processes. So think about Japan. Japan
doesn't have any petroleum to speak of.
It doesn't have a very vibrant nuclear
sector anymore thanks to Fukushima.
um very very few options and real
pressure to innovate in order to
continue to support its industrial
sector. I think we'll see things there
start to happen. I think in Germany
where there's a very strong green
movement again no nuclear power or
declining nuclear power but a very very
strong industrial base as well
particularly chemicals. There's huge
pressure to see innovation that that
will bring these processes online first,
I think. And as I think it's just
reflecting on the names of the guys who
invented the processes we've been
talking about, those are all Germans.
Yeah. Aubber and Bosch and Fisher and
motivated, you know, actually for the
need to generate those things due to war
efforts, you know, in in the early 20th
century, right? That's what really
motivated those similar issues of of
stranded capacity, right? But for
different reasons, geopolitical reasons.
Now different reasons are motivating
that. But but I I agree that I think
that the places where you will see this
are is where you have one an appetite
political or otherwise appetite for
making these investments, right? Um and
also a really need because there isn't a
readily available lowcost alternative,
right? You think about I mean some of
the pilots have been done in this area
not necessarily in the industrial space
but you think about a place like Hawaii
right you know just the the cost of
transporting something there means that
there are cases where on-site generation
production of certain things makes a lot
of sense right um uh but but you know
and Japan's a great example where you
know local resources could be tapped to
be able to generate some of these things
and that landscape is going to be
complicated and it's going to be also
very sector dependent right an example
you could think of even in a different
way right is you you have uh mining
operations in in remote locations of
Australia, right? And would you rather
bring in a fuel there or have a
dedicated power plant that allows you in
a better way to decarbonize that mining
operation? Right? There are many
examples that will be the sort of uh
beach head places where these things
probably will get demonstrated. I think
they will get demonstrated and I I mean
this in a very sincere way as they must
with pretty legacy technology. The
technologies we're working on in our lab
aren't going to be the ones that are de
obviously are not going to be the ones
demonstrated today or next week or next
year, right? The ones that are going to
be demonstrated in that short time span
are the things that we already optimized
a lot, you know, 20 years ago or 30
years ago or 50 years ago, right? But
the reason we work on that basic science
is we would like to give new
options when we're 10 or 15 years out
that allow us to think about when we
need to go to even larger scales. Do we
have another a larger pallet of options
that give us the better ability to work
with intermittent supply, the better
ability to make things at higher
efficiency, the better ability to deal
with intermittent operation of
industrial processes? Those are those
are why we kind of work on those basic
science to give new options for the
future. So we're going to have, you
know, opportunities in in different
countries that are have their own
motivations, have different natural
resources, have different financial
resources,
and things are happening. Things are
happening in Europe where governments
and the the you know, the the EU is
funding a lot of demonstration work. The
Japanese are working very hard on
things, but there's there's going to
have to be shared learning. So I think
there's a real opportunity here for
scientific exchange and technical
exchange that goes beyond just leaving
it to companies to promulgate new good
ideas. We we really need international
cooperation on technology. And there's a
another practical reason for that as
well. If we're talking about making
fuels, for
example, they're going to go into things
like ships and airplanes. You can't have
a different fuel in Europe than you have
in the United States or South Africa.
you got your you're back to your Betamax
VHS problem, right? And and you know
that that means that there has to be
coordination on policy at a very high
level to make all of this stuff work
ultimately. and and the the piece of
fuels is actually a really important
piece. Um because you know what you're
going to actually have in the future is
you know you may have certain countries
because of their renewable energy base
and the type of industrial sectors they
have that might be really good
candidates to produce certain renewable
fuels like ammonia or electricity
derived hydrocarbons for example, right?
And those may not be the historical
places where we generated those. Right?
which means that even like the transport
of fuels around the world is going to
have to change. That means there's going
to be geopolitical consequences to that
for sure, right? Um and then that also
means there needs to be coupling between
how you best leverage the fuel where it
may be used with how it's generated.
Like an example is you may for example
have a really high wind or solar
resource that you're going to use to
make ammonia in in in let's take an
example in Brazil and you transport that
to Europe where you're going to cash out
that ammonia into hydrogen to power an
industrial sector. So then there has to
be coupling between those two. Um and
and actually, you know, some of the
major energy trading companies have
actually begun to open desks that trade
ammonia because they recognize in the
future there are going to be new energy
vectors that are going to be used around
the world and that those are going to be
traded like commodities just like we
trade commodities of fossil fuels right
now. So give me your best guess given
like the science trends now, the policy
trends. When are we going to have plants
that produce steel in a better way that
produce uh fertilizer in the ways that
like the kind of stuff that has come out
of your lab? Is that is this a 10 year
away thing? Is this a Well, I think you
know some of these some of these plants
exist now. I mean there there are
demonstrations. There's a there's a
green ammonia plant that was built in
the Sinai, but it's more demo couple
versus like big scale. Yeah, it is. And
they're looking at an opportunity.
there's a lot of sun uh that they can
use and and there's conventional
generation and a reasonable grid.
There's a big market for ammonia in
Europe that they can easily access with
short ship trips and so on. So, you
know, you get facilities like that
starting to pop up and knowledge being
acquired. There is some direct reduction
of iron ore that things are starting to
happen and the question is how fast can
the pace be? There are demonstrations of
those like I said you know these
developments when they get to scale they
proceed through kind of this iterative
process right I think the question is
not so
much because we already have things at
at at reasonable scales I I think that
those are going to mature but at the
same time they're going to be new things
that will supplant them right um and
those will start to come online as we
progress at the end of this decade and
into into the next one right and that
process will continually
get to a point where we reach a level of
decarbonization, a high level of
decarbonization in these industrial
sectors that meets all these other
criteria. And that's a, you know, I
think what's fascinating about it and
maybe a little unpredictable about it is
that all the pieces are each moving. The
ground is moving in every way around us,
right? There's changes to the grid,
there's changes to policy, there's also
changes to feed stock inputs, there's
changes to the regulatory landscape. And
that's also coupled with new
developments in the technology and new
science that's that's coming up, right?
You know, in a way, the fact that
everything is moving makes me optimistic
cuz if only one was and the others
weren't, then I would say we should be
really worried cuz we need them to all
move together. But the fact that they're
all moving together makes me think that
this is something that is very tractable
time scale that's going to matter for
climate. But it's going to only matter
if we are cognizant of aware of and we
have both the political will and and new
uh of our best and brightest working on
the basic science and technical
challenges to address these problems but
they're tractable. I mean I haven't
heard you say once in the course of this
discussion we don't know how to do that
or there's no way to do that or can't be
done. It's it's a question of finding
the ways and that's why I feel
optimistic as well.
Yogi Sarendra, professor of chemistry at
MIT. Thanks for being here. Thank you so
much.
[Music]
What if it works is a production of the
MIT Energy Initiative. If you like the
show, please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen. And remember to
subscribe on Apple Podcast, Spotify, or
wherever you get your
podcasts. You can find an archive of
every episode, all of our show notes,
and a lot more at energy.
mit.edu/mpodcast. And you can learn more
about the work of the energy initiative
and the energy transition at
energy.mmit.edu. Our original podcast
artwork is by Zitler Design. Special
thanks to all the people at Mighty and
MIT who make this show possible. I'm
Cara Miller and I'm Rob Zer. Thanks for
listening.