It would be really awesome if we could
regrow limbs just like lizards do, but
we can't. The closest we can get is kind
of sort of regenerating our livers. So,
we have these things called stem cells
which can morph or differentiate into
say a liver cell or a blood cell. When a
lizard's tail falls off, a bunch of pur
potent stem cells rush to the stump and
will differentiate into skin cells,
muscle cells or bone cells. It would
take a lot more time and energy for one
of us to regrow a whole arm. But our
livers are a little bit different. Even
if you lost 75% of your liver, the
remaining liver cells could grow and
divide and reform a mass of liver
tissue. The problem is that liver cells
don't survive long enough outside the
body to grow into enough tissue to
transplant. Scientists and MIT's lab for
multiscale regenerative technologies are
trying to solve this problem. So, for
now, our reptile friends have oneuped
us, but we're catching up. For more MIT
moments from MIT Open Learning, like,
subscribe, or