Associative learning is a powerful
example of kind of learning and the best
understood form of associative learning
is classical conditioning sometimes
called Pavlovian conditioning. Pavlov
was awarded the Nobel Prize in
physiology in 1904 for discoveries about
the digestive system which he studied in
dogs. Pavlov noticed that the salivation
could be triggered not only by the food
in the dog's mouth but also by other
stimula that were associated with the
food. In this case, the unconditioned
stimulus is the food. The unconditioned
response is the salivation in the
[music] dog. A neutral meaningless
stimulus is presented just before the
food. The tone then becomes the
conditioned stimulus. But if a tone is
presented multiple times just before the
food is given, the dog salivates to the
tone even before the food arrives.
Indeed, the dog salivates to the tone by
itself, having learned by classical
conditioning the association between the
tone and the food. This is now the
conditioned response.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.