A lot of people have a hard time seeing
[music] that climate change is affecting
our day-to-day lives. They see it as
something distant. But the reality that
climate change is already here. I want
everybody to close their eyes. Imagine
that we're all on the same team and the
game is on the line. We're not just
playing for ourselves. We're playing for
the next generation. Open your eyes.
Who is willing to do what it takes to
win? This is the city of champions,
right?
So I think we should all take [music]
responsibility and carry a championship
mindset in our environment starts with
us and we can start a global movement in
the future. Let's stand together united
in our purpose with unwavering [music]
commitment. The time to act is now.
Thank you.
[applause]
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.
>> [applause]