Co um so we are um Emma Enterprise
machine assistant company based out of
uh Silicon Valley uh I am a Sloan 06 MBA
um and uh have spent last couple of
decades actually in executive roles at
at coinbase and and Google and other
places the company is founded by a bunch
of exg googlers and the problem we are
trying to solve is how do we improve
productivity in every Enterprise by
using agenti AI we started working on
agenti AI in 2023 even before the ward
was Quin right after like chat GPT came
out like late 22 we started tinkering
with it and we have built some of the
most complex agentic AI design patterns
today and we call them AI employees we
have Fortune many Fortune 500 customers
as you can see on the on the on on this
slide and uh funded by Axel uh we have
raised $62 million to in total from
various investors and very well
capitalized today I'll play a quick
video to give you an overview of of what
the product is what would your
organization accomplish if you could 10x
the productivity dramatically accelerate
Innovation disrupt your industry and
deliver exceptional customer experiences
at scale hi I'm Emma your Universal AI
employee here to help you harness the
power of a gentic AI and unlock
exponential
growth you can hire me in different
roles across your
Enterprise from standard roles such as
sales support data and finance to
specialized ones deep into your
industry's workflows I can onboard
myself and learn from your best
employees I have a vast library of AI
agents at my disposal each helping the
excel at specific skills from writing
Illustrated docs to validating complex
rules writing code and even taking
actions across
tools I use my generative workflow
engine to instantly create agentic
workflows that help me meet my
goals just give instructions like
talking to a human and I will
orchestrate multiple agents to work
together in a simple workflow creating
an agentic mesh that will act as your
new AI
employee my agents are powered by MF
Fusion a proprietary model that
integrates results from the best public
and private language models to provide
unparalleled accuracy at the lowest
cost I can easily on board any new tool
or knowledge base you have and can
connect to hundreds of pre-integrated
apps in seconds and I have been
certified in leading international
compliance standards and keep your data
secure with robust governance pii
masking and audit
logs I've emerged as the top performing
employee in every role I've been hiring
in don't just imagine what is possible
with 10x more productivity unlock your
organization's potential with Emma today
I can't wait to see what we can
accomplish
together so what we have built is this
pre-built AI employees that that work in
different functions in in an Enterprise
uh you just connect them to the right
tools right applications and databases
and data sources and and they quickly
learn based on Enterprise data uh and
they can based on what humans have done
in that role they learn from humans as
well and start mimicking humans in those
roles if we don't have a pre-built
employee we can just build one very very
quickly using our generative workflow
engine which is just a drag and drop and
actually conversationally kind of
bringing multiple agents together to um
to uh accomplish a complex task we have
a employees today in in three main areas
sales and marketing automation customer
support and HR or employee experience
I'm going to skip through this um I have
a quick uh customer uh testimony I think
that was one of the things that was
asked I'll just play this video real
quick this is a one of the largest uh
b2c lending companies in the world and
they um invited us to help them with
their customer
support just a few seconds uh s of that
one
sorry yep um I'm out of time should I
stop no just tell us the the benefits of
that um partnership and then what your
ask
is U sure I I'll I'll I can skip this
that's not it um my ask is uh connect
connect us to um more companies
Enterprises forun 2000
specifically uh we sell to kind of four
archetypes Chief a officers or CTO or
chief digital officer is the primary one
and then there is a secondary one which
is some functional leads like
chro cro or chief customer of experience
officer or VP of customer
support um yeah that's that's basically
it okay thank you so much there's a lot
more to show um which is exciting thank
you um again reminding everyone to
please post your questions to the
startups on the Q&A tab at the bottom of
your screen and uh indicate which
startup it's for maybe you're coming up
with questions now even if it's later
and you can also engage with the ones
who already presented uh via the chat um
suit so let me know what a little more
about your Global Focus you also are
able to use different languages so tell
us a little more about
that um sorry I missed the question um
you have a a Global Focus as far as
Partnerships and also you're able to use
different languages so tell us more
about that yeah we have customers today
in three continents in Asia uh Europe
and in the US so we are capable of
handling um almost all top languages in
the world um and also capable of um
handling data localization that's
another actually issue in in in AI today
uh we we are fully also um uh compliant
with all the international standards
like sock 2 type 1 type 2 gdpr Hippa ISO
42,1 27,1 and so on okay great thank you
so much thank you