thank you all for inviting me here today
I'm excited to talk about the company so
I'm Joyce Wang CEO and co-founder of
onlogic during my PhD in Neuroscience
here at MIT I encountered many technical
hurdles that prevented me from moving as
quickly as I wanted to in my research um
and these hurdles are actually common
throughout biotech and
Pharma um if you're not familiar with
this space essentially one of the most
challenging things you can do in the
discovery phase of research is to choose
which experiments to run right now to
Der risk your leads um the problem is
biology is hard so you wait for cells to
incubate or for animals to be born and
when every experiment takes a quarter to
run you have six tries to get it right
before your program is
cut even when your early experiments
succeed as program matures research
teams run into friction scaling up
especially around data management and
Analysis the practices that benefited
fast exploratory work in the early phase
are not built to handle the large
volumes of complex data that uh happen
further down the line and this is where
teams run into the most
problems for a bench scientist this
looks like relying more on the
bioinformatics team to analyze their
growing data backlog and longer riskier
experiment
timelines for a computational researcher
this looks like putting out urgent
one-off analysis fires instead of
developing a robust pipeline to track
and record data issues in the long run
and for a team leader this looks like
spending more time finding data than
leveraging it to guide the
program being unable to scale the
program could mean never getting to the
clinic because you couldn't show enough
proof in
time at onlogic we formalize data struct
infrastructure so that our customers can
make sense of their
science with our platform computational
researchers can develop novel analyses
in a browser based IDE and then quickly
cast their code into a reusable workflow
that runs on the cloud this frees them
up to focus on analyzing data for others
to build
on bench scientists can then use these
workflows with the click of a button no
more waiting on others for new code for
every new experiment they can now look
at the results directly and determine
how successful their experiment
was and by gathering the important
updates from these different data
sources it allows leadership to quickly
get the key insights from each
experiment all in one place now they
what they need to course correct the
company and make sure that those six
tries
count with these three functions onlogic
allows scientists to focus on the
science by automating the technical
infrastructure that is so often a hurdle
rather than a benefit and most
importantly our platform meets
researchers where they are it's almost
everything agnostic which means no
requirement for specific programming
language compute backend or
orchestration system it runs analyses
deploys code and tracks data right where
people need
it together these functions provide
flexibility at every stage of research
one of our users a cell biology
researcher ad of Emory was starting a
new experiment um she was facing a
massive time sync trying to troubleshoot
both her protocol and her analysis at
the same time with onic Alicia was able
to use a field standard analysis
pipeline all on her browser without
having to write any code running her
data through the platform right after
every experiment she estimates that onic
saves her 10 to 20 hours per month
our dedication to serving growing teams
is how we've chosen to Define our beach
Head Market we're working with assay
development teams in Pharma C and early
stage biotech companies to make sure
that they're scaling up their processes
well from the
beginning we know that our platform can
serve this Market because it is built by
and for scientists with software
engineering best practices from Google
and
Cisco today we're looking for design
Partners in Pharma and biotech we work
with R&D teams of around 20 to 50 people
and would love to start a PC with your
group thanks for your time thank you
Joyce right um let me start by asking
what is the biggest problem that you are
encountering as as companies um look
into this yeah so as we all know um it's
kind of a hard time right now in biotech
and Pharma um as I'm sure we're all
familiar um people are sort of
tightening their belts and hoping that
the existing resources that they've
already invested in can yield the
returns that they expected um and and so
we basically help you make the most out
of your resources by um supercharging
the scientists that work already with
them so um we take the scientific data
that you already have and we track all
of it for you we automatically Trace
Providence and help you search through
the metadata for you to be able to find
the results um out of the things that
you already
have thank
you and what kinds of contacts in large
biofarma um would be helpful at this
point to connect with and how do you
adapt to like
custom um cases yeah so uh I'll answer
the first one first um we're mostly
focused on the Discovery phase of
research so this is uh before you go
into the clinic so pre-clinical work in
general um we tend to work best with
companies that are developing new assays
in Pharma companies so not necessarily
focus on a specific asset but uh trying
to make a method that advances the
capability of the entire company um if
that makes sense um and I'm happy to
talk more uh during the breakout rooms
if you have more questions um uh sorry
your second question was about um just
how you adapt to uh custom cases if you
can give an example so that's kind of
our biggest um strong suit our strongest
suit um yeah so as I said before um we
have uh in the example that I gave with
one of our customers um we gave her a
pretty field standard analysis tool um
but that's not the only thing that we do
we're not just providing a tool boox of
existing code um our specialty is
working with custom data so any
programming language that you write in
anybody in your team who knows how to
code we basically work uh with them on
our platform so that they can
automatically package that into
something that is reproducible and easy
to use by everybody else so most of our
customers write their custom code on
onto logic and can easily share them
with everybody in the organization
immediately thank you Joyce