Hello, everybody.
We're going to start the
health care session now.
Thanks so much for being here.
We have a really exciting
session for you today.
My name is Jon Gruber.
I'm the chairman of the
Economics Department
here at MIT.
And my work is in health care
economics and health care
policy.
We also have speaking
Kate Kellogg, who's
the David J McGrath junior
professor of Management
and Innovation and a professor
of Business Administration
at the MIT Sloan School.
Kate's work is helping knowledge
workers and organizations
develop and implement
narrow AI and generative
AI solutions, on-the-ground
and everyday work
to improve decision-making,
collaboration, and learning.
We have Joe Doyle,
who's the Erwin H Schell
Professor of Management
and applied econometrics
at MIT Sloan School as
well as the co-chair
of the health sector
at the JPAL Action Lab
and co-principal investigator
of the NBER Roybal
Center for Behavioral
Change and Health.
Through all these
many initiatives,
Joe partners with large health
care providers and payers
to conduct randomized controlled
trials aimed at improving
health care delivery.
And then finally, we
have Michael Yaffe,
who's the director of the MIT
Center for Precision Cancer
Medicine, the David H
Coke professor in science,
professor of the MIT departments
of Biological Engineering
and Biology, intramural
faculty at the Koch Institute,
and also, a real doctor.
So if any of you are
having pains or whatever,
you can ask him
during the session.
His laboratory studies how
signaling cancer cells focusing
on cell stress, DNA
damage, inflammation
control the response of tumors
to conventional and novel types
of cancer treatment.
And he's particularly
interested in building
the bridge between
basic biological science
and clinical treatments
for human disease.
So great panel here today--
we're just going to talk
for about 10 minutes
and then hopefully have a
little time for Q&A at the end,
depending on how much
we abuse our privileges.
So I will go first.
And I'm going to talk--
if you can put my
slides up, I'm going
to talk today about risk
sharing in the life sciences.
So we're just waiting,
I think, for my slides.
Anyway, so there we go.
Insurance, paying for health
insurance in the life sciences,
great.
So let me see.
I think if I go like this,
it'll go to the-- no,
that's the pointer.
If I go like that--
how do I get to the next one?
How about that?
There you go.
So today, I'm going to
focus on risk sharing.
This is a term
economists use glibly.
But let me be clear
on what I mean,
which is that medical risks
are the greatest risk facing
most Americans.
They're difficult to
prepare for in that they're
large and unexpected.
So what do we do as society,
as developed societies
all around the world?
We spread that risk
through insurance.
How does insurance work?
We prepay a fixed
amount in return
for coverage of our medical
costs when we need care.
OK, so that's how we share the
risk of getting hit by a car
or having a heart attack
or developing cancer.
We prepay now.
And then later, those
costs are covered.
Now, in that world,
we have to recognize
that life science innovation
is incredibly expensive.
New innovations in life sciences
are expensive, becoming more so.
The estimates suggest that the
cost of developing a new drug
is $2 billion.
That results in high prices to
the end users of those drugs.
Those high prices are what
we need insurance for.
And we need it because we are
making miraculous steps in life
sciences innovation every day.
We can talk about a moderately
expensive miracle, which
is GLP-1s, these
new drugs, which
can be used to control weight
and help with diabetes,
have been shown in large
trials to be massively
successful at curbing weight
and increasingly shown impacts
on curbing other behaviors.
And that's moderately expensive.
That's $15,000 a year.
Then, we have incredibly
expensive miracles,
which is cell and
gene therapies, which
are coming online, which are
literally curing the incurable.
These are diseases which through
loss of a genetic lottery
was killing people.
We can now literally
cure them and let
people who would have died
at age two live to old age.
They're miraculous.
They're unbelievably expensive.
A typical cell and gene therapy
costs millions of dollars.
So you talk about something
you need insurance for.
You need insurance against
losing a genetic lottery
and having to face a
$2 million expense.
But the US insurance
system has key holes.
The first hole is
discrimination.
So before the Affordable
Care Act was passed in 2010,
it was completely
legal in the US
to discriminate against those
who were sick in your insurance
decisions.
You could deny
insurance coverage
to someone who was sick.
You could charge a sick
person or a woman more
for health insurance
than you'd charge
a healthy person or a man.
Or you could exclude those
with pre-existing conditions
from coverage.
That ended with the
Affordable Care Act.
We banned discrimination
in insurance.
Now, insurers have to
charge men and women
and the sick and healthy the
same price for health insurance.
This is critical in a
world where we increasingly
predict risk.
Increasingly, I can tell
who's going to be sick
before they walk in my door.
What that means is any
profit-maximizing insurer
is going to want
to avoid the sick.
So in a world where we know how
sick people are going to be,
it's critical that we don't
allow insurers to discriminate.
Now, the ACA solved
this problem.
It seems safe for now.
But there are still
opponents of this protection
now in power in the government.
And that's something
we need to monitor.
I think the ACA is pretty safe.
But this would be a critical
loss for risk protection
if this went away.
There's also the
uninsured, however.
About half of 25 million
Americans lack insurance.
About 25 million Americans,
sorry, lack insurance.
This was cut in about
half by the ACA.
But it could rise significantly.
There are policy decisions
that matter here.
The number of uninsured
covered by the ACA
went down by about four
million under the first Trump
administration, rose
by about 5 million
under the Biden
administration, and is
anticipated to fall again.
Who are these remaining insured?
Many of them are actually
eligible for free insurance
today if we could just
automatically enroll them.
Some are young
invincibles, people
who feel that they could just--
they don't need insurance
because they're healthy.
And some are
undocumented immigrants,
which is by itself a
political minefield.
So it's going to be challenging
to get these remaining
uninsured.
But it's an important goal if
we want to once again protect
against medical risk.
There's also the fact that
we have a multi-payer system.
Individuals move across
different payers.
So if I'm an insurer, and I
have a decision about investing
in preventive care for you,
but by the time you're sick,
you'll be with a
different insurer,
I don't want to make
that investment.
Why should I pay that $2
million for a cell and gene
therapy that's
mostly going to save
money for some other
insurer down the line.
So insurers don't want
to provide investments
because people might leave
and go to other insurers.
On top of that,
insurers are worried
about these really
expensive risks,
these things like
cell and gene therapy
that are incredibly expensive.
So what do they do?
Insurers get insured.
They buy reinsurance.
There's a contract
that says, look,
you're insuring everyone at MIT,
but if someone has costs above
$50,000, we'll pick
up the difference.
They buy it from big companies
that offer that reinsurance.
The problem I
realized recently is
the ACA did not fix
the reinsurance market.
It's completely legal
to discriminate.
So MIT could go to
a reinsurer and say,
look, we're going to cover
the cell and gene therapy.
And the reinsurer can say, nope,
I'm not going to reinsure that.
You're on your own for that.
So there's still
holes in the system
even for those insured
we need to address.
So let's do an
important case study.
We're going to talk about
innovation a lot today.
Let's talk about one of
the most innovative areas
in medical care, which is
cell and gene therapies.
The adoption has
actually been slow.
There are some new cell and
gene therapies being introduced.
And the adoption has been
slow despite the fact
that they're literally
miraculous and life-saving.
Why is that?
Well, insurers are very
wary of paying for them.
First of all, as
I said, they have
to make a major investment
in paying for them,
but they might not get
the lifetime benefits
of people staying on the plan.
Second of all, these
drugs are miraculous,
but the trials are so
far very short-term.
We don't know if
five years from now,
they're going to stop working.
And insurers are like, I
could pay all this money,
and five years from now, it
could wear out and stop working.
And so as a result, I'm wary
of making that investment.
And finally, reinsurers won't
cover these drugs in many cases.
So insurers have
been slow to adopt.
When they do adopt,
they try very
hard to limit who can get
these new innovations.
The problem is people can't
afford them without insurance,
and life-saving opportunities
are being missed.
And this can in turn feed back
to investment in these new areas
because people are reluctant
to invest in cell and gene
therapies because they're
afraid they won't be covered.
So what do we do?
Well, single-payer
health care is not
walking through
the door in the US.
It's too politically
difficult. But we do actually
have single-payer
health care in the US.
People don't realize it.
We actually have
single-payer health care
in the US for a particular
disease, renal failure.
For those with
renal failure, they
are almost called the end-stage
renal disease program.
And it's a universal
government-provided single-payer
insurance.
Why couldn't we do this
for other diseases,
say genetic abnormalities?
Why couldn't we say for those
born with genetic abnormalities,
they will be on a
government-funded single-payer
insurance system?
That would solve
all these problems.
And basically, as
a society, we'd
all pay a little
higher taxes because we
won the genetic lottery
to support those
who lost the genetic lottery.
It's a perfect case for
government intervention
where we as a society
share the risk.
Alternatively, if
that's not feasible,
we can think about developing
private sector models
to spread the cost with things
like value-based reimbursement
that allow us to have
the manufacturers share
the risk of drugs not working
and subscription models that
put the risk on manufacturers.
These are things that
I'm working on, trying
to see if we can push
these in the private sector
in the absence of a government
solution to this problem.
Now, one of the last
thing I'll talk about
is what about pricing.
These treatments
are very expensive.
You might say, well,
why do they have to be?
Why don't we just tell
these manufacturers
they can't charge much?
And the answer is because
innovation won't happen.
Innovation does respond
to financial incentives.
So the traditional
approach to dealing
with this around the world is
we measure something called
comparative effectiveness.
All around the world they have
organizations which say, look,
if a drug only delivers
this much of health value,
we'll only pay this much for it.
The US is the only country
that doesn't do that.
As a result, we pay dramatically
more for our medical treatments
than anywhere else in the world.
The typical medical
treatment costs about twice
in the US for innovative
treatments as it does in Europe.
So that's something we
could do in a step that
was started with the
Inflation Reduction Act.
The problem is for these
incredibly expensive new drugs,
they're actually worth the
price they're charging.
So they're charging $2 million.
And you know?
They're delivering $2
million of benefit.
So dealing with pricing
in this new sector
is going to be much
more challenging.
And we're going to need to
think about other mechanisms
to deal with that.
So finally, I guess the
last thing I want to say
is, how do we finance
this innovation?
This is another area
economists are thinking about,
which is basically we
need to not only cover
these things for insurance
but actually promote
more R&D funding of
these valuable things.
This is discussed in my
book, Jump-Starting America,
where we talk about the role
of public funding of research
and development, which
actually at its peak
amounted to 2% of US GDP
and is now only 0.5% today.
This funding complements private
R&D. It promotes private R&D
and has huge economic returns.
Yet, as I said, investments
have been falling.
So the bottom line is we need
to think about creative solution
to get more innovative
funding in this area
and to help bear or share
the risks that people face
with expensive new treatments.
I'll stop there.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
I am delighted to be here today
to talk to you about my research
on narrow and generative AI.
And both of these forms
of AI have great potential
to transform health care.
Here's an example of narrow AI.
Some of my coauthors at the Duke
Institute for Health Innovation
worked with hospital doctors to
develop a highly accurate tool
using machine
learning which detects
unexpected patterns in patients
in the ER to predict sepsis.
And sepsis is a life-threatening
illness infection
where you need to
predict it quickly
in order to treat it quickly.
Here's a generative
AI example developed
by some of my coauthors at
NYU Langone Health where
they use GPT-4 to read
clinical notes of patients who
are inpatients and create
patient-friendly discharge
summaries for patients.
And discharge
summaries have been
shown to be really important
to transitions of care
from inpatient to outpatient.
And yet, 88% of current
discharge summaries
are unreadable to patients.
So clearly, these
AI solutions can
result in improved quality,
reduced costs, and increased
revenues.
And that's often what
developers are focused on.
However, what they
often do not focus on
is the workers who need to
implement the solutions.
And based on my work
with coauthors at Duke,
we found that narrow
AI tools often
offer few benefits to workers,
require laborious development,
and also, are a threat
to user autonomy.
And with colleagues
at Langone, we
found that generative
AI solutions often
have unclear applications,
require laborious iteration,
and result in harmful outputs.
And workers don't
like these solutions
that make their lives worse.
So how can developers
design AI solutions
for successful implementation?
I've done research at Duke
looking at their narrow AI
solutions and NYU Langone
looking at their generative AI
solutions.
And what we found is that
each of these solutions
have particular
characteristics that
raise challenges for workers.
So the challenges
with narrow AI are
that it's predictive,
laborious and prescriptive,
and with generative AI are that
it has unclear applications,
is laborious, and
results in new risks.
So developers need to design AI
tools with worker implementation
in mind.
So with narrow AI, let's look at
this predictive characteristic
first.
At Duke, what they found
is that specialists
who treat patients for
particular diseases
often asked the developers to
develop tools to flag patients
at risk of developing
these diseases.
So, as Jonathan just
told you, AI tools are--
in medicine, we're going to be
able to predict a lot of things.
And so this is great.
We can now intervene
earlier with patients
with all of these disease states
in order to have higher impact.
The problem is it means
that upstream clinicians are
expected to use these tools.
And now, they're bombarded
with a host of narrow AI tools
that they didn't ask
for in the first place.
So what they do at Duke is they
identify the true end users,
in this case, the
primary care physicians.
And they develop solutions
to address their pain points.
So in the case of a
narrow AI tool which
can detect chronic kidney
disease early, what they found
is that the
challenge for PCPs is
that they already have limited
time to prepare for patients.
So they don't have time
to use another tool,
and they also don't have time
to ensure appropriate follow-up
for patients who get
flagged by the tool.
So the Duke development
team worked for solutions
where it was the
nephrologist who
asked for the tool who
actually are the ones who
use it to detect this problem.
They send their recommendations
to an EHR system,
which gives doctors the
recommendations directly
before the patient visit.
And they provide
dedicated care managers
so that any patients who
are flagged to be at risk
get appropriate follow-up.
Another issue with narrow AI is
that it's laborious to develop.
It requires a lot
of back and forth
between clinicians
and developers
before you can make
these tools work.
And so specialists came to
Duke developers and said,
help us detect low-risk
pulmonary embolism in the ER
because a lot of patients
with pulmonary embolism
are getting admitted
to the hospital who
don't need to be admitted.
And it's the emergency
room physicians
who need to use this
tool who were initially
asked to help develop it.
And they said, we've got
a lot of other things
we're already working on.
So Duke then went to
the downstream vascular
and cardiology
specialists and got
them involved in this
laborious development
to do things like validate
outcome definition,
make sure that model
inputs were fit for use,
and do a silent trial to test
the performance of the tool.
Finally, narrow AI
is prescriptive.
It tells doctors what to do,
and that can threaten autonomy.
In the case of the sepsis
tool I told you about,
it was rapid
response team nurses
who wanted ER doctors to use
this tool to detect sepsis.
And initially, they were
the ones using the tool.
And ER doctors
didn't like having
these people far away from
the ER all of a sudden
being the ones to detect sepsis
on the ER doctor's patients.
So the rapid
response team nurses
started, whenever an AI tool
flagged someone with sepsis,
they would do a chart review.
But they would call
the doctors in the ER
to make sure the doctors were
the ones who did the diagnosis
and placed all the orders
for patients with sepsis.
So Duke developers have
learned to increase benefits
for true end users, reduce
labor for end users,
and protect the autonomy
of true end users.
Generative AI similarly
raises particular challenges
for workers.
At NYU Langone, one challenge
is that generative AI
is general purpose,
so it has a million
different potential
applications.
And what they do is they
involve the workers themselves
in widespread decentralized
experimentation
so that it's the workers,
not the developers, who
are deciding what are
the applications that
are going to be most valuable
for the health care workers.
And one way they do
this is prompt-a-thons,
where they provide workers with
basic education in generative
AI and hands-on ability to use
the generative AI with health
care data sets in order
to get a feel for things
and begin to develop ideas
for good applications.
One developer said, "GPT has
these fascinating moments where
it just does stuff."
And that's motivating for people
working with generative AI.
Another challenge is
that these solutions
require laborious iteration.
So for that tool I
told you about with
the patient-friendly
discharge summaries,
that required clinicians to go
through dozens of patients who
had been in inpatients
and their clinical notes
to figure out how to
draft an accurate prompt
that resulted in a good output
for the patient-friendly
discharge notes.
What the developers
do is they need
to sustain worker motivation
for doing this iteration on top
of their regular job.
And so they provide on-demand
assistance in office hours,
provide help with what they
call "prompt tricking,"
which in this case involves
things like with GPT-4 using all
capital letters when
giving instructions,
and even telling GPT-4 that
you'll give it a tip if it gives
you good outputs.
Finally, generative
AI presents new risks
because of hallucinations, bias,
and lack of interpretability.
So developers use a
Gen AI risk screen
where they screen all
potential applications up front
to see which ones
are worth developing.
So in one department, clinicians
came to developers and said,
we really want to use generative
AI to translate consent forms
into other languages.
But what the
developers discovered
is that GPT-4 tends to
miss important nuances.
So it's not a good technical
fit with generative AI,
and it also raises
regulatory concerns related
to this bad interpretation.
So they stopped the
development of that tool.
So at Langone, they
catalyzed this decentralized
experimentation
with prompt-a-thons,
used this on-demand
technical support,
and also, use a risk
score to prioritize which
projects are going to be best.
So in sum, what I want you
to take away from today
is we often focus on how these
tools are great for quality,
costs, and revenues.
But we forget that
they often present
problems for the workers
who need to implement them.
Developers need to
address these challenges
to design AI solutions for
successful implementation.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
All right, hi, everyone.
My name is Joe Doyle.
I'm an economist at MIT
Sloan, and a lot of my day job
is partnering with
payers and providers
to try to get patients
to be healthier
and providers to be
more guideline adherent
and do a better job.
So I help run our Health
Systems Initiative at Sloan.
And we have three
pillars of research
backed by about 30 faculty
members and a bunch of PhD
students working on health
analytics, healthcare
operations, and health
care incentives.
On the analytics side, we
build new frontier tools,
but also, we have
people like Kate
who help think about how do
you get those tools adopted
in a meaningful way.
Operations are to get more
efficiency in our health care
system.
And then, as an
economist, I think
a lot about these incentives.
How do you get people
to behave healthier?
How do you set up the right
procedures and incentives
to get that to happen?
So let me talk about one
part of my research, which
is randomized trials in
health care delivery.
Most drugs or medical devices
will have some randomized trials
behind them to show you
that they're effective.
But when we go to change how
we're going to deliver care,
there's much less that's
done in that rigorous way
that we can learn whether
things work or don't work.
And so I'm here to evangelize
that we need more of this.
So let me talk a bit about
the economics underlying it.
Here's a map of Boston.
And if you think
about the Bus Route 1,
if you get on in Roxbury, the
life expectancy is 59 years old.
If you go a couple of
miles north to Back Bay,
life expectancy is 92 years old.
So that's 3 miles buys you
30 years of life expectancy.
So you often hear people
say there's genetic code.
There's zip code.
This is the zip code part of it.
Through poverty and
other social risk
factors are major
drivers of whether people
are healthy or not.
So health care in
the clinic needs
to think a bit more
broadly and think, well,
what can we do upstream?
How can we address the issues
that are really driving
a 30-year drop in
life expectancy?
So one way we
think about it is--
and John talked about
the need for insurance
if you get unlucky.
Well this graphic here shows
you that 1% of the population
drives about 30% of health
care costs in any given year.
And we're spending $4.5 trillion
in health care in the US.
So 1% of people are driving,
have over $1 trillion
of spending on them.
If we could figure out how
to treat those patients
in a healthier way, in a
more effective way, more
efficient way, we could
save a lot of money
and improve their lives.
So in the health care
delivery literature,
these people are called super
utilizers or health care
hotspots.
And there was this really
interesting article
in The New Yorker
a few years ago
about hotspotting could make
people's lives better and save
money at the same time.
So it was a profile
of Camden, New Jersey.
It's a high-poverty city
outside of Philadelphia.
And Dr. Jeff Brenner, who's
sort of a hero of mine--
I'd say he's a very
inspiring physician there
who organized the collection
of data from all the health
care providers into one
health information exchange.
And then, they would
try to figure out,
who are these hotspots, and
how can we treat them better?
Their idea was to create
a team of about 10 people,
including nurses, psychologists,
social workers who
would make home visits, I
think about 5 to 10 home visits
to the super utilizers,
send nurses with them
to their appointments, and
try to navigate that system
in a more effective way.
If you had all the
health care problems
the people in the 1% have,
1% of health care spending,
then you would really appreciate
having this team of people there
to help you.
So here are the number
of admissions leading up
to entry into that program
and then afterwards.
And you can see in the quarters
before, you see a ramp-up.
People got unlucky.
They lost the genetic lottery
or some kind of lottery,
and they are going
to the hospital more.
That's how you get
into the program.
And then, after they're in
the program, their costs fall.
And that's exactly what The New
Yorker article and hotspotting
programs that were popping
up all across the country
were pointing to this
graph and saying,
we could save a lot
of money and improve
the lives of these
people at the same time.
Now, economists and
health service researchers
wonder, well, what
would have happened
if they didn't get that program,
what we call the counterfactual?
Against the fact that
they got the program, what
would have happened?
Well, the nice thing
about a randomized
controlled trial,
you flip a coin
and figure out who's in
the treatment group, who's
in the control group.
The control group gives
you the counterfactual,
what would have happened
if we flipped the coin
and got heads instead of tails.
And so in the
orange bars, that's
exactly what happened
to the control group.
It exactly mirrors what happened
in that treatment group that
got lavished care, all these
home visits, phone calls,
appointment collaborations.
And so what we learned
from this experiment
is that the drop in health care
spending was a bit of a mirage.
It wasn't the program
that did that.
When people get
healthy and unlucky,
they tend to get luckier
than they were before.
And they sort of
revert to the mean.
Now, I wanted to go
into this program
and say, well, let's show
that this thing works
so that it will spread even
faster than it's already
spreading.
This is a very inspiring
program, helping people
both in their clinical
needs and their social needs
to improve their health.
And what I learned
was that it's not
going to be sustained by
lower health care costs.
We might want to pay for
it for other reasons,
but we can't make
the claim that we're
saving money at the same time.
And it might have felt good
to pat ourselves on the back
and say, we're saving
money at the same time.
But if you're not
actually doing it,
then you're just going
to chase your tail.
We need to know
what works in order
to have that spread so we
can make real progress.
So the paper came out
just before COVID.
There was a lot of attention
devoted to it because this
was a very popular program,
like I said, springing
up all across the country.
And what folks said
across the country was,
well, I used to assume
that this works.
This seems like it should work.
In our own data,
our own dashboards,
people get healthier after
they go on the program.
And what they had to do was
go back to the drawing board
and figure out, does it
work in my area or not?
So going from a
presumption that something
works to actually let's
figure out if it works,
that's what we do at MIT.
We actually try to figure out
what works in a rigorous way.
So then, we can march down the
path of progress as opposed
to window dressing
that feels good when
you say that you're doing it.
So I partnered with Geisinger
on another study that
targeted patients
who had diabetes,
and they were uncontrolled
according to the clinicians
there.
They had a blood sugar
that's HBA1C level over 8.
So to put it in perspective
would be diabetic.
And over 8, they call
it an uncontrolled.
On average, people had
a score of over 10.
And if your doctor tells
you have an A1C over 10,
that's kind of a scary number.
So this program
was also inspiring.
It gives lots of healthy food
to these low-income patients
with diabetes.
It gives about 10 meals per
week, not only for the patient,
but for their entire family.
They go to a clinic every week
to pick up their groceries.
And at the clinic, there's
a dietitian, a nurse,
and a community
health worker that
will try to address their
needs through foot exams,
have dietitian consultations,
have cooking classes,
diabetes self-management
training.
And these are brand new
clinics that are well-lit,
staffed with
super-friendly people.
People love going
to these clinics.
But what I found was, again,
a mean reversion story,
that when they were targeting
the people with very high levels
of A1C, the treatment
group got healthier,
but the control group
also got healthier.
And this is back to this
mean reversion story.
And so what am I taking away
from this sort of now growing
evidence that when you target
people with a pretty sick,
some measure that
they're pretty sick--
so it was a high blood
sugar level or high spending
in the last year--
you really have to be worried
that they might mean revert.
So one idea is you can't
just trust those dashboards
that you're seeing that
people are getting healthier.
If mean reversion is a story
that you have to worry about,
you can't just rely on
a pre-post comparison.
You need a credible
control group.
The other idea is to target
durably eligible people.
So the research
I'm doing right now
is I'm finding that if you could
predict who would get healthier
regardless of the
program, then you
could target the scarce
resources of this program
toward the people who would
actually need the program.
And when I did a reanalysis
of the people who
predicted to not get
healthier on their own
based on what we could
observe when they enrolled
in the study, those
people, their HBA1C
would fall by more than
a point if you gave them
the program, which is
better than a lot of drugs,
so getting people off of drugs
toward healthier food, which
was the initial
goal of the program,
but learning how to target it
in a way that actually makes
that difference as opposed
to just hoping that you're
making the difference.
And also, just back
to that bus route map,
social risk factors are
obviously important.
So there's just
more work that we
need to do to learn
how to address them.
We don't just give
up on those 1%.
We think about, well, what
we were doing before wasn't
working to save money.
Let's see if we could--
are there other programs
you could do, like
better remote monitoring,
other technological solutions
that you'll be seeing here
at MIT throughout the day.
Just really quickly,
just to point out that
I work with Geisinger on these
large-scale messaging campaigns.
So you might get these
text messages reminding you
of your appointment.
Well, what should
be in those messages
to get you to do healthy
behaviors like get your cancer
screenings on time, get
vaccinated, and so on?
And with machine
learning, we can
try to target those
messages, figuring out
exactly what types
of messages get
you to behave in the
healthiest ways, so at least
giving you that
advice so that you can
choose to do so for yourself.
At Sloan, we're working
with Quest Diagnostics,
which takes blood from
almost every American
every three years.
Everybody will go into
there at some point.
And we're doing randomized
controlled trials
to see what we could do to get
people to be healthier when
they get those results back.
And then I just wanted to end
on you don't need to always do
a randomized controlled trial.
Sometimes with data
analytics, we can do more.
So just my last example here is
the x-axis here is birth weight.
And at 1,500 grams,
3 pounds 5 ounces,
newborns below that are
labeled very low birth weight.
And what you can see here
is that as you get lighter,
we spend more on you.
And you see a discrete jump
if you go across 1,500 grams
because especially at
lower-level hospitals,
they increase the amount
of treatment they give you.
If you get categorized
in that way.
And then, what we see
is as you get lighter,
the mortality rate is rising.
But it falls against
the trend if you
cross that magical threshold
that got you the extra care.
And so here, if we're rooting
around for waste and value
in health care, here's a
place where people born just
above and below that threshold
is like a genetic lottery
or a birth weight lottery.
Some people win the lottery,
and they're actually too light.
They're just below
the threshold.
They get more health
care, and actually, they
get better outcomes.
And then, this was replicated
in other countries like Chile.
Here's the mortality
result for Chile.
But here's eighth grade test
scores or first to eighth grade
test scores.
If you were born too late, you
do better in school in Chile.
And you do better
in school in Norway.
But in high school,
you're better off
if you were born a few
grams less at the time
that you were born.
So there's a lot to do.
And I really appreciate you
guys spending the day with us
here at MIT to figure out
how we can do it together.
Thanks very much.
[APPLAUSE]
I'm Mike Yaffee, and it's a
great pleasure to be here today.
As you heard, I'm a
professor in biology
and biological engineering.
And I direct the MIT Center
for Precision Cancer Medicine.
But I'm also a
practicing clinician.
I'm an intensive care physician,
and I'm a practicing surgeon.
And what I'm hoping to do in
the next nine minutes or so
is to connect this session on
health care delivery with some
of the basic science
and engineering concepts
that we heard about during
the first half of this,
during this morning's session.
And so to start off, I'm
going to focus on cancer.
And just for fun, I took every
paper that had been published
in Cell or Nature 43 years ago
in 1981 that contained the word
"cancer."
And I used deep learning
to build a word cloud.
And the words that
jump out at us
are things like gene, protein,
DNA, virus, transforming,
principle.
And in fact, that fit
with 1981's view of cancer
as a genetic disease in which
oncogenes were turned off
or tumor suppressor
genes were silenced.
And MIT was at the very
center of this work.
In fact, many of those papers
in science, in Cell or Nature,
were authored by the luminaries
here at MIT, Bob Weinberg
and Phil Sharp, David Houseman,
Rudy Jaenisch, Sheldon Penman,
David Baltimore, all
the people that you
heard alluded to this morning.
The problem is, let's
look 42 years later.
There are many more papers
about cancer in Cell or Nature.
And so I limited myself
to the first 160 papers
that I could identify.
And now, all of a sudden, the
main text in the abstracts
are things like patients, human
treatment, therapeutic response.
This should be very
worrisome for us
here at MIT because we
don't have a hospital.
We don't own a medical school.
Fortunately, however, if
you look a little deeper,
there are many ways
that MIT can contribute
because underlying this is a
much more systems-based approach
where instead of
just oncogenes, now
we see the immune
system and the tumor
microenvironment, metabolic
defects, and signaling defects.
And so using that, I want to
talk about how in the future
we're going to bridge the divide
between the clinical world
and the basic science world.
And I'm going to use
my own lab's research
just as an example of
how to illustrate this.
So I want to leave you with
three take-home messages.
The first is that the future
of precision health care
has to be an active and
ongoing dynamic collaboration
between clinicians
and basic scientists.
In 1981, the basic
science was revolutionary.
And it was directing
clinical care
or beginning to
illuminate clinical care.
Now, we have to go both
ways in order to do this.
And an example that
I'll use for this
is our lab's research
related to tissue injury.
We've been very interested
in tissue injury
in the setting of both trauma
and cancer, and in particular,
how tissue injury is sensed
by the innate immune system
and how that interacts with
the blood clotting pathways
to further stimulate the immune
system for or against tissue
injury.
And this was work that is
the typical kind of thing
that a biologist
does in his lab,
doesn't think too much
more other than the system
in which we're looking at until
the COVID pandemic came about.
And I say that because during
the COVID pandemic, as you know,
many additional
intensive care units
were opened across the city.
All of us that are intensive
care physicians got
recruited to take care
of those diseases.
And it was clear
to us that this was
a very different type of
respiratory failure caused
by this virus.
It was not the same
respiratory failure
that we saw in patients
with pneumonia or patients
with sepsis that
Kate alluded to.
This was a disease where
the mechanics of the lung
were completely normal.
But for some reason, the lungs
were unable to transfer oxygen
into the blood.
And that turned out to be due
to a blood clotting problem that
was induced by the virus.
In fact, what the
virus was doing
was activating the
immune system and causing
microvascular
thrombosis, something
that's been referred
to as immunothrombosis.
Well, this turned out to
be exactly the process
that we had been studying in
a completely separate context
related to cancer
and tissue trauma.
And this ultimately then led
us to use clot-busting drugs
like alteplase, a drug that
we use for strokes and heart
attacks, to treat
these patients who
had COVID-induced
respiratory failure.
That was the STARS trial that
grew out of the basic research
here at MIT.
Let me spend a
minute and tell you
how a failed
operation completely
changed my view of inflammation,
tissue injury, and cancer.
In 1987, when I was
a medical student,
I was invited to
participate, which
really means hold retractors,
in a case where a patient had
pancreatic cancer.
And in those days in 1987,
we didn't have the imaging
that we have now.
And every patient who
had pancreatic cancer
went to the operating room, and
we would make a big incision
and take a look and make
a decision based on what
we saw about what to do.
And this operation,
unfortunately,
was what we called
a "peek and shriek."
We made a big incision.
We took a look.
There was cancer everywhere.
It was obvious there was no
benefit to operating further
on this patient.
And so we simply
closed the incision
and told the patient
to go home and enjoy
the last few weeks of her life.
Two years later,
when I was an intern,
this patient reappeared in the
emergency room with a bowel
obstruction, two years later.
Now, no one wanted
to operate on her.
But eventually, we had to.
And when we operated on
her, her bowel obstruction
was due to a single
adhesive band.
There was not a spot of cancer
left anywhere inside her body.
And this idea that injury and
trauma combined with live tumor
cells because we hadn't
resected any of the tumor
could somehow activate the
immune system and result
in a complete cure has motivated
a fair amount of our research
ever since.
And here's a paper that we
published just two years ago
that shows how the injury
response in live tumor cells
can promote anti-tumor immunity.
And I think that this ability to
go back and forth between what
we see in the clinic and
what we see in the laboratory
is going to lead
to new approaches
where we can combine surgery,
chemotherapy, and immunotherapy
more effective.
Now, of course,
we're always taught
as physicians above
all else, do no harm.
And so this has
also made me wonder,
maybe the tissue damage and
inflammation and wound healing
response from surgery is making
some of my patients do worse.
Perhaps, I'm adding
fuel to their cancers.
What determines if surgery or
injury or inflammation results
in cancer cure or
cancer progression?
We don't know.
But those are the
types of things
that we should be working on.
The second take-home message
I want to leave you with
is we need to think about
diseases and treatments
not in terms of single genes
but in terms of cell networks.
Now, some of you may
have a cardiologist,
and maybe you have
a pulmonologist,
and maybe you also have
a gastroenterologist.
And you know how
frustrating it is
when you go to see
those physicians
because your
cardiologist only wants
to treat your heart problem.
And he doesn't understand or
doesn't think about the fact
that when you treat
the heart, you also
affect the kidneys in the lungs
and the brain and everything
else.
And as an intensive
care physician,
I don't have the luxury to
treat just one organ system.
I have to think
about my patients
in terms of how all those
organ systems work together.
The same is true moving forward
with how we think about cancer.
We can't think of cancer as
just a mutation in an oncogene
because the cancer
cells are living
surrounded in their
microenvironment by other cells,
including normal--
and this is colon
cancer shown here--
including normal cells and
additional stromal cells.
And the same is true
with genes in cancer.
We can't think of a particular
gene as being mutated.
We have to think about
how that gene is working
in the setting of a network.
And this leads to a
new concept, which
I'm calling network medicine.
And that's because the
connection between genes
and proteins is different
in a disease state
than it is in a
non-disease state.
And this gives us
a new way to be
able to use
disease-specific drug
combinations because if
certain nodes in this network
are connected together
in a disease state,
I could use two drugs that
target two different nodes.
And those drugs would be
particularly effective in cells
in which this network
has been rewired,
whereas it would be much less
effective in the normal state
where only one of
those two nodes
is functionally wired together.
In our own laboratory,
we've discovered
a way in which this works.
We found a
vulnerability that seems
to be cancer specific
that relates to how
cancer cells undergo division.
And this has now led to
two clinical trials and one
proposed.
One clinical trial uses
two different drugs
to treat castrate-resistant
prostate cancer.
Another uses two different
drugs to treat metastatic colon
cancers that contain
a KRAS mutation.
And a proposed
trial is now going
to look at using two
particular drugs in a way
that we think will
dramatically benefit patients
with ovarian cancer.
And the very third point
that I want to leave you with
is the fact that many of the
drugs and treatments we now use
work differently than we
previously have thought.
Now, oftentimes, when
we prescribe a drug,
we're fully aware that in
addition to the way this drug we
think works, there are a variety
of side effects of that drug.
But sometimes, the side effects
could actually be the mechanism.
And as an example of this, we
were working on a drug called
5-fluorouracil.
This is a drug that's
been around for 40 years.
It is a standard of care that is
used to treat advanced-stage GI
cancers like pancreatic
cancer and especially
colorectal cancer.
And in fact, the
textbooks will all
tell you that this drug works
very effectively because it
blocks DNA synthesis.
It targets this enzyme
called thymidylate synthase.
And that's how this drug works.
There's just one
problem with this.
And that's if you look
objectively at patients
who respond to the drug or don't
respond to the drug, responders
in red, non-responders
in blue, and you
look at the level at which
this target is expressed,
there's absolutely
no difference.
How can the drug
work in some people
and not work in other people
if the target of the drug
is equally expressed in both?
And I'll simply cut
to the chase and say,
a few months ago, we were
able to publish a paper
and show that, in fact, that's
because the drug does not
work this way.
The drug works effectively
in cancer patients
because of a side effect.
The drug gets incorporated into
RNA, what Phil Sharp talked
about this morning.
And by being
incorporated into RNA,
it blocks the production
of functional ribosomes,
the machinery that
makes proteins.
And these functional
ribosomes turn out
to be essential in
certain GI cancers.
And that's the reason that this
drug works particularly well.
Now, my friends in
computer science
like to say it's not
a bug, it's a feature.
And the same is
true with medicines.
Sometimes, the side
effects aren't bugs.
Sometimes, they're
actually the mechanisms
of how the drugs work.
So I hope I've left you with
these three take-home messages
for how I think MIT as part
of HEAL can move forward.
We have to have
better collaborations,
active collaborations
with clinicians.
We have to start
thinking about diseases
in terms of network medicine.
And we have to recognize
and explore the fact
that many drugs we use probably
work differently than we think.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
All right, so we are
going to sit on the stage
and do Q&A. I've got a
couple of questions teed up,
but I'd rather hear from you.
So I'm going to start with
one to get us started.
And we're all going to answer.
But I really would hope we
can hear from all of you.
So if you have a question,
you can come on up
and stand at the mics.
And I'll call on you if there
people that are interested.
But let me start
with one question.
And Mike, you sort
of hit on this,
but I'll let you flesh
it out a little bit more,
which is what makes MIT such a
unique place to do what you do?
I think the thing that's
so special about MIT
is how incredibly smart
all of our colleagues
are, the students, the postdocs,
the staff physicians, the staff
scientists and engineers,
and particularly
all of the other faculty.
Really, a great piece of
advice I got from Phil Sharp
was if you really
want to be successful,
just surround yourself
with smart people.
And you can't find that
anywhere at the density
that you can find
them here at MIT.
Kate?
For me, as someone
who studies AI,
MIT is just an
embarrassment of riches.
Literally, in every department
across the institute,
we have experts studying AI
development and implementation.
And that's great
because it creates
this ecosystem of researchers
not only within MIT.
But because of conferences
and speaker series,
it means we get lots of
industry practitioners
and other researchers
from around the globe
to work with on the problem.
Yeah, I'll just echo this.
When it comes to
innovation, it's
that levels of expertise at
such world-class level across so
many different domains,
they work together
to make those innovations
first get developed
and then get implemented.
That's pretty unique.
I think, simply, MIT is
just a no-bullshit place.
I mean, basically, you can't
do good work of the type we
talked about unless
you're incredibly
rigorous and self-critical.
And that happens more at
MIT than any place I know.
That's why our students
sometimes are unhappy.
And basically, we are just a
place that believes enormously
in scientific rigor.
You saw it in
Joe's presentation,
the willingness to take
on strongly held beliefs
and challenge them.
And you saw in the
incredible science
that's being done up here that
MIT is just the perfect place
to be working in areas where
lives depend on it because we
don't get so full of our
beliefs that we're not
willing to challenge them
and take them seriously.
So I would add that as well.
It seems like we might
have some questions.
Please, go ahead.
Sure, [INAUDIBLE] Walter
Bender [AUDIO OUT]
Scream it.
I'll scream it, and
then you can echo it.
Yeah, no, we hear you now.
Oh, OK.
My question has to do--
let me make an
assertion first, which
is scientists
write to scientists
or write for scientists.
When I open up a
nature journal article,
in order to understand
that article,
I've got to have
some background.
And I noticed that a lot of
you and a lot of the speakers
today have behind their
name, MD, comma, PhD.
So when you talk
about communication
between the scientific community
here at MIT and the clinicians,
the practitioners across
the river, the ones that
don't have that PhD
as well as the MD,
how are we going to bridge
that communication gap?
Well, Michael, you're a natural
person to start on this.
I think that's a
brilliant question,
and I don't have an
easy answer for it.
But something that I've been
arguing for for a long time
is we need to embed
PhD scientists
for at least internships or
short visits into the clinic
itself.
The only way that
people are going
to learn to speak
the same language
is if they live in
the same community.
And so I think some interchange
in which basic scientists spend
some time with
clinicians and clinicians
have the opportunity to spend
some time in our laboratories
here at MIT--
in fact, one of my colleagues,
one of my surgical colleagues,
is sitting here in the third
row because he's decided
that he wants to understand.
He wants to get a
deeper understanding
of health economics.
And I think that ability
to go back and forth
and to embed in each
other's cultures
is the only way we're
going to make progress.
Kate, Joe?
Yeah, I mean, I guess
I would just add,
so I'm an ethnographer, which
means I'm an anthropologist.
So I train my students to go do
exactly this where they embed.
But I think one other
thing we try and teach
them is to really
understand what
are the problems of the people
in the setting, not problems
that you come in with, what
problems that they're really
dealing with because
that's where the most
interesting work happens.
I'll just say really briefly,
at the Poverty Action Lab
here at MIT, we put out a lot
of policy insights and things
that are geared toward policy
makers as well as practitioners,
and something that you guys
can look up after today.
Yeah, I just want to add.
The question was talking about
clinicians and researchers,
but let's extend that
further, which is let's
talk about Kate's work and
about how AI needs to speak
to the people using it.
And we need to be able to--
and this is something I
think MIT needs to work on.
I think that's why I'm glad the
School of Humanities and Social
Sciences is involved with
this health and life sciences
collaborative, which we need
to get better communication.
We need to just not
create the new science.
We need to explain to
people why it's important
and what we do is important,
how it can change lives.
And I think that
communication needs
to go not just PhD to MD but
PhD and MD all the way down
to people who don't have a
college degree so that everyone
can really understand why we
do and why it's important.
Yeah, please?
Yeah, thank you all so much
for the insightful comments
and for the wonderful
work you do.
I was curious about this
conflict between AI and autonomy
because I think there have
been some studies published
that show that these AI models
are able to, for example,
diagnose diseases better
than a radiologist.
But also, there is this human--
as radiologists, you are
trained to do the same job.
So I was curious
about, should AI
be taking over the
role of radiologists
if they are able
to predict better?
And sort of, where do
we draw the balance?
I guess I can start with that.
So what we know from other
technological revolutions
is what we see is that some
job categories get completely
displaced and that humans learn
to do higher-order thinking,
higher-order tasks.
And so what's going to
happen with AI, I think,
depends on how fast the
technology progresses
and what frictions there
are for deployment.
But one thing, for sure,
is that in the near term,
many AI solutions are going
to require human and AI
working together.
And so what we're going to see
is role reconfiguration where
humans used to do everything.
Now, they need to figure out
what is the AI best at versus
what are they best at.
Let me just add, the Economics
Department and the Sloan School
were blessed with the
recent Nobel Prize
jointly in economics.
And the two people won the Nobel
Prize, Daron Acemoglu and Simon
Johnson, wrote a book called
Power and Progress, which
is very much about this history
and exactly this set of issues.
So I urge people to
take a look at that.
Yeah?
Obviously, from
your presentations,
health care is a
very complex area.
There's so many
different stakeholders,
and there's
competing incentives.
It seems like health
care, we're very reactive.
We wait for all these
trends and these diseases.
Someone has cancer,
obesity, diabetes.
There's cost disparities.
There's an aging population.
Has there been any efforts
to look at health care
at time of birth?
I know it's the long term, and
we're very reactive society.
I want instant
gratification, and we're
dealing with the crisis
when the thing is burning.
But is there any
analysis or any appetite
for dealing with health
care at an early stage
so we're not dealing with such
a snowballing crisis effect?
Michael, do you want to--
I would say the
extent to which we've
been able to address
health care at birth
is really through
early disease testing.
So there's some
immune deficiencies
that are now standard
of care in all newborns
so that we can
diagnose those early
rather than wait
for those patients
to then develop some
immune-related disease, at which
point, it becomes
much more expensive.
Now, as genomics becomes
more personalized,
I think we will be in a better
position to at least risk assess
and decide who should get
a test and who shouldn't.
As you're probably
aware, we're all
in this dilemma about
Prostate-Specific Antigen, PSA.
Should we use it?
Should we not use it?
And it only works if the
prevalence of the disease
is high.
So I do think the
place this will
be helpful is once personal
genomics really catches on,
we should be able to risk
stratify and better decide what
tests people should get when.
But I can't tell you about
the economics of that.
Well, when we think about the
incentives of the repair shop
gets paid, there's going
to be a lot of focus
on repairing as opposed to if
the prevention shop gets paid,
there'll be more
focus on prevention.
And so the move
in the US has been
toward trying to put
more risk on providers
so that if they get
people healthier,
they would actually benefit
from that as opposed
to welcoming them
back through the door.
And that's a slow-moving process
because of all the stakeholders.
But it's, I think, slowly but
surely going that direction.
What do you think?
One of my colleagues,
Nathan Hendron,
is running something called
the Policy Opportunities Lab.
And what this lab--
Policy Impacts Lab, I'm sorry.
What this lab does is actually
quantify the social value
of different interventions.
And the ones that
are most valuable
are the ones on kids, things
that intervene at birth
and early age are incredibly
socially valuable.
And I think we do
need to be directing
our focus in that area.
Joe talked about some
research on low birth weight,
which does that.
I talked about cell
and gene therapies,
which are really for these
birth defect diseases.
I think we need to be shifting
our focus that way, for sure.
Yeah?
Building up on a
comment, building up
on the comment on the
stakeholders misalignment
and the reimbursement
model, we have
been talking about value-based
care for a long time now
and have not been able
really to accomplish,
at least in oncology,
very significant progress.
Where do you see is the best
way to try to accelerate that?
I'm sorry, I didn't
quite understand.
The value-based care model.
Oh, value-based payment.
Yeah, so basically, this is a
really interesting and important
issue.
Like I said, we've
got these drugs that
look incredibly good
in early trials,
but we're not sure
how well they'll do.
And I think that, actually,
the government has recently
put together an initiative
on this for sickle cell.
There's new genetic
treatments for sickle cell.
And the government
just today announced
that they've got
a new initiative
to work with states to set
up essentially a rebate
system where if the
drug doesn't work,
the drug companies will rebate
the money that the states paid
in.
So I think we're making
good progress there.
But I also think
it's been somewhat
of a failure of-- the
economist said, like I said,
just change the incentives,
and value-based payment
will take care of itself.
And it turns out
it's incredibly hard.
You have to put a lot of work
into it, and that takes time.
So it wasn't going
to happen overnight.
I don't think-- people
who knew this area knew
it wouldn't happen overnight.
But I did think it was going
to happen faster than it has
because I thought the providers
would know where the waste is
a bit more than the payers did.
And it turns out, we all
need to figure it out.
But changing the incentives is
the first step, not the last.
Last question.
Hey, sorry, this is kind
of a technical question,
and we've got a
broad panel today.
But still, I'd like to ask it.
The sobering statistic
that I've come across
in a couple of different places,
including with Michael's lab,
is that maybe only about
a third of patients
benefit from putting
all of our best data
together for
personalized medicine,
so in the context of the best
care we can bring to patients.
And as Michael
knows, I'm sort of
betting on the computational
biology AI racehorse
to really help us there.
But that's only a piece
of the picture, I think.
So from a collaboration
standpoint,
I just wonder if the rest
of you, and together,
Michael, just have some
initial ideas about how
we may make progress through
collaboration on this really,
again, very sobering fact
that all of our best efforts
with all this great
technology, it's
only helping a small portion
of our patients right now?
All the omics, proteomics,
genomics, all the rest of it
combined, it's not getting
us nearly as far as we
need to as fast as we want to.
So I'd like your
thoughts on that.
So I think part of the reason--
so what Scott Ritter Bush is
talking about is the fact that
at least using genomics,
right-- genomics hasn't really--
only 10% or so of
cancer patients
really benefit from genomic
analysis of their tumor.
Only 10% or less actually
have a change in therapy
that results in improvement.
And part of that, though,
is because we've been
so heavily focused on genomics.
So I do think just integrating
in in a patient-specific manner
other types of omic analysis,
looking at metabolism,
looking at immune infiltration,
looking at proteomics-- now,
that's harder to do
because we have not
evolved the technology
that allows us to do this
in a rapid, high-throughput
way on patient samples
like we can do with genomics.
That's exactly the kind
of thing we can do at MIT.
But the other part of it is
we can't do it in isolation.
We have to do this
together with looking
at patient historical records,
risk assessment, family history.
And that's even
harder to incorporate
into that type of thing.
Yeah, I would just add-- it's a
great question, great comment.
I would just add,
as a society, we
play a role in directing
technological advance.
And I think we need to be
thinking about directing
technological advance to
things which are helping
a narrow slice of people
very well versus a broader
set of people maybe through
birth improvements less well.
And that's the kind of
trade-off that economists
love to think about and
that we'll be working on.
So I think we just stop there.
Thank you very much for
your comments and questions.
[APPLAUSE]