Okay. So, uh let me just recall first
that
so what we were talking about so this is
a very important concept uh of a
sequence concept of a sequence.
So sequence is is the formal definition
is that you have a map from the natural
number into R
and then we denote so then the image of
a particular natural number n it's
usually denoted like a n like this you
know it could be some other instead of a
it could be bn potentially it could be
another subscript but it's this is like
the most common thing to denote it like
this instead of like but it really is a
function. Okay, so that's a sequence a
subsequence.
So subsequence is that you have a
sequence and then you have another map
but this map is not just any map from
the integers to the integers. It has to
be strictly increasing.
And why does it have to be strictly
increasing? Because we want for the
subsequence. If you think about the
numbers that come out when you plug in a
when you're looking at the a then you
want
some of those numbers to be in the
subsequence, but you want the ordering
to be the same. So this map so that's
why this map has to be strictly
increasing right can't sort of I mean
you and you can't pick the several
elements many times if it wasn't picked
many times in the original uh sequence
right
so this is so a subsequence is where you
have another map from the natural number
to the natural number that is strictly
increasing and then you're looking at
the composition of these two maps so
you're looking at sorry uh this thing
here
right and you call this here and then
that's usually
denoted something
like this a n k a n is the original
sequence k means that it's really that
you take the image of k under this
strictly increasing map and then you're
looking at the element in the sequence
right so it's sort of n k is really you
should think about it as G of K.
Okay, so that's that's what a a a
subsequence is. And again, it's
important that it's strictly increasing
because you want the elements to be in
the same order than it was in the
original sequence. And you don't want
things you don't even want things to be
picked more times than it was in
original sequence. Mhm. So that that's
that's you know so this this whole
concept of a sequence of subunits is
really important. Then
the next really important concept is
uh is of convergence.
So if you have a sequence a n then you
say that is converging to a. So so a is
another real number. It's not infinity.
is another real number and so a n
converts. So a n converts
to a if for all
epsilon greater than zero there exist
n an integer n you know by capital n
such that if little n is bigger equal to
this capital n then a n minus minus a
have to be less than epsilon. Right? of
those. So if you are sufficiently far
out in sequence then everything in that
sequence is bunch epsilon close to a
okay that's what it's saying
and so as if you have a sequence
so a sequence
that
is not convergent
uh is set to be divergent.
Okay.
Um and the next thing for sequences is
[Applause]
I'm just briefly reviewing this from
last time. The next thing for sequences
are the are the break
to break uh
uh laws or whatever you want to call
them.
And so that is that if you take a
sequence, if you have a sequence a n and
a n converts to a bn converts to b
then if you form the sum of these two
uh a
n + bn.
So this is a new sequence where the nth
element is the sum of the nth element of
the other two sequences. then this
sequence here CN also converge and the
limit here is the sum of the limits.
Okay. And likewise if you take a if
you're looking at at if you define a
sequence so this was one
two is that if you take a constant so
this is a constant
and you define cn to be c * a n then
this cn also converge and the limit here
is just c * a right that's the second
one then uh this one I might have done
it in the other order but there's no you
know it's not you know there's no
particular order
um to have it in.
Uh the third one is that if you are
looking at the product. So if you define
a sequence that is given by the product
of the two then C and converge also and
the limit is the product of the limits.
And then the fourth rule is that if a n
is not equal to zero for all n and the
limit here
is also not equal to zero. Then if
you're looking at 1 / a n then those
converge to one.
Okay. So those are the four four the
four roots.
Just write it as four. And again, it's
not like there's any particular
convention with the ordering. And I
think I might have done it. I might have
exchanged the order of one and two last
time. But
okay. Um now, uh let's see an example of
how that works.
So let's define a sequence.
Uh let's define a sequence uh n 2 + 1 n
2 + uh n +
uh + one. Let's look at this sequence
here right for each n that give us uh
actually a rational number but it's only
real number.
Now in order to understand this I can
rewrite this one here as I can factor
out 1 / n well I can factor out n squ
here. So I can write it like this
[Applause]
like that. And then of course I can get
rid of the n squ
in both denominator and denominator. And
now I can look so so this so you may as
well think about the sequence as this
thing here. So now if I defined um so
now I can just look at say uh I can look
at uh the sequence which is one I can
just first look at the sequence which is
1 / n. If I'm looking at this sequence
here, right, one / n, this here converts
to zero. This is essentially just
followed from the ardian property,
right? But we already we've already seen
this that 1 / n converts to zero.
And the same hold for 1 / n^2, right?
This here also converts to zero, right?
And so if you're looking at the
sequence, you could even look at the
sequence.
Let's call this x n. This here is yn.
I'm going to run out of character very
quickly. Uh set n. This is just going to
be the sequence which is constant one.
Right? Well, if if it's constant one,
then obviously it's converging to one,
right? And so now I can just think about
I can think about the sequence bn
to be equal to x sorry equal to set
plus uh y set n plus yn right this here
is a sequence here is what yn is here's
what set n is right so if you add these
two this is converging to one this is
converging to zero by the algebraic
property of limits this converts also to
the sum of the limit so this here
converts to one right now I can also
define a sequence where I'm just adding
set in and then I'm adding x in and then
I'm adding y in right
this here converts to one this here to
zero
this here to zero. So the sum here also
converge to the sum of the limit but the
sum of the limits is one.
Now you have that
one over c sorry now you have that
put it up here and then then I will I'll
just go over here.
So now you have that um that CN
converts to one.
Um and let's call this here C. And so in
in particular, I mean all of these
numbers here, these things here are all
strictly positive. So each of the CN are
strictly positive. So they're definitely
not zero, right? So the CN so not only
do they converge to one but the CN are
not equal to zero and the limit C well
that's one so that's of course not equal
to zero either right so you can apply
the fourth rule here the fourth rule for
the sequence not for the sequence CN not
right so apply the fourth rule to the
sequence CN and then you have that one
over CN converge to one / c. But one c
was one. So this is one. Right?
Now you can look at at um at bn
* 1 / cn. But bn * 1 / cn, right?
Remember what bn was? Here's bn. And bn
is really the denominator up here.
Right? It's the nominator up here. when
you have divided by n squ on both sides
uh by not on both sides but both in the
top and the denominator.
So bn is the denominator and cn is the
denominator. So bn divided by CN this
here is a n right
and now this here converge that's what
we saw over there using the algebraic
rule it converts to one this here also
converts to one by the algebraic rules
number three of the algebraic rules is
that for the product it will also
converge so and it converts to the
product of the limits so that's one
And obviously so I you know this is like
when you're looking at a sequence it's
often uh expressed in some form with
some functions like this and you and you
do this reduction and very quickly you
know this would be almost automatic
right I mean this is too easy almost
this one I mean you know this is the
first time you see it but you know in in
a couple of weeks this will feel uh too
easy uh then then there would be
something more complicated.
Okay.
So that's that's the algebraic rules uh
of for sequences.
The next thing I want to talk about is I
want to try to make more precise
um you know this about square. I mean,
you know, we made it pretty precise, but
I want to think about
uh uh I don't have a very good eraser,
unfortunately. Let me just see. This is
a better one.
This one here will make it very dirty.
Okay. So, so the next thing I want to
So, we did define square of two and we
talked about that quite extensively. how
square root two, you know, how it really
was defined and it was a real number and
the real numbers followed from
that the field the reals is complete.
But we also
we also sort of in the back of our mind
we had that we already sort of knew what
square root of two were, right? Because
when you think about square root two, I
mean at least I think about square root
two. I think about it as 1.4. I mean
just because you can't really express it
as a fraction. So you think about it as
1.414
etc. And then I don't remember I don't
remember the second years third and
fourth whatever but you know you may
remember just a few of the digits fine
and but so how do we make so so that's
sort of our intuition
uh with 1.4 four with with square two.
Uh but how do we make this more precise?
Right? And so to make this more precise,
we want to look at particular sequences.
So what's called monotone
sequences?
So what is a mono sequence?
So there's two types of monotom
sequence. There's one which is monot
increasing sequence
and then there's similarly monotum
decreasing sequence. So a monotum
increasing sequence this is just means
that for all n
you have that the next element is larger
or equal to the previous element. That's
a mono increasing sequence. Right? Some
people talk about strictly monotum
increasing and then this have to be a
strict.
Uh the second thing is kind of the
obvious parallel to this is monoton
decreasing
decreasing sequences.
So that's these two types. Okay. And
this just means that the next element so
a n + one is less or equal to the
previous one.
Okay.
And so now there's a theorem and and
I'll prove this in a in just a minute.
But I also want to
and I want to come back to square root
of two and then I want to look at
another
classical example of a monotum sequence.
So
um
right so this is a mono sequence and now
let me state the mono convergence
theorem.
So suppose that so this is the following
theorem. Suppose that
that and there's two versions of this.
There's one version for monotum
increasing sequence and then there's one
version for mono decreasing sequence. I
just state one of them because the other
one's kind of obvious parallel. So
suppose that a end is a monotone
increasing sequence
[Applause]
then it is bounded
bounded. So this just means that there
exists
i.e.
[Applause]
there exist
some a real number.
So that's
right. You have a1 this here is that is
monotum right this is monotum that they
cannot increase but but the claim is
that now the all of the a is lesser
equal to this a
it's any monotum increasing sequence is
clearly bounded from below right because
already the first element is a lower
bound right so if you have a mono
increasing sequence then Um
then uh that is bounded then it's
convergence
and
uh we limit say we limit
a
where
a is the soup
of the a inch.
So that is a mono convergence sequence.
Okay. and and and that is the the kind
of main theorem about mono convergent
sequence is that if you have a monotum
increasing sequence
that is bounded then it's also
convergence right and likewise if you
have a monotum decreasing sequence that
is bounded from below
right then it is also convergent and so
maybe maybe I will state it
u but it's is the obvious parallel.
So,
so this is part one
of the monome converting sequence.
Part two of part B is that if
if A is a monotone
decreasing sequence
sequence
then
uh that is bounded uh that is
that is bounded from below.
Then
uh a is convergent
with limit a where a is now the in
of these numbers.
Okay.
Now,
so you might say the first thing you
might say, we'll come to square root two
in just a minute, but you may see that
this seems rather special, you know,
like if you take a random uh sequence,
obviously it's not going to be monitor.
Um but but here's the thing that so
uh let
be any bounded sequence.
So bounded again means that it's bounded
from above and bounded from below. So if
you take any boundless sequence
then we can form two other sequences.
Two other sequences
I mean obviously form many other but
here's two other very natural
uh sequences.
The first one I call BN
and BN is is the soup
of where you're taking where you're
starting at a end
and then you take the soup of all of the
ones from A in and outwards in the
sequence. Right? So this is one
sequence
right we know that that you know the set
of a ends is bounded right so you can
certainly take the soup and you get a
real number right that's that that gives
you another sequence
you can also look at cn similarly where
you take instead of the soup you take
the in of the same that
[Applause]
like that. All right. So, in particular,
right, just to make sure it's totally
clear
that
that if you were looking at
say BN, so what is BN? If you're looking
at say B3
then this is the soup where you're
starting at A3 A4
etc.
And so you see of course that B23 here
well obviously B3 is bigger equal
to B2 right because B2 here
is sorry it's no it's not bigger equal
to it's lesser equal to B2
because you see in B2 the definition of
B2 so let's just write B2 down
so B2 is that you take the soup here of
A2 and then A3
A4 etc.
Right? But you see that B2 here it's
both of them are defined to be soup but
B2 is defined as soup over a larger set
because in addition to these elements it
also includes A2 right. So clearly B2
here is bigger equal to B3
right and in fact the same argument
tells you that if you take B
n + one then this is or bn sorry bn is
bigger equal to bn + one
because this here is the soup over a
larger set it's soup over all the ones
you take soup in here plus a n right so
you have this property here right and so
yeah
>> what do you
Yeah.
If it's a monot increasing um
>> yeah because monotum increasing uh then
this here uh right yeah then it becomes
very special.
Uh so it's it's if you take a mon if the
a was monoton increasing then the all of
these any element here would just be the
a we talked about before it would always
be the limit.
So so it's um it's it somehow wouldn't
be that interesting a sequence. It would
be a constant sequence and and it would
be just
>> but but but that but nevertheless it's a
good example you know. I guess that's
still anybody.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Definitely. Right. Because
it's just constant. Exactly.
>> It's a it's a good example, but it's
just kind of almost like too simple
because you get a constant sequence,
right?
So, okay. So, we have for this sequence
that we defined. So we have again these
if you take any sequence then you get
then you have two sequences B and a CN
and B and here is now a decreasing
sequence and in instead of writing
decreasing sequence then uh it's much
easier to write it like this. This is
pretty standard. I mean you know it's
just to uh if you just look quickly at
it uh you know what this means.
going to write out but let's look at CN
also
remember that we assume that a n we a
could be any sequence but it is supposed
to be bounded right so this is now a
monotum decreasing sequence that is
bounded so it actually has a limit right
the cs what about the cs so the cns
So
the CN
well CN was defined to be the in
starting at a end
like that
right
so it' be starting like that and so this
means that if you take CN + one
then you take the infom But you don't
include this element. Right? So it's a
infreum over fewer elements. But then
this here must be larger equal
right to that. So you see that the
sequence CN
is monotum. This here is monotum
increasing again is bounded and and and
just copying from over there. The BN was
decreasing.
>> Okay. This is like I mean it's also like
I mean this is an important thing. It's
also something that you would see in lot
of different context where you define
something some sort of sub and then you
have these property
and so now the thing is that if you're
looking at so aure it might not be so
clear to compare a random element in
this sequence to a random element in
that but what is clear is that if you
try to compare BN with CN And
right
it's the same set. It's the same set.
And one you take the soup, the other you
take the in. So of course BN is bigger
equal to CN,
right? So you have this, right? And so
now you see that if you take like a
random element here, if it was like
further out, if it was N, sorry, if it
was C N further out, I just write it as
something further out. So you adding
something else to it. So this would be
like further out. We know that this
sequence here.
Yeah. Anyway, so you get Sorry, now
you're getting this. I'm getting this
here.
like that
and right so you have this so what you
should what I should have done is that
this sequence here so you have so let
let me rather draw it like this so I
have that this that so here is maybe C1
here is B1
and now the next one the next element
the sequence C n is increasing and the
sequence
bn is decreasing. So then but you always
have this here. So c2 have to lie to the
right of this but it has to lie to the
left of b2.
So you're getting this here.
So, so you see that this is a way to
kind of you know this gives you a way to
compare right that that the CN will
always lie to the left of the BN.
So you have so so now what we have done
here is we took any boundary sequence
and we formed two mono sequences.
They're both mono
And we have so so this means that now
from the monot convergence that we
haven't quite proven yet but from the
mono convergence uh convergence theorem
because these are bounded we have that
bm converge converging they are going uh
they're going down right so they're
converging so one often would write it
like this more suggestively
that is converging downward to a limit B
and the CN
is converging upward to a limit C.
Right? And so what you get is because of
all of these elements, all the C ends
lie to the left of the B ends. This
means that and we we'll prove this later
but it seems probably pretty obvious
that the limit here C is less or equal
to B
and this so we'll come back to this also
next time um when we talked I if I have
time I'll talk a little bit about cushy
sequence but I won't really prove too
much about it and and and but this here
will play a important role
uh when we prove the the basic theorem
about cushy sequences.
Okay. So so the takeaway here at the
moment is just that uh so you have you
have this concept of a monot
uh either increasing or decreasing
sequence. If such a sequence is bounded
then it's convergent. That's a mono
convergence theorem. And again from any
sequence
any boundary sequence you can act that's
there that's a very natural mono
increasing sequence and a very natural
mono decreasing sequence.
Now let's try to prove the monotom
convergence theorem and then let's get
back to how to think about square root
of two in a more intuitive way using
this.
[Applause]
Okay. So now the proof of the monome.
So we So now let me just remind you what
we have.
So I'm only going to prove one of the
two versions of it where the sequence is
monotum increasing because the other one
is just proof is is just the same with
obvious modification. So I'm assuming so
this is the assumption.
So this is the assumption.
So, so this is just that the next
element is larger equal to the previous
one and they're all bounded by this a
right
now I take I we set
little a equal to the soup
uh of the a
Okay.
And I want to show we want to show
that a converts to a.
Now to do that what we need is we need
this stuff about that for a given
epsilon there exist a capital n.
Okay. So now let me first make the
observation
that
that the that the soup right so a here
since
a here is the soup
it is
right. Remember that the soup of a set
is the smallest upper bound right so but
since it is so it's partic so a is in
particular an upper bound so you have
that a n is less than a for all n
since
a is an upper bound. It's actually the
smallest upper bound. But for this you
just need it's a upper bound.
Okay.
So I'm going to look at a n sorry I'm
going to look at a minus a n.
And what I want to prove is that for a
given epsilon if I'm sufficiently far
out if I'm bigger than some capital if
little n is bigger than some capital n
then this here is less than epsilon
right that's what I want to prove but
this thing here you see this here I
don't need the absolute value because I
already know that this is bigger than
that so I don't need the absolute value
so I can just so this is what I want to
prove that I want to prove that for
given
given epsilon greater than zero there
exist.
So maybe let me just write it a little
larger here. So what I want to prove is
that given
epsilon greater than zero there exist
a capital n such that
if little n is bigger equal to this
capital n then a minus a n which I know
is positive I just need to prove that
this is less than epsilon.
Okay.
Now, so now how do you do that? Well,
I know.
So, at the moment, I just use that A was
an upper bound. Now, I'm going to use
that is the least upper bound.
So since
a is the least upper bound
then
uh a minus epsilon is not
an upper bound.
Right? A minus epsilon is not an upper
bound. So this means that there must
exist so
there exist
capital n so that a n is bigger or
equal. So a capital n just this one here
is bigger than a minus epsilon. Right?
because otherwise it would have been an
upper box but it's actually strictly but
maybe I should strictly because I'll put
it up.
Okay,
but I already know that this thing here
is less than a
so but and I also know in fact I know
more than this. I know that this thing
here is less or equal to a little n as
long as little n is bigger than capital
n. That was just because the sequence
was increasing and all of them is
smaller than this upper bound. So now
you see that so here you have a all the
elements a in lie to the left and if
you're looking at just the one from a
capital N outwards then here you have a
minus epsilon and then they lie between
this one here and that in particular
they lie to the right of this and to the
left of that. So this means that they're
squeezed in this little interval and
it's so this difference here this
difference from here to here is
certainly bounded by the distance to
here which was epsilon
right?
So this proved that this in here is less
than.
Okay.
And with obvious modification
uh the proof of that if you take so this
was an increasing sequence. The proof uh
that if you have a decreasing sequence
that is bounded right that that that the
limit of that is the in proof with
obvious changes is is know the same.
Okay.
So now let's come back to square root of
two. Right. And so we have this idea
that square two in a way the way
you know to just get an idea about how
large it is you think about it as uh you
know you think about it as one and then
a number of digits afterwards right
that's a kind of approximation
so so let's try to make this more
precise
Um
[Applause]
and so
I'm going to look at a I'm going to
define
uh two sequence uh two sequences
uh a n and bn sorry two. So we'll define
two sequences
a n and bn
and a n will really be a n where
where a n
is going to be bn
/ 10 to ^ nus one.
Remember that anything to you know if
it's 10 to the power zero by definition
that's one. Okay. So this here in
particular means that a
a1 should be equal to b1.
And we're going to define it like this.
And we are
going to define the BN.
So and the sequences here the the so
there would be some properties here is
that the sequence
uh sequence
uh a is monotone
increasing
a just real numbers that it's monot
and um
and uh and the a
um is going to be defined to right so
and and and a is defined like that sorry
um and the bn
and the bn are just
natural numbers Okay.
So, so a n is defined from bn. It's
really a n that we are interested in,
but bn is going to be a useful tool
here. And so,
and it's going to be and the bn to some
extent is very simple because they're
just natural numbers.
So, now um so now we define
bn.
So bn
is the largest
natural number
such that
uh
b
is bigger and less or equal to 2 uh * uh
to the power 2 n - 2.
So that's how right so this here so this
so the sets of natural number that is
bounded by that right that's like a
finite set so you just take the max of
soup or whatever the max of that's it
right it's just the max of that's it so
that's a natural number
okay
and now
and now again we
right and then we define. So now we have
the bs
and then again a ends
the a
n are defined to be bn divided by 10 to
the n minus one. Right? Right. And so
again you see that and so right. So now
the first thing you observe is that if n
is equal to one
if n is equal to one then this thing
here is zero so this means this has one
so it's the largest natural number so
that the square is less than two so this
means that bn
so n= to one bn is equal to one and
because this thing here is also
zero. So this the denominator is is one.
So a n a1 sorry a1 is one. b1 is one and
a1 has to be the same as b1. And so
that's also one.
Okay. So that's how it starts.
And now what we want to prove is that um
we want to prove that the sequence a n
is monotm increasing right we want to
prove that a end is monotum increasing
so let's just try to understand that
right and so again for mono increasing
you just need to compare two consecutive
elements right so so we want to show
so so this here remember that there's a
kind of you know there's ways to write a
formal proof and then there's like
things you have on the scrap paper to
get the idea. So this is would be what
we're going on may maybe the first
statement is so we want to show this you
could certainly put as part of the proof
want to show
that
a n is less or equal to a n + one
and so this is equivalent
to
that right? So a n since a n here is
equal to bn / 10 ^ n minus 2. You want
to prove that this thing here is less
than a n + 1 which is b n + 1
over 10 to the n + 1 - one. So this here
is b n + 1 over 10 uh to the power n.
That's what you want to prove.
So we want to show so so you see that
we want to show so this is what we want
to prove that this thing here is less
than this. If you multiply by 10 to the^
n on both sides then you get over here
and after you reduce it you get 10. So
en so need to show
needs to show
that 10
bn
is less or equal to bn + one
right that's what we need to prove right
and again this just comes from that you
we want to prove forget about the a now
you can just think about that we need to
prove that this in here is less than
this multiply over by 10 to the n on
both sides then there's still 10 * bn
left and here it's just b
okay so we need to show this one here
right and so if I was to write it down I
would probably have some of this on
scrap paper and then I would instead
sort of establish this here first and
then say therefore you know and then
I'll conclude why you So you but but of
course that's not the way you're
thinking about it right I mean you first
try to analyze what you have to prove
and then once you know that then you try
to write it down nicely
okay so so we need to prove this here
and so now
uh right so now the thing is that we
have
we have that so The definition of bn
which is right here that's the
definition of bn but let me copy it over
here. So we know that bn squared is less
or equal to it's the largest integer. So
that you have this in here,
right?
But this means that if you're looking at
10 bn, that's still an integer. And if
you square this here, right? Then this
is the same as 100
times bn squared. And so that's that
actually has to be less than 100 * this.
So this kills those uh I mean so it just
becomes less or equal to two 10 to the
2n
right like that
and this here you can also write as 2
to the 10 * 10 to ^ 2 n + 1 - 2 right
but now you see that bn so this so this
so 10 bn is an integer and it has this
property but bn + one was supposed to be
the largest integer so that the square
here is less than 2 * 10 to to 2 n + 1 -
2 you see that bn + one is a is the
largest one with this property so you
conclude that so since
bn + one is the largest such
and both are integers
and and bn is is an integer
then uh bn + one must be bigger equal to
bn
uh must be bigger than 10 * bn right
and that's exactly what we want to prove
right that that uh bn + one was bigger
than bn.
So we now have that the sequence a
defined this slightly cryptical way but
really it's not I mean it sounds maybe
cryptical but it's just to instead of
using somehow digital numbers you just
multiply you're just thinking about you
want this and that many uh by so uh like
the n is referring to the number of
digits but including the digit that is
for the the point right so it's actually
not very cryptical but it maybe sounds a
little formal here okay so we have a n
is a increasing sequence okay now why is
a n bounded right
so but the a is defined from the bn
so in order to show that a n is bounded
you have to figure out you have to
figure out what is a bound for the BN
right but you have this here bn is the
largest such number if I take if I take
two * 10 ^ n minus one suppose I take
this number here right and I square it
this is a definitely a integer I square
it then I'm getting 4 * 10 ^ 2 n - 2
right so this thing here This here is
the same as over here but it's now four.
So this number here would not be allowed
as a bn. In fact it would be larger than
bn. Right? So this here so bn is less
than 2 to the^ 10 to the n minus one.
Right?
So this means that a n
which is equal to bn over 10 ^ n minus
one but this is now you see less or
equal to two right
so the sequence a n that we have defined
is uh as you would have expected they
are they're increasing because they
really define the way they're really if
you think about it is really defined to
take you know the number of digits sort
of it's going to be like the number of
digits in square roo including the one
the starting one right
so and so
um and so they all are going to be less
than two right okay now
let's try to
Okay.
Right. So now um we have so we have that
a n is an increasing sequence and is
bounded.
So a end here uh is convergent
by the monitor
uh convergence here.
Right? So the a is convergent by the
monotone convergence.
But now if I'm looking at a n squ a n
squ well a n squ it's the same as a end
obviously times a n right but um but um
but uh a n by definition was bn divided
by 10
uh uh 10 to the power uh n - one right
and so I can write like this
10 ^ n minus one and so you see that you
can write this as bn^ squ and then these
here combines to 2 n minus 2 right and
by assumption
if you divide by this here this thing
here is lesser equal to two
so you have that. So you have that a n
converts to a. And if you want to think
about it, you think about this sequence
again.
And so now you know that a n by this uh
by the product rule for sequences a n
times a n the sequence times itself is
converging to a n square a square.
Right?
And this thing here because they are
because each of these squares here each
of them is less or equal to two then the
limit must be lesser equal to two.
What I want to prove now is that this a
that we get as a limit that the square
is in fact equal to two. So I want to
show that it's the square is so I have
so I have so you know when we're doing
it this this is one more proof of that
square root of two is a real number but
this is sort of in a way how you think
about it in terms of the uh decimals
right
and so we have this sequence a n and we
have proven that it's converging to some
a and we've shown that this a here has a
property that is lesser a squ is lesser
equal to true. So I want to prove so I
want to show
that a and
that sorry that a squ is actually equal
to not one but two right that's what I
want to prove right and but I already
proven that a squ is less or equal to
two so enough
to show
that a squ is bigger = to
okay so let's try to do that
and I'm going to use this is going to be
another illustration of the algebraic
rules for sequences
so
I I haven't really I mean I I here now I
really you know to prove
that is less or equal to two. I didn't
use fully the definition of the A
because I didn't use I didn't really use
that it was the largest such that A was
defined in terms of BN where BN was the
largest such uh such um
such number
and so if I'm looking at
suppose now I'm looking at BN
and I'm adding one
and I'm squaring it. Right?
Well, this here cannot also be smaller
than this here because then then then
the BN should have been this thing here,
right? So, this here must actually be
strictly larger than 2 10 ^ 2nus 2.
Okay.
And so now you write,
you know, you just divide by by this
here on both sides. So you have b n + 1
squared and you divide it by 10 to the
power 2 n - 2. So you know that this
thing is bigger than two.
So now but you can write this in here.
This denominator 10 ^ 2 nus 2 you can
write as 10 ^ n -1 * 10 ^ n minus one.
So in this way you can split this up and
you can write it as bn + 1 over uh 10 ^
n minus one
and then times itself.
This is is just to make sure that it's
not
it's BN and then to the BN you're adding
one.
So like that
you write like that.
But you see this thing here, this is
this here, this thing here. You can
split the fraction up. You can write it
as bn
uh over 10 ^ n minus one. And then you
can add 1 / 10 ^ nus1
and then you can multiply that by
itself. Right? You can write it like
that.
Right? But now now
you see now I can write this in here
as
so now I can think about it in a
slightly different way. So I have that.
So so I can write this thing here. This
thing here is just that is the
definition of a n.
Right?
So I can say so what I have here is that
a n + 1 / 10 ^ n minus one times itself
but I'm I would just write it nicely out
like this
that this thing here remember the way
the it go that this is equal to that
which is bigger than one two so this
here is bigger than two
right Now 10 1 / 10 to the n you can
think about that as a sequence right you
can think about this as a sequence that
sequence go to zero this here goes to a
the sum of these two sequences by the
algebraic rules go to the sum of the
limits so this is a plus zero so that's
a so this thing here goes to a and and
this is the same so this goes to a so
you see that the limit here then goes to
by the product rule for the limits. The
limit here is so you get that a squared
here and since it holds for each element
then it also holds for the limit right
except you had to be a little bit
careful it's may not be strict
inequality but just big or equal to and
of course in fact it is by equal to
because now you have established the
other inequality that a^2 was bigger
equal to 2. We had already proven that
a^2 was less or equal to two. So you
conclude that a^2 is equal to two.
If you kind of just think about it, this
is really how it sounds maybe a little
bit convoluted, but it's really kind of
writing down precisely what you think
about when you're singing about a square
root of two because you think about the
number of digits. And so if you take,
you know, including the first the one in
1.4 four B including that one. If you
think about the number of digits
like the A N then the A end is really
defined if you were to make it precise
you would define it in terms of this
other sequence BN. Okay.
Okay. So now the next thing is so this
was just like
a little illustration of how the mono
convergence theorem worked.
and and and and then and we this will
you know play an important role next
time we Yeah.
>> So uh the reason why at the top we have
like strictly greater than two and then
at the bottom we have greater or equal
to because the a and the a limits
whereas on the top we're considering
each element.
>> So so this um the a
this you were talking about this here
right?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the a n converts to a right
this here you I think about this here.
So think about a sequence plus another
sequence, right? This sequence here
converts to zero, right? So the sum of
these two sequences converts to zero.
And likewise for this and then I'm
thinking about it as a product of this
sequence with that sequence. And so but
but it's like each element is in that in
this in the product sequence is strictly
bigger than two. But it doesn't
necessarily mean that the limit is
strictly but the limit has to be bigger
than two, right? Because they could kind
of approach two and that's exactly what
happened of course. Yeah.
Uh okay. So and and so I also just want
to say that this with lee soup and le
mint well we didn't actually define it
but I defined you know and this is it is
how you defining but but we haven't
talked about that concept yet but this I
talked about with that if you take a
boundary sequence then you could form
two mono sequences this this will play a
really important role for several things
this is how one define the soup and the
min haven't talked about those yet. It's
also going to be used
to prove an important theorem really
important theorem and that's what and
that I will talk about that theorem next
but we won't prove it before next time.
So what is what is that stuff going to
be used
and and and how does the monotone in
what is another application and in fact
there'll be several other applications
of the monotone convergence theorem
but so here is um here's a really
important concept
and so sometimes it's hard to you know
in in if it was a monotom sequence then
you could kind of write down explicitly
what the limits were, right? And in all
of the examples we saw so far, it was
easy to write down the limits, but in
general,
you might not be able to write down the
limits, but you want to prove that the
limit exists. And so, this is the
following notion that is then becomes
really handy, and that's a notion of a
cushy sequence.
So what is a cushy sequence? So a cushi
sequence. So it's a sequence a sequence
with the property
that
for all
epsilon greater than zero there exist
n
there exist a natural number n
such that
if n and m are bigger than this natural
number
then the
two elements a n and and a m are less
than epsilon apart.
So like the so this is a different
notion than convergence. Convergence
say that if you that a sequence is
convergent if everything kind of far out
accumulates around the limit. Right?
This here say that that and
and of course it will. So this has say
that if you that a cushie sequence
that's a sequence so that if you are far
out then syncs a bunch together
basically right now of course we will
prove and so we prove for the on r
we will prove that the cy sequence
so we prove
that
so we prove the following
um
put for
that that's on R but everything is on R
at the moment uh that any that a
sequence
is a cushy sequence
if and only if
only if it is
convergent.
Okay, I won't prove this now but but
I'll prove this next time
and and again the proof of this involve
this stuff with we define these two
sequences from a bounded sequence. So it
it would be useful there. Um
uh now let me give you some examples. Um
so one uh one uh
one um example and the thing is that
that and we'll get to that later but as
at the moment we talk everything is in R
and then we will later generalize this
right and so to generalize this a lot of
these concepts work much more general
and and that's extremely useful and Um
and it can be used to
find solutions to differential equations
but uh and but then you have to abstract
these concepts. So uh to where sequences
are not anymore real numbers but they
are of some other space and then you
have to talk about convergence etc.
And so you can use this to to define um
solutions to def to show that various
differential equations
uh have solutions. Okay. And so that
often goes over using what's called the
contracting mapping the
mapping.
and and the contracting mappings
theorem, you know, have all kind of
forms and uh the but they're all, you
know, it's just a matter of what space
you're looking at and and so on. Uh but
so we're looking at R here in this case.
And so the contracting mapping theorem,
that's a map is just a it's just a map
here now from R to R.
And that the map is contracting means
that if you take two elements
uh in
uh so it means that sorry T is a
contracting map
is a contracting map
[Music]
if they exist.
[Applause]
And this is really important. C is is
positive. I mean that's not important.
It sort of had to be positive. So that's
but the the the important point is that
C has to be strictly less than one. That
that's a crucial point.
Um and then it then it has a property
that when you apply when you take X and
Y in this in R and you're looking at the
how close X and Y are together. So the
how close that the image
uh under t of x and y how close they are
together
then those have to be some factor and
this is the factor the c is the factor
and that has so they have to come
closer. This is why c have to be
strictly less than one because they have
to come closer. If they come closer by a
factor than the original one was then
then so the contracting mapping theorem
say so this is a contracting map sorry
so a contracting map is a map from R to
R so that there exists some constant
strictly less than one so that for all X
and Y you have that the difference
between the images is this factor that
is strictly less than on with what they
were originally
and so now you get the contracting
mapping theorem and we'll talk about the
proof next time and and again this you
know
you know once you have know the more
abstract concepts then it's quite easy I
mean the proof is going to be the same
etc etc and will give you existence of
solutions to a lot of differential
equation so this is the contracting
mapping term
So it say the following that if
uh t from r to r
is a contracting
Then
then C
has a fixed point.
It has a fixed point.
And this means that t of x is equal to
x. And when you apply this theorem,
the contract. So this is the contracting
mapping. And again, it's crucial that
this C is less than one. That's what
makes everything go. If it's if it was
equal to one, you wouldn't get anything.
Okay? It has to be strictly less than
one.
And this thing here, if you set it up
more generally, you know, if the spaces
are more general than just the real
numbers, then then this here will be
that you have a solution. It it could be
it can be applied to many other things,
but it could be that you have a solution
to a differential equation. This
statement here, you know, is like a
standard application to get solutions to
differential equations and you know, you
can do use for all kind of stuff. Okay.
And so uh so we'll talk about that next
time. Uh and not maybe not the the the I
talk about the contracting mapping the
won't talk quite yet about the
applications.
Any questions?
Okay. Great.