hello everybody we're going to be
looking today at how we can use machine
learning and artificial intelligence in
order to learn more about musical
behavior and music theory and just music
in general our first task is going to be
how do we transform music into formats
that computers can learn from because a
score alone is not something that can be
used for artificial intelligence and so
our first task is going to be
understanding how feature extraction the
conversion of musical scores into
intelligent numerical data how feature
extraction is able to make machine
learning possible so go ahead and load
up juper notebook and follow along as we
do some work with music 21 first
separate from the music 21 machine
learning tool kit and then with music 21
features in order to learn more about
some genres and other ways of
classifying
music so go ahead and start Jupiter
notebook and we're going to create uh
the first step which is to understand
what features are so I'll I know why we
might want to extract them so what is a
feature that's the first thing we're
going to work on feature is something
really really really basic let's say
that we have a piece um will load from
music 21 Corpus our favorite B Corral so
you don't even need to know what comes
up from this Corpus pars BL bwv 66.
six and just to remind yourselves how it
goes here's the
buck so great let's go ahead
and choose a feature from the this um
from this let's do the parts feature and
we'll call it num Parts equals 4 and
let's do the time
signature numerator
feature equal
4 there we've now extracted manually two
features from this
Coral feature extraction is the
conversion of musical elements or any
element but musical feature extraction
is a conversion of musical elements into
single numbers or lists arays vectors of
numbers it is thus the most boring thing
in the world as you've just
seen it is just a bunch of numbers
feature extraction sucks out the
lifeblood of Music it takes everything
that's beautiful in music and turns it
into a bunch of numbers it is the life
sucker it is the zombie of the musical
world
but but there are tons of amazing
machine learning and artificial
intelligence and deep learning
algorithms in the world as far as I know
they all have one thing in common they
only work on collections of single
numbers or vectors of
numbers I'm not a machine learning
expert so maybe there are algorithms
that work on two or multi-dimensional
arrays of numbers that would be amazing
for Machine Vision or what we do but
nothing as far as I know in the
artificial intelligence World works on
things
like this
notation or
[Music]
sound so if we're going to work on doing
artificial intelligence or predictions
or anything super amazing on music
notation at least at present we need to
convert music to
numbers so that's what feature
extraction is basic feature extraction
is pretty
simple so in this case let's just
extract
automatically the meter from this piece
so we'll uh write something that does it
we'll import from the typing module
because we like to do things like this
turn python which is a weakly typed
language into slightly stronger typed so
that we can um understand a little bit
better um what's going to go on so we'll
also import from music 21 the meter and
stream modules now let's write something
called
extract extract meter which takes in a
variable score which is a
stream. stream object maybe it should be
a stream. score object but let's keep it
flexible and it returns a tupple of two
integers and we'll say here that returns
a two tle of the
numerator and
the
denominator of the first time
signature
siger found in a
score returns 0 comma 0 if the score has
no meter why do we return 0 comma 0 if
there's no meter in feature extraction
it's generally assumed that we want to
return out of bound number rather than
raising exception if there's a
mistake and the reason is you'd hate to
be running extract meter on hundreds or
thousands of pieces and you're always
getting 4 comma 4 or 3 comma 4 or 6
comma 8 or even something wacky like 11
comma 32 and you it's all working
successfully only to have your entire
feature construction artificial
intelligence pipeline fail if there's
one piece that doesn't have a time
signature like let's say it's Gregorian
chant or some kind of trans
meditation so that's why we're going to
be putting returning 0 comma 0 on the
other hand maybe it's a bad assumption
and we should raise exceptions when
something's not right and then we should
fix our work rather than hiding
errors but we'll get to that in just a
bit first meter but first let's see how
we do this so let's just remind
ourselves we can take from anything get
Elements by class meter. time
signature and if we do not have the any
the first meter will
return 0 comma
0 and otherwise we'll return the first
meters numerator and the first
meters
denominator we're kind of hiding an
error in our encoding um is that the
right thing to do and I think this is
something that when we're talking about
it and I would love to talk to anybody
directly about about ethics and morality
and sort of what who artificial
intelligence is working for because I
think there are often important
considerations of artificial
intelligence with moral and ethical
consequences when we hide things that it
can't do and so I want you if you're
going to be somebody who's going to be
working with artificial intelligence and
the rest of your life and Technology to
think about such things maybe we
shouldn't be hiding our error so
much okay so we have this extract meter
to get back to this whoops um doesn't
matter if you put a parenthesis around a
tupple when you return it but if you
start with one you have to do the other
okay so let's take this B Corral and
let's run extract
meter on the B
oh0 comma 0 oh I know why because we
forgot to do
recurse you know flat would do just as
well but recurse is a little bit faster
and oh by the way something I didn't
mention uh you might have seen that
we're sending in the class actual class
meter. time signature we could also put
in the um strin time signature doesn't
matter either way there um but this
actually doesn't get us the first meter
this gets us all the meters and so if
there are no
meters that says if there's not a single
one return that we'll call First
meter the first of all meters so of
course it's number zero now that's
should be there now extract meter Bo
fantastic returns four comma
4 so why would we want to extract the
meter as two numbers as part of future
extraction we might do it as part of a
series of features in order to make a
prediction about a piece let's say we
wanted to predict if a piece of music is
a waltz or not so we might first think
is this a
waltz or is this a Walts
[Music]
is this a
Walts so what makes something a Walts
well it probably has something to do
with a meter we fortunately already have
a meter extraction for types cure for
the piece and now we can use this to try
to figure out if something is a Walter
not so we would assume that the
prevailing time signature in a piece and
the opening time signature in a piece if
it's a Walt would be 34 and therefore
our extraction should be 3 comma
4 that is the worst assumption ever the
most famous Walts of all time Johan
truss's blue Dan Waltz which you just
heard doesn't start in 34 it starts with
a slow introduction in 68
time I happen to have a random Waltz on
my computer it's Yan strauss's Waltz
called on the blue denu it's not in the
music 21 Corpus but it's instead on my
hard drive on my desktop so I'll need to
import the converter module from music
21 I mean it's just a wrapper around
loading things and stuff and now instead
of using Corpus parse I'll use converter
dopar I'll give um the full file name to
file path to my um to my
Walts it's a music XML
file oh great so the guy who's making
this recording just goes online grabs a
random music XML copy of the blue danu
from the
internet and this version skips the
introduction completely so it has 34
when it should have gotten 68 so it's
going to get the right answer but for
all the wrong reasons have you ever
heard the expression goo garbage in
equals garbage
out let's not do that in our own work
what we're learning from in this
tutorial let's instead make the world of
artificial intelligence a better place
and always check whether our training
data is correct whether this is actually
a score of the Blue danu rather than
just the main theme of it let's check
things like this before we use
it great so it's in 34 so our extract
meter function is going to return 34
let's try that
oops sorry don't give the answer give
the question there we go so now we have
our first feature that might help
identify a Walt it's Tim
signature now let's do something a
little bit more advanced and let's let's
look at this piece and see H is there
anything that seems to happen pretty
often well it looks like the last beat
beat three of the piece or offset two is
more often higher than offset one I
don't know if that's true but that that
looks like something that's a
possibility so we'll create sort of a
more sophisticated feature extractor
which uh Returns the proportion of all
the measures where beat 3 is above beat
1 first we'll make the assumption that
beat 1 is always at offset zero and beat
3 is at offset to these aren't very good
assumptions uh but maybe together with
searching for meter they'll too will
make a good case for whether something
is a waltz or not so here we go uh if
we're going to we're going to eventually
write something uh proportion uh prop
proportion of
bat3 above beat one which is going to
take a score stream stream and it's
going to return a float because it's a
proportion and I'll just say pass now
because in order to write this of of
course uh we're going to need something
that figures out for any given measure
if beat 3 is above beat
one for a single measure for one measure
so we'll take an M which will be a
stream. measure and this is going to
return true or false oops it's going to
return true or false someday we going to
have an incredible production crew
that's going to edit out all these
mistakes but I don't have that yet so
we'll say that measures notes are get
all the elements by class note and that
returns this stream iterator for now I'm
going to say recast that stream iterator
as another stream uh you can do this
with any of the get something bu
something uh classes in music 21 great
so within this is now a stream of just
nothing but notes and so I can say the
first notes are those notes
that appear at an offset
zero and if there's no note there return
fulse great now we'll check bat3 notes
are those
notes
that are at offset 2 and that began at
offset 2 so that should work pretty well
and if there's no note
that satisfies that
condition we're going to return false
again but what if there is more than one
note at the beginning of the measure or
at
bat3 so we have to make sure that first
note is the first of the beat3
notes and the beat3 note not is the
first of the beat3 notes not the third
the first now we'll go ahead and say if
the first note pitch is lower and we're
going to measure the pitch by pitch
space or midi number uh is less than the
beat3
notes pit space will return false
otherwise we're going to return true
um great we'll let's be good we'll make
this a second thing we'll put cut and
paste that there Meanwhile we're going
to um let's write a little test on this
so we have blue um let's get measure
zero so
m0 actually it's measure one so blue.
measure one and we'll
see is
beat3 above beat 1
oops
little elements
you so this
fight this is why we test things great
is beat three above beat one in
measure one actually is
huh oh I know what it is we have a
reverse of a sign it if this pitch is
greater than or equal then we returned
false actually if it's yeah the equal
sign there and now that's working
measure two should be true also measure
three should be false let's make sure
that
works yep and false great so that seems
to be working um here's the irony uh
actually except for the fact that our
label would be completely wrong uh
having every single thing that should be
false be true and true be false probably
wouldn't change our answers very much
but who knows we call this is beat three
above beat one in one
measure it better do what it says okay
great now we're going to get the
proportion that is U the proportion of
measures in this piece where B3 is above
B1 so
we'll keep track of the total number of
measures equals z the total we'll call
them Walts like measures those where
beat 3 is above beat one we'll call it
zero for every measure in the score
recurse get Elements by class
measure um there's a reason why we'll
use get Elements by class measure
instead of measure 0 1 2 3 so mostly to
do with the fact that sometimes there's
two measure 3es or they're missing
Measure 11 or something like that with
there's measure 5 a and 5B if there's a
first ending or something like that
anyhow so we're going for every measure
we increment the total number of
measures by one and now um we look at
one
measure and we say if that's true then
the total Walts
like measures plus equal one and we're
going to return the
total WTS like measures divided by the
total measures
uh we're coding pretty fast so we'll
just put as a to-do later um what if
there are no total measures always make
sure that we don't do a division by zero
measure uh error but that can be a later
thing so let's check this um
proportion of beat 3
above beat one in the blue danu
26% not really true seems a little bit
low one two
down well we'll check that later turns
out it's not not that bad and BWB U
sorry Buck CL this time it's actually
even a little bit more interesting okay
so in any case this is a feature we've
just defined this particular feature
figures out how often beat 3 is above
beat one great what we can do now is
these are individual features let's
create something that does chains a
whole bunch of features together well
not this one whole bunch of features
we'll
get four features so we'll
say our feature
extractor will take in a
score and it's going to return a tupple
of a string an INT an INT a float and a
b end okay what the heck what are these
things going to be so first what we're
going to do is we're going to take in
score and we're going to
um well we're going to say the file
name of the score is going to be that
first string um and you can get the file
name from any music 21 core by getting
his file path which is a path lip and
getting the name which gets rid of all
the directories and stuff great so we'll
get the file name of something and we'll
get the next thing we're going to get
these two ins which are going to be the
meter so we'll say the meter
feature is where I get that from
extract extract meter on that
score next we're going to get this float
which is going to be the beat 3
feature so we'll get the beat3
feature is the proportion propor sh why
do I keep doing this beat three above
beat one for that score great super oops
I hit shift enter then we want to get
the Boolean what we're going to do is if
we're training a data set we're going to
know whether or not something is a waltz
so we'll say that Boolean is going to be
true or false on whether something is a
waltz and so we could say is
Waltz
equals if true if Waltz is in the file
name or if lowercase vaults is in the
file
name file name so then we know the file
name numerator and
denominator a float of the proportion
beat3 and whether or not science Walts
this last particular um thing we'll some
call this instead of is Walter sign
we'll use generic term ground truth
we'll also see it called the class so
whether it's belongs to the waltz class
or not so we can call it Walt or non-
waltz or true false something like that
now we want to return all these things
as a tupple so tuples are created
with a comma or with a parenthesis so
we'll use the parenthesis the file name
the meter features first argument which
is the numerator meter
features second argument which is the
denominator the beat3
feature and the ground
truth so let's see we'll run this
feature ex let's call extractor let's
call
snap it properly F feature extractor on
the blue denu
and uh I still didn't spell it right why
do I copy and paste there we
go oh we can see blue Denny Waltz was in
three
four 26% has this beat proportion and
true it is a Walt let's run our feature
extract
Tour on BW on
B we'll see file name 44 35 false
great So eventually we would want to
have a computer system that can
distinguish between one up between a
waltz and not by learning all this
information
unfortunately I don't have enough waltes
in my data set to do this so we're going
to move to the next best thing we're
going to get a jig so let's go ahead and
um and grab a particular jig we have all
of these jigs in this um in this data
set which is really useful for people to
know it's called
Ryan's uh
Mammoth
collection it's for 19th century thing
you can look it up it's very famous hi I
wanted to jump in for a second and say
something about this collection I'm
planning on not using it again soon
since I made this video I've realized
that within Ryan's Mammoth collection
there is a lot of what are called
minstral songs that is songs that were
performed um in the style of negro
Melodies but by uh by white performers
often in blackace and with texts which
are not included in this collection
thank goodness but with texts that uh
denigrated uh Black Americans and black
experience so I'm going to try to uh
change this example as soon as I can and
my apologies
for what I didn't know then and what I
know now and what I plan to continue to
do to make computational musicology a
more welcoming
place we're going to be looking at the
blooming Meadows Chi so um let's just
we'll load that um
blooming Corpus
pars blo Meadow jig don't need the ABC
you can leave it in however you want
let's look at
this in case you haven't seen a jig in a
while it's kind of helpful for
understanding so
jig we speaking of 68 we got these
violin bow marks we could use that as a
feature extractor if it has violin
markings it's more likely to be a jig if
it doesn't it's less likely lots of Bo
pieces of violin bow marks the boach
violin part just they're not all jigs
but you know so it's not going to be
perfect but all these things kind of
help but maybe that meter extractor 68
is going to be a little bit
helpful so I happen to know that this
little piece is a jig it's kind of nice
short piece but there's a whole bunch of
things so we're going to get from Ryan
MTH collection and we'll use a different
thing uh that we've used before into
Corpus pars we're going to search
everything for Ryan um I think
everything in there is uh is part of
this Ryan's mavi collection and we'll
see that within Ryan there's going to be
quite a number of pieces
1,63 you'll see the first time you use
Corpus search you um it takes some time
but you can um you can use after the
after you do it once it's often quite a
bit faster super
fast there we go okay so we're going to
um have use that beat3 feature why not I
mean we already have a feature and we're
going to use the meter feature but let's
use one more thing I've heard that jigs
tend to come in a
few in a few Keys a few key signatures
um maybe one flat one sharp you know
they don't tend to come in five flats
that's kind of a hard thing for violin
so let's go ahead and create um a sharp
extractor so we'll call it uh we just
called get
Sharps because we'll just remind
ourselves that feature extractor is
nothing more than something that takes
in a score some other piece of data and
returns numbers in this case an integer
uh we'll just TR put a try thing we'll
return the score we're going to go
through
it
recurse get all the elements okay use
plural This Time by class key
signature get the first one and return
the number of Sharps remember if it's
two Flats Sharps will be -2 and in case
we can't find it uh might be an index
error because uh there's zero um you can
always in your own code that you don't
turn in um and you don't put sign there
you can just say except all
errors return zero let's double check
this um do we call it yeah
blooming
Sharps
blooming get one let's remind ourselves
blue denu should also be one
great and that Bo piece should be
three super okay so that seems to work a
little bit now let's write our feature
extractor or our multifeature extractor
never really sure if our if feature
extractor just refers to sign that gets
one feature like get sharps or sign that
gets a whole bunch features people
aren't really clear on that so we're
going to return again the string it's
going to be the file name uh two
integers for the metered mearian
denominator pretty important float for
that kind of silly uh beat3 thing but
we'll add one more integer on
um whether or not um yeah on the number
of Sharps and instead returning a
Boolean at the end we're going to switch
this last little thing to returning an
integer for whether or not something is
a jig the ground truth and it's because
most of the machine learning toolkits
really
um like working with numbers so might as
well make our ground truth a number uh
make a file name the file path name
again as before you don't really need
that there but it's going to be really
helpful for figuring out why something's
working or what particular pieces are
wrong or right IOP I still had propor
shot in my uh we in my clip board but
okay so proportion B3 above B1 I always
hit shift enter too early Sharps feature
is better be get Sharps from score add
our ground truth this case we said it's
going to be an integer so we'll say int
jig in file name or jig in file name two
things to know one python int on true on
int on true returns one int on false
returns zero in fact uh in earlier
versions of python true and false were
just kind of aliases for one and zero
thankfully that's a little bit better uh
the other thing is again this what we've
learned about garbage in garbage out I
don't actually know if every single
thing in uh this collection that has a
word jig in its title is a jig and I
definitely don't know that there's every
piece in this collection that isn't a
jig or that is a jig has jig in the
title or that yeah that there might be
jigs that don't have jig in the the
title just as most rag rags in rag time
in Scott Joplin have rag in their title
Maple Leaf Rag so on but some of them
don't the Entertainer is a rag it
doesn't have rag in his title so so our
ground truth isn't exactly the world's
gospel truth this is something that that
people neglect all the time in machine
learning they keep training the computer
to replicate
truths that aren't necessarily true and
you'll see this all over the place I was
just working with uh Master student on a
project where we're trying to train
Optical music recognition to produce the
exact ground truth that we had found
encoded the thing is the ground truth
had lots of Errors too so that's theci
to know anyhow getting back to what are
we going to return take a second see if
you can figure this out based on what
we've said return value is and what
we've defined here great so we're going
to return the file name meter
feature zero meter feature one P3
feature Sharps feature and the ground
truth
great okay so now we just need to
iterate over everything I want to show
something when you iterate over a corpus
search object object there's this thing
called a metadata bundle that is to say
you haven't actually parsed 1,63 pieces
it just knows about the existence of
1,63 pieces so when we say for um bundle
in
Ryan we can print the
bundle and we can see that we have all
of these um different Ines for
pieces so what we'll do go ahead and do
is instead of um getting but not actual
pieces so to get the pieces we can say
um piece pars equals bundle actually we
call it to bundle say metadata
entry since out in there metadata entry
in Ryan
entry piece pars is the metadata entry.
parse that's going to take some
time then we're going to print out the
feature extraction
on the piece
pars you're going to learn to use this
little button in a second because the
stop button because it's going to take
some time if you hit run but you're
going to have to do it in a little bit
oops feature extractor used to call it
feature extraction but that
and extract meter exact meter extract
meter here we go so we're going to put
this back here and uh let's go ahead and
run this
oops oh my goodness I cannot spell
anything today okay here we go let's go
ahead and runting this it shows that
adil's hornpipe is I don't know this
piece but it's in
22 really seldom does beat three um is
uh was offset two higher than offset one
wow that is really really low and um
it's in one sharp oh good Flats do work
and it is zero it is not a jig it is a
hornpipe I know we all know these
differences between reels and hornpipes
and Jigs and all these things um well
maybe some of us got our Pirates like
okay we can see here Bano o barley meal
jig uh which is in
68 has this feature it's in two sharps
and there's a one here so is a jig so
that works pretty well and we can scroll
all the way through wow there's a lot of
pieces okay great and some of them are
jigs some of them are
not okay so now we've extracted all this
data if we put all of this into some
sort of file somewhere um we will have
it all done so I'm going to take a two
second break and show how we move from
feature abstraction to machine
learning okay one of the most important
things we're going to be thinking about
when we think about machine learning is
that we're going to be training the
computer on a certain set of data
training our algorithms training our
neural networks or whatever artificial
intelligence and machine learning
algorithm we choose to use on some
portion of the data and then we want to
see how good is the computer doing so
we're going to hold out some portion of
the data to be our test to see well if
the training data is somewhat like the
test data but the computer seen the
training data and it hasn't seen the
test data how well does it learn from
the training data in order to make um
identifications in the test data and
there are lots of different ways of
doing this please take a machine
learning class take an artificial
intelligence class so you can learn
about one hold out out cross validation
or on10th uh hold out lots of different
ways that we can do this better than
what we're going to do but instead for
now to make things very simple for those
who for whom this is going to be your
first introduction to artificial
intelligence and machine learning what
we're going to do is we're going to
divide all of our training data into two
parts all of our data into half of it as
the test data and half of it as the
training data and I'm just going to go
through and almost always do everything
in up this one to test this one training
this one test this one training it's
just going to make things easier but
there are better ways to do
it not for now let's get to some
artificial intelligence and machine
learning okay let's go ahead and and
open up two files for writing I'm going
to call
them uh they're on my desktop o now you
know my secret secret path um we'll call
it train data. tab we're going to open
this for writing and we'll call it as
training if you're not familiar with
python um file handles please take a
second to look this up because otherwise
this won't make much sense but
essentially we're going to have um two
files so we're going to be able to write
two going back and forth one versus the
other there's going to be better ways of
doing this but this how we're going to
do it first okay we're going to need to
say uh for a lot of various algorithms
we're going to need to be able to say
what our column names are so we'll say
our columns are going to be a series of
tab separated values so that's what
these tab files are going to be series
of tab separated values that join these
um titles file
name numerator doesn't matter what these
are called
denominator beat3 proportion I'm not
going to make myself type that again and
we'll say is jig at the end for a ground
truth fantastic okay those are columns
and first I'm going to do is write to
each of our
different
files write our columns with a line
break at the
end go testing is going to write columns
with a line break at the end great now
we want to describe what kind of value
what kind of value um will a machine
learning toolkit expect to get from file
name uh stram numerator integer beat3
float things like that so we'll say our
descriptions are going to be and these
are pretty standard formats but they're
not python so look at this it's not Str
it's string and we'll say that our
integers are discrete data with a I not
discrete like indiscrete
but okay I won't make a joke but discret
like integer values uh but beat3 data
can be continuous it can be 1.2 1.21 so
on and then another discrete data for
the number Sharps and then for is J it's
also it's 01 so it's going to be
discrete data fantastic we're going to
write
these to these files the descriptions
also boom okay
great this um we also tend to put these
meta variables in and they say um if
anything is special if anything is
unlike the rest well the ones that are
special is the first thing string is
just a meta data that is to say it just
means um something so that we can more
easily diagnose uh problems and look
things up later we don't actually need
it we're not going to study the file
name um and then these are just normal
things numerator denominator beat three
number of Sharps and then at the very
end the final thing is our class the
thing that's we're trying to learn we're
trying to learn does this
information
98.1
11112 describe a jig or not the class of
objects that is a jig great so these are
our meta variables and we're going to
write them to again our see do I still
have that
no going to write that to our training
and to our testing
great um here I can kind of do this
anyhow we can
cat that file this is a um these magic
things are stuff you can do in Jupiter
that you can't in normal python um but
it'll see train
data tab yep we can kind of see what
we've written out there okay great now
we're going to take this and we're going
to write more things it we're going to
write to um these into these two files
information about from our feature
extractions so we're going to go back
for each piece in ryion um
enumerate Ryan um and enumerate says our
first thing goes into piece and we'll
call it I actually we'll not call it
piece we'll call it uh metad data entry
great
uh we'll say piece pars is our
metadata entry
parse great and our
features are our featured
extractor on pie
pars pie pars and now we're going to uh
create make a string out of that feature
string equals tab separated version of
the string value of each element for the
element in features okay yeah we should
call it
f
fantastic and if I is
even no if I is odd uh we'll write it to
the training
data with uh new
line and
otherwise we'll write it to the testing
data with a new line great hopefully I
didn't type anything wrong we'll find
out in a
second great it seems to be working it's
slow one of the things I'm going to
eventually learn is that everything's
slower when I'm screen recording so uh
we could see that yep there's a bunch of
of things in here most important one can
we get a jig good it has a one at the
end if it's a jig zero at the end if
it's something else oh these jigs are 68
oh look there's a jig it begins in 98 so
maybe it's the eight that's more
important I don't know we'll see if the
computer can figure this out uh we don't
need to look at all 1,000 entries
Jupiter does a nice way of not putting
that all together okay great so now we
have something that we can feed into an
artificial intelligence classification
program so we don't have one so we're
going to write one of our own so we're
going to say neural network ah just
kidding no that's not what this class is
about that's other classes we're going
to install one so go ahead and install
Orange 3 which is a really great pass
package oh hey I already have installed
yours probably takes a little bit longer
than that great
super so now I have orange 3 um orange 3
names it stuff kind of funny um so I
always because I've been using it for a
long time I just imported it it's not
Orange 3 let's call it orange great now
what we're going to do is we're going to
load in our training
data from an orange data table based on
that information
so train data.
tab uh I reverted myself to using camel
case things I probably shouldn't but I'm
not going to
rewrite everything now though it doesn't
look like much but I have a lot in my
sleeve okay so we're going to load those
two great um we can look at train data
little bit yep whole bunch of stuff uh
these are I think map plot live is type
things okay great so what we want to do
is um create a bunch of Learners things
that can classify and understand data
and try to make guesses about things our
first learner is kind of like the
placebo of Learners uh it's called the
majority learner uh and there's other
ways of doing this but we'll use this
one
and the majority learner is um is is
pretty cool it just looks at the data it
um it looks at what we put in the
training data and it says you know what
there's about three times as many things
that are not jigs as there are jigs so I
can get three out of four right if I
just learn to always vote with majority
I don't know anything about music but
I'll just say I'll always say that's not
a jig and you know what I'll usually be
right um so never classify things
according to hey uh is this right or
wrong you know did did it get it right
more than half the time no classify how
you're doing against did it do did it do
better than the majority learner
correct um you're going to now if you
don't know what this is we're going to
learn what um in uh uh K nearest
neighbors is KNN learner uh
classification
KNN learner and this is a pretty
standard artificial intelligence
learning algorithm um and so I'm not
going to say too much about that so we
have we create a kind of learner thing
and our classifier is a learner that's
been that's going to work on a
particular set of data our training data
okay good so we create a learner create
a classifier hasn't actually learned
anything yet but it's going to be ready
for for doing that okay
um now we're going to check how often
does the majority learner get things uh
how many times does it get it correct
and how many times does um the kers
neighbors learner get things
correct and how many total things are
there
uh we get that as I need floats still
thinking too much how to think like
python
Tu so how many test data there
are go ah and see okay 532 in the test
data the training data does not need to
be exactly the same size or even close
the same size as the test data
but in this case they are great so now
we're going to iterate through each of
the rows
um of um of our test data not our
training
data so we're going to know what row
number we are on I and then test row and
then the majority learner is going to
make a guess based on the data in the
test row wh the majority learner is
really stupid so its guess is always
going to be it's not a jig then Ker's
neighbor is going to make a guess and
we're hope that K's neighbor is making a
guess based on some intelligence that it
has or fake intelligence I mean it's
called artificial intelligence for a
reason and then we get to see in this
case what the actual answer is with the
class whether it's a jig or not so
that's our real answer so we know this
but K nearest neighbor is not allowed to
look at this we really hope the
computer's not peing uh otherwise all
artificial intelligence is kind of
screwed okay we'll just print out some
test data that um the
row I is
uh a little bit of the information about
our set that should be good gri will'll
print out that the answer to row I
is
jig
give whe
answer I think that works else not
check
and and then we'll put in a tab we'll
say k neighbor got it right or wrong
correct right if k&n's if the K nearest
neighbor's guess is the same as the real
answer else
wrong that's some pretty tough stuff
Oran can't even get that right good
okay um we'll print a blank line after
that if the majority guesss if the
majority guessed
right then the majority correct
INR if k n
neighbors guess is
right so we're just checking at this
point how how good is this cares
neighbors correct okay this going to be
one
bigger
great so we'll go ahead and let that run
oops uh claes are very nice oops they
screw siging up
um oops there we go uh I have to cast
this as a list because where is it this
data can't be sliced but lists can okay
so that going on you know I probably
need to reset my data so let's go ahead
and do that it's going to be printing
cool not jig K neighbors got it wrong
not jig Kors got it right good good so
hey see a lot of got it right I like
that I like that okay here's the Moment
of Truth um without machine
learning there's a majority learner
majority
correct always put things into um into
uh percentages always round your
percentages toci reasonable nobody wants
to see all those dangling digits okay so
it got that number right and we'll say
with K andn Machine learning we got the
KNN correct how well do we
do without machine learning got it 77%
right K nearest neighbors got it 95%
right wow okay that's pretty awesome
that's a lot better than I thought when
I um when I thought I would do this um
by the way one of the things we can do
you you probably want to keep track of
your uh of your data and don't um don't
do this but we'll just go ahead and
check does it make a difference if we
swap the training and the test
data oops not training data training
data do we get a fluke
and we can go ahead and
run 72 and 94 so yeah still pretty good
doesn't matter which one we do I'm going
to switch that back because I will
totally uh make that mistake but yeah so
we're doing really well with this so
this is how you can do artificial
intelligence with machine
learning but that's been a little bit
hard so
fortunately music 21 has some tools to
make a lot of these things even easier
here so music 21 feature extraction will
be the last topic that we're going to
talk about
today so we can go ahead and import from
music 21 the features
module great so within the features
module there are things called data sets
so let's create um um training
set which will be a data set um with a
class label of is jig we call ground
trth or whatever and we'll create an
identical one U for our test
set testing set great so these are just
um things that are ready to
add two important things a set of data
that is Stream So a whole bunch of
streams uh will be added to both the
training and the test set and also a set
of feature
extractors I'm not going to explain
today how to write new feature
extractors in the way music 21 expects
them but they're basically pretty
similar to what we've just been writing
with functions except they're kind of
expected to be
classes but we don't really have to
because music 21 has a whole bunch of
features
extractors some of them come from this
amazing toolkit called J symbolic or the
reinterpretations of Corey McKay's J
symbolic toolkit which is in Java and um
they have numbers like D1 is the overall
dynamic range features not all of them
have been implemented um eyes are
instrument features you can probably see
that um the percentage of all notes
being played by electric guitars
if you know something about jigs is
probably not going to be very helpful to
um to classifying whether or not
something is a jig but maybe the average
melodic interval will tell you something
like that or how often there are melodic
thirds or melodic fifths or maybe you
know other things might tell sign so
these are Melody features pitch features
and so on um there's Rhythm features
that's going to be pretty important um
uh where do we have r31 initial time
signature feature R32 compound or simple
meure features and so on so we could add
a bunch of these features in and we
remember the names and within the music
21 documentation there will be um
certain things that will tell you you
know uh triple meter features set to one
if the numerator of the initial time
signature is three or zero otherwise and
this shows you how how it can work um so
we can give a particular piece and it
will tell us that BWB 66.6 is zero not
in triple meter okay um we've already
done something really really great um
and so I will tell you that if we use
this very similar feature extractors the
ones we did before we're going to get
the same um the same results but one of
the other things we can do is we can
just use a whole bunch of pretty random
ones so we'll get um these features by
ID and these are a bunch of features
that I used to classify um various
pieces of I think it was 16th 15th
century music no 16th century music so
they're not exactly super tuned for what
we're going to do um um a lot of them
are melodic features and so on uh well
you see scroll over see which ones
haven't done pitch features pitch
feature
10 R up
feature wa we guys see what they
are I'm already going to tell you uh no
surprise these aren't going to work
nearly as well as the ones we just made
um note dens feature isn't going to help
us very much I would have thought range
might have told us something about a jig
but maybe it's not um some people will
tell you hey just throw lots of feature
extractors in um it can't hurt it kind
of can but because we often don't have
enough data to make use of all these
features but let's give it a shot we're
going to add these feature
extractors to um our training set and to
to our testing
set okay so our training set and testing
set any uh is now ready to go where any
stream we add to these sets we're going
to um going to have these feature
extractors added to them so we'll say is
for I add metad dat entry in a
numerate
uh Ryan again P's part
equals metad dat
entry.
parse if I is odd then training or test
will be we'll we'll set um so we only
have to write things once we'll set our
training or test set will be the
training set in this case otherwise our
training or test will be our testing
set great uh file name is the pie PAR
file path name is jig same thing we were
doing
before here we're not going to um music
21 smart enough it doesn't need us to
cast this to an integer that'll figure
out what to do itself
okay we going say what row are we is
this a jig and what's its file name
that's easy part and then whatever
dating data set we're working with
training or test we're going to add
the data from the here's a stream our
score whatever you call it class value
what is what is the right answer it's
whether or not this is a jig and then
the identification for this will be the
file name okay boom it's going to go
through it has 1,000 of these to run so
I'm not going to wait for all of it to
um happen I'm going to stop for a second
um
because we don't have all that time in
the world um that's part of the reason
why we also don't want to do everything
but our that small training set we're
going to process and we're going to take
that training set and write it out to
train
to. no we're not you should do that
because you have time to wait but uh
nobody wants us do that we'll do the
same thing with the testing set process
and then testing set
we're going to write that to test
2.tap I'm not doing that right now
because like they do in those old
cooking shows um I've already done all
this and I'm going to uh load it from
what I've already done
so um you know what I mean the old
cooking shows where they put they put
the turkey raw turkey in the oven and
then they just immediately go to the
other oven and the turkey son. sorry all
right I you know you all can read my
mind right that's that's
what that's what you pay me to do make
you read my mind to not actually
teach that's fantastic um okay a no
enough I'll make this line up so I
don't so I don't make any
typos on my
desktop test 2.tap that's why it broke
okay so again we're going to do
everything as before why do everything
as before when you can't just copy
and because now we've already written
everything out for um yeah this this
whole process and right thing takes care
of everything we did before where we
where is that where we had to Define we
had to open our datas we had to Define
our columns we had to write that out
Define our description write out all our
meta things um extract write our feature
extractors do all that
stuff these little um process and then
write did all that for us so now we're
we're actually back on to
uh uh feature extraction is
done let's do machine learning anybody
who tells you that the machine learn
learning is the only hard part and that
feature extraction uh is easy stuff uh
is lying to you or is doesn't know what
they're talking about or whatever
because um feature extraction and doing
it right is really really hard okay so
we're going to cop basically copy and
paste everything that um that we did
before totals something like
that great we're going to run this
again and then we're going
to print everything
afterwards great and that's going to go
through and uh it's going to print a
couple things what are we
doing oh has to we giving it a lot more
things to train on so a lot more data
these are much bigger files because of
all the different feature extractors so
it takes a while you can see in all this
time it's just done one
row and two rows are we going to wait
for
uh you know oh I think it's like an hour
and a half and I ran this at like 2 in
the morning are we going to wait an hour
and a half we can all do that no I'm
going to hit stop for a second on the
recording and then I'm going to load up
our
results okay here are the results I
got again our majority learner got 77%
right and our K nearest neighbors super
intelligent artificial
intelligence only got 4% better I mean I
don't even know if that meets the margin
of error in a political poll or
something so all that extra time didn't
actually improve anything what's
important is always to choose your um
choose your
feature extractors well the fact that I
didn't include that one simple extractor
about the time signature made all the
difference in the world I think um okay
I just want to show that there's um you
can uh you can print all of the
different features onto various charts
and zoom in and stuff like that if
people want to do that but that'll be
something for another
time this is what is available to you
now um maybe not this kind of low-level
one but using the these feature
extractors simple ones like Sharps and
meter and uh what was that percentage of
compound time range features things like
that in order to classify pieces is
incredibly powerful and when put
together with the right machine learning
and artificial intelligence algorithm
there's a lot of possibilities for the
future of computational Music
analysis this lecture is run pretty darn
long so I'm going to say for a second
little supplement on what are some of
the things that I have learned through
using computational artificial
intelligence what are some of the
projects other people have done and why
the world of the-art blackbox deep
learning or um other sophisticated
algorithms might not always be the best
ones that we want to use when we're
doing artificial intelligence and
machine learning techniques on musical
scores but we'll leave that for another
time thank you so much for listening go
ahead and play around with some data
sets you've learned how to use Corpus
search to be able to find various pieces
on there's a music 21 uh I think chapter
users guide chapter and tutorial on how
to do more interesting things with that
there's the paper written with Chris ARA
and Lisa Friedland on using feature
extractors with music 21 and there's
also some other um music 21 feature
extractor papers that were written with
MIT undergraduate europs on how we can
use feature extraction to go beyond what
we can do with midi to really look at
the Nuance of musical scores in feature
extraction I'll be sending all those
around the meantime please go back
through your the most interesting parts
of this lecture to you hit pause and
play around with your own data
sense good luck in applying this to
Future projects