Hi everyone. Thanks a lot for joining.
Uh it is my great pleasure to introduce
today's speaker, Professor Joshua Yang.
Uh who is the Arthur Freeman Chair
Professor of Electrical and Computer
Engineering at University of Southern
California. Uh Professor Yang joined USC
in 2020 coming from the faculty of the
University of Massachusetts Ammerst
uh specializing in postmos hardware for
neuromorphic computing, machine learning
and artificial intelligence. uh he has
published many groundbreaking research
papers in these domains. Uh and his
innovative work has led to granting of
over 120 US patents. Professor Yang is
the associate editor of science advances
on neuromorphic topics and the founding
chair of the ITE neuromorphic computing
technical committee. He serves as the
director of an air force funded center
of excellence on neuromorphic computing
at USC and he is recognized as a clarate
clarivate a highly cited researcher and
listed among the top best scientist in
the electronics and electrical
engineering category by research.com. He
was elected fellow of the IT in 2020
2022 and of the national academy of
inventors in 2023 for his contributions
to resistive switching materials and
devices for nonvolatile me memory and
neuromorphic computing. So it is
tremendous pleasure to be able to hear
from him today. Thank you for joining us
and we're excited to hear your talk.
>> Thank you. Yeah, thanks uh finance for
the candy invitation and the
introduction and uh good afternoon
everyone. It's great to be here see a
lot of older friends and uh I didn't
expect you know Friday afternoon there
are so many people still interested in
this topic. Thanks for coming. So what
I'm going to talk about uh um neomorphic
computing uh with different type of
memory stores. Okay. So um speaking
about neomorphic computing actually um
one month and a half ago I was in a
conference and during lunchtime I was at
a lunch table with a bunch of editors
from nature research journals. I was
trying to advocate neuromorphic and
trying to talk about how exciting it is,
how promising the future is and then one
of the editor you because camera I'm not
going to name it.
So uh suddenly said um didn't jacoma
indeed just wrote a paper said
neomorphic is dead.
So
I I was said what? By saying that
actually I exposed
my ignorance of two aspect. First I
didn't even know that paper exist.
Second I didn't know why someone like
Jacoma would say something like that. So
then uh after that conversation you can
imagine immed immediately I went to my
hotel room and find out their paper and
here it is
it does say neomorphic is dead and but
it also says long live neomorphic. So if
you read it it says um actually it
blames the recent shift toward digital
and AIcentric approach. In that sense he
think the old um you know definition of
neomorphic is there because they shift
but he blamed this trend and he advocate
um the you know for us going back to the
original um principle of neuromorphic
and emphas emphasizing on analog brain
inspired systems and also the importance
of fundamental neuron science for the
future progress. So basically in that
sense um that's a long live neomorphic.
Okay, it still have a very bright future
if you do it right. Okay, how to do it
right? And if you keep reading and uh at
the beginning he said the term
neuromorphic was originally coined to
directly emulate the bios system not
simulate right and to mimic the dynamics
of iron channels. So after reading to
here then I was much relieved. So
because this is exactly something we
have been doing in the last uh decade.
For example uh starting with this paper
uh we started to advocate that you can
use memorist diffusive dynamics to mimic
um the synapse faithfully
and more recently we did it for neuron.
I I will talk about that later. So
basically it's good. Okay. So neomorphic
is still alive and we can we can talk
about it and do it right. So then what
does neomorphic covers? Um obviously it
will cover uh the natural intelligence
approach. So in this approach you use
spike based signals, you use dynamic
synapse and neurons and you use the
biological learning rules right. Um but
as Jacoma said in his paper and there
are a lot of people also trying to use
neuromorphic to cover other types like
the
uh digital uh AIcentric approach in this
uh category um you are using value based
signal instead of spec you after
training you have a fixed weights and
static neuron and you are using
gradientbased learning um such as
uh back propagation rather than here you
know such as STDP spike time independent
plasticity.
So in this approach
um the mainstream um computing platform
you use uh digital but no architecture
right. So such computing platform
bear almost no similarity to neuronet
network. So in that sense it is a
simulator you know of the neuron
network. It's a um it's a mainstream
though it is something large scale you
can use but it also face the deep crisis
of energy efficiency right and our
long-term goal of course is to have the
natural intelligence emulator right
rather than just a simulator and uh
using analog approach but that is a very
long-term goal you know it's not going
to happen very soon at large scale but
there is a middle stage. So in this uh
middle stage what we can do is we can
use some of the neuron science
principles not all of them but some such
as inmemory computing, analog computing,
parallel computing with only these three
principles for example you can already
get a very efficient AI accelerator.
So to accelerate um those uh computing
and in this case of course you use both
analog and digital it's a mixed signal
system.
So um in the next few slides maybe we
can um first look at uh why this type of
approach the digital mainstream um
platform is uh in trouble and how this
can help and why this you know is the
bright future. So what's wrong with the
digital system? the digital system. The
biggest trouble as everybody here
probably know already the digital
hardware is way behind the demand of um
the AI the algorithm needs as you can
see everybody use as CH GPT I assume
right but do you know um CH GPT is so
power hungry it use 45 gawatt hour daily
for inference so you may say I don't
have no idea what this means actually
this means means 1.5 million household
power consumption daily just okay that
is actually more than 1% of the
household in the US and that will need a
two to three um nuclear plants to power
up just for CHP you know Google has a
Google version and other everybody so
you can imagine um how much uh you know
energy we're going to um put in just
those things so basically in the Last
few years you can see the computing
demand
increased by million times.
But around the same time frame the
hardware improvement represented by the
CP GPU of Nvidia it has made a lot of
improvement but even that allowed is
about 100 you know compared to the
million times demand you have a huge gap
and that gap cannot be met by continuous
increase uh you know the computing
efficiency just along the same direction
using digital system as you can see the
trend Right? So you have to use some
disruptive technology to do that. Okay.
So question is what's wrong with our
digital system and uh and probably
everybody know as you know the the
device level MOS law is coming to an
end. We know that and also there is a
memory war um because the the processor
performance is better than uh memory and
the gap between the processor and memory
is increasing with time not decreasing.
So this is called the memory war. Memory
is the bottleneck. And in addition
the dard scaling law uh has ended a long
time ago. Basically, even if you can
make the device smaller and smaller, you
cram more devices on the chip, but the
power density of the chip is not
constant anymore. It increase
dramatically, which means even you have
a lot more devices on the chip, you
cannot utilize them simultaneously
anyway before you burn the chip. That's
called the heat wall, right? So those
are at the device level. at the
architecture level the challenge is as
big if not bigger that's the phenomenal
bottleneck I think you know a lot of
people um should know here so you know
in your phone your laptop um everything
the stream digital system is bu built
based on the nomad architecture
which means you have a separate
processor from the memory these two are
physically separated you store your data
in the memory when you need a processor
You send it to the processor, get it
processed, you send the result back,
store here, you take the next piece of
information and to the processor to
process, you do it in sequential. And
that was perfectly fine in the past. Uh
when the computing did not involve a lot
of data, but now we know computing are
all pretty much datacentric. So
constantly shuttering data between the
two units takes a lot of time and a lot
of energy.
It's just too much we cannot afford.
That's a a bottleneck called of a no man
bottleneck. And this is a digital
system. Our world um is analog. Our data
from the analog world. You have to
digitize it first then uh process in the
uh digital system. The analog digital
conversion also is notoriously time and
energy consuming. Right? So how to solve
those problems um for the digital
system? So we learn from um something we
know um to be the most energy efficient
computer that's the brain. So then if
you look at the nature then you find a
lot of our problem have been solved um
by you know millions years of evolution
in animals in human being and the
answers um for many problems are already
there right so uh how does the brain um
perform computing it use neuron network
and the network is uh is neurons
connected by synapse and the synapse is
a memory here So store the data in
synapse and the computing is done where
the data is stored. So it is inmemory
computing. So you don't need to shutter
data between the processor and uh um and
uh uh the memory. So that is a very big
deal. It's inmemory computing computing
happens everywhere in parallel. It's a
parallel computing and uh it can deal
with analog data directly. It's analog
computing. So with these three
principles you can build AI accelerator
okay to be very energy efficient high
throughput.
So there is more and the brain is also
known to be much more efficient in
learning. It use much less data much
less energy for learning learn much
faster. It is because brain is using the
neuron science principles for learning.
Okay very different from what we are
using in AI. Um so with those principles
included then you will have something
more like a natural intelligence
emulator right. So to include those
principles um into artificial system we
build we will need to have a new type of
devices rather than just um you know
semos silicon devices. Um so there are a
lot of types u memorist is one of the uh
leading candidate uh we have been
working on um for those who do not know
how memor work it is shown here simp
simplified mechanism you have two
electrode and in the middle you have a
oxide material let's say titanium oxide
which can be viewed as a semiconductor
with um wide band gap okay as a
semiconductor it has its dopend the
dopend here are oxygen and vacancies. So
the doped region are conductive. The
undoped region had a metal semiconductor
barrier shaky like a barrier has uh give
you high resistance. That's why the
entire device now is in the off state.
So the beauty here is um the dopant are
mobile electrically mobile. So you can
use electrical field to move the dopen
and also dope the top region and make
everywhere conductive. then you get the
on state, right? And uh so if you want
to change it back, you reverse your
voltage polarity, you move the oxygen
vacancy dopen back, you get the off
state and you can stop in the middle as
well. Um so the oxygen vacancy is the
doped here, but you can use many other
type of dopend with other type of um
dialectric material to make a memory. Um
so as you can see here um the doped
migration is critical uh for the um
function of such device. So what determs
um uh the doped behavior um largely is
the activation energy. For example, if
you have high activation energy like
oxygen vacancies in oxide, the um
activation energy is high and you need
to pay more energy to move them to
switch the device. And the good thing is
after you switch the device, you move
them, they like to stay there, you know,
in a stable way. Um so that you get
nonvolatility.
So then when you do reset you switch it
back move it back you need to reverse
your voltage polarity you move the ions
back by drift. So that's why we call
this drift memory right. So this type of
device has very stable conductance
levels it can be used to um serve as AI
accelerator I talk about.
So instead if you have a low activation
energy such as silver in
ox and the activation energy is so low
you need to use very little energy to
move them to switch them but easy come
easy goes. So after you switch it, you
remove the electrical bias, the ions can
easily diffuse back to give you the
reset automatically
without electrical bias. That's a
diffusion process for reset. That's why
we call it a diffusive memory. So this
is a volatile type of device. It has a
very interesting ion dynamics. Remember
at the first slide I talk about ion
dynamics is very important for
biological neuronet network. So this is
very useful for something like a spike
neural network and I'm going to talk
more about that later. There's something
in the middle if you have a activation
energy not too high not too low and uh
that give you also very interesting
behavior. Uh for example this is a
traditional device with a high
activation energy oxygen vacancy as the
dopen. So typically you need a high
switching current and the switching can
be abrupt. So those behavior are not
something you lack when you use a device
for training in your network. And uh
interestingly if you rem replace this
tantelum with something else like
ruinium immediately you see switching
behavior different and you can see now
the switching need much lower two orders
of magnitude lower current and the
switching on and off are much gradual.
So those low current gradual switching
is something you like to have when you
use a device for um neuronet network
training and uh this is oxide agnostic
um as long as you keep lucinium
electrode you change your oxide it
doesn't matter you can see um in this
case it's get similar switching behavior
local and gradual switching so it can be
do um done with something else uh like
in paravsk material Um uh I'm not an
expert of this but we have a
collaborator they make this type of
device and it suppose uh in such
materials mobile species is iodan
vacancy which has a media activation
energy that give you low current um
switching and uh can have gradual
switching behavior if you um do it
right.
Okay. So there are actually a lot of
fantastic um study uh along those land
in um this camp on this campus you know
such as in Belg group um they use
different ion proton and make uh in the
three terminal device and show very nice
potentiation depreciation and show very
fast switching behavior and a lot more
and also in Joan's group they use some
very interesting
um mechanism to control the ion
dynamics. So they use dislocation and
you use alloying approach to
make much more uh reproducible device
and control the variability. So there
are a lot more I know today you know I'm
supposed to talk about my work. So in
our group um we have been uh in the last
few years we have been uh trying to
focus uh uh on using different type of
memorist devices for different um
computing applications and uh some of
the main result are are listed here and
it can be categorized into three groups.
In the first group um as shown here
we're trying to build the AI accelerator
I talk about and in the second group um
we are trying to build a more faithful
device uh to um biological so um that
trying to make um natural intelligence
emulators and in the third category
we're trying to interface it with
sensors I will talk about that that is
also important direction. Um I I will
mention about that at the end. So you
know due to the time limit I'm going to
pick a few examples to talk about in
each category. Um so the first category
is to build AI accelerator in this case
with drift memory and then I will talk
about to build a natural intelligence
emulator with diffusive memory and then
last I'm going to talk about how do we
interface it with sensors um using both
drift and diffusive memory. Okay.
So um the AI accelerator I assume a lot
of you already know um the the trick
here this is um basically our
accelerator is accelerating one thing
vector matrix multiplication which may
sound trivial but it is a big deal for
uh AI machine learning because over 85%
of computing are pretty much nothing but
vector matrix multiplications. So how we
accelerate that is we can um map a
mathematic matrix into the conductance
um matrix of a memora array by switching
each device to a certain conductance and
then we can use uh a vector of voltage
to represent the input data and the
voltage is applied to the rows and we
collect the current at the end of the
column. So the current is the dotproduct
of the input vector with uh the vector
in the matrix. So this is because um you
are using actually Ohm's law for
multiplication everywhere and you are
using Kokoh's current law for summation
also everywhere simultaneously. So
basically if you think about this it is
a in-memory computing it's a parallel
computing it's analog computing it
implement the three principles the um
the brain actually is using so that's
why it can lead to all of the magnitude
improvement in speed and energy
efficiency and to um demonstrate this in
hardware we did it a while ago we did
show order of the magnitude improvement
in throughput and energy efficiency
However,
for such analog computing, it also have
its weakness. So the weakness is the
precision. Okay. Um, so in order to
improve the precision, we have done
something at the device level and also
the circuit level. At the device level,
it turned out that a memory is not a
resistor and after all it is noisier
than a resistor. And if uh you um switch
the device to a fresh state then you
read it with a constant voltage then you
can see uh the current reading is quite
noisy. You have the random telegraph
noise. With such big noise you cannot
have many conductance levels very close
to each other and still distinguishable.
So fortunately actually work with uh
Julie, professor Julie from MIT group um
they did a theory analysis for us and we
understand um the origin of the RTA and
we derived a simple electrical operation
protocol to den noiseise it and after D
noiseise you can see um the resistance
uh noise is now much smaller like the
red curve now you can have two
conductance levels very close to each
and still distinguishable. So with that
we can get a thousands of conductance
levels from each device that is
demonstrated um you know in a large
array um memory fabricated on CMOS made
in the foundry.
So that 11 bit precision is good enough
for inference application but not good
enough for many other applications such
as training of neuron networks such as
signal processing such as scientific
computing. To get even higher precision
we need to do something at a circuit
level. And uh to do that we designed
architecture and algorithm allow us to
in principle obtain arbitrarily high
precision by we call it arrow
compensation approach. Um so the concept
is shown here. Um the circuit shown
here. Um I'm not going to go into detail
but rather um by saying that um the key
is instead of using just a single device
to represent a number we use the
weighted sum of multiple devices to do
that. For example, if you uh wanted to
represent a number thousand microsemens,
um you can program uh one device and
because it's an analog always have arrow
let's say 10% programming error for
those devices then you end up with 900
microsemen. Okay. So instead of keep
programming the same device over over
again hope you luckily hit on this
target which is not guaranteed need many
steps and you just program a second
device to compensate that arrow you know
the arrow is 100 microsemens you program
the second device you give it a smaller
weight um to make sure it uh converge so
then with let's say the second device is
happen to be programmed also with 10%
arrow
And then with this smaller weight um it
end up representing 90 microsemens. Then
then you add these two together you have
uh 10 microsemens away from your target.
You can keep programming the third
device with a even smaller weight and
you you can get um uh this device
represent nine microsemen. Then you add
them together with their weight, you get
999 microsemens. And that
drops the arrow from 10% to 0.1% by just
using three devices, right? You can keep
doing that uh if you need a higher
precision. Um so the circuit overhead
turned out to be quite a affordable. Um
and we made this demonstration
um in Foundry made SOC. So here is a 12
inch wafer and um there are a lot of
dice on it. Each d is So obviously I
cannot bring the
wafer there. I hope I have something
here that that is one of the dice. I
think you can pass around actually it's
one of the the chip we made u with
meister on cmos. Um so and each of the
SOC uh has uh 10 neuron processing unit
and uh each MPU has um 256 by 256 array
and um then each of the device is
capable of a thousand conductance
levels. Um so with onchip uh CPU SRAMM
and everything you you basically have a
computer you can program um the chip to
different neural network or different
other things for different applications
right so um first uh we use it for high
precision scientific computing um in
this case we use it to do the magneto
hydrodnamic system simulation And you
can see the comparison between a digital
system and analog system. The result are
quite similar. Um the difference is you
have order the magnitude higher energy
efficiency for the analog chip. Okay. Um
and because now it you have high
precision you can use it to also process
signal not just neuron network. For
example, you can program the array into
uh DFT which is discrete for transform
coefficient and then this um matrix can
be used to um process the input signal.
The input signal here is for example a
spectra spectra uh the the signal is in
time domain. Okay. Then um this DFT can
convert the signal from time domain to
frequency domain within one shot. And
then the frequency domain spectra
represent the fingerprint of the input
signal and that fingerprint can be sent
to a neuron network also made of memora
array to do the classification. So
basically um what you can do is to use
the signal processing layer as a first
layer of your network. You form a fuse
network um to do the signal processing
to the classification um all u on the
same chip. Right?
So in the next few slides I'm going to
show you how we experimentally
demonstrate the DFT and then the uh
neuron network then the fuse network for
signal processing in real time and um I
apologize uh we cannot hear the sound
here basically student is playing a
music here and you can see the music
temporal spectra uh here and that is
converted by the DFT on tip here into
spectra domain. That's a red curve you
see uh here. And to compare we also use
the software to uh convert it. Um you
can see the software and hardware result
quite comparable. So you're supposed to
hear the sound but you can hear uh you
can see it from there. So this shows we
can use it to do signal processing right
DFT and then to show the neuron network
on chip. Um and we do uh uh real time
video uh edge detection. This is the
video student is holding and this is a
processed uh by software. This is the
process result by the chip here. And you
can see they are quite comparable. So
now we have the signal processing DFT.
We have the neuron network. We can
combine them together to form a fuse
network also programmed on the chip. And
then um we can use it to classify a
temporal signal.
>> Um
>> the sound is converted into spectra
signal by the DFT layer and then the
spectra is classified by the neuron
network all done in real time on the
chip and the monitor and the computer
here is just to visualize the input and
output. So as you can see here the real
time um you know processing is um
something already you know demonstrated
on the chip even though it's not large
enough to do large language model yet at
this stage but uh it is coming you know
um as you see um there are quite a lot
memorist effort now um is going
commercialization
um as shown by this recent perspective
paper
So that is something very close. Okay.
Now let's talk about something still far
at the you know early stage that is
something like the natural intelligence
emulator. Um
for example you by by diffusing meister.
So you know you would say we don't know
much about na natural intelligence yet.
How can we emulate it right? And so the
approach here is one of the approach
which is bottom down is a understanding
by building. So we're trying to build
something then we play with it. We're
trying to use it to help us understand
some of the bio principles. That's a um
in order to do that we need to have a
lot of faithful building blocks um to
the bios system and actually uh we
published this in the special issue
organized by Billy in chemical uh review
uh it's a summary of our effort um in
this direction
so if you look at the biological network
um and the major component capab apps um
s dendrites and immediately you will see
the ions and the ion migration the ion
channels are playing the critical role
in generate their functions. So um like
you know in the first slides that we
talk about we wanted to emulate the ion
dynamics okay you know to build those um
component faithfully. Um so take a
neuron as an example. You know the
neuron uh key function is to generate
action potential like this. And if you
look closely how the action potential is
generated, you would find that you know
first you have a ATP pump that is
pumping sodium ion out and um potassium
ion in and to build the concentration
gradient of um potassium ion and sodium
ion just in the opposite direction the
gradient and then um the this neuron me
uh start to integrate input signal. Once
the integration is over threshold then
the um voltage controlled ion channel is
open. Once this channel is open remember
we have the concentration gradient built
by the ATP pump. Now the sodium ion
flood in once the gate is open the
motion is driven by the concentration
gradient and that will increase the
polarization and uh the then the sodium
ion channel will close by itself. Even
before this close the potassium ion
channel will open then the potassium ion
will flood out also driven by its own
concentration gradient and that will
decrease the polarization and then the
whole thing will go to a resting state
and the ATP pump is keep working you
know maintain this resting state.
So in this whole process um the iron
channel open and close is very
important. So in order to um build a ion
channel emulator by a nano device we use
a diffusive memory and uh uh here you
looking at a snapshots of INC2 TEM
showing at each moment um when you apply
electrical bias between the two
electrode of a diffusing memory you can
see in the gap you have a silver doped
silicon silicon nitri oxide at the very
beginning when you apply electrical bias
between the two electron control and uh
because you have a gap here the current
remain low this process mimic the ion
channel closed state and but it it's
even though uh the current is low
actually something is happening inside
the device you can see the silver are
actually moving and this is more and
more silver accumulated here this mimic
the integration process of the neuron
before firing
and then uh Once it reaches threshold
you build a complete channel bridging
the two electrode then the current shoot
up. Okay. So that mimic the process it
generate action potential the spike and
the channel size is about 4 nanometer in
diameter. So interestingly
um after firing um there's no electrical
signal anymore and zero electrical bias
you can see this filament reshape itself
spontaneously into a sphere. So break
this channel and this mimic the process
uh the channel the neuron goes back to
resting state after firing automatically
doesn't take any energy right so this is
a diffusion process from here to here
because there are no electrical bias and
so this give us a faceful ion channel
and then we can also use a capacitor to
mimic the membrane capacitor put them
together you have a simple leak,
integrate and fire neuron. Okay, so as
shown by this experimental data here, it
does show the leak, integrate and fire.
Um, so with this, it's a more capable
neuron. It's a dynamic neuron. Um, now
you can combine with synapse and you
build a neuron network full of memory.
And uh so you only have eight neurons
here, small neuron network, but because
the neuron itself is much more capable
and it can perform unsupervised
learning. And we were very excited to
show for the first time you can um
experimentally demonstrate unsupervised
learning with the um memoristive
network. And so this is because now you
have a more capable neuron. But even
this neuron like I said it just have
very simple function like a leak
integrate and fire. But we know in the
real neuron there are a lot more
functions. Okay for example it can also
cascade signal from one layer to the
other. Neuron is active device. Um so it
also have intrinsic plasticity. It have
refractory period. It has stochasticity.
So in order to capture all these six key
functions, if you build your neuron with
a traditional CMOS, it will be a bulky
circuit like this. You will need 24
transistors and three capacitors. And uh
we know we have so many 10 to the 11th
neurons in the brain. You cannot afford
to have such bulky circuit to represent
just one. And it will cost a lot of
energy and and uh area.
So fortunately now we have um the
dynamic device like diffusing meister we
can build a neuron with uh only three
component but still capture all the six
key functions. Okay. So in this um
neurons you have a transistor and you
have a drift memory and a diffusing
memory because memoristas are typically
much smaller than the transistor. So you
can build the memory on top of the gate
build a 3D neuron and the entire
footprint of this neuron is no bigger
than a single transistor. Okay. So that
easy to say than done. Actually uh it
took a student almost a year to um f to
successfully integrate the um two uh
trans uh memorist one drift memory one
diffuser memory on top of a transistor
and show you can get this very nice um
you know neuron behavior. And if you um
look at in detail we experimentally show
that such 3D neuron can show the leaky
integration firing threshold cascade
propagation intrinsic plasticity
refractory period and stoasticity. The
the six key functions all um come from
you know area with just a single
transistor. The reason is you utilize um
the ion dynamics in um you know simple
devices.
So we do not have a a large array of
this yet. And in order to understand the
array level performance, we build a
model that can faithfully reproduce uh
the neuron behavior. And with that model
uh we are able to um in simulation build
a large recurrent spiking neuron network
with thousands of neurons and multiple
layers. So with this um
recurrent spiking neuron network we are
able to um classify spiking hedinber
digits. basically it's a spoken version
of amnest. Um so we can see um the
neuronet network can do a decent
classification with good accuracy of
those spoken digits. Um but we also show
if you remove one of the six neuronal
functions from your neuron um your
network performance is going to be
affected um negatively. So that shows
all those functions are actually useful
for the neuron. Okay. So we um also
compare um the memoristive neuron with
the neurons in the living monkey. And
with our collaborators of course they
did the experiment to measure the neuron
firing behavior uh in different regions
in the monkey and as you can see these
are the memoristive neuron and uh
qualitative quantitative qualitatively
they they are comparable. Um so
basically this all due to the ion
dynamics you have.
Okay. Now let me switch gear talk about
the last part um is um integration with
the sensor. So if you think about um you
know the natural intelligence system
they evolved
um by better deal with their
environment. Okay. Right. So that means
they have to be interact with the
environment very um uh efficiently. Um
so this comes from the fact that the
natural intelligence usually seamlessly
integrate sensing encoding and learning
all together. And for example uh you
have a different sensors and uh they
generate sensing signal. Then the sense
signal will be uh encoded into spiking
signal either many spikes with a
different frequency or a single spike
with a different spike timing to
represent the data. And such a spike
signal is going to be sent to the brain
which have the neuron network to do the
sensor fusion and also the learning
typically unsupervised learning. To
mimic this system in artificial um
system uh you will need to have a
sensors then you will have a spike
encoder and then you have a neuron
network to do the sensor fusion and
learning. So if again you do it with the
SMOS circuit because SMOS circuit is not
designed optimized for this purpose and
you are going to need a bulky circuit
like this just for encoding okay
encoding signal and again um using uh
the new type of memora diffuser memora
we show that we can uh realize uh spike
encoder with just a single diffusive
memory. Okay, rather than such a bulky
circuit and as experimentally shown here
um you can have a sensor in this case
let's say a pressure sensor then a
diffusing meister circuit wise it looks
like this you have a sensor when you
have a pressure it generate a voltage
that voltage is going to turn on the
diffusing memory generate a current
spike okay if the pressure is high then
the voltage here is high then the
merista is turned on quickly, it
generate a spike within a very short um
delay time. That's a spike timing. If
the pressure is low, then the voltage is
low. Then the memory is still turned on
but only after a long delay time. That's
a long spiking time. So basically this
diffusing meister
convert the pressure amplitude into a
spike timing right that's a spike
encoder and if you think about this you
don't need uh external power and the
pressure sensor itself power the memory
it's a self-powered system and it's
event driven only if you have event
something happen and it's very energy
efficient so this is not just for
pressure sensor. It works for many
sensors such as temperature sensor, such
as light sensor as we shown here. For
the light sensor case, a single
diffusing memory, it convert the light
intensity into spike timing. Okay, it's
self-powered event driven. So now we can
combine those component together to
build a sensing and learning system as
shown here. Um experimentally we have a
pressure sensor. Oh that's a pressure
sensor. We have a light sensor and we
have a diffusive memory. So two of them
serve as a spike encoder. We have a
drift memory here serve as the synapse
um for the learning part. And um then um
we use this experimentally demonstrate
some learning like input timing
dependent plasticity. This is a learning
row commonly observed in the bios system
like STDP.
So this learning row actually generate
the biggest um weight change um if the
two spike signal are synchronized. So
use something like this. Uh we can find
many applications such as we use it as a
lightning um detector. Um so because a
lightning event you have light you have
sound and sound is like the pressure. So
you can um use such a system to um um in
simulation we show we can use it to uh
distribute it in a large area to detect
the lightning event which may not be
important here but it's important for
where I come from. You know in
California each year we have a lot of
wildfire caused by lightning event. We
want to know the lightning you know
distribution. So but anyway if you look
at this system we don't need external
power. It is used the sensor itself to
drive the system. It's self powered and
it naturally do the sensor fusion with
multimodel sensor and the learning is
unsupervised learning and also you know
um realized inside the system with only
few component right.
Okay. So uh to summarize um I talk about
um you know for uh the the memory the
activation energy of the mobile ions are
important um it largely determines the
memoristive behavior and if you have um
large activation energy you get a drift
memory it's nonvolatile reset has to be
done by drift but it shows stable dense
conductance levels with high precision
it is good for AI accelerator
application. If you have low activation
energy, then you get a volatile device.
The reset has to be done by diffusion
and uh it ex shows desirable ion
dynamics. It will be very efficient for
a natural intelligence emulator and both
diffusive memory drift memory can be
used directly interface with the sensors
to enable efficient and intelligent
sensing system. So after all I think um
neomorphic computing will be long lived.
Okay that's another takeaway message if
you don't remember anything else. So I
like to um thank my co-workers post
doctors and uh as shown here and I also
like to um thank the sponsors um for the
work. Thank you for your attention
>> for the great talk. Thank you. Wonderful
talk.
>> Thank you.
>> So we have time for questions. Um anyone
wants to go first? Let me there also
>> go ahead.
>> Okay. Thank you Joh. Uh thank you very
nice talk and I have a question about uh
the capacity capacity of the member
company uh elements. Mhm.
>> So if the capacity of uh this technology
is not that large than the uh large
language models or media scale models is
hard to convince ourself that's a
inmemory computing.
>> Yeah.
>> So uh I want to ask what's the uh ideal
scale or ideal capacity of
>> uh single chip level and also single
array level computing.
>> Right. Yeah.
>> Um okay then that's a very good
question. So um so far we are um each
cell is one T1R it has one transistor
one um memory um so the density is
limited by the T by the transistor you
know as everybody know even if you use a
three nanometer transistor tech 3
nanometer technology node a transistor
you make is three is still going to be
3,000 nanome square but the memory
itself can be as small as 3 nanometer by
3 nanometer. We even showed a 2
nanometer by 2 nanometer area for a
single memory. So memory will be much
smaller than the transistor. So the
density now is um limited by the
transistor. Then you can think um at
this stage it will be a DM density. DM
is one T1C right and u um so DM you can
stack right you can stack and the high
bandwidth memory but uh uh the issue
there is once you stack more then the
energy consumption will be too high the
heat dissipation will bother you you
cannot go probably more than 16 layers
so those devices they they will have a
much lower energy consumption so they
probably afford more you know um
stacking
layers and um also people trying to uh
um develop
um one T multiple R. Okay. So in
addition to that um you should also
think one R you know you can have 11 bit
precision maybe even higher. So that
equivalently
um you know one one T1C
that is only one bit. This is a one cell
one transistor region you have 11 bit
right that density. So if you think
about that actually the density is a
pretty promising. We we can do uh larger
one and we can scale it uh you know with
two down to 5 nanometer 3 nanometer and
eventually I think a single chip we can
probably have um you know um
uh let's see
>> gig giga will be something for sure.
Yeah we can do yeah yeah yeah giga.
Yeah. Yeah. But you know still like the
languages model we will need a more than
that. Yeah. So we we will need a multi-
layers. Um but uh uh for um
many edge applications um probably we we
yeah we do not need a large language
model. I I think that will be far but
there are a lot of lowhanging fruit we
need to pick first. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Any other questions?
Hi, thanks. Um, for the LAF transistor,
you showed that the area decreased by
about order of magnitude. Do you have a
metric for how much power decreases from
CMOS?
>> For the neuron, right?
>> Yeah. For a neuron,
>> right? Yeah. So if you look at the paper
I think uh um for per neuron even now um
for our experimental demo is still a
micron two mic four micrometer by four
micrometer neuron that was already go to
a um femto something like that and we
also did the uh calculation to project
when you use advanced technology node go
to three nanometer technology node we
can go down to
yeah so that that will be actually
comparable or even lower than the bio.
Yeah. Mhm.
>> How do you perform the plasticity
experiment?
>> Um for the last part or which part?
>> Uh the second part?
>> So you showed some six different
principles of neurons which are
satisfied by the by the artificial
neuron.
>> Right. So the intrinsic plasticity you
mean
>> the intrinsic plasticity or
um so you
>> after this
>> this one this one right so the the you
talk about this
>> right so that's the intrinsic plasticity
that that is neuron not synapse we know
synapse can have you know the plasticity
synapse is just learning so this is a
neuron meaning um you know it fire from
one fire cycle to the next fire cycle.
If the next fire cycle is close and then
the firing behavior threshold everything
will be slightly different. Basically
the neuron if it fire frequently it has
the history
uh yate but if you um next firing event
is after a long time then it forget that
effect. So that is the intrinsic
plasticity we talk about. It's intrinsic
inside of the device. We don't need to
do anything to get it. We just need to
build a device like you know our bion
neuron using ions. It will be
automatically there. So that is the way
you know we say um understanding by
building because if you have something
like a diffusive meister they share the
physical mechanism uh at a physics level
with the biological component then
automatically you get multiple
properties you're looking for all
together without have having to engineer
one by one engineer this one lose
another one right so that that is the
philosophy if you make it similar you
will get similar function multiple.
>> Great. Thank you for the talk. So you
did a great job of showing the
applications when you have a mature
technology that you can fabricate at
scale and what you can do with like two
of an emerging technology. Do you have a
sense for what the lowhanging fruits are
once that emerging technology gets to
like 10, 100, a thousand? Like what is
the kind of opportunities and the gap
between this brand new technology and
something that's kind of more mature?
Um so you are talking about more like
the AI accelerator or the
>> whatever you think like what is the best
thing you can do once you have 10 to 100
of some new emerging technology
>> um
so this is not specific I don't know how
to um so for if if we think about the AI
accelerator right so we we can show uh
orders of the magnitude higher energy
efficiency
Um then GPU for example right then then
then you can find a lot of edge
applications you use it in the Google
glass you use it in XR and you use in
variables and those are all the places
you require two things one is a low
energy because it's energy constraint
and second you want to process
information in real time you know high
throughput and th those fit such
technology you know perfectly well
because that's its advantage age for the
uh for the um a longer term. If you also
have um the natural intelligence
emulator part um and capability then um
the robotics you know much smarter
robotics that can learn from the
environment by interacting with the
envir environment and uh it can learn
without using backup propagation. those
will all be possible and uh um so but
that still I think is a little bit far
but even with the AI accelerator
um we actually start to um use our chips
the SOC chip I showed you to develop
some algorithm that is simple enough but
also general enough and it can be
applied on a a single SOC see and
perform um learning and uh uh planning
all on chip so that it can already you
know fly a drone or something. Um so th
those are all you know the things um can
be used. Yeah.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. One last question.
uh given you did a really good job
motivating the problem that you're
trying to solve the energy consumption
also just the growth of AI and I was
wondering um you covered briefly some of
the alternative approaches and I assume
there there are many um I was wondering
if you could maybe shine a light on what
are some other approaches to uh inmemory
computing that could also be very
promising and should be investigated
more
>> so other technology you mean um the
technology to use inmemory computing or
something outside of inmemory computing
>> I think better described as like other
approaches is to doing it outside of
Memorist or
>> right. Yeah. Okay. So outside of
Memorista we can use other type of
devices. I I know there are many
promising candidates uh you know like
Pharaoh electric um M RAM phase change
and um some of the new devices like um
Belgi working on EC RAM um you know um
so those are all very interesting um
possibilities to as a building blocks
and but outside of a in-memory computing
um I know there are you know other types
the quantum and uh and using photonics
though those those are all you know very
interesting as well it's out of my
expertise I don't want to you know to
make say too much on that something I
don't really know much yeah
>> thank you
>> great thanks a lot for the great talk
let's uh help me thank speaker again