[Music]
okay well welcome everyone um I W to I
welcome you to to uh this
um uh week's Nano exploration seminar so
um today's speaker is Emma Batson who's
going to be talking about uh superc
conducting nanowire Electronics in
magnesium diboride I'm Carl bergren um I
have the Good Fortune of being Emma's
adviser and uh Emma is a fourth year
grad student in the group uh she is an
NSF graduate research fellow and she's
been working she's worked on couple
projects over time uh all related to
superc conducting materials in one way
or another and so I'm very happy to host
this a couple quick housekeeping um
points uh if you have questions during
your talk we won't be able to answer
them during the talk but um go ahead and
answer them into the chat or into the
Q&A or raise your hand and we'll get to
them at the end um so with that I'd like
to go ahead and welcome Emma Batson
thanks for the introduction I'll jump
right right in uh because I know that
not everybody here is uh familiar with
superconductors I thought I would start
with a quick discussion of how our
devices work uh the main principle is
that we actually use the superconducting
transition of our Nano wires as a switch
so superconductors can switch through
temperature current or field um how it
might look if we Ed the temperature
transition as a kind of a device level
information is that when the device is
cold uh there's zero resistance and we
could treat that as a kind of zero State
uh but then once it's warmed up above a
certain critical temperature uh now
suddenly we have all of this resistance
and we have a measurable voltage so that
could be treated as a one state but for
a number of reasons using this thermal
transition wouldn't be very great for
devices it would be slow and um not very
high signal so what we usually use in a
device is a switching current transition
in this case when a current below a
certain level is applied to the device
uh the current can pass through without
any resistance at all this is actually
kind of a a bad example in this plot
because this this device was fairly
heavily uh shunted but normally um this
the line in the middle would just be
straight up and down and so we can pass
current through without getting any
voltage whatsoever but then once the
current rises above a certain amount uh
we we suddenly enter this resistive
regime and all of the current that was
being applied now is shunted into
voltage what this looks like for a
practical device uh our kind of um main
focus is on superc conducting single
Photon detectors what happens is we bias
the device to a current just below what
would cause it to switch such that even
a single Photon hitting the device is
enough to cause a small region to switch
into that resistive regime as a result
we get this nice sharp voltage pulse uh
before the device relaxes back into the
superconducting
state this has a lot of potential
applications in fields like dark matter
search biomedical Imaging or astronomy
anywhere that we have uh low signals of
low energy photons and we want to detect
them with very little noise um one one
way in which these detectors imp prove
over something like a silicon based
detector is that silicon is actually
transparent in the near infrared so
these devices can detect photons that
silicon simply cannot so for that reason
we're very interested in these
detectors and fortunately for us we also
have some compatible logical devices
that can work in exactly the same
platform we have the nanoc cryotron that
work kind of on the same Principle as
our detector but instead of switching
them with a photon we actually switch
them with a controlled current pulse
that we inject intentionally to perform
logical operations and similarly we have
a device that works on the thermal
switching called a heater Nano prron and
with these three terminal switching
devices um that have you know kind of
transistor like operation we've actually
managed to create superc conducting
memories in logic that could potentially
be used to read out these detectors in a
scalable way all within the cat and on
the same platform so with very little
losses of of our
information however uh the typical
nanowire device materials that we've
previously explored are are pretty
limited to a very specific family of
kind of transition metal nitrides and
pilicides uh while these devices in
these materials are great for a number
of reasons um they're fairly Limited by
the low gap uh which leads to a low
transition temperature and the fact that
they're almost always these amorphous or
poly crystallin films um at first this
may not seem like maybe such a bad thing
uh but when we consider for instance
that our current Dynamics are actually
dependent on temperature uh the closer
we operate our device to the transition
temperature Point uh the less we have
these really dramatic uh hysteretic
switching shapes to our current voltage
curve uh and so that really degrades the
device performance so we want to be able
to operate our
devices pretty much um as cold as
possible relative to the transition
temperature A good rule of thumb is that
it's pretty tough to operate these
devices at uh let's say more than half
of the transition temperature and the
materials that I was talking about uh
that tends to be 4 Kelvin operation or
even less and to get to 4 Kelvin we need
these expensive and energy consuming
compressors uh and very high quality
heat pumps uh in order to reach these
temperatures and that really limits uh
right now the the the deployment of
these devices that that limits the kinds
of places that might be able to operate
such a
system but state-of-the-art cry stats
can get 35 Kelvin operation uh with just
something that sits on a table and plugs
into normal wall power so with the
cryocooler technology advancing um we
should be catching up to to take
advantage of these new cryocoolers if we
could operate at 35 Kelvin then we could
use a device like this and we could
deploy our uh devices much more widely
that's where magnesium dorite comes in
it's a superconductor with a transition
temperature of 39 Kelvin so it would be
a challenge to operate this at 35 Kelvin
but it's within the realm of possibility
we can at least hope to to operate it at
20 Kelvin or so without any heroic
efforts um it also is a good material
because it has a high critical current
and high critical field um and and part
of this comes from the interesting fact
that it actually has two distinct gaps
the larger of which um contributes a lot
to the high transition temperature uh
while still
maintaining superconducting behavior
that is understandable within common
models of super conductivity namely BCS
Theory so we found some collaborators at
chers and JPL that can give us different
kinds of magnesium diboride so we have a
very large space that we can explore
with this material at Chalmers they
specialize in hybrid physical chemical
vapor deposition or
hpcvd this provides magnesium diboride
with the best properties very close to
bulk sometimes even better because of
strain in the film uh but unfortunately
it's slow to grow and we can really only
get you know a 1 cm square piece a
handful of those at a time from them
we're also working with a group at JPL
that's learned how to magnetron sputter
magnesium diboride more similar uh
technique to the way that our s
pilicides and nitrides are usually grown
we have some compromise on the film
properties in this case the TCS tend to
be lower maybe more like 35 Kelvin but
it does allow wafer scale deposition and
that give us a lot more space for
instance to iterate on our fabrication
processes and that's important because
fabricating devices in magnesium
diboride is extremely challenging it's
somewhat easily corroded by moisture and
that can be moisture that's present um
in hygroscopic solvents like acetone uh
it's not very easy to reactively etch it
has a very different chemistry than the
transition metal nitrides and pilicides
that we're used to trying to added
and as a result of these challenges
although people have successfully made
Single Photon detectors in this material
uh there are very often one-off events
um people rarely report multiple
detectors made with the same frication
techniques um and so there's a huge need
for scalability and reproducibility of
Fabrication in this material and uh Nano
gives us a great OPP opportunity um to
work on those
things so first I'll talk about our
efforts with epitaxial or hpcvd films
and uh this collaboration is a bit older
so our results here are a bit more
developed um and and particularly what
we've made with these films are wide
wire superconducting nanowire single
Photon detectors not really nanowire
anymore more like microwire but uh that
SPD isn't quite as catchy so the
fabrication process that we use used for
these detectors involved first
encapsulating our films with a thin
layer of silicon and then using an ebam
resist as well as a charge dissipation
layer we favor Electra 92 and using ebam
lithography with either the hs50 or the
f-125 depending on what we're trying to
do to pattern our
wires we can then rinse off the charge
dissipation layer and we do a cold
develop and we used the Argon ion Mill
in Lucha L's lab to do the pattern
transfer to magnesium diboride this is
under construction uh we're no longer
really using this fabrication process
for our our device patterning we're
working on bigger and better things
mainly uh looking at improving our
encapsulation looking at better resists
for the pattern transfer and ways to use
the Samco miixed R ICP that's in Nano um
for the pattern transfer instead but
that's all coming soon um the final step
that's interesting and and a little bit
novel in this fabrication process is a
sort of post fabrication step of helium
ion exposure and we do this in the
zerion tool in Building
24 it has an atomically sharp tip that
can excite a very narrow beam of helium
ions at about 20 to 30 K and we scan
this over our entire device to give it a
uniform radiation of helium this has
been done for other superconducting
material materials such as niobium
nitride and mly pilicide and actually
found to improve the performance of the
detectors as a
result when we do some simulation of
this to get insight into what's going on
we see that indeed um a lot of helium
ions can make it through the resist
Collide in our film and actually embed
themselves somewhere in the substrate we
compute that about 150 helium ions is
colliding with our super condu in thin
film uh you may be wondering why does
that make the detectors better and
that's exactly the question that we've
been trying to answer uh with STM and
other techniques within Nano but the
theoretical hypothesis is that each of
these collisions can create a single
point defect it displaces one of the
Magnesium or Boron atoms into uh what
should have been a vac a vacancy so the
defect pair is a vacancy interstitial
pair as a result the micro structure is
locally changed in some ways it's made
more defective it might seem odd that
that would make the device performance
better but in the case of our wire
geometry detectors what we really want
is to have as great a percentage of the
device very close to being switched so
if there's one point Point that's
constricted then the whole device is
limited to being biased at a lower level
if we can introduce a uniform film of
defects everywhere that floods out these
native defects then perhaps that's
actually sort of bringing the whole wire
down to the same level as the original
worst part uh and that increases the
uniformity letting more of the detector
uh participate in detection at a given
current Vias
level um so we can also uh simulate that
there's a difference in effective dose
depending on encapsulation so you may
have noticed that in my fabrication
process I never actually stripped the
resist this is because of concern about
what harsh solvents that can take in a
lot of water like nmp and acetone might
do to the side walls of my film um
however this is definitely going to
change the effect of the helium ions
whether you choose to do that or not uh
the resist layer actually slows down the
ions uh leading to up to three times
more vacancies predicted in the
Magnesium diboride that had resist on
top um so here we can see this line is
the depth within just the superc
conducting film of the Magnesium
diboride that was
encapsulated this line represents the
Magnesium diboride that wasn't encaps
ated so little choices like this in the
fabrication can make a huge difference
to post fabrication techniques like
helium ion
radiation uh so all of that said let's
take a look at what actually we get what
are the results when we expose magnesium
diboride that's encapsulated in this way
with helium ions um I don't have uh a
plot showing the negative but just take
my word for it that before IR radiation
this detector was completely insensitive
to light uh we put tons and tons of
light down the the fiber optic into this
device and absolutely nothing happened
except that it got a little bit warmer
um post radiation we actually sort of
radiated it too much leading to a a
pretty major suppression of the
transition temperature but at about half
of the transition temperature we still
have this nice IV curve that has this
dramatic transition at the switch in
point and indeed uh we're able to get
counts we get up to a th000 counts per
second with 100 dark counts per second
at 1550 nanometers light at 10 Kelvin
which is half of the transition
temperature this is for a one micron
wide wire that was radiated to a dose of
1 time 10 15 ions per square cm another
thing that's interesting here is that we
actually get these relaxation
oscillations at a much faster rate than
our maximum Photon count rate this sort
of indicates that the efficiency of our
device is not so good it could count
faster the Dynamics can go up to higher
speeds um but we're not able to get
enough of the device sensitive to
measure that many photons um so our
sensitivity is is maybe a little bit low
but our material is still pretty good it
still has these fast Dynamics
and um one thing oh and this this work
has been accepted to i e transactions on
applied superc conductivity so keep an
eye out for that and uh some results
that were even better uh were on helium
exposed magnesium diboride without
encapsulation so in this case at an even
higher dose so 5 time 10^ 15 ions per
square cimer uh we actually see that the
transition temperature is effective very
little uh so if we get the correct dose
then the sort of broader properties of
our detectors are largely unchanged but
they still go from being insensitive to
light to Counting photons at up to 20
Kelvin again uh we see this count rate
of a thousand counts per second and we
also have a very fast pulsing Behavior
Uh so again our our our efficiency may
be limited but our detector Dynamics are
really fast and we're able to go up to
really high operating temperatures so
this is very exciting and and the next
step as I see it is to explore this
hypothesis of of why the irradiation is
improving our results um and this is
this work has been accepted to Nature
Communications so keep an eye out for
that as well so uh we took these
detectors and we prepared a Lamela from
them to explore in the Themis and what
we find is really striking actually so
on the the epitaxial parts of the film
um some of them remain epitaxial and we
can actually see the single Atomic
resolution in these areas however to the
to the left of this image there's
there's no single Atomic resolution at
all in the Magnesium diboride layer
anymore and we attribute this to the
helium ion irradiation amorphizing this
part of the film which is in line with
our understanding that it's introducing
these defects it's damaging the lattice
structure uh so that's good support that
this is uh what's going on here another
great thing we can do with the Themis is
look at where the different atoms are
located with eels uh so if you're
familiar um EDS allows us to see
magnesium and Eels allows us to see
Boron unfortunately it's very difficult
for us to see both atoms at the same
time time but magnesium loves to oxidize
so the location of the Boron atoms is
actually a really good proxy for where
the Magnesium diboride th film
originally was and the location of
oxygen is a good proxy for what has
oxidized and where the Magnesium may
have diffused out of the film and
oxidized instead so what we can see here
is that we do still have a really clear
stripe of boron where it should be so
this is again evidence that the atoms
are moving around as a result of a
radiation but they're not getting kicked
out of the film or anything like that uh
but the other thing that's striking is
that we do have these oxygen-rich layers
uh strikingly above and a little bit
below the Boron so we can kind of tell
from that that our encapsulation may not
be good enough right now we are losing
some of our film um so that's one of the
reasons why we want to go back and
improve our fabrication techniques a
little bit and that's really been
enabled by these STM characterization
studies so that's all for the uh wide
wires on um epitaxial films I think the
work we've been able to do there is is
really exciting but at the same time it
points to some limitations in our
fabrication processes uh that could be
better suited uh to exploring with large
batches of films such as the magnetron
sputtered films
so I'll talk a little bit about about
these just briefly uh We've also done
some stdm interface studies of these
films um we confirmed what our
collaborators told us which is that it's
about 30 nanometers cap capping layer of
boron on top of 40 nanm magnesium
diboride on top of 30 nanometers of
silicon nitride the reason for the
Silicon nitride is that again magnesium
loves to react with things if it's
sputtered directly onto the Silicon then
a large quantity of silicon will tend to
migrate uh and and react with the
Magnesium we can also confirm through
again EDS in this case that indeed the
Silicon nitride capping layer is
protecting us pretty well the Magnesium
remains really well localized um within
the Magnesium diboride layer um in this
case I I guess I wasn't able to get a
silicon signal um but the the nitride
and the the oxygen have also kind of
stayed where they belonged um so this is
all indication that this magnetron
sputtering technique does work pretty
well and produces pretty clean
films so uh thanks to papia blocks we've
been able to plan and prepare some
pretty crazy uh long fabrication
techniques that allow us to keep the
film encapsulated as as much as possible
uh so we really appreciate the the use
of this tool for helping us visualize
you know um how well our film is
protected at any given point and um
we've actually managed to go through uh
our first run of this new fabrication
method and create some devices a and uh
we're actually undergoing testing of
these devices uh right now so we're
pretty excited to see where where this
leads us with these new magnetron
sputtered films and to iterate on this
fabrication technique going
forward future directions are going to
include continuing the STM studies
particularly comparing irradiated to
non- irradiated films and looking at
more STM of these sputtered uh film
lamelas to make sure that we're looking
at really the best possible um technique
there we also need to work on this
fabrication technique a little bit not
all of our devices come out uh this one
in particular is an example of a device
that was incredibly overed uh so that
they don't all work we need a few more
iterations to improve the stability and
reproducibility here and we're also
exploring other characterization methods
that would help us figure out what's
going on a little more easily as we're
going through the fabrication such as
trying to De develop a vasal lipometry
model uh for these films which is quite
challenging um because magnesium diorite
is quite anisotropic and we don't have a
model for it or for the Boron capping
layer um so as you can see from these
fits we've had some progress on this
front but the model isn't the best um so
I'd like to thank uh everybody in the
group but especially iliaev for the
original magnesium dor experiments Jessa
and kalza for ION radiation and Audrey
jaat for device design and Fabrication
assistance I'd also like to thank all of
the MIT Nano staff uh we took made great
use of the facilities for all of this
work um but especially Aubrey pen for
stdm assistance and Juan Ferrera for
bellan
assistance thanks for thanks for
listening to my
talk uh I'll take any questions
okay well uh thanks Emma that was great
so um we have time for plenty of time
for questions so um please go ahead and
put them in the chat or uh the Q&A or
raise your hand I'm not sure um don't
see any hands raised yet so I think I'll
start it off um by
asking um so you you showed can you
could you flip back to the eels uh data
so uh you mentioned that there was
a there was Boron and I'm trying to line
up the EVS pictures below or sorry the
eels pictures below with the temm above
and you see this interface layer so U
the first thing I'm wondering is is that
interface layer just silicon carbide or
is there something else in there
um yeah so it's a little hard to tell
unfortunately the eels detector is a
different detector than the one we get
these really nice images from so I don't
have anything that quite exactly lines
up these single Atomic resolution images
with eels in
part um I think the I believe that based
on the scale of things the Magnesium
diboride layer was quoted at being seven
nanometers thick so I think that the
interface layer has to be affected by
magnesium diboride otherwise we're kind
of missing um some material I I think
it's possibly um if we look at eels we
can see that there is this layer below
the Boron that looks sort of oxidized or
something so it could be that this is
kind of a
magnesium uh mixture on on top of the
silicon carbide I'm not exactly sure it
could also just be the that it's
magnesium diboride with a kind of weird
lattice uh going on um yeah I've thought
about it but I don't I don't totally
know okay great thank you um so we have
some questions now in the questions and
answers section thanks everyone for
putting those in um so let's start with
Chang sub Kim um so CH says maybe I
missed it but what kind of vacancies
Atomic like mg or B are you creating
when you irradiate with helium
ions that's a great question um so
because we don't expect these atoms to
leave the film we expect that they're
knocked out of their original lattice
position but they remain within the film
it would be a little hard to tell with
compositional techniques like eels or
EDS I believe
that uh because the Boron is lider it's
probably more prone to getting knocked
around and I think we could probably
double check our simulation data to see
if that's what we would expect uh but I
I think it would be kind of tough to
experimentally confirm which it is um
it's a great question I'd have to think
about it yeah changsub suggests that
maybe we could use XPS to check the
veilance states of the residual films
you know as you bore down which is an
interesting idea so I a great I wouldn't
know how to do that but maybe now we
know who to ask for more information oh
um I actually do have XPS experience I
used it a lot for the I
project I just haven't thought about it
in a while well yeah I guess the right
yeah I think that the question is sort
of what are the veilance states that
tell you whether it's magnesium that's
missing or Boron that's missing I guess
um so uh
so ODed Rabin asks a second question
which is I think you or yeah their first
question I think you said that this type
of single Photon sensor uh has a lower
dark signal than other types why why is
that um
it's uh pretty stable I believe so so
the main limitations are the stability
in your operating point so if you can um
extract a really stable current um then
then your operating point will be quite
stable if you're operating at the base
temperature of a particular cryogenic
system so where it's designed to to hold
at then in that case uh the temperature
component of the operating point is
usually very stable as well uh part of
the advantage comes from operating it at
a cool temperature so due to the the
cold operating Point uh we're going to
have less thermal photons that are going
to confuse the noise so to some extent
if you're really trying to minimize the
dark counts you actually don't want to
operate it at a higher temperature in
operating it at a higher temperature we
would be having some tradeoff in the
dark count rate but we still get these
other advantages like the ability to
detect uh single photons in the near
infrared uh and having very fast reset
times yeah so I think
you're maybe to paraphrase that just the
fact that we're able to operate at a
lower temperature
helps us in terms of the dark count rate
um yeah okay so then there's a question
here um that says can you comment
further on specifically what's improved
in the new fabrication method compared
to
before uh yeah so I
think a lot of the complication that you
see here is efforts to keep the film
encapsulated more thoroughly uh so we've
we've we've tried very hard to make sure
that you know we're using a hard mask um
so that photo resist never has to come
in contact directly with our film um
after we Mill the sidewalls we're re
encapsulating it with silicon nitride uh
which again as we established with STM
is going to result in very little
diffusion into the film that could
damage it um I've put ion Milling here
in this particular iteration but we've
also been explor exploring ways that we
can do the pattern transfer using the
ricp tool um which is nice because that
would allow us to do everything in the
clean room um it's also a load locked
tool and if you have some chemistry
involved you have a little bit more
ability to determine the selectivity uh
so it's kind of a complicated answer but
I think the short of it is just trying
to understand a little better the
chemistry of this material and how we
can take advantage of that as well as
trying to really minimize the contact
our material makes with solvents and air
uh those are the main changes
here great so then there's another
question here from Chang sub uh which is
can you sweep through the frequency
wavelength the frequency or wavelength
of the photons to check the threshold
presumably as a way to kind of
understand the the material
um like for the detection I'm assuming
yeah that's what he means I think in in
theory yes in principle it's a little
hard just because you know you get your
Optics set up it's kind of optimized for
one wavelength um 1550 nanometers is the
longest wavelength that we have on site
um we also do some testing with 780
nanometers or even um UV I think like
440 or or similar nanometers uh but to
go much longer than 1550 I think the the
setup becomes a little more challenging
so it's something that in principle we
can do um but in practice uh it would
kind of be a full study on its own I
think to get the apparatus set up to to
perform an experiment like that it could
be worth it um but I think it's not what
we've been focused on so
far great um
one uh one we have a question from
pankar gusain who says in the magnetron
sputtering fabrication process there was
also a boron layer on top of the
Magnesium diboride layer what is the
purpose of
that um yeah so
the yeah go go ahead sorry so this
actually has to is is kind of an a
result of the way that the group at JPL
does magnetron sputtering um the Boron
layer on top is actually required to
sort of maintain the stability of the
underlying film and to maintain a a
smooth surface of the Magnesium diboride
uh while they uh they have to do a post
analing process to improve the
uniformity um it's actually a very
interesting technique where they sputter
these different layers alternating of
boron magnesium and boron and then they
anal it all together into the Magnesium
diboride layer as a result um they
require a layer on top to prevent
evaporation of different atoms off of
the surface I believe I might be uh I'm
paraphrasing this myself so I hope I
haven't um misrepresented the process
but I believe it's a sort of protective
thing for the various steps of their
sputtering
process great
all right well um thank you again Emma
for the very interesting presentation
and to all the participants for their
questions and attention um I want to
just uh before wrapping up uh mention
that the next uh Nano exploration
seminar is going to be on May 14th and
it's going to be given by jeppe Romano
uh from The Institute of
[Music]
nanotechnologies and this presentation
is going to be
um posted at the the Nano Explorations
website um after it's been edited and
captioned and so forth so with that
thank you everyone and uh let we'll U
end the
session thank you