and what we'll be doing is getting
started with our panel discussion uh
we have structured this discussion uh to
leave a lot of time for questions and
answers and discussion from the floor
so this afternoon we've heard about ways
in which open courseware
and similar resources
are being transformational in how people
get access to information and how they
use it
now i'm going to turn our attention more
to the future and the changes we're
likely to see in the years to come
my pleasure to introduce this panel uh
the moderator for the panel is professor
hal abelson he's a class of 1922
professor of computer science and
engineering
in the mit department of electrical
engineering and computer science
he's joined in the panel
by three distinguished individuals dr
charles vest who of course all of us
here know
extraordinarily well
is currently the president of the
national academy of engineering and of
course the president emeritus of mit
john celie brown
is the chief innovation officer of 12
entrepreneuring and the former chief
scientist of xerox corporation
and then sam petroder is the chairman of
the india knowledge commission
as well as the chairman and ceo of world
tell limited how we'll introduce the
panel's topic and the questions our
panelists will be addressing he'll just
he'll briefly describe that each of the
panelists will make a brief
statement about those questions and then
how we'll control the flow of questions
and answers from the floor
please help
so i wanted to start by saying how i
feel
what i want to say is to yell we did it
so
and that comes
and that comes with a
a certain amount amount of pride susan
you heard susan mention
a little while ago that we have mit
students using open courseware
in teaching mit courses at places around
the world including china one of those
cities is dalian
so the students are
going to die and learning that it's not
enough to change light bulbs
and
a lot of people have a lot of friends
here in dalian
but the main
the main emotion i feel right now
is one of tremendous humility
and it's a sense of
how tiny a step we have made
and how tiny a part
of this transformation is mit open
courseware tom talked about
the change from globalization 1.0 to
this
other
amazing emerging thing that's happening
and i think what mit opencourseware has
led us to do is to
see that we're in something like
education 1.0 we weren't we couldn't
even see that before
and now the question is what comes next
what
what are the opportunities that come
what what are the things that having
gotten to this point we can't predict
but we can maybe maybe try to imagine
and we have
a tremendous panel of three people to
help us imagine it uh sam patrotta is
chairman and ceo of world tell limited
he's science he was science advisor to
uh prime minister rajiv gandhi and was
responsible then for india's foreign and
domestic
telecommunications policies
he's been a force for innovation since
the 1960s when he invented what's
considered the first electronic
diary one of the first examples of
handheld computing he's particularly
known for having introduced
microprocessors and telephone switches
sam is widely considered
to be
responsible for india's communications
revolution and this began with a crusade
in the 1980s where he worked for prime
minister indira gandhi on a one rupee a
year salary where he put together a team
of professionals a digital switching
system set up rural exchanges
set up the factories that made the fiber
optic cables
introduced automatic dialing
international dialing in 1980
india had about a million telephones
altogether
and by 2000 three-quarters of india's
half-million villagers had phone service
sam is currently chairman of india's
national knowledge commission which is a
high-level advisory committee to the
prime minister whose objective is to
transform india into a knowledge society
he is passionate about the hunger for
education in india and the fact that
education is the key to economic
transformation
and that the key to that is the
expansion of universities and colleges
and he's often quoted as saying why does
india have uh
seven iits when we could have 70.
john celie brown is the inspirational
seer
for the age of people and information
he's he's been chief scientist of the
xerox corporation
a position he held for 20 years director
of xerox palo alto research center when
that was the leading computer science
research center in the world
he was the first computing research
manager to really focus on the profound
relations between information technology
and social issues and to bring
sociologists and architects into the
computing research community he's
written widely on research management
and on innovation and on the human
context in which information technology
is embedded
john's leadership in technology goes
back to the 60s when he created what is
still one of the world's best examples
of artificial intelligence-based
computing tutoring
and he maintained that during his years
at xerox when he was co-founder of the
xerox institute for research and
learning and it persists to the present
day with his thoughts and writing on how
the net is changing the fundamental
relations between
people and knowledge and between
learning and society
i've been asked to do many silly things
when i've been at mit but
ranking up there was the silliest is the
idea that i would be introducing chuck
vest to an mit audience
so let me just say that people talked a
lot about the genesis of open courseware
and i won't repeat that but i do want to
say it was chuck and his administration
who took this nutty idea that was
presented by a bunch of faculty and
glued that to a sense of a institutional
vision and a sense of the civic
responsibility of a university in the
modern age
but i've got to say that as honored as
we are
to have our guests the real honor is you
both the people who've made it but all
also many of the leaders of the open
educational resources community who are
here
so we don't want this to be a one-way
discussion of hearing great thoughts
this is really meant to be a discussion
and a hope
that maybe we can all
together start imagining something this
afternoon that'll take us from this
education 1.0 finally seen in a global
context to something that could be much
much greater
so chuck let me ask you to start
thank you
the views i'm going to express are
solely my own and neither those of mit
nor the nae
i'd like to begin sneaking up on the
future
by looking back
very briefly at the beginning
and looking at the present and
giving you my idea of what some of the
big forces are out there
first of all the question in 1999 when
all of this
started
was
were residential universities dying
dinosaurs
and
would information technology and
so-called distance learning
render residential universities obsolete
and by the way
was there a great opportunity for
universities to make a whole lot of
money by teaching other people at a
distance
mediated by information technology
and the answer that mit's faculty gave
to that was of course
ocw
so at the time
mit's open courseware initiative was
absolutely counter to the trends of the
day
it was revolutionary
and tom i don't know we used the word
harm but we certainly knew it was risky
revolutionary and risky
and it was entirely consistent
with mit's culture
and tradition if it weren't for that we
wouldn't be sitting here today
and also to me
the fact that ocw is actually realized
and funded at least up to this point
demonstrates the power of a good idea
if you have a really good idea in
today's world and in this great nation
you can still find a way to do it
and above all i always viewed and i
think my colleagues did
ocw as an adventure we really didn't
know where it was going to lead when we
started out and you'll hear lots more
about where it has led today
so some personal beliefs and
observations about all of this
i'm a great believer in fact i'm in love
with the residential university because
i still believe that nothing can
actually replace
the magic that occurs when you get a
bunch of bright motivated diverse young
men and women around 18 19 20 years of
age
coming together living learning in a
very intense environment
teaching and learning no matter how they
occur
are really deeply human activities and i
think as we try to understand the
potential for technology and all this we
must remember
teaching and learning are deeply human
activities but
there is also no question then and
certainly no question now
that computers and communications that
is information technology
are clearly a hugely transformative
force
and
history tells us that technological
process
always outpaces social progress so the
kind of conclusion that i drew from this
and
i think that in in fact that is what ocw
represents is that what began to emerge
at least for a period
was a way in which relatively stable and
indeed conservative institutions like
universities
can develop enormous synergies through
the use of ever expanding technological
tools
so you can at once be
conservative and then in very new ways
evolving and innovating very rapidly
so add to all this the fact that mit's
ocw
combines the educational quality
and pedagogical approach and ways of
organizing knowledge of a great
university
with
the democratizing and empowering forces
of the internet and the world wide web
in this
increasingly interconnected world that
we just have heard so much about
but of course there is much more than
just mit's educational content going up
on the web everywhere for everybody for
free
there was a whole movement which
actually preceded it starting with uh
building vast
digital archives of scholarly materials
starting with things like jstor and art
store and on and on
there is open digital publication that
has developed things like the public
library of science
there's open academic software platforms
and pedagogy like sakai
and all kinds of other open content
initiatives around the country and
around the world
and i want to particularly mention
quickly something that we really haven't
talked much about today
which is the promise of web lab which
again was started here by mit faculty
particularly colleague jesus del alamo
which already although in an embryonic
way it's real is allowing young people
in say sub-saharan africa to sit around
in front of a laptop and in fact control
real experiments for educational
purposes
using equipment that may be an industry
maybe at mit maybe at stanford what have
you
so there's a whole lot more out there
and also if we step back there's a huge
number of driving forces that are kind
of pushing and shoving and shaping all
this or at least creating the
opportunities
one is the connectivity
that worldwide connectivity that tom has
so eloquently explained to us
and second is in fact globalization
itself this new world in which we must
compete and cooperate simultaneously in
all kinds of different ways across
traditional boundaries
and third and all of you travel like i'm
fortunate to be able to do
the rest of the world whether we know it
or not in this country the rest of the
world is really tuning in to the
increasing importance of education they
really are understanding that if the
young people aren't educated they're not
going to be able to play in this
evolving world
so what all of this leads to is what i
like to call the meta university
the meta university something i may
return to in a minute
is really a new
digital substrate or infrastructure of
all this content all these platforms all
this connectivity that teachers learners
and institutions worldwide can build
their own education for their own
purposes shape to their own context upon
so on to the future
first let's start with the pragmatics
how the future plays out not just for
mit ocw but for the entire open
course and open content movement is
going to depend on how well and how
creatively we meet at least four
barriers or obstacles and they really
are obvious
one is intellectual property can we
really pick up and run with creative
commons and so forth and have the
commitment to work with what we have to
work to enable us to have this openness
in an age of ownership of property
second is quality control
the web by definition is the wild west
of information and
if people are going to be serious
learners
somehow things like the imprimatur of
great universities like this are going
to be very important
third is of course how do you meet the
costs i sometimes give talks about
things like ocw and i have a slide that
say what's the business model and then i
say next slide please and we go on to
the next topic because we are providing
a free good somebody ultimately has to
see the value and pay for it in this
open sharing way will we do that by
partnering are there new funding models
susan and the whole team here are
thinking very hard about these issues
going forward and of course finally is
bandwidth we're all used to having lots
of connectivity and bandwidth but
despite the flattening of the world
there's still plenty of places
who don't have it in the
extent that it is needed and so new
delivery mechanisms like the creative
use of ipods and so forth and so on has
to be a big player going forward
so what's the conclusion i draw about
draw from all this
first of all
in addition to having a great idea that
came from this extraordinary faculty
committee most of the members of which
you met just a few moments ago
mit ocw had first mover advantage
first mover advantage coupled with
an institutional quality level and a
literally iconic recognition factor
around the world combining those two
things allowed us i believe to move
forward
and also and keep this in mind as we try
to think through the the future and
decide what waiting function to put on
all the things john's going to tell us
we had what was fundamentally
a very simple accessible product
and
wrestling with that tension about what's
innovative new and different and what is
really easy to put in people's hands and
use is i think a lot of what we have to
think forward in the whole movement
going forward
ocw here and elsewhere is going to have
to thrive based on i think at least four
things one excellent standards of
quality and as i say the sort of quality
control and recognition factors
scale and comprehensiveness were what
was
particularly unique about open
courseware there was nothing new about
the idea of putting some material on the
web it was the scale and institutional
comprehensiveness that gave it its
uniqueness and still gives it uniqueness
today
it will thrive depending on our ability
and will to continue to define the
cutting edge
and in fact to innovate fast and well
which is what of course has to go on
everywhere in this globalized world
and finally i would put out that it will
thrive depending on how we address the
widening uses because we've talked about
this as this wonderful global free good
which is something i passionately
believe in but it's having enormous
impact inside mit
students and faculty members using it as
kind of a time clutch to shift forward
to see how fundamentals are going to be
applied in later courses or to look from
a course backward to refresh and so
forth
uh what can we do in the daunting tasks
facing this nation and and others in
secondary education
and lifelong learning something that has
just got to be a reality in any advanced
society today
and i believe that mit ocw must by
definition thrive on globalization we
must embrace openness and the creation
of electronic-based learning communities
we must continue to define the cutting
edge
while remaining
widely globally accessible in what we do
and above all we will thrive if and only
if we continue as you have done so
marvelously really standing tall for the
basic principle
of sharing and empowerment
i was going to read you two paragraphs
from a book i wrote on the meta
university but i'm going to skip that so
we can go on and hear from sam what is
really happening beyond the boundaries
of cambridge thank you
thank you
i'd like to comment on
ocw from the viewpoint of india
india is a country in
hurry
growing at the rate of nine percent
1.1 billion people
550 million below
age of 25
expanding everywhere
and demanding
low-cost solutions
just to give you an idea
when i entered telecom scene
in 80s
we had about 2 million telephones
for the entire country of 750 million
people
then
today we have
or we are adding
seven to eight million cell phones every
month
the cost structure is such
that while world is looking at 11
aarpu average revenue per user
india can survive and flourish
with five dollar arpu
so today our main need is
speed
scale
and low cost
models
in this process of development we
recognize we have serious skill
shortages
we don't have enough engineers
scientists
teachers
including truck drivers
today india needs 500
000 trained truck drivers
a lot of crazy people driving around
without license
as a result of this
prime minister of india decided to set
up a national knowledge commission
a couple of years ago
we have seven members in the commission
we meet once every two months for three
days
and we look at five areas
of knowledge
access to knowledge
to us that means
literacy languages translations
libraries networks portals reservations
affirmative action programs
then we look at knowledge concepts
primary education secondary education
distance learning
open courseware
higher education
vocational education so and so forth
we also look at
creation of knowledge science and
technology patents copyright trademark
entrepreneurship
innovations
application of knowledge
for
agricultural health and small and medium
scale industries
and finally e-governance
in education we are focused on three key
challenges
expansion
we don't have enough schools enough
teachers enough
professors
at all levels
second excellence
leaving aside top tier of maybe
five percent of universities iit's iims
and some other universities
quality of education at university level
is very poor
and third
equity
we have to make sure
that poorest of the poor can
have the opportunity
to go to the best schools
as a result of all these discussions in
the last two years government of india
has decided to quadruple
investments in education
in the next five years
according to eleventh plan indian
government would be spending 65 billion
dollars
in education
we are building 30 new major national
universities
4 000 colleges
providing additional meals
to 60 million children mid-day meal
program
we want to grow from 320 universities to
in next five years how do we do all of
these things
we are beginning to ask questions that
we have never asked before
questions like
do you really need classroom to learn
today when you think of education you
think of duster blackbird chalk
teacher textbook exam grades
so and so forth
so that's one fundamental question we
are asking
second
what's the role of the teacher
traditionally teacher has been busy
creating content and delivering content
can i take that away from teacher
and have content created somewhere else
and delivered through electronic media
so future teacher would be more of a
mentor
third
what would the university of 2050 look
like
do you think they would
have a campus like this
today when we are building university
automatically we are going off and
acquiring 500 acre land
creating huge amount of buildings
and people like me are saying look this
is not feasible we just don't have
enough resources in spite of 65 billion
dollars
to one
train teachers
and to create infrastructure
and that's where i believe ocw kind of
an experiment
gives some hope
we don't know how it's going to unfold
we had a group on ocw
in india
we had one of your mit
representative on the
group
vijay
we spent about six nine months studying
the whole subject
and we have submitted recommendations to
the prime minister
our normal process is we have a working
group set up on a subject
and we deal with about 50 different
subjects
like say
national knowledge network
we would have about 30 people working on
national knowledge network spend nine
months come back with a white paper
which we would debate at the national
knowledge commission
and the output would be a three-page
letter from me to the prime minister
saying we suggest following things
for the government
we are planning to build a knowledge
network to connect 5000 locations with
one gigabit
broadband connectivity
to connect all our universities
major libraries r d institutions
agricultural research and health
research
ocw becomes an important part
of our effort
we are still learning
we are not very clear
as to where we are headed
but i see a lot of hope
and i hope we can work with mit to learn
more about this
experiment some more
and get some help
thank you
i want to do something slightly
different
but building on everything we've heard
today and
tom also pulling off some of the things
you were saying
i'm really struck um
you know i spent some time in india and
wrote a helped write a report called
minds on fire
the interesting question
how do we get minds on fire is not our
real challenge the challenge of
imagination inspiration and intuition
i think those triads are very powerful
notion
i thought it was strange to come to mit
to talk about inspiration imagination
and so on because every time i come here
i walk across campus
i run into students
i gotta tell you the students on this
campus have more fire in the belly
mine's on fire than any place i know of
in the world um
i'm not going to comment about the
faculty i'm talking about the students
i don't meet the faculty very often but
the students you meet in the bars and
things like this
and it's really interesting and
you step back a moment
you might even say back to the future
and you go back to the origins of most
of our physical sciences
and you recognize that science grew out
of tinkering
we were tinkerers and we were tinkerers
and we were bloggers
those bloggers happen to be formed
called letters into royal society of
letters
but that's how science got off the
ground to a very large extent
i think tom if you go back to your
platform
we're now beginning to enter a new world
a new flat kind of world with a new kind
of platform a platform fundamentally
empowering tinkerers
all kinds of tinkerers
some might call them mashups i might
call them remix some might call them
actually engaging in tinkering in the
old style tinkering that built our
automotive industry i might point out in
the 1900s and so on and so forth
tinkering building real stuff as well
i'm really struck let's take some
examples think about open source
we may actually be enculturating
maybe a million students not into the
theory of computer science but the
practices of certain communities of
computer science communities of practice
different open source communities linux
communities different than the apache
community it's different than red hat
each of these communities have their own
kind of distinctness distinctiveness
sensibilities and so on but you have the
passion to join those and enjoying those
you pick up their practices their ways
of looking at the world
let's go on that's so obvious but it is
pretty pervasive around the world
let's talk about astronomy
think about for the moment the fox
telescope
two beautiful telescopes one i know well
in maui
i'm actually paid for by by the english
government actually by a man named folks
and this is a completely robotically
driven
telescope
students all over england
australia and now opened up through ocw
a limited amount can actually program up
interesting experiments to run on this
telescope there's only one catch
the catch is you got to make it open
source that's to say that you have to
put whatever you take up on the net and
you have to give your interpretations to
that and other people from the community
including professionals
are there to comment on what you do with
that
a new kind of learning community between
i'm going to come back to it amateurs
and professionals is starting to emerge
here just naturally in the white space
so to speak
what do we have here in boston
something called the micro observatory a
micro observatory up the street
has either two or three telescopes
robotic telescopes fairly simple
telescopes
interestingly every night this week
before i got on the airplane last night
i have grabbed time on those telescopes
and made certain measurements that get
delivered to me in the morning to go
over and then i can put it through my
own digital signal processing algorithms
because they give it to me in the right
kind of format to actually be able to do
even more processing on that
now let's think about
the world of insects
by the way today's kids aren't
necessarily turned on by digital chips
like we were they are turned on by how
bugs work how the animal world works now
let's think about bug scope bug scope is
a fairly serious electron scanning
microscope again robotically controlled
and put on the net kids from all over
can submit samples they get prepared
and actually high school students from
around the world can use that as a
remote instrument to explore things
kids get turned on by this kind of
tinkering they can actually as i did by
mistake two nights ago drastically
overexposed things on one of your
telescopes here
you learn by failure you learn by
tinkering again now think about going
back to the topic that tom ended with
the whole issue of global climate change
and what are we doing both to the water
and to the climate think what global
labs does in terms of empowering the
world's kids to go out and take
measurements around the world of water
for example and then compile that data
together run analyses off it and so on
and so forth and of course what do you
have here when i first got this idea is
ilab or
is it now called weblab
okay
okay i only knew it as ilab uh in terms
of a very interesting set of heat
exchangers that i can actually run
remote experiments this way so i just
want to call it our attention that
although ocw in the first phase looked a
lot at content
maybe the next stage is to also look at
activities and what are the activities
you do around this content having to do
with tools having to do with instruments
because we can virtually put any
instrument we want today on the web
and most schools can't afford the three
or four million dollars for the fancy
electron scanning microscope but the
nation can afford that
it can be put on the terror grid if
nothing else and so i think we have an
ability to bring back tinkering
the tinkering that actually is the basis
of our intuition because it is one thing
to be inspired but if you're inspired
without intuition
then that's only so good but most of us
get our intuition from playing around
with stuff
and that stuff can be done remotely and
by the way it can also be done in terms
of things like tech shop in terms of
machine control
computer controlled machining tools
building real things again like neil
gershenfeld has led here in the in the
media lab so i really think that we're
beginning to build another kind of
platform tom a platform that brings all
the kind of content we're talking
activities we're talking but now tools
many many tools into kind of an informal
learning context where tinkering can
come back because i really think content
plus tinkering with real tools really
does
lay the foundation for a way to kind of
get gut understanding for things and
reignite passion not just on mit
students which you have no problem with
here but for the rest of this country
which we do have a problem with thank
you
well we'd like to hear from some of you
they're microphones being around they're
supposed to be microphones going on
so we'd like to hear some of your
visions and
some of what you think and if you don't
volunteer we will call on you i'm a
professor
up there here
i'd like to
ask you to look again at this notion of
tinkering
because i remember
talking to colleagues of mine in
engineering saying that what's wrong is
that
the devices that are now available you
can't tinker with anymore
so how can you tinkle tinker with an
ipod those are the engineers who grew up
taking
watches apart
so tinkering i think is not the right
word or at least you have to rethink
what you mean by tinkering because
you're tinkering with things that are
really quite abstract now
and that seems to me to be in a kind of
a collision course with what
you said sir
about
you need 500 000 truck drivers
those are really two different worlds
the world of the truck driver and the
guy who's going to uh
tinker in your sense
and what worries me is how you're going
to uh
how are you going to
mash those worlds together are you for
example going to think well the way to
do it
might be to take up the technology of
driverless cars that we're doing here so
that you can free up those 500 000 truck
drivers to tinker the way
a user wanted to do it
so those were just some of the thoughts
that i had
the idea is not to buy 500 000 trucks to
train truck drivers
but the idea is to get some technology
to help in the training of 500 000 truck
drivers otherwise you will never do it
i think technology is the hope
to meet the kind of scale we are talking
about what i was concerned is
don't you aren't the 500 000 truck
drivers
sort of excluded from the tinkering
world
maybe that's okay
i don't think everybody i don't think
everybody would be capable of tinkering
i don't expect everybody to be tinkering
but if some people tinker enough to come
up with something interesting for truck
driver
that's more interesting
that's how i look at it
yeah yeah i i have kind of mixed kind of
i mean i understand exactly where you're
coming from and in fact um
you know what really struck me is that
most of us grew up as tinkerers till
about 1980. and then tinkerine
disappeared um and i in my fancy
terminology i said everything became
cognitively impenetrable means i
couldn't grok it
and what hit me is about 1995
i suddenly discovered tinkering was
coming back
and was coming back by the way in media
and kids were doing incredible remixes
mashups and so on and so forth and
starting from that platform you know
that kind of tinkering really did take
off and just look at youtube and a lot
of that actually comes from all kinds of
tinkering with content with media modes
of expression and so on so that i saw is
the beginning platform and then i
started realizing more and more of these
tools are now being made robotic
robotically capable that actually if you
join the community
the community actually as a set of pure
learners actually is a pretty
interesting scaffolding structure and so
it's kind of looking at the notion of
the long tail in terms of these very
niche communities that you may want to
be passionately kind of joining so i
mean i think the story i agree has
gotten more complicated and i was very
happy to see
um a movement called make it's more on
the west coast and the east coast
although i think it's propagating over
here too where now you're finding in
essence community libraries
that are now setting themselves up the
particular thing called tech shop in
menlo park where basically you can get
as a student now or myself as an ancient
can get access to almost any kind of
mechanical device to kind of do
you know machine controlled
computer-controlled lathing and building
stuff with the physical stuff and so i
actually think that we're finding new
ways to fill that gap but no we're not
going to be opening chips and watching
how they work um i agree with you but i
think that somehow tinkering is going to
be happening at a higher level now your
real point is are we just talking about
the abstract tinkering with ideas of
course is what you do in good share of
science but i think if you look at the
remix game in media you're really
thinking about emotion you're thinking
about communication you're thinking
about other things that underlie how do
you communicate and capture people's
attention and i think that's going to be
a new kind of tinkering that i think is
going to be critical at all stages of
the kinds of economy we're talking about
hello
i was wanting to draw the attention back
to teaching and learning
and propose to
propose to the panel a question
it seems to me
that most of us in the room
have
grown up in a world in which the
information and knowledge that we
consumed or learned or acted with
was structured say by the dewey decimal
system or by
traditional classroom
based disciplinary categories
and as i see a new generation coming up
with google searches and so forth
and as i look at my son who is a senior
in university
doing papers and being able to put
things together in the way that i would
never have been able even to imagine
when i was a student
i'm just wondering if
the whole
new technologies
isn't rewiring
the brains of our children
in such ways that we can't
even
imagine or catch up with as we think
about the future of
teaching and learning i'm wondering if
the
actual
structure
and
access to human knowledge isn't being so
restructured that we now have
different i hate to use the word
paradigms
to to imagine as we think about the
future of of learning and education i'm
wondering if the panel
had any of the panel have thought about
that or considered it as we think about
the future
yeah we don't have the answers but we
have lots of questions
one question is why does it take four
years to get a bs in something who came
up with that idea
is that idea valid today
i don't know
why does it take so many courses to get
a masters
can we change that
i do agree
that all of the paradigms of the past
needs to be questioned
role of teacher role of classroom
content
the kind of material we teach is it
relevant today i know this kind of stuff
we teach in india today in many cases is
absolutely irrelevant
i don't care about the history of
british raj in india anymore
so i don't need to learn about george v
it's not relevant to me but we still
teach
so i do agree that this is the time to
question
i think the answer to your question is
yes
but what we do about it i have no idea i
think one
question i only want to disagree with
you one thing somebody has to be
learning about and thinking about george
the fifth sure we have to don't teach me
as a engineering student perhaps
okay
and it's okay it's your privilege if you
want to learn learn
but don't force me into it i i think the
one point i do want to make to this is
really uh embedded in something that
john select brown said
and that's one of the really exciting
things that's happening today whether
it's tinkering-based or not
are the increase of learning communities
where you have older people who may have
some wisdom but not a clue what's
actually going on and you have young
people who do think in absolutely
different ways and i think this
continual mixing beyond the formal based
learning is really exciting and i don't
know where it's going to lead but i
think it's going to lead in a good
direction but unfortunately people who
are planning education are all in 60s
no i agree yeah but you know chuck
your observation is what really sets the
stage for a culture of learning
i mean because now that really if you
can get these types of communities to
self-form and interact you know
productively as i think they are
happening um that is probably the single
best way to you know to crack the
original problem of lifelong learning
that you know that ocw started out with
but two brief comments
you know one thing that's really
happening um and you guys know it here
tremendously well um is the role of
visualization i mean many kids today are
much more are really in fact most of us
in this room are probably much more
visual than we want to kind of really
understand our ability to do incredible
visualizations of very complex systems
really provide you kind of a gut
intuition again of something that is
very hard to capture just by looking at
partial differential equations i think
the second thing is we've got to pay a
little bit attention to reading
practices because the reading practices
are going to be changing let me just
look at wikipedia which was talked about
earlier
the catches
when you ask the quality of stuff on
media wikipedia and compare it to
britannica that's not necessarily a
well-formed question
because the reading practices of a
skilled person in britannica are
completely different than the reading
practices of a skilled person in
wikipedia because if you know how to
read wikipedia you know how to go to the
edit page you know how to see what are
the edits what are the rollbacks so you
know how to find out what's being
contested
so now you have a window into the con
what is conte what is the contested
knowledge part of that definition which
gives you a tremendous insight which you
almost never see because we have opened
up that completely so now you see what
is still under negotiation or being
contested
that is a new practice
so i think the the issue that you
brought up really is
it's kind of the the answer to the
question i asked is what can we imagine
coming after
education 1.0
so those of us who think about the world
wide web and how it's put together in a
in a technical architectural way
the web is designed in a very particular
way so that every piece of it can link
to every other piece of it it sounds a
little trivial now but to say that in
1992 would have been a
revelation and what's happening now is
we have the ability to take knowledge
and organize it so that every piece of
it can link to every other piece of it
on a very fine grained scale
that brings up the possibility of the
kinds of things that that you've been
talking about about sort of niche you
know personalized learning experiences
based on putting things together but at
the same time
it raises this issue about what's
quality what's an education if it's sort
of random putting together we don't know
how to how to judge that how to assess
it and i think that's one of the real
challenges
that as we look ahead from what this
revolution is ringing that we're going
to have to face
larry
a proposition to the to the group and
let you react to it
um we live in a world because of all the
changes that have already been noted by
the various speakers including tom
in which knowledge has been democratized
um and access to it
has been greatly increased and we've
greatly reduced
the cost of gaining access to knowledge
to learning and to the tools of
knowledge and learning
colleges and universities
convey knowledge they teach that's one
function that we we perform but the
other thing which we do is that we
certify
we we send signals to the world that in
fact in fact people have acquired it and
the proposition that i'd like you to
react to is that
in a world in which knowledge is
becoming more diffuse and access to it
is becoming much easier
that ironically the value of the signals
that are being provided by institutions
like this one are
ever more
valuable
and so we have more and more people
in fact trying to gain access to the
signal that is represented by having
studied at an institution like this when
in fact
the knowledge is is that much more
available and diffuse that's a
proposition
no
mr president
the
larry i'm not sure i grasped totally
what what you wanted to say
if if we go back
i agree that
what's very exciting today what we've
all said many different ways is with the
amount of information which by the way
may or may not be knowledge but at least
the amount of information that is out
there
the game is putting it together in the
most interesting creative and in some
cases useful ways
and that our
traditional roles in universities of
certifying that
yes this young woman knows the
fundamentals of the following profession
and so forth
the meaning of that
may be
maybe in question but i i'm not sure it
is if you think of it as only one stage
along a life of learning and working
but then the fact that uh that we
amplify
signals
as you put it i think is very important
one of the things i tried to say uh a
little earlier today
that what i thought was really important
about
about ocw was that it put out there the
thoughts of our faculty about how
knowledge should be organized
and what our fundamental pedagogy
was
and i think that's probably more
important than the details of the
content but i'm not sure exactly how to
answer your question about
what the
meaning and what it says to us about the
amplification of these signals really is
other than that we should be very
careful
so this is more of a comment actually uh
so we all understand that content needs
to be engaging if you put it somewhere
and the two examples that recently came
from mit are actually how tunes which is
a comic book
uh written about how to make stuff and
then drew andy synthetic biology
so do you see ocw actually playing a
much more important role in this type of
a content creation
or actually at least promoting it
further
i mean i certainly i certainly see that
it could i mean one of the things that's
to my mind a little bit absent from ocw
are more materials that are written by
mit students
both of the things you mentioned
are examples of that
but i
also i also think there's this constant
uh
tug of war
between a lot of things that are made by
a lot of people
and saying this is the mit curriculum
put up as a something for the world to
examine in the world to build on and for
me this is a this is a real issue going
forward and how we resolve it
but
i guess the other thing i wanted to say
is
this is too much about mit and ocw i'd
like to hear
i warned you i'd i'd call on you i'd
like to hear dick rowe actually talk a
little bit about this notion of
empowerment and how you think about that
so maybe
if you give your question and then ask
to
again speak having quit
a subject on ocw
i suspect that there's a lot of faculty
around the world
that would be willing to
augment
much like wikipedia and the question is
is there a model that people come up
with
for
somehow
an in-between model where you where you
maintain excellence
and at the same time
draw on this huge energy from the
community
to develop materials
you know i think
and
mike can talk about this at uh uh mike
smith but
i mean one of the kind of next stages of
a lot of this open education resource
movement has to do with how do you close
the loop in various ways i mean take a
piece of material you know a course
remash it uh remix it and mash it up in
different cultures all over the world
what an incredible learning opportunity
that is what are the mind bugs students
of different cultures have when they
read your text and so on so how do you
actually feed all that stuff back
you know it is a very interesting
question um then how do you start to let
other people be able to add material to
it which is like what connections does
how do you then try to figure out what
hold it now i've lost the warrants uh
and so you know this is a this is kind
of pandora's box but i think we're going
to find some very clever types of
recommendation systems warranting
systems lenses that you can put over
this material to see you know which of
this material has been vetted by whom
and so on and so forth so i think this
is
this is a new kind of a platform i think
we're just at the very beginning to be
able to uh understand how to really play
this out
just just very quickly on this this is
why i use this term meta university
because i think it is a platform it's an
infrastructure and at least for the
foreseeable future i think the loop's
not going to be closed it's going to run
open loop that's what we're observing
right now
and so i when we first got started in
this my assumption was that it would
ultimately morph into something like
more like
linux or wikipedia where the community
was really building a thing but i'm not
sure there's going to be a thing i think
there's going to be
a big multiplicity of things built on
this platform
by the way i wasn't implying it'd be one
thing no no no okay right i mean loops
can be closed on niches yeah
dick
yeah um dick rowe i'm
with open learning exchange which is
kind of a child if you will of ocw
we're we're we're starting with the
assumption that
to really
meet the
goal of universal basic education you
have to start with with young kids you
have to start basically the elementary
and then following with a secondary
level
and we're starting also with the
assumption that forget for this to
happen it has to be done at that local
country level it can't be
a central place which is then
distributed but in fact the actual
course development has to be done within
the context of each country so we've
identified 100 countries around the
world where we're helping to open what
we're calling open learning exchange
centers
that have the responsibility for
defining what it is needed for to meet
the goal by 2015 of universal basic
education for their country
and to have the resources to be able to
develop that content in an open source
manner to my to my left here is uh is
matthew carlos who is the librarian for
the billion kids library we have an open
source free billion kids library that
we're developing where all of the
content developed in each of these
countries
customized and localized for that
country in fact is shared on a global
basis through this billion kids library
a key element of that which is the
quality control issue the certification
is that every item in that library will
have a field for comment and rating
and the comments you have to be a member
of the network to comment and rate but
then we know a bit about who those are
so that fourth grade math teacher in
brazil can say give me the fourth grade
math courses that have been rated by
teachers and students at least a four or
five right
five star rating that way they can begin
select by the users themselves what is
quality and not and it's all an open
source it really spins off of ocw if
that's the idea so we think of ourselves
as the child of ocw focusing primarily
on elementary education but also
addressing and hopefully with mit
addressing some of the secondaries as
well but our focus is really on
okay elementary and then mary can i ask
you to speak next
first question up there
so my question um or more comment to
address the issue of scalability that
was talked about earlier um and also the
the problem that we seem to see about if
you open it to everyone and everyone can
address or and everyone can add to it
then you lose the warrants that you were
talking about but why not do what a lot
of companies do which is outsource
different parts
of the business so to speak so for
example with
so mit we're really good at engineering
and with some other fields and so we do
that really well and those sections and
open courseware are done really well but
then there's like other fields so for
example
truck driving we don't do that at mit so
we could have
people who do do that who their
profession is training truck drivers and
then if mit or some other organization
kind of certifies that and then it
becomes part of
the website so it's kind of
a mechanism of outsourcing and then
bringing back into the fold and then
that way you get your warrants because
the people who are doing or who are
adding the content of that specific area
are then professionals in their field
they know what they're doing
and so then that's where you'd get your
warrants
i think it's already happening to some
extent
you know like medical education is being
done by somebody stanford is doing
something you know people in japan are
doing something you know south koreans
are doing something
indian
iits are doing something so it's already
going on
it's little early
but i do want to
i feel a little bit nervous about a
model like that because this isn't about
you know mit and
20 other places dividing up knowledge
and providing certification that's
that's not the way this platform is
going to grow as
chuck and john just said this is not
it's not at the place where it is
appropriate or even possible to think
about
about closing it off this is not
you know mit statement in open course
here's what we do
you don't have to like what we do you
don't have to think it's any good but
it's what we do
and there have to be lots of other
places that say here's what we do
um you mentioned medical education let
me just marry
mary to say something about tusk
hi i'm mary lee from tufts university uh
we have been working on the tufts
university sciences knowledge base
for about 12 years now and
it's
a system that is built with open source
software
that's a powerful infrastructure for
health sciences education
what it allows
institutions to do is build their own
content but also share it
the system is used by several schools in
the u.s
several countries in africa and actually
more recently in india
and it allows faculty actually to
collaborate
not only across disciplines but also
across countries
so faculty as their share we also are
part of the open courseware consortium
uh we have courses from our medical
school dental school veterinary school
nutrition school
uh as well as
our fletcher school law and diplomacy
and these courses
certainly are shared but
we also do curriculum co-development
with these countries
so our faculty and medicine and public
health
and these other disciplines
actually work with faculty in these
other countries to create content that
is locally relevant
so it's a it's a combination of sharing
core content on that
really
allows them to leverage faculty that
some of these countries do not have
so for instance in on the consortium in
east africa
there is one pathologist who flies
across three countries to teach
pathology to medical students
well with uh
sharing content
uh you can actually have other faculty
at these institutions help to teach that
pathology
um in addition to that one pathologist
who's who's the expert who's flying
around
um so i think we're going to see
a pretty rapid development
in these in these countries which really
have major faculty shortages
but able to leverage
faculty from here from other countries
who are willing to share their content
and co-develop the content which then
can be
customized to the local needs and
the other thing that the system allows
is
because it's a very powerful
database structure every learning object
that's in the system
is tagged with metadata so that all of
the content can be reused and repurposed
and so histology which is taught about
across dental the dental curriculum the
veterinary curriculum the medical
curriculum actually those learning
objects can be used and reused across
all those disciplines so
it allows
incredible
leveraging of the content not only
within an institution but across all of
these institutions that are
participating
if i may just say
one thing we have to
pay a lot of attention to is a multiple
meanings to content and you know your
content in terms of learning objects is
both content and activities
and a lot of the repositioning of it to
different cultures different contexts
has to do with actually changing the
activities and i think we kind of
overlook how rich we could get if people
contributed new kinds of activities you
know to the content so to speak in terms
of you know because very often for
example it is the problem sets that
really determine how good a course is
and finding better and better problems
such as something can be done in a very
kind of microwave
could i just uh
ask the the members of the panel
if you would concur that
the configuration of control
the the ability and i think the question
about verifying learning that was asked
by this gentleman over here earlier goes
to the heart of it
or one element of the heart of it that
we have a very set established in the
united states and most other countries
concept a hierarchy of power control and
authority
in which standards are determined by
experts who almost always have been men
in rooms with the door closed
riding the encyclopedia britannica
now i'm
charactering it of course
against which now you have
legions of people in a flat world
reinterpreting and remodifying and
restating and dare we say socializing
standards and reality and modifying it
in a way that is literally
uncontrollable
by any terms that we have understood
historically
and so to me one of the riddles we face
as we go forward because i think it's
like
trying to stop water from going down a
mountain
you aren't going to stop the tendency
what we have to figure out is how to
understand it
that then led me to think
about an itinerant professor
in the 15th century going to a village
and talking to people how different is
that
from a learning group formed
on the net
that begins to
talk with each other
about something they share in common
the former led to something we know as
universities
over time
and what we're trying to imagine now is
what the latter will lead to
in some future iteration
but under it is the societal control
it seems to me in determination and
definition of quality and standards
and i'm i'm curious as to whether people
i'm not i'm worried about it i'm not
worried in a negative sense about it
but in how do we understand it how do we
get on this horse and write it and
understand it do you see those kinds of
things up for grabs
in this
migration we've started where we don't
know
where the ultimate destination is
at the moment
i think we have the modern day
equivalent of the itinerant
professor comes by and
leaves his notes
here's what i know
and then leaves the
conversation and the group continues i
think that's really what we are
talking about here and i recognize now
maybe
why i missed larry's point because i was
answering it in the context of
that person leaving the notes can
certify
the quality of the information knowledge
and structure that he or she has left
but
we are not at least at this point in the
business of certifying what the people
have gained from that and did it
and whether
they are now qualified in in some way
and what is interesting
many things it's fascinating about the
evolution of
both mit's ocw and the larger notion
and the larger movement is what i tried
to say about the origins was really
about
what does a university do in this world
and the real excitement that is emerging
is what individuals do with it and i
don't think we know how we do that
second level of certification
or whether we should
you know again the different types of
signals that we're going to be
encountering and one of those signals
are going to be more the portfolios i
mean so somebody comes to you and
presents a portfolio uh just like
seriously i don't look if somebody they
come from mit i look at what lab do they
come from who do they study under
there's a much more micro thing we
already use in terms of those signals
and i think looking at a portfolio now
the question is at some point that
finesse is a problem
who has the authority to be able to
evaluate the the portfolio but but you
know what is so wonderful and we tend to
over journalize this in open source
you know truth is determined by does
this code run
you know so you actually have an
arbitrator sitting behind the scenes
there which simplified
the mechanisms to make open source
really flourish we move to these other
domains we don't have that kind of
intrinsic arbitrator so we come back to
much more serious types of questions
my comment perhaps addresses questions
sorry
okay my comment addresses perhaps this
question that has been discussed in the
last few minutes
if we are all moving to individual
learners and that this platform is
providing that opportunity
then is there no room for the meta
learner
because it seems to me that if you
cannot certify what is being learned and
if the market is not clearing the
tinkering products because if the if you
are tinkering with products the market
can clear those
who is going to be clearing the market
of learning
uh is is there no room for a meta
learner and i think that's perhaps a
question that i'm posing to the panel to
see
what your thoughts are on that
so i don't think anyone knows but
i'm very optimistic
so if we relate this to what peter just
asked
about
where's the authoritative place and who
is going to be doing this you know this
is exactly if we go back
four years
the the discussion that the news media
was having around blogs right there all
these people are going to put stuff on
the internet and there's all this junk
and all this crap
you know and that's not over yet
but the result has been
there is still the notion of quality but
it's based on an incredibly
richer version of discourse and what i
would hope is that we'll see the same
kind of thing happen
as you open up these these sort of micro
ways to get together for education now
you know this isn't going to happen for
several for several years but
the other thing that it tells you
from the world of blogs is that it could
happen pretty fast once it gets going so
i'm pretty optimistic
and take multiple forms right