and thank you uh John for basically
giving my talk dur while I was uh
putting the slides up so we can probably
go home a Tey bit early today let me
just try the um
how okay yeah how do I go to the next
slide oh the other green botton okay
good wonderful thank you all right so
thanks for the introduction thanks
everyone for being here um we're going
indeed to talk about deployment of large
charging infrastructure for electric
operations for basically accompanying
that ongoing transition that is needed
uh to meet all of the uh climate targets
that we have collectively that that
involves electrification of
transportation and Logistics so roughly
speaking we are um we're developing This
research agenda so I'm at the stone
School of Management and I'm also
affiliated with the operations Research
Center at MIT which is our big doctoral
program in in in optimization and uh
what my research agenda really focuses
on is developing all of the analytics
and optimization uh capabilities that
will look at emerging problems in
transport transportation and Logistics
so we have one research program in uh
demand responsive Transit and micro micr
Transit and how to design and operate um
uh Hybrid models between right sharing
on the one hand and public trans it on
the other hand so how to make Transit
more flexible or vice versa how to take
a right sharing Fleet but decrease their
Reliance on single occupany vehicles
that do contribute to emissions
congestion and high cost for daily
commutes how to find this middle grounds
how can we get the cost of Transit with
the convenience of right sharing what
would that look like and how to optimize
that so that's one big area of research
another big area of research is actually
transportation for social good um if we
look at so we've been looking at at um a
number of problems surrounding the
allocation of vaccines uh the
transplantation of organs from the
patient locations to the medical centers
um and the suppression of wildfires
across a uh a big um um a big uh a large
regions where we have not only to think
about how to suppress how to optimize
suppression activities one fire at a
time but we also need to basically
triage wildfires when they occur and
also route our um fire resources from
fire to fire so there are a lot of
opportunities to have impact across the
systems with uh the type of special
temporal allocation um methodologies
that are at the core of Transportation
optimization and large scale
optimization um today I'm going to talk
about this uh oops
sorry this uh last area here which deals
more specifically with the problem of
decarbonization so we are looking at
this uh again transition to a an
electrified future for uh Transportation
operations and um and the problem is not
only do we have the right CA
technological capabilities in place do
we have the right vehicle Technologies
do we have the right charging
Technologies do we have do we have the
right interoperability between these
Technologies it's not only do we have
the right planning goals of putting
stations where they're needed but it's
also how to make it happen where to
locate these charging stations and how
to operate them and how to operate and
how to revisit how we operate our
transportation and Logistics systems now
that we have additional charging
requirements and so that's where all of
the mechanical engineering civil
engineering layers need to be also
augmented with dedicated analytics and
optimization layers to support this
transition and that's where our ALG our
algorithms are trying to make a de right
so that's kind of the framing of
everything that we doing the group and
uh what I'm going to present here today
in
particular so I'm going to go over two
studies uh um today one is the
electrification of logistics uh with a
particular focus on lold operations
which is a study that we have been doing
in collaboration with the MIT
sustainability climate and
sustainability Consortium Ela was here
just before she's leading that effort um
and then we're going to talk more
specifically about um the
electrification of urban areas um in
collaboration with the MIT Mobility
initiative so if we look at L haul
Logistics uh we have this very ambitious
very ambitious agenda that uh calls for
widespread electrification of Highways
so roughly speaking we have already some
charging infrastructure in urban area
especially again uh when people have um
the the opportunity to have um a
charging station in their driveways and
whatnot um but we're still lacking
fundamentally some charging
infrastructure along interstate highways
and and there is this uh call for Action
to ACC to accelerate uh the transition
toward uh toward uh clean buses school
buses and trucks in particular which are
really taking the Lion Share when it
comes to Transportation related
emissions um in this country and
abroad and so here we're not necessarily
asking the question of if electric
electric trucks uh will become a um uh a
competitive technology uh a lot of uh
signals are saying that the technology
is coming to um is coming to uh uh to
the country relatively soon the question
is how should we plan for it and how
should we improve our um our
preparedness and so what we've been
looking at in this context is uh the
what is called the electric the electric
vehicle routing problem so roughly
speaking the vehicle routing problem is
one of the very old um optimization
problems in our field that deals with
the alloc the the routing of trucks to
deliver packages um in a in a
metropolitan region or in a in a in a
larger region so this is all great and I
think that by now a lot of the companies
that we can think of in that space the
UPS's fedexes Amazon of the world and
whatnot have all very Advanced routing
software the problem is that if now we
are replacing our vehicles by
electrified Vehicles then we have a
major challenge that deals with how to
revisit the routing operations in order
to make sure that our trucks will not
run out of
battery and when we think about electric
driving at a personal level the range of
the vehicles are such that now they
exceed what we would typically drive for
a day or a couple of days but when we
look at trucks that have a very high
utilization and high payloads then that
is not necessarily true and we need to
also think about shifts that are
multi-day where people do not
necessarily sleep for uh I mean the
trucks doesn't necessarily stay idle for
12 hours at night and so now we need to
rethink how we operate in conjunction
with how we charge and so that's what
this problem is doing and so in this in
this research we had the I'm going to
learn how to use this by the end of the
talk I promise but um we we need to
rethink how we uh how we are uh
optimizing these operations with
electrified requirements and um and in
particular we are uh motivated Again by
practice we we needed to model something
that is very important that is
heterogeneity in charging cost across
charging stations some charging stations
are in locations where it's sunny some
charging stations are in location where
it's not Sunny the cost of electricity
is not the same
some El some charging stations are in
locations where the grid has capacity
some uh charging stations are in
location where the grid is already
operating uh near capacity the impact of
charging actions is not the same uh some
charging stations are owned by a
logistics providers some are um actually
not owned by the logistic provider and
the electricity is contracted the
charging cost is not the same so all of
these factors are integrated into this
um this
model and so rough speaking if there are
some optimizers in the room uh we have
uh this interesting column generation
algorithm that will basically build
candidate routes iteratively and
optimize out of those and so we have
this decomposition algorithm of a very
complex decision space into something
that is a little bit more manageable I'm
happy to talk about that offline I'm
just going to go um to go um over some
results uh briefly so the main idea of
this algorithm is that we are kind of
separating operations from charging
station to charging stations and then
we're gluing them together for each
truck and then we're optimizing all of
the all all of the operations of all of
the trucks within the fleet
simultaneously and uh so again um this
is you know the technical part of the
work but uh there is still an
interesting uh lesson here is that we
are making a problem that used to be
instructable now tractable with
dedicated optimization Technologies and
dedicating algorithms and one of the
practical lessons that this is telling
me is that if we want to support that
ongoing transition toward
electrification in sustainable
operations in logistics it's not only a
technology problem it's not only about
when are the trucks going to be cheaper
be more effective be more efficient it's
also about can we support the operations
with new algorithms right and what I'm
trying to what I'm going to show in the
in some results is that operating
business as usual uh systems is not
sufficient to make these new systems
effective and so in this case what I
call a business as as usual setting is
to say let's actually optimize routing
of operations as we used to with
gasoline
trucks and then at the margin optimize
the trips to the charging stations in
order to make sure that our trucks do
not run out of battery right in other
words we operate um uh we operate
according to business as usual rules we
replace all of our Fleet with
electrified Technologies and then we
adjust operations marginally to make
sure that we remain feasible that we
don't run out of battery right and um in
contrast the model that we have here re
optimizes the overall operations by
taking into account the charging needs
and that has an impact on Upstream
operations that has an impact on routing
operations and what we find is that when
we do these two things get together we
get cost improvements that can go up to
5 to 8% in operating cost as compared to
this routing then charge
characteristics and this lesson is very
important that means that again
strategic planning technology
forecasting technology integration needs
to go hand inand with optimization and
data science and analytics to enable
that that these new systems can be
appropriately supported by these
dedicated
tools uh and similarly we have uh
benefits of accounting for heterogeneous
costs as I was arguing
before so this is a project that we've
been doing again for kind of medium to
longall Logistics um on in um an ongoing
next step in this in this uh in this
area is to also think about the location
of charging stations um from the
perspective of a logistics provider but
also from the perspective of a
Consortium of logistics provider and a
very Salient question right now is
whether there is any incentive for
Logistics provider to collaborate in
planning charging stations in order to
take a simple and cartoonish example
FedEx and UPS are competing on the
delivery Market does that mean they have
to compete on the charging Market or can
they actually jointly invest in a shared
Fleet of charging stations that they can
then Co operate in the future in order
to get win-win saving in acquisition
cost and a wider footprint right so
that's um for next
year okay and so now um in collaboration
with the mobility initiative what we've
been doing is Shifting Gears toward the
urban Mobility
landscape and um and in this space we
also have a number of um important
challenges uh the main one being that uh
again there needs to be a dra drastic
shift in uh the penetration of electric
vehicles um if we want to meet a number
of um a number a number of uh climate
targets that were set forth by a number
of cities and states um and this is
something that is really top of mind for
uh many cities across the country that
are races to add uh charging stations
and actually what is interesting is that
there is this realization that the the
EV
the EV Market has been primarily um
addressing a need for people that have
long Ag commutes and a driveway at at
home so think let's think about someone
who lives in a suban area has a uh
access to sufficient land and capital to
invest in a charging station and then
can actually power their EVS to go to
work and to come back home at night
right so this is really the case in
point range is small enough so we can do
that efficiently um
reliably and um commute the commute
costs are high enough so that it makes
sense for that person to invest in a
charging station because um because the
the cost can be recouped relatively
quickly okay but now what what happens
for people who live in
cities um and so there is this kind of a
nice uh uh nice and provocative title
which is hey wait but where will
urbanize charger e is next and actually
this is another policy issue OB
obviously for efficiency reasons because
we want to promote the adoption of
electric vehicles but also for Equity
reasons because you have a lot of people
that are in areas that have underserved
um underserved Surly that that remains
underserved by the current EV
Supply so the question that we're asking
in this research is how to deploy an
efficient reliable and Equitable
charging Network and so basically what
we're looking at is the number the
location and the size
of charging uh stations but also the
technology so roughly speaking we can
think about them as level two Chargers
versus Fast DC
Chargers and one of the question that I
find I mean two of the questions that we
find interesting here
are what what what does um what should
the network look like so on the one hand
I could think of an argument that says
you well actually better technology is
better technology if you have access to
a fast charger put fast Chargers
everywhere the concern is that the cost
is also
higher and so if I can if I can do that
I can also replace that Network by a lot
of slower Chargers that can cover a
bigger area so what's the right strategy
here and another question that we find
interesting is how many charging
stations should we have the mental model
that I think we all have is the mental
model of gas stations because that's all
we know where we have to be to be simple
and
simplistic uh let's just put one
charging station per intersection or per
block per little
neighborhood should that be the case for
Ev
Chargers and there is actually this
interesting question because e EV
charging takes considerably more time
than filling up your your tank and so if
you show up at your local Charger
charging station and it happens to be
occupied by somebody it's not going to
be it's not going to become available in
five minutes it may actually take two
hours for that person to to charge their
cars and if locally your all of your
stations are
actually uh occupied as well then you
may uh that may jiz your ability to
drive your own vehicle so potentially
that would be an argument for a few for
fewer bigger charging stations that will
be centrally located so these are the
core trade-offs that we're looking at
which technology and what network
structure so before jumping into the
modeling elements of This research what
we actually did is actually can we learn
something from data that we have and we
have access to excellent data uh data
sources that come from uh Google Street
View so what we've done is that we have
scraped Google Street View uh
extensively and we have done manual
labeling to try to understand where we
could put charging stations out of a
predefined data set
and then we have trained machine
learning and computer vision models in
order to learn what are the
characteristics of the of the street
that enable us to place a charging
station here and so the example on the
right shows a a parking a parking space
with a fire hydrant and so that is
clearly not a place where we can locate
a charging station and the model will
pick up on that really quickly on the
left we have uh we actually have a
driveway in this case so similarly we're
going to we're going to learn that and
say that no we cannot put a charging
station right
here um and so anyway so we have uh we
have done this and uh from a modeling
standpoint what is interesting is that
we have access to an incredible number
of data uh because Google Street View is
extremely granular every corner of the
street every every every house every
every parking spot you can have access
to it the problem is that this is a lot
of data and that data is actually not
labeled so we could ask all of our
undergraduate students at MIT to
actually label everything here can you
put a charging station here or not I
don't think it's the best use of that
time but it's also extremely labor
intensive and
unreliable so what we need to do in the
space is to do what's called Active
Learning where we actually labeling a
few data points training a machine
learning model trying to understand
where we do well where we do not
retraining new data points and ET ating
that
way um and then the other thing that is
quite interesting from this uh from this
field is that um we have access to
images so images calls for computer
vision methods but actually what we
realize is that we get way better way
more information when we look at
multiple images of the same location
rather than a single one in other words
if you want to understand a
characteristic of a location don't take
a picture take five pictures with
different angles and slightly different
locations the problem is that these five
pictures are not independent so from a
technical standpoint what we actually do
is to use methods from videos rather
than uh pictures in other words instead
of treating one picture at a time we
treat five pictures as basically a very
B very boring movie of the same location
right and uh these five pictures will
tell you way more than any picture
independent all right so this is um this
is number one so uh we ended up with a
model that reached 90 plus% accuracy and
area under the curve um we have trained
um models on hundreds of thousands of
data points we have used um we have used
this model uh to deploy in the entire
city of uh Detroit uh again this is in
collaboration with the mobility
initiative in Michigan Central um which
is um which is a a think tank based out
of Detroit um and we have in Ed quite a
bit of time and resources to build these
types of uh interactive visualization
tools so that users can actually go
there look at where we project charging
stations can be located in green and
where we project that they cannot in red
we allow and we have that platform that
allow for user feedback uh so we can
retrain our models uh iteratively and so
we're actually going to uh going to
Detroit in in a couple of weeks to um to
uh get gather more uh more deployment
data here and see how this can uh how
this fails in a real world setting so um
interesting lessons here in terms of
active learning in terms of video
analytics and in terms of human in the
loop
assessment um and finally um back to our
original question which is how should we
build a network of charging stations in
an urban area so now we take the output
of the machine learning model mainly all
of the Loc
that we were uh we project can host a
charging uh a charging uh
station and we uh cross correlate that
with two other types of inputs one is uh
where are people living where do they
work and where do they travel so we take
granular information on there on trip
trip level um trip level data um and
then there is also another uh another
type of input that is the grid capacity
in each location so how cost would it be
to invest into a new charging station
here so again we we get uh we get this
we feed that into an optimization model
so large scale integer optimization
model that will
essentially Place charging stations in
the network and then replicate the
travels and the trips of everybody in
the city to make sure that we can power
the existing trips with the with the
available uh
Network in and uh we have two types of
results the first result is um a result
on technology and the other result is a
result on optimization so on technology
we find benefits of hybrid networks and
that goes back to what I was saying
before level two fast DC answer both and
the reason and so we have developed uh
we have developed some theoretical
results to guide uh to get these
principles but the the main reason is
that you have a lot of heterogeneity in
your network so in a sense if you have
everyone that goes to work to the same
location DC is great you just put one
gigantic DC charger at the work location
call it kendle Square everyone goes
there you're going to have enough
capacity for everyone to charge between
900 and 5:00 p.m. then they go home and
they can come back the next
day the problem is that you may not have
enough capacity in kle square to satis
all of that demand or everyone may not
be working in kendle square right and so
they may be going to many different
locations if that's the case you end up
with some nodes in your network that are
much smaller and actually from an equity
standpoint this is fundamental because
these are the people that also need
access to charging station that do not
necessarily have the right recourse with
other options to charge and so we need
to complement the big fast charging
stations by small and cheaper charging
stations that will be based on level two
Chargers and we have again theoretical
results for this but uh practically we
find that hybrid networks can deliver
benefits on the order of 10 to 20% as
compared to uh investing all in in one
technology all level two all all DC uh
fast
Chargers and number two is um so again
we built that optimization model we uh
implemented it with real world data we
build our algorithm we made it work
right question you know was it worth it
and um and I think that a good Benchmark
here is to say you know what let's
assume that we don't know where people
are and we we don't we're not as you
know granular in terms of like where to
put the charging stations could we do
something like common sense and to me
common sense is let's put charging
stations where people live where people
work right and so we do like a sort of a
clustering algorithm here where I'm
clustering home locations work locations
putting charging stations there and then
I decide the Technology based on the
number of people that live live around
and then we get Ben benefits on the
order of 20 to 30% again that echo my
result in the previous uh section where
it's not only a matter of you know when
are the EVS coming when are the charging
stations coming and what should we do
what type of Technology should we have
what type of Technology will be
available but also how to use all of
these Technologies right and how to
design a network that can satisfy the
broad needs of the population in an
effective and reliable
manner all right so this is um this is
essentially wrapping up my my talk um so
again the lesson is optimization models
and algorithms for emerging applications
in transportation in logistics with a
focus on electrification and
decarbonization happy to talk more
offline or here if we have time but uh
thank you so much for your
attention will okay any
question yes
please
yeah yes yes yes
yes no uh this is a very uh this is a
very good uh very good question uh this
is um there is a price to pay in what
we're doing which is we're solving a
more difficult optimization problem and
so we are
getting a solution that is like within
1% of optimality and sometimes whenever
the true benefits are actually small um
the loss in accuracy in a sense can be
can uh outweigh the the benefits right
so I think about it as like I would
benefits of charging of a better
optimization is 0.5% but the cost of
difficult optimization is 08 and so here
we have the3 loss uh but this is this is
really an anomaly and roughly speaking
we got I think five 5% benefits in in
most cases yes
please so you talked about where you
live and where you work but also where
you shop wear a lot of them our today
and also you see some in
airports but you know if somebody's
going away for two weeks that's far more
than than the time they need to charge
so probably
sitting absolutely absolutely so to the
first point where you shop yes and so
that's why we need uh trip level
information trip level information will
tell you where people go and then
whenever we have an opportunity if we
have reliable information that tells you
that one person that lives in one place
that works in another place but always
go goes to you know that mall on
Saturday and then you if you have a
charging station in that mall well that
actually serves a lot of purpose so
that's what that's actually one of the
drivers uh of these benefits is that we
have visibility to that and we can
leverage it so absolutely good good
remark when it comes to the airport um
yes you're right and there is a a a big
question that I think we don't have an
answer to um as a society which is how
will people use these charging stations
and um
again if we take the analogy of the gas
station I go there my T my tank is empty
I fill it up and then I leave this is
manual and I stay here with my car the
whole time and then there is a stop
start there is an
end if I think about charging stations
it's very different because the time to
charge can be 2 hours 3 hours and I
don't want to stay with my car during
the whole time I'm going to go to work
I'm going to go shopping and whatnot um
the problem is that I don't have a
three-hour work day I wish um but I have
a much longer work day so if I plug my
car when I show up to work not even
talking about a two we trip at the from
the airport I'm just talking about like
an 8 to 10 hour workday if I plug at
9:00 a.m. my car will be full at 11: but
I may occupy a spot for the entire day
and I think that this is actually a
major challenge underlying all of this
and this is something where we
collectively don't have the right answer
we're going to need to think about new
mechanisms to incentivize people to
exactly charge what they need when they
need it and there may there may be
multiple answers so here I don't have
any research to share with you I'm just
thinking out
loud pricing can can be an option right
and uh whenever you are here and you're
full you're going to have a higher rate
so then okay during my lunch break I'm
going to come down and move my car and
come back up uh there may be companies
that can do that right I mean where you
basically give your car to company and
you ask for some level of charge and
then they can actually do the routing
within the parking garage I'm not sure
exactly what's going to happen uh but I
think that the management of um the
management of uh charging times so to
speak is uh is fundamental and this is
something that we're not really used to
doing right it's the analogy I have in
mind is whenever I Char charge my phone
overnight my my phone um my phone needs
one hour of battery and I sleep for more
than one hour and um and so how to how
to how to manage that will be a question
the difference is that my phone taking
of space in my home doesn't prevent
anyone else from charging but my car
taking a space in my in mit's garage
prevents other people from charging um
another exciting opportunity with uh the
with Michigan Central in Detroit is that
they actually have deployed charging um
charging stations in their own garages
uh and they're collecting a lot of data
on usage and what we would love to do is
to try to understand whether we can
actually do some experimentation here to
see how people respond to different
pricing incentives uh so again maybe
hopefully more to come next year on this
but uh but I think that this is a very
important question on how to manage uh
charging
Cycles any parting
question oh cool thank you all your Alex
thank you so much thank you I you
know I just I just want to tie this last
conversation back to sort of where we
started this afternoon which is you know
know looking at the 10 Trends talking
about sort of the impact on uh Battery
Technology a couple points on charging
okay so ginoa mentioned that Neo a
Chinese OEM has uh about 3,000 battery
swap stations now across China now this
is really an interesting model to think
about in the charging Universe right
because for those of us who have been in
the mobility space for a while we might
remember a company called better place
they had this you know business model to
do battery
swap and and it didn't work out and
there's a lot of sort of interesting
analysis we can do when we dig down into
why it didn't work out and to why it
could work out now in this sort of
second attempt uh that's happening with
Neo in China and it's really interesting
because if you think about
um the battery of an electric vehicle
right the battery of an electric Hummer
weighs more than a Honda Civic so the
energy that you're expending to move
around that heavy battery is very very
significant and arguably very wasteful
so as we start to think about new
modalities of charging beyond the work
that you know Alex is doing on
optimization of the existing system we
can think about you know some of these
these new models and another really
interesting model is wireless charging
there's a company right here in our
backyard witricity and MIT spin-off that
has been working on this for many years
and has an ex exceptional
technology and where is it being
deployed does anyone know the first OEM
to actually integrate witricity
technology is First Automotive Works in
China
so you know I'm just trying to tie
everything back together that the world
is changing quite quickly particularly
in the mobility space um I hope that
this uh Mobility track has been
informative for for everyone and we want
to thank you so much for for joining us
today thank you
[Applause]