Victory Yinka-Banjo was born
and raised in Lagos, Nigeria
and moved to the United States
on a student visa in 2021
to attend MIT.
She's majoring in Course 6-7, or
computer science and molecular
biology.
And she's done
undergraduate research
with Professor Jonathan Weissman
at the Whitehead Institute
and Professor Caroline Uhler
at the Broad Institute.
Currently, Victory is
preparing for graduate school,
where she'll prepare--
pursue her interest
in molecular medicine.
And for those of
you here who are not
involved in this
process, I'll mention
that the applications
to most graduate schools
were due Sunday.
So between that and
this performance,
I'm not sure how restful
Victory's Thanksgiving break
was.
Victory excels in science,
in computational thinking
and also in the arts.
She's involved with the
MIT Black Theater Guild
and has composed and
performed spoken word poetry
for MIT student groups and
for the celebration of Sally
Kornbluth's inauguration.
For today's celebration
of the life sciences,
Victory will present
her piece "Systems,"
which will weave together ideas
about systems of molecules,
disciplines, people
and countries.
Please join me in
welcoming Victory.
[APPLAUSE]
M. I. T. As my words
meet your minds and minds
meet your hands and your
hearts, I need you to zoom out.
Adjust the magnification
of the lens
that you walked into this
room viewing the world through
and give me a chance to
communicate what I argue
is an extended breakthrough.
Because if there was one
thing that my pending biology
degree has shown
me, it is that there
is power in thinking beyond
what exists in our proximity.
Now, travel with me to
a world observable only
by electron microscopy
and you will find
meaning behind this philosophy.
Now, under a microscope adjusted
to its highest magnification,
you might see a nucleus, a
mitochondrion, a ribosome,
individual organelles packed
with biological power.
But if you dare to zoom
out, what you will find
is the subcellular
components operating
in ways far more powerful
because together they are parts
of a whole, subparts of a cell.
In synergy, these organelles--
they form a system of whole cell
complexity.
Now, zoom out again and you'll
find that these cells come
together as tissue, and
tissue together as organs,
and organs with systems
of blood vessels,
and fluids and
skeletal structure.
They create something
systematically
beautiful and dependent as
every human in this room.
To see that you don't need an
external lab tool in accounting
for this larger
picture, our eyes
do more than a
microscope's view see.
Gone are the days of
reductionist biology
of taking pieces apart,
considering them individually.
We are at MIT, so we
build with mind and hand,
put pieces together.
This collaborative is not just
about one part, one subject,
just about biology.
It is interdisciplinary and
to claim otherwise is to fail
to zoom out and look back on
our rich history of revolutions,
be ignorant of our promising
future of expansions,
a history of fundamental
discovery decorated
by the sequencing
of the human genome,
unleashing a scientific
era broader than the Broad
Institute, a history of sharp
Nobel laureates transforming RNA
splicing and medical imaging,
a history that birthed HST,
solidifying relations from
MGH and Harvard Med to MIT,
and a future of expansions
with breakthrough synergy that
advances cell and gene
therapy, uses AI to accelerate
diagnostics and fight antibiotic
resistance of mechanical
engineering building 3D-printed
hearts that pump life into new
treatments, a future of
memories governed by McGovern's,
collaborations with the Picower
and understanding of brains
fueled by molecular power.
This collaborative is
not just about biology.
It is a celebration of
an institute and industry
identical to a table where
everyone can find a seat.
A celebration of a
system built by parts
where everyone
finds their niche,
whether that's in
science and engineering,
where you can
interface technology
into clinical medicine
to develop a therapy
and design its delivery.
But for that therapy to
become a patient's reality,
we need people who
innovate beyond science
to overcome policy, understand
the nuances of clinical trials
and testing.
We have to think about
the markets governed
by a for-profit motive.
And so we need economists
for investor connecting
and for strategized
research funding.
But we also need entrepreneurs
for commercialization advancing
and for biotechnology
proliferating.
And, of course,
we need physicians
to understand the anatomy
of the very people impacted
by this pipeline
of R&D to ensure
the final life-changing delivery
that brings all of this back
to the ordinary people going
about everyday life activities,
see all these [INAUDIBLE]
must synergize
to go from bench to bedside.
But to claim that this
collaborative is only
about medicine is to ignore
the achievable global scales
of science where living
systems can power
the sustainability of life
on Earth as we know it.
Enzymes for plastic waste
degradation, bacteria
for decarbonized food
production, [INAUDIBLE] scales
that allow us to zoom out
of continental borders,
considering systems
of land bridged
by oceans, networks
of nations and synergy
to tackle global
health issues, networks
of nations that come together
to deliver breakthroughs
like a record time vaccine for
a pandemic that was unforeseen,
networks of nations
extending from the Americas
to the ends of the
Earth, including Asia,
including Europe, including
Africa, where I come from.
Gone are the days where science
just stays within our proximity.
To be at MIT is to take
our innovations and science
to a world that needs it
but also bring the world
to a science that needs
it, bringing people like me
to a campus where
they're welcomed.
Would you have imagined that a
Nigerian-born visa holder would
discover at MIT her superpower,
that at the crossroads
of computation and
biology she would tower,
would break glass ceilings
and surmount racially
discriminatory systems,
a woman who 100 years ago
would have been a
victim but today
is contributing
to the advancement
of multiple disciplines.
To be at MIT is to strive to
increase the representation
of minority groups,
where even when
we have declining
diversity in admissions,
we can hold steadfast to our
exemplary all-women president,
provost, and
chancellor positions
and hope the next
time we do better.
To be at MIT is to contribute
to an era of infinite impact.
It is to look beyond the
microscope, zooming out
to embrace the grander scope.
To be at MIT is
to latch onto hope
so that in spite of a global
pandemic, we fight and we cope.
We fight with science and
policy across clinics, academia
and industry for the betterment
of our planet, for our rights,
for our health.
We fight with might.
To be at MIT is to
pursue translation
for more than just Cambridge,
for more than Massachusetts,
for more than one nation,
for a network of nations,
for the globe.
It is right here,
right now that we
set this foundation and
this continuous pacesetting.
Oh, it goes far beyond
differential equations.
It will take collective actions
today, our minds and our hands
to ensure a future that
outlasts us tomorrow.
MIT.
To be here is a privilege,
one that we can pay forward.
So will you exist as yourself,
as an individual cell
unnoticed without a
microscope or will you
become visible by
staying connected
to the far-reaching life
science and health system?
Will you zoom out.
[APPLAUSE]