great well good morning everybody it's a
pleasure to be here in Houston um if
only because it's 20 degrees warmer than
Boston right now so um as Jim said I
have been working both in Academia and
in government around issues of uh
importance to the country particularly
right now in manufacturing Supply chains
and and Industrial strategy at large and
my goal this morning is to really set
the stage for our conversation today and
to do a little framing s what are some
of the trends that are affecting the
country and the globe and help tee up
some of the conversations that will be
happening today from my colleagues uh
later in the later in the day so let me
start with saying I'll be looking at the
changing Global landscape um a little
bit on Industrial strategy otherwise
maybe known as competitiveness or
competitive
strategy next Industrial Revolution
priorities for us manufacturing uh which
will my colleagues Ben Armstrong and and
Anthony will go into more detail and
then finally work of the future which
we'll be doing on a panel uh later today
I'll also make sure that I have time for
some questions and some discussion at
the end of this so that we can uh engage
together on some of these topics so let
me begin with some of the first key
trends that are going on in terms of a
changing Global landscape and I think we
are all aware of these sort of um as
bits and pieces but when they come
together I think they help uh explain a
lot of the Paradigm shifts we see going
on in in the country country and around
the world so the first is supply chain
disruptions and as uh Jim said earlier I
was in the thick of supply chain
disruptions in the White House in 2021
2022 so even talking about this topic
gives me a little bit of PTSD um but we
all understand that we saw through the
pandemic that we had a real challenge in
terms of Supply chains whether it was
low commodity products like PPE or
high-end products like semiconductors uh
what we saw were real risks to National
and health and health security issues uh
as well as economic Prosperity Economic
Security issues we saw about a third of
inflation in 2021 was caused by uh the
supply chain crisis around
semiconductors and for many of you you
are well aware that Supply chains are
complicated and if you look at some of
the major corporations in the country uh
in the in the world they have thousands
and thousands of suppliers and there has
been an effort in many ways to
consolidate this but we're still talking
about thousands of suppliers and one of
the challenges we had uh during the
semiconductor crisis is that neither the
companies nor the government had any
real insight into those semiconductor
Supply chains uh and that became a real
sort of warning and and call to action
particularly for I think for a role for
government to figure out what is you
know how do we understand supply chains
and their vulnerability how do we look
around the corner uh and and if we if we
sort of looked at what was going on
nationally we would have said oh huh 90%
of our Frontier chips are sourced from
one company in one region in the world
that doesn't sound so smart you know I
don't need to be an expert in Supply
chains to tell you that that's probably
not a great strategy um and we knew that
you know 10 years ago but now I think
we're seeing the economy in a very
different light through the lens of
Supply chains uh and that's really
shaping a lot of our our thoughts on uh
on the economy and on strategies and
that's both at the country level and at
the company level and our colleague in
at
MIT um David simchi Levy has come up
with a couple metrics to help companies
think through how resilient are our
supply chains so time to survive how you
know what what number of components do
you have on in your inventory to survive
A disruption uh whether that's in stock
or with another supplier and time to
recover how long does it take for
suppliers to uh get back into full
production and really interestingly his
recent work on some on semiconductors in
Taiwan provided a case study that showed
a 10-day shutdown in Taiwan took almost
a year for production to be back in
track so which what we saw which is what
we saw in the US right bullwhip effect
on Supply chains multiple years to
actually get back on track right now the
Federal Reserve of New York would say
that we are at pre-pandemic levels uh
for S supply chain disruption but at the
same time you know what are we short of
now IV fluids right we one Factory in
North Carolina for the entire country
that again could we have seen that
foreseen that uh drone production right
now the Chinese have now um cut off
exports to one of our uh critical drone
manufacturers in the US uh that Supply
Ukraine again vulnerabilities that exist
today so that's I think something that's
Now new in our our our minds eye of how
we're thinking about the economy and
there are multiple ways toward
resilience companies are thinking about
this and I would say from what my
observation is there's no single answer
here the answer is not let's throw out
just in time practices that's probably
not a good idea I remember all of the uh
containers on the port of LA Long Beach
dock you know we don't need to stock up
but we do need to bring in agility and
um and other ways of um of flexibility
so what we're seeing right now is
increasing Investments
in transparency so let's understand what
we can uh see through sort of digital
connectivity through our supply chain
redundancy the power of two let's open
up uh another sort of supply chain
Channel if we can in our with our
suppliers as well as regionalization
regionalization or distributed
manufacturing creating hubs around the
globe so that you're not vulnerable to
just one you know to one disruption in
one part of the world sustainability
also another key priority uh we're
seeing compan companies very much
investing in understanding where they
can improve their carbon footprint also
of course reduce energy usage as a whole
given the demands on energy uh through
uh compute Etc going forward um and then
digitalization is critical to all of
this if we can't measure what's going on
in our companies and across our supply
chain you actually can't start to
address resilience and sustainability so
all of these are Trends in the supply
chain piece that I think we're seeing
now again in in companies as well as in
countries next next uh major uh Trend
that I think we need to acknowledge is
climate change and you you know we we
perhaps most of us would see uh an
existential threat to the planet on
climate change but if you didn't see
that and you're only uh observing the
economic impact of negative uh weather
effects you would find that we are
seeing this increasing number of
dramatic uh impacts on uh on weather
events negative weather events to the
economy so billion dooll events uh
happening now in 2023 28 of them and if
we looked at 2024 this is before uh we
saw hurricane Helen Etc um so the the
impact of this on the economy the impact
of this in terms of rebuilding for the
country uh is enormous so about a
hundred billion dollar in in expenses um
and impact in 2023 now we're saying
hurricane Helen was probably just 200
billion in on in itself so we just
expect those to increase and we have to
think about how are we're going to
rebuild and what does resilience look
like when we rebuild our Energy Systems
our infrastructure
Etc third Trend geopolitical landscape
when we were in the white house and we
you know were dealing with all of the
supply chain crises and the big issue
was would there be enough gifts under
the Christmas tree in December of 2021
because you know everything was going to
be uh uh disrupted and we finally said
oh we got the gifts and everybody was
you know happy and more throughput than
the US had ever seen um we sort of sat
back and then we didn't sit back for
very long because there was Russia's
invasion of Ukraine uh then we've had
the Middle East uh and we've had you
know what what I learned over time and
many of you will already know this is
that there's always a supply chain
crisis uh and they are more the rule
than the exception uh so in terms of the
geopolitical landscape you know what
we've seen is a conflicts first uh one
One impact for the US is that the
conflicts in Ukraine the Middle East the
tensions with China have exposed some
weaknesses in our defense industrial
base and if uh if we take xiin Ping's
words you know seriously the US is now
focused on trying to build up its
deterrent capabilities um in the South
China Sea for 2027 and what we
understand is that we've got some
vulnerabilities here we have a uh a
supply chain that has uh shrunk over
time uh we have challenges in bringing
Innovation into our defense industrial
base um and we have a bureaucracy that
is that it needs some uh reform so
that's been one major I think uh impact
right now that we're seeing in the
country the other is of course the
rising concerns with China uh of course
if you're if you're you're operating in
China there have been more tensions for
the multinationals whether it's
surveillance uh Etc
if you are um working in certain
industries and semiconductors and EVS
they're concerned about their overc
capacity and flooding the global market
the US has that concerns Europe has that
those concerns as well uh we have supply
chain dominance of course critical
minerals they control 60% of global
lithium 80% of cobalt in the world um uh
infects our drug Supply affects a whole
host of areas as well in terms of uh in
terms of energy and then of course they
spend hundreds of billions on scaling
their Industries and scaling new
technologies we're seeing this in
biomanufacturing we're seeing this in
Quantum and the question is you know how
does the US uh continue to lead
technologically and otherwise in these
areas so a lot of Shifting one point I
would like to make is that I don't
believe that we are de globalizing I
think we are reg globalizing I think
there is a you know concerns about uh
actors like Russia and China in the
world but I don't think that means that
we're going to see a um you know a a
massive shift of domestic manufacturing
for example I think we're seeing uh
significant amounts we're seeing some
reshoring but in fact I think we're just
going to see a a very broader a sort of
different configuration if you will on
how we think about
globalization all right fourth
inequality so what we know about
populism is that at its core is economic
insecurity and we have seen in this
country as well as others a lot of
turmoil and threats to what i' call the
Social fabric of the country um uh
threats to democracy Rises of autocracy
around the globe and I think one of the
things that helps explain this can be
found in what's happened for the typical
worker in the US this chart um is
basically comparing productivity growth
to compensation growth in the US uh from
about 1950 until close to 2020 and if
you were say well let's track the
average worker of compensation compared
to productivity growth youd say well the
two top lines they're looking pretty
good and everybody's you know chugging
along it's looking like uh like it
should um but if we were to take out the
compensation growth for the four-year
College worker and look at uh average
compensation for the nonsupervisory
worker so median and um you know
non-supervisory rules what we see is
this Flatline relative Flatline for the
typical worker in the US and while there
was a you know significant growth until
the 80s we had what we call the great
Divergence in the 80s and that is I
think explains a lot about our political
economy and our politics in the country
right now now the good news is that H
that those numbers have slightly ticked
up since the pandemic we've had a a rise
in the um sort of lower income levels
minimum wage and other reasons but this
isn't important piece of understanding I
think what's behind some of our uh
policies what's behind some of our uh
politics uh in the in the US right now
and again not just in the US you can see
this certainly in Europe and other parts
of the country of the
world so let me move now to what the
implications of all this are so these
four sort of uh I'd say uh Global Trends
if you will around Supply chains around
climate around geopolitical tensions and
around inequal equality have led to at
least in the US and and not only here
but a whole move in this industrial
policy an idea that actually we have to
rebuild in the country areas that we are
vulnerable um that are important for our
National Economic Security so the theory
here is that and the practice is that
the private Market has underinvested in
key areas of the economy that are
important for the country so it it may
be that you're investing you know
companies are doing exactly what they
should be doing in terms of their
semiconductor strategy but as a whole
we're vulnerable as a country and we
have to look through that lens um in
terms of that the same thing with
critical minerals for example so we
Public public dollars are used to
leverage private dollars because our
public dollars will never have enough
public dollars to address some of this
building this capabilities right you
need to bring in private sector dollars
to make this
worthwhile so what's the transformation
that's been going on a couple in the
last few years so a federal agenda that
emphasizes building resilient Supply
chains rethinking globalization and
investing in critical Industries what we
saw in many ways uh how this is played
out recently has been this legislation
over a trillion dollars in public Dollar
in public investment going on over the
next 10 years uh about a trillion in the
bipartisan infrastructure act so that's
our uh physical infrastructure Rail Port
train Broadband also energy
infrastructure uh 52 billion for chips
and science that is essentially
semiconductor investment around the
country and then also about 370 billion
which is mostly in tax credits for clean
energy in the IRA and that would I just
to say that that is while there are tax
credits for particular types of energy
essentially the model has been whatever
produces zero emission is is essentially
fair game for those tax credits so
trying to maintain a sort of a Level
Playing Field for investors uh as to
where they're going to invest and the
and and this has been you know extremely
successful if you'd only measure these
policies based on how they crowded in
private sector investment you'd say
hands down success we've got close to
250 billion in clean energy Investments
close to 250 300 in semiconductor
Investments you know this is this is
looking successful of course that is not
uh success is not just about the money
it's how we land the plane uh which uh
which we're all very focused on but
Goldman Sachs uh has said that this at
least just in clean energy we'll see a
three
trillion dollar investment in clean
energy total for public and private
investment which is enormously
successful and has um not made us uh May
made us very popular with our European
friends uh as we've seen a lot of
investment coming from Europe into the
US this is just an example of what we've
seen uh in terms of the clean energy
it's mostly been in batteries and in
solar and I will say that the uh states
that have been seeing most of that
investment actually California and Texas
so Texas actually is leading the country
on renewable investment uh including
critical minerals um and so it's been a
very exciting time to see some of those
uh Investments uh start but we need a
Whole Decade I think to really see this
play
out let me move now to the issue of an
industrial revolution and priorities for
us manufacturing as I said before I
spent a lot of time on Supply chains but
what I see as the flip side to supply
chain resilience
is actually um increased Advanced
manufacturing that you can't do one
without the other uh and again I think
Ben and Brian will be talking uh to ways
this plays
out but um let me start with us
manufacturing now I would say about a
decade ago um actually it might have
begun more than that in the late uh in
the in probably in the like early 2 th
mid 2010 Etc um we have had a sort of
recognition that said us manufacturing
is critical to our Innovation capacity M
MIT was involved in a produ in a
research project called production in
The Innovation economy and historically
the model sort of was evolving to one
that said as long as we keep the
design uh and the services in the US the
production can go offshore and we'll
just keep the higher value added work
but what it turns out is that in fact
that starts to affect actually our
Innovation our capacity to innovate in
these products that you have to know how
to make uh and so slowly but surely the
US you know created uh We've the
manufacturing USA institutes there's
about 17 of those around the country we
started to recognize that our
manufacturing capabilities have been uh
depleted uh and now we see just in the
last uh year or two both the defense
industry as well as our nationaly which
is sort of a broader I'd call it I just
call it the civilian view on this
recognizing that manufacturing is
critical to our um Innovation and uh and
our competitiveness more broadly so what
does this mean this means resilience
Supply chains this means sustainability
energy and energy usage um and it means
digitalization as I mentioned before uh
how do we bring connectivity to our uh
to our industrial base RIT large because
that's what's going to lead to
productivity and that's what's going to
lead to increasing wages cyber security
also another critical area uh for those
I'm I'm sure many of you are aware of
the the risks there the manufacturing
bases have been most um most at risk
here that's been where the highest
percentage of attacks has been um and so
addressing that and working with
companies and government to try and
address cyber security another key issue
and third augmenting workers and we'll
talk about this uh later today but if
people have been tracking the
manufacturing uh industry essentially
what we see is that in the next six
years we will have um about 2 million
unfulfilled unfilled jobs in
manufacturing um so how are we going to
address that what does it mean to fill
those jobs I think technology plays a
role um but it also means uh trying to
upskill our current workers and also
increase wages so we attract the Next
Generation uh because they have a lot
lot of options and they're
technologically savvy and so what do
they want to see they want to see
actually technology as part of their as
part of their work so all of this is
part of an agenda for manufacturing in
the country and what we've um seen I
think recently is a is a sort of
bipartisan Collective Agreement that
this is an area that the US should
invest in and that there are a lot of
positive spillovers for the country
let me just walk through I mean because
I was sort of the policy adviser I
apologize but I kind of have to provide
my view on the policy side of this um
but there are a number of areas where I
think that we should uh look for
investment both at the state and the
federal level in fact states are leading
in this in some ways more so than the
feds and so how what does that look like
and the first is accelerating technology
adoption so the US is amazing at
innovating we invent a lot of the
technology here but it it's amazing how
we fall behind when it comes to adopting
technology so when it comes to robotics
for example China and Germany have a
higher penetration rate than the US on
robotics when it comes to additive
manufacturing Brian will fill fill us in
there but I think we have in the US we
have um the you know we're driving The
Innovation driving the patents but we're
just not seeing the adoption as quickly
as we'd like so how do we get the
adoption not only in the large companies
but in small and mediumsized companies
which are the backbone of the country
about
250,000 small medium-sized firms that
make up our manufacturing base um you
know if we only wanted 50,000 of those
to be at The Cutting Edge of
digitalization we don't really have a
mechanism for doing that we just the
states have no capacity uh you know it's
not about necessarily more uh more money
per se we've got to find the right
incentives for for getting companies to
actually get on board on
this uh another topic which I've worked
a lot on is how we enable scale up so we
all have seen models that the you know
the US leads of course in um software
development and in uh all of the scaled
large technology companies that are
leading in AI uh again uh Europe and the
dry report you know underscored the
challenges for Europe in doing that and
some of what dragy pointed out is that
the US strength in financing scaleup is
partly what explains the growth of some
of our leading software and and sort of
AI related companies um but that
ecosystem that sort of scaleup model is
very much um oriented towards a software
scaleup and not necessarily the hardware
scaleup so what we know about some
technologies that have a lot of you know
engineering and and Hardware is that
they take a longer period of time to
scale and they take take more Capital
they're Capital intensive it can take
tens to tens of billions tens of
millions of dollars if not a billion
dollars it's certainly an energy to try
and bring a technology to Pilot scale or
certainly commercial production scale
and so what can we do as a country to
try and accelerate some of that and so
there's been a lot of experimentation
going on uh venture capital is dipping
its toe in here in a way that it hasn't
in the past um but we're seeing shared
pilot facilities so how do we how do we
to bring some public private dollars to
bringing that pilot capacity uh online
uh how do we do this in terms of tax
credits we've seen the again the
investment tax credit has been very
successful in bringing this kind of
investment for clean energy um and then
how do we have other funding Vehicles so
can we imagine firstof aind funds can we
imagine Insurance that's helping with
tech Innovation what are the ways in
which we bring in more capital for that
growth stage of uh of of it early stage
kind of technology companies uh other
countries don't think twice about this
they subsidize this area uh China's got
a very you know robust way in which it's
supporting a lot of its companies in
terms of their growth we have to come up
with a model in the US that building on
what we have already that's going to
help fill that gap of what we call the
missing middle in terms of
capital okay Workforce Development again
there'll be more to be uh said on this
uh and my uh colleague Ben Armstrong has
been working uh deeply into this area um
but what are we missing in terms of
technical uh a technical Workforce and
an upskilling of the workforce and what
we know is that actually when companies
invest in technology they actually
invest in in upskilling their Workforce
it's almost this virtuous cycle so
rather than sort of moving to the lowest
Comon neor of no new technology lower
wages Etc how do we actually move that
in a different direction uh so we need
to invest in the in in bringing that
technology into the firms and then we
need to create incentives for companies
to actually build uh that new that new
pathway forward for workers uh because
the reality is as I said before wages in
in manufacturing are not keeping up and
we're not attracting the Next Generation
so how are we going to actually do that
I think technology is a piece of that
answer is a piece of that puzzle um and
there's a lot of a lot of efforts at
every state I I know uh the Texas area
has you know really robust
uh manufacturing organizations uh the
MPS Etc um but we need to now bring that
at a na to a national level we need to
really look at ways in which we're
trying to bring the Next Generation and
see a path forward a pathway to the
middle uh because what we know for
example is that for technicians which do
not require a four-year degree um you
can make a very good living and there's
a middle class pathway for those workers
and remember that about 40% of those who
start a 4-year degree do not finish in 6
years so that's a waste of money a waste
of time you know let's find those
Pathways forward for workers in the uh
in this
space tariffs and Export controls uh I
don't want to go into too deeply into
this topic it's uh you know it's highly
charged and we don't know where it's
going to land I think at any point in
time we have no idea where this is
landing um but the reality is that we
are now um looking for ways to kind of
level the playing field if you will and
that I I believe that the US has
suffered from a very aggressive Chinese
policy uh to uh invest in um if you will
dumping products and then pumping up
prices and you know wiping out a lot of
us industry so tariffs I think have a
role to play we're seeing them used uh
selectively and uh and we'll see where
that plays out going
forward finally um Advanced
manufacturing R&D of course as someone
at MIT I I'm I need to talk about the
science of this the science of
manufacturing processes and the
importance for investment on that front
uh as much as we are uh you know making
advances in kind of operations the the
R&D of manufacturing is still critically
important and this can be foundational
uh science breakthroughs uh or
foundational engineering breakthroughs
like what we need in Quantum or can be
much more applied like continuous
Manufacturing in biomanufacturing
but across every single one of the areas
that we see the US needing to compete in
whether that's critical minerals
semiconductors clean energy all of this
actually is needing an R&D component an
R&D engine to get us uh into leadership
roles and help us Leap Frog on the
technology because that's ultimately I
think how the US uh competes in this
area and actually leads globally is
actually going to be through the
R&D let me now move on to
uh the work of the
future and this was a billboard that I
drove by for a whole year uh on my way
to work and it was um it was sobering
because I thought wow is that all we've
got as a response to the robots and if
some of you remember the um the Super
Bowl in 2019 I do um every commercial
had a robot serving you a beer that was
our future right the robots are coming
they're going to take your job they're
going to take your kids' job we're going
to need a universal basic income because
everybody's going to be on a beach not
working what are we going to do um so
actually I think things have changed
right and that fear subsided and one
could argue that if we had had more
robots during the pandemic we might have
saved more lives and our challenge as a
country has always been quality of jobs
not the quantity of jobs right and and
what uh MIT did in 2018 to
2021 was set up a task force on the work
of the future our president at the time
Raphael re was approached by you know uh
the Great and the good and everyone else
on campus to say you guys are inventing
the robots what are you doing about
their impact on society and uh he took
that very seriously and we set up a task
force that had all five schools involved
so we had the technology folks we had
the engineers making robots but then we
had the political scientists the
anthropologists the sociologist coming
together saying what does this mean uh
you know what we haven't this we have
we've been here before this concern
about technology and and frankly right
now the robots have Sub sub you know
subsided and now ai has moved forward
and that's our our latest fear about
technology um but what does this all
mean so I won't go into great detail um
about about the findings of the report
but I I like to say I mean I'm proud to
say that I think the results of that
report still hold strong and stand 5
years later so let me just run through a
couple of those High you know
highlighted
points so three key findings the first
is that technological change is
simultaneously replacing existing work
and creating new work often as humans we
can only see what's been replaced you
know we used to have a medical
transcriptionist um who was taking you
know taking down the dictation and
typing it up at the hospital no they no
longer exist you know what's happened to
that person it's very hard for us to see
the new creation of work and what we
know from our work uh from our colleague
David otter is that about 60% of the
work today did not exist 80 years ago
you know there's a lot in which it gets
recreated of course none of us would
have said uh at least I wouldn't have
said 5 years ago oh I want to be a
social influencer I think I'll figure
out how to make money off Tik Tok
I still can't say that and I hope my
daughter will not be saying that but in
any case there are all the ways in which
you know new jobs are being created and
as I said before our challenge has not
been about the quantity of work uh
outside of of course business cycle
works it's been about that quality of
work and that leads me to the second
point which is Li Rising labor
productivity this is a a chart I showed
earlier hasn't really translated into
broad increases in
income and what we decid what we sort of
landed on as a task force was to say yes
there are impacts from technology so
technology has wiped out a lot of in you
know that middle middle rung jobs in in
in manufacturing in clerical work so we
we have a bit of a dumb a barbell
economy right where we see growth in the
low-skilled workers growth in the
high-skilled workers and and this
missing middle that has technology has
played a role there and yes we've seen
the impact of globalization
so uh when China entered the WTO uh and
we start CH Chinese Imports into the us.
and the manufacturing we saw a major
impact on our manufacturing communities
right textile industry all these
industries moving offshore competing
trying to compete with lower cost
products and as a country I think we we
did not do enough for those communities
and for the intergen generational
impacts of that um but the reality is
every country faced technological change
and faced global global Trends as well
um those you know those have hit every
every country um but what's really
different are the
institutional uh conditions in a country
and the US's institutional conditions
for workers are are quite different than
what we'd find for example in Europe so
what does that mean that means like a a
minimum wage minimum wage the rise of
minimum wage a number of states in this
country has done more to compress the
income inequality in this country than
just about any other policy it means uh
unemployment insurance it means Health
Care it means training and investment in
training it means worker voice all of
these ways in which workers the typical
worker um can be supported through these
transitions we we should be less
interested in supporting the job the job
uh than we are are about supporting the
workers and I think when we see
reactions that are you know hostile
toward Innovation or technology or
automation it's coming from it's coming
from the place that chart showed earlier
people have been left behind they are
they do not trust that this technology
is going to actually you know help them
get ahead and move forward and be part
of the economy going forward so I think
this issue of you know what we broadly
call institutions is important for us to
to look at and uh and I believe as a as
a society we have been in a number of
different
ways finally momentous impacts of
Technology change are unfolding
gradually now uh you know the first
reaction to that is no AI is happening
so quickly what are you talking about
but let me remind you of where we were
five years ago and the autonomous
vehicle and if you can all recall that
you know the Panic that we were going to
all of our truck drivers were going to
be out of work and I can tell you if we
had had more truck drivers during that
pan the crisis of the pandemic we would
have done much better through it but the
fact is the that this technology
technology does take time and a lot of
the research at MIT has shown almost a
30-year Arc for new technologies to
really uh take hold uh again I don't
think that'll happen with the AI I think
things have Mo are moving much more
quickly but the fact is we do usually
have time to adjust as a society and to
help our workers transition
uh and to get ahead of this and I think
I think with AI in fact we see a lot of
uh public and private leaders trying to
quote get ahead on that topic in a way
that maybe we haven't in the past so I'm
encouraged by that but we can't be
complacent we have to be you know
actively looking for ways to help make
sure that everybody can transition
through these technological changes
because they will continue to come uh as
we know so I'm going to wrap up right
there and uh leave a few minutes for
questions but thank you all very much
[Applause]
raise your hand if you have a question
and we'll bring the mic to you or a
comment yes right
here M you go and please introduce
yourself oh hi uh my name is Brian
Thompson I work at Cisco uh food
distribution organization um I was just
curious in any of these findings um has
there been a inclination to look at
education I mean I feel like young
people right now it's it's almost a
crisis of Despair uh they don't see a
path to Victory so you know instead of
becoming an electrician maybe I should
get familiar with a CAD program right or
um you know any variety of other kind of
skill sets and our education system or
at least our public education system is
not doing a very good job of providing
that hope right you know that path to
Victory so is there any policy
initiative or Forward Thinking portion
of this that deals directly with the way
that the federal government is planning
on dealing with education at scale yeah
very very good point I I will first say
I don't feel I'm an education expert but
what you are pointing to which a lot of
people point to is actually our efforts
at Workforce you know the workforce of
the future have to begin from K through
12 so I think there's a lot of focus on
what do we bring into the K through 12
uh experience and education curricula
that helps expose students to the
critical learning and thinking that has
to happen for the for that path forward
the other thing the other area that I
think as a country we're focused on is
that um you know we have we know how
students March forward through high
school and get a high school degree uh
which most high school um students do
which is a great achievement in this
country um
but then there then it's like a cliff
you're on your own to figure out what
you do next right and that is not the
model you'll find in uh in Europe and
and what we need to do is create that
pathway that allow that takes takes the
student uh right from high school into
their next secondary career path and
that is an area that people have been
focused on in terms of trying to build
up apprenticeships uh and get get high
school students into early you know
college
associate degree um credits IBM has a
program where they're taking uh high
school students and bringing them into
community colleges to help train them
over a three-year period to be um cyber
security analysts so I think that
there's uh an understanding that that's
that there's a a crisis I mean I don't
know if I use the word crisis I think
others would in terms of in terms of the
education process but there are points
in the system that we where it really
breaks down in the US and we don't find
it elsewhere necessarily yeah
atomically those things were
relevant but now with the Adent of a lot
of these Technologies those skills are
not necessarily asant right maybe
there's
aing that a little
yeah giving young people this vict
you're talking about a you're talking
about Rare Minerals a lot of these take
10 15 years before they exactly start
producing
anything right no and I I think that
that's I mean the idea of the skills
that need you know that the students are
going to need or or the next generation
is going to need I think those have been
well identified um how they're taught
how we bring them into the system I will
say for vocational training now in the
state of massachusett for example the
state has doubled down and is trying to
vastly increase the number of seats in
vocational training which is bringing
you know more sort of the shop floor
training and the engineering piece
together for uh for a pathway that's not
doesn't involve a four-year degree and
has an associates degree associated with
it but we'll have more time for this
conversation later today yes other right
here so my apologies the question is a
little complicated you shown the kind
flatlining of the uh incomes what I'm
wondering is if you have a sectoral
breakdown of that so what I'm getting at
is it people doing the same job being
paid the same salary or are people
moving from higher paid sectors into
lower paid sectors so it averages out as
um you know as a flatline even though it
really is reflecting a different thing
and indirectly what I'm getting at is
the impact of offshoring and I remember
a while back Alan binder at the FED had
done some work showing the uh your
incomes depend not on the skill required
to do the job but the ease of offshoring
the job and I'm wondering if that aspect
of that flattening of the income has
statistically expect yeah I believe it
does it is part of what we're seeing
there because the the this flatlining is
in part the wage distribution that we've
seen that what wages used to be you know
concentrated in the middle and the lower
income have headed higher up so I think
that is a reflection of some of the uh
of the jobs that have headed out and so
those who had the those um those better
paying jobs have moved into lower paying
positions yeah into sectors and so the
question I mean again what's the answer
to that is actually how do you build the
quality job what does that look like to
go forward and and Ben might have some
thoughts on that later today uh okay um
I think I'm gonna have to oh there's one
more question I'm gonna squeeze in one
more question sorry I know they hate it
when I do this so but really quickly
thank you my question is uh you know you
mentioned about the friction in uh the
you know adoption of technology and
innovation in US companies compared to
say uh Germany and I think it was China
what are some of your thoughts on how to
tackle that yeah oh good a small a small
question and it just happens that our
next speaker is going to speak to that
so I'm going to punt and do and find the
halfway point here and allow Ben to
answer that question in his talk so
thank you all very much