The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
>> Uh, okay. So, I'm actually going to keep
discussion today pretty short because
the games that we've got lined up are
pretty long. Uh and uh there are
>> two of them I know are really good. One
of them was good last year. So we'll see
again this year.
So So we'll see. Um are they all for
playing games at least?
>> I'm blessed. I we're going to have
Puerto Rico which I told
>> I call thieves.
>> Cool. Uh for people have you played
thieves before?
>> No. Good.
>> Okay. So, uh, for people
>> who played San Juan last time, I think,
uh, Puerto Rico is an interesting
comparison. Uh, because San's actually a
sequel to Puerto Rico. Uh, so you're
kind of playing in reverse order.
>> Uh, that was the one where, uh, sort of
like, how would you describe it?
>> Is it related to Race the Galaxy as
well?
>> You choose the action.
>> Ah, Race. Okay. So that that takes us
right into today's uh
>> so Puerto Rico is kind what was
>> Puerto Rico is the um I'm going to I'm
going to guess it was actually the first
in the series. I certainly do not know
of any immediate predecessors or
inspirations and uh San's kind of the
carc version of this. um which is why we
introduced it earlier because you guys
were working on on card games. Race to
the Galaxy is more of a um
spiritual successor uh as as described
in in in reading or uh but you could
also think of it as a clone with few
upgrades because it wasn't the same
people. It wasn't the same people who
made uh
>> to clarify the guy who did San Juan and
the guy who did Race for the Galaxy were
kind of collaborating
So the games are really similar. They
influenced each other, but they were not
strictly the same project. So you can
think of it as multiple people from the
same artist community turning out
similar games at the same time.
>> Nice.
>> You know, uh but yeah, informed by each
other. And um and when Race came out, it
was very much seen as this is this is uh
Puerto Rico with problems fixed or uh or
gameplay expanded uh
>> problems added to
>> and problems added to and you know and
of course a completely different scene
but you can s but at least in terms of
game mechanics that's a nice a nice
connection that you can actually see
among the games that you played before
and you're going to be playing today.
Um, not every single game that we've got
here is got that kind of u that kind of
heritage. In fact, today's games aren't
specifically picked to meet to meet to
match up with today's team uh of our of
sequels. The only reason why I talk
about sequels cuz we have to talk about
it sooner or later.
>> Um, of course, Battle Star is, you know,
straight up adaptation of of of the TV
series. And uh and you know I wouldn't
quite call this a sequel in a sense
because simply this is not based on a
previous Battlestar Galactica game. I'm
sure there were previous Battle Star
games that you know were based on the
old 70s TV series that have nothing to
do with this one. This is more of a
adaptation. Um and I and the reason why
I'm using that that phrase is so that we
can be fairly clear in our in our
vocabulary. This is taking elements of a
something that's in a different medium
like a film or a TV series uh and trying
to figure out what in that TV series in
that world that has been created that
fictional world um might be might yield
interesting gameplay and this game is
pretty much about figuring out who is
Sylon among all the players
>> uh you know among all the players
there's going to be traders and you try
to hide your activities and you try to
help people uh help human race survive.
Uh if you happen not to be a traitor,
but some of the things that you end up
doing in order to help the human race
not to survive, they end up looking
suspicious. And if you play Mafia, it
kind of has a little bit of that feel.
This is way more heavyweight in terms of
game mechanics because they really
really wanted to make you think like the
charact like you have the same dilemas
that the characters in in the TV show
have.
>> Does the Sylon know that he or she is a
Sylon? I believe that I believe you can
find out halfway.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Uh if I recall the rules
correctly. Um and then there are people
and then there are uh players who will
know right from the beginning. So there
may be more than one
>> generally is more than one.
>> Um
>> I'm psyched.
>> Okay. So um to um there were a bunch of
different things that were that were
listed in previous reason as reasons why
people want to do SQL but for for the
most part the big one is just you're
building off an established base. You're
not having to build everything from
scratch. Um in many cases a sequel
doesn't actually cost less or take less
time than making the original game. you
just end up spending hopefully spending
the development time a little bit more
wisely, right? You start you you you you
avoid a lot of pitfalls because they're
pretty much making a very similar game.
And game industry has been one of those
fields where uh um oddly enough, part
two, you know, the the followup tends to
be better than the original as opposed
to um you know, how many movie sequels
are generally better than the original.
Godfather, that's
>> back. Uh, it's rare.
>> It's really rare. Um, I'm thinking
>> the Kendy's word man of No Name series,
Godfather. Any other
>> Back to the Future?
>> Back to the Future.
>> I don't know. It could go either way.
>> I don't agree.
>> It could It's arguable.
>> It's arguable.
>> You mean like Empire Strikes Back?
>> Spider-Man.
>> Spider-Man, too.
>> I don't know. I felt like they were all
>> true.
>> It was better.
But yeah, you know, it's really
difficult because
>> Dark Knight. Uh yeah, I will yeah, I
will give you that. Um but you know,
it's it's still kind of tough. Uh
whereas how many good game sequels, how
how many games can can can you think of
where you play both the first the
original and then the sequel to it?
>> Also,
just the sequel.
>> Oh. Oh, okay. Because Okay. for some of
them the space apart so far that you
actually only ended up playing
>> I mean like Halfife
>> Halfife Halfife 2 for instance you know
Starcraft
>> Starcraft 2
>> Age of Empires
>> Age of Empires one two and then three
>> Shogun Total War
>> well the Total War series
>> yeah Total War is kind of an interesting
thing because they don't pitch them as
sequels but they but they very much
pitch them as a series and they and the
whole idea is that if you liked one game
you actually know a lot about what any
of the other games in that series do.
Sure. Graphically they're upgrading game
game mechanics wise. They're trying to
port over a lot of things. They just
some of them are medieval, some of them
are Japanese.
>> Yeah.
>> In reading they mentioned that Final
Fantasy 7 was a sequel to six. Is that
corre? I don't think is that like
correct nomenclature.
>> Uh you see and I and I will disagree
with that actually. It's like I don't I
mean Final Fantasy 7 actually has a
sequel for instance. Uh was it crisis
score
actually? There's more than one and it's
okay. Sure. Well, I mean, first it was
the movie, right? Their sequel was the
movie and then they they did a bunch of
things.
>> Oh god.
>> Final Fantasy 7 is Final Fantasy
>> an entry in a series, but
um
>> but I think when it comes to this is
what we're going to be pitching to a
publisher. I I'm not sure if Square Enix
needs to pitch Final Fantasy.
>> I I think of another game that has a
long series, you know, um if anyone can
come up with one.
Bersgate might be actually a good one
because different different companies
end up working
>> working on different types of revisions.
Uh actually most of the sort of yeah
that well actually Fallout and Balders's
Gate both come from inner play I believe
originally. So like
>> they went out of business after
Bloodlines. We were talking about this
yesterday.
>> I suspect that that was vampire
>> Yeah. But uh but basically it know
leaving aside what makes a company go
out of business. Um yeah the the the
issue of when you have a series and then
you have different companies making
different brands. Guitar Hero 3
nice old re
so boware was did the first one and
Obsidian did the second one. Um Fallout
was Bethesda. Obsidian, I believe. OB
Obsidian's really built a whole business
model around making part two or
something. Um,
>> or expansion packs and stuff.
>> Oh, expansion packs. Yeah. Closely
closely
re related to that. And in those cases,
sometimes like in the case of um boware
obsidian connections, they they have a
good relationship. They're borrowing a
lot of technology and they are getting
that advantage of. We kind of we we
we've kind of ironed out the kinks.
we're just sort of continuing the story,
especially if it's a story based game
like Knights of the Old Republic.
Clearly, you've got to fit it within the
whole Star Wars story. Um, and they had
the interest to basically keep the tale
of these characters going. Uh, even more
so for well for Mass Effect it was by
the way by you know that sort of thing.
Um but then you have the other you have
the other angle where uh you just want
to sort of get the same success but you
want to tell a different story or in the
case of Guitar Hero 3 have a completely
different set of set of music. Um, and
uh, you know, Final Fantasy 7, you have
the certain game mechanics and certain
things that carry on from game to game.
And definitely you want to carry the
fans from game to game, but part of the
appeal of the Final Fantasy series is
that every single one is going to be a
different story. Not dramatically
different, but it's going to be a
different story um, with different
characters and different world.
So um but it's pitched very similarly
when you go to a game company and the
whole idea is how do we get the fans to
buy even more or even more fans to buy
version uh two.
There is a there are kind of two ages to
that sword though because what typically
happens in a lot of sequel development
is that you're trying so hard to please
your original fans and often by adding
complexity by adding things that build
on things that you that players of the
first game already know that you
actually start alienating new players uh
the game becomes just so complex or you
know just complex enough that people
start getting turned off. Um
uh couple of weeks ago over here we
played Guitar Freaks um on Friday on
Friday games for Gambit and the first
version is actually extremely
accessible. Once you get from the second
version all the way up to I think the
version four that we were playing uh it
is almost impossible for a new player to
jump in because they've got like one
beginner friendly song and everything
else is based for fans of the game. So
you imagine a Guitar Hero game that's
built entirely for people who've already
mastered expert on the previous game.
That's kind of what happened with Guitar
Freaks. And in many cases that might be
enough to, you know, if if game was
particularly successful the first time
around and you only get 80% of the fan
base to buy the second version, that's
still a lot of money and it's a way
lower risk compared to, you know, coming
up with new IP from scratch. Um but um
and and a lot of companies when they're
creating IP they're very much
specifically thinking right off the bat
what are the SQL opportunities even now
of course you got downloadable content
so it's even narrower than that is what
are downloadable content uh uh
opportunities how do we release
expansion packs you know really really
quickly and uh how do we create stories
worlds technology that just going to be
able to anticipate all that um there's a
game up there now on Xbox Live Arcade
called Monday night combat um and uh and
they they did some little clever hacks
to basically allow them to update the
game on a week- toeek basis. Whereas
typically that that kind of
certification that's required from
Microsoft is really expensive. Every
time you want to release a new version,
you have to put it through an entire
rigorous QA testing schedule again. But
they came up with some technology that
lets let them make at least game tuning
changes on the fly uh without having to
go through the Microsoft tuning uh uh
testing uh so it's not technically
releasing a sequel. Uh but they were
very much thinking about how do we keep
updating this game. Um I wouldn't be
surprised if Steam started off as that
Blizzard uh battle net kind of started
off as just an easy way for them to get
up patches and to keep tuning this game.
Eventually someone involved decided hey
we could sell games this way and you
know launch was kind of bumpy but you
know it's fine now
um
there is one thing which the which the
book didn't mention which is the reboot
the sort of franchise reboot um this can
sometimes happen when you have a uh
publisher who's got control of an IP
that kind of floundered halfway you know
maybe there was a bad bad execution on
the on on narration and lost most of the
fans or they just played out the formula
to death. Uh and then they want to try
to get a new batch of fans. You know,
few people who like the original one.
Um, and I was talking about the Tomb
Raider game uh uh you know that that um
where they're just trying to they've
rebooted the Tomb Raider several uh Tomb
Raider franchise several times at this
point each time trying to say okay
you've probably heard from Tomb Raider
from the huge amount of advertising that
we've done but you may not actually have
liked the previous versions of the games
and we're going to reboot this franchise
by making a different game in that same
world where maybe we'll make and Tomb
Raider will use the characters and we'll
use the fiction but we'll change the
game play significantly. Um because
we're not going after the old fans
anymore. We're going after a new batch.
Um it's uh probably about the same
technical challenge as uh updating as
trying to make a SQL for a completely
new platform. So uh uh because you're
basically having to write everything
from from from scratch. But the good
news of course is that all that previous
advertising that you did, you know, a
decade ago still still still works. Um,
let me think of uh Can anyone think of a
good example of a good reboot?
>> Is Mario 64 a reboot?
>> Uh, I think it was seen to a lot of pe a
lot of people that it was cuz it wasn't
clearly a uh a sequel to any of the
previous Mario games. And it was kind of
Nintendo kind of saying, "Hey,
>> it's not really a clone of anything.
>> It's not really a invented a lot of
invented a lot of things for the first
time." In fact, I would say that Mario
64 and and and and of course the way how
they branded it, they didn't brand it
Super Mario World what, five or Super
Mario World 4 or something. They called
it Mario 64 to sort of distinguish it
from
>> I would almost call it an upgrade more
than a reboot though because it was
mostly just the move from two uh 2D to
3D. Um,
>> it was more it's a good challenge
because to the player it may seem like
it's not that, but for a technical point
of view, they had to completely reinvent
the way how Mario moves, the way how
Mario jumps, frankly. Uh, uh, the way
how the camera moves never used to be a
huge problem in the 2D games. Uh, but
was the primary thing that they managed
to figure out how to get working in in
in 3D was was the camera. Um, I think I
mean I wouldn't be surprised if their
marketing pitched it a little bit like a
sequel, but it was also very very clear
of like this is going to be a whole new
generation. You've never played a Mario
anything like this. So don't expect your
previous Mario experience to cover to
carry over necessarily.
>> I was going to say Metroid as well.
>> Metroid Prime.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. That's that's a really good
example of um in fact Metroid Prime was
an instance where they gave the
franchise to a completely different
developer. You know, previously it was
all old internal Nintendo and then
Nintendo went to Western Developer um
Retro Studios over in Texas and
basically had them make the first person
uh version of of Metroid, but they had a
very heavy hand in controlling that.
Whereas um I'm not sure we're going to
be playing this later, Castlevania Laws
of Laws of Shadow, which just came out
was a kind of windy other way around. a
western developer, a spe a Spanish
developer decided to make a Castlevania
clone. Um, you know, they love
Castlevania and they were going to make
a game that was just like Castlevania,
but they wouldn't call it Castlevania
because they didn't have the rights for
it. And then they showed it off at like
a E3 or something. And Konami basically
said, why don't just turn it into a
Castlevania game and they put Kojima on
it to to to make it work.
>> That must have been their dream come
true.
>> That was probably their dream come true.
That's probably what they wanted. And
you have the advantage of all the
Castlevania fans now now now saying,
"Okay, this is this is going to be in
Canada. If we like Castlevania, we
probably like this one." Which is
exactly what they were trying to get
across. It's like imagine the people who
made Torch Light being approached from
Blizzard say, "Why don't we just turn
this into Diablo 3?"
>> A bunch of people who made First Light
were from Blizzard, right?
>> Uh I wouldn't be surprised Diablo team.
>> I wouldn't be surprised in the same
sense that a lot of people who made
Guild Wars were from the World of
Warcraft team. Uh so that's that is less
issue of sequels and more an issue of
just that's just how the game industry
works. People move from project to
project and carry knowledge with them
>> like Call of Duty was elemental modern
people, right?
>> Yes. Call of Duty. Yes.
>> Got tired of it. We're like we can do
better.
>> That that that's an interesting
discussion of the instead of sequels uh
you have companies making effectively
clones uh competing against the original
franchise. And this particular case that
you're drawing yet there's people who
left EA uh of 2015 I believe and then
they started Infinity War and they made
a game that basically competed with the
original.
>> The first Call of Duty was so
ridiculously good. At least it marked me
when I played it the first time.
>> But it but it's very clearly trying to
be Medal of Honor the next version.
>> Yeah, clearly. Yeah. No, of course. Of
course.
>> Yeah. So, so, so that's that that's an
interesting situation where uh it's hard
to be a spiritual successor when you're
competing against the original
tournament. Uh, but you know, you can
think of them
>> by that dragon I mean not competing
spiritual success with Dragon Age
because they don't have the right gate
anymore.
>> Uh, yeah. Well, Dragon Age is more of a
DND clone I would say. Uh, which
>> yeah, I guess
>> Empire Earth is reinvented itself with
with Empire Earth. Empire
>> with with zero success doing wonder.
>> Oh. Uh I kind of lost track of this. You
>> in the whole game the whole game the
first game was like you can go through
15 ages. We will like model you can
literally play a game against someone
and go from prehistoric units to nukes
>> in the same game with everything in
between. And then they release a sequel
which I think overseas and then they
decide to read it themselves and go
we're going to simplify everything.
there's just going to be like four ages
kind of like in ancient empires and
we're not going to have this like
massive progression and and they try to
simplify everything and it totally
>> you see I think that's a reboot
>> but but but I think that's that's that's
a reboot gone wrong that's that that
that's a our original game is not
selling well enough among new players it
maybe and it's not entirely satisfying
our old fans. So, we're going to take
this franchise that we've advertised
really, really well. Uh, and we're going
to make a completely effectively a new
game, maybe with the same theme, but but
a new game that's targeted at a new set
of players. Sometimes it works,
sometimes it bombs. Um, Mind of Magic
released a game called Clash of Heroes.
Might Magic. Clash of Heroes for the
Nintendo DS. And who's played any of the
original Mind and Magic games?
>> They're different from Heroes of Mind of
Magic.
>> Uh,
either of them, actually. So, who's the
Heroes of Mind of Magic?
>> Okay. Can you describe the game?
>> What's it like?
>> Do you want to go for it?
>> Well, it's like a it's essentially just
a turn-based strategy game
>> where you have cities and you have
heroes and these heroes lead armies and
you encounter other smaller armies and
try and defeat them and stuff. And you
have like
>> and build up your city and turn to have
you have an economy.
>> Yeah. you have an economy and and you
you build things in your city that can
then like produce better units for your
armies and stuff and you can take over
other cities and
>> so
civilization I would say
>> yeah it's it's like civilization but
if you took civilization removed
everything that wasn't like military
>> and battles are played out we sort of
distinctive like arena
>> yeah you have like a battlefield field
where it's turnbased and you have your
units on one side and the opponent's
units on the other side and you move
units together. So like if you have, you
know, Pikeman and Bowman, you have like
the clump of all Bowman who then move
together as a unit and so on and so
forth.
>> So Clash of Heroes is a Nintendo DS game
in the in the Might Magic series. And
what they did was they made a match
three game. They made a game where you
it's like Bejeweled. You take three
Bowman, put them in a row, and then they
become a bunch of Bowmen who are going
to attack. Uh, so they they get the same
idea of let's take and because of
Nintendo DS, there are two screens, so
the enemies uh armies are on one and
yours are on the other just kind of like
sending troops up and down. Uh, but the
game play is dramatically different. Uh,
it's effectively a franchise reboot. Uh,
they they they want to sort of get the
same idea of, you know, leading massive
armies against each other. I think they
take some of the characters or at least
some of the technologies that came from
the original heroes might m magic. Um
but that that that's as far as it got.
Everything else that everything else
they changed because they're going for a
completely different audience. The the
assumption being Nintendo DS players
like match three games. Um like Joel. Um
it's actually really good. I I I will
encourage you if you like match three
games. Um, so,
uh, I was going to put Sarah on the
spot, uh, for, uh, having worked on, uh,
Thief 2 and Thief Gold and Thief Two
Gold and, uh, a number of, uh, of
releases, but you can start telling us a
little bit about your original
involvement on Thief.
>> Sure. Uh, you're going to stand up so
you can actually hear me.
>> I can bring the microphone.
>> Um, so, um, Thief, the dark project, um,
I came on as actually as lead tester. Um
partway through it I became QA manager
essentially and then I actually stepped
into design role um for about the second
half of the project. Um and I continued
to work as a design designer and a
project manager on thief 2 and uh thief.
>> What were you designing in thief?
>> Um in thief one I was pretty
specifically designing gameplay for a
level that someone else had already
built. building levels took a lot longer
than putting in gameplay. Um, at least
from my point of view, I think the
person who built it thought that
building levels was a lot faster than
putting in gameplay. Um, so it was a
good combination, but it was built by an
artist who didn't have the scripting
experience or the testing patients to go
through and make sure that all the exper
the gameplay experience was working. So,
I was basically handed the level and
said, "Okay, make it fun."
>> Now, Thief is a first person stealth
game. Basically, you're looking through
the eyes of a thief who is not
physically all that robust, but uh he
can sneak and uh he can shoot arrows
usually at your back uh and you know and
hide. So,
>> and the AI is unlike in most games where
AI is tuned to sort of aha we noticed
you, we recharge you. The AI is is
carefully tuned to both tell the player
if the AI sort of notices you if the AI
thinks he's looking for you and is
looking for you and if he's actually
coming after you so that a player who
makes a noise while sneaking up on them
will realize that oh he noticed that I
should go be more quiet. Um so uh the AI
feedback and tuning the AIS was actually
really pretty important to playing
experience apart. If you didn't give the
player an avenue to approach a guard
from behind or to sneak up on them in
some way, you were pretty much
guaranteeing the player would get play
get killed because the player could not
in fact take one guard on one to one um
many times. You could probably kill one
guard face to face, but then he'd be
sufficiently wounded that the second
fight would finish off. So, you had to
be giving the player uh channels and
ways to sneak up and places to hide and
things like that if you wanted to have
an interesting game. a challenge.
>> And that's the gameplay tweaks that
you're talking about.
>> Those are the gameplay tweaks I'm
talking about. Yeah. Placing AIs,
determining their paths. Um, putting
actually this little particular level
had a lot of traps in it. So, um,
creating the traps and then giving clues
to the player in game so that they could
a either notice the trap was there
before getting hit by it and, uh, find
some other way to trigger it or, um,
notice that it was there or notice it
was there and then discover how to get
out of it.
Thief is a uh 199
>> 198 at this point.
>> 199 1996 was it was it was released
around the same time Doom was.
>> And and it's pretty impressive because
in Doom you can't look up. I believe you
can shoot them but you can't.
>> Yeah. In in Thief you can crouch, you
can lean around corners. Um you can in
fact shoot your bow while leaning around
corners and Yeah. um you can look up and
down and all around. So yeah.
>> So that's Thief one. How what happens
when Thief 2 gets approved or you know
>> um well the first thing I need to do is
convince people they want to do Thief 2
because while Thief was a great game and
it has actually sold fairly well over
time. Its initial sales were not what
publishers want to see because the
initial sales the publisher wants to see
is oh my god it sold 10 million copies.
Awesome. Instead, what we did was we
sold a fairly good first initial sell
through and then it just kind of kept
going. So, the first thing we had to do
was convince them that yes, Thief 2
would be a good idea. Enough people are
continuing to buy Thief 1 that those
same people will all run out and buy
Thief 2 on the very first day. Um, and
the way we did that was first of all
taking a look at forums and saying,
"Hey, look, people are pretty excited
about this. They're enjoying it. It's
got good lasting power. Our fans are
going to stick around to play with it a
second time." And that was sort of a
marketing and analysis that kind of went
into the publisher. And the other part
was saying, okay, what are the
improvements we're going to make to this
game? How are we going to change this
game to make it better than Thief 1
while still taking advantage of
everything we did? So, we created
basically a big design doc with here are
the areas that we thought we could have
done better in Thief 1. Here's what
we're going to prove. And here are the
changes we're going to make. So, we're
not going to make Thief 1 again. We're
going to take what Thief One was, add
some improvements to it, make a deeper
story, and hopefully give a more variety
of gameplay was what we actually ended
up aiming for in our initial docs. Um,
was we wanted to give Garrett additional
abilities, give him a little bit, give
him give vary the gameplay. The gameplay
in Thief 1 was all speed. We tried to
have some additional types of missions
in Thief 2. It's been long enough that
there was a little more face-to-face
fighting. there was a little more um
subtrafuge instead of just sneaking
around. We also had okay so now you need
to disguise yourself to someone and
sneak in and sneak out again because you
need to achieve you need to pass for
them while getting a goal done and
things like that. So we tried to find
what are additional stealth and
subtrauge um issues in gameplay we can
have.
>> How many of those features in teeth do
were inherited from like dropped
features of teeth or ideas? A lot of
them, a lot of them inherited from
dropped ideas from Thief 1, but when we
first when they first started designing
Thief, and I was not on the initial
Thief design team, so now I'm I'm making
up what they were talking about. Um, it
wasn't clear that it was going to be it
was it was sort of like it's going to be
a stealthy e game, but we hadn't
actually defined what stealthy gameplay
was yet. So, um, it was Thief one that
kind of told us what this is what
stealth play is that works. And once we
found the one or two things that worked
and kind of went with that and hung with
that, it was a thief too. We got to play
around with what are some other ideas of
selfie gameplay. What are some other
ways to trick people into
if people have played Metal Gear Solid
or any of the games in the Metal Gear
Solid series, it always a lot of
especially the really really noisy NPCs.
You want I heard something. I wonder
what's over there. That's awesome.
>> DSX also.
>> But but DSX also also got
>> Yes. Well, that's what I'm saying is
that DSX also actually took a lot of
thieves lessons and went on with them
from there.
>> Again, a lot of people working on thief
DSX
>> uh DSX 2 or DSX 2, but yeah, um Looking
Glass folded and went out of business
and um a lot of people moved to Austin
to then work on Thief 3 and DSX 2 and
and and those projects there. So,
>> um I have a question about um the gold
the gold version.
>> The gold version. the gold versions of
the games are um really a way to try to
convince from the marketing point of
view is a way to convince players to buy
the same material again. So it was it
was I'm being a little cynical here and
I admit that. Um but we added new we did
in fact add what we did was we added
several new missions. So, it was
expanded play and then we went back and
problems that we knew were in the
missions, we fixed them and we actually
added some richer gameplay to several of
the missions that, oh god, we have to
take this out the door. We have to take
this out the door. This would be so cool
if we could set this up, but we don't
have time to. And out it goes. And so,
we went back and we touched up over half
of the missions. We added some
additional gameplay. We added extra
goals. We added we took areas where we
thought the gameplay was particularly
weak because we'd gotten rushed on
finishing it. and we made the levels a
bit longer and a little more interesting
in our opinion. And then we also added
three new levels in. It was kind of a
chance. It was a doover. Um, we had very
limited programming resources, so we
didn't really need to add any add in
much in the way of new features, but we
were able to go back and tune it and
make significant changes to the levels,
to the way that the guards worked, to
the scripting behind the levels. If
anyone's working on a 3D mod, you know,
there's usually a fair bit that a
designer can do behind the behind the
walls of of telling the AIs what to do
and how to think and how the gameplay
flows. And Thief especially had an
extremely rich editor that u more
powerful, I think, than any other editor
I've ever worked with. Even though it is
now 15 or 20 years old, 15 years old, I
think, um, it's still the most powerful
editor for a designer that I've ever
seen.
>> So, um, Do you feel that in like how
much you you mentioned you looked at the
forums and you looked at pan input and
how much of that of what went into
creating the sequels actually came from
pan input or was it just like verifying
what you already wanted to do?
>> Part of it was to verify what we wanted
to do. Part of it was to verify there
was enough interest that people would
want to do it. Part of it was to see
what did people like most? Which of the
missions did people like most? And what
are there any good ideas out there for
how to play how to play a game that we
think yes, you know, they're right. We
never thought of that. I think that one
of the things people talked about a lot
was actually disguise missions. And I
think we had two disguise missions in
Thief 2 where you kind of disguise
yourself as as no, no, nobody look at
me. I'm I'm just another guard walking
around. Don't worry about me. Um,
and that was something that we said, oh
yeah, that would be really cool. And
that's something we had no time to
implement for Thief. But if we're
choosing our if we're choosing which
features new features to implement for
thief too, that was actually not an
amazingly difficult one because you just
figure out a way to put a tag on the
player that says, "Oh, guards don't get
upset when you see them."
>> Did you have uh situations where players
came out with exploits that you tried to
address in the gold version?
>> There were not. No, actually there were
a couple of places where people found
bugs that were um level enders that got
people stuck that we went in and fixed.
There were not a whole lot of exploits
um that I recall us trying to get in and
fix.
>> So if somebody like deliberately found
something that put them on the roof of
the castle or something like that that
you didn't bother trying to
>> um if it if it allowed the player to get
to the place where it broke the game, we
did try to fix it because we tried to
fix anything that was a game breaker
where you could get up on the wall and
then leap off into the void. Um, but
sometimes what we do is rather than stop
you from getting up on the castle and
proving how cool you were, we'd let you
get up on the castle, but we put
invisible barrier so you couldn't hurl
yourself into the darkness and then
crash the game. So, right there, if
players enjoy finding those things, so
taking them out doesn't taking them out
doesn't enhance the gameplay. And the
point of the goal project was to try to
make something where the gameplay was
sufficiently enhanced that it was
worthwhile to go out and buy again.
>> So now we're in an environment where
patches are pretty much just downloaded,
right? We don't we don't necessarily
have that situation in the early 90s. Uh
is there still a rule of space called
gold versions re-releases?
>> I think now again that would be an
expansion pack. I don't think I don't
think that you would do a gold version.
you do an expansion pack and with a with
an expansion pack patch you could fix
old problems and you might introduce new
versions of levels but I don't think you
go through the hassle of doing you just
expansion pack
>> thanks
[Applause]
questions for
your experience
>> so pretty much all your dat
forums we
>> oh no oh no that was just one of the
places where we looked we also looked at
sales
and continued sales and things like
that. Like I said, that was actually
more of a marketing sales to sort of do
here's the hard here's why we think
players will like it. Here's some
experiences we got. Here's the hard data
on our sales, how our sales are
continuing. Um, and the fact that Thief
is having while it did not come out and
sell 100,000 copies the first month,
it's continuing to sell 20 or 30,000
copies a month, which means that word of
mouth is pretty strong and people are
continuing to go out and buy it and go
out and play it. And here's the forum
where a whole bunch of people are using
the editor we released and the activity
in that forum is going up over time, not
down over time, which indicates you've
got more people coming into it. People
are coming in, they're staying at it and
using it. And you've got more people
continuing to come in. The community is
growing, which is means that there's
interest there and there's people who
are paying attention to project continue
to pay attention to product.
>> But also for gameplay, for finding dead
ends, for finding So you said you fixed
some dead ends of games you found out
about those. Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Well,
the difference between a Let me think.
At our height, we had a 12 person QA
department.
Um, and 50,000 users is pretty big. Um,
I we did our best on testing it and we
had like another 10 or 15 helpers
through our publisher, but
I mean, we had comparatively speaking a
ridiculously small QA department for for
the game. But then you have a situation
where someone does something on the
forum and then you can verify it when
you give it to.
>> Yeah.
>> And you can actually figure out whether
what they were seeing was exactly the
problem they were describing.
>> And it being a solely single player
game. I know a lot of games do um you
know beta do large beta tests where they
ask you know 500 200 or a thousand
people to to play the game. We did not
do any external testing like that at
all.
>> Yeah.
>> Also back in the 90s that would have
>> also Yeah. It was not the sort of thing
that was really done in the 90s as well.
So, it's a it's very much a
developmental shift.
>> Did you ever explicitly ask on the
forums like if there were another
sequel, would you buy it
>> or did you just
>> I don't know. I did not do that. Um,
>> I was not on the forums. I helped some
of the forum data and read forums, but I
didn't really post on the forums a lot.
>> Um,
>> do you think that'd be a viable tactic
or would you just say people would
probably just say
>> I think that your data would be very
good. Okay. I mean, the most you're
probably going to get is a thousand
people who read the forum say yes and
that's a thousand people and that's um
not enough sales to justify doing
anything.
>> It's more interesting. I think it's more
useful to look at trends like if you've
got like a survey out maybe. I don't
know. I've seen I've seen companies
bring in focus groups of their people
who played the first game to come in and
they're bouncing off either prototypes
or features that they're planning for
the second version to see how they will
respond to them. I would say that the
information you get back from that is
also not very good. Um, but it might be
something that is done to gain traction
in internal studio politics. And I was
like, well, we did this exercise where
we brought these people in and they said
these features are okay, so we can take
the risk of actually developing it as
opposed to, you know, saying driving the
entire process of
>> games. Games don't respond really well
to um focus test based development.
Well, focus group.
>> Focus group based group development. Um,
getting feedback on your games is great.
Um, finding out how many people are
likely to like your game is a lot
harder,
>> especially if they never if they can't
actually see it when you ask them that
question. Uh, then they have no idea uh
what they're commenting on. You'll make
something up that they think you want to
hear. Uh, it's like, "Yes, of course,
we'll buy a copy of the game. We love
the first one. Sure." You know, but
they've never actually seen the second
version of the game. of you. So you
don't actually know that the case. Um
for those of you who do miss Iran Goi's
talk uh last week uh he was talking
about how um in amplitude which was a
sequel amplitude or frequency
>> frequency
>> frequency is the first one amplitude.
>> Oh yeah I think it wasn't the very first
one. So that was frequency. uh he was
talking about how uh how the folks from
Sunny were helping them run their their
focus groups and um and they did two
tests and one of the tests was you know
after they played the game they would
they did a survey of how many people
were planning on buying this when it
came out and they had like some
ridiculously high score like 80% or
something like that like the highest
but they also did a survey of how many
people were planning on buying the game
just by looking at the box before they
played the game and that was a
ridiculous be no number and it's only
and it's only people called it. It's
like this is not going to sell because
you know sure the people who played your
game are going to enjoy your game but no
one's going to play your game in the
first place because people can't figure
out what what your game's about and you
try to address those problems with the
sequel. Uh that's that uh that's one
thing Brenda talks about your your
chance to do a doo a chance for you to
go back and fix the problems that you
found in the first one especially when
you find those problems really close to
ship date. There's nothing that you can
do about for the first time around, but
if you're lucky, you get a second chance
to do it.
>> Yeah. I also noticed that frequency was
not called in or rather it wasn't um
frequency too.
>> It was it wasn't frequency too. They
called it amplitude. So, it was actually
kind of a reboot as well. It was like
they kind of just wanted people, okay,
let's pretend frequency didn't happen
and that's we'll make sure that the
frequency people who love the game know
that
>> have a ton. Yeah. It's much easier to to
tell the a small base who liked you, oh
yeah, and buy this game than it is to
say to tell a large group of people who
weren't interested the first time, no,
no, you didn't like it the first time,
but trust us, you'll like it this time.
Um I've seen a couple of uh companies do
uh effectively uh go versions every time
they move to a new platform like the
latest platform which they release it
from tends to become the definitive
version that if you're a big fan of the
franchise and you're willing to buy this
game multiple times you want to get that
because of a few extra features that
they put in. Maybe it's different
endings. Maybe it's upgraded cut scenes.
Uh if it's a role playing game I see
that a lot. uh maybe they redided the
cut scene from scratch or reded the
audio from from from scratch. So it's
the same assets but clearer and science
higher resolution. And of course, you
have games that uh that started off
their lives as online flash games and
stuff like that and then get moved on to
other platforms like DS or PSP. And
those those games tend to have not only
completely reworked controls because
controls are different um but also a lot
more features because you have to now
justify to people who may have loved the
game but didn't pay any money for the
first version to actually put down money
for it now. Um so N is a good example of
that. It's one is a game that came out
by Xbox live arcade. um and did DS and
PSP but started it live as a free flash
game and lots of people loved it but
lots of people didn't have to pay any
money for the first version so how much
they love it is uh kind of a weird
factor
okay so well that's not really
I guess we should start with the games
more questions