All right, our next speaker is Jesse
Angrates who's an assistant professor of
genetics at Stanford University and also
a member of the NNFC Center for Genomic
Medicine here. Jesse,
>> thanks so much. Really happy to be back
here at the Broad and uh see um so many
friends and familiar faces. Uh I'd like
to share today some of our um two recent
stories um trying to map the regulatory
wiring of the genome to link varants to
functions. So, building on this
beautiful framework that Molina laid out
um now 10 years ago, um we know that
each of these variants that we've
discovered regulate some gene in some
cell type to affect some pathway to
affect disease. And if we could map that
uh variant to function connection, uh we
might discover clues that help us
develop new drugs. Um there are of
course beautiful examples from uh this
community that have illustrated this
paradigm. uh one that I love is uh VJ
and uh Stuart Orcin and Dan Bower's work
to characterize variants associated with
cickle cell uh or fetal hemoglobin um
where they showed of course that there
are non-coding variants in aniththroidid
specific enhancer of BCLNA which BJ
showed is a repressor of fetal
hemoglobin um and that if you can if you
target crisper to cut at this enhancer
you can create a therapy for cickle cell
disease and I wanted to share this uh
example example uh to illustrate three
you know key points. Um one of which is
that most of these disease variants are
non-coding. Um these disease variants
tune gene expression in specific cell
types and this is proof of concept that
editing regulatory DNA has therapeutic
potential.
So we're working on a number of
different approaches to systematically
accelerate this process and uh um to
more rapidly convert variants to to uh
to functions to medicines. And I wanted
to share two particular stories. The
first of which is to think about how
could we interpret non-coding variants
by identifying all of the enhancers in
the genome and linking them to their
target genes and cell types.
So, of course, there are a few different
approaches to link non-coding variants
to their cell types and target genes.
Um, one might be to apply single cell
ETL approaches like we heard about
today. Um, the challenge here is power
and scale.
Um, we could also use crisper to go in
and edit variants or perturb enhancers
that contain variants. And of course
here there's a similar challenge is that
these non-coding sequences can have very
cell type specific effects and we can't
possibly crisper every possible cell
type in the human body. So what we need
instead or in addition to these two
approaches are really good predictive
models that would allow us to take a
particular non-coding variant and look
up its function across nearly any cell
type in the body and identify the cell
types in which that variant might act as
well as the target genes.
Um so one simple approach that I I
developed together with Charlie Fulkco
when we were both here at the Broad um
is called ABC or the activity by contact
model. And the idea here is that if you
simply estimate enhancer activity using
bulk DNA or K27 cell chipsseek data and
you multiply that by the 3D contact
frequency between an enhancer and its
target promoter which you can measure
with high, you can actually predict many
enhancer gene uh links and begin to
build these genomewide maps across many
different cell types. The challenge with
this model is that it's not 100%
accurate and it relies on these bulk
epigenomic measurements that are
difficult to acquire in the uh many
thousands of cell types and states in
the human body. So for this project we
teamed up with Robin Anderson's lab and
in a project led by Maya Sheth in my
group and Wayan Chu uh here um we
thought about could we use single cell
data to predict these enhancer gene
links instead. Could we leverage the
growing amount of single cell epigenomic
data uh to build predictive models to
learn enhancer gene links in any cell
type?
So the first step here was to build a
large gold standard data set. Good good
first step when developing predictive
model. Here we're using crisper eye to
perturb many different enhancers and
measuring their effects on target genes.
And for this study, we used u an
integration of many previous studies um
that was led by Andreas Gashwin in my in
my lab um where we integrated some of
the data we had collected with data from
Jason Dur's lab and Lars thus's lab
reprocessed and harmonized everything to
create a data set of about 10,000 gold
standard examples where um we've landed
crisper eye in a particular element and
very precisely measured the effects on
gene expression and the effect sizes of
these elements span a large range. range
um from zero to you know almost complete
repression and then you know the red
dots are the regulatory um uh enhancer
gene connections and the gray are the
ones where you perturb with crisper uh
we had good statistical power but you
don't see an effect so we can use this
data set to evaluate different
predictive models and the first thing
that we did was compare these crisper
data to various uh uh models that have
been previously developed to predict
enhancer gene regul population from
single cell data. And so here's a
precision recall curve predicting uh the
crisper data. The perfect model would be
up here. If you simply link every
element to the closest gene, you get it
right about half of the time. Um if you
link an elements to genes based solely
on distance, you get this curve here. Um
if you build sort of a um poor version
of the ABC model where you estimate
activity using attack only and you
estimate contact with a function of
distance, you can do slightly better
than distance alone but not particularly
uh well and it turns out it seems like
attackseek in particular is not a great
uh measurement of enhancer activity
compared to DNA seek or to K20 cell
chipsseek. And then in gray are a number
of other models that are based either on
uh correlation between accessibility and
gene expression across single cells or
cell types or based on regression models
that are trying to use uh accessibility
at multiple nearby peaks to predict
expression. And none of those models did
particularly well at predicting the
crisper data.
So the model that we developed is called
single cell E to G. And it works like
this. So we're going to take a
particular single cell data set that has
many different cell types. We're going
to look at one cluster or group of cells
at a time and within that one group of
cells we're we're going to compute a
number of different features. Uh first
we're actually going to compute the ABC
score from the pseudobul attack in here.
And then Whan developed an approach to
uh integrate um information about
accessibility gene expression
correlations with ABC that actually
strengthens the predictions of the
score. We also add in a few features
like distance um the class of the
promoter which we've shown tunes
responsiveness and other um features
that are sort of based on molecular
mechanistic studies of how enhancers
work that we thought would be important.
Um and then we train a very simple
logistic regression classifier directly
on the crisper data uh in cross
validation. So this is an eight feature
model. It's not uh you know a billion
parameter foundation model and
fortunately there's no um no chance of
it gaining sentience soon. Um so here's
uh here's the performance of this model.
Uh it actually does quite a bit better
than these previous approaches in cross
validation in the in the crisper data
set.
um showing that when we combine uh this
ABC score with other features, we can
indeed boost the performance and now
accurately predict uh crisper the
crisper data from a single cell
multihomem experiment.
One of the limitations of this analysis
and of many of our previous work is that
a lot of this crisper data is in a
single cell type in K562s. Uh and so we
were also wondering whether this would
generalize to other cell types. In in
theory, the model which we trained on
K562 cells should now be able to take in
multi-m data from another cell type,
transfer to that cell type and make cell
type specific predictions about which
enhancers regulate which genes. And so
to test this um we collected and again
aggregated a number of different studies
that we and others have have done since
we trained the model um and created a
held out data set that's about uh 4,000
examples across five different cell
types. And when we evaluate single cell
E to G in this data set it also does uh
quite well much better than distance or
the ABC model and much better than these
other simple correlationbased
approaches.
So we're now really excited that we have
a model that we can apply to many
different cell types and build genomwide
maps of enhancers. And just to
illustrate um what we've been finding
when we are starting to use these maps
to interpret variants um we've been
interested uh uh since moving to
Stanford in understanding the genetics
of heart development and heart diseases.
And in one study in collaboration with
Will Goodyear's lab, we collected a
800,000 cell single cell atlas of human
fetal heart development between 6 and 22
weeks of age across 41 different
samples. Um there are 90 different cell
types and states in this atlas. um
including all of the major cell types in
the developing heart as well as many
subtypes that we're starting to
recognize now that we have sufficient
depth and really deep attack sequencing
in the single cell atlas. So for example
among the endocardial cells if you
subcluster the endocardial cells you
find clusters of cells um that are
specific to particular spatial locations
in the heart. So the endocardial cells
along the the lining of the atrial
septum look very different than the
cells that are lining the inflow side of
the valve and those look different than
the outflow side of the valve. And so
they're very uh specific and in this
case spatially distinct um gene
regulatory programs at play in these
different uh cell types.
So here's an example where we are using
these single cell enhancer predictions
to interpret a variant that's associated
with atrial septile defect as well as
with uh various quantitative
measurements of valve structure. And
when we look up this variant across 90
different cell types in the developing
heart here are just a selection of
different cell types. We can see that
this variant um is in an intron of a
gene called GSR2. it overlaps an an
enhancer that's predicted to regulate
both GSR2 as well as this other gene w
9B um and in specifically in endocardial
cells in various locations in the heart
and most strongly in um endocardial
cells on the inflow side of the valve as
well as in the atrial septum. Um, just
as one sort of confirmation that this is
working, um, we cloned this sequence in
a mouse reporter assay together with Len
Pinocchio's lab. And I'll, it's a little
hard to see here, but basically this in
human enhancer sequence lights up in the
outflow tract here. And when you section
this, you see that indeed uh, this
enhancer is active in the endocardial
cells, which are the single cell lining
along here, the developing valve.
So this is a great example I think of a
variant um that we've puzzled over for a
long time and that we could only
interpret once we had really cell type
resolved predictions of the regulatory
genome. In this case we have no good
cellular models of endocardial cells and
certainly not of the different subtypes
that exist in these different spatial
locations in the heart. And so it's only
by looking at the uh cell types in their
native tissue environment in vivo with
these predictive models that we're able
to interpret and start to understand
what this variant is doing.
So we would love for you to try this
out. This model is generally applicable
to any you know single cell multiome
data set. We also have a version that
works with single cell attack only. And
of course, you know, as we expand these
data sets into many individuals in
health and disease, these types of
predictive models, as well as the one
that Yesper described earlier, will be
able to make inferences about what
variants are doing across many different
cell types and contexts. We've also
recently just uh made public an EDG
browser. So, if you go to
edg.stanford.edu,
this extends the open target interface.
You can type in your v favorite variant
and look up its predicted effects across
about 1,600 different predictions that
we've made across all of encode and many
single cell data sets. So let us know uh
how that works for you and we're we're
curious to see um what we can learn.
So in the second half of my talk, I'd
like to um share some of our work
starting to explore if we could rewrite
regulatory DNA to reprogram gene
expression in desired ways. And this is
work by a graduate student in my lab
named Mike Montgomery who just defended
um who was thinking about casi uh casvy
and this example of b1a
um where you know of course that
involves cutting at a particular tf
binding motif and in theory you could
also imagine adding a new TF binding
motif and you know uh would that
downregulate or upregulate gene
expression in a specific way. Um, of
course the genome knows how to turn
genes up or down. And if we wanted to
recreate that for various therapeutic
approaches, it would require us to have
a really good understanding um of where
to edit, which types of edits, uh, to
introduce as well as a better
understanding of how programmable this
all is.
So, um, we thought it was a good time to
start thinking about this um, uh, when
when Mike joined the lab because of a
few developments. One of of course which
was the introduction of prime editing
which for the first time made it really
efficient to delete or insert let's say
10 nucleotides at a time which is about
the size of a transcription factor
binding motif. Um there are also new
sequence-based models for uh for
learning the language of the genome and
how DNA encodes epigenetic states um
such as enfor uh that made us think that
perhaps we had a better chance of
figuring out what we should write into
the genome. And what was missing was a
high throughput screening approach that
would allow us to measure the effects of
all of these edits. um ways to adapt
these models to design uh edits as well
as a better understanding of how
programmable the gene regulatory
sequences actually are.
So Mike teamed up with a postoc in the
lab uh Gabby Martin to develop a method
that we call variant effects. And the
idea is that uh what variant effects
enables is to introduce hundreds of
edits into a particular enhancer or
promoter sequence and quantitatively and
precisely measure the effect of each of
those edits on gene expression even in
cases where editing is in inefficient.
So the way this works is that we'll uh
design a library of PEG RNAs that will
recruit the prime editor to a particular
enhancer promoter, introduce many
different edits, um create a population
of cells, uh including hetererozygous
and homozygous edits of each of these
different sequences. Then we're going to
use RNA fish to stain cells based on
their expression of this nearby gene of
interest, sort them into bins, and then
sequence the cells in each bin to read
out the distribution of edits in each of
those expression levels. So, for
example, if you have an edit that
decreases expression, you'll see that
that edit has a much higher frequency in
the low expression bin um and a lower
frequency in the high expression bin.
And so this enables looking at hundreds
of edits in one element. Um we're
looking at hundreds of thousands of
single um of single cells carrying each
edit. Sort of uh sort of allowing us to
average over a lot of the clonal
variation that can occur. Um this
accounts for inefficient editing because
we're sequencing the edited site and
directly reading out the edits that are
created. Um, and there's other tricks
that we use to get precise precise
effect size estimates which is really
what distinguishes this method versus
many of the others that have been
developed.
So uh to illustrate um that this works,
we took a particular gene um PPF which
we were interested in for its role in
inflammatory diseases and just as some
positive controls, we designed small uh
four base edits right at the first um
splice donor in PPAF which we thought
should break splicing and lead to
nonsense decay. And so first we did this
the oldfashioned way. We introduced each
of these PEG RNAs one at a time into
cells, picked clones, isolated and grew
up those hundreds of clones and measured
their effects by qPCR. And indeed um
each of these edits decreases expression
of PPF by about 80%.
compared to many wild type clones.
Although you can see that there each of
these dots is a clone, there's quite a
bit of variability which is just sort of
how uh the the the amount of variation
that's introduced um when creating
clones of this particular cell line.
So now we can do the same experiment
with variant effects where we're going
to introduce uh these three edits as a
pool. And so here for example each of
these edits um is present at between 10
and 15% frequencies with 40% total
editing in the pool of cells. We sort
them uh using RNA flowfish against PBF
sequence uh by PCR this edited site and
then look at the frequency distributions
of each of these different edits across
the different expression bins. Um, and
so for example, uh, compared to the
reference, each of these edits is much
more frequent in the low expression bin
versus the high expression bin. We can
plug these into sort of a maximum
likelihood estimator to figure out what
the original effect sizes would be and
learn that uh, according to this
estimation, each of those variants does
indeed uh, decrease expression by about
80%.
um both in the sort of poolled format as
well as when we do this individually.
And here each dot is one of the
biological replicates of this
experiment. So basically one pool of
cells that's been independently edited.
And so these are much tighter because in
each of these pools, we're looking at
many hundreds of thousands of clones
carrying the same edit.
So we repeated the same type of analysis
across edits of many different effect
sizes. And here's sort of summing up um
a lot of TC, a lot of like tens of
thousands of clones and many qPCRs uh to
show that across um many different
edits, the effect size that we measure
in clonal cell lines with homozygous
edits matches the effect size that we
estimate with variant effects in this
sort of poolled screen that includes
cells of many different genotypes. So
this was very uh satisfying and you know
hopefully that means that in the future
we don't have to individually edit quite
as many of these and that we can trust
the effect sizes that come out of this
experiment. If the experiment says that
this you know edit leads to a plus 100%
effect on expression or doubles
expression then we can in fact believe
that measurement.
I'll skip over some of the um I'll just
just really briefly uh the math for this
is involved and just for you know future
reference a few of the key pieces are
that we have to use a precise editor
here we're using PE2 rather than PE3
because if you start throwing in
unexpected edits um that creates
correlations between uh edits due to the
you know a single editor creating two
different alals in the same cell. So in
order for this to work, you do have to
use a precise editor um that only
creates a single the single desired
edit.
Okay. So now we that we have this uh
variant effects tool um we decided that
to take it for a spin and see if we
could start to reprogram gene expression
in in a specific way. So we tried a
couple of different strategies and the
first strategy was let's look at the
promoter of the gene and we had
previously done some experiments to find
a few really efficient PEG RNAs that
worked with up to 80% 90% efficiency and
so we took one of those PEG RNAs and we
decided we would just insert a bunch of
different transcription factor binding
sites into this particular site in the
promoter. Um here we chose these 41
different sequences to match the
consensus sequences for transcription
factors that we thought were active in
this particular cell line.
So we clone these into the PPF promoter
um do the pulled prime editing measure
each of those effects. You know for
example maybe we're inserting a motif
for Mick or for Foss
um and here's the results of this
poolled experiment. So the effect size
on PPF gene expression across two
biological replicates of the experiment,
the replicates are really highly
concordant. Um, and many of the uh
variants do in fact manipulate gene
expression but not by particularly
impressive amounts. Um, so for example,
inserting a McMax motif decreases
expression of PPF by about 10%. um but
maybe not exactly what we were looking
for in terms of uh thinking about
potential therapeutic applications.
So we explored a second strategy um
which was to leverage computational
models to design stronger edits than we
could trivially think of uh ourselves.
And in this particular analysis, I'm
going to show you work that was done
using the informer model developed by
ZAB and and and David Kelly um at
Calico. Um and this was work by Johannes
Linder who at the time was a postto in
lab and then moved on to Calico himself.
Um and the idea between this behind this
particular model is that it is using a
few hundred kilobases of DNA sequence to
predict um different measurements around
the promoter. In this case, we're going
to look at the predictions of PPAF cage
or gene expression in uh this particular
cell type. And what Johannes did
together with Mike is to use the
informer model to create um what's
called a simulated kneeling design
process where we would take the wild
type sequence of the promoter. We would
probabilistically choose to either
insert a base, delete a base or swap a
base um create a new edited sequence,
score it with the informer model and
then accept edits with the desired
effect with some particular probability.
And the particular uh novelty of this
approach is that um we're using this
iterative process but also constraining
it to only edits that should be
efficiently delivered with prime
editing. So instead of redesigning the
entire promoter, we're only going to
tweak a few bases here and there and see
what we can do with very small edits
that that should be very efficient with
prime editing.
Okay. So in this experiment we targeted
five different high efficiency sites in
the PPF promoter ran the design
procedure tested them with variant
effects and again two biological
replicates. The effect sizes are really
highly correlated and we did actually
get a small number of edits that lead to
up to a two-fold increase in gene
expression or as low as a um I guess
this would be a seven-fold decrease. So
for example, if you insert a Zeb one
motif, which is a known repressor, you
can reduce expression quite dramatically
at this like really highly expressed
gene. Um, and if you insert um, you
know, a composite elk one MIB binding
site, you can increase expression. And
this is also a good example of the model
doing something that we like we didn't
trivially think of ourselves. In this
case, it's inserting about 10 base pairs
and it's creating this composite motif
using a few of the sort of endogenously
encoded nucleotides in the genome um on
each side. So, it's actually creating a
a composite uh element that uh wouldn't
fit uh in the 10 base pair constraint
that we gave it.
So, we can in fact turn expression up or
down by very large amounts with very
small edits. Um there's another preprint
from Keith Jung's lab that observes
something similar. And so we think that
this could be really useful in the
future for both understanding gene
regulation, the principles how you turn
genes up and down, but also potentially
for gene therapies for certain types of
diseases. Um one type of disease that
we're thinking about are hloins
sufficiencies where you inherit one loss
of function variant from one parent and
you have one good copy of the gene
meaning that you have 50% the normal
dosage. And because these are loss of
function and variants, different
patients with the same disease will all
have different variants. And so if you
wanted to trivially like correct the
mutation, you'd have to have individual
editors for each person. But instead,
maybe you could instead imagine a
therapy that upregulates the good copy
of the gene by twofold, restoring the
proper dosage, and the same gene therapy
uh reagent could be useful for for many
different patients with the same
disease.
So there's a long way a long road toward
uh realizing that one of the challenges
is that while we were ultimately
successful in finding edits that
upregulated gene expression the
predictive models still aren't amazing.
So here's a comparison of the measured
effect on gene expression from variant
effects with the predicted effect from
informer. And you can see that the
single edit that upregulated gene
expression quite a bit actually informer
doesn't think it should have done
anything. So there's a lot more to do
here to figure out, you know, how to
improve the models, how to improve the
design procedure, um will it work
differently to edit promoters versus
enhancers. We're interested in digging
this into this further, but for now, we
have an initial platform combining this
variant effects uh experimental method
with sequence design that we think will
be really useful for exploring this.
So uh to summarize um we're really
excited about understanding the
regulatory genome to accelerate this
process of connecting variance to
functions to therapeutics. Um would like
to thank everyone in my lab as well as
our collaborators for their support
including um seed funding from the
variant to function initiative here at
the broad over eight years ago. Thanks
very much and I'll take any questions.
[Applause]
a terrific talk. Uh
question. I'm gonna ask a question then
they'll get organized there. But you
snuck something in there that was early
on. You said that attack is not so good
in the E2G DNA is much better and I
think you've told me that K27 acetle is
maybe better
which is disturbing because a lot of us
are using deep learning models to
predict attack and we were hoping then
to be able to predict E to G from that.
Um what are we missing in the attack?
What's the problem?
>> Yeah. uh I don't know for sure but what
we suspect so the specific statement is
that if you simply count attack reads in
a peak
um versus counting DNA seek reads in a
peak DNA seek seems to be a better
estimate of activity when you plug it
into these models um and I think that's
because when you have really dense TF
binding in the most active enhancers the
TN5 enzyme is just bigger than DNA seek
and so it can't get in and make as many
cuts. Um, and so it ends up missing out
on the really high activity elements.
Um, but hopefully that information is
still there once we add in sequence and
use sequence models to start
interpreting um, you know, which
transcription factors are binding and
you know, we're going to have to learn
how to infer which transcription factors
confer enhancer activity versus
accessibility.
>> Um, that was a really good talk. Thank
you. Um I was confused about this last
uh edit where the nformer model thought
it shouldn't do anything but it did uh
it doubled uh activity. How did it end
up in your test set actually if didn't
think it would do anything but you used
enfor to pick the test set right?
>> Yeah. So I didn't explain this detail
but we designed edits to activate the
gene in two different cell types. So in
this case it thought that this variant
should activate in the other cell type
but it actually did um more strongly in
this one.
>> Okay. Thanks.
>> So I have a question about the uh gene
edits. Let's say for some variance you
tested to uh try to upregulated the gene
expression you see maybe less than
twofold or effects is weaker. Do you
think it due to let's say for the WP
cells two alles did you test some ads
using let's say hetererozygus with you
know the gene was downregulate first and
then try to upregulate it to the uh to
restore the gene expression will effect
will be larger compared to the wild type
context
>> yeah that's a good question um I guess
it um it comes down to whether yeah
there's uh nonlinearity in the promoter
that controls how it responds um to
different levels of gene expression. As
far as we can tell from
other studies where we've synthetically
combined enhancers and promoters in many
combinations is that most promoters
don't seem to saturate um and that you
can always turn them up farther with
enhancers. Um but certain promoters are
just intrinsically less responsive. So
there there must be some point where
like the pelraases are filing, you know,
firing so quickly that you can't turn up
a gene far uh farther. Um but it doesn't
seem like we've hit that point for most
human promoters.
question.
>> Hello Jesse, I'm wondering in the SC E2G
model, how to you how how do you
incorporated the bulk high data in the
single cell attack and RNA seek data
because the the cells are heterogeneous
sample if you measure high C there are
mixture of many structures but how to
use that to predict the specific cell
type specific enhancer and promoter.
>> Yeah. So in to estimate contact in ABC
there are a few different ways. The best
is if you have really deep let's say
micro C or intact IC in your exact cell
type that leads to a boost in
performance. If you don't have that then
what we do is we use an average high-C
map across 40 different human tissues
which will capture basically the the you
know average relationship between
distance and contact as well as let's
say conserved CTCF boundary elements
that create specific loops at longer
distances. So in all of these
predictions, we're using an average a
cell typed average high-C map uh um
in com which is the same in combination
with cell type specific attacking data.
>> That's great. Thank you Jesse.
>> Thanks a lot.
[Applause]