so where do we
stand we gone
uh long
way not yet uh done heat but we've done
temperature and we introduced this
diagram energy versus entropy
that allows us to um represent most of
the results that we have uh uh discussed
so
far so I want
to do a little more with this um
diagram notice that um it took us a
while to get to temperature because in
order to Define temperature we
need uh the state principle the
fundamental relation for the sa
equilibrium States because it's only for
those states that we can Define the
slope of this curve which is the
temperature in other words states that
are inside the region these are
nonstable in general non equilibrium
states there is no temperature defined
there although we will see as we go on
that uh we may be able
to uh represent the system as a
composite of several uh smaller systems
for that are close to equilibrium so
that somehow we can assign temperatures
that's what we do in fluid mechanics
that's an interesting application of
what we
doing okay we have seen that with this
diagram we can if I have a generic State
here and I want to uh presentent what I
can do the best I can do in a weight
process best in in the sense of trying
to extract as much energy as possible uh
from our system in such a way that we
make uh um something useful uh like
lifting a weight okay the maximum we can
do we can do in a weight process is the
adiabatic availability of that state
which is represented here
by the difference in energy on the
vertical
line uh and in fact the the final State
when we reach when we do this maximum we
have done the process reversibly
otherwise you get
less and in a weight in a reversible
weight process the entropy remains
constant we've seen as one of the uh
theorems that we cited and
so the process that it extracts the
weight process that extracts diabetic
availability moves vertically down until
you reach the um lowest uh energy state
with that entropy you cannot go below so
you cannot exract more en more energy
because there are no stat below that
one
we uh discussed the fact that the
thermal Reservoir as constant
temperature and um you actually have in
the homework um this uh discussion to
try to reproduce it the definition of
temperature for a reservoir so for the
reservoir the stable equum State curve
is just a straight uh line the allowed
states are onthel these are also
reservoirs can have non equilibrium
States but most of the times we are
interested in their equilibrium stable
equilibrium
ons and then we also constructed the
available energy and I want to so do the
somehow do this again on the Blackboard
just so that we can uh um see together
this uh uh
construction I'm going to do it uh in a
slightly different way so that uh
so that uh we can
uh so say that this is our system a and
this
is It's e sucess
diagram and this time let's
do you see in in the view
graph State A1 is to the left of the
final Mutual equilib state to reservoir
uh which is a so I'm going to do it uh
just for a change
differently so I assume now that the
state is here
A1 and that
the final State when I will uh reach
Mutual equilibrium with the reservoir
it's going to be
here that means
that the
temperature of the
reservoir is this
one because when they're in mutual
equilibrium the system and the reservoir
have the same temperature we haven't
proved that yet but uh we we do it uh
hopefully today just after this example
uh so let me draw below here also
the E versus S diagram for the
reservoir
look so you see that in order to go from
here from this state to this
state the system must decrease its uh uh
its ENT
okay definitely it cannot do it in a
weight process because in a in a weight
process the most you can do is keep the
entropy constant but if you're not doing
things reversibly you generate entropy
so you going to move to the right not to
the left so in order to do
that this is the reason
why wanted
to we
can use the reservoir because we're
considering you're studying the
uh a diabatic availability available
energy is the diabatic availability of a
composite system in which there is a
reservoir so my initial state is here I
have a reservar and what I want to do is
lift the weight as much as
possible so the reservoir is
available to do this
job we need to to remove entropy from uh
the
system so we can transfer that
entropy from system a to the
reservoir
okay so the system must
decrease its uh
entropy from
S1 to
Sr the reservoir can take
it so okay so the reservoir as a as a
stable equilibrium state with this slope
so it's
this
um it must take and y so its entropy
will
increase so the initial state will be
here like R1 and the final state will be
here
R2 and the entropy uh of the resir will
go from s1r to
S1 uh
s2r now
so you would like to give just entropy
to the
reservoir because look so far suppose
you consider here this is the initial
energy of a and this is the final energy
of
a and we call uh Omega 1
R uh the energy that we transfer to the
weight so if we could do that
process um ex with without the um use
the need of the reservoir it would be a
weight process for system a and we would
extract this much
energy okay
but we cannot do it in a weight process
because we cannot uh subtract
uh entropy cannot destroy
entropy so we need to transfer it to the
res so we need to give it to the resir
and the
reservoir uh in order to accept
entropy you see you would want to move
this initial state of the reservoir to
the right but there are no states to the
right because that's the maximum entropy
for that value for the
energy you need to give it also some
energy okay
and that
energy is the is the difference between
uh E2 and E1 for the
reservoir
so uh
E2 you last
subract
that and so all your so you take this
segment you put it up here if you
want and it's this
much I mean it's not precise in scale
but this much is that
much so you
subtract from this energy difference
this energy difference what and what you
are left with is
again uh
you see from this point to that
point and that's Omega one R notice that
this point is a geometrical construction
it doesn't correspond to a state because
it's below the stable equum State curve
it's just the construction of bringing
from uh mean translating this energy
difference into there so that I subtract
it from the segment that represents the
difference in energy for the
res and then all I have to do is
remember that
U the stable equilibrium State curve for
Reservoir is a straight line
so I can rewrite this as t
r time s2r minus
s1r and then I also uh remember that the
amount of entropy that must take that
the restor must take is equal to the
decrease in entropy that I need for my
system so S2 minus
S1 uh is equal to uh
s S1 a minus
Sr
a and so we finally
get um the
expression for the available energy that
we have uh uh we we want we started with
we wanted to represent
graphically
hey so this brings us uh uh to a very
important concept
the uh for applications for applications
in engineering where you want to extract
convert energy from
systems so you need
to and
often the systems you start with are in
stable equilibrium States maybe hot but
still stable equilibrium
States for example when you in in a uh
uh steam power plant you just heat up
water you make Steam and that steam is
some sort of a high
temperature uh stable equilibrium state
in so here here's the state and you
would like to extract as much energy as
possible so you would like to go down
but going down on the diagram it would
be any
impossibility I mean a perpetual motion
machine of the second count so it's
impossible in order to go down in energy
you need to
subtract also
some but then you need a
system that takes up that
entropy and usually that role is played
by the environment or maybe the nearby
River or or lake or the
sea or the air
that is the system in which
you dump the entropy that you must
extract from your
system okay so it's like an you use the
environment as an entropy
sync but the environment has its own
needs uh it uh does not take entropy for
free it takes entropy only if you give
it also enough energy so that it can
climb in the uh stable equilibrium State
curve
okay so that energy that you are giving
to the environment in in a in a typical
uh Energy Systems
application is
not uh a waste sometimes you say well
I'm wasting energy no no it's it's not
waste you use using the environment for
a very important function you're using
the energy there that's not where the
inefficiency of our your power plant is
the inefficiencies come from the
internal irreversibilities that are in
your
Machinery instead the
role
um the role of the of the r work here uh
is uh is important because otherwise it
wouldn't uh uh you you wouldn't be able
to do anything
useful yeah we'll we'll come back to
this when I do a quick review of heat
engines uh and uh exy stuff in in a
couple of
lectures okay but
today I want
to go into some
details on how we um
uh show that uh for systems to be mutual
equilibrium you need the quality of
temperatures when they can exchange
energy you need the quality of pressures
when they can exchange volume you need
quality of chemical potentials of the
various constituents for those
constituents that can be transferred
from one system to the
other and the way we prove this is by
means of the uh Max maimum entropy
principle you remember that we proved
that
U the stable equilibrium
state is the maximum entropy one among
those states that have the same energy
and amounts and parameters I'm not going
to repeat amounts and parameters let's
keep them fixed for the entire day so
how does we how do does the proof um um
work you say all right let's start from
two systems A and B that are in mutual
equilibrium therefore the composite
system C this is the E versus S diagram
of the composite system of the
two so the composite system is in
um is on the stable State curve because
um by definition of mutual equilibrium
it's when the two systems the composite
is inable
equili
okay so now what we do is all right
let's construct another state we'll call
it
C1 is the same
energy uh but a different
state being a different state with the
same energy it necessarily has a lesser
entropy okay we have many choices for
this other state C1 so we are going to
choose one that is easy for us in some
sense so for
example here's my system a here's my
system
B uh in the mutual equilibrium state so
now these are the the
the partial the the local um energy
entropy
diagrams sometimes I forget to write the
es because I give it for granted but I
shouldn't all
right uh so let's say that this is
temperature
t0 of system a and this is temperature
t0 of system
B and we were going to we want to prove
so I build it in already in the in this
construction that the two temperatures
must
be okay so I
start
from uh them being in a stable equum
State and then I consider another state
which is this
one with the same energy for the
composite but different for the parts so
let's see uh I've put let me arbitrarily
choose a a small amount of energy
de and therefore assume that uh my
system a I'll make it bigger so as to
presentent it it's as an
energy um Higher by by an amount
de and
B as an energy smaller by the same
amount so that since energy is additive
the total energy remains constant and
therefore the composite system it still
has the same
energy plus I mean I I have many choices
on how to do this but I'm going to
choose the easy way easy for our proof
so that uh both system a and system
B change their energies but the
remaining stable equum state
right so this is how I construct State
uh A1 and B1 so as to make up the
composite
C1 um since I want to do
um also equality of pressure I want to
prove also that think also of the
volume that changes so this become said
three-dimensional surface I'm not going
to represent it otherwise it gets too
messy but
imagine um that in addition to changing
the energy I'm also going to change the
volume
so the partition
between uh system A and B are is movable
and let let's move the uh the partition
to slightly to the right so that a gains
a little volume DV and B uh yields a
little volume DV okay so now we
constructed this state C1 that has the
same energy and also the same volume for
system
C
okay and what we want to uh um make use
of is the fact that the maximum ENT so
that that the entropy of um of C in
state zero is greater than that in say
in C1 so that I can write it this
way S1 C minus S10 must be less than Z
okay so we start we want to compute this
and the end we end up uh uh imposing
that it is it must be
negative okay then
the next steps are simply using the
additivity of
entropy so in state initial and final
State the entropy of C is the sum of the
entropies of A and
B just uh rearrange so that it's the
additivity of the entropy
differences and then because of our
construction because we selected this
particular stage that U uh uh still
belong to the stable equilibrium State
curve we can use a tailor series
expansion of the fundamental relation
which describes this curve to represent
uh how the entropy changes for the
subsystems you
remember um let's see yeah we had the s
or stable
equilibrium is a function like that and
if I want to to
compute
uh the value of
uh so this represents this curve so if I
want to
compute uh the difference of say
S2 minus S one this being State one and
this being state
two or actually sorry let let's make it
zero and
one so S1 minus s z right that's what we
want
yeah I can do a stor series
expansion uh around the initial State
the initial point of the the function so
around
e0 so it will be let me do it only for
as if it were only a function of energy
so this is like forget about these ones
for the moment so that would be
S of uh
e0
plus uh S
Prime of e0 times
E1 minus
e0 plus s double Prime uh divided by
two or two factorial whatever it's the
same times E1 minus
e0 squared plus dot dot dot and the
series
continues of course in the limit as a as
the E1 minus e0 is B the first uh the
the dominant terms are the the first
ones that you find in the expansion so
that's what we are doing here with the
notion that this S Prime is what we call
the inverse
temperature and when you do this also in
terms of the second variable is the
volume that's what we called pressure
over
temperature so here is
the that expans f for system
a the second
derivatives um let me write them as
D2 because it it contains several terms
since I'm doing that in terms of two
varibles
subsequent slide will have the details
and we do the same for system
B then we use the
fact well then we combine terms
and uh here is what we get 1 / T minus 1
/ t for B A and D * D p/ T minus p/ t a
DB plus the second uh differentials so
as plus dos dos
dos
okay so what can we infer and this must
be negative strictly negative
of
course notice and remember that when you
do a series expansion the
first the terms here like this one are
evaluated at the initial State okay so
they do not depend on uh how much you
move
around
so these terms in parenthesis and that
term is s parenthesis is
fixed by the initial state state zero
it's independent of how you move around
to another state so it's dependent on De
and
DV and on the other
hand you see here I could have chosen to
give to like uh to choose another state
of a with higher energy but also one
with lower energy so I could have chosen
de to be positive or
negative large or small positive or
negative whatever as long as of course b
gets the opposite equal and
opposite so that means that de and DV
can be chosen arbitrarily positive or
negative and if if these terms in
parenthesis were different than zero
suppose they were
positive then I could choose a positive
de and this would be a dominating term
in the
series violating the fact that that
sound must be
negative so the only possibility due to
the arbitrariness of the choice of DV
and de is that these terms in
parenthesis be equal to
zero and of course then the burden to
keep the inequality
satisfied is going to be shifted to the
second order terms in the expansion
which are going to be
negative right
so essentially what we proved here is
that in order for that system here to be
in a a stable equilibrium State the two
temperatures must be
equal and also the two pressures must be
equal so above here is the same as
before uh I simply wrote more
explicitly the expression for the um
second order
differential which
is uh must be nonp positive so it's
either zero or
negative if it is zero it's the third
order terms and fourth and and and go on
uh that must uh obey must be take up uh
uh uh and satisfy this Inequality For
example see if I have a
reservoir the second derivative is equal
to
zero of the the fundamental relation so
for this Reservoir I need that somewhere
in along the the line
uh the there is a derivative which is
negative and uh since
a straight line isn't like that it means
that the this straight line in practice
is really an approximation so in other
words a real Reservoir with a true
straight line as a stable equum State
curve cannot exist it would violate this
so so the the the reservoir is is an
approximation extremely good
approximation if you make it uh uh like
water at the triple point with
sufficient amount of water but if you go
to small very small uh
amounts uh then you may have
difficulties uh constructing a real uh
Reservoir
okay so we proved the I mean equality of
temperature and quality of pressure and
we proved
also the sign of the second derivatives
of this uh of the fundamental
relation the reason why I have drawn the
E sucess diagram this way and not the
other way so with the concavity
upward is now proved
here the second derivative of s with
respect to e is negative or zero
negative or
zero the same you can
prove since this form differential form
must be negative for all possible values
uh you uh you
need that the it's a it's a quadratic
form and you need that the the
coefficient The Matrix of coefficients
be positive uh I meaning negative
definite or actually non positive
definite meaning that for example not
only the terms on the diagonal which are
these two but also so the determinant
must be non negative I mean non
positive okay so which gives us also
this expression
here okay now uh we can do also but more
quickly the proof for
when instead of
um yeah here um instead of putting the
the movable piston I should have um I
must change this um um drawing this
should be should be replaced with a
porous
material not nonmovable so this is
should be a porous
material that would um allow the
transfer of constituent I of so of
molecules of atoms of typ I only one
time
so they are in mutual equilibrium at the
big a state
zero and we construct a state uh another
state with the same energy by shifting
some energy from A to B and also some
amounts so I I give a I take a with some
more uh particles all that type and Me
by the less particle so it's like moving
them from from B to a
well exactly the same procedure I'm
going to exploit the fact that the
entropy of S1 must be less than that of
S
zero only that when I do the series
expansion okay for the energy it's still
the same but um now I'm not I'm not
changing the volume and changing the
amount so instead of p/ T the partial
derivative with respect to Amounts is
minus the chemical potential
overt combine in the same
way and this
term by the arbitrariness of our choice
of system C1 of say of State C1 so the
amounts dni the difference are
arbitrary like the energy and therefore
we find the same conclusion that these
coefficients must be uh
zero and uh of course also that second
uh order differential must must be non
positive we prove therefore that we need
the equality of temperature and equality
of the chemical potentials of that
constituent in the two
systems for Mutual equilibrium and we we
prove some
other convexity or concavity
relations in fact if you do it for
several
variables you end up with the fact that
uh uh all these second derivatives must
be
zero but more than that
uh this Matrix which is the H Matrix of
uh partial all the possible second order
partial derivatives uh must
be negative definite or negative semi
definite and U and uh and therefore you
can apply all your uh all that you know
about positive definite matrices and so
on and obtain the number of
inequalities for example from some of
these uh one of these inequalities that
is is well known is that the specific
heat of a substance which is related to
the second derivative of s with respect
to e uh must be
posit but as you see
here the the there's only one result you
can you could obtain
several
okay now by the same
technique to prove the inequalities we
can also prove um another interesting
relation which is known as the Y
plus uh equation for a surface tension
so let me do
um this because um it's po so useful for
those of
you who are in the fluid mechanics or
mechanics of interfaces for example
take the
system which is a which contains a
drop so this stands for drop say of
uh h of one phase
in immerse or surrounded by another
phase and there are many examples here
and just put three of
them it could be let's start with the
last one it could be liquid and
Vapor so a drop of liquid and outside
you got Vapor like water VAP or VAP of
any
substance or or you you could have a
like
air on the
outside uh which is partially dissolved
here's a drop of water in which there is
some air
dissolved it's not air like CO2 or some
other
substance or you could have two liquids
like oil and water that are not missible
so in the bulk of each one you don't
find uh any of the other
but in the interfacial
region they
must U live together these different
molecules so in this region the
properties of this layer which is
generally very
thin and therefore you can uh these
properties uh of the substance uh feel
the different um forces intermolecular
forces than any of the two BS because
here you have just forces
between the's say gray molecules here
you have
U just intermolecular forces of the the
dark molecules and here you have some
and
some so they are really different
systems
and the fact that the the interface is
interfacial region is is is generally
very very thin allows you to model it
you can model it of course in a
continuous
way but here we're going to do it uh uh
like when you do Anga plus equation you
model it in a much simpler way as if it
was just
another very thin system
uh when which which can exchange
molecules uh on both
sides but on the right it can exchange
only dark molecule on the left only gray
molecules whereas the situation in which
you have coexistence of the two can only
move uh along the surface in a 2d
geometry
so it's it's only by moving along this
um Circle here if it is if it is a
spherical uh geometry that you can find
this
coexisting uh
situation and it it's the same kind of
idea when you have
a phase separation when you when the
system in order to reach stable
equilibrium doesn't
um doesn't find it um um doesn't find
the maximum entropy state by by
remaining homogeneous but it separates
so
molecules like to go uh to bump to each
other and become a liquid on one side
and on the other side you got the water
we the interface
interfacial region is a very very thin
region in which the density changes
drastically now the factor of a thousand
is the density difference between the
liquid and the vapor like for example
for
water so the density drops in a
matter of a uh few
uh what is
it
nanometers uh
drops uh it drops uh by a factor of a
th all right
so if we have a system like
this it's
confined on a layer so its extension is
not measured in terms of
thickness but it's only in terms of the
surface area where it can uh
develop so for that system the parameter
of the
geometrical
um container or or let's say mental
container that uh where those mod
molecules are
confined uh is not the
volume but it's it's the surface
area or if you want it is still the
volume but the volume can be split in
the surface area and a very thin
layer so area of the surface becomes a
parameter for that
system which plays a parallel
role all that played by volume for M
systems and like we Define p over the
the partial derivative of fundamental
from the stable equilibrium state of
fundamental relation with respect to
volume we call it P /
t for this particular
system the derivative of s with respect
to a we call it minus Sigma /
T and if
we invert the function we see that you
can see like the for the bul system the
pressure is minus the derivative of the
uh energy with respect to to volume of
the uh energy form of the fundamental
relation and for the interface system
it's the sigma the surface we call it
surface tension is the partial of the
energy with respect to a with without a
minus sign that's why one is a pressure
the other is a tension
so okay so that that is for the
definition
so now we can play the
same uh
role the same U
trick of applying the maximum entropy
principle to see what happens at Mutual
equilibrium between those three
phases those three systems b d and the
interface
C and the trick is to construct another
state we call it F1 because now I'm
running out of letters so
f is the composite system of B CD so
this overall system is
f I'm not using letter A because now a
is the area so that's uh used up okay so
uh so we need to construct another
state and the way we do it is by
changing
we do it in a particular
Way by
changing um the
shape per perturbing the the the shape
of the original uh drop
in and then we proceed in the same
way we have uh we
we want to prove that this thing is
negative there is a yeah there is
negative here is the minus the
negative
sign we apply additivity we now have
three
systems so the
one
uh B and D are like we done before but
now we have also system C for which uh
the Tor series expansion in the first
terms in the expansion uh contain the
surface
tension of course it's the value like
the pressure evaluated at the um stable
equum State
F0 here the dots represent many things
they represent also I should have
written also but I didn't have space
enough on The View graph the derivative
will check to the amount
and the second order
terms but in order to focus on on the
interesting part new part let me
choose a
particular
uh situation in which this very
particular value state as1 in which
uh I have U Already
satisfied the temperature
equality
condition I already satisfied the the
chemical potential
equality and so all I am interested in
is changing the
volume okay so that allows us to
essentially concentrate on these three
terms this one
that one and that
one and by getting rid of uh yeah there
was there should be a one / T here that
disappeared I have to fix also that on
the do
graph uh
P because these temperatures are assumed
to be equal so I'm left with this
equation and this equation has to be uh
NE negative strictly
negative but as we will find out is
that again because of the arbitrarily
arbitrariness of uh the choices of U the
change in in the geometry in the
volume it will turn out to have to be
zero and so the burden for the
inequality will be uh uh carried by the
extra uh additional terms
okay all
right so yes uh again also here I have
to fix the view graph so this is just
smaller to make room for something
else uh all right so now there is an
easy way of proceeding here is assume a
geometry if we assume a geometry just to
see what what comes out
so if you assume for example spherical
geometry of the
drop and we assume that we uh change the
volume so we we consider a perturbed
state with a volume slightly
increased by an
amount if R was the radius of the drop
it becomes R plus Dr or the Epsilon
Epsilon to stress the fact that it's
small
okay okay so the area of U of the
interface of the surface of the sphere
is 4 pi r
squ the volume that is
the if if I increase this the sphere
from this solid light to the dash line
the increase in volume is is equal to
the surface the area
times uh the shift in so times the
Epsilon so that's
DV and that's what happens what appears
in this part of the
equation also the since I am um going
from small to large also the area
changes now the area changes
because the radius uh is changed so I go
from 4 pi r 2 to 4 pi r + D
Epsilon
squared
and if I forget about the D Epsilon
Square because it's small with respect
to the put it to the
others what I'm left
is so one of these cancels with that I'm
left left with 8 pi r
V and this is the change in area that I
put
here still the the Epsilon is
arbitrary so that expression now becomes
this
expression and it should be equal to
zero for I mean negative for arbitary
values of the
Epsilon they could have chosen also the
Epsilon negative instead of positive
and still that should be satisfied so
essentially it's just what multiplies
the Epsilon that has to be
zero so the 4 pi r squ r 4 pi r cancels
and you get this expression here there
is a two that uh emerges from the 8
divided by
four and so you find that the condition
for Mutual equilibrium between those
three systems is that the pressure in
the inside the drop must differ
must be greater than the pressure uh of
the
outside by the surface tension
multiplied by 2/
R now if you repeat that for a
cylindrical
shape we just keep that but here are the
details uh you get a similar expression
only with one / r
okay but the true
story is that
uh we don't know this shape so we we
shouldn't in principle assume that
shape
because
uh in principle who who tells us that uh
the shape should be spherical or
geometri or or
cylindrical that is also a
result of this maximum entropy principle
and the young La
plus
it it's a bit complicated so Ian it took
me days to construct this uh these u
pictures so I'm not going to spend too
much time on them but simply uh I assume
that you know that if I have a surface
space uh I can can define principal radi
of
curvature and uh there like in a
sphere or in ellipsoid you could have uh
the centers of curvature on the same
side of the
surface but in a subtle point or of your
surface you could have the centers of
cure on the two opposite sides so for
example so suppose this is the
drop in this
situation you have one Center of
curvature inside the drop and one
outside whereas here they're both
inside and uh but you see this is a
local
picture if you have an arbitrary shape
you suppose if you have a drop of
arbitrary shape like for example when
you have a a drop of water in gravity
field uh you know this is the
shape uh
so the local
curvature and the the surface must be
represented somehow by running over the
entire surface with local variables and
integrating so in order to calculate the
entire area you have to do an
integral of these uh local
areas so here is a lot of uh uh
Expressions that I hope are correct that
allows you that um describe this um
geometrical uh situations
one for the system when the two centers
are on the two sides of the surface and
one for this the case in which they are
on both on the same side
the the
difference is it
locally the the purpose of these
formulas here is to
compute the
ratio of the area change to the volume
change as you shift to see remember that
we were talking about this situation we
want to um perturb the shape of of the
drop and go to uh a
another state and we comp we want to
compute the volume and the area so the
what is important is the ratio of the
area change over the volume change and
that's why here we uh we compute it for
locally so as I
perturb uh the move the the surface that
entails a Chang in volume Delta V and a
changing surface area Delta a and they
and this ratio is related to the inverse
it's called the uh mean local
curvature it's the sum of two
contributions but it is an algebraic sum
because one of the U when the radius out
is on the other side it has a negative
in
front Okay so if we go back to our
picture here and try TR to
compute these areas and this uh changing
volume we have to integrate somehow over
the entire
surface that's why I need a double
integral over some variables so Theta
one and Theta 2 maybe is a is a way to
describe a local uh
angles and uh
and then if you okay if you go on and do
all the the math you calculate again the
change in area it's again R plus the
Epsilon and
R now it's plus or minus the Epsilon
because when you when you move the
surface on one side in this case uh
um one
radius of curvature increases and the
other decrease
phes by the amount the
EP and so uh in the
end you get a double
integral over
the surface
coordinates and the D
Epsilon now you you you can choose
arbitrarily the D Epsilon at every
location in the in the in the
surface and that's arbitrary so that
integral must be equal to
zero for arbitrary choices of how you
want to distribute the
epsilons which says that therefore is
the integrand that must be equal to
zero and so you find that you can
rewrite it this way
and you find that therefore the sum of
the of the inverse of the radi of
curvature so the mean
curvature which in principle could be
different
locally from point to
point must be equal to this ratio of
difference in
pressure and different and surface
tension which is something that uh
that doesn't depend on location of the
ccle so that means so this
result means that the the average uh
curvature must be uniform must be equal
everywhere on the surface when you are
in mutual
equilibrium like in a
sphere like in a cylindrical situation
there are some
other uh interesting surfaces if you
look up in u the
Wikipedia um surfaces of the uh constant
mean curvature you find that somebody
has found a very interesting shape
where it's a more complicated than a
than than a sphere all right Plus of
course so this is the main result the
uniformity of the mean curvature and
this is the standard uh Yang plus
equation for where system for a for a
surface with the two uh different radi
of uh
curvish
okay okay so now we are already
for the next
move we want to prove the Claus
statement of the
second so we want to capitalize now on
the fact that a
system
uh systems can
exchange energy and entropy
and we would like to consider this
particular situation two systems A and
B initially in stable equilibrium
States uh for Simplicity for the moment
we just consider fixed volume fixed
amounts and we want to transfer uh some
energy from one to the
other the question question is is it
always possible or when is it
possible do I me do I need to transfer
also some entropy in order to make it
possible okay so that's the question
answered by the Claus uh the the
inequalities that we will uh that we
will uh prove right
now so look
it's again the same story as we started
with if my system a starts in a stable
equilibrium State here and I want to
extract energy so that I give it to
system B I need to go down in energy but
in order to go down in energy I also
need to go down in
ENT so the so already from the picture
we
see a geometric
proof we will we will have view graphs
that do that more detail but also more
complicated
uh but first let's do it with
equations so how do we Model A system we
make energy balances and entropy
balances and
uh let's consider a small change in uh
in a small amount of energy
transferred all right so if I
make the energy balance for system a
simply says that the rate I mean that
the change in the energy of a is uh
equal to uh minus the amount that I uh
gave to B that I extracted from
a and for system B its energy change is
equal to the amount that it
received notice the arrows
uh the arrows tell you when
these uh symbols are positive it means
that the flow has been in the direction
of the
arrow entropy
balance the change in the entropy of
system
a okay as it goes uh to the left
is equal to two contributions one is the
entropy that has been transferred out of
system
a and the other if any is the entropy
that has been produced by
irreversibility Within systa if the
process is
irreversible if you do it reversibly
this one isn't there but if you do it
irreversibly this one this term must be
greater than zero
for system B the entropy balance says
that the change in the entropy of
B is equal to the entropy that it
received from a plus if any the entropy
that was generated Within Me by the
RSE
now again
uh this is State uh
A1
that's and we
moved we extracted this much
energy I call it Delta
E A out of a it goes into B
okay if
I I do not
necessarily uh have to go to the stable
equilibrium State I could go to any of
these
states and
principle well maybe maybe I cannot go
all that far but that will depend
because if I want to go this far I need
a system on the other side that since I
reduce the entropy I need a system that
picks up that entropies it it has to
have uh the ability to do
that so at a certain stage we will uh
see that we cannot go too far uh uh to
the
left but in any case these are the
possible changes of state of system a
what I know is that the stable
equilibrium State for the new value of
the energy is the one that has the
highest
entr so gain maximum entropy PR so the
entropy
S2 of the find the entropy of State A2
suppose that's this
one is less then the uh maximum entropy
corresponding to that value of the
energy which is the entropy of the
stable equilibrium
State corresponding
to the new value of the
energy okay so here
is uh the inequality and here the factor
is the fundamental relation for which we
can do as usual uh a series expansion
around State
one it will have a linear
term and let's keep also the second
order
ter plus Dots
Dots
okay so uh you see this expression it's
S2
S1 but S2 is S1 plus
DS so we can uh uh take the S1 on the
left hand side here it becomes the S and
uh here is the rewriting so
DS is equal to d e over t plus the
second
derivative plus Dots Dots
Dots what do we know about the second
derivatives
when we just proved that they are
negative okay
so if this is a negative number and this
is a squared
number this thing will
subtract therefore this will be less
than just d e over
T there is an exception
though if the system is a re were that
second derivative is equal to zero
right uh so here we would have an equal
sign for if a is s were and the same
identical um treatment goes for system
B okay so now we can put these all
together just uh shuffled things around
up to here it's the same that we've seen
so far now let me combine U those
equations said we have 1 two 3 four five
six we can eliminate four variables and
the remain two equations
I let you do the algebra it's it's um
it's easy
enough and since I want to concentrate
on the energy and entropy transfers so
the Delta e and the Delta s uh these are
the variables that I keep eliminate the
other the other Force
changes so this is for system um for
system a from the balances from system a
and this is from system
B they both contain Delta
s so I can combine these two in a single
uh uh train of
inequalities where Delta
s the entropy exchange is at the
center and it's
less than if I add the and to be
produced by reversibility and this must
be less than Delta the energy over
t1b and on the other side side this
is greater than if I subtract something
positive and it is in turn uh greater
than the energy over
T great all right so this is interesting
by
itself because
it says all right remember we started
from our two systems in two different
temper two different two states sa equum
states with different temperature so T1
a and t1b are
different and here we found uh uh we
find a if you forget about if you look
on only at the Central and the two
extremes of these
inequalities it
says that definitely if you want to have
a finite I mean not a finite but nonzero
transfer of energy from A to
B uh you
need an entropy change an entropy
transfer with some value that stays
within this
interval of the energy transfer divided
by uh the two temperatures of the two uh
systems uh
okay so let me let me do it
uh so it says
what is it I could write that
inequality this
way take things on the left hand
side and uh am I right if I do
this yeah I'm taking
this all the way to the other side right
okay so what does that tell me if I want
Delta e
a
positive in other words if I want to
transfer energy from A to
B if this is positive that has to be
negative if this has to be
negative uh it means that the second
term must be bigger than the first one
okay okay uh so that means that the
denominator must be
smaller so that
implies t uh 1
a greater than
t1b is that what we expected
yeah we can transfer
energies only in the direction from the
hot to the
cold that's close your statement of the
second law of course if you want this
negative it can do it only in the
opposite
situation
next and all right so that's uh so by
looking at the two end
parts you uh we proved that was a
statement of the second law that uh uh
energy cannot uh uh flow spontaneously
and spontaneously is well while there
are no other external effects you're
considering a system in which this is a
composite A and B is
isolated so uh only can only occur from
hot to cold high temperature to low
temperature
if there is a
finite if the two systems initially are
at different
temperatures it says that the there must
be also an eltropy transfer between the
two and this entropy transfer must be
contained between these two
extremes it doesn't have have to have a
specific value as long as it is within
that
interval and
clearly if the
temperatures are
positive as they are for the most
systems uh that entropy transfer occurs
in the same direction as the energy
transfer
so the sign of Delta
S I mean if this is positive temperature
is positive so this is a positive number
and Delta s must be greater than a
positive number so it's positive
two I need also to transfer entropy
which is also uh the geometrical idea
here yeah D NM all what do it 2 a 3 y
z yes yeah let's discuss
that um this is just a way to identify
the inequalities because I'm interested
also in when are the strict equalities
valid in these various
situations and uh so I kept the trace of
where they came from
for example one a comes from here
if system a under go a reversible
process so that the uh there's no
entropy produced in a this becomes a
strict equality okay and you and so this
becomes here's one a so this becomes a
strict equality when this is
zero that Al so for system
B then we have uh uh like 3 a oh no I'm
sorry 2 a is
here when is the uh strict quality
valid
okay remember there is is where we did
the taor series
expansion so if we if we remain on the
curve for the stable equilibrium stat so
if state two of system a uh is stable
equilibrium uh we have strict equality
because we are in the maximum entropy uh
State here if you instead go somewhere
inside uh then you have an inequality a
strict inequality so in other words that
inequality measures how distance you are
from
equilibrium
okay so that means that if system a ends
up in stable equilibrium State you have
the equality here in 2 a them for
2B ah 3 a and
3B are
um okay when do I have equality there we
said it if we have a
reservoir if we have a reservoir the
second derivatives are zero and
therefore this is equal uh so in order
for the DS a to be strictly
equal to D EA over T1 I need both these
inequalities to be strict equalities so
I need system a to end in a stable equum
State and system a to be a resir
even for
me
now it's clear also that since these two
extreme
values are different if I start from
different
temperatures okay it's
impossible that all the strict
inequalities equalities apply at once
otherwise I would have a situ in which
one number is different from a different
number okay but for example suppose
system a is a
reservoir and suppose it does end in a
stable equilibrium
State and suppose that there is no
entropy produced by reversibility within
a okay that is enough for this strict
equality to apply and that strict equ
quality to apply so that means that the
amount of entropy that is uh uh
extracted from a is equal to the amount
of energy extracted divided by the
temperature of
a and
that's we're converging to the idea of a
heat interaction because that will be a
heat interaction when the ratio of the
energy to the entropy exchanged is equal
to the
uh the temperature of the system that
gives the end the and the
energy okay but so if if a is a resir
and ends up in an an equilibrium
State then suppose then either this one
or the other one
must not be uh strict equal cannot be
strict equality so uh either if system
B if you insist that system B also ends
in a stable equilibrium State and maybe
it's also a reservoir so now we have
having two
reservoirs uh it means so this one is
equal so it means that this one cannot
be equal and therefore it means that you
have you need to generate some
entropy by reversibility in system
B which we can
uh we can
uh we can picture this
way oh no
sorry I said worse
we do it
here system
a system
B okay it just say A and B and you know
what we mean energy versus
Center so if I extract
energy
uh from
a it ends up in a stable
State and no
entropy production by irreversibility
here now system
B must take that same
energy so somehow I should take a
segment this
much uh it receives an entropy which is
equal to this
so it
goes
here so the effect of the interaction
with a is to transfer this much energy
and this much
entropy to b b ends up in a non-e
equilibrium State and if you want it to
go to an equilibrium state it needs to
generate this entropy by reverse
possibility all right so this is a
complicated picture that
I it's another couple of days of uh uh
playing with um PowerPoint but
um it does uh
provide a geometrical explanation of
this uh train of
inequalities essentially showing that um
the
entropy
change or actually the entropy
transferred is between a minimum and a
maximum value that is
uh related to the slopes the local
slopes of the table stable equilibrium
states of the two systems A and
B and I think there is also an even more
complicated
one you
see
um clus uh
statement we proved it for incin
decimal um amounts of energy
transfer but what about you want to
extract a finite amount of
energy
okay well finite amount of
energy uh it is U
again we
cannot reason this way I'm starting from
system a in state A1 and I want to
extract this much
energy so as I said it could
go in any of these
states system B starts from
here it receives that
energy and and in principle it can go in
any of these
states
okay so that means that if you give to
be this much energy it is able to
accommodate only this much entropy it
cannot go to the right to the right
because there are no states there so
this is the
max the maximum amount of entropy that
we can accommodate and
therefore that's the maximum amount of
entropy that a can
decrease so that means that
somehow uh uh a can only go uh down to
here and that is
uh the meaning of this construction so
uh there is a limited range of possible
values and here is the is the analytic
expression
for the Claus inequality let's call it
Claus inequality for um
for
yeah uh
okay yeah we have 5
minutes I think it's enough oops I know
next yeah sorry I decided I I decided
that I couldn't get this far but so I
don't have VI graphs anymore so next
time we'll do work and uh and heat but
let me anticipate the idea first of all
we Define
work as an interaction in which there is
no entropy
transfer see that we we shifted the the
order of of of typical presentation
usually in fine
uh see here we are using entropy to
Define
work and um the
other anything that transfers entropy is
a non-w work
interaction and if
uh if there is an entropy
transfer is not necessarily always heat
we're going to call heat a very special
limiting
situation essentially that limiting
situation that is captured by this train
of inequalities
here when you squeeze the
interval in which the entropy transfer
values are
confined and you squeeze that interval
it becomes just a single
possibility how do you squeeze that
interval by having the two systems begin
at close temperatures close and close or
actually in the limit in which the two
systems have the same
temperature the the entropy transfer as
a precise value it doesn't have any more
in range just a precise single value
which is equal to to the energy
transferred divided by the temperature
of the two systems that's we call it
heat and that's so energy we will call
it Q so Q over
T so the entropy transfer will be the
heat over the
temperature which I'm sure is uh the way
you have seen
uh probably the definition of entropy in
previous uh courses
okay so yeah I think we can stop uh here
for today