[MUSIC PLAYING]
MEGAN MITCHELL: All right.
Hello and good morning to
those of you joining us.
And welcome to part two of
our AI Innovation Series
here at Jameel
World Education Lab.
For those of you
who don't know me,
I am Megan Mitchell and
Acting Director for Operations
and Strategy at J-WEL.
And I'm here to serve
as a moderator today.
But what we're hopeful is
that this will be really
a lively, interactive discussion
with folks, chatting with one
another, asking questions.
Of course, I have questions
prepped and prepared.
But I am hoping that I become
almost irrelevant as people
start diving in.
So don't hesitate, please,
to speak up and share
your perspectives.
This actually builds on our
first event of the series,
which happened last
Tuesday on August 6th,
and the video is
available for that,
where we hosted MIT Dean of Open
Learning and Digital Learning,
Cynthia Breazeal.
She's also a professor at the
Media Lab to talk about her work
and the work that's
happening at MIT on applying
AI for intelligent agents to
serve as learning companions
and mentors and
really the great work
that's being done on
leveraging social and emotional
artificial intelligence
is key to optimizing
learning for
particularly younger
learners with the promise
of this transferring
to older learners as well.
And really, these
AI powered robots,
which are exciting
and fun to see,
can be used as peers
and learning companions,
because it's really critical
that that social activity stays
in as a part of the
learning process.
And beyond that, Dean
Breazeal also really spent
a lot of time talking
about not just AI literacy,
but AI fluency, and what does it
mean to not just learn about AI,
but learn how to use
AI and how to use it
as a responsible actor,
and really driving it
forward as a learner as well.
So with that setup,
we have two colleagues
of Cynthia Breazeal's,
of Professor Breazeal's
here, Hae Won Park,
and Sharifa Alghowinem,
who will be speaking
about the work that's
being done they're doing also
as part of the MIT Media Lab's
Personal Robotics Group
and really building
on the discussion
that happened in what
Professor Breazeal presented.
And then from there,
we've actually
asked two of our
members to join us
as well from the National
Autonomous University of Mexico.
We have Maura Pompa Mansilla.
And from University of Sao
Paulo we have Seiji Isotani.
So they will be responding
to what they hear also
from Hae Won and Sharifa.
So this is hopefully going
to be an engaging dialogue
and gives you all a chance
to really engage and react
and respond and share
what's happening also
at your universities.
This is being
recorded so that we
can share it with our members.
But wanted to lay
that groundwork
and excited to have you here.
So just a little bit of
background first on Hae Won.
Hae Won is a research scientist
with the Personal Robotics
Group at MIT.
Her PhD is from Georgia
Tech, and she actually
is the co-founder of
XAI Robotics, which
is a spin off from some of the
work she did at Georgia Tech.
And she really
focuses on developing
interactive social machines
that really personalize
for their users over long term
interactions and keeping in mind
the unique needs and
goals of a learner.
And her research
agenda is centered
around developing those
personal robots and agents that
are capable of transforming
learning from one interaction
to another and utilizing
collective knowledge
and sensing across intelligent
and intuitive interfaces
that are embedded
in everyday objects.
And then we'll hear
from her colleague
as well, Dr. Alghowinem, who's
also a research scientist
with the personal robotics lab.
And her PhD is in multimodal AI.
And that's from the Australian
National University.
And with this expertise that
she has in multimodal AI,
she really focuses on
modeling human behavior,
using these frameworks.
And issues like mood and
behavior recognition,
using speech and gaze
and body movements
to detect conditions like
depression or suicide
and deception among learners.
So those types of really
maybe more subtle--
things we think of
as more subtle cues.
And she's also an
Associate Director
of Postgraduate Programs at
Prince Sultan University.
So she has eight
years of experience
teaching computer science topics
and working with students,
graduate students as well.
So excited to have
them both here.
Before we turn it
over to them, they've
prepared a little
bit of a presentation
to lay the groundwork
and to build
on what Cynthia,
Professor Breazeal
had done in our last session.
I would be remiss if I didn't
say a few words about Bill
Bonvillian, who is
really the person who's
been the driving force behind
this AI Innovation Series.
He leads a lot of our
thinking series here at J-WEL
and has been doing a lot
of work with MIT Open
Learning over the years.
He's actually been teaching
at the intersection
of policy and technology at
MIT for quite a long time.
And he has a unique perspective,
because he's actually
the director of MIT's
Washington, DC office.
So advocating for MIT and in
the science and technology space
and with our government
and policymakers.
Because he spent a
lot of his career
in Congress working, supporting
our congressional leaders
to make sure they were
informed and prepared
for the types of transformation
that was happening.
So with that said, Bill
would like to say a few--
I would like Bill to say a
few words to set the stage,
and then we can turn it
over to Hae Won and Sharifa.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN: Sure.
Thanks.
Thanks, Megan.
Thanks for that good summary.
I'll just say a couple of things
for about a minute as kind
of backgrounders for
all of us to think from.
I mean, Cynthia's, obviously her
big message was how personalized
education is, how social
it is, and how much
learning is really
social learning
in the context of other people.
And if AI is going to be
successful and add a new tool
set, the social and
emotional features of AI
really need to be made optimal.
So that includes emotional
engagement with learners
and that includes treating AI
really as a collaborating ally.
And AI, as Megan
noted, will need
to be designed to perceive
interpersonal cues,
to develop a form of rapport
and social inferences
and pick up emotional cues
that reveal the kind of learner
state of mind.
So that means it's going to have
to be good at social observation
and picking up guidance
from that observation.
So social AI powered
robotics, which Sharif and Hae
Won have both worked
on in turn can
be used really as kind of
peer learning companions,
if they're optimized.
But she also emphasized
that because learning
is a social activity for people,
teacher engagement is critical.
AI is in no way a
real replacement
for that social engagement
and mentoring from teachers.
And then the other
big theme of her talk
was really around AI
literacy and fluency.
Educating students
in the first case
as how to be literate
so they understand
the new technology and
its potential uses,
but also its limits and the
problems that it can cause.
So to be good users,
they've got to understand
both sides of this technology.
And she argued
that we really need
to strive towards AI fluency,
where students really
learn how to make AI.
And this is, essentially
in education terms,
this is a
constructivist approach
advanced by educators like
at MIT Seymour Papert.
It's really learning by doing.
And she discussed how we
begin to introducing this
and discussed a lot of
tools that MIT has developed
for both students and
teachers to help bring AI
into classrooms.
So with that, let me
turn it back to Megan,
and we'll go to the next stage.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Absolutely.
I'm just here to
turn it now, we're
going to hear from
our two colleagues
from the Personal Robotics
Lab at the Media Lab.
So I know Hae Won has
some slides to share,
and we will jump into
their presentation, please.
HAE WON PARK: Yeah,
thank you, Megan.
Thank you, Bill,
for the staging.
Yes, I have my background
Media Lab space.
This is where people
hang out and we really
emphasize the power of
collaboration and just people
with collaborations
being birthed from just
people mingling together.
So here's our fun space.
Yeah, great to be here.
Thanks for the invitation.
I'm also a co-director
of MIT RAISE,
which is Responsible AI
for Social Empowerment.
And I particularly
lead the AI augmented
learning component
of MIT RAISE, which
is about how to integrate AI in
education to empower learners.
So we have also Hal and Eric,
who are also other co-directors,
Cynthia being our overarching
director of MIT RAISE.
We also have [INAUDIBLE]
how to bring AI education,
teach about AI, and how
to empower teachers,
professional development.
And AI augmented
learning focuses
on how AI can support learning.
So how can we use
AI for education?
So that's the big picture of MIT
RAISE I'm going to point out.
And also apologize for my voice.
I'm just recovering
from COVID, and I still
have a stuffed voice.
So you might hear my
voice breaking at times.
That being said, I
bring you a presentation
that goes a little bit more
deeper than what probably
Cynthia shared, like
our overarching vision,
last Tuesday.
Going a little bit deeper
into basically the components
that Bill pointed out.
That was just a
fascinating summary, Bill.
So yeah, let's get right to it.
So we've been working on this
personalized AI companion
agent for over 10 years,
over 15 years, I would say.
And where we really focus on is
how can we bring the powerful AI
tools, but not as just the
tool, but as a companion that
can really integrated
in your everyday life
and be that companion that
personalizes to you over time,
understands how this student
or what kind of a learner
this student is, what
motivates the student.
And really leverage those social
power to support the learner's
motivation to learn,
to really build
a foundation over a long
term, to really set up
for student success over time.
So we are not particularly
too interested
in trying to instill
the actual knowledge
part of the curriculum
versus we've
been working a lot on
how to support students
to have a mindset,
have an attitude,
have a motivation so that
they have this intrinsic power
to support and propel
their learning forward.
Because if the students actually
have those intrinsic motivation
to learn, you don't
really have to instill,
embed knowledge in them.
They will self learn,
self teach them,
or find resources to learn.
So that has been our focus.
And so that being
said, we will learn
more how social
AI agents support
those kind of
development in especially
young early childhood.
Because we think the school
readiness and diversity
in classrooms needs
to be supported
in the right direction.
And worldwide now,
every learner when
they enter the public
school system in the US,
depending on the state
and district that
happens in preschool,
sometimes in kindergarten,
some districts might not
even support kindergarten.
The public school system
starts at first grade.
But when they first enter
the public school system,
they are a unique distribution
of their cultural and linguistic
background.
They might not
come from a family
where English is their first
language, which then that might
actually be a factor for them
to have a harder time being
integrated into the classroom
learning and interacting
with others.
And because at that
early of an age,
interaction is key to learn.
No one starts to learn
and read and write
by just studying the book.
They learn by social interacting
with the teachers, the peers,
people around them.
So that's why what we are
really highlighting here,
learning is not just about
cognitive engagement,
it's about social and affective
and relational engagement.
I'm sure you all had experience
where you studied harder
for a subject when you
liked the teacher more.
So we're trying to really
highlight these aspects of what
we can bring with social AI.
So before a lot of the
intelligent tutoring system,
they primarily focused
on the cognitive part
of students learning.
But learning is not just
about cognitive engagement.
Let's bring in social,
affective, and relational
aspects to learning as well.
So the video is essential to
any kind of presentation we do,
because we actually install
a physical embodied agent
in the scene.
So take a look at
how the children
is engaging with this physical
embodied social agents.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- Nice to meet you.
Want to play a story game?
- Yes.
- Once upon a time, a
little penguin named George
lived in the South Pole.
Go ahead.
You tell a story.
- I want it to be
about a snowman.
- Ooh.
- Once upon a time,
there was a snowman.
And he was alive.
- I'm a baby dragon.
See my wings?
- Yeah.
- Will you play with me again?
- Yes.
Yeah.
- Ooh, hi.
- Hi.
- Remember me?
I'm Green.
- I remember.
- Is it your favorite game too?
- Yeah.
- Your turn.
- The penguins took
back the hat and put it
on the snowman's head.
The end.
Your turn.
- I'm gonna tell a
story about a snowman.
- Ooh.
- Once upon a time there was--
there were two penguin sisters.
[END PLAYBACK]
HAE WON PARK: OK.
So I'm not sure if you
noticed, but this work
in the video, the particular
video I showed you,
was done when Frozen
was a bit hit.
So you could notice
actually children
telling a story about two
sisters, penguin with two
sisters, [INAUDIBLE] snowman.
So the reason I'm
bringing up this old work
is because we built a
lot of foundational work
in our early years of
this investigation.
And what you just
saw in the video,
I think if you focused on
how the children is treating
the robot, you could also see
their development of theory
of mind.
Placing the tablet
or reorienting it
so that it's on the correct
orientation for the robot.
And then later on, actually
being on the same side
with the robot and
sharing these experiences.
So why do they
engage in such a way?
Because this is also
not an observation
we can take when
children are just
interacting with a tablet
or a smartphone or a TV.
They're actually interacting
like a social being.
And what's actually
happening inside
them is there are papers that
actually saw why people engage
with social robots, these
physical embodied agents,
in such a different
way than they interact
with other technologies.
And they found out
that the actual brain
area that lights up
when people interact
with a social embodied
agent, they're
the same regions in
the brain light up
when they are socially
engaged with another agent
or human being.
So we are just leveraging
this kind of impact
the social agent have.
Because we also
get into, oh, isn't
installing robots expensive
in classrooms and in homes?
So can there be other more
scalable and less expensive
ways?
So we will actually get
to that discussion later.
But that's why we
are emphasizing
these physical embodied
agents, because we actually
see in the field
of difference it
makes in terms of
students' engagement.
That also leads to
the learning outcome.
So yeah, so in our
early investigation,
we focused quite a bit on
social emotive perception
and expression.
So recognizing how the
children is engaging,
what are their
interpersonal cues
that they display to the
robot, because then you have
to react to it accordingly.
Also use that information to
personalize the interaction.
The social emotive expression,
as you saw in the video,
we also put a lot of
effort in designing
the cues that is
displayed by the agent,
because it needs to be
transparent and interpretable
by the user interacting
with the agent.
And also that becomes the factor
for engagement for the user.
And then combining those
understanding and the expressive
cues of the agent, we leveraged
them to actually learn
during the interaction.
Well, what kind of a learner
is this particular student?
Do they welcome
challenges or do they
like more hand-holding
and support over time
propelling them to be a more
challenged, focused learner?
And in all of this
picture, we really
have this long term
relationship building.
So we've seen in the
field that students
build a rapport and emotional
bond with the agent.
And how do we actually
leverage an engineer for that
so that it can actually
propel the learning forward?
And also in a ethical way.
So a lot of great discussion
points that we can get into.
And these are all little
projects and capabilities
that we did.
Not to overwhelm
you with a text,
but building a social agent is
not just about machine learning.
It has to also combine
human psychology education.
So we had a lot of
collaborators along the way,
a lot of sponsors,
including J-WEL,
that had been working
with us to really
bring this kind of
technology forward.
So I'll speed up
a little bit here.
So this is about learning how
the robot should be expressing
and displaying the right
sentiment as it interacts
with the students.
We also tried to
understand, because we
are working with young learners,
like five and six-year-olds.
And we noticed that their
encoding and decoding
of social cues is actually
quite different from how
adults encode and decode.
Like Megan right
there, you are nodding.
That's a great
backchanneling cue.
We actually noticed that kids
this young of an age rarely nod.
It's not one of their
encoded cues, a cue
that they use to communicate
that they are engaged.
So we need to utilize
different cues.
So take a look.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Broke the window.
[LAUGHS]
And then it ran through the
school and peeked inside.
He saw-- they saw--
[CHILDREN CHATTERING]
[END PLAYBACK]
HAE WON PARK: So we
collected this data
to train to
recognize and develop
expressive cues of the robot to
make sure that when the robot is
listening to a children's
story, they can feel the robot
is engaged to their
story and vice versa.
When the robot is
telling a story,
we also want to recognize
the right cues from the kids
to recognize when they
are engaged and disengaged
so that the robot
can also then perform
different actions as reactive to
and responsive to the student's
cues.
So we did a bunch
of studies and we
recognized that we found that
when the robot is actually
able to recognize and encode and
decode the engagement cues, then
they are more engaged
with the robot
who can actually
backchannel accordingly
to when they are talking to
the robot, telling a story.
And then the highlight part of
our research is personalization.
Because no one
learner is the same.
No two learner are the same.
Every student learns and they
get motivated differently.
So how can we develop this
personalization strategies
for robot?
We can, for example, adapt
the robot's personality
to the learner.
We've done a ton of work on
adapting the robot's role.
So should the robot
be always this expert,
like more knowledgeable peer
that always offers information
and knowledge to the student?
Versus can we actually design
a vulnerable robot that
asks for help from the student?
And then can it actually
be a dynamic, adaptive role
that is like a very natural
peer to peer interaction?
You can be more knowledgeable in
one part or less knowledgeable
in the other.
So that really
brings the building
of the reciprocal
interaction and relationship.
And can we actually leverage
that to engage the student
and propel their
learning further?
We had so much fun
doing these projects.
So this was a work that we did
to really adapt the robot's role
to the learner.
So when the student
is struggling,
the robot offers support.
Oh, I think lavender means this.
Versus when the
student has knowledge
that they want to demonstrate,
kids love to teach others.
And then that's a point
where the robot is actually
asking, hey, do you
know what this means?
Or can you help me with this?
And kids just jump in and
they offer their knowledge
to the robot.
And for the robot,
that becomes a moment
to learn what the child
knows and doesn't know.
And also that becomes a factor
for personalizing interaction
and personalizing the learning
for this particular student.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Lavender?
I don't know.
Lavender.
- What are we trying to find?
- We are trying to find
lavender color stuff.
- OK.
The word was lavender.
- Yes.
And what is lavender, though?
What's lavender?
No, that's blue.
What is lavender?
Girl jumping.
[CHIMING]
[END PLAYBACK]
HAE WON PARK: Just to pause
the video at that point.
So what they are
actually doing is
they are playing a word
vocabulary learning game
like I-spy.
So find something
that is lavender.
So they need to collaborate to
find objects that are lavender.
In the meanwhile, we have
these cameras on the tablet
and on the robot that
monitors the child's
expressive and engagement cues.
And also the robot,
if you noticed,
gazes at the child,
gazes at the tablet.
It's also signaling
its engagement
and also creating opportunities
to observe the child's cues.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- I'm sure you will
do better next time.
I believe in you.
- Robot's turn.
- Time to perform.
Lavender is purple.
- Yes.
Just like my--
[END PLAYBACK]
HAE WON PARK: So there we go.
So the robot decided that the
child would need a demonstration
and offers its knowledge.
And when the child
is confident, they
know what lavender means and the
robot will actually back off.
And when it's turn, it's
going to ask for help.
And that gives
another opportunity
for the child to
demonstrate their knowledge,
practice their knowledge.
And over time, we are
making this reinforcement,
leveraging reinforcement
learning, which basically means
the robot gets rewarded for
how the child is engaging well
and propelling their learning
forward, thereby understanding
that, OK, this child now is like
a learner that loves challenges.
So even if the
child is struggling,
let me back off, because this
worked better for this child.
Versus if the child is--
they need like a little bit more
hand-holding at the beginning,
then it learns that, oh,
this child does better when
I actually offer more support.
So let me give more
support to the child.
So thereby over time,
the agent can actually
personalize its role and
actually adapt its behavior
in real time along the way.
So graphs.
But this is basically
showing how powerful
the personalized and adaptive
learning agent supports
children's learning.
So it shows that over time,
and especially over long term,
that we see the
personalized robot offered
much better support
in terms of propelling
the learning forward and
also in terms of engagement.
We also went back after
three weeks to a month
to do a post-test on if
the learning actually
stuck with them.
We actually found that with
the personalized robot,
more knowledge actually
stuck with the child
even after the
interaction had ended.
So we've been applying
this kind of mechanism
for adapting robot's role
in vocabulary learning
and syntax learning.
A lot of literacy and
language education,
because that is a foundation to
any kind of learning, including
STEM education along the way.
We also applied it to how we can
foster creativity and curiosity
in children.
So this all results points to
how personalization actually
works.
This is one of my
favorite projects
where we worked on not
actually teaching a vocabulary
or anything like that, but
really growing their growth
mindset, which means
growth mindset means
it's a belief of your
ability that when
you put in enough effort and
try hard, you grow over time.
Versus a fixed mindset is,
oh, I'm born with my skills.
My parents aren't smart.
Probably I'm not smart.
So how can we actually intervene
with those internal beliefs
about their own ability?
If the robot is actually showing
these beliefs about itself,
can it actually transfer and
affect the student's belief
about themselves?
And we actually saw
a very strong impact
of this interaction.
And this work was
really well recognized
across our community,
education community.
Because before the growth
mindset was studied mostly
between parent and
child relationship,
teacher child relationship, but
not a peer to peer relationship,
because you can't have
a five-year-old actor
act out to another
five-year-old.
But we can because
we have a robot.
So the robot is demonstrating
how it deals-- sorry.
How it deals with
failure and success.
And when it's failing,
it's not saying I'm dumb
or I'm not good at this.
It thinks of it as a
learning opportunity.
Same as when it succeeds.
It doesn't say,
oh, I'm so smart.
It says, I put in a lot
of thinking into this.
And this time, I succeeded.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- So I will try even more.
Let's move this piece.
[CHIMING]
I never gave up even
when it was hard.
You're next.
Try hard and you will--
[END PLAYBACK]
HAE WON PARK: So actually
doing our pilot test,
we actually found out
the fixed mindset,
because we had a fixed mindset
robot and a growth mindset robot
condition at the beginning.
And we found how quickly
kids actually grasped
the fixed mindset that we
had to bring those kids back.
So when the robot is saying,
oh, this is too hard for me,
this is beyond my level, kids
were adapting that so quickly
that we had to bring
those kids back
and actually do several sessions
of growth mindset sessions.
And then in our main study, we
had ditched the fixed mindset
condition because
of that very reason,
and we replaced it
with a neutral mindset
where the robot is just,
oh, I failed, I succeeded.
Just talks about its
factual information
versus displaying the mindset.
So we found out that
even in a single session,
after a single session, that
this impact was so significant
that we thought of bringing this
result to a longer term semester
long classroom.
So here we installed
robots in classrooms
and did a similar
puzzle activity.
Some puzzles are really
challenging to solve,
but we measure what kind
of difficulty level puzzle
the children were selecting
over time, what kind of behavior
they are adapting.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- If my pronunciation
is a bit wrong.
[END PLAYBACK]
HAE WON PARK: And eventually
what they actually
believe about their ability.
So I'll skip the first
interaction part.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- As we become friends
with-- rotate pieces with--
[END PLAYBACK]
HAE WON PARK: Then we later
on went back and interacted--
wait.
This video doesn't have it.
Sorry.
We went back and actually
interviewed the children.
What do you think about--
why do you select
a difficult puzzle?
Because when they select
a difficult puzzle,
the robot will ask, why did you
select the difficult puzzle?
Then kids will actually say,
because it helps my brain grow.
It won't get me more
stickers, because we gave out
stickers as a reward when they
were able to solve the puzzle.
But we were actually fascinated.
Kids with stickers, you
know their relationship.
But they were not dwelling
on stickers anymore.
They understand that
selecting more challenges
and being more welcoming
of difficult challenges,
it actually helps them with
growing their brain over time.
What we also found out is that
when growth mindset was paired
with curiosity
fostering interaction,
they stuck longer after
the robot was removed.
So we really understood
that power of growth mindset
and the persistence of the
effort that you put in.
That will eventually--
and the belief
that it will eventually
come back to them,
reward them in a longer term.
Amazing.
Oh, here's the interview.
OK.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- If you were playing this
game, which game would you pick?
- This one.
- This one?
Why would you pick that one?
- Because it looks like a
challenge and I love challenges.
- So if you had to
choose which one you
were going to try to play,
which one would you pick?
Which treasure chest?
The mystery one?
Why?
- I like mysteries.
- You like mysteries?
- One, two, three.
Which would you choose?
Three?
Why is that?
- Because it looks mysterious.
And I wanna do something
that will help my brain grow.
[END PLAYBACK]
HAE WON PARK: Amazing.
It gives me chills
every time I see this.
So I want to end this talk with
one of the most important aspect
that we found across
our investigation.
We actually found that when
children rated how close they
are with the robot,
those children who
rated the robot as
being close actually
had a very strong positive
correlation to their learning
outcomes.
We also see this not
just in vocabulary
learning and things like that,
but we see the same phenomena
for instilling growth
mindset and other behavior,
other kind of behaviors too.
And this correlation
was even stronger
when the robot was
personalized to them.
So it actually brought
that personalization.
Kids actually feel
that the robot
knows them, understands them,
can match their learning
pace, their learning style.
So with that, I want to
open up for questions
or I will actually
hand it off to Sharifa
to talk about our
AI fluency work.
And that will be
a nice transition
to how we engage
with older students
beyond this early childhood
stage of their education.
OK.
Thank you so much.
MEGAN MITCHELL: That's great.
And for those of you
who've just joined us,
once we hear from our guests
from the MIT Media Lab Personal
Robotics Group, we've invited
two of our member organizations
also to share their perspectives
on what they've heard
and really launch a dialogue.
So just I know a few people
joined us after we started,
so wanted to reset.
But please, Sharifa, would
love to hear from you.
SHARIFA ALGHOWINEM:
Yes, thank you.
So my piece is short.
I just wanted to touch
base on the AI literacy
and AI fluency that Cynthia
mentioned in the last week
session.
So we do also a
lot of curriculum
like design
curriculums that allow
the kids to interact
and play with AI
and learn about it
and, for example,
creating models and such.
So when it comes to if there
is an overlap between what
Hae Won mentioned and what
the AI literacy is designing,
we design two curriculum
that actually use the robots
into the AI development.
So we had created a curriculum
for Jibo, one of the robots
that Hae Won also
showed in the videos,
and attach it to scratch blocks.
So the kids will
create an interaction
with a conversational agent.
They will create the
AI models for NLPs,
like a Natural
Language Processing.
If Jibo ask how are you
and then your response
is a positive or
negative, so they
would create the
model to classify
what is the person have said
and then how the robot should
interact.
So it's a
conversational dialogue
that they create
through scratch blocks.
And also it has elements
of AI, either NLP or we
have the blocks for
vision, and then
we teach them all
of these things.
And the other curriculum
that also integrate robots
is the Doodle Bot.
But this is one of the new
robots that we're creating
and we're hoping that
will be cheap enough
to be deployed and be
sent to the schools.
And for that robot, also
kids will use scratch blocks
to control its movement.
They will draw together.
And the robot will be using
its vision to navigate.
And then one of the
curriculums that we've designed
is automatic navigation
with these robots.
If the robots-- the kids
will create algorithms
that finds the coins.
And so they could compete
with the other child robot
to who would collect more coins.
And that's a specific curriculum
design for automatic navigation,
search algorithms,
and all of this
and where the kids would
learn these things.
When we're not
using robots, and I
think this is one of
the questions that
was asked last week,
how could people
at schools who doesn't have
enough resources play with AI
or use AI into their own thing?
So we create curriculums for
using Scratch, for example,
or App Inventor.
App Inventor is a mobile,
also block based programming
for mobile applications.
And they use these
with the sensors
like cameras or
microphone or other things
to know what is perception and
how to create these models.
And that is the AI literacy.
In each of these curriculums,
we integrate policy and ethics.
So kids learn about what are
the ethical implications?
What are the harms of AI?
And they so they will be aware.
One of the new curriculum
that we're designing
is the digital
citizenship or how the AI
could influence their voting.
And that is specifically
designed for high school,
since they're very
close to voting
in the polls in the
next year or so.
And then when we talk
about AI fluency,
it's where how could they use
these curriculums or these AI
into projects.
With these, we
have a few things.
Like we have the future
makers where the focus is not
the curriculum itself, but
the focus is with the projects
that they create that
has social impact.
So they design with
their community
some apps, mobile apps that
would help their community where
they could have an impact either
for the financial or social
or for their own community.
Kids come up with
amazing projects.
And I think they presented
their work last Friday.
It's a six week project
during the summer.
And it's amazing what
you could see from those.
And this is where we're
thinking about how they use AI
as, again, we're not
designing curriculum,
but we're designing the
entrepreneurship mindset
with this program.
And they have mentors that
will take their teams week
by week into designing
their final project.
With this we do, I mean,
we mostly focus on K-12,
but we have also a few
curriculums that are for adults.
But we don't do undergrad or
algorithmic side of things.
But it's more like, for example,
one of the things we did
is a learning machines
curriculum where it is designed
and focused to the leaders
who have to implement AI
into their workplace,
but they might not
know enough technical background
to ask the right questions
before they integrate
AI into their workplace.
So we do these
workshops or curriculums
that are specifically designed
for them to understand
policy and ethics and
harms and benefits of AI
and how they could
create it themselves.
They see it, they navigate
with it, and they build it.
So they would see
what's the error
rate that comes
with these models
and how could they avoid them.
Hae Won, you wanted to talk
about the elderly with robots,
so I'll leave that to you.
HAE WON PARK: Do we have
time for that, Megan,
or do we want to
move on to questions?
MEGAN MITCHELL: Let
me see if that gets
integrated into the questions.
I would like to give our
discussants some time.
But thank you both very much.
I think this has
really opened open up
a lot more of the
depth of the work.
We had a wonderful
overview from Cynthia,
but the real depth of the
research and the nuances.
So thank you very much.
Now I'd like to turn to we
have two discussants here
from two of our
member universities
who are going to share a
little bit kind of response
and how their work is reflected
or not in some of this.
So first I'd like to turn
it to Maura Pompa, who's
with the National Autonomous
University of Mexico,
UNAM, which is a little
bit easier to-- it rolls
off the tongue a
little bit more easily.
And Maura, her background
is in pedagogy and really
has worked a lot in
the conducting research
on education issues related to
teacher training and performance
identity and the inclusion
of ICT in the classroom.
And currently works
as a coordinator
of management and
systematization of knowledge
in the education,
in the coordination
of assessment,
education, innovation,
and development at UNAM.
So, Maura, can I ask
you for your thoughts
and just hear a
little bit from you
to bring the member voice
into this conversation?
MAURA POMPA MANSILLA:
Hi thank you, Megan.
And it's great to be here.
Thank you for the opportunity
to share this really insightful
presentations that
they both have made
and connecting it with
Dr. Cynthia's talk.
And what Hae Won just
showed us is so powerful.
The way AI is introduced
is very powerful.
And how it's used
in the classroom.
And also not only
in the classroom,
but in the
educational practices.
It's really powerful.
And that is regardless
of the educational level
that is being introduced.
The approach of
the social robots
allows a whole spectrum of
the social emotional aspect
of learning as well as
the student engagement.
So I think with the
videos, of course,
it's really powerful how
to see the interaction
and how everything there's
behind those interactions
gets to work.
And all the back and forth
you have with all the data
that you collect.
And you go back and then
you see some of the results
and the interaction.
That for a research project
must be really mind blowing
and really exciting also for the
things that are next to come.
And as Dr. Breazeal pointed
out in her talk also,
well, the importance of
being able to make mistakes
as part of the learning
process and this role switching
with the robot.
And it's also very revealing
as well as the growth mindset
that it allows the
students to do.
It's different when even if
it's a social interaction,
it's different when you are
with a peer or with a teacher,
as it's been pointed out,
as doing it with a robot.
I don't know.
You kind of relax that part
of the social interaction
and you don't feel as judged.
That's what I get from
what you were just sharing.
And it allows room
for that interaction.
And as the robot
itself makes mistakes,
that puts mistakes as part of
the learning process, as I said.
And that's really,
really interesting.
And what Sharifa
just said is also
about literacy and
this term of fluency.
I really like that, since the
talk of Dr. Cynthia Breazeal,
because I hadn't heard
that term in particular.
And it really reveals--
the concept really
resonates with me.
And because it's more than being
literature or knowledgeable
about AI.
I think it brings
more to what it
is to know what AI and
generative AI really is
and how to interact in
a way that you really
understand what is happening
and take advantage of it.
I think it also relates with
affordances, not only literacy.
So it's a broader way
of seeing what AI really
means, because
you can understand
that you have to have critical
thinking in order to use it.
And also the answers that
it gets to you when you're
using something like ChatGPT or
another not robot related AI,
but also to understand
how is it built.
And also by this
using these apps
and creating apps
focused on the greater
good for these
communities and what's
been shared about the
work you're doing,
I think it's amazing,
because it transcends
the educational process to being
put in practice towards society
and the greater good.
So it's really good.
And regarding what
we do at UNAM,
well, we're also not prescribing
what we do to teachers.
What we're doing
really is just the
focusing on teacher and faculty
development and also in student.
It's not literacy, but it's
also this fluency, as you say.
Because it's important
for us to establish
that they are the
ones that are using
AI and they are the ones
that are introducing AI
to the classroom
in a certain way.
So as you just pointed out, that
is really powerful in the way
that not only
faculty but students
engage with this
type of interaction.
So it opens the way or
it really determines
on how AI is going to work
in favor of the learning
that process that is
going to take place.
So I'm going to stop there to
give time to other comments
and what's next to come
in the menu for today.
Thank you, Megan.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Yes,
thank you, Maura.
Thank you.
I'd like to now turn it
over to Seiji Isotani, who
he's a professor of computer
science at University of Sao
Paulo, and spent some
time in the recent past
also at Harvard Graduate
School of Education
and the Berkman Klein Center
for Internet and Society.
And his research
really in mission
focuses on the social
impact of these types
of educational innovations and
educational practices and AI
technologies and policy.
And with particular
emphasis on what
this means in resource
constrained environments
and for low and middle
income communities.
He has a passion also for
this every student receives
that personalized
support they need.
So I'm sure he was watching
the different interactions
with great interest.
And how to best personalize
that learning at scale,
which is obviously kind of
maybe the next frontier.
But with that, please,
can I invite you, Seiji?
SEIJI ISOTANI: Thank
you, Megan, Bill,
and guys for the kind
invitation and Hae Won
and Sharifa for
the presentation.
So what really stick to me
in this presentations as well
as synthesis
presentations was how
you are able to design
the technology, thinking
about both the pedagogical
approach as well
as the technical part.
So combining the two, I
think it's a really good way
to reduce potential bias that
people from technology use
usually have.
They're trying to just
design a technology
and see how it plays
out in education.
So if you see many
people just using ChatGPT
without any pedagogical
consideration,
this is one of the
concerns I have.
And many people in the
community is speaking out
about these challenges of
combining pedagogical approach
with AI technology in
a way that we actually
enhance human capabilities
to learn and teach
rather than just using
in any other way.
So one thing that
when I'm listening
to this presentation
is, OK, so how
can I use all this
knowledge that
has been built with robots
if we don't have robots
or if we don't have
infrastructure?
So the challenge for the
developing countries like Brazil
and other countries
in the Global South
is that infrastructure
is not there.
And how can we bring--
the question is,
how can we bring
the benefits of AI technologies
into places and for people when
infrastructure
and, how can I say,
and teachers are not ready
to use AI technologies?
So this is a big challenge.
For example, we've
been working in places
like in the Amazon with several
different cities over there.
And you don't see internet
connection at schools.
They do have some
internet connectivity
with their cell phones,
so it's not a strong one,
but they do have.
They don't have
computers in classroom.
Teachers do not have access
to computers in classrooms.
And then I keep asking
myself, is there
a way how we can bring
the benefits of all
these real interactions and
experiences into those places?
And if we think that
a cell phone could
be a possible infrastructure,
can we mimic the same results
that Hae Won and
Sharifa presented to us
into this particular device
or creating a low cost device
that you can actually add scale
to use in classrooms where
every student possibly have
access to this technology?
Maybe asking questions or
trying to design interactions
in the same way.
So when I'm trying
to listen and trying
to extract all this important
research into the topic.
These are one of the
questions I do have.
And thinking about AI
literacy and AI fluency,
that pose the same challenge.
So in managing
students and teachers
that do not have
access to a computer.
So can we teach AI literacy
and AI fluency just
with computer science
unplugged approaches?
I'm skeptical about this.
So I don't know if you have
any comments or ideas about how
we can explore the potential
of these technologies
in those regions.
But I really do believe that
to reduce the inequalities
and to reduce the
gap, we can think
about redesigning all
these tools and initiatives
to actually support
these regions.
Because if we can do that,
then at the discussion
that Cynthia and
Hae Won offer to us
to reduce inequalities
actually will
happen if we can actually
find a way to co-design
with AI in those places.
So these are my
first impressions.
And just a final
comment to summarize.
What I love about
this presentation was
it connects well
with a framework
that project 0 developed
a while ago where
to understand or to
improve human learning,
first we need to think
about who are my students?
And thinking about
personalizations,
social components, creativity,
growth mindset, and so on.
It goes exactly
to this direction.
Then we can think about
what students are learning,
the components, the
content component,
and how they are learning,
which is all the process
and the interactions.
And finally, what students can
do with what they've learned.
And I think this
component is still
missing in the presentation.
But I'm sure that you all
were thinking about this.
So after students
have learned and have
acquired those skills
and those knowledges,
what they can do with it?
And I think somebody,
I think it was Sharifa,
talking about digital
citizenship I think goes
directly into this direction.
So thank you very much.
So it was really
wonderful to listen.
And hopefully you
have some ideas
about how we can actually
use all this knowledge here
in the Global South.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Well, I
certainly saw both Hae Won
and Sharifa giving
the adult social cue
of nodding to that question.
So do you have a response
in thinking about
in those low resourced
environments,
how do we transfer
this great work?
Or what is the
time horizon maybe
for these types of things to
come from a lab to fruition
in a variety of settings?
HAE WON PARK: So let me first
lay out the landscape of robots
are expensive.
But for example, Jibo, the
white robot that appeared
in my presentation, that at
the time when it was launched
in 2018-ish time frame, the
full price was $899, US dollars.
Often went on sale
until the company,
the Jibo Inc. had closed.
So at that time,
if we compare that
to how much like iPads
cost, the cheapest iPad,
I was just looking up
apple.com, and it's currently
like $349, US dollars.
So just to give you a
comparison price point
that even for these social
robots, they did have come to,
and that was, what, 2018?
So that's already six years ago.
The price has
quite significantly
come down to the level of
these other smart devices
like a tablet.
So just laying
that landscape out.
And yeah, so when
we approach and I
work with countries that
have lower resourcing
than in a typical
setting in the US
where we are expecting
that when we are installing
these devices in schools, we
expect the schools have Wi-Fi.
That's the one stable
network and Wi-Fi
is the minimum necessity that
we currently perform our work.
And that is where
we like also use,
because these robots, the
lower end cost robots,
they don't come with a
super computer inside.
So we leverage a lot of
it on the cloud compute.
And that's why that Wi-Fi
connection is so important.
We are using latest, the best
automatic speech recognition.
API, for example, for especially
for children's speech.
Then that is all
cloud calls, right.
So oftentimes in the
current technology
that we are working on,
we use a lot of those.
We leverage a lot of those
internet connections and cloud
compute.
And cloud compute is not free.
Every call is a cost.
Now, let's rewind back,
because I just told you
that we've been working on
this field for about 15,
maybe a little
more than 15 years.
If we just rewind back to about
10 years ago, where were we?
Back then we were developing
this personalization
reinforcement models that
run locally on board.
Because there
weren't any powerful
LLMs back then that we
need to make cloud calls
and things like that.
We are also leveraging
because some of the schools
didn't have stable network.
Especially oftentimes we were
given rooms in the basement
and we're like even
if they had Wi-Fi,
there was a very low
network connection.
And then we were leveraging
offline ASR models
on the phones.
Is the performance on
par with cloud APIs?
No, but we still
were able to develop
personalized interactions
and models that
can learn run locally.
And we had to be prepared when
suddenly the school network goes
down but our study
interaction had to go on.
So we do have, because
we worked on this project
for so long, we do have--
the first video I showed
you, you won't believe it,
but that was completely offline.
The ASR was performed
on a local ASR model.
The robot interaction,
yes, it was a little bit
more prescriptive of the robot.
Like saying you should like say
this when the child say this.
You should say this at this
point in the interaction
and things like that.
But still, it is a interaction
that we can provide.
We are also always
thinking about scalability.
Because still, we show the
power of physical embodiment
of the social robot
and how it brings
this affective and relational
engagement from the child.
Yes, we believe that it's
the most effective way,
form of AI agent to use
in this kind of project.
But at the same time,
there can be trade off,
because for
scalability, we probably
want to put something
on mobile devices.
So we also have works
that we developed
a replica of a physical
agent as a virtual agent that
lives on the screen.
We've also done work
where there's a hybrid.
The kids have access
to the robot at school,
but also have the virtual
agent when they go home.
So to provide that
continued experience.
So there are many
ways to also engage.
And Julia, I did saw your
comment on the chat message
as well.
And yeah, we also had a
collaboration with organizations
like curious learning people.
They were also involved with the
one laptop per child project.
And these devices go to areas
where there's just 0 Wi-Fi.
There's no connection
to the internet.
But the interesting thing
about building interactions
on those devices and what
our curious learning also
had pushed through was
developing these offline apps
that you can't really
play it by yourself.
You have to play
with someone else.
So that kind of provides
setting for that.
You are actually socially
learning with another peer
teacher, because you
have to work together
to figure something out.
Even turning on the
device, they have
to think together because
there's no online manual
that they access.
But they also spread
their learning.
They develop
different forms of how
to engage and use these
devices amongst themselves.
So when Curious Learning
went back after a year,
they observed that
the students there
were using these apps
that they had put
about 20 apps on the tablets.
But kids were actually, they
invented their own way of how
to use those apps
amongst themselves
and created their own mechanisms
of how to collaborate,
build this challenging
competitive interactions
amongst themselves.
Use that as a mechanism to
also propel physical learning
outside the apps and all
different creative ways
that they actually
utilize the technology.
So it's also about
designing these technologies
in cases where we can't
have this ideal setting.
The social robots can
be purchased, embedded,
connect to the cloud
compute, or everything.
There's always a
design and component
that we can adapt, take pieces
of the important aspects,
and instill and design for
that given environment.
So Sharifa and I also has got
this J-WEL grant this year
to transfer our developed
technology that's
all developed for
English learners
to Arabic speaking children.
So we can actually install
them in refugee camps,
support their social
emotional learning, and also
the school curriculum.
And in those settings,
we are expecting
that in sometimes
like those cases,
we won't have the same
setting as in the Media Lab
or at public school
systems in the US.
Sharifa, if you want
to add anything.
SHARIFA ALGHOWINEM:
No, thank you.
I wanted to add this statement,
but you did, so thank you.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Well,
I'm mindful of time,
and I'm going to
make you promise
that you will come back
and talk about that
at all points in the study and
keep us up to date, because I do
think that is of particular
interest to our members
who work across--
I mean, I know there's
been a lot of work that's
gone into working across
different socioeconomic groups
and settings in the
US, but then looking
at the next level
of accessibility
from a connectivity perspective,
and doing this at scale.
I wish we had more time.
I have all sorts of questions.
I could have dove more into
that entrepreneurial mindset
and the growth mindset and
how you carry that forward.
I think there was lots here
that we could have unpacked
in a lot of different ways.
But time is precious,
and we are at time.
Bill, is there anything you'd
like to say to close us out?
Because we didn't get to hear
much from you, and I'm sure
you had lots of
good questions too.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN: Seiji,
you raised a crucial question,
and I'm delighted to hear, Hae
Won and Sharifa, that you're
definitely putting
this on the agenda
and at a high point
in the agenda.
Because these are
crucial questions
for how this technology
can really scale.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Well, thank you.
Thank you all very much for
your time, your contributions,
your attention, and have
a wonderful day, evening,
afternoon, wherever you are.
Thank you all.
HAE WON PARK: Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]