[Music] MIA is the avenue where you get the
most cutting edge development and application of
machineing. learning MIA is a seminar series where
we bring in scientists and researchers from other
universities and even from all over the world. So
it it just creates communities which is important
in science. All are coming together to solve a
problem that will eventually impact patients life.
That's the community that NIA has created. It's an
interesting community, right? I mean now the field
of machine learning or artificial intelligence or
modeling uh is really you know fusing essentially
with the biological systems. 10 years ago the two
fields would really speak different languages have
different cultures different taste and so on. And
more and more I think we're seeing a convergence
of the biological sciences and the computational
ones becoming part. It's wonderful to have such
a seminar hosted here uh where different
researchers can come and and also focusing
on some of the details and technicalities that go
behind behind the methods that have been developed
for biological data. MIA community is very unique
in the sense it's very cross-sectional because we
focus on models and inference and analysis as
opposed to like a specific biological problem.
the current place where MIA is especially with
its strong association with the Schmidt center is
that there are a lot of people who can provide
input to projects that are happening in other
parts of the broad and maybe even contribute.
So I think kind of harnessing that availability
of computational expertise and the variety
of computational expertise I think would be
very helpful. I've found mentors, I've found
collaborators, people that I get to just kind
of talk to about my science. um thought partners.
It's been really fun to be a part of the community
and then just kind of be able to like if I have
a random idea, I be like, "Oh, this person had
talked about something adjacent to it." It's quite
exciting how much MIA has evolved over the past 10
years. But I feel like that central theme of being
a community of people that can work together and
like kind of just rift off of ideas has stayed
true, which is exciting. I hope that, you know,
as as the field evolves, we're able to continually
kind of change what we're talking about and change
the nuances that we are considering in these
conversations. Personally, I've I've gained
so much. I love this community. I presented here 6
years ago and it was probably one of the most like
interactive talks I've ever been in with like
the most like diverse group of computational
people probably that I get to interact with. You
have people who are in statistics and math and
physics and they all have this interest in biology
kind of widely speaking. the richness of always
trying to to look out for new ideas and uh I just
think it's a special community. This community is
important because it's really important to stay
grounded in both like the fundamentals as well
as like the new things that are emerging in our
in our field. I think it really helps in cross
crosscontamination between different fields. Like
I think those are one of the few places where you
can take a computer scientist and a biologist and
both of them can enjoy the talk where in other
cases one of them will not have enough knowledge
to understand what we're talking about. Presenting
at MIA is a very uh unique experience. The
separation between the primer and the main
talk forces you to sit back and think about
what is actually the best way to deliver this
material and to engage with the audience. Getting
to hang out with a bunch of cool speakers and cool
organizers. And so I think that the MIA is just
a very fun community in that regard. The concept
of MIA is very special. In that span of a few
hours, you're getting a beautiful throughine from
foundational concepts all the way to the research
that is state-of-the-art. I hope that others who
attend the talks, they really do feel welcomed
to join in the conversation, whether they're in
the room or online, and recognize that MIA is more
than just the talk series. We're putting a lot of,
you know, powerful heads together. We're getting
a lot of people in the same room who, you know,
don't have the same background, may not have
the same goals, but have have to understand
in principle all of the same uh types
of uh of things. At the end of the day,
what's cool is that um you have a core group
of people from at the Broad, other institutions
and also industry that are coming that you see it,
you know, again and again. One thing that's really
cool is that we have a lot of junior people um
and they feel comfortable asking questions and
and having discussions and I think that um makes
it really a lot more lively. The community that
the MIE has created is so meaningful especially
because it's trying to bridge the gap between
industry and academia that has existed for
a long time in this field and I think with
AI needing more computational resources bridging
that gap is super important right now. Hopefully
this community grows more and more and more
people are involved and learning a lot from it.