good morning I'm Maher Dak I'm the
co-founder and CEO of infinite cooling
uh which uh I co-founded after my PhD at
MIT with Professor kppa Varanasi who
spoke earlier this morning and our
mission is to address um industrial
cooling towers and make them more
efficient and the reason we're targeting
this problem is that cooling towers
account for over 50% of all uh
industrial and commercial water
consumption uh and they are used across
Industries like power data centers
manufacturing and uh air conditioning
and recently cooling has become a major
bottleneck in a number of Industries so
we've seen headlines about power plants
having to shut down because they
couldn't get enough water for cooling
we've seen similar headlines about data
centers struggling to build more
infrastructure in water stressed areas
and with climate change air conditioning
uh is growing a lot whether it's on the
building level or District
Cooling and all of these applications
use very similar uh cooling towers that
we
addressing so very briefly the way
cooling towers work if you're not
familiar with them is they take hot
water in from a process and then they
cool it down and send cold water back to
that process and the mechanism they use
is evaporation so essentially they
evaporate some of that water vapor uh
and then some of that water that's
coming in and then water vapor is
generated and then released and you
often see these plumes or white smoke
coming out of these cooling towers and
that's essentially from that water vapor
that's
condensing so what we developed at MIT
and now commercialized is a technology
to capture the water that's coming out
from those cooling towers uh to be able
to recycle it so essentially we use um
an electric field uh approach where we
apply a high voltage electric field that
generates a cold plasma at the um EX
exhaust of these cooling towers that
charges the water droplets um in the
Stream and then we use an electric field
to attract all of those droplets toward
the collection surface and then we
capture it all and then send it back for
reuse and there are a few ad advantages
here first the water is very pure it's
water that's evaporated and then
recondensed so it's essentially
distilled or demineralized water uh the
second um effect is the plume abatement
or elimination of that white smoke as
you can see in that picture from one of
our sites
uh which can help comply with
regulations uh around those uh those
emissions so that's what we are selling
on the equipment side and then we also
provide um uh sensors and analytics for
also for cooling towers so we have a
suite of sensors specifically designed
for these environments plus um physics
informed machine learning algorithms
that can do real-time monitoring
predictive maintenance uh optimization
on these industrial cooling towers and
the goal there is to minimize their
energy and water consumption and make
them as efficient as uh as possible to
increase the process efficiency of
whatever system they're
cooling um so let's look at the case
study here so this is one of our
customers uh it's a waste to energy
power plant in Pennsylvania and the US
so uh this customer contacted us because
they had um water scarcity issues that
were was impacting their reliability so
they were not certain they could get
enough water to run their operations and
they didn't know how well their cooling
tower was
behaving so we uh started by installing
our Tower pulse solution which is the
analytic solution to kind of evaluate
the system and find low hanging fruits
we're able to do a number of
optimizations there on their water flow
controls for example we identified some
maintenance needs that they needed to do
that they followed uh followed on um
just after and uh and then we also
installed our water capture system on
one of the of their cooling towers that
you can see uh See there
and within the first year of operation
just to give you an example here we were
able to save them over a million gallons
or 4 million liters of water and 4,000
megawatt hours of additional um
electricity production due to the
cooling efficiency
increase and then beyond cooling towers
another application we started doing
recently is also carbon capture so
actually um carbon capture systems
whether it's point source capture or
liquid direct air capture uh systems
will use a mist of liquid
uh to contact the air and then there is
a lot of that mist that's released as as
Drift from these systems that's a big
problem so we can use the same
technology we're using to capture the
water from Cooling Towers also on carbon
capture um
applications so these systems you know
are already deployed at a number number
of sites across the world so these are
um some of our um customers in various
Industries so we work in power
generation all thermal power like we
have customers in nuclear gas waste to
energy um in various industrial
applications like chemicals um you know
like fertilizers Pharmaceuticals Etc uh
data centers Metals Etc and then the
final category is air conditioning or H
vac whether it's District cooling or
smaller
applications and um you know the reason
we're here um uh today is we're um you
know looking to collaborate with
Japanese companies on a number of topics
so first if you have cooling towers we
can definitely help make them more
efficient reduce their energy and water
consumption that's a direct uh
application if there are regulations
around the plumes or the white smoke
from cooling towers and I know those
restrictions are pretty harsh in Japan
we can uh help address those a lot more
efficiently and then if you're
developing any carbon capture systems we
can also collaborate on those to make to
solve that emissions problem and then
beyond Japan you know we're looking you
know at number of projects within Asia
and the Middle East as well where you
know a lot of Japanese companies are
very involved and water scarcity there
is a huge uh issue so we're looking at
um you know uh collaborating uh in those
um uh on those projects mostly in power
generation chemicals production and
Chiller plants so you have my contact
information there I'll be at lunch uh
and yeah happy to discuss uh more thank
you thank you Mar