Hello I’m Youyeon Choi,
I'm a 3rd year PhD student
in the Department of Nuclear Science
and Engineering here at MIT.
My research focuses on advanced
modeling and simulation of nuclear fuel
for water cooled, small modular reactor applications.
Fuel is the core of the reactor
core designs
and what you use
for the fuel really matters
for the economics of the nuclear reactor.
So I think really using the advanced
modeling and simulation for the
nuclear fuel is a key
in designing a nuclear reactor.
All the reactors which are operating these days
are all using standard cylinder fuel,
which is ceramic fuel
using uranium dioxide as a fuel material.
But the fuel that I'm working on
has a different concept.
It is helical cruciform fuel.
So it has a cruciform shape
and a twisted surface.
So in that way, we can have a high power
density in these small modular reactors.
We can improve the economics
of small modular reactors.
So there are a lot of things that I like
for being at MIT.
First thing is there are a lot of
brilliant people who are really passionate
about what they're doing,
so I'm really motivated by them.
This is very exciting time
for all the nuclear engineers and students.
There are a lot of interest
and investments for the reactor designs
but I think there are still
some challenges that need to be overcome.
For all small modular reactors
it has a lack of economies of scale
and we need to improve the economic
competitiveness of small modular reactors.
So I think this fuel will help
to be more economical in the future.