it's truly an honor to have you here and
it's mindblowing to sit through the day
of presentation after presentation that
inspires in yet another dimension um the
state of MIT Nano as an organization is
very simple we are extremely lucky to be
where we are being embedded in the MIT
Community allowed us to reach dimensions
and be exposed to Comm to sub
communities of it some of which we
didn't even know existed some of them
are even formed through the accumulation
of the user after user into the tools of
MIT n um six years ago when we opened
October 2018 uh we had no users because
we had no tools our first users arrived
roughly in January 2019 and today there
are
1,500 individuals plus some that utilize
the tools of MIT know uh 340 of them are
not from MIT there are humans that saw
that we have the tools and we are
absolutely delighted to offer those
tools to them in those 350 individuals
outside of MIT you'll find over a 100
different companies most of them
startups and many of those supported by
some of our programs like star. Nano
that indeed you had the choice to be
exposed to a bit uh through the session
that Joyce would L earlier today I'm
tremendously thankful to you for
spending the entire day with us I look
forward to what's next there are many
many great things that come next you can
maybe find out about some of them by
joining us for the reception that is
coming up next so relocate from here you
can join us in the first floor of MIT
Nano both east west lobby and most
importantly the space in between that we
call our Gallery you will for the first
time be able to see our rejuvenated
gallery that was turned on last night
and that does at this moment display a
series of recently captured digital
images from the various nanoscale
Dimensions we have captured on tools of
MIT Neno please do stop by please do
keep celebrating up with us indeed this
is our sixth anniversary and we very
much look forward to indeed engaging you
in whatever is next hopefully you
realize if you're one of the
corporations that are members of ILP or
indeed just want to know about m n the
strength of your ability to learn is not
just seeing us on Zoom or finding online
things we do indeed it is that human
friction and engagement that lead you to
the next set of grand ideas you might
have 10 ideas I might have 10 ideas if
you stay home that that's 20 ideas Al
together but if we meet there are 100
permutations of the way way your 10
ideas and mine can be combined and that
is where the Innovations happen that's
why I say the most dangerous place at
MIT or in the most dangerous thing to do
is to stop someone in a corridor and ask
them so what do you
do because you'll be left with the next
hour of just true amazement as we have
been throughout the whole day today
listening to our colleagues thank you so
much for spending the time with us and
we'll see you next year but first of all
maybe we'll see you in the lobbies of M
Nano celebrating uh at our reception
thank you