the MIT energy initiative presents to
decarbonize the chemical industry
Electrify it researchers urge industry
and the research Community to explore
electrification Pathways to reduce
chemical industry emissions written by
Kelly
Travers the chemical industry is the
world's largest industrial energy
consumer and the third largest source of
industrial emissions according to the
International Energy agency
in 2019 the industrial sector as a whole
was responsible for 24% of global
greenhouse gas emissions and yet as the
world races defin Pathways to
decarbonization the chemical industry
has been largely untouched when it comes
to climate action and dealing with the
emissions that come from the chemical
sector the slow pace of progress is
partly Technical and partly driven by
the hesitation on behalf of policy
makers to overly impact the economic
competitiveness of the sector says Dar
Mala prata a principal research
scientist at the MIT energy initiative
with so many of the items we interact
with in our daily lives from soap to
baking soda to fertilizer deriving from
products of the chemical industry the
sector has become a major source of
economic activity and employment for
Many Nations including the United States
and China but as the global demand for
chemical products continues to grow so
do the industry's emissions new
sustainable chemical production methods
need to be developed and deployed and
current emission intensive chemical
Production Technologies need to be
reconsidered urge the authors of a new
paper published in Jewel researchers
from DC Muse a multi-institution
research initiative argue that
electrification powered by low carbon
sources should be viewed more broadly as
a viable decarbonization pathway for the
chemical industry in this paper they
shine a light on different potential
methods to do just set generally the
perception is that electrification can
play a role in this sector in a very
narrow sense and that it can replace
fossil fuel combustion by providing the
heat that the combustion is providing
says Mala prata a member of DC Muse what
we argue is that electrification could
be much more than that the researchers
outlined four technological Pathways
ranging from more mature near-term
options to less technologically mature
options in need of research invest
and present the opportunities and
challenges associated with each the
first two Pathways directly substitute
fossil fuel produced heat which
facilitates the reactions inherent in
chemical production with electricity or
electrochemically generated hydrogen the
researchers suggests that both options
could be deployed now and potentially be
used to retrofit existing facilities
electrolytic hydrogen is also
highlighted as an opportunity to replace
fossil fuel produced hydrogen
a process that emits carbon dioxide as a
critical chemical feed stock in 2020
fossil-based hydrogen supplied nearly
all hydrogen demand 90 megatons in the
chemical and refining Industries
hydrogen's largest consumers the
researchers note that increasing the
role of electricity and decarbonizing
the chemical industry will directly
affect the decarbonization of the power
grid they stress that to successfully
Implement these Technologies their
operation must coordinate with the power
grid in a mutually beneficial manner to
avoid overburdening it if we're going to
be serious about decarbonizing the
sector and relying on electricity for
that we have to be creative in how we
use it says melaga otherwise we run the
risk of having addressed one problem
while creating a massive problem for the
Grid in the process electrified
processes have the potential to be much
more flexible than conventional fossil
fuel driven processes this can reduce
the cost of chemical production by
allowing producers to shift electricity
consumption to times when the cost of
electricity is low process flexibility
is particularly impactful during
stressed power grid conditions and can
help better accommodate renewable
generation resources which are
intermittent and are often poorly
correlated with daily power grid Cycles
says Yuri dorin an associate research
professor at the John's Hopkins Ralph o
Conor sustainable energy Institute it's
beneficial for potential adopters
because it can help them avoid consum
consuming electricity during high price
periods dvorin adds that some
intermediate energy carriers such as
hydrogen can potentially be used as
highly efficient energy storage for
day-to-day operations and as long-term
energy storage this would help support
the power grid during extreme events
when traditional and renewable
generators may be unavailable the
application of long duration storage is
of particular interest as this is a key
enabler of a low emission society yet
not widespread beond pumped Hydro units
he says however as we envision
electrified chemical manufacturing it is
important to ensure that the supplied
electricity is sourced from low emission
generators to prevent emissions leakages
from the chemical to power sector the
next two Pathways introduced utilizing
electrochemistry and plasma are less
technologically mature but have the
potential to replace energy and carbon
intensive thermochemical processes
currently used in the industry by
adopting electrochemical process or
plasma driven reactions instead chemical
Transformations can occur at lower
temperatures and pressures potentially
enhancing efficiency these reaction
Pathways also have the potential to
enable more flexible grid responsive
plants and the deployment of modular
manufacturing plants that leverage
distributed chemical feed stocks such as
biomass waste further enhancing
sustainability and chemical
manufacturing says Miguel modestino the
director of the sustainable engineering
initiative at the New York University
tangent School of Engineering a large
barrier to deep decarbonization of
chemical manufacturing relates to its
complex multi-product nature but
according to the researchers each of
these electricity driven Pathways
supports chemical industry
decarbonization for various feedstock
choices and endof life disposal
decisions each should be evaluated and
comprehensive technoeconomic and
environmental life cycle assessments to
a trade-offs and establish suitable cost
and performance
metrics regardless of the pathway chosen
the researchers stressed the need for
active research and development and
deployment of these Technologies they
also emphasize the importance of
Workforce training and development
running in parallel to technology
development as Andre Taylor the director
of DC Muse explains there is a healthy
skepticism in the industry regarding
electrification and Adoption of these
Technologies as it involves processing
chemicals in a new way the workforce at
different levels of the industry hasn't
necessarily been exposed to ideas
related to the Grid electrochemistry or
plasma the researchers say that
Workforce training at all levels will
help build greater confidence in these
different solutions and support
customer-driven industry adoption
there's no Silver Bullet which is kind
of the standard line with all climate
change Solutions says malap Pata each
option has pros and cons as well as
unique advantages but being aware of the
portfolio of options in which you can
use electricity allows us to have a
better chance of success and of reducing
emissions and doing so in a way that
supports grid
decarbonization this work was supported
in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation