Jim Flynn thanks for uh
participating so you're all wired up I
[Music]
see
yep
yep yeah I have a couple students that
are working to try to commercialize
figure out the right
[Music]
Pathways okay they're trying to okay
okay yeah would love the chat more good
idea oh look at you you have my my sheet
should have brought my sheet up yeah
we're doing some work in um well as the
standin I thought I should prepare a bit
more T that's some of the things you're
thinking about awesome supply chain so
I'll have my resch happy to hand it off
to you I some point we get right now all
right she us what did I not talk about
that's what I'm GNA talk about awesome
okay all right we're going to go ahead
and
start so this is our last panel and like
we did with the future of work we're
going to talk about the future of
operations so you heard
from our two friends from MIT about
cyber and digital
twins um we have now some industry that
have joined us so I'd like you to go
ahead and start and tell us about
yourself thanks uh name is Rob Scott I'm
the managing director of Americas for
Tech nip energies uh we're a
company really in transition uh we spun
out from Technip FMC about three and a
half years ago and we're heavily focused
uh with 177,000 colleagues in 34
countries and executing energy energy
transition circularity in terms of the
chemistry around uh polyester and
working extremely hard to uh remain
positive through the pendulum as it
swings back and forth with the markets
uh and what owners do as a prime
contractor in engineering procurement
and construction you really are at the
at what is able to go to market uh on
Final investment decision so I'm pleased
to be here it's an honor to represent
Technip if you got any questions after
this we'll be around and I'm here with a
a couple of colleagues uh as well
awesome all right Eric take it away yeah
Eric Lee with halberton so work in the
Upstream uh energy oil and gas um I've
been in the industry for about 12 years
at a couple different oil and gas
companies prior to this was in the
Aerospace business and somehow ventured
my way out into oil and gas uh my role
currently is a technology director and
so I look after sort of everything
digital building the technology and sort
of building out our strategy the company
on what we're going to do with digital
so things like automation controls AI uh
sort of anything in the digital space
I'm working on Super Harry anything that
you want to
add so one project I didn't talk about
because didn't have time to talk about
everything is a project we're doing on
supply chain cyber security our team's
looking at how large companies are
helping or can help small suppliers in
the supply chain be more secure the
issue being of course if you're a small
and medium business you understand you
have to be secure provider however when
you have each customer asking you to
prove to them that you're a secure
supplier and you don't even have the
resource to make sure you're a secure
supplier it's quite a conundrum so we've
been looking at how large companies can
help small companies be more secure and
I'd love to share that if that comes up
as part of the operations discussion
yeah okay we'll talk about that more and
then our Emmy Award winner down there my
brother one an M too so it's very
awesome um throw in a new thing um how
do I win the Nobel I'm not sure or the
Oscar no so I think the one thing just
on the cyber security and the thing I
skipped over is as to keep your eyes
open on a technology called homomorphic
encryption um so as another tool in the
Arsenal it allows you to do end to end
mathematics on encrypted data so for
example if you were to Outsource your
data science you could share your data
but nobody would have to decrypt it in
order to do their learning or the
mathematics on it and so as a tool Intel
Microsoft Samsung are working on both
accelerators um software to make these
um that type of Technology available
yeah I want to say so I think I might
have mentioned I was the president of
Technology review which is mit's Media
company and every year there we do a top
Technologies and homomorphic encryption
I think was
2016 about 15 or 16 yeah so that it's
interesting I feel like these things
often when they're on the list they
start to enter the vernacular about five
to 10 years later so and and it's just
starting to use it's been it's used in
banking and it's used in at government
levels and and the the accelerators that
are happening from a technology
perspective are making it more feasible
to use it at the time skills that are
necessary for manufacturing I guess the
other thing I'll notice I had to I'll
leave at 4:00 we'd had to catch a plane
yes we we haven't figured out time
travel yet we're working on that okay so
then topic of the day is about
transformation right right and so now
we're talking about operational
transformation and and with the panel
the discussion uh with from Carrie and
Brian you heard you know some basis of
things so I want to take have each
panelist talk about sort of what do they
see as sort of the biggest Factor around
transformation in operations what do you
what is hitting you in industry and then
maybe building on either a concept that
you see in in your discussion or
something new rob you want to go ahead
and start I think first and foremost
it's uh human in the loop and how do we
take these
Technologies uh and work to get them out
at first of a kind and scale in a place
that folks don't feel threatened by it
and I understand that's been a large
large part of the conversation today is
you know the
workforce it getting them to understand
that it's human plus machine and that
there's a human in the loop and that's
the critical importance of of being able
to do the Creative work with the tools
that we have I think the second part of
of that is
affordability the the challenges you
have at going to uh out of a Lab First
of a kind to scale up and doing it
affordably so that there can be uh the
investment decisions that it takes to do
this are
also require a lot of stakeholder
participation not just uh companies but
also government local state federal to
do these things so to me at the end of
the day it continues to be about the
human in the loop and how to do that
efficiently uh so that you have a safer
work environment that's more productive
yep really
important I think one of the biggest
things we run into is honestly the
change management so I think you know
the technology is hard and coming from
the technology side uh you know we we we
fight that battle every day and it it's
not easy but uh I'll say I've worked for
many years on the product management
side as well rolling the stuff out and
uh it's fascinating because I think you
can sort of bought the math and physics
as much as we can with engineering but
it's almost getting the people to buy
into it in operations which is super
hard and so I think often times that's
overlooked and I would even go further
and say you know product management is
is a hard role I'm not even sure that we
train our folks well to be ready to be a
product manager and roll out digital
technology so I think to me that's one
of the hardest parts of getting
transformation happen in a business yeah
yeah the change for sure yeah to add on
to that I think that we underestimate
just how hard changes on our
Workforce uh things happen so fast now
that you know for example in in 10 we
have 75 different corporate initiatives
around digitization
75 75 around
digitization enhancing project
management uh tracking the numbers
safety uh environmental and I don't
think I'm any diff I don't think
technique is any different than
halberton or Exxon or shell but 70% of
major change initiatives fail yeah and
this is in companies that are doing it
you know one or two at a year in the
environment that we're in the ecosystem
that we're in you either have to do it
at that pace and at that scale or else
you're out uh I think that's part of the
human in the loop change management
discussion is how do we take it from the
theoretical or in a room where people
are very comfortable talking about what
if and making it real to somebody by
demonstrated that it's going to make a
value ad to their life yeah I think the
culture change topic has been a theme
throughout this right I would expect
yeah Carri you want to build on that or
top I want to build build on that but
also add another top another area I
think this um human in the loop is
really important back in the 90s I did
some research on uh we were just we had
PCS you might remember PCS the big
luggable things or things on your desk
and at that time we were all asking the
question um how do we build our
organizations so that we took advantage
of are the best of people and the best
of technology and I think along the way
we've kind of lost this joint piece of
people do some things really well and
computers do some things really well and
computers are doing more and more things
really well but people still do things
really well we notice things that
computerss will never notice we we can
design the next application that
computers can't maybe AI someday will do
it that's the Hollywood version maybe
I'll get an me for this it's a Hollywood
version of of the how the where these
Technologies are going but the truth is
today and I think for the next few years
it's all about marrying what people do
really well with what technologies do
really well not trying to move one of
them in or out of the loop and that kind
of speaks to my second point I brought
it up briefly in my talk but um we need
to build for and design for security and
I think that's gets lost when we start
looking at transformation we start
thinking about how do we design for
efficiency how do we assign for
Effectiveness for competitiveness for
lower costs we have a lot of uh criteria
for our design but we rarely see
designed for security built in um is
becoming more popular it's certainly
something the White House has been
promoting through uh cisa the cyber
security Center there and many other
organizations are talking about design
for security but as we transform our
operations we want to transform it not
only including Concepts like safety but
including Concepts like security and
resilience because we aren't thinking
that that's just not we're not rewarded
for that we're rewarded for Elegance in
design not for more secure design and we
need to be thinking about more secure
design super Brian I guess in in this
context I guess it would add sort of
design for AI and what I mean by that is
even just the simple thing of having
your maintenance
data logged alongside your process data
it's impossible to get companies
currently they that's where all the
problems like the the tools exist the AI
machine learning tools exist it's
actually getting the clean data and
getting the data in a singular database
where time is known across like hey we
did this to this machine at this time
and that's important event in contextual
knowledge to be able to understand why
your process data is varying so even
that simple thing designing your how you
collect your data like the simple
instrumentation to make sure that
there's a common time base saved
throughout the organization if you were
able to do that you the the amount of
potential in just that that that
solution that problem solving that
problem would be huge you wouldn't need
tools but your point on models I think
is critical there because when you start
the design and you're putting the
attributes of the data into the model
you have to think from Project to
production uh procurement construction
operations and it's hard to get the
capex people and the project people and
the Ops people and in a room and agree
if we could get to what the men standard
is of what those attributes are that
we're going to do this with then you can
also start designing in for security and
a couple of other you know holy Grails
that we're after reason we're here and
we're talking about it is it sounds
really easy but it's super hard and
everybody has a different view of what
they want based on the 40 Years of
operating a plant or a floor
and comes like a discussion on
religion let's double click on this I
like this so um the idea of I mean a lot
who here is running an AI pilot in your
organization one two three you're sort
of hesitantly holding up your
hands okay so a few AI Pilots are does
that mean everyone else has fully
integrated into your
organization you haven't started yet
okay great so this is hard so the
question is how do we basically take
something that's a
pilot and go to sort of full scale
operation like let's let's talk about
that in industry and then let's bring in
like what what we're seeing in
Academia on the horizon so you want to
take that Rob first or Eric yeah that's
more his baileywick I break his
thing I think um maybe one of the big
pieces about and I think maybe I'll
speak broadly to AI there's geni kind of
the new Hot Topic but I think you know
broadly algorithms that do things are
some form of AI uh and I've got so many
War Stories from doing this in our
business I'll say the last five years of
my life maybe prior to this past year
was in our hydraulic fracturing business
so a really you know you talk about hard
tech I mean it's a harsh environment it
reminds me of sort of the military type
application where you're out in the
middle of nowhere there's no internet
it's 24/7 Ops it's I won't say low skill
people I'll say they're very skilled
people but they are very low digitally
Savvy people and so when you take things
out there you know most of the times I
brought back my hardware and it was
smashed with a hammer this is really
what happens every day in the field They
smash my sensors They smash my cables
they break everything so and so you know
this is just to set the context this is
what we're taking our digital Tech out
into and and what I'll share so I think
the answer to your question to me is
transparency I think making the digital
solution is transparent about what it's
doing is possible drives the change
management and makes it easier and I'll
give you an example when I would go out
into operations in the middle of Saudi
Arabia or which if you go to West Texas
it's bot lock Saudi Arabia in some
places um get a beer but you can get a
beer yeah maybe no self service but a
beer but but you get out there and you
know these guys are running just to put
it in perspective they've got 40,000
horsepower about 100 million assets and
super high pressure and and huge safety
risks and so you know these guys are
making two or three decisions every
minute about how they're going to run
this basically a mobile manufacturing
plant to manufacture it well um and so
we roll out there with the piece of
technology says you can click one button
and run the entire thing autonomously
and I'll tell you we went out cuz we
want to get first to Market and get
these things out the door and went out
with PC's that didn't have transparency
like it's making decisions every minute
and these guys are literally freaking
out because they're saying I don't what
this thing's doing and you're commanding
you know a million dollar asset so I
think the lesson learned there is you
know I think and what these guys wanted
was really simple every time it makes a
decision write it out on the screen for
me and tell me what it's doing every
minute so I can evaluate it and give me
the ability to take control if I want to
back and in this case like a a fra crew
may have the manufacturing plan may have
20 machines so we did some things to
give them control of individual machines
but automate as much as possible and so
in that context I think transparency is
they want to know exactly what's
happening every time and why the
decision is being made I think you move
to kind of The Office application you
know and so by the way that would be if
I went to my ux team they would say
that's an absolutely horrible ux Eric
you shouldn't report all this stuff we
make it clean and simple but this is
what these guys need in the field
because they have a you know business
critical application it's high risk I
think when I go to the office it's still
transparent but it's you know gen
hallucinations are a big problem I mean
fundamentally the algorithm is lying to
us this is what it's doing we can use
hallucination these words but it's in
essence telling us uh a non- truth and I
think there it's you know how do we
Shield against just just tell me you
don't know the answer this is really I
think what gen needs to do to work well
in the business and this is what we're
working on every day is trying to detect
hallucinations if you will various
metrics and algorithms and just say we
don't know we know the answer I think
you know it's it's a level of
transparency too to allowing us to scale
AI I think this is the biggest challeng
got today though is I think transparency
is one of the main um things you need to
implement to to make it work and what
we're working
on Super Carrie Brian you want to build
on that in thinking about some
experiments you've been doing or
things want to take it first sure I I
guess the the thing that we recommend
and best practice is that it's never
about a singular tool like I presented a
decision tree a neuronet but you should
be using all the tools and if they I'll
give you the same answer that's great
and if they're telling you if one of
them is telling you something different
if it's hallucinating if it's giving you
an incorrect answer it's a little more
obvious if you're getting answer one
from a decision tree answer two from a
support Vector machine answer three from
a neural net and so in terms of practice
you it's not just say hey I have the
hammer that I'm going to hit everything
with I have the hammer the wrench the
screwdriver I'm going to use all those
tools and all of them are going to give
me a different answer and if I believe
if they all are giv me the same answer I
have a lot more confidence that it's the
right thing I was going to add a little
bit different angle there um I I think
part of the issue we're seeing as we
transition to more AI is a concern that
we're going to lose the skills of the
people whose jobs are being supplemented
with AI and that's what I heard in your
example too the guys in the field they
need to know what's happening they need
to see the million dooll machine being
transformed with AI or with the tool in
a way that they understand what's
happening but there's another piece of
that for me which is we have skill sets
that once we automate them the people
who are doing the work either never had
the skill in the first place or stop
keeping that skill current and that's a
big problem especially where for
something as as sensitive I guess is the
right word in the field where something
could go Ary I mean a little something
electronically this is my big fear of
anything that we digitize whether it's a
digital twin or something in the field
the minute it goes a little Ary if the
people in the system don't have the
skill set or the experience to from
before we autom everything how are they
going to know that it's going a whether
it's a hallucination or whether it's a
process that goes AR and I think that's
a big fear that we haven't really
addressed um in in the implementation of
a transformation transformed system and
we want to think about that as part of
the design we don't we want to make are
part of the buildout we want to make
sure that we don't lose the skills we
we've already lost a lot of skills
because of things we've automated along
the way I I remember um work done by one
of my colleagues many years ago 30 years
ago about automating paper the paper
process and the people paper you know to
make paper making paper paper used to be
you know you boil all the components and
the people that made the paper could
tell by the smell and the the
consistency and the feeling they
automated it all and all of a sudden
those people weren't the experts anymore
because the system automated it but then
nobody ever really had that expertise to
make the paper anymore they was all done
through electronic controls uh the the
the person who did that research her
name was shos zubo and she wrote some
work called automate or infomate and it
was about adding information to A system
that then um changes the way that the
systems done and I I see the same kind
of thing happening with AI the problem
is people start to trust the AI and it
might be wrong and we don't know yet I
mean maybe we'll get to a point where
it's not wrong and we as scientists
would like to think that it's never
wrong but it it is it does hallucinate
does tell us the wrong answer it may not
even be smart enough to tell us that
it's telling us the wrong answer but the
point is that we can't lose the skills
in the interim while we transition to
our new operational um environment
because we need that skill to be able to
make sure that we're doing our processes
correctly I don't know the answer to
that right now but that's that's what
it's sparked in my head is this work we
did many years ago about automating
processes and infom mating processes
isn't it funny that we've picked the
word hallucination that it's
hallucinating and that I I like that
sounds like it's having
fun we know what you were doing back in
it's another example of just giving a
new name to something it makes a mistake
it's giving you the wrong answer it's a
hallucination that's a good one okay so
Rob you got out of that one but I'm I'm
you're not done with me yet so I'm gonna
give you a different question um this
morning Liz talked about uh climate and
that you know we're seeing a lot of
weather issues and different things um
that's also need needs to be imp
impacting how we think about operations
so why don't you talk that a little bit
about
that um so I'll I'll give you an example
okay uh let's start with how you
engineer it right and where the engineer
sits when I was on uh the Keystone XL
pipeline the bulk of the engineering for
the pump stations was being done by
engineering teams out of
Calgary now they're designing for what
they understand to be their weather
impacts long Winters Etc but you're
putting pump stations down here on the
Gulf Coast and it's a much different
environment then when you're trying to
get it signed off by a PE or get it into
operation you're the person is used to
looking at a very specific set of code
as it is applied to weather Etc where I
think we are today more and more is your
plants uh your assets have to be able to
operate at the low end to the very high
end of the temperature sphere so it take
what was it four years ago we had three
days of freezing here in
Texas um plants because they you don't
put heat tracing on the pipes all the
plants stopped operating and we froze
our tail off for three days there's a
whole other set of reasons around that
but at the end of the day it was a
design decision based on cost that that
I wouldn't have as long ax period that I
would have to do this so I'm not doing
it and I think those days are over so
we're going to have to start either
accepting those
costs and Andor being ready to be cold
and freezing for three days or four days
as that works through because it's
happening uh you lose uh it's it's
hotter and wetter on the Gulf Coast
every year where folks are out there
operating and you Eric's talking about
the desert I I don't think that people
are really want you know it's not that
they want to see every decision they
just want to be in the loop with the
decisions that are being made and being
able to say a go noo on an asset that's
multi-millions of dollars and ultimately
they're responsible for that also comes
down to when you stand it up when you
shut it down how you shutter for a
weather event long answer to a short
question but I think we have to start
designing for both ends of the Spectrum
in the in the
Americas good okay so we're gonna now
move to a speed round Brian I'm going to
start with you uh first question and
sort of do a 15 20 second sort of just
response and we'll go down the line what
is the most impactful technology driving
operational transformation today
I I I guess actually what I'm seeing is
an
underutilized tool that's commercially
available whether it be from seens or
any logic things like discrete event and
discret time simulation as tools that
allows you to simulate sort of at the
factory level and and those are things
that are underutilized like they're
commercially available they're well
practiced in some Industries but you
know when small medium companies are
sort of getting exposed to these tools
it's it's it's transformational in in
how they think about their operations
so I told Kathleen I was going to change
questions to what I wanted to answer I'm
not a tool expert so I would my first
thought is AI but we already talked a
lot about AI so I'm going to talk about
what I think is a more transformational
idea and I think the idea here is
designing for resilience I think um as
we're thinking about um uh driving
opportunities for transformation uh we
want to make sure that we're building
something that that can be around for
the world we're expecting with all of
the new um threat and vulnerabilities
that are coming our
Direction I'll go with an old Tech kind
of but containers uh I mean containers
are a simple idea but when you look
across a lot of these Legacy businesses
they're not deployed everywhere and I
I'll use this in the context of
operations I mean the ability for a
piece of software to go down and spin
back up instantaneously is huge I mean
we can't afford downtime I think the
other thing is the ability to push small
updates in low bandwidth environments is
huge I think these these are very simple
foundational things but once again it's
the foundation that kind of we build Ai
and other things on top
of to me it's uh because I'm on a theme
Here human in the loop that's affordable
to me it's uh back to wearables and what
you can do with uh technology Brian
touched on this a little bit earlier I
think that is severely underutilized
when we're trying to figure out uh Time
On Tools how can we get uh equipment or
materials to the craft so that they can
work their magic uh in a much more
efficient manner
what their bodies are doing in these hot
cold humid temperatures and how we can
do things to regulate help them regulate
that so that they can be more productive
uh and safer in the environment to me I
think that's the underutilized tool all
of us have uh most of us in this room I
would say will have some form of
Smartwatch uh you know now you can get
them for 15200 bucks but you know when
you say you have a work site of 5,000
people the construction man maner says
no way am I doing that but I I think as
that becomes more commoditized we'll
find Opportunities and the data that
we'll get from it will reinforce some
things but we'll also learn some things
that we haven't really thought
about okay just just add on that for a
moment like as an intellectual field
people are introducing the concept of
Industry 5 which is actually just this I
actually like also instrument the person
um and having both ergonomic awareness
health awareness of the of the worker as
a part of the the of the overall
operations so that it is a exiting a lot
of academic attention and there are some
some companies that you know BMW they
can think of one in particular that's
trying to use that to accelerate the
rate with which they train do training
uh for manual operations yeah I just
invested in an MIT found a company
that's doing augmentation I think
there's a lot of really interesting
stuff there uh Brian back to you for our
speed round second question question
biggest
misconception about Ai and
operations biggest misconception um I
guess I'll map it as maybe sort of going
back to sort of the point of of the user
interface and how how do we help the
operator know what's going on AI tools
are really good at interpolating like if
whatever your data set is okay I can I
can learn how to predict and what's
happening in the data within the space
that I've observed and the to improve
operations to improve how we understand
the tools to make aware to the person
when a data point that we're trying to
understand is outside of the things that
we've seen in the past um and and have
the tools be able to convey that
information I think that's not exactly
the question you asked but sort of being
able to like flag like yeah we don't we
haven't seen this type of data before so
anything any answer we're going to give
is wrong and this is a prime place where
human context understanding could be
really helpful to make sense of of this
aberant thing that we're trying to use
to predict yes the questions are me to
prompt discussion and interesting ideas
so it's okay if you change them Carrie
go ahead this one I think I'm going to
answer uh I think the biggest
misconception we've already addressed
number one which is that you can replace
people with AI but I think we also have
to remember that um people aren't
perfect either and we've seen lots of
instances where people have introduced
information into an AI system that has
had unintended in this case security
consequences where um people think that
they're entering a schematic just to
make it better into some geni product
and it ends up being part of the
learning to the learning tools that
train a publicly available AI so I think
the biggest misconception is AI has the
answers uh because I think sometimes we
we've got to make sure those guard rails
are in place for the people using our
AIS uh and they understand the risk of
putting something into an AI system that
might unint have unintentional
consequences
I want to Bild on this one I think the
misconception is AI is be is better than
people I think it's absolutely false
maybe in a narrow context in some cases
yes uh and I don't know the why but I'll
I'll hypothesize I think one why might
be that we've got a lot of sensors on us
every day and I'll tell you if you go
out into operations and watch people and
sit there they are seeing smelling
hearing getting input that the AI
doesn't get fundamentally so I think we
have an advantage because we have a new
data stream lots of data streams that AI
doesn't have I think two there's still
something special about humans maybe
this is just my desire to have humans
not get beat by AI here but you know I
think in a broad context of doing really
Dynamic things it's still super hard to
beat humans I I don't foresee AI beating
us in 10 years the humans are still
winning
excellent II I think
that humans have to realize that uh
virtual presence is physical absence and
why do I say that uh I think we've all
been around for quite some time we've
seen different revolutions Evolutions
changes the one constant in all of that
at any site in any lab is the human so
the misconception that I keep working
with with the team on is it's not about
that the human is going to become
replaced or or irrelevant it's about how
do we upscale the human so that they can
use the Technologies in a collaborative
way to get a better outcome than the
outcome we have
today that's what that's what we talk a
lot about at MIT Horizon um okay so
Brian you've got five minutes so I'm
going to let you drive the next this
next portion of conversation and then
we're going to have the mics and and
open up for questions um what would you
like to talk about what have we
missed um so I think the just top of
mind because of a what we do at MIT and
what's sort of what I'm hearing is the
AI as a tool um is a little scary and I
guess the thing that I would like to
hear from the audience is how you how
you demystify and what what are the
things that you do within your
organization say listen okay it's it's
may sound new we give new terms to
things you know I have a hypothesis that
we we we we call it all these other
things and it's we can ground it and the
things that we're already doing so i'
would love to hear like from the
audience in terms of like are there
within your organizations like how are
you socializing and say is there are we
missing the message in how we
communicate what these tools are doing
for us and are we sort of trying to say
that there's something very different
and new when in reality we've been using
them called different things for a long
time um calling it process control
calling it physical process feedback
control I guess that's my bias I see
like there's a lot of just sort
of dictionary creation uh that scares
people and grounding it and things that
they already know I think is the way is
one of the paths forward so right okay
so I did a poll earlier and asked
everyone who was using generative AI uh
and it seemed like most people were
using it
personally but a lot of a very few
people were actually working it using in
their daytoday as an office tool um so
is that was is that right on like who
uses it for
work there's a Nuance to it
yeah so instead of Google you're using
TPT yeah so and and another thing I
wanted to convey before was lot of
generative AI that we see that is been
commoditized is based on generic
knowledge yeah that's why I think uh the
the presenter in the in the morning
session was showing it at the low level
um the of Effectiveness and and easy to
use but there are some gen AIS which are
specific to
Industry that are deployed in a special
circumstances it depends on the industry
specific data and and that has totally
different uh you know the the Nu around
it so I think the question would be
whose organization has built like a rag
system thank
you
yeah okay just a couple that's
interesting that's coming that's what
you're going to do next well can sh I
can share the journey that my company's
going through right now at the moment
with adoption right so I work for a
company called BMC Software and at the
moment we have ai obviously in our
products but for the uh for the general
population what's happening is uh we're
noticing that people were just kind of
like doing chat GPT and stuff like that
and we were really concerned about our
data being out there on those different
models so what we ended up doing is that
at the moment we're doing this thing
called the flight of AI which is
basically we have a series of trainings
for the general population on how to
actually you know what is AI how do we
use it internally externally Etc so you
have to take that no matter who you are
uh we're also doing p we're piloting
just a standard utilization from a
productivity standpoint like with um
Office 360 U co-pilot and also with uh
with Ms teams Pro and you know
summarizing and stuff like that uh and
then we did a pilot just to make sure
that people know how to use it uh the
one thing that we understand at the
moment is now we have every single
organization uh within the company is
now actually uh kind of like trying to
understand who's going to be able to use
it and the use cases the problem is when
you ask people hey you going to use it
they don't know how to use it right I'm
I'm going to use uh gen in Excel for
instance or co-pilot in Excel so there's
a lot of the adoption that's not
happening so now we're going to go ahead
and actually uh enable everybody to
understand with it it subf function and
create our own use cases so we can
actually Target the usability of it um
and then we also looking at elements
like for instance uh the uh agent force
from Salesforce at the moment that we
just looked at dreamforce uh to look at
the uh the next uh you know the the
virtual agents at the moment so work in
use cases with that as well so the
problem is if we just kind of like let
everybody use it it there isn't really a
full productivity that we can actually
measure companywide and we also uh did
uh manage to work with a third party to
try to understand how to actually set
governance around it and and guard rails
and uh if you actually do want to uh do
uh a provision AI tool whether it's
cloud-based or whatever uh you have to
actually go through a system through it
to make sure first of all do we have
anything of this of the matter of the
sort you know obviously their budget if
there's it's actually on our policies as
well uh but also they're looking at if
they do their own models uh for instance
there was one that we we wanted to
provision and the it said no we'll build
it for you so they build it they built
it internal so I think a lot of that is
going on in there but they're trying to
kind of like a ring fence yeah so it's
not a freefor so that's kind of how we
approaching it I run I do want a parting
comment is a as a fear we're lumping in
we're calling AI gen Ai and there's so
much diversity in what AI tools are like
and so like it's great you know gen is
solving some real problems but there's
so much more than to AI as a set of
tools than than what gen AI is so okay
thank you all right stay quiet All Right
audience
questions
there so just on j i you know I'm a True
Believer that it's transformational uh
but if we were here three years ago
probably the main technology Trend that
we would have been talking about was
blockchain blockchain yeah and two years
ago yeah probably the one that we would
have been talking more was the metaverse
none of those two has been mentioned at
least once today so what's the future of
blockchain and metaverse from your
view ah I'm reading I'm reading the book
about Sam bman freed right now that I
highly recommend very interesting he's
also an MIT grage but uh what are your
thoughts on on blockchain Andor
metaverse I I think the reason you don't
hear about it is because it's already
ingrained and incorporated into what we
do and that's goes back to the rate of
change and what we were talking about
earlier about there's so much change and
it's coming at such a rapid pace and
even faster you talk blockchain
underpins Financial transactions at
every stage now it's a large part of
supply chain uh nobody's excited about
it anymore now it's about how do I use
AI
to predict where my next supply chain
Log Jam is going to be or how the
Straits are horuse or XYZ is going to
affect it and you know as for the
metaverse that's something my kids play
in not me so I can really can't speak
much to that but I think it's because
it's ubiquitous now it it is just part
of doing uh work in today's
world I was going to change your
question no
uh actually uh I don't have a comment on
an additional comment on blockchain or
metaverse but we're also not talking
about Quantum and I think Quantum is the
next thing we're going to talk about a
few years from now because right now
we're getting our arms around AI um but
we're at MIT at least in our group we're
also looking at Quantum and we're saying
you know AI is here today and here's all
the risk and here's how we're seeing it
used for cyber and there's all sorts of
applications and there's news technology
implications and Brian's not wrong it's
not all about gen AI there are all sorts
of new AI tools and old AI tools but I
think the next one for cyber for the
cyber world the threats and the get our
arms around is quantum and if you
haven't even looked into Quantum you
should uh it's not here today it's not
ready for prime time it is here but it's
not ready for prime time but I think in
five years that's what we're going to be
talking about we have a whole segment on
on Quantum and basically what are the
basics that you need to understand just
like the gentleman here was talking
about that he had has the whole
organization doing what are the basics
around generative Ai and AI we have that
on 17 different topics and quantum's a
real popular one because that's what
people need to understand the key things
yeah and maybe we're not talking about
blockchain metaverse in the same way as
we are AI because when you were talking
about them two or three years ago you
didn't talk about them taking over the
world or making us irrelevant I think
there's also part of what Brian was
talking about the the lingo that comes
out uh the buzzword Bingo that gets
played as these things roll out it AI is
been much scarier if if you just sit
back and read it and you're not
technologically oriented than blockchain
or metaverse ever were I think maybe
that's also another angle to view it
from and maybe a different take on on
your comment there I I'll speak to upw
and gas broadly um I mean I think my
view on this is those two technologies
are sort of solution looking for a
problem maybe in oil and gas and I mean
there's some scenarios around smart
contracts I think some companies will
try to make it work and it's really gone
nowhere from what I can tell uh and in
metaverse I mean we've worked with a
number of companies trying to sort of
create immersive environments to look at
well trajectories and things I mean it's
like my kids sort of VR device cool but
uh we get back to our desktop computer
and go back to work every day so it
feels it's cool Tech I just don't think
I think it hasn't solved a real problem
for us yet at least in in the oil and
gas space that I can see well but isn't
that right so I mean thinking about like
meterse um in 2010 we called it second
second life so and then VR goggles have
been around for 30 years yeah so we've
had these things and they I feel like
they have a hype cycle and then you know
someone tries to make it big but so in
200 what 21 we were using gpt3 and I
would go on stage and talk to people
about about we're using gpt3 and
everyone would look at me and blink and
say oh that's nice MIT person and then
in you know and then chat gbt came out
and then everyone understood what it was
so it's sort of like something has to
hit that massive inflection point where
Mark Zuckerberg tried to do it with meta
Chang the name of the company but it was
exactly that it was still trying it's a
technology looking to solve a problem
and it was just sort of gaming still you
could almost look at digital twin yes as
a a a smaller version of metaverse
because what you're doing is you're
digitizing something that's physical
same idea and then you're manipulating
it in a digital space to see what the uh
impacts could be what the changes might
be uh and then potentially going back
over to the physical side to make a
non-digital twin back out of it but so
it's almost like that concept is still
around it's just kind of morphed into
something a little different maybe a
little more useful in the in the
operation space I think you hit on the
key part of it is if it doesn't help the
person do their job more efficiently or
save the organization cost it it it'll
no matter how much you push it from on
top it'll go away well I think there's a
piece if it's a competitive advantage
and I think that's where Meta Meta was
going in the first place yeah you know
you can make money on the metaverse you
can set up shops you can do all these
other I mean I don't think we ever found
a solution But Eric and I can't I think
is what we're trying to say from an
operational standpoint physical world
where you're cracking molecules or
you're doing things that you know 20
years ago only a guy up in the Woodlands
thought we were going to do um it's
where the conceptual academic meets the
real world and all all I'm just trying
to say is it's a harsh reality and you
can get opportunities to let it to work
it but even the companies with the
deepest Pockets aren't going to let it
go more than one or two years without
being able to see the the benefit and
that's where I think really for me if
you could get AI to help you get through
the trls faster with some confidence
then we'd really be talking about
differentiators of where we can help
societies and get more things done uh
back
yeah I I don't disagree with the the
application of AI I was just saying that
part of the and maybe it doesn't apply
in your particular industry but the
promise was basically the same thing as
digital twin you make something digital
and then you can manipulate it
differently and and test out things it's
the old you know testing and beta
testing without actually building and
that was where I thought the promise of
metaverse was but it never really
materialized it maybe because it was too
hard to do it the tools just weren't
there to make it easy like ja chat G
BT
yeah yeah
yeah yeah training people to do what the
training yeah so that's an environment
where the simulation is really we saw
the same thing with was that airplane
you know thing we all saw back in 30
years ago where people learned how to
fly airplanes with a simulation
oh that'll be interesting to watch yes
question over here so I I did want to
ask a soft tissue question around trust
particularly around um cyber resilience
um we've been talking a lot about the
human in the loop but I talk about the
machine in the loop now and what happens
if a machine does make a mistake does
create a cyber incident how do we start
rebuilding trust ah good question for
those who are interfacing for the humans
in the loop with the machine how do you
start rebuilding trust how do you start
recovering from it how does the
communication plan that you talked about
does it have an aspect of that it is
things things like that that keep people
concerned I'm I'm I didn't I didn't pay
you to say that right so um two weeks
ago I was fortunate enough to be invited
to the world economic Forum cyber
security meeting and they asked me to
chair a session on building trust post
incident so I happen to know a few
things about that right now in addition
I'm working on a paper right now with
one of our companies one of our cons
Consortium companies about the same
thing so the angle we're looking at is
building trust post incident so and the
question is how do you rebuild trust and
right now the the research we're looking
at is build trust with your customers
and with your employees so it's a
broader stakeholder question but my
research has really been been on
customers and what we're what we're
seeing of course I'm a you probably got
this already I'm a behavioralist person
I look at the people's side and what
we're seeing are mechanisms companies
have been putting in place uh to rebuild
trust things like Chief trust officer
things like um uh trust uh advisory
boards things like um the same kind of
thing we talked about with building
resilience in your process doing that
ahead of time if you've identified that
Trust might be an issue post incident
you should be starting now to build
those trust mechanisms so if there's an
incident you've already got the
groundwork for the trust it's a little
hard to come back after an incident and
say oh sorry now we want to build trust
with you it's a little bit better if you
start up front and say you know we're
trying to build resilience we all know
that cyber attacks can come we know that
the Cyber vulnerabilities are out there
we're doing the best we can we know
you're doing the best you can and let's
build some trust mechanisms now so that
we're transparent transparent is a big
word in trust and we're um we're
building those mechanisms for those
conversations and so if and when
something happens we have those
processes and we have those guide rails
in place to recover the trust or maybe
it doesn't even erode if you've built
those mechanisms in place before an
incident after an incident a little bit
harder to do but that's what we're
looking
at um uh I I have a question and um
actually um this thing whole thing about
the metaverse right so iq3 connect I
mean we're I wouldn't call our solution
metaverse but we've been through the
that and we've been U working with
industrial companies that have
tried and spent millions of dollars and
there are so many carcasses lying around
because they do a pilot and it fails uh
and nobody's been able to scale this
technology or the metaverse or these 3D
environments uh to a level where it
starts delivering you know real uh
business value and I wanted to ask if
that's I think I came late to this
conversation but is is that kind of what
you are seeing
at maybe halberton has played around
with this technology or I know Technip
uh because we worked in the we have
customers in the oil and gas space as
well yeah I think that's it I mean and
yeah I think there's some training on
drilling so there it is being used in
Pockets I shouldn't say it's not being
used but is it transformed to Industry
by no means I mean maybe if you break it
down if I break it down mentally why is
it not worked out maybe it's the cost to
build these things is so high yes and
the value is
not barely there it just doesn't make
sense to do it from a business
standpoint so I think that's why it
hasn't scaled honestly I don't think
that it's useless by any means but I
think it's really I mean so if you can
make it really cheap to build it's free
we probably use it because it's it is
adding some value but it's not big
enough to Warrant the investment yes I
mean that's just an observation I think
that's probably the reason it hasn't
taken off yeah I mean there's just too
many friction points the hardware is
very expensive you know you you put it
out in the on the manufacturing floor it
breaks and people just throw it aside
nobody has a patience to you know say uh
you know and and Microsoft has pushed
this very hard and you know they've
moved away like Hollow lens and all
these big Investments are just complete
failures but I I think the so I'll and
there's a question over here that wants
to bounce on what Eric said but what I
would say look at Technique we take 1%
of our profit and we bake it back into
R&D every year that's pretty phenomenal
for what is really at the end of the day
a company that does technology products
and services is an EPC project delivery
um I don't know of anyone else that does
it at that level now you have to choose
where you're going to put that amount of
money now if I'm a company that's
working in trying to pull through
technologies that deliver a product or a
service to a customer I'm probably going
to do that or I'm doing that today in
the space where I can take somebody to a
lab and I can show them the next
hydrogen or the next ammonia or some way
to do it get more with less energy
versus the metaverse which there's a ton
of other folks out there mining or
pioneering in that space and I'll stick
to what at the end of the day underpins
the two areas that I'm able to create
value internally and externally I think
that's ultimately the challenge uh
around it and we also hype it up a lot
it gets hyped up that it's going to have
this big cycle and you said it was you
know 2016 you were talking about X and
today we're talking about it you know 8
years later I think that's the other
part we're humans and our flash to bang
is near instantaneous you know we're not
looking at this over uh long
generational periods and and that's
really at the end of the day what
organizations are doing whether you call
it R&D or digitization we're all working
in the same space trying to find a more
efficient way of
delivering okay I mean um I'd love to
talk some more after with the yeah if
you're buying the beer for Eric I'm
there I think we had one question over
here so so continue on the same theme of
um metaverse style environments the one
really sound application area that I've
seen in in an industrial environment is
safety so safety training it's it's a
bit bit of the same problem as with
cyber security which is there's annual
training and there's books and there's
exams and people pass all the exams but
in an actual incident they don't behave
the way uh that they did when they
passed all the exams and trainings and
in practice the only way to in the real
world the only way you know that someone
actually has internalized information is
how they function in actual disaster the
problem is we cannot create actual
disasters to figure that out so in a in
a metaverse environment you can sort of
say okay there's you hear a fire alarm
go off are you following the prescribed
routes now a staircase collapses do what
the fall back plan is in real time you
don't have the time to think and reflect
you know your fire blocks your Escape
Route do you know what your alternate
course of action is so these things are
absolutely infeasible to create in the
real world you know short of blowing up
a plant to do it so it it is it is
obviously it's a fringe application but
in that Fringe space it has tremendous
value the in the environment I looked at
which was very very
dangerous the problem is it's very
dangerous and kind of like the I worked
on the BP Monda incident the problem is
they happen once in 50 years uh so no
one has actual real world experience of
it
nobody and but but when it happens that
instant decision making in real time is
critical so that's but I think Carrie
talked about that you know it's uh you
know there's there's a lot of tools to
do it whether you're talking about trust
or transparency Etc you have to walk the
walk every day you're when your people
ask you hard questions you got to give
them the hard answers and and build that
level of trust and then there's
tabletops exercises there scenarios
those things I think apply we're not
arguing or stating that there's not an
application what we're what
we're trying at least I'll speak for Rob
Scott not for anyone else what I'm
trying to say is those applications to
deliver large value either internally or
externally are difficult to find with
the
metaverse and and and the hype around it
uh has put it in in where people are
skeptical and they're now there's other
things that could help us deliver uh
safer more
efficiently uh with less carbon Etc than
than those that's what we're what I'm
trying to say and that's where we're
investing is around circularity
sustainability uh that's where we're
putting Investments today and I I would
just add one thing I think again back to
this question about um uh the cost as we
see Quantum Computing coming in we may
be revisiting the metaverse it might
really bring down the cost of computing
which might really bring down the cost
of simulations like metaverse so maybe
we'll start to see when the costs come
down and the technology advances a
Resurgence of this question but right
now it's just not costeffective from
what I'm hearing for for the major plays
in the organizations
back to you yeah well so I think we'll
do a very fast last question and then
I'm going to go back to the audience for
something else
um Rob let's start with you so we're
back together in five years sitting uh I
think maybe I'd like lower comfortable
chairs and yes this does feel a little
bit like I'm outside the principal's
office in grade school not that I was
ever there just saying okay and uh so I
I I think I heard loud and clear that
you don't think we're going to be
talking about the metaverse um what do
you hope to be talking
about I touched on it earlier the the
use of scalable technology with our
craft in order to make it uh safer and
more efficient uh on the work sites
because those places are extremely
dangerous um and as people get tired and
they're exposed to those stresses you
can start to make suboptimal decisions
that ultimately will result in a loss of
life life changing accidents or uh
catastrophic events around the plant so
to me what I'd like to be back in five
years is we've cracked the code on what
the wearable technology is how we
leverage cameras and drones in order to
be more efficient and safer for the
craft because if we can do that then
we'll be more more sustainable more
affordable to me it just starts with the
folks doing the work super all right and
maybe I'll play off the question earlier
from the gentleman so maybe I My Hope Is
this I hope that gen has played out to
be everything it's it's cooked up to be
and isn't another metaverse uh I think
this happens in in I think there's
Fringe or I think there's use cases
where it will work for sort of in
documents and things like this it it's
probably going to play out well if you
fast forward that and may maybe five
years is May five years is about right
actually for us to adopt these things if
you've got thousands of Agents let's
just call it running your business today
at least in terms of filling forms out
and doing documents how do you manage
this I mean we aren't prepared to manage
it what are all these people today who
are actually really skilled Engineers
that used to design jobs now what are
they doing I you know I hope we're here
in five years say seeing that have
worked and asking those questions on how
do we manage this stuff at scale and and
what are these people that we had in
place doing and now what are they doing
yeah super how we transitioned that's
the other yeah yeah I'm assuming you've
transition yeah how do we pull how we
did it and lessons learned that we're
sharing amongst each other and the way
that we share
safy I think is going to be critical for
the work
yeah okay so what do I think we're going
to talk about in five years I hope we're
not talking about cyber security I hope
we've cracked that nut I hope it's all
ether for everybody's work I hope it's
as ubiquitous as safety and all the
other things that are important and
Baseline in our organization I hope we
are talking about strategic Advantage
from whatever the next technology might
be whether it's um uh Quantum or the
next uh applications of AI uh I hope
we're talking more about how we can do
things new and different uh and create
strategic and competitive advantages for
our companies with whatever the next
thing
is awesome all right Applause for the
panel
[Applause]