Even if it was cold, what I would
do is go outside at night and get
a blanket and just, you know, stay
all night just watching the stars.
There is something fascinating in
watching the sky for hours at a time.
First of all, you see the
spectacle of different stars
as the Earth is turning, right?
There's a satellite and
there's a shooting star.
And sometimes the shooting
stars have different colors.
Depending on what is the material they
have, they will glow in a different color.
And they will glow with
different intensities.
But if you're not looking for
hours, you will miss all this.
Yeah, I don't, I don't even remember
when I started, but I was very young,
so, so young that I don't remember when
I started to be interested in space.
My parents took me to a planetarium
for the first time, and actually
it was, I think back then, the only
planetarium in Mexico City at least.
And for me it was just eye opening,
because the history of the universe from
the Big Bang and then telling the things
about the lives of stars and planets.
And the fate of these stars,
depending on their size, and some
of them will blow up and some
others will turn into black holes.
So I was like, just, you know, I was,
it was just like too much for me.
Again, it was probably the again, one
of the, the most memorable- I still
remember it, and I was about 10 years old.
And I think it was mostly because of, you
know, kind of getting to know the unknown.
And there were so many fascinating
things out there that we didn't
understand as humanity And I was so
interested about each one of them.
And then the prospect of actually
going to space and exploring.
For me that was just, uh, too much.
It was fascinating.
I just wanted to contribute to space
exploration, uh, and understand the
physics behind the, you know, the
working principles of the universe.
And the more tools I could
get to help me understand this
and contribute it, the better.
You know, where is the
action happening, right?
And of course I knew about NASA and all
the other places that I would hear in
Carl Sagan's Cosmos series, for example.
MIT's name will come up, right,
eventually, in one way or another.
Because, you know, you can find
pretty much an expert on every
branch of interesting science
and interesting technology.
And, and just the fact that you can,
you know, walk around the infinite
corridor and suddenly you see the
person who wrote the textbook or
the person who won the Nobel Prize.
I, I mean, that, that,
that is also inspiring.
I never imagined that I could be
a professor in a place like MIT.
And the fact that that happened,
that was very inspiring for me.
It's a community that
is very open to ideas.
And find weak points on hypotheses
and discover new things and, you
know, all these kind of things.
And now since I'm a faculty, I
would say that what makes MIT very,
very truly special is the students.
We have the best students.
I mean, they are way
smarter than the faculty.
I mean, we probably as faculty don't
want to admit that, but the students are
like here and we're like that, right?
And it's amazing to work with them.
You know, every time you're riding your
bike or driving to campus or taking the
bus, you're looking forward to actually
chat with your students because you're
always going to learn something from them.
And I think that that's one of the key
things that make, in my view, MIT special.