good morning
everyone and welcome to the 27th
annual MIT Japan
conference May Steven
[Music]
P so the rest will all be in English
unless we're going to get some beer
later on and then then I can help you
out so 150 years ago um icho honma mit's
first Japanese student
graduated from the class of
1874 Japan and in particular their
Japanese industry has
been interested in education and
Technology from MIT for a long
time now I'll bring us forward 140 years
so 10 years ago I joined MIT I left the
Aerospace industry and wanted something
flat and
Innovative and I was lucky enough to
start working with Japanese
companies
primarily and one thing I noticed was
that they were very focused
on
technology the
aperture for their
interests were somewhat extremely natur
narrow they were here on a scale of a
closed aperture to sort of more of a
wider one the core Market was what drove
their connection to
MIT now if we come along about five
years I started noticing the trend
changing
slightly everybody was aave about
startups but again the aperture was over
opening but somewhat still closed in the
sense that they were interested in the
technology that the startups were
creating two years ago I started
noticing yet another
Trend the Japanese industry was not only
interested in
technology startups but the ecosystem
itself a good progression though the
aperture was open
moving more to a transformational
market what I'll say the trend is going
to now is that they're interested more
along the
lines of how ecosystems are created the
processes the
procedures and you're starting to create
your
own the aperture is almost fully open
what I contend though is what's next for
Japan if you have a ecosystem in a
vacuum it's a great start but what my
hope for the Japanese industry and
thereby your nation and our partnership
is that we create a symbiotic Innovation
ecosystem now my talk is going to be the
non-technical talk of today
because what I
hope to draw from is from business and
hum's insight it's really the
relationships that you will be building
between these amazing professors these
amazing smaller companies that we
brought with us today and
yourselves so two professors are from
MIT that I'll draw from one is Tara
Schwarz she's a
neuroscientist and one is Kieran Setia
who is a philosopher in the humanties
department and then I'm going to draw
from the third who is a professor of
management at Kyoto
University so Tara draws her research in
Neuroscience to a conclusion that we
have to take care of our mind and body
our
brains we have to be open and have a
mindset that
is engaging and curious
then she assures us that even at old age
our neurons our neuroplasticity we can
change the way we think and I argue that
today is one of those
examples in trying to erase cognitive
biases now
Kieran has some of the same thoughts
which is pretty amazing because he's
really a basic philosopher at heart
but he talks about the
process over
goals and also having that open
mindset
in looking for
meaning over
achievement if we go back to the first
slide where I said a lot of the Japanese
companies I engaged with were focused
solely on the
technology as opposed to the inovation
Journey the process of learning from
these new professors or startup
companies now Professor
yuchi I find fascinating because his
research focuses
on the sushi
chef he's an ethnog an ethnographer at
heart and what he's done is assessed why
the stern somewhat angry looking sushi
chef still gets so many customers to
come and the magic behind this is he has
something called reflective
routines and actions shaping our
context so these actions that are deeply
embedded in the way we engage with each
other and I contend again that if you
use this methodology to engage with the
professors in the startup
the results will be this do we all know
who this
is so noou masah is one of the most
famous Sushi chefs or I would say at
least successful maybe you have your own
preference but he is somebody that has
engaged with the
client and the more open the client is
to new experiences
the better the
sushi the better the experience for both
parties the chef is allowed then to
experiment and do things that he or she
never dreamed dreamt of and the client
is then getting a world-class
experience so I think the result is
successful Innovations for you in the
future the MIT professors that we will
work with in the startup
companies I really believe there's a lot
of Promise
here and it all comes down to your
willingness to be creative have an open
mind and
allow that otaki that connection with
the sushi chef to give you new ideas
although they may not align
perfectly with what your technology road
map
has hopefully that would be a nice start
to
opening the aperture today on how to
engage with this amazing group and I
would lastly
say part of the networking is also
allowing you the opportunity to connect
with peers or competitors or forming new
Partnerships thank you very much