the MIT energy initiative presents
making hydrogen power a
reality hydrogen fuel has long been seen
as a potentially key component of a
carbon neutral Energy Future at the 2022
MIT energy initiative Spring Symposium
four industry experts laid out their
efforts to produce it at scale written
by Calvin
hanik for decades government and
Industry have looked at hydrogen as a
potentially game-changing tool pool in
the Quest for clean
energy as far back as the early days of
the Clinton Administration energy sector
observers and public policy experts have
extoled the virtues of hydrogen to the
point that some people have joked that
hydrogen is the energy of the future and
always will be even as wind and solar
power have become commonplace in recent
years hydrogen has been held back by
high costs and other challenges but the
fuel May finally be poised to have its
moment at the MIT energy initiative
spring symposium entitled hydrogen's
role in a decarbonized Energy System
experts discussed hydrogen production
Roots hydrogen consumption markets the
path to a robust hydrogen infrastructure
and policy changes needed to achieve a
hydrogen future during one panel options
for producing low carbon hydrogen at
scale four experts laid out existing and
planned efforts to leverage hydrogen for
decarbonization the race is
on H and and
a senior scientist and group manager at
the national renewable energy laboratory
enil is the director of hydren a
Consortium of several US Department of
energy doe National Laboratories that
accelerates research and development of
innovative and advanced water splitting
materials and Technologies for clean
sustainable and lowcost hydrogen
production for the past 14 years D has
worked on fuel cells and hydrogen
production for enr we think that the 20s
is a decade of hydrogen she said Den
believes that the energy carrier is
poised to come into its own over the
next few years pointing to several
domestic and international activities
surrounding the fuel and citing a
hydrogen ccil report that projected the
future impacts of hydrogen including 30
million jobs and $2.5 trillion in global
Revenue by 2050 now is the time for
hydrogen and the global races on she
said D also explained the parameters of
the hydrogen shot the first the Doe's
energy Earth shots aimed at accelerating
breakthroughs for affordable and
reliable Clean Energy Solutions hydrogen
fuel currently costs around $5 per
kilogram to produce and the hydrogen
shot stated goal is to bring that down
by 80% to $1 per kilogram within a
decade the hydrogen shot will be
facilitated by $9.5 billion in funding
for at least four clean hydrogen hubs
located in different parts of the United
States as well as extensive research and
development manufacturing and recycling
from last year's bipartisan
infrastructure law still D noted that it
took more than 40 years for solar and
wind power to become cost competitive
and now industry government National Lab
and academic leaders are hoping to
achieve similar reductions in hydrogen
fuel costs over a much shorter time
frame in the near term she said
stakeholders will need to improve the
efficiency durability and affordability
of hydrogen production through
electrolysis using electricity split
water using today's renewable and
nuclear power sources over the long term
the focus May shift to splitting water
more directly through heat or solar
energy she said the time frame is short
the competition is intense and a
coordinated effort is critical for
domestic competitiveness Den
said hydrogen across
continents wambui maturu principal
engineer for international commercial
development exploration and production
International of the Norwegian Global
Energy company equinor said that
hydrogen is an important component in
the company's Ambitions to be carbon
neutral by 2050 the company in
collaboration with Partners has several
hydrogen projects in the works and
maturu laid out the company's hydrogen
to Humber H2 project in northern England
currently the Humber region emits more
carbon dioxide than any other industrial
cluster in the United Kingdom 50% more
in fact than the next largest carbon
emitter the ambition here is for us to
deploy the world's first at scale
hydrogen value chain to decarbonize the
Humber industrial cluster maturu said
the project consists of three components
a clean hydrogen production facility an
onshore hydrogen and carbon dioxide
transmission Network an offshore carbon
dioxide transportation and storage
operations maturu highlighted the
importance of carbon capture and storage
ccs and hydrogen production equinor she
said has captured and sequestered carbon
offshore for more than 25 years
storing more than 25 million tons of
carbon dioxide during that time maturu
also touched on EC equinor's efforts to
build a decarbonized energy Hub in the
Appalachian region of the US covering
territory in Ohio West Virginia and
Pennsylvania by 2040 she said the
company ambition is to produce about 1.5
million tons of clean hydrogen per year
in the region roughly equivalent to 6.8
gaw of electricity while also storing 30
million tons of carbon dioxide maturu
acknowledg that the biggest challenge
facing potential hydrogen producers is
the current lack of viable business
models resolving that challenge requires
cross industry collaboration and
supportive policy Frameworks so that the
market for hydrogen can be built and
sustained over the long term she
said confronting
barriers Gretchen bear executive
external strategy and Communications
leader for da noted that the company
already produces hydrogen in multiple
ways for one dowo operates the world's
largest ethane cracker in Texas an
ethane cracker Heats ethane to break
apart molecular bonds to form ethylene
with hydrogen one of the byproducts of
the process also bear showed a slide of
the 1891 patent for the electrolysis of
brine water which also produces hydrogen
the compan still engages in this
practice but Dow does not have an
effective way of utilizing the resulting
hydrogen for their own fuel just take a
moment to think about that bear said
we've been talking about hydrogen
production and the cost of it and this
is basically free hydrogen and it's
still too much of a barrier to somewhat
recycle that and use it for ourselves
the environment is clearly changing and
we do have plans for that but I think
that kind of sets some of the challenges
that face industry here however bear
said hydrogen is expected to play a
significant role in Dow's future as the
company attempts to decarbonize by
2050 the company she said plans optimize
hydrogen allocation and production
retrofit turbines for hydrogen fueling
and purchase clean hydrogen by 240 Dao
expects more than 60% of its sites to be
hydrogen ready bar noted that hydrogen
fuel is not a Panacea but rather one
among many potential contributors as
industry attempts to reduce or eliminate
carbon emissions in the coming decades
hydrogen has an important role but it's
not the only answer she
said this is real
Colleen Wright is Vice President of
corporate strategy for constellation
which recently separated from Exelon
Corporation Exelon now owns the former
company's regulated utilities such as
Commonwealth Edison and Baltimore Gas
and Electric while constellation owns
the competitive generation and Supply
portions of the business wrri stressed
the advantages of nuclear power in
hydrogen production what she said
include Superior economics low barriers
implementation and scalability a quarter
of emissions in the world are currently
from hard to decarbonized sectors the
industrial sector steel making heavyduty
Transportation Aviation she said these
are really challenging decarbonization
sectors and as we continue to expand and
Electrify we're going to need more
Supply we're also going to need to
produce clean hydrogen using emissions
free Power the scale of nuclear power
plants is uniquely suited to be able to
scale hydrogen production rate added she
mentioned constellation 9M Point site in
New York state which received a doe
grant for a pilot program that will see
a proton exchange membrane PM
electrolyzer installed at the site we're
very excited to see hydrogen go from a
research and development conversation to
a commercial conversation she said we've
been calling it a little bit of a middle
school dance everybody is standing
around the circle waiting to see who is
willing to put something at stake but
this is real we're not dancing around
the edges there are a lot of people who
are big players who are willing to put
skin in the game today