okay so good
afternoon and uh
uh we
are hopefully we'll uh
finish the topic on uh liquid VAP or
equilibria
today now
uh we we have seen that everything is uh
contained in mechanical
potentials and uh so this U summarizes
for example for a pure substance when
you have the two phases in mutual
equilibrium like liquid and
Vapor the equality of chemical
potentials uh for the pure liquid and
the pure uh
Vapor gives a relation between pressure
and temperature which we call
Pat or the inverse function is tat
that's what you find in for example the
steam tables for water or every other
substance has
this uh establishes the PO the boiling
point at a given
pressure so the equivalent for a binary
mixture is that now we have if if both
substances are volatile and
condensible then you have two uh
chemical
equilibrium uh chemical potential
equalities that are required for Mutual
stable equilibrium between the two
phases of course uh the chemical
potential be is now not only a function
of temperature and pressure but also of
composition but because this the mole
fractions add up to one uh you just need
one uh in independent mole fraction to
represent the
composition but you need one mole
fraction for the uh liquid phase and
another mole fraction for the vapor
phase because they are not necessarily
equal so these two
equalities in the uh four variables TP
y1f and
y1g can be solved to
give uh this relation so you only have a
variance of two GES a phase rule
variance of two meaning that for example
if you fix temperature and
pressure that automatically fixes a
unique composition for the liquid and a
unique composition for the uh Vapor that
are not equal and the Raul's law that we
have
developed establishes the relation
between the composition of the in vapor
and the composition of the
liquid
uh you can also rewrite solve these
equations for other inde independent
variables for example you keep T and the
mole fraction of the liquid and you get
a from these relations a function which
we called the B the bubble
line or if you instead like to keep the
temperature and the composition of the
vapor you get the DU
line which can be expressed as pressure
is a function of temperature but also
temperature is a function of
pressure okay so these are all
equivalent
forms and here is a sort of a thre
dimensional representation of how these
uh things look of course in the limit of
the pure substances you get the usual PT
diagram for that
substance this is for one this is for
two but uh halfway when the mole
fractions go from between zero and one
then you get uh uh these
relations uh as we have seen gives rise
to gaps so to Regions that are forbidden
that cannot be uh
obtained uh in in which the substance
doesn't behave in doesn't exist in
stable equilibrium it likes to
separate so today uh to finish up we
need to see a little more about about
this so the first uh result that we can
uh talk about is called enry
law which is a byproduct of R's law so
remember R slow was a relation here this
one uh that gives us as we just said the
Rel the composition of the vapor phase
in equilibrium
is a function of the uh composition of
the liquid phase with which it is in
mutual
equilibrium and the saturation pressure
of the pure substance enters in the RS
equation we derive this by equating the
chemical potentials of substance
one and
U of course if you have if your mixture
is
ideal uh at all
compositions and both substances are um
volatile and condensible you have also a
r slow for the second second substance
and so you have the same expression like
here only with the subscript two instead
of
one
however very few
mixtures uh in the liquid phase are
really uh ideal
at all
compositions but we
know that in a dilute limit so for a
dilute
solution uh we argued that every liquid
solution is always uh in that limit
behaving as
ideal so that means let consider
component one as the solvent for
which uh this equation is
valid in the limit
of uh y1f that means uh the liquid
composition is very close to the pure
substance so that's a dilute solution
limit substance two does not behave a
slope but we will see that now next
lines are going we're going to need to
prove this relation here which looks uh
which is enry law which looks
similar to R's law except that instead
of the saturation pressure of the
substance of the second
substance you
have uh another function of not just
temperature but temperature and pressure
which is called enris volatility
constant and it's going to be given by
this relation here so how do we how do
we obtain this and this is
[Music]
valid
um for any uh mixture in the dilute
solution limit there is a there is a a
constant like that it's called Enis
constant but it's really a something
that is independent of composition and
it's a function but it is a function of
temperature and pressure so it's
constant once you f F temperature and
pressure so where does it come about
come it comes about from the Gibs doem
relations because they can they must
always hold remember GBS do relations
are the ones that we use also to derive
the GI phace
Rule and the clus claperon
relations for the pure
substances uh for a binary mixture
uh the usual summation becomes just two
uh contributions here so this is uh
minus sdt plus
VDP plus the summation minus the
summation of the mole fractions times
the D of the chemical
potentials now suppose we fixed
temperature and pressure so we set DT
and DP equals z then you see this gives
a relation between how uh the chemical
potential of uh the second substance so
of the solute in the dilute solution uh
changes as uh you have changes in the
chemical potential of the solvent so
they are not
independent so if since this
solvent uh behaves like like this it's
ideal so it obeys this uh ideal relation
for chemical potential if you do the
differential of that uh at constant T
and
P you are left with just the the
differential of log of Y which is the Y
over y okay so that's the mu1 in the
liquid phase so you can substitute in
this relation
here so see this relation it can be
Rewritten this
way and then here for this one you
substitute what we obtain from the ideal
solution and here is what you get you
get a similar
relation so you get that also chemical
potential of the second substance in the
liquid uh solution behaves
logarithmically with the
composition so that means that
if it is
logarithm see this for the ideal
solution this is a logarithmic
dependence and here you have the pure
substance so the the constant here is a
pure substance whereas for a oops okay
whereas for for this other case if you
integrate this
relation uh you get something similar to
the one up there but uh with a different
integration constant that is not NE
necessarily equal to the pure component
chemical
potential it is equal to the pure
component chemical potential in the
limit of Ideal solution all at all
compositions so but in general this is
some other function of temperature and
pressure which nevertheless can be
measured and uh and therefore you uh if
you use this relation to obtain like we
did for a obtaining R's law you obtain
enry
law and here is the explicit expression
that derives for theis constant in terms
of the saturation pressure of the second
substance there is this correction
factor and this correction factor can be
very uh large for
example
um one one important example in in some
practices is is the one for nitrogen so
the AR is
constant as a value which is
85,000 atmospheres so very high
pressure uh from the point of view of of
graphic point of view um okay suppose
this one is mole fraction of the solvent
say that we are talking about uh water
okay so this is the dilute limit is is
is in this area
so Mo fraction of water is very close to
one and so what is missing to get to one
is the mole fraction of the
solute and supposed solute is
nitrogen uh okay uh the
N slope me if you had ideal ideal um
Behavior
H this line represents the the partial
pressure so it's the product of uh mole
fraction and
pressure and it's a straight line
because that's a linear relation that
takes you to the um saturation pressure
of uh
nitrogen okay uh since this Conant is
very high the en constant is very high
the actual slope here is much
steeper okay and that is sort of the
tangent of this uh IDE non- ideal
Behavior U
um Bubble uh bubble
line now it why nitrogen is
important for example for uh
divers you know that there is this um
problem of the compression and if you if
you dive and you stay for a long time uh
at high
pressures
nitrogen uh uh you see here if if I
increase uh the the
pressure the the mole fraction uh that
of nitrogen that can stay in uh in the
liquid so let's say the let's call it
the solubility of nitrogen in the
blood uh gets
higher so the longer you stay the more
nitrogen goes into your
blood and then uh and this happens in
the lungs now if you uh come up to C
Surface too quickly and you don't let uh
uh the necessary time to adjust back uh
through the
lungs uh this nitrogen will um evaporate
from your bloodstream and form bubbles
all over and these
bubbles uh typically collect in
joints and gives you a lot of pain
especially when you move the joints and
that's why the disease is called also
the bends when you bend you you suffer
uh but of course the enris Conant has
also some other applications that also
have to do with uh atmospheric and ocean
science and uh so this is
um for example it determines
the the
the
uh composition of clouds Cloud droplets
and also it is important in how for
example pollutant some pollutants are
absorbed in Waste Water Management uh
plans treatment
plans okay so this was an example of
application of the Gibbs DM
relation which has some practical
applications um okay before we go on I
have
to stress again something that we have
already discussed so I'm not going to go
into too many details here but I I leave
it this slides for
reference
because when we like we're going to do
next we deal with models of uh
mixtures to describe U these nonideal
behaviors
um we are going to have to be uh
concerned with the stability or the
solubility limits uh uh the stability
conditions for these mixtures because
sometimes uh for example liquids you
know oil and water don't mix at least
not at all
compositions uh so that is an effect of
the the fact that at certain
compositions a a a
homogeneous mixture of oil and water is
unstable at most
compositions all right well so our
models will will give uh expressions for
the uh GBS free energy and you can
express the G free energy as
the total value or the specific value
and of course if we we are we are
talking
about large systems with large numbers
of particles so we uh the we can apply
the oiler relation and this is uh the
fact that the GS specific GS free energy
is essentially you can write it as the
weighted sum of the chemical Potentials
in weighted by the mole fractions of the
components
uh but we have remember that see you
might be tempted to say that the the
chemical therefore the chemical
potential is the derivative of little G
with respect to
Y but it is not that's why you have to
be careful the chemical potential when
you want to write it in terms of the G
fre energy is the partial of the G three
energy capital G with respect to
n at constant TP and all the other ends
okay and if you do all the correc
steps here it is here is the expression
in terms of the uh specific Gibs free
energy there are lots of contributions
it's not just the partial of G with
respect to
Y there are other
stuff for example
if you assume uh if you apply this to
the GI free energy of the ideal
solution which we discussed last time
also which is given so by only by this
term plus the mixing mixing entropy type
term and you do this derivative
here you so you see that this this
derivative of of the um lowercase G with
respect to the mole fraction is equal to
the pure component plus something like
that so there is an RT term uh uh too
many which makes it different from the
uh
ideal chemical
potential but if you put this expression
into here then you get the
proper expression for the clinical
potential for a binary
mixture which is something that so these
are relations that we will need uh in a
few moment
moments the for a binary
mixture uh the specific EX3 energ is
function of only one mole fraction of
course because the other is is one minus
one my 1us
y1 the chemical potential if you use
this
expression can be written this way
and for the second component can be
written this
way in terms of the derivative of little
G with respect to
Y and uh
so why where where do we need these two
expressions we need them when we want to
apply the conditions for Mutual
equilibrium between two
phases because if we have the two phases
in equilibrium component one must have
the same chemical potential in both
phases and component two also so this
gives give two relations and these two
relations can be
written from these two relations you can
obtain this by substituting the
expression about these two expressions
here so it tells you that uh uh the
partial of G with respect to
Y must be equal for the two phases even
if this derivative doesn't represent the
chemical potential but only a part of it
still it has to be equal for the two
phases and plus it represents a slope
that of a geometrical construction that
uh uh looks like this so if I have if I
plot uh
G with respect to uh mole fraction why
sometimes we will see you get
uh Expressions I mean plots like
this and we will see that uh the
condition for Mutual equilibrium the
first one this
one says that if there are going to be
if if you find a line which is tangent
both here and there
okay
almost okay so this slope is
DG uh d
y also there but here is evaluated at y
Prime
first uh phase one and here it is
evaluated at y double
Prime so that uh so finding this tangent
line identifies those two mole
fractions that are in neutal
equilibrium and also see this is G Prime
and that's g double
Prime and as you see the equation of
this
line is precisely
this equation
here okay so that
construction helps us identify for a
given uh temperature because here we
have fixed a given temperature and
pressure it helps uh identify these two
points
so
again that means suppose I fix now the
pressure and I take that
temperature so at this temperature
T I'm going to
plot these two points that I have found
y Prime and Y double
prime those this represents
uh the two phases in mutal
equilibrium so this would be say y1 for
example for the for the phase
um this would be y1 F and this is y1 G
if you're talking about liquid Vapor
equilibrium now if I change the
temperature and make another plot of the
same kind I'm going to identify
by the same
way the two
other uh compositions that are
correspond to the mutual equilibrium and
so
on until I get to a temperature in which
these Point are going points are going
to coincide so I'm going to
obtain a curve like
that maybe it's a bit smoother for in
practice
uh this is called this is a critical
[Laughter]
point uh it's critical in what sense
it's critical in the sense that above
that
temperature you can see that all
compositions are possible for
equilibrium whereas below
here there is a gap so this area
here is
forbidden and it's called the visibility
Gap there are no stable situations
inside
here but as we have seen for the pure
substance we may have a metastable
situations which is
now what we want to uh analyze
so let's try to do that construction
with one of the uh models that we have
assumed the simplest the one parameter
marulas model for the binary mixture so
just parameter a so the Gibs free
energy is a sum of an ideal part and
excess part the ideal part is given
here something can be computed from the
pure substance properties something is
related to the entropy of
mixing and then here the excess part is
related to the composition and to this
constant a which you remember is is is
a essentially the uh mixing enthalpy
of the two components which in this
model are equal for the two
components okay so that's the
model
now we
apply uh the
stability
conditions because you remember that for
Mutual I mean for stable equilibrium
we've derived while ago U General
conditions for stability that are not
just yes they are the theoretical things
but which have practical consequences
consequences uh and that therefore allow
to describe uh some physical
reality okay so the second differential
of G um if I move out from a state in
which the system is in equ mutual
equilibrium with Reser at temperature T
and P and uh and I move out uh by
changing the
composition while keeping T and P
constant uh this differential must be
greater than zero so that
implies that if I uh keep also n among
the various possibilities uh I can of
changing the composition I'm taking the
simplest so I take uh uh keep constant
the total amount and just change the
relative
composition so I just change the mole
fraction of component
one and this second differential
uh gives rise well maybe here more than
an equal sign there should be an arrow
because this is not an equality it's
wrong mathematically but uh because here
should we should have also a d uh
y1
squared which being squared as
a positive sign so it doesn't that it's
always
positive so I have to correct that
and so this uh is the second derivative
and on this graph the second
derivative is the convexity no of the
curve it has to be
positive so you we see here that uh it's
positive here it's positive here it's
positive up to a certain point here but
then it becomes negative second
derivative so from from where it becomes
negative to where it comes back
positive this is the region of
instability and these two points here
are going to
Define so they're not they there are a
different uh there are a different uh um
mole
fractions than the two phases in a
mutual equilibrium so see this is a
different mole fraction and a different
mole fraction so this will identify
another
curve inside
here so the locus of all these other
points this other curve is what we will
call uh this spine noal
curve so usually one calls this one is
called
bodal and the one inside that's the SP
no
SP
okay so we have the expression for the G
free energy we can take derivatives let
me skip the steps and go to the uh
result here this is the second
derivative it's in terms of the mole
fractions RT and a the constant
a for this to be greater than
zero I see this is subtract so you need
that a should not be too too
large the maximum value of this fraction
is one is um is two no is four because
half and half and therefore a equals 2
is the maximum
allowed value so the stability condition
is satisfied is if a is less than
two the critical situation is when a is
equal to
two and if a is greater than two
uh you can
still
satisfy this
condition but only in a certain range
see this is the expression is a like um
a second order equation so you can solve
it and you find uh this range so this is
the um this is these uh this mole
fraction and that is this other mole
fraction as a function of parameter
a so this is one part of the condition
for it's a necessary condition for
stability but the other condition for is
that the the two phases are in mutual
stabil stable equilibrium and therefore
you also have the conditions that the
chemical potentials must be
equal and this two conditions
essentially are correspond to this
construction of the tangent line that we
just
described so this equation here if you
fix an a you
find uh you find the mole fractions of
the phases in mutual
equilibrium so this is easy enough that
you can implement it for example in an
Excel
file H so you see the the Gibs free
energy uh little G uh mol is given by
this relation it's the sum of the two
contributions the
ideal which is
this and the excess which is
that okay in this case for a less than
two at all
compositions the second derivative of G
is positive and we have
stability so at
this uh in general this a depends on
temperature let's say these
temperatures uh so um the two liquids
are completely
missible as you decrease the temperature
the Val the value of a changes and
eventually you reach the critical value
a equals
2 at that
moment you still are okay in terms of
stability but there at the minimum here
um you have a second order derivative
equal to
zero not a minimum at this at some point
you get a second order second Dera equal
to zero
of course this plot for these plots we
had to assume something about the
properties of the pure substances so I
assume the these values 02 for one
substance and point uh uh four for the
other if you uh Set uh uh lower
temperature so you go to a greater than
two then you get uh partial Miss
ability you get this uh
uh mbil Gap so from the spinoid
composition here to the spidal compos
composition there for the liquid and the
vapor there is the this entire uh range
of compositions in which the mixture
doesn't
uh want to
stay so if you find if you manage to
produce a mixture with this composition
at these conditions of temperature and
pressure it will separate spontaneously
in search for
stability and it will
form
um two phases so it will form a phase in
which uh uh which is rich in component
one this one and a phase in which is
lean in component one which is this and
eventually it will reach Mutual
equilibrium I mean it
will will face
separate uh to two phases that are in
mutual equilibrium at these
compositions okay these equations are
again that constructions that we'
already
done so if you uh
by some means for example one
possibility is to start from a mixture
at a temperature above
critical uh say here and then you find a
way to quench
it much like what we discussed also for
the Vander bals spinodal decomposition
so you quench to this uh Point
here uh
and uh so you uce the temperature at
this point the the
instability uh
triggers what you see uh here it
triggers that the fact that from
homogeneous the phases uh U begin to
separate because substance one uh either
wants to be close to uh a lot of
substance ones one or or a little of sub
substance on so it you get diffusion U
uh process and this is
fast because you have uh uh as we have
seen for the Vander vals case we have a
lot of free energy available to create
uh the um the surface that separates the
two phases
and then once that
happens
uh
coalesence
makes uh uses up that surface
energy and tries to to find
configurations of of lesser uh um free
energy by um
making drops or bubbles uh drops in this
case uh uh bigger and
bigger and also here if you do the
separation uh if you do this quenching
at
exactly the critical comp uh
composition then uh the mixture the
separation as you see doesn't doesn't U
um
either neither do U uh drop drops nor I
mean doesn't do yeah in the Vander vals
it's neither drops nor bubbles here it's
uh it's drops in in all cases but you
see instead of drops it's continuous uh
um continuous
regions that become gross and
grosser if you instead are
off critical on either side uh you get
drops of uh one into a
continuous um region of the
other
okay now there is also this uh region
here of meta stable States between the
spinodal and the binodal uh
curve there is a a
metastability and these metastable
states are uh interesting because
sometimes they uh can be used for
applications for
example this is uh
you U I know that
um one of you is Greek and so uh
certainly knows uh this uzo effect but
uh
these
um uh in the
Mediterranean there is these liquers
that uh have very different names so
let's see I wrote them down because I
forget like in France get Anette or ptis
and uh in Italy sambuka that one I know
uh turkey is
raki in Colombia uh there is some kind
of
guent which is um flavored with with
anet with
Anis uh Mexico also has its own and also
uh some of the
uh Egypt
and Israel have
araq uh so essentially this is
uh the the funny thing of these U
liquers is that they they are
transparent
so and when you mix it with water which
is another transparent
liquid they become they give you a Milky
kind of
opaque um thing so that's um always a
sort of a mysterious U effect if you see
it the first
time uh it turns out that this effect it
has been named Uso effect only
relatively recently maybe 20 years ago
when somebody uh some real
scientist uh visited the
Mediterranean uh but
um and it is not spinodal
decomposition it is just the
fact uh that you start you generate a
mixture okay this has to do
this is more complicated because it's
not a binary mixture it is a three
component mixture it has uh water it has
uh
alcohol which is
ethanol and it has a little amounts of
this um oily thing that you extract from
the seeds of uh the of a plant of of a
flower that is called an amet or
something like
that no I don't have the name of
that
uh I think the chemical uh the the
chemical composition of this oily thing
that gives the flavor is trans anol and
it's like C10 h12
o you find uh all these in in these um
nice articles that give U the scientific
explanation and from which I have
extracted these
pictures so the idea here is that you
have
uh uh three
substances so let me just uh see uh they
call it
dvb in that uh graph that this plays the
role of the an is uh an his
um yeah
an
is oil but I don't think they prefer to
do it with a polymer that has
polymeric oil that uh so they used d d
venil Benzene so this is
D
vile
Benzene at least in their experiment so
let's say this is a substance uh C
okay now it turns out that this
substance is
soluble in
alcohol is not soluble in
water so let's call water B
and alcohol a okay so
essentially here we
have the mole
fraction of the organic oil that uh
that's our
C and this is the mole
fraction of uh the uh ethanol which is
our a
okay this is how this the the the the
equivalent of this diagram looks at a
fixed
temperature as function of this
compositions of course the mole fraction
of water is one minus the sum of these
two hence the uh triangular uh line
here so up up here we got just pure
water uh if you plot this uh since is
very skewed if you plot it in a
logarithmic scale in the composition of
the organic
oil uh this is how it
looks it opens
up so what you typically have is
uh Uso is a is a is a 40% by volume
meaning about 35 or 34 % by weight and
here is by weight uh so this is the
alcohol
content and let's say the content of
this oily um
an organic oil uh extract from these
flowers from these seeds suppose is this
much okay what happens is when you add
water you dilute the solution and so the
the fraction of ethanol goes down from
35 say to uh you cross this line and you
get into the the metastable
region in that metastable
region you get an
immediate U
separation or formation of these minute
droplets which then
because you so you
release the excess G gives free energy
that forms those minute
droplets those droplets are the the
reason uh why then uh light does
not get through gets diffused by these
droplets so that's why the
liquid uh loses the transpar to
light it's the the reasons are these
droplets but differently from spinodal
De composition if you
had generated this kind of situation
from the unstable State H the separation
would would have been uh much more
vigorous and it would
generate have more energy so generate
bigger uh drops in the end and and
eventually the mixture will uh will
separate or maybe in any case it will
form bigger drops whereas uh in the oo
effect you generate you produce very
small uh droplets they they remain in a
sort of an Emulsion that is relatively
stable in other words it survives uh
hours and u
and in some
cases this kind of process is wanted
because uh there are applications in
which you want to generate
emulsions uh which is precisely a
mixture of of a solvent with a lot of
small droplets in it uh like when you do
vinegret that's an Emulsion and
uh many times in order to uh produce
emulsions you need uh surfactant but
this is
instead a way to
produce uh emulsions without
surfactant and chemical industry is full
of processes that go back and forth uh
with with this kind of uh of of effects
in know order to uh separate or mix and
uh uh generate uh things
also uh I think that this um this method
has also been used in order to generate
scuffles for biological applications for
example uh because if you once you have
this Emulsion you freeze
it in such a way way
that uh okay if you freeze it in such a
way that the the the bul phase remains
liquid and the uh the droplets be become
solid then you've generated small
spheres so in this this is a way in
which you produce small
feares or conversely if you uh perhaps
not these ones because they are not
connected and so if you freeze
this and
uh uh the the liquid droplets remain
liquid you you still have droplets and
you not there is no path for the liquid
to go away but if you use a situation
like this one generated by a spinodal
decomposition and you freeze then uh uh
you because there is a path in which the
say the the the dark phase becomes soft
solid and the liquid in the white phase
can drain away and then you you produced
a a a porous material which can be used
with a high surface um material that can
be used for uh enhancing or studying uh
biological but also for other uh
applications in which you need you need
a lot of surface for things to happen
like uh catalysts
uh okay all right so with this
uh I think we
can terminate the mixture stuff at least
uh uh of that kind but uh we start with
mixtures that are subject also to
chemical reactions
so this is uh the two main um situations
that we will uh
approach uh at the beginning
here it's two kinds of
systems in which we have chemical
reactions one is a closed system and the
other is a open system
so this is a model for a batch process
and this is a model for a uh steady
state flow
process or flow
reactor in the close syst situation you
have
U
Box uh the the application that I uh I
like to have in mind uh is the internal
combustion engine so you imagine that
this wall is the is the Piston of your
uh uh the cylinder of your um internal
combustion engine and uh so this wall
goes up and down and uh at the top dead
center it will be at a certain volume
okay and
suppose the Piston stops there for a
while okay so uh at that moment uh you
have a mixture inside your um combuster
chamber which is a mixture of air and
your
fuel and some water vapor sometimes
because air air is humid so there is
water vapor content also at the
beginning of the combustion
process um it has some temperature some
pressure because the Piston has
compressed that mixture of course since
we are in a stable equilibrium state it
also has chemical
potentials and if we want to compute the
energy and the entropy because they will
enter in the
uh energy and entropy
balances we know how to do it because we
we've deal we've dealt with mixtures for
a long time
now so the energy in general is simply
given well simply is given
by uh the weighted sum weighted on the
amount
s of the partial
properties and the partial properties
depend on composition and we here we can
apply all our theories about ideal
mixtures or other models and so
on and the same holds also for the other
properties like entropy which is the
other one that is needed for the entropy
bance Okay now what's new here is that
uh next
you sort of turn on chemical
reactions so the composition is allowed
to change according to one or more uh
chemical reaction
mechanisms we will describe them um I'll
go into detail of the of this
description in the next slide but we
will describe it by this General
notation
and what will happen is that um the
process the the the fact that you turn
on the possibility of the chemical
reaction makes the the the the state
evolve towards uh
equilibrium and the composition will
change so in the end you will have a
composition that is different from the
beginning so here you have the reactants
so R stands for reactants here not for
Reservoir and uh P stands for products
see these are the products of combustion
for example in which case you have a uh
a
air which you've consumed some of the
oxygen
um and then you have a carbon dioxide
water
vapor and maybe some and nitrogen
oxide
okay they will be because the reaction
occurs
irreversibly uh spontaneously there will
be some entropy produced by
reversibility you can compute once you
have or at at least in terms of the
final composition and the final
temperature and
pressure um you can compute the energy
and the entropy the same way
only of course relative to the new
composition maybe the F not all the
final things are
known uh if you can uh use up only the
energy and the entropy balance and
perhaps also the volume balance if if
you assume that this volume remains
constant or relatively constant because
that reaction at the top dead center uh
occurs very quick quickly and so the
Piston doesn't move a lot uh then you
have three equations energy entropy and
volume balance with which you can solve
for three
unknowns so the various possible
problems that can be solved are
variations of this this
thing and of
course even though that is uh happens
quickly maybe there is some U exchange
of uh heat
between your
mixture uh and the walls of the
container like the cylinder because the
internal combustion engines are cooled
water cooled or air cooled and so uh
some of the energy can be exchanged with
heat to the wall
temperature and also the if the Piston
is moving while this is happening there
may also be some
work due to the pressure times the
volume uh
change okay so that's the setup of the
close system so internal combustion
engine here instead is
a steady state burner or reactor again
if I have in mind a combustion of the
hydrocarbons this is a State burner
which is typically uh inside a power uh
combustion fossil fuel power
plant here the idea is that you have a
flow bulk flow one if it's all the
substances are premixed or maybe you
have several if you have some of the um
substances that are inject for example
air in you have a injection of air
through one stream Al so one blf flow
interaction and then uh your fuel
injected in from another pipe that goes
in so I indicate here a simple single
Arrow but uh and but of course you you
may have many the properties of for bulk
flow
interactions what what enters in the
energy balance as you remember is the
enthalpy
and so we need the enthalpy the rate of
enthalpy uh brought in uh by this uh
Inlet uh bulk flow interaction which has
to do with the partial
enthalpies of the components in the
mixtures for those that are mixed and
that would be the specific if they are
injected as pure components
and the same for the
outlet so the outlet here would be the
hot product for example the hot products
of
combustion uh but in other
configurations they could
be uh if this reactor contains not only
um just is not a diabatic but it
contains also the machinery and the
thermal cycle that extracts the energy
and so on these would be just the
products that gets that get exhausted at
the chiminy or the stack of your power
plant all
right and so then u in that case we may
have heat interactions and work
interactions while while this uh complex
uh uh
[Music]
power plant is evolving there is of
course entropy produced by
irreversibility and again the new aspect
of that we need to deal with is the fact
that inside here chemical reaction or
chemical reactions can occur changing
the composition from the inlet to the
outlet the energy balance equation for a
steady state says that the rate of
change of the energy is zero because
it's steady
state and therefore uh that must be so
the the rate at which the energies are
exchanged in and out must balance to
zero so the
enthalpy uh of the
inflow is a positive inaly of the
outflower and the uh heat uh flow
positive if if if it has the arrow
inside it means positive if
received minus the work which is as the
arrow outward and so it's positive if it
is
produced and similarly for the uh
entropy
balance the entropy the rate of change
of the entropy of the reactor because we
are making a balance equation for this
reactor here
uh if it is steady state the properties
don't change so the rate of entropy
change is
zero and uh so then you have a balance
between the net amount of entropy that
uh comes
uh in and out and the entropy that is
produced by
reversibility okay
now if you look at these ones if you
look at these equations uh and compare
them you are often tempted
to for example rewrite these ones with
HP and minus HR on the left hand
side which is
okay just a legitimate mathematical
step however
you should be shouldn't be confused
because otherwise say well why do I use
enthalpy here why do I use energy there
okay you're not using enthalpy here the
same way it doesn't play the role of the
energy the rate of energy change is this
zero here that zero is important so if
you if you do that mathematical step you
sort of kill a zero that is important
and giv you remind reminder that you're
talking about steady state uh
process
okay how about
notation so let's take an
example of the reaction in which you you
have two
hydrogen
molecules this and that and an oxygen
molecule and they get uh
reassembled by this mechanism into two
molecules of
water
okay
so I use the equal sign
here to say that this refers simply to
the mechanism it doesn't say which
direction uh it will
go it simply defines the
mechanism and therefore you can go in
One Direction but also the
opposite
okay and there is therefore some
arbitrary uh choice you could put on the
left hand side hydrogen and oxygen or
you could put on the left hand side the
water
the symbol for water it's either one is
okay you can also once you have written
that written it this way you can also
put them all on the left hand
side
and with the stochiometric coefficients
positive for what you will consider the
products of the reaction and negative
for those for those that you will
consider consider the
uh the the
reactant okay now the meaning of the
stochiometric
coefficients are that they
determine the possible changes in
composition so if I start with a
composition which is given by these
numbers any anything
and then I want to see uh how the
composition that composition can change
according to this reaction mechanism and
only this
one then you can write these changes are
not uh completely uh
arbitrary because you have to have the
fact that the the ratio of the change of
one component to the to the
respective stochiometric coefficient
must be equal to the same ratio for all
the other components so this ratio we're
going to call the reaction coordinate or
change in reaction coordinates that
defines the reaction coordinates the the
change over the stochiometric
coefficient notice that this
stochiometric coefficient must be
taken with the sign the proper sign so
negative for the reactant and positive
for the uh
products okay so with that in
mind
then in order to introduce a notation
that also uh that is typically used
in software that deals with
calculations uh of chemical equilibrium
or chemical kinetics
uh we can
Define a symbol a sub I a sub 1 a sub 2
a
sub3 uh to represent the the chemical
symbols in the list so for
example
um we make we make a
table one two three we decided to call
uh the first component to make it H2 the
second component is oxygen and the third
is
water okay so the stochiometric
coefficient we use the symbol nuai for
the stochiometric
coefficient is
min-2 for hydrogen minus one for oxygen
and two for water
and
then you you see that this equation here
that presents the chemical reaction
mechanism translates into this summation
which we we can write in the summation
way the advantage of
that is that so I have um
this for my first reaction but suppose I
have because in general uh life is not
simple and uh very few things can be
described with just a single chemical
reaction for example even for that uh
formation I mean water just for the
combustion of
hydrogen uh
I think that
the the mechanism you have to consider
at least uh forget now probably eight
mechanisms and uh for the combustion of
methane it's probably 250 or
more that play a role uh and determine
the
kinetics different thing is for
equilibrium but for the kinetics you
need many
mechanisms Okay so for example suppose
we have also
another
important equation
for
for combustion which is the dissociation
of CO2 in Co and
oxygen uh if together with my uh initial
reaction which is 2
h2+ O2 =
H2O which we already represented in our
list if we also have that one we can
keep going in the in
our um list of of uh chemical species
that are relevant to our
problem we add CO2 and
Co of course they don't play a role in
the first reaction so we'll have
psychometric coefficients for reaction
One let's say this is reaction one so
I'm putting a superscript one for the
first
reaction and
then I put here the chemical
uh sociometric coefficients for the
second reaction so for the second
reaction I have plus one since it's a
product for Co So Co is one
oxygen 1 12
so5 positive and CO2 it's it's on the
left hand side so it's negative it's
minus
one of course the
others are
zero because in reaction one there is no
play by CO2 and Co and in reaction two
there's no play by water and
hydrogen and so you see I have just put
a j there and I have a system of as many
chemical reactions as we
want now the proportionality
relations namely these relations here
that uh represent the role of chemical
um I mean sociometric coefficients in
order to uh represent what compositions
are changes in composition are possible
are written this way or
also in generic terms like Delta n over
new subi equals Delta Epsilon which
which we
can
write uh more uh explicitly for example
if we like in the previous uh uh
examples with like in the batch process
the composition goes to uh from the that
of the reactants to that of uh the uh
products so the change Delta n is equal
to
uh final minus initial so this is NP
minus
NR is equal to U new sub Epsilon new new
sorry new sub times
Epsilon and this Epsilon here could
be
uh it's actually it's it's a Delta it's
the difference between the value of the
reaction coordinate that describes the
products and the value of the reaction
coordinate that describes the reactant
composition if we have instead this
steady state
[Music]
uh um flow
uh continuous
reaction then we talk about the rate of
change of uh the composition so we take
we Define we divide this by DT so Delta
n by delta T is the stric coefficient
times Delta EP delta T let's call it
Epsilon
Dot and so you you find that the rate
that which the the difference between
the rate at which the products and the
reactants come out and in is related to
this rate of change of the reaction
coordinate which uh somehow is related
to the uh reaction rate or
rates in
fact do I have it in the next slide no
uh so in
fact so we have n
dot
i
p is equal to n do I
plus uh okay so if you have only one
reaction is uh the summation of uh
Epsilon Dot
times new I but if I have several
reactions then each one has its own uh
reaction coordinate and I have to sum
up the
contribution uh to the change of the
various reactions in
play
okay so now let's let's go back sorry
let's go back here to the
structure of the balance
equations in the balance
equations you have we have to deal with
differen between the energy between
products and reactants the entropy
between products and reactants also here
the enthalpy between reactants and
products the entropy these differences
yes it is true that uh we can um write
them we know how to write them except
that we have to learn a proper way to
deal with the fact that uh the
composition is changing here so some
molecules are disappearing and some are
appearing uh that have different
properties and therefore we have to be
careful in how we take uh
reference
value for these
properties and this is done
here for example U of those differences
let's take uh one which is the
energy so we write the
energy difference between products and
reactants as uh as we said okay so this
is just the implementation of what we
said
in terms of partial
properties
now we let's add and
subtract something which will not change
therefore the result and which we select
to added
subtract for each um
constituent the specific property of
pure component of that constituent at
some reference and here let's say at
some reference temperature and
pressure I'm going to call the pressure
p not because typically it's taken the
standard pressure is the one
atmosphere whereas here for temperature
let's use the generic temperature for
the moment if it will
be the the standard temperature to to
298.15 that we we will denote it by T
not
but for the moment this can be done at
any temperature and this temperature is
not necessarily equal to either TR or
TP okay so we add and subtract so here
is here it is so we uh we subtract from
from this summation we subtract from
that
summation but then we realize that since
we put it in this summation here it is
um multiplied by
NP and here it is multiplied by NR so we
have
to add up
uh what we
subtracted so
this multiplied by the corresponding
amounts
here so in this summation that
compensates for those subtractions is we
we we recognize
uh the difference between composition in
between products and reactants and
that's related to
the uh reaction
coordinate through the proportionality
relations so the Epsilon doesn't have a
subscr it goes out of the
summation and here we are left with the
summation of the stochiometric
coefficients which multiply this
reference with with the
pure component
properties uh specific properties at
those reference temperature and
pressure
this
summation we call it the energy of the
reaction at standard pressure and at
that temperature and we denote it by
this symbol here so that defines the
energy of the
reaction you can do that for for all the
other uh for all the other um differen
here for example this is for the
enthalpy the rate of
enthalpies add and
subtract uh the pure component specific
enthalpy you get
uh in this final term you get the
proportionality relation for the
continuous process Epsilon dot goes out
of the summation the summ you also call
it the enthalpy of the reaction uh at it
is the enthalpy of the reaction because
uh it has in it refers to a specific
reaction because it depends on the
stochiometric co efficients of that
reaction okay so I'll have an enthalpy
of this reaction another enthalpy for
that reaction so each reaction has its
own value for these properties of
reaction we call them properties of
reaction and here's the list you can do
that for for all properties including
energy entropy enpy gives fre energy and
even
volume and of course since they these
are uh pure component uh uh
properties
um the relation that hold
between properties also hold
between uh the properties of reaction so
since the Gibs free energy you can write
it as H minus TS it turns out that the
GI free energy of reaction is equal to
the enthalpy of reactions minus t times
the entropy of
reaction or since the enthalpy uh is
equal to energy plus PV U plus PV there
there is a relation also between the
enthalpy of reaction the energy of
reaction and the uh volume of
reaction this is for a generic
temperature T at standard temperature
pressure also the temperature is fixed
we we drop the symbol uh function of T
and for for Simplicity we just uh by
convention say well if if there is
no dependence of of t means that we are
at at T not so the KN here is uh has two
meaning uh pressure and also temperature
are at standard
values now it turns out that if you want
to uh
compute the properties
of reaction you see as we've said every
reaction has its own properties
should then be uh all uh measured so if
you have one
uh interesting in one reaction you have
to find the experimental values of
somebody who measured these the
properties for your reaction well the
answer is no
fortunately because of the EST relation
which we will prove in a
moment uh whereby you you
it turns out that uh there is a minimal
set of uh measurements that you have to
make which is um the measurement of the
reactions of formations of the various
component once you have those uh using
these relations H
relations uh you can find the
um properties of reaction for any
reaction by just taking the weighted sum
with the
stochiometric coefficients of your
reaction of the reactions of formations
of the various uh of the various
molecules that play in your
reaction so essentially
here I'm interested in
energy
uh symbol yeah okay the F goes before f
i not and then I'll have to list
somewhere here the values of the en
energies of formation for these various
components and these ones I find
tabulated in the handbooks of
chemical
physics now before before we prove this
relation let's
U uh
see the meaning of this Delta
U and
Delta actually this is for enthalpy and
entropy and so let's consider one
particular reaction like that of in
which hydrogen molecule splits into uh
two hydrogen
atoms so here I'm drying I'm drawing the
uh eus s or actually the enal versus S
curve for the stable equilibrium
states of atomic hydrogen this is atomic
hydrogen in the amount of one fixed
fixed amount one
mole and at standard pressure one
atmosphere this other curve represents
half a
mole
of molecular hydrogen
H2 also at standard
pressure then I take a
slope equal to
Kelvin and search for the point on this
curve
what I have that temperature turns out
the derivative of the of H with respect
to S constant p is uh equal to the
temperature so also on this diagram uh
the slope is the
temperature and here I find it
here and for this other substance I find
it
there now these two curves
uh until uh yesterday
or until we didn't consider chemical
reactions we're sort of
independent if we needed to describe the
properties of this molecule we just draw
this curve anywhere taking an
arbitrary zero for the enthalpy I didn't
matter but now instead what matters is
the fact that you with a chemical
reaction mechanism you can go from one
substance to the
other so they the you cannot arbitrarily
choose reference values for the
properties uh for
both because
for example if you look at um suppose we
were at zero
temperature
uh in order
to
split uh this molecule of atomic I mean
molecular hydrogen into two hydrogen you
have to break a bond chemical Bond and
the strength of this chemical
bond corresponds to an energy that you
have to provide in order to uh
detach these two atoms that compose the
the
molecule this energy this bond
energy is what you have to plot here so
that is is uh the the number that allows
you to place in relative position the
two
curves because this value you
measure uh and
therefore these two curves must be at
this distance
here then using the properties of the
the substances of the pure substances
here you can compute like using specific
ke and so on you can compute what would
be the value of the enthalpy at this
temperature
and then also using the specific Heats
of this other substance you can uh
integrate the equation this
the the fundamental relation and get to
this point okay these are correspond to
the standard the
conditions
and the enthalpy of
formation of uh Atomic hydrogen so of of
this state here uh from from molecular
hydrogen is is given by the difference
in the inal between here and there this
is the amount of energy that you have to
provide in a steady state
reactor uh where as input you have
hydrogen at standard conditions and as
output you have
a atomic hydrogen at also standard
conditions all right
and this also there is a difference in
entropy this difference in entropy
corresponds to the entropy of uh
formation okay
now
this the strength of the bondes we will
return on this graph but just to the
strength of the of the bonds
um is uh also um describable
using for example Leonard Jones's
potential
but the strength and the distances in
play are very
different for
example this would
be uh the Leonard Jones potential that
describes the calent
bond uh which is what happens when um
this
um hydrogen atom gets close to the
oxygen
and U gets to share
U they get to share two
electrons and these two electrons form a
a negative charge enough
to to cover up the repulsion between the
positive charges of the
nuclei okay so then this this is the
repulsion of the nuclear this is the
attraction and this is a very heavy um
dip it is 459 KJ per
mole if you compare it with the Vander
vales forces between uh um that that are
that you can calculate for water
molecules
in that describes the liquid and Vapor
phase for water molecules using the
lonard John's uh fluid model that we
discussed the value of the
Epsilon is uh you see
it's what is it 4,000 times smaller
5,000 time times
smaller so much that in order to show it
in the plot I have to multiply it here
by a factor of a
thousand and still it's smaller and also
the minimum
here for the Vander vales forces the
attraction between
molecules uh which are also of
electrostatic nature but of from
different source is
uh makes
the has very larger much larger
characteristic uh distances so it's like
uh uh three angstrom here or or 300
picometers here and instead for the
calent bond is of the order of
74 so they have to get much closer in
order to in order for these um much
stronger forces to to to get in play and
hold the molecule so this is
a to to say that uh
um yes you can use Leonard Jones
although it's not really a great model
for for this kind of of bonds but it it
gives you the first order
uh idea and
but you have to realize also of the
different order of magnitude of the
strengths of the bonds with respect to
the V vales
forces okay so yeah let's stop here I
guess yeah