in this video we'll look at an
application of the probabilistic method
to extremal set theory extremal set
theory is an area of combinatorics
concerned with questions such as what is
the largest collection of sets that
satisfy certain desired properties and
the question that we'll look at in this
video is the
following what is the largest enti chain
and more precisely what is the largest
collection of subsets of some ground set
numbers one through n so this is an N
element set so I want as many sets as we
can such that no none of these sets is a
subset of another set okay so this is
what we mean by an anti chain and for a
given value of n what is the largest
number of sets you can have what is the
largest L that we can have as a function
of
n to give an
example when n equals to
3 you can have the sets one
two 1
3 and 2
three and you see that none of these
sets is a superet of
another more
generally when you take all K
element
subsets of 1 through
n this collection also has the property
that no set is a subset of another set
because all these K element subsets have
the same size so none of them can
contain
another now this collection of sets
have n choose
K
sets
and which value of K maximizes this
quantity and choose K well it is
maximized at K being n /2 or when n is
odd we I can either round down or round
up leading
to n choose k/2 or the floor of k/2 so
this is so n choose n /2 so n /2 floor
meaning that's rounded downward
equivalently rounded up produce the same
answer so this many sets we can get
forming an anti
chain now this is just one example and
the question is is this the best example
can we do better can we get an even
larger collection of sets that form an
anti-chain and the classic result of
sperner so spers
theorem says that actually no this is
the best that we can
do and what the theorem says is that if
you have L subsets of one through
n such
that none of the sets is a subset of
another
then in fact L is at
most
n choose the floor of n
/2 okay so this answers the question
that we were asking and in this video
we'll use the probabilistic method to
prove sperner's theorem and it's quite a
beautiful proof and the introduction of
Randomness into the proof is quite
remarkable for a theorem that really
doesn't involve any Randomness at
all what we will prove is
actually the following
theorem which is slightly stronger than
sperner's theorem and we'll prove the
following Al also known as the L IIM
inequality named after three people who
discovered the
theorem and it says that in the
hypothesis that we just set
up we furthermore have the following
consequence if you take the
sum over I from one I uh I being one to
L of the quantity one
over and choose the size of
AI then this sum is at most
one okay so let us first prove this L ym
inequality and then afterwards we'll
deduce spurn theorem from this LM
inequality let's now introduce
Randomness into the problem
so let Sigma 1 through Sigma
n be a randomly chosen
permutation
of numbers one through n and here we'll
choose this permutation uniformly at
random meaning that of all the N
factorial different permutations we
select one with equal probability of
being any one of those n factorial
permutations and now let's consider the
following chain of
sets starting with the empty
set and then the set containing just the
first element of this permutation Sigma
1 and then the set containing the first
two elements of this permutation Sigma 1
Sigma 2 and so on until we add all the
elements into the set okay so these are
the set of prefixes of this permutation
where we add one element at a time so
this is a chain of subsets of 1 through
n and let's consider the
event for which we'll evaluate its
probability so the event that AI so AI
is one of the sets that was originally
given in the in the theorem statement so
what's the event so the event that we
consider is event that AI appears
in this
chain okay so this chain means this
chain over here now this chain is random
because the sigas are a random
permutation even though the AIS are the
deterministic the AI are given this
permutation Is Random so this is some
event for which has a
probability
now when do we have ai appearing in this
chain or if all the elements of AI
appear in this permutation before all
the non elements of AI so we can count
how many different ways this can happen
so of all the N factorial different
permutations the number of permutations
where the elements of AI
appear first is AI size factorial and
then all the non elements of AI
appear afterwards it's n minus the size
of AI
factorial and this quantity here is
equal to one over the binomial
coefficient and choose the size of
AI okay next let us note the
following that no
two different AIS ajs can
simultaneously
appear in the
chain why is that well we assume
that no AI contains is a subset of
another AJ and if indeed you had Ai and
AJ both appearing in the chain then one
of them would contain
another so this chain cannot contain two
different AIS at the same
time and therefore these events
meaning these events over
here are
disjointed as we run I from one through
L if the these events are D joined and
each of them have this
probability well
the sum of these probabilities then must
add up to at most one and that's indeed
the conclusion that we're looking for so
the sum of these
probabilities the probability that AI
appears in the chain in this random
chain the sum of these probabilities add
up to at most one because these events
are disjoined from each other and we had
calcul calulated earlier
that the event probabilities are given
as one over n choose the size of AI okay
so this
concludes the proof of the L ym
inequality you see the final line the
final inequality is precisely what we
were trying to
establish and finally let us prove
sperner
theorem by deducing this theorem from
the r ym inequality now here's a this is
a quick deduction because n choose the
size of
AI is at most and
choose the floor of n / two for o i so
the binomial coefficients for a given n
maxes out in the middle we have this
inequality and
thus here I'm just rewriting the L ym
inequality this sum from um so I from
one to L of one over and choose size of
AI this is at most one so that's what we
just proved and then applying this
individual bound to each
term we get L different terms and each
one of them in the denominator we have n
choose the floor of n /
two and rearranging this inequality we
get the desired upper bound on
L so this concludes the proof of spner
theorem it's a beautiful result with a
beautiful proof that is a wonderful
illustration of the probabilistic method
in combinatorics where although the
theorem statement itself is
deterministic doesn't involve any
Randomness the proof
works by introducing Randomness into the
problem so this is the application of
the probabilistic method in
combinatorics and is I think it's one of
the most beautiful applications