energy powers our homes our cars our
lives but many of the energy sources we
use are rapidly changing the
climate so how do we transition to
cleaner energy sources what do
scientists still need to hammer out what
role will governments University
researchers and big corporations have to
play what will this transition actually
look like
what if it works is a new podcast with a
new approach understand the
solutions coming out of the MIT energy
initiative we will look at various ways
to address climate change we'll speak
with experts about the science
technology and policies that can
transform our Energy
Systems what will it take to remove
carbon from our atmosphere how do we
most effectively harness the power of
the Sun or use microbes to generate
electricity and how do we address the
hidden cost of powering electric
vehicles and electrifying our
homes join us as we hear from those
testing new ideas and working on
exciting breakthroughs in Labs industry
and government people who aren't afraid
to ask what if it
works join us on Apple podcast on
Spotify or wherever you get your podcast