uh I'm going to switch over to the
Jupiter notebook to talk sort of a
review of last class and then going
forwards so what are some of the things
we unlocked last class so music 21
objects that we can
use shout them out
what's that stream good pitch Corpus I
heard anything else duration duration
and Pitch from duration lets you do what
not note good we remember that and
there's one other one uh I just want to
remind you we're not going to use it
very much it's called converter let me
make this a little bit bigger oh that's
nice for me too um and
sorry great um
and because converter does the same
thing as Corpus but loads any file on
your uh hard drive or anywhere on the
web but um since I don't know what your
what's on your hard drive uh we're not
going to use it that much great
um and what's something we did last
class what what's the problem so let's
all load our that Bo piece I remember
what I should type Corpus Corpus do par
parse good and and um I said it was Bach
bwv 66.6 the only thing you actually
need is whatever is necessary to
distinguish it from anything
else so you'll you'll sometimes see I'm
U going to be taking a shortcut there
good and uh how many things were in Bach
do we remember estimate six oh good we
have the exact number yep uh
why what where are the
notes we have a score object and pretty
sure just a
recall yep um we've score object and
then what's inside of it the main thing
four of the thing of the six thingss
parts good and then inside the part
Hannah did you you had your hand up on
the last one I'll get you in uh what's
inside of a part uh measure measure
objects good and what's inside the
measure
objects notes and other things but
primarily so we have this higher
hierarchy this nested hierarchy score
Parts um measure notes there may
sometimes even be uh another level of
hierarchy for instance in scores like
this where you have two different voices
on the same part um there uh what do you
call it there may be a voice object
inside of a measure and if you have a
whole collection of scores we call it
something begins with an OP Opus Opus
yeah so there you can have something
that's bigger than a score you can have
opuses op opra technically an opus that
has scores inside it and then you can
put opuses inside opuses because I
didn't want to make anything bigger yeah
go ahead can we close the door oh yeah
sure sure can you close the door for
somebody who can get there thanks
um thank you appreciate it um great so
let's how did we get down to the
um how did we get down to the uh notes
last time we did something like um for
thing in score you don't have to type
this is all review in
Bach if thing in if uh we remember the
is instance is the python way of
figuring out um so I thing in score is
uh stream. part we can also just say
stream. stream if it's some sort of a
stream then for thing in part in thing
in
score I don't want to waste too much
time on this uh I can do
this if instance thing in part somebody
tell me if I type something wrong on
this because I'll probably do it and
that's not the there's no tricks on this
um for thing
in uh what is
it measure in thing in part
print thing in measure hopefully that
works yep so that let's us get down to
the lowest level of what's Happening
Here we have a whole bunch of notes what
are we doing is that are these are we
doing uh you'll remember the two
representations the Box representation
or the slami slice TimeWise
um what are we doing are we going
through all the parts here first or are
we going through one part and then
another hint you can always look back at
your score you know the piece and you
have the
notes go ahead and when you when you
have it just look up and then shout it
out part by part we're going part by
part right the soprano C Shar b a b c
formada oh it's nice to see that
formadas are not in here so they must be
someplace else e c yeah so we're going
uh part by part in this case
great um and we also saw last class that
we could do something if we knew exactly
where something was we could say B two
which I happen to remember there's a
metadata soprano then Alto so that would
be two uh I don't know let's choose a
random
measure and we can make a list out of
this I can't remember if I think I
demonstrated that and get what is in
here and we'll keep seeing that these
random other things keep popping up here
like system layouts and so on
um so um we'll need a better way to get
to notes questions this is review so I
went pretty fast but um the important
thing is if I'm reviewing it it's
probably important that we have good
understanding before we move
on yeah Jake curse on the first use so
we're going to get to that in just just
a second yep good yeah close that sure
great
great there we go sorry that the
blackout blind over there doesn't seem
to be
working
should um if email me after class I'll
REM remember to put in a facilities
request or if you email me right now in
class I'll you'll hear a ding then I'll
put in a facilities request because
that's going to get annoying as um after
daylight savings time starts for this
class good
um okay any any other things that we
want before from the review last time
yeah I showed a whole bunch of things on
the first class that are not on done yet
but we'll um we'll be getting to them
sooner so assume everything on the first
class I think I said at the end uh was
then immediately relocked but but as far
as recur this recurse thing um we're
going to get to it and unlock it in just
a few
seconds great
um so any any stream can be converted to
a list by doing it so we can get the
list of everything that's in the top
level score for Bach here and then we
can um
yeah do do other things and we can um
there are some differences between a
stream and a list that are pretty
important so when I say a list list
array in other languages what are some
of the things you can do um it's a
mutable container so what some things
you can do to
it yeah you can add to it you can add to
it great other
things usually can add you can yeah pop
you can pop things off of it great you
can remove things out of it what is some
other things that lists to uh yeah go
ahead you can change things at certain
indices you can change things at certain
indices yeah you can replace one thing
with another good any other things we
can do we're
getting yeah Jason find the length you
can find the length great you can find
the length and you can append to it and
change the length all those things um
one other thing beginning with uh
it you can do yeah John iterate you can
iterate it you can put into a for Loop
and get things great great any uh
there's one more over here splicing
splicing yeah you can you can CH get
little parts of it too so in this way a
stream really does work like a
um like a list we can get out get rid of
that metadata we can get rid of other
things here um if I had been smarter uh
20 years ago it probably would inherit
from list but it does not um but it has
a lot of things that are like list like
um but there's some things that you can
also do that are a little different
let's get um actually where what was
that over here um we went up to Bach
24 let's get that um out here I think
that should be
measure uh measure three let's see m m
equals this and we'll see what m is y
measure
three great so measure three of the
second thing up here so the third thing
because we're doing two Z index 0 one
two measure three of the Alto part here
is something that I don't think um for
all the amazing things MIT CS training
does I don't think it does very very
well I think that we this says measure
three of the Alto part and here's the
contents of it let's just go through and
make sure remember pickups are measure
what Z zero so let's make sure that this
is actually measure three uh
of is that right do we get the right
measure um the next problem set the one
that we're going to be talking about at
the end of class today uh it's not as
it's it's probably the least time
consuming of any of the ones you've had
so far so good I fig figure every third
one you need a little bit of break so
we'll go down on that I will tell you in
advance where people lose points on this
problem set is that they write the code
the code works and then they go on and
there's a little programming error
somewhere that could have easily been
fixed by looking at the score during
show and checking that your answer was
actually what it should be so just just
to have that there and that's now I've
uh you know my my feeling is everybody
can get an A+ we can all get perfects on
everything I don't need to do play
gotcha games for um you know hahaa now
now there's nothing to mark off so good
so make sure that you're always doing
that and make sure to do these uh call
them sanity checks that you're getting
out from your data what you should be
getting in okay so these are some things
that they're similar um one of the
things though in
uh so we have this measure object and
we'll look
oops shape of your brackets does matter
right
um you have something here now if this
was just a a normal list m.
insert to we're going to put it position
two let's put a note. note let's let's
do one that we can immediately recognize
a double flat for okay uh we can create
an object in here actually we'll we'll
be smart we'll call that n and Define it
before uh n equals so we can reference
it again sorry I'm try not to get this
at the very bottom of the screen
great so what should have happened if
this
were um If This Were a normal list where
should where would you expected to see
that double flat a double flat
after the G after the G I think
that everybody agree sometimes Professor
everybody agrees when the professor's
like yeah does it go after two or does
it I can't remember but yeah I'm pretty
sure that's right so it should be
somewhere over
here why is it here let's go back to
that Alto part measure
two and see it's coming after the C uh
does the C have a formada on it or
not just want to make sure we're all in
the same
place yeah John's John's nodding his
head and John's almost always right on
these things so good good um and yeah so
we have it on the last yah of that word
that I'm not going to say uh during Lent
right um and good so it's coming right
after there and yet we said we should
put it at
two what might be happening here get on
it's being put like the second beat well
zero index the second beat yeah Z this
with the beginning being zero now I told
you that's very very close to the right
answer so great great I said at the
beginning there was a reason why I
didn't like to use beat as a fundamental
unit what was that
or if if don't because of things like 58
where um fast
58 y one and and one and two and uh
where beats can change their duration
even within a measure so what might um
what's something equivalent what would
durations measured in I'm going to call
on Misha next but I want to make sure
that we have yeah yeah I think it was
just I think you said you use quarter
notes as your yeah so quarter links so
in this case it's exactly the same as
beat so this a correct answer in this
case because we're in 44 right but so we
put it in if what do we have 8th eth so
that's all within 0 0.5 one
two okay but there might be a problem
here why is it after the
C well let's let's do this we remember
some of our iteration for I'll still say
thing in M even though they're mostly
notes print thing and things new term
that we haven't seen it's
offset so the offset just like the
duration has a is measured in quarter
lengths the offset from the beginning of
the current container is measured in
quarter LS so we have here and we can
actually now have two notes at the same
time so you can have multiple position
things at the same position that makes
it a little bit harder to remove by um
by offset that you want to have because
there unlike in a array where there can
only be one thing at a particular index
here you can have multiple things at the
same index um this is a simplification
we'll see in a little bit that notes and
everything else can have an infinite
number of offsets simultaneously but um
this is good enough to start
here yeah go say if you do show it
doesn't like put them in the same place
H if you put it show it doesn't right
because not uh that that's that's a
great thing you're going to find it is
easy to create things that are valid
musical Concepts that cannot be shown by
any of our um of our sort of uh music
representation software our Muse scores
or alleys or whatever like that um why
because do you usually if you have a
part do you have two this is this is an
ontological question do you have two
notes that sound at the same time in one
part or do you have something else that
happens when you have two notes at the
same
time what what other representation
might be for two notes for two two
things that sounded the same same time I
won't sing
notes
anybody what do we different parts you
would have you would have a you could
have it in two different parts which is
what we've normally seen or
yep one person like going up yeah you
see you have a split yeah a split we
call those voices in this you have two
voices at that thing what's the other
other thing that um another fundamental
part of our
ontologies chord so in this case your um
software wants me to have created a
chord object which is not yet unlocked
for us out of these two so it just does
whatever it wants with it great question
super so keep playing with the limits
we're a little bit behind in time
because we're um we're really uh asking
great questions so I'm going to um hold
off a little bit on some until we can
get a little bit further into um some
things so let me um yeah question go
ahead how do you remove well um you'll
be able to you can either remove the
thing and it will find it or you can
remove something at an offset and we'll
get um that will be fortunately all of
these other things will be uh all these
other options uh will be uh revealed to
you in uh in the reading before next
time we meet together um which is the
users guide chapter on streams so I
think that remove is mentioned in there
it's can be a little bit more
complicated as I said so I want to um
hold that off for just a little
bit okay um let me do another little
thing for a second and we'll jump to
some ways that we can make our life
easier by not doing for thing and thing
then for next thing and thing next thing
and next thing and previous thing um
obviously we're going to have some other
um ideas so this is a one notion one way
of a score score might be represented in
music 21 with two parts and So within
the score and this its scores length is
how
much just Sout it
out two or three because we have this
metadata and so I've put underneath is
the offset of everything both parts
start at the beginning of the score
right so they have offset zero Within
part one there are two I'm calling
measures measure 1 a measure 2 a um
their offsets are at zero and four which
makes sense because somewhere in here
there's a
44 time signature right um and within
and notice though that when we're
looking at measure two measure 2's
offset is four but we start again with
offset zero so so if you want to know
how many quarter notes into the piece
quarter note 9 happens you'd have to add
2 +
4 plus
zero fortunately adding zero is easy so
get ah it's six quarter notes into the
piece so this is one uh the
representation that's
happening now when you iterate over the
score for uh I'll s use l element um
thing things comes off the tongue better
but L is quicker to type and um when you
do this you'll you'll see that that
we've already seen you get the
metadata you get part
one and then you get part two and that's
all right so you get the three things
that are there um the more powerful way
to do this is something called recurse
the recurse
method on here and um what this does is
it goes through the first thing and then
if there's anything inside the metadata
which there isn't it's not a container
it would go into it then part one is a
container class uh all containers are
called streams but the general term in
computational music theory is the
container and then within this container
we have another container and it will go
through uh these things that are not
containers sometimes these are called
leafes leaves the leaf mod node like in
a graph the thing that has no
Descendants on it and then it will go
through the second one then it jumps
back to part two and goes through each
one and tells you that so that's going
to be make life a lot easier let's
recurse through um do I have can I move
over here we go let's recurse through uh
Bach for l in Bach
recurse print let's do L and L's
offset oops and now I have to get my
scrolling
back
go so now we're seeing ah there's the
metadata there's the soprano part if we
were writing a program we could keep
track of what part we're certain we're
in at a certain point and every time we
see a new part do something and then we
see up where it measure zero
here we go here's all the different
things to measure one measure two and if
I scroll far enough eventually we should
see um Here We Go part
Alto so that's um it's pretty good there
this all this information about what's
its offset and things this can be done
also gotten um in a way that just prints
it's not useful for parsing I would not
say parsing this but if you do bach.
show
text and it just gives you basically the
same information as that routine but
nicely
formatted so I'll give second where the
current offset is given first and then
the next thing um also puts everything
like
this questions on this part
part okay now your computer science
question
recurse is what type of graph search
don't shout it out yet everyone think
what there are a number of ways of of
searching through a a graph or iterating
through a graph what kind would we call
this us I'll give you a hint the second
word is usually
first okay that wasn't much of a hint so
okay uh give raise your hand if you're
confident that you know the answer to
this now and raise go like this if
you're if you're not confident that you
know the answer great could you talk
with the person next to you uh and
especially if you're some if you have
couple people who aren't so confident uh
just and share your answer and see if
you're in the same um same boat
okay who is who is uh now a little bit
less is still unconfident who who's come
to an agreement on your thing you're you
guys are still in disagreement no you're
you're in agreement good good okay so um
let's all shout it out at us the kind of
search is
a first search a depth first search good
so we're always going to be following
the leftmost I should do this in
different colors so it's easier to see
um right the leftmost node that we
haven't yet seen and doing something
with that and then going back up here
going back up down right does that
seem to fit other people's computer
science things I have neither a
concentration minor major um or PhD in
computer science so please if I get
something wrong you all shout to me
because you've done more of that than I
have okay great so we have depth first
search what are some of the things uh
anybody knows from other things that
depth first searches are good for and
what are some of the things that they're
not good
at so good for anybody wants
say don't worry it's a safe space
and shortest path problem shortest path
problem good good shortest path problem
anybody do you want to explain or
anybody else want to explain what that
is for those who
have shortest path between two notes
right how to how to get there right you
don't might not want to do something
else that might be good
for yeah just when you're in a scenario
where you think you want look over like
every possible
option great when you scenario where you
want to look at every possible object
now that there's other search methods
that also have that um property but this
one has that property so it's already a
lot better than for thing and thing than
thing and thing thing and thing right
you know that you're going to get to
every Point what's something it might
not be good
for that another search method might be
a better way of doing
it yeah case of like breath resch versus
depth resarch like if something's close
by there's not a lot of it or the tree
is like super deep but the answer is
like super close yep dep research will
search through everyone like to go to
the depths of the tree just check in the
first couple great super super and we
should we should say what we're
comparing um there's lots and lots of
searches but the two key key ones we
have depth first search and it's
compared to what bread first search yep
the the breakfast search as I always say
breath first search so that one um what
are we going to do if we want to a bre
first search in here what are we going
to see
first what's the first node we're going
to visit SC SC the score right good so
so far it's exactly the same as a depth
for second node we're going to see in
this High part one good third note part
two ah okay so we're already different
next
note was one yep so would isn't BFS
better for shortest path
searching rather than DFS it depends on
what how you're doing your path if
you're looking for dist one like pass
and you want to find the first one that
gets you there that's better you're like
positive L
distances trying to remember the exact
what I remember which one of these like
AAR even better yeah so we'll get to
these particular types of searches later
uh controversy in the class I'll try to
remember exactly what which one uh do we
have a um but yeah I'll I'll Trust um
that we'll solve that because we're not
going to be doing uh shortest path yet
um in this in this class but we'll we'll
see that there's there's certain
advantages to one versus the other the
other um thing so what's a musical thing
that we want to uh how about this um do
all parts start with the same um with
the same uh key
signature bread first or depth
first which one's going to be fastest to
get you your
answer I heard depth and breadth who's
on depth who's on breath yep okay good
so we're going to want to have both
types of searches
available um so recurse will give you
always um a what do you call it the uh
depth for
search there's another one that we're
going to have and um you're going to see
it's the flatten operation and you're
going to see it sometimes in my old
slides I haven't figured out how to
update um flat but it's it used to be a
proper
um that is to say you didn't need the
calls called Flat now it's a method
called Flat in U thing there are two
reasons for this one if anybody has a
new um uh uses an IDE like VSS code or
py Charm or something like that which I
highly encourage you to do um you know
it's nothing Elite to use vhm anymore uh
in life um then a lot of those will now
um go through and call and check every
one of the properties as point so it can
repeat for you and flat ended up being
um for a very very large score um very
time uh very space and time sensitive
and so I would uh once I upgraded to a
thing I realized okay that that can't
work anymore that flat so we had to do
it this I also wanted to make it a few
more letters so that people would stop
calling flat instead of recurse uh just
because it was less to type so now that
now they're much more equal flatten and
what flatten does is it gives you the
option of doing everything first that's
at the same
offset everything so we start with I
think I have an animation on this the
metadata
again we get one
cff next Cliff both the time signatures
everything that's at the same point when
you have a half note here we'll get both
e both quarter notes before getting to
the other thing the other thing that
flatten does that's different is you'll
see the offsets are now because it's
flattened um it's they're now all
relative to the start of the
score so um because of this they're
implemented in different ways recurse
the bread for search just sort of has a
little pointer that's going around
figuring out where I am figuring out how
to to go back up to the next hierarchy
level and walk around and do this so
it's very very fast and not very memory
intensive the flatten on the other hand
in order to compute where everything
should be and which one is actually
coming next into this hierarchy and for
historical reasons flatten will take
that same score and put it all into a a
a new score object a new thing but with
oh it also removes all the parts and
stuff uh flatten there are no parts or
anything there's just the things just
the leaf nodes at the end so you'll get
the clef the other cleff the time
signature the other time signature and
so on all in a new stream
object and this is the first time when I
was saying that a note might have more
than one offset because this is the same
oops
this quarter note here is the same as
that quarter note there so do offset
will be changing as this
happens um this is something that will
occasionally bite you but usually not
what does um which offset does it tell
you when you put dot offset it tells you
whatever the offset is in the last
stream that you iterated over that um
has that object in it
so we call that the active
site so it tells you the offset in its
active
site you will find that um it's often
you're looking at something in a
flattened stream that should say
flattened up there and you want to know
something about oh I've uh professor
cber said get me all of the notes
between off set five and seven and tell
me what measure they're in shoot we've
gotten all things five seven from the
beginning of the score um the problem is
we've lost all the measure information
we here so there is a property on all
streams. derivation do origin which will
take you back to the original the place
where it came from so the pre flatten
stream and that's something you're going
to be working with a lot um this is an
on logical Choice I've made on how
things are R how flattened versions of
scores have a derivation to the origin
of the original score uh now I'll take
questions on anything it's pretty
confusing it's a lot to jump in yeah
Adam last time what was verba in the in
the German Anthem coding what was what
what was at the very very top I said it
was the composer oh boom okay so we're
jumping jumping quite a bit back uh it's
the location uh Bohemian uh originally a
Bohemian
song that that is that was a pop quiz to
see what I remembered great
um any other questions on on this
material specifically and then uh on
anything okay well let's
um let's start start by having a little
bit of programming exercise time um we
have this Bach
Corral bwv
66.6 are there more Yep go ahead so does
flat mate object so flatten mutates
um yes it it mutates something on every
object called sites that keeps track of
where things are but it does not um
change I think there were some choices
that um now that music 21's 20 years old
almost um there's some things that I
would have done differently and I think
it probably time for somebody who's um
you know younger and more ambitious and
wants to do something for the next 20
years uh to come up with things because
I did not listen to our great software
engineering Professor Peter Jackson's uh
warnings against mutability uh in
objects as well as I should have and now
I'm trying to make more things immutable
but you will find um that a lot of
things will by default not mutate but
then can and objects can be mutated so
that's great question everyone knows
mutable versus immutable objects you can
change you Cann lists
are what is the equivalent of a list in
Python that is immutable tup Tuple good
good you all say Tuple here I always le
as Tuple but Tuple okay
great super um well so here's uh any
other questions before I go on to my
question for you about
Bach okay here is the question for
you um to answer and let's do this in
groups of two because it's much more fun
to uh be talking to does Bach use more
ascending
notes or descending
notes descending
notes or about the same
I mean you might think the peace the
peace doesn't start off Hallelujah and
end right and it doesn't go the opposite
so it must be about the same maybe but
we'll see so talk um who's everyone know
who they're going to be paired up
with paed it's easier if you're sitting
on thing s PA paed great so start
talking about um about how you how
you're going to do this and what which
type of I a great question
flat flatten why does flatten
show because it's able ah because recurs
is not a stream recurs isn't yeah so I
should say recur recurse just gives you
an iterator around that you could do um
recurse thing and then there's a DOT
stream that you can put onto it and
that'll give you a stream but it's just
going to give you the same thing you
started with because yeah I
don't no no no then do it then yeah
thank you thank you always say we're
going to talk first about how to do it
then then implement
but I don't it's in class I don't care
however you'd like to do it but but
always start talking then
implementing okay I'm hearing the
discussion start uh dying down and
hearing some some clicks you can keep
talking but just informal poll which
which groups are on are on team
flatten we got one two three good good
which groups are on team recurse is the
best way good good good and which groups
are in team for thing and thing and
thing and thing and thing okay there's
one no just there was a smile with that
one okay so keep keep going there's ways
um to keep working on it I think you'll
find there's one that's better than the
other but we'll figure out which one
that
is and if you're lucky to be sitting
next to a group that's on the different
team maybe talk across groups and figure
out
we'll dialogue across religions and
political
views I'm going to interrupt for one one
second to say something that I've heard
just a second uh should yeah just one
second can I interrupt for one second to
say something I have heard from two
different groups Matthew get introduced
for two different groups um I have heard
this something like oh but think of the
memory we're going to have to keep a
reference to the previous note what is
to keep a reference to the previous note
what is the the Big O memory
consideration that we're thinking
about what one do we care about o of one
memory no no we do not not good keep
going with that just wanted to make sure
that we had that we don't care about o
of one operations very often
occasionally but just piece just this
piece oh oh it was just this I I just
heard is it just this piece or Olive
Bach um just this piece is what I'm
asking for but you could do
for
Corral in Corpus
so you um Derek if you wanted
to there is a for Loop you can do above
it and since we've unlocked Corpus that
will give you all looking good good so
if anybody if anybody's finished and's
gotten a thing oh a couple questions
once once you have that they're not
exactly the same I'll say that and what
explain what are some features in the
Corral that explain that the other thing
you could do
is do this for all 360
Cals that's a lower case C
Corpus do
coral. okay uh just before we go who
just uh who is still on who is still on
team
flatten you use flatten a little bit
okay and who who actually it will say
who used flatten anywhere in that score
and who used recurse anywhere in this
score okay I'm curious how um how did
flatten work for getting getting this
did you do you have the same she your
first flat it and it's the same for
ascending and then for descending we're
off by you interesting I'll be curious
to see how that that happened um great
um so I think we're we're wrapping up a
bit you can keep um keep working
obviously I'm um what is it item nine on
your thing sound to score I it's one of
my favorite things to teach in class cuz
it's really really fun but I have made a
video so we can save some time outside
um and that uh I'll add that that's
about a 10 minute to watch there's um
trying to make it quite a bit easier on
this this weekend try to make it a
little bit lighter so it's just some um
some interesting added things that are
happening there and um for the first
time I'm going to really recommend that
you um read the music 21 users guide
chapters uh there's an optional one
chapter 26 at the end you don't need to
read it because it's a little bit
complex but if you do read it and get
through it uh there are some tips in
there that can make some aspects of the
problem set three uh a little bit easier
so um any any other questions on what we
did oh one one last thing one last thing
on on this um I always recommend and I
really really recommend uh readable code
right readable code write code so that
you can do this collaboration and give
it to friends right things like that but
one year a while back um the um the
class did decide to go code golfing on
this particular uh thing to see who
could write the um shortest uh code to
do all this and uh I oops sorry why do
they do that to the eyes because uh back
then we were using uh Piaza for a
discussion board which used a
proportional font so using eyes made it
also makes it a little bit more
scrutable so never write code like this
but um I do believe that that works if
you want it and um you're Prof
one but see if you can beat uh that one
thanks everybody