now our next speaker next Kino speaker
will give a a talk on very specific
science computer science computer vision
and data uh it's called synthetic data
so now let me introduce our second kyom
speaker Professor Phillip is Sola who is
an associate professor in MIT e and a
principal investigator in mitc cell his
work focus on why we represent the world
the way we do and how we can
replicate uh the
abilities in
machines he has WR a book just published
very very few months ago it's called
found foundations of computer vision
that covers topics not standard in
textbooks
including for example
Transformers diffusion
models statistical image
models issues of fairness and uh ethics
and the research process now let's
welcome
Philip ask to ask
[Applause]
questions repeat
okay okay he hi everyone um yeah thank
you for the intro and for having me here
and happy to share um some of my work
and some of the trends that I'm seeing
going on in the field right now in
generative AI okay let me see if I know
where to point okay
good so I'm going to talk about
generative models as a data source for
AI systems and this is a topic which
sometimes goes under the name synthetic
data and a lot of companies and a lot of
uh applications are now building uh
their systems not on top of real data
but on top of data made by models and
these are two examples of synthetic data
this is a generative model of images of
cats um it's a model called the Gan and
this is a generative model um which is
called a Nerf and neural Radiance field
and I'll mention some applications of
those as well as um some of the even
newer
models
okay let's see
okay there we go finding the slide
Advanced button is always the first step
so uh a lot of work in AI proceeds as
shown on this slide here you take a data
set as fixed in in Academia this is what
we used to do all the time and it's
still what most people do they take data
as fixed that the rules of the game are
you have a data set and you want to
model that data you want to have an
algorithm that analyzes that data and
the entire um action is in the learning
algorithm
okay and then the learning algorithm uh
you know fits a function or a model to
the data and gets some intelligence out
of it but you don't have to do things
that way that was just the standard way
that we have done in the past instead
what I've been more interested in
recently is can we just freeze the
learning algorithm the rules of the game
become the learning algorithm is frozen
and instead change the data that we feed
to that algorithm and if we feed at
better data uh perhaps we'll get a
different result or a better result okay
so we're changing the focus from being
on the algorithms to on the data sets
and one motivation for this is that
we've all seen that data is the big
thing that has uh driven a lot of the
recent progress in AI the algorithms
haven't changed that much but the data
sets have scaled up incredibly and the
compute is the other part that's changed
but I'm not going to touch on that in
this talk okay so the hardware and the
gpus and all of the computational Power
has also been a big driver okay but we
know that data is um the fuel of machine
learning it's data driven intelligence
you get a lot of data and that data
tells you how to make intelligent
machines so we should really study the
data and we should really figure out
ways of making better data and um
generative models are going to be one
way of doing that okay so here's the
perspective that um that I like to take
on this problem uh so generative AI is
often thought of as just a you know fun
tool for making you know creative
stories or images uh but I think I think
it's actually much more fundamental and
powerful than that um so normally we
start with a uh data it goes into a
learning algorithm we get intelligence
out but instead we're going to think of
uh we're going to add a generative model
to the first part of the pipeline we're
going to take data fit a generative
model to that data this is going to be
like an image generation algorithm or a
text generation algorithm so think um
chat gbt or do uh these types of things
and what we're going to get out is not
just more photos or more text we're
going to get out something which is
actually fundamentally different it's
like the original data but in some ways
it can be better it's data with more
potential I like calling this uh data
Plus+ and I'll tell you uh the ways in
which this can be an augmentation or an
improvement over the original data okay
and it's a little bit weird I mean some
of you you should be kind of skeptical
like you have real data and then you
make this approximation to it with a
model and it's actually better that
doesn't make any sense right we think of
models as making like artifacts and
hallucinations and not being ual so it's
could be data minus minus after modeling
but I'm going to talk about some ways in
which it can actually be data
Plus+
okay okay and and I think that uh one uh
perspective on this is that this is just
what's happening in the world so whether
or not this is a good idea and I'll try
to argue that in some ways it can be a
good idea but whether or not it's a good
idea this is kind of the Paradigm that
has emerged uh we have
sorry we have companies that will train
these large generative models like
language models or image generative
models and users will take those models
and do something with them so rather
than the user directly Gathering
training data for their algorithm and uh
then training their models on that on
that data they will interface with the
data via a massive Foundation model a
massive generative model created in an
industry so this is just the reality of
how most people will interact with data
it's VI an interface which is through
another model generated by a large
organization or a company it could be an
open source model as well okay so we
have to I think understand uh this
Paradigm of learning from model uh data
that's mediated by a generative
model okay so we had an era previously
which was this era of Big Data Big Data
drove the advances in Ai and deep
learning and machine learning uh now we
have these big models and these are more
and more becoming the interface and just
for example in my fi of computer vision
um it used to be that whenever we'd
start a new project I would tell my
students or it could be in a company
You' tell your employees okay first you
want to uh collect a million labeled
photos for your application area and for
research we would often use this data
set called imag net but that's not what
we do anymore instead the starting point
that my students go to is called stable
diffusion we don't download imet and
train our algorithms on that we now go
to a model called stable diffusion which
is a generative AI system that is our
interface to data so our interface to
data is no longer a data set it's now a
model
okay and I think that this might this
trend might continue and there's also a
lot of talk about the social
consequences and the concerns about the
internet no longer being like a data set
the internet's just going to be a big
repository of synthetic data that's and
most of the um uh the dialogue about
this right now has been critiques of
that setting where the Internet is just
polluted by fake data so I want to give
a little more optimistic take that there
are some benefits as
well okay so here here are going to be
the benefits at the end I'll mention
that some of the limitations uh it is
true these critiques are also valid but
let's look at the positive side first
okay so generative models um what what
do they do one thing they do is they
take a finite data set a small in some
sense data set and they out they create
a system that that can uh produce an
Infinity of data okay so the way they do
that is you start with I'm going to talk
mostly about examples in computer vision
uh start with a set of photos and these
are like discrete points in some data
space okay so the set of photos here is
just going to be dots in this
distribution and I could sample photos
from that set and I'll get real photos
and if I train a gener model what you're
what you actually do is you fit a
continuous density you you fit a
continuous function to that discrete set
and that continuous function uh has
filled in all the gaps so you can you
know interpolate and potentially even
extrapolate a little bit outside of the
distribution of the training training
data and produce samples which you know
look photo realistic because that's the
point we're at now but you can produce
infinite samples uh they the diversity
of that set won't be infinite it will be
uh bounded by the training data but you
can interpolate and even extrapolate a
little bit beyond the the actual
training data so you get more data out
that's one simple sense in which the
output of a generative model can be uh
like data
Plus+ okay so generative models turn
finite data into continuous data into
Infinite data in some sense and uh
that's that's one like starting point
for understanding what they can do but
we'll see is that actually going to be a
good thing is that useful for
anything
okay so I want to tell you a little bit
about how these generative models work
uh to give you the next the next benefit
that I see in them um so most of the
generative AI systems we have now for
making images uh follow this pipeline
you start with a set of uh what we call
latent variables uh so sometimes people
call these noise but I don't really
think noise is the right way to think of
them instead think of them as the uh
control knobs that when you spin those
control knobs you'll get a um a
different image you'll get a random
image okay so you have a set of control
knobs labeled as Z in this diagram here
and you put those inputs you set those
control knobs to whatever setting you
want and you put them into a neural
network G that outputs an image and if I
bin my control knobs to a different
setting I'll get a different image okay
so these controls uh can be visualized
as follows so this is a real result this
isn't like just a cartoon uh if I have a
set of control variables maybe I have a
hundred of these knobs and I am just
going to look at two of them now I'm
going to look at um two of them on these
two axes on the right then if I take the
setting of The Knobs that makes this
bird and then I tune turn one knob
individually uh left and right then I
will get the bird rotating and if I uh
turn another of these control knobs uh
left and right I'll get the background
color changing so these control knobs
act like um interpretable kind of
controls that create this little
manifold continuous manifold of uh
natural images okay so this is something
you can't do with real data very easily
I can't just find photos of this bird
from all these different angles with
different background colors but with a
generative model I have these uh
independent latent variables that can be
tuned uh to create a visual like
this
okay so the other super powerful control
knob is uh that we can use Text Now to
control these uh these models so we
don't just have to use these kind of
so-called latent variables which are
like continuous knobs your turning you
can also just describe what you want and
I'm sure most of you have seen things
like this where you can do text to image
text to video here is a generative model
which is taking the text input a photo
of a group of robots building the status
Center and right this is the output like
these are the things that would have
been mind-blowing a few years ago but
you know the world changes and updates
very quickly and now it's like okay yeah
this is we've seen this is but just
remember a few years ago this would have
looked like magic nobody saw this coming
um that I know okay so we can control
our images via text that's a new
capability that generative models allow
that was not really easily possible if I
just had a tradition
data set of
photos Okay so this is the the next
benefit I see is that generative models
uh take kind of small unstructured data
as input and they output bigger
continuous data plus controls with these
control knobs so it's like the data plus
the controls and that's actually the
mostow powerful part of it in my opinion
because we can intervene on the data via
those controls to steer it and change it
into the type of data we want uh we can
change the properties of of the data to
be maybe less toxic or sensor content
that we don't like or we can make it
more beautiful we can do a lot of
interesting things to it okay I'll talk
I'll show some of these
applications okay but the big big idea
of these control knobs is they allow
what uh we can call counterfactual
reasoning okay so counterfactual
reasoning is a reasoning of the form uh
what would it look like if so what would
it look like if the lighting changed
what would it look like if the camera
angle changed what would it look like if
the pose of that cat changed and so
these control knobs allow you to ask
that question and uh visualize or
sometimes we would say hallucinate uh
these counterfactuals but this is like a
positive version of hallucination it's
it's imagination more than it is like
making up things that are unfactual in a
negative way okay so um how do we do
that with a photo that we want to
imagine this counterfactual for what
we'll we can do is we can take our photo
of this cat and we can do this data to
data Plus+ conversion process where we
find the setting of controls so find the
setting of latent variables Z that when
put through a generative model will
replicate that photo of the cat so we
call that encoding the cat into the the
um control variable space of the
generative model and then we can um
decode that cat back into a photo uh via
our generative model okay now we have
converted the the static real photo of
the cat into this generative version of
the cat which is coupled with its latent
variables and if we change those latent
variables those control knobs then we
get the cat changing its pose maybe we
can change the lighting conditions we
get this living object so we've
converted the static real data into this
more alive controllable um synthetic
data and that's that's what I see as the
kind of most qualitatively important uh
new power of synthetic data that you
don't have in real data okay so there's
a bunch of papers these ones are from a
few years ago but this is very much an
ongoing and hot research area right now
on what you can do with counterfactual
interventions into synthetic data to um
improve your data processing
pipeline okay so I'm going to talk about
a few things now that you can do a few
applications so we have this new type of
data uh I've argued that it is better
because it is uh continuous controllable
um and what can you actually do with
that how can that make applications
better so here's one paper we had from a
few years ago where we uh tried to prove
a kind of crummy classifier so we had
this classifier which I've labeled C
this is just a system that looks at
photos and decides is it a cat is it a
dog is it an airplane and what we did is
we tried to get a more robust classifier
by using these counterfactual um
visualizations okay so we have a noisy
imperfect classifier C it might say
that's a dog but we can then um do what
I just showed the previous slides and
convert this input photo into this um
these counterfactual variations on the
input photo and this now is saying well
the cat could have been in a different
pose the lighting could have been
different here's all the different ways
that the image could have been taken
Without Really fundamentally changing
the content of the image and now we put
all of those into our classifier
Ensemble the results and as long as one
of these kind of counterfactual
visualizations is clearer or more easy
to understand by the classifier then the
then the The Ensemble the set of all the
classifiers averaged together will uh
get a more accurate result so this is a
way of making more accurate and robust
classifier by just uh revisualization
okay so what we showed in that project
is that um generative augmentation so
counterfactual augmentation of what
could this cat look like under different
poses and lighting conditions can help
but it's at at what we call test time so
we we take our system and when we're
actually going to deploy it and use it
we're going to do this augmentation but
could you do these same augmentations
when you're actually training the
underling classifier or the underling
computer vision system uh you know
training at
now we would call it
pre-training okay and in the era that we
worked on that which was the um Gan era
of generative models it didn't really
work those models just were not
realistic enough they had too many
artifacts the hallucinations were too
unrealistic uh so it looked the cat
looked pretty good but it didn't work on
harder scenes okay but time goes on
these models just get bigger and better
uh now we're in the era of what are
called diffusion models and uh now train
time augmentation is starting to work
and I'll show a few examples of that on
the next on the next
slides okay so here's the basic Paradigm
which we started a few years ago which
is using generative models as a source
of of training data uh and this is work
led by Ali Janan and the other authors
shown here and uh we're just going to
contrast between training a computer
vision system on a data set of real
images like the imag net data set versus
training a computer vision system on a
data set
of synthetic images that are made by a
generative model and this cartoon is
just meant to say the the synthetic
images are like this data generating
engine it can produce you know Infinity
of data with underlying control knobs
indicated in that that uh circle with
the Z uh the technical details I'm not
going to get too much into but you think
of it like this engine that can have
this potentially endless
creativity okay so we're going to
combine our synthetic data generation
with a computer vision learning
algorithm called or a machine learning
algorithm called contrastive learning so
here here's how this algorithm works
this algorithm takes data this is like
the learner on that first slide it takes
data and it tries to create a computer
vision representation from that data and
the way it works is you take two crops
of a photo and you say these two crops
of that tiger probably represent the
same thing because they came from the
same photo so we will try to learn a
representation in which
two different crops of the same photo uh
m to the same representation Vector
we're trying to learn a vector
representation of an image is what they
call it and uh it's done in that way so
two different views of the same object
should map to the same representational
Vector okay and normally you do that by
just taking two a data point and then
taking another data point which is a
sample from the same image a crop from
the same image you know patch from the
same
image okay and in contr of learning you
say that a different image entirely that
is not a crop from the the tiger photo
should map to a different um
representational
Vector okay so we can combine these two
things together and we can say now we
have our latent variables which are a
way of getting two different views of
the same thing so rather than doing just
like cropping Patches from photos which
seems like a very crude way of look
finding two different views of the same
thing we can use a generative model to
create two different views of the same
thing and that's what in here so we take
our generative model that produces two
different views of the same thing but
now they they're not just different
crops they're actually you know the cat
potentially with different lighting or
pose or semantic and physical changes
like
this okay so um one of the most popular
contrast of learning algorithms from
real data is called Sim clear that's
shown on the left here and that just
takes crops it also might drop color
channels and do other types of um simple
augmentations but with a generative
model we can do U these more physical
and semantic augmentations like changing
the dog's expression or the angle at
which the photo is taken and in this
this paper just kind of set out that
basic Paradigm uh and at the time uh I
do have to admit that if the computer
vision system trained on the real data
actually was still doing a little better
but the synthetic data was doing almost
as well despite that this was using the
Gan era models which had all these
artifacts it wasn't quite the same dog
so there were problems with that but but
there there was some hope
Okay so we've continued on that and now
we just did the same thing recently with
um the latest generative models
diffusion models rather than Gans and
and now it actually starting to get get
to the level of actually outperforming
real data in some interesting ways okay
so I'm going to talk about this project
called stable rep it's going to be
basically the same idea except uh we
just updated with the latest generative
models okay
so here's the experiment that I'm going
to describe
we're going to train a contrastive
representation a vision system on either
n real photos or n synthetic
photos so we're going to sample n real
photos or and generate n synthetic
photos and we're going to train our
system on that so it's kind of equal
setting on a per sample basis which is
better a synthetic image or a real
photo okay so here here's the Bas the
first result so um on the y- AIS is
performance of our computer vision
system measured on a standard Benchmark
it's measured on the image net Benchmark
just this is how good that computer
vision system is at classifying you know
objects and cats and dogs and on the
x-axis are a few different
representation learning algorithms just
to show that um this approach works with
different methods uh and the green dots
are if I train on N real photos and the
orange dots are if I train on N
synthetic photos and you can see is that
training on nend synthetic photos is is
better in general okay so on a per
sample basis one fake synthetic image is
more valuable to your Downstream system
than one real
image okay so we're kind of in the plus
plus regime we're not in the in the
minus minus regime in this project okay
and so we want to understand why is that
like this is fake data should shouldn't
it be worse but one key thing is that we
actually intervened on one of those
control knobs to make the data more
useful to us and what this plot is
showing is the x-axis is how we set the
control knob so I'm not going to tell
you the technical details of this
control knob it's a knob that changes
the distribution that we're generating
it kind of Trades off between uh
diversity and realism and we can tune
that knob back and forth we can set it
to be low or set it to be high and what
this graph is showing is that by tuning
that knob for some settings on the y-
AIS is accuracy on for some settings the
synthetic data is worse than real data
and for other settings the synthetic
data is better than real data so the
synthetic data is just like data with
more opportunity and you can use that
opportunity to make it more useful than
real data or less useful than real data
but you have this control knob that can
intervene to make the distribution
different and that's where the power
comes in so we had to tune that variable
and if you don't tune that variable then
yes you do get this data minus minus you
get synthetic data that isn't as good as
the real data but you can intervene and
make it better that's that's the trick
okay
so so far what we showed in these
projects is that synthetic data on a per
sample basis can be more useful than
real data but there is a caveat which is
that these generative models are
themselves trained on massive massive
real data and where the rules of the
game so far are that we just are given a
generative model already trained that
cost has been paid up already we don't
have to worry about that what should we
do but what if we actually don't haven't
trained the generative model now we have
to make the choice should we train a
generative model or just directly use
our real data for the downstream task
can a data set X be U Can a model of a
data set X actually be more effective
than directly using X itself if we um
were making that choice okay this is a
harder question this is still somewhat
of an open question but I think we're
also now seeing some evidence that um
that this the answer can be yes to that
question so here here's a a followup
project to the stable rep project okay
so in the stable rep rep project we
compared these two paradigms the on the
top we have you have learning from data
you have um a data set of images that
are generated from a data set of text
prompts but it's real captions written
by humans that gener um that's the text
data and it's real photos downloaded
from the internet that are the the photo
data and you put those together and you
get one of these good computer vision
systems um in the stable rep project we
used actually a text image generative
model so we started with real captions
and we generated fake photos and we um
got on a per sample basis better
performance but if we actually take into
account the cost of having trained the
original generative model it was worse
performance so that was the caveat I
mentioned it's a little bit of a detail
but it is important uh but in this
project we said what if we replace the
real captions that generated the fake
images with fake C captions generated by
um chat gbt or a language model so now
the entire process is synthetic the
language is a generative model and the
images are a generative model and
putting those two things together now we
actually do see we're outperforming um
the state-of-the-art systems that are
trained directly on real data okay so
just by a little bit here but I think
this is the direction things are going
and if you you talk to people at openi
these big companies maybe some of you
have done this at your companies uh I
think synthetic data is part of you know
a lot of the actual pipelines in
production right now okay for example
the the uh the do 3 system is a little
bit old but it was trained um as an text
generation system that's trained on
synthetic captions so not so different
than this this idea
here okay um
so let me let me show one reason why why
this uh may have happened so we're
looking at
uh three different systems I'm going to
show three different ways of generating
um kind of classes for training a
computer vision system so the most
standard way to do it
uh 10 years ago was to label photos with
the object category so in this case all
of these golden retrievers would be
labeled Golden Retriever and you would
train your system to say these are
golden
retrievers okay but if I have a text to
image generative model now I can create
classes that are at a much more fine
granularity because I'm not saying all
golden retrievers are the same I'm going
to say I'm going to say all photos that
have the same caption that are generated
by the same caption are the same so this
is again something that's not easy to do
with real data because we don't have two
different photos with the same text
caption but with the generative model
which goes from text caption to photo
it's easy to make infinite photos that
all have the same text caption I just
run the generative model over and over
again on those text captions so because
the generative model has these
underlined text controls it allows you
to redefine the class grity in this
fashion and that's actually what we did
in this that that project I didn't get
through all the details but that's
actually what we did
and that's what allows us to get um this
other granularity that's uh finer
grained than just using labels to define
the classes and in the Sim clear and the
self-supervised stuff uh that that I I
mentioned that just uses two different
crops from the same image you're
essentially defining the classes in your
visual concepts the categorization and
vision that you're using is that every
image is its own class and it's too fine
grained so this intermediate level of um
of class granularity is the one that
actually works best and the numbers I'm
showing here are just kind of an Apples
to Apples comparison if you define the
classes in these three different ways uh
and you run everything else the same
then defining it with the two images
with the same caption or the same class
that's your granularity does the best
and that's a granularity that can really
only easily be achieved with generative
models
okay okay
so so moving right along so generative
models can be a good data source for
training they can be useful for doing
counterfactual reasoning at test time uh
these are a few different things they
can do here's here's one more uh which
is you can take a generative model of
your data and you can intervene on it
toward human preferences this is
probably the most popular way of
intervening on generative models it's
what led to chat GPT it was the big
thing that chat GPT did it um it's uh
related to this idea called
reinforcement learning from Human
feedback but let me show you what it
look what what you can do with images
intervenient in this way so what you can
do is you can take a generative model of
photos that has these underlying control
knobs and you can now take a a model of
human preferences so we have a human
that looks at these uh images and make
some Judgment of whether or not they're
beautiful or whether or not they've
fairly depicted reality um whether or
not they have kind of demographic parity
and how they're representing different
um occupations and genders and
demographic properties like this um
there's a lot of questions you could ask
a human that you might want to tune
toward you might want to get rid of
violent images so we can ask a human in
in the project that I'm showing here uh
we did this a few years ago and we
actually were interested in making
images that are more or less memorable
so so it's kind of a weird question but
it's fun so this photo is actually super
memorable you're all going to remember
this after the talk because in our
experiments from a long time ago we
found that this was the most memorable
photo like that on the whole internet
that we could find okay not the whole
internet but a section so you're going
to remember that photo and a human we
look at this and say it's memorable we
create a model of what a human would say
and then we'll just tune the knobs of an
image generator to make an image that's
super
memorable okay
so we'll start with this photo here and
we're going to now tune the knobs in the
direction that makes it more memorable
according to our model of memorability
and what happens is the dog face becomes
super zoomed in and kind of cute and the
eyes are bright and if you tune in
toward the knob that will make the image
very forgettable it become has artifacts
that the dog recedes into the background
it's kind of hard to make it out okay so
this is tuning a with with generative
data you can actually change it
intervene toward human preferences or
make it more memorable make it less
toxic make it whatever you want right uh
and this is the general Paradigm there's
a lot a lot of work that does this in
language models the most famous example
is chat gbt that's the difference
between chat gbt and the previous models
was they tuned it toward human
preferences and suddenly it talked to
you in a polite friendly way and it just
was a lot more fun um okay so generative
models provide data you can optimize you
can optimize over the generative process
because you have continuous control
variables you can actually do um
gradient descent and back propagation
through those controls that's like the
technical term
okay so generative models can provide
better data in in the sense of it being
bigger and continuous in the sense of it
having um control knobs in the sense of
it having optimizable controls that can
be tuned toward Comm preference uh in
the last section I want to talk about U
some applications to
robotics okay I'm going to switch to an
entirely different type of generative
model which is called a neural Radiance
field um and the way these work is you
take a set of photos of a room this is a
set of photos of one of the offices in
stata uh on the campus at MIT and from a
set of photos just about uh 60 photos of
this room you get a 3D model that you
can navigate through and it looks you
know photo realistic so it's like a
generative model and that you take
photos and you create something that can
sample more photos of that same place
but kind of fill in the gaps interpolate
it between all of the the missing
images okay so um here's a generative
model kind of picture of a neural
Radiance field and the way you can think
of it here is it's also Al a model with
control variables but now the control
variables are camera controls so you can
input into this generative model what
where is the camera going to be what at
what point do I put my camera and what
would I see if I put my camera there so
I'm going to put in the angle of the
camera and the location of the camera
and get out a picture of what I the
camera would have seen at that location
okay so as I tune and move around in
this latent variable space control knobs
I end up rotating the camera to see what
the image would look like like from
different angles okay so this is another
generative model that has taken the raw
photographic data and added these
control
variables and these control variables
are actually quite powerful uh you can
not only change the location of the
camera but you can also change the
camera's Optics so if any of you are you
know photographers or you know work on
um you know on Imaging or even just
hobbyist uh you'll know that there's a
lot of complicated Optics within the
lens system of a camera and the model
that we fit to these images can uh
synthesize what would it look like if I
changed those lenses okay so I can
change those those those lenses to
create uh what's called an orthographic
projection of the scene so an
orthographic projection is equivalent to
if I zoom in to Infinity if I take a
telephoto lens and I zoom into Infinity
I get an orthographic projection of the
world so it's not easy to achieve with
actual real Optics but with synthetic
Optics it's just you just change these
variables around it's just an equation
it's really simple okay so here's what a
photo of some mugs looks like from top
down with a regular camera but with an
orthographic camera like a telephoto
lens zoomed into Infinity it would look
like that and the model can hallucinate
this so the model can take my photos and
revisualization
orthographic projection makes things
much easier okay so if we have a robot
trying to manipulate some blocks on a
table perspective effects where the mug
shapes and the block shapes get all
distorted due to perspective they make
it very hard to for the robot to reason
about where things are but orthographic
projection is much simpler to work with
the math is just much simpler and uh for
example if I want to do operations on
the imagery you can often just do in 2D
in the 2D plane you don't have to reason
about 3D it can all be kind of done in
2D okay so orthographic makes certain
Vision algorithms especially for robotic
applications much easier people like to
use these like close to orthographic
cameras with robots but there's physical
limitations what you can do but with
synthetic data you can hallucinate what
it would look like if it were
orthographic and that works quite well
okay so this was just a project I'm only
going to show you the the result here
where the robot could pick up this kind
floss and put it into these different
containers and it improved uh despite
all the you know transparency and
Reflections because the orthographic um
synthetic data it was kind of
revisualization
of that that scene from the robot's
point of view and orthographic and what
you should see is that the orthographic
um shapes don't change as much undergo
rigid transformation as opposed to
distorting okay so in the last few
minutes I'm just going to um tell you
the basic recipe I've presented and a
few limitations so the basic recipe that
I think is quite powerful is first take
your data fit a Model A generative model
to your data second sample more and
better data from your model to get X
Prime it's like data Plus+ and third use
x Prime for your task rather than
original data this recipe shows up up in
a lot of pipelines right now and one way
to think about it is well you're taking
data and you're making better data so if
you're going to send that data to a data
processing system then it's kind of safe
like anything you can do with the
original data you can do with this this
new sample data uh if your new sample
data is truly better than your original
data um but it's not always going to be
the case that your generate data is
actually better than your original data
uh you know we all know that if you have
a bad generative model then it's going
to have art facts and if you have
applications where factuality really
matters where you know you need to know
who is the president today and the model
says the wrong person uh and you're
going to you know write some journalism
article about it that's just a problem
so hallucination and unfactual can can
matter sometimes okay so we're just a
few minutes left
um and another thing that's uh become
kind of a popular and interesting
critique is that if you train models
recursively on their own samples you can
potentially get drift and collapse of
these models uh so this is all to say
that generative models can produce good
data or bad data but we have some tools
for making them produce good data and if
they produce if you use those tools then
potentially you can you can get a
benefit okay so let's improved AI on the
data side let's make generative models
that produce better data than we started
with data Plus+ and I'll end there and
have a few minutes for questions
[Applause]
okay great so I think I can uh read the
questions and go from there okay so the
first question is uh the IDE is great uh
images are similar to the ones that are
available on the internet um but how
would this perform on Specialized
domains like x-rays MRI thermal images
yeah so you need to have a lot of
training data for your gender model and
we have a lot of training data for
random internet photos but we don't
necessarily for X-rays and MRIs um so if
I used a off-the-shelf generative model
as a data source for MRIs well that
wouldn't be appropriate because the
off-the-shelf models just don't know
what MRIs look like so what I would
recommend here is uh we need to make
good generative models good foundation
models for X-rays and MRIs and of course
there's legal and privacy and ethical um
constraints on this but I imagine this
could also be done like hospitals do
have a lot of data and potentially we
could make Big Data dat sets for that
purpose okay um next question synthetic
data Bears the bias of the models that
uh generated it what can you need to
control or prevent these biases what
these biases propagate to the end result
um yeah yeah this is a really important
Point uh so data sets have bias and we
should always be careful and aware of
that and generative models are no
exception so a generative model is a
system that produces data dat and it
might produce bias data but it's not
really fundamentally different in in
that sense from other data sets which
also are systems that can be used to
sample data and potentially um showcase
biases that we don't want uh but I think
there's a nice opportunity here which is
that you can because we have these knobs
and we can intervene and change our
synthetic data we can potentially debias
it and there's actually a lot of
interesting algorithms that do study
this they do try to take a generative
model and uh remove social biases that
we might not want or other types of
biases so we can say let's say that the
gener of model has made photos and it
shows uh images of doctors uh but it uh
we we potentially want it to show
occupations at kind of demographic
parity that might be one application
that we we care about for an
advertisement we want to show that you
know all different genders and races and
can be represented as doctors well with
real data we might not actually have
that distribution out there cuz
historically there have been biases but
with synthetic data we can manipulate
those knobs and create a world which is
different than reality and that could be
beneficial or it could be uh something
you don't want so it's it's a trade-off
yeah
okay uh so what real life applications
and sustainability in climate and life
science do I anticipate in this line of
research on synthetic
data yeah I think that's really
interesting um I'm not really involved
in that side of things too much but I do
have a collaborator uh Sarah beri who's
another professor at Mi it and she's
been using um we've been working
together on synthetic data for trying to
uh detect
rare uh bird types um so if I have some
unusual species or bird that I want to
identify in the forest I don't have
enough real data to train on but I could
potentially use a generative model to
create uh a lot of hallucinated images
of this bird and then create a better
detector for that rare bird type so
that's actually an application we're
even working on now
ask one more question uh it looks like
Philip just demonstrated or showcased
the how powerful gen generative model as
a data source for AI systems can you
also say more some words about other
different applications of just using
generative models yeah uh so right
generative models can be a great data
source for any data consuming algorithm
uh but maybe one other big class of data
algorithm is uh systems that are kind of
doing modelbased control so in robotics
we often will want to have a model of
the world that we can reason over to
decide what action will be optimal to
take like imagine you're controlling a
car and you want to have a model of
where the other cars are on the street
to know when you're going to turn your
wheel you have to have a model of the
velocity of the car and a model of the
you know the friction on the ground and
there is this kind of upand cominging
class class of generative models which
are called World models which actually
try to not only model text or 2D images
but model the entire physical dynamics
of the world around you and this kind of
generative model is going to find a lot
of application in robotics and control
where you actually need to know the the
physics and then all of these ideas I'm
talking about like counterfactual
reasoning show up there as well you say
you know what would I what would happen
if I steer my will really quickly to the
left and then you run your generative
model you know traditionally you run
your class physics simulator but in the
future you know you'll run your
generative physics engine and it will
predict what would happen and then you
decide should I actually take that
action if I'm going to crash I would not
take that action if that's my prediction
and if I'm not going to crash maybe I
would okay thank you