[Music]
how you doing today sir can I see you
like a registration please what was I
doing yeah speeding how'd you know I was
speeding you're looking a little tired
how long you been driving today maybe 2
hours where'd you come from New Jersey
how far away is New Jersey uh 170 miles
so 170 miles divided by 2 is 85 mph sir
isn't that a little fast okay you knew
my average speed was 85 but how do you
know there was an instant when I was
traveling at
85 sure simple math the mean value
theorem states that at one moment your
instantaneous speed is going to match
your average
speed you got
me for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow