So now let's switch over and talk about
how the data looks uh and uh the the
data object that you'll be um receiving
to work with. So two packages that will
be uh relevant for you um by way of
introduction are scanpie and data. Uh,
scanpie is a very commonly uh used
package in Python in the single cell
community
and data uh is a package within that
that is specifically um very useful for
uh dealing with these single cell gene
expression matrices and the associated
uh metadata that they might have such as
the pertubation uh identity that we've
been discussing.
And so here I've just provided um some
very kind of initial code that you might
want to use uh to import some of these
packages um and work with their
functions. And so going a little bit
more into uh the and data um package. So
um you will be able to use it to read in
uh the uh data that we'll provide to
you. uh so with this function scread h5
ad and uh if we actually then look at
what the resulting a data object is here
you can see that it's made up of
multiple objects but the two really key
ones in here are first of all uh this
green uh matrix x which you can access
uh by writing a data dox uh and so this
is the single cell uh expression matrix
um that you um will be familiar with by
now and that generated from the
perturbse experiments. Uh and the other
um particularly relevant object here is
this obs uh object which you can access
by uh a data obs. And this will give you
uh associated metadata for the cells uh
in the expression matrix. So we can see
um every row here is a cell and we can
see uh in the second column uh the
pertubation assignment. So again,
whether this was let's say MLXPL that
was knocked out um or another gene or a
non-targeting control
and there's another column that we'll
provide which will be uh the assignment
of cells um based on high expression of
certain uh programs. So uh for example
you can see uh a differentiated
adiposite program that um was high in
cells two and three and five. And so
diving into these objects a little bit
more uh we can see first of all uh this
just tells us the shape of the um a data
dox object. So the gene expression
matrix um which should correspond to the
number of uh observations i.e the cells
times the number of um v variables or
features which are the genes.
Uh we can also uh use this to show just
the first few uh cells and genes. to the
first five cells and genes uh expression
values uh in the a data.x matrix.
Similarly, we can use a data uh obsc
names to see uh the names of the first
five cells or the unique cell ids.
Uh and finally uh similarly we can write
a data.var var names to see uh the names
or the ids of uh the genes that are uh
again the first five uh columns in the
matrix.