Today our goal is to focus on the
curriculum which is probably one of the
most important reasons why you will be
thinking about MFIN. And now for all of
you you're at a stage where you're
probably in you know in your senior or
junior year in undergrad or you're
working and you've been you know been in
the market for a few years and you're
thinking about coming back to some of
the fundamentals about the program. um
or you're just curious do you you know
you're exploring an MBA we're thinking
about an MIN um so you're at the right
place to learn more about our curriculum
today obviously uh a master of finance
program is um is is an uh is a pathway
to your career success and as Diane
mentioned you know we just had a session
on careers specifically but we do know
that in the world of Master of Finance
there are several programs that one can
consider consider and we believe that we
have a very unique curriculum and I'm so
excited to share that with you. So let's
start with uh something that I'm really
passionate about. I I have been in MIT
um for almost 14 years now. I I was in
the industry before that and what truly
keeps me excited about the opportunities
of working at MIT is is truly this
mission that guides the work we do. We,
you know, all the four of us here who
are, uh, on the call today, uh, are
excited and invested in, um, you know,
shaping future leaders, yourselves, um,
in a way that is grounded in ethics, in
principled innovation, in advanced
thinking, and that's exciting to me and
our curriculum reflects that aspect of
it. So, Master of Finance is part of a
portfolio of programs that the MIT Sloan
uh school offers. And this is a actually
a really unique aspect of being in an
MIT class that your classmates are not
just folks who are from your own program
and in your age and stage group, but
from across uh different experience
levels, parts of the world. and it
really makes for a very dynamic
classroom experience which truly impacts
your learning education learning
opportunities here. So let's dive in
specifically to the Master of Finance
program. It is an 18month program that
starts in the summer uh and it has a
fall term, a spring term, a summer
internship and another fall term. So
that is typically the program. a handful
of folks go into the 12-month program
and we can talk a little bit about what
that is. Essentially, the degree
requirements are exactly the same. It's
just a much more compressed period of
time and it's well suited for students
who either have a job or are sponsored
or are very focused on what they're
trying to get out of their master of
finance. What I love about our
curriculum is that it it has a very
strong core that stands the test of
time. you know it was built by professor
Merton and professor low and you know um
stalwarts in the field who understand
that in order to have a master's degree
in finance there are some fundamental
principles and things about the markets
and tools you need to know but the
markets will keep evolving and um what
you need to know to be successful in
those markets um will be something that
we will teach through the electives. So
the beauty of our program is it's a
strong core that is not flexible but the
electives are and the pathways you can
create out of the program are
customizable tailored to your career
interests and that is extremely unique.
The most fundamental difference about an
MIT education is I would say this whole
notion of applying what you're learning.
It's it's um part of our ethos. It's
part of our um moto mens and manos which
means the mind and hand. And so action
learning or applicationbased
um coursework is something that is very
essential and is a required part of the
MIN experience. We also have some
interesting optional concentrations. uh
you can think of it as some kind of a
major maybe uh where you can drill down
on certain areas of finance that you
want to uh develop more specialized
skills and knowledge in. Um it's also
good to as a signaling tool for your
career purpose. Um and so we have five
of those. capital markets, corporate
finance, um social impact and climate
finance, financial engineering and a new
one that we introduced on fintech. So
that's kind of the summary at a high
level on the curricular side. That's
what we are focusing on today. Now
I can jump into um some of these I can
go through each and every single
concentration but I won't do that. So uh
you know I talked about the fintech
being a new concentration
um and uh you know so every
concentration is comprises of some
finance courses that you would like to
take or you would be required to take
and then a bunch of electives that are
not just finance but gives you much more
interdisciplinary way of thinking. So um
fintech for example there is a course
that we want all students to take which
is on consumer finance and fintech but
then you have these different
opportunities um to take courses from
VCs from financial engineering you can
go more advanced um you know analytics
and machine learning u new enterprises
is a fantastic course taught by our
Martin trust center for entrepreneurship
you typically will find a lot of MBAs
taking this course um fintech venture is
product design. Again, in product
design, you will actually see these are
mostly digital products that people look
uh working on, but you will also see
people from other uh degree programs
like you know um product uh from um sort
of undergrad from uh PhD students as
well. So it's very exciting to to be in
this sort of interdisciplinary space
where you are focusing on something you
are developing advanced skill sets but
you're also getting to take classes from
across Sloan courses as well as a
courses across MIT. So let's look at
another one. Um financial engineering
you know we have a very significant
number sometimes half the class is uh
looking at financial engineering
and uh we've got a very robust selection
of courses. This is uh starting with
your core right. I mean even in the core
we teach two um we have two coursework.
One in finance financial mathematics and
the other one in financial um analytics
and uh you're there are two versions of
that. There is a regular version and an
advanced version. If you are someone who
wants to pursue financial engineering,
maybe you're thinking about hedge funds,
quadrant trading, prop shops, you know,
as your future careers or even asset
management, investment management. Um I
often see our students uh venture into
the financial engineering world. Uh so
you would be taking these kind of
courses and then again there are um you
know as you see there are very advanced
finance electives for you to choose from
and then um you can take courses beyond
that. The machine learning and AI
courses listed over here. Some of them
are taught within uh by our finance
faculty. Some are taught at Sloan level
and then there are some that are you are
taking courses at computer science and
electrical engineering or at physics or
math and some uh you know a glimpse of
those courses are listed over here. So
it's really exciting uh opportunity for
you to develop capabilities um not only
through core and fundamental courses but
newer applicationbased courses
projectbased courses and then sitting in
classrooms where you're working with
MBAs and PhDs and then uh you know
undergrads and graduate students from
across the campus very vibrant
so um I'm not going to go through every
single concentration because you you
know there's there's climate a there's
climate action work that u our students
do there is you know corporate finance
uh but what I wanted to highlight about
students who uh you know are interested
in climate and sustainable finance is
again not only are they taking these
finance courses but they get the
opportunity to work with energy
initiatives at MIT um that particular
course or with the energy market
dynamics in a decarbonizing economy. I
think most likely this is a course that
is uh offered uh from one of the
engineering side of the campus. So it's
exa it's exciting that you can be in
this environment where you're learning
finance, you're learning tools, you're
learning how to think about business
problems, organizational problems and
then go as deep and quant as you want on
certain topics. Uh so that's just
fascinating.
So I thought what I'll do um because I
definitely want to go uh into questions
that you may have. Um but before we jump
into all the questions um let me give
you some an actual taste of what
students have done in the past because
that helps to understand and relate to
this whole gamut of coursework. Um
incidentally I mean I uh you know we we
did a study once to look at how many
possible electives or variety of
electives have our students taken and
it's um
from across 800 electives and and again
I I'll caveat that by saying there's not
800 electives in finance absolutely not
um but you know you're at MIT so if you
you know want to take a class in fluid
dynamics u you can do that so you know
And that's not going to be the whole um
listing of your coursework, but if
you're curious about something and if
you just want to take a couple of
courses outside of sort of the finance
and related fields, you're absolutely
welcome to do that. So, let's dive in
and see. Uh so, this is let me think uh
let's go back to that. Yeah. So, this
particular student I'm trying to
remember. Okay. So this student um you
know is as comes from an engineering
background and uh his goal was if I
remember him correctly his goal was and
he is um working in a quant research um
capacity in an asset management company
right now. and he had he had a very
solid engineering background and he
wanted to kind of maximize as much
finance as he can uh do um in his two
years over here. In fact, if I remember
some of our conversations, he said, you
know, he was actually working in the
industry for a couple of years and his
goal for coming back to doing a master
of finance was actually to strengthen
his knowledge in finance fundamentals
and core and knowledge of markets
because he said I felt that if I really
want to commit to a career in this
field, I want to I want to strengthen my
understanding uh of finance. So
the courses you see listed over here are
not core courses. Core courses everyone
has to take. So here are some additional
courses that he took, some electives
that he took. Uh one the first one that
he took in the first fall it's uh about
understanding financial statements and
the other one is about making uh
decisions
and you know he's right now in an asset
management company. So obviously there's
a lot of kind of that strategic thinking
when you're using quant research into
asset allocation. Uh and then he did
finance lab. He did a phenomenal finance
lab project. He took uh the advanced
finance uh courses. He obviously took
asset management. You know any uh
investor is obviously going to learn a
little bit about crypto and blockchain.
And so he took the crypto course some
derivatives not surprisingly being a
good investor you you want to learn
about uh global economics and the
implications of that. So that's how he
kind of designed his coursework and an
interesting course that he took you'll
see corporations at crossroads. This is
something he took in his second fall
when he came back from his internship
and he said you know um this is a course
where uh senior leaders some seale
executives a lot of CEOs uh uh come to
the class and it's a close class
actually taught by our senior leadership
at MIT and uh the these these executives
discuss with students what difficulties
what what um real challenges they faced
at certain junctions of their career and
how they thought through that
decision-making. So again, this is a
really well-rounded
uh portfolio of courses where a student
with an engineering background, very
strong quants is pursuing a quantrol
right now really wanted to um strengthen
his understanding of finance and global
economics. Let's look at another co
another student.
Um this is a student who uh had a
certain amount of quant background but
not as much as the previous person we
were talking about. And so one of the
things you will notice is uh that this
student um they took a little bit more
coursework in
fun like economics uh decision-m
um programming uh if I remember this
person correctly um this person had a
very strong background in economics and
statistics but hadn't done enough
programming. So they actually took one
of the uh intro courses that computer
science department offers to sort of um
strengthen that aspect of um their um
programming skill sets. And again you'll
see the student also took a course of
leading in ambiguity. So what's exciting
is that our students absolutely focus on
the fundamentals. they develop some
extremely strong quantitative uh skill
sets. Um but they also don't do that in
the absence of the context in which
they're going to be uh you know working
in. So all of them we train our students
to think about not just your first job,
not just that you know I'm going to make
this crazy model and um just geek out on
it. Of course you can do that. But the
idea is how can you actually become a
finance leader in the future and you
know start thinking about some of the
more macro aspects uh of running an
organization while also studying the
depth of quantitative finance.
Do we have another example Rachel? Uh
probably not. So maybe at this point um
Katie, would you like to tell the
students about sort of the arc of how
this experience goes? I know that you
advise hundreds of MFN students and
you're probably more suited to talk a
little bit about that arc of that
experience. Yes, thank you so much. So
um as you will notice here, first and
foremost, we have a summer start. This
is really what sets the EMIN program
apart and sets our students up for
success by getting ahead of the game uh
in the summer term. This is an
accelerated abbreviated summer term that
takes place during July through August.
Uh that sets the foundation for your
learning at Sloan and more largely at
MIT. During the summer term, you will be
enrolled in um four courses which are
part of your mandatory core in the
program. And these courses will lay the
groundwork for more advanced studies and
those that you can tailor later on in
the program. After the summer term in
the fall, you will continue some of your
core studies with financial markets,
corporate finance, ethics, which is a
half-term course, and analytics. Here
you have the options for advanced or
regular analytics. Also during this
time, some students begin their action
learning uh requirement with a
proseminar or take electives. Following
that, this is when students really start
to dive in and curate their studies to
their specific career. They do this
through the type of action learning
requirements that they enroll in and the
projects that they're ultimately
assigned to as well as their restricted
electives and the more large electives
that they take at Sloan across MIT or
even crossregister for at Harvard.
This allows students to pursue a
concentration if they like, enroll in a
certificate program, or just deepen
their studies in an area that might be
suited for them in terms of their
recruiting for an internship or a
full-time position. So, uh, our unique
period um during January is part of AP,
which is independent activities period.
This is when, uh, our very popular
finance lab runs. Um, and then it goes
into the spring term, which runs from
February through May. After May,
students in our 18-month program, uh,
pursue their internships, and then
return in the fall for their final term.
At this time, this is when students in
the 18-month program would complete a
communications requirement, which is
really tailored to finance careers and
communicating the data and the
day-to-day work that you are doing. um
as well as finishing up their elective
studies and any additional
concentration, certificate or other
opportunities such as a thesis
independent study they may be pursuing.
Um students in the 18-month program
finish their studies in December and are
conferred in February and welcome back
to celebrate in um May or June of the
following year.
>> Thank you, Kitty. Thank you so much. And
all of this amazing experiences is
taught by our world-class faculty uh
comprising Nobel laureates, global
experts, practitioners in the field. um
you know the one of one of the new
courses in AI research in applications
AI and um research and um finance has
been launched by Hu Chen and Dennet
Kogan who's our faculty director as you
can see and again just fantastic courses
uh you know there were several questions
around how we stay on top of uh the
trends and how we evolve our curriculum
it's one of my favorite questions
questions uh to get because I love to
boast about how our courses keep
changing every year. You know, we have
this course list uh that um you know,
you're going to see on our on our
website and while the co core remains uh
sort of more or less the same in terms
of the coursework, the content changes,
but new courses are constantly added. Um
we've had you know four new courses in
AI and um this year that have been added
in sort of the intersections of AI and
finance in different ways and you know
one of them is being taught it's called
AI and money and it's being taught by
professor Gary Gensler who was the
former um chair of the SEC and his the
way he's thinking about the course is
how the presence of AI uh and its
influence on financial markets uh
requires you to develop more critical
thinking capabilities. On the other
hand, Professor Kogan and Professor Chen
has introduced an AI and machine
learning research course in um in in
finance where you're literally learning
how to model various types of uh you
know financial phenomenon and risks
using AI. So for example, there's a
course uh there's a you know team that
is looking at political risk and
volatility. There is a and sorry
political risk and firm valuation. there
is a team that is looking at uh trading
volume and uh volatility alpha you you
know so from very quant um applications
of AI to critical thinking uh using AI
uh it's just so exciting that our
coursework keeps changing and as you
know the fundamental aspect as I was
talking about is is um action learning
it's you know you have these amazing
courses that allow allow the students to
take the classroom learning in across
public and private markets into real
world projects um that you can do
throughout the year. So that's just so
phenomenal. So with that um Diane, is it
back to you and then we can pick up some
questions.
Yes, it is busy answering some of those
questions. That's great. Thank you all
for all these great questions that are
coming in. um we are working very hard
to get to all of them. Um but I know
that um for many of you hopefully this
has inspired you even further in hearing
about the amazing courses and and
learnings that you'll be able to get our
faculty all the the you know academic
resources that are also provided to our
students both one-on-one as well as
collectively. There are many
opportunities for you to really sit down
and say have you know these are this is
my plan these are the skills or the gaps
where I really think for me to be able
to launch a career in finance is going
to make sense um and to have those
conversations you know with Hermy's team
um is really an an important part an
aspect of what we offer in addition to
of course our um career services and
those adviserss. So, in terms of the
application, I'm just going to quickly
go over this because, uh, this is all
available online. The application is
live. Um, first and foremost, let me
just say that, um, you can apply to
multiple programs at MIT. Uh, there's
absolutely no negative inference if you
choose to do so. Um, the other thing I
will mention is we do not have rolling
admissions. So, as you can see, the
deadline to apply is the 5th of January
2026. And that's for anyone who's
planning or intends to enroll in July of
2026. Um, we as a policy in terms of a
standard, you should only be applying if
you intend to enroll next year. That's
something that um is really important to
think about. If you're not ready, that's
fine. then you may want to wait um until
a time such that you feel more
comfortable and ready to to take on the
Master of Finance program. Um it goes by
so quickly. Um and as you can see from
everything that you've heard from Ermy
and Katie, it is um really chock full of
lots of information and skills that
you're going to need to get through. So
in terms of the application components,
and these are not listed in any
particular order other than just
alphabetically. So every component of
our application is important. Um it's a
little bit of a cliche but our our
admissions process is very holistic. We
are looking at everything. And I will
also say that upfront if you look at our
class profile which is available online
and and perhaps Rachel um will be able
to put the link in that um in the chat
in the Q&A for you to be able to see it.
Um they come from multiple disciplines
and backgrounds. uh to quote one of our
faculty, uh you don't necessarily need
to come with a lot of finance coursework
um as an undergrad um or in if you've
already earned a master's degree or
advanced degree. We can teach you
finance. What we're really seeking are
individuals who have the academic
strength, the problem solving and
analytical skills, um who have a passion
and understanding of what it might be
like to pursue the field of finance. um
this isn't a pre-professional or early
career program. Many of our students are
coming directly from um university. So
you'll see all that information is
available on our website. These are all
the application components. So obviously
we're going to be looking at academic
transcripts, looking at what courses you
take and are some of those courses um
more, you know, substantive and
quantitative in nature. uh it you know
it could be from many different
disciplines engineering physics um other
sciences or other coursework that you've
done econometrics
uh we are you know offering if you'd
like to submit the GMAT or GRE they are
acceptable uh but they are optional so
it's really your decision and your call
if you believe that that uh providing
those test scores are really going to um
help to us on the admissions committee
to get a better sense of your academic
strength and then we are looking for
three letters of recommendation. Um,
this is all detailed out in the
application itself. We're looking for
two academic and one professional,
meaning, you know, presumably you've had
some internship experience, so a more
recent internship. We're also looking
for relevant coursework on, you know,
the MIN program is a deep dive into
quantitative finance. a lot of the
essential foundations in work such as
you know mathematics and we again we ask
about this in the application whether
that be calculus statistics probability
these are all really ways to help you to
be able to thrive in the program um
given all the financial modeling and the
stochastic processes and vector analyses
and all the different um aspects of the
program that you're going to be working
on. So, we are looking at some specific
coursework. Uh, you may be uh able to do
some of that online if you haven't been
able to do that as part of your um
undergraduate or graduate studies and
that's perfectly acceptable. And then if
you have any professional
certifications, um we're happy to see
those as well. A resume, very specific
um instructions on what that should look
like and how to um put that in place. Uh
as well as some short answer questions.
You'll see all of that. Um, some of them
are just, you know, a little bit more
about you. And then we have a couple of
video questions. Um, I would say, you
know, one is a way for you to introduce
yourself to your future classmates and
for them to get to know who you are a
little bit better as well as the
admissions committee. And then there'll
be one um question that's a purely
randomized
uh what I would call general interest
non-technical question um that will be
um a timed one. Uh but again this is all
part of as I said all of these
components uh are really important and
part of helping us to understand who you
are why you're applying to the Master of
Finance program uh and hopefully to
demonstrate that you'll be able to
thrive at MIT.
Okay. So how are we doing on questions?
I'm going to actually stop. This is the
general um email um that you can send
certainly send questions. I believe we
also have a specific one for MIN which
is on our website. Um and maybe Rachel
if you can just put that one in the um
chat or Q&A because I know there's a
specific MIF admissions email that you
can send to us. And then again, if you
want to scan this QR code to join us at
an upcoming event, both virtual or in
person, um please go ahead and do that.
All of this information around
admissions is all available on our
website and in the application. So I am
going to stop sharing my slides and um
lean to into our um other folks here
Rachel Katie others. Are there any
questions in particular that we want to
answer live um for that be of interest
in terms of the curriculum?
Let's see.
Okay.
>> Hi Diane. Yes, I'm happy to share from
both the questions that came up today as
well as questions that were submitted
prior to the session. Uh there were
several questions around concentrations
if you must do one. Um and if you can
pursue more than one. So I just want to
clarify that concentrations are
optional. Yes, more than half of our
students do end up pursuing at least one
concentration
um specifically because these are to
help you position yourself within the
job market and show how you've tailored
your studies um specifically to your
desired career path. However, they are
not mandatory and yes, you can choose
more than one. Uh I think in recent
years, we've had some students do as
many as three concentrations. All this
requires is your flexibility and
dedication and working closely with your
program advisor.
Okay, great. Um, someone is asking about
venture. He's interested or she is
interested in venture capital
postgraduation. Any suggestions on
concentration in the program um for
following that career path?
>> Yeah. Um so you know before I answer
that question I I I want to just uh you
know piggyback on what uh Katie just
mentioned. The concentrations and the
design of the program in general the MIN
program the design of the program in
general is to help you support your
pathway uh and as as long as it's
related to finance and related spaces.
Uh so we are not dis you know we have
done a study about our our curriculum
looked at other curriculums and what's
very exciting and unique is that we have
a whole span of coursework and our
students going in a whole array of
careers um that span from the highly
quantitative rigorous mathematical work
to the behavioral finance and economics
and sort of um you know the consumer
aspects of finance as well. So it's it's
uh we have students who go into
investment banking and private equity
and venture capital. We've got folks who
go into traditional um you know
financial fields like asset management,
investment management, those who go into
prop shops, quant trading, quant
research. Um we also have people who are
looking into fintech opportunities from
being in product design to actually
fintech in you know ventures um real
estate. We have a couple of folks who go
into real estate as well. So really it's
when you think about why should I come
to MIT think of do you have a passion
and an interest in finance that you want
to explore? Do you want to strengthen
your qu skills while also expanding your
uh world view? Do you want to strengthen
your network? Do you want to be a part
of an institute like MIT where you know
not just take courses within a business
school but within an engineering school
and a and a science school. So it's it's
that holistic way of thinking is what
makes it so exciting and our adviserss
like Katie and others will help you sort
of cater and design a pathway that makes
you successful. So your question, one of
the questions was on um you know venture
capital. Absolutely. We've had uh I will
say that VC um as a field is hired to is
is tougher to break into straight out of
an Min because they don't hire a lot of
people in general. Um but you can start
your um journey here. We have fantastic
courses uh that are specifically VC
focused actually but also in general the
fintech concentration uh is a phenomenal
concentration to be part of because you
also build your cohort of likeminded
peers um and then you can be part of the
VC club at MIT Sloan and and take other
coursework at our Martin Trust Center
which helps you not only develop the
understanding of finance but
understanding of early stage ventures uh
and how to kind of help them scale, how
to help them um build their momentum.
And so it's it's really an exciting
field to be in. We do have a couple
people going into VCs every year,
>> right?
>> What else Diane?
>> So we have another question about in
addition to the core modules for the
18-month program, how many electives can
you take? I know this is always a what
what's the the course load that anyone
can really take? Um and from different
concentrations even. So as I mean I'm
going to punt this question to Katie but
I will just say this everything is
dependent on your goal your career goal
your academic learning goal and how you
want to and how much other stuff is
going on in your life. Are you someone
who has a job already and therefore you
know uh you have uh more time to take
even more rigorous coursework. you know
it's really a balance of many things and
at what point of time you know sometimes
we have people taking less coursework in
their first fall besides the core
courses uh and then you see the second
fall they're taking a lot of courses in
spring but Katie any specific sort of
average you see when you're when you're
advising your students
>> yeah I would say you know the summer is
lock set for you so um that's really the
only term that uh we enroll you and you
have a set number of courses after that
it's totally up to you, your goals, and
um your ability. So, I would say on
average in the first fall term, we see
students take four to five classes uh
and then they only increase from there
typically. Uh, of course, for students
in the 12-month program, that's much
higher. In terms of the degree
requirements, so you have restricted
electives. We ask you to take at least
four of these. If you are pursuing a
concentration, you will likely take more
than four, usually around six. Um,
however, beyond that, you are able to
enroll in any Sloan courses, uh, MIT
courses. So, it's very common to see
students, as my mentioned, taking higher
level economics, finance, computer
science courses, um, as well as
crossregistering. Many students choose
to in future terms, be it spring or
second fall, crossregister at Harvard.
um they often do so for leadership
courses, maybe some niche negotiation
courses to supplement their finance
studies as they think towards long-term
management roles as they progress. Um I
think one of the many benefits of the
program is this ability to understand
what your recruiting cycle looks like,
supplement that with classes that really
matter in real time. So, what do you
need at this point in time in recruiting
and what will you need for your future
internship or job and tailor your
schedule to that?
>> Thank you, Kitty. Um um you know, you
mentioned the negotiation class, which I
think is really important for me to
mention. Um we have every year a good
handful of students going into
investment banking and for those
students you know they are taking
obviously corporate finance advanced
corporate finance they're taking um you
know valuation courses but they're also
encouraged and many of them take courses
in negotiations in law in organizational
management um in decision- making. So,
you know, these are all very, you know,
interesting ways of thinking about
expanding your skill set, not just in
from a quantitative perspective, but a
holistic perspective, an
interdicciplinary perspective. Um, and
while I'm on the topic of investment
banking, I I you know, you're going to
hear me say this many, many times, but
if you are interested in pursuing an
investment banking internship, you must
be looking into those opportunities by,
you know, early um in during winter. Uh,
so January, February are often the
deadlines. And so this is this catches
our students surprise. It's basically
even before we've given decisions about
EMIN. So just please track that on your
own. That is extremely important. We
don't control the market. Diet.
>> Yeah. Um no great. So we did have I know
I think are we running short on time
here? So I want to make sure there's a
lot of questions about the application.
Can I just um say to all of you um we
have many um info sessions that are
already um posted recordings of them
about that are more specific to the
application and admissions process.
encourage you to take a look at those.
We will have an application tips webinar
coming up in another month and a half.
Um so definitely stay tuned for more
information. The application really is a
great resource. Um we have a lot of
details and instructions and it's very
you know for the most part should be
pretty clear about what we're looking
for um and what's required. So please
just read through those. But we are here
to help. Please email that Empress.
If we don't get to some of your
application questions today, I want to
take the time that we have with me and
Katie to really focus on um more of the
the core of the curriculum itself. So I
think maybe as a closing question uh
there is one about what are the common
traits you see among the most successful
students in the program.
Um, thank you for asking that and and
I'm sure Diane will say more in future
sessions, but but honestly curiosity.
Um, you if you are coming to MIT,
uh, we're looking for someone who's
really curious to expand their
worldview, expand the way they think,
uh, to somebody who's who's excited to
participate in a community and build a
network. Um, if your only goal is to get
a job, I wouldn't say this is the right
place for you. You will get a job.
That's not the point. But that's a very
narrow way of thinking about the MIN
experience. The Master of Finance at MIT
is is a very holistic experience and you
can go as deep as you want academically
and build incredible proficiencies in
tools, markets, knowledge that you
didn't have before, but you're going to
make the best use of it if you want to
build a network. If you want to uh if
you're curious, if you want to hear
about talks uh that are happening in
different parts of the campus that
really expand the way you think um
because the what we see is the people
who make a difference in the market uh
after graduating from our program are
the people who are able to be original
thinkers, problem solvers with the tools
of finance but they go beyond uh the
call of duty and that's what we are
trying to look for as we look at your um
you know as we look at your uh
applications. Um I know that was
supposed to be the last question but
there I did see a lot of uh questions
around in the past around sort of give
us some examples of some you know action
learning work that we do or applied work
we do. So I'll just give one example or
two example just to help you understand
how expansive your uh you know worldview
can become you know uh fin example or
the research course um they allow
students to work both in private and
public markets you know one AI based
application that our students are
working on is to identify how political
risk influences firm valuation you know
that's one work they're doing it's a
research paper that you're working with
three or four faculty members. There's a
team working on that. There's another
team that is looking at the inclusion of
gold, crypto, um commodities, real
estate in um and how that is enhancing
asset allocation. Um you know, uh
they're trying to hedge against
inflation. They're trying to reduce
portfolio volatility. They're looking at
long-term growth. So, that's a very
different type of uh an application that
folks are looking at. There's another
team that is um that worked on um
long-term you know sustainable housing.
So uh and then of course there's a whole
bunch of folks who are working on pitch
decks, valuation models. So it's really
a very exciting vibrant place where you
learn
with amazing like-minded peers but then
you go into a world where you have so
many people from different backgrounds,
different parts of the world taking
classes with you. uh you you have very
foundational courses, very advanced
courses, critical thinking courses,
teamwork, um a place that is passionate
about problem solving and about making
the world a better place. That's what's
MIT about. And so you have to be excited
about that vision and and come here for
that purpose.