so uh looking at the presentation it
seems like this may be more
computationally focused uh talk so just
quickly how many people here have heard
of quantum computers and know okay and H
how many of you all know about like what
they can do what what algorithms they
target okay very cool so just quickly
what what are these machines these
machines are new kinds of computers that
harness the power of quantum mechanics
okay this this is the same quantum
mechanics that governs uh the particles
at microscopic scale okay and these
particles could be atoms and molecules
the systems you see in biology and
partly when you go and you try to
simulate those systems using short injur
equation you require exponentially large
computational resources so the same
thing that makes it hard for you to
simulate those quantum mechanics systems
comes for free in quantum computers
which is why uh at a high level
intuition this is the reason why you
could expect exponential advantage in
simulating these Quantum systems using
quantum computers right so now that you
all are experts in Quantum Computing let
me tell you more about what we do so we
have a One-Stop platform that you can
use to get access to these all the
quantum software and Quantum Hardware
that's available in the market so we
work with over 50% of the quantum
Computing companies and make uh their
software and Hardware available in one
location okay and uh you can access at
at this point there's not a single
architecture that is a winner for
Quantum Computing you have whole bunch
of whole sorts of quantum computers uh
being made out of the super conducting
circuits you have atoms being used as
cubits you have crapped ions being used
so all of those are available for you to
test your Quantum algorithms uh and the
way we work with uh the various
different stakeholders is for the
Enterprise world we provide them uh
support for Quantum algorithms so if you
are an end user company will work with
you to come up with algorithms for your
specific use case so this is where we we
provide extra support but overall the
the platforms built for and uh anyone
who wants to use these machines and
write their algorithms we also work with
quantum computer uh Computing companies
to launch their software and Hardware on
your computer so it's sort of like a
Marketplace a single player place where
you can get access to all the different
Quantum algorithms specific to and the
these are some of our uh clients and
companies and partners who who we work
with specifically I would like to talk
uh to this audience about what quantum
computers can do for the biotech world
for the past year or so we've been
looking at this specific problem of beta
ameloid that you heard today about and
the the idea there is you have this beta
ameloid uh molecule and it's been widely
accepted for at least past 20 years it
interacts with metal ions and it it
leads to formation of these plaques so
the pathophysiology of this reaction is
actually not very well understood as to
where do these metal ions go and
interact with what active sites on these
beta ameloid molecules which lead to
these plaque formation right so if we
could understand this reaction maybe
there's an there might be an easier way
to uh develop drugs for for targeting
that active side and uh thereby uh
allowing not allowing the the clumps to
form right and so uh this again you
probably already heard you you already
know it over hundred billion dollars
have spent in on Research understanding
Alzheimer's and Parkinson's with
relatively low progress and even this
amalo beta hypo hypothesis has been
brought under the question and so our
our job is like let let's look at it
from physics point of view to understand
whether um you you these protein
molecules interact with certain metal
ions and these lead to clumps so either
uh answer would be very cool and
actually NIH has spent two to 300
million dollars on just computational
studies and it comes back to you do
require exponentially uh large number of
computation resources and this is sort
of the problem that you can probably
address much faster using quantum
computers and the reason you have uh
even machine learning models fail is
because machine learning models need
need data and data has to come from
these quantum mechanical simulations so
if you can't even perform those
simulation where aren't you going to get
your data or you need Quantum sensors
which again you may know they aren't
ubiquitous or you don't have Quantum
sensors available in your body so which
is where machine learning models tend to
fail as well so here's the the pipeline
we've been working on when we have a
full functioning pipeline available here
what we do here is you have uh sort of
this protein molecule uh and you you you
what you do is you you fragmented into
smaller pieces and you recognize the
piece that has some strongly interacting
metal line ions and these are transition
uh Metals which are known to be hard uh
for classical algorithms so those are
the algorithms you you send it to a
Quantum pipeline the classical tractable
ones you you you can simulate using
classical molecules sorry classical uh
computers and so again what we do is we
have further fragmentation techniques
which are quantum in nature that run on
a quantum computers and so once you do
that um you have like good answers for
the algorithm and so uh quickly the the
state of the field right now where
quantum computers are at the hardware
needs to catch up it's been making
tremendous progress over the F past five
years but it's still not there where it
can run uh these large calculations so
what we've come out with this Innovative
pipeline to use the current generation
hardware and run these simulations it's
sort of like if I got uh maybe instead
of 10,000 Nvidia gpus what if I had 1
million gpus right so but you only have
few thou 10 to 100,000 gpus so your
algorithm Innovation comes in place it's
the same idea our algorithm Innovation
enables you to use current generation of
hardware and to get the best answers and
this is where we're at and quickly we've
got our whole bunch of data which I'm
not sure it's going to make oops what
happened
oops there you go so here the major
place where you should pay attention to
is we reduce these numbers 27 10 ra to 9
to 10 what that means is the circuit
depth the amount of calculation you had
to do on a quantum computer went from 10
raised to per 9 to just 10 the number of
cubits you required for uh a certain
simulation went from 27 to uh just four
and this is sort of the Innovation we've
done over the past year that would
enable you to Target uh large molecules
and I'm happy to tell you much more
about uh all the achievements we've had
and similarly you can see the numbers
here you have 65,000 going to 2500 so
again uh I imagine like because these
may be foreign numbers to you but the
idea is we've had some really cool
couple of orders of magnitude
Improvement in algorithm development
where you can Target many of the complex
systems uh in the coming years and with
with these things you can probably uh so
when can you use quantum computers in
your pipeline definitely before your
next clinical trial finishes so all
right that's my talk thank you thank
you just a quick ask we are actually
looking for uh companies who would like
to test this Pipeline and we're happy to
Pro work with you yeah