[Music]
so now I want to talk to you about the
Technologies we can use to measure gene
expression and gene expression programs
in single cells so we'd really like to
know what genes are being turned on in
each of these t- cell States so we have
this really uh amazing experimental
technology where we can take a group of
te- cells and apply a technology called
single cell RNA sequencing and read out
for every single cell what genes are
being expressed and to what levels
they're being
expressed so the output of the Single
Cell RNA sequencing experiment is this
gene expression Matrix where we've
measured the expression level of every
single Gene in every single cell and so
the rows of this Matrix are the
individual genes and there are 20,000
genes encoded in the human genome so
there's 20,000 rows in this Matrix and
the columns are the individual single
cells that we profiled so there's 50,000
columns because there were ,000 T cells
measured in this experiment now the
actual values in The Matrix are the
expression levels of the individual
genes inside a single cell so here we
can look at tcf7 and what this value
means three means that there are three
rnas that were counted from the gene
tcf7 in cell one but only zero RNA
molecules counted from tcf7 in cell
three and likewise we can look at the
Gene gzma and we find that there are
zero counts of RNA molecules in cell one
but three counts of RNA molecules from
gzma in cell
3 so once we have this gene expression
Matrix we can actually start clustering
cells together based on the Sim their
similarities in what genes they're
expressing so for instance we can see
cells one and two are similar to one
another because they both Express tcf7
and Bach 2 at high levels and they have
lower levels of all these other genes
likewise cells 3 and four Express prf1
in enzyme a gzma at high levels but they
have lower levels of all these genes and
finally cells five and six have high
expression levels of pdcd1 and
EES but they have lower levels of
expression of all these other genes here
and by clustering cells by their
similarities in the genes that they're
expressing we can actually identify the
programs and the cell States so if you
remember tcf7 and Bach 2 they Mark the
progenitor t- cell state in prf1 and
gzma mark the effector t- cell State and
finally pdcd1 and EES Mark the terminal
exhausted T cell state so from this data
we can really learn what the gene
expression programs are and remember
we're not just measuring two genes at a
time we're measuring all 20,000 genes
that could potentially be expressed in a
single cell so that's kind of the the
the output of a single cell RNA
sequencing experiment and we'll discuss
how this works momentarily but then the
other technology we'll discuss is um how
do we measure the effects of genetic
perturbations in single cells so why do
we want to do this so ultimately we want
to take t- cells in modify them in some
way make a perturbation in some way to
make them better at killing tumors
killing cancer cells because right now
te cells and cancer normally enter this
exhausted State this terminal exhausted
State and are unable to kill the cancer
so we really want Technologies to
measure the effects of perturbations in
te- cells so here's the t- cell
differentiation pathway we've seen
before and in this example we're just
going to change one gene this Gene
called to and we're going to delete it
from the t- cell and in general tox
deletion um strengthens the anti-tumor
te cell response so deleting this tox
Gene favors the progenitor te- cell
States and the effector t- cell States
over the terminal exhausted t- cell
state so we're going to introduce this
perturbation into the t- cells let the
cancers grow up in in the context of a
tumor and isolate the te- cells and then
do this technology called perturb seek
and we're going to Define perturb seek
in the later slides so the output of the
perturb seek experiment is again a gene
expression Matrix where we have all the
genes that are measured across the
single cells but we're also able to
detect the presence of the tox deletion
inside the single cells and the tox
deletion acts by affecting the
expression of many other genes and that
is going to shift the distribution of
the t- cell states to favor the
progenitor State and the affector state
and so now if we look at the gene
expression Matrix we still see uh the
genes that Mark progenitor t- cells and
affector t- cells but the genes that
Mark the terminal exhausted T Cell
states such as pdcd1 and EES their
expression level is close to zero and
that's because again this tox Gene is
affecting many genes and it's affecting
the distribution of the t- cell States
and so we no longer really are observing
the terminal exhausted t- cell state
after making the tox uh genetic deletion
these technologies have really taken off
in the last decade or so uh so what
we're looking at here are different uh
single cell RNA sequencing profiling
Technologies and these are uh on the
xais are the dates in which the studies
were published and the Technologies were
first demonstrated and on the Y AIS are
the number of cells that were profiled
in that uh by that technology and what
you'll notice actually is that the y-
axis is on the log scale so in 2009 the
first single cell RNA sequencing
experiment was performed this was on a
mouse Blaster mirror which is a four
cell stage embryo and that was the first
experiment done single cells and then
now or you know 5 years ago in 2017 we
reached the level where in a single
experiment we could profile 1 million
single cells so what this means is for 1
million single cells we could quantify
the expression level of all the 20,000
genes in those single cells so this is
really amazing growth and it's really
led to a revolution in many fields in
biology and it's also impacting our
studies of cancer immunology and cancer
immunotherapy so now let's talk about
how the Single Cell RNA sequencing
experiment really works so we always
start with a piece of tissue so in this
case it could be a tumor like melanoma
and that tissue gets taken out of the
patient and then the tissue is made up
of individual cells that are kind of
working together and communicating in
the context of that tissue environment
we take that tissue and we dissociate it
into the individual single cells and now
once the single cells are isolated we
want to extract their RNA and the RNA is
what tells us which genes are being
expressed in the cell and so by looking
at what RNA is inside the Single Cell we
can identify gene expression programs
and the cell states of these t- cells
that we extracted uh from the solid
tissue so I next want to give you an
overview of how we isolate the single
cells in the Single Cell RNA sequencing
experiment and label uh the transcripts
now this is really amazing and really
cool technology but the exact details of
how it works are not critical for your
ability to perform in this data science
challenge so let's get going so what
happens our single cells are isolated in
water droplets using microlitic Chambers
so this is a blow up of a microfluidic
chamber the cells are flown into the
chamber and they get encapsulated in
these droplets and you'll notice within
each droplet there's also these colored
beads and these colored beads are going
to help label the transcript from the
single cell and it will tell us which uh
cell that transcript came from so
remember trans scripts are just the RNA
that's being transcribed from the Gene
and now all these RNA molecules in these
single cells get labeled with different
barcode which is really like a a
different DNA sequence and here we have
cells labeled with a purple barcode a
blue barcode and a red barcode and now
when we read out those transcripts using
sequencing in the next slide we'll know
which cell each transcript came from and
so now let's go back to this earlier
cartoon I just explained to you how
single cells are isolated using
microfluidic and we're a to label the
RNA and then we take this RNA and we
actually reverse the process of
transcription so if you remember from
the introductory uh materials uh DNA is
transcribed or copied into RNA we can
actually reverse that process and make a
complimentary piece of DNA and we do
this because DNA is much more stable and
we can also make many copies of DNA and
which is useful because then what we're
going to do is sequence all those DNA
molecules that were dered from the RNA
and sequencing is literally just a
process of reading out the a c's and G's
that are going to Define that DNA and
once we have those sequences we can
actually identify What gene that
sequence came from because the entire
Human Genome uh was sequenced and we
know the sequence of all individual
genes so when we have a DNA sequence we
can look up What gene does it match to
in the human genome and that will tell
us that okay tcf7 was found in this cell
and pdcd1 was found in this other cell
and that's literally just by sequencing
out uh the DNA that comes from this
experiment and matching it against the
human genome and so the final outcome
then are these big gene expression
matrices and let's look at them in a
little more detail so to remind you
again the rows of this gene expression
Matrix are the genes and there's 20,000
genes we could measure and the columns
are the individual cells and here in
this experiment we've measured 70,000
cells and then the values are how much
each gene was expressed in every single
cell so tcf7 expressed level three in
cell one gzma expressed level zero in
cell one but level three in cell three
and so forth so what you notice as well
in this Matrix is that there are many
Zer actually and this is not a surprise
because um there are many biological
reasons why a gene would be at level
zero in a Cell so remember all our cells
are defined by gene expression programs
and these gene expression programs don't
include all 20,000 genes they include
tens to hundreds of genes these gene
expression programs Define what the cell
is doing and all the other genes are
really not needed for what the cell
needs to do in the tissue context and so
they don't get expressed on purpose so
the level zero here is for a biological
reason however the zeros also can arise
from technical reasons because it's very
hard to actually capture all the RNA
that comes from a single cell so you can
imagine a single cell is very very small
it's on the order of 10 microns or so
and the rnas there's many of them and
being able to capture all of them is
difficult so sometimes you just fail to
capture the RNA and you get a zero in
that Matrix so once we have this gene
expression Matrix now we start to do
computational analysis to identify the
cell states that we're finding in this
experiment and there are several um
steps in the computational analysis
starting from quality control and
normalization of the data and then
feature ction dimensionality reduction
and clustering and so we're going to
walk through each of these steps so you
understand you know how we go from the
Gen expression Matrix to actually
identifying the cell states that are
there the gene expression programs and
learning you know what we actually see
in in the sample that we're profiling so
the first step in our single cell RNA
sequencing analysis is quality control
and the idea here is we want to remove
low quality data that we don't want to
work with and here I've ordered um all
the single cells by the number of genes
were detected in that cell and the
maximum for this AIS is 20,000 because
that's the number of genes in the human
genome so the cells are ordered by the
number of detected genes and you'll see
there are two taals to the distribution
and we uh focus on those two tails so
this tail here where a low number of
genes are being detected is often uh
found due to low quality cells that have
been damaged in the sequencing process
and so we remove those from analysis and
then this other tail here is often found
because the same single cells are
actually still stuck to one another when
they go into the droplet and so it's not
really a single cell we're looking at
but multiple cells and so we also remove
those from the downstream analysis after
that after we perform quality control we
then normalize the data so um uh why do
we normalize the data so if we look at
the total gene expression in a Cell we
find that that value often varies for
technical reasons and the total gene
expression in a Cell uh is just taking
the cell and looking at all the genes
that are expressed in that cell and
summing up all those values to get the
total level of gene expression in that
cell and we find that that total varies
quite a lot across cells and this is
often for technical reasons and if we
don't correct for this technical effect
this is a confounding factor in a lot of
our Downstream analysis so we end up
what we end up doing is for every cell
we normalize the total gene expression
so now the total gene expression is just
going to sum to one and then what we do
is we multiply all of that by 10,000 so
now this total expression sums to 10,000
we add one and take the logarithm and
this is a standard kind of approach
that's done in a lot of these uh
sequencing studies and the reason we're
going to be adding one is if you
remember a lot of these gene expression
values are zero so if you take the
logarithm of zero you know that's bad so
we add one to avoid doing
that so now we've done the normalization
we move on to uh the feature selection
step so I first want to start with this
cartoon of cells in this sort of
threedimensional space where the axes
are the expression levels how much each
gene is found inside those cells so we
have Gene one gene two and Gene three
and there's a group of cells here here
and here and they're kind of all in
these different kind of clusters where
you know these cells have hydrogene one
and two these have hyene one and three
and these have hyene two and three so
this is an understandable way to look at
cells and their gene expression however
unfortunately fortunately depending on
how you look at it cells actually exist
in 20,000 dimensional space where they
don't just Express three genes they
could express up to 20,000 genes so this
would be very hard to imagine like
humans cannot visualize higher
dimensional spaces however this is
really the dimensional this is really
the space in which the cells are
existing and so this is hard to
visualize it's also hard to work with
from a machine learning perspective it's
hard to Cluster things that are in very
high dimensional space
so what we do is we do feature selection
where we only focus on those genes or
features that have highly variable
expression across the cells and the idea
here is that genes that are variable in
expression are genes that are going to
explain the cell states that we're
seeing so let's think about a gene whose
expression level is the same across all
the cells we're seeing so that's not
going to help us differentiate a
progenitor t- cell from a terminally
exhausted T Cell because the Gene's
expression level is the same across
those States however if a gene is
variable meaning its expression is high
in one cell State and low in other cell
States that's actually informative about
what differentiates the cell States so
for instance you remember the TCF Gene
is highly expressed in the progenitor t-
cells but lowly expressed in the
terminally exhausted t- cells so that's
an example of a gene with variable
expression across the cells and so what
we do is we take these 20,000 genes and
we select the 2,000 to 5,000 most highly
variable genes and that's our feature
selection step and so at this point
we've gone from describing our data with
20,000 genes or features to 2,000 to
5,000 so this is a reduction in the
dimensionality of the data and now we
can go even further with that so now
let's pretend or we can imagine that our
cells are in 5,000 dimensional space
after this feature selection and we want
to go even lower and we're actually
powered to do this because let's return
to the idea of our gene expression
programs so remember in the gene
expression programs you have groups of
genes that are turned on or off together
so if I have a gene expression program
that defin say the progenitor te- cells
if I tell you that you know um tcf7 is
high in these te- cells that actually
tells me a lot about all the other genes
that are are in that gene expression
program because they're turned on
together so knowing the expression level
of one gene actually tells me a lot
about many other genes that are being
expressed in that cell and so because of
that uh genes are really not independent
of one another measuring one gene can
tell you about many other genes and this
is really the key that allows us to go
to even lower dimensionality spaces when
describing our data and so uh a really
common technique is this linear
dimensionality reduction technique
principal component analysis or PCA um
and this allows us to move from
describing cells with 5,000 genes to uh
this new space where cells are described
with 10 to 100 principal component
scores where these principal components
are really reflecting the different gene
expression programs within the cells so
at this point now we've gone from 5,000
dimensional space to about 10 to 100
dimensions and this is a lot easier to
work with when it comes to clustering to
identify the T Cell
States so uh the last step in the
analysis is we've done this
dimensionality reduction using principal
components analysis and now we're going
to do graph based clustering so we're in
the principal component space and we're
going to calculate the distance between
every pairs of cells uh this is the
ukian distance between cell one and two
cell one and three and so forth for
every possible pairs of cells and then
we're going to use that distance Matrix
to build a k nearest neighbors graph so
here are the individual cells in sort of
this lower dimensional space that we've
moved into and we're going to ask for
every cell who are my K nearest
neighbors and we're going to build that
graph so for instance this cell the
nearest neighbors are here here and here
and we do that for every single cell and
we build that graph and now once we have
that graph we start to Cluster in that
graph space and you can already by I you
know where would you draw the Clusters
you would probably draw a cluster here
because there's a lot of connections
between these cells a cluster here and a
cluster here and there are many
clustering approaches out there uh one
of the most common clustering algorithms
is the lien algorithm and this is a
algorithm to detect communities within
graphs and this algorithm works by um
optimizing a metric called modularity
and so we do lien clustering and we
identify three clusters in this toy
example okay so at this point uh I've
gone over with you all the steps in a
typical single cell RNA sequencing
analysis we started with quality control
and normalization and then we went to
feature selection dimensionality
reduction and this graph based
clustering and now let's apply
everything we've learned to the actual
data that's in the data science
Challenge and so this is data collected
by um The Physician scientist Mark
Schwarz and uh near hakohen at the bro
and Dana Farber Cancer Institute and in
the challenge we have te- cells that
have been collected from mice with
melanoma and we're showing all the t-
cells in this plot here and this is
what's called a umap embedding and the
umap embedding is a visualization
approach to take high-dimensional data
which is existing in this High
dimensional space and showing it in a
nice two-dimensional plot and so the
umap embedding is calculated from those
principal component scores that we
introduced in the previous slides and
the idea with the umap embedding is it's
trying to preserve local distance uh
similarities so if two cells are similar
to one another in the high dimensional
space and by similar to one another I
mean that they have similar genes being
expressed so if they're similar in the
higher dimensional space then we want
them to be close to one another when we
visualize them in two Dimensions so what
this means is like these two blue dots
here that are really close to one
another in the high dimensional space
they were close to one another and so
when we plot them in two Dimensions we
want them to also be close to one
another so this is a separate embedding
that gets calculated and you can read
more about it here and it's calculated
from the principal components and then
we take that embedding of all the T
cells and now we color the t- cells by
uh the identity of the Clusters that we
learned in the previous slide so
remember in the previous slide we
identified about three clusters here we
have um e clusters and they're all
colored uh differently and uh what we
see is that there's this really strong
clustering in the data where these t-
cells look like they're one cluster and
these t- cells look like they another
cluster and this is really what's going
to lead us to identifying what the te
cells are doing so the idea is that te
cells in this cluster are having one set
of gene expression programs that's
distinct from t- cells in this cluster
over here and so to get at that uh we
start to look look at what genes are
being expressed in each of these cells
so remember every single cell here in
theory we have up to 20,000 genes
measured so we can take cells in one
cluster and ask what genes are more
highly expressed in this cluster
relative to all the other clusters so
for instance if we take the progenitor
t- cells in this um kind of brownish
orange color we can ask what genes are
more highly expressed and so what we
would see or what we do see in the
actual data is the gene tcf7 is higher
in this cluster relative to all the
other clusters and that Clues Us in that
this t- cell cluster is actually
reflecting the progenitor t- cell State
and we can label it progenitor likewise
if we go over to this cluster of t-
cells over here and we look at what
genes are more highly expressed meaning
they're higher levels than all the other
clusters we see the gene pdcd1 coming up
and remember this is a gene that marks
the terminal exhausted t- cell state so
by doing this game for every single
cluster we can actually annotate every
cluster and say what T Cell State uh
these cells belong to and what's really
beautiful is that we see all the t- cell
states that we would expect to see in
the context of a cancer in this case
melanoma so we see those progenitor t-
cells we see the uh affector t- cells we
see the terminal exhausted t- cells and
we see the cycling T cells so um at this
point you know now you have an
understanding of how single cell RNA
sequencing works and how we can take a
population of cells measure the gene
expression program within the single
cells and with some analysis identify
the gene expression programs and the
length cell States for those single
cells so the next problem that we really
want to solve is what happens when we do
genetic perturbations uh to the te-
cells and how does that affect the gene
expression programs and again the reason
we care about this is because currently
uh regular te- cells enter this
exhausted State and are unable to kill
the tumor so we really need to make some
change to the te- cell to enable it to
better kill the tumor to kill cancer
cells so what we would like are
technologies that allow us to test
perturbations in cells and see what
happens uh to the gene expression of
those cells and the resulting cell
States
[Music]