well now that we've all turned in our
proposals for repertories for uh for the
second problem set I want to go through
some of the problems that arise even in
uh Western notation and even in
classical music that raise interesting
questions for representation so we're
looking at a Piano Trio this by clar
Schuman and it might look like there's
not too many problems to represent but
we'll get back to it a little bit and
look a little bit deeper here's a little
piece from Don Giovani by Mozart and you
can see it's not a highquality scan but
there's still uh interesting things here
this is not actually Don Giovani this is
a piano reduction so we have the singer
Donna alira and all the orchestra
reduced to two staves here is uh the
similar uh passage the same passage
actually with uh different language we
have Italian and English before and now
Italian and German but where we have the
full orchestral score out and how do we
represent the differences and the
connections between these two
scores this is already a difficult
problem that hasn't been fully solved
but wait till we try to represent oh how
do the manuscript parts for various
pieces uh
relate when we go into the 20th century
and 21st centuries there are even more
complex problems this is a late score by
osinsky which is actually pretty uh
standard in many ways in that uh it uses
notes and things but the um the clefts
if they continue into the next staff
they're continued with lines and
probably most obviously when an
instrument doesn't play its part is it's
staff is
removed or something like this this is
from one of my scores when I was in
college where the stabs staves are
removed where people don't play but also
at various points the representation the
distances between notes are not given
with standard note heads but are given
with uh with time durations and some of
the some of the notes such as the these
here that are accelerating aren't given
in ex exact uh they're they're not given
exactly between a quarter an eighth note
or 64th note but some Continuum in
between a lot of the greatest music
being written today such as this piece
by Kate soer uh uses extended um
notational techniques so here we have
filled in circles representing uh closed
mouth and we have open mouth signal
signals and we have uh symbols for pure
speech and the violin part you might see
actually uh isn't in trouble cluff but
it's in percussion cluff with four lines
each one representing just to play on
that string these are the notes these
are the strings to be playing
on there are many pieces such as this
piece by Brian fer how
AAL that that require us to have
notational formats that uh that go again
beyond what we might think of as com
common notation but only push it a
little bit further such as uh early on
here we have a triplet in the place of
21 over 20 in the place of 74 or at the
end we have a measure whose time
signature denominator is not a power of
two how do we represent such
things we don't have to get into 20th
and 21st Century Music to run into
problems like this here is another path
message from Mozart D Giovani where
there are three different orchestras
playing on stage and in the pit and they
are in three different time signatures
representing the different classes of
people whose dances would be represented
in different tempos in 38 24 and
34 measures do not necessarily line up
how do we even count measures in
something like
this in other wise seemingly normal
passage by DBC we have this moment and I
thank Donald bird for pointing this out
where we actually have two different CS
active simultaneously on the same staff
how does this get
represented if we go back to the clar
shiman example with which we began we
can see that there are actually certain
things that are extremely difficult to
represent why is this rest here but
there's no rests before what part of the
measure does this mean well it's kind of
obvious this voice is moving up to here
but how is that obvious for a computer
or what parts exactly are these notes
that cross staves part of um how do we
represent cross staff beaming how do we
represent some of these U the time that
would actually be used in a Grace
note and when we go earlier in time
there are problems that expand even
further this is a only a little bit
different from common western music
notation in this uh example from I
believe the 16 no from the 17th century
um of church music but we are using
different symbols for for different
notes and not not having leaving out one
layer of the open
Notes when we go very far back in time
uh such as in this I believe 9th century
uh chant manuscript from the opening of
the mass for Christmas uh we have
symbols that just tell us the direction
that notes go not their exact pitch do
we want to be able to encode things such
as
this here is a beautiful manuscript from
the beginning of the 15th century in the
shape of a heart because the composer's
name b cordier core means heart and do
we want to represent the graphical
layout of the original score let alone
these notes that are in uh red or other
uh unusual
formats and here's another example from
the same time period where the harps
strings become the staff lines but the
notes only appear on the staff lines
therefore all of the notation is sort of
expanded into double
size what we want to do with this what
do we want to do with a piece such as
Cornelius cardu Trea where notational
symbols are used to give inspiration to
the performers to the singers and how to
perform this there is a score but every
performance is
different here is another score for Earl
Brown folio from December of
1952 how do we interpret this how do we
store the interpretations of this piece
I already mentioned in class that
non-western music and popular
music have their own difficulties as
well have their own problems and
interesting points as does Machine music
electronic music or in this case a piano
player role where exact precise
differences distances between notes can
be encoded so I hope that this gives
some sense of some of the rich variety
of representation and I'm looking
forward to seeing how your
representations end up