Hello everyone, welcome and thank you
for joining MIT Startup Exchange
Lightning Talks. My name is Ireina Gazva
and I'm a program coordinator with MIT
Startup Exchange. Shortly you will hear
from two exciting MIT connected
startups, Altaatada and Tinfoil. Both
are active participants in our program
offering bold new solutions to secure
data collaborations and encrypted
computation. I hope you'll be inspired
and take the chance to engage with the
startups during the Q&A and afterwards.
And if something you hear sparks your
interest, feel free to reach out to me
or your program director to explore
potential collaborations.
And this is just one of the examples of
how our program helps connect industry
leaders with MIT connected startups. Let
me tell you about our program. MIT
Startup Exchange was created 10 years
ago to support MIT connected startups in
growing, expanding and solving the
world's greatest challenges. We do this
by fostering partnerships and
collaborations with LP members like many
of you in the audience today and as well
as an extensive MIT innovation ecosystem
and beyond.
Our startups are have a strong
connection to MIT. Many of them have
founders or co-founders who are MIT alum
faculty or staff while others have
licensed technology from MIT. Some of
our startups are also vetted and
supported by our MIT peers such as the
engine start. Nano or CEL startup
connect plus we have about 800 startups
in our program who join who typically
join at a pilot stage or beyond and may
cover any sector or geography.
So what is the value for you and our
startups? Well, startups in our program
gain exposure to a global network of
industry leaders while our corporate
members have access to a curated
selection of MIT startups. We host local
and international events including
conferences, webinars, demo days, all of
which could can be tailored to your to
address your priorities. We also
facilitate one-on-one meetings between
startups and corporate members. A key
feature of startup exchange is that we
help members to find solutions to their
industry challenges. We do that through
targeted startup calls known as
opportunities. Startups can apply, get
selected and collaborate with members to
test and co-develop the solutions.
Overall, startup exchange has a highly
curated and customized approach. We know
that some of you are already taking
advantage of these benefits and if not
please feel free to reach out to me and
our team. And with that, let's turn to
our startups. Each speaker will have
five minutes followed by one minute Q&A.
So I ask you please use the Q&A tab at
the bottom of your screen to post your
questions. Hope you enjoy the
presentations.