Thank you. Um we're harvest AI we do
crop prediction and beyond. Uh we do
that on the basis of computer vision and
machine learning. Uh currently for
commercial indoor farming operations
that is uh both uh traditional green
houses and vertical farms.
Why are we doing this? Um, indoor
farming um has been uh growing
exponentially um uh in part uh to a
number of um uh macro effects including
the impact of climate change on
traditional agriculture, urbanization
and fears uh by a number of countries
about disruptions in supply chains uh
especially since COVID and hence um uh
problems with food security.
Uh the sector has experienced a number
of uh of problems despite this demand.
Rising opex uh market pressures
especially supermarkets squeezing
margins um and a lot of untapped
potential of the of the data that modern
green houses spit out uh but that are
currently unused through any form of AI.
Um we are um going into that by
providing what uh indoor farmers uh
demand the most according to our
customer discovery that we did with MIT
3 years ago. Namely, we're providing
them with an insight into when they can
expect to harvest how much, which is for
them crucial uh for a number of
operational reasons, including, you
know, what sort of um for for their
labor planning, for example, but also
for example to align harvests with sales
uh so that um what they've harvested
doesn't rot between uh the point of
harvest and the point of sale. As
mentioned, we're doing that on the basis
of machine learning and computer vision.
This is illustrating these two strands
if you will. Uh modern green houses um
already provide a lot of these data
automatically uh that we that we need
for our for our machine learning
component. These are data around CO2
content uh about temperature about
humidity and so forth. Uh we uh we
provide in addition to that um uh
further accuracy through uh through
computer vision where we're essentially
tracking changes in the size, color or
shape of tomatoes, peppers, cucumbers
and other fruit and vegetables that we
cover and provide extremely accurate
forecasts on that basis.
This is an illustration of how computer
vision works in our case. um uh here for
the case of tomatoes and changes that as
you can see uh in the in the colors and
and and sizes of tomatoes being used for
highly accurate prediction.
This has led to unrivaled forecasting
accuracy the leading uh uh forecast uh
technology in the industry. we can
forecast when you will will be able to
harvest how much uh with 96% accuracy um
and have done so with a number of of the
major players in the in the indoor
farming industry uh worldwide so far
for our ask um we're first showing here
that we've uh built our MVP and entered
the market in Europe um we've then uh
recently conducted a product expansion
where we've successfully applied our
forecasts But then gone beyond that and
now enable for example indoor farmers to
not only understand when they will be
able to harvest how much but we also
enable them to influence that. So if you
see a forecast that you don't like
because it's the day after Christmas or
it's on Thanksgiving day we tell you uh
how much you need to change your inputs
in order to have exactly the time and
amount of harvest that you'd like. And
on that that basis we're now
internationalizing. We've gone into a
number of European countries and even
recently arrived in the US um at
Greentown Labs.
Um we are for our indoor farming
operations particular uh seeking
partners uh that are interested in
helping us scale internationally and uh
secondly those that feel that that they
have a technology that we can integrate
with. So to give you an example, we're
currently integrating with a number of
players in the indoor farming technology
industry including uh those who provide
AIless and predictionless softwares for
for farming or indoor farming. We're
also integrating with harvest robots uh
and a number of other technologies um
that are already available in the
market. We've also recently conducted a
study with PWC on where else our
technology could be applied. And it
turns out that for example, seed
producers are highly interested in our
ability to accurately uh show what
ripeness stage a certain type of fruit
or vegetable is currently at. And
supermarkets are interested in
understanding how far what they
currently have on the shelves is from
rotting and therefore needs to be
reduced 50% in price today. If you have
similar ideas and would would like to
engage uh with us on uh any of these
applications of our technology to your
industry, we'd be extremely interested
uh to talk.