Welcome everyone. Uh, it's my pleasure
to introduce our robotics seminar
speaker today, Professor Caitlyn Becker.
Kate is an assistant professor at our
mechanical engineering department here
at MIT, uh, where she leads the
fabrication integrated design lab. She
works in the area of soft robotics with
a focus on creating gentle and adaptive
soft robots through new design and
fabrication methodologies. The soft
gripper that she has developed can
operate in the deep sea and it has been
deployed at a depth of 3.5 kilometer to
sample fragile ocean species. Her work
is quite popular. They are featured in
top journals such as PNAS uh advanced
functional material soft robotics etc.
and in particular has been featured in
the American Museum of Natural History.
Kate is a recipient of multiple awards
such as the Robosoft Rising Star award
and the Roose and Joe Spear teaching
award. Today uh Kate is going to talk to
us about mechanical programming of soft
robots via fabrication
uh integrated design. Um Kate, we look
forward to your talk. Floor is yours.
>> Beautiful. Can everybody hear me? Okay.
Wonderful. Uh well, thank you for the
introduction. Thank you every for
everybody for being here on a Friday
afternoon. I really appreciate it. I'm
excited to be here myself. Um so
just a little bit of context about me
before I start. Um you've heard a little
bit, but um I'm actually coming from the
Mechy department as an undergrad and I'm
a manufacturing and design engineer. So
I worked in medical device manufacturing
and then nanop fabrication before I then
joined Rob Wood's micro robotics lab. So
you'll see some of that color how I look
at soft robotics and navigate those
spaces. Um my lab actually has two
tracks in parallel. I'm only going to
talk about soft robots today, but we
also work on additive manufacturing with
molten glass. So both of those I see
sitting at the intersection of machine
design and manufacturing both using
unconventional materials. So squishy
robots and masonry made out of glass.
Um, I really couldn't have done the work
today without uh a lot of the students
in my lab. This isn't everybody that we
have and there's a few people on here
actually who have just graduated which
is bittersweet but it's a huge thanks to
them that were able to kind of show you
this today. Um, whether it's soft
robots, rigid systems or soft rigid
hybrids. So to explain a little bit
about what I was thinking of starting
with when I say what I mean by
mechanical programming. Um you could
interpret that as embodied intelligence.
You could inter uh interpret that as
intelligent mechanical design
potentially. But um here are three
examples of what I mean that are going
to show up a little bit later. And I
guess what I mean is to design a soft
robot you're affecting the form as a way
of getting function. And so in that way
you're mechanically programming it
through the structure and through the
fabrication process. So on the lefth
hand example um we have a gripper that
takes a single high low square wave and
converts that to a sequenced output
through kind of three integrated
actuators and a little valve. And then
in the middle section here, we've got a
gripper that upon inflation will coil
around that SE whip, but then is limited
specifically to not apply more than 2
psi of contact pressure. On the right
hand side, I have a robot that's
completely open loop, but the mechanical
programming comes in its compliant
structure so that it can adapt passively
to the objects that are picking it up.
So, I've both kind of mechanically
programmed it in the fabrication
process, but it's almost like I'm
mechanically programming a little bit
with the assistance of the objects that
we're picking up.
And then I suppose not everybody in the
room is a soft roboticist. So, I thought
I should motivate kind of why we care
about soft robots. And so, I'm going to
start with two applications that are
either motivating or near and dear to
me. And then I'm going to move to kind
of how we can't quite serve those
applications and how that's motivating
the rest of my talk. So, I would say um
for those for the general audience,
Baymax is kind of the platonic ideal of
a soft robot. If you haven't seen Big
Hero 6 from Disney, it's very cute. I
recommend it. But essentially, it's a
big nurse robot that's very adaptive,
very capable, and resilient. And to me,
this kind of draws a parallel to the
first application of soft robotics that
caught my eye that interested me, which
is in uh assisted devices and
rehabilitation devices. I know, for
example, Professor Sada has done some
work in that area. Um, but thinking
about how we interact between soft
machines and organic soft machines,
there's a lot of complex motion in your
hands, that's difficult to create from
rigid systems. But if you have actuators
that are compliant, they can naturally
conform to a lot of variation in hands
and help patients that either need to
regain the ability to use their hands or
maybe to augment their limited strength.
So, I asked ChatGBT kind of what they
thought a assistive robot would look
like helping a physical therapist. And
believe it or not, it's less creepy than
what I came up with. Um, so in my
envisioning of assisting physical
therapists, I thought, ah, yes, I have
grippers and I will pick them up like
the squishy creatures in the sea. Um and
it will extend our touch so that when a
caregiver can't then reach their patient
they have this kind of extended virtual
but also physical touch. Um now working
with professor Sada and some uh key kind
of stakeholders we then realized that
okay much more acceptable would be if
we're side by side with patients um
whether that's remotely operated or
maybe kind of assisting physical
therapists in the same room. And so this
was from a visit to Spalding
Rehabilitation Hospital actually with
one of Professor Assatada's students.
This is Ravi. He's working with uh Dr.
Kathy Pila and going through some upper
extremity exercises that they might
habitually do. We then tried these back
in our lab. And so I have we have a
Sawyer robot applying a soft gripper to
Daniel who doesn't look super enthused
but at least not terrified.
Um, and I would say even just having the
payload to pick up an arm is sometimes a
big ask for a soft robot. And then what
I'll come back to is whether we can do
that reliably as well. On the flip side,
I actually focus more on deep sea
biological sampling, which is something
I started in my PhD with Rob Wood. and
to motivate kind of the criticality. I
think you can guess that we don't want
unreliable robots around people and we
don't want we want robots to be gentle
around people. But for some of these
deep sea creatures, well, all of them,
they're animals and if you stress them
out, it actually changes their DNA
expression. So, it's quite important
actually to be gentle when you're
picking them up. Even if you're later
going to stress them out bringing them
to the surface, you have to apply RNA
freeze while being gentle to them. In
addition to that, running one of those
vessels is actually on the order of
$50,000 a day. I wouldn't be the only
researcher on the boat. But that means
that when we deploy a remote operated
vehicle with a squishy gripper like this
attached, it takes three hours to go
down to depth. Maybe we're at depth for
3 days. And if I pop a leak in one of
these, they're not going to turn the
boat around for me. I've lost probably
three days of testing at 50k a day and
I'm only really at sea for a week. So
that's a huge loss. and a necessity to
then be more reliable. Um, but what we
like about the robots though is if we
can get them to last at depth, they're
actually really able to be gentle while
withstanding thousands of pounds of
hydrostatic pressure. Also, the
corrosive salinity that often eats up a
lot of the more rigid uh prototypes.
So I would say I don't know if any how
many of you are familiar with the field
of soft robotics but it doesn't have the
reputation for being durable reliable or
strong and I would say that that's a
limitation of design and manufacturing
specifically I think we need to come up
with a framework for soft machine design
and manufacturing now in that process we
have centuries of work in traditional
rigid machine design that we should be
leveraging there's a lot of work in
what's compliant machine design that we
should be leveraging, but at some point
we should also kind of move away from
that. And if you look about at how we
build rigid robots,
well, translating that to soft robots,
you can't bolt,
glue, or weld parts together. You can,
but then you should anticipate some
delamination and failure. Okay. So the
other thing is the way we teach hardware
design at least in this campus as I
experienced was to start with rigid
materials and small deformations. But if
you're using compliant materials for
your robots, part of what you want is to
really emphasize large deformations as a
way to get interesting fun and useful
functionality. Okay, so you get your
engineers to say, "Great, big
deformation's good."
But then how do you actually move past
the point that in Solid Works or Fusion
360 that a lot of us use to design
robots, those tools are designed to
design rigid systems and fabricate rigid
systems. The primitives are based on
turning and milling.
So I think as we mature in this field,
we're at a point where to get to greater
impact accessibility and by
accessibility I mean like how many
people could actually have a software
robot operating in their home? How many
of those can you reliably make at scale
and how many of those would be
commercially viable to get there? Well,
one thing that we've been employing and
we need to do is geometric and material
optimization. And that's necessary but
not sufficient. I would say that soft
robots are also going to need soft
machine specific design and
manufacturing frameworks. I would also
argue if you integrate the two of those,
you get much more efficacy than if
you're doing more what we call design
for manufacturing traditionally where
you're more focused on taking a design
and then tweaking it for one
manufacturing method and then usually
focused on operational efficiency or
cost.
If you then do a cross-pollination of
the two, I think you can get a lot
further. This is honestly a kind of
communitywide effort, a
multi-disiplinary effort, but it's
something that my lab is pushing. And
with that, I'm going to go kind of
focusing this on kind of what
functionalities we want to start with
from deep sea biological sampling. I've
talked about them some already, but so
you know what this looks like.
Basically, I'm on a ship like this. This
is the Nautilus. That's Bob Ballard's
boat that operates two ROVs. one of
which is Hercules on the right here. And
then when I show you a video, that's
mostly going to be from this bubble cam.
So, a lot of times you only have one
camera that you're watching uh a view
through and you're using a titanium
craft arm like this. So, an example of
what this looks like, these are some
videos that Noah gave me uh when we were
asking for particularly challenging
grasps that they have to deal with. And
some of the things that they struggle
with is moving targets. You got to be
gentle to the moving targets. if you're
not gentle, they do stop moving.
And then these are really clear videos,
but a lot of times we struggle with
limited vision, whether it's shadows or
marine snow
and compliant and complex shapes. So, a
having a hard time figuring out kind of
what pose would be best, but also when
you grab something, a lot of times it
bends and or breaks apart and falls
through the gripper.
Not great when you're on live broadcast.
I'll save this one as a surprise for
later. Anyway, so uh with Kevin
Galloway, uh we deployed the first
insitue deep sea biological samples uh
sampling from soft robots. On the left
here, that's 300 meters underwater in
the Red Sea. And then on the right is
one of my later prototypes that's gone
down, as Kevin said, 3,500 meters and
has been on tour recently, but
previously in the American Museum of
Natural History. And so from the get-go,
we're fairly successful with soft robots
because they're compliant and can start
to adapt to some of these squishy
creatures. And so, of course, um, and I
think, uh, I didn't mention before, in
addition to being compliant, um, and
being able to withstand the hydrostatic
pressure. I didn't mention this, they're
inert to the salinity. And the fun part
about this is that we can actually use
salt water as our hydraulic fluid. So,
if we spring a leak, we're just leaking
salt water back into the ocean.
And of course
the old adage goes if it ain't fixed if
it ain't broke you should definitely fix
it more. So how I will fix it more is
with fabrication integrated design first
tackling durability and reliability I
think as being kind of the most critical
and then adding some adaptiveness to the
contact and then sensing and control
towards reflexes. So we'll go in this
order starting with durability and
reliability. So Kevin and I came up with
a way of softcore monolithic molding.
And I have one of these squishy fingers
with me, I think. Yep. Um, and basically
by coming up with a molding method where
we can mold the entire thing as one
monolithic piece and eliminating seams,
we double the operating pressure. Going
further down the rabbit hole of the
additive technology used specifically to
make the molds that we're molding with,
then we can double the operating
pressure again without changing the
geometry. So again, I said geometric
optimization necessary, but there's a
probabilistic occurrence of defects that
you need to take into account when doing
fabrication. If you do so, then what
we've been able to accomplish here is a
4x increase in operational pressure and
over an order of magnitude increase in
cycles to failure. The next thing we
worry about is then the manual errors
because that was kind of manual casting.
Let's then change that to a prototype
method that Michael came up with for
injection molding of soft robots. and
then you have a little bit more
reliability and repeatability of those
results. Now, if I were to say we have
to make all robots all monolithic all
the time, you should shoot me down. Um,
it's not possible. It's not worth your
time. At some point, you're going to
need some seams. And so, Charlotte's
been working on then better
understanding kind of what that design
and manufacturing space is. Now, a lot
of times people then ask me when I
mention this, oh, what's the best
option? What's the best substrate?
What's the best glue?
And as my manufacturing students could
tell you, I repeat frequently, well,
that's relative and context dependent.
But if you start looking at the failures
that you're getting, whether they're go
cohesive, adhesive, a combination, or
substrate failures, then you have a good
idea of kind of how to update your
design to improve your weakest link. But
that's frustrating if I say that you
have to build something in order to see
how it fails, in order to make it
better.
Charlotte has been working on a
framework to then talk about kind of
what our parameters are, our functional
requirements we should start with for
soft robotics because they're not
exactly what we're we should be using if
we port them directly from traditional
rigid machine design. So, we talk about
things like flexibility and toughness as
a starting point in selecting both your
substrate and the glue that you're going
to use and then the bonding method
because it both matters what materials
you use and how you apply them. And just
as an anecdote of kind of I think one of
the misconceptions that we're working
against here is that you can go directly
from let's say elongation to failure as
one of the basic things that most
software botistes site. It's not
actually the most productive thing to
start with. It turns out then um it
doesn't kind of reveal what's
necessarily happening in that kind of
region of peeling and deformation or
sometimes we site maybe oh we'll use a
stiffer material and that'll be
stronger. That doesn't really correlate
to kind of how the failure modes then
propagate. What you could then start
doing with stiffer, softer materials is
deciding, would I like something that uh
fails slowly so that I can detect
failure and have time to respond or
potentially maybe I'd rather have a
stronger bond to begin with, but then I
risk catastrophic failure. It's a
trade-off.
Now, I did say I'm interested in soft
and rigid systems, not just fully soft
robots. And that's what Cat's working
on. and then applying applying a
industrial scale process called flocking
where you apply fibers to either rigid
or flexible surfaces. But you can also
do that now at a laboratory scale uh
method that cats developed. So
essentially we can take things like the
hubs that we would glue into soft robots
and just directly overmold them. So
maybe it saves us some time but it
actually expands the design space of how
we can start to then configure some of
these arrangements of soft rigid
assemblies and then putting in more
securely different sensors for example.
Um just as a side note this is largely
motivated by kind of observing uh soft
tissue that has floating rigid elements
in it such as uh soft coral scarites
or oicles from brittle stars. So what
we're doing is essentially not so much
working on the materials because I'm not
a material scientist, but we're taking a
trick that allows us to use the
traditional materials that we're already
that we already have at play and
increase the mechanical engagement of
them either with synthetic fibers or
with natural fibers.
Natural fibers work better, but they
don't tend to come in the form factor
mass-produced that you'd like that you
can get synthetic fibers with.
So to see what this looks like, we have
a short video
sped up of our laboratory scale version.
And then I do have if someone if you
want to come up later and see what this
looks like, you'll recognize it
immediately. It's on jewelry boxes and
then some car dashes and things, but
this is like $1 widget I got from Amazon
that has been flocked.
So we can leverage of what has already
been developed on an industrial scale. I
wanted to show this one in particular.
So, we don't just use this for rigid
parts. This is actually a flexible
sensor that we had a hard time
connecting to some of the soft
actuators.
By flocking one side and putting it in
the actuator,
then we reduce kind of the delamination
that was essentially instant previously.
I'm not going to be able to find my
cursor between these, so I feel like I
should just not push it. So, you get to
sit through the calming view of
degassing the flocking. It does trap
air. So, you got a lot of fibers there.
Yeah, Sean,
>> please.
>> What was that?
>> Yeah. Thank you,
>> Barry.
How you is the blocking material chosen
in some way that guarantees bonding for
wide variety of substrings or what's is
there any secret material?
>> Yeah, I think absolutely. Oh, and here's
the um actuator with the sensor in it
just to show kind of when previously we
tried to attach these by lacing them on,
you get a lot of noise and shifting from
the actuator. And so now because it's
bonded in place, like a we're happy that
it's not delaminating, but b we have an
also a cleaner signal. Um Sean, the
short answer is we mostly only tested it
with dragon skin. And so I think you
would want to be mindful, especially
given Charlotte's results of what
materials you're using. Um but we didn't
go so far as that. Mostly just looking
at how an array of materials would work
with uh dragon skin.
>> What about the other end? Like for
example, this is a sensor some kind of
plastic substrate.
>> Totally. Yeah. So um like a cyanoacryal
for example would work really well in
that plastic substrate. Um, and so it's
basically you're just playing the game
of which thing fails first and see if
you can kind of chemically increase the
bond to that thing. And then between the
silicone and the fibers, you're mostly
depending on mechanical engagement.
>> Ah, talk my Norwegian speaking phone.
Sorry. Um, okay. That's all I've got for
you for kind of the hardcore mostly
focused on manufacturing. Now we start
to build in between manufacturing and
design. So the previous ones are in
previous topics are increasing our
design space but fabrication focused.
Now I'm kind of mixing between the two.
And to motivate and kind of um show you
again what the deep sea sampling looks
like I have this video of about 800
meters down of a deep sea crab.
And so again we have something that has
uh or sorry now you see the situation
where we have limited vision. So there's
a lot of marine snow floating around and
outcropping and some shadows.
It's a complex shape we're going after
that doesn't particularly want to be
picked up and you still need to be
gentle. So the idea is that this is a
fairly dumb robot. There's not a lot of
feedback, but it's mechanically
programmed to then be able to pivot the
fingers just enough around those legs
and then not apply so much pressure that
we might hurt the crab because I would
rather not pick it up on live broadcast
than pick it up and hurt it. Um, so
basically the ROV pilot can just reach
around blindly under that outcropping
and just kind of hit go when you're in
the vicinity of the crab.
And the way we started this was I asked
the marine biologists what uh surrogate
we could use for testing. And push comes
a shove, we got them to say pretzel
sticks. Okay, I didn't succeed in
closing around pretzel sticks, but with
the same baseline actuator, adding some
strain limiting elements and then some
to then restrict the radial expansion
and force more of that deformation kind
of around the pretzel rod and then
actually adding some open cell foam to
close the rest of the gap and further
reduce the stress concentration. we get
to the point where we can hold something
anywhere from a half an inch up to
around like three or four inches and
then ensure that it's strong enough and
we have a low enough contact pressure as
we measure from this kind of contact
sensor array.
Now, taking this idea of kind of what I
did manually of kind of futing around
blindly, we said, well, wouldn't it be
nice if we could more intelligently
optimize based on a particular task?
This slide is a lot to look at, but I'm
going to walk through it. Um,
essentially Annie who's in the decode
lab and also in fiddle started with me
in Harvard on this project of creating a
tool for designing that is aware of the
manufacturing process and gives you
control over different objectives. In
particular, I was it was very important
to me that we started looking at a
larger nuanced variety of objectives.
So, not saying I would like my actuator
to bend at the lowest pressure possible
because that would give me a very weak
gripper, but starting to incorporate
things like the bandwidth and the max
strain or the force at a particular
level of closure as well as being able
to tailor the operating pressure for a
specific level of closure in
anticipation of what we're going to pick
up. Okay. And then you'll see some of
those come in. Ly, did you have a
question?
>> Yeah, I did. I noticed on the last slide
you had um you're actuating with
something like one and a quarter
atmospheresish.
>> Yeah.
>> Is that right? And you're trying to hold
yourself to a very low external contact
pressure.
>> Yeah.
>> So I I haven't done the math, but 2 PSI
is not
>> No. Some of it is So some of the trick
there is both kind of compliance in the
overall structure. So it's a pressurized
vessel. It's a relatively thin skin and
has those bellows that are also
flexible, but then also adding the
nonlinear stress strain response of the
foam is quite helpful. So, it basically
acts as like a capacitor and between I
think it's like 10% and 50 or 60%
compression, you can use the foam also
as a buffer to limit the contact
pressure.
>> Okay. So, so do you have a sort of noise
floor challenge with
>> the required actuation pressure versus
the external uh do you have a good sense
of where that floor is?
>> Uh, no. I have to get back to that. We
could probably dig it out of Annie's
results, but I would say no. But we do
have then control to be able to kind of
modulate those. There's a limit
obviously as you're suggesting um but
you have some ability to control that.
And um it can also relate to you can
start playing with the cross-sectional
area over like which that's uh applied
and the compliance of um the bellow side
of the structure.
Okay. So you'll see some of these come
back up again as far as u for example
bandwidth or the volume of actuation um
in particular to optimize for. But we
started out saying, "Okay, well, we'd
like a durable and strong gripper." Um,
and we parameterize the space just for
these bellow actuators. So, it's a
little bit limited, but given kind of
the prevalence of those as an archetype
within soft robotics, a really nice
place to start. And then we can do we
can start with the naive thing of a
parameter sweep, which probably doesn't
sound interesting to a lot of people who
are in optimization, but for me as a
designer, that's my bread and butter. I
would like to understand the sensitivity
of each individual variable and how that
then affects the performance so that I
can do that trade-off from the design
and manufacturing standpoint. But from
there, we can then dig into a grid
search or an evolutionary search with a
couple objectives in mind if we have
clearly defined functional requirements
for our task. And so for most users,
it's not particularly helpful to look at
a grid search and kind of a large array
of these kind of inner connections of
parameters. But for someone like me,
it's actually really nice to then start
playing and poking around in there and
see how that relates to the
manufacturing space. And so finally, u
basically what Annie's done is then
taken a Python controller that then
feeds these models into Abacus to do the
simulation and then navigates kind of
where we go to get an optimal design or
when we've uh converge and are close
enough, we essentially then export the
core of that. And the mold generation is
not automated yet. that's manual
currently but certainly could be
automated.
And then sorry going from here I've been
talking about essentially the underlying
structure optimization but then you can
also start to add some adaptivity in the
surface structures. So I'll just be very
quick with this one. Essentially um a
lot of these silicones are really high
friction. So to get a little bit more
dexterity you can then add elements to
be able to turn that friction in your
fingertips on and off. So by having a
constrained
high friction elastoic membrane that's
hidden behind a perforated low friction
membrane, I'm essentially just turning
friction on and off by pressurizing that
internal membrane. The pressure in the
fingers stays the same the whole time.
Pressure goes on and off like little
friction polyps popping out of the
fingertips. Okay, so between Annie's
optimization and then playing with
dexterity via friction,
this is all assuming that I have a
pretty good idea of what I'm going to
pick up and where I want to place my
stubby robot fingers. Now, sometimes
though, the things that I want to pick
up, I don't know what it's going to be.
So, often times the months leading up to
a trip, I have no idea what I'm going to
see. And then even once I'm on the boat
looking at something, A, I'm not sure
what it's going to do when I close the
claw, and B, even if I did close one of
these grippers over it, it's still not a
great fit with that topological or that
geometric complexity.
Thankfully, this one didn't go crunch,
but neither these soft robotic fingers
nor these rigid grippers are really well
suited for this. So, this is what kind
of gave me the idea. Well, all right.
We're trying to take this thing that we
love about soft robots, their
compliance,
but it's also kind of annoying because
the compliance means that they're less
predictable, harder to kind of carefully
arrange on an object. What if instead of
trying to make soft robots more easily
controlled, we just give up control and
instead go with a stochcastic approach?
So by adding
structural compliance to the material
compliance essentially we can passively
adapt to different objects. So some of
the mechanical programming is in making
them very high aspect ratio and then the
other is by letting them directly
interact with these objects.
Just to show you that this is indeed
stochastic. I have six grasps that are
overlaid.
They'll all look different but the
trajectory is generally the same. This
is not a precision operation, but it
deals with imprecision in the starting
point fairly well. And when I'm aiming
for a big bio box, my end precision is
less sensitive. And so, like I said
here, we can actually deal with a fair
amount of error and still retrieve an
object.
Okay. So, the gripper that I'm showing
you is mostly 12 filament, what I call
entanglement gripper. And this is dip
molded. So essentially, I can make large
arrays of very repeatable filament
actuators with very cheap molds because
I'm just leveraging surface tension and
gravity and viscosity to mechanically
program them.
So that gives me essentially similar to
making balloons or dipping candlesticks,
a very even film thickness. And an even
film thickness is boring. It needs some
mechanical programming. Ways that I
mechanically program this are through
gravity, fiber inclusions, electric
fields, and surface tension. Not really
going to get into the weeds, but I'll
tell you that that gives me control over
the direction of motion, the operational
pressure, the curvature, and the grip
force. And I won't dig through the
results, but just show you that kind of
this is how I map then how a
manufacturing recipe then gives me a
path towards a particular performance
metric. And then I can start to
incorporate those into larger arrays. So
in the top we have a gravity programmed
array. It's 16 x 16. They all bend in
one direction because that's what
gravity does. And then the bottom array
is then programmed by fiber inclusions.
So then I can actually have an arbitrary
vector field there.
As we then make those longer, you can
see how they could start to interact
with objects in different ways. Though
the trajectory is the same. kind of move
the filaments over the object, turn the
pressure on, turn the pressure off.
Basically, it's an eccentric balloon,
thicker on one side than the other. When
you inflate it, the thinner side
inflates more, it buckles, it curls, and
they start interacting with each other
and the objects. And again, the objects
then define the shape of the gripper. We
can characterize this digitally by
taking a CT scan,
then turn that into kind of a digital
recreation of the filaments. And there's
a lot of nice ways that we can quantify
the level of entanglement that I'm going
to skip today, but I'll at least show
you then how we're able to map the
contacts. The contacts between grippers
or sorry, between filaments in addition
to the contacts from filament to object
are particularly important. That's how
we get a grasp that is greater than the
sum of its parts. And so I'll bring
these contacts back up later because
they give us an idea for a different
sensing modality. Um, but I'll just
mention that with a collaboration with
the Mahadavon Lab and using a
modification of Gaza's um,
uh, software, we're able to do kind of a
sweep of the different prototypes so
that, you know, we can do some spot
checks physically, but get a better
sense or a greater sense of what the
design and manufacturing spaces are.
Okay. So, at this point, everything I've
shown you is open loop. I want to start
building in sensing or first control. So
we have ability to kind of um have a
little bit more finite control over
where we're actuating different
actuators especially as we move to
larger arrays and then build in sensing
to then build up to reflexes.
So in the top and the right here I have
a large array that's just all actuated
from one manifold. Not particularly
complex, not that interesting. I can
start to kind of segment arrays um like
the 16x6 array below. Each of the
columns is actually fed to one channel.
But that means that I need to have a
tube for every single channel and that
results in a lot of tubing. So then
inspired by some work that I collabored
on um with Dr. Nicholas Bartlett where
we put together a mashup of the dip
molding process and micrfluidics to make
a demultiplexer that essentially could
take a small number of inputs and make
it into a larger number of outputs. Then
we get to something that has a little
bit higher throughput as far as like flu
fluid flow that Chief came up with. Now
this takes a couple different sources of
influence. We take the results from
Annie's optimization show us that the
inside of these actuators the dimensions
inside of here are actually quite
critical when we start looking at the
bandwidth the volume to actuation and
also the max strain in an actuator. So
by then switching to these really low
profile, we call them low volume cores,
we're able to increase the bandwidth,
decrease the volume actuation. Obviously
those are tied, but then also decrease
the overall strain,
which then in this case comparing one of
these to a traditional gripper, we can
get uh on average two orders of
magnitude increase in cycles to failure.
uh but in addition to that we can start
harnessing that extra design space to
make more complex structures that can
then convert simple signals into more
complex motion. So a single square wave
gets turned into a sequenced uh action
of then manipulating a pen and embodied
intelligence that like this is not new
in the field of soft robotics but what
is is being able to do that in oneot
monolithic molding so that you have a
more reliable and durable device. In
addition to that, by putting in these
really slender
uh low volume cores, so this is an
example of our check valve core, then we
can get to greater compact complexity.
And another nice thing is, you know, we
could do this with
fancier printers. Um, but really this
demonstration, which we're demolding in
the video, is essentially just a hobby
scale FFF printer and a $100 vinyl
cutter, Cricut cutter. So, Chief and I
are actually going to then take this
down the road to a local high school
that actually Michael Bell and I, who's
in the audience, taught at previously,
taking the Harvard software toolkit,
teaching students there. It was a mess.
It was difficult to get actuators,
successful actuators out in the first
few days. And then with this process,
I'm very confident that on the first
day, we're going to have functional
actuators.
Okay. So, in addition to this kind of
lowprofile internal geometry for a
single actuator, then we can build in
multiple degrees of freedom into one
actuator. So, we have four degrees of
freedom in this finger instead of one.
Now, we tried to put two degrees of
freedom in one of these and take it to
C, and it popped. So, we glued one of
the chambers and limped along. Remember
how painful I said it was if we miss a
day? That was a sad day. Okay, so Chvang
has made it so that we can now reliably
have many more degrees of freedom.
Whether it's four degrees of freedom in
this one kind of linear bending actuator
or then six degrees of freedom in this
spherical gripper, we then can put check
valves in. We can put uh pinch valves or
proportional valves in. Um, and I've
cleaned out a lot of the beautiful plots
that Jivang has to make the uh view a
little bit simpler for you all, but
trust me, he's gone through all the
different uh parameters and geometric
kind of parameters of this to be able to
see how it affects the output. So, for
example, this is for a static geometric
output. We're just changing the pinch
pressure to adjust flow. Seems pretty
obvious. And the hold pressure. Um but
then with the check valves an example is
changing the height of this uh core then
gives us an ability to change the flow
or the diadeicity of the valve being a
measure of kind of how directional that
flow is and how successfully it performs
as a check valve. Okay. But then
so we have this control but I really
just want to go back to high bandwidth
low volume of actuation that becomes
really helpful when we start designing
for untethered operations. So we have um
Sam's monopropellant engine which is
kind of miniaturaturized and fits in the
base of an actuator. It's essentially
using hydrogen peroxide when then
exposed to silver. This is the catalyst
in this case. then decomposes into just
steam and oxygen and can power our
actuators.
But then we of course care how much fuel
that we have to consume. Um now this is
not in the line of the manufacturing so
much as I just want to note the really
clever design that Sam came up with. He
incorporated a compliant bladder inside
of the engine that divides the engine
and the actuator is essentially like the
designs for deep sea pumps. What it does
is it automatically resets gauge
pressure of the engine to the internal
pressure of the actuator which then
helps to feed the forward reaction. So
traditionally you'd have a central fuel
tank pushing fuel into a fuel reactor
that reacts. It powers the actuator. You
need a higher central fuel tank pressure
than your reactor. But with a bladder,
you can have a low pressure in your
central fuel tank that then flows and
recharges the engine, pressurizes the
bladder, that then starts to push fuel
through the reactor, which then
increases the pressure in the actuator.
When it increases pressure in the
actuator, it then pushes on that
bladder. And because I have a one-way
valve here, then it's continuing to push
that reaction so that we can actually
get to a higher pressure than you would
otherwise with a traditional set of uh
engine architecture. If that was
confusing, that's fine. I'm going to
keep going and you're welcome to ask me
about it later. But what that lets us do
is have a really fast reaction time
because we have this miniaturaturized
engine that's then normalized to the or
adjusted to the gauge pressure of the
actuator and then fuel is delivered
directly to the base of that uh
actuator.
So in this demonstration, Sam's going to
push a switch that turns the LED on just
to show you that the switch has been
pushed and then you can see the reaction
time of the gripper. So this is a
combination of both the efficiency of
the engine design but then also the LVC
gripper having a relatively low volume
to actuation and thus higher bandwidth.
>> Yeah.
>> How adabatic do you need the u gripper
to be if you're driving steel?
>> Um
it's fairly I mean I think
>> if anything it might Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Um, I think it long term we might
actually have an issue where we need to
draw heat out faster. Um, where I think
you you can get to the point where some
of your efficiency as far as like the
percentage of fuel reacted is limited by
keeping a low enough pressure that you
actually have enough dwell time and you
don't get this light and frost effect on
the catalyst itself and thus pushing
unreacted fuel through if that makes
sense but happy to discuss it more
after.
Cool. So the other thing that we can do
from this um in having a miniaturized
engine which hopefully we will
miniaturaturize more um so we have a
really light uh or compact engine
relatively small payload. So we actually
load it onto a drone. In this case I've
moved the LVC actuators or I haven't but
Sam and Chiang have and they've replaced
them with some of the entanglement
grippers.
So fully untethered
and then those grippers are compliant
enough you can just land without
worrying about crunching something or
knocking your drone over.
We're still in this section but now I'm
transitioning to sensing. So we have
some ability to modulate control. Now we
build in sensors for the feedback. Um
trying to do so mindfully from a
manufacturing perspective. So I'll start
with uh Nah's work which is essentially
starting out with this small array of
three celiaike actuators but the idea is
that it's a test bed for then
controlling larger arrays without then
making the cost of fabrication or the
complexity of fabrication unbearable. So
what we've done is try to take a
relatively few number of sensors. So we
have the pressure sensor that's
controlling the or looking at the whole
thing and then three photo resistors
under one under each psyllium and then
three resistive sensors. They're cracked
graphite custom sensors that give us
some ability to sense kind of
directional motion. But we get a more
rich kind of mapping of propriceptive
and exterceptive
uh feedback by looking at like using
that redundancy and looking at the
clashing between the signals that we're
getting to then figure out what's going
on.
So the idea is that eventually we can
move this into larger arrays
and again just starting with basically
two uh resist resistance sensors per
psyllium and then one global pressure
sensor.
That's what this looks like. Um and
something to note is that the cracked
graphite sensor does meaningfully affect
the kind of structure and the mechanical
behavior of that actuator. So the next
thing we thought about is is there a way
that we can actually make this
mechanically transparent. So in this
case we used it strategically and used
the sensor itself to then guide the
curvature. But then Via in the lab was
an undergrad in the lab who graduated
recently and essentially added ears or a
microphone to the entanglement gripper.
So we have a microphone mounted kind of
up near the top.
And remember I talked about those
connection points. Basically, we think
about kind of where the filaments start
touching each other that changes the
natural frequencies at which they'll
vibrate. Now, we started with a speaker
on the entanglement gripper, and that
was both annoying and unnecessary
because you can actually just use
ambient noise as your signal or your
input signal. And then look at how this
peak, for example, from electrical noise
then shifts based on, for example, the
actuation pressure or the weight of an
object or the shape of an object. you
can actually start to hear shape of
objects based on how the contacts are
distributed presumably between the
filaments and the object. Um, so VIA
essentially created I think this is a
four they're four centimeter cubes.
They're all the same or they fit within
this 4cimeter cube. All the same weight
but then different spatial densities so
that we couldn't because we knew we
could detest detect weight and so we
wanted to make sure we were detecting
shape and not weight if that makes
sense. And I would say it wasn't a
perfect result, but I'm pretty excited
about initial results about being able
to essentially hear something about the
shapes that we're picking up more than
just ah yes, we have something.
Okay. But then if we want even more
information, reviving kind of a um
project that I did with Dr. Clark Tel at
Harvard and now Chief has expanded this
here in making arrays of optical fibers
within a soft sheet as a way to both
detect deformation and pressure. And so
the idea in putting this in a soft sheet
is well we could customize that to a
particular geometry and I think that's
an adventure we do want to go on at some
point. But from a fabrication standpoint
it's a lot simpler if we could make this
sheet flexible enough to then wrap
around an object so that your sheet then
kind of detects the shape of let's say a
robot or a person and then further
tracks those the deformation or
movement. So the way this works is with
wave guides that essentially have two
different elastimemers, one with a
higher refractive index than the other.
The higher refractive index is on the
inside. So that as you shine light down
the core of that, then light bounces off
that interface and keeps traveling down
the wave guide. If you then we take a
trick then from our friends across the
river and then if you roughen one side
of that, then it becomes a directional
kind of uh bending sensor. So we can
detect if you're kind of bending towards
or away from the roughen side of that
core. So then Chief played with that and
realized that you can start to really
tune kind of the sensitivity and
linearity um from modifying the
manufacturing process. Now usually it
takes a while to manufacture any given
thing. So um to save us some time he
developed a simulation tool a design
tool that then also takes into account
where the kind of manufacturing
limitations are and then by putting in
some noise he chugged through to see
kind of which configuration then gave
him the most reliable recreation of
these target shapes despite the noise.
And so
you can see we can recreate it's not
fast. There's some optimization that
could be done there, but we can recreate
the shape. And then once we're done kind
of shifting and deforming, we can't do
this at the same time, but separately,
you can then detect both the location of
and intensity of pressure. This was less
so for the deep sea projects unless we
talk maybe about wets suits more so for
in hopes to be useful for the physical
therapy applications.
Okay. But then we take just one of these
wave guides and kind of quickly attached
it to a finger for one of Sam's
demonstrations. And so we essentially
show that we can use that as a feedback
mechanism for this finger that's being
actuated by the engine. And what you're
going to see is that this engine gets
tired. The finger starts drifting and
doesn't hit its target curvature.
And then it's the bladder here is where
we're emptying. That's our kind of
standin central fuel source for the
moment. Okay. Okay, so inspired by this
then Sam and Chiang basically
implemented a very simple P controller.
And so here there are tests where we've
got it under damped, critically damped,
overdamped, but showing that you can use
the optical sensors plugged into the
monopropellant engine to then apply
feedback to a simple actuator.
And I hope you'll see kind of more of
these soon. particularly I'm excited to
tell people about some of our soft rigid
stuff but for today that's the end of
what I have for you
and so I'll end with a little summary
starting with a quote form follows
function
familiar one especially to designers I
would say for soft robotics soft robotic
form defines function
and to design a soft robot is
necessarily to design the process by
which it's made.
If we apply fabrication integrated
design, we can get soft robots that are
more durable, reliable, stronger,
faster, and scalable. And I mean
scalable in a manufacturing sense.
And along the way, geometric and
material optimization is necessary but
not sufficient. Now, the same can be
saying said about manufacturing. It's
necessary but not sufficient. So, we're
working towards a framework of soft
machine design and manufacturing. And
this is a multiddisciplinary
community effort that we should all be
working on, but certainly one that I'm
excited to push in the fabrication
integrated design lab.
There's lots of people that I need to
thank and I should really thank uh more
than this, but mentors and collaborators
that I wasn't able to catch along kind
of the way of the slides and then my
students. They're certainly kind of some
of the very best moments of this job and
I'm very lucky to be able to work with
them every day. Thank you very much for
putting up with me. Um, and also thank
you all to listening to me on this
Friday afternoon. I really appreciate
it. And if we have time, we'll take
questions.
[Applause]
>> All right.
Thank you, Kate. Um, I found that the
the kind of a combustion engine like uh
power plant is very exciting because
robot may have its own power plant
inside, right? Um but I remember someone
built the kind of octopus like machines.
So is that different your stuff is a
different principle or what's the
difference one?
>> Absolutely. So basically um and I meant
to mention this but so using
monopropellants for powering both soft
robots and rigid robots is not new from
us. There's a gard lab doing it with
rigid robots and then it came out of
Jennifer Lewis and Rob Woods lab with
the octabot with Mike Vener and Ryan
Trouy. Um so the piece that I think is
really exciting here is that addition of
the um that's new uh is the addition of
the compliant membrane inside allows us
to get to a much higher actuation
pressure or yeah higher kind of output
pressure than you could with any of the
previous kind of demonstrated work. So
the idea is by having that design that I
would love to say is inspired by deep
sea pumps, but it really just happens to
look a lot like a deep sea pump that
enables us to get higher pressure and
then um kind of miniaturaturizing it in
a way where to let us then distribute
some of that power to soft robotics um
so or to actuators. So it's we're
getting to a higher flow. we need kind
of more electrical signals and kind of
active control of this and so you need a
brain in the current instantiation
whereas with the Octabot one it's all
passive and just kind of runs out
natural oscillations to control the
behavior. Um so more direct control at
the cost of electronics but then the
ability to get to a higher actuation
pressure so you could p power also um
potentially larger systems. So I guess
it's both. It's pressure andor just
throughput of volume.
But good question.
>> All right. Is there more?
>> Okay. Um I'll preface this with I'm not
sure if a human is a soft robot or not,
but it seems like a lot of the things
that you're trying to achieve with soft
robots can be done by like for example a
human hand. um especially like the
object detection or you know we can pick
stuff up like very gently or very
rigidly. Um have you looked at like
humans for inspiration or have you
thought about like what gives us the
ability to do things that like maybe
robots struggle with?
>> Yeah, absolutely. I mean even just down
to having a fingernail is really
helpful. Um and so that's why a lot of
my robots have this kind of like funny
beak shape at the end. I think it's
actually vestigual effect of exploring
fingernails um and how that would be
helpful in picking things up. But sure,
absolutely I feel and then I feel
inadequate every time I try to measure
up to a human hand. Um but it is a great
source of uh inspiration. I would say I
certainly don't try to tend towards
anthropomorphic mostly because I would
say I'm an engineer to a fault and a
manufacturing engineer to a fault where
I try to make things that are then more
streamlined for fabrication which is not
necessarily anthropomorphic and then the
form factor that that uh constraint puts
on you then makes things a little bit
tricky as far as your power output but
yeah absolutely um there's a lot of fun
things also even with perception kind of
outside the hands too um or if you If
any I'm sure a lot of people in this
room have seen the video, if you numb
someone's hands, um their ability to
manipulate things is like so much worse
than if they have all that full sensory.
So, for example, someone I think it's a
Swedish video of someone trying to
strike a match and they struggle for a
long time when you numb their
fingertips. So, yeah, and I think it's
going to be a balance for for me. I
think the exciting piece of that is it's
a balance of how certainly there's on
the computation side. I'm on the meat
space and fabrication side, which is to
say what is the cost of implementing
those. Can we because there's usually
there's usually a trade-off between cost
and complexity and manufacturing
unless you come to something innovative
where you can kind of break the trend.
And so are there ways that we can kind
of break the trend and be clever about
fabrication. So it's so we both get more
information but at a hopefully a lower
cost.
It's a good question.
Is there more questions from the
audience?
>> Hey Caitlyn, lovely presentation by the
way. So my question I have was I'm very
curious about the use of sound as sort
of a feedback sensor. Yep. and being
able to sort of use like those patterns
to detect shapes.
>> Yeah,
>> I know it's still very early and
everything, but what I was curious is if
you can go a little bit more into the
estimation techniques you use to sort of
infer what those shapes
>> Yeah. are.
>> Um, I would say I can't go too far into
I mean it's uh I think we use a random
forest uh machine learning algorithm
which means that I won't be able to tell
you much more than that but what I can
tell you is more about the physics
underlying it which is really cool. Um,
basically you can your ear can hear kind
of a surprising number of things based
on the frequencies that come out of
structures. So you can hear for example
if something is made of wood or metal or
glass. You can hear that if you hit
something. You can hear that when
instrument like musical instruments are
played and someone can tell the
difference between a French horn and a
violin or even a French horn and a
trumpet for example. And a lot of that
is based on not just the fundamental
frequency, which is the pitch that you
hear, but the harmonics. And that's what
we're looking to play with. And
basically, it's both the kind of like
intensity of harmonics, how many you
have, and harmonics being multiples of
the fundamental frequency, and then also
how much aberration you have in each of
those. Are they kind of very stark,
sharp lines at multiples of the
fundamental frequency, or is there a
little bit of aberration and noise? So
what you hear in for example like a
violin is there's actually many more
overtones and then with that wood sound
you actually get a little bit more
aberration versus a French horn you have
very few overtones or harmonics and then
they have a really sharp peak. Um so we
hope to use that a little bit in kind of
getting more information about objects
but it's really it's a really I think
great result for an undergrad research
project. I'm stoked and excited to see
where it goes. Thank you for the
question.
Great. I think we are reaching the end
of the hour. So, let's thank our speaker
again.