okay everybody can hear me okay great
okay well fantastic I want to thank ILP
for inviting us to be part of this uh
important conference and I thought what
we do to kind of warm us up is to First
say a couple words about what we do at
the MIT Mobility initiative and then to
go into something that we call our 10
Trends so I will explain this uh shortly
uh but we've got a hold track uh signed
up for you today so I am going to be
immediately followed by Jin waza who's a
professor of city and Transportation
Planning and ginoa was actually the
founder of the MIT Mobility initiative
so it's wonderful that he'll be with us
shortly talking a little bit about some
of the Dynamics that we see in um the
electric the trend toward
electrification and in particular
distinctions between uh the US and and
China then we'll have a short break we
have uh Professor Elsa olti coming to
talk to us about uh the critical
materials the supply of lithium and
graphite and Cobalt and all the things
that we need to go into an electric
vehicle battery um and then finally we
have H Professor Alex jaot who is at the
Sloan school who will join us and talk
about some work that we've been doing at
the MMI on optimization of electric
vehicles
uh charging infrastructure so that's our
program for the afternoon um let me just
say a couple words about what we do at
the mobility initiative our focus is on
Transportation as a system and that word
system is is really critical what does
that really mean it typically means a
complicated mix of people and
institutions that come together to
deliver value and that's what Mobility
really is it's that's what it's all
about um and what we want out of that
system and I think many of us would
agree boils down to three very simple
words right what do we want out of our
transportation system we want it to be
safe we want it to be clean and we want
it to be inclusive safe and clean are
very
self-evident inclusion is a concept
that's received more attention recently
and it really boils down to um
affordability both in terms of time and
in terms of money um so how we achieve
this at the mmis through these four
pillars research education
entrepreneurship and engagement this is
a bit of what we're doing here today
meeting with folks Business Leaders um
and really sort of fostering um dialogue
and interaction around the work uh that
that that we're doing um and so just
briefly our approach is around
technology of course but I can't
underemphasize how important human
behavior is and uh ginoa who's just
walked in the back of the door someone
I've learned a lot from has mentioned
that if you think about how do we
influence human behavior in
transportation there's re how do we
change people's behavior and there's
really kind of three big levers to that
so one is about rules you know we might
set speed limits and so forth one is
about Norms Norms is you know why is it
that people don't cross the street
illegally in Tokyo but they do in New
York City that's a kind of cultural norm
right and then there's pricing so these
are really important uh metrics to look
at when we talk about Transportation
Systems of course there's the whole
policy and Regulatory domain uh we look
a lot at business model uh Innovation
and in particular and I think this is
something unique to the MIT Mobility
initiative we really try to sort of
Foster Real World deployments um in the
city of Detroit in uh the city of uh
Phoenix Arizona we're doing work sort of
on the ground and applying our our
research um you know why here at MIT
these are some of the strengths of MIT
as an institution they align very well
with transportation systems and there's
a number of labs AC Across The Institute
and a number of people across the
Institute that are involved in looking
at some dimension of the mobility system
it could be what Elsa is doing with the
supply chain for for Batteries it could
be around electrification it could be
around autonomous and so forth um so we
look at these systems challenges and we
ask these sort of big picture questions
like how much energy is required for the
future of autonomous Mobility for the
compute not moving the vehicles but just
for the compute itself and the short
answer there is that it's probably a
very significant amount of energy uh we
look at Connected vehicles um you know
looking uh I mentioned this in Phoenix
Arizona this project on intersections
where we're balancing very
highresolution and expensive liar
sensors with very low resolution sensors
and and trying to find the optical mix
to increase safety at uh four-way
intersections um on electrification
we've looked at policy uh issues around
the gas tax um a number of other
questions and then uh on public
transportation as well hugely important
area for the for the mobility system
okay so um you know we are we have
companies that are members of the MIT
Mobility initiativ these are some of the
companies uh that we that we work work
with um and with that short introduction
let me get into the uh the 10
Trends okay so this is really first of
all what I'm about to say are really
actually not Trends they're more like
issues or tensions that we observe
within our Global transportation system
and I should say that uh we're looking
at surface we're not taking this to
Maritime we're not taking this to
Aviation and you'll see it's it is a bit
of a US Centric view so it's always
interesting when we travel outside of
the United States to get a very
different
perspective let's start with the first
of the 10 Trends uh and this is what we
call the
criticality of um China's role in the
electric vehicle uh battery uh Market um
now you know that
the battery of an electric vehicle
composes about 30 to 40% of the cost
basis of the vehicle so it is truly a
critical and strategic component and
what we have seen is um after uh many uh
Decades of um various consumer
incentives and V various production
incentives and subsidies uh China has
built up a remarkable uh Capac capacity
and capability in the EV battery space
um and you know uh we've just we and
it's it's really challenging for us in
the west I mean those of you from Europe
are probably familiar with the northfold
story where you know we're looking at
after 11 billion EUR of investment into
building a sort of European battery
Powerhouse there are some very serious
challenges uh within that within that
Institution
so if we look at the sort of global
market share right these are uh data
from the first half of 24 two companies
catl and byd account for well over half
of the global market and what's really
surprising is if we compare the share of
those two companies in 21 the share has
increased remarkably byd from about 7%
to about
16% so things are moving very quickly uh
in this space the other companies in red
are also Chinese origin uh battery
manufacturers um and if you look at it
from sort of breaking down the
components of a battery um at a very
large level the cathode the anode the
electrolytes Etc you can see that
there's a great degree of sort of
influence from Chinese industry uh in
this um in in the uh the functionality
of the battery but this is something
that really caught my attention so last
year when we did the 10 Trends we were
talking about the shifting geopolitical
world and we're talking about what the
heck is going on in China right so China
is they became the largest Automotive
Market in 2009 they have the capacity to
build nearly 40 million vehicles per
year but the Home Market is more like 30
so what do you do with that difference
the 10 million difference you push out
to export that's what we talked about
last year and we're what's concerning is
we're seeing this kind of overc capacity
Trend this is some data from Bloomberg
uh new energy Finance where they're
looking at a very high degree of
production overc capacity in the
electric vehicle battery Market over the
next uh year or two um So that obviously
has very real uh
implications so that's the first Trend
the uh second trend is about this kind
of
intensification in um the sort of in the
global uh trade situation with um
increasing tariffs with a kind of
movement toward two different a
bifurcation you know I spent a good part
of my career at the world economic Forum
where it was always about sort of
integration and globalization and so
forth and now we're living in a very
different world uh where we see these
kind of uh different camps forming with
big implications across Mobility from
building ships to building commercial
aircraft uh to the automotive Market
which of course you know we'll we'll
talk uh more
about um and I will say this I've never
seen the term National Security brought
up more in transportation related
conversations than I have like over the
past uh year or
two okay just a little footnote on trade
you know you may I'm sure many of you
saw this but you know sort of an
important development much earlier this
year was when Mexico became the number
one importer to the United States
surpassing China and this is very
important for those of you familiar with
the structure of the automotive industry
I understand that you know there are
there's a lot of Automotive trade uh in
components and fully built Vehicles
between Mexico and the United States
there are Chinese uh oems that have
entered and built production facilities
in Mexico and so forth so many uh
implications
there okay a third Trend uh one of our
uh senior fellows at the MIT Mobility
initiative is a gentleman named David
zipper and he has been writing a lot
about this topic and has sort of coined
this term that I really like it's called
car bloat and this is very much a it's
not just a US phenomenon I mean we see
the this this growth in the size and
weight of the vehicles on our roads uh
in Europe as well and um you know if you
look up there you'll see the sort of
bestselling vehicle here in the United
States and how it's kind of changed over
the over the decades and the chart shows
you the you know the weight of your
typical vehicle which of course
plummeted during the 1970s oil crisis
but then has regained and then surpassed
where we were um and the implication
here is about um
fatalities um safety right I mean larger
heavier Vehicles clearly are more
dangerous the data in the United States
are very much moving in the wrong
direction we've been having more and
more Road
fatalities uh in this in this country um
and you can see particularly the data is
alarming for pedestrian or so-called
vulnerable Road users cyclists and and
pedestrians um and you can see a
researcher at University of Hawaii sort
of tried to quantify the fact that you
know as the ve the front end of the
vehicle gets larger and blocks
visibility what impact does that have on
on safety and I I think actually this
chart is a a nice very simple kind of
summary of the situation that we're
seeing here in the United States where
we've moved from you know more and more
people when there are Road fatalities
are pedestrians they are cyclists and
you know very tragically we had one of
our own a graduate student here at MIT
who was who was killed several months
ago not I mean minutes from where we're
where we are right now um just you know
uh on the street as a as a
cyclist uh by a very large truck that
couldn't see her so this is a a deeply
uh concerning um challenge that that
that we
face okay Trend number four is um you
know we've seen the movement toward
electrification and and it's really
exciting and but you know we and those
of you with an energy background in the
room will be very familiar with this
situation which is to
say we've seen demand increasing for
electricity from people putting heat
pumps in their homes and people putting
electric vehicles in their garages but
of course as you all know every time you
type something into chat GPT it uses 10
times the amount of electricity as when
you use to type something into Google
and so that has a big sort of impact on
you know where where is demand going and
what's that going to do to uh
residential um electricity prices uh
here in the United States so this is
some data that looks at that price in
terms of uh dollars per kilowatt hour um
or cents per kilowatt hour and looking
at sort of how that has very much been
uh trending up so as an operator as an
owner as a user of an electric vehicle
this changes your sort of operating uh
Dynamics it changes your Calculus right
um makes it less favorable if you will
on a cost basis to drive an
EV and this is a study from Goldman
Sachs that just looked at um you know
the this demand from data centers and
from Ai and it's not so much to like
look at the numbers here but it's to
look at the shape and the shape is very
much what what we call here a hockey
stick right where there are many smart
people who have Insight in this area who
are thinking that this is the shape of
that curve moving forward we don't know
we look at Mobility systems but we know
that this will have a big impact on our
transportation ecosystem if this does
indeed
evolve um and you know the iea has done
this study um where they looked at the
amount of energy that's just sort of
waiting in line to be connected to the
grid and the Aging Grid in some parts of
Europe even older than here in the
United States as a kind of bottleneck in
the electricity grid to you know to
deliver those electrons that we would
need to power our future
Mobility um one of our researchers uh
Professor Carman noted that you know
currently Computing accounts for about
1% of global electric consumption that
figure by the way is about 2% here in
the United States and but we expect that
to increase to say 10% in in 10 years um
and this was in reference to that work
that I alluded to earlier looking at if
all of the if if a significant share of
the vehicles on our streets converted to
some form of autonomous Mobility that's
going to require a lot of computing
right which is going to require
electricity to power that Computing as
well okay um the the fifth trend is uh
around you know last year we were
looking at sort of this depressing
moment around autonomous Mobility many
of you will recall that um Crews uh in
San Francisco had had this terrible
accident um you know Business Week had
headlines like we've spent a hundred
billion dollar on this technology and
it's gone nowhere right so now what
we've seen is a little bit more raise of
Hope if you will as people consider
applying foundation models uh large
language models sort of the AV what you
could call AV 2.0 technology and and
certainly investors have also taken note
of this and we've seen some big
Investments uh in in the space um you
know a billion dollar flowing into one
company in the UK uh with soft bank
money but I wanted to kind of highlight
this story here because we don't hear as
much about this in the United States
that over the summer there's a kind of
protest in Wuhan where many of the uh
taxi drivers were saying look um how are
we supposed to compete with these uh
Robo taxis so um you know BYU runs a a a
service called a go they have um almost
I think now almost a thousand Robo taxis
operating on the streets of Wuhan and
this is sort of the data point that
caught our attention a 10 kilometer ride
costs 4 to 16 R&B which is somewhere in
the range of 60 to
$240 just if you think about that for a
moment that's a six kilome or six mile
ride think about what you pay for your
Uber or your lift convert that is it in
the range of 60 cents to
$240 probably not and then compare that
to what the um a human driven ride Hil
service is offering in Wuhan and it's
you know times two times four uh so this
starts to point toward you know could
there be this um Breakaway where the
economics of autonomous systems really
do start to achieve the the vision that
drove so much of the hype 10 years years
ago uh Trend number six is around what I
what we would call growing pains with
softwar defined Vehicles what does this
mean what is this what I mean there is
so much ambiguity around this term
softwar defined Vehicles we like to
think of it having two sides there's a
consumer side to this which is to say
how do you bring the
personalization that you want off of
this device that you carry with you how
do you bring that into your automobile
how do you customize it to your tastes
and your preferences that's this one
side of the sdv coin the other side is
totally different it's an industry or
production side and to it's how do we
what is the fundamental architecture
that we use to build Vehicles where in
the past Automotive oems have worked
with suppliers that supplied uh
processors for Subs systems of the
automobile and did that very very well
and now is there a movement towards a
sort of unified processing architecture
within the vehicle and what are the
potential benefits and efficiencies to
be gained from that but it's been a hard
slog right it's been a hard slog because
you know car companies have certain core
talents and those are quite different
than the core talents that software
companies have and this has been this
fun mental tension in the automotive
industry for the past 10
years okay Trend number seven was one
that I kind of took a leap of faith on
and I'm I was sitting there and I'm like
does this make sense is this really a
thing and so it's a funny concept that
I've been testing with people uh we just
had our vision day recently where it's
it's our big event and you know we
brought together um well over a hundred
real leaders in the space and it's and
it resonated so what the way that I
would Define this is to say you know
we've always had sort of you know our
values shape our politics our politics
shape our values of course that shapes
the decisions that we make in daily life
for all of us but it feels like it's
become more sort of pronounced more
polar sometimes more
acrimonious and you know we've looked at
like what has happened in New York City
with congestion pricing where um you
know many of us in the MMI were so
hopeful about what that could mean for
the public transportation system in New
York City and the setback that we saw
when the governor of New York put
congestion pricing on hold many of you
know that now she's put it back on the
agenda at a lower rate this is a really
big story in
transportation and you know ginoa who's
worked in you know in London and helped
tfl to implement their congestion
pricing scheme has worked in Singapore
there's much that can be learned about
what this can mean for the world uh
going forward but it's driven
by us it's driven by our values and our
perceptions and when ideology enters
into this
debate we make I think I would submit
worse decisions so that's uh Trend
number seven Trend number eight is for
all of the urban planning um enthusiasts
in the in the crowd uh this is something
that uh those of you from Europe will be
very familiar that actually in many
cities in Europe they have uh so-called
parking maximums that say you cannot
have more than a certain amount of
parking per unit of housing that's
provided here in the United States we
have just the opposite we have this mish
mash of M Municipal requirements that
say if you build build a condominium or
an apartment unit or a single family
home or what have you you have to
provide x amount of parking um and
finally that's being sort of seriously
looked at and questioned about the cost
implications of that uh here in in the
US um Trend number nine is about uh it's
really two trends that are here okay one
of them is about sort of this post
industrial manufacturing uh this
struggle that we have
where
in many advanced economies the capacity
to make things seems to slowly be
deteriorating right even even here at
MIT right there's a lot of you know the
young students come in and they want to
go into you know Ai and software maybe
less interest in Industrial Systems
mechanical engineering things like that
and so you have to ask what are the
implications you know for for the future
and then you have to flip that with the
other side of this coin which is
Illustrated in this picture in um you
know this could be in New York or San
Francisco we I I mentioned that we work
with public transportation agencies here
in the United States we work with the
seven
largest Fair
evasion people doing this is a epic
issue in public transportation systems
and people didn't used to do this as
much it's shocking how much it's
happening in in San Francisco and other
cities and that is a sort of Norm you
know getting back to those behavioral
Norms that is a Norm that's being
established you people might say well
that guy didn't pay why you know on the
bus that guy didn't pay why I'm not
going to be a sucker I'm not going to
pay no one else is paying and this sort
of vicious cycle starts to establish
itself so there's a lot to unpack here
but I think two sort of important sides
of a similar uh of a so societal Trend
that's impacting the world of
Mobility okay and then finally we always
uh look at the financial uh ecosystem
because it's really really important in
transportation systems um and
here
there's the if you look at money that's
coming from Venture Capital into
Mobility so the chart here shows the
flow from venture capital and private
Equity combined and you know I've noted
this before isn't it strange that in you
know covid we're all stuck at home
oceans of money floods into Mobility
right I mean that's kind of odd but
that's what happened and since then
we've seen that volume declined
significantly and now start to
recover but we have to ask where does
the money to drive electrification
where's that really going to come from
it's not coming from Venture Capital
it's coming from large corporations that
are making big Investments it's coming
from governments that are also making
big
Investments um so there there's this
this understanding of like how the
financial ecosystem impacts uh the
transportation ecosystem and they tend
to sometimes seem to be out of sync uh
is an important Trend uh that that we
have been
monitoring okay so with that let's talk
a little bit um and I want to hear from
all of you um so it do any of these kind
of resonate is there anything that you
just completely disagree with and said
no no that's that's not it or is there
something like huge that we missed in
the in the space of surface mobility and
I'm just going to check we have about 10
minutes to to uh to have a conversation
so questions comments
Reflections
Carol hello thank you very much it was
very very clear uh just a question about
uh customers and clients uh um could it
be um an important input to see what the
customer is ready is ready to go to to
switch or not to electrical
Vehicles yeah yeah absolutely consumer
sentiment around around electric
vehicles and I think uh jenoa is going
to cover this a little bit in in his
talk as well but let me just briefly say
this I mean first of all it's surprising
that I think electric vehicles got
caught up in a little bit of that Trend
about the
politicalization of mobility and it
became almost a sign of you know who you
vote for what your political party is
and I mean even here in this country
even cooktops became a political issue
do you cook with electricity or with
natural gas and so I think there is that
Dimension uh that that has uh entered
the equation but I think consumers are
learning more about electric vehicles a
major factor on the consumer side is the
charging system and so we started
looking at the reliability of the
charging
infrastructure two and a half years ago
and realized very quickly it's not good
the reliability of the public electric
vehicle charging infrastructure in the
United States is not good and we thought
that with the investment that the
current Administration has made you know
$7.5 billion in electric vehicle
charging that we would see some
significant improvements in that
reliability and it seems to me like we
definitely saw a big Improvement in the
availability of public EV charging the
um you know the Gabe Klein who runs the
joint office will tell you that they've
doubled the number of EV Chargers in the
US which is great that's a great
accomplishment but Camille Terry who
runs charger help which is a startup
company out of Los Angeles where their
whole business was let's go and fix
broken electric vehicle Chargers and
understand why they're
broken they just did a reliability study
over the summer that she shared with us
at our at our vision day and the numbers
were are really concerning I mean we're
still at under 80% reliability true
reliability of EV Chargers in this
country I mean you still have more than
a one in five chance that you're not
going to get the electrons any electrons
or the electrons that you thought you
would get the rate of charging that you
thought you would get and so that starts
to have a backlash effect on how you
know consumers feel um about
electrification uh so I have a question
so today we you don't much mention about
EV oil like fra but so how do you think
about such kind of fi
yeah um you know if we go back to I
mentioned in
2021 which was we had two things happen
we had tremendous amounts of capital
Venture Capital particularly invested in
the mobility space and we had the spack
wave happen as well which is another
story but the if you look at where those
dollars were invested Three core spaces
dominated about 80% of it so Electric
vehic iic Les and batteries autonomous
mobility and the third one being the
question that you asked about electric
vertical takeoff and Landing
vehicles um we don't we don't do a lot
of work in this space we're running a
project in Detroit that looks at sort of
the equity implications of drone
delivery systems but when you talk about
people moving being picked up in the air
and moved
around what we have seen is a shift in
thinking from Urban aerial Mobility
which is I'm going to zip around Mexico
City I'm going to zip around Los Angeles
or Tokyo in this vehicle that comes this
Air Taxi that comes and picks me up and
moves me to another location we've seen
a shift in thinking from that model to
more what we could call Regional aerial
Mobility which is to say I'm going to
get from here to Providence Rhode Island
in a in a EV tall some maybe not even as
far as New York New York City but some
place where there's there is a real
market and and this vehicle actually
makes sense to deploy in that kind of
point pointto point mark rate and we've
seen experiments with um you know for uh
for airport connection as well and of
course there you have a a market that's
more willing to pay uh you know a
premium to to get to the airport quickly
um so I I can't give you deep ins into
this into this area I don't know if jino
just jump in if you have things to to
contribute okay all right um next
question please thank
you nitpicking uh number
three uh you show that
chart that U had the increase in
pedestrian
Debs that's in
percentages what are the actual numbers
of deaths and and the issue is do you
take into account the increased bicycle
and other kind of Transportation modes
that make
pedestrians you know collide with
vehicles uh because I mean look at the
Boston area we used to have a couple of
bicycles on the road we now have lots of
bicycles on the road the road so that
increases the potential conflict between
the two uh the the cars have gotten
bigger and heavier but they're also
gotten safer in terms of technology that
allows you to avoid things the cars have
gotten safer for the occupants of the
vehicle so what they haven't gotten is
safer for those outside of the vehicle
and in in fact The Economist ran a very
clever study simple simple study this
past summer that some of you might have
seen they ran a a cover article called
America's killer cars and what they
looked at is the the the chance of a
fatality inside the vehicle as a
passenger or driver clearly decreases as
the vehicle weight increases that's
intuitive right I mean if I'm driving a
big hulking heavy pickup truck and I
collide with a typical vehicle I'm less
likely to be hurt but then they looked
at the occupants of the other vehicle
and and you know when you see when a
large pickup truck hits a Honda Civic
it's a very bad equation for the
occupant of the of the Honda Civic
right it's still it's still bad exactly
exactly and I think you rais a good
point that we've seen we've seen a rise
in uh bike Lanes in the United States we
absolutely have and we've I guess maybe
in some cities You could argue we've
seen a rise of pedestrianization we'd
have to ask Andreas this question
but our sense is that that does not
that's not the the main causal driver
here right of what what's driving
remember this is a percentage you're
correct but the overall is an increase
toward 40 3,000 fatalities you know and
that number was was in the low
30,000 just 10 years ago so our the faat
the road fatality rate in the US has
overall has been increasing
significantly for the past 10 or 15
years and then on top of that then you
have this proportionality issue as well
and I'll just say one more thing if you
look at the number of fatality I have
this chart maybe I can pull it up if you
look at the number of Road fatalities in
the United States per 100,000 people
it's a very crude metric and you compare
that to the countries in Europe and you
compare that to Canada the United States
is not in an enviable position at all in
fact we are number one in the way that
you don't want to be number one we're
number one by significant margin and
that rate is five times worse than in
Scandinavian countries which happen to
be the lower end of the European
countries it's also worse in in than
Canada now you can say look in the
United States we drive further than they
do in Luxembourg that is true the
typical American drives more and
therefore there's more likely to be a
fatality and that VMT difference vehicle
miles traveled difference that accounts
for some of the difference in the
fatality rate but it does not account
for all of it in fact it it doesn't
really account for half of it so there's
something going on in this country and I
think that this thing about car bloat is
a is a reasonable Contender for you know
what's what's driving those uh
fatalities um and I think okay let's do
one more question excuse me sorry
um I had a question about the uh
autonomous mobility
and just the idea that the cost could
shift uh Mobility towards you know
autonomous are you looking at it sort of
like the same Trend with the gig economy
um Uber versus taxis Airbnb versus
hotels um what kind of lessons can we
learn from
that okay well there's a a lot to unpack
here it's a great question so the first
thing we have to recognize is when Uber
and Lyft were introduced they were sold
as environmentally friendly Solutions
because the idea was going to be that
people would drive less and that they
would share rides and you remember the
early days of lift when there was a pink
fuzzy mustache on the front of the
vehicle and the idea was not that you
sat in the back seat the idea was that
sat in the front seat and shared a ride
with somebody who happened to be driving
from Kendall Square where we are now
over to coolage corner on the other side
of the
river that's not the reality of what it
became it became four higher Services
right where the people would sit in the
back and then when you look at the
amount of time that Uber and lifts spend
um driving around empty this uh kind of
so-called Dead Heading where they're
basically going either waiting for a new
assignment or driving to go and pick up
a
passenger the environmental implications
of that are are not are not good at at
all so that may not have been the exact
question that you're asking but that's
kind of with there's a long sort of you
know history now to this is not to knock
on Uber oryt in in any way I think
they're you know great services and it's
transform the way that we move around
and it's wonderful to have choices out
there and to be able to make these you
to have a a greater portfolio of options
in Mobility but let's not fool ourselves
that it is something that's like saving
the planet it's that movement towards
shared Mobility that will drive you know
the environmental sustainability of
transportation and of course there's
nothing more shared than you know a
public transportation system
yeah is just decrease in cost enough to
drive human behavior towards trusting
autonomous Mobility across the board in
the same way that you can willingly just
go live in a stranger's house rather
than a established Hotel
think it's a great point and actually
I'm really glad you brought up trust
because I mean if you think about it
let's go back again to ride hail to Uber
and lft if you told somebody 20 years
ago you're going to push a button on
your phone some guy's going to pull up
in his you know in his Honda and you're
going to jump in the back seat and you
don't know this person at all you might
have said well I'm not doing that I
don't trust that person but trust became
quickly established and I would think
that what we're seeing in in in Wuhan as
may be a test case and in San Francisco
and other places is trust and Phoenix
trust does start to get established
right people will start to trust the
system provided that you can there's
some perception that this that the
safety is is there and I I think that's
kind of what's the you know the big
question in autonomous Mobility has
always been how safe is safe enough
I would just say this this is so hard to
quantify but it does certainly seem when
you look at the like studies that are
coming out of wh and so forth it does
certainly seem that autonomous Mobility
is getting safer