[Applause]
we're so honored to be part of the ILP
and the startup exchange hi everyone I'm
Katie tro Taylor CEO and co-founder of
narti AI and we're The Trusted AI
research and writing platform for
innovators we help Enterprises launch
products and discoveries to Market 20
times faster that's the kpi that we're
tracking across the Enterprises who have
adopted our technology and it's really
designed to help product and Tech teams
in R&D be able to share the technical
Nar narrative much much faster and get
through product documentation so that
they can ultimately ship better faster
products that customers
love across all of our Enterprise
engagements uh most of our users say
that this saves them nine hours per
person per week and when you drill down
and ask them well what are your people
doing to reallocate that time they say
they're spending it innovating more
strategically spending more time with
customers falling in love with the
customers problems and being able to
share the right discoveries to those
groups I want to share a little bit
about our journey and how we came up out
of seale here at MIT we've been uh we
were founded about three years ago first
concepted um as a an organization to
help use AI to support technical
documentation technical writing
especially within manufacturing and
industries where it's a major paino it's
taking up 30% of a product and R&D
professionals workday and we we had
essentially created a knowledge base of
narrative algorithms that were proven to
be more clarifying or convincing and
mapped them to different types of
product Innovation things like metaphors
are more helpful to a consumer when
they're uh when they're used to explain
a product iteration but metaphors will
absolutely leave the consumer confused
and baffled if you use them to
articulate a futuring
concept because of much of that research
and our team's background my my PhD is
in narrative science
um we were tapped by open AI really
before most folks even knew what open AI
was doing in their big skyscraper in San
Francisco and we were one of their first
seven developer ambassadors we launched
and built proof of concepts with our
earliest adopters um and then finally
launched publicly about a year and a
half ago and we've been growing and
scaling ever
since when we started this journey
because we were alive sort of before the
chat GPT uh user experience took the
World by stor we always asked how can we
embed AI into teams authoring and
research workflows and make their lives
easier and so we thought really outside
of a chatbot design we broke the chatbot
from the very start and we said why
don't we create an AI that prompts you
like a great colleague would or a great
mentor would you they ask the right
questions that's what makes an amazing
colleague so valuable and so narti is
designed to ask you the right questions
and help you um share your best ideas
and then it co authors those into
product requirements documents concept
notes pitches technical reports and
fully designed presentation
decks and so it's true oh I I think this
demo unfortunately isn't working but um
please do come see me and I'll be happy
to share more insight into the actual
technology oh there it goes never mind
[Music]
um we'll try one last time if not please
come see me in the expo hall oh okay
anyhow I'm happy to share more about how
it does that and what it looks and feels
like but um because we designed an AI
that prompts you uh immediately our
product and R&D users said well how can
we then do more research with this
technology so we built a research Hub
inside of narti and you can ask the AI
any research question and it will pull
for millions of peer-reviewed and
competitive gray literature and Trends
reports and it'll enable you to select
into those sources and build Out full
literature reviews and evidence tables
20 times faster than we've been able to
with human intelligence to date you can
also upload existing sources and API
into technical repositories within your
company safely and securely and be able
to extract out methodologies key
findings and even gaps in
Opportunities we also then created an
ability to allow you to capture stories
and insights at scale so in Nar ties you
can create a UR uh URL or a QR code that
that someone can scan if you scan this
actually you'll get to see what the
experience is like the AI starts to
prompt you and it then co-authors your
Innovation idea or your challenge
statement or your product review and
then as a narrati user all of those Rich
stories show up within your feed and you
can extract insights across them or use
them for your Innovation efforts and
this is really where we're growing and
scaling we're about to announce another
raise uh in October and I'm so proud of
our team for achieving this next
Milestone and our journey and we're
going to be able to uh not just
essentially build complex graph rag
systems that call appropriately into the
right Source within your company but
also leverage the rich real-time
insights that the narrati platform is
inspiring folks to share and build that
back into the core knowledge of your
company we've been so proud to grow in
scale within some of the world's most
Innovative organizations helping them
hypers speed best practices and
Technical communication and storytelling
and uh even to see some of the data
coming out around how this platform is
more uh is helping professionals be much
more effective and even though it's
taking maybe a second longer than their
use of chat GPT they're actually
successful in crafting Tech uh
technically accurate and professionally
appropriate Communications in the
platform so this is my ask for you today
please do come say hello to me in the
expo hall I'd be proud to meet you would
love introductions to our next
Innovative customers
um we specialize in advanced Industries
as you could tell from some of our
existing go to market and so would love
to make that uh continue to grow with
you and with the MIT Network you can
start free today actually um and get
started we also do Enterprise free
trials where we track kpis and help you
validate quickly whether this is the
right solution for you and I would love
to meet with you please feel free to
scan that again I'm Katie trout Taylor
CEO co-founder of narat ties