hello my name is Josh Santos and I'm the
co-founder and CEO of noya I'm an MIT
chemical engineer and I have the
pleasure of working with this incredible
team of people here that you see behind
me we're based in Oakland California and
we're working on what I believe to be
the world's biggest problem which is
climate change I think it's the biggest
problem because uh I uh because it puts
places like this at risk I took this
picture in a mile five of a 13m hike at
a place called Glacier National Park in
the United States and this place and
many others like it are places that are
at risk due to our changing climate my
vision for the future and our vision at
Noya is that we can provide the same
exact planet that we experienced during
our lifetimes to all future humans and
generations and the reason that this is
hard is because we are not decarbonizing
our planet fast enough to actually allow
for us to meet that shared Vision that
we have Noya the gray bit that you see
at the top here represents Humanity's
carbon emissions over the past 50
years I don't know what that looks like
to you but that looks like it's getting
bigger over time to me and that is in
fact the case we have been growing our
emissions dramatically over the past 50
years the United Nations in 2018 stated
for the first time that for us to
maintain a chance of giving a happy and
healthy planet to Future Generations we
need to do something called carbon
removal which is a sweet of Technologies
to actively pull historic CO2 emissions
out of the
atmosphere we need to scale this
industry fast if we want to maintain
that Vision to the tune of 50% year
on-year for the next 25 plus years to
say that differently that's the same
thing as growing in new industry from
nothing to the size of the oil and gas
industry and less than half the time it
took the oil and gas industry to get
there that's a massive Challenge and one
that is made even harder by the fact
that there are new industri
that are coming up specifically
artificial intelligence that's driving
up emissions of companies and Nations
worldwide it's driving up demand for
clean electricity that the rest of us
need in order to decarbonize the economy
and it's continuing to drive up the
demand for what we're building at Noya a
carbon removal approach so we have a
need to decarbonize we have challenges
that are very real and being made even
harder by all of what's happening in the
world around us and thankfully at Noya
we're bu we're building something that's
designed for this moment our technology
is built to permanently remove carbon
dioxide from the atmosphere while
producing lots of clean water and
operating in a very interruptible and
intermittent way we are flexible on how
we consume power and right now I'll tell
you how it
works in step one we move air through
what we call a module I like to describe
our technology as a solar panel for
carbon negativity because we can build
multiple of the same design to achieve
an increasingly large
scale as we move air through that
equipment that that contains a material
that we have engineered to capture both
CO2 and water from the atmosphere the
CO2 and water stay behind so that a
cleaner drier air move out of the back
of
it in step two we turn on electricity
every other approach to direct air
carbon capture which is what we're
developing at Noya requires a big
expensive piece of Capital Equipment
that makes something hot like an oven or
a kiln or steam generator that requires
base load electricity to run efficiently
Bas load meaning 24 7 electricity that's
really hard to get if your main way of
delivering and and creating Renewable
Power is uh is through solar and wind we
are different in that we can deliver
electricity directly to our material
that we've engineered and flow currents
through it to release the CO2 and water
that we've captured this allows us to be
flexible in how we consume power and
integrate with existing large loads and
we'll talk more about in a
second when we run power through our
through our material the CO2 and water
come out in a gaseous pure State and we
move them out of our equipment so that
we can use the equipment to capture more
CO2 we then separate the CO2 and water
from each other the water we have no
need for and so we sell it to folks that
have a big need for it like data center
companies Industrials and agriculture
some of our earliest clients and the CO2
we are currently planning to inject that
underground so it no longer warms the
planet in the atmosphere but we can also
put that CO2 to work in CCU applications
where you're taking CO2 and turning into
into new types of
products this unlocks two benefits that
are very unique in direct air capture
that we are the only company to be able
to actually harness due to the
technology that we're building the first
is that we can turn our equipment on and
off like a light switch the lights you
see above us here that makes us able to
Source really cheap really clean power
in a way that no other large industrial
climate Tech startup can and it also
allows us to integrate with large
existing loads like data centers and
other large loads to use the Excess
power that they are not consuming to
consume it ourselves to create CO2
removal the second benefit I mentioned
we produce lots of water from the
atmosphere we produce between 5 to seven
tons or 5 to seven cubic meters of water
per ton of CO2 that we capture we have
no need for that water and we believe
that at our full commercial capacity of
1 million tons per year with our
technology that water can change the
lives of many people around our projects
especially for building in water
stressed areas additionally we can sell
that water to generate additional remove
additional Revenue to subsidize the cost
of our carbon removal
technology we've got an incredible team
of folks my background as I mentioned is
in chemical engineering at MIT I also
worked at Tesla scaling up the model 3
Program I joined the week after the
model 3 launched and spent a lot of time
in manufacturing lines which is exactly
the expertise we're using at NOA in
addition to the expertise that our head
of equipment engineering JC has to help
us ensure that our module mod are being
designed for manufacturing from day
one John Greenfield is on our team he
scaled up Industrial Products he's right
here in Tokyo with us come say hi to us
later on today Sylvia actually worked at
a Japanese corporation kioser I'm sure
many of you know that company she
developed solar panel materials and
actually held the world record for solar
panel material performance for four
years when she was at
Kera so we have an incredible team of
folks who have scaled Industrial
Products before and are ready to do it
again we're currently working on
building our first demonstration
facility of our technology in the San
Francisco Bay Area that's where we're
based and that's where we're building
this piece of equipment this is going to
be operational uh it's going to be uh
the installation will be completed at
the end of q1 and it will be operational
in April we're also developing our first
commercial facility across three
different locations in the US California
Louisiana and Texas that facility will
start at a capacity of 1,000 tons per
year and scale over time to our full
commercial facility capacity of 1
million tons per year this facility will
start delivering its first credits in q1
of 2027 in addition to delivering its
first water to local water
consumers we've got some incredible
Partners as carbon removal credit
customers that we've been able to sign
the largest customer that we have so far
is Shopify we have others that are not
on the screen and we have some water
customers that we are also signing right
now as we speak to ensure that we can
offer the full Suite of benefits that
our carbon removal technology carries
with it here in Japan we've learned a
lot uh over the past week we've had uh
we've had lots of meetings with Japanese
corporations and what we've learned is
that not only are lots of Japanese
companies interested in DAC but they're
interested because of the potential it
has to support the GX ETS commitments
that a lot of companies are required to
comply with direct our capture is a way
for Japanese corporations to comply with
those regulations and so we are here to
talk about how we might support you in
meeting those Meeting those requirements
additionally if you got if you if you
have a a big need for lots of water and
you want that water clean and pure we'd
love to talk to you about it and um and
if you're looking to invest new project
capital or Equity Capital into a uh into
a very young and exciting startup that's
talking about changing the world we'd
love to talk to
you as I said John my colleague and I
are going to be right across the way
here over lunch this is a this is a
picture of the very first module that we
built here at our office in Oakland or
in our office in Oakland and um we'd
love to continue the conversation and
tell you what the heck's actually going
on inside of this thing thank you very
much for your time and really looking
forward talking