Thank you and good morning everybody.
Let me start this again.
>> Good morning.
>> Two out of 10 to be not great. So um
I'll try to cover all this in half an
hour. I had to just before the talk to
take some slides out because I was told
it will be half an hour. Anyway, so we
start what what I call when we deal with
disruptions and resilience
the anacarina principle. What is the
anacarina principle? To wrote happy
families are all alike. Unhappy family
are each unhappy family is unhappy in
its own way. And you know every
disruption to supply chain to to the
economy comes in its own its own way its
own causes its own its own effect. No
two are the same. But turn out that
management of risk involve prevention
detection response. There are generic
preparation step that are good for most
type of risk most type of of disruption.
If you open a book on risks, the first
thing that you'll usually see is
two-dimensional classification.
People try to prioritize what to respond
to by trying to see what event what
disruption can how likely it is to come
and if it comes how bad it's going to
be. So usually they do you see it in
every risk book they usually do the
disruption probability and the
consequences if it happen it can be say
probability or likelihood go from low to
high the consequences can be light or
severe and they put that's just example
they put all kind of events in order to
think about how to prioritize
and in most book you'll find something
like this it's called heat map and they
say the most the things that you should
pay attention to are the things that are
high probability and bad consequences.
The only problem with this is that it's
actually wrong because what you have to
worry about are these things. The things
that are very low probability and high
risk or severe consequences.
These are the so-cal black swans
Talib in his book called it black swan.
black swan were you know European
thought that black swans don't exist
until they found one in Australia. So
these are the the risks that you don't
anticipate and the reason that it's not
that you should not worry about the
risks that are high probability and and
and large consequences but you can
identify them if it's a high probability
they happen to you they happen to your
competitors they happen to somebody
already and you can prepare response and
you can drill because you can prepare
for them. The problem with this uh low
probability is that you don't know what
to expect. And just an anecdote after
911, the Pentagon hired fiction writers,
sci-fi fiction writer to start to
imagine what will be the next attack
because they were caught
unprepared so to say. And you can for
this you can prepare you know what we
call general general response.
The the term resilience is actually
taken from material science is the
ability of of a metal or other material
to retain its shape after deformation.
When we talk about business resilience
or organization resilience we're talking
about the ability to get back to its
prior
performance prior KPI. it it could be
manufacturing, it could be customer
service, whatever.
So I actually
that was in my first book and my second
book I added another dimension because
these are the two the two dimension we
talk about but I added another
dimension. This is the detectability,
the time from you get some information
that something is happening until it
actually hits. And
this is how long it takes from sensing
to impact.
This axis is different than the other
two. Usually I ask my students why. So
I'm not going to embarrass anybody. It's
different because it has a negative
part. This axis has negative part which
means some events can be realized only
after the fact you don't realize them
before you know. So what you can realize
after the fact is you industrial
espionage somebody stole the plans for
the next great product the some pathogen
sleeping pathogen you know
let me say a word about it the most when
we do simulation of what can destroy
societies it's not a nuclear bomb in New
York Harbor actually it's a pathogen
that does not show any symptom until the
entire population is infected
In fact, COVID 19 had some of this.
COVID 19 was infectious when people did
not show any symptoms. In fact, there's
a whole I wrote a whole book about it
and it's about supply chain during
uh COVID 19. And there were German
scientists, a woman German scientist
that scream bloody hell that people are
infected without showing symptoms.
the French government, the Swedish
government, the American government, all
men laugh at her said it cannot happen.
It's against all men. Only the only
problem is she was right. Of course, a
cyber agent, you know, when somebody
attack your systems and you find it only
later. Somebody stole all customers uh
data
something immediate tsunami center that
tsunami all around the uh uh the sensor
all around the Pacific coast and when
there's a tsunami there are actually
alarm throughout the beaches from
Vancouver to the southern tip of Chile
and when something is being detected the
alarms going on to get people off the
off the beach This can be between five
seconds and two hours depending on where
the tsunami is over few hours.
Short-term of course weather forecast we
can know within two three days. Uh
medium-term can be deteriorating labor
relationship strike might might come
superior competition some Nokia thinking
that a computer company will never
develop a product that can be
competitive.
The result is going from 67% worldwide
market share to 3%.
Um
then there's long you can think about
long term um aging of the population now
happening in the United States happening
in many other country you know the the
number the replacement number is 2.1
children per woman at 2.1 children per
woman society stays about the same
level.
South Korea is a 0.8.
Within one generation, they're going to
be half their size.
China already reached peak, but that's
because of the one child policy. Uh
southern Europe is not in good shape,
and the United States now is not in good
shape. It it used to we are now at 1.7
or so. We used to be above above two.
A global warming, of course, and there
are other long long-term effects. And of
course the dangers are
the more immediate it is the more
dangerous it is. And if it's long-term
there's actually an opportunity a
business opportunity and you can even
think about climate change many many
business opportunity built into into
climate change. I we can talk about it
later.
So
many companies invest in what's called
visibility
trying to see what's coming down because
they allow if you sense problem early
the earliest you sense a problem the
better you can response
so how do you prepare you know you
prepare option for for the respondent
you multisourcing for example again I'm
not going to spend a lot of time I'm
trying to run quickly leave maybe two
minutes for questioning. So you can
either if you look at this you can
either do you can either have a
you know if you have one supplier you
better have very strong relationship
with them. If you have if you don't it's
expensive but if you don't you have you
better have multiple suppliers. That's
what this is this is trying to show. Of
course keeping emergency inventory
something that companies are now trying
to do.
What we have now is a lot of apps that
do supplier mapping that you know where
the and this is not easy because knowing
where the supplier is. You need to know
where the supplier's factory is not when
the headquarters if you go into the SAP
system you see where you send the check.
That's not where the where the action
is. You need to know where all the
plants are. But anyway, there's a um
there are apps to to um to find out if
something is going on there and then a
lot of it is in news, a lot of it in
other but the trick is what people what
some companies did they tied the bill of
material
to this risk. So they know that if
something happen in northern Italy, this
supplier plant that makes this part is
going to be out of commission and this
parts going to this products and this
product going to these customers. So we
better alert the customers and customers
can be alerted within seconds that
something has a problem.
uh flexibility of being able to move
fast and there are many elements of
flexibility you know whether it's cross
trainining whether it's a
standardization you know all interplant
are standardized
being able to collaborate have good
relationship with other companies and I
can talk about at length about all of
this the problem with talking to half an
hour is I'm trying to summarize six
years of research and four books into 30
minutes so I missing some part. Um,
postponement we'll talk about in a
minute. And culture,
what do you mean by culture?
Flexibility. Culture is the ability to
speak truth to power. The ability to
move information to decision making very
quickly.
Another element is having decision
making close to the action. So the
frontline people can make can take
action without going all the way up.
This is this does not only happen in
um in crisis. One company is very good
in this is Zara.
Quick example few years ago Madona had a
concert in Barcelona.
Three weeks later, she had a concert in
Madrid, and all the young women in the
audience were wearing the same outfit
that she wore in Barcelona. Within three
weeks, Zara was able to redesign, send
it to manufacturing. It's all local, and
send it to stores.
It would have taken Marks and Spencer
about 10 months to do something like
because there was no the young designers
who were there had the right to do it.
And the trick is of course in all of
these things is praising them when right
but never punishing people who are in
the front line when they're wrong.
Difference to expertise it's another
thing that expertise
trump
um rank. So if you are on the
tower in uh in JFK and it's foggy and
it's rainy and there two pilots who
hardly speak English around you.
Suddenly you see something amazing
happen. Suddenly the controllers stop
listening to the FAA managers. They're
starting to ask questions of the veteran
controllers people who are there for a
long time. Experienced Trump's rank.
This this is happening in nuclear power
plants. It happened in many high-risk
environment. It happens in the military
and good organization understand and
encourage it and conditioning for
disruption. I mean the organization
airlines airlines are conditioned
disrupted all the time. So honestly they
get used they simply get good at it at
responding.
Um
the essence of flexibility is
interchangeability. For example, all all
interplant are the same. Basically, uh
it started from the old days of um
making chips when getting a good yield
out of a wafer or getting a bad yield
out of a wafer is the difference between
making a lot of money and losing a lot
of money. So once they got it right,
management say copy these suckers around
the world and you know partsization that
anyway lots of examples here. I can go
more of these the product standatization
the example here is the difference
between the treat you know you can order
Mercedes E-Class in Germany not in the
United States in 3.9 trillion
combinations you can order it any way
you want so think about when you have a
recall you don't know which car you have
by comparison Honda Accord which sell by
the way a lot more cars than um than
Mercedes has only 529 combinations
um pliable people people are basically
cross trains and many examples of this
postponement is something that
I have several examples I'll talk only
about one Tom Brady my favorite
quarterback
retired unfortunately for those in the
United States you know what you're
talking about um
you know you don't know at the beginning
of the
which team and which player
will catch the fancy of the fans. So you
make basic
basic jersey they make in in Costa Rica
and some of them they they come with a
color of the team.
No, almost none come with a name because
what happens is they send it to a center
in Indianapolis and then only once the
season starts and they see what's going
on, they finish it. So it costs more but
it sells a lot more.
Anyway, many more example. You know the
basic of crisis management is having an
emergency management center
concentrating all information decision
making one place and communicating a lot
if theo don't or anybody not
communicating to the market to the to
the communities to the analysts people
will assume the worst decision making
authority you know and protocol you know
in many risks companies look like
children playing soccer everybody's
running after the ball everybody's
trying to help And GM had a term for
this. He says swim your lane just do
your job. Don't don't interfere. And in
my books I have many other examples when
you know senior VP came and had you know
made all kind of decisions that were
screwing up the whole the whole system.
Uh look at suppliers
review the product and customer. You
have to make decision ahead of time. If
you don't have enough to build the
product for all the customer who gets
the product and what and it's better
done before the crisis not under the
gun. Uh finance of course if there's a
recession or problem you know cash
becomes king and people start
you know lengthening the term of payment
to uh to supplier putting them putting
them at risk. People reduce the number
of stocking unit. So for example,
General Mill during COVID went from 90
variety to 50 variety. This does two
good things. First of all, it keeps the
the best sellers on the shelves and
second, it reduces cost because you have
less changeovers. So
planning for the recovery, you know,
it's a
it's really crisis are an awful thing to
waste. You find out who are the good
suppliers, who are the good customers,
who are the good employees. Some of
today's issue we talk about tariffs
and I explain let me skip this I
explaining why trade in the first place
and we can talk about it but let me let
me skip it for for for the sake of time.
It's a simple example that shows that
even if one country is better than
another country in everything,
they should still trade. They can both
get advantage from from trading.
So the reason for the current tariffs
are pretty clear. Um other countries
mainly China did take advantage of the
United States. That's a you know whether
you like tariffs or not you have to
acknowledge that there was problem with
intellectual property and all kind of
barriers and currency manipulation and
state support. So this administration
decide to do something about the trade
deficit was was going through the roof.
So um so what they do decide to do
tariffs however tariffs are problematic.
We all know that reshoring will take
decades. real reshoring of entire
because you don't reshore just the last
stage of manufacturing you have to
reshore the entire supply chain between
the supplier and their supplier their
supplier their supply takes decades um
the US does not have enough workers does
not have enough factory workers so who
is going to manage who's going to work
in all these factories then of course
tariffs create gets more tariffs it it's
there's always retaliation and
retaliation to the retaliation. The
stickiness some companies like it
because they their competitors are now
tariffs and their costs are higher so
they can increase cost. It can lead to
inflation, loss of product quality. If
you don't if you don't have to compete
worldwide,
quality over time will go down. Uh
possible recession. Not even clear that
tariff will help because reduce imports
there will also be reduced export
because companies because other other
countries will respond and then what we
see now is dumping when Chinese is
particular China huge manufacturing uh
capacity creates a lot of extra stuff
that is dumped all over
um creating problem. The uncertainty is
of course the major problem. Um this is
this is more a slide for some of your
supply chain manager how how you deal
with the tariff when when you have to
pay attention to it. There's a after
several processes it it goes to the
custom and border protection page.
That's the only page that counts.
everything the white house said and all
this don't pay any attention because
this exactly show what is the tariff on
exactly what product and at what rate
and then the question is who should
carry the burden the supplier the the
company the customer the retailer you
know China warned Walmart against
pressing Chinese suppliers and Trump
warned Walmart against raising prices so
a little problem
um again some some idea on how on how to
deal with some of this some of these
problems.
The one thing that I want to emphasize
here is the last point, guard customer
trust. Companies who raise prices
because they can
uh have are in danger of losing customer
trust. Companies may have to raise
prices. If if the tariff goes up by 20%
and Walmart margin is only 4%.
They'll have to do something about it.
But they have to explain it. Explain,
explain and communicate all the time.
So what's next? Uh we'll see what we
call bullip effect. As the tariff is
changing, there's a oscillation that go
through the economy and this is very
much not helpful.
Finally, these are some issues of
concern in general. So, sustainability
may becoming a luxury good. When time
gets tough, people stop paying
attention. Of course, the polarization
of everything. Inequality is growing
now. We see it in the United States. We
see it in in other country. Some people
living large. You know, some stores are
doing great. Yet some people are voting
for Mandi in uh in New York because of
the lack of affordability.
The rise of populism and nationalism
that's you know the examples galore all
over. I even include Mandani here. Um
industrial concentration it's a
long-term issue. The media which with
fake news is now going to be a huge
problem with AI. the next pandemic which
may be which may be more contagious and
deadlier.
Uh to me for the United States the most
worrisome issue is the lousy level of
there's no other way to describe it the
lousy level of education
in the United States.
You know, you heard from the director of
the industrial leazison program about
how great MIT is.
Let me give you a reality check.
I've been at MIT 51 years. I did my
master's PhD at MIT.
We now offer remedial physics for
incoming
incoming students undergrads.
What? At MIT? Yes. Students cannot do
the math.
There is a deterioration of K to2
education. There's a water down of the
SATs.
And this does not look good because
the only
The only good start I can tell you is
that we're honestly better than other
schools, which is not a great, you know,
you know, not a great thing to say, but
it's true. um
AI, we're still dealing with AI, how to
supplement more jobs and we are in for
huge social changes and the US depth is
just going out of going through the roof
and geopolitical event what may happen
with the you know China, Taiwan, who
knows anyway.
All right, let me stop here.
If you want to read more about what I
do, these are some of my books. And then
there are questions. So I let me read
some of the question are hard. Let me
let me rephrase them. The first question
was
are your books available on Amazon?
Yes,
it's a good question. Um,
how will advances in artificial?
How will advanced artificial
intelligence shape supply chain
resilience? And what new risk might AI
itself introduce to global logistic
networks? The real the real answer is
who the hell knows? The problem is I'm
now writing a book on the actual use of
supply chain, the actual use of AI and
supply chain. And it's a problem. The
train is running faster than I can
write.
The technology is moving so fast and
things that six months ago I said this
will not happen. This this is a hurdle
that are now taking place. So it's very
hard hard for me to answer but we see a
lot of automation,
autonomous vehicles, autonomous
warehouses, you know, dark stores, a lot
of these things that work with very few
people. I just landed in Barahas airport
in Spain over last last weekend. Just
came back.
I was stunned. The jetway that comes to
visit to uh to to meet the plan is
robotic. There's no person there. It
just comes that they had a red light
that shut right into the little hole
that the stewardist look through to
decide when to open the door. Then
suddenly it turns green. They open the
door and it fits like this. There's no
step or anything. It's the only airport
in the world that has it. But I was
looking at the future right there. So
they are they didn't want to answer me.
I went to the to the Barahas airport to
the the management asked how many people
work in moving the jetway. Find out how
many people no don't talk we will
reassign them. Reassign them to what? I
mean nobody had an answer. The answer is
some people are going to lose their job.
Some pe many jobs are going to change
but some people are going to lose it. Um
what can university bridge the gap
between theoretical advances in supply
chain analying and the practical
industry partner? Glad you who asked
this question. Best question because you
got you know an advertisement for the
industrial as an office. Now let give
you the the advertisement to the people
who work in the salt mines to the people
who actually do the work. We are the
center for transportation logistics. We
are funded unlike large part of MIT 85%
of our funding comes from companies. We
work directly with companies. Our
students that do the thesis, master of
PhD, they have to work with a company.
They have to to use real data.
Understand that real data does not come
in nice spreadsheet style. You have to
clean it. You have to work with it. You
have to understand it. You have to be
realistic about it. So we are absolutely
an element that bridges the gap in our
in our area. We by the way as long as we
do advertisement I didn't plan on it but
why not? Um we have our own industrial
lean office. We have 50 companies. We're
not as big as the ILO. We have 50
companies and usually
membership in the industrial lean office
is for the techn the the chief
technology officer or the technology
people. Our member are the chief supply
chain officers of all these companies.
We have some of the same companies and
lots of others
around the globe and we work with all of
them. They are students. We we do
masters and PhD. We don't do
undergraduate centers at MIT do not do
undergraduate. They just do graduate. So
we have
it's a big it's the it's the the unknown
biggest secret at MIT. Just give you
some statistics. We have we have an
online program in supply chain
management. We have 1.4 million
learners.
Every country on earth excluding North
Korea. North Korea we didn't break it.
Nobody from North Korea. But every other
country in the world we have we have
people who work in refugee camps who
take it on the phone. So it's huge
impact. We have centers around the world
that we start. We have a whole network
of centers around the world. We have our
own as I say education program. We have
our own um ILO type
thing. So this was a good question that
gave me the opening to give an
advertisement for CTL. If you want to
talk to us, you can find us of course
CTL, Center for Transportation Logistics
at MIT. You can find my name Sheffy.edu.
Just send me an email and we'll be happy
to talk to you. Let me stop here.
>> No, you can go through a few more
questions.
>> Oh, I can go through more of question.
Absolutely. Um,
what can we learn from supply chain
resilience approach to determine ways to
manage workforce planning in the coming
turmoil?
I have I actually have an answer for
you. Amazing. I have part of my group. I
have three students who develop together
we develop of course based on AI. We
develop a system that predicts which
jobs are going to be eliminated, which
jobs are going to be augmented by all
kinds of AI. So this is a
and it's a self-learning system. We just
did it with we so we developed it and
and and gave a theoretical presentation,
but some companies got excited. The
first company that got excited was the
US the Texas Department of
Transportation.
And they are wonderful to work with
because they don't care about privacy.
I'm just they send us database that I
was oh my god anonymize it immediately.
I don't want I don't want names of
people and to have it you know on our
computers but it's wonderful to work
with them and we are working with them
over time to see first of all to check
our forecasts which jobs are going to be
eliminated which jobs are going to be
changed and they are very progressive if
I may say this word about Texas very
progressive
agency See, they really want to become
better. They want to understand how to
work. They want to understand how to
augment the jobs, what kind of uh um
what kind of uh upgrading or education
they should give. This is the
interesting thing is of course we use
very sophisticated AI to get into this
and some huge databases the the the US
labor labor department has in order to
create this type of uh uh of forecast.
We are now doing it for
three companies
doing it you know
getting paid for do it. So we are
improving the algorithm every time we do
another another implementation. Of
course
um
I applaud my I applaud my company that's
a good start somebody like what they
work with I applaud my company for
developing long range view of the future
in a similar fashion to your research. I
find much of the qualitative work
though. Yes. Yes. That's my reason
that's exactly my personal work and
others I
if you look at my books I work on many
many areas. I don't work in one area.
They're kind of all tied to supply chain
all with application to uh to supply
chain. But that's exactly the question
that we looked at. You see all these
estimates that are either based on
anecdotal evidence or economists making
pronouncement but there is no underlying
mathematical rigor. Now honestly at this
point I don't want to claim that
mathematical rigor is better than the
best economics
best economist professor in the world
but uh but it's true. No I'm at least
you have something to I'll tell you
what's the difference. The difference
when you have a structured algorithmic
process is you can make it better and
better all the time because you get more
data, you get more experience, you get
it better and better and better all the
time. As it runs, it gets better
automatically. So it it it learns from
itself and embeds this learning in what
it does. That's part of the magic of the
new AI. So
yes, we do it.
But I should say
data is still a problem. For example,
just some of the database is taken from
the New York Times. The New York 20
million records in the New York Times,
people talking about
what will happen to uh you know to jobs
and some and stories. So we took a lot
of these stories about people losing or
not losing or changing the job. We had
the same type of data from agency France
in in in it's the the Reuter of France.
Um
we have and had huge data sets of the
several data sets of the um labor
department and actually we look at it
just to explain because you ask we look
at the elemental unit is not a job it's
a task. So we know at every jobs the the
this labor department said every job has
multiple tasks and they talk about task
at the job. We look at what task may be
augmented and then we can aggregate it
to jobs to to to industries to companies
to states to countries whatever. So what
we can do because of this just a simple
example so we look at the two jobs and
say we this job is going to lose three
tasks and this job is going to lose two
task maybe in the future there'll be one
job but this is not only oneonone it's
kind of around the whole the whole
component so we reoptimize
everything so
as I said it is still the problem is
that the the technology technology what
people actually use is moving so fast on
and also there's a big difference
between when as I say when everything's
said and done in this area a lot more is
said than done so
my current book which I'm working on is
seeing what's actually being done and is
there ROI on this you know MIT had had a
report that said only 5% of the company
can see any ROI in AI implementation
Maybe I don't know we are checking we
are getting some different uh different
results but it it's hard to get because
it's very hard for a company on an
interview to say yeah we spend you know
a few million dollars but we got nothing
for it. There are not too many
executives that are willing to say
something like this in public. So this
is who knows what it exactly but we are
trying trying to work at it and get
there. Anyway,
let me stop here. Thank you very much.