in this video let us look at a basic yet
important Concept in probability known
as linearity of expectations and use it
to deduce some interesting consequences
in combinatorics via the probabilistic
method linearity of expectations set
that if you're given random variables X1
through XM and constants C1 through
CM then when we took it when we take a
linear combination of these random
variables as such so C1 * X1 so imagine
these are real valued random variables
and these are real constants for
instance then the sum of these uh C1 *
X1 plus C2 * X2 and so on Plus CN * XM
so this sum has
expectation the following which can be
computed by Distributing this
expectation symbol across to the
individual
variables so this is a basic and
important property and it's worth noting
that a similar statement written for
products is often not true so it is not
usually the case that the expectation of
a product of two random
variables is the product of their
expectations unless you're in some
special circumstances such as when X and
Y are independent or
uncorrelated okay anyway let us focus on
the linearity of expectations and see
some ways to use this in combinatorial
applications and the first example is
the following question which will be
able to give a very quick and clean
answer the question is what is the
average number of fixed points of a
permutation of 1 through n
chosen uniformly at random as a reminder
if we
have numbers 1 2 3 4 here n equals to 4
then a permutation can be thought as
some way to map these numbers the sets
back to themselves in one to one
correspondence and a fixed
point is some number
that gets mapped back back to themselves
so in this permutation there are exactly
two fixed
points okay
great let's answer this question using
linearity of
expectations
well one way to think about the problem
is that well there are n factorial
permutations and maybe we want to try to
go about counting how many of them have
zero fixed points how many of them have
one fixed points how many have two fixed
points but that method can get pretty
cumbersome and pretty difficult quite
quickly however if we look at this
problem through the lens of linearity of
expectations there turns out to be a
very quick
solution and the method is to let
introduce some random variables let X I
be a random variable that equals to one
if I is a fixed
Point meaning that in this permutation I
gets mapped to itself and zero
otherwise so X of I is the indicator
random variable for the element I being
a fixed point of this random
permutation what's the expectation of XI
well this is the
probability that I is a fixed point
well this being a uniform permutation
chosen uniformly at random I is sent to
each of the elements 1 through n with
equal probabilities so in particular it
is sent back to itself with probability
1 /
n and then the number of fixed
points equals to the sum of the
X XIs so X1 plus X2 so on to xn and now
we can take expectation of both
sides and apply linearity of
expectations and see that while each
individual term is 1 /
n and there are n such terms so the
answer is one and that is the answer to
this question so the average number of
fixed points of a permutation chosen
uniformly at random is exactly one and
you see that there's a very quick
calculation once you get a hang of the
idea of of linearity of
expectations let us look at a slightly
more interesting
example and for this example we'll
consider the concept of a tournament
okay so a tournament is a concept in
graph Theory referring
to the
following there are nend vertices think
of nend players in some tournament and
between every pair of vertices we have
some directed Edge pointing in one of
these two directions so every pair of
vertices there's some Edge pointing to
one of the two directions
okay so that's an example of a
tournament I'll need to introduce
another concept which is that of a
Hamilton
path so a Hamilton path is a directed
path meaning we travel along the
directions of these ver these edges
according to their directions so
directed path that passes
through each
vertex so every vertex of the graph
exactly once no more no
less so let's see if we can find any
hilon paths in
this in this examp example well I see
one so if we start with the middle
vertex and go along this one this Edge
then this Edge and then this Edge okay
so that's a hemoton path that goes
through all four
vertices each vertex passing through it
exactly once and it always traverses
along the direction of the
edges okay let us prove the following
theorem for every n
and there
exists a
tournament on N
vertices
with at least
n factorial * 2 to the minus
n +
one hoton
paths okay so in other words for every n
there is some way to orient the edges of
the complete graph on N vertices so that
it has lots and lots of Hamilton paths
specifically at least this many okay so
that's a theorem that we're aiming to
prove we will not prove this theorem by
explicitly constructing such a
tournament instead we'll invoke the
probabilistic method and show that a
random tournament has in expectation
this
property so here's the
proof let's consider a random tournament
on N
vertices chosen uniformly at
random one way to do this is to take a
complete graph on n verticy and for
every Edge flip a Fair coin and use that
coin to decide which way the edge
orients of the two different
directions now let's think about the
number of Hamilton paths right so
each
path of the so each um
okay so each of
the N factorial permutations of
vertices
forms a directed
path okay so first consider a
permutation of vertices so for example 2
1 3 3 4 and think about what is the
probability that the edges that go in
the direction of these uh of this
permutation that the edges are all
oriented according to the
permutation well we have to Flip n minus
one coins and all of them have to come
up in such a way so that the edges are
pointing in the direction of this
permutation in order of this permutation
so the probability
that this is a directed path for a for
each of these permutations is precisely
2 to the
minus parenthesis n minus
one okay and now we invoke the linearity
of
expectations to claim that the expected
number of Hamilton
paths must then be well each of the N
factorial permutations has probability
of 2
Theus n minus one of
being a directed path right so this is a
calculation that is analogous to the
calculation that we did in the earlier
part of this
video this is what happens in
expectation on average and
thus there must be some instance where
we can beat this average or at least be
at least as large as this average so
thus
there
exists a
tournament
with at
least this
many Hamilton
paths okay and that concludes the proof
of this theorem that we laid out earlier
so this is an example of applying
linearity expectations as a step in the
probabilistic method to prove this nice
and simple result that there exist
tournaments with lots of Hamilton paths