storage is a bit different because there
isn't really a widely proliferated
um state-of-the-art already. You know,
the form of energy storage we use today
is basically leaving fossil fuels in the
ground. Like we we have like one-time
use storage. So, it's like it's all
stockpiled in the ground. We draw from
it. We use it at the rate that we want.
Um but there isn't really a rechargeable
form of storage above ground that we
that has been widely proliferated.
Lithium ion batteries are are working
their way out, but they're limited on
cost. And so they're going to very
quickly push up against a ceiling um you
know in terms of how much deployment is
going to happen due to cost. And so we
are trying to prep for the second wave
and come right behind them with with
something better that's much cheaper.