welcome to the first video of the third
topic for 21m 383 and this is on streams
as containers in music
21 nearly all
computational music processing systems
especially those that work with scores
have a concept cep of a
container and something that's contained
in it size they're called leaves um
sometimes they're in music 21 they're
called elements or boringly music 21
objects and there usually the concept of
a container whether called it or not the
concept of a leaf whether called it or
not and a third thing we'll talk about
later called spanners This is the
representation from a python music
composition toolkit that works with
musical scores called objat which uses
leaes containers spanners and something
they call indicators which are
attributes in music 21 will be
attributes on
elements so now that we've seen how
containers and elements or leaves work
in general let's look at how containers
work in music 21 where they're called
streams