and uh welcome to the startup exchange
thank you so much for having me I will
be speaking about Lighty AI let me share
my screen so I'm Richard rabbat I was
previously VP of product at Twitter I've
exited my previous startup that I sold
to Snapchat and I've spent a number of
years at Twitter Google Zinga and other
places TW 20 years experience and a PhD
from MIT co-founding team is all MIT
alums as well and the problem that we
decided to address is the fact that with
uh you know AI in general most of these
models have been actually trained on
public data as opposed to capturing the
unique uh unique DNA and of the
Enterprise itself so these AIS that you
use today are not trained on your
private data they're just trained on
publicly available data meanwhile uh
everybody's under pressure to adopt AI
because of productivity Improvement
potential and Lighty AI is an agentic AI
that
allows a company to capture the DNA of
that Enterprise so our llm is very
specific to the Enterprise and it's
powered by a Knowledge Graph and that
Knowledge Graph is all the data that is
collected you know that is private to
the company emails wikis documents
calendars that allow our AI to be much
more effective when it comes to like
supporting uh the organization and the
things that we talk about in terms of
workflows are things all the like all
the way from the beginning from like
onboarding a person to planning and
coaching because like these days you are
we're in a situation where people like
are looking for help to like actually
you know improve their uh their
productivity schuling is a very
important task because like you know
typically people are very interrupted
all the time and we you know our AI
helps you with scheduling Tas
assignments but also tracking of your
objectives and key results all of this
is based on personal personalized
interactions so that the AI like really
speaks to you as an individual the team
and the or the
organization here's an example of the AI
agent at work in this case it is helping
with scheduling a meeting instead of me
conent like looking at my calendar and
trying to like offer some times the AI
will just like look at my calendar
propose it to the other party schedule
it and then put it on the calendar and
I'm not interrupted every interrupt
today actually cost us about 20 minutes
of like know trying to get back into
Zone and like liy basically does away
with all these
interruptions and it's all powered by a
knowledge graph that is private to the
Enterprise this is something that we're
very excited about where like you know
on the day before your next day Lighty
send you an email about like reminder of
like what your plan is for the for the
next day and highlights some issues in
this case I have uh I I'm looking at my
schedule and it looks like I'm like I'm
all set if I need to make some changes I
will ask it like in this case I want to
cancel a meeting I'm going to cancel the
daily leadership syn and lightly does it
I don't have to get out of the flow and
it just does it for me
uh and then finally like as Lighty
learns about you and your goals it like
looks at like how you can actually be
better at like how you manage your time
in this case I've told ly that like I
want to spend spend more time on deep
work and then it looks at my you know
where I'm spending my time and then that
tells me that in this case I should
actually spend more time on like
blocking times for my deep work and
other things as well
uh and then finally like you know we all
come out of meetings and we've had like
a lot of you know action items that we
sometimes forget what liy does is like
actually capture all the transcripts and
turn them into action items and uh you
know follow-ups that so that you're
effectively conducting your meetings and
the post meeting work that you're
doing uh we're looking for additional
Pilots we have we already have some
companies Enterprises and mid Market
in this case we would like to you know
work with more Enterprises to like help
teams accomplish more and like deliver
on their goals and objectives uh we you
know we propose a two- Monon pilot where
we you know identify specific kpis to
deliver on and really solving about like
each Enterprises unique problems thank
you this is my email I'd love to have
more conversations with you as we
progress through this uh day demo day
thank you Richard let me um ask a couple
of questions again a reminder post your
questions um in the
Q&A and um I'll start with one um some
companies are still trying to figure out
where best to use AI so how would you
work with those
companies so we we actually spent some
time like working with uh the companies
asking about like what problems they are
trying to solve because like you know AI
is not about like you know putting a a
technology and just like making it
available so you can say I'm using AI
it's about like solving specific
problems in this case we look at like
specific ways of improving productivity
where we see uh that a company like one
of the teams are like you know
struggling to like meet their goals and
objectives and then we work with them
and we bring liy to like help with
improving that
productivity and you stay on how does
that what's the bus yeah so so it's a
it's a it's a PL platform that like you
know becomes available it first can be
used by a team and then we we usually
extend it to other teams as as uh you
know people get to see like the value
and then they can you know on board to
that to the platform as well great and
then another question um can you combine
it with other uh communication apps like
teams and others yes so this is like
what's really great about like liy like
light is a platform that connects with
multiple ways like teams uh Outlook
slack and other systems notion and like
you know whatever you use because like
we know that like communication happens
and uh happens in different ways and we
adapt to each company's unique way of
communicating okay Richard thank you so
much and again you can engage further
with Richard in the chat and in the
breakout rooms