(upbeat music)
- The type of data robot learning needs
has to be a lot more flexible
and has to contain real
physics so a robot knows
how to interact with the world.
As it turned out, there are these things
called generated models
that can produce realistic
and very diverse images on
demand if you tell the model
what you want in the language we speak.
So our key insight is that we
can use these generated models
as internet scale data on steroids
or internet scale data on demand,
and use these models to generate the data
for the robot to learn from.
This is what the robot sees.
Each frame is rendered
with a generative model.
By flashing between
different visual experiences,
the robot gains an understanding
of the many ways the world might look.
So our research program
is called Lucid Sim.
It's a simulated learning
environment for like robots
to learn how to do visual
parkour from generated images.
If you really want household robots
that can live in the same room as we do,
you need robots that have legs.
The impact of our research is
to give robots the mobility
and needs to operate in the
places like our humans live in.
- Typically, people use image
generative models to make art,
but here what we want to
do is teach the robot how
to master its environment.
What we really want is to have
the physics from the physics
engine drive the image generation process,
and the complication here is
that you typically don't
have any control over the
composition of the image that you produce.
Fortunately, turns out
that this technique called
control net, which allows you
to control the composition of the image
through means like depth or semantics.
So that's how we make these
images realistic physics wise,
the second problem that we
face is that we want the robot
to take in a series of images
rather than a single frame.
So we develop dreams in motion,
which helps us generate
subsequent frames from a single
generated image that aligns
with the robot's movement and experience.
So there's a technique called
image warping, which amounts
to moving around the pixels
in an image in accordance
to changes in a robot's
camera perspective.
- If you just teach the robot
using data from another robot
actually wouldn't work very well.
So it's really, really
important for the robot
to learn from its own
data that's generated
by its own actions.
And this type of data is
called on-policy data.
So with this paper, we show
that on-policy data is
responsible for most
of the performance of the robot
that's learning in the end.
(upbeat music)
If we look at robotics as a whole,
there are really three
problems that we have to solve.
The first problem is how to produce robots
and performing policies,
and that's Lucid Sim.
Once you master individual policies,
then the next question is
how you can get the number
of skills you need so
that when the robot enters the
real world, it doesn't have
to learn new skills on
the fly from scratch.
Now the third problem is
a little bit more subtle,
and I believe the hardest
problems in robotics are not
problems in robotics, but
problems with intelligence itself.
So the final part of
this program is to expand
what Lucid Sim does on individual
skills to an entire quest
that involve many, many steps.
And the goal of the third
step is to give robots ability
to handle these long horizon
tasks and to reason about
and to explore the open
world at its own will.
We're so excited for you to see Lucid Sim
and what these robots are capable
of doing in the real world.
I truly believe that this is
how you'll be training
your robot in the future.
That is to learn from generated data.