In here. They don't want perfection.
They want talent.
They want willingness to improve.
They want beliefs, conviction, values.
Show MIT how you are special.
Why you are special.
And you will be here.
Sometimes we just
feel that we don't have the capabilities.
We don't have the skills.
We are not good enough
and we just tell this story
one time
and add another, another, another.
And it's like, a recorded cassette
that we have in our minds.
We are capable,
we are smart, we are powerful.
And when we are determined,
we can do everything.
Remember how unique you are,
all the things that you've done.
And then if you made it so far,
why can't you go even further?
I actually postponed my application for a
while because of the fear of failure.
I believe that the first thing
you should make sure
is that you don't let the fear of failure
paralyze you.
The worst thing that can happen
is that you don't get approved.
And you know what? It's okay.
There isn't one person in my program
who did not have imposter syndrome.
Talk to your friends about it.
That is what makes it go away
is first of all, admitting it
Saying, hey, that's how I'm feeling today.
And then having your friends
lift you up from that
Sometimes we are hesitant
about taking a big next step.
We think a lot about everything
that can go wrong.
Those thoughts run a lot in my head
when I'm, like, facing a new challenge.
I think we need to look at the upside too.
All the things that can go
right. All the doors that it can open.
Women are not represented
in higher management.
We know that women are not represented
in senior roles,
especially women with children.
If more women come to these programs.
If more women say, yes, I am a woman,
maybe I'm a mother, maybe I'm not.
But I am putting my career
first because it's important to me,
because I can make
a difference in the world,
because I can do good in the world.
Then the world will be a better place.
We need women,
you know, in the workplace to shine.
I don't know how other ways
to say it.
a lot of times
maybe over the years, in the centuries,
you know, times have evolved and women
have shifted from different roles,
you know, more into the workplace.
But I think there's still a ceiling
that needs to be broken. Right.
Everybody was very courageous.
And has to be courageous for everyone
to actually pause their career
and say no to the promotion.
You know, in order to come here.
There was a moment of time
that people experienced doubts.
Am I doing the right thing?
Would I be able to continue my progression
when I go back?
Would I be able to pivot to
to where I want to go?
I understand there would be many doubts.
I had as well, but,
it's the nicest gift
that I ever gave myself.
I hope if we can change one life,
if one woman that is watching this video
think she's not capable
or not up to the task.
And after viewing this video,
she convinced herself
that the first limitation
that needs to be removed is her own belief
We already made a lot of for these word.
In my experience,
it was like, I can try let's see.
I'm going to work towards that.
I didn't believe in me.
It was just exploratory
and the results?
It was, totally amazing.
I am here sharing this story.