hey everyone pleasure to be here uh my
name is Evan I'm the CEO and co-founder
of Helix carbon and we're a climate
technology company obviously like like
everyone else here but we're
specifically focused on carbon
utilization and so you know I I was a
graduate student here in mechanical
engineering and business and this
company is really one that was born kind
of organically out of a lot of work we
did here at MIT so know before before
coming to MIT I worked in climate
technology and Consulting and but when I
came here I met David my co-founder who
who's in the back uh and and Ariel who's
a professor in the chemical engineering
department here and we really wanted to
focus on okay what what is the the sort
of biggest chunk that we can take out of
out of global carbon emissions and for
us the the clear answer was Heavy
industry you know it's it's centralized
it is high scale it's about a third of
global emissions and it's an industry
that is you know facing a lot of
increasing Global pressure because
there's a lot of regulatory regimes
whether it's know cap and trade systems
outright carbon taxes that are starting
to affect particularly in the US and
particularly in Europe the the price and
and the cost to produce a lot of these
industries um and there's also sort of a
carrot as well right there's not just
these these Global penalties but there's
also proven green premiums in heavy
industry whether it's for polymers or
liquid fuels particularly and as well as
for steel I mean if you look at steel
alone there have been multi-year
multimegaton off agreements for massive
green premiums for for low carbon steel
and there's also a revenue opportunity
on the tax side right there you know
there's there's there's tax Equity
agreements that you can leverage so
basically the bottom line is if you're
an innovator here there's a huge Revenue
opportunity as as a player in heavy
industry to to lowering your carbon
emissions and what we wanted to do is
really sit at the intersection of this
can we take the carbon dioxide that is
coming off these heavy industrial sites
and convert it to something that is of
value and for us that looks like an
electrochemical system that we developed
here at MIT that takes carbon dioxide
from flu gas passes it through our
system and converts it to a series of
value added industrial gases and you
know of course I think there's there's
there's the Energy Efficiency benefit
that we think we have over many others
in this space there's the fact that our
systems don't rely on on precious metals
and so they're a lot cheaper to build
but also it's you know and it's not on
this slide but I think the biggest
differentiator we have is we're the
first system that actually has sort of
industrially relevant lifetimes you know
there's a lot of folks who can achieve
really good carbon utilization for for
tens or even hundreds of hours but I
think the differentiator our system
really has against those is we can run
for thousands of hours and and it
finally makes this something that can be
relied on as a source of a lot of these
industrial gases and so we are taking
this to Market by by partnering with
with existing industrial facilities so
we take in the the carbon dioxide from
your flu gas convert it on site into one
of several feed stocks that you may use
carbon monoxide ethylene or methane and
essentially just give that right back to
you right and this eliminates
Transportation costs it it insulates you
from volatility in in where you're
getting this today so coal and natural
gas particularly natural gas prices have
been extremely expensive and extremely
volatile over the past several years and
it's also a drop solution you know if
you're someone who's particularly in the
iron or the polycarbonate or the
polyurethane industry that uses carbon
monoxide from natural gas today this
requires no operational disruption
against your current
systems and so we're building this by
first going to a 10 kilowatt pilot that
we're building today actually here in
Massachusetts at a py at a biomass
pyrolysis facility and we're scaling up
so we're looking for for partners to go
to that next step we're building 100
kilowatt system slated for 202 six and a
getting to the megawatt scale in 2028 so
you know if this is something that that
resonates with you and your companies
and it's something that you would be
interested in piloting with we're
continuing to look for partners in that
sort of two to 200 kilogram to two to
two ton per day scale as well as you
know this is broadly speaking a pretty
generalizable electrocatalysis platform
at the end of the day what we do is is
not just carbon conversion but but
chemical conversion and electrical
chemical conversion and so if there is a
specific process that you're looking at
that you want to Electrify or you want
to Electrify more efficiently um we're
also more than happy to to work with you
on customizing this this platform to
your needs so with that thank you for
your time and uh we'll talk to you at
our at our booth after
[Applause]