hi my name is aishi and I'm the research
coordinator for the r health study today
I'll be showing you how to complete your
saliva collection upon completion of the
first two surveys you'll be mailed an
rhealth saliva kit to the mailing
address that you've
provided in the kit you'll
find the saliva kit collection
tube instructions on how to collect your
sample
a biohazard bag to put your specimen
in a sticker to seal the kit once you're
done and a QR code to help you locate
your neuros FedEx facility to mail the
kit
back now I'll walk you through the
collection process we ask that you avoid
eating drinking smoking or chewing gum
half an hour prior to collection to
avoid compromising your sample when
you're ready will open the collection
kit spit to the fill line make sure that
there are no bubbles at the fill line
and that your saliva sample ends here
when you finish collecting the sample
and there are no
bubbles snap the lid
shut make sure you hear a loud
click this will release the stabilizer
fluid into the tube with your your
sample once it's released screw the cap
off and replace
it with the blue
cap shake the cap up and down for 5
seconds once You' shaken
it put it into the biohazard
bag make sure that you do not remove the
absorbent
pad seal the bag
shut and put it back into the
kit once you're done you'll use the
sticker to seal your saliva
sample the kit already comes with a
prepaid return label so all you have to
do is Drop It off at your local FedEx
facility upon completion of the saliva
sample you may discard the kit and the
lid if you have any further questions
please feel free to reach out to the our
health study team via the contact
information listed on the our health
website thank you so much for your
participation and for your contribution
to advancing South Asian cardiovascular
research