Hey, everyone.
So it was really wonderful to
get to hear from Yann LeCun.
And now, my name is Sara Beery.
I'm a professor of AI and
decision-making here at MIT.
And I'm going to kick off
our next session, which
is three different talks,
about the use of generative AI
across scientific disciplines.
And so I'm going to kick
us off here specifically
talking about generative
AI in the field of ecology.
So in my research group at
MIT we sit fundamentally
within the AI cohort
within the AI discipline,
but we consider ourselves truly
interdisciplinary scientists.
I've been working in the
ecological applications of AI
for over a decade.
And in general,
our large goal is
we want to be able to understand
and monitor biodiversity,
all life and the interactions
between life on Earth,
and be able to detect
change in biodiversity,
risks to biodiversity
across scales
globally and in real-time.
Now this is a very
ambitious goal,
and I am not the only
one who has this goal.
And in recent decades,
the combination
of advances in hardware
and sensor technology
that help us capture much,
much more data than we'd ever
seen before across many,
many different types of data,
everything from satellite
images to cameras on the ground,
bioacoustic sensors,
environmental DNA
where we can collect
evidence of species
even if they've
no longer actually
are there in the environment.
And increasingly, things
like community science.
So organizations
like iNaturalist
that help any of you,
any passionate volunteer,
contribute species data to
our scientific understanding.
This data is incredibly
valuable and has really
expanded exponentially.
But the problem is,
none of these data types
are directly measuring
what we care about.
Unlike, if you're
interested in measuring
surface temperature, which
is a measurable quantity,
instead we get pixels.
We get sound waves.
We get point clouds.
We get hyperspectral data.
And then we need to
actually figure out
how to translate those
streams of raw data
into some form of
actionable insight,
some form of scientific
knowledge about the world.
And this is really
where AI has already
been absolutely transformative.
We've seen models get deployed
for many of these different data
types to be able to turn that
into scientific knowledge.
Now, one of the big
challenges that we have
is that ecological imagery
is often highly degraded.
Unlike data that's captured by
a human photographer where maybe
you're using your own
intelligence to get a photo that
captures the thing you care
about, is reasonably well-lit,
is focused, is well-centered,
if you're collecting data
from all of these
remote sources, what
you get is data that can often
be very difficult to interpret.
It can have haze, it can have
noise, it can have occlusions,
we can deal with
weather challenges.
And so what we've been
trying to do in our lab,
as one of the many different
diverse applications
of generative AI,
is figure out how
to address the
challenging noise,
these compound degradations of
data, for ecological imagery.
And so what we've proposed is a
method that we're calling PRISM.
It stands for Precision
Restoration with Interpretable
Separation of Mixtures,
but at its core,
it's essentially an
image generation model
that takes in both an image and
input from a scientific expert
and is able to
iteratively remove
these distortions with a
focus on scientific accuracy.
So there's a lot of
work in image generation
that we've seen, but
one of the challenges
is all of our metrics
in the AI space
for image generation
seem to be grounded
around the idea of
human perceptual value.
We want things that look pretty.
I don't care if it's pretty,
I want it to be correct.
I don't want pretty at
the expense of correct.
And so what we've
done is we've really
focused on two key components.
We recognize that we're
going to have complicated
compound distortions,
so we train
the model on the types
of difficult distortions
we're going to see in reality.
And we actually have built this
contrastive latent space that
helps us separate the
different types of distortions
and learn how to deal
with them interactively
and independently, which
then means that we can almost
see them as pieces or tools that
we can put back together to be
able to try to get to the
correct version of an image.
So the cool thing here is
that now with our system,
we enable both controllable
and joint restoration.
So you can restore multiple
types of distortion,
and you, as a scientist,
are in control.
So let's look at this the
satellite image, for example.
So you can see here,
this is a satellite image
taken of the Earth.
And we're looking here,
I'm highlighting this area
because I think it's a
nice place to look at.
And there's two different
types of distortions
that are affecting our ability
to see what's going on here.
We have both clouds and
low light and noise.
So three.
So, one thing you
could do is you
could try to, with this kind of
controllability, by prompting
our model, remove each of
these types of distortions
independently.
So you can try to remove noise,
you get something diffuse.
You can try to
remove the clouds.
All right, now we
have some blurriness,
but we are anticipating
what might be underneath.
We can try to remove low light.
And, OK, we can see, yeah,
we've done something.
Is it correct?
That's the interesting question.
How do we know
that this generated
image is actually correct?
So here, what we've
done is you can
think of this
sequential restoration,
but our model actually
enables composite restoration.
So we can do all of this
simultaneously, which
is much more
computationally efficient,
and we find actually also
introduces less artifacts.
You have less opportunity to
add incorrect information.
And, if we look at
the true clear image,
which we've collected from--
basically we've come up
with this really nice way
to evaluate the models where
we use difference over time
to find the true value of what
we actually want to recover,
so we can evaluate on truth,
not quality, we can see,
it actually is a
really nice match,
both qualitatively
and quantitatively.
And this cool thing
about controllability
is that it enables
you as an expert
to drive scientific precision.
So like I said, the
more you change,
the more opportunity
there is to add mistakes
in these generative models.
One thing that has
been brought up a lot
is this idea of hallucination,
but yeah, generative models
can introduce errors.
And what we've seen
is that if the goal is
to be able to do some sort of
scientific inference downstream,
you don't always need to
remove every type of distortion
to be able to do
your task correctly.
So in this case,
what we're showing
is that an expert identifying
that we want to just remove
the contrast, but we don't
necessarily want to also try
to affect the light, is better.
And the way that we're
actually showing that is these
are camera trap
images, and we're
trying to identify species.
And I bet all of you don't
necessarily even what's
going on in these images.
That's because you're
not an ecologist
or a scientific expert,
and this is really
where that expertise comes in.
So here, there's an
animal can see its eyes,
and that part in the
red box is its tail.
And what we're showing is that
by only removing the contrast,
but not also trying to change
the haze, the low light, all
of these other
distortions, you're
better able to pick up the
stripes on the tail, which
enabled an ecologist
to correctly identify
this as a northern raccoon.
And again, we're
identifying correctness,
and we're doing that by
using changes over time--
so an additional image in this
sequence which had a much easier
to identify species as
our way to evaluate.
So you can see this for other
types of modalities, too.
Here, we're looking
at microscopy.
And you can see that if you're
trying to segment out objects
here, if you just do it on
this low-resolution sensor,
you miss some stuff.
You can do super resolution.
And here, OK, just
by super-resolving,
now you have some
additional objects.
If you try to
super-resolve and denoise,
you've removed those objects.
So here, you can focus
specifically in this area.
You can see, there's two objects
here that have been removed.
Now if we compare this to a
high-resolution sensor that
was actually taken
of the same thing--
so we know this is ground
truth, you can similarly
see, by carefully removing
or addressing only some
of the dimensions of the
data quality challenges,
we get much more scientifically
accurate results.
And so the other cool thing
is that by disentangling
in the latent
space, by taking all
of these different
types of distortions
and learning them
independently, this
means that our model is able
to generalize, in some ways,
to types of data, types
of scientific data
that it never saw
during training.
So for example, this is
a drone image of a reef--
so this is taken
over a coral reef.
And you can see that with
an expert in the loop,
you can unwarp the
wave distortions,
you can fix the coloration,
this distortion of the color
that you're seeing through
the water, and you can unblur.
And based on undersea
imagery of this,
the ecologists
thought that this was
a much, much, significantly more
improved version of the data.
And the nice thing
is, using our method,
you can also do this without
an expert in the loop,
and it does work OK.
So you can identify
types of distortions
that the model thinks
might be in the image
and remove them for things like
images of species on the ground.
Again, underwater ROV images--
so now instead of above the
surface, below the surface.
Or the ability to even remove
the surface of rippling water.
And so I think this is a--
it's just a first step,
but there's a few key components
I want to emphasize here.
First, I think
that generative AI
across many different
dimensions is really
going to be fundamentally a
transformative tool for science.
But I also think that there is
a key piece of understanding,
which is I think
it's a tool, and I
think the hard-won
knowledge that scientists
have built through decades of
training is also adding value.
And so I like to think about how
do we design these systems so
that scientists can work
interactively with these tools,
but the scientist is still
the one who's in control.
The scientists are the one who
is able to do that verification,
use their intuition to ensure
the correctness of what they're
trying to measure.
So thank you very much.
And of course, I'd be
remiss without thanking
the many, many collaborators
in the ecology space that
have contributed to my
group's work at MIT.
Thanks.
[APPLAUSE]
As you have seen, I am
currently the Vice Provost
of OpenLearning.
My name is Dimitri Bertsimas.
I have joined
OpenLearning a year ago.
I've been at MIT about 40
years, and one of the reasons
I joined OpenLearning is to
try to work with colleagues,
students, and so
forth to accomplish
the dream of
personalized education.
What I'm doing today is
far from personalized.
All of you see a common
lecture even though you have
many distinct characteristics.
So if somebody would have
told me that in a year or so,
I would have been able to talk
about some of our progress,
I wouldn't have believed it.
So the word magic is relevant.
I hope you feel the same
at the end of the talk.
So this is a vision
and our efforts
on creating a
customized adaptive
online education using GenAI.
This is work with two of
my exceptional students,
Romain, and Dewang,
who are starting
their second year at the
Operational Research Center.
So online learners have
obviously different interests,
backgrounds and goals.
So as a result, this calls
for customization adapted
to these characteristics.
First, motivation.
Also, learners have different
learning pace, abilities,
and preferences.
This calls, naturally, for
personalized adaptive learning.
And this is, so far, from the
point of view of the learners.
However, the people who
create all the context
are professors, teachers.
So improving
instructors' productivity
to fulfill these needs while
retaining control is also
relevant, and I will show
you the progress we have
made on all these three areas.
So, one of our efforts
this year in OpenLearning
is what we call
universal AI, which
is about to launch
in a week or so.
This is an ambitious
program of reaching
a lot of learners in the world,
of teaching the basics of AI.
So this is an example
of one-- this is--
in a particular topic.
Let me give you
some of the details
of multiple linear
regression model.
We are given data of the
dependent variable YI,
the price realization
of auction I.
So let me show you how
GenAI can customize
this content automatically
for the health care industry.
The previous was about auctions.
Let me give you
some of the details
of the multiple linear
regression model.
We are given data of
the dependent variable
YI, the hospital
length of stay in days
for patient I, and independent
variables X subscript I.
Similarly, for the
energy industry,
I would like to stress that
this is automatically generated
with a very simple command.
Let me give you
some of the details
of a multiple linear
regression model.
We are given data on the
dependent variable YI,
the day ahead electricity
price in market interval I,
and independent variables
X subscript I superscript
1, the system load
forecast in MW.
XI2, the natural gas spot
price in US per MMBtu.
XI3--
Now I would like to
demonstrate to customize
the length of the presentation.
So the previous were more
elaborate presentations.
And quite often, the need
arises for a much shorter bite.
Here's the 30-second summary.
We model log line price as
YI equals beta plus beta 1 X1
plus E fitted by minimizing
the sum of squared errors SSE.
R squared equals 1 minus SSE.
SST measures how much
better we do than predicting
the overall average only.
Using age, temperature,
and rain as predictors,
a simple model reaches R
squared to 0.42 on Bordeaux data
and beats the average baseline.
Takeaway-- a few variables
plus linear regression
yield useful,
quantifiable forecasts.
So now, I would like
to demonstrate the need
to customize simultaneously
the language of instruction,
as well as the domain expertise.
Of course, there are
multiple other combinations,
this is just an indication.
[SPEAKING SPANISH]
So, I mean, I
don't know Spanish,
but I checked with
one of my students,
and the assertion
was that this is OK.
I was worried about that.
So now, I would like to
say the bigger dream.
So far this was the
customization adaptation story,
but suppose you
have the following.
Suppose you have
a lecture, as we
do in universal AI, in which
you have an assessment.
After five slides, you have
a brief assessment that
can be done in a few seconds.
This is an example where
the student clearly
does not understand what R
squared is and its values.
The specifics is not so
important to understand.
But the key here is
that it's very simple
to detect that the student
didn't fully get it.
So therefore, a need
arises for a system
to perhaps review and repeat the
story in an understandable way
targeted for this story.
The key performance measure
in linear regression
is called R squared.
R squared is defined by
calculating two quantities.
First, the Sum of Squared
Errors, SSE, which is the sum of
squared distances of the
points to the green line.
And this is something we
actually are currently
implementing in OpenLearning
to do it in a very customized
way, adaptive to the learner in
a personalized manner for all
the content that we have.
Final, how to put the
instructor in the loop.
So, what we have built
and what we envision
is that the biggest bottleneck
in high-quality educational
content is the time of my
colleagues, as well as mine.
So this, we expect, will
help accelerate the story.
So human in the loop and
instructor in the loop.
So the idea is--
so this is a system
that the instructor
can give some instructions.
Also, what information,
what papers, books,
slides to use, and then
appropriate instructions
to synthesize the story.
Clearly we don't
have a lot of time
to demonstrate all
the details, but we do
envision that this would be--
we have a working
prototype, a tool
that we are currently
experimenting
with in OpenLearning
with various instructors
responsible for various paths.
So although, of course, this is
still in a research environment,
this is a prototype only,
but it is our aspiration
within OpenLearning to utilize
all these features in everything
that we do.
Our first step is we're about
to launch universal AI for, we
hope, a lot of learners,
and that would be, in a way,
our first experiment.
We, of course, will
adapt and learn.
But we envision that the
idea of customization
for different audiences
for different industries,
the idea of personalization,
and the idea of translations,
adaptations in
length, and difficulty
is going to be present.
So I would leave
you with this vision
of customize adaptive
online education.
As I mentioned,
when I have worked
in the area of personalization--
I tried, anyway, 10 years ago,
and it was an enormous effort.
In the topic of
linear regression,
we have developed, in the past,
various paths for learners.
Just for one lecture
and one homework,
it took myself and a
student months to do.
This is not the case.
This is, I believe--
that's why I said if
somebody told me a year
or two ago, I would say this
is probably science fiction.
And this happened within a year.
Of course, it wouldn't have
happened without the ability
and talent of my two
students, but my hope
is that this will
change education
in ways that I think will
be beneficial to learners,
and perhaps in the way even
MIT or other universities
around the world will be
adapting to this new knowledge.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
So we're all used
to seeing graphs
like this of AI's capabilities
improving over time.
This doesn't even
show the last year,
and Yann LeCun just told us
how we're going to get lots--
reach a lot further heights.
But I work at the
Media Lab, and we
focus on what technology
does to our human lives,
how technology affects
the way we live our lives.
The way we learn, work, take
care of our health, communicate,
relate to others, and so on.
And so the question
that I'm focused on,
and a lot of my colleagues
at the Media Lab
as well, is, as AI
keeps advancing,
how do we ensure that
people will advance as well?
And are we sure that
people will actually also
be better off in a world where
they use AI all the time?
You may know that by now, over
half the US population uses
AI on a regular basis,
and frankly, it's
almost hard to avoid
using AI because it's
integrated into every single
app that we use and always
eager to assist you
with all sorts of tasks
that you may be involved in.
The promise is, of course,
that AI will improve our lives.
health care, education,
accessibility, performance,
our daily life at home,
scientific research, et cetera.
But I want to talk
today about the reality.
I think the reality is much
more of a mixed bag of how AI
is influencing our daily lives.
There is an increased risk for
misinformation and manipulation
as we increasingly rely on AI
to provide us with information.
There's a loss of
understanding and agency
and control over our world.
There's less interest and
motivation for learning,
and we are losing the
skills that we once
had because we relied too much
on AI to do the work for us.
We are weakening our social
skills and our social ties
to others as we
increasingly just talk
to chatbots for
everything we need
help with rather than to friends
or family or peers or experts.
There are mental health
issues such as delusions,
even more serious
problems like suicides,
the result of our
interactions with AI.
And of course, a loss of jobs,
especially at the junior level,
and a loss of meaning
and pride in the work
that we do as we increasingly
have to just be the people
that check the work
that is done by AI.
So the AI gets to
do the fun part
and we have to figure
out what mistakes
they've made because we're
ultimately still held
liable and responsible.
So let me talk
about all of these
in a little bit more detail.
AI's impact on human beliefs.
You may have heard that AI
as a sycophancy problem.
AI systems basically
prioritize agreeing
with the user over issues
rather than providing
accurate information or
objective information,
and thereby, they reinforce
some of the strange thoughts
and beliefs that people may
have, they reinforce biases,
they spread misinformation,
and they really
limit people's
critical thinking.
Unfortunately-- so the AI
industry knows this, actually,
and unfortunately-- and
ChatGPT-5 is less sycophantic,
but a lot of people rebelled
because their AI was no longer
acting as their best buddy that
agreed with everything they
said, they would
occasionally push back.
So people actually
these sycophantic AIs
even though they are not
necessarily good for them.
The sycophancy can result
in delusional spirals,
and we have learned what
the negative impact is
of social media maybe 10 or so
years after social media was
introduced.
I am predicting that with
AI, we risk a similar--
something worse than
polarization, actually,
and people just
talking to people
like them in that ultimately,
we may have bubbles of one
where people just
talk to their AI
and live in this
unrealistic world
that they've created
together with their AI.
We all know AI
models are biased,
and it turns out that working
with an AI model that is biased
affects your views
and your decisions.
A colleague of mine at
Cornell, Mor Naaman,
did a study where
he just had people
use a text editor
with an AI assistant
to write essays
about climate change,
and he gave people different
AI models that were slightly
biased in different
ways, believing
in climate change or
not or climate change
being human-created, et cetera.
And he saw that these biases
were reflected in the essays
that people wrote.
And when he asked
the subjects, did you
realize that the AI was biased?
They said, no.
Do you stand by everything
that you wrote in that article?
Yes.
Those are my beliefs,
those are my thoughts,
even though he could clearly,
in a statistical-- using
statistical evaluation, show
that they basically had been
influenced by the biased AI.
AI is also impacting
our decision-making.
We did a study in my lab.
We gave people a number
of newspaper headlines--
some were true, some were false.
We gave some people no AI,
they had to decide themselves
whether it was true or false.
Others had an accurate
AI or a truthful AI
that said why something
was true or false.
Also, it gave an explanation.
But then yet others we gave
a deceptive AI that gave them
the opposite of the truth.
And what we noticed is
that people just trust AI,
and in fact, often
you hear people say
explanations are so important.
What we learned is if
you provide explanations,
people trust the
wrong AI even more.
They don't really look
carefully about the explanation,
they just trust
that if the AI has
an explanation for why something
is true or false, well,
it must be right.
So, we try to come up with
new methods also in our lab,
new designs for AI
and AI deployments
that actually will mitigate
some of these problems.
For example, a
simple intervention
where AI will first
engage the user
in asking a question about
that newspaper headline,
do you really think
the Pope would
wear a Balenciaga jacket that
costs thousands of dollars?
That alone immediately
improved their accuracy
even if they had an
AI that ultimately
would give a wrong suggestion.
Now agents are, of
course, a thing in 2025.
It turns out that all
of these same problems
exist with agents, but
even at a worse level.
We know from the work
of behavioral economists
that human choices
can be manipulated,
and in our work, some of
the work funded by MGAIC,
we show that LLM
agents are even easier
to influence in their decisions.
So go see Manuel Cherep and
his poster in the hallway
later who can tell you
all about that work.
In one example, we actually
used AI assistants,
just an AI assistant, just
to evaluate resumes for a job
opening, and what we learned
is that the exact same resume,
if you have a famous last
name, Kennedy, Gates, whatever,
you get ranked higher
than if you don't.
So maybe think of changing
your name in the era of AI.
Learning and skill development.
We did a study with
54 college students
where we monitored
brain activity
while they were writing an
essay on an SAT topic, actually.
And we had three groups.
One group used ChatGPT,
another groups just search,
and the third group had
to work by themselves.
What we noticed in
the EEG patterns
were striking differences.
A lot more connectivity
and activity
in the brains of the people that
did not have the ChatGPT tool.
But interestingly, we noticed
some other things as well.
We asked people to
write about happiness.
What does happiness mean to you?
It turns out that the whole
group that had ChatGPT
to help them, they all wrote
about how success in your career
will lead to happiness.
And we didn't see that as much
in the other essays that were
written by the other group.
So again, showing
how AI actually
influences your thinking,
influences your beliefs.
Worse, the people that
had used ChatGPT could not
quote from their
essays or could not
make that same argument
orally later down
the road, but yet
at the same time,
they claimed ownership
over this work.
They said, yes, I stand
by my essay that I wrote,
this is my work, even
though they couldn't even
remember what they had
written a week later.
So we think there are
solutions for this.
Again, we are developing, for
example, in the area of AI that
assists with writing a system
called Critical Thinker that
acts more like an editor,
an editor that tells you,
this is a good
point you're making,
but you need more proof or
more evidence for this point.
Or maybe here, you could
use an example, et cetera,
teaching people to write
rather than doing the thinking
and writing for them.
Now AI is also resulting in
the loss of skills, actually.
A study done by
other people actually
showed that for oncologists
who use AI for three months,
they become less good
at spotting cancer
spots in medical images because
they rely so much on the AI
that they lose their own skills
that they previously had.
Is this what we
want, or do we want
to benefit from both
the expertise of the AI
and the expertise of the doctor?
We need to think about how
to design these systems so
that they really still
engage the doctor
and not just make it too easy
to just rely on the system.
So for AI deployments to be
successful in a real context,
it is not sufficient
for the AI model
to be accurate and fair and
ethical and unexplainable.
It is important that we
also test AI models and AI
systems in the context,
the human context where
they will be used.
And that we look
at other outcomes,
not just how well
the AI system does,
but how well does that
person do with AI?
Do they lose their
skills, do they lose
their motivation, et cetera.
I want to end by talking
about some other work
that we're doing as well on the
impact on our social connections
with others.
You may have read a lot about
that people are increasingly
lonely, and I think that AI will
only exacerbate that problem.
In fact, if you look at the
top AI apps, the ones that
are about the AI being a
buddy, a close companion,
are the ones that
get the most use.
Guess where the
money is going to go?
I mean, all of these
companies ultimately
have to make a profit from the
AIs that they are building.
So we have actually, funded
by OpenAI and in collaboration
with OpenAI, one of
the first studies
to evaluate how
daily use of ChatGPT
affects social and
emotional outcomes.
And we saw in a sample
of a thousand people
using it for a whole
month that the people who
use AI more often in a day or
for longer periods of time,
they do report feeling
less lonely, interestingly,
but they also socialize less
with other humans, which
is a little bit worrisome.
Together with
OpenAI, actually, we
came up with a new
method for evaluating
the social and emotional
impact of AI models on people,
and we now have classifiers
that can actually
look at interactions,
conversations
between the user and
the AI, to figure out
whether a model does well in
terms of being more pro-social
and encouraging the person
to reach out to people
rather than encouraging the
person to just talk to the AI,
for example.
So in summary, AI's impact
on our human experience,
on our human lives, risks
being negative unless we really
think carefully about how to
design AI and deploy AI and not
just think about making AI
ever more powerful and capable
and then throwing
it over the fence
into the hands of real users.
AI should present
the presented truth
and occasionally
push back to the user
and encourage a user to
see other points of view
rather than reinforcing
their point of view.
It should engage the users
in critical thinking in areas
where it's important that the
person maintains that skill.
It should stimulate curiosity
and development of knowledge
and skills, especially
for young people,
and should promote and support
deep human relationships
rather than aiming to
replace human relationships.
If you're interested
in this issue,
come and find me
at the Media Lab.
We have a large
program, actually,
with multiple faculty
involved called Advancing
Humans with AI--
uh huh-- that focuses on
designing AI so that people
ultimately flourish.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]