My name is Trisha Denl and I'm with MIT
Startup Exchange and I will have the
honor of introducing today's MIT Startup
Lightning talks. Today you'll be hearing
from two startup companies. Both of the
presenting startups are part of MIT
Startup Exchange and they're developing
critical technologies and services to
improve data center management and
infrastructure. With this selection of
startups, we hope to give you a sense of
the technologies that are emerging from
MIT that are truly advancing data center
innovation. They're going to show us not
only their technology, but also some use
cases that they've been working on with
partners and customers. So, I do
encourage all of you who have interest
or would like more information to follow
up with the presenters today because
that is what we do here at MIT Startup
Exchange. We help startups identify and
experience partnerships and
collaboration and then we bring together
MIT connected startups and ILP corporate
members to foster collaboration and
partnerships between them. The startups
that we support have a strong connection
to the institute. This connection can
come through the founding team, through
the technology, and in other cases where
they don't have an origin here at MIT,
we will work with them because they've
been vetted and supported by our MIT
peer programs that work with startups in
this case like CEL Connect Plus,
Start.no, and the engine.
We have a network of over 800 startups
virtually working in any sector and we
are also geographically agnostic working
with MIT connected startups all over the
world. Everything we do is to expose and
to connect startups and industry in a
highly curated way and we also provide
learning opportunities to both parties.
So that includes launching calls for
startups based on corporate priority
priorities or challenges. Also
facilitating one-on-one meetings or
introductions, hosting virtual demo
days, workshops regarding the learning
opportunities. This is often when we
partner with other MIT peer programs on
campus in order to bring those again in
a curated fashion to our members and
startups. This here is a very small
example of the successful outcomes that
have come from the connections that have
been made through the ILP and MIT
startup exchange program. It's the
intent with every introduction, every
event, every meeting that these success
cases emerge. So if you have any
questions or would like more information
about MIT Startup Exchange, how we work
with ILP members, you're more than
welcome to come up to me or any of our
team. And of course, our program
directors are always happy to connect
you with startups through our network.