Thank you so much. Well, first of all, I
hope you had a great break and that you
are ready to engage again on the
conversation. I first of all would like
to thank CIRC for giving us the
opportunity to be providing a Latin
American overview of um what is the
landscape of AI in a region that data
and research shows that is under
reppresented. So it's quite important
for us and it's personally very
important for me coming from Costa Rica
uh part of Latin America. So we started
thinking about what are the impacts of
AI that actually is being produced the
models let's say are dominated to
different geographies right now
currently the domination is the United
States you have China and you have
Europe but the deployment of AI it's
been global so we started to think and
reflect what are those
deployments are going to be the same are
going to be perceived the same in the
US, in China, in the global south? And
if so, do we need to have a better
context and a better understanding of
the nuances of the social infrastructure
of these places to really engage in an
ethical way of AI in the in its whole
life cycle. So we believe that cultural,
political and economic factors within a
given region, country or community will
shape how we engage with technology. How
we shape social technical imaginaries
could influence positively or negatively
the impacts of each
technology. So what is it that we did? I
will walk you through what we did a
little bit of how we did it. So the
methodology is quite important but I
will try to go to the conclusions um the
vulnerabilities that we have found and
then a little bit of what needs to be
done. So what we did is to create an
ethical assessment of the
vulnerabilities of AI in Latin America.
So how can the region sees the
opportunities? There is a lot of
promises regarding AI being able to
close gaps to help us with our um
structural and historical inequalities.
But at the same time that is possible if
we can also mitigate the risk and we
cannot understand how to leverage the
opportunities and mitigate the risk if
we don't understand our own status our
own landscape and where is Latin America
standing in the global landscape of AI.
So very very briefly, Latin America it's
very diverse. It's very vast. Very hard
for me to let you know exactly what
Latin America is. Just give you two
facts. First of all is one of the most
biodiverse regions in the whole world
and we produce a lot of data. Some of
you may be working in that area. We
produce a lot of data regarding
biodiversity. At the same time, Latin
America is the most not one of the most
the most unequal region in the world. So
this is very important to keep in mind
because we are going to put on top of
that the layer of technology. So how is
that Latin America can leverage the
opportunities while we have still to
catch up with these
challenges? Why this is important? Well,
for me it is important because AI it's
already being deployed and we are
actually feeling the positives uh
impacts of AI but Latin America it's
also already experiencing the negative
impacts of AI in regards of are we ready
for this? Do we have the provisions to
mitigate the risk and the reality is our
case studies shows that not not too much
ready in certain areas. So for example
there is biometric information that has
been collected in Argentina during the
economic crisis. So people was selling
let's say selling their their biometric
information to worldcoin which is a
US-based company without entirely
understanding what is it that they are
providing what the company was going to
do with this
information because Latin America
provides a lot of data work and
microwork let's say um for data
collection and tagging and content
moderation.
Most of the times because of instruct
because of structural informality in the
labor market in Latin America. Most of
that work is also informal sometimes
very very poorly paid in very precarious
conditions but they are part of the
supply chain of the AI ecosystem. And I
will go back to this because I think
when we are talking about ethics in AI,
should we think about the bias of the
model and the deployment or we actually
think about AI in the live in the in the
live uh
cycle. It is important because Venezuela
it's already using Gen AI to provide
propaganda, misinformation,
disinformation from the government. But
also it's an interesting case because
journalism in Venezuela that has been
repressed by the authoritarian
government of uh Nicolas Maduro they
have been also using
Genai to create journalism without the
journalists to be threatened by the
government. So it is very important.
Geni was started to produce propaganda
for the government but now also is an
innovative way for the opposition to
also provide information. It is
important because we are very very
vulnerable to cyber attacks. fraud and
scams and cyber attacks are on the surge
in Latin America. And the reality is
that we are somehow prepared for some of
those, but mostly if they are targeted
into our critical infrastructure, which
was the case for Costa Rica, they
targeted our health care system. So
sensitive um we are we need to be
prepared for this. And also, and I
wanted to point this out um in a very
nuanced and sensible way, Latin America
needs to catch up with a lot of
investment. AI is not possible if we
don't have the infrastructure that make
that possible. That means that Latin
America needs to catch up with
5G. Currently, there is telecom
operators in Latin America, but there is
no deployer of 5G in Latin America. That
will mean that Latin America needs to go
to do an international beating and that
beating usually if you want competition
will mean that you will have US
providers, Europe providers and China
providers. Needless to say that China
currently is the global leader in 5G
deployment very competitive. So if Latin
America is trapped in a geopolitical
battle between the US and China, the
reality is that it could be very very
detrimental in how we can catch up with
our deployment of 5G. So it is important
to to provide that
perspective. So going back to the ethics
and the AI AI system life cycle. Um
where is Latin America currently in the
life cycle? This is the OECD life cycle
just to provide a reference. Latin
America right now is engaged in the AI
systems providing low added value
inputs. So we provide data collection
and processing content moderation that
could be in the loop. uh going back to
data collection and processing and
obviously we are full on on deployment
but when we are talking about ethics
going back to my point are we just
talking about biased in the systems in
the
models should we think about the ethics
of AI thinking about the whole supply
chain now that it is a hot topic in the
conversation why because maybe we could
also think about that Latin America is
engaged in the AI system life cycle
through critical minerals providing the
critical minerals that makes AI
possible. Should we think that these
inputs should be ethical
sourced? Do we think that the data
workers that are part of the supply
chain should be ethically um should be
ethically be be within ethical dynamics
of labor. If they are
not, can we say that our model, our
system is an ethical
AI? So this is just um it is important
just to to say that Latin America right
now has very uh little participation in
the design, planning and um and
development of the models. We are very
engaged on deployment providing feedback
and there's obviously Latin American
talent in all the phases but we should
be um we should be more engaged in
decision making and how we design and
shape these models to capture the
cultural nuances of Latin America of our
own language of our own culture and of
our own social infrastructure.
So how we did this ethical analysis to
understand where are our critical
vulnerabilities. So Latin America is
very broad. We took as a reference the
Latin American artificial intelligence
index as a reference. What they do is
that they just measure the readiness for
each country regarding AI. They don't
get into AI um ethical dynamics or
compliances. they just measure where the
countries are in regards of readiness.
So for our research we took um two
pioneers the leading countries in Latin
America which are Chile and Brazil. They
are leading the way very much. We have
the standards let's say the the adopters
which are the standard of Latin America.
We took Mexico and Costa Rica. And for
the explorers, let's another word to say
the the countries that needs to catch
up. Um we took El Salvador and Honduras.
This is important not only to understand
a little bit of the the differences
between the region but also to have
representation from um North Latin
America, Central Latin America and South
Latin America.
We took um we needed to define which
principles which ethical principles are
we willing to work with to understand
the ethical type of dynamics in Latin
America. Our countries and these six
countries have signed several
declarations, several international
agreements. So what we did is that we um
we did a mapping of which agreements are
shared but all of by all of these six
countries and basically these six
countries Chile, Brazil, Costa Rica,
Mexico, Salvador and Honduras. The the
three of them have committed to the
UNESCO's recommendation on the ethics of
AI. This is probably the most uh
ratified agreement in terms of ethics
globally. So many countries have signed
it. Uh we also took the Santiago
declaration that is based on UNESCO and
the Interameric framework on data
governance and AI. Sorry the typo. Um
those two are based on the UNESCO. So
based on these three agreements that
these six countries have signed, we
created what are the shared principal
principles that we are going to work
with. So we came up and this is quite
important. with 15 ethical principles
uh because they were very different. So
we came up with the 15 ethical
principles that you can um share with
all those declarations and after
understanding these principles we went
country by country understanding how
each country um creates provisions for
proportionality. Is it rightsbased type
of uh proportionality? Is it um
riskbased? How is the regional status
around proportionality? How is the
regional status around
security? And for each one of those
principles, we provided if you if you
want to have security, what are the
indicators that will guarantee to your
population that you will have security
in AI? Well, maybe cyber security is one
of them. So, that is one indicator. And
then we anal we analyzed all the
provisions, metrics, mechanisms that
each one of these countries have in
order to guarantee these commitments
that they have ratified. Because the
reality is that ethical commitments
sometimes can be very very vague and
sometimes unfortunately very
aspirational and there is um little
monitoring or enforcement control
afterwards.
So we took three benchmarks to provide
also inputs to our analysis. The first
one was um a global benchmarks. We took
the Stamford AI index 2024, a regional
benchmark um which is the Latin American
AI index that provides regional metrics
around AI and then uh in order to
provide the ethical base the UNESCO um
we took all um reports paper literature
that we had and also everything that has
to do with regulatory frameworks and any
type of
provisions and what we did is a cross
analysis. A cross analysis for each one
of the principles, each one of the
indicators, each one of the countries in
a regional status in general. This is uh
through two um cross analysis methods.
The first one is the cross tabulation.
So just to give you an example here, uh
we're talking about data protection. The
indic the sub indicator will be cyber
security and we went through understand
what is the regional status what is the
status for each country what are the
metrics that we have for any type of
indicator the other indicator will be
automation exposed jobs etc etc etc this
is for gender equality this is just a an
example um the research is uh is based
on numbers and numbers of tables because
we did that for each one of the 15
principles for each one of the countries
and for a regional overview And after
that we said well if we think about AI
as a system we should also think about
the principles of ethics of AI also as a
system because they actually are
intertwined they relate to each other.
So for example um we needed to
understand what is the relationship
between the principles and what is the
impact that each principle has in any
other principle also as part of our
cross um analysis. So just to give you
an example, there are some principles
that they be in tension, meaning that if
you want to go high with security, you
may go a little bit lower in
accessibility. So they could get into
tension or some others that when we have
more non-discrimination probably you
will have better gender equality or if
you have better gender equality, your
non-discrimination will al will actually
also go
high. and how they um they uh impact
each other. So um again security and
accessibility will have a three because
they are strongly impacting each other.
What we found in the the relationship
and the cross impact analysis is that
when we are talking about these
principles, what it's at the core of the
conversation, it's human rights and also
what it's at the core of the
conversation that we need to take into
consideration is participation.
participation has a strong impact on how
we manage gender equality because if
women are participating then they will
provide a better strong and different
points of view. If you want to make sure
that you have non-discrimination well
depending on who is at the table you may
improve those numbers. So human rights
at the core any principle is going down
human rights are going down. It seems
obvious but it's important to measure it
and also participation multistakeholder
engagement. Um so based on those um
methodologies we got to 10 conclusions
10 critical 10 critical vulnerabilities
and some recommendations. I will go
through because I think I'm short of
time. I will go through the critical
vulnerabilities very very briefly. This
is what we found. Um some of them are
not necessarily just for Latin American
region but they are especially critical
for the Latin American region. Um we may
have expansion of surveillance and
social control. Just to give you an
example of this, more than 30
initiatives for facial technology for
facial recognition technologies are in
Latin America without necessarily the
proper regulation. Um proliferation of
misinformation, escalation of AI enabled
organized crime. Organized crime is
already used in AI in Latin America.
They have the resources. They are
flexible enough to navigate uh the use
of AI. While the government and the
police officers, well, they have other
type of limitations. So we have these 10
critical vulnerabilities
um and then we provided five action five
sectors where we think are the
priorities of the actions and
recommendations. First of all we need to
collaborate and work as a region. If we
want to negotiate we need scale. If we
want to enhance and leverage on data we
need to create synergy. If we want to
fight organized crime that actually has
no borders, well, we need to create a
regional synergy around that
institutional transformation is not
enough to do national AI strategies. We
need a more comprehensive development
vision that it's um that it's
transversal to AI prioritize education
mostly gender equality and urban rural
this will be more important uh very
important for Latin America industrial
policies and investment 5G and other
type of investments. Thank you. Thank
you so much.