For me, metal has always been a research
topic, but this class kind of just
introduces you to another idea of like
bladesmithing is an engineering effort
and it's fun and it's creative. What I
got most out of it personally was
feeling that connection with with older
techniques.
>> All this physical intuition that you're
very far removed from when you're purely
pursuing an academic route was kind of
developed through this class. It relates
back to who we are as creatures on this
planet. If we didn't have that creative
spark, we wouldn't be here today. And so
when you give someone the opportunity
and guide them to actually make
something with their hands, there's very
few things that are as satisfying as
that.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.