Moving your life for one year is terrifying sometimes.
It was terrifying to me, but I really think it is worth it.
I really think it's a once in a lifetime
experience and opportunity.
My why of being here is my whole career was in the public sector.
I really enjoy the feeling of giving back to my community
and to my country and affecting
peoples’ lives for the better.
Knowing that you've done something good,
that you've had a good impact
on people's lives, that you made the world a better place, even for
a small fraction of humanity
or even a small fraction of your community.
Just know you have one year of this
and you have to make the most out of it.
Make time to make the friendships and make time to have the one-on-ones
and make time to go to the events of the programs
and the events of the schools and the events of MIT.
It is so important because
those are the experiences that will stay with you after.
I have three girls and one boy.
I am super excited for them
coming to graduation
and seeing me with the MIT
regalia, like, in front of The Dome.
And, you know, the signals
that that gives to my girls about,
and to my son also, about
what it means to have a true partnership.
What it means to be a successful career woman, right.
That is something very vivid of a picture that will stay with them,
that I'm not sure any achievement
in my career – as an economist
it's really hard to explain
what I do to my kids because it's very abstract sometimes.
And so this is a very good visual for them to sort of
see of what a successful career woman is
and I think they will all take it with them
and I hope it will give a really good life lesson to them.