Okay, let's move on to the second
category. Uh, optimized biio
manufacturing process for cell and gene
therapy by Dr. Stacy Springs. She is the
executive director at MIT center for
biomedical innovation CBI. The center
integrated institute expert to solve
complex bio pharmaceutical challenges.
CBI is multi stakeholder
multi-disiplinary research and
education. initiative with real world
impact including two industry consortium
uh biio manufacturing consortium biomman
and also advantageous agent
contamination in biomuction
cac is a principal investigator on
several research program in biologics
manufacturing such as continuous
production of monoconal antibodies viral
vectors and vaccines Dr. Spring is also
a principal investigator at Smart Camp,
a Singapore MIT alliance for research
and technology. Today's talk is titled
innovation in manufacturing biio
medicine from new modality to scalable
accessible therapeutics. So, welcome Dr.
C Springs. Thank you Mickey.
Well, it's my pleasure to be here. Um,
how many of you work in
manufacturing? And I see a show of
hands. Anyone? How many of you work in
manufacturing cell and gene therapies?
Okay. All right. Great. That helps me,
you know, set the tone for what I'm
going to say today. Um, what I really
want to tell you about are the
activities at our center. So, I'm going
to give you an introduction to the
Center for Biomedical Innovation where
I'm executive director. I have a number
of roles here on campus. This is one of
them. Another role I have on campus is
at the Sloan School where I run a food
supply chain analytics and sensing
initiative. So, if you have interest in
food supply chains, please come see me
later. Um but today we're going to talk
about biologic medicines which are
important and challenging to manufacture
and we'll talk about some of our
research projects uh that we are doing
to overcome some of those obstacles to
development of manufacturing practices
and these you know have to do with
mechanistic modeling approaches, process
intensification, process analytical
technologies and rapid safety
tests. So the CBI is a center at MIT
that's been here since 2005. We are um
what I would consider a um a an a center
that accelerates uh the development and
adoption of advanced biommanufacturing
approaches and we do it in two ways. One
is driving the demonstration of novel
new technologies uh that are fit for
purpose for biommanufacturing and the
other are through um industry consorcia
activities where we're working together
with industry to develop consensus
opinions, develop consensus approaches
to drive best industry practice and we
do that in a variety of ways that I'll
just mention quickly. So um we are
really focused on the entire healthcare
value change. we've settled in to some
extent on you know development uh of you
know clinical development and
manufacturing distribution and global
delivery and specifically on
biioharmaceuticals but really in
everything we do we're bringing together
teams and innovation initiatives that
might be a research program or a
pre-ompetitive consortium activity or
developing educational material for the
industry. We're bringing together people
to collaborate in what we're doing and
we do that in different ways. Um we
consider ourselves experts in regulatory
science and data analytics. So we're
always looking to apply data analytics
to the things that we are doing uh in
our in our our work. We work uh have
worked over the years quite a bit to
understand the regulatory um
implications of these technologies and
how they might be implemented, where
they might be implemented. And um we
also work on really understanding risk
um and risk risk assessment and risk
management and putting together tools
that the industry can use to basically
assess their own risk um related to for
instance uh adventitious agent
contamination and their
biommanufacturing processes and we
create tools that then they can use to
manage that risk. Um everything we're
doing really is with the end goal in
mind of providing better access to
biologic medicines which are comp
complex to make expensive to make and
not accessible to everyone around the
globe. So as I mentioned we have two
different or three different ways that
we approach this. It's through
collaboration, education and research.
And I'm just going to give you some
quick examples of collaboration and
education and then we'll move into the
research port portfolio for the rest of
my talk. So in terms of collaboration we
run two industry consortia. One is
called the biioan consortium. It focuses
on applications of machine learning and
AI in biio manufacturing, cell and gene
therapy manufacturing, product quality
control and vaccine manufacturing. And
we have 10 companies that you know meet
twice a year for uh workshops and we do
projects and other things within the
consortium. The other consortium as I
mentioned is on adventitious agent
contamination and that's where we really
look at you know what is the risk. It's
a it's a black swan type of event for
instance to have a viral contamination
in your manufacturing plant but we all
know it has happened and that puts
companies at significant risk. It puts
patients potentially at risk of not
receiving their products but it puts
companies at risk. It's very time
consuming to um do a root cause analysis
and understand what has happened and
then put in preventative and corrective
actions and then restart. You know,
you're talking months if not more of
downtime. So, we we have worked with the
industry to confidentially collect all
of their data around viral contamination
experiences, anonymize that, analyze it,
and share it back with the industry in
in a lessons learned exercise. as one of
the activities of the CAACB. But we also
look at new technologies for instance
next generation sequencing and others
for advantitious agent control um to you
know address some of the pillars of
safety that we use which is you know
basically testing your raw materials
being able to um you know always test
and um prevent any advents from getting
into your process. Well you need
technologies to do that. So what are
those? What are the best ones and how
can they be used? And then we look at
new challenges for adventious agent
control. So we had a pandemic not too
long ago. What does that mean when you
suddenly have a virus circulating and
you need to be making other vaccines or
you need to be making monoconal
antibodies? How do you think about that?
Um how do you uh determine what cell
lines are susceptible? How do you
decontaminate um your your workspaces?
So we think about that and then we've
also thought about in the face of ad uh
of um excuse me of uh of new you know
therapeutic modalities such as cell and
gene therapies. Are the types of
controls that we have put in place for
monoconal antibbody production fit for
purpose or do we need you know
additional ways to think about viral
safety uh or even bio burden in in the
context of these. So that's that's what
these two consorts should do. In terms
of education, we've we create a number
of different um online and residential
courses, short courses, professional
education courses all in the in the area
of biio manufacturing. So I'll just
focus on a couple of these. Um,
principles of biio manufacturing is an
online course. It takes you through six
weeks of the production of a monoconal
antibbody and insulin and it's you know
available now through our expro um
platform here at MIT but it ran for
years on at the edex platform for free
and you could get a certificate. We do a
vaccines short course with University
College London. It'll be June 3rd
through 5th this year at the MIT campus
and it rotates between MIT and and uh
London. Um so this year it's at MIT,
next year it'll be in in the UK and then
um we um have residential courses to
really teach uh the students about
biommanufacturing and we have developed
a cell therapy course most recently
we've been working on it'll launch this
fall um a vaccine development and
manufactured blended learning course. So
there will be online um learning you can
do through MIT and you can do hands-on
learning at Quincy College and that was
supported by Nimble and done in
collaboration with Merc and Sanopi. And
as we develop these courses, you know,
we really work closely with these
companies to, you know, review the
curriculum we've developed to really get
input and also we go into these
companies. We film real, you know, uh,
machinery and and equipment that is
being used. Um, we interview experts.
So, there's a lot of really great stuff
in these courses to check out. Um, we're
doing a short course this year. It'll be
the first time through professional
education at uh on cell therapy
manufacturing only. Um and that'll be uh
the first or the second week of
July. So just in terms of outcomes of
these courses, these courses have
reached literally you know thousands of
people 15 16,000 people between the biio
manufacturing course and the cell
therapy course. And it's mostly people
in healthcare and biotechnology um and
pharmaceutical industries but sometimes
you get others. And so you can see that
the the reach of these courses is quite
wide. And we um have also written some
uh some you know academic papers around
the curriculum development and
assessment that we have done in these in
these uh particular courses. All right.
So with that go on to research. So we do
a wide variety of research at the
center. So we have been focused on um
you know basically any way that we can
intensify or apply modeling or develop
analytical tools for all biologic
medicines starting with monoconal
antibodies. We have developed at MIT a a
test bed um for continuous manufacturing
where we have um been doing something we
call smart data analytics which is
trying to understand how to use all the
data both in the process um but also at
the plant level where we've collaborated
with industry to get um a whole plant's
worth of data around two monoconal
antibodies to develop basically models
um that have helped us with um looking
at you know root cause analysis,
predictive um predictive maintenance,
things of that nature. And then we've
also worked with um a company to look
outside of um the plant in the
manufacturing ecosystem. So once a
monoconal antibbody is uh being
manufactured you have postmarket data
and how do we look at that and
understand where there could be u
specific um issues that arise in terms
of drug safety signals that relate back
to the drug manufacturing or supply. Now
I'm not going to talk about any of that
today because I only have time to talk a
little bit about the the cell and gene
therapy manufacturing but I did want to
mention that that is a very active area
for our center. We also work on uh
continuous manufacturing of vaccines. We
work on exoome manufacturing. That's a
new area that we've just started working
on about a year ago. And um we work on
postmarket drug safety surveillance as I
briefly touched
upon. So what I'll talk about today um
are our efforts in gene therapy and cell
therapy manufacturing. And I just want
to give a shout out to some of our
affiliated faculty who work on different
aspects of this work. Um you'll hear uh
work today from myself, Professor
Richard Bratz who's a professor in
chemical engineering. Uh professor Jay
Han who's a professor of electrical
engineering and biological engineering.
Professor Scott Manales uh professor uh
in engineering and associate head of
biological engineering and Rajie Ram uh
potentially among
others. So uh gene therapy has
tremendous potential um against genetic
disorders and other severe uh illnesses.
As you probably know there are already
eight FDA approved therapies um if not
more depending upon you know how you
define a gene therapy. And um we have
specifically focused on recominant AAV
as a delivery vehicle for gene therapies
and we have worked on uh how to improve
the manufacturing of that viral
vector. So there are a lot of critical
challenges in AV manufacturing. Um there
is a uh demand that exceeds the
production capacity. um very high
manufacturing costs that contribute to
the price per dose of these medicines.
And as you know, we have both small and
large patient populations that we're
trying to serve. So you may be wanting
to make a an um a gene therapy for an
ultra rare disease that you know only
has tens of patients or you may be
looking like in the case of cickle cell
to be serving you know millions of
patients and so that has different
demands for the
manufacturing. So this is just uh
showing it pictorially in a different
way where the dose is shown in red um
the total production scale is shown in
blue and then the total number of
patients is shown in green. And so for
Libr's congenital amorosis you really
need a very small dose. Um you you know
basically uh have a small number of
patients. Um but in the case of you know
muscul musculardrophe you basically need
very large doses for a very small number
of patients and then for cickle cell you
need essentially a large scale of
manufacturing. So we need this
innovation to meet the demand of both
rare disease and large patient
populations and that's what we've been
working on. So, you know, some of the
other challenges just to lay them out in
this one slide. It's it's a rule at MIT
that everybody uses 10point uh font and
tries to put as much on their slide as
they possibly can. So, apologies for
that on these small screens. But um
there are two platforms uh for AAV
manufacturing. One of them is triple
transffection of HK293 cells and that's
shown over here on the right where
you're basically delivering your trans
gene um the replication and capsid
producing uh genes rep and cap and then
a helper gene which is needed. So three
plasmids basically going into HK293
cells to produce your viral vector that
then has to get packaged with the gene
of interest. The other way that we can
make these vectors is through using a
bula virus infection of insect cells
where it's typically SF9 cells. And here
there are a number of different um
constructs that are being used. But
typically in all of these systems,
they're very highly inefficient. You're
making anywhere between, you know, um
five and 30% of the material after
you've purified it. It requires multiple
downstream purification steps. and every
one that you go through cuts into your
yield even more. So the you know the
final yields are not good. You have a
number of both process and um product
related impurities. So not only do you
uh end up making these um capsids that
have the gene of interest that you're
you want, but you make some that are
partially filled and you make some that
are empty and you know to a
chromatography column that all looks
pretty much the same. So it's hard to be
able to purify these away from one
another which makes it very um very
challenging in terms of the
manufacturing. So what are we doing to
address some of these issues? So the
first thing that we're trying to do is
better understand the biology because
the better we can understand how these
um capsids are actually made and
packaged, we can find levers that can
help us to uh make choices in the
manufacturing that will improve the
yields. Then we're developing new tools
that can help us in line be able to
detect whether we have you know full or
empty capsids and can we distinguish
between those um at line rather than
needing to wait and do it offline which
right now it's done through a very
laborious and timeconuming set of you
know methods um although there are new
technologies coming along and I'll talk
about some of those as we as we go along
and then we can work on intensifying our
manufacturing process. So we could make
it continuous for instance. So instead
of just you know putting everything in
the bioreactor adding essentially the
nutrients and let it go until it it it
eats all of those we can you know
basically take cells and media off and
replenish the bioreactor with new new
material and keep that culture going and
producing. So these are all things and
approaches that we are taking.
So first on the mechanistic modeling,
the reason that we use mechanistic
models, as I said, is to really combine
not only just the cell biology, but the
viology and the process dynamics of
what's happening. And we're really
trying to go up this triangle I'm
showing here to move away from datadive
trial and error experimentation to where
we really understand the first
principles and understand how this is
working within the cell. And so um if
you create a mechanistic model then you
you can you know identify what's
happening and the bottlenecks and
overcome those. So we've done this quite
a bit. We've published a number of
papers um in this area. I'll review a
little bit of that work with you today
but I encourage you to go look at these
papers if this is of interest to you. So
the first model that we developed was
for the um PEI mediated triple
transfaction in HK293. And so what this
process um involves is actually creating
a number of equations that describe
essentially what's happening in the
cell. So what we do is we go to the
literature and we find as much
information as we can and then we go to
the lab and we add more data to support
the development of this model. And so we
developed um in in 2021 the first model
um for this process and essentially it
describes everything from you know how
we get the the the different plasmids
into the nucleus um to the processes
that then happen thereafter to make the
capsids and and secrete them. And so it
talks about the rep protein and viral
protein synthesis and dynamics, the
regulatory functions, the capsid
assembly, viral DNA replication, DNA
packaging and capsid secretion. Um we
assume the empty and full capsids have
the same secretion um kinetics for the
purpose of this
model. And then you can see that you
know from our data inhouse we have very
good um uh so essentially you're seeing
the experimental data points are shown
as the um the triangles or the diamonds
and then the lines are the model and so
we have very good um reproduction of the
dynamics of viral
production and what we learned from this
particular work was that um in fact most
of the empty capsids uh I'm sorry most
of the um capsids that were making and
harvest are being made um later or
earlier than the DNA is being
replicated. So we've got this
discoordination or this mismatch between
you know expressing the capsid proteins
assembling a capsid and and when there's
actually DNA available to put in into
it. So aha that gave us some some ideas
about how we might address this and um
this was you know around extending the
capsid production timeline to improve
that full empty
ratio. We did the same thing for the
bula virus insect cell system. We built
uh this was work from friend uh Chesco
Destra and Richard BRZ. We built a model
that uh again allowed us to understand
that in this case um these you know
replication uh the transcription of
these replication proteins um such as
rep uh 78 that rate controls the full
AAV production and we also found that
among the different um systems that are
used for bacular virus infection um two
back seems to be better than threeback
because there's stronger rep expression
um because there's a stronger promoter
in particular system. So you know you
can learn things like this through the
model and then you can um you know set
some hypotheses around how you might
address that. So we said okay well what
if we you know feed plasmid uh in in
multiple stages. So we do not just a
single stage transfection but we compare
that to basically splitting those
plasmids in half and dosing twice or
even dosing three times. And so that's
what we the experiment we did. And of
course we saw um a a reasonably modest
but still very significant increase in
the full cap caps capsid harvest when
you had um two rather than uh one or
three. And just in the interest of time
I'm going to keep moving because I can
see that I also was ambitious in my
slides. Um so we also developed a
continuous highdensity multid-dosese uh
AAV production process um based on this
and um so we looked at different um uh
you know basically different approaches
to doing this where we would um
retransect if you will at different uh
times into the continuous process. So
now we're, you know, we could
continuously growing these and then um
every so many days we're
retransfecting. And what we were able to
see was that we could grow these cells
at high density. We could also model
this. We could um increase the vector
genome tighter. Um and um we also
noticed that um interestingly there was
an order of magnitude um increase in the
um reccominant AEV inside the cells
compared to the supernate. So that's
probably another area um where you could
work on improving yields. Um but as you
can see we you know when we look at day
zero versus um days seven and nine
combined we can see almost a order of
magnitude improvement in the production
of full
capsits. So really briefly one way that
we are approaching um the purification
challenge um is to develop selective
viral vector crystallization uh
capability. So again, we need the full,
not the empties, not the partially
filleds. And so um what Richard Bratz
lab and um has done is to you know map
out the space um much like you would
like a phase diagram of where you can
actually preferentially crystallize
different um stereotypes of AAV. And so
you can see here at different phes he
looked at this and these you know would
be where you would be able to
crystallize the foss over the empties.
And so that gives you essentially and he
did this for a number of cereotypes and
found that um you know you could find
these sweet spots for crystallization.
And so we've done that at a very small
like hanging drop scale and now we're
doing it at a midscale um with uh with
the different stereotypes of AEV. So
that's very exciting and could be a
really important way of being able to
improve um the the purification of
these.
The other thing I want to share with you
about the AAV work that we've done is
that we've tried to work also at a very
small scale to understand how we might
um improve the economics around um you
know just making a few doses of these
for individual or patients where there
are not you know there's only a few that
have a particular indication and so um
at
MIT professor uh Rajiv Ram and also
professor Tony Sinski um invented these
really cool microb
bioreactors. They were um spun out into
a company and then acquired by
Millipore. They're currently called the
Mobius Breeze, but they are they're
basically two millimeter
microbitors that um you can basically um
run these in a variety of different
modes um anywhere from you know batch
fed batch to to uh perusion or
continuous and we've been able to um you
know basically grow HK29 cells which are
kind of sensitive um all the way up to
like 100 million cells per mill in these
little micro bioreactors and uh and then
start doing transfection reactions in
these and we've learned a couple of
things so far and one of the great
things about these um systems is that
you know you have um basically real time
uh measurements of pH ox dissolved
oxygen um and many other factors that
you can um monitor from your laptop at
home and so um we get a lot of data
coming out off of these about you know
essentially how the process is
proceeding
Um so we've done the triple
transffection as I mentioned uh in here
and what we identified is that you know
PEI is essentially like a poison you
know it's it's required you need it to
essentially create a charge around the
you know um DNA that you're trying to
put into the cells but it also you know
has a negative effect on the cells and
so you know we did some we looked at you
know after transfection letting the
cells uh grow for nine for for 9 hours
versus 24 hours. And what you find is
that um you can actually get a lot of
improvement if you only um if you only
let these grow for 9 hours um instead of
24 after you start after the
transfection. And so um we found that
the percentage of filled capsids was
significantly higher um apologies for
that. and um and the vector genome
tighter uh per cell was also twofold
higher for at the at the 9h hour
compared to the
24-hour. Okay, so um this is really like
the the drink from the fire hose version
of this talk. So I apologize for going
so quickly through so many things. The
next thing I want to talk with you about
are some of the analytical technologies
we've been working on to be able to
better um separate and or analyze um
full versus empty capsids um and other
features of um you know AEV. And so in
this particular work that was done by
professor Jong Yun Han and Ming uh Su
basically they've been able to use
electropharetic um chargebased
separation in these micrfluidic devices
to be able to turn on the electric field
and go from you know a single stream of
a mixture into a very clear mixture of
empty versus full AAVs.
In addition, we've been working with
Professor Scott Manales who um has
developed these single nanoch resonator
devices. So you can think about this as
being a um little diving board that
resonates with a certain frequency and
that frequency is um related to the mass
that's you know going through there. And
so you can use this um basically we he
has used it over the years to do a
number of of really interesting
mass-based measurements related to
cells. But in this case he made a nanoch
resonator. So even smaller small enough
that we um we asked the question can we
use this device to detect the difference
between a full and an empty AAV um
particle. And so as you can see we got
this very um you know messy looking uh
signal coming coming off of this. But um
Yorgos uh Katsikus who basically did
this work um was able to deconvolute
this and we worked together with
Biomaren who did essentially all the um
standard analytics including um the
dynamic light scattering which is shown
in purple here. And then basically um
what you're seeing here is both the um
the predicted and the you know the
actual data coming out of this uh model.
And you can see we do pretty well
actually at being able to um both
simulate uh what's happening in the
experimental data and match what's
happening uh through other other
measurements. So this actually in fact
is a method that can distinguish empty
and full capsids uh in real time and and
um it's b basically able to distinguish
the difference between literally an add
of
material. And then more recently we've
been wondering whether we could use um
the these this same kind of approach um
for the cells to ask questions about you
know the cells and whether we could
really see whether we could um measure
the tighter that was uh developing for
the full capsids because it's it's
currently as I mentioned you know it
takes a long time to um do essentially
you know you measure the total capsids
um through uh a combination of both
Eliza and digital droplet PCR. And so
these are labor intensive and and um you
know we want to have real-time tools at
our disposal that can tell us how much
material we have. And so what um what um
uh Francesco um Destro and Wayda Woo or
Richard Woo did is they basically um
took this um this device and then they
put a microscope on it and they were
able to actually um you know ask
questions about these different
biohysical characteristics, the buoyant
dry mass, the volume and the density of
these cells and then put them into a
machine learning model and ask whether
there they they could um develop a model
that would be predictive for the full
capsids. And so they did a number of
different um experiments with different
packet plasmid ratios and um and
um and then they uh added this you know
they they did this experiment where they
had time matched samples and you know
basically I'm not sure what's going on
with my slide here but um basically they
were able to do a number of different
single cell measurements put them into a
matrix do the machine learning model and
basically look at the capsid and how
well it predicts the capsidin genome
tighter and so they don't need to do
that that part then on a regular basis
except for the model development itself
and so here essentially is just showing
you know some of the um data both zero
and 72 hours post transfaction then as I
mentioned it goes into um all the raw
data goes into this matrix they do
feature
extraction and then um that that is you
know goes into um a matrix that can feed
the machine learning models. And so, you
know, from that um they they've been
able to do this
unsupervised learning process to um use
a a principal component analysis of
feature matrix spontaneously organizing
the samples um with respect to
transfaction process. And then this is
sort of the the end result here is
comparing both the data points in um in
black for Eliza on this side and DDPCR
with the SMR plus machine learning shown
in red or purple and we do pretty good
actually for you know the the first few
experiments out of the gate. This is all
unpublished um data as for the moment.
All right. So um they did some cross
validation and uh and also they did work
to um develop an interpretable
interpretable model for this um so that
we understand essentially you know what
what what relates to what here. Okay.
And um and so one of the things one of
the takeaways so far that we've been
learning is that high high recominant
AAV production correlates to um uh low
mass and volume of the cells. So smaller
cells seem to be making more AAV. Um so
that's interesting and they've validated
that with single cell GFP uh
measurements as well. So one of the
things that we've been doing in
Singapore um is we have an
interdisciplinary research group called
CAMP or critical analytics for
manufacturing personalized medicine. And
so there's a group myself and a group of
about five or six other faculty working
there in Singapore. Um we are making
analytical technologies that support
basically you know stem cell cartis cell
IPSC cell uh isolation characterization
cell processing and engineering quality
assessment um including potency and
safety and then we're working with the
clinical environment there to test our
technologies uh in these areas and while
I won't have time today to tell you you
know more about these um I just want to
you know end by saying that um you know
we've developed a number of different
sterility tests, a number of different
tests that uh a number of different
technologies that can sort cells into um
populations and we've also done a lot of
work to develop um small those smallcale
bioreactors for CARTT production as
well. So, with that, I'm gonna have to
stop apparently and um I'll be happy to
take any questions and I'll try to stick
around through like 10 minutes or so of
the break in case people um would like
to ask me anything. And you're welcome
to email me um and I'll be happy to to
uh answer any questions you have if we
don't have time here. Okay. Thank you.