So remember last lecture I introduced
you to the idea of tailbounds where we
want to get a rough handle on how likely
it is for a random variable to be far
away from its expectation.
So we talked about uh you know marov's
bound, chbachev's bound and each of
these used more and more information
about the random variables as a way to
get a better bound on the tail
probabilities. So marov just used that
the random variable was non- negative
and then we already could bound the
probability that it was double its
expectation. Chbashev we used its
variance which is a measure of how
spread out the random variable is and
you know today we're going to do you
know the the most important tool uh the
highest powered tool which is called the
churnoff bound.
So this is going to use that not only
you know do we know properties about X's
expectation and its variance but that X
itself is composed of the sum of
mutually independent random variables.
So we'll see that implicitly in the
proof of this we're going to be using
not just the first moment which is the
mean and the second moment but we're
going to be using all of the higher
moments at once. Uh but the basic setup
for the turnoff bound at least the plain
vanilla version is remember from last
time we have these random variables xi
that are mutually independent. So this
is critical turnoffbound only works when
you have mutual independence not just
pair-wise. It's completely false
otherwise. And these XI's we're going to
assume for simplicity that they're Berni
random variables. So each of the XI's is
probability PI of being one and is
otherwise zero. And just to have some
notation, we'll let mu denote the
expectation of X, which is the sum of
all the XI's. But of course, that's the
same thing as the sum of all of the PIs.
So the turnoff bound comes in a lot of
different flavors. Let me state a few
different versions you might care about.
First, there's what's called the upper
tail, which this is the probability that
the random variable is way larger than
its expectation. So for all delta
greater than zero, we can look at the
probability that X is larger than its
mean by a 1 + delta factor. So you
should think about delta here as being
something like 0.1, right? Uh the chance
that this happens is exponentially
small.
And it depends on this delta parameter
of course, but then it also depends on
mu.
So this is a complicated algebraic
expression, but it's important to have
some intuition for what's going on here.
So if I take a fair coin and I flip it,
I know the probability that it's heads
is 50, right? Is 50%.
And you know, intuitively, if I flip my
coin a whole bunch of times and keep
track of how many heads I get, I should
expect that the empirical average of the
number of heads is very quickly going to
50/50, right? Maybe if I flip it three
times, you know, I'll get two heads out
of three and that'll be far away from
50/50. But the larger the number of
flips, well, the more it should be
driven to going back to the average,
right? That's what things like the weak
law of large numbers are telling us. And
you know the way that this shows up is
really in this mean mew because as the
number of flips n gets larger and
larger, my mean is larger and larger. So
the chance that I have 10% too many
heads is going down exponentially
with the number of flips I make. So this
is the critical distinction between the
churnoff bound and things like the weak
law of large numbers is that here our
failure probability the chance that you
know we're outside this range where we
think it lands is exponentially small in
n whereas for things like the weak law
of large numbers it was only inverse
polomially small in n. So that's called
the upper tail because all I care about
is the probability that x is too big
compared to mu. there's a corresponding
lower tail. The only reason we separate
these two things out is because they
have a slightly different dependence on
delta. So here it really only makes
sense to have a delta that's between 0
and one. And now the probability that x
is at most 1 minus delta * mu that I get
too few heads instead is again something
that's exponentially small. it just has
doesn't have this two plus delta in the
base. So it looks like this instead.
So this is the lower tail. And there's
also a way that you can combine them if
you don't have to worry that much about
what the dependence on delta is. So what
I claim is that when you just put these
bounds together, so for all delta
between 0 and one, you can just write it
instead. The probability that X minus mu
an absolute value is larger than delta
mu. So it's more than delta mu away from
its expectation goes down like 2 * e
minus mu delta^ 2 over 3. So turnoff
bounds aren't really just one bound.
There's a whole family of bounds. The
ones I'm stating here, you know, these
are for bernoli random variables. and we
have you know an upper tail, a lower
tail, a combined bound. Uh in fact there
are versions of churnoff bounds where
the XI's aren't Berni random variables.
There are other kinds of random
variables you know with bounded second
moments. So what you know the way you
should think about turnoff bounds is I'm
going to give you one proof of the
turnoff bound. It'll be in this
restricted case of Berni random
variables. The same basic proof works
for a lot of other exotic variants of a
churnoff bound. And when you need a
different kind of turnoff bound like
your XI's are not Bernoli, you just look
it up and quote the bound. So the key
thing is really just to understand one
of these bounds, how the proof works and
intuitively why the proof should extend
beyond literally the assumptions I'm
making. So are there any questions about
it?
Okay, so this is uh probably the most
complicated proof uh we've done up until
this point and it's something which
we're going to spend a bit of time in
recitation thinking about. Yeah.
>> Uh does mu have to be positive?
>> Uh so mu is positive here just by
assumption because my x i are non-
negative. I mean if mu were zero it
would be kind of trivial. So you have to
be a bit more careful when you have a
churnoff bound with random variables
whose uh which are not non- negative and
yeah you have to shift and scale it and
you'll see through the proof that a lot
of these things can be done. It's just
that it changes subtleties like what
exactly happens in the exponent here. So
there might be, you know, other
quantities that show up, but the
important thing is really the mu and the
delta dependence and then the other
scalers might change in different ways,
but good question. All right, so we're
going to cover this in more detail in
the recitation, but I'm warning you. So
this will be one of the most complicated
proofs we've done up until this point.
But what I'm going to try and do is I'm
going to explain the high-level strategy
for the proof and that way we can then
try and fill in some of the technical
details, the actual estimates to get the
overall strategy to work. So what I
really want to focus on is like how
we're going to prove this bound at a
high level because you know in all
proofs there are you know the hard parts
of how you're going to fit the pieces
together and then there are the tedious
parts of like how do you do the literal
computations to execute the different
steps of your strategy. So let's start
with the main idea and this will be a
very similar trick to what happened when
we proved the chbashev bound. So let's
say I have my random variable X and for
some A that I'm going to set later
because I'm going to set it to be equal
to this you know 1 plus delta mu or 1
minus delt you know that kind of thing.
Let's say I'm interested in the
probability that X is very large that
it's at least some value A. I claim that
this is the same thing as the
probability that E to the BX is at least
e to the BA. And this is true for all B
that are non- negative.
Okay, so this is the first key trick. So
remember when we had the proof of the
chbashev bound, you know, chbashev
doesn't assume any kind of non-
negativity about the random variable.
And I had this trick where when I wanted
to look at the probability that X is too
large, I squared both sides and then I
defined a new random variable Y. And I
said that that random variable Y is non-
negative. And I just said those two
probabilities are the same because
they're literally the same event. So
that's exactly what's happening here.
You can take B to be one just for
simplicity. I'm just saying that, you
know, these two events are the same. X
being at least A is the same thing as E
to the X being at least E to the A. And
that's just because you know E is a nice
you know monotone function, right? And
this is true now even if I put in a
scalar B in there as long as B is non-
negative. So is everyone on board with
this? This is fine.
>> Yeah.
>> Why doesn't B need to be strictly
greater than zero? Uh,
I don't know. Let's just make it strict.
I'm not going to use the equality
anyways and we'll get into a
technicality, but thanks for the catch.
Any other questions?
All right. So, that's the first idea.
So, you know, just to belabor the point,
right? So, why is this true?
It's true because e to the y is an
increasing function.
And so that really means that these two
events are the same. The set of all x's
where x is at least you know a are the
same as the set of all x's where e to
the bx is at least e to the b a. So
they're literally the same event. So
this is the first thing in our trick,
right? And so now exactly like in the
proof of the chbashev bound, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to define a new
random variable y which is e to the bx.
Right? So this is a really interesting
trick. Just like for chevb I defined a
new random variable y which was the you
know square compared to the expectation.
Now I'm doing this funny thing where I
take the exponential of my random
variable and I'm using that to define
this new random variable y. Right?
So now
just by construction y is non- negative
right it's a non- negative random
variable which means we can apply
markoff.
So let's apply markoff and see what we
get.
So the probability that you know X is uh
at least a is at most
e expectation of e to the bx over e to
the b a.
Okay. So what is this doing right here
is I'm just using two facts. So first of
all, this one right here is just the
probability that Y is at least E to the
BA. And I'm using the fact that you know
if I had probability of Y at least E to
the BA, this would be my expectation of
Y. This would be my threshold. So this
is just markoff. And now I'm using this
fact that these two probabilities are
the same to replace my left hand side
with the probability X is at least a.
So this is subtle, right? Does everyone
follow that?
Any questions?
Give me a thumbs up if it makes sense.
Okay, good. All right. So now it turns
out that uh the quantity on the right
hand side, this thing right here, this
is important for its own right.
It actually has a very special name and
a special role. So before we go on uh
with the proof, let me explain what this
quantity is and why it's so important
because otherwise it'll seem a bit too
magical. So this is called the moment
generating function.
So the moment generating function
you know we've seen generating functions
in the context of cominotaurics, right?
And here it's a generating function in a
different disguise because it'll be
keeping track of other things. So when
we talked about generating functions in
the context of combinotaurics, you know,
the coefficients that showed up in
different powers of a different powers
of x that kept track of things we wanted
to count. So you know it turns out that
this quantity right here keeps track of
uh you know important quantities of x.
But you know the way it keeps track of
it is that there's a free parameter B.
So what I really care about is how this
term depends on B. And so it turns out
that the series expansion I get in terms
of B keeps track of a lot of interesting
properties of the random variable.
That's why we call this the moment
generating function. So the moment
generating function of X is literally
just the thing on the right hand side.
We denote it by MX of B and it's equal
to the expectation of e to the bx.
So even though x is our random variable,
that's not the thing that shows up in
the moment generating function because
I'm taking the expectation over x. The
important thing is really just how that
expectation depends on b. So let's you
know tease out these properties of the
moment generating function just to get
some intuition for what properties
of uh you know the random variable this
proof of the churnoff bound is using. So
let's do some intuition.
So first of all mx of b is a function of
b.
In fact, you know, one way that we could
think about it is we could take the
tailaylor expansion of e to the bx,
right? So if we take the tailor
expansion of e to the bx because inside
the expectation x is just you know some
particular realization
and it could look like 1 + you know bx
plus 1 over 2 factorial b ^2 x^2
plus 1 over 3 factorial b cub x cubed
and so on. Okay.
So if we just take the tailor expansion
of our exponential function, this is
what we get. And now we can use
linearity of expectation and this is the
same thing as the sum from i= 0 to
infinity of 1 / i factorial b to the i
the expectation of x to the i.
So this is what I promised you, right?
So the moment generating function is
this generating function that uh depends
on B and what is you know the first term
of this well it's trivial when I equals
Z right because I just get one out of it
but now when I do the you know the next
term corresponding to I equals 1 what am
I getting well the coefficient of B is
the expectation of X
and when I look at I equals 2 it's not
the variance of X but it's the second
moment of X and so on and the third
moments. So the moment generating
function keeps track of the moments of X
and in fact what I claim is that you can
extract the uh moments from the moment
generating function.
So we'll see how this works just in a
simple case
and this will parallel what Peter taught
you about uh generating functions. So,
how could I go about extracting a
particular moment
of X from the moment generating
function?
Well, in particular, the way that I can
recover the first moment of X is just by
taking my
moment generating function,
taking the partial derivative with
respect to B and then evaluating it at B
equals Z.
All that would do is it would kill the
first term that's just a constant and I
just pick up the expectation,
right? And then when I evaluated at B
equals Z all of the higher order terms
would disappear. Uh so you can check
that this really does give you um you
know what you want right
in particular the partial with respect
to b of mx of b we can just apply it to
this expression that I wrote out right
here. And you know that's the same thing
as the partial with respect to b of 1 +
b e x and so on. And then we'll get this
expression that looks like e x + b e x
squared and so on. And we evaluate at b
equals z. We get exactly what we wanted.
So for example, how could I extract the
second moment of you know X from the
moment generating function just to make
sure we're on the same page.
>> Yeah.
>> Second derivative. Just have to be
careful with the constants but they all
work out uh nicely here. So you know
this gives us some intuition about you
know I told you that the churnoff bound
would be using higher order moments of
my random variable. I'm not just using
the first and second moment like I am
with Marov and Chevbashev and the way
that I'm using it is really what's
happening on the right hand side. That
moment generating function contains all
of the information about X that we'll
want. Okay.
So now uh let's get back to the proof
and figure out you know why this is a
productive thing to do.
So here's our first key lema. So in the
setting of the churnoff bound where we
have X equals the sum of these XI's
and all these XI's
are mutually independent.
Then what I claim is that the moment
generating function of X evaluated at B
is the same thing as the product of all
of the constituent moment generating
functions for each one of the XI's all
evaluated at the same thing B.
So that's the first key statement. This
is why the moment generating function
plays nicely with mutual independence is
because it decomposes as a product of a
lot of things. Was there a question? No.
Okay. All right. So the proof for this
is very simple. It's just about
unpacking you know what's happening in
this definition.
So by definition and our assumption
we just have to remember what the moment
generating function is. So mx of b is
defined to be the expectation of e to
the bx that's where it came from. And
then we can remember what exactly x is
right because x is the sum from i= 1 to
n of the x i's.
And now what should I do in my last step
right here? So how am I going to
proceed? Yeah.
>> That's right. So just to you know
belabor this right. So let me write it
out you know in two steps. First I can
write this as the product from i= 1 to n
of each of these ebxis
right. But now the crucial thing is that
by mutual independence of the x i's
I actually know that not only are the x
i independent but so are the e to the
bxis as well. Right? And so by mutual
independence
we can write we can pull the product
outside. This is where I crucially need
not just pair-wise independence and I'll
get the product of all of these
expectations of e to the bxi.
And that's literally the product of
their moment generating functions
exactly as I promised. So that's the
first lema, the first key thing we need
for the ingredient for the turnoff.
Okay,
any questions.
So you know this is the basic
architecture of the proof for the
turnoff bound is that you know we
defined this new random variable y
that's the exponential of x and then you
know when we applied markov we ended up
with the moment generating function the
right hand side and the moment
generating function turns into the
product of all of the constituent moment
generating functions. So now what we
need to do is we need to actually
estimate the individual terms that go
into the right hand side. So now you
know the whole name of the game is
executing the strategy and figuring out
what the right hand side looks like in
this one bound that I wrote down right
there. So now we're actually going to
use the properties of like the pis. So
let me tell you the second key lema
which will be our second main ingredient
in the proof.
So let's figure out what these moment
generating functions are for each of
these x subis.
So here's what I claim. This is our lema
2.
So if x subi
is one or zero again with probability
pi and zero otherwise. So same as the
assumptions of the turnoff bound. Then
what I claim is that the moment
generating function of XI evaluated at B
is at most e to the pi e to the b minus
one. Okay. So this is now just the
numerical value for it. Obviously it has
to depend on what the probability pi is
of x i being one for that bernoli random
variable. And then it also depends on
where we're evaluating the moment
generating function at because that
shows up in the as a double exponential
bound.
So what we're going to do to prove this
is we'll use the fact
that 1 + y is at most e to the y. And
this is true for all y.
All right. And so this is a very simple
thing to prove just with calculus or you
can just plot it to check yourself. You
plot uh you know 1 + y and look at e to
the y and you'll see that you know the
line is strict is below um you know the
exponential curve. Um so this inequality
is going to play a crucial role in
getting a convenient form for the right
hand side. So now let's prove this lema.
Well, we're going to prove this just by
direct computation and eventually we're
going to appeal to this fact in order to
write it in a more convenient form.
So, you know what is the moment
generating function of xi? Well, we can
write it out because you know there are
only two possibilities. So either
x i equals 1 or x i equals zero.
In the case where it's zero, our
quantity contributes a one, right?
Because we get e to the 0. And the case
where it's a one, we get an e to the b.
So this is just literally using the
definition of the expectation.
And now we can plug in for you know what
the probability of x i being one is. So
this gives us on the right hand side p i
e e to the b + 1 minus pi.
And we can write this in a slightly more
convenient form. We can write this out
instead as 1 + pi * e b minus one. So
I'm just collecting the two terms.
And now I'm almost done because I should
use this fact I told you I needed about
the exponential.
So [clears throat] I'm going to think
about my y variable as just being this
pi quantity on the right hand side. I
have something that looks like 1 + y and
I'm going to upper bound it by e to the
y. So using our fact about exponentials
we get that the moment generating
function is now at most e to the pi * e
to the b minus one. Right? So literally
all I'm doing is I'm appealing to the
fact where this is my y right here.
Right? And that's the end of the proof
for limit two.
So right now it's not totally obvious
why we want an expression like this.
Like why did we not just stop at the
expression I had above. Let me give you
a little foreshadowing of where we're
going. See at the end of the day the way
that the churnoff bound works is that
the right hand side has this quantity mu
in it right which is the average of your
random variable. And that quantity mu is
the sum of the pis. So in our lema one,
we're taking the product of all these
moment generating functions. And so
what's going to happen is we take the
product of terms that look like this
where the pi is happening upstairs and
then we're going to get a sum of the
pi's and that's where our mu is going to
fall out. So if id kept that other bound
over there, that would have been still
true and just, you know, an even sharper
bound. But it doesn't give me a
convenient expression for actually
getting the churnoff bound that I want.
Okay, so now we can prove the turnoff
bound. Uh,
and I'm just going to prove the upper
tail, but you can check the notes for
the proof of the lower tail, and it
works very similarly.
Um, what I'm going to do is, you know,
at the end of the day, I have to figure
out how to execute this proof strategy,
right? because I have a whole bunch of
parameters that I now need to set. So I
have to set my threshold a you know in
that bound that I wrote up there. I have
to choose my parameter B which is my
helper parameter so that I get a tight
enough right hand side that I get the
upper tail for the turnoff bound popping
out. So let me just tell you what I'm
going to choose for these A's and B. So
A is the obvious thing because it
corresponds to the event we care about.
So it's 1 plus delta time mu because
that's our upper tail condition. And b
we're just going to set to be equal to
the natural log of 1 + delta. So this
might look a little strange, but the way
that you would prove this yourself or
come up with this B is you would just
work through the calculations I'm about
to do, but keeping B as a free
parameter, you would get a right-hand
side that depends on B and then you
would optimize over what is the best
choice of B that gives you the tightest
upper bound. So all I'm doing here is
I'm doing the work for you and I'm
telling you that this will be the answer
for B. So let's just work with this B
and then we'll check you know what
happens for the upper tail.
So now we can put this all together.
I told you this will be a long proof.
All right.
So let's put this all together.
Well, we care about the probability that
X is at least a. And remember, A is 1 +
delta * mu. We know that this is the
same as the probability that e to the bx
is at least e to the a b where a is
again my 1 plus delta mu. Right? This
uses that first fact that these two
events are the same. We know by marov
that this is at most the expectation of
e to the bx. That's where we first saw
the moment generating function. Now we
can appeal to lema one
which told us how to write the moment
generating function as the product of
the moment generating functions of its
constituents. So we get the product from
i= 1 to n of all of these individual
moment generating functions still over
this denominator eab.
And finally we can use lema 2
which gave us a good quantitative upper
bound for the setting of the churnoff
bound. We get the product from i= 1 to n
of e to the p i e e to the b minus1
all over e to the ab.
And I'm going to call this right hand
side star. And the name of the game is
really just to figure out what star is
so that the churnoff bound pops out.
So you know our bound star right here we
can plug in for all of our values of a
and b we'll get uh the product of i = 1
to n of e to the pi
time delta. Right? Because b is natural
log of 1 plus delta. So when I plug this
in, I'm going to get delta sitting out
right here. And then my denominator,
well that's e to the ab. So I claim it's
equal to 1 + delta to the 1 + delta time
mu, right? Because again, when I have e
to the ab, I can take the b downstairs
and I'll get 1 plus delta instead of my
e. And that'll be being raised to the
ath power which is exactly this 1 plus
delta * mu.
So you see for the choff bound it's very
easy to potentially get lost in some of
the computations but the highest level
point is really what's happening over
here the architecture of how the pieces
of the proof fit together. The rest of
it now from now on is just calculus
because all we have to do is figure out
how to actually bound the right hand
side so that the upper tail for the
turnoff pops out.
Okay, so now we have this expression
right here and uh we can write this out.
Of course, the sum of the pis is mu. So
we're going to get e to the delta mu all
over 1 + delta to the 1 + delta * mu.
And what I claim this will be my lema 3,
the last piece that we need for the
churnoff bound. I claim that this right
hand side is at most whatever shows up
in the upper tail. This e to the minus
delta^ 2 mu type of term. So once I
prove that last lema 3, we'll be done.
Okay.
So, let's prove that last part
and it's not too bad.
So, the way that we're going to do this
is like this is what our lema 3 is. We
want to show that this is at most this
quantity right here. So what I'm going
to do is I'm going to take the natural
log of both sides.
So the natural log of the left hand side
of my expression is equal to delta mu
minus
1 + delta mu
natural log of 1 + delta
right
and I can rewrite this expression and
pull out the mu. So I'll get mu * delta
minus 1 + delta natural log of 1 +
delta.
Nothing fancy is happening here.
And now we need our last you know basic
fact that we're going to take advantage
of which is that I claim for all
x that are strictly positive
we have the following bound.
So the log of 1 + x is lower bounded by
x over 1 + x / 2.
So this is all very natural. I mean I
told you these things follow from the
churnoff bound from you know from
calculus types of proofs. And the idea
is that if I took the tailor expansion
of natural log of 1 plus x my linear
term would be x. And now what I want to
do is I just want to make sure that um
you know the way that I get rid of the
other terms I always have a valid lower
bound. So here what I'm going to do is
um you know you have to choose the right
expression to put in the denominator.
But this is again something you can
check either you know with elementary
calculus or just by plotting these
things to convince yourself it's true.
But now we're in good shape because you
know what this tells us is that uh boy
okay
sorry I'll have to do it over here.
So using this fact and our expression
for the left hand side
this is at most mu delta
minus mu 1 + delta delta
over 1 + delta / 2.
So you can see what's going on here is
that I'm just plugging in this natural
log of you know 1 + x uh in order to get
rid of this term right here, right?
Because I'm replacing this with delta
over 1 plus delta / 2 and then I'll get
exactly this expression that I've
written down right here. And now when we
collect terms we'll be home free. So
this is equal to mu times a whole bunch
of things. So I'm going to multiply this
part by 1 plus delta / 2 just so that I
can put everything to have this
denominator of 1 plus delta / 2 and then
I'll get delta + delta^ 2 - delta minus
delta^ 2
and then life is good because I get
minus mu delta^ 2 over 2 + delta and
that's the proof.
So one of the points that I want to make
so we'll talk more about this in
recitation.
So uh you know the turnoff bound is
definitely one of the most complicated
proofs we've done up until this point
but you know when you're presenting
things that are this complicated or
things like this in your term paper. One
of the things to keep in mind is that um
you know it's not really just begin
proof end proof, right? So the way that
you break up the proof makes it a lot
easier to understand the overall
strategy, right? So for example, the way
that I broke it up into these, you know,
lema 1, lema 2, and then lema 3, it
allows me to give an overview of the
churnoff bound even though it was like a
full lecturer long proof that fits very
compactly.
So a lot of times when you're, you know,
first doing proof-based math, you have
this temptation to prove everything
linearly where you just start at the
beginning and you keep proving things
until you're at the end.
when I was uh you know first starting
out that was also my temptation too. I
think my first paper when I wrote it, it
was like a 15-page begin proof, end
proof and then my adviser told me
afterwards that he didn't understand the
proof which was a little bit worrisome.
In fact, it wasn't even so obvious from
the way I'd written it that uh you know
when you look at the dependencies
between the different pieces that they
were actually asyclic.
So you know to a certain extent
sometimes you can refactor a proof so
that it's not just linear so that you
can give people a preview of how exactly
it fits together right because there's a
difference between you know what are the
parts where the action is happening
where you're telling me about what's the
strategy you're going to use where
you're going to use mutual independence
and the parts which are you know
mechanical and are more technical to
actually execute because a lot of these
things are algebraic computations
I can follow these things and check
them, you know, myself, but the truth is
that I don't learn a whole heck of a lot
from the proof of lema 3, except for the
fact that, you know, if I massage things
algebraically, I'll get the right
expression that I wanted. So you should
think about a lot of these pedagogical
things for you know your own writing
because you know uh are there ways to
you know assert some pieces of the lema
so that you can give people a blueprint
for how the pieces fit together and then
maybe fill in the parts which you know
are the most interesting first and table
the parts which are more mechanical and
algebraic for later. Right? So another
thing I did to try and present this
proof was that there were things that I
explained that I didn't literally need
to explain. So can you give me any
examples of things in the proof the way
that I presented it that aren't strictly
necessary for getting the upper tail for
the churnoff bound? Just out of
curiosity.
Most of it's on the board
and also are there any questions about
the turnoff bound proof?
>> Yeah.
>> So at the beginning we said like if you
want to adapt it to a different variable
we could like use bounds on like the
moments. Yeah. Where exactly the proof
like let's say we want to get like a
stricter inequality where would we
incorporate that?
>> Great question. So where in this proof
did I use the fact that the XI's were
Bernoli?
So um now you know like when I have this
architecture the proof just sitting on
the board it becomes a lot easier to
think about you know each individual
piece right that's the advantage of
presenting it this way. Did I use
Bernoli here?
No.
Did I use Bernoli here?
No. What about here? This was the place
I used it. So that's what I was saying
when I meant that, you know, the
churnout bound can be adapted to many
different settings. It's really just a
blanket statement that sums of
independent random variables, uh, you
know, have nice tailbound properties.
And the only thing that would change was
if you gave me non Berni random
variables I would have other explicit
estimates.
Now here you know I just used Berni to
figure out what exactly the moment
generating function was literally this
is an equality but then I had to do a
bit of massaging to get the pis to be in
the exponent.
So that's the part that would change is
that if you gave me some other random
variables, I could plug in and compute
literally what the moment generating
functions are for them. But then I would
have the same problem about how to
massage that into an expression where
you know when I take the product of all
of them, I get the mu sitting out there.
So those are things which you know you
can be done but for the most part
they're not very instructive. So you can
just cite whichever churnoff bounds you
want when you have to use it and you
should know that the architecture the
proof is not very surprising right are
there any other questions about it so
the other thing I'll ask which I asked
before right is what part of my
exposition was not literally needed to
prove the turnoff bound yeah
>> moment
>> yeah actually I didn't need to talk
about moment generating functions at all
right
so I could have just said that the right
hand side is the right hand side. It is
whatever it is expectation of e to the
bx and then you know I could have just
said because x is the sum of x i it's
equal to the product of their
expectations and we could have skipped
straight to lema one. That's one way I
could have proved the thing and there
would be nothing mathematically wrong
with that. Right? But this class is, you
know, a CIM. So it's not just about
writing mathematically correct
statements, but it's also about thinking
about, you know, how to do the
exposition to get the audience to better
understand and appreciate it. Why do you
think I talked about the moment
generating function even though I didn't
literally need to?
Sorry to put you guys on the spot, but
this is the way I designed it was I want
to interrogate you guys about why I
presented it the way I did
just for fun. Stalling.
>> So it's more modular.
>> So it's more modular. Yeah, that's one
good thing. Any other ideas why I did it
that way?
Modularity was definitely very important
for being able to fit together a
blueprint of the proof on just one
section of the board. But there's no
there are other reasons I used the
moment generating function. Yeah.
>> To like demystify why.
>> Yeah, that's a big reason, right? So I
used it to demystify because otherwise
this would look like black magic. You
know, we proved the chevbase bound where
we did that same trick of creating a new
random variable and that was very
natural because we had a random variable
before which wasn't non- negative. So we
squared it to create a non-gative random
variable. But you know here, where would
you come up with the idea of taking the
random variable and exponentiating?
That's a very clever idea and it's used
throughout probability. We're not going
to see much more exotic examples, but
otherwise this would seem totally
exotic. Like why wouldn't I try other
functions? It's really because the
exponential is the thing that keeps
track of all of the relevant information
about the random variable I could care
about. So I not only told you that this
is called the moment generating function
but I explained how you could extract
properties of the random variable from
that moment generating function. You
know that way we can talk about what
properties are we literally using about
the random variable. There's another
reason I introduced the moment
generating function.
You know I introduced it for several
reasons. Yeah
>> maybe.
Yeah, that's a good thought. But let's
all that's a good idea, but it also has
to do with you, the audience,
right? So, if I were teaching a
different class, I might not have said
the things I said about the moment
generating function. What did I use
about the moment generating function
that was specific to you and what else
you've learned in this class?
>> We just covered generating functions.
>> That's right. We just covered generating
functions. So the way that I chose my
exposition was also based on what I know
you know and how to make connections
between it because uh you know when we
started the probability unit we then
switched gears and talked about counting
and there are a lot of connections
between probability and counting things
like you know inclusion exclusion
formulas. we already saw, you know,
binomial coefficients coming up. And the
same way, you know, I wanted to further
strengthen the connections between
probability and counting because usually
they're just, you know, different
languages for talking about the same
thing. Okay?
All right. So, these are all things you
should think about uh you know, when
you're doing your own exposition. I'll
tell you, you know, one last thing and
then we'll call it a day. Um so the
churnoff bound is this amazingly
powerful tool. It was invented by Herman
Chernoff who was here for a long time.
Uh it's one of his most famous
discoveries. But uh you know what's kind
of funny is he he I mean he actually
just turned I think a hundred. So he had
his hundredy year birthday uh recently.
Um, in fact, another fun fact about him
is that his wife is alive, too, and
they're believed to be the oldest living
couple in the state of Massachusetts.
So, that's uh quite something. But uh,
you know, the churnoff bound also gets
misused quite a lot, right? Because it
sounds like this amazing fact that you
know, when I first introduced it, I
talked about how we wanted to drive the
failure probability of some randomized
algorithm down.
And if we repeat it a bunch of times,
things like the weak law of large
numbers would tell us to get our failure
probability down to like 10 the minus30,
we have to repeat it like 10 the 30
times.
The churnoff bound would tell us that
because the right hand side is this
exponentially small decaying
probability, we only have to repeat it,
you know, natural log of that many
times. So it tells us that random
variables concentrate at extremely fast
rates. But what's really critical about
it is you know the assumption of mutual
independence. You know all of this was
predicated on it. The moment generating
function keeps track of not just
pair-wise information but all higher
order moments. And you know there are a
lot of famous examples uh that affect
all of us of people thinking about using
the churnoff bound even though it
doesn't really apply. So, this is
probably pre your time, but I'll tell
you uh a story about the financial
markets, which was certainly relevant
when I was finishing up college.
Uh so, right around that time, there was
um this big financial crisis
in 2008.
And so here, you know, you really have
to be careful when you try and use this
reasoning and when you do and don't have
independence.
So it's not just important,
you know, uh I want to say that it's not
just important to know how to use the
turnoff bound, but I want to claim that
it's just as important
to know when tail bounds don't apply.
So you know uh just a little bit of
personal background. So both my parents
are computer scientists. My whole family
is computer scientists. So I really
didn't want to be a computer scientist.
Uh I really showed them. Um but uh you
know I tried out all kinds of things
when I was at your age. So around that
time I worked in Wall Street. uh you
know and I worked on some quantitative
finance problems and this was pre the
financial crisis but I remember you know
one of the things that they were big
into were very fancy assets so there are
things called collateralized mortgage
obligations
has anyone heard of collateralized
mortgage operation uh uh CMOs no okay so
the way that this works is that uh you
know you have a whole bunch of mortgages
that you sell to people uh you know for
them to buy their
And then implicitly when you're giving
someone a mortgage, you have to assess
their creditworthiness
to figure out the likelihood that
they're going to pay back the loan. Now,
for people have great credit ratings,
maybe that's not such a big risk, but
you know what happens if you're making
riskier mortgages, right? So, those are
things that you can charge more for. You
can have a higher interest rate. uh but
you have to deal with the fact that the
probability that they pay it back might
be less than you would hope. Right?
So you had all of these issues in 2008
that uh there was a huge amount of
construction going on. People were
buying a lot of these houses. Some
people had multiple houses and they had
very poor credit ratings. But you know
the banks didn't want to hold on to
these mortgages because they're risky
products. So how exactly you know what
do you do with these financial products?
So there was this great idea which was
to create synthetic products instead. So
what you do is you take a whole bunch
of, you know, what are called subprime
mortgages
and you bundle them together
because the hope is that all of these,
you know, small probability events of
the person failing and defaulting on
their loan, maybe if you combine them
together, you can appeal to things like
the turnoff bound and say that, you
know, things concentrate more around
their expectation. So you have the issue
that these subprime mortgages still have
a reasonably large failure probability.
So no one would buy them. So what you do
is you create what's called a waterfall
payoff structure. So you do something
called creating tranches. So you have
this baseline of all of these subprime
mortgages and then the first people who
default on their loans. The people who
are going to eat the losses are the
people at the bottom of the waterfall.
That's where the water dries up the
first. And the people, you know, at the
very top of the waterfall, they only get
losses if, you know, basically
everything collapses or a large fraction
of the mortgages collapse. So maybe each
mortgage, you know, has a 10% chance of
defaulting. And in order for this person
at the very top to eat any losses, maybe
40% of the mortgages have to default.
So, you know, if you thought about these
probabilities as being independent, this
would be an extremely safe asset, right?
What's the chance that I take a coin
that has, you know, is heads with 10%
probability and I flip it a thousand
times and I end up with 40% heads? It's
ridiculously small because we just
proved it with the upper tail, right?
So, that allowed people to get credit
rating agencies to say that these are
very safe assets. So when you have a
retirement uh plan and you put money
into your retirement account, there are
certain rules and regulations about what
uh the financial risk and the gradation
for the asset needs to be in order for
these retirement companies to even
purchase the asset because these uh
things that are managing your retirement
shouldn't be purchasing risky accounts.
So all the credit rating agencies rated
these things as if the failure of the
mortgages were independent events. And
that made them say that actually these
are extremely safe assets. Maybe they're
even safer than things like the US
currency.
The trouble is that uh churnoff bounds
don't really apply. So what's the
problem with this? Why don't tail bounds
apply? Yeah.
>> They're not independent.
>> They're not independent. That's right.
You know what causes someone to default
is, you know, a lot of economic strife.
And when that happens on a massive
scale, all of a sudden you have this
domino effect. And these things that
were you know previously viewed to be as
very safe things are not really safe
even though at the time I remember
people were using things like Gaussian
approximations to figure out their
probability of default. So I'll leave
you with that last nugget which is you
know probability is very important for
your lives. You should use the turnoff
bounds and the classes we give you in
problem sets. But in real life, you
should be critical about, you know,
whether or not it applies because the
dependence between these random
variables is a nasty thing. And there
are whole courses you can teach on
dealing with dependent random variables.
But, you know, to be continued. So, see
you next time. And we'll be starting our
modular arithmetic unit on Tuesday.