great thanks Chris really appreciate the
introduction and uh great great to see
uh so many people here um really a
pleasure to tell you about Quantum
Computing let me get right to it because
we've only got about 20 minutes
um want to wish MTL first off a happy
40th and um you know Tomas is doing a
great job also want to recognize Jesus
who helped us get this Center for
Quantum engineering off the ground um
and so I think it's appropriate before
we get into Quantum to think about
classical electronic Computing um the
vacuum tube was invented in 1906
originally used for radio transceivers
um and it was about 40 years before it
saw its way into um a computer called
eniac uh 1946 uh the following year the
transistor was invented and within about
10 years we had a fully transistor-based
computer called tx0 developed here at
MIT uh but it basically had transistors
soldered together
to get closer to our chips today we
needed the integrated circuit in the
late 50s but it wasn't until the 70s
that we saw chips like the Intel 44 uh
4bit processor 2000
transistors um you'd have to go to the
90s to get to a chip that I remember
using maybe some of you do too called
the Pentium Pro with millions of
transistors and then another 25 30 years
to get to where we are today multi-core
processors gpus CPUs xus tpus
um approaching a 100 billion transistors
this this technology is really really
fantastic but it took a hundred years to
get from the fundamental discoveries out
to where we are today and we should keep
that in mind when we think about Quantum
Computing and Quantum Computing um
started in the 1980s it's relatively new
um Richard feeman and others suggested
that if you want to simulate or emulate
a Quantum system you should use another
quantum system to do it because it's
really hard for conventional computers
to do that that was true in the 1980s
and it's still true today and people
thought about you know what does this
actually mean within about 10 years we
had a lot of the theoretical algorithms
uh that underpin Quantum Computing uh
perhaps the most famous is Shores
algorithm for Crypt analysis but also
Quantum analing adiabatic Quantum
Computing Etc that was the mid90s fast
forward to today 30 years later we do
have quantum computers they're just very
small you can access them in the cloud
and um you know use them to test
algorithms at a small scale so what's
the takeaway the takeaway is this
quantum mechanics was developed in the
early 1900s and it laid the foundation
for this development um and this
development is our present National
Security Economic Security information
security Quantum 2.0 now is actually
using quantum mechanics as the switch
and and that's the difference and um
that holds the promise to similarly
impact this Century although it may take
um some time the third thing is you know
related to that advancing from Discovery
to useful machines takes engineering it
takes time this isn't going to happen
overnight just like developing these
fantastic chips we're using today that
didn't happen overnight either um and
maybe a fourth point which I didn't put
here is you got to be in the game to
play the companies that are making these
chips today didn't just jump in 2010
once somebody else figured out how to
make a GPU they were in it for decades
and for Quantum Computing which is also
Hardware hard tech it's the same
story so just a quick differentiator
what's a quantum computer versus a
classical computer well let's start with
classical computers they're based on
bits for example a transistor has a
voltage or it doesn't have a voltage
these are discrete States zero and one
and transistors are almost perfect um if
you set it in state one you'll measure
it in State One set it in state zero
you'll measure it in state zero and
that's it that's the entire world to a
transistor but a quantum computer is
based on a Quantum bit or a coherent
Quantum coherent two-state system and we
think of it as the planet Earth and if
you're at the North Pole you're in a
state zero which is classical and if
you're at the South Pole you're in a
state one which is classical so if
you're if you're a transistor you live
at the North and South Pole and that's
it but if you're a cubit just like
people you can be anywhere on the
surface of the planet Earth and when
you're anywhere other than the North or
South Pole you're in a Quantum
superposition of zero and one North and
South Pole simultaneously now that
sounds weird it is um but that is
quantum mechanics and that's what
quantum mechanics tells us and one
consequence of this is that measurement
becomes probabilistic because we can
only realize classical States so if you
happen to go to the equator and and then
you're measured as a cubit you will
instantly snap to the North Pole or
instantly snap to the South Pole and
which one you go to it's random it's one
of the purest forms of Randomness that
we know of um in our physical world go
to that same point on the equator again
just like flipping a coin 50/50 you'll
end up at the North Pole or the South
Pole so that's strange um it also has
consequences for how we build quantum
computers um they rely on encoding
information in a fundamentally different
way now one consequence of this is is
related to why quantum computers are
powerful and in a nutshell if you let's
go back to classical computers if you
have end transistors or n Bits you
actually can form an exponentially large
number of states two to the nth power
but you can only represent one of them
at a time that's the point and so if
let's say you have three transistors you
have everything from 000000 or 001 all
the way up to all of them being one
there are eight of those and if you for
some reason wanted to process all eight
of of those as inputs you basically have
two choices you can either buy one
computer and feed in those inputs one at
a time 000000 get an output 001 get an
output Etc or you can buy a really large
number of computers and do it in
parallel but either way if you have an
exponentially large number of inputs you
neither need exponential time or
exponential Hardware to do that
task now a quantum computer again let's
have n qits n Quantum bits there are two
to the N classical components but we can
put them all into a single state that's
the difference and so you end up with a
single Quantum State um which represents
all of these classical States
simultaneously and this leads to a
Quantum version of parallelism and
importantly Quantum interference which
I'm not going to talk about today but
that is what underlies the power of a
quantum computer so how do we take
advantage of this Hardware
and the answer is with algorithms and I
show here at the bottom many of my
colleagues here at MIT who are doing
various aspects of the work on Quantum
algorithms and I won't read the whole
chart but let me just say the algorithm
is in this column um the classical time
is in this column and you can see that
the size of the system n tends to be
upstairs in the exponent whereas if you
look at the time on a quantum computer
that n comes downstairs that is an
exponential Improvement and some of the
um algorithm or use cases are of course
simulation of uh chemistries reaction
rates materials Etc um Crypt analysis
sampling solutions to large uh linear
systems of equations that pervades
engineering optimization and
search so what do we need to achieve
commercial Quantum Advantage well first
off there better be no fast known
classical algorithm if there is use one
of those fantastic G pus or tpus or CPUs
because they're awesome they really work
well but let's assume we don't have that
the second thing we need to do is have a
known fast Quantum algorithm there are
lots of problems where we don't know how
to do it on a classical computer and we
don't know how to do it on a quantum
computer so you need of course a fast
Quantum
algorithm and the third thing for
commercial success is it better be a
useful problem we have a number of
examples of quantum algorithms which
demonstrate exponential Advantage but we
don't know how to commercialize it okay
so if we look at this overlap today it's
a rather small region and I you know
every talk I give I encourage people to
go out and develop new Quantum
algorithms for specific use cases this
is very
important and with this there are two
types of quantum advantage and what that
means is that the size of the computer
you need how much time it takes to get a
solution how much energy you'll use um
however you want to think about it it's
proportional to two factors one is a
polom in the size of the system n and
the other is
exponential so one Improvement that
quantum computers can do is they can
improve the preactor that's a polinomial
Improvement for example Grover search
algorithm something that goes as n
becomes square root of n we would say a
quadratic speed up that's good we'll
take it but that pales in comparison to
the exponential speed up here we reduce
um exponential to polinomial meaning n
appeared upstairs but now it appears
downstairs and and this is exponential
and we generally don't um see that in
our daily lives um and let me just give
an example of how fast exponential
growth can be let's imagine you wanted
to simulate a quantum computer on a
classical computer and then you ask how
much classical memory do I need to keep
track of all of those two to the end
coefficients okay so if you have 30
cubits that's 2 to the 30th power you'll
you can do that on a
laptop go to Just 50 cubits and now you
need a top 500 supercomputer in all of
its
memory go to 80 cubits and now somehow
we need to link together all of the
computers in the world and use all of
their memory okay and and now it's a
clearly in fantasy land go to 160 cubits
and now we need to use all of the
Silicon atoms on Earth and each silicon
atom is a memory element and finally
just 10 times higher than where we
started 300 cubits and now we would need
to employ all of the atoms in the known
universe each each one of those atoms
being a memory element okay that's
exponential
growth the challenge of course is to
harness it and use it so there are two
time scales that are related to Quantum
Computing and one of them is the
coherence time so if you have a quantum
computer in a known State and you start
a computation from that point forward
immediately it starts reacting with its
environment of course I'm trying to run
an algorithm but in parallel with that
the environment is conspiring against me
and what that means is that over time
you can think of that Quantum State
blurring and eventually being lost now
the cubits are still there they didn't
disappear but the state that they're in
is unknown to me I tried to get to An
Answer over here but the environment
took my quantum computer somewhere else
the time scale over which that happens
is called the coherence
time the second time we care about is
the gate time how fast can I Implement
my algorithm that's like the clock speed
of your classical computer
and the figure of Merit is how many
gates per coherence time can I Implement
okay with that what we can do is compare
different Technologies against one
another and so this figure of Merit is
on this axis how many gates before an
error on average and that's one to one
in what we would call the gate Fidelity
so one air in 100 that's 99% good or 99%
Fidelity One air in a th
99.9 Etc the horizontal axis is the gat
speed in hertz you can think of that
like your clock speed in your
conventional computer and of course you
want to be in the upper right corner for
best performance and to run a Quantum
algorithm there are two types of gates
that you need that's it one is a single
Cubit gate you apply a gate to one cubit
or a two Cubit gate where you apply an
operation to two cubits together and
with that you can do any arbitrary
Quantum logic and so now you can see
where these different Technologies fall
for example trapped ions and I show some
folks here at it working on trapped ions
um are one of the leaders
today superc conducting cubits is an
area that I work in along with my
colleagues here at MIT and you can see
in some sense they're both equidistant
from this upper right corner which is
part of the reason why we don't have a
clear winter
today neutral atoms have also Advanced
tremendously in the last few years um
here are some folks working on neutal
atoms and then also Envy centers uh
we'll hear from Dirk in just a moment um
and and my own group is also starting
some work on silic and Quantum dots so
there are many candidate Technologies to
realize a quantum computer and which one
will be the winner I don't think we know
and if we look at the last century of
classical electronic Computing there
won't be a winner the technology will
evolve from one technology to the next
to the next okay this is what quantum
computers look like today um here's IB
IBM's Osprey 433 cubits you can see it's
3D integrated this technology was
invented and patented here at uh MIT
here is uh the Sycamore chip from Google
the first uh demonstration of quantum
Advantage this is a neutral atom quantum
computer you can see an optical table in
here uh this looks like a big black box
which it is but inside there would be a
trapped ion quantum computer and this is
a Quantum analer from d-wave now this of
course you'll recognize that's not a
quantum computer that's the uh right
flyer it was the first um well let me
say this it wasn't the first time that
humankind flew we had hot air balloons
we had gliders but this was the first
time where it all came together that a
person's on there steering it it's
self-propelled it got off the ground it
maybe went 100 feet six feet off the
ground that's about it I put this
picture on here because when we saw this
demonstration or at least in hindsight
when we see this demonstration we know
that we knew that that commercial
Aviation would come it might be 20 years
away or 30 years away but this brought
it all together and we know okay this is
going to happen and I think that the
demonstrations that we've seen here from
these quantum computers are at this
stage it's still very early stage but we
do believe that commercial Quantum
computation will come so to realize this
though we need to engineer systems that
are robust reproducible and
extensible so last slide I believe um
one of the grand challenges today is to
do active Quantum error correction so
what is that
well we just saw that the error rates of
our physical cubits are 1 in a th000
maybe 1 in 10,000 that's not enough for
commercial applications at scale for
that we need to be able to run a billion
or even a trillion operations so the
error rates have to be much much better
how do we get there there's a huge gap
um well the way that we get there oh by
the way transistors are almost perfect
uh thankfully we don't have to get this
good but there's a reason that
transistors have done so well because
their error rate is almost one part 10
the
20 so the way that we're going to go
from the yellow physical cubits to
practical applications is basically to
form teams of cubits we call those um
logical cubits Quantum Eric correction
so rather than one cubit we'll encode
the information shown here in nine
yellow cubits and then we have some blue
ones nearby which you can think of as
referees that are just checking where an
error occurred uh what type of error it
is and it tells us so that we can go and
fix it and this is just like forming a
team of people
and the concept is quite similar if you
think of say a kindergarten classroom uh
with say 20 kids in it that's obviously
total chaos and if you add more kids to
that the chaos only increases right so
fortunately along our education at some
point we reach a threshold where
individually we are good enough that we
can work with another person and
together we outperform each individual
and that's the concept for logical uh
cubits is that the cubits if they're
individually good enough putting many of
them together actually makes the
situation better that's where you want
to be and of course there's a cost that
goes along with that you have to have an
HR department now to take care of all
those people but there's an exponential
Improvement in the size of the team
which we call the distance so if you go
from three on a side distance three to
five on a side distance five you get an
exponential Improvement in your error
rate and it's a very powerful
Improvement what I'm showing here on
this axis is the physical Cubit rate
that's the individual and on this is The
Logical error rate that's the team and
you can see this is this is log scale so
even each time I improve my team members
by a factor two Factor two Factor two
you can see that the error rate is
dropping exponentially for different
size uh teams distance three distance 5
Etc all the way up to distance 25 and
already we're at 10 Theus 6 here so
getting down here it will happen okay I
just want to mention quickly that Google
very recently put a paper out this
summer um where they actually
demonstrated and we'll try to explain
this whole chart but let me just say
that they've demonstrated a logical
Cubit that outperformed any of the
individual physical cubits on the team
the team outperformed any individual and
that was a real milestone for the field
um that they went from distance 3 to
seven there have been several other
demonstrations with other Technologies
but this was the first one that showed
Beyond threshold old um demonstrations
so truly last slide so today's reality
with quantum computers um first off
they're not going to replace classical
computers for two reasons one we need a
classical computer to do the error
correction and second quantum computers
don't solve all problems and so there's
still going to be an important need for
classical computers going forward I
already said this um but I'll say it
again we need more Quantum algorithms
and we need to apply them to specific
use cases of interest to Industry
um didn't talk too much about encryption
or um Crypt analysis but Shores
algorithm does compromise the RSA crypto
system um we don't have a quantum
computer large enough to do that today
and it will likely be 10 or 20 years
before we do but nonetheless we need to
switch over to new crypto systems they
call them postquantum crypto systems and
we need to do that right now because
there's information that we are
encrypting now that's being stored on
hard drive somewhere that will become
susceptible to attack in the future and
we want to retain security over that um
and then likely we'll need Quantum error
correction to go forward and so um with
that here are some takeaways uh Quantum
2.0 is going to in fact impact our
future information and economic security
uh we do need a Quantum aware Workforce
and uh we're working hard here at MIT to
do that we do have some professional
development courses if you're if you're
interested in that um and and the last
one is that we need to judiciously
protect our nation's IP you know there's
been some recent developments in export
control regulations around Quantum
Computing that's very important because
we need to protect this but at the same
time we don't want to break the
Fantastic Innovation engine that we have
at our us universities so we got to get
that right I don't have the answers
necessarily but but we should keep that
as a topic of discussion so so that we
can both Advanced Quantum Computing uh
and also uh do it quickly um and here's
my email address be happy to to uh
correspond and thank you for your
attention
[Applause]