I feel like social media has led to very
many terrible outcomes in our society.
And I often think 25 years ago, if we
knew what we know now, what would we
have done differently with social media?
What could we have done differently? I
don't really know the answer, but I feel
like that's a conversation we should be
having now about AI. We shouldn't get
behind. We know bad things are going to
come out of AI. We know good things that
come out of AI, just like bad and good
things that come with social media. We
need to be getting ahead of the bad
things in [music] a way we didn't with
social media.
>> So, it's up to us how AI can affect the
economy and how it's going to affect
life. It's up to whether we establish
the proper regulatory frameworks and the
proper way of thinking about it so that
we can deal with the negative effects
while capturing the positive effects.
Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.