Okay. So
um so right so we're going to prove the
picard lindel theorem and it may we'll
see it may take us
it may um we may need to continue on it
also on Tuesday and then when we're done
with it we will just do review on
Tuesday but let's see how far we get so
the picinder theorem
is the following theorem
and it say that uh it's it's a it's a OD
so it's a what's called ordinary
differential equation Okay.
And so again a differential equation is
something about an unknown function and
its derivative. Right? So differential
equation just mean it's an equation. So
this here means that it's an equation
in an unknown function
uh and its derivative.
ordinary just as we talked about last
time ordinary refer to uh that is just
of one variable. Okay. And so the OD
that the picard line theorem is about is
so the unknown function is y. And the od
is is this that we want the derivative
of this unknown function to be equal to
a function of the unknown function plus
another function that just depend on x.
So y here is the unknown function and y
is a function of x right x is x is a
real number
right and and it's just a yeah so this
is the differential equation and then we
have some initial condition so at zero
we want it to take a value a okay so
this is the differential equation and
what we assume Assume here is so f and g
are function on r
and you should think about those as
being known
and uh they are an f here is
differentiable
and the derivative
is continuous.
and G is just continuous
doesn't need to be differentiable
and the pal Lindel theorem is so the
again the pard Theorem
is the following
that given
uh given f
uh g as above
and sorry n a was this constant. It's
just a real number as above.
There exist
uh delta greater than zero.
Um um such that and and and a solution
why
defined on
the integral from minus delta to delta
and and solution y to uh the OD
right and so again meaning that is uh
that is solution that means that at the
in at zero it takes value a and then is
satisfying that equation okay
and Moreover,
and I'll get back to that, but we won't,
you know, that's it's quite possible. I
won't get to that uh today. Moreover,
uh um solutions are unique.
Okay. And so, so right. So this is like
a standard problem in when you're
looking at differential equations. You
have a differential equation that may
describe something in nature and you
wonder does this uh equation have a
solution
and uh and if it has a solution or
solutions unique. Okay. So this is what
this answer in this case
and the interesting thing or part of the
interesting thing I mean so this is a
fundamental question u used all over
science and engineering and one of the
interesting things is that it's uses the
proof of this uses metric spaces and so
the proof is has been used you know
various version of the proof have been
used to prove existence
uh and uniqueness of various
differential equations.
So the pro the proof
uses
the theory of metric spaces
which is sort of surprising because it
seems to have nothing to do with metric
spaces.
And so it uses in particular the metric
space that it's using is
uh the continuous functions on some
interval here
right and on the space of continuous
function we have the metric that we
talked about the metric so if f and g
sorry f is so bad uh because it's the
and g also let's call it h1 H1 and H2.
Suppose that these are continuous
functions. H1 and H2
are continuous functions
on an interval
like this.
Then the distance is this that we have
considered various times. This is just a
maximum
uh over uh x in this interval here
of uh f of x of h1 sorry h1 of x minus
h2 of x and then the absolute value of
that right.
So this is the distance on the space of
continuous functions that we have looked
at a lot.
Okay. And it's actually not quite this
space as I mentioned last time. It's a
ball in this space that is using
right okay
so what do we need about this metric
space? So one thing we've proven
couple of lectures ago is that uh that
this this space here of continuous
functions
uh with this metric here
uh is cushy complete.
So we're going to use that. Okay,
another thing we're going to use is this
notion of contracting map. So, um
another tool
will
be that
of a contracting map.
And so but and remember
this is a number of lectures ago we
talked about a contracting map but we
need a more general notion of
contracting map because when we talked
about it we talked about a map from R
into R. Uh and then we use this notion
of contracting map to u uh in to finding
zeros with using Newton's method. Okay.
And but here we're going to use it for
something different and so we need a
more general notion. So suppose that so
uh contracting map.
So this is the general version
as opposed to uh the version that we
talked about already that was for for
the line for for R. So contracting map
sorry.
And so this is so you have a metric
space XD. This is you know could be like
this but it also just could be any
metric space.
And then you have a map from this metric
space
into the self.
And T here is set to be T is set to be
contracting.
uh if there exist
uh a constant C less than one such that
if you're looking at the distance
between the images
then they are squeezed together. So this
distance here between the images under
the map is less or equal to
this constant that is less than one
times the distance before you apply the
map. Right? So this means that under the
map sinks get closer together. Right?
So that's a contracting map.
And so now we proved a theorem when we
did the new measuring we proved a
theorem but we needed a about fix points
and we need a generalized version of
that. So um so if you take a map just in
general
from a space to a space then a fixed
point
a fixed point
is uh a point
x in the space
so that t of x
so t leaves X invariance. So T of X is
equal to X. That's a fixed point, right?
Okay. And so now if you have a
contracting map, so if
if T here is contracting,
then
T can have at most one fix point.
Why? Because suppose that X so if
if X and Y are both fixed points.
Well, then you have that g of x
is equal to g of y. Sorry, g of x is
equal to tox and t of y is equal to one.
Right?
And so now you have that the distance
between t of x
uh let me make make a little more space.
Then you have that the actually we just
continue down here. So that the distance
between t of x
comma t of y
the map is contracting. So this is less
or equal to this constant times
this here. On the other hand they're
both fixed points. So t of x is x. This
here is x and this here is y. So if we
write this out so this is x comma y. And
so you see that this thing here is some
constant less than one strictly less
than one times itself. So this means of
course that this number here this non-
negative number must be zero. And so
this of course implies by the
actions of a metric space that X is
equal to Y. Right? So a contracting map
has at most one fixed point.
Now the other thing is that if you take
a metric space
um if you take a metric space
right so this here is cushy complete so
now I'm going to take a cushy complete
metric space so it could be continuous
function on some closed interval and
that's how we will apply it but it works
more generally
So we have a fin.
So if
if this here is a complete cushy
complete
metric space
uh and t
from x into x
is Yeah. Uh contracting map
then
t
has a unique fixed bot. We know it only
have it have at most one. So the
statement really is that that it has one
right? has a unique fix point.
Okay. So,
so let's try to prove this.
And you might remember and if you don't
that's fine but you might remember how
we used it in the new methods because
the new methods was like it was a
version of this on a
So you had a map from R to R and to find
the fixed point and so you wondered what
you were there and you knew the message
was something about finding a point
where a function vanishes, right? And
that was set up as a fixed point
theorem. And so what you did is you made
a good choice. I mean a choice that look
reasonable, right? This is not exactly
where the function vanishes, but
something that looks close to where it
vanish. And then you iterate, you took
the image under the map and you iterated
this. And so it's the same we're going
to do here. So, and this time we we we
don't even need to make a good choice.
So, we just take um we just take let
x here be any point in the metric space.
So, you're just fixing some point in the
metric space.
And now you're looking at so you're
looking at the sequence x t of x
and then you apply t to t of x. So this
is I write this as this. Then you apply
t to t squared of x. So that's right
like this. And so you keep applying t
more and more times.
Right? And so this gives you a sequence
and so on. So this gives you a sequence.
Okay? And now the claim is that this
sequence here. So claim
that this sequence here
converge
to right. So it converge and the limit
here this here
is a fixed point
for G. So that's a claim. Okay.
[Applause]
Now,
so we wanted to prove first that is
converging.
Okay. So we're going to prove first. So
we first show
that TN
is a cushy sequence.
Okay. So now let's look at um so we're
supposed to look if you're looking at a
if you try to prove that something is a
cruise sequence then you're looking at
the distance between
elements in the sequence
where both of these elements is
sufficiently far right that's what
you're supposed to look at
and so let me write the m here so I can
sing about one of them as being further
out than the other one. So I'm going to
think about m here as being n plus some
number k, right? Some integer k, right?
And so I'm interested in estimating the
distance between tn of x
and t n + k
of x.
Okay.
Now
in order to do that let me start with
something
simpler first.
Let me look at the distance
between T of X
uh let me look at the distance between T
um
L of X
and T L + one of X.
Okay. So two consecutive elements in the
sequence. Okay. Now I can sing it. So
this thing here well this is equal to
the distance between t of t
uh l -1
of x
and then uh t of g l of of x like that.
Right?
I can write it like that. Right? I just
But now of course, so you see here
there's some elements in X in the spa
space X. Here's another element.
They both have T applied to it. T is
contracting. So you get C
T L minus one X
uh TL
of X.
So you see that if you take two
consecutive elements and you're taking
the distance then it's bounded by
this constant C times right where you
have one less uh where you have have
have applied t one less time on both
right these are again consecutive
elements but but the highest one is one
less right
okay so now if you iterate this
uh okay so iterating this so let's see
maybe maybe okay maybe let me wait with
iterating let me just look at at what we
need so we have this in here
and this here I can write as as um so
here you see here I can write this as t
the distance t and then t n minus one
x
and then t
t n -1 + k
x like this right and so here I can
use the same trick that it get c and
then d t n minus 1 x comma t n -1 + k
of x right
and this one here I can keep going like
this right I can keep going until
there is the I' I've used up all my ends
right and so I can keep going and so
this is lesser equal to c to the n and
then the last one I get is I get x
and then I get t k
of x
right
I want to show that this thing here
becomes small as long as n remember k is
a positive integer as long as n is
sufficiently large right so I need but
this. So this is a hopeful sign because
when n get large this here get really
really small right but I still need to
estimate this here right now. So how do
I estimate it? I using what I did over
here.
So I um so you're looking at
so you have the distance
between x and t k of x
This thing here I can use this triangle
inequality. So I can say that this is
less than dx
t of x
plus d t of x
g ^2 of x
plus
d t of x,
you know, like cube of x. and then all
the way up to
d
t k minus one of x
t k of x right so this is just a
triangle inequality right
now this may seems ra rather bad
estimate but let's see how bad it is so
uh right so now this first thing here
I'm just leaving it I can't do anything
about that so
I need to just take that this one here.
So I'm using this with between two
consecutive. So in this case it's just
bounded by C * D X
right and the next one here
this one here is bounded by C ^ 2 D X GX
and then and the next right and so on up
to this one here
is bounded by uh C K - one
uh D X T X
right and so you see that now this here
factor out so this here is so this
factor out
and then in this bracket you get 1 + C +
C^ 2 plus all the way up to C K minus
But this is a geometric series right
this is a geometric series and this is
certainly less than when I take remember
C is strictly less than one so it's a
geometric series it's a convergent
geometric series so this here is less
than d xt of x and then this sum well
it's less than when you're summing it
all the way to infinity so this is less
than one. This is the sum of the
geometric series. C is strictly less
than one,
right? C is positive and is strictly
less than one.
Okay? So you see now that we have
right so we have that so what we were
interested in is we were interested in
saying that as long as I choose little
and sufficiently large then this thing
here must be very small. Right?
And we know already that it's bounded
like this. And now I fill in this and
you see this here. So this means that
this is less than cn. And then what you
get here is uh 1 minus c and then times
d x g of x,
right? x is fixed.
And so you see that when n little n is
sufficiently large then this whole thing
here is as small as you want. Right? So
this means that what we have proven here
is that this sequence here
is a cushy sequence.
So we've proven that. Okay.
Now of course this is where the
assumption comes in that this metric
space is cushy complete
right. So, so uh since
x this metric space is cushy complete
and this sequence here
is a cushy sequence.
It is convergent,
>> right? Yeah.
>> I'm sorry.
>> Yep.
>> Are you able to explain again how we got
that
for the DXDX or we're just saying that
>> right? So I'm saying that X is fixed.
You you pick any point you want. And I
claim that if I you know it may be a
very bad candidate for the fixed point,
but it doesn't matter. It's okay. Uh it
may just take you longer to get to the
fixed point, but you fix X and then
you're looking at this sequence
and then I claim that this sequence will
be a cushy sequence, right? And so x is
fixed. And so we have this inequality
here. And what we need is that when
little n is sufficiently far, you know,
large, then for all k is positive
integer, right? This here is like
further out than n. Then for all k and
it should be independent on k. This
thing here is small. But this is
>> get rid of the whole thing from the
previous step was now not a TK of X,
right? So,
>> so so so since X is fixed,
X is fixed, TX is fixed.
>> So, this is just a constant.
>> Yeah.
Okay. So um right so what we have proven
is that so we have so we have this koshi
complete metric space and we have this
sequence x was fixed again that is a
cush sequence and so since this metric
space is cush complete this is
convergent and I can denote the limits
so I just call the limits x infinity
right so if you have is
now I want to show that uh that uh so so
the next claim is
is that x infinity is a fixed point
for for g
okay okay
so if I'm looking at this sequence here.
Suppose I take this sequence and suppose
I take T of this sequence.
So if I take T of this sequence, this
here is nothing but the next element in
the sequence.
So this one here will still converge to
X infinit,
right? Because it's just shifted by one.
But then on the other hand, so now if
you're looking at
um at so so you have that if you're
looking at t so you want to we want to
prove that um
right so now uh so now if we're looking
at t of x infinity
the distance between t of x infinity
and
uh and t
uh n + one
of x suppose I'm looking at this
distance here right well this here I can
think about as the distance between t of
x infinity and t of tn of x
but here there are now both of these
element you can about this is just some
element applied t to it. Here there's t
applied to that. So this is less than
the distance
x infinity to t n. There's a constant c
less than one in front.
So like this
right by the contracting map property.
But now you see that as n go to infinity
this thing here goes to zero. Right? So
this means that this thing here
converts to this point.
Right? So you have that.
So you have that
you have that that if you're looking at
uh if you're looking at um right again
as
as n go to
as n go to infinity
uh Since
since tn of x converts to x infinity
then we have that the distance this is
equivalent to that the distance
here
goes to zero. And then by this
inequality it means that the distance
here
tx infinity
and t n + one of x goes to zero right
and so this means that this is just some
fixed point. It means that this sequence
here, so this implies that this sequence
here
converge to t of x infinity, right? But
on the other hand, we already observe
that this sequence also converge
to x infinity, right? But you can't can
you know there's the so it converges to
this and it converts to that, but it can
only have one limit. So those two things
are equal. So you conclude that x
infinity is equal to g of x infinity and
so x infinity
is a fixed point.
Right? So this proved this theorem. And
again we already knew that the limit was
uh was unique. Right?
Okay. So now what how is this related to
the picar linda lift theorem
and so it's related in the following way
and again this is uh something that have
been used to solve a lot of differential
equations
um
and so we need to define space and a
map.
the spaces initially but we have to
restrict it but initially let's think
about some continuous functions
on some interval
let's start with just continuous
function but it's not quite going to be
this space I will have to look at a
smaller yeah
Right. That's a good question. So, so
that's right. So, this comes with this
Newton method. So, we used the so we
used this contracting mapping for R in
the Newton method to find a zero. Okay.
And to some I mean that was a great
idea. Uh Newton was a pretty famous guy
for a good reason. uh but in a way this
is more ingenious I think because it's
like you know metric space what the hell
does this have to do with differential
equation right but and the reason why in
the other one we had to restrict it was
that the map we defined wasn't
contracting everywhere it needed sinks
to be pretty close initially for for
there to exist a c strictly less than
one right so that's where I came in it
wasn't really it wasn't really because
in in N or if Yeah.
Okay.
So now again so so we need to relate
this that seems to have nothing to do
with differential equation. We need to
relate it to the differential equation.
So again what is the space the metric
space that we're going to look at and
again it's not exactly this but it's
just a subset of it. So, so, so, so it's
it's this space and with the usual
metric that we have talked about, right?
That is going to be the
the metric space.
Now, what is the map T?
And so the map t is so t here
um so t here is going to be a map from
continuous functions
uh into the space of continuous
functions
and it's going to be defined
um as follow
and if yeah I'll come to this in a
second so uh t of x t of y. So y think
about y as being a continuous function
on this integral, right? And t of y is
now equal to uh a plus and then the
integral in and then right
then the inte uh integral. So this is a
so t of y is of an element here. This
one here is also supposed to be an
element here. So this is a function.
So we want to find out what the value is
at x. And it's a this constant a plus
the integral from zero to x
uh and then of f of uh y
uh plus uh g of x
and this here is a function of x right
also it's like this
uh and I shouldn't write x because I use
now x up here
so I write it like DF
okay that's how the map is going to be
defined
so again if you take so y here so y is
going so y is a continuous function on
this interval
and I will have to restrict it and this
is exactly when you asking what you know
in Newton methods right why why did we
have to pick this good choice it's
exactly like this that it's this map is
not contracting on this whole space.
Okay. So we have to in a way we have to
do the same stuff. We have to make a
good choice first and so that's why we
have to restrict the space. Okay. And it
actually is I mean it's part of the
beauty is that it's pretty much optimal
this stuff this sort of general
principle uh we can come back to that.
So this is the map t.
And so the first thing that you observe
is
that t. So this gives you a this
function here.
Right? Remember that. So if y is
continuous,
g is continuous. If y is continuous, f
is continuous. Everything here is
continuous. And so this means that by
the fundamental theorem of calculus this
function here is actually even
differentiable right and the derivative
this is just a constant so this function
here is differentiable
let alone continuous so it's definitely
in the space and the derivative of this
map
by the fundamental theorem of calculus
This
uh
so by the fundamental of calculus the
derivative is just what is inside here.
So this is just f of y
plus g of x right and if you want to
write x in then it should be like this
right
so that's so and then one more thing you
observe which is also immediate that if
you take
a continuous function like this and now
you evaluate this now you evaluate this
at zero right if x is zero but then this
integral it's over just a point so this
here is zero so this means that the
value here is a
right okay
and so now the next thing you observe is
that
So the next thing we observe is that um
that if uh if you have a fixed point so
if
I mean I think this is another nice
thing is that you know that the way it's
set up is that you just need to use
continuous functions.
Right. But of course, if you want a
solution to this, it means that the
function must have a derivative. Yeah.
Yeah. We don't know that yet. I mean,
that's a major point actually, right?
And again, just like in the Newton
methods, we have to restrict where we're
looking at it. Yeah. Okay. So but but
the first thing I want to observe is
that
if uh if y is a fixed point
well then t of y
is equal to y and so what does this
mean?
Well, the derivative. So it means that
if this is the case,
right?
Then we have that t of y is of this
form. So it has a derivative and that
derivative is this. Right? So this means
that y would have it because y is equal
to this. So y is differentiable
and the derivative is equal to this.
And we always have whether it's a fixed
point or not. We always have that t y of
zero
is is a and since it is a fixed point
this is also this. So you see that if it
is a fixed point then it is a solution
to the differential equation. Okay.
Now then then the the the point comes in
the key point comes in with um
proving that the map is contracting.
Okay.
And so so now so we need to prove
need to show
that t
is a contracting map.
Okay.
So
I define so set I I I I have to define a
number of things because again I have to
it's not t is not going to be
contracting on the space of continuous
function. So I have to look at some
subset of continuous function and the
right subset is just a ball. It's a
closed ball. So it's so
it's going to be so so
we're going to maybe I'll just say first
that we're going to restrict
uh t. So t here will be restricted now
to we will think about it as a map on
some ball
into itself.
But it's not at all clear that this map
takes a ball into itself. Okay. And what
do I mean by ball? So I have this bar up
here. So I just means that this thing
here
is going to be the function y that is
continuous. Sorry continuous.
And then it's not quite going to be this
either. I have to restrict but I'll get
to this in a second. So at the moment
you can think about it as being
continuous function on the interval so
that the norm of y at each point x
is less or equal to r
and this bar here refer to that lesser
that equal is also allowed. Right? Now
this here is really like the board right
these are are functions if you're
thinking about the function in the space
of continuous function that is constant
zero right then these are the functions
whose distance this is the same as the
space of continuous functions
whose distance to the constant function
zero is at most uh
this is the zero function is less or
equal to sorry this is getting a little
small over here
right so it's just
okay and again it's not it's going to be
I will have to restrict the interval
here to make to make sure that the map
is contracted
so but first I want to define and this
radius here. Okay. And so the radius is
so I'm setting r here equal a was just a
constant. I take the absolute value of a
and I add two to it.
Then I define two other yeah and there's
no way around it. Uh you have to define
we will require to define several
constants. First
L1 capital L1 is going to be another
constant. It's going to be the maximum
and then you take uh then you take of
over set where set here is less than R
and then you take the value
like this.
Okay, remember f is continuous.
So if I looking at where the norm of x
is less or equal to some constant
then this the maximum is achieved on
this. So this a
just some real number positive real non-
negative non- negative real number
and then I define L2 to be the maximum
of
where I of maximum on the unit ball here
and where norm of X is less than one of
G of X
like there.
Okay.
And now
what I want to do is
so the first step is so the first step
is the following.
So first first step
And the proof
uh is to prove the following that there
exist
there exist
uh uh uh delta zero. This is not the
delta that I will use eventually. Um I
would have to restrict it further. There
exist delta serum. So that if you're
looking at the space if y here
is in the space of continuous functions
on this interval here
then t of y sorry if y is in this here
and y is in the unit form
and not in the uniform that y here is
lesser equal to r
right so it's a continuous function on
this interval and the norm is lesser
equal to r so this means that so this is
of course the same as saying that y is
in this ball here
uh when I'm now thinking about this as a
space but you can forget about that if
you want it's the
Okay. But I and I want to show that t of
y is in the same space, right? So I need
so t of y.
So I need so I want to show so want to
show
want to show
that t of y
at each x
here the norm is lesser equal to one
right then it if I have that I already
know that this function t of y is
continuous it's it's actually even
differentiable right But it's in
particular continuous.
And if I have this then I know that this
space is taking into itself. Right?
Okay.
So now how do I do that?
So I I that's where I need to restrict
the interval that I'm looking on and and
again we'll come back to it but there's
a good reason to rest that we have to
restrict otherwise it couldn't be
possibly be true.
>> Yeah. to be contracting. Do we need it
strictly less than?
>> So remember contracting means that there
exist a constant C strictly less than
one. This here had nothing to do with a
constant C. This here is just the space
that we're looking at the map on. Okay.
So, so, so and the reason why I make
here. So, again, so this have nothing to
do with that C. But the reason why I
want this lesser equal to is that I want
to have that the space is C complete.
Okay, sorry. So, let me just try to make
that clear. So I take I have a to get a
fix point for a contracting map you need
a space that is cushy complete right
that when we prove this for the metric
space we have a good candidate right we
have the candidate of continuous
functions
on some closed interval like this right
this is cushy complete right with a
usual metric but I'm not going to look
at that space because my map is not
actually contracting on the case it's
contracting on a subset right and so I
need that subset so so so in the end I
sort of you know I'm not working on this
but I'm working on a subset right and I
need that subset to be complete so
basically what I have is that this here
is the metric giant metric space I start
with then I'm looking at a ball in this
and if I take the closed ball
and and it happened to be at the origin
but it could be just at any point right
if you take a metric space and you're
taking something like this if the metric
space is cushy complete then this subset
is also cushy complete and but this
require
I have less or equal to right because
else it could kind of converge to
something where where you got equality
right so so that was why I I do it like
Okay. So um so let's see. So
we are trying we we defined we have
already defined this radius capital R
and then we have these two constant
uh L1 and L2 and what I need to prove is
the first step here is to prove that if
I'm going to look again so the first
step is that I need to restrict so I
need to restrict so I'm going to look at
are subs these spaces of
this is a subset of the continuous
functions and I need to prove that if y
is in here then the image is in the same
space.
Okay. And so this is the statement that
if y is continuous
the norm of this function is less or
equal to r. So at each point each x the
absolute value of y of x is less or
equal to r. Then you have the same for
the image under t. We already know again
that the image under t of y is
continuous. Okay.
Okay.
And so but I and what I can do is I can
restrict my interval.
So
I will restrict the interval as follows.
So I'm going to pick delta zero to be
the minimum
of one
uh one over
L + one. L is non- negative. In
principle it could be zero. I don't want
to worry about that. So I just add one.
And L2 could also be zero. Although it's
pretty unlikely that any of them are
zero. But I'm just to be safe. if I'm
just adding so I don't divide by zero.
So that's why and the so and and the
first thing is that I'm so and then I'm
going to look at the interval from this
and this is not going to be my final I
will have to do some further restriction
but I'm going to look at this interval
initially okay and the one here just
comes in that I want this here to be a
sub subset of this unit interval
Okay.
So now let's let's try. So now we are in
good shape here.
So now let's look at t
y
and we need to estimate this at each x.
Right? We want to say
that the norm is less than capital less
or equal to capital R. But let's just
look at what this is. This thing here is
equal to this function t of y is defined
to be a plus the integral from zero to x
of uh f of y of s
plus g
of s
ds and then I have to have absolute
value like that.
And now I can just use the triangle
inequality of course sort of trially. I
get absolute value of this and then plus
and then the integral here
uh like that.
Oops.
And then I can just take this absolute
value in under. So I get less or equal
to a plus and then the integral
and then the absolute value of f of y of
s.
And here I can also take the absolute
value
using the triangle equals on each
individually.
So I can write it like this.
Now
this is where I use. So s here will have
to lie between zero and x right
and so x is between
let me write just draw it here. So here
I have zero
here I have delta zero and then I have
this is zero and here I have x.
somewhere X, right?
But since, right? So this means that
that um this means that so here you have
X but but right but X itself X
has to lie X has to lie between
delta 0
minus delta 0 and delta 0 and S has to
lie between zero and X. So this means
that s here lies between like x will lie
in this interval
also
right
but now you see that um
so now if we're looking at so we have t
of y in x again remember that x here
is less than or equal to delta z. So we
have that this thing here is less or
equal to a plus and then the integral
from 0 to x of f of y of s
plus
g of s
ds. Right? And and the first thing I
observe is that s here is is also just
because x was in that interval, you also
have that s because x is in that
interval,
s is also in this interval. The second
thing I observe is that I'm assuming
that the function that I start with at
each point
have no less than R.
Now if I using these two things then I
have that. So this means that g of s
this one here this is how we define l2
right because this interval here is
contained in the interval between minus1
and one this here is contained in the
interval between minus1 and one right so
we have that g of s
is less than this l2 lesser equal to L2.
Right?
The second thing we observe is that
because we have
this here for each S we have this
then it means you see by the first
by the f by the definition of L1 that uh
f of y of less
this thing here is less than L1.
Okay, L1 and L2 are are now fixed
numbers, right? And so you see that this
second thing here I can bound this thing
here by so this is lesser equal to a uh
and that should have been an absolute
value somehow lost it when I copied from
this line.
um a absolute value of a and then on the
first one here the length of this
interval
but that is of course bounded by delta
zero right so this is plus delta 0 and
then the maximal possible value of this
that would be l1
and then likewise the length of this
interval you're integrating over is at
most delta zero and this one here cannot
be larger than L2. So you have this
right
and now remember what delta zero was and
I will just I have it I think on the
both on board below here but let me just
write it here. This here was what delta
0 was chosen to be the minimum
1 / l1 + 1
uh 1 / l2 + 1.
Okay.
So now,
so now we have that this thing here is
less than this here. We just keep
this thing here.
Well, delta
is in particular less than this thing
here.
So you see that if you put plug in this
so it's like plus 1 L1 + 1 * L1.
Likewise over here you're using this. So
you're getting 1 / L2 + 1 L2. And now
you see that this thing here is less
than one. This is less than one. So this
is less than a. It's actually strictly
less but it doesn't really matter. a +
uh plus uh 2 like this. Okay.
So this means that so then but this here
this here was exactly the definition of
capital R right and so you have that and
when I copied it over I also forgot to
put absolute on here right so you have
that the if so you have that if so the
conclusion here is that if y here is a
continuous function
on this interval here
and the norm of y at each point is less
or equal to r. Well, then you have that
t of y
at each point is lesser now lesser. It's
actually strictly less, but we don't
care about that.
Okay. So, so,
so what you have now is,
so what we now have proven is that we
have this map t
and now I'm going to sing about this map
sorry on the space of
of y that is continuous
on this interval here.
Um and what you have is and also sorry
and I'm thinking about with the norm at
each point this here is less than r and
again you can this is really a ball in
this metric space but let me just write
it out like this
and what you have is that sorry this is
the space and you have that t of y
if y is in this space then t of y is in
the same space. So t of y is also
continuous
on that interval
and t of y at each point x is less or
equal to one. So the map map this space
into itself. Okay.
Now
the next thing we will we want to prove
is that the map is contracting.
Okay.
Right? You see that you need you know if
this space is not stable right so
imagine that you take so you we're
starting with some giant metric space
this is the continuous function say on
this interval
this
and then we're looking at some subspace
of that. So these are continuous on a
smaller interval. Okay. But this
but if the and then we have defined a
map
but if the you know if if if somehow the
map was taking us out of the space where
it's contracting then we couldn't keep
applying the contracting map right it
wouldn't anymore be you know by and and
the thing is that you want to just
iterate. You want to keep you want to
pick some point and then you want to
keep applying the contracting map. So
you want it to stay in the space where
it is contracting, right? And so this is
what we did in one, but we haven't yet
proved that the map is contracting. And
so now to prove that the map is
contracting, we're going to further
restrict the interval. Okay? And so this
is so I'm going to set I'm going to
define now one more constant. Sorry
about that. So this is m here and m is
going to be just the max
of fprime
uh of uh fprime of set absolute value of
this where set here is lesser equals
one.
Fine. So this is my uh this is my um
the the well almost the second last
constant unfortunately
and now I'm going to define this. So the
last constant is going to be the
integral that I'm going to work with.
Right? So remember what I'm trying to do
is
I have this differential equation and I
want to say that
near zero there is a solution but near
zero just mean that there exists some
tiny interval around zero where I have a
solution and again if I have time or
else I will do it next time I will give
an example where you can see that in
general you would need to look at a very
tiny interval for this to have a
solution otherwise it doesn't have a
solution on a very large set.
Okay. So I define it like this and then
I define delta here. So delta is now
going to be the minimum
of delta zero the one from before and
then 1 over 2 m + one.
And now I want to look at the space.
So I want to look at t.
And then t is going to be a map from the
continuous functions. So y here is a
continuous function on now this little
interval. So this interval here because
it's you have the minimum of this. This
is interval is contained in the
corresponding interval with the delta to
zero. So it's y in this space such that
the norm here at each point is lesser
equal to r. That's a space I'm going to
look at. And we already know that t maps
this space into itself, right? Because
there's really no new statement if the
function is is right. So as long as you
have this here and you apply t on it, t
when you apply t on a function it's
defined on the same interval. So it will
automatically defined on this smaller
interval and and we already have this
property. Okay. So so t maps this space
here into itself. Okay.
And now I want to prove I want to
estimate. So I take two elements in this
space.
So I have y1 and y2. So you're looking
at so y1
and y2 are in this space.
And you want to look at what is the
distance
between y1
and y2.
Right? So we want this here and we want
what I want to prove is
that it's contracting.
So I want to show
and I want to prove I'm going to prove
it.
You know my constant C will be explicit.
It would be just a half. So that
certainly is less than one.
And this is what I want.
Okay.
So now
um
So now let's look at then.
So t of y1
minus t of y2.
this thing here y t of y1 is defined to
be a plus the integral sorry and let me
write so I'm going to let me just make a
little more space here I worried I'm
running out of time but let's see so
this thing here minus t of y2 and I'm
just looking at the difference in some x
and again x here is now in x here will
be in the interval
um you were looking at x in the interval
in this interval
and so I'm just writing down first here
what this is this is the integral of
from a to x of f of y1
uh s
plus
g of s
Um and then you have minus
this is what you get for a2 for y2 a. So
minus this thing here.
So this is the difference right.
And what you see is the first thing you
observe is that this a here cancels
right but it not only does this cancel
but this term here also cancel okay and
that actually there's a good reason that
there are lower order and and the point
here is that right the the the the main
point is in the unknown function anyway
right and it's it's a what's called a
nonlinear equation
um So that's a difficulty.
So but what you then get when you write
when you have when you have after the
cancellation what you get is f of y1
of s
minus f of y2 of s
ds. Okay. So you have that.
Now I will now I will
look at this thing here and that thing
here and I'm going to and you have to
now abstract. So, so now I'm going to
look at this difference here. And then
now the thing is that you have to kind
of abstract from it and you have to
think about S as being
if you think about S as being fixed,
right? Then this is just two numbers,
right? You could think about this as set
one
and this here as set two, right? This is
set one and this here is set two. So
it's like f of set one minus f of set
two. Right? Now the mean value theorem
tells us that this thing here is equal
to the derivative at some intermediate
point. Say let's say set three where set
three is between
is between
set one and set two,
right? And then times set one minus set
two,
right?
And but you okay? So this is so this is
just for you just for any xs you have
this. Okay, but this means that
this means now we almost out of time. Uh
so this means that the when you're
looking at the norm of this
f of y1 of s minus f of y 2 of s
right that the norm here is so the norm
is equal to fprime at set three
times set one which is and set one I can
write Again it's really this and this is
set two.
This thing here remember set is some
point in between those two points right?
But both of these points both of these
points here both this one here and that
one here have norm less than r.
Right?
So this here is so but now where the way
that m was defined
uh and it should have been on the same
board.
So m here was defined to be the maximum
of fprime of set
where set was less or equal to one.
And so you see that this thing here
where you take the derivative that is
bounded by m right. So this thing here
is less than m y1 s minus y2
of s like that. Okay I so I'm not sure
where we should stop. I mean we're over
and I probably need a few more minutes.
Maybe we should stop and it's not a
great place to stop, but uh but that's
how it goes. Uh so I will uh keep you in
suspension
uh and um and so we'll pick up uh from
here on on Tuesday. And so I I want
anyway to explain to you why actually
this method which seems a little crazy
in a way because it's bringing in all
these things why it turned out to be
basically optimal.
Okay. And then we'll do a review the
rest of the time on on Tuesday.