I'm Ed Chung. Um I'm COO and co-founder
of Black Mesa. Um I have bachelors in
the course 7 and 10C from back in 99. My
co-founder um is HST alum uh from the
church lab. So we are trying to provide
process process assurance and bio
manufacturing. So if you know the
biommanufacturing industry, you know
that so much other industry there's a
lot of push towards automation and
computerization. This is great. Um the
issue is that there's still just a
minority of manufacturers out there who
have completely electronic systems.
Probably the vast majority still on
either hybrid electronic and paper
systems or completely paperbased systems
where all manufacturing records are
produced and documented on paper. And so
what we're trying to do is use AI to
bridge that gap to give these companies
the benefits of electronic batch record
systems or manufacturing execution
systems without all the cost time hassle
of migrating to a big enterprise level
solution.
So we've done the work on this and we
actually look back at FDA 483 letters
and these aren't letters that are
pleasant to get. These are the uh
letters you get from the FDA um in
response to inspections that identify uh
deficiencies. And so if you look back at
these 483s, 48% of them uh come from
documentation data integrity errors. So
in manufacturing in bio, there's a lot
of issues with documentation.
On top of this, we know that sub% of
batches just fail and usually from
contamination user error. And on top of
that, you have this QA system in biio
manufacturing that's designed to stay on
top of this, to police it, and to try to
mitigate these errors when they occur.
The issue is they have 800,000, 1200
page batch records to look through page
by page in order to execute their QA
functions. And even in the professional
proof reading industry, there's a 6%
error rate there. So, this is an area
that's just rife for disruption and
optimization with AI. So, here's how we
do it. So the company just uploads their
blank master batch records to our system
called Veriscan. We don't alter their
records. We don't have them create a new
system. We just ingest whatever they
have. Um they view it within our system,
print it out like usual and then the
manufacturing floor, the technicians,
they execute their processes and they
document just like usual. You'll notice
that there's basically no change um in
this in this process from prior
workflows. We try to meet people where
they are.
Um, the little change that we that we
add to the batch record is that we put a
unique uh 2D barcode up in the corner of
the batch record that allows us to trace
every page throughout the whole
manufacturing production cycle so that
if you were actually to take two
different batch records, shuffle them
and then put them into our system, the
system would be able to sort them
automatically. Not that you should ever
ever shuffle batch records like
um so these pages are scanned at some
frequency. It could be every shift,
every day um to enter them into the
system. This is a very, you know,
lowmaintenance process. Again, because
of the barcode, these technicians just
walk up to the scanner, put it in, and
then pick up the scan files, walk away.
There's no sorting or anything that has
to happen because of that barcode. Then
our AI models automatically identify the
documentation issues within those
documents. So, this could be missing
signatures, this can be um bad
calculations. Um in addition to that
they OCR the entire page and capture all
the data that's available there. Those
alerts then go to the QA team
automatically and say hey you have
issues here here and here. This is what
you need to do to to identify that uh to
to mitigate that. Um and in addition we
allow these documents we allow this
production of record to be shared in
basically near real time with
stakeholders whether that's a sponsor um
government observer what have you.
And so the end value propositions
obviously QA has helped a lot because
they're allowed now to essentially
review by exception. Instead of looking
again through a thousand pages of batch
record line by line they can just be
alerted to where the actual issues are.
Um number two shorter QA times allows
you to release batches more quickly and
so then a manufacturing facility can
actually fit in more batches within a
given amount of time.
Um and then lastly
in manufacturer by offering increased
transparency into their manufacturing
process actually attracts sponsors who
need that sort of visibility into you
know where their baby how their baby
project is doing. Um and again that same
data that we OCR and capture from these
documents that is data that's now
available for trending for analytics
that was not available before previously
locked in paper repositories but now
available for digital analysis.
Um as sort of a case in point um our
first install is actually happening next
month with a stealth startup um that is
using Indian source body manufacturing
resources for better for worse uh
wrongly or rightly um Indian body
manufacturing has an has a reputation of
being somewhat lower quality. Um on top
of that um they have almost universally
paperbased processes. Um this is in a
context of more and more bio
manufacturing actually going to India
being outsourced to India. Um and they
are in a financial situation where a
full electronic batch record or
manufacturing execution system makes
zero financial sense and so they're
bringing us in they're bringing very
scan in to provide um a number of
solutions to the situation. So we have a
cryptograph cryptographically secured
timestamp manufacturing record that
results from our scanning process. So
this helps regulators, this helps
sponsors feel more confidence and
assurance in what's being done. Uh
contemporaneous QA allows them to again
speed batch release, get paid faster and
actually fit more batches in a given
year. Um and they are using beer scan to
actually extract data from prior batches
to then use for future process
improvement and trending. Um and lastly
the process transparency that Veriscan
offers um benefits their sponsors who
now instead of having to spend send the
person overseas to India to monitor by
manufacturing processes can actually
look remotely as it happens.
Um so we are looking for more clients.
Uh potential clients for us include
CDMOs. These are the contract drug
manufacturers who make substance for
sponsors who own the molecule rights. Um
farmers themselves also are potential
clients for us whether they do their own
production inhouse or outsource. Um and
obviously um we are very open to
international engagements. Um we do have
we are a past performer for HHS a sole
source uh uh for the for the US
government as well. Um we have ongoing
contracts with DARPA and a pending award
with ARPAH. So we also have interest in
government and national national
security. Uh so if orgs have those
interests we'd love to talk to them as
well. So thanks for your time. Looking
forward to talking.