in this video we'll look at a powerful
tool in the probabilistic method known
as bounded differences
inequality which also goes by the name
auma hofing
inequality this inequality tells us that
if we have a function of independent
random
variables and such that this function
doesn't change very much if we just
change one of the inputs of the function
then the output of this function given
the random input is fairly concentrated
around its
mean let's look at this actual statement
of this
theorem we have
X1 random variable taking values in the
set or in the probability space Omega 1
and so on so so X1 X2 to xn so these are
independent random variables and it's
very important that they're
independent we have a function f which
takes as input and coordinates and
outputs a real number and the hypothesis
of this theorem is that this function f
satisfies the following
property that if we look at two
different outputs of f on inputs X and Y
such that X and Y differ on exactly one
coordinate right so by only changing a
single coordinate of f the assumption is
that the value of f changes by no more
than
one right so F in some sense is fairly
smooth to the fluctuations in the input
if you change only one input coordinate
then the output of f does not change too
much does not change by more than
one okay what is the conclusion of the
theorem it says that the random variable
obtained by evaluating F on these
independent random input coordinates
right so we call this output Z this
random variable Z satisfies the
following concentration
inequality for every non- negative real
Lambda the probability that Z is exceeds
its expectation by at least Lambda is at
most this quantity here which goes down
rapidly as Lambda is gets
large and also we also have a lower tail
concentration
bound which says that the probability
that Z is significantly below its
expectation by more than Lambda at least
Lambda
is this probability is upper bounded by
the same quantity which again decays
extremely quickly when Lambda is large
okay so this is the statement of the
bound the differences
inequality again the intuition here is
that given independent inputs to a
function which satisfies this property
that it does not change by more than one
upon changing any single
coordinate the output random variable is
very concentrated around the
mean in the rest of this video I want to
present three applications of this
inequality the first application is
meant to illustrate a very simple
example of a function where we can apply
the theorem and this function is simply
the function
taking Boolean input so n Boolean inputs
outputs a real number obtained by simply
adding up the input
numbers another words this is a sum of N
different coin tosses each coin toss
resulting in zero or one and you can
check that this function has the
property that we require in this theorem
namely that if you flip just one of the
input coordinates the output changes by
well in this case exactly one but
certainly no more than one
now we can apply theuma hting inequality
or the Bounder differences inequality to
this function and that gets us a tail
bound
on the binomial
distribution this case you know that the
expectation of Z is exactly n /2 and it
tells you that the deviation cannot
exceed very much Beyond something on the
Square on the order of the square root
of uh the square root of
n
this bound is also known as the turnoff
bound
and in fact the proof of the bound
differences in equality is very Sim
similar to the proof of the turnoff
bound which you can view in a different
video let me now go on to the next
example the next
example concerned a problem called the
coupon collector
problem the setup is that we have
independent random numbers S1 through SN
and they're each chosen uniformly from
the numbers 1 through n so these numbers
are
uniformly and independently
chosen so you can imagine a setup as
having and different coupons and each
time you draw a random coupon see what
it is return it to the box and draw it
again and these S1 through SN are it's a
list of coupons that you draw from this
box and the random variable that we're
interested in Z is the number of missing
coupons the number of coupons that you
have not seen through this
process okay in other words this is the
number of elements of one through
n that are not among the elements S1
through
SN okay so this is a number of missing
coupons it is a random variable because
S1 through SN are
random we wish to understand how Z is
concentrated around its mean and for
that we can apply the bounded
differences in
equality note that this
function given viewing this quantity as
a function from S1 through SN as inputs
to the output number this function
satisfies the required hypothesis namely
if you change one of the SI you do not
change the number of missing coupons by
more than
one number of coupons missing coupons
might not change at all but it cannot
change by more than
one so this means that we can apply the
bound differences inequality to deduce
the conclusion that
the probability that Z deviates from its
expectation by more than Lambda is at
most two because here we're using upper
and lower bounds simultaneously time 2
to the minus E 2 Lambda 2 /
n
and the expectation is something that we
can calculate pretty easily using
linearity
expectations of these n different
numbers these n different
coupons each single coupon is missing
with probability one minus 1 / n to the
N right because in this does this is the
probability that a specific
coupon coupon I is
missing which is the event that coupon I
is
not drawn in each of the N different
random draws and this quantity is very
close to n/
e okay so this is an application of
the bounded differences inequality to a
function which is not linear like before
right so the first example is a much
simpler example because the function f
is simply a sum of its inputs and here
there's a more complicated
function our last
example involves an even subtler
function and here the result is a
classic theorem in probabilistic
combinatorics due to Shamir and
Spencer from the
80s the theorem
concerns the chromatic number of a
random graph so let Z be the chromatic
number of
the
random graph
GNP okay so GMP is the airish r random
graph obtained by taking n vertices and
putting an edge between every pair of
vertices with probability P so throw a
probability P coin for each possible
Edge independently and construct a
random graph this way and then Z is the
chromatic number of of this random graph
right so it is the minimum number of
colors required to color all the
vertices so that no two adjacent
vertices receive the same
color this is some random variable and
this random variable is pretty
complicated it's pretty hard to
analyze but nevertheless using the bound
the differences inequality let us deduce
the following concentration bound
showing that Z
typically is not too far away from its
expectation and
specifically we have the bound saying
that Z deviates from expectation by more
than this quantity
here and this event has probability at
most 2 * eus 2 Lambda
s okay let's prove this
theorem the interesting part of this
proof is how to set up the function f so
that we can apply the bounded
differences
inequality so right now Z is some
quantity which seems kind of complicated
and it's based on Something That Is
Random so how can we phrase it in terms
of independent random variables in a way
so that we can apply the bound
differences
inequality well one way to do it and um
it's a natural first attempt is to view
Z as a function with n choose two inputs
one input for each possible edge of the
random
graph that is a valid choice in the
sense that it satisfies the bounded
differences condition but it will not
give the correct bound
because it will turn out to have way too
many variables in this
function we'll take a look at a
different method that will be able to
provide us with the desired bound
and there's some neat idea here on how
to Cluster the random variables
together so we will represent our graph
on N
vertices
labeled 1 through n
and this graph which has some edges and
we'll need to represent these edges um
will represent them as an
element of the following product
set Omega 1 * Omega 2 so these are
cartisian products * Omega
3 so on to
Omega n minus
one and how we're going to encode the
graph using the element of of this
product set is as follows Omega 1 will
be the set0 comma 1 and this set will
record
the which either zero or one which one
gets chosen or record whether there's an
edge between the first vertex and the
second
vertex okay so
if we choose zero then there's no Edge
between one and two if we choose one
then there is an edge between one and
two Omega
is the
product set of 01 with itself and this
two bits
encodes whether there's an edge between
one and three and also whether there's
an edge between two and three that
information is encoded in
the element of Omega 2 that we
choose and Omega
3 is now 0a 1 raised to the 3
power and
here these three bits
record whether the three edges from 1
two and three to the fourth vertex are
included or not included in this graph
and so on
okay so every graph on N labelled
vertices can be represented as an
element of this product set and vice
versa basically we are clustering the
edges together according to the end
point of its uh the right end point of
its Edge according to this vertex order
of the vertices
okay so why is this
useful well if we have two graphs G and
G Prime that
differ
on
edges
around only one
vertex okay um
so if G and G Prime differ on edges
around only one
vertex
then the chromatic number so Kai of G
minus Kai of G
Prime this in absolute value is at most
one so if you have two
graphs and one can be obtained from the
other by modifying edges around a single
vertex then their chromatic numbers
cannot be differ cannot differ by more
than one and the reason is that well we
could have just chosen a new color for
the vertex that is
involved so we would not need to use
more than one color change to go from
one graph to
another okay so this is a important fact
that turns out to be incredibly
useful and it's useful because
if we have a graph represented as an
element of this product
set
then having another graph that's
obtained by just changing one
coordinate results in a graph where the
only changes to the graph itself are
edges around a single
vertex and
therefore the function
F that sends an element of this to an
element of the r basically the chromatic
number of the graph
satisfies the bounded differences
hypothesis and by applying the theorem
we can then deduce the concentration
bound here so that finishes the proof of
this theorem on the concentration of a
chromatic number of a random graph
all right so in this video we saw the
statement of the bound differences
inequality which is a important
versatile tool that is used all over
probabilistic
combinatorics it says that the
concentration of a function of
independent
inputs or this as long as the function
has the property that it doesn't change
very much if you only change a single
coordinate then the output as a random
variable is highly concentrated around
its mean and we saw three different
examples applying this Bounder
differences in equality