let me introduce our first speaker for
this afternoon Josh Westerman senior
lecturer at mit's long School of
Management and founder of global
opportunity Forum today he will guide us
through an essential conversation for
you the leaders of our business world
how to confidently navigate and level
the potential of AI and he will provide
a clear executive level overview to help
you make informed uh
decisions the talk talk title is making
business sense of AI key questions for
leaders please join me in welcoming
George thanks
y so yeah You' be getting Ai and all day
and yesterday and again today so what
could I have to say about it what I have
to say about it is that it's complicated
and I'm going to try to help you make it
a little less complicated if that helps
I should also say I teach in the
management school not in the engineering
school so what I'm going to tell you is
aiming to be 100% clear and 95% correct
not the other way around okay uh that's
why you have you know if you're a
technical person you'll understand why
I'm doing this and if you're a
non-technical person you can talk to
your technical folks and get the other
5% okay okay uh of course it'll take 3
hours to get the other 5% so listen AI
is getting a lot of attention we know
that here's the you know the standard
Google Trends chart and you can see you
know the the red line of AI lots of
attention that blue line starting to
sneak up here's the other thing though
sorry the colors changed but that red
line now the Blue Line see how flat it
is that red line is chat GPT so is this
attention is it hype it's hard to know
and you know in this world of generative
AI we're almost 2 years in into the
launch the first launch of cat
GPT how many people have used cat GPT
CLA something like that okay if you are
not raising your hand raise your hand
next time use it the only way to make
sense out of this stuff is to use it and
play with it you're not going to hurt
yourself right but you will hurt
yourself by not having played with it
because it's the kind of thing you
explore and you get to know a little bit
better what it's good at what it's not
good at and you can choose your model
right there are a bunch of things out
there but it's a different paradigm
worth paying attention to okay and just
to give you an idea what generative I AI
can do in business uh we no longer shoot
videos for our training courses we just
give a script to an AI and it comput it
creates the video for us uh in whatever
face you want and whatever language you
want and if you want to get really
fancy I can give it a video of a very
convincing video of me talking when I've
never done that you know deep fakes for
the use of for good rather than e evil
um so you know if I want to learn how to
speak Vietnamese I just push a button
and I'm speaking Vietnamese and
evidently it's pretty good at it okay uh
coding many people doing interesting
things with coding and you know this is
this is taking off we don't know how far
it's going to go but it's making a big
difference right now uh Cresta is
helping in call
centers they uh the idea of using this
is it becomes a coach it listens while
you're talking and gives you nudges and
after the fact it can also from what I
understand come and say you know across
those last 10 calls you had this
tendency you might want to try to fix it
the same way if you had a really amazing
coach everybody gets better using a tool
like this and the new people get wildly
better right so they raise the bar to
here and of course the new people and if
this is Cresta there are many others in
there they have these for legal now they
have these for Consultants they have
things other there's another very nice
randomized study in a a consulting firm
that they're using G uh they're using
these tools
to
solve strategy Consulting problems and
it's really pretty good at it so um you
you want to you want to be careful there
are limits where it's the wrong tool to
use and then if you haven't seen what's
being embedded in the tools you already
use some really fancy stuff uh Adobe has
the entire marketing chain now where you
can customize uh you can create new art
you can customize and uh every message
you send out all this kind of thing it's
being embedded in the tools you use okay
so you know we're seeing things like
this AI writes 98% of our policies 98%
of our first claim notices and handles
50% of claims instantly and it's getting
better and better this is lemonade they
do kind of simple Insurance products but
you know how disruptive technology works
right you start by fixing the taking
care of the simple ones and then you
move up market and they're doing that
here now the really important thing here
also is this is not just generative AI
it's other kinds of AI and analytics
processing also put together to solve
the right problems in the right way and
that's really an important
point then if you you know if you think
Beyond information business there's you
know Cisco they basically are the the
global supply chain for every restaurant
in the world and uh you know they're
shipping hot things cold things
different
different delivery speeds all kinds of
things to make this work for the
restaurants around the world they have
one of the world's largest truck fleets
I learned uh just sending the you know
getting things around to the the
restaurants that need them each of these
is a use of where they're using AI in
their supply chain or in their customer
support and the little weird little
circuit board things with the brain in
the middle that's where they're starting
to investigate generative AI in here but
once again they're not solving whole
problems with generative AI they're
solving parts of problems and they're
linking it to other Technologies to
solve other parts of problems and
and so as you think about it you might
want to think about it the same way in
what you are doing so we're seeing it in
a purely information-based business like
Insurance we're seeing it in marking
very information based and you see it in
a very hard Goods product like this the
AI is being used and generative AI is
being used in many ways okay so what I
want to do is I want to share four
categories of
ai ai Advanced analytics first of all is
generative AI you know I mentioned that
we'll talk about it in more detail uh
but there's three others right
and these are all advanced analytics and
you can argue that they're all versions
of artificial intelligence some are just
a little bit more intelligent than
others right but they're all useful in
many different ways but when you're
thinking about using these tools what
you really want to start with is not the
technology but the problem it's very
easy and I'm seeing it happen in many
many companies where they're saying go
out and find a a way to use generative
Ai and you know the slogan right if you
are a hammer everything looks like a
nail and that's what's happening is
they're there're they're hammering
generative AI in where it doesn't really
belong now sometimes they're finding
where it does belong too uh but you can
have a lot of cost and a lot of risk if
you use it in the wrong way I am not
saying don't use it I'm saying use the
right tool for the right job right I'm
renovating a house right now I'm
learning all about the right tool for
the right job I'm also learning that
when you're renovate a house it's a
great chance to spend a lot of money on
Cool Tools right uh but hopefully I'm
I'm buying the right tools for the job
so just for two examples at Airbus when
they were trying to fix some problems in
their
manufacturing uh Matt Evans was in
charge of that process he says listen
strictly speaking we don't invest in AI
or natural language processing or image
analytics we're always investing in a
business problem and what they were
doing is they were trying to to detect
when problems were happening they were
trying to sense what was causing those
symptoms and they were finding ways then
to distribute that information across
shifts and across managers so once they
solve the problem it didn't happen again
okay another example is Home Depot where
I'm spending a lot of time right now
right and they are saying we should
always be looking for Extraordinary
experiences experience that Delights the
technology we use that's underneath its
secondary so the first question you can
ask if somebody goes out and says hey
I'm going to I want to find a generative
AI problem or a deep learning problem is
what problem you trying to
solve then you can go from there okay
and each of these a the experience that
Delights that's a lot of problems to
solve it's a lot of tasks and they'll be
solved in different ways okay so then
you choose the AI approach you want so
what I'd like to do is walk you through
all four and give you a a
non-technical understanding of what
these are just so you can speak the
language okay rule base systems when I
started working as an engineer in the
80s one of my first jobs was to build a
rule-based system engine rule based
engine for where I was working and you
know what you got is basically if this
then that okay and then you put a lot of
those together and you can kind of
constrain what the answer should be you
put a lot of them together also you get
a lot of conflicting rules but rules
engines have gotten really good and I
would argue that every one of you has
some kind of a rule engine in your
company already whether it's Finance
rules purchasing rules uh medical
prescription rules all these kinds of
things where it can take information in
and just kind of classify good or bad
from some of these things every time you
go to the pharmacy and it says don't
take this with that there's a rule-based
engine helping with that okay so these
have been around forever they are very
very precise in their answers but
program them requires programming it
requires
a set of experts who can tell you if
this then
that and it can't do anything else it's
pretty R rigid right uh next up
econometrics we've all many of you learn
statistics in class whether you enjoy
that or not uh and those of us who have
come to enjoy really love statistics in
econometrics they can do really amazing
things but really what they're doing is
you're classifying right how do we get
the the data point the the the data
elements that will distinguish The Blues
from the greens on there or you're
trying to find trend lines and now you
can do causality and some other things
in special cases um but you know while
it's easy to draw those lines as you get
into multiple Dimensions it gets a lot
harder no problem at all for the
computer right and of course it doesn't
even have to be linear you can fit
curves that look like this okay so those
of you who have done this you know what
I'm talking about those of you have not
done it just believe me it works and the
thing about it is it's not that hard
unless you're doing the really fancy
stuff it's not that hard it doesn't take
that much data it doesn't take that much
processing power you just need somebody
who knows how to do it without getting
without creating problems okay then we
got deep learning now this gets a little
trickier deep learning is a new a
different way of thinking about it in
regressions and and and econometrics
you're basically fitting you know here's
three or four inputs and we're going to
do weighted averages of those inputs to
try to predict an output of some kind
very simple that's basically what you're
doing now coming up with what those
weights are is the tricky part in deep
learning it's the same thing but you
don't just need numbers you can do it on
images you can do it on text you can do
it on voice you can do it on lots of
different things and the scary picture
that the experts will show you is that
picture in the middle see it the green
and the green and the green picture if
anybody wants to impress you with how
smart they are they'll show you that
picture if anybody wants to make you
convinced their that you're not smart
enough they'll show you that picture
okay that picture is the same thing as
what was happening before but just amped
Up by many orders of magnitude right you
take a bunch of
inputs you take a weighted average of
them on this first here let see if I
okay and then those things you do a
weighted average of those and a weighted
average of boom boom and then you get
outputs okay and once again the hard
part is coming up with the weights but
where on the expert systems you had to
have an expert say what's happening in
statistics you don't statistics figure
out what those weights are and the same
thing happens here just in a much more
complicated way now the other thing is
when you're looking at conom metrics you
can read those you know we got 10
parameters and those weights this one is
more important than this one and this is
negative compared to that one don't even
try with machine learning uh our best
scientists are trying to make these
things explainable and they're making a
little bit of progress but you just have
to believe it it's just magic okay so
let me show you what the magic is is uh
first of all what you do is you
iteratively develop a formula by running
things through you do many many many
iterations thousands millions of
iterations and um eventually by figuring
out where it's wrong and where it's
right and adjusting it comes up with
pretty good answers so if you think if
you want to think about this think about
it like you know the pachinko machines
where you drop a ball in and you hope it
comes out in the right slot at the
bottom and if it comes out in the right
wrong slot you just adjust you could
adjust adjust all those little things
and hope it moves a little differently
that's basically what it's doing imagine
doing a million of those and adjusting
these little things all the way down
okay um you need data you need
truth every time you log in and it says
proed you're a human tell me where the
stop signs are in this
picture you're creating labeled data for
some algorithm to use every time
Facebook does its or sorry I showed
myself to be old Instagram does its uh
brothers and sisters challenge or the
young versus old me challenge we're
creating labeled data to train
algorithms okay um you need that labeled
data you need to know what the right
answer is so you can train the
algorithms to get there now and then by
running through many times you adjust
the little Pinko knobs and then
eventually you come up with the right
answer uh the answers tend to be get the
same answer every time for a given input
um but you can't explain you just just
believe it it just works okay uh the
good thing is it can adapt over time I'm
going to walk you through a little bit
more detail on this one just so you
don't have to be scared by that silly
picture anymore okay um what's what what
are these they're numbers right we know
the numbers imagine writing a bunch of
if then statements to figure out whether
that whole row is twos okay so look here
uh two has a loop in it right well it
does but that doesn't have a loop right
and a two tends to have a little curve
at the top and end a loop but there's no
real curve there right
um IM writing the statements for a two
or how about sevens
right do you allow for the little line
or not and you know how curvy can it be
look at that eight those Loops are
filled in but we still know it's an
eight but I've written this code it's
about 25 30 lines of code and about
20,000 iterations on data and it works
totally fine how here's how it works
right you start off by taking an image
and unrolling it into a line of bits
okay a line a line of line of data a
line of line of bytes and so what
happens is you lose all the idea of
what's next to what you just have 28x 28
becomes a line a vector of data okay and
you use that as input to
a waiting thing then you put a piece you
put in a picture that nine and it's and
using just you start with random numbers
put it in and it makes a guess which of
the follow which of the digits is it
okay and it guesses that's a one well
that's wrong okay then you back chain
the data and adjust some things
depending how wrong it was then you put
number other numbers through and other
numbers through and eventually it gets
to the point where it's pretty darn
right okay you put the all the pixels in
the left hand side you get likelihood
that it's each number on the right hand
side and iterating over and over again
it learns what's right okay so now you
don't need to be scared by that that uh
picture anymore that's all that's
happening it's statistics on steroids
okay um then the generative AI what is
generative AI it does the next step of
this it takes those same kinds of ideas
but in in addition
to
classifying it starts creating so once
again I am way oversimplifying this
but to give you an idea what happens
here it'll randomly generate if I say
you know uh how what what should I say
in a talk about AI for non-technical
people it takes that statement plus
everything it knows and it creates a
couple words okay and it creates
thousands of those types of words and it
says which one best fits with what
George just said and what we know
before let say to that one and then it
takes another couple words and it says
what best fits with what I just chose
plus what George said plus what we know
before and it just piles on more and
more words and it's fancier than that
but that's basically it it's randomly
generating stuff and choosing the best
it can out of what it just randomly
generated and through magic meaning
trillions of data points that is trained
on it's pretty darn
good it's also you'll notice it's
sometimes
wrong uh it's you'll also notice that it
tends to be a little bit Bland often
because it's trying to do the best fit
not the most creative for or whatever
unless you tell it to be more creative
and then you're turning up the dial more
creative more wrong but basically the
key point is it's creating Randomness
and trying to choose which random
outcomes is
best and it can do it for imagery it can
do it for film it can do it for lots of
different things um it can create lots
of not but it can be used for evil as
well as good uh that year ago some
friends and I wrote an article called
from chat GPT to hack GPT and we said
man this is really good but just wait
till the hackers get a hold of it and of
course the hackers are really getting a
hold of it now and the fishing attempts
are getting really good I got a
voicemail from the dean a couple weeks
ago sounded just like her said George I
got to talk to
you it wasn't the dean and I you know I
kind of figured out at a certain point
that it wasn't so I played along with
the game and I said okay Dean what do
you want me to do she goes can you buy
some gift cards I need gift cards
right oh what are you going to use them
for so anyway uh that didn't work so
well uh it does tend to and you have
these hallucinations my favorite
Hallucination is this one happened about
a year ago a lawyer used chpt to create
his court documents and the judge was
not very happy because all of the C the
case law he cited much of it was
completely fake it did not exist and I
learned this very quickly first time i'
had it do a bio for me it said George is
the author of four award-winning
books I'm the author of three
award-winning
books so then I went and I said what's
the name of that fourth book and it gave
me a title which was a really good title
and I can't remember it so there won't
be a fourth award-winning book
okay uh it depends a lot on data uh it
there are questions you know is this
data going to be reused other places
you've all been through these
conversations there are ways to be safe
with this the other thing to really be
important about to remember importantly
it randomly generates so if you ask it
the same question twice you'll get two
different answers which is actually a
really interesting way to think about
creativity I am a pretty good writer but
I'm terrible at titles so I'll say okay
give me a good title for this give me 10
good titles and I'll say then take
number six but make it sexier it can do
that kind of stuff okay so I'm saying
what you probably already know here's
the thing I've just given you four
techniques
um rule engines
econometrics deep learning and
generative Ai and I said already you
know what is the problem you're trying
to solve and actually I should say what
part of the problem are you trying to
solve and here's how to think about what
answers might be right for you number
one what's the cost of being wrong if
you can't be wrong don't do generative
because generative by its nature is
wrong and it becomes more right but it's
creating new stuff for you I said that
wrong wrong generative AI can be right
but it can be also wrong the other
models tend to be very you know they're
going to get the answer that you've got
that you've trained it for uh
explainability do you need to explain if
so
regressions uh rules work the other
one's not so explainable even if you ask
can you explain yourself it's not really
explaining itself okay uh repeatability
do you need the same answers every time
and then the confidentiality which we
are finding answers to the
confidentiality so it's less of a
challenge than it was before for okay
the other questions you want to ask
yourself though
is what's your
data for any technique you're going
what's your source of Truth do you have
data that's labeled or not and also is
that data labeled for the type of
audience you're talking about so imagine
you know that you train something only
on white
men and you try to apply it to people
who are not white men it's very likely
you're going to get answers that don't
quite fit but we do that all the time
right um one of the most famous examples
is um at Amazon their resumé scanning
algorithm was programmed on their best
engineers and so basically it rejected
all the women because they didn't have
very many women Engineers right and they
found it out they had to fix it but they
had biased data and it was causing
biased outputs that you had to fix and
they owned up to it and they told
everybody about it and we've all learned
from that process okay so the formatic
major categories then up this chart in
this chart you can see you know you
don't need a lot of data but you do need
experts it it's repeatable and
explainable but it really can't ex it
can't it's rigid right and over there
right uh you need a whole lot of data
doesn't have to be numbers it's
repeatable but it's not explainable so
if this helps you as you think about
what you're doing
okay so hopefully that has helped you
understand these a little bit better
I've got 10 minutes left and I want to
give you a set of questions also to ask
beyond the type of algorithm using and
more to think about AI in general okay
so can I use that can I shift the topic
on you a little
bit you know how many people know Mo's
law all right more of you you know Mo's
law than used the gener of things that's
good and you know we can all talk about
Moors law this exponential growth and
how important that is and we can even
argue about whether Moore's Law is dead
uh I don't typically bet against Mo's
law but you know we can argue about that
I have my law westerman's law you ready
for
it technology changes quickly
organizations change much more
slowly so that means when you're doing
digital transformation digital is not
really the problem transformation is and
that means it's not really a technical
problem it is a technical problem but
it's also a leadership problem how are
you going to change the organization to
go with
this and we forget this all the time you
just had a bunch of startups brilliant
people doing really cool stuff they're
not going to tell you that you got to
change the organization to use their
stuff right it's not their job to do
that but it's everybody's job to
remember when you buy those things to do
that right um so if we think about
getting the organization ready for Gen
AI or for AI in
general how are you going to decide how
to change the organization and what to
do and and here are just three simple
categories and of course simple
categories mean complicated answers okay
how are you going to prioritize what to
do how are you going to manage the risks
involved and what organizational
capabilities do you need to do so I just
want to share two ways from the uh that
so how two companies are doing it for J
and they're asking some questions around
governance how do we ensure safety and
value of these expensive projects we're
building right number one do you have
any policies in place and if not why not
right because people will tend to follow
policy in general if it's a reasonable
policy but if the policy doesn't exist
or if they don't know about it well
shame on you right so that's number one
number two are you prioritizing top down
to have control are you prioritizing
bottom up to be in Innovative and really
you know push the envelope or are some
hybrid of that are you technology driven
business driven in how you're doing this
how are you linking to other things
right these are key governance problems
dealing with any technology and those
governance problems apply in the AI case
also another set of questions you can
ask is how you as you're doing this how
are you going to learn how you going to
find what's happening and build upon it
how are you going to make sure that what
you build integrates with other things
another key set of governance questions
so to share how this is happening in as
gen came out we saw kind of a top- Down
centralized approach this is dangerous
it's costly we're going to control it
don't don't use this stuff or if you use
it wait till our it people are done and
then you can use it it is lower risk in
some way except the risk of you know you
got no agility there right but at least
you know some of the other problems go
away and you can you can control how it
rolls out then there's a decentralized
approach go have fun right just don't
break the company and we saw kind of
both of these go have fun with in policy
guidelines or and what we're seeing is
some more hybrids come out so I want to
give you two examples of how two large
companies have done this Society General
is a large french bank they are subject
to financial regulations they're subject
to European information regulations
they're also subject to French societal
standards and so there's a lot that they
want to be really careful about and when
geni came out they said you know we
should figure out how to use this we are
an information-based business but at the
same time there's a lot of laws that we
can break and so what they did is they
put out a call and they said how might
you use this and they got more than a
100 qualified use cases they actually I
believe got over 700 but there were 100
kind of common problems they were
looking at and then they said okay
here's the deal um out of there we see a
lot of things that you want to do
and we want to be careful about that but
these things we want to do there are
some underlying elements that are common
to there and you see the virtual experts
the content generation the client
assistance the coding let's figure out
how to do these really well and then
once we've got those then you can start
to do these things on your own so what
they did is they drisk the most common
elements and then they work with uh now
while they were doing that they also had
a few things that were just such such
promising things that they started doing
them right away and in talking to them
recently what they're doing is they're
still thinking about this let's do small
with Gen as we build up the capability
to do the big stuff and then we'll do
the big
stuff then there's another one back to
Cisco Cisco is saying this is just
another kind of AI this is actually just
another kind of technology and we have a
way that we govern technology
Investments basically we start saying
how do we do it in the cheapest most
reliable way and only go more complex
less reliable if we absolutely have to
so they go through and they they think
through where can we use this and then
they say well can we do our your robotic
process automation Bots can we do it
there first because that we know how to
do that uh or can we just use things
that built into the tools we already
have and only if you can't do both of
those then you build up your own custom
Solutions it's their way of managing in
this very complex global company how to
manage the cost cost and the the the
risks in making this happen so one of
the questions I would have for you is
how many of you know how your company is
governing
AI so the rest of you there's one really
wrong answer to that question about how
whether your governance is working and
it's if you don't know the answer it's
not
working okay now once you know the
answer you can argue about whether it's
the right way to do it but if you don't
know the
answer that's a problem now you could
also argue in my role I'm not required
to that's fine right but if you want to
get anything done with technology you
should know those rules all right so
those are some questions that you can
think about from the governance the
prioritization and the risk management
standpoint there are a couple other
questions as leaders that you really
should be ready to ask about AI in
general and one is
culture is our culture ready for
this so when analytics first came came
out there was a real question about wait
I've been working at this company for 40
years and you say that kid with a
computer is smarter than me did any of
you experience that kind of shock it's
happening again right and so do does
your culture have the humility to work
with these tools or is it going to
aggressively fight and then another
piece of this thing that's really that
has people worried is wow when that
computer gets done what job is left for
me right
and so one of the things to do as as as
a leader is think about how can you help
people get over these worries a little
bit because most of many of the
applications especially for genitor AI
we have an article on this can help you
do better in multiple ways they don't
have to replace you right they can take
care of the boring stuff they can make
you more creative and then you got to
figure out what to do with those people
that you will replace right um but in a
way simple from to say of course because
I'm not in those jobs but if you're
doing routine work you should stop doing
that anyway because eventually a
computer will start so as Leaders if you
have people doing routine work how can
you help them be ready to do something
else right um because as the computers
get better they will be there so the
ethics the humility are going to be
really important the other really piece
is this
experimentation these tools just like
many digital tools you don't you want to
go from Perfection to speed of
learning can we do simple learn fast
learn cheap fail fast fail cheap
experiments well-designed experiments to
learn the answer because in a Moors law
world it's hard to know these answers
and a world as complicated as the
digital world and and our customer
environments or our Global Supply Chain
environments it's hard to know the
answers use the data and is your culture
ready for that kind of
experimentation and then one more um
Talent do we have the
skills if we don't have the skills what
are we going to do about that because
those skills are hard to buy although
you can train them if you're willing to
experiment or do you just let your
vendors do whatever you know you use
whatever the vendors have but also what
does it mean for people's careers I
talked about the people doing routine
work but also everybody how can we make
everybody better so for example one
place that you'd think would be a lot of
replacement going on with generative AI
is the advertising industry and here's
here's a creative company denu one of
the biggest in the
world there might have been a little bit
of worry about it but they've adopted
this now everybody's adopted this right
we can't see ourselves going back to the
way we used to be before it frees up the
time that creatives need to be creative
right help me lay out my plan for this
project it just does it right um hey can
you take that and change the colors on
it that used to be hard now you can do
five different conv versions right away
right um flushing out the text so what
where you think wow this is a a
threatening role they've actually
adopted it and making it better they're
making it part of their culture because
they took it on in a proactive way to
make it work okay by the way we're doing
this thing called the global opportunity
Forum uh you talked about it um we're
trying to get companies talking to
companies about how you're developing
your
people and discussions on on Career
navigation discussion on training and
many other things uh if you are
interested in this we're you know as I
with ILP we're getting people from ILP
together so if you're interested in it
talk to me talk to UI talk to Graham and
we can link you into the things that
we're doing in this this this initiative
okay so one more piece of homework for
you if you're interested if you thought
that these governance questions were
kind of interesting or challenging we
have an article in Harvard Business
review about a bank where the digital
person wants to go all in and the CEO
and the CFO are not quite sure and so it
lays out a bunch of real interesting
problems it's a lot of fun to think
through together about this what would
you do it's also a really interesting
discussion thing for teams to talk
through how they would do it and I will
say go forth and read this thing
unfortunately I get zero dollars of
profit from anything you read so it's
just because it's a good thing read this
and see whether it's useful we have a
bunch of other articles also so one last
thought those of you who have changed
tires and it turns out that I've learned
that I am a very bad father because my
son got to 25 years old and got a flat
tire and I never taught him how to
change a tire um but those of you who
know how to change tires you know you
don't screw down one screw and any the
others you're going to bend the rim that
way you a little bit over here a little
bit over there a little bit over there
and eventually it's in a nice solid
place and uh Ari who runs digital at H&M
said the same thing don't plan it all
out in advance try it here try it here
learn from what those what you're doing
there and you're going to make great
things happen for your company okay so
uh here's the conclusion and after that
there are some more articles you can
read on some of these contents if you
want and you can always just send me an
email if you want also I'd love to talk
to you about what you're doing because I
can help you with what I know and I'll
learn from the kinds of challenges that
you're going through so conclusion a is
not intelligent it's numbers right it
can act very intelligently and so be
creative but also be careful in how you
use it okay
uh number two the right tool for the
right problem not the reverse number
three get
started the best way to work with these
things is to start using to build the
care capability know what they can do
and what they can't for yourself and for
your organization right and and make
sure the policy's there so you can
people can at least avoid doing the
really stupid or really dangerous stuff
and last but not least help your people
your people may be nervous your people
may want to get started on this help
them get there to do great things so I
want to thank you thanks for listening
I'll be in the the room at the breaks
but have fun with the rest of the
afternoon thank you Jorge what question
oh we have questions yes I should have
left more time I'm
sorry sorry no questions all right what
are the questions do you have
suggestions for navigating bias issues
in models that risk become PR PR
nightwear yeah uh number one if they
become risk becoming PR nightmares be
really careful about your bias right so
uh you know some things you don't really
care that much right uh others you do so
if it's you know if you're giving
medical advice probably you want to make
sure that those are really correct um
when you think about the repeatability
it's an interesting question also
because for example human resource
systems if you three look exactly the
same in terms of
capabilities I don't actually care which
one of you three I get
right I don't have to choose the same
one but if I have a bias for people like
you against people like that well then I
have to do it so think about you know
the bias the repeatability how much do
you need it uh the way you think about
the bias in this situation is run the
numbers try it out with your sample
group and see whether you're getting
biased answers or not it's the way I
know how to do it um and you can do that
in autom weighted way or a less
automated way to get there one more
question was there uh how do you justify
the value for invested why do people
always ask the question this this same
way the answer is always the same the
answer is always the same I need to do
is how do I make my CFO convinced and
the answer doesn't matter on the
technology come up with a business case
where you can show the value of using
it it doesn't matter what the techn heck
e-commerce 25 years ago it was the same
I'm sorry I don't mean to be insulting
anybody it's the same answer though find
somebody who has a business case you can
solve and try that now the other answer
is well we don't know the business case
we just want to invest in experimenting
well then you're asking for just a
little bit of money and you go out and
you make the case say this is
potentially really big I'm going to do
something with a little bit of money and
here's what I'm going to do to show
whether it's the right answer or not
okay but it doesn't matter gen or
anything else it's the same answer to
those those technology questions what
have you found uh well my old company
wants to start using it how to start
okay I've given you lots of answers on
that one uh what have you found very
advantageous problematic uh you know the
question is with the geni tools uh
certainly you want to think about the IP
issues right are we using somebody
else's information in what we do the
tool vendors are starting to negotiate
those things out so you don't need to
worry as much for example with whether
you're using copyrighted imagery that
should be is part of your vendor
relationship the other question is um
you know what happens if I use my
information in a public gener of a i
tool and the answer for that of course
is don't use private information in a
public
tool okay um which means policy it also
means helping your employees know the a
safe place to go because if they don't
have a safe place to do this they will
use the public tools okay so companies
are building up their own private safe
places they can do this stuff and you
just help people use that okay it's very
hard to say don't do it because people
are going to do it uh what do you think
best way for company to discuss how to
develop our Workforce talk to me about
the global opportunity Forum I'd love to
talk to you more about that and then
let's see there's one more what
industries will be most disrupted and
can be most disrupted that's a really
great question with a really complicated
answer let me just say the places where
you're heavily information based and
especially where that information-based
work is a lot of manual work right now
those are just asking to be disrupted in
someplace
I would add one other place the places
where the Gatekeepers to money or The
Gatekeepers to customers are information
based right now and have people
involved um it's very likely that they
that that information automation will
disrupt not that not that all real
estate agents will go away but they'll
have to act differently not that all
lawyers will go away they'll have to act
differently I I see big changes there
same thing in finance okay so these are
not promises don't invest based on that
but I those those would be some rules I
would go to look through okay I'm going
to go away thank you very much see you
later