Our next speaker and then we'll go right
into that discussion is Dr. Phil Button.
Now Phil is uh Fiona's co-conspirator if
you will in the innovation ecosystems
work. He is a senior lecturer at the
Sloan School of Management. But that
title does not do Phil justice. Phil is
an intellectual leader in corporate
innovation and an evangelist for
advancing the art and science of
corporate innovation both within MIT and
elsewhere. So I'm really looking forward
to what Phil has to say on this subject
and then to the interplay between Phil
and Fiona. So Dr. Phil, please take it
away.
>> Well, thank you very much uh Dr. Ron. I
forgot you got your doctorate uh at the
end of the Cold War. And thank you, Ron,
and to our friends at ILP and corporate
relations here at MIT for pulling us
together for this uh fireside chat. And
thank you for all you participants who
are either uh joining us live. And
please do put things in the Q&A. I will
be sifting through those as part of the
upcoming fireside chat, but also welcome
to those of you out there who are
watching this uh recorded, possibly at
double speed. Um there are useful
insights in what Fiona has just shared
from the cutting edge worlds that she
inhabits of tech innovation. She
mentioned fusion but also the national
security area and she mentioned uh
conflict in Europe. I'll pick up a
little bit on that given her role um and
how these strands come together. But as
Ron kindly said, I'm very interested in
how leaders of large organizations,
primarily corporates, but also uh in the
public sector as well, think about how
to work in this world. And as Ron has
said, you know, for the last 35 odd
years, people especially in the west and
perhaps especially in America, were able
to separate out the geopolitics from the
economics. Anything could happen
anywhere as in Tom Freriedman's book,
The World is Flat. um other parts of the
world did not forget the interconnection
of politics and economics and
geopolitical power. But now in 2025 and
mid August, it's on everybody's agenda.
And I think it's great that we're
getting together in the middle of the
summer to feed into people's thinking as
the new term, the new financial quarter
comes along because you do need to be
planning on the geopolitical dimension
because it will affect your plans
whether you are in corporate strategy,
innovation, R&D. So I I thank Ron for
bringing us together. And let me just
check. Dame Fiona, are you ready for
some fireside chatting?
>> I am. I'd be very happy to answer
whatever questions that you or others
have.
>> Well, there's quite a few questions
coming in, but let me just pick up on
your wonderful presentation. Thank you
so much for pulling those various
strands together. Now, in the
introduction, it is clear that you are a
tenure professor here at MIT. You have
an engineering PhD. You've been
associate dean for innovation and
professor of entrepreneurship. But
you're now thinking about the
international security and geopolitical
dimensions. You mentioned Europe and you
mentioned NATO. So I wonder if you could
say a little bit about NIF which you are
now chairing so that people have a bit
of a context of what the NATO innovation
fund is doing and how it brings several
of these strand strands together.
>> Yes, thank you Phil. I'm very happy to
do that. So as Phil mentioned N is the
NATO innovation fund. Uh it's a it's one
of the first or the first multi-
sovereign venture capital uh funds. It
was established by NATO. Uh 24 of NATO
members have contributed as limited
partners. Uh and they've contributed to
a billion euro fund. And the fund
through independent investment
decision-making is investing in startups
largely sort of tapping into deep tech
dual use sorts of technologies that are
going to solve defense security and
resilience uh challenges that are faced
by the um billion people who live across
the NATO alliance. Now, part of the
fund's job is obviously to sort of
evangelize and and identify and invest
in commercial deals in in some of the
best companies that we can find across
those 24 nations, all of those in
Europe. Uh but we have two other jobs as
well. The first is to make sure that
those ideas are really adopted. And so
we have a very powerful uh sort of
mission platform group that is trying to
make sure that we help those companies
get into the doors of ministries of
defense and others so that all the
countries that have made this very
significant commitment to 5% GDP spend
um not only have the large prime
contractors to work with but also have
opportunities to work with these agile
uh you know ambitious scaleup ventures.
The other thing we're trying to do is
make sure that we in doing that we
really support innovation ecosystems
that are producing these companies not
just in uh the US but also in the United
Kingdom. So we've made some really
significant investments in London and
Oxford in Germany around Munich
companies like Issa Aerospace but also
across other parts of Europe to really
make sure we do that capacity building.
And the last thing I'd say because I
think this is incredibly relevant here
is that we want to make sure that our
companies are protected. We worry very
deeply actually that particularly for
early stage innovation innovators.
Capital is not always as available as we
want it to be. Not everybody can kind of
walk into the door of a Silicon Valley
investor and kind of get the capital
that they need particularly when they're
doing something difficult. they're at
the frontier of innovation and
especially if the government is their is
their customer because we know
governments don't always work very fast
and when they are in this position of
financial vulnerability that's often the
moment when adversarial capital comes in
and so we spend a lot of time focusing
on protecting those companies making
sure that they are protected from some
of the adversarial intent of investors
and others um and so it's a it's
important part of the journey NATO has
absolutely sort of recognized that
innovation is is key and I think our
work and your work around innovation
ecosystems has informed that right from
the early days and the most interesting
piece of this is the move of the whole
innovation function in NATO into defense
investment because what it says is that
innovation is at the core of how we need
to be spending money and I think that's
an important signal that tells us that
governments and somewhere like NATO is
caught up with the private sector who
know that we need to invest in
innovation not just a nice to
Well, excellent. Well, thank you for
bringing all of your uh experience in
the world of this particular university
of MIT and putting it to play in in
NATO. So, NATO is facing off against
Russia. You mentioned US and and China.
That probably accounts for sort of 20%
of the population in the world. And so,
just having asked people while you were
doing your talk about where they were in
the world, it seems very globally
distributed.
um expanding out to the wider world. Do
you see these emerging innovation
ecosystems as just something in in the
west and Russia and China or do you see
the logics of these the logic of these
innovation ecosystems uh not only in
military and defense but in other areas
perhaps applying around the world?
>> Yes, absolutely. I mean I certainly and
as I've said in in the context of the
NATO Innovation Fund, we've been looking
at innovation ecosystems and and the
extraordinary entrepreneurial teams that
are emerging from those ecosystems
across Europe. Uh in the Nordics, we see
some very exciting and interesting
things happening. But as you and I both
know from the work that we've done
together with with RE, our regional
entrepreneurship acceleration program,
there are some quite powerful innovation
ecosystems in South America. Um
definitely in in Chile. uh our work with
Rio and particularly around sort of
clean tech and emerging technologies and
absolutely in um the Middle East in the
Gulf. very interesting work happening I
think in in Saudi and Riyad really sort
of building up that innovation ecosystem
uh and beginning to have that be very
much more focused on science and
technology as well as sort of more
digital activities and not to mention of
course you know the very very large and
important markets and market
opportunities um and innovation that
we're beginning to see in places like
Lagos Acra you know or in Egypt in Cairo
and elsewhere so absolutely I think this
is a global phenomenon. Um, it doesn't
always have the same flavor to it. And I
would say that the best ecosystems, as
you and I know, are the ones that are
often quite focused on a very particular
comparative advantage, things that
they're really good at. You know, think
of Nova Scotia, right, in their with
their ocean cluster, that sort of type
of expertise. And we're definitely
seeing that worldwide.
>> Interesting. Thank you for that. I put
the link to to Reap in there. So these
innovation ecosystems despite what Tom
Freriedman was trying to sell us 20
years ago are not evenly distributed.
They are happening in particular places
and we look separately at why those are.
I'm thinking about some of the corporate
leaders we've got here who are in global
industries and I just wonder uh as we've
been sort of talking about this over the
summer how you see the connection for
these very focused place-based place
specific innovation ecosystems to global
industrial sectors what governments call
the industrial base economists would
call industrial clusters. um why should
those who are operating in global
industries across supply chains and
value chains, why does this sort of very
geospecific innovation ecosystem logic
matter to them?
>> So look, I wonder let me let me use the
life science industry as a as a good
example of this, right? So the life
science sector is extraordinarily
global, absolutely important, right? our
health and well-being depends upon our
ability to to develop and and produce,
right, the new kinds of medicines that
are that are hugely important. Um, and
so you might argue that this was a quite
global industry and and has been for
many many years across sort of Europe,
in the United States, uh, production of
generic medicines in India and really a
growing life science sector in China.
But we also know that over the last 25
years, almost every single large
pharmaceutical company has come and set
up some sort of significant presence in
Boston because the innovation ecosystem
in the life sciences in Boston has been
a a global powerhouse. And so that is
the ecosystem logic at play that says
every single one of those companies
wants some sort of presence to tap into
the frontiers of knowledge whether
that's coming out of Harvard or MIT or
the medical school the hospitals
extraordinary startups that we see and
the very specialized risk capital and so
that's the sort of world kind of coming
to Boston
um on the other hand we know that those
companies very wisely have been very
globally distributed in where they
produce and increasingly have um
produced in China companies like Wooi
have been really important in making it
much more um economically efficient to
produce some of the biio medicines at
scale and yet there again the the sort
of the geography is going to kind of
come into play because you ask the
question well the government will has
had a recent executive order for the
United States to say actually we don't
want you to have that level of
vulnerability and so this sort of
globalized industrial uh sort of logic
is suddenly coming into question we're
having to start to really think about
how we do reshoring of production um
back to the US but also with allies and
of course if you're not in the US and if
your company is based for example in
Europe how you exactly think about those
relationships so it's not just
relationships and how you deal with
adversaries but how we deal with
partners how we partner what do we want
to be good at as a sovereign nation
versus what do we want to be good at as
a group of friends and allies I think is
a really important set of questions
>> excellent that ties in very nicely with
your point about the the geopolitical
calculus. A lot of corporate leaders for
the last couple of decades have just
been able to decide let's do things
where it's cheap or where they've got
access to certain things. And we'll come
on to minerals and rare earth in a bit.
Um but increasingly they need to factor
that into their geopolitical thinking.
Um given that we are both at MIT which
is a remarkable institute of technology
I want to talk a bit about some of the
emerging technologies that you see out
there and I know there's a question
about AI which is very much already with
us but I just wondered if you could with
your technology perspectives give us
perhaps a sense of what other people
should be thinking about as emerging
technologies what are the emerging areas
that perhaps could start to to change
things. I think 5 years ago uh we at MIT
might have talked about the coming AI
wave coming out of the labs and now by
2025 it's very much with us. It's
affecting business as usual. But just a
bit of a glimpse what do you see as a
professor here at MIT are the kinds of
thing things people should be thinking
about.
>> I think you're absolutely right that um
you know we might we might not see AI
and as the cutting edge in quite the
same way that we did five years ago.
although as as you I mean you make this
point I think better than I do that this
is not new and at MIT we've we've worked
on this for for decades um but certainly
there's a very interesting I think an
ongoing question about control of
innovation in AI control of some of the
foundational models whether each country
wants their own model um and the
dependency that that brings on massive
data centers and on energy and so very
quickly even when you're thinking about
something that perhaps is a little bit
more well-developed like AI, you get
straight into sort of data centers and
you get into energy security and that
puts us right back at the frontier of
asking the question whether it's to do
with fusion. I'm also particularly
interested in the next generation of
battery technology. I think there's a
really important set of questions to
understand as to whether or not
given that we have effectively lost the
race I think in lithium ion batteries
although they were um invented uh in the
in the US and sort of perfected in the
US and Japan and elsewhere um what what
about the next generation and so working
with our MIT colleague Yetman Chang
who's one of the leading experts in in
battery technology to really understand
that materials frontier um absolutely in
in sort of quantum computing
And you know there's definitely the race
is is sort of on um particularly in
China. I don't think we know exactly
what's going on there but we do know
that um researchers have spent time in
the US and particularly in Europe and
then taken much of that expertise back
to China and are now uh developing
extraordinary expertise. People might
say why do we care? Well um if we had
really effective quantum computers then
we could also decrypt all sorts of
interesting things. And so that goes
hand inhand I think with the frontier of
um postquantum encryption. So those are
some of the things I think we're we need
to be paying attention to. So uh and MIT
I think is working really hard on on
many of those things. But we absolutely
I think are seeing a world where
20 years ago on campus I'd say it was
all about software and the extraordinary
transformation of computer science.
Today, I think we're coming back to what
we would call deep tech, to things that
are often connected to the physical
world, the material science, the
chemistry, you know, the physics of it.
It's not just ones and zeros, it's atoms
as well. And as a former chemist and
engineer, that makes me extremely happy.
>> Excellent. Well, thank you for that uh
overview. in terms of emerging areas. I
love the fact that you're talking about
a variety of areas, batteries, quantum,
how AI is is used. Um, and also the
material world with with the deep tech.
I ask you a bit about uh critical
minerals. It turns out that while we
pretended not to care for 20 years where
semiconductors were made uh and where
the minerals were dug up and where they
were processed, it turns out we're
starting to care again. And so maybe
just to tie the sort of the geopolitics
of the minerals together with this deep
tech innovation that's coming out of the
the ecosystems. Do you see geopolitics
affecting where these these rare earths
are and where they're being processed?
>> So I mean absolutely. I mean geopolitics
can't quite affect where they are. Um
you know the earth's crust has sort of
been given to us as as it is. Um and yet
it it absolutely matters where they are
of course and and so we shouldn't be
surprised that we've seen recent maps of
Greenland I think in the news again
today or this last week maps of where
some of the critical minerals are in
Ukraine. Um they are a very very
important resource and access to those
resources absolutely matters um
particularly because they are powerful
inputs into a whole series of
extraordinary technologies. I've already
mentioned the role uh that some of the
high temperature superconducting tape
plays in fusion and there are some
really important rare earth inputs into
that tape. Rare earths are are important
in the semiconductor industry. Uh
they're extremely important in certain
kinds of battery technology um and so
on. And so you could sort of think about
mapping some of the absolutely frontier
industries to their dependencies on you
know things that we dig out the ground
in everywhere from sort of well we could
dig them out of the ground in Greenland
but we largely don't um to Ukraine to
Australia and also to China. What's
interesting about rare earths is in fact
the real bottleneck is not where they
are actually, it's about where they're
processed. And for many decades, we've
decided that the processing technology
was not particularly interesting and it
was very dirty. Um, you know, you take a
lot of rock, you grind it up, and you
sort of basically put a lot of acid over
it. And that is a is a pretty nasty
process. And it made sense then for
countries said, "Look, we don't want to
do that." And China said, "We don't
mind." And so China invested
significantly in processing both in
China and in Indonesia and elsewhere um
in parts of Africa which means that
regardless of whether we have control
over where these rare earths are, we
actually have to really think carefully
about whether we can use our innovation,
our private sector ingenuity to come up
with cleaner ways of extracting and
really be willing to actually do that
and make those investments
and make those investments in a way that
is connected into the whole value chain
of the end industries and so I think
it's a it's a really fascinating
industry to understand this our
colleague Elsa Oletti is obviously a
significant expert in this um but the
the sort of corporate perspective I know
Phil is one that you've been thinking
about so I mean what have you been
seeing in in this and how has that
debate changed from your point of view
if I'm allowed to turn the tables and
I'll
>> go you're the professor um well
fortunately Ron has made me smarter
about the minerals and the rare earth
elements
Um, I had not traditionally thought
about them. Um, and yet it really
matters for me as a former diplomat, you
know, where they are in the world. And,
uh, this is being recorded on the
Thursday ahead of the Trump Putin
discussions tomorrow. So, those watching
this later will know how that sequence
turns out. It turns out people care
where the minerals are. And you're
right, they they are where they are.
It's a question of how they can get them
out of the ground. But also, you know,
our very important mining industry
doesn't always find it easy to extract
them in some of the jurisdictions that
uh loves having the technologies but
doesn't necessarily want to have the
mine there. And so I think the
corporates need to play in that
multistakeholder space as the world
changes to make the case why they need
to be able to extract the minerals but
also process them uh without supply
chains having to cut across certain
international borders that uh could
become problematic in the near future.
And I I mentioned reap for the eagleeyed
ones. You will see that we've had in the
before times we had teams from uh China
and Russia. And so we have a bit of an
understanding what's going on there. And
yet with the new geopolitical
fragmentation, corporate leaders and
strategists will need to think about
where are they sourcing things whether
it's minerals or semiconductors and just
have that geopolitical uh calculus.
Can I just add? So I think one of the
things that makes this quite hard is
that at the moment um
a number of governments, US government,
UK, European governments, I think
increasingly recognize the vulnerability
of production of supply chains of some
of these critical inputs, but and they
talk quite a lot about it. And so as a
corporate leader, you know, I want to
factor that into my calculus as as we've
been talking about. But at the moment
they often don't price it. And so
they're not willing necessarily to pay
extra for something that has been
sourced, you know, from a friendly
nation or from somewhere that is a much
more reliable source that is less likely
to be subject to embargo and so on. Um
we're beginning to see a little bit of a
shift. And so we saw this with um the US
basically making a particular commitment
to um a US mining company and having a
sort of a floor price on their offset.
And so we are beginning to see that.
We're beginning to see resilience,
sovereignty, control being priced by
governments. And I think that will,
interestingly, that will make it much
easier for for corporate leaders because
at the moment, I think we want to do the
right thing. We want to give good
advice. We want to have the right
boardroom discussions, but it's quite
hard to tell whether or not these are
nice to have on the part of governments
or things that they will ultimately
either regulate or price. And so I think
there's a very interesting set of sort
of discussions but it does mean that uh
keeping an eye on that is going to be
important.
>> No, it really is. And I I see a question
I'm going to move on to the space
industry in a moment and but just to
pick up on that I think this is why
those who are involved in business doing
MBAs being corporate leaders need to
think about this because in this global
competition the relationship between
states and markets is different in
different countries, different
jurisdictions. some can manipulate
markets for geopolitical effect. I think
one of our strengths in what used to be
called the west is that we have fairly
free and open markets. So thinking about
how can we help uh economic actors,
corporate leaders to play through that
what is the role of the price discovery,
price mechanisms uh and I I hope that'll
be something that we can continue to
come back to. But somebody asked about
space and so you can either take the
space race to Mars, you can take the low
earth orbits but I know from both your
studies, your NATO work and a variety of
boards that you sit on. How would you
talk about space in this geopolitical
area?
>> I mean look I think there are a number
of obviously there are sort of different
layers and one can think about the space
economy I think as one that is is
obviously profoundly important. I mean
if we start with just space launch I
think that is perhaps one of the most
essential pieces of having a space
economy. We've got to get stuff up into
space and you know increasingly we have
been and and many of our companies our
countries have been very reliant on
SpaceX. Now that's a fascinating example
of a shift from having these large
audacious innovation projects happening
um being done by governments by
organization like NASA and now being in
the hands of the private sector and and
using all that private sector ingenuity
and that I think has been a very very
important lesson and I think has sort of
forged the path for us relying on
entrepreneurial ventures to be some of
the leading innovators. But of course,
if I'm sitting outside of the United
States, I might ask myself, do I want to
be that reliant on a specific country
and a very specific company? Um, and so
what we're beginning to see, and we see
this through the NATO Innovation Fund,
is real efforts to um develop new space
launched capabilities um in other
countries. We've seen we've made an
investment in ISSa Aerospace, which is a
German um space launch company. And
interestingly, they are doing their
physical launches in the Andoya Space
Center, which is up on the west coast of
Norway, right up in in sort of the high
north above the Arctic Circle. I had the
privilege of going to visit um not very
long ago, and you recognize a big
investment by the Norwegian government
in having that space launch capability.
Think of that as a very powerful asset
for the nation that they can use as part
of collaboration with other like-minded
nations. And so we definitely see I
think a growing market but also a
recognition that we don't want sort of
monopoly of one country or one company
over that. So that would just be sort of
launch. I think when it comes to
satellites you see the same thing. I
think people not necessarily wanting
sole reliance on one particular company
whether it's Starlink or anybody else
just because that gives a very hefty
amount of control and latitude of action
to that one company. So I think we're
beginning to see um sort of more
different opportunities from different
countries. Again, I think that's going
to change the structure of industry.
>> When it comes to Mars or the moon, you
know, look, I I do think that there's
discussions about we get back to
critical minerals. There's discussions
of are we going to mine the deep seabed?
Are we going to mine on on the moon?
There's some really serious discussion
at the moment. I think China and Russia
have made a commitment to put a nuclear
reactor on the moon by um I think 2030
or 2032. Will the US do likewise? And so
I do think that that is going to be a
new terrain for geopolitics.
>> Look, it's one that I find quite
troubling. I I um I don't know whether
this is just me or whether it's just
because I'm a girl. I I sort of think we
should sometimes leave our planets
alone. I'm not very fond of the idea of
terraforming Mars, but that just makes
me um you know, old-fashioned, I think,
probably. Well, no. I think it's uh I
think it's important to be cautious uh
about these things and and have
discussions even at a time of
geopolitical fragmentation. I think it's
important to have uh international
discussions and and communication was
one of the the topics um out there and
it ties into a little bit um with the
the US not being so open to some of the
international talent that has
traditionally come here to to the United
States. Do you see opportunities out
there for other parts of the world to
think through, you know, you mentioned
the German company in Norway? Are there
parts of the wider world, formerly the
the the
developing world, some call it the
global south. Are there ways with the
way that innovation and technology is
playing out for others to try and
specialize with their innovation and
their industries?
So I absolutely think that there are
huge opportunities for different
countries, different regions to
specialize. Um and you know we see this
quantum computing is actually a really
interesting area where we've seen
something that is not just that's not
just a US being in the lead nor China.
We see extraordinary leadership on the
part of the UK um but increasingly in
Denmark for example very large
commitments uh by the governments in
some of these countries. when it comes
to things like space technology, we've
seen the UAE, you know, being really
quite forwardleaning when it comes to
sort of space space launch and and um
space technology, which I think is a
very interesting piece for me. What that
means is it's not just a a willingness
to attract global talent and to perhaps
use the fact that the the sort of the
magnetic attraction of America's very
very leading academic institutions, you
know, MIT included, is more complex
today. And so that does mean that
perhaps there are opportunities for
other places, but really building up
that ability to educate at the highest
level, do research at the frontier of
knowledge is a long-term commitment. And
so as countries think about that and
make sure their universities are fit for
purpose and focused more specialized
than I think would be traditionally the
advice that they would um sort of be
given or have for themselves. The the
mental model um is a long-term
commitment. It's not something that we
can they can do for sort of two years
and say well oh we've changed our mind.
Um the places that have absolutely built
these sort of the new worldclass
institutions and think you know
Singapore or elsewhere have been doing
that for decades and have made that
long-term commitment not just to
education but also the the research
training. But I'm incredibly hopeful and
again we've seen this with some of our
regions in reap particularly in the Gulf
and elsewhere where there is funding
available to make to make that
commitment. And so perhaps the next
generation of talent will move more
seamlessly backwards and forwards come
to the US. I'm I'm hopeful because we
benefit so much from having global
talent on our campus. I mean, what a
pleasure to walk into a classroom and
hear so many different accents. You
know, I think as professors, we're not
unusual in not sounding as if we were
born in the United States. And so this
is something that our faculty has always
been so global. Um, and I'm hopeful that
that will continue to be true, but we
have to be extremely careful because we
are developing things that are of
significant national and international
importance. And I think we have to
protect those ideas.
>> Well, that's great. I'm going to shift
on to the energy transition uh after a
quick comment on the international
talent because I think corporate leaders
have a role to play with this as well.
uh you know, wherever they're
headquartered, they can definitely lean
into opportunities to improve the local
uh skills and talent, which can give
them competitive advantage in the
markets they're in. But as we see here
in Boston, quite a few corporates also
spend their people here. Uh it's worth
dropping into innovation ecosystems to
get a glance at the future. uh some of
the great ILP events bring out some of
the best MIT professors to talk about
you know cutting edge quantum fusion
cyber security postquantum decryption um
or webinars if you can't get here but I
think there are various ecosystems
around the world and it's worth
corporates thinking about putting some
people in them to get glances at the the
future one of which is on um the energy
transition which some look at through a
decarbonization perspective others
through how do we make our way from
traditional hydrocarbons to other
approaches and just this week we've had
an amazing Saudi delegation startups in
the environment space from that ministry
a country that is definitely leaning
into to that transition I was wondering
if you could say how does the energy
transition look from a geopolitical
perspective is that changing things and
are there a role for not only the big
corporates the sort of oil majors but
also for startups as we think about
future energies
>> so I I think the energy transition
certainly has you know a very
significant sort of geopolitical
dimension and again I think that
geopolitical calculus is increasingly
important both for the startups and the
large corporations and I hope the
partnership between the two I mean just
to sort of put it in the most I think
the starkkest terms is that part of that
transition the transition to electric
vehicles has been built on the back of
you know massive availability and huge
sort of reduction you know in the cost
curve of batteries and that has come
from the economies of scale and scope
that have been had by PE companies like
BYD and CL in China. And so on the one
hand we have the extraordinary ability
to make much lower cost uh lithiumion
battery technology but on the other hand
that provides both huge economic
benefits to China um through a very very
long-term investments in those companies
and uh significant strategic dependency.
And so I think as we think about the
next generation of energy transition
technologies um whether that be actually
the energy transition that we're going
to need to power what we might do in the
space economy uh for electric aviation
for example or say gridscale storage
there's some areas where we think there
might be real opportunities for for
example US or European or other
ingenuity and innovation ecosystems. I
think the thing we have to try to make
sure of this time is to have an
industrial policy to have that sort of
economic statecraft that allows for us
to hold and own more of that
industrialization. And that I think is
going to be the the debate if you like
or the back and forth between the
startups and the large corporations in
the energy transition is how those large
corporates will use their balance
sheets, how Wall Street will think about
them. And so we haven't said very much
about the capital markets but of course
for any one of these decisions that sort
of any boardroom decision which is a
decision being made in the shadow of a
belief about what your investors are
going to think about it. So really
understanding where the capital markets
are with respect to how much they value
um you know sort of investments in
resilience how much value is given to
sort of having less geopolitical
vulnerability in your supply chain. I
think it's going to be the capital
market response that's going to be quite
important to this energy transition both
in the private capital when it comes to
investors and in the public capital with
the with the capital markets for the
large corporates. But I think we're
going to see both hugely important next
generation technologies and we continue
to and the energy transition I think is
exactly the place where the ecosystems
embedded in this sort of industrialized
sort of global clusters these
geopolitical questions are going to come
to a head um and I think there's so much
work to be done so I'm really
>> I'm always very delighted when we have
teams in our reap program for whom this
is their focal activity and they're
asking the question can we be an expert
in this particular particular piece of
it, you know, are we going to be
extraordinarily good at sort of solar or
something else? I think very very
important.
>> No, I I think that's great. I love tying
that into your point about, you know, I
think there are going to be
opportunities around the world coming
out of innovation ecosystems, coming out
of parts of the world where our
listeners today are are from. Um, as we
move into the final uh minute or so
before I hand back to Ron, he very
kindly mentioned you'd written a book.
Could you say something about that?
>> Um, I think actually you wrote a book
and I helped. Um it was you know really
a pleasure I think to take the work that
we have been teaching um in our classes
about innovation ecosystems to our MBA
students our mid-career executives um
take some of the material that we've
been working uh with leaders in regions
around the world those five uh
stakeholders uh working with corporate
leaders in particular government leaders
and really sort of putting all that
together and saying no if you want to
accelerate innovation in your large
organization how can you How should you
work with innovation ecosystems around
the world? You know, what do you want to
do that for? What's the strategic
imperative? Who do you want to talk to?
And how are you going to do that? And
it's been a real pleasure to um you
know, put all those ideas together and
actually have that discipline of writing
it all down sort of in a book so that
those ideas can can kind of be put
together all in one place. And so, um I
hope that people find it helpful. It
absolutely is aimed at the corporate and
government leader. And so it's brilliant
to share that with this audience and um
we should say thank you to you for it
was your idea to put it all together.
>> Well, it was a team effort and I see
links to that and our corporate
innovation work uh are there. Fiona, as
we wrap up and um prepare to return to
Ron, thank you so much for taking time.
We have worked so closely on corporate
innovation and now we got this new
geopolitical dimension. I know uh
there's going to be an ILP event in
October um which we can pick up with
these conversations in that globally
relevant city, but let me give you the
last word and then Ron can take over.
Well, I just want to say thank you and
I'm incredibly appreciative of having
the chance to uh talk about this um sort
of the role of of geopolitics and this
idea that we need to have a geopolitical
calculus in our boardrooms and our
investment um committees, you know, in
all the places that we're making these
essential economic decisions. We need
that uh geopolitical calculus as a lens
over um our innovation activities. Thank
you very much.