what was that moment when you knew that
ocw are the people who you know you
watch five minutes of gilber string it
is impossible not to be
impressed welcome to open Learners a
podcast that tells the stories of
Learners all over the world who use
mit's open courseware I'm uel Li kasigi
and open L myself from campala Uganda in
East Africa I'm Michael Jordan Pilgreen
an open learner from Memphis
Tennessee hi Michael hey Emanuel how you
doing I'm doing great man I can't
believe we're here yeah I can't believe
we're actually recording this this is
something we've been talking about for a
while now I think over 13 14 months do
you remember the first conversation we
had about starting this podcast I do I
actually remember that conversation a
lot this was 16 months ago
I had reached out to you over LinkedIn
you know a story had been written about
you in MIT news yeah we scheduled a call
to uh connect and the first thing I see
on once the camera finally comes on is
just like this dark
room with with with with you sitting in
the room and uh you know later I figured
out like the power had been off and
kalala I ran from walk that day
I came earlier home I Was preparing
myself a little meal so I was like
blasting music on my laptop and I was
consuming the laptop's battery so I get
on I'm tethering from my phone my batter
is low that first conversation became
you know this idea about open Learners
making a global community of open
Learners and creating this podcast of
the might surprisingly they said
yes and you know later here we are uh
but for our listeners who are unfamiliar
um open coare is an online publication
of nearly all of mit's courses and
content it's available to all Learners
all over the world it's free MIT open
courseware is one of a collection of
open educational resources at MIT open
learning you know and one thing that
might be helpful to know is why we in
particular wanted to start this podcast
you know just like the Learners we will
be featuring in each episode we both
have our own open course where story and
Emanuel you know we should start with
you um maybe tell us a little bit about
your story yeah like I mentioned before
I'm from Uganda a small country in East
Africa and I've been i' been learning a
lot of things online and then one day I
really wanted to look into this a I
think so on my journey I'm looking to it
when I'm on YouTube searching something
and I see course on AI my first shock
was this which MIT is this this can't be
the MIT you know why would they give out
knowledge for free I check out the
courses in my skepticism I first
download a psychology course I watched
the full course I thought to would take
me months I watched it in a really short
time cuz it was really really
interesting so I told myself I should
thank this professor it's the least I
could do uh but some days later the
director of ocw writes me back and
they're like we like to do a story about
you
I always tell the team that at first I
thought they trying to scam me or
something like why what what do you want
for me but turns out it was a really
great experience there were real legit
the Articles came out and then I say now
meeting the people in the background
Michael reached out then we got on calls
with more
people and the journey has been amazing
since so Michael what was your story
like yeah so during 2019 I graduated
from undergrad 2020 roll around and I'm
getting ready for my first art show of
about six to eight oil paintings and the
pandemic happens So within two months
I'm
unemployed and it doesn't look like art
is going to be coming around soon I was
a public artist before that doing murals
and
sculptures and I knew I need to make a
change I had heard people were still
hiring in finance and I knew technology
was still hiring so I started looking
for free resources online where I could
learn finance and Technology I stumbled
upon MIT open course fors YouTube
watched Andrew Lo's Finance Theory one
course and the rest is sort of History
you know that's that's just my story in
a short form so ocw changed our lives
and connected us with Learners from all
over the world which is amazing for me
personally and the point of this podcast
is to share their stories what led them
to ocw what their experiences with ocw
was like and how their lives have
changed because of it over time given
the different backgrounds will be
speaking to Learners from all over the
world so in each of the six episodes
this season we share a story of a
learner from a different part of the
world each learner will tell their story
in their own words uh so today we will
hear from Maria eduarda babosa she's
from sou Pao Brazil Emanuel and I first
met Maria um last year towards the end
of
2023 and the thing that really struck us
about her story was the fact that there
was this learner that was ambivalent
about learning she was probably smarter
than the rest of the people in her
school and her class but she was just
disengaged you know through the power of
MIT open courseware and her ability to
learn new knowledge in English she was
able to transform her life in a way that
uh many people aspire to but few people
follow through on but I think that's
enough of us talking about Maria let's
hear from Maria herself here is Maria
eduarda Barbosa from Salo Brazil
my name is Maria I'm from Rio Brazil but
I live in s Pao where I go to medical
school in the University of s Paulo so
I'm going into my second year right now
and I'm
22 I want to have a career in
research I've always wanted to teach
like for long as I can remember I like
to run and last year I ran a half
marathan for the first time so you can
probably tell just from that
introduction that Maria is an
enthusiastic person who is passionate
about her own education but according to
her it wasn't always that way my father
is in the military so uh when I was 14
we were transferred for the first time
and that was very hard on me and I went
to like this small school so I went to
the small school and it
was not challenging so to speak at some
point I realized I wouldn't I could not
possibly fail even if I didn't like know
homework because I would a the test and
that would give me enough grade to pass
and so I wouldn't fail I knew it there
was like this teacher who was the math
teacher and the physics teacher was also
very helpful in that sense and one of
them came up to me and said someone like
you really should be studying
this was the first time when someone
demonstrated he expected me to be more
than what I already was and that was so
special for me and I and I was like oh
what the hell am I doing with my life
and at that point I was like okay I'm
going say something um okay everyone
says like calculus is really hard let's
see if I can learn it I Googled like
calculus intr trory course and that led
me to Professor gilber Gilbert Strang
calculus big picture which is to this
day one of my favorite classes of any
topics like
ever and I was fascinated and I was
expecting to like challenge myself and
and sure I did but I started to enjoy it
like a lot and I was like doing this
while I was not a at school and things
started changing for me pretty rapidly I
could relate to
that so I understand her view of not
feeling challenged enough and then you
meet these other people who are teaching
you the same thing but in a more amazing
way and for the first time ever it makes
sense so I can I can relate to that I
was also uh a unconventional learner
that struggled to stay engaged in
Traditional School
so I definitely relate to that Journey
but also the idea that when you first
see Gilbert string it kind of makes you
start thinking about education and
learning these complex topics such as
calculus and linear algebra more
userfriendly
and um you know just inspiring you to
learn more about these complex
topics and Michael we ask Maria to
reflect on the challenges she fa at the
start of her ocw journey one common
obstacle for many in the global learner
Community is all ocw classes are taught
in English so I actually took very few
English classes as a kid but when I was
very young my older siblings they they
spoke English and they would speak
sometimes uh between them so that I
couldn't understand but I was a kid I
was like a machine of learning languages
so I I I picked something up at at that
point between 12 and
13 uh my mother was involved in
the let's say an institution inside the
Catholic Church which which deals with
refugees and so we received a family of
refugees um at our house and there and
there was a guy who was like a little
bit older than me and if you haven't
realized I tend to talk too much and so
I didn't consider the possibility of not
talking to him for for the other
language option I I didn't even know the
alphabet so I picked English and
practiced a lot throughout these months
and that that get that made me really
comfortable with with English and then
like a few years later I met uh ocw and
started using it like pretty much every
day
so taking classes in English wasn't the
only first Maria encountered when she
started ocw it was also her first time
taking classes online I think it was one
of the first times I was doing learning
by the sake of learning and that was the
main transition for me not from like uh
seeing the professor and or watching
online classes it was like uh
from sometimes liking something and
maybe studying a little bit maybe
studying to get a medal on that Olympia
or but this was more like I I want to
see what I I want to see what this is so
I was like they out of curiosity and
self motivation and so that was the
biggest transition for me was not it
wasn't hard at all to go to online
actually but one thing that really
helped me helped me was like uh at the
same time to be like more open and
honest about it and to be more humble in
the sense that okay like you do you do
you do like the last part of calculus
course which was in edex I think it was
calculus 1C you do infinite serious you
do not think you're so smart anymore
Maria may have been questioning herself
at the start of her ocw journey but when
she was done her professors were
questioning how she knew so much
interesting if you ask me actually one
day one Professor asked me so what was
your first undergraduate course and I
was like no I didn't have another
undergraduate course I just uh watched a
bunch watched a bunch of of ocw classes
and he was like oh that's great I
thought it had learned chemistry or
something Maria shares how ocw changed
both her professional and personal
trajectories I wasn't very close to to
my friends even at that time because I
was so Shell Shocked from the from
moving from R to
Brazilia and so i' be home and I would
count a days oh how long do I have until
I go back home you know uh because I
really didn't like the city and I I
missed everything like so bad what
happened was like I started having
something to something more to think
about uh I think it made me a lot more
useful for the people around me and
that um opened me up for them and then
uh as a consequence I was happier I was
learning more stuff and I was uh more
integrated uh to to my
community after finishing ocw Maria was
happier more social and more grounded
than she was before she also noticed she
was approaching learning
differently and so I sat that
the point where I where I think ocw has
made like the most difference in my life
is after I got into the university
because I was really comfortable with
not knowing things and that's like a
lesson that I try to bring to my
colleagues like all the time because
they always want to give like this so
specific and fancy answers and sometimes
the the answers do not exist and they
think they should know because all their
education was geared towards a test they
had to do well on so it creates a
culture of
validation and one colleague of mine
she's amazing and she was like okay I
know I made this mistake I know I did
not answer that correctly but and but I
want I want to know how do you study
because I don't feel like I'm learning I
feel like I'm lost sometimes when we're
studying together and I was like okay
sometimes I also feel lost and then I I
tell you guys I'm I'm lost because I get
lost the difference is I do not think oh
I'm lost because I'm stupid I think I'm
kind of lost because I haven't learned
this yet and sometimes you the best
thing you can do is to ask what you
think is the stupid questions because
odds are you're not the only one with
that questions and what was learning at
ocw at that point was so key for me to
grow as a student and as a person
Maria's ocw Journey also inspired the
people around her including some of the
youngest members of her family and in my
family this is kind of cute because I
have a small niece she seven now it's
it's nice because I don't live in the
same city and when I come came to visit
she was we spent a little bit of time
together and we were kind of doing
chemistry experiments and she was so
excited and her eyes were glowing and it
was so funny and I think that aspect of
not trying to do something useful just
trying to do something that's
beautiful
and that that's something I I want to
bring to her and and I I think that's
that's working because people are so
like uh St that useful usefulness thing
and it's like I play the guitar I will
never make any money playing the guitar
and I couldn't care less and I think
sometimes with our studies and what I
want to bring to to to my niece I think
there are two good reasons to study one
of them is to be of service and the
other one is to contemplate things is
like art is the product of your studies
are not
what what you do with it directly it is
the person you become while you're
studying I think some of the people that
I've inspired the most in my ocw journey
has been other Learners around the world
I think I've given a lot of
people um the fuel to light the fire
that's within all of us to become a
better person to keep learning to always
be curious you know to keep you know and
it's not just studying for studying sake
it's really like how can I expand my own
Consciousness how can I expand my view
of the world and how can I bring these
Frameworks back to my family my friends
my
community beautiful beautiful you
mentioned something about inspiring
Learners all over the world that's
something that took me by surprise I
would say but also from studying for the
sake of becoming a moreful person most
of the courses I take I did have done so
far and I'm currently doing on
ocw were for personal reasons I studed
psychology not because I work in
Psychology but because I like psychology
I studed everything else from there for
the love of it so obviously her cew
workk had a profound impact on Maria we
asked her if she had any advice for
others around the world who are
considering ocw any other Learners any
curious people what advice you have for
them one thing I would say it's like
this is just the beginning they're not
this is very cool but do not close your
eyes and be so stubborn with things
remain open to learn to learn new things
do not be so confined to your Niche uh
and actually for me and for everyone
who's like in their teens or early 20s I
hate to break that to you but you do not
have a niche and you don't have to like
close your mind now
remain open to learn new things and of
course when you love something you
probably have some constructive
criticism for that thing as well Maria's
advice to
ocw get more of it this is sort of a
funny one because I was kind of thinking
the other day I don't even
remember what I was looking for but I
remember there was like a bunch of
things it was biophysics it was
biophysics and I didn't find a lot of a
lot of stuff and I was like
I might be be like being totally unfair
to the usw team do not be afraid of like
oh you know maybe people won't want to
come here I doubt it I double doubt it I
triple doubt it actually um I wanted to
go to MIT because of ocw people will
know the institution better people will
want to collaborate with it please uh
record more courses because sometimes we
want to we want to learn by a physics
with someone like youber stringers or
Barber
Imperial even though Maria is done with
her ocw cewor for now she continues to
reflect on where she would have been
without it in the last last time I I
talked with someone from the team I was
at at the roof of my grandmother's house
it was a place where we hang our clothes
to dry them up but you don't know what
it is because in the US when you take
out your clothes from the machine
they're already dry it's a very
different
reality very different culture very
different place as a also because here
it is warm enough so that things can dry
up pretty quickly it's far it's it's
like this how much further this
initiative has brought mit2 level
education is what I want to convey and
maybe I wouldn't have become the person
who's like a student who's passionate a
enough about studying to get into the
medical school I got into it probably
wouldn't be where I'm at today if that
this initiative didn't exist and so um I
cannot express my gratitude
enough and Maria's clothes drawing is
the perfect visual because it gets at
this bigger theme Emanuel and I are
trying to convey in the season of open
Learners While most of the classes at
MIT are taught in Cambridge
Massachusetts m Open courseware is a
global program and phenomena I wouldn't
be where I'm at today if it wasn't for
these kinds of platforms not only
because they give me the opportunity to
have like MIT level education in my
small small High School library in
Brazil
still but because it shows me it opens
the window to a w that was not part of
my ward and as a result I grew up and I
learned to really love learning and
doing it for the sake of it so when
you're if if this platforms do not exist
people are confined to their geography
and this is not fair people are confined
to their geography and they do not reach
their full potential because they do not
know everything that's out there because
they have very good grades in this small
place in this small school which is fine
but they could be doing more and they
could be better for their communities
and better people as a result of it and
it's like number one the knowledge they
provide and number
two uh an open door to the world and
it's like oh hey you in Brazil like you
want to challenge yourself or something
you want to learn something
new yeah that's whole world of there you
have no idea and that's exciting and
that that changes your perspective on
life and
education and that's the key of it it
gives people hope and G it gives people
IDE ideas about the warden and that's
like the main thing for
me well Michael that's episode one in
the
books how do you feel I'm feeling great
I'm so excited and honored that Maria
was willing to share her story with us
and engage with our audience how about
you I'm psyched I'm psyched I'm psyched
that we're first of all doing this and
I'm excited and great F that we got to
this stage and we are speaking to great
people like Maria uh for the first
episode I won't have it in any other way
so do what's your biggest takea away
from Maria's story I I think my biggest
takeaway and this is something we
touched on in our very first
conversation with Manuel
was MIT open course where the people at
open learning are you know tenaciously
going after the this Grand Narrative of
fulfilling the destiny of the internet
you know what what better way can we
show that Destiny being fulfilled than
an naturual learner that has been
impacted in such a deep and profound way
that it literally changed her life um
for the better with free information
that was freely given over the Internet
yeah I hear you I hear you yeah so how
about you Emanuel this this has been
grand and you mentioned something about
the information age and I feel my
biggest take away from this is first of
all this works this not works but this
is real this is actually changing lives
you will hear several stories in the
coming season but this is actually
changing lives for sure for sure and I
think you know one thing that we learned
in this episode is you can get so much
wisdom from just one learner and we have
five more to go this season uh you know
I might be a whole different person by
the end of the season who knows yeah me
too me too we'll be back in two weeks
with another story from a different
Learner in the global ocw Community see
you
then open larner is produced by Alexis
hot special thanks to the supporters and
donors who make ocw possible to learn
more about mit's Open course rare and to
check out the courses mentioned in this
episode visit the open courseware
website at ocw w. mit.edu
[Music]