My name is Tvor Baharav and I'm a
secondy year postdoal fellow at the Eric
Wendy Schmidt Center. I'm delighted to
kick off the afternoon session and
introduce our next speaker Donna Pel. So
Donna is the chair of computational
systems biology uh at Sloan Ketaring and
is an HHMI investigator. Her lab's
research combines advanced genomic
approaches with various computational
techniques including machine learning to
address fundamental questions in
biomedical science spanning gene
regulation, cellular plasticity and cell
communication. Donna received her PhD in
computer science from the Hebrew Hebrew
University of Jerusalem and she has
numerous awards uh including the IC ISCB
Overton Prize in 2014. So with that,
let's welcome Donna for her talk on
decoding tissue architecture. Thanks so
much.
And so really things are fun and this
morning we saw super cool imaging
technologies and imaging is the name of
the
game
and there's lots of technologies and and
we saw incredible work in cell biology
but I would actually argue that for you
know my field of looking at tissues and
I call it painting molecules and adding
you know, hundreds of of RNAs and where
they are in this tissue and and dozens
of proteins, which is what we're able to
do now. Um, we still don't know how to
interpret these tissues. We're actually
not as advanced as my cell biology
colleagues. Even something as simple as
segmenting these cells is something that
we us our spatial transferics haven't
yet solved, uh, let alone interpret the
data. And one of the problems that we
suffer and this is why I'm a little bit
jealous of my cell biology colleagues
that we heard from you this morning is
that our problems are illdefined. They
come and you know uh Jennifer said go
find me something that looks exactly
like this ribosome structure that I've
resolved and that's what I want. It's a
very well-defined problem. You can train
an AI to do that and you can tell an A
to do that successfully.
you know we uh tissue biology people uh
are asking it interpret this image teach
me biology from it and you know AI is
not magical and uh we need to give it
you know in order to train it we need to
figure out what we want to ask it and we
need to give it the the right training
data in order to be able to ask it. So
that's where my field is at and uh you
know we've made I I'll tell you a little
bit uh progress that we made. We need
new algorithms. We need new foundations.
We cannot take chat GPT out of the box
and say let's throw it at this as well.
It just won't uh help us to get new
biology. And you know, if if you're in
this audience and want to do anything uh
meaningful, your goal should be I want
to use my my toolkit, my AI toolkit to
really advance our understanding of
biology and and help people in medicine
rather than, you know, just say, "Hey,
I'm doing AI." And so, you know, here's
a typical image. This is a slice of
premalignant pancreas tissue uh measured
with uh 480 molecules from zenium. And
as I said, we can't segment it. So this
is a really quick uh thing of of an
algorithm where we've made a tiny
progress. It's not perfect, but it's
benchmarked as the best. And you know,
here's a ground truth that we
collected. Here's what 10X gives you out
of the box. All the orange molecules are
contaminations. These are molecules from
completely different cells. If you
include these molecules in your
segmented issues, you're going to get
completely wrong biology. And you're
like, okay, why do you trust NX? But you
know, Baser, nothing else does better.
We've benchmarked everything and here's
how you get all the wrong things. So,
you know, there's just so many problems
with the problem of associating
transcripts to the right cell. Even if
you have perfect cell membrane
segmentation and so we just, you know,
build a heterogeneous graph of saying
these transcripts are next to each other
and these transcripts are next to a
nucleus and we're going to learn a a
latent of cells as represented by their
nuclei. and and uh transcripts so that
the transcripts are near and correct to
the right cell. That's what we train it
to do. And we train it using the more um
you know the more correct uh transcripts
on the nucleus. They're not perfect. We
say okay um those that align with the
nucleus are probably belong to that
cell. Those that are in a nearby nucleus
probably don't. We frame it that way.
And now we do link
prediction. And lo and behold, it's not
perfect. And we have like is this is
still work in progress even though it's
available. And you can see we do a much
better job and and we outperform on
metrics and get that sweet spot of of
you know not getting contaminations. The
solution of just looking at the nuclear
transcripts isn't good enough but also
uh not getting incorrect or or
infrequently getting incorrect
transcripts from other cells to get much
cleaner biology for all the downstream
analysis that we want to do. So now we
have this image uh which now we have
everything linked spatially. We can
assign the transcripts correctly to the
right cell and map it back to the
phenotypic landscape that we're used to.
And now we can have accurate cell phen
phenotypes embedded in
space. Yay. That's a well- definfined
problem. So I can solve it. But how does
one describe and interpret this image?
You know, no even, you know, let's
define some questions. What type of
niches? what type of environments exist
in this cell? Uh how do change uh change
when I perturb it towards malignancy
under drug?
Um you know the idea the problem is that
what do you mean what is a niche? You
have all these nice spots. How I need a
formulism for a niche? The reason single
cell uh genomics worked so well is that
we had a wonderful representation for
cells. It's a vector of the expression
of everything we've measured in that
cell. And we had a semi okay workable
definition for similarity. You know two
cells are similar if the L2 norm of
their expression is similar. And we
don't have that uh for niches and that's
a problem. So what I'm going to try and
tell you today in a pretty uh more
technical uh talk which I've gutted most
of the biology out is how do we begin to
try and tackle
that? And so the critical thing to get
anything to work is we need to be if if
we want the AI to help us. AI is
actually really dumb. It doesn't know
biology. It's not smarter than us. We
can't just give it images and saying you
know we can't figure it out so you do.
Uh we need to tell them we need to teach
it what what's meaningful and
specifically what is biologically
meaningful similarity between niches and
that you know is actually you know
stumping the field now for for about two
years because defining which two niches
you know you just have these little
snippets of images and and and tell me
if this little field of view of a of a
cell and it's like 10 20 neighbors and
this little snippet of another cell and
its 20 neighbor neighbors. Is it similar
or different? Is it meaningful? How
similar and how different? Even
something like that we haven't defined.
This is work mostly by Doran who
recently graduated from my lab. He
celebrated his defense uh two weeks ago.
And uh a lot of innovation is thanks to
him and not to me. But I'm going to tell
you his story. So again, we're going to
start with something fairly concrete.
We're going to take an anchor cell at
the middle and we're going to look at
its neighbors. You have to decide how
many neighbors do you do it by radius?
What resolution? I'm not even going to
go into that and I would say that
different resolutions give you different
biology. So if you ask me how big is a
niche I ask you what is your biological
question and we're saying that a niche
is a distribution. So we're going to try
and treat treat the anchor cell and its
behavior and its neighbors as a
distribution. And actually this is what
the field has been doing without even
knowing. most of the field is being is
collapsing this information this very
rich inter information to frequencies of
cell types. This is remnants from when
uh we had 30 markers and all they could
do is distinguish cell types. So if you
have 30 markers to distinguish cell
types then collapsing it and saying okay
I have three T- cells two myoid cells
two fiberblasts and three epithelial
cells that's all all you can barely do
and that's all you can get. But if you
have 480 transcripts representing rich
states and rich differences between
cells which you've spent a lot of money
to collect, collapsing it and throwing
most of the information out the window
is a wrong idea. So we want to keep as
much information as possible in our
distributions. So again, when are two
matrices uh similar? Here are two
matrices of cells and their neighbors.
Uh, and uh, you know, uh, some of you
know this because I've been doing this
for a while, but those of you who don't,
are these two
environments very similar, very
different? Who uh, sort of different?
Who thinks that they're very
different? Who thinks that they're, you
know, they're intermediate
different? Okay, who thinks that they're
very
similar? Most people don't want to vote.
They're identical. It's a permutation
and you can get this permutation by
rotating the image. I don't want the way
that the that the technician put the
slide into my microscope to make the
whole thing differently. So we need a
rich representation that's permutation
and variant and um we need it to really
not chuck away most of the gene
expression I worked so hard and paid so
much money to
collect. And uh again when you just take
um all the gene expression I mean this
is a a niche
um in you know this permutation
invariant this it looks at all the
expression mean that's been around for a
while now recently there's a couple
papers saying okay let's take the mean
of the niche but you can see these are
actually genuinely very very different
they're not permutations and we get the
same mean so we really have to stick to
the full distribution. ution. So we
started by working and this again we did
a few years ago uh taking one of my
favorite tools optical transport.
There's a couple people here who love
it. Optical transport is a very rich and
expressive uh uh language and uh you
know you can basically say okay we want
to find the permutation that makes this
most similar. That's really really nasty
computation but you know we we we don't
like permutations. we want to smooth
things. Uh let's just look for an op,
you know, a mapping, a probabilistic
mapping that's smooth, a soft assignment
that says, let me try and basically move
one distribution to the next.
And you know we were really happy for it
for a while and then discovered you know
as much as I love optimal transport you
know the you know I have data sets a
single posttock now is collecting data
sets of 15 million
cells a data set of 50k cells takes two
weeks on my most powerful GPU to compute
that is not scalable. So we were stuck
for a while like how do we handle these
big data sets with optimal transport? I
want to preserve a rich metric that
actually is is rich and biologically
meaningful and I want to run it on my 15
million cells and and counting and we
just saw data sets of you know 200
million cells and it's you know just
going to grow. So again each of these
niches is a point cloud. It's a
distribution of
distributions. And so, how do we model
this distribution of distributions? And
again, I'm going to give the credit
where it's due. This was entirely
Doran's aha moment. He got this aha
moment when he was giving uh journal
club on a paper that was using a
transformer. This is why actually giving
journal club can lead you to a you know
great insights by understanding other
people's ideas and being forced to
explain it to the group. something
clicks in your mind and it's like yes
this is exactly what we need a
transformer can is um you know
permutation environment the fact we
actually for like you know chat dpt
force it and tell this is the order of
the words the transformer itself
actually is is is permutation invariant
and it's you know you could take
different niche sizes it doesn't need a
a a a a standard input so we have this
transformer and we're going to take our
optimal transport distance and use a
transformer to learn an embedding that
actually um is an
approximation to um the optimal
transport distance in L2. So what we're
really going to take is really small
batches that we're going to choose. And
for each of these batches, we're going
to learn a latent and use optimal
transport distance in the training to
say we want our the distance of these
cells in the latent space to match their
optimal transport distance. We also want
to be able to decode. So we want the
optimal transport distance between you
know the original input and the decoded
input to be close according to this
optimal transport distance and and yes
it's a little bit you know heavy to
compute but because we need to train it
on just small batches then I have this
magical latent that then allows me you
know this is you know training I can
train very quickly in these small
batches and the latent actually works.
So once I've trained it on some pairs
and I have a latent and if it works then
I can now take any pair of cells and
compute their distance in L2 which is
very quick and if the latent is good it
will you know match optimal transport
distance and again we actually ran this
uh we ran a you know a a ground truth
for a month trained on a very small
subset and actually got incredible
accuracy. And I sometimes like to ask,
well, how well did we do and how well
can we do? And what makes me happy about
this is there's some theoretical
guarantees and I can actually look at my
data and and and know am I if I'm doing
well or not. Now, this is all published
in in in archive and in ICML
proceedings. So you know just to
summarize very quickly we can be
accurate if um our distance metric we
can embed our distance metric if our
dist met metric is
ukitian and unfortunately a metric is
ukitian if all its values are positive
and optimal transport is not ukitian. So
this is certainly not distance. So it is
impossible to get a perfect embedding.
So I asked, okay, how bad can we go?
Because you know, perfect is the enemy
of the good. And what really made me
happy is
that you know you can get really good or
or the the way you sort of break it is
by having a lot of negative values with
with heavy absolute value. So if your
actual signal, your real positive igen
values are really big relative to the
sum of these small values down here at
the bottom, then you have a really good
chance of doing really really well. And
this is fortunately the case of most
real world data sets uh that we've
looked at. So now we have this uh latent
space that approximates Waserstein uh
distance but it is fully L2 and we can
do all the fun stuff that we like to do
with all the power and the ease and
efficiency of L2 and I'm going to
actually bring airplanes because no
one's going to actually see cells and
say oh yeah that makes sense and you
know even computing the Barry center in
in in optimal transport space is is
really hard because you have to do all
the pair wise things and stuff But you
know computing the mean airplane in
uklitian space is is awesome. And
another thing that we really like to do
and we saw actually a lot of examples
today in the morning of of actually
something that that we do in latens is
interpolation. We can again do these
linear interpolations and take this
slant and turn it into a toilet
gradually in this L2 space and it
actually learns paths because our latent
space is a good approximation of
Waserstein distance a little bit of
biology and I said I gutted you know
most of the biology and the really cool
cancer stuff out but neurobiology is
very structured so it's very quick to go
through and you know here we have
Washington applied to to this neural
cortex text data. You know, this is the
UMAP data. And now we can actually say,
let me actually define archetypical
niches of this data set around uh these
uh inter neurons which are sort of
really small and they're dispersed and
they have very different niches. And we
can actually say, okay, find me
inside the latent. Now, what we're
looking at is the fusion component in
the latent that's approximating the
wormhole space. And okay, what does this
look like? And we see that this
latent in the wormhole space perfectly
recapitulates cortical depth of these
neurons. You know, here's the diffusion
component. Here is the cortical depth
mapped back onto the original image.
Now, we can look for these archetypicals
looking at Barry centers and see how
things change around in terms of
neighbors as you go up through the
cortical depth. And you can see that
things shift around. The neighbors shift
around. And even within a cell type,
let's look at the blue cell types, these
neurons right here. Here's how this cell
type looks at this depth. And you go a
little bit deeper and you see that the
same cell type is expressing genes in a
completely different way. So while the
cell type label has just collapsed this
information and if we were using just
cell type just the blue um then you know
you would have thought it's the same
thing. But look at how the the state of
these cells is so very different in
these different cortical depths. And
this sort of gives us these archetypical
behaviors of this is the typical niche
that you see at different cortical
depths in in the
neuron. Now I said interpolation. So I'm
going to you know Dorne tried to push
this forward and I actually thought it
would never work. I told him you're
crazy. And so he's saying, okay, so
let's actually try and take a cell and
predict its environment
uh generative AI. And so we're going to
use um diffusion uh flow matching. And
basically you have data. It's hard to
generate a sample from that. So you're
going to sample from noise and learn to
go from noise to a sample. That's what
the fusion does. You have a forward
process to learn a reverse process. And
what you really need to make this work
is interpolation. But I've just shown
you that I can do interpolation in this
washerstein space. So I could take the
classic flow matching algorithms. I can
sort of lift them into wa into the
washerstein space through the wormhole
embedding which now allows me to
approximate this you know
weirdasserstein space but in a uklidian
world and now go from noise to airplanes
uh in in this sort of space which allows
me to map entire distribution so this
space doesn't map single objects which
works in uklidian space it actually
allows me to map distribution ions in a
meaningful way actually using the
Waserstein uh optimal transport distance
between these distributions in an
embedding that approximates uh the
Waserstein space. So we can say okay how
does it look like on on these niches I
just showed you and this is like going
from noise to creating you know niches
that that look like real niches from
real data. This is entirely generated by
flow matching. And these niches actually
really ma match the examples I showed
you earlier except they're generated
from random noise at the beginning. And
if actually you look uh at the real
neurons and their environments versus
those that I you know pulled out and
generated uh from uh you know generative
AI, you can see that it actually does a
pretty good job. And you know, I was
shocked because I actually thought it
would never work. I'm a pessimist. So
why does it work? It's the scale of the
data. You know, we're we're learning
from, you know, millions of samples.
Each niche is very very different. We're
actually sampling a lot of biological
variability. These niches are very very
different from one another. uh this is
actually uh very different than some of
the perturbation challenges you said at
the beginning where your pertibbation
challenges are you know learned this
thing after we've sampled a small number
of samples that only take a fraction of
the space here we have a very large
number of samples that seem to capture
the space which is because some of the
things I can say is that these models
don't know biology and a lot of the
problem with these models and everyone
that uses them needs to be careful is
that They are still pretty bad at out of
sample distributions. Anytime you take
one of these algorithms that work and
you say look at how awesome it does and
look at my R squared, I ask you show me
it on out of sample and I'll believe
you. Here we cheated because all these
things I showed you wasn't out of
sample. So as long as I'm not out of
sample, it hasn't learned anything new.
And we're working to try and teach it to
learn something new now that at least we
gave it a metric of of real biology. But
I want to and and again this is
something that I I I I want to you know
warn you you know foundation models are
are great except for the fact that the
real ones trained on trillions of images
and you know we don't have enough images
yet to learn out of enough biology to
learn out of sample. And so where you
want to be in my opinion the sweet spot
for having impact is yes you can try and
build this is going to be a foundation
model in the future once we have you
know 20 billion patients where we've
like thrown the kitchen sink at it but
by then the AI architectures are going
to be really different. So my advice to
you is work where you can have actual
impact today on learning something new
learning new biology that you
know learning you know having a real
impact on medicine and that's currently
not the foundational models simpler
architectures are you know maybe less
sexy but they actually have enough
data to give us real progress in in
biology today. What I really like and
what personally excites me about this um
transformer that takes optimal transport
and embeds it into L2 is you could use
any easily computable optimal transport
distance. This actually gives us a
language where we can actually give rich
biologically meaningful uh distance
metrics between biological entities and
try and map them into a latent that now
has more biology imbued into it. So just
to give you a quick example, something
completely different. We saw some attack
this morning. I'm going to go through
this real quickly, I promise. Um I'm
going to now model distributions of cut
sites. So this is a taxi data and rather
than taking peaks and whatnot I'm going
to ask exactly what is the distribution
of each and every cut site and we see
that you know different places we have
very very different distributions of cut
sites. This is ex I mean this is earth
movers distance this is the simplest of
optimal transport distances that you
have and now we can take all these
attack uh regions. We take a region, we
could look at their cut sites and define
the optimal transport earth mover
distance in this case distances between
all these little snippets of of DNA uh
profiled with a
paxi and you know we we try and push it
a little forward. So this is the actual
chromatin accessibility data. You see it
has a really really rich shape and we
were like really excited at first. Then
we read Anchul's paper and we realized
most of it is actually uh PN5 bias. So
of course if you have that it's going to
create a lot of structure for any random
sequence of DNA irregardless of the cut
sites. So what we really want is the
signal beyond this TN5
bias and this TN5 bias isn't exactly
aligned. So again we use Anul's approach
to actually learn a function of this
bias using a simple net again like
classic nets that existed a decade ago
works perfectly and now we're going to
take the signal we're going to remove
the bias and learn an optimal transport
distance between uh the residual which
is what we care about and now we have
embeddings and we can actually you know
attack is really sparse so we can
aggregate these embeddings in different
ways here We're aggregating it at level
of transcription factor in a meta cell.
This is all the places where we have
CTCF motifs in a particular cell state
during hematocesis. We see that this has
a lot of structures. The cells are
colored by cell type and we see at
different cell types and different uh uh
uh progressions in hematis. we have very
very different cuts site distributions
for CTCFS which again both told us how
important it is how the the genome and
uh 3D genome is being completely
shuffled jiggered and jigged over the
course of of hematopolesis
um we can take another viewpoint and say
let's take a a specific region for and
and and look at how it changes across
cells so now we're going to take these
enhancers we're going to average them
we're going to sodtobulk uh But we're
going to look at the enhancer level and
we can see that there are very different
regions that actually now you know some
of them are TF bound by CTC or CTCF
bound some of them are repressed and
some of them are active and we can look
and see that this structure has real
meaning. We can find co- uh um binding
of CTCF CTCF with additional factors
CTCF with differential chro
modifications. These cuts sites
distributions have a very rich biology
so that we can extract very rich
biological interpretation from this
latent that we just defined. In fact, we
can even go towards a universal
chromatin expression. So people like to
go from um you
know sequence to expression from
promoter accessibility to expression and
there's lots of models that do that
really really well and we can use our
latent to do the exact same thing and
it's sort of almost as good as these
really high-end models that are designed
to predict sequence from accessibility
except what is the difference between
this latent that we learned uh from uh
the cut sites themselves
is you know these are very gene
specific. So if you actually use this
model on all genes rather than the
individual gene it trained for it
collapses to random noise. We can train
it on you know a subset of genes and
then run it on uh test genes and we've
actually learned something real about
accessibility that generalizes beyond
individual cut sites. a real example of
out of sample. Um, but this is passible
because we imbued our model with some
biological meaning and a distance metric
that has some biological meaning. So,
you know, what I hope we take out of
this beyond the fact that you should be,
you know, working on on fundamental
things that actually push biology
forward rather than the fanciest
architecture is that I'm hoping that
this tool allows you to take your
favorite problem, define, use the
awesome, expressive, powerful, flexible
language of optimal transport to define
what is a meaningful biological distance
between these entities. And then you
could use the wormhole transformer to
embed it into L2 and explore to your
heart's desires. We're using it right
now as a building blocks of a lot of
more fancy models to get a lot better
interpretations of images to distinguish
between cell intrinsic, cell extrinsic,
predict perturbations. But this building
block of a biologically imbued
um latent which actually has more
biologically meaningful distance metrics
is is something that I think really we
need this and more things like it to
push the field forward. Um I still have
money. So there are positions including
staff positions for those who don't want
to enter the academia right now. My
single cell innovation lab also has lots
of philanthropic money and we're hiring.
But really what's awesome is is my
group. This is Doran. Uh he did most of
uh what I told you about. And thank you
very
much. I think we probably have time for
one question.
Oh yeah, now you're getting back at me
for saying foundation models are bad.
Not at all. Great talk and this is
fantastic. Now my question is more about
the starting point to define the niches.
You say I represent a niche by a cloud
point, you know, a set of points and you
seem to forget about the relative
positions of the cells. And I wonder if
this is on purpose or if you think an X
version could be optimal transport on
not only the the values of the gene
expression but as well the relative
positions of the neighboring cells
because in a sense in in your current
interpretation if I understand correctly
you don't care about how they are
organized. We've played a little bit
with representation because you know
again I've smoothed out and this doesn't
work perfectly. So it's you know it
helps get biology but this is still work
in progress in terms of getting the rich
biology I hoped it would give uh the
exact order of of usually the exact
order of the cells around that their
distances don't impact things very much.
The thing that actually makes really
really big difference is how to actually
represent these cells. So when when we
are at these data sets which have 500
genes let alone some of these you know
cosmx 5,000 gene data sets uh actually
this thing you know optimal transport
doesn't work really really well you know
to go from such high dimension and so
actually featurization of the data and
how do I go and not represent all 480
genes but actually uh represent them
down to a 100 genes and again PC PCA is
too blunt. So basically getting better
featurizations uh that aren't the full
gene expression and not PCA as input is
the way uh that we've seen the biggest
impact and we're trying a bunch of
featurizations depending on the
biological question that that really
helped. That is that is where we need
more because we've pushed and and I
already know that even the
featurizations I've pulled out of the
hat are are not the best ones. So, um,
that's how to featurize the space is is
where the money is right now. But yes,
optimal transport allows you to do all
sorts of stuff. It allows you to go
multimodal. It allows you to represent
the geometry of the cells. It allows you
to to represent the distance. It's such
an expressive
language. Okay, let's thank the speaker
one more time then.
[Music]