good afternoon
everybody hi um I'm Sangita welcome to
the session nanom medicine for all um we
have a great uh session planned for you
today I'm going to start by just giving
a little bit of overview about what we
mean by nanom medicine for those of you
who aren't used to thinking about nanot
technology and medical terms um and then
we're going to have three fantastic
speakers um and we're going to close out
with a
panel
um okay so uh for this crowd I think
it's you're you're well familiar with
the idea of nanotechnology emerging from
a combination of top down fabrication
and bottom up synthesis um and
collectively now we have nanoscale
materials that have these fascinating
properties that emerge Optical
properties electronic properties
magnetic properties and this is all of
your world um what's been really
exciting for those of us like me who are
trained as a physician as well as an
engineer is that when you make materials
this small you can open up new areas
areas of biology and medicine these
materials are now right sized to talk to
biology and there are emerging nanoscale
biomedical properties as well as these
sort of physical properties so so what
does that look like first of all on the
left here you see that there are a
number of materials that have emerged
that have made it all the way into
clinical trials so these are materials
that were synthesized on the bench
characterized looked up for their safety
they had these emergent properties and
they're they're now in humans many of
you actually got one of these nanop
particles in the MRNA vaccine those are
lipid nanoparticles so those are
materials that have been in millions of
people um and what's so amazing about
them if you look at this sort of
molecular ruler is that the Nano scale
is actually the length scale at which
biology happens DNA is nanometer scale a
virus is 100 nanometers a cell is about
10 microns a single receptor is
something that you can interrogate with
one of these nanomaterials and as a
community studying nanom medicine which
is nanotechnology applied to medicine
for about 20 years researchers around
the world have been discovering new
properties and on the right here you see
some of the properties that we've
discovered about biological nanoscale
systems for example materials of
different size at the nanoscale when
injected in the human body will traffic
to different organs 100 nanometer
particle will go to the liver a 3
nanometer particle will go to the
bladder the shape of a material can
affect whether a cell internalizes it or
not if it's long and floppy or if it's
small and hard
you can make materials that actually are
activated by the human body by enzymes
or low PH or oxidative state so they're
bioresponsive and when you put materials
in the body they actually get coated
with proteins and biomolecules and that
those codings those interactions can
then direct where the nanomaterials go
so the combination of Nano
nanotechnology and medicine is giving
rise this whole set of new insights and
new capabilities that we are collective
really excited about and I hope you can
learn a little bit more about
today I just want to give you sort of
one last snippet which is that this is
an incredibly exciting time for those of
us in nanom medicine and that's because
there's a convergence of Decades of
science coming from two pretty disperate
Fields so on the top here you see the
convergence really of fabrication
Technologies and the speed at which
those have accelerated of course this
has really been driven by our
interesting computation collectively and
many of you work in this space but what
you may or may not know is there are
areas in biology and medicine and
chemistry that have been quietly
accelerating on their own and here I
give just one example which is the
example of RNA RNA being Advanced as a
therapeutic RNA interference mRNA
packaging of RNA into nanomaterials and
those two things really came together
over Co to scale up materials and as I
said to show that they were safe in
millions of people now the these same
materials are are being used to enable
crisper or genome editing so if you look
at the convergence of these time scales
in this moment of time um it's
incredibly powerful to think about how
we get to leverage all of this
engineering and all of this biomedical
work um and and think about ways to
combine
them um I run a center here at MIT uh
the marble Center for Cancer nanom
Medicine Kurt is actually here today and
we have a fantastic group of
investigators we're localized in the
Koch Institute we have collectively over
200 community members thinking about
some of these problems so please come
visit us we were super productive we
publish a lot about this we patent a lot
we've had a lot of startups um which
some of you may be um exposed to and
some of the ideas that we are really
excited about right now are listed here
the idea that you can intercept cancer
before it's lethal the idea that you
might be able to vaccinate in a
personalized way against cancer the idea
that you can precise ly treat cancer U
by knowing more about its genetic code
and finally really the theme of today is
how we can take all of these discoveries
and make them accessible to patients all
around the world um which is actually
not the case today as you know the lipid
nanop particles that I described to
require a cold chain they require being
frozen at minus 80 degre so we really
want to think about how we can enable
these medicines um spreading all around
the world so as I said come visit um
today we have some community members
here that you're going to hear from
we're going to start off with Muji gendi
and then Angie beler and then Bob Langer
and um then we're going to have a panel
um and take questions from all of
you so with that I'm going to briefly
introduce M Muji um he is the Lester
wolf professor of chemistry he trained
at Harvard the University of Chicago and
Bell Labs before arriving at MIT in 1990
to join the Department of Chemistry his
work on the basic concepts in Material
Science synthesis of high quality
nanoparticles and dots led to the 2023
Nobel Prize in chemistry his lab's
research ranges from the very
fundamental applications in
electrooptics uh to applications in
biology and he's going to tell us in
just 10 short minutes about what he's
thinking about now so welcome
[Applause]
mui well thank you Sangita and I'm
really delighted to be here um I'm going
to tell you about this this journey
start uh in the mid
1990s when uh the field discovered that
we could make really bright uh Quantum
dots of multiple colors with an
absorption where um uh that was uh
continuous into the visible and
especially at 465 nanometers which is
where the blue Gallum nitride diod that
were had just been invented and so that
meant that we can think about
multiplexing using one of these new new
fangled blue diodes and if we could
Target different parts of cells or do
indal
biology uh uh then we could image with
one light source but if only we could
get the quantum dots to be compatible
with Biology um and um so we were able
to do that uh in the late 1990s and then
I that's when I first met uh Bob Langer
because I went to his office and we were
um about to start Quantum dock operation
I had no idea what I was doing and so I
went to Bob and asked him for advice on
what to do with starting this company so
I started this company with Paul vados
and shiman vice at Berkeley and a couple
business and and so this
company's created the first product of
quantum dots coded so that they would be
able to target cells uh this was an
example from a a paper from that period
of time looking at a cell uh comparing
Alexa 488 which is a d labeling this the
skeleton of the cell and then the
nucleus being labeled with a quantum dot
showing the difference in in the uh
photo bleaching um so um that that is
actually a hard application of quantum
dots but we pursued it the easy
application is all over the place today
if you have any Samsung screens
somewhere here uh they're full of
quantum dots to to get the beautiful
green and and red colors at low
efficiency so when you you know as a
side note if you create something that's
more energy
efficient humans find a way to spend as
much energy so we just make it bigger
and brighter and it uses much energy so
you have these beautiful big bright
screens thanks to the quantum dots um so
but anyway so we had to learn how to
handle
nanomaterials um in the biological
environment we had to learn how to make
them non-sticky so that we could inject
in this mouse model here the reds are
the quantum dots the green is gfp so
that they would be able to get out of
the of the vasculature into the tissue
so we could access things that we wanted
to Target so we had to learn how to coat
these things you with PEG or or zionic
molecules we realized that size was
incredibly important we did some
biodistributions and realized that if
you wanted to have something that could
go in there Target and clear it had to
be probably less than about 6 nmet in
hydrodynamic diameter otherwise go to
the liver or just stick around for a
long time and you'd get this background
and so we worked very hard to make them
as small as possible and also we worked
hard to understand the effect of shape
this was work done with Rakesh Jane at
at MGH so we looked at different sizes
uh this is an a tumor micro environment
going from 12 nanometers to 125
nanometers in size and you look at the
penetration depth as the distance from
The Vessel up here you see that you know
the big ones 60 nomers they just just
don't go into the tissue at all they
just stay in the blood vessels so in
terms of delivery that's terrible the 12
NM one is able to penetrate out of the
blood vessels into the into the into the
tumor um then if you look at uh at the
effective shape U also uh so these are
two particles of different shapes mology
is the same volume same volume but if
you look at the the rod one like you
know it's pretty long but it's pretty
narrow you find again that the tumor
transport for the rod the red bar here
is much better than the sphere even
though they have the same volume so it's
a small it's a small Dimension that
really matters in terms of being able to
go through the vasculature into the
tissue and being able to
diffuse so um we learn how to Target
things in Vivo in ways so the these are
rare hematopoetic precursor cells that
um you know generally before in the old
days you'd have to take them out label
them and put them back in if you wanted
to in Vio but here we were able to show
that with a multicolor Imaging we could
take Quantum dots of two different
colors uh and and um which then go to
receptors that are overexpressed on the
on on these particular cells jointly
they're not um they don't uh label blue
hers blue so what you're really looking
for is yellow then in your microscope
and then you can find these very rare
cells in the uh in in in the this is in
the um in the bone marrow of this mouse
model and then and then you can look at
different ones of these and see where
where they uh where they reside and you
know eventually one would like to
understand about the micro environment
of these particular cells and so doing
this in Vivo is super important because
then you're not affecting them you're
not differentiating them you're looking
at them in their environment without
without uh disturbing them this is kind
of a hero experiment um uh and and so we
thought you know what are what are um
dos good for that D molecules aren't
good for one of the things it could be
good for is to go into the infrared
where tissue is less scattering and so
we worked again with with
Rakesh we created these composite
particles that are about 100 nanometers
why do we do that is because you can
actually see the individual particles so
if you want to track the individual 100
nanom particles that are floresent you
can actually see them in real time um so
we use regular dots the the four five
nanometer dots to label the the um the
arteries and the veins and the uh the
the the the tumor itself this is
actually uh separated in time because
the arteries come first then you wait
and the veins come out you know as the
particles clear then you wait more and
then everything clears except what's in
the tumor because it gets stuck in the
tumor and so you can label then the
different time snapshots different
colors to label different things then we
can go in with the composite particles
now we know where to look and we can
look at the disease tissue versus the
normal tissue and then we can see the
difference in flow and you see in the
normal tissue you know very fast flow
these are the little white dots are the
individual 100 nanometer particles uh
using uh you know uh basically Night
Vision Imaging and uh in the disease
tissue you see the flow is really not
great right so this is a real this is a
visual way of seeing why it's hard to
treat cancer you can't deliver it you
can't deliver Therapeutics Rakesh was
interested in figuring out how
to first uh use a therapeutic to change
the flow from something that was really
pendular you know not going anywhere by
snipping out the small the growth of
small small blood vessels for instance
to make it more like the normal flow so
you can actually deliver things you can
make it less acidic you know get oxygen
in there and all these things and so I I
really enjoyed this but then you know I
I was always interested in going into
humans and so we had learned a lot uh
from doing all this over the years we
applied this to uh FDA
approvable stuff this is the story of
lumel which was funded by the marble
family seed funded initially back in the
um early 2000s or late 2000s
actually and um and and so uh we created
this nanometer size object with die
quencher pair so that in attached with
the peptide so then the presence of a
solid tumor this peptide gets cleaved by
enzymes that are overexpressed in the
tumor releasing a d molecule which is um
which is uh fluorescent and what we
learned from the quantum dot work was
all about clearance and biodistribution
because given the specification of the
surgery we knew that we had to have the
injection early morning the surgery had
to be a few hours later you couldn't
have the injection the night before
because patients often just come in for
for you know outpatient surgery and so
it had to it had to become active within
a couple hours then it had to clear by
the end of the day you know within six
seven hours and so that defined the size
of the molecule right and had to clear
through the kidneys and so by defining
the size and defining all the little p
where were able to create this agent we
um combined it with a handheld Imaging
system that came out of our work on
being able to see single Quantum dots we
knew how to do things very sensitively
and uh I'm happy to say that after a
long period you know this company
finally got FD approval for fluorescence
assistance surgery back in April so now
they're busy scaling it up and hopefully
going to a commercial product for
helping breast cancer patients uh uh
very soon
basically uh first quarter of
2025 um another thing that I was
interested in was also this issue of
gatal linium which I think doesn't get
enough play what gatal linium is not is
used in uh in in MRI imaging I mean it
works really really well you know the
Radiologists love it it's just amazing
but it's got some problem G Lim is not a
normal element that you use in the body
and so it's been shown to accumulate in
the brain if you have multiple sessions
of this agent it's an environmental
problem like the Boston Harbor Tokyo Bay
San Francisco Harbor they're full of
gatal lium from the hospitals that are
around it and the patients get injected
they pee it out and uh turns out of iron
oxide if you make iron oxide really
really tiny and we made this really tiny
ligan that's zonic so that we could keep
the size to sub five nanometers in the
hydrodynamic diameter you can create an
iron oxide that looks like galenium it
reacts the same way it's a positive
contrast so you can see the injection
you can see the the arteries and then
the the bladder showing up in this case
these are slightly bigger agents about
23 minutes later the bladder is is is
full um you can see this beautiful
Imaging in this mouse and then if you
make it then you can look at the
biodistribution and see that you know
most of it comes out in the urine there
a little bit in the the liver um and if
you make it even smaller you you can
then try to think about actually
targeting with these small iron oxide
particles so now this is even faster so
by 10 minutes it's already gone into the
into the bladder this is mimicking the
biodistribution of
galum very well this is after five
minutes it's already going into the into
the kidneys and then um depending on the
size you can decide either to do imaging
of the of the blood flow or you can do
decide to Target into tissue uh we
applied this first with Peter Caravan
and Ellen jasenof at MIT
to look at um uh
at uh liver fibrosis and so this is an
image of on the right hand side here my
right hand side is a standard sha Mouse
and then the left hand side here is a
mouse that's been fed so that it create
it has this fatty liver and and this all
this collagen and you can see then the
uh The Binding so these Aron oxide
particles are bound with peptides that
bind to to the collagen and you can see
then the liver show up with these little
particles without using any gal ium so
anyway that's the end of my talk you
know learning how to use the nanop
particles was super important how they
interact with the body and I'm sure
you're going to hear more from the other
speakers next our speaker is Angie
Belcher she is the James Mason crafts
professor of biological engineering at
MIT she received her PhD from UC Santa
Barbara in chemistry her work on novel
nanoscale materials has been Rec
recognized by many prizes including the
MacArthur genius award and the lemelson
prize her lab seeks to understand and
harness Nature's Own processes in order
to design technologically important
materials in medicine which you'll hear
about today but as you all may well know
she also works on energy and the
environment um she's a close
collaborator and it's a real thrill to
have her here
welcome um thank you so much it's uh an
honor to be part of this uh this panel
um what a great topic uh and great panel
um I have been working on nanomaterials
my entire adult life um I have been
fascinated with natural uh materials
like like Abalone shells how Abalone
make U materials these are biomaterials
made by an organism the reason they're
so beautiful and so tough is because
they have a protein that makes it and
controls this type of of material um I'm
really lucky to work with s and part of
the the marble Center and um and Paula
Hammond as well two of my my best
collaborators um and I'm going to talk
about some of the work that we're um
that we're working on
today um so I work at the interface
between nano technology in in uh in
biology um and in applications and so we
work on energy Health Care in the
environment and just like this organism
the Abalone um used proteins and used
DNA to make proteins to control exquis
init control over calcium carbonate
nano-based materials what our lab has
done is evolve organisms to have
proteins to genetically control anything
we want on the periodic table uh and
we've worked on I think 135 materials in
the last couple of years that now we can
genetically control at the nanoc scale
so um I always say I've never been
accused of focusing um and we we focus
on making these nanomaterials for all
these different applications from energy
to the environment to uh Therapeutics
and we've spun out several companies on
this today I'm going to focus on on uh
Imaging um so um we work also like in
Professor Bundy's um very beautiful talk
we also work on on Imaging with
nanomaterials um and we also work on not
Imaging with um with without label so
label free Imaging and we use
hyperspectral Imaging and Hyper diffuse
Imaging in near ir1 um and near ir2 so
we're interested in imaging between
about 800 and 1,800
nanometers um and hypers um spectral
imaging has been used um for a long time
for non-destructive food inspection and
remote sensing but when you shift to the
near IR when you shift to Imaging above
a th000 nanometers you start to be able
to see things at much greater depth as
as Professor buend showed a few minutes
ago um and we developed a technology
called dolphin um which um which we can
look up to 8 cm inside of a um of a
tissue or an animal to look for um for
tiny
tumors um and we we develop these data
cubes we do three 3D reconstruction on
it U I wanted to to tell um us well okay
so one of the things that's really
interesting as was referred to before is
you know when you start to sh shift to
these wavelength there's less dyes and
um probes that you can use so there's
organic dyes that are uh in the uh in
the IR they don't tend to be as stable
there's um Quantum dots which we learned
a lot about there single um tube carbon
uh single W carbon nanot tubes and rare
earth nanop particles and so we're using
an indium Gallum Mara detector to to
look um at tissue and samples at depth
and so in my lab we've worked on
developing many different kinds of
nanomaterials to be able to look at
these um some of which are making um
single wall carbon nanot tubes U
brighter some are using plasmon enhanced
near1 D um to look for tiny tumors and
ovarian cancer as well as rare earth
nanop particles for doing uh single cell
tracking I want to show you an example
of something that we went from idea to
Clinic um in 3 years and this is a
collaboration with my um postto Jeremy
Lee shown here um this work was all
funded um through the um through the
marble um Center at at MIT we actually
applied for NIH um funding for this
twice and got um got rejected um but the
idea was that um that we could use um
short wavelength infrared and orthogonal
polarization to see lymph nodes and so
what you see um up here is um what this
is human tissue where there's a lymph
node you really can't see it but if
you're Imaging it uh at particular
wavelengths and particular polarizations
you can see the difference in contrast
for the for the lymph nodes and so what
um what Jeremy incision Vision did and
we want a a best 2023 invention and also
a moonshot from um President Biden for
for this is we um we invented a
technology where when a patient's
undergoing colon cancer um they take a
bunch of tissue out and they take a
bunch of tissue out and they probe with
their fingers to find lymph nodes and
they have to look for 10 at least 10
different lymph nodes it's different for
different kinds of surgery um what what
Jeremy did was invented a technology
that when that that tissue comes out of
the patient it goes over to um a
technology called Envision where you can
quickly count how many lymph nodes there
are you go okay here's 10 lymph nodes I
don't have to go back and get more and
so it actually really speeds up the
process of uh looking for lymph nodes
and classifying them for disease and so
um we it was um idea to clinic in 3
years we're now in 15 hospitals and
multiple companies and looking at breast
cancer colon cancer and prostate uh
cancer and so this was this was all
based on this um near uh Imaging and so
um there's all these lymph nodes uh in
the body um and the idea was to use a
combination of uh of NE um and
polarization to be able to find the
right wavelength to be able to pull out
these materials and this is in a mouse
you you can see the lymph node here you
can actually see this is all without
staining you can see lymph vessels um
here we're looking at adant response
during monitoring in real time in mice
and this is before the adant and 24
after so it's very non-invasive way of
uh of Imaging um animals or or people
samples and then you can really get a
lot of new information about lymph nodes
inside the body and look at size
symmetry border Clarity um vessel
patterns and from there start to try to
um understand and predict dis disease
and we've done that in triple negative
breast cancer where we we have um
animals that we're monitoring on a
day-to-day basis or twice a day um
monitoring changes in the lymph nodes
and what we see is that there's this
great increase in lymph node size um in
the animals that end up um becoming
metastic okay that's that story that's
all label-free Imaging so I'm driving to
work one day and I'm I'm listening to
the news and I hear about this um this
asteroid called asteroid benu have you
heard about this asteroid before so I
don't work on asteroids I would love to
work on asteroids I do not but what what
NASA did was they they sent a probe 63
million miles to an asteroid that was
traveling at 63 um 63,000 mil per hour
and is about 16 1 ft uh across they
landed on it they grabbed rocks from it
they did a biopsy of an asteroid moving
in space collected them took pictures
and sent it back back and you can see
the the uh the images I mean there it is
they have pictures of it landing and
this is an incredible feet and it cost
$1.16 billion which was well worth it
right but and yet in 2024 we cannot go
this far inside of a woman's abdomen to
find a 1 mm tumor you can't tell me
that's not possible if we can biopsy an
asteroid surely we can look this far
inside of an abdomen to find a tiny
tumor so I think that we just haven't
tried hard enough we haven't had enough
Engineers working on it and so we think
it's unacceptable so here's the team
that's working on this um you all know
Sangita Paula Hammond kppa Varanasi and
our um our collaborator Becky Stone
who's head of gynecological oncology um
at John Hopkins we think that you should
be able to diagnose ovarian cancer at
much early stages at stages where you
can also intercept it um so why ovarian
cancer one woman is diagnosed with stage
three or stage four every three minutes
worldwide the fiveyear survival rate is
39% for stage four and 177% for stage
177% for stage 4 um and this the
survival rate has not improved in 20
years
okay um the the the rates haven't in
improved um and there's a lot there's a
lot that needs to be understood about
ovarian cancer and so I I um am not
accepting that so there was a large
scale clinical trial out of the UK
recently which said that patients that
underwent CA 125 um blood test um and
transvaginal ultrasound there was no
increase in
survivability which means there is no
screen for ovarian cancer and again as
an engineer you throw up your hands you
said impossible there has to be a way of
being able to detect it detect it early
here's another thing about ovarian
cancer is that ovarian canc doesn't come
from the ovaries 85% of ovarian cancer
comes from the fallopian tube it's a
fallopian tube origin it comes from the
fallopian tube it sits on the Fallopian
tubes for sometimes up to 9 years before
it starts to to become cancer and starts
to metastasize we have a window of years
to be able to detect it and intercept
before it becomes stage two stage three
stage four when it is
treatable um and so what happens is you
have a little mutation called a p53
mutation it starts to come into
something called a stick stick lesion
and then develops into ovarian cancer
over a year period of time now we also
know that women that have their
Fallopian tubes taken out this is also
another large scale clinical trial out
of Canada um women that have their
Fallopian tubes taken out after
childbearing years zero cases of ovarian
cancer it's a way of preventing ovarian
cancer is removing your fallopian tubes
which says that it's another way of uh
of of showing that it comes from the uh
the Fallopian tubes so we've embraced
the goal of developing accessible
detection and Diagnostics technology for
ovarian cancer in the next 5 to 10 years
and that's with my partners and we won't
accept um failure on this this is
something we plan on doing one of the
ways we're doing it in my lab is we're
taking that technology that we talked
about called dolphin earlier and some of
the the work from Invision um and we've
uh developed something called EK to be
able to scan Fallopian tubes that come
from the o o so it was during the
pandemic and I was on it was during the
pandemic and I was on a zoom call and my
I met Becky Stone who's a surgeon at
John's Hopkins and she was saying that
when a woman uh has her phian tubes
taken out sometimes opportunistically um
as a way of preventing ovarian cancer or
if she has a genetic mutation that leads
to ovarian cancer that they take the the
tubes are like about this big they take
the tubes and they embed them in wax and
they cut them and they look at 0.1% of
them she goes if only we had a way of
looking at a whole fallopian tube i' met
her before but I instant messaged her
which is advanced technology for me um
and I said we can design a system to do
that it's actually pretty easy so we
adapted dolphin to EK so now when a
patient under goes um has her Fallopian
tubes removed from John's Hopkins
they're put into organ transport media
and FedEx to us overnight where we scan
the whole fallopian tube either using
nanoparticle probes for particular
markers for pre-cancer lesions or
collecting enough data using
hyperspectral Imaging to try to look for
interesting spectral characteristics
that would show us that the pathologist
needs to go in and look
here I was really overconfident I'm a
professor so I don't actually do any of
the work I was overconfident that my
students could actually do it and they
did um they we also used these um IR um
dyes which are not very bright or very
stable but when you complex them with
Nano particles of gold it actually makes
them U much much brighter um and this is
the the team that is uh working on these
and our idea is to move diagnosis back
to where it can be treated um much much
easier and much much
better um here's what a fallopian tube
looks like it just came out of a patient
um it comes to us um we track it um with
asset Panda um we start Imaging and so
when I would go to these meetings um um
Radiologists would say Fallopian tubes
are
invisible uh you can't see them by um
contrast enhanced CT can't see them by
Ultra sound they're invisible and I'm
like an engineer I'm like okay they're
not invisible right you have to be able
to be able to to find them and so when
you find the right wavelength of
exitation and the right wavelength of of
emission They're Not Invisible so we
hyperspectral scan them we find these
wavelengths that works and so now we can
we can follow them um and this is a a a
patient that um that we scanned we found
a region um and we marked it we sent it
back to John's Hopkins where they took
it and they they went to our Mark they
did pathology on it and they found an
adnormal region that was
250 um micrometers in size so you would
have never seen it um otherwise so we
scanned a 5 cm tube and found a a a a
pre-cancer lesion that was 250 microns
and so you say well that's kind of cool
what do you do there well now um
um now Sangita is going in and trying to
find biomarkers for these so so we're
doing the Imaging Sangita is looking for
biomarkers and ways of amplifying the
signal so you'd be able to tell from
urine blood or um or other uh fluid um
that you actually had a pre-cancer
Legion um Professor varasi is going in
with technology he's developed to pick
up some of these cells so we can culture
them live because there are no cultures
alive of these pre-cancer lesions and
Paula Hammond is working on developing
um layer by layer um Therapeutics
Immunology Therapeutics that would
actually work on trying to treat a very
early pre cancer lesion or maybe even
prevent it we're also looking at
vaccines can you develop a vaccine for
pre-cancer lesion so that the patient
never develops aarian cancer so we also
um are on a platform this was uh
developed by uh Dr Gross um John's
Hopkins and pit to where we're trying to
to turn on its head um like the
Henrietta LAX idea of um of your not
having your control of your own samples
so um there's an app that the patients
get yet they know that their Fallopian
tubes were taken out they see them going
to uh MIT they see images of their
Fallopian tubes um they can uh interact
with the scientist and they can they own
their own bios specimen they they track
their own bios specimens um we say this
is bed to bside and back again um but it
is a team effort it's a team effort of
all these scientists and Engineers
Physicians and the patients the patients
are an active an important part of this
and so thank you for your attention
[Applause]
you can see why we're having so much fun
um in the nanom medicine space um okay
uh last but but not least we're so
excited to invite Bob Langer here he is
one of nine Institute professors at
MIT um Bob trained at Cornell and MIT
before joining the faculty in 19 1978
his work on materials for sustained drug
delivery and Engineering new tissues has
been recognized by so so so many awards
but um I'll just list a couple the US
national medal of science the US
national medal of technology and
Innovation the Queen Elizabeth prize for
engineering and the Breakthrough prize
in life sciences Bob's patents have been
licensed to over 400 companies across
pharmaceutical chemical biotech and
medical device sectors and he is the
most cited engineer in history a current
focus of the lab is the study and
development of polymers to to deliver
DNA and RNA and genetically engineered
proteins continuously and at controlled
rates for prolonged periods of time it's
a great pleasure to invite
[Applause]
Boba well thank you boy I I really
enjoyed the the talks that's just great
work that mie and Angie are doing
um so I thought I'd tell you a little
bit about how I got started in this area
which was very I think kind of unusual
so my background is chemical engineering
and when I got done with my degree in
1974 you know for those of you that were
old enough I was 50 years ago there was
like this gas shortage and if you lived
in Boston you actually had to wait in
line for two hours to get your car tank
filled up but the consequence of that is
that if you were a chemical engineer you
got a lot of job offers from oil
companies and pretty much all my
classmates that's what they did and I
thought that's what I do too so I you
know I actually got 20 job offers from
oil companies four from Exxon alone and
and and really I wasn't that good at all
but they just had so many openings but
when I went to some of these you know
they tell you you know if you could just
increase the yield of of one of these
Petro chemicals by a tiny percentage
they said that'd be wonderful be worth
billions of dollars but I remember
flying back to Boston that night from
Texas
thinking to myself that I I really
didn't want to spend my life doing that
so I started to think about other ways I
could use my chemical engineering
background to to to help people and I I
won't go through the whole story but in
the end what I did is I had this idea of
maybe doing something in medicine
because nobody would hire me for a lot
of other things so I wrote to a lot of
hospitals and medical schools and and
none of them would write me back but
finally one of the people in the lab I
was said to me he said Bob there's a
surgeon in Boston at Harvard in
Children's Hospital named Judah folman
and he said sometimes he hired unusual
people he he thought very highly of Dr
folkman I won't say what he thought
about me but Dr folman had this idea
that if you could stop blood vessels you
might be able to stop cancer and that
and that it was actually mediated
chemically which turns out it was a
super controversial idea since I didn't
know anything about biology I thought it
was a great idea but um at any rate one
of the biggest problems or the biggest
problem is there's really no way to
study blood vessels because wherever
you'd go there were background blood
vessels except for a couple places like
the corne of certain animals and the
chick coral and Tech membrane had
actually very few so what we our idea
was we put certain tumors in in in these
tiny little animal eyes and then we need
a tiny which would cause blood vessels
to grow but then we needed a a tiny
delivery system like a nanoparticle or
microparticle that could deliver large
molecules our Dr folman's theory was
that they were all and mine too was that
they were all large molecules that would
do this so at this time 1974 the idea of
having an advanced Drug delivery system
you know was pretty much unheard of
there was only one company in the world
company called alza uh that was
developing these systems and late they
had done approved but later they'd come
out with what are called transdermal
Delivery Systems and things like that Dr
folman was on their board he went out
there he asked them could they help but
they all told them it was impossible
they basically Bally said that the
molecules that we were talking about
were too big it's like walking through a
wall so uh but if we were going to solve
the the the um the blood vessel problem
we had to solve this bioassay problem so
I spent several years working on this
experimenting with different materials
lipids polymers other things uh
different designs uh different
procedures and I actually found over 200
different ways to get this to not
work but but eventually we were able to
make little microparticles
like shown on the left or nanop
particles cut in half on the right and
we published in the journal Nature in
1976 for the first time that you could
release any large molecules also the
first uh study that ever showed you
could deliver nucleic acids which would
include DNA and RNA now uh I would like
to tell you that this met with you know
people were very excited about it but in
fact it was kind of the opposite I
remember three months before this I got
asked I was giving a talk at a major
scientific meting meeting it was
actually the first talk in my life that
I gave at one of these meetings I was it
was 48 years ago uh in Michigan and I
practice this talk for weeks into a tape
recorder and finally the day came and I
got up and I gave the talk and you know
I felt I did all right I didn't forget
too much what I was going to say or
stammer too much so I thought when I was
done with this talk all these older
engineers and chemists being nice people
would would want to encourage me this
young guy but when I got done I stepped
off the podium and a whole bunch of them
came up to me and they said well we
don't believe anything you just said um
and and and this again they said the
molecules were too big and the solvents
we were using like methylene chloride
and and ethanol would destroy whatever
we put in and actually things went
downhill for me from there if that were
possible I tried to get research grants
to support my work and my first nine
were very soundly rejected and then you
know I love being a postet children's
hospital but a lot of my friends said
you know maybe you shouldn't do that
your whole life and so I I did I started
looking for faculty jobs and since I'm a
chemical engineer I applied to chemical
engineering departments no chemical
engineering department in the world
offered me a position I finally got a
job in the Nutrition department here
it's a long story I won't go all into
that but anyhow so um but so so anyhow
but I and then I had some other ideas
munie referred to one of them that was
maybe a little bit different I I I
wanted to see the work I did get get to
out to the world and I was so naive I
thought if I published papers people
would just use them it didn't work out
that way um but so I also wrote patents
and then I even got involved in starting
companies and as Zang mentioned
licensing things to companies and
because of that which actually had a lot
of opposition and ridicule also even at
MIT back almost 40 50 years ago there
were a lot of products based on on this
uh you know all over the world from
companies we've started or worked with
uh ranging from new treatments for
prostate cancer uh endometriosis
schizophr all kinds of things hundreds
of millions of people you use these
these are all like implants or
microspheres but if you didn't use them
the drugs would get destroyed uh even
opioid addiction is up there from one of
the things we started but that being
said you know when like I say a lot of
these might be
microspheres or even implants like the
drug alluding stent which I put up here
U but the thing is is that when you make
particles smaller you can using the
approaches we wrote in the nature paper
it works but sometimes they stick
together and Aggregate and and sometimes
macras eat them so working with Vladimir
torchilin and others we had this idea
you could take something in Miralax like
polyethylene glycol and coat these and
that was a paper we wrote 30 years ago
uh cited uh I think about 4,000 times
and you could even go further and put
targeting molecules on these which only
faric Asad did in our lab I always
explain this badly but Nova the TV show
they made a video of what we did and
it's so much better explanation than
anything I could do so here it is he
starts with a nanop particle of
anti-cancer drug that gets encased in a
plastic that releases the drug over time
that in turn gets a special wrapping
that disguises the package as a water
molecule to fool the body's immune
system and last but not least the
address where it should be delivered
a key that will only fit the lock of
cancer
cells yeah you can see why it does a
better job than I do um I should say a
lot of the clinicians I work with tell
me it doesn't really blow the cell up
like that but the idea is you could use
this for small molecules or for genetic
therapy you could use these approaches
for with lipids or polymers and so forth
and one of the things of course over the
years and you know we've worked on these
for a long time but if you look at
various people including Phil sharp at
MIT and and others they say really if
you want to deliver genetic therapies
the biggest problem to solve would be um
would be delivery and so over the years
I felt we could do that and even start
companies in that there were about five
things that we did one showing that you
could deliver nucleic acids back in that
nature paper even though people said it
was impossible that then the idea of Peg
then the idea of what's called I
ionizable substances because if you make
things charged initially it might cause
toxicity but if you so if you make them
neutral at regular pH and then get
charged inside the cell they can get in
out out of the endone Dan pack who's now
at University of Kentucky postto of ours
and David putam showed this in the year
2000 and then other people uh Advanced
that in the lipid field as well then Dan
Anderson who was a post With Me Now full
professor at MIT had this idea of making
thousands of different lipids libraries
so you could have your choice of what
ones are going to work well and finally
roohi carnik who was a postto with me
now a professor at MIT in mechanical
engineering had the idea of using micro
fluidics to to make a lot of these and
so all these were published you know
something like 20 years ago so I I
certainly and we had patents on some of
them so I thought well you could create
these products so a couple companies I
thought I'd just give an example uh this
is on this is from Al nyum which Phil
sharp was a founder of and I was on the
founding scientific Advisory Board this
product was the first uh nanop particle
approved by the FDA for delivering uh
RNA it was actually done by aenna Kink
who was MIT student working in in my lab
uh started uh and and now he's CEO of
his own company and then of course the
other one that I should show you which
was alluded to by Sangita early on is I
I helped start this company with new
baray and whose thesis committee I was
on and now on the MIT Corporation um and
and two others to create nanop particles
that could protect messenger RNA and of
course that led to the covid vaccine
which is now used all over the world um
and and you see almost every other
attempt at at trying to make this
vaccine didn't really work uh only two
companies madna and bio entech both
using lipid nanop particles and
messenger RNA got these approved and and
that's the tip of the iceberg you're
going to see I think new cancer vaccines
and other things on the last slide I
just wanted to say areas that maybe we
can do better on and these are things
that we're actually working on with
funding from the from the marble Center
and from The Gates found and from with
Bill Gates but and I'll just really list
them but reactogenicity could you
immunogenicity could you make them less
immunogenic so that if if you gave a
drug you know you wouldn't get an immune
reaction more immunogenic maybe having
what's called ad property so that you
could get a better long even a better
immune response longer shelf life which
Sangita actually mentioned in her very
introductory remarks so you can ship
these all over the world Anna Jackal
lenic in our lab working with the Gates
Foundation has been doing a lot of work
on that targeting to specific cells
which Dan Anderson and I have been
working on other materials there's all
kinds of materials that may be useful
right now when you use lipid
nanoparticles people use four but maybe
you don't necessarily need that many and
could you come up with with things that
might work better than Peg finally could
you cross barriers that right now you
cannot cross like the bloodb brain
barrier which could be helpful in
Alzheimer's and other diseases so those
are just a few of the things that we're
thinking about and working on and thank
you very much for for having
[Applause]
me thank you Bob well thank
you you can go all the way down
then middle thank
you all right well um for those of you
not in medicine hopefully that was a
little bit of like rapid fire medical
school education and you're excited
about what nanotechnology can do in
medicine um this is a time for some Q&A
from the audience we have a whole bunch
of things coming in on this um
fancy new app I don't know what we call
this um let's
see maybe we can start with there's some
pretty specific questions um and
interest on near infrared wavelengths um
maybe for um Muji and and Angie thinking
about you know what's the promise of
near infrared Imaging how far can things
go how could we make it better do we
need new materials what are your
thoughts on
that um how I think it's a um very
exciting uh field I think there's a lot
of opportunity because I think it's an
early development um I don't know if you
mean how far can it go in terms of how
deep can it go the deepest we've gone is
about 8 cm and it depends on the
material type right now um I mean that
it depends on the the type of uh of
tissue um and do we need new materials I
think that we definitely need new
materials um U and I think that m showed
some really uh exciting new materials
around that that area um you know we
hope to be able to to use it um for um
actually uh ovarian cancer um breast
cancer and colon cancer in the next few
years and we're working on um
technologies that you'd be able to to
see it um you know inside
patients great M yeah so I I think uh
it's a very exciting area um I think the
label-free work that you've done I think
there's a lot to do there as well just
because you know normal tissue doesn't
really flues in the near for in the swe
um but pathological tissues tend to have
some signature there so you can you can
uh do multispectral imaging there and
really see things new materials would be
great different kinds of uh Optical
tricks like what you've done with the
polarization for instance um you know I
don't know how deep you can go but
there's a lot of lot of things you can
do without going too deep there are many
parts of the body where you can don't
have to go more than a few centimeters
in to really see things um so I think
there's a I think there's a lot to do
there for sure yeah I think that's a
great point I mean one thing that may
not be on everyone's radar is the
advances in surgery um you can actually
get into most compartments now with
robotic surgery or endoscopy and and so
you know you could probably get pretty
close to almost everything actually even
for Optics yeah
um so there's another question I think
we talked about the excitement of
getting these Technologies into patients
and a challenge in medicine which is
appropriate is that um you know we have
regulatory bodies that we have to um
collaborate with u and I I'm curious
maybe starting with Bob first how
um do you have advice for how how to do
that or how has it changed I know when
we started the cancer center for
nanotchnology excellence that you and
Ralph Co almost want to say 20 years ago
right now um you know the NIH was trying
to reform its approach to nanotechnology
and they started a toxicology service
how have you seen um you know the
regulatory bodies change their
perspective or not over the over the
years yeah well I think that I mean it's
a great question I don't know that
they've changed it that much I mean in
an Emer there's a couple times that you
know I mean in general are very
conservative I mean the idea is first Do
no harm
and so and I think always the the
concern that you might do something bad
is there but there have been a couple
cases couple situations both in the AIDS
crisis uh back in the 90s uh and more
recently with the co uh you know issue
where they approve things much much more
rapidly I mean I think at the end of the
day people make it they make a decision
right which is the risk reward ratio
that that when the risk is so high and
so many people are dying and there's no
real treatment then then they do things
faster in terms of advice I mean really
I mean I think that what you do is you
want to bring them in early rather than
later you know if you have a product
that's different you know it's good to
talk to some of the people there or who
used to work work there um so but but I
mean it's it's a long road yeah I think
precedent and collaboration are are
really important and as you point out I
think now that these materials have been
in so many millions of people at least
that's a precedented material right that
we can leverage for other applications
so you talked about cancer vaccines or
other applications of those same four
lipids um you hopefully the hurdles for
them will be less High um because
they've been shown to be safe at least
in some
applications mui we were talking before
the session about um The Long Road the
long road and also um um sort of parsing
the different sections of the FDA right
there's a drug Division and a device
division can you tell us a little bit
about how so for instance the example of
lumicell was a drug device combination
where we invented a handheld device to
be able to look within the surgical
cavity for for fluoresence that was
generated by this this agent which was
regulated under the the drug division
because it was an injectable and it was
a small a relatively small molecule is
a nanometer size but still drug likee um
and so those two those two regulatory
buies just don't talk to each other and
so the device division was extremely
enthusiastic and tried to bring the drug
division along but you know they they
just so it made it twice as hard
basically uh to to get approval but I
think there is approval now and there's
a
protocol that they've developed to talk
to each other better and hopefully in
the future that will Grease the wheels
the rular regulatory Wheels yeah it's a
proof of concept that it can be done it
will be a precedent Angie I think that
um that in the case of San Vision um
what um what Jeremy the the co-founder
did was was quite um you quite brilliant
which is uh he developed a technology
that in the end the in test still goes
through regular pathology so the
technology that that he developed was a
way of getting samples more quickly into
the pathologist hands so um uh there
wasn't the same kinds of FDA regulations
so that the next step is um for that
technology is um um working on um
Inhumans and during surgery but I don't
think things will go as invention wise I
think they'll go as fast but um but
Regulatory and uh acceptance will not be
as fast as it was in that in that case
and he he thought about this long and
hard um he he was very smart in in that
yeah I think you know another
opportunity in our space and that for
early innovators is thinking about that
clinical workflow and how to design your
materials and and really where where in
that process to be you mentioned you
know you have to inject in the morning
of the surgery and and you're talking
about accelerating decision- making for
pathologist but not taking the
pathologist out of the lube which is
super important um so I think that is a
real important part of the ideation we
have a couple minutes left so maybe we
could just do rapid fire um I'm going to
ask you all what you're most excited
about in nanom medicine um and I'm going
to start with Bob and come this way well
I I mentioned one of them in the talk
like Target you know can you target
right now you can Target nanop particles
to the liver pretty easily but not to
really other parts other cells or other
parts of the body including ining cancer
cells so I mean I'd be excited about
that so we Dan Anderson and I are
working on those kinds of things great
Angie U I love working directly with um
the surgeons and I love working with
patients I see them in clinic I see them
before and after surgery I love getting
to know them um and it makes me even
more passionate about really trying to
make an impact on ovarian cancer and
that is what I'm most excited about is
trying to impact um patients lives in a
a positive way as an engineer I never
thought that would be possible um you're
a physician and engineer so you know
it's it's possible but um so I'm excited
about that amazing I would say that
working very closely with the clinicians
you actually are both so you can work
closely with
yourself you know learning what what the
specifications of what you're trying to
do have those are super important you
can invent the greatest thing but you
know like this injectable if it takes
three days it's a non-starter right that
we did and so knowing ahead of time what
are the constraints so that you can
design around the constraints I think
and we know how to do that in in the
Nano world we just have to make sure
that we talk to the clinicians ahead of
time before we start inventing things
yeah well I think all three of you are
great examples of Team science and um
and why we're on such an important
precipice for the field so thank you
very much thank you thank you
[Applause]