All right. Uh I want to introduce our
next speaker. We have uh Hammed Okravi.
He's visiting us from MIT Lincoln
Laboratory. He's a member of the senior
staff in the cyber security and
resilient systems group there. And he's
going to share his thoughts on cyber
security today. So let's hear it.
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone. Thank you Jim. Uh as
Jim mentioned, I'm a senior staff member
at MIT Link Laboratory and today I'll
talk about uh securing the stack. I'm
going to talk about cyber security. Um
I'll start by sort of motivating the
problem by looking at what the main pain
points are today and then I'll talk
about some of the technologies that
exist in this area. They're nent
technologies here. There are
technologies that being that are being
built that would help to address some of
these issues. Uh and uh some of them are
built in our group in our lab. Some of
them are being built at other places. Uh
but let's get to it. So
in any area it's helpful to first look
at the trends in that area to see which
way things are shifting. Uh same is true
in cyber security. So if we look at uh
for example the amount of investment
that's being made in cyber security this
is both public and private investment
total dollars uh it is encouraging right
it's going up it's trending upwards uh
it's close to $70 billion being spent
every year in cyber security again both
public and private sectors uh so that
means more and more attention and
investment is being made in in cyber
security but then let's look at the
outcomes are we getting the outcomes
that we expect to get with this
investment? The other two uh two charts
on the top left and bottom right uh top
right and bottom left uh are some sort
of essentially some of the outcomes that
we should see. The first one is showing
the number of software vulnerabilities
that we discover year-over-year in these
uh in these in applications that we use
in data centers and sort of in general
purpose computing. Uh but the trend is
not downward. It's not even plateauing.
It's going up, right? And in some ways
it's exponentially going up. Uh so what
is happening? Uh but it's not just the
number of vulnerabilities either. If we
look at the amount of damages that's
being caused by data breaches in terms
of monetary damages, those are also
trending up, right? So we are spending
more and more in cyber. But on the
outcome side, we don't really see the
outcome that we need to see. We need to
see these going down or maybe
plateauing. But we are not seeing that.
We are seeing things trending upwards.
And according to various sort of threat
studies, uh the attacks are being
attributed more and more to nation
states these days as opposed to sort of
activists or script kitties. So things
are getting more sophisticated. The
stakes are being higher, right? So this
is not for hobby or for fun or activism.
This is serious business. This is now
competition between nation states and we
see things trending in the wrong
direction. So why is it that while we
are spending more and more in cyber we
are not seeing the outcomes we are not
seeing the benefits.
So they always say ask the five wise
right ask why and then why to the to
that reason and keep asking until you
get to the root causes. And if we do
that in cyber, it inevitably goes back
to history of how computer system have
been built over time. Uh now this is
certainly older than most people in this
room. But if we go back to the 60s,
there are influential projects like
project multic.
Project Mac is by the way what led to
MIT sale. uh these were sort of early
influential computer systems that
influenced essentially everything that
came afterwards.
Uh even to this day it's hard to come up
with an idea in computer science that
somebody doesn't say well this was
mentioned somewhere in multics. So it's
amazing right it's few decades
afterwards but we still h live with
those ideas and say very similar
concepts of course you know we have to
acknowledge that computing has become
much more versatile much faster much
more speed much more sort of power
however the core ideas have sort of
remained through uh throughout these
decades so those early projects
influenced commercial successes like
PDP11 IBM systems 60 uh back in 70s and
early 80s and those really led to a lot
of technologies that we use to this day.
So this can be programming languages
like C and C++
operating system designs that we use
today. Uh this really permeates through
all types of them Windows, Linux, Mac OS
even mobile operating systems and the
way we build processors x86 and ARM.
Now that era that era that started in
60s and perhaps sort of uh close to
2000s was the era of what we call add-on
defenses. So people rarely thought about
cyber security back then. One the need
wasn't as well understood. Two the
computers were not powerful enough to be
able to uh defend themselves. Uh so if
there was any defense it was add-on. It
was add-on after the fact. people built
the system and then sort of sprinkled
defenses on top of this machines
afterwards.
Uh and there was this realization that
this wasn't working right. Uh we were
always playing catch-up.
In 2000s and 2010s there were a number
of initiatives most notably by DARPA
DARPA crash and MRC programs but also at
other places that tried to build in
defenses into systems. So they tried to
sort of change the paradigm and
incorporate these defenses more into
systems as they were being designed.
And this really led to this modern era
which we call sort of era of inherently
secure systems. Systems that are really
built to defend themselves to be
resilient against wide classes of
attacks as opposed to sort of reacting
to individuals or instance of attacks.
We are preventing large classes of
vulnerabilities by design. This is by
the way mentioned in various cyber
security strategic plans. I've uh
mentioned one of them here 2025 uh
federal R&D strategic plan that
specifically mentions cyber resilience
by design. But this is not the only
document talking about that. If you look
at various strategic documents they they
need the so they mention the need for uh
inherently secure systems or resilience
by design. Again it goes by various
names but the the core idea is the same.
So I mentioned that a lot of sort of the
problems that we have in cyber security
today are inherited from that past era
right from 80s and 90s and even before
that but what are those exactly like why
is the problem permeating to this day?
Well, it's it would be helpful to look
at a typical cyber attack, right? An
anatomy of a cyber attack. And again,
this is a simplified example, but uh the
core concept is the same if we look at
sort of the vast majority of attacks
today. You know, in a system, we have a
stack like this, right? And this can be
in a data center, it can be in your
personal machine, can be really on your
cell phone as well. It's not that
different. At the bottom we have the
processor x86 or ARM are dominant to to
this day. The operating system Linux,
Windows, Mac, iOS, others libraries that
we rely on. Uh and then on top there are
applications and these are being more
and more AI applications. Of course AI
is is the hype these days. A lot of
applications are AI based. And then user
on top, right? So you're what does a
system do? receives data, processes
data, returns back something. Right?
Now, during normal operations, what a
user does on a system, again, I
intentionally don't sort of narrow this
down to a specific type of application
or a specific type of system because
this general concept applies essentially
everywhere.
But what the user does sends a data for
processing. This data is being copied to
the system usually to a space what we
call buffer, right? And then under the
hood, what's happening is that there is
some piece of hardware, the memory of
that system where this space to hold the
data is sitting right next to important
things like for example the AI model or
it can be, you know, if you're talking
about a system that's controlling
something, it could be the control logic
of that system.
During normal operation, this data is
copied to that space and is processed
and the result is returned back to the
user. Great.
The problem is that under attack what
could happen is that this data could be
malformed. It could be larger than the
space that it needs to be or it could
have some mal uh mal formality in it.
And what happens is that when this data
is copied to that space, it could
overflow. It could overflow to adjacent
data and that data or code could be some
critical thing. It could be the AI model
that's that system is running. It could
be the control logic of that system and
through that an attacker can modify the
behavior of the system and hijack the
control of the system.
Now this is a simplified view of a large
class of attacks today. It accounts for
by various studies 70% of attacks uh or
vulnerabilities to this day. But and
there are you know complexities that
that are added to this sort of
simplified uh view. Nevertheless, the
point stands that this type of attack is
very common to this day. It's being used
uh to hijack control of important
systems to modify them in malicious ways
including AI systems and we need to do
something about it. So what are the root
causes that I mentioned that sort of we
have inherited from early computer
designs? Well, the root causes really go
to essentially all layers of this stack.
At the bottom layer, the processor does
not have notions of different types of
data, right? It's processing everything
as strings of zeros and ones, right? So,
it it cannot distinguish the fact that
you know what I was trying to copy here
was the data whereas you know what's
underneath it is the model. It shouldn't
overwrite the model with that data
that's uh that the user is sending to
the system. It doesn't have any notion
of that, right?
It treats everything as raw bits,
essentially raw ones and zeros. The
operating system is built as a monolith,
meaning that it's a gigantic piece of
code that's running at the highest
privilege level in the system and every
part of the OS has access to the other
part of the OS. This is true to this
day.
uh and if a small part of the OS gets
compromised the entire system gets
compromised because there's no
additional safeguards inside the OS to
sort of contain the damage to limit the
damage
and also importantly applications and
libraries are written in unsafe
programming languages programming
languages that don't have notions of
size of the data right type of data
right sort of temporal validity of the
data uh and this is notably C and C++ ++
again the idea here was that the reason
is not that people who designed C and
C++ didn't know about these issues they
certainly know about knew about these
issues the problem was at the time the
machines were not resourceful enough to
be able to perform complicated checks uh
and they intentionally wanted to build
these systems these languages to be
close as close to the hardware as
possible so they didn't want to add
additional checks and additional
safeguards into the language
but we have lived with the consequences
of those decisions ever since and this
permeates to systems to this day. So the
core issues are are those three core
issues. The processors are sort of um
are not in secure by design. They cannot
perform security checks. Operating
systems do not have enough safeguards
inside them and we use unsafe
programming languages. So what are the
pillars of an inherently secure system?
Well, essentially addressing those three
root causes,
we have in in fact created uh uh a
vision for an inherently secure system.
This was part of an initiative at MIT
link lab called the moonshot initiative
cyber moonshot initiative that sort of
tried to address these core uh root
causes and using these three new pillars
and as I mentioned we have built some
technologies to address some of these
but there are many other places that
work on these problems and they're
building technologies to address them as
well. So what are these pillars? The
first one is hardware enforced security.
Uh so more and more in modern uh
hardware systems that are being uh sort
of enriched with proper checks, proper
types to enforce on data so that the
type of attack that I showed uh would be
prevented in the in the hardware itself.
This has multiple advantages but one is
that uh it's more efficient to enforce
it in hardware than have to enforce it
in the software. It doesn't make the
software more complicated by additional
sort of software to check other software
right uh and uh and it sort of sol
solves the problem at the layer that is
appropriate uh for solving this includes
sort of x86 architectures uh again Intel
AMD processors ARM has uh has its own
sort of type that's being added to newer
processors uh but today I'm not going to
talk uh get deeper into that I'm going
to talk about the other two areas. Uh
the sort of next pillar uh of a
inherently secure system is uh what's
called compartmentalization or another
name for it is zero trust. We want to
minimize the amount of privilege that
each part of the system has so that when
it it gets compromised it cannot impact
the the rest of the system because
inherently we're not going to be able to
remove all vulnerabilities. These
vulnerabilities are going to exist. So
we want to minimize the damage when
they're exploited in the system.
Uh and then the last pillar is safe
programming languages. Programming
languages that have notions of safety
built into them at compile time and at
al at also runtime to be able to prevent
these attacks. I'm going to talk about
the first area first which is the
compartmentalization and then briefly
mention the safe programming languages.
So what should we compartmentalize?
Of course, the software system is very
complex. There are various pieces to it.
If we look at the targets of attacks, it
turns out that a large chunk of them are
the operating systems. Uh 28% in fact,
it's the biggest chunk. Uh but the
problem is even worse. We only have a
handful of operating system whereas you
know if you look at applications, there
are millions of applications out there.
So operating systems are a juicy target
for attackers because there are a
handful of them and they're sort of
they're built as a monolith, right?
They're easier to exploit than many
different applications. And this shows
up in the data. In fact, 28% of the
attacks are uh target of attacks are
operating systems.
Uh and can we just fix this by better
patching? Well, some part of the
problem, but not really the majority of
it. The majority of exploitation is
exploitation of unknown vulnerabilities,
vulnerabilities that are not that
haven't been known to that up to that
time. So patching can fix you know that
pink part known vulnerabilities but it
cannot really address the unknown part.
So we need to do better. We need to put
enough guard rails inside the OS so that
when it is exploited one part of it gets
exploited the entire mission system
doesn't go down.
In fact, that's uh one of the
technologies that we have created in our
lab. Uh we call it hardware assisted
kernel compartmentalization or hacks.
Um and sort of we take the Linux
operating system. Why Linux? Again,
that's the predominant operating system
in many data centers. Uh Linux and its
variants, right? So there are many of
course variants to Linux. Uh but it also
shares its internal design with similar
operating systems as well. But as I
mentioned, if you look at the in the
internals of the Linux OS, everything
has access to everything, right? So you
have your Bluetooth module, your power
management, your file system. Every part
of the OS can access the other part of
the OS, right? It's the highest it's the
millions of lines of code running at the
highest privilege level in the system,
but there are no additional guard rails
inside of it.
So what we do um there are philosophies
that people advocate for building new
operating systems from scratch and those
are sort of worthy goals. However, many
existing systems use Linux right and
it's very difficult to build everything
from scratch. So what is said what we
have done is to minimize the amount of
privilege that exists inside the
operating system kernel in this case
Linux kernel. So we limit those to only
the interactions that are absolutely
necessary for the system to function. So
meaning that we put additional guard
rails in the system to say okay these
modules may need to talk to each other
and need certain types of access to
other modules but those additional
interactions are never necessary and
should be explicitly disallowed. And by
doing so we significantly reduce the
amount of privilege that exist in the
operating system kernel. uh and by the
same token if there is a vulnerability
in one of these modules and it is
exploited then the attacker is only
limited to that particular module and
cannot own the entire mission system.
This is again applying the principle of
zero trust to the operating system. So
we are minimizing the amount of
privilege that exists in the operating
system to what's absolutely necessary
and limiting the damage uh from
vulnerabilities. So again this is not
trying to remove any vulnerability. I'll
talk about safe programming languages in
a second but this is to say
vulnerabilities are going to exist. We
have to somehow limit their damage and
this is trying to limit uh damages from
vulnerabilities.
So this prototype is actually uh fairly
mature at this point. We have built it
over uh multiple years. Uh in fact I
believe the slick sheet for the
technology was included in your
packages. uh but it can run on data
center platforms. It can run on so all
those platforms that are pictured here
typical laptop. We have tested it and
actually demonstrated on robots. Those
Roomba like machines are uh what are
called turtle bots. The robots that uh
developer in robotics use for various
applications. But we have actually
showed that we can secure uh its
operating system using this idea of
compartmentalized Linux.
And on the left side you see uh a secure
processor developed by DARPA. So again
going back to hardware for security.
This type of processor has notions of
capabilities right what certain parts of
the software can do what they cannot do
and through that they actually enforce a
lot of the security checks for us. So it
can run on commodity processors even
sort of IoT like boards like you know
those ARM boards uh robotic platforms
data centers laptops as well as sort of
security enhanced processors. Now the
second area that I'm going to talk about
is safe programming languages. As I
mentioned, one of the main pain points
in cyber today is that legacy
programming languages like C and C++
don't have notions of safety to check on
to perform on the data. And because of
that, this sort of safety check is
delegated to the developer and
developers are human. They make
mistakes, right? They forget to perform
certain checks and this leads to
vulnerabilities.
For decades, we didn't have good
programming language options. uh sort of
safe languages that existed let's say
two decades ago where languages like
Java which requires a language runtime
it requires a heavy virtual machine to
be able to run the code is not really
appropriate for developing a system
level software right a piece of uh
system level software uh luckily in the
past sort of decade or so uh programming
languages have come up that actually
have notions of safety built into
Most prominently Rust and Go are two of
those languages. Rust uh performs
compile time checks many compile time
checks uh to ensure sort of the type of
data is correct, the size of data is
correct uh and it performs bounce check
what's called bounce check on the data.
Bounds is just a fancy term for saying
you know there are limits to how big
this data could be and it could not lead
into other areas in memory.
It also has ownerships of uh concepts of
ownership and lifetime to enforce
temporal check. Uh more on that in a
second. It performs some runtime checks
as well. So as the code is running it
performs runtime checks but luckily the
speed that it performs is uh fairly
optimized. So speed of Rust is
comparable to C++ today. Uh which again
something that we couldn't say 15 years
ago, 20 years ago.
Another language is Go. Again, Go is
used heavily for data processing. It
also has compile time checks and runtime
checks. Uh I would say the only downside
with Go is that its runtime checks are
heavier um particularly for garbage
collection. So it it has some slowdown
when when compared to system languages
like Rust. Um and as I said, Rust uh is
applicable uh to because it has a very
small runtime uh for system building for
things that need to be high performance
again applications, operating systems,
things of that sort.
I'm going to get a little deeper into
how technically this is performed. I
promise not too deep. Uh so again rust
has notions of uh static and dynamic
checks. Uh and it really provides two
safety properties. One is called spatial
safety meaning that if I have a piece of
data it cannot bleed into something
that's more critical in this case the
model right. Uh so it performs those
bounds check on the data so that it it
is it contain it is contained within its
sort of area of memory. Uh it does so
for most of the checks are compile time
but if the data is dynamic data it would
uh perform runtime checks. It also
performs uh the second type of check is
called temporal safety. So meaning that
if I store a piece of data in a part of
memory and later on I free that data now
and reuse that piece of memory for
something more critical again model
parameters or control logic. Nobody in
the program has access remaining access
to that data or residual access to that
data and it does so by this notion of
ownership meaning that you know in this
case one owner exists to that object and
if that object goes away the ownership
is immediately revoked. So nobody has
res will have residual access to a piece
of memory that could contain uh crucial
data.
So you might say okay this is lovely but
we have millions and billions of lines
of code already developed in C C++ what
should we do with that code right even
if we adopt Rust for everything that we
develop starting today we still have a
lot of libraries a lot of code that's
already written in those legacy
languages what should we do what should
we do with those
luckily there's a DARPA program called
DARPA tractor program that tackles this
problem uh explicitly. So the idea of
this program is to take a piece of C
code and automatically translate it to
safe ROS code. Uh it uses a combination
of techniques static analysis, dynamic
analysis and LLMs. So LMS have also a
big role um in this program and the key
sort of insight is or key hypothesis is
to be able to take C code uh translated
into safe ROS code not just sort of
um you know mechanically ROS code but
unsafe code but but to safe RS code in a
way that's also idiomatic so in a way
that's human readable that's sort of
looks like a code that a human has
written not a machine generated ated
code. If you have ever seen machine
generated code, it's just a mess, right?
It's very difficult to make sense of it.
The idea of of this program is to write
idiomatic code that looks like human
written code. And um the even today
there are a lot of things that could be
done. So this this is showing one
example of a C code that's being
translated into Rust code with Google
Gemini. If you look at the left side,
the C code takes an input from the user,
compares it with a string given a string
and if it matches, it prints welcome
otherwise it terminates the program.
What is this program? It's a password
checker and if we feed it into uh
Gemini, it is intelligent enough to
actually rename this variable to
password. So it recognized that it was
actually a password checking program
even though the name of the variable in
the C program wasn't password and it
could translate in into
fairly decent Rust code. Uh but of
course there's a lot of work to be done
here to be able to translate larger
amounts of code uh and uh preserve the
quality and sort of um the functionality
of the code as we do.
To summarize, today's systems remain
vulnerable to cyber attack mainly
because of their legacy design. Uh, and
in order to sort of break out of this
cycle of more investment but also more
vulnerabilities and more attacks, we
really need to move into this era of
inherently secure systems that can
achieve resiliency by design. The really
uh the three core pillars of building a
inherently secure system are what the
three main pain points are in existing
systems. Safe programming languages,
hardware enforced security and
compartmentalization or zero trusts or
these additional guard rails to uh to
limit the damage that can be done by
attacks.
Future directions focus on enabling
automation as I mentioned sort of
automatically transitioning code from
unsafe to safe code being able to do
this at large scale. Of course we are
dealing with large scale systems every
day. So it's not enough to be able to do
this on sort of simple uh strawman
examples. We want to really do this on
large scale code and being able to do so
with minimal overhead. Right? Of course
the functionality of the system is first
and foremost right? we shouldn't have a
lot of overhead that would sort of
inhibit uh adoption of these
technologies. So being able to achieve
minimal overhead is also key that's
captured in a lot of these including
hardware and for security as well. With
that I conclude my talk. I'll be happy
to uh happy to take questions.
Questions for Hamemed.
>> Going once, going twice.
>> You mentioned the hard word for
security. How much are you guys looking
at trusted execution environments? And
>> that's a great question. So we have we
have looked at it. We have looked at uh
trusted execution technology. We have
looked at sort of uh tagged
architectures. uh so they help but they
help with different parts of this
problem right so if you're thinking
about uh enforcing security checks on
the data sort of tagged architectures
are great for that uh if there are
applications where a part of the
application is really the crucial part
and the rest of it is less important and
that happens a lot right so the core
logic is very important and you want to
pro protect that against sort of um
untrusted libraries untrusted code
trusted execution technology helps with
that so yeah it uh It's really a
spectrum of solutions. I would say uh
trusted execution technologies are a
point in that spectrum and they're
appropriate for some things, but there
are also other technologies in that
area.
>> All right, then let's hear it for Jame.
Thank you.