You know, I think as a young child, I was
always just very curious.
Always asking questions about why things
are the way they are.
Perhaps not wanting to
take things for granted.
I'm an only child, and when I tell that
to people, sometimes
they look at me and say,
"Ah, that makes sense."
And I always wonder
what that really means.
I think that means that, you know, you
have to sort of have your own ideas,
you have to be willing to
live inside your own head,
thinking about things, having lots of
curiosity and imagination.
I was born in England. I was
born in the south of England,
which is a very green sort of place with
rolling hills, a lot of countryside.
My mother's English, my
father, was from Scotland.
And so already, even in British terms,
that feels like
you're quite international.
You know, the English
culture is quite calm and polite,
and the Scottish, more Celtic culture,
it's quite argumentative and
straightforward and brusque.
Chemistry had always felt like a subject
that bridged really sort of fundamental
science with the real world.
So chemistry seemed to me to be that
gateway between the fundamental sort of
properties, if you like,
of the universe and the kind of real
world as we saw it around us.
It felt as if coming to the US was coming
to a place where you could really be
authentically enthused
about sort of science and fundamental
knowledge production.
And so that was something that I really
wanted to do when I came from my PhD.
I've spent time at MIT since I was a
graduate student, and
it's a very special place.
So when I got to Harvard and I recognized
that not only could I roam around all of
Harvard's course catalog,
that there was an MIT catalog as well, it
seemed to me that it was just an
opportunity not to miss
to be able to take classes down here and
experience something different.
I was offered a faculty position in 2000,
and particularly for what I
have always been interested in,
that lab-to-impact journey, an ecosystem
that was flourishing and really
supporting some of those extraordinary
deep-tech entrepreneurs. It felt like an
incredible privilege to be able to be
here at MIT, being
part of that community.
So I think for me I want
to have impact in two ways.
And so as I've said, one of the ways I
think I have impact in the
world is to teach my students
and to give them both the inspiration,
and the tools, the methods that they need to
go and actually make a difference.
And for myself, in terms of my own
impact, I increasingly
do work as an advisor.
I work advising
governments and large organizations.
I work quite closely with NATO and with
the UK government and others.
And the question I want to ask is, how is
it that our countries and our
organizations can actually draw upon
that inspiration to build the kinds of
companies and ecosystems
that they need to keep,
whether it's the UK or Europe, kind of
strong and resilient, so that we can
really have the kind of
latitude of action to take the hard
choices as countries and really do the
things that matter to us.
What MIT does so well is the thing that
the world needs so desperately, the mind
in hand, the thinking and doing,
the sort of the
practical genius if you'd like.
There's something really interesting when
you walk into a classroom.
You hear so many different accents. You
hear students from all over the world.
You meet faculty from all over the world.
It's very rare at MIT to walk into a
meeting and be the only person
who's a foreign-born individual. And you
see people who are
drawn to MIT as a place,
as much as they're drawn to being in the
United States, they're
drawn to the idea of MIT.
Well think it's a brilliant opportunity
to be able to talk to our students
and to draw upon their different global
experiences. So it's not just
me sharing my own experiences,
but also my students' experiences,
because so many of them have
lived in different countries
and are from different countries. And we
can really start to compare
notes and take a very sort of
global perspective on these complicated
times. It felt like an incredible
privilege to be able to be here at MIT,
being part of that community. Getting up
every day and coming to MIT is something
that is always really intense
and interesting. It sort of feeds your
curiosity and your ask of the possible.