So up next we have Yen. She's a posttock
at the Ericcomi Schmidt center and
she'll be giving a talk about
segmentation free analysis of submicron
resolution spatial transcrytoics
right uh we've heard about spatialics in
this section. So spatial traptomic
technologies uh have been developing
rapidly in the recent years. Um two of
the key aspect of those technologies are
the spatial resolution and the number of
genes profiled. So imaging based
technologies can measure the precise
location of every molecules but can only
profile a pre-esigned gene panel and
commercial platforms expanding their
throughput scaling from a few hundred to
thousands of genes. Sequencing based
technologies on the other hand can
violously profile the whole
transcriptton but earlier technologies
have rather low resolution at a
multisellular scale. So more recent
technology like six scope and sterosk um
have achieved submicron resolution
comparable to
microscope. So our method are designed
for any special transcript data that
with subtle
resolution. So the data from such
technologies are specially resolved
transcripts. Each pixel contains one or
a couple of transcripts. Here the color
representing different gene identities.
So such high resolution
uh and high throughput data does not
automatically enable high throughput
imprints. A basic task of data analysis
is recover cells and their cellular
functions. The current standard approach
is to use nuclei staining and cell
boundary markers to perform cell
segmentation before doing single cell
level analysis. However, high quality
imaging information is not always
available especially for some sequencing
based platforms.
So even when cell segmentation is
physible is still a challenging task
since we have we are making a
two-dimensional section from a
three-dimensional tissue the
cross-section of a cell is of often of
reg irregular shape and some self nuclei
may not be captured in this 2D wheel and
they may be missed from downstream
analysis. So there are more techn
technical difficulties in practice that
jointly resulting in perfect cell
segmentation.
An alternative way is to do grid based
analysis to collapse those sparse
information from individual pixels into
bigger unit in able to do statistical
analysis. This approach can use all the
transcript but lose spatial resolution
and obtain such a grid contain a mixture
of different cell types.
The ideal solution should annotate
cellular function at each individual
pixel and do so efficiently for large uh
tissue regions. And this is what we aim
to
achieve. So here's the intuition behind
our method. So we start from a hexagonal
grid and infer each hexagon as a mixture
of multiple latent factors representing
a cellular functions. These factors can
be learned in no from the data. But we
could also incorporate prior knowledge
or use external single cell reference
panel. We call the center of the
hexagons as anchor point. And then we
slide this grid to generate a denser
letters of such anchors. But at this
stage each anchor still represent the
mixture. So the key step is to allow
each pixel to look around and pick which
anchor it goes to. And then the anchors
will collect those pixel and update
their fraction uh their factor
proportions. When this process
converges, we have a probability factor
assignment of every single
pixel. We will use um public data from
four different platform to show that our
method works in practice. But we do
emphasize that we uh we works for data
from all such cellular subscellular
technologies, right? Um sterile seek is
a next generation sequencing based
technology. This is a 16-day mouse
embryo session. Over 750 million
transcript are captured but only 40% of
them are assigned to any cell because on
this platform only nuclear staining was
available. So cell segmentation is very
challenging. On the left is the
published cell level annotation. On the
right is our unbiased uh is our
unsupervised pixel level analysis
without using a nuclear information.
we recover or similar global structure
but with additional details. One example
I want to show is the developing muscle
tissues. So during myiogenesis myoblast
matures into myophiber cell segmentation
is particularly difficult for the later
stage with this nuc m multi-ucleated
fiber-l like cells. The top right panel
shows nuclear staining and the bottom is
a published cell segmentation based
analysis colored by annotated cell
types.
We cannot see mature muscle fiber in
this view and almost all the cells were
labeled as
myoblast. However, when we applied our
method, we see the emerging strided
muscle cells. The top image color each
pixel as our inferred latent factors and
the bottom highlight two two factors.
The red pixel coming from myoblast and
the yellow pixel belonging to
differentiated muscle cells.
So imaging based platform often have
higher high quality imaging with
multiple channel to support better cell
segmentation. So let's look at the
muscle tissue at this mouse pop data
from zenium with 5,000
panel. So in the middle is um the image
with nuclei staining and cell membrane
markers. On the right is a standard cell
level analysis. On the left is features
output. The color here also represent
the inferred Ling factors and we label
them by the signature genes. The purple
background here is has a signature of
immature muscle fiber. The yellow marks
the same fiber-l like structure located
between muscle cells that are has the
signature of fibroblast. Another type of
inter muscle signal we see is from
endothelial cells in green. So uh well
in this data the cell segmentation is
quite good but still the fine scale
tissue structure is
lost right um the next example is from
brain tissue here's a mouse half brain
with uh from cosmics again there are
almost 40% of transcript were lost in
single cell level analysis let's look at
one such uh cell sparse region near
hippoc
campus so starting From this gr um this
uh granu cell layer uh we have three
distinct molecular layer that are filled
with dendrid and axon but not uh does
not have dense cell
bodies. Um between the dendritic layer
of hippocampus and the cortex we have
the white matter uh track that are u
dominated by melaninated axons. The cell
body inside this uh layer are indeed
melaninating
olodendrites. Right in the cortex we
also observe a diff different expression
pattern near nuclei versus other part of
the cell. Um here the green factor here
um uh often appear at the center of the
cell body is enriched for two long
non-coding arrays retain the nuclei and
different neuron may share this nuclei
signature while having distinct
dendroitic or synaptic
activities. Um we check another public
brain data from Moscope to see if we
observe similar subset of loop pattern
in a different technology and from a
human instead of mouse u especially in
this case those nuclei markers are not
available in the gene panel.
So although the nuclei um non long
coding RNAs are not uh present the model
still seem to learn a soma specific
signature the signature gene of the red
factor encoding encode neurotransmitter
receptor and voltage gated channel
subunit that are predominantly located
in the cell body and the pink and yellow
are um both enriched for MRA targeted
for dendrites or presinaptic channels uh
terminals and they seem to be from
different two sub uh two different
subtypes, right? Um another major
application of spatial omics data is
cancer biology. So here is a human
breast cancer tissue from 10x Indian.
The release data includes cell
segmentation based on nuclei. Um we will
zoom in in this regions uh around the
duct ductal caroma in situ. So the top
right hisystologology image shows edipo
tissue. The empty spots are created by
large lipid droplets in edipo size where
no RNA is present. The nuclei of edipo
size are much smaller than the cell body
and located at a cell boundary. Often
there are immune cell that are much
smaller and located between edipo sites.
The cell segmentation from line uh from
t platform is quite misleading in this
region because nuclearizing is just not
very informative.
So our uh approach is not affected by
such cell morphology. The top right
panel shows color each pixel by our
inferred factors. The bottom one we
highlight uh edible sites in yellow and
indothelial cells in blue. We also
identify different immune cell
population in this region. So overall uh
we provide a more realistic picture of
the underlying
biology. Right. In breast cancer cancer
associated fibroblast and extracellular
matrix are major component of tumor
micro environment and are important for
cancer progression. So here we use
another uh public data from uh breast
cancer tissue in mcope to show the
potential advantage of our approach. In
this case on the left the white p uh the
white pixels are shows the extracellular
matrix building related signature. They
are in the region also reach in tumor
associated macrofage. On the right we
see the co-loization of this uh two
factors in a different context. The
light green pixel well uh with this
similar uh fiberl like structure are
also cancer rel uh cancer associated
fibroblast but it has a different
functional signature.
So if we look at uh the image um uh this
region is actually uh cell sparse um
those fibroblast does not seem to be
well captured by cell boundary markers.
Comparing with cell level view uh our
approach is perhaps better suited to
study tumor micro environment in a more
unbiased
way. Right? So not only does feature
provide biologically meaningful
inference across platforms but is
lightweight and highly scalable. So here
we compare with two representative
method beta has been well uh one of the
most accurate pixel level analysis
method but it's not designed for such
for current high school data and the
memory requirement is prohibitive for a
fraction of the state of bar data set. A
graph is a method that use popular graph
neural network. It works at lower
resolution and or require segmented
cells. Um but still is is the projected
cost for analyzing large data is quite
huge. So we uh we have adjustable memory
budget in that's independent of the size
of the data set.
In terms of runtime, uh we scales
linearly with a number of transcript and
can be massively parallelized. We either
scale superlinearly and cannot scale to
more than a thousand genes. And well,
our pixel level inference is even more
scalable uh efficient than the cell
level inference from from the graph
neuron
network. So in summary, we present a
segmentation free analysis tool that
infers cellular function of set micron
resolution. It applies data from any
subtitular level platforms is orders of
magnitude more efficient than existing
method and is built for future large
scale multis sample data set and it does
not rely or im limited by imaging based
cell
segmentation. Uh we just made public a
new version of our software and we are
actively working on new functionalities
to support different use cases. Um, I'm
looking for collaboration and maybe
looking for a drop soon. With that, I'd
like to thank all the wonderful people
I've worked with and happy to take any
[Applause]
questions. Think we have time for one or
two more questions.
So I I guess as the spatial technologies
get like finer and finer resolution, uh
do you foresee this kind of continuing
to be uh a question of doing this in a
self-free manner versus segmenting like
going forward with the way spatial
technologies are developing? How do you
see this uh being used?
I'm not quite understanding the
question. Um
so well spatial resolution is proving
but there's a physical limit of what you
can measure because after some point for
imaging based platform you have this
optical crowding issue for sequencing
based well we are doing slightly better
but still um there's a lateral diffusion
of transcript so I'm not entirely sure
how much we can improve upon current
technology in terms of resolution.
Thanks.
Okay, let's thank each one more time.
[Applause]