[Music]
okay so next let's think about uh the t-
cell response to cancer and how uh this
goes wrong so uh we know from just
Decades of work that cancer really is
evading uh te- cell killing and how this
happens is it's driving the te- cells to
a state called exhaustion so uh normally
te- cells are circulating in our blood
and we're going to call these naive tea
cells and when there's a tumor the te-
cells will migrate to the side of the
tumor so for instance in melanoma the
te- cells will migrate to the skin and
these te cells will encounter the cancer
cell which is displaying on its surface
this non-self antigen and they will
enter What's called the progenitor State
as they become activated now these t-
cell States then start to transition so
the progenitor State goes to a state
that's called the affector state which
is good at killing tumor cells and then
this state unfortunately transitions
over to a state called the terminal
exhausted state which is not so good at
killing tumor cells so these t- cell
States they're all considered to be
exhausted te- cells but they are
exhausted to different degrees and the
t- cell States themselves are encoded by
gene expression programs so remember
this are these are groups of genes that
are turned on together in sort of a
shared biological process and these gene
expression programs are really analogous
to the gene expression programs we'
introduced for cancer when talking about
melanogenesis or this epithe to meenal
transition so similarly each of these t-
cell States the progenitor State the
affector state and the terminal
exhausted state are encoded by gene
expression programs and measuring these
programs will tell us what the te- cells
are doing so now let's look at this from
a more visual setting so here we have
this diagram where we're going to look
at the t- cell response to cancer and on
the left Y axis we have the cancer
burden so how much cancer there is and
that's shown in this um Brown Line and
on the right y- Axis we have the t- cell
response in purple and so again what
happens is a naive t- cell will migrate
to the side of the tumor as the cancer
starts to grow and it will transition to
a progenitor State and then it will
further transition to an affector State
and as it transitions to the affector
state the te cell starts to actually
kill the cancer cells so this is where
you get this peak in the cancer burden
and it actually starts to go down now
unfortunately the effector t- cell state
does not last it actually starts to
transition
to this terminal exhausted T Cell state
which is weaker at tumor killing so the
T Cell response start the T Cell
response starts to go down the cancer
burden just starts to stabilize and so
you reach the stal where the cancer is
still there and the te- cells aren't
quite able to clear out the cancer so
this a stalemate or Deton between the
cancer cells and the tea
cells so scientists have been studying
uh terminal exhausted te- cells for
decades and here are some consensus
features about those te- cells so the
first is that they have this inability
to control the cancer growth so you
don't go all the way to having no cancer
it just sticks around uh there's also
this loss of the t- cell affector
killing function so the te- cells are
blunted and they're no longer really uh
actively killing the cancer cells in a
manner that controls cancer uh there's
also these expression of these
inhibitory receptor uh genes and this is
going to be talked about in the cancer
immunotherapy section and then finally
the tea cells in the terminal exhaust
State have less ability to undergo
self-renewal and make more of themselves
okay so let's recap what we just learned
in the past two slides about te- cell
exhaustion so naive te cells are
starting in the blood and then they
migrate into the tumor and they enter
into this sort of exhausted set of
programs and the te- cells when they
encounter the cancer cell enter the
progenitor State and then they
differentiate or transition into an
affector State and finally they enter
this uh bad termin exhausted State now
the terminal exhausted State as we said
before is weak at killing tumor cells
whereas the progenitor and affector
states are very strong at killing tumor
cells and finally there's a last state
that the te- cells can enter which is
the cycling State and uh the cycling
state is just the te- cells entering the
cell cycle and making more copies of
themselves as they undergo cell division
so cycling is particularly good
especially for the affector te- cells
because these are the ones that are
going to uh go in and kill the cancer
and if you're making more of those
affector te cells it's like having a
bigger weapon uh against the
cancer so what's happening in the cancer
environment again is that there's
something about the cancer and the
surrounding tissue environment that's
pushing cells away from the progenitor
States and these affector states and
forcing them into this terminal
exhausted t- cell State and so you can
think about this as a distribution right
the te- cells can be in any of these
states but in the cancer environment
there's a strong push to be in the
terminal exhausted state
[Music]