Hi everyone, welcome to Dimmitri
Bertimas's office. Dimmitri, would you
like to introduce yourself to the
audience?
>> Uh, hello everybody. My name is Dimmitri
Bertimas. I have been a professor at the
school Sloan School of Management since
1988, but I've been about 40 years at
MIT. In addition to being a professor at
the Sloan School as well as the faculty
director of master of business
analytics, the associate dean of the the
analytics myself. I'm also leading uh
the u I'm the vice provost for open
learning which is uh what MIT does in
education for non-residential
education.
Wonderful, Denitri. And wow, you've been
here for so long and you have so many
titles. Um, what is your favorite part
about MIT?
>> Favorite part about my is the students
uh far and away. So, uh, both um, my
doctoral students of which this year I
will have more than 100 graduating have
25 at the moment. And then the master of
business analytics students which
Michelle and I started 10 years ago. And
I have to admit even though I'm a person
who has high expectations, it exceeded
the already high expectations. We have
developed what I consider one of the
very best if not the very best program
in the world in the in the space of um
of business analytics.
>> Wow. So 25 doctoral students and then we
have 80 students in the program per
year. Um what makes a student stand out?
What do you look for in a student?
>> Uh a variety of things. First of all,
the students who both at at the PhD
level, the operational research center
or have 90 of those 25 m and 80 of the
master of business analytics are among
the very best students in their home
institutions. Typically the the top one,
two or three students. Uh the quality of
the students is exceptionally high. In
addition, the aspirations of the people,
the people we are attracted to MIT are
not random people of course, but in
addition their aspirations is to try to
improve the world and uh via
quantitative analytical techniques. And
um this combination of ability, high
aspirations and character makes what I
consider the the key ingredients of a
fantastic intellectual environment that
we have here at MIT.
>> Great. And could you tell us about some
of the research that you're doing with
the students?
>> Yep. Uh having um typically every year I
I as you heard I have about 25 doctoral
students and about five master of
business analyticians who do research
with me. I have a variety of topics. I
particularly work in uh applying AI um
gen AI but also more general purpose AI
in healthcare uh of which we have been
developing what is called multimodel AI
models models that utilize computer
vision language tabular data genomics
and time series a variety of data to try
to predict and prescribe treatments that
improve uh improve the condition of
patients. Another area of significance
is the climate. I have a also a working
group of where we utilize AI for
improving climate. We currently have um
a a product a research on u wildfires,
how to predict them and how to mobilize
resources to uh alleviate the effects. I
have another significant effort on
methodological methods. When you have
multimodel data, how do you do
prescriptions? How do you make decisions
in the in the presence of multimodel
data? And finally, a very significant
effort in my group is how to use genai
in education motivated by my role as the
as the as the vice pro profess of open
learning. We have developed together
with some of my students uh a tutor AI
tutor a guidance system where we we
basically advise students what next
classes to take. We currently work on
personalized education where we uh adapt
the educational environment to the
student um and many others of the sort.
So these are the three major areas
education, healthcare and the climate
that occupy my thinking.
>> Wow. Um, so an AI tutor. Are you
planning to use this tutor in one of
your future classes that you teach?
>> Yeah, we actually use it in one of the
Karen classes. Oh,
>> we I teach a class the analytics edge
for executive MBAs about 70 70 students
in the class and about 80 90% use it
already with good results. So next year
I'll be teaching the machine learning
under the model optimization lens. I'll
be using the tutor. I'm also planning to
have uh an online education for what's
called universal AI. This is trying to
teach AI for the for many people
including MIT students. So indeed uh
tutor is already in the classrooms and
hopefully will be even more so in many
significant ways.
>> Um and can you tell us more about this
course machine learning under a modern
optimization lens? I know that you
created the course.
>> Yeah. So this is a class um you know I I
have u I come from the area of
optimization. This is sort of my home
base so to speak. About maybe 15 years
ago I started learning more about
machine learning and AI and I have
observed that uh many machine learning
uh models are huristic in nature. So by
using optimization and the so we can we
developed a much more exact uh
methodologies that basically have much
higher performance and um and this the I
wrote a book in 2019
uh that actually won a major prize in
the my professional society that we use.
The the title of the book was machine
learning at the modern optimization lens
which is also the the name of the class
we teach here at MIT. It it is a it is a
class and a corresponding book with a
with a particular view that machine
learning needs to be much closer to
optimization as opposed to durability
and you can get the benefit of uh
significant uh improvement in
performance. And these days we have
augmented the material in the class with
more deep learning applications which I
in my opinion is the is the next
frontier where optimization can also
play a significant role.
>> Wonderful. And for those students out
there who are very interested in taking
this course or being your research
assistant or PhD student, how can they
best prepare um to to do this research
or to take your class?
>> Yep. Um I would say the class requires
some knowledge of linear algebra which
most of the students have but so please
uh review it and they need to know some
optimization at least uh the language of
optimization in terms of research uh
with me and so forth. I only I take
students from MIT. So you have to be
admitted in our programs or the PhD or
the mast's program. And typically I the
key criterion is uh to try to affect the
world. Every student at MIT are high
quality people. So uh what I look at
aspirations and character.
>> Thank you very much. Those are all my
questions.
>> Thank you many for many of you. I hope
to meet you in the near future in the
MIT campus.
>> Hi everyone. Thank you for watching. If
you like this video, check out our other
videos in the series where I interview
influential professors at MIT Sloan. If
you would like to learn more about the
Master Business Analytics program, we
also have a playlist where you can see
more videos about the admissions
process, student life, and the program
overall.