And last but not least, please welcome
QET. Developing scalable hardware
solutions for quantum device
connectivity that seamlessly integrate
with existing infrastructure to enable
deployable quantum networks.
Thank you. All right. Thank you very
much. Excited to be here and talk to you
more about what we're building. My name
is Laura Andre and I'm the president and
CEO of QNET where we're building quantum
networking hardware powering the next
generation of global connectivity.
So a little bit about the company. Uh we
spun out of the work of professors Durk
England at MIT and SYOT Gua at the
University of Maryland in 2022. And in
just three years we've secured five US
government contracts and are backed by
leading accelerator programs and state
innovation funding. We've also developed
an early product sales pipeline and are
seeing active interest from commercial
partners. Our mission is simple but bold
and that is to build the hardware
foundation for scalable platform
agnostic quantum networking all the way
from local links to global connectivity.
So there are four major trends driving
the future of connectivity. We have AI
and hypers scale data centers reaching
the limits of encryptionbased security.
the geopolitical race for securing
critical infrastructure and also the
rise of quantum computers. These four
forces point to um an underlying issue.
The network stack that our digital world
relies on is only as strong as its
foundation and the network security
depends on the physical layer and today
it's vulnerable. So we're building the
foundation that secures the full stack
and powers the next generation of global
connectivity
and quantum entanglement is the ultimate
solution beyond today's math-based
encryption standards. Uh first it's uh
tamper evident guaranteed by physics. So
any uh detection of um interception
attempts is immediately detectable. It's
also provably secure because it's not
reliant on math problems or computing
assumptions. It's also resilient by
design withstanding advances in
algorithms and quantum computers.
So by securing uh channels um we can
secure channels end to end uh by
distributing entanglement across the
network.
However, the problem is that today's
networks are not compatible with quantum
information. There are two main
barriers. Uh the first challenge is that
sign signals suffer losses that grow
exponentially with distance and we can't
just amplify or regenerate uh quantum
signals like we do with uh classical
signals. Uh so what we need are um high
rate uh entangled photon sources that
overcome these losses at scale. The
second challenge is that conventional
hardware like routers and switches
destroy the quantum properties of the
signals. Uh so we need to build uh
quantum routers and quantum repeaters
that are capable of preserving the
fragile quantum states we want to
transmit.
And so quantum information demands a new
hardware stack and uh we are building
it. So uh we're delivering provably
secure communications today while also
uh laying the foundation for the quantum
internet of tomorrow.
and those two barriers that I mentioned
um we've uh solved these two major
challenges uh through uh two um systems
that we are focused on building. So the
first is entangled photon pair sources
which deliver entangled pairs of photons
at high rate on demand uh in the telecom
band that are uh ready to be integrated
with current infrastructure and are
capable of overcoming loss at scale.
Second are our mega cubit quantum
routers with integrated quantum memories
that enable buffering, synchronization
and switching for quantum signals. And
our uh integrated quantum memory skills
directly to uh millions of cubits, the
levels we know we need for commercially
relevant applications.
So our near-term target is
unconditionally secure communications
where we're securing existing uh
classical channels for sensitive data
transmission. But the same uh hardware
foundation that we're building is also
capable of the next generation of
applications where we're allowing
quantum devices to coherently share
quantum information. So extending this
to quantum security and precision um
precision of pnt and sensor networks all
the way to network distributed quantum
computing.
Uh we also have some upcoming pilot
deployments planned for our hardware
along with uh partners uh in Boston and
Maryland. Uh we're getting ready to
deploy our hardware stack on uh quantum
network test beds uh which will prove
out our hardware working not just in the
lab but in real world networks.
Uh so if you're interested in exploring
uh quantum networking uh we'd love to
talk to you um in our uh break coming up
next. Thank you very much.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you so much, Laura. Questions from
the audience? Anyone?
I have a question. Where do you see the
first real world impact of quantum
networking? uh and how close we are we
>> yeah so um with the um sort of
applications roadmap I showed uh we
really see the near-term impacts in uh
securing classical channels and then as
uh professor Freriedman also talked
about those more quantum internet type
applications where we're really
eliminating those interfaces between
classical and quantum and allowing
quantum devices to coherently share
quantum information
>> thank you and one more question what
parallels exist between the early days
of classical internet and where are we
today with quantum internet?
>> Yeah. So, um you know as uh computers
were first being developed they weren't
uh beingworked and uh people didn't
really you know know what you know that
would be useful for. I think you know
quantum networking is still sort of
searching for that killer application.
Uh but we'll find it and we'll be um
building the hardware that will allow us
to get there.
>> Excellent. Thank you. Anyone else have
question?
Oh, sorry. here. I think I saw somebody
in there.
>> Thank you.
>> Get your steps in.
>> Um, is there currently a pointto-point
uh demo of [snorts] uh a data link that
you have running?
>> Um, not that we have running yet, but
we're hoping to get that up and running
uh in the next year or so on the Boston
test bed. Uh, some uh partners at MIT
and Harvard have already demonstrated
that with some really nice work. So,
>> it took quantum to get MIT and Harvard
talking to each other. Is that what
you're saying?
>> [laughter]
>> Not necessarily, but it helped.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Thank you so much, Laura.
[applause]