[Music]
my name is Lupe Fiasco I'm a rapper and
I'm a
MLK a visiting scholar here at
MIT so I've done a lot I've learned how
to sail since I've been
here done a lot of karate since I've
been here the statement here at in my is
it's like trying to drink water from a
fire hose so I just kind of fully went
with that and you get invited over to
the biology lab and I'm in there the
gloves and the the pipets and I'm making
bacteria do stuff and it's like you know
there's a scientist like you know good
job kind of thing and that leads to like
hey you want to do a research paper it's
like you're getting pulled in all these
like really high level places by people
who are like experts in their field and
it just feels like I'm just a rapper you
know what I'm saying but it's like no no
no no no you got insights into this and
we can talk about this and build
this for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow