next thing I want to do now that we have
fear CH so now what do we know we have
this protocol again I'm always think of
this protocol as parall repetition
parallel repeated and we know the sound
on it now what's really nice about it
that this gives us so now I wanted to
say two things in the hour or so
remaining one thing I want to say is
that it gives us an isic okay
non-interactive a zero knowledge uh
proof and the second and so I want to
explain what that is and the second
thing I want to say is uh to mention a
little bit what was me the question uh
here in the beginning which was wait
this contradicts all this idea with
something weird is going on so I want to
talk about that and I want to end with
explaining why this technique is more
General okay
H okay so let's first see why
why why we get an isic okay
so okay so now what did we get Once once
we apply the fum we have an
uninteractive protocol so let's look at
this protocol and
see what this protocol becomes when we
apply the F Paradigm to it
so let me just write it down Actually I
don't even want to write the
explicit
uh constru like everything explicitly
let me just say this protocol had like a
public key associated with
it now it also has a a hash function
associated with hash key which we use
for the fure hash function and now
essentially the
verifier he sends Alpha which is the
other commitments FAL repetition like
the first message and then he tells you
beta he doesn't need to send it
everybody comput it but that's kind of
evaluating with a hash key Alpha by the
way I abuse notation a little bit and
actually every time you don't you
you uh let's see there's also a g here
like the instance the
graph really what you where you hash is
the graph in Alpha I kind of omitted the
graph from the notation because it's
kind of cumbersome and it's kind of
fixed in advance the alpha is the one
that's not fixed so I the G but the G is
always there when you apply F you apply
it to the first message and the
instance okay so that's the beta and
gamma this is the pro that's the it's
one message right because we applied F
okay so this protocol which consists of
three messages Alpha Beta gamma now once
we applied F we have not only the public
key in the CRS we also have the hash key
corresponding to the fiir
and now this Alpha Beta gamma are sent
all at once there's no interaction
that's what F
does but beta the PR's hands are tied
and they it should be the evaluation of
G and Alpha the hash function evaluated
on G and Alpha so this is completely
noninteractive and it's sound because we
just worked hard to prove that it's
sound if we use this hash
function under Circle Circ yeah is
this a isic argument now then because we
used like f SEC good a we'll see there's
you can make it and is a proof or
argument so we'll talk about that in a
second but uh so this is a one message
it's sound and it's complete now what
happened to the zero knowledge let's see
what happened here we said we had zero
knowledge we could simulate
it what happens
here and what I want to argue is that
it's still you have zero knowledge even
though before we said f actually Ru zero
knowledge supp it's not zero
knowledge this non intractive version
you can can prove that it's zero
knowledge however the definition of zero
knowledge here is a different bit
different because we have a common
random string so now this common random
or common reference string denoted by
CRS it consists of the public
key used for the commitment for the
message Alpha
and the hash use for the
CRS now let me I want to argue that this
protocol is a non-interactive zero
knowledge or is an isic non-interactive
zero
knowledge but to prove that let me
Define first what noninteractive zero
knowledge is okay because it's the
definition is similar to the interactive
setting but slightly different so the
definition is the following anic for a
language out
is the following it says that for any PP
VAR or poly size it can be non it can be
poly but okay me for any PPT V
Star there exists a simulator a PPT
simulator po time
simulator such that the simulator can
simulate everything that the verifier
learns in the real world so what does
the What is the view of the verifier in
the real world such that the view of the
verifier in the real world which is what
it's the
CRS so every niic is a it's not
interactive and there's a CRS so the
verifier learns the CRS and he learns
what he got he learns uh H such that
sorry for every X and L I forgot to say
for every X in the language he learns
this and he learns the proof of the
actual prover so I guess what the actual
prover gives is when he gets
CRS X and
witness this is what the verifier learns
in the real world he sees the CRS and he
sees the actual proof produced by the
prover and the prover is given CRS X and
A Witness instance and
witness and zero knowledge says that the
simulator can simulate this so I forgot
to say security parameter there's also
security param oh actually you know what
you don't need security parameter
because the CRS you can think of
including in this
includes also security parameter you can
always assume the CRS includes a
security parameter so here what the
verifier learns in the real world he
sees the CRS which includes a security
parameter and he sees the proof that the
verifier gave and now I want to argue
that the simulator can simulate this
entire thing
okay typically we also allow auxiliary
information so for any ax and for every
auxiliary information
augs
a the Dy also see sees augs and still he
cannot tell the
difference so when we talk about Zer
there's just Zer and then there's
auxiliary input Zer knowledge this is
stronger we usually want this so I'm
just writing it but uh there's also the
without auxilary information uh
definition but again what is zero uh NK
non interactive zero knowledge it says
that for any efficient
varar there exists an efficient
simulator said that for every X in the
language that had a witness and for any
auxiliary information that the you know
the simulator may have or the verifier
may
have what the verifier learns in the
real world can be simulated by the
simulator
yeah here we don't even need
right yeah sorry there's no
v ah yeah there's no V whatever you can
learn you're right thank you for every L
there exist a simulator for every X for
any auxilary that's it that's the
definition okay cuz V doesn't send
anything okay now here's note what what
the reason this is still zero knowledge
is
that now the simulator he gets to choose
the
CRS the simulator he outputs this
simulator outputs a CRS and some fake
proof P that should be
indistinguishable even given
augs so really it's
um a and the point is the simulator he
can he can he has the power to choose
the CRS this is a power that the
cheating prover does not
have and that's
why if you could prove that Fe the the
fact that F works for the fact that you
have a it's it doesn't there's no
contradiction with the fact that it's
zero knowledge and F chir sound because
the fact that it's zero knowled the fact
that it's F chir sound
or in other words the fact that it's
zero
knowledge does not mean that you can use
the simulator as a cheating prover the
simulator succeeds in simulating because
he has the power to fake the CRS the
cheating Pro does not have that
power okay again remember before we said
oh if you have fear then the simulator
because he can
simulate uh the view he can he can also
simulate a view in the case of cheating
so he can actually break Fe here he
can't break F because I mean the prover
can't the simulator can because he has
an additional power that a cheating
prover does not have he can fake the
he's the one who gets to choose the CRS
and that's the only reason why we can
actually get ank here because he's we're
gonna he's going to choose the CRS to
his liking in an indistinguishable way
of
course but I mean this CRS and This Ss
are
indistinguishable but he can kind of
program it that's that's the idea
so let me just tell you why it's zero
knowledge and then you'll see because
you know why it's F secure I'll tell you
why it's Z knowledge and then you'll see
how I'm where how I'm abusing the power
of the
simulator
okay so the way the reason why it's uh
Zer it's NK it's nonactive zeron so I
need to come up with a simulator I need
to simulate the F
protocol and actually if you think about
it how can I simulate it I need to come
up with an think what I need to do I'm
the simulator it seems like a hard task
for me what do I need to do as a
simulator so what does the Sim do Sim
needs to he he needs to generate CRS
somehow I don't know okay I can just
generate publicly and hash key but
then I need to find like Alpha Beta
gamma accepting so I guess first note
look the simulator is given oh wait he's
given also X forgot to write X he's
given the instance X and
augs now note I'm the Simulator X can be
in the language X cannot be in the
language I have no idea what x
is okay so in if I if I succeed I should
also succeed for some for some x's not
in the language because I I can't break
the language now if to succeed for X9 in
the language I need to generate beta
that's bad otherwise I can't
succeed but how can I generate B bet
that's bad I remember the encryption H
it's a problem the reason it's not a
problem because I'm going to break the
encryption I get to choose it I choose
the encryption I chose it with a secret
key and actually actually let me be a
um actually for this specific hash
function I actually don't know how to
prove that it's an isic it may be I
don't know but I don't know how to prove
it but if you slightly change that hash
function in a way that doesn't affect
soundness at all then I can prove that
it's AIC so I'm going to slightly change
the hash function the F hash function
okay I'm going to slightly change it
just add a constant to
it I'm going to argue that it doesn't
change the uh soundness and uh but now I
can use it for niic so let me show you
how this is
done so how do I generate this Alpha
Beta gamma so the first thing I'm going
to do I'm going to you know what I'm
going to just generate beta completely
random okay so I'm going to actually use
kind of a the way remember last time we
showed why the
single um uh the the one bit protocol is
zero knowledge I'm going to use that
that idea or in other words I'm going to
first use a simulator first I'm going to
use a honest verifier ZK simulator this
is just short for honest verifier
so I'm going to use a simul I want to
First argue this protocol alpab beta
gamma even repeat it in parallel repeat
it in parallel right so it's honest
verifi your knowledge what does it mean
honest verifier the verifier just sends
beta completely and random so B1 B2 up
to B Lambda completely
randomly then it's zero
knowledge okay so that we kind of saw
last time so first of all I want to
argue that we have honest verifier of
zero knowledge that's the first thing H
the interactive protocol the interactive
but parel repeated okay the interactive
par repeated protocol is onest verifier
zero
knowledge
why well it's very easy what I'm going
to do I'm the simulator what I'm going
to do I'm going to first I need to
generate a transcript what I'm going to
do I'm going to first generate it
generate the B's B1 B2 up to B Lambda at
random now I know what I'm now I know
okay if B equals zero I'm going to just
commit to uh I'm going to commit here
just a completely random hamiltonian
cycle have nothing to do with the graph
if I need to open if B was one I'm going
to just really commit to Pi of G won't
have any antonian cycle in it but I'm
going to commit the pi
ofg so that's going to be my simulation
okay we it's kind of a little bit of
what we did it's similar to what we did
last time but it's even easier because
the verifire is completely honest
okay and let me repeat it how do I
generate this transcript repeated Lambda
times in parallel I need to generate
Alpha Beta gamma that looks like real
I'm going to first generate the beta so
B one of to B Lambda that's the first
thing then I'm going to generate Alpha
I'm gonna take it out of order how do I
generate Alpha well if the B
corresponding to the let's say how the
first Alpha if the B was Zero I know I
need to open to the hamiltonian cycle
I'll I'll I'll commit down random aonian
cycle if the bit B was one I know that I
will need to open the pi and the
non-edges then I'll just commit to Pi G
honestly there's not going to be a homon
cycle in there but I know I'm not going
to be asked to open it and that's what I
do bit by
bit so because I know beta I choose
Alpha to be kind of I exactly choose
Alpha to hit the bad on
purpose okay so that's I I so I I can
choose Alpha so I can choose Alpha Beta
G
to hit the bad but now what do I do with
the hash function how do I I didn't
choose the hash function yet remember
now I'm going to choose the hash
function so now I want to be able now I
want to
choose hash key such that you know eval
the hash key and Alpha actually an G of
alpha but I'm going to Adit G for
Simplicity is equal to that beta which
is the bad beta
how can I do this is it so can I choose
hash key subject to
this I I can choose the public key the
secret key everything you know I can
break the encryption but can I choose it
subject to so actually to tell you the
truth I don't really know if you can do
it but let me change slightly the hash
function and now I'll be able to do that
how do I change the hash
function my hash function
it's going to be the original hash
function plus some fixed kind of Lambda
so the hash function outputs some string
0 one to the Lambda small Lambda I'm
going to just add a random completely
random Lambda bit string to it ah now I
don't like this letter because it
sound I'm going to add Z in 0 one to the
Lambda a random Lambda bit string
now now I'm in business that's easy now
because now I want to make sure that
okay so now I need this to be equal to
Beta no problem I'll choose hash key
honestly I'll compute this and I'll just
in in the CRS so I told you how I
simulate Alpha Beta gamma now I need to
simulate the CRS what does the CRS
consists of it consists of the public
key and the hash key I'll choose the
public key randomly now the hash key
consists of of this part and this part
it's like now two hash keys because it's
the original hash keys but I also add a
fixed Z to it that's my new hash key
okay my new hash
function does the previous hash function
and adds z z is fixed it's part of the
description of the hash
function so now how do I generate the
CRS so for CRS so to generate a CRS I'm
going to choose a random public key a
random hash key
and Z such that this equation is
satisfied I'm going to choose Z which is
equal to I chose Alpha Beta gamma I
chose the I chose already Hashi so this
defines this the the eval so Z is just
going to be beta minus or xor I'm in I'm
over strings so xor this
Evan and this is a good simulation
so now let me go back to your question
which
was so okay so the question was so this
is going to be it's zero knowledge it's
computational zero knowledge it's not
statistical zero knowledge because the
alpha contains actually the when I
simulate it I don't simulate it with a
real Pi of c i simulate it with junk so
it's only computational zero knowledge
but it's statistical um and it's not
even statistical soundness because I'm
using FH so I don't I I don't get
anything computation is zero knowledge
and computational
soundness there is a way to get
statistical if you play with it but this
the way I I explained it it's everything
is
computational
yeah the final
key is the and then you have that random
but in real case it will be just good
good good great great great question so
you're saying you're saying wait so I
changed the I changed the hash key on
you so before
a let me erase
this before the hash key was exactly
what we wrote there that was the hash
key now I changed the hash key now the
hash key is
what tell me first now the hatch key is
going to be
this and
z h a random Z so the has key consists
of the
a public encrypt FH public key publicy
for fully homic encryption an encryption
of a g that's in the analysis going to
be okay in the analysis we're going to
see what it's now changing a little
because it's the Z but some G of fixed
size like uh 0 to the T okay and a
random Z and 01 to the Lambda that's it
now I still want to argue I still want
to argue that that um a that this G is
not bad right I want to argue that I
want to say that uh when I en when I do
the for every Alpha when I do this fom
morphic encryption it's it's not bad so
for which G for which G Star when I do
this so now okay now what I want to
argue let me change this a little bit I
guess now I want to argue that when I do
this and I add Z it's not bad because I
add Z so I want to argue that this is
not equal to this minus Z or I guess xor
we're doing everything xor so minus plus
it's uh don't worry about it we'll we'll
get it later um so I want to AR arue
that this does not equal beta X or Z
because my hash is not just this it's
this X or Z that's my hash so I want to
arue that this X or Z is not beta which
is the same as saying that this is
different than beta X or
Z so now what I'm going to do I'm just
going
to here I'm going to exore in the
analysis I'm going to say sure let me
tell you if you change the G
Star if you take G Star to be the
decryption of bad X or Z and then change
it a little bit xort was just one like 0
z0 one or then I can argue that you get
statistical soundness so in the analysis
I'm going to say okay you started with
this g whatever it was suppose it was
just this G and then I can argue that
for this G it's never equal to this
because exactly as before well if for
this G star it will it was it was equal
to a so now I guess a if it was equal to
you
know beta X or Z then if then the
decryption would be equal and we got a
contradiction so it's exactly the fact
that I did I added Z has no significance
on the proof it's exactly the same
proof okay
so uh so and that's how I I simulate and
now I have a simulator so essentially
the way I proved that it's zero
knowledge is by doing just the honest
verifier zero
knowledge and then what I did in the
with the CRS I chose the Z I chose I
programmed part of the hash key if the
hash key was programmed by someone else
ahead of time and I couldn't touch it I
don't know how to prove a soundness
okay but I I don't know how to
simulate but because I could I could uh
do it I could simulate so the fact that
I could I I had the freedom to program
the hash key that's what allowed me to
simulate and that's
why there's no that's what broke the
tension between and zero knowledge
because in the interactive setting when
there's no
CRS then a simulator really has the same
power as a cheating prover and now say
if there's a simulator there's a
cheating prover and when you think about
the simulator thing about like a
verifier who's like a f verifier like
verifier that behaves like a f hash
function then the simulator is exactly
like a cheating Pro and then you say
well there's no cheating Pro they can't
exist a simulator but in the niic the
simulator has much more power than this
cheating prover he can choose the CRS he
can program the CRS to his desire and
that's what breaks that's kind of what
allows us to get like both F and
noninteractive z and the non like both
sist and noninteractive zero
knowledge any questions yeah does the r
help is
not ah okay okay good good good so now
the qu okay so now the question is what
if beta bad was not unique okay so let
me I'll answer that because I have a
longer question a longer answer to that
but are there any other questions about
this before I I answer that
question okay
so let's step back and see where where
we are I I'm I'm on my way to your to
answer your question because it's about
how General this technique is so I want
I'll get there uh but before I go to J
technique let's see what we did today so
far so we uh started
by a we looked at this protocol the
parallel repeated version and we said
okay this protocol guess what it's F we
actually constructed a certain hash
function very specific hash function
said that with respect to this hash
function we proved
sness and then we proved not only is it
sound respect to now that it's not
interactive we can also prove that it's
zero knowledge like zero knowledge still
maintains by playing with a
CRS okay so uh so even before talking
about generalization I just want to
point this this was a huge open problem
for a very long time to get niic under
lwe uh even though what you saw it's
only circular secure LW or under if you
think under fhe you just saw the
circular secure version but even with a
circle secure
version It's I still find it remarkable
that I'm able to teach it like from
beginning to end uh in one class uh I
hope you understood but it seems like
from your question you were pretty good
A so um I don't know I wish I I could
torture you with previous attempts that
were much worse and much more
complicated so you will really kind of
appreciate this one uh but uh for me who
you know uh shed a lot of tears and
sweat with these previous approaches I
totally appreciate the beauty of of this
one uh
okay but now so so far it was kind of
the focus was on this protocol you know
had this protocol we now we have under
lwe great but how General is this
technique and that's what I want to talk
about next okay how General is it and I
want to point out actually we said we
used this specific structure very little
what did we use a so let me actually a a
let's see what I should
erase let me start here
so we use the fact what did we use here
we used the fact that the beta was
unique that's one thing we used can we
do non-unique betas we can do non-unique
betas but we pay so the number of bad
betas can be let me we call it uh D but
our assumption degrades with one over D
because the way we deal with if there's
many bads then essentially what I do is
I'm going to guess which bad the the
approver is going to cheat with and if
I'm going to choose a b a a random beta
out of this you know dbad betas with
probably one over D I got I got the I
guess his beta correctly and then
everything else goes kind of continues
as if it was unique so we canal with
more betas but we pay with the number of
betas of number of bad betas so if it's
really really huge then it's a problem
okay so we use the fact that it's Unique
beta but we also used one more thing
which is that we can efficiently compute
the bad
beta okay and that the the number
actually I feel like the unique beta as
I think your intuition was well you can
get around it a little bit like is it
unique well you know we can more as long
as I'll guess it and as long as you know
there is some degradation but the
efficiency of the beta we really used it
uh you know and the the C the hash
function computes the bad data so I
don't know at all how to deal with
inefficient a bad betas but let me just
um mention that still this result is
very uh
General and actually you can frame this
result in a much more General framework
uh which is than than kind of for this
specific protocol and the general
framework is the framework that's called
correlation intractable so let me tell
give you like let me just start with the
definition what is a correlation and
tractable hash function so correlation
tractable hash function was you was
defined in order in an attempt to
prove and a hash function is correlation
and tractable essentially if it if works
with it that's kind of the idea so let
me Define a Spector relation R so here's
a
definition a
correlation
intractable hash function Hash Hash
family with respect to a relation R so
we have some
relation
r r is a relation it's like a subset of
X comma
y okay you can think of X as let's say
in 0 1 to the
n and y I know 0 1 to the
n and you can think of both n and M is
like functions of security parameter so
n is like n of Lambda so for any
security
[Music]
parameter you have like a a uh length n
and M and you have a
relation and the hash family's
correlation intractable with respect to
this relation it essentially means that
for any for every poly signs
adversary the probability that this
adversary who gets hash key so the
adversary gets a hash key there's a hash
family let me call it h
that has gen
andal now the aders he gets hash key
generated according to
gen and his goal is to Output
X such
that h of
X is or such that X comma h of X is in
the relation such that X
comma eval hash key of
X is in
R okay so
again a correlation intractable hash
family with suspect to a c relation
R satisfies that for any poly siiz
adversary he gets a hash in the family
his goal is to find an X that hashes to
a y said that X and Y is an r and we say
that this probability is
negligible I didn't finish to write
it okay so for every poly size a there
exists a
negligible
Lambda such that the probability so any
poly siiz adversary he gets a random
hash key in the family and he's able to
find X at that h of X so that X comma h
of x is in R only with n probability so
he he always EV kind of uh evades the
why in the
relation that's called correlation
attractable hash
family for for specific
R questions about about the
definition so first note this makes
sense so I want to say do we have a
correlation tractable hash family and
for which relations
okay so this is kind of a major open
question because this is very related to
F so F we know take x n in the
language we want so think of Alpha Beta
gamma just think for three messages
everything I say now extends to more but
let's think of of three it extends to
constant at least but let's think of
three for
Simplicity so we want to evade like not
to tach to be correlation TR so the
relation in our case in F CH the
relation is like Alpha and beta are in
the relation if there exists a gamma
that will make it
accept Okay so for the relation contains
Alpha and the bad betas and we want to
avoid these bad betas so we want to say
that any adversary that gets a hash key
managed to hit a bad beta onlyn with
probability so there may there may exist
Alphas but he won't find them it'll be
hard for him to find kind of a X or an
alpha that hashes to Beta that is
bad okay and here I'm the idea is here
take any inter take any think of any
interactive proof like of the form Alpha
Beta
gamma and I want to say think the
relation think of the relation being all
the the relations of X take X not in the
language I guess now this x this x
corresponds to Alpha here but takes any
X not in the language and the relation
is all the alpha
beta so that exists a gamma
accepting so that Alpha Beta gamma is
accepting and I know that for every
Alpha there's very very few betas and I
want to say that the adversary output
Alpha Beta and the the relation like
alpas that the hash of alpha is in the
relation only with NE probability then I
have soundness of the
Fe was that too fast should I repeat the
connection to
F let me repeat it once more okay so I
want to argue that I have correlation
tractable hash family for a lot of
relations
actually before I I go note I can't hope
to have it for any relation the relation
has to be sparse if the relation is
everything maybe the everything every X
Y is in the relation then of course a
hash will hit like
trivial so the most I can hope for so
the question I really want to ask or the
most like the most general question
is
does there
exist uh correlation intractable hash
for every
evasive or also people sometimes call it
sparse
relation that's the question and by a
vas of over by sparse I just mean that
for every X there are very few y's that
are in the
relation so sparse means ah forgot me
sparse means this
this
means that for every X the probability
over a random
y that XY is in R is
negligible
yeah
for yes yes yes yes yes good okay good
so now let's go to yeah so now let's go
to F good so I want to ask if the exist
a correlation trable for every such
evasive or sparse language uh relation
now if there is I'm done why if there if
you can prove that there's correlation
tractable hat for every sparse
language I here's now I'll tell you now
here's the fature take X not in the
language the uh so take the correlation
tractable hash you had said there's a
correlation tractable hash take that
hash function now what I'm going to do
now I want to now take ex the language I
my the evasive relation that I look at
is this relation Alpha Beta is in the
relation if there exists gamma of course
it's evasive because it's a proof mean
there there's only negligible amount of
betas I can answer so it's evasive and
therefore the probability that you hit a
bad beta is negligible I'm done
proof so if I have a collision hash that
works for any Bas so for any Bas of
relation this holds for any R then I'm
good okay so if that for any R yes that
for any
R you don't hit it then I'm done
sound okay so then this was actually um
defined in an earlier work like 2004
maybe I don't really remember but a
while a while
back and then people ask okay so we need
to construct this evasive
functions so they proed that the random
Oracle model is the random Oracle is an
evasive function but beyond that they
were
stuck and what this result that the
ketti Lombardi weeks result show so let
me now uh def uh State the result in in
more general terms what it shows that
there exists a correlation intractable
hash for every
relation that is
a here okay for any relation that is
they call it
searchable I'll
explain in
time
T So search on time T just means that
searchable means that for every Alpha
there's a unique beta it's a search
problem it's like for every Alpha
there's a unique beta beta and this beta
can be computed in time
T so what they show is there exists a
coration in hash correlation intractable
hash for every that that is correlation
intractable for every relation
searchable in time T and this hash the
time to compute the hash grows with
T so essentially what they say is for
every polinomial t because the hatch
grows with T so for every polinomial
T there exists a Corr a a hash function
that grow depends on T and it's
correlation intractable with respect to
all relations that are searchable in
time T and again relation searchable in
time t
means that for every uh Alpha let me
don't note the relation in by this and
not X because
X often
denotes uh input and I want to think of
the relation as Alpha Beta instead of X
Y because then there's a confusion
between the X here and the X instance so
it just means that for that the relation
is a set of alpha
betas such that for every Alpha there
exists a
unique at most a unique maybe less but
at most uh so
at
most
unique
beta such that Alpha Beta is in R
and to go from alpha to Beta or B if
there's no beta is
computable in time
t Okay so a searchable relation means
for every Alpha there's a unique beta at
most unique maybe there's no beta but if
there is a beta it's Unique and from
alpha to compute the beta corresponding
to it in the relation can be done in
time
T and what they showed is that there
exists a single hash family so first
note of course of course if you fix a
relation that's searchable in time T of
course there's a hash that's correlation
tractable with respect to it just take
compute the beta and add
one okay again let me
uh let me move there so we'll have
[Applause]
this so we want to show a correlation
intractable hash with respect
to any relation that's searchable in
time te
and first I want to note I want one hash
that's correlation attractable for all
relations of course if you first choose
a relation if you first Cho of course
this what I'm saying now is a trivial
for any T
time
searchable relation there exists a
correlation intractable hash running in
time t
or close to
T that's easy what is the hash the hash
of
alpha will just be the beta that you're
searching for in the relation plus
one just avoid it somehow plus I
whatever one like just move move out of
the beta that's it that's
easy but what they show is something
much stronger they show the oppos they
show the the reverse order of
quantifiers they show that there exist
one hash
family and this has family is
correlation intractable for all T time
searchable
relations that's the difference
okay so let's so that's kind of what I
want to end end with I'm I want to prove
it to you because we we saw this proof
it's exactly the same thing but let's
just see it in this language but before
we go over the proof again or or just
remind the proof it's a so this is a
much stronger a this is a pretty general
statement and this thing
ment uh is used in many follow-up works
for
example this can be used uh almost to
prove the soundness of gkr for example
so or or some check let's do some check
for Simplicity because that's all the
ideas are there how can you do how can
you prove F sound for some check let's
just recall just for a
minute what the sum check is just so you
see how it it's not immediate by the way
it requires more crypto but I want to
give you a sense a little bit of the why
this is very useful so it's not
immediate but it definitely uses this
fact okay so let's see why let's as an
example let's look at the sum check so
suppose I have I want to prove that sum
of G B1 up to BM is equal to some value
V and I wanted do it in the in in the
F so what is the relation let's see it's
many rounds so it's harder but let's
just look at the first round for a
second so or the first three rounds so
we have a prover and a verifier suppose
this is false right so it's this is
actually it's actually
false but the Prov is trying to cheat me
so now the first thing the prover does
if you remember he gives a univariant
polinomial
now this uni mod is wrong I I'll put
star because it's wrong why because I
know the value here is actually not v
he's proving that it's V he should be
giving the value that he should be
giving is
G1 which is sum of G of
G on B2 up to BM
that's what he should be
giving and I would check that when you
take this and sum it only over B1 you
get V but of course he's not going to
give me this because when you sum this
over B1 it's not V because the real
answer this is not V so he will give me
another one
star what are the bad betas the bad
betas so now beta bad
are all the elements T in the
field such that G1
star is equal now with this now he can
cheat if he managed to give me G star
that's equal to GT now he kind of
continues like with a good now he has a
true statement lucky him so these are
going to be really bad for me but there
are very few of them like the degree the
univ degree of this G so as long as I
don't hit the degrees d as long as I
don't hit this D bad I'm
good and it's pretty easy to compute
this thing because I'm gonna hard like I
I'm gonna so Computing G1 may be hard
but I can hardwire it it's like a trapo
I have this I have this statement I can
use G1 as a
trapo and now compute once I have G1 as
a trapo given G1 star Computing all the
inputs that collide with my G1 there
algorithms there's efficient algorithms
for this so now it's efficient so all I
I need to avoid so it's not searchable
it's not one beta like we have here it's
D betas but to go from one to d as I
said you just guess you lose a factor of
D it's really extends pretty easily so
you apply
done okay it's not that easy the reason
it's not that easy is because now a t
comes out from the
F and the next G depends on this T
because the next G is going to be the
next G Star the next real G G2 is going
to
be some G that the real G here
T1 and then B3 da d d d d d da so I
don't I I I can't hardwire G2 ahead of
time I don't know what T1 is things are
not as simple so there's more it's not a
but the first me the first part is
Trivial and then you need to add add to
throw on it a little more crypto and do
some more work but it's this technique
is used to prove gkr this technique is
also used to prove the result of churi
Jin and Jen Jen and Jin where Jen Jong
Jin is gonna uh present next class where
they use FIA to prove uh this uh the
existence of a batch AR batch
non-interactive argument so he'll
explain what that is next time but again
this technique so this technique is
really is pretty
General
okay question before I just kind of REM
remind you why why this
holds questions yeah so you
said compute all
the keys Pi a random one okay exactly so
in the analysis you can think of it yeah
I'm going to so I have a cheating prover
and ah okay it's a bit complicated but
yes in in the analysis I'm going to say
look I have a cheating prover so it
means he he cheats with respect to one
random with a random one here with
probability one over D and then I'm
going to get a contradict contradiction
because it's going to cheat with anyone
with netive probability for each one fix
it with that he's going to CH with that
with negtive probability so then you
Union bound kind of and say okay so for
he cheat the probability that he cheats
with any of these is D times negligible
so as long as D is polinomial you're
good what will our function look like
it's the exact same so okay so actually
let me what so the question what was our
hash function look like I'll I'll tell
you exactly what it is when I prove this
and you'll see it's the exact same hash
function so I say here and that's the
hash function that I'll use up there I
say here
that there exists a hash function that's
correlation tractable respect to any T
time searchable relation what is this
hash function I'll tell you so the hash
function so to say hash family I need to
say what's
gen and what's
Ian so here is the
Gen help me out what do the gend do
key exactly he computes a public key for
the fhe and encrypt something nobody
cares we're never going to decrypt it it
encrypts with public key just let's say
the all zero string so it's not exactly
T it's a little more than T we'll it's
the T we'll see what encrypts T Prime
like 0 t Prime T Prime is going to be
very similar to T but tiny bit more t
plus the decryption plus one we'll see
but that that's the that's gen it
outputs a publicy an encryption of a
bunch of zeros how many a little more
than T we'll see the exact number that's
what gen does what does eval
do eval given this this hash key so this
is a hash key and given
alpha or yeah Alpha what it does it
simply
computes the eval of the FH
so FH can be evaluated a new Alpha and
the cipher text and let me call this G
hat because it's kind of describes a
circuit and G hat which is what it does
it essentially computes G of alpha
encryption that's what this eval of f
does it takes this is a universal
circuit takes this input a circuit g a
description of circuit G and outputs G
of alpha
and this event does this under the hood
so he outputs whatever is encrypted here
the all zero circuit whatever a
description of this is let's say
description of
circuit so in that case it'll be
encryption of zero that's what it does
that's the that's the hash function that
I'm going to argue as correlation
intractable for every relation uh for
every T time searchable
relation so now give me your favorite T
time searchable relation and I'll show
you why it's a correlation tractable
with respect to it so okay you give me
your favorite relation let me say a
relation is a bunch of Alpha and F of
alpha it's searchable so there's
some function that for every Alpha
there's a unique beta find the unique
beta okay if if in in the more General
case where there's D think of there's d
fs like so there's a few more but for
one you can think of just one okay so
now now I want to argue there's no way
you can find okay so I'm going to I'm
going to argue you can't find F1 but if
there's more I'll I'll then you also
can't find F2 and F3 but let me focus on
the first F let's see if there's only
one I'm going to show you on the first F
so you cannot there's no way why
because if you could if the adversary
given hash
key could find Alpha so that the hash of
alpha is f of alpha then he could also
do it in the case where I
replace Alpha with where I replace G
with a fake G and my fake G that I'm
going to replace it
with
so so
Suppose there exists an adversary that
breaks then okay so uh that so there
exists an adversary that such that
the adversary given hash key outputs
Alpha such
that eval of H key and
Alpha is equal to F of alpha that's what
we want to avoid we say no you shouldn't
be able to find something in in the
relation if you can if you can do that
with probability greater than some
Epsilon then I claim then
a succeeds in the same thing
succeeds with probability close like
close to Epsilon
also by semantic security also with HK
star a different HK and what is HK star
this it generates the same public key
but it generates an encryption of G Star
not of G so here I encrypted all zero g
was all zero I'm encrypting a new g a g
star what is
gar g
star uh an
input Alpha outputs the decryption I
know weird it has secret key hard wired
in it and it outputs the
decryption of kind of the bad
function an alpha
XR with
one and we show that actually if this is
what you put
there you really that you you never it's
impossible to Output F ofx this is never
it's never the case so we want to say
that G Star
theal G Star
Alpha is never F of f of alpha it's just
never why because if it was then if you
decrypt this and decrypt this you would
get the same value but if you decrypt
this you get G Star Alpha and if you
decrypt this you get this and they're
not the
same
yeah what
is no F sorry I'm uh let me so we have a
a t time searchable relation T time
searchable relation it means that for
every alha there's a unique beta so I
call this beta sorry sorry so then is
this over like all
good so exactly so I want to say I say I
constructed this hash family that just
has an encryption and he does
computation under the hood and I'm
saying this hash family it's a
correlation and tractable with respect
to every T time searchable relation why
fix your favorite T time searchable
relation your favorite one the fact that
it's searchable means that for every
Alpha there's a unique beta and it's
computable in time T so I call F the
function that computes this beta and now
I say look there's no way an adversary
can find Alpha for which the hash
function takes him to to Beta to F of
alpha because if he could he could also
do it where I where the hash key which
encrypts zero actually
encrypts this G Star another G what is g
g star now G star depends on this F but
it's under the hood nobody can tell the
difference and this G Star it decrypts
this F even though f is not a cipher
attack so it's a very weird thing to do
but it decrypts this F and changes
something changes a bit and now I want
to say the hash gives you encryption of
G Star Alpha an encryption of gar Alpha
cannot be F of alpha there's no way
because if it was any encryption
actually because if it was if you
decrypted this and decrypted this you
would get the same thing but you decrypt
this you get G Star
Alpha and G starpha is not decryption of
f of alpha by by Design
so once you change the hash key to this
you're
statistically C and and all powerful
adversary cannot hit F so there's some
kind of we use computational assumption
but then once we once we move to Gar we
we can we don't care about the
Assumption anymore we're in statistical
land even in all powerful adversary
cannot
cheat sorry I don't to ask no no it's
fantastic question this still fine if
the adversary picks the relation after
it knows the hash key exact H yeah yeah
exactly you're right so think about this
the adversary get the hash key public
key and encryption of something
encryption of zero now he gives me f he
tells me f with this F I can cheat I can
find I can I'm get really okay can you
distinguish between encryption of the
all zero and encryption assuming
circular security yeah cuz this is kind
of subse secret key but let's so it's
I'm I'm using semantic this gar depends
on F and then the secret key but
assuming you can't break semantic
security circle of
security then he even if he chooses F he
cannot distinguish between encryption of
G star and encryption of zero assuming
circular secure F I guess what prevents
from just piing like f evaluation of
Alpha and
why can't F just be like
evaluation like why can't he's just said
oh okay good point hold on you're saying
why
a no okay okay okay sorry
a no it's kind of weird yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah no no no you're right okay
sorry sorry sorry uh he can choose f
after he sees the hash family the hash
family the hash family no once you have
the specific key then you're right
you'll just be the hash key sorry I I
miss I yeah there's one hash family
after he sees the hash family he can
choose the relation but of course for
the specific hash
key
he'll yeah then yeah and and yeah
exactly and that should just follow like
the fact the cyer text is randomized
right like once you have an an
encryption of had like predicting the
evaluation should be very exactly
exactly exactly and just going back this
T Prime is the time the the size of G
Star so it's a little more than F
because you also need to decrypt but
it's very very similar to have just
uh
question this like the same kind of
issue as to why it mattered that in some
TR like the later bad relations depended
on the verifier messages it's like if
that wasn't the case then this exactly
exactly exactly that was the same issue
that came in GK that the things the T
dependent yeah yeah that me yeah great
great great question anybody else yeah I
still don't
see
how if f is if f is what is not unique
okay good so if f is what not unique
what I'm going to show suppose Alpha has
many FS F1 up to FD associated with them
then I'm going to say look first let me
argue that adversary cannot the
probability that he outputs F1 is
negligible so for every the probability
that he outputs Alpha and F1 of alpha is
negligible this I kind of convinced
you but that's Al also for F2 and for F3
oh so you use many yeah I'm just using
exactly in the anal exactly so I'm
saying exactly in the analysis I'm going
to change my G Star exactly
fantastic yeah so a simar idea how you
define like our Cal or like relations
that have like many Bas instead of
exactly the the doing the many betas the
only difference is it's exact same proof
except that I'll I'll need to kind of
choose one of them a I I'll degrade with
d because I'm going to show for each one
the probability that with that one you
succeed is negligible and then I'll just
do a union bound I guess my question a
little I guess in
cist uh CI function for all relations
that are searchable in time and I was
trying to how to extend the r definition
to handle like cases where beta isn't
easy yeah exactly so yeah essentially
think of r instead of searchable it's
like it has like F1 so for each Alpha
there's F1 of alpha up to FD of alpha
these are the betas corresponding to it
so now that's your relation that's yeah
okay great okay we're out of time guys
thank you so much have a great peaceful
fun Thanksgiving and I'll see you
uh not the week after but the week after
after