Disentangling causation from a mere
correlation is one of the main jobs of
an empirical economist. [music] In 1988,
a Harvard University dean interviewed a
bunch of Harvard freshmen. He found that
the students who taken an SAT prep
course on average did worse on the SAT
than [music] those who didn't take a
course. So, the dean looked at his data
and concluded the prep courses caused
students to do worse on the exam. That's
the dean's interpretation of the data.
But maybe students with a lower test
taking [music] ability were the ones
signing up for the prep courses to try
to catch up. In a sense, the lower test
scores caused the students to want to
enroll in a prep course in the first
place. The point here isn't that the
dean is definitely wrong. The point is
that we just don't know what the causal
[music] story is if all we have is a
correlation between prep courses and SAT
scores.
>> Find your MIT moment. [music] Visit
learn.mmit.edu.