thank you um for for coming back uh or
for joining us if you have not been in
here before um so just again to welcome
you to a a series of sessions this
afternoon on generative Ai and copyright
um that sponsored by the MIT schwarzman
College of computing um and just I'll
start by introducing myself and then uh
I'll introduce Clare Schneider uh
momentarily um but I'm a professor in
the history Department um uh here at MIT
um and that usually I follow that by
saying yes you can major in history at
MIT um and I teach and publish uh in the
field of 20th century US legal history
um and and teach students about
questions uh sort of like this um full
disclosure um I am uh I am not a lawyer
um uh although for years I have taught
uh many MIT students who have gone on to
become lawyers um and uh can advise you
I I always say I can talk you into law
school or out of law school but you have
to tell me which one um you want and and
one thing I also wanted to just share
with everyone in the community uh here
if you are looking for a lawyer um I
also like to uh alert people and
particularly students um as or really
just students um to the MIT Buu student
Innovation law clinic um this is a free
and confidential legal service for MIT
students undergrad or grad who uh are
seeking um or may not even know that
they should be seeking uh legal
assistance related to their research
advocacy or creative projects um and so
if you are a student um or know a
student who would benefit from this I'm
happy to uh give you information about
that
group um what I'm going to do before uh
before CLA starts is just um give a a
brief sketch of uh some of the range of
scholarly views around some of the
questions that we were discussing with
um um just uh in the previous hour um
and one of the remarkable things about
the scholarly approaches to generative
Ai and copyright is there's actually one
thing that pretty much everyone agrees
on uh in the legal scholarship World
which is that the uh the existing
copyright regime um is not really a good
fit um for this new emerging
technology um but that's about where the
uh consensus breaks down um and beyond
that um Scholars um who may themselves
not be sort of practicing attorneys
defending either authors or AI companies
um but Scholars thinking kind of more
conceptually about this um differ in
terms of whether that means the
technology needs to be more rigorously
regulated to bring it into line with the
existing copyright regime or that the
copyright regime needs to be reformed um
in order to accommodate the new
technology um and this is some version
of uh the chicken and egg or if you
remember the old Reese's Peanut Butter
Cup uh commercial you know you got your
peanut butter in my chocolate um it's
it's obviously there will be a series of
both of these unfolding over the next
few years um as the Law changes um and
as the technology continues to evolve
and also to be subject to uh regulation
both in the United States and in other
jurisdictions like the UK or the EU um
but just to give you a sense of it you
know one of the first um there are those
who really feel um that that that
copyright is in fact actually um the
thing to defend and renew um by um and
using the law to bring the technology um
into alignment with it um and who do
really feel um that uh that the task is
basically to uh sort of accelerate and
expand regulation um to meet the new
technology u a good place to look for
this is in a piece in an article called
uh in a journal called issues in science
of Technology this is published by the
National Academy of Sciences um by Kate
Crawford a professor at USC and the
author of the atlas of of AI an
excellent book and her co-author NYU Law
Professor Jason Schultz um who uh
together sort of reflect on the ways
that generative AI has as they put it
been driving copyright into a crisis and
just to briefly quote from their work it
may be time to develop concepts of
intellectual property with a stronger
focus on equity and creativity as
opposed to economic incentives for media
corporations we are seeing we meaning
the authors are seeing early prototypes
emerge from the recent collective
bargaining agreements for writers actors
and directors many of whom lack
copyrights but are nonetheless less at
the creative core of film making the
lessons we learned from them could set a
powerful precedent for how to pluralize
intellectual property making a better
world will require a deeper
philosophical engagement with what it is
to create who has a say and how
Creations can be used and who should
profit now a second almost uh sort of
very different sort of approach um is uh
coming from people who have been argued
in some ways that the copyright regime
um is not only a bad fit for this new
technology but maybe has been broken for
a very long time um and that have been
seeking to dismantle it jettison it or
develop alternatives to it um whether
they're coming from Worlds of of Open
Source software open publishing um open
uh access worlds um more generally um
one really great place to look for this
is an an an essay published in the
journal science um by the law professor
Pam Pamela Samuelson from uh the
University of California at Berkeley um
who has really sort of been at the
Forefront of sort of arguing against
copyright uh for a very long time and so
in some ways is sort of adapting her
argument against copyright to the new
technology of generative AI itself um
and argues that in the end uh this this
task uh requires balancing the
legitimate interest of copyright owners
to prevent misappropriations of their
works that undermine incentives to
create with the legitimate interests of
developers of Innovative Technologies
and followon creators who need some
breathing space in which they too can
innovate um and so as we talked about in
the in the the previous session you know
trying to find that win-win um for both
creators um and uh and sort of AI
innovators at the same time is really uh
as a high stakes uh task these days um
one place that that I personally and and
many in the MIT Community have looked to
this um is from our as past engagement
with an organization called Creative
Commons uh Creative Commons is an
international nonprofit uh that exists
to build a network for the open sharing
of knowledge and culture um in many ways
emerges from from the MIT community and
and key players here and in recent years
has been advocating the creation and
Adoption of preference signals um ways
that creators can signal uh to large
language model developers uh the
Creator's preference for how their
material is or isn't used um so just as
when you would publish a work and maybe
have a Creative Commons license on it CC
CC by Etc and there may emerge sort of
from the community um sort of preference
signals that you could use as an author
uh to communicate whether you wish your
model you know wish your your materials
to be trained with AI wish them not to
be or train not trained trained you know
trained by AI or ingested by AI Etc um
and they have also been arguing for a
broader Suite of communication uh tools
um and these may or may not necessarily
be uh legally enforcable mechanisms
right what they aim instead is to as
they as Creative Commons puts it is to
define a new vocabulary and establish
new norms for sharing and reuse in the
world of generative AI right so as we
look forward from this afternoon I think
that kind of work um sort of thoughtful
creation um is is what is going to be
necessary to get us to the kind of next
phase um past this moment where Scholars
uh creatives and in fact many uh large
language model developers themselves
agree that the existing copyright regime
is not a good fit for the technology as
it
exists now uh what does all this mean
you know uh at MIT right um and so we're
very lucky to have with us today uh a
member of mit's office of General
Council um and we're particularly likely
to have her today as you can imagine um
uh uh lawyers um are very busy um these
days um reading the news and and
responding to it um so we appreciate CLA
taking some time uh to join us here CLA
fine Schneider is a member uh she's
Council uh to the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology she's been with
the ogc since September of 2018 and her
areas of focus at MIT include
intellectual property sponsored research
conflict of interest entrepreneurial
activities and academic and business
transactions and for uh some time now
maybe uh since around
2023 um she has been sort of part of U
of people of groups of people at MIT who
have been helping the community
understand how generative AI is changing
the way that we teach learn and research
uh at MIT she is a trained attorney uh
with a degree from the Boston University
School of Law um and with previous years
of experience before MIT uh in private
practice at mince Levan and Wilmer har
and so with that I'll turn it over to
Claire thank you so much Chris and um I
wish that I had had you as a history
Professor so you could have talked me
out of law school but
that that ship has sailed yes um and I
know this is a small group so tell me if
the microphone is too loud and I will
adjust it so I'm going to do a bit of
internal marketing since it's such a
small group and just ask who in this
audience has had occasion um some might
say for bad but I would say for good to
interact with the general council's
office Chris knows us well we have one
other taker Okay so I just want to give
a a very very brief overview um of who
we are and what we do at The Institute
so of course um as Chris said I am an
attorney um myself and 10 other Council
uh are in our general council's office
and then we also have a deputy general
counsel and the vice president general
counsel uh Mark Devan chenzo um we all
represent the Institute first and
foremost for most but it's obviously
more complicated than that because there
are many stakeholders within the
Institute right so we often are working
for and with groups of stakeholders and
part of our job is to figure out how
those interests are aligned with the
interests of MIT so that we can uh be
sure that we are always representing MIT
um we do a variety of things we give
counsel we give advice we defend the
institute in litigation we represent the
The Institute in the rare instances when
we're on the other side of the V and
litigation um we advise on transactions
we advise on policy issues um and we
generally act as thought Partners to
other senior leaders on campus to
administrators to faculty and also um to
graduate students and other students as
Chris noted and I'm so glad you called
out the Buu law
um MIT law clinic because it's a great
resource for our students because we in
the ogc can't represent students
individually whether they're undergrad
or or grad students um but I find in my
practice personally that I spend a lot
of time talking to students especially
about intellectual property and
entrepreneurial activities um and as
Chris said my focus really is primarily
intellectual property I do not uh take
part in actually protect inventions on
campus so you know our technology
licensing office does that and I I work
closely with them at times and advise
them but mostly I'm thinking about um
intellectual property in terms of big
transactions technology licensing IP
terms that we are granting to our
industry sponsors so many of you may
work on or spis may have industry
sponsored research agreements um and in
exchange for funding research we permit
the company to elect um to exercise
rights to intellectual property
developed under those sponsored research
agreements um so there's lots of ways in
which IP sort of touches the day in and
day out functions of MIT but as Chris
alluded to there's also these sort of
sea shifts that happen that also touch
on IP um in this case mostly copyright
but there are um patent questions that
surround generative AI too and so I have
really had the Good Fortune of being at
MIT during this sea shift cuz obviously
it is
fascinating um I did want to sort of ask
you know the audience cuz for for me I
mean generative AI for many of you who
are engineers and scientists this is not
all that new um of course there's been
significant leaps in the past few years
I actually went to Dartmouth as an
undergrad and Dartmouth is always
touting the fact that like they had the
first artificial intelligence conference
back in the 50s or that's what that's
what they say they lay claim to that
whether or not it's true um so of of
course I am aware and have been for some
time that researchers and scientists
have been working on this but I would
say from from a legal perspective and
the tentacles that generative AI has had
um in my world and at MIT as a whole has
really as Chris said happened in the in
the past few years I think you know
since early winter J you know in
2023 um and it's now pervasive you know
it's it's a real Zeitgeist and it's
changing kind of all aspects of um of my
practice and I think others others like
me so I I wanted to start by before we
get a little bit more deeply into the
precise topic today of data and content
generators and creators at MIT I wanted
to kind of give a
broad swath or almost a list of all the
different places and community members
on campus um that we're trying to track
when we think about um you know ways in
which generative AI issues are affect
ing stakeholders at MIT so we've been
Loosely and you know as we go on I don't
know if we'll wait till Q&A or feel free
to raise your hand now but you know
we're we're starting to collect this
information um you wouldn't necessarily
be able to go to MIT you know the MIT
website and find a lot of this written
down but we are starting to think about
it and we've been breaking these
categories into three groups so we're
thinking about community members
obviously who use generative AI tools
we're thinking about MIT community
members who create generate models so AI
systems and then of course um most of
the MIT Community who is generating
content that can be used by both MIT
community members to train models in you
know during research efforts or um by
Third parties that can use that content
to train third party models by virtue of
the fact that we have an open campus and
the goal of fundamental research is to
publish right so um in fact I don't know
if any of you know this maybe some of
you do that actually in I think it's
section 14.1 or something like that of
P&P um is our open research campus
policy and indeed all research on campus
must be open and must be published and
if it's not intended to be there is a
special
escalation um process that goes all the
way up to the vice president for
research of course that excludes Lincoln
lab which has its own rules and much of
what Lincoln does um is of course not
published so this is really
fundamental you know to who MIT is and I
think you know Chris and I will both
touch on this a little bit more later
but that's when we think of those three
categories that's kind of what we're
we're trying to track and when I say
track I mean if issues
concerns legal rules or
regulations um and then Downstream
consequences or exposure from taking one
position or taking another position
that's you know and then the type of
guidance we need to provide to MIT
community members that's what I say when
I mean like sort of keeping track of all
of these different categories so um with
with respect to the first one which is
kind of the easiest and the the category
in which I think you'll find most of our
peers including MIT do have some
guidance out already it's using tools
right so how to use them responsibly um
should you be downloading the open-
source version of chat GPT or should you
be using the one that we have a license
to under an Enterprise um license
agreement um do you have the right
permissions in place to be using tools
for certain projects so of course you
all and I assume mostly researchers in
this room though correct me are using
tools for research purposes but remember
we have a lot of other folks you know in
HR or admissions who might want to use
these tools and that's that's a very
different story right we have to think
about what data is being used and
inputed into these tools in terms of
sensitivity Etc but back to the
researcher side we also have to be
giving guidance to researchers who are
using thirdparty Tools in terms of using
and inputting unpublished research
results right will you is does that
constitute a public disclosure under the
patent and trademark office's rules such
that you might be limited in the patent
protection that you could get from
subsequent outputs or inventions after
inputting that data so these are all um
items that we are trying to think
through and and provide guidance about
but those are those are a little bit
simpler and I think that we all kind of
generally understand the issues that we
need to think
about the second category
is you know for the developers of models
and I think you know traditionally we
don't give a lot of uh structure and
Scaffolding nor I do I think we should
you know necessarily to piis and
researchers when they are putting
together their Grant proposals um scopes
of work under industry sponsored
research agreements and thinking through
the research that they want to pursue
that is has never been um part of the
MIT you know core but as we think about
models that may have risk associated
with them and may be regulated and when
we think about the data going into those
models that also May um be associated
with risk and have potential you know
legal ramifications of using data in one
way or another we're starting to try to
get our arms around that and thinking
about what kind of guidance can we give
researchers as they are putting together
research projects um and obviously this
is early stages there's a lot of
conversations happening among and
between research administrators dlcis
and faculty to think through this um but
it it really needs to stem from how we
think about when and where this model
will be released and accessible outside
of MIT um and again as I said before
traditionally you know models um are
publicly released it is my understanding
that for publication purposes and you
know for certain journals um there are
requirements about
releasing uh Parts at least of
algorithms and data sets etc for
replicability and transparency Etc
there's also rules under certain federal
awards that require data to be be
promptly released and easily
accessible and we are trying to think
through sort of are there um are there
guide posts that need to be considered
when doing this for
instance there are regulations that have
started to be developed there is a EU AI
act which many of you may be aware of
that has officially come into Force um
the EU is very frequently ahead of the
US in terms of Broad and sweeping and
detailed regulation that happened with
gdpr and data privacy some years ago as
well um in America of course the Biden
Administration put out their executive
order an AI that addressed some of these
topics in October
2023 um that order will probably be
revoked under the Trump
Administration but regardless we can
assume that there will be regulations
that will apply to AI systems and keep
using that word AI systems it might not
be something that rolls off the tongue
for all of you but that is because it
was defined as such in the Biden
executive order so trying to keep some
of the wording the same um we can assume
that these models will be regulated in
some way shape or form even if they are
used just for research purposes or
developed in the context of research and
that is really you know that's that's
different and when Chris alluded to
before sort of the traditional IP rules
not necessarily fitting with generative
AI um I think this is a little bit
similar in the sort of regulatory space
because previously this is a good
analogy um and you may know this export
control
rules I won't say they don't apply but
they're they're less of a thing for MIT
because everything we do falls under the
fundamental research exception and under
that fundamental research exemption
under the export control rules we don't
have to worry about getting certain
licenses from the government to share
certain otherwise sensitive technology
with non- us persons um on our campus
for instance that's not true for for um
companies that are not operating under
the phom fundamental research exemption
caveat to that is that those rules under
the Trump Administration we could see
some of that change too which would be
really
unfortunate but the way this relates um
to the models is that I think
historically the thought was if you
wrote software code and you put it on
GitHub and you you know slapped a you
know MIT open- Source Institute approved
license on it um you didn't have to
really do much more than that now the
thinking is if there is a model that
perhaps was trained um with very very
large data sets or with high compute
power or otherwise has dual use
capabilities or Falls in you know the
number of other buckets that the EU AI
act references as being potentially high
risk um that we have to be and I mean we
MIT as an Institute have to be more
thoughtful about who um might pick that
model up and run with it and use it for
purposes that perhaps were unintended or
for which we now somehow um are going to
be I don't want to I don't want to use
the word
responsible lightly but you know
responsible for in some way shape or
form whether that's legal responsibility
or reputational or
otherwise so we're we're trying to get
our arms around that I can give you I
wrote it down here it might be
interesting the EU AI act um thinks
about sort of various levels of models
in terms of risk categories you may have
seen this there's high risk medium risk
low risk and then kind of like no risk
you can do whatever you want um and
there's a lot of reporting obligations
and restrictions for high-risk models
and those are models that at least the
EU would Define as obviously I noted
before correlated to compute power dual
use capabilities um also the capability
to be used for purposes that are judged
to be functions that could result in
high-risk outcomes if performed
improperly well that's quite broad right
um or whose output serves as a basis for
decisions or actions that have a legal
or significant effect on an individual
or community so you could imagine um law
enforcement you could imagine hiring
decisions admissions decisions Etc um
but you could also imagine a model you
know being used for a purpose that was
otherwise not intended by researchers at
MIT but shared with collaborators and
research sponsors so these are all you
know areas it's a little bit off topic
from the what we're talking about today
but they're it's all connected and one
of the uh most precise ways it's
connected is that the EU AI act requires
that for all high-risk and medium risk
models and this includes models being
developed at research
institutions that there is um TR
traceability of the data that is
ingested and used to create the models
and that all the appropriate consents
and permissions have been you know uh
have been gotten for for the data that's
being used um that is not something
necessarily that we currently bake in to
our research projects although we do
have many researchers on campus who are
dutifully and diligently working with um
the libraries and other stor of content
that we'll talk about in a moment to try
to access data for training purposes in
permissible
ways so I think that now when we talk
about you know the the third topic the
third category that I was mentioning
before that's really the the focus of
today's um Talk which are data and
content creators and
generators um we really think about sort
of a few different buckets we think
about researchers who are accessing
other MIT content for their own research
purposes and we think about researchers
who are accessing thirdparty contact
content for research purposes and then
we also think about all the researchers
who make their own content available
perhaps as part of a journal or other
scholarly publication um and now want to
have a voice or a say which is very
appropriate into how that content is
going to be used moving
forward and the libraries and open
learning um you know Chris can talk to
us more about Open learning are two of
our biggest stewards of content that MIT
either owns
licenses or otherwise um houses for lack
of a better word at MIT and those
offices on campus really are trying to
think very thoughtfully about how to
continue to give researchers the access
they need under the appropriate
permissions preserve the openness of
content and encourage Scholars to
continue to embrace the value of that
openness while at the same time
acknowledging that sometimes this
content is being used um either for
purposes that are not aligned with that
author or content generator's principles
or values or in a way that they're just
not aware of which of course takes away
um you know some autonomy and and makes
it a little uh less likely perhaps
subconsciously to want to make things
available and open in the future
um I think there are a a very and and
and those categories that I just named
of course there's overlap right so you
could be a researcher training a model
who is desperate to access content from
a thirdparty publisher through an
agreement with the libraries let's just
say and that thirdparty publisher could
be pushing back on the librar about
giving access to that data for training
purposes and the research could be very
frustrated on the other hand that
researcher could have published a book
let's just say with the MIT press and
could now be being asked to opt in to
licensing that book to open AI or Google
to train their commercial product and
that researcher could have a very
different
perspective um on whether and to what
extent to allow that access um I also
think there's a really big difference in
perspectives you know at MIT in terms of
if we make if we don't make our content
available and open to anybody to train
models um those models and the public
will suffer right because we at MIT you
at MIT have the best science right so we
want the best science to go into
training um others feel that if we have
no control over how content is used for
training especially outside of MIT we
will be disrupting the way that um
attribution has worked for you know
science and scholarly
advancement um for decades if not
centuries so I think and I want to be
mindful of time here um I think one of
the the big items that we're thinking
about in terms of providing guidance is
also education I think there are a lot
of particularly grad students and other
researchers who are very used to
culturally um simply making things
available whether it's software on
GitHub or other content um on you know
whatever Lab website they have or Etc
sharing it very freely um because it's
part of our culture so I I think part of
the guidance is going to be around
educating and and talking about sort of
um you know what choices are available
if there are choices and what do certain
things mean when you you know take path
a versus path B um and then I I really
quickly just wanted
to touch on another group of
stakeholders that I briefly mentioned
before and those are our inhouse
publishing entities so to speak and that
includes the MIT press the MIT tech
review and the slow management
review and those entities and for those
of you who don't know the MIT tech
review is separate from MIT it's an
affiliate it's a wholly owned subsidiary
but they are not you know part of the
the educational research institution
bubble but MIT press is um they're just
like any other dlci and that is really
fascinating because their interests
are not always perfectly aligned right
with um complete openness for research
purposes and they along with the tech
review and Sal management review to a
certain extent see an existential crisis
in terms of science
journalism and scholarly book publishing
um that I think is is you know those
concerns are very real and very valid so
we are also trying to be mindful of
those interests um while thinking
holistically which kind of gets me back
to my first point about how working at
MIT as a lawyer is challenging and
fascinating um because MIT as a client
is not as simple as one might think so I
think I'll Chris should I stop there and
go to questions thank you all right than
you all right so I might just kick us
off with maybe maybe one or two um but
then I'll move very quickly to the the
Q&A um for the audience thank you um so
um you know I mean I think
that uh we touched on on this this sort
of question of of open and maybe I'll
come back to that in a minute but let me
um let me talk actually a little bit
from where uh you know where Circ um
kind of fits with with this so you know
uh social and ethical responsibilities
of Computing as as I mentioned in the
first session exists to Foster uh what
they call quote responsible habits of
mind and action for those who deploy
Computing
Technologies and and I think that you've
kind of hit on some very concrete
moments where um you know there there
may never be brightline guidance that's
going to come from your office um but
what in your view you know what what
might respond ible habits of mind and
action look like both you know what
advice you know might you give to MIT
students or those of us who are teaching
MIT students to kind of foster foster
those responsible
habits so I think I is this on yep I
think that's a great question um so I
have a a few different thoughts about
this and I have you know spent a lot of
time thinking about this because I do
think when so there's I think about MIT
as being a very open Kingdom but then
there's all these Gates and there's sort
of checks at all of these Gates um where
technology leaves and once it leaves you
know you you can never take it back
right um so I
think there is something to be said in
in the context of wanting to make
research open so that researchers can
build upon each other's work um Advanced
knowledge and also for you know science
sake and for curiosity there is
something to be said for balancing that
and taking a breath right and and being
thoughtful about potential
Downstream uses of technology and
whether there are ways to um you know
you use the term before signaling with
the Creative Commons I think you know
there's you can't have a lot of control
but can you signal and can you put up um
some gates that you know where you have
to walk through them before you leave
the MIT Kingdom and one of those this is
a great example this happened with the
crisper technology um that you know was
developed by MIT and bro and Harvard and
I don't know how many of you know this
but you know we have an agreement with
broad so broad actually does our our
license agreements even though we
partially own that technology
and the way broad very thoughtfully
licensed the crisper technology is with
with a with a set of very um intricate
thoughtful Provisions in license
agreements and of course I'm going
straight to the legal the legal thinking
but that restricted what you could do
with crisper technology right so very
early on you couldn't use it to make
designer babies you know very early on
you couldn't use it to basically dis
disrupt certain um agricultural
agriculture activities with seed um
genetics especially in developing
countries I mean I'm just naming a few
these were very lengthy thoughtful
provisions and the licensing um and the
choice of commercial Partners was made
very strategically and very thoughtfully
in terms of who is going to take this
technology and commercialize it now that
was a really easy thing to do because
crisper technology was covered um by
Patent protection right and patent
protection is easier to control than all
of the different pieces that you know go
into an AI system whether it's the model
which is usually not patentable and the
data sets and you know the parameters
and weights Etc um but I think there are
you know bodies and Chris you may know
about this who are thinking about ways
to thoughtfully license generative AI
tools I'm forgetting the names off the
top of my head but there a few nonprofit
organizations that are coming out with
models for how to thoughtfully license
this technology so something really easy
for a lab to think about would be do we
have a lab policy like an internal lab
policy where we we are thoughtful about
under what license we release something
on GitHub you know will it control
Downstream use maybe not but it's
certainly signals and I think MIT has
such a loud voice and and a power full
voice in The open- Source community that
I think you know I mean the MIT license
itself that that everybody uses the open
is called the MIT license you know we as
lawyers often get law squeamish because
it it's not like we licensed to them
it's just in fact I'm sure that some of
you even saw that um deep seek said they
had an MIT license well they don't they
they're you know they licensed things
under the open- source MIT license right
so the point being is that we have a
powerful voice and I think we can be
really thoughtful about how we um
proliferate
technology yeah I think um you've just
answered the other question I was going
to ask which is what's different at MIT
than at other universities right in some
ways if you were in your job at at any
university in the United States a
research University in particular you
would be facing these things but at an
MIT with this long-standing commitment
to the world of open and also This
Global reputation for it whether it is
through the publication of materials on
open courseware the open uh uh
publishing license first you know
initiated uh through the MIT libraries
and adopted at you know thousands of
universities around the world and the
the the MIT license or so-called MIT
license that is a real gold standard for
for open source software um does that
make it does that make your job easier
or harder
another really good question I think
it's a little bit of both I mean I think
it's easier in the sense that we get to
think the big thoughts and when we talk
people listen to us um and I think we
have a real opportunity to be
forward-looking and sort of put out some
thoughts about how we think things
should be done and I don't think that
all universities have that but on the
flip side we are in the news um we will
be judged uh by historians in terms of
of what actions we took or didn't take
um so I think it's I think it's really a
mix great all right well let's open
things up to uh Q&A and then again as
last time um you know we'll I'll try to
pass a mic to you and if you're too far
I'll just repeat the question into the
mic so people watching the recording can
can hear so the floor is
open yeah go for it come on up
I I just want to say what they just
shared is very very useful helpful I
just
wonder if you are preparing your office
preparing or plan to prepare some
document about like a AI guidance or
something uh for the entire campus that
could be really helpful I know it's not
easy to be complete especially still
developing right but it still be very
even some key points will be very very
helpful you can show some point if you
can surely um so and and can I ask to
are are you what's your um
M I'm part of MIT office of relations oh
great Interac excellent yes I know
you're office as well okay thank you um
so absolutely the goal is to come out
with guidance sort of for the three
categories that I spoke about at the
beginning um it won't come from my
office per se you know we we try at MIT
to keep the lawyer guidance to a minimum
um but we will certainly be
participating in preparing that Guidance
with a number of stakeholders on campus
um who really need to be involved and I
think that's what's making things slow
believe it or not I think MIT is ahead
of the game in terms of a lot of this
but it's still hard to ensure that we've
properly considered which is really
important different perspectives from
all over campus and we have the right
people in the room um you know Chris can
attest to this sometimes when we don't
have the right people in the room we
miss things and and we need to backtrack
a little bit so we're trying to be
careful there is guidance that first
category about users of AI tools um
there is some guidance actually oddly
enough on the isnt website about
responsible use of AI tools just in
research or in other offices on campus
you know as researchers you may
find it interesting because it gives you
the breakdown of what types of data MIT
treats with different various levels of
of security and so when you're using
certain types of data you know whether
certain permissions are needed but
probably not so useful to all of you I
think it's a it's a little bit more
basic the next two categories are a
little bit harder um the second category
I I hope there will be up dates sort of
about that research scaffolding soon but
I I don't really know what the timeline
is for that the last category um there
has been a new working group that has
been tasked by the vice president for
research um Chris and I will be
participating on that working group I
hope I can say that oh you've caught me
publicly I know he can't say no now um
but so I I think that there will
hopefully be some guidance coming out of
that which will be written and that will
be you know very specific you know for
instance researchers giving them offices
and actual administrators that they can
go to for questions about how to
permission and access certain data sets
properly and in a timely manner stuff
like that um some of these bigger
questions around how do you ethically
and responsibly think about sharing your
technology and your research results I
think that will be
a little bit trickier to put together
holistic comprehensive
guidance all
right other thoughts
questions a specific challenge that you
think we could come up with a solution
for that we don't yet have like I feel
like we're
anticipating so much and there's also
already so much to respond to you're put
in an impossible
position just repeat yeah so um I was
asked can I think can I pinpoint sort of
a a specific instance where there's
something I guess we can do
preventatively is that right to try to
head off maybe some big risk if I could
reward that does that okay um so I think
I touched on this before with various
licensing models
um the same way that Chris was saying
and I totally agree with this that we
need to have new IP rules to cover
generative Ai and inputs and outputs and
um you know copyright Etc I think we're
going to need to think through how we as
research
institutions um think about sharing
right I I think that we want sharing and
collaboration and openness always has to
be a priority but I think we're going to
have to think about new ways to do
it in a manner that bakes in this ethic
com ethics component and responsibility
component um and I would argue also
maybe a little bit of sort
of foresight and predictability
component instead of
simply not thinking about about those
things but I think that requires some
centralization of how we do things and I
don't know that we are close to that for
many good reasons
too yeah I think you know another
concept that's useful for thinking about
this and this came up in our
conversation with um earlier uh is what
the author's Guild calls you know their
three C's right consent credit and and
compensation and what credit means in in
a kind of scholarly context is is very
different right because of as you
mentioned it these sort of questions of
attribution citation replicability those
kind of core values of scholarly
research in not only in The Sciences but
across you know disciplines um are are
very much disrupted by generative AI
models as they exist now um and you know
that's I think an area where um you know
as a research Community we'll we'll be
looking for for guidance from MIT on how
to do our work but it would be great
then also to share share that and maybe
model for other research communities you
know best ways to kind of capture the
the spirit and values of academic sit a
and adapt them to the new technology I
think that's absolutely right and the
you know maybe this is just the lawyer
and me but the immediate response I have
that and we we have to solve this we
have to figure out a way to manage this
is the simple misalignment
between you know academic attribution
the the three C's the you know consent
credit and compensation although maybe
compensation is less important for us
and the um ability to access data and
other research freely to advance your
own research so um I think that's the
and and as I was ref referencing before
I mean you could be the same researcher
and have a be of two
minds B
absolutely all right uh yeah
question uh so the question actually
that you already touch also is uh I
wonder when you're thinking about all
this issue and come up with some kind of
guideline for the community what kind of
like a uh guiding principle that you
follow I I I think you mention a lot
about openness and I wonder what other
the factor and in terms of priority wise
and how does it uh incorporate like MIT
is a historical like a value uh into
this kind of things thinking so that
will be a question that i' like to ask
you Clarity on that so first of all I
appreciate that question because I'd
like to take a note to remember this for
the working group because I think that
should be part of our first order of
business is to think about what are our
priorities and list them you know in
terms of the values we want to be
thinking about um my short answer is I
don't know what
mit's position will be I can tell you
what personally I think Mak sense which
is that openness because first and
foremost we are a research and
educational institution and we want to
um pursue research for research sake
right we science for for science sake so
openness for sure I think um autonomy
and choice I think we want to
preserve uh our you know
the people who undertake that research
and develop that scholarly work I think
we want to listen to you know what they
want to have done with their research um
and then third I think we want to be
good Community we want to be good
worldwide
citizens right we need to think about
what how what we do affects the rest of
the world and I think it's not too
far-fetched to say that in the world of
generative AI especially at a place like
MIT we decisions we make or don't make
can have
worldwide
consequences so that would be those
would be the first priorities I would
think about I don't know Chris if you
have something to add to that I think I
would start with M's mission statement
which I don't know by heart but I I know
how to find it on the website
and assume that you know what whatever
whatever there is whether it's formal or
informal guidance or education you know
should be
about um advancing you know advancing
the mission that's the kind of that's
that's certainly square one where I
think we would want to
start I think uh do we have maybe one
more
question I'm cognizant that many of you
are are staring directly into the sunset
and are having um uh depending on the
afternoon harder and harder time
watching the this the session um I think
we've had a a really kind of amazing
conversation we've all actually learned
a great deal of information um uh got
answers to some questions got questions
in response to other questions um and
know that in this rapidly advancing
field um that that we will continue to
explore in this area but I'd like to
thank um from our first session and
Claire from the second session for
making time for us today and thank you
all for coming and Carry On from here
thank you
[Applause]