So with that, let me introduce our first
speaker, Professor Hussein Ranima. He's
a professor at the MIT Media Lab and
Toronto Metropolitan University. He's
also the founder of Flybeats, which is
an AI and data science company.
Hussein's research is focused on the
design of human AI systems, data
governance, human computer interaction,
and the design of missionritical AI
systems. He works on many super exciting
projects but today the title of his talk
is unlocking human potential with
perspective aware AI agents over to you.
Thank you very much Ireina and it's a
pleasure to be with you all um and a big
thank you to our friends at ILP to
continue to host these uh great events.
Uh I'm looking forward to our
conversation today and especially
sharing the great research that my
teammates are doing at the uh MIT media
lab. I will be taking you through a uh
presentation uh with a focus on not just
our thinking but also a new program that
we have created at the MIT media lab
called Sapion which is a new way to
think about the future of AI and human
collaboration especially when you have a
lot of people a lot of AI models and the
ecosystem between them and the
complexity that comes with that. I will
start with um just going to shrink my
um yeah I will start with some of our
older projects. Some of them are 10
years old. Like we had coffee machines
that could sense the stress level and
the sleep level of our labmates and
based on that it changed the change the
intensity of their espresso and sent
them a message that their coffee was
available. We built the very first
navigational system for Paris Metro
Authority that it navigated people not
just based on location but based on a
number of context elements that
surrounded that passengers. We had
augmented reality solutions that instead
of using radio signals, we could
navigate people in an airport using
augmented reality uh on signage systems
and then we navigated people accordingly
to their gates to restaurants based on
the needs that they had at an airport
and many many other things. But since
then many things have changed and
especially that's our relationship with
data. In almost all those projects, my
mindset as a graduate student and then a
new faculty member and many of our
students
where the fact that hey we have all the
data give me all the data and when I
have the data I'll do my work or I'll
write my thesis that is changing now. We
are now surrounded by zetabytes of data
not just within our organizations but
also outside our organizations.
Uh and many of that data does not belong
to us. They come with different legal
contracts. They belong to different
people. Of course we need to synthesize
and model them and use them for
inference and learning. But it's not as
easy as before. So what I always say is
that we are moving from an era of
personalization
which was all about putting all the data
in one centralized location inferent
model and push things to people to a
model which is based on participation
collaborating and co-creating with the
machine. And that drives a fundamentally
different way on how we design systems,
build infrastructures,
manage data relationships, trade mo
train models. So the program that we
created at the MIT Media Lab is
addressing these six pillars. moving
from personalization to participation,
breaking data silos and forming
alliances not just between units in a
company but also with their partnerships
outside the organization
all the way to things such as making AI
auditable like when you deliver an
answer or a generated prompt to an
individual or a group of people. What
about your audit track? What if someone
calls a call center and say excuse me
why did you give me that answer or that
information? So similar to what we
learned in the financial industry we are
also doing a lot of work to be able to
audit um generative AI uh interventions.
The program that we created looks at uh
five key pillars looking at looking at
AI using an ecological model rather than
just a technological or a design model.
We focus a lot on AI literacy to empower
people not just boards of directors and
seuitees but also K12 students to
understand what AI is and is not and how
best they can use it as an enabler and
an augmentation tool rather than a force
that will replace uh people's cognition
and their ability. We have a strong
focus on the importance of data and how
we control the data, own it and even
monetize it correctly with transparency.
And also a very big focus at the MIT
media lab is the cross-disciplinary
aspect of AI. Not just technology, but
how do you design with AI? We are at an
era in which we are throwing terabytes
of data on these two-dimensional screens
and we want them to be trackable,
auditable, verifiable. It's very
different than how we used to design
user experience and user interfaces in
the past.
similar to how we created a
communication spectrum in the past 25
years that allows us to have this
amazing highdefinition
uh zoom call from all around the world
and we take that for granted. We also
believe that we need to invest on an AI
spectrum. We need to focus on new
experience architectures, on our ability
to abstract data and systems without
keep removing old systems and putting
new systems in. and a big focus on our
research team on human AI service agents
which is not necessarily building and
incorporating LLMs but it's about
encapsulating people's knowledge in AI
agents allowing them to share this
expertise with a decentralized learning
network and even down the rope benefit
from it or monetize it. You're
interested in forming data alliances.
How can a telecom carrier, a bank, a
travel company, a utility company, a
clinic can all come together to share
signals and decision patterns on behalf
of the user with the consent of the user
to generate new value. So our programs
are based on six pillars. generating
moonshot ideas, not necessarily
interested about what's coming tomorrow,
but envisioning the future of industries
using our moonshot thinking at the media
lab on the future of industries in the
next 10, 15 and 20 years. big focus on
data mechanics, building products and
platforms, building new experiences and
design and most importantly empowering
people, empowering organization and
improve their AI readiness.
MIT Media Lab has been very strong in
the area of human computer interaction.
In the literature, this is usually being
defined as a literature in which a human
collaborates with a machine or a few
people collaborate with a few machines.
What we are interested in are what I
call HCI 2, humane, calm, and
intelligent interfaces. We are actually
interested in AI systems that can run in
the background allowing us the human the
people to communicate more effectively
with with each other. We are not
necessarily interested to put you
behind, you know, um goggles and
headsets and locking you down in these
digital echo chambers. We want you to
use the best possible user interface
that has ever been invented and that's
human. We are empowering human to human
interfacing using AI in the background.
Now I want to show you some examples.
Our project started using some of the
early software and AI agents. People
think that AI agents are new. They are
not. They were actually invented at MIT
in 1994.
We use them to create a social GPS a few
years ago in collaboration with a
telecom carrier. So instead of using
cartisian coordinates, you can use the
knowledge base of a celebrity or a
famous person. You can apply that
knowledge graph on Google maps, a food
ordering app, a media channel. And let's
say in the case of Google maps, I could
go to Paris and I could walk the shoes
of Gwennet Paltro and see what would she
do if she was here, what bakery she
would go to, what music she would listen
to on Spotify. We interconnected to open
banking rail so people can actually
could use the category of their
transactions to recommend what they
bought and what they like. Through this
we learned a lot and we realized that AI
agents are not ready to deliver on their
promises. They are very good in doing
one or two things very specifically
related to functions. But when it comes
to the complexity of um building these
workflows in which human element is
active there they were not there. So we
decided to build these new data
structures called chronicles.
These are data structures that can
capture the behavioral pattern using
causal and correlational model of
individuals using ontologies and then
they will be used to provide a much
better humane interfaces when you're
building AI agents. We have written a
lot of papers on that that you can read
about around the notion of perspective
aware AI and the role of these new
software engineering paradigms using
chronicles and demonstrating how they
bring value to the future of AI system.
So essentially learning from the user
and keep adding subgraphs to a master
chronicle representing your knowledge or
even an organizational knowledge. An
example that I can give you is a work
that we have done with the US government
for a particular US agency and we use
these chronicles to capture human
dynamics
capturing expert knowledge, role,
workload, competency and then we use
that to figure out things that AI is
actually not very good at. If I have a a
a a company of about 100,000 people, how
do I form teams that can achieve a
particular project very well and if I
optimize for that, what are the risks
that I need to be aware of? Or if I want
to figure out mentor mentee
relationships between people to form
groups, how do I do that?
uh we actually outperformed many of the
research out there using generative
agent-based modeling by incorporating
our chronicles into them and we have
seen significant improvements that if
you compare them with the incumbency we
can now capture soft human dynamics in
AI models on a multimodal basis on a
much more effective way for example look
at a video and an image an email, Slack
channels and figure out who may work
better with whom or who likes you know
to form a team that is delivering a
particular objective. So we are getting
some very good results for that. And now
I want to show you some examples.
The ORC chart on the left is very
familiar to all of us. A two-dimensional
ORC chart project comes in. We get
together based on budget, availability,
calendar and we deliver that work. We
are now creating a human AI agent for
every single member of that uh
organization. So when a project comes in
in form of a prompt with a large context
window, it's actually the human AI
agents of the employees that are
collaborating with each other to deliver
the first part of that task. They they
the agents bring the project to a level
of maturity that essentially most of the
grunt and mechanical work is being done
and then the AI will notify people to
join and make the project more polished,
better, innovative and our thesis in
this project is that AI is not
necessarily here to replace us. If used
correctly, it is giving us more time to
learn, to collaborate, to meet with each
other, and our human AI agents will get
better. Now, I'm going to take you
quickly through a number of examples in
the industry. We have built a tool
called Open Dome that allows us to
create a digital twin of a space using
Gaussian splatting within about an hour.
We work with this organization to
capture data from uh HR systems, payroll
systems, tax systems, CRM systems and we
applied that chronicle to the digital
twin of that uh office. So now you can
go to that office and say today I want
to come to the office digital twin but I
want to see the office through the lens
of the CEO. we now go capture data from
across the chronicles and create a lens
for this employee to understand what's
important for the CEO that day or you
can change the lens to the ESG
specialist in this case and see how the
organization is doing in terms of um
carbon footprints and and and uh some of
their sustainability metrics.
I welcome all of you to visit us at the
media lab. We are a very unique
interdisciplinary organization and one
of my incoming graduate students just
used this technology to create a tour
guide for the lab using perspective
aware AI. So when you come to the lab
you can wear the lens of different
professors and faculty members or even
staff members we have and by choosing
that lens you can now go and read about
all the projects but as you read about
the project you can also see the
perspective of that professor. So this
way you can choose a professor who is
interested in climate or technology or
user interfaces and you can develop a
much better perspective in terms of uh
their viewpoints and we are measuring
that this actually brings people
together.
Another great example is how we can
generate new ideas. I have a dear
colleague Joe Jacobson who is very good
with genome engineering. My background
of course is not genetics. I'm more
focused on AI, but there are lots of
interesting synergies between our work,
but I need some ideas to figure out what
it could be the reference for our
collaboration.
So now we have fine-tuned models from
knowledge base in the lab, fine-tune
them, orchestrate them, control them,
and now if I'm looking for a base
collaboration, I can use Gen AI using
audio and generative signals. And then I
can interconnect two projects together
and come up with a new project that is
interfacing between his area of
excellence and my uh focus. We are now
applying this to many verticals from
working with loyalty program providers.
Then when you choose your seats you can
use you can see the plane through the
lens of others. One of my favorite ones
is what we are doing in the medical
sector. So when a doctor is looking at a
medical doseier, he or she can activate
the lenses of two other doctors from
across other hospitals, see their
diagnosis and misdiagnosis risks, but
make a better decision uh with more
calculated decision uh when making the
diagnosis. This is a reason that we
always say biases are actually good in
AI as long as we are transparent on it.
We are working now with triathlon gold
medalists in the US to get information
from these new um health companies that
are giving you a lot of access to
biomarkers, genome data, health trackers
to essentially give you a lens h as a
health concier. So when you go to a
restaurant, you can basically look at a
menu and based on all your needs, we
will be able to fetch things from you
for the menu that is aligned with your
health goals and your uh plans. We do a
lot of work with financial institutions.
One of the things about the Sapion
program is we build these fundamental
technologies that we think are
gamechanging and then we partner with
organizations around the world that
really want to change their sector and
we work with them to apply this
technology to give them competitive
advantage. So we do number of things
with financial institutions to build
let's say a decision support space for
your financial needs. This is in
collaboration with some of the work we
do on um Apple Vision Pro. You can go to
this space. You have access to Genai and
you can talk to your uh finance agent
and say, "Hey, activate my home. Show me
how much mortgage I have left. Give me a
retirement plan that allows me to pay
for my mortgage and pay it off by this
time or uh manage my retirement savings
or I want to buy that car. Show me how
to do it." It's a very interesting way
for us to bring a regulated complex
industry, combine generative AI and
spatial computing and rethink how the
future of these enterprise services can
look like. My team is very much focused
on embodied AI. We actually want down
the road for the phones to go away and
objects to become active. Uh we have now
built a mobile banking app that doesn't
even need an app or a mobile phone. We
have partnered with a French company to
build biometrics in a card. You can now
use um augmented reality glasses and
voice and you can use gestures of the
card to activate balances, offers
looking at your transactions. You can um
share bills uh or or split bills if you
go to a restaurant without the usage of
any app. And although the hardware
requirements are still not fully
commercialized but we are really
building the research foundation for
these for the future. We do wick robots.
So uh this is for us the future of
electronics that instead of setting up
configurations on machines and robots.
We are now incorporating these
chronicles into robots and we measure
things such as empathic values when kids
and robots interact on a multimodal
basis. So parents can now incorporate a
lot of their value systems um when their
kids interact with robots. And we have a
very big interest in helping especially
kids with autism to use these ro
humanoid robots to develop better social
skills. One of the last projects I show
you is what we have done recently uh in
collaboration with Bloomberg. Um Emily
Chang is a well-known technology
reporter. Uh we worked with her to
develop a program on uh Bloomberg
originals. You can watch it. It's called
Postthuman. and we connected our
chronicles essentially to create a
digital version of Emily. So we used our
chronicle builders, we used her
interviews with Natalie Portman, with
Cheryl Sandberg, her books, her social
media. We built her chronicle and then
of course we could run this as a chatbot
or textbased interfaces but we also
reached out to a group in Hollywood that
were experts in building facial
expressions because a lot of these
synthetic characters and uh deep fakes
are either not secure and safe or they
are essentially gimmicks are not really
giving you that empic response that you
need. So we them
fine tuned our model their facial models
and that's the inter that we created. So
we could now have the your colleagues or
friends available to you. Um you can
choose your ideal chronicle. You will
parse their graph based on you have
based on what you have access to and
then you almost logical in the workplace
enhancing productivity and streamlining
tasks but it brings significant
concerns. The training data driving
these systems can be biased. And now if
you look at here this the most important
thing here is an audit confidence
dashboard. As she talks, we measure
things such as provenence of the data,
um,
uh, provenence of the data, lift of the
data, uh, confidence on data. As she
talks, we can tell you how we are about
the answer that she's giving you. You
can also now activate different agents
in in your network. activate multiple
agents and chronicles and you can ask
them a question and observe their
conversation and learn from that. We
recently have a very large media company
working with us to use this of election
debates on TV channels. We are now
working for organizations to prepare for
board meetings when an executive wants
to present to the board or in capital
markets when negotiation happens. You
can now simulate these social behaviors
not just based on one or two but you can
activate tens of agents to do that. The
last thing I say is even the work that
we have done with Deepak Chopra and
programs that we have built called
artificial immortality.
Something is becoming more and more
clear to us. The biggest problem is not
technology. It's us. It's how we
understand emotions, human values,
empathy and incorporating them into AI
systems. And those are also some of the
work that we do not just with technology
people but people who even let's say ran
paliatic care centers for Mount Sinai
hospitals for years and understanding
some of those um learnings and applying
it to AI.
And the last thing is our human AI
empowerment programs at SAPN. We bring
some of the largest organizations to the
lab. We participate with them. We
connect them with our students. We run
hackathons that have Fortune50 CEOs, but
they also have grade three and grade
four students as part of one team
because we believe it's this AI as a
fabric that brings a lot of our uh
capabilities together and bridge our
gaps. And the way we think about it is
that we believe in a hub model. Sapion
is unlike any labs. We connect to
startups, projects, ideas and we create
these eological hubs for everyone to
learn uh from each other and they have
built tools that you can use to really
measure the AI readiness of your company
oration and with that decide what you
want to do next. Thank you very much for
your time and uh I am very uh much
looking forward to staying in touch with
you and a big thank you to our friends
uh at ILP for hosting us.
Thank you so much. This is absolutely
fascinating. Obviously we have uh great
questions. So let's get at least some of
them answer it. Uh question number one.
Normally to get to know someone you
speak to them or you listen to them
speak. Are these AI lenses perspectives
trying to remove social interactions?
Uh absolutely not. I think it's trying
to address some of the challenges that
we have seen before that people try to
replicate people by using linear systems
to incorporate personas and and clusters
and associate people with certain
things. What we are doing with these
chronicles is that with the permission
of the user, we allow the user to go
about their daily lives interact
especially in a work setting and these
agents in the background will learn from
these people. they are in a much better
than learning your preferences and
context than an algorithm deciding for
you and putting you in a cluster just
let's say for the sake of selling you
ads. So uh if you I'm happy to share
some of our papers or you can look them
up on on Google Scholar. That's the
whole point that you trust these
chronicles to learn from you what to
learn from you and they understand let's
say what belongs to you that is personal
that should be completely encrypted
versus what belongs to your organization
and should contribute to uh a broader
collective um chronicle.
Great. Another question, uh, what is the
future role of junior employees with
human AI agents?
Question. One of the funniest LinkedIn
job post I saw two months ago was this
very well-known company that of course
I'm not going to mention their name. Uh,
that was looking for a Genai
expert with experience
doesn't exist. M uh so what I always say
to companies the CEOs the boards of
directors
invest in your new generation of talent.
These kids we grew up with MS DOS. I
don't know who remembers MS DOS but I
remember it like you use prompts to type
and tell the machine what to do. One of
the reasons that chat GPT learning curve
was so low is that we were very familiar
with that interface. The generation that
is coming is not growing up with MSUS.
They're growing up with Roblox. They are
already being trained on multimodal
interface, multitasking, spatial comput.
How as a company you're preparing for
this generation, not just as your
customers, but as people who will truly
move your company forward to the next
generation. So the role for those and
the reason I want to bring K12 and
universities together is that we need to
understand the next generation of our
employees are in high schools now are in
junior schools now invest in them. They
are current junior associate does but
their type of jobs will be very
different and companies who will be the
ones who can identify that right now.
Yeah. Uh we have many more questions. I
have many more questions but
unfortunately we have to move on.