Now, we don't often experience
exponential growth in our everyday
lives. To gain an intuition for how
powerful it can be, you may remember the
old riddle where your employer asks you,
"How would you like to be paid this
month?" And you have two choices. Either
I'll start you with one penny and then
each day for one month I'll double the
number of pennies and you can keep the
pennies from the last day. [music] Or
you can have a million dollars. Now,
it's quite normal to think through the
first few days of pennies. for example,
two pennies on day one, four pennies on
day two, double that to eight pennies on
day three, and you begin to think that a
million dollars is starting to look
pretty good. But in fact, if you take
that million dollars, you've lost a lot
of money because the number of pennies
is growing exponentially as 2 to the nth
power, where n is the number of days. So
on the 31st day, the last day of the
month, you have 2 to the 31 pennies, and
that's equivalent to about $21 million.
That's the power of exponential growth.
Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.