Our next speaker is Manish
uh Reagan and he is
a J Houston career development professor
and also assistant professor in MIT
school management with joint appointment
in school of engineering.
uh he's going to explore the
AI's social impact, societal impact from
the lens of computer science, economics,
and law. Let's
welcome Manish. Thank you.
All right. Great. Thanks for having me
here. Uh it's good to see some familiar
faces in in the audience. So, my name is
Manish. I am a computer scientist but I
also sit in the business school and
broadly I do a lot of research on trying
to understand the societal implications
that AI is going to have for us. So this
can be at the small scale so individual
decisions here and there or it could be
at the policy level sort of macro across
an entire society. And so I'm going to
try to give you a few vignettes of what
this research looks like and where I
think we're headed as AI
progresses. This is a picture that I
show my MBA students some of whom are in
this room right now.
uh in one of the first few lectures I
give and it's I always return to it
because in my computer science education
we very much focused on the sort of
isolating AI from the rest of the world.
So when you take a machine learning
class as an undergraduate in many
computer science departments they hand
you data sets they tell you make some
good predictions build AI models they
don't really tell you where that data
came from or what you're supposed to
actually be doing with it. And I find
that those are often the more
instructive questions, at least from my
perspective, when we're trying to
understand what AI is going to do to the
world. And so I find these blue arrows
that I've drawn in here to be really the
generative pieces of research for me.
What is the stuff that we're putting
into these AI models? And what are we
doing with them once we've built them?
And lots of people spend a ton of time
optimizing the AI models themselves.
That's not really me in particular. Uh I
love that those people exist. I'm really
interested in the connections, the
interfaces between AI and the world,
which that's where where we're going to
try to live
today. One of the real difficulties and
and this I think I came across pretty
early in my PhD of trying to think about
well how what is a good general recipe
for thinking about AI in society, right?
Are there some broad principles that we
can apply everywhere? Learn a few things
and then just sort of repackage them and
repurpose them for every different
domain. This is what a computer science
computer scientist is trained to do. You
abstract away the problems. You solve
them at abstract levels and then you try
to propagate them all over the place.
But the problem here is every domain is
just so different. If we try to put AI
in medical domains, that's going to look
very different from putting it in
employment domains. Very different from
building code assistance for software
engineers. There's different risks.
There's idiosyncratic problems that you
run into. Of course, there is common
technology and we're going to try to
pull out that thread a little bit, but
we really need to incorporate a lot of
domain expertise in order to make good
decisions here. And so, I'm going to try
to squeeze in a few examples in very
different settings of where I think it's
interesting to think about AI and its
social impact. So, we're going to talk
about decisions being made in medical
triage. We're going to think about
employment decision-m and how
discrimination and discrimination law
should govern machine learning. And then
we'll think a little bit about where the
future of creative production is going
to look like with the rise of generative
AI and how we might think about
that. A general recipe that I try to
employ, I'm not going to say that this
works all the time. This this is not by
any means the only thing you have to do,
but it's basically two questions that
you need to keep asking yourselves over
and over again. What are the risks of
building and deploying AI in a
particular system or in a particular
setting? And how should I measure those
risks? and what could I what steps could
I take to mitigate them? Okay, and so
that's the the process that we're going
to go through here. Again, there's more
comprehensive frameworks you can find if
you want to, but this is a really good
first pass just trying to understand
what do I think AI is going to do in my
setting, in my business, in my uh
domain, whatever it might
be. Okay, so let's start by trying to
think about the use of AI in medical
triage decisions.
I'll give you a canonical scenario that
we we run into a lot and our our
collaborators at the Yale School of
Medicine run into a lot. Uh a patient
shows up into an emergency room. Okay,
they have some symptoms. They're going
to be waiting there for a long time.
It's going to take them a while to see a
a doctor. Doctors are short staffed. So
on eventually once they do see a doctor,
that doctor has a decision to make.
Should I send this patient home or
should I keep them in the ER? This is of
course not the only decision they have
to make. But in the particular setting
that we're going to be thinking about
here, which happens to be
gastrointestinal uh gastrointestinal
bleeding, these are the types of
decisions that doctors are making.
Should I is this patient in good enough
condition to be sent home or should they
be kept in the ER? And so doctors have
to make these decisions every day. These
are going to be idiosyncratic decisions
that they make and there's some
standards of care around this. But by
and large, doctors have a lot of
discretion.
But increasingly in these types of
settings, we're also starting to build
algorithms, build AI models, predictive
models, whatever you want to call them,
to help doctors make these decisions.
And so these often take the form of risk
scores. So you the doctor plugs in some
data about the patient's vital
statistics into some calculator. Uh
medcalc or mdcalc is one of the ones
that people use quite frequently. And
this gives them a score. It says this
person we think is a seven on a risk
scale from 0 to 23. Okay. Hey, now if
you're a doctor, what do you do with
this information? All right, you talk to
the patient. You have a lot of
information that you know you got to
have a conversation with them. They said
their stomach hurts, whatever it might
be. And this algorithm gave you a score.
The real challenge here is how do you
take these two very different sources of
information and use them productively.
Okay. And so that's the the challenge
that we were trying to tackle here.
uh the there's if we think about what
are the risks involved in this scenario.
This is one where the doctors actually
have a really good sense of what the
risks are. If you talk to them, the
primary thing that they're worried about
is sending home patients who really need
care. Okay? They do not want to send
people home who are going to suffer
adverse
consequences. But beyond this primary
cost, there are also secondary costs as
well. We have limited resources. We have
limited ER beds. We have limited
physician time. And we need to allocate
those responsibly. Right? If you only
cared about this failure to admit
patients who need immediate attention,
what would you do? You'd admit every
single patient, right? You will never
make any mistakes on our primary risk
category. But that is not the only thing
that we care about. And so we have
complex trade-offs at play that we need
to deal with here. And what we want to
do is come up with a recipe or a
framework that allows us to express
those trade-offs and allow physicians to
make good decisions within them. Okay.
So what is the right way to combine
these sources of
information? At a high level, I'll I'll
tell you the framework that we developed
and I'll uh give you a sense of some of
the the capabilities that we have here.
Our high level approach is this. We are
going to build the best models we can
that group patients together by risk.
Okay, so they say from the algorithms
perspective, from our models
perspective, we're going to put together
all the patients who look identical. We
can't tell the difference between them.
Sometimes they are truly identical and
this is because you can have patients
who show up with exactly the same
characteristics. So if you plug all
their data into MD Calc, you actually
get exactly the same information that
you're putting in. No algorithm is going
to be able to tell you the difference
between those patients. But the crucial
piece of information here is a doctor
can, right? Because they don't just see
the eight numbers that we passed into an
algorithm. They talked to the patient.
They saw the, you know, that their skin
tone had changed. They saw how much pain
they're in. Maybe they know them. They
have a history with them. With all this
information, doctors might actually be
able to distinguish between them. And so
what we're able to do is learn where are
the groups of patients where doctors
have lots of information that our AI
models don't. And how do we allocate
physician time towards them? And so what
this lets us do is actually make
decisions that are better than either
algorithms or doctors in isolation.
Okay, we make fewer mistakes. We take
less time to do so.
And one of the qualitative takeaways we
found from this is algorithms are really
good at identifying patients who are
super high risk. And those are precisely
the patients who should not be sitting
in ER waiting rooms for hours to see a
doctor before they're admitted. These
are the types of patients who we would
like to identify as soon as possible
that this person needs to be in a uh in
the ER. They don't need to see a triage
doctor in order to tell you that. Where
where doctors do particularly well
though is for these ambiguous patients
who the algorithms can't really
distinguish between them. They all look
kind of medium risk. Uh but it turns out
that doctors actually have a lot of
valuable information that is unavailable
to our algorithms. And so what we're
able to do is combine these sources of
information to lead to better overall
decisions. Now I mentioned that we're
able to put these sort of the trade-offs
at play uh and and try to figure out
what are the right ways to make these
types of decisions. I'll give you an
example of the type of thing that you're
able to do in this sort of framework. I
mentioned to you that um true positives
are really the thing that are the most
important here, right? For all the
patients uh who are really at high risk,
those are the people that we want to be
keeping in the ER. And so you should see
each dot on this plot is a way that we
can combine humans and algorithms to
make decisions. It is a policy that a
hospital could set. The the points over
at the top are the ones that have really
high true positive rates. These are the
ones that hospitals are most likely to
want to adopt. And what we can show is
without making any additional mistakes
with just matching exactly the
performance that humans already have, we
can automate some large fraction of c
cases particularly the ones who are high
risk. And what this allows us to do is
maintain the quality of our decisions.
We're not putting any additional
patients at risk, but actually manage
the trade-offs and resources
effectively. Okay. As we go on, I'll
I'll talk a little bit about employment
decisions and how they differ from from
medical triage decisions. And we'll talk
a little bit about what are the the
concerns at play
here. Many of you may be using these
types of algorithms. Maybe you're on the
receiving end uh of of this pile of
resumes that you have to sift through or
you might be going through interviews
yourself and you might be seeing AI
interviewers uh on the other side. Okay,
this is becoming increasingly common.
And you know, it's a it's a cliche at
this point in the business world.
there's too many applications and yet
it's impossible to find good talent. And
on the candidate side, you go through
hundreds of interviews and you never get
a single job offer and you may not ever
talk to a human in the first place,
right? So somehow we've we've landed an
equilibrium that nobody seems to be
particularly happy
with. So what are the risks in using AI
for employment decisions? There are
tons, right? This is me spending five
minutes writing the ones I could think
of off the top of my head on a slide.
This is by no means exhaustive, right?
Uh early on a lot of the concerns were
around discrimination and that's still
remains true. But there's also just
quality considerations. Are candidates
having bad experiences? Are you
rejecting high quality candidates? Uh
there's concerns of anti-competitive
behavior as more and more firms adopt
the same hiring algorithms. There's also
just a lack of signal and AI generated
resumes. Perhaps a lack of signal and AI
conducted interviews. Today I'm going to
talk about discrimination in our work
there. But these are just there. The
risks are vast here. Many of them may be
small, but they're still worth thinking
about and wondering if we can do
better.
Now, one of the things that you might
want to measure here is whether people
are discriminating in making employment
decisions with
AI. Now, there's a couple ways of
thinking about this. I'm not going to
give you the the the history of
discrimination law in the United States,
but you should think of there's
basically two ways that you can
discriminate as an employer. One is to
explicitly treat people differently
based on their demographic
characteristics or protected uh
characteristics and the other is to have
unjustifiably different selection rates
across different demographic groups um
or to forego a less discrimin less
discriminatory alternative when you
could have used one. Okay. Now what
we've started to do and what the law has
started to require is that we audit AI
models to see if they're going to
discriminate. Right? One of the benefits
of using AI, which you couldn't do with
your human recruiters, is to actually
just test them before you put them into
practice. Right? When you have a new
recruiter, you can't really predict what
they're going to do until they actually
make decisions on live candidates. This
isn't necessarily true for AI models,
though. We can stress test them before
we even put them into production. So, we
have some sense of what their operating
characteristics are going to be. So,
this is a new opportunity that we have,
right? We can do these so-called
pre-eployment audits. And in fact, some
jurisdictions in the United States have
started requiring them, includ in
including New York
City. But with this new opportunity also
comes a new challenge. How should we
measure
discrimination? Is there just an
off-the-shelf measure that we can use?
What data sets should we use to evaluate
them on? How should we conduct
litigation around employment
discrimination as it pertains to
algorithms?
One of the key observations that has
come out in the recent years is that we
often think of machine learning as
producing the right model given the
data. Right? The goal of machine
learning process is you hand it some
data, you get back a model, you don't
really ask too many questions about how
you got there. But it turns out there's
actually lots of different ways to
construct a good model. And one of the
things that we've learned how to do in
I'd say the past 3 to 5 years is search
over the set of good models the sort the
set of accurate models for ones that
have the uh characteristics that you
want on other domains. So for instance
if you want an accurate model that also
doesn't discriminate that is something
you can specify in your model search
that isn't just as simple as maximize uh
the utility of the model just from an
accuracy perspective. This has lots of
legal implications which I'm not going
to to bore you with too much. But we've
been talking a lot to regulators
specifically under the previous
administration at the EEOC around what
the standards should be for litigation,
right? How do you construct policy
around the capabilities of machine
learning and how does that change the
way that we should think about
discrimination law? Can we use
statistical tests in courtrooms and to
what extent can we rely on them when
we're talking about machine learning?
These are all open questions just raised
by the possibility of using machine
learning in a previously human-driven
setting. Okay, I'm going to end it on an
example which hopefully will will give
you guys all an opportunity to
participate before you you go off. One
of the things that's been really
interesting to me just from a personal
level uh over the past few years is that
we've moved from this paradigm of using
AI for prediction to using it for
production. And the set of things that
you can do from a production standpoint
are just vast, right? there's so much
room to build uh and to produce things
with generative AI and I've been
particularly interested in how this
changes the landscape of creativity.
Okay, now this is a very broad topic. I
don't know enough about uh the sort of
creativity literature to give a sort of
expert informed view here. But one of
the things that we've seen in empirical
studies over the last couple of years is
a surprisingly consistent
fact. The the short version of it is
when you get people in a room and you
ask them to think creatively. Okay, you
can do RCTs where you say this group of
people does not get access to AI and
that group of people does. And so you
look at the people who who did not have
access to AI and they gave you some
ideas and those ideas look good. If you
give people access uh to AI, it looks
like they actually produce more ideas in
isolation or they're more creative in
isolation. But somehow when you take the
set of all the things that they produce,
that set is smaller. Essentially, what
they're doing is every single person is
just coming up with the same few ideas
over and over again because that's what
they asked ChatgBT for and they all got
the same answers. Okay, now this isn't
something that could have really
happened before. We didn't have an
artifact that would cause people to
converge on their beliefs or converge on
the things they were producing. But now
we have this this sort of monoculture
created by the use of AI, right?
Everybody is going through the same
centralized processes and so everybody
is getting correlated or identical
outputs from them. And so the question
was to what extent should we expect this
to happen in the wild and how is this
going to affect the market for AI
models? Okay, I'll give you a a really
nice metaphor that I've been toying with
for the last few years that's been sort
of an interesting way for me to think
about this. And that metaphor is a word
game. It's called categories. Many of
you may have played this. It is a game
that re rewards both correctness and
creativity. So effectively what happens
is I give everybody in the room a letter
and a category and say can you come up
with an object that starts with the
right letter and matches that category.
So if I said you know the letter is L
and the the category is things with
tails. Somebody shout out a possible
answer to this. What is a thing with a
tail starting with an L? Great. Lion,
leopard. These are all things that
language models would say. Uh and so you
it turns out you can just do this,
right? And this is a way to assess the
sort of creative capabilities of
language models and a benchmark by which
we can compare them. So I'll give you an
example. If you try actually running a
language model, many of you may be
familiar with the there's sort of a a
parameter. There's many parameters with
language models that you get to tune.
One of them is known as a temperature
parameter which basically allows you to
diversify the set of things that you're
sampling from. It sort of increases the
randomness in the model. So if you run a
model at a temperature of zero, it is
deterministic. It always gives you the
same thing over and over again. It turns
out for this particular language model,
if you ask it this question, you
deterministically get the answer lemur.
That is the thing that starts with an L
and has a tail. And as you start to turn
this knob up, you get a little bit more
creativity, right? So, lion starts to
sneak into the mix here. And as you turn
it up further and further, you get
things like lizard and uh llamas and so
on. And we can keep going with this. But
what you'll notice is as you turn this
temperature up, as you ask for more
creativity, you lose quality. So the
answers in red are the ones that uh my
personal verifier uh said does not
really have a tail like a ladybird. And
so you see that there's this trade-off
between quality and creativity, right?
The more creative you try to get these
models to be, the less accurate they
are. All right? And this is okay, right?
Sometimes we want a balance between
creativity and accuracy. we're willing
to to handle some mistakes because we
actually want a broader set of things to
come from it. Okay. And so that's the
thing that we're going to try to to ask
here. To what extent does this quality
creativity trade-off manifest in
practice? And is it perhaps different
across different models? And without
going too much into the the details, you
can actually show that this sort of
market has a naturally competitive
structure. And what you should expect to
see is creativity is rewarded as there
is stronger competition. And you might
find that a model that does really well
according to your benchmark isn't
actually the one that does better uh in
a more sort of competitive world where
more creativity is required. So without
explaining too much what this plot says,
here's a simulated world sim you can
call it a game of
categories where I pit two models
against each other. And you should think
of each of these axis representing the
market share that each model gets. Okay?
And what you can see
is for this for a small number of
competitors in this marketplace, you end
up with one model dominating, right?
This is the one that takes all the
market share. But as there's a more and
more competitive marketplace, a
different model takes over. And what
this speaks to is that we haven't really
done a good job of benchmarking these
models according to their quality uh in
creative or competitive settings. We're
really good at benchmarking them in
isolation. And one of the things that
we're working towards uh in in the near
future is try to try to figure out how
do you get these things to balance both
quality and creativity simultaneously
and to what extent is the market going
to reward you for doing that. Okay. So I
know I'm out of time. I'll stop here.
But for me the takeaways of this sort of
broad line of research are it's
important to try to identify these
highle risks or new phenomena that can
occur when we put AI in society. Right?
Some things occur just because when you
use AI in a setting that you weren't
before, stuff that was previously way
too expensive now becomes feasible.
Right? One example that has been on my
mind recently is what happens when every
child in the country gets access to both
a homework aid and a personal tutor for
for basically for free all the time.
Right? Now, you could have said, well,
this could have happened before if we
had a lot of money. We could have paid
for private tutors for everyone. But
this wasn't happening at scale. It was
previously too expensive. But now this
new phenomena is possible and it's going
to create social effects. how should we
analyze those? There's also systemic
effects that come with this sort of
coordination at scale as we're all using
the same AI models. Is it going to
decrease our diversity of thought uh of
our scientific production? And how do we
maintain that diversity going forwards?
And the last thing I'll end on is for me
personally, it's been super critical to
integrate domain expertise beyond
computer science. As a computer
scientist, I was only trained to think a
certain way. And the more I've talked to
economists, to doctors, to lawyers, I've
learned different ways of looking at the
world and as a result, different ways of
looking at the way that AI is going to
interact with it. All right, I'll stop
there. Happy to take any questions if
you have any. And thanks for coming.
Thank you.
How do you approach data privacy issues?
Good question. So data privacy when
you're using AI in a healthcare setting
is obviously complicated. Thankfully, we
we have basically two main protections
uh that we have to follow. One is that
there's federal law governing healthcare
records and so we have to maintain HIPPA
compliance with whatever we do. Usually
that involves properly anonymizing data
and stripping as much of it as we can
before we start using it. Uh only
accessing it on servers that belong to
the hospital. And so for some of this
work, we actually have to have our
students hired by the hospitals that we
work with. So they become become
employees and they are subject to all
the policies of the hospital. The second
thing that we're we're governed by is uh
IRBs. So when we run experiments, we
submit IRBs that say here's what we plan
to do. Here's why we think it's in the
benefit of the patients. And we end up
just being somewhat conservative with
the things that we do as a result. And I
think that's a good thing. There are
techniques from a technical perspective
to try to preserve privacy in people's
data. Like you add some random noise
into a data set uh that gives you
additional protection beyond uh the
anonymization. But for the applications
that we have and the ones that I talked
about, anonymized data is is actually
good
enough. Is the creativity problem a
function of us not having the right
theory of mind and philosophy how to for
how to engage with these world
models? It's a couple of things. So yes,
I don't think we have the right theory
of
mind. The other thing I'll say is we
don't really have the right objective
functions by which to measure these
models. And what I mean by that is the
way that we build models, including all
of the big AI labs, is you go out into
the wild and you find here are examples
of ways that people are using models,
right? Maybe it's benchmark data that
people have collected. Maybe it's your
own chat transcripts from all the people
that you've interacted with. And so
those if you optimize for those, you get
good performance on certain types of
tasks. What's really hard to do is
predict what are the future use cases
that we haven't yet seen. what are
people going to want to do or what would
they do if we got really good at it and
how would we design a model that's
really good for those types of
applications. So if you look at a lot of
the benchmarks that we have today, they
look like ELSAT questions and multiple
choice questions. They're basically
things that we've already created a lot
of uh knowledge based questions to
evaluate students. We're just going to
use those to to evaluate language
models. And that's a great start, but
that's not really how people are going
to be using these models, right? the
primary use case uh for a large language
model isn't to pass the LSAT for you. So
I think a big problem that we have is
just trying to figure out how do we
measure what it means to perform well.
And as I talk to my friends who work at
the big AI labs, this has been a
predominant concern that they have. How
do we evaluate? How do we make sure
these things are doing well? How do we
make sure they're not going to go uh off
the rails or or bypass our guardrails in
some way? Evaluation for these models is
really hard and it involves aligning
these models with our own values, right?
So what do we consider valuable in this
world? That's really hard to write down.
It's hard to specify. So in my mind that
is the big obstacle uh beyond behind
incentivizing the type of models that we
want to see in the world. Thank you very
much Manish. Thank you.