Hello and good afternoon everybody. My
name is Trisha Dingle. I'm the
engagements and partnership manager with
MIT Startup Exchange and it's my
pleasure to introduce today's MIT
startup lightning talks. So you will be
hearing from four companies. Many of you
have already experienced that each of
the presenting startups have established
as a designated high-top table outside
during the networking breaks and
immediately following during the
networking lunch. All four of the
presenting startups are part of MIT
Startup Exchange and they're developing
critical technologies and services that
align with the focus areas for today's
events. Novel drug delivery, uh AI and
machine learning for biomolelecular
modeling, biio manufacturing, precision
medicine, and advanced diagnostics. So
with this selection of startups, we
really want to give you an idea of the
technologies emerging from MIT that are
advancing health science. They're going
to speak to some of the use cases that
they've been working on with partners
and customers. So, I encourage all of
you to meet throughout the day, talk
during the networking to discuss
potential joint opportunities because
that's what we do at MIT Startup
Exchange. We help startups identify and
experience collaborations and
partnerships with industry, bringing
together MIT connected startups, ILP
corporate members to foster these
collaborations and partnerships between
them.
The startups that we support, they all
have a strong connection to the
institute. This connection can come
through the team, the founding team, the
technology, but in other cases, startups
that don't have an origin at MIT, uh
they'll they'll be vetted and supported
by our MIT peers, and we welcome them
into Startup Exchange. So, examples of
MIT peers would be CEL Connect Plus,
Start.no, Nano and the engine, many of
which I'm sure uh you've heard of and if
not, we're happy to give you more
information about those
programs. We do work with uh hundreds of
startups virtually in any sector. We
also have geographic uh agnost uh we're
agnostic in terms of ge geography
working with MIT connected startups that
are headquartered all over the world.
But everything we do is to expose and
connect startups and industry and we do
this in a highly curated way and also
can provide learning opportunities to
both parties. So examples of how we
build these connections foster these
introductions. We launch calls for
startups based on corporate's own
challenges or initiatives or priorities.
We facilitate those one-on-one meetings
between both parties. Um we host virtual
demo days and other events. And in terms
of those learning opportunities, that's
again where we have the opportunity to
co-organize them with our MIT pairs. So,
uh, peers such as Martin Trust Center,
uh, E14, VMS or the Venture M, uh,
mentoring
service. This is a small, very small
sample of the success cases that we've
had to date. Um, they include proofs of
concept, pilots, uh, joint development
and acquisitions. So it's really the
intent for every event, every meeting,
every introduction to produce that
valuable connection for both parties
that are ultimately going to lead to
their own success case. So if you have
any questions or want more information
about how we're working with the ILP
members and the ILP program to make sure
that you do have these opportunities to
engage with startups and new
technologies, uh find one of our team
members, your program manager, and we're
happy to give you more information. Now
on to the good stuff. Today's lightning
talks we have um a sample of great
startups and again this is
representative of some of the focus
areas that we've heard talked to today.