all right thanks Aran this five minute
um presentation format is great I'll
test it tomorrow in my class let's see
how the students react um so I'm yob
bjon I'm a professor of nuclear science
and engineering at MIT also co-founder
of um fto energy we refer to it as a
clean energy solutions company so who
are we well we might not Shine for um
gender diversity but we have a good
diversity of backgrounds here ranging
from architecture Norman Foster you
might have heard of him um nuclear
technology myself Roberto kazoua the um
uh energy World Michael Ford uh for
operations of energy systems finances
wad uh design
Etc okay so what's the problem or what's
our goal uh is to deliver plentiful
energy that is secure environmentally
sustainable and uh equitably uh
equitably distributed
um and I would argue the challenge at
the moment is that current low energy
Alternatives whether they're wind solar
or even nuclear on the grid are often
not um easily adapted to remote offgrade
locations industrial process they don't
scale well they're not available
everywhere and often they're not U
affordable so what is our solution well
it's center around a technology that we
call uh the nuclear battery nuclear
battery really is a small nuclear
reactor nuclear fusion reactor just to
be clear not Fusion which is still a few
years out there um generating of the
order of 10 maybe 20 megawatts a nuclear
reactor is a heat Source if you want
electricity you got aou it to a turbo
generator and you get electricity but
naturally you get both heat and
electricity combin which a lot of
customers are interested in um nuclear
is zero carbon in operation life cycle
CO2 emissions very low comparable to to
wind lower than anything else out there
the idea of these small reactors here
you see in our artistic rendering not
very realistic but great because it was
made by Norman himself um of what a
nuclear battery might look like but um
the idea of this small reactor these
nuclear batteries to be uh Mass
fabricated in factories completely
standardized sort of plug and play uh
which means really days between the time
that these machines arrive to the side
to the time you start generating your
your heat and electricity um they could
operate for 3 to 10 years without
refueling that's the beauty of nuclear
the energy density of the fuel is
extraordinarily High millions of times
higher than fossil fuel so there is not
a need for frequent refueling um they
can be air cooled you know reject the
waste heat essentially to the atmosphere
instead of um being linked to proximity
to a body of water be it the ocean a
river Etc semi-autonomous operations
that's required because a lot of uh
operators would basically break the
business model for these
things now um what is unique about these
nuclear batteries other than what I
already said well um they're very small
side footprint this basically fit in
shipping containers and the whole site
could be order of an acre for generation
of say 10 or plus megawatts of
electricity 24/7 and clean uh
incremental capacity you could basically
uh provision the capacity incrementally
um with small um initial capital
investment unlike traditional nuclear
plants which of course will set you back
building ions and billions of dollars I
already mentioned transporter
redeployable very very robust uh safety
profile and nuclear is not the cheapest
is never the cheapest but once it's
built then actually its cost is pretty
predictable and for some applications
this predictability over a long period
of time is um is highly desirable now
fto is not a nuclear technology
development company we don't have our
own nuclear battery design in spite of
the pretty picture that I show you
earlier but we work with very
established nuclear re reor companies
I'm sure you have heard of Westing gals
you might not be familiar with bwxt
that's actually the company that makes
reactors for the US Nuclear Navy for
submarines and AFA carriers and these
companies have been developing these
nuclear batteries and so so what do we
do well we are really a uh project
development and execution company so we
pull together the expertise that we have
in house with working with uh reactor
vendors with customers Etc to set up
projects where these nuclear batteries
are Caple to some production activities
that the clients are interested the
customers are interested in and realize
and integrated a clean energy clean
energy system and so here you see some
of the keywords of things that we um are
eager to work on that they range from
technoeconomic analysis of course that
would be the front end to show the
promise of the project um nuclear
reactor design safety and materials
evaluation operations and training
assembly etc etc so we like to think
about ourselves as being at the center
of a little ecosystem of again vendors
prospective um operators of these
machines and the model here that we have
in mind is a fleet of nuclear batteries
it doesn't make sense to have one off
you got to be able to operate a fleet of
potentially hundreds maybe thousands
being optimistically of these nuclear
batteries because that's how the cost
particularly the operating cost are
going to come down because there is a
range of services that operating
refueling and maintaining these machines
is going to require and that again makes
sense if you you have a multiple of uh a
multiple of units so we are ready to
support across many sectors again this
is sort of the uh the value proposition
here is this is not for the grid and as
we know the grid is only what a quarter
of the CO2 emissions uh is associated
with the grid the rest is industry
buildings um transportation Etc and so
this solution we think based on our
analysis is almost like the you know the
Swiss knife equivalent of the energy
world you could use it almost everywhere
and so we're ready to support and
deliver and we just finished our first
front end assessment for an offshore oil
and gas that desires to uh decarbonize
their offshore applications and it looks
pretty promising so with that I stop I
think I ran out of time so I can't tell
you exactly uh what the meaning of fto
energy is but if you're curious come
come see me at the at the table out
there and I'll tell you what's behind
the name thank you
[Applause]