hello computational music theorists
here's a short video on what some of the
problems in Mir or music information
retrieval are and how they can be
connected to music theory and musicology
which is the main topic of this class
21m 383
these slides owe a lot to AI feffer
professor at Harvard who inspired them
with his
lectures the main question that we'll be
working on is how do we move from sound
that's made in the real world to a score
that's printed out or displayed on the
screen what kinds of Technologies are
needed and what kinds of problems need
to be solved in order to do this really
well
well first when we sing or play an
instrument we're making actual sound
waves in the real world so we need to
solve the problem of how to most
accurately transform sound into a signal
and this involves microphones and other
devices and it's kind of a pure
engineering problem that we're not going
to be focusing on in this class but it's
very complex and very valuable and we
offer some courses in the music
department that will help you do this
better
but once we've got the sound from The
Real World into an electrical signal
we're working in the time domain as we
call it and that is the amplitude of
sound at a single moment forward
backwards positive or negative and we
usually record in something close to CD
quality or 44,000 times per second we're
measuring the amplitude as a 16bit
signed integer
and so the sound at this point looks
something like this if this was a I
don't know an attack of an instrument
that's decaying maybe a piano or
something of that
sort the problem here is how do we
convert from the time domain to
frequency to being able to say okay all
these impulses add up to a particular
frequency how do we decode it from the
signal
and understand that hey in this sound
there's two principal frequencies that
are uh being heard and to do this we use
foryear
transforms and the fast fouryear
transform algorithm is something that
it's very good to know in order to work
in this field so now we have
frequencies and we want to translate
them to pitch and Pitch connections and
that's not just um thinking about you
know what is A4 440 Herz or but which of
those frequencies that pop up are
prolonged to make a particular pitch
because even while I'm speaking there
are particular frequencies that are
popping up but they don't necessarily
make pitches the attack on a flute isn't
necessarily the pitch that we want so
which ones are connected for this then
once we have these particular frequency
pitch connections we want to move from
there two pitch notes as we saw with the
piano example there were two frequencies
there does that mean two pitches or is
one of them a reverberation in the room
or if you're listening to another
instrument maybe you hear seven pitches
six of them are higher and much quieter
and you might think oh that's the
overtone series of that instrument and
so going from Pitch connections to pitch
notes involves the estimation of tomber
what is the tomber of the instrument
what is the overtone series that one
expects and who we remove them and from
there do we end up still with multiple
pitches in
accord now that we know the musical
pitches that we're interested in we want
to go from there to understanding the
duration of these pitches and the tempo
of the piece and so there are particular
algorithms that we can use to estimate
the duration that means
one thing is you know you just
milliseconds and things and then say
okay well that's going to be the most
common note we'll call it a quarter note
and so on and from there we can estimate
the
tempo or we can do it in the other way
we can take all these pitches and try to
estimate a Tempo based on what are the
recurring onsets that seem to be beats
and from there go and figure out the
duration quarter note half note uh three
beats long something like that for each
of the notes so which direction do Mir
people go um it turns out that we
usually create a sort of feedback loop
so we try to do both at once and
estimations of tempo lead to durations
uh which then can be rejected or
accepted and estimations of duration
lead to estimations of
tempo and so the Technologies involved
are beat tracking and self-similarity
Det ction and
others from the pitches the duration and
the tempo we can create what we call the
the full notes or just the notes that is
something um Pitch and duration
combined from all these full notes we
can construct what we call a virtual
score and that is the score as
represented purely as collections of
notes and other events uh we might be
estimating at this point crescendos and
de crescendos and maybe we're hearing
certain notes are slurred and we're
keeping these all as objects inside
memory and so this involves the
technology of Music representation which
we will be getting to very soon in this
class and so how might we represent a
score maybe as a set of parts with
measures and notes in
between from the virtual score
we need to figure out okay how is this
going to look on the page or on the
screen and so we perform layout
estimation and we create a laid out
score where it's not just notes inside
of a array or a list or something like
that but actual positions on a page and
this involves some technologies that
we'll be getting to in the class here's
an example of very poor layout
estimation
from the laid out score we choose what
the glyphs that would be appropriate are
and where are they going to be placed on
the page example of some of the things
that might be involved in doing
that and then once we have the laid out
score the glyph selection and placement
we move to pixel rendering individual
dots no longer connected to any semantic
meaning but just is this XY coordinate
going to be black white or something
between or something
else and from there we have particular
technologies that we're going to need um
such as screen drawing you know old
school cath array tubes LED display
things like that or how to actually make
a printer distribute ink on a page and
these again are engineering problems
that are beyond the scope of this class
but still very very important so let's
look again a summary of what we have
here we move from the time domain to
frequency frequency to pitch connections
we estimate the duration in the tempo
creating full notes create a virtual
score or logical score some people
separate these two out um then we try to
make the layout and to the
output at each of these points in the
process we can involve music theory or
musicology and we can learn
aspects about music theory or musicology
from the data that we're getting at this
point so for instance the duration Tempo
uh level we can start to ask well what
are the most commonly used rhythms in
this piece and from there hey let's
create a backing drum track to accompany
The Soloist because we we figured out
you know what kinds of durations what
kinds of rhythms connected this with a
database so
on or at the frequency to pitch
connections level we can we can Now
understand based on which overtones were
removed what instruments were being used
are they playing their natural ranges
and from there we can you know might
estimate the year of this recording uh
based on particular sounds and sound
artifacts or the year of the piece based
on instruments that are used and so
on so these are places where music
theory and musicology can get data from
this Mir process
but there's another side that's uh been
much less talked about and it's a place
of great potential that I think people
in this class will be able to contribute
to and that is going from music theory
or musicology back and um using things
that we know about Theory or history of
music or music studies to enhance the
quality of the algorithms being used in
these places for instance at the pitch
connection level um we can say well
let's look at the metadata and it
suggests that this is a piece by Mozart
he died in 1791 so so let's look at
those instruments um now the frequency
uh overtone estimation was saying okay
the most likely instrument is electric
guitar uh this is very likely wrong I
mean I don't know maybe it's a a modern
Arrangement but it's pretty likely wrong
why don't you try this overtone profile
of a forte piano a early piano said and
wow you find out okay that was the
second best uh score but probably the
best one When taking into account the
metadata on the
piece or we can um use music theory and
musicology at the frequency detection
level so we might say hey all of the
notes you've been detecting around this
note have been an E major and then you
hear an a sharp and H that's seems a
little frequent a little fishy oh hey
there's a runnerup note of a natural
that was 95% as like
from music theory
standpoint I think that more likely um
we've detected the wrong note so these
are ways that music theory and
musicology can enhance this
process most exciting at all though is
when parts of the process feed into
music theory and musicology algorithms
and we get and and are enhanced by it so
we say oh hey given these frequencies
pitches durations and we get a style of
the piece and we suggest that it's from
the swing
era and then we can help later parts of
the process by saying you know if the
style of the piece is from the swing era
when you do your virtual score your
logical score probably all those
triplets those yum bu bum bum should be
written down and represented as a that's
what the conceptually they
are but we can not just move forward we
can at the virtual score level maybe um
it's beginning to lay out the score and
you know they're putting everything
nicely into 34 and the musicology or
music theory algorithm says well these
rhythms are highly unusual for 34 time
um let's go back and rerun some of the
previous steps with that notion that
that was highly uh improbable and try to
make the score again so we can move
backwards in time redo a particular part
of the process rerun it and then maybe
come up with a different result ah we'll
put this in
68 so here are some of the ways that
music theory and musicology can feed
back into the Mir sound to score
process next time sometime soon I hope
to say how we can do go the opposite
direction how we can take a score and
automatically perform it and even though
we're going to be going in the opposite
direction
turns out that there's a totally
different set of problems that we have
to solve