Our next speaker is professor Marcus
Bureau. Many of you have worked with him
as you can imagine. Uh professor Bureau
is a professor of engineering in both
the civil and environmental engineering
and mechanical engineering. Today he's
going to discuss some new AI
architecture driving the breakthroughs
both in science and in real life
applications. Let's welcome Professor
Bork. Yes. Um well, thank you so much.
Um really great event and nice to see so
many of you. Um yeah so I'll be talking
really about how we built AI for
scientific applications and you know
where we are today and building AI that
can think and you know make predictions
that are not obvious uh maybe discover
new things. So where we're today I mean
we've seen a lot probably in the
presentations um the last day or so
about machine learning uh we can train
complex functions we can even generate
new data um you know code sequences and
things like this but the the real
challenge really is how do we really
create something absolutely new things
we haven't had before things that aren't
in the training data and that's what the
presentation will be about you know we
refer to this as um broadly reasoning
models um agentic AI AI that can take
actions um with the world and interact
with the world and make um you know
decisions that hopefully bring us bring
us forward. So that's what the about and
I my research deals as you've seen with
materials. I I study materials um these
are really interesting systems. So I
mean how many of you work on materials?
Not everyone. Some. Yes. Great. Some.
But you all of course know about
materials. So you can look at anything
fabric in your clothing. And if you take
a microscope, it it will ultimately look
like an atom, a molecule. And you can
imagine it's a very challenging problem.
Economically very important because
everything's made from materials. You
know, even if you're not making
materials, you're relying on materials
obviously. Um and the challenge a lot of
times is how do we design these systems?
How do we understand them? And there's a
lot of relationships across scales. Now
for I would say um 50 years 70 years
since the 1950s really since we had
bigger computers what physicists
scientists chemists did we broke down
the problem in different scales you know
we said okay we have a a a chemical
scale we have a molecular scale a
continuum scale for engineers and we
kind of try to bootstrap our way out of
these systems. Now what the problem with
this is that first of all the the
complexity is very large. The other
thing is that many of these problems
across scales cannot be captured. So if
you're in the protein business or
chemistry business, if you're ignoring
some of the details in your sequence
that matters for a disease, you're not
going to capture how the organism, the
human will respond to it in drug design
and things like this. Um so this idea of
sort of coarse graining and simplifying
things really doesn't work. And in fact,
um that's sort of the road we've been
hitting for a couple of decades now. AI
has potential for us to change this
game. change the equations here. And um
something that I think is happening as
you've all seen you know we have um
better models even though you know these
models are they look kind of impressive
but most of these models are still
pretty simplistic and primitive actually
you know and especially you know even
though of course you know today's jet
GPT is here frontier models that
unreleased yet are all the way up there
but still a lot of these models aren't
really able to produce new things and
you can see this if you interacting with
these models right and you ask them
something totally new they really just
interpret a lot of times between what
they've seen in the data and this is
shown here right so if you um look at AI
today machine learning you're really
limited to the kinds of things the model
has seen maybe you can interpolate and
combine things here and there but you
you really cannot go to those white
spaces where you have never seen any
data and that's of course what we want
to do as scientists we want to engineer
discover things and create insights and
knowledge of of of systems we have never
studied um and that's what we're trying
to build um and so this you know can be
done and I think we've made a lot of
progress in the last couple years uh to
do this by by really thinking about how
do we actually train AI how do we teach
these models and in conventional
learning you you teach models examples
and they remember these examples and
they produce sort of new combinations of
examples in in in the solutions what we
got to do though to have models really
understand like scientists do like
engineers do we have to sort of go one
level deeper and understand principles
and this is what's shown on the right
hand side. So for many years in my group
we've worked on something called
category theory. It's a a branch of
mathematics that really deals with
relationships. So that looks at the
world not as a collection of facts but
of as relationships and relationships
between relationships and abstractions.
And this is how we understand the world.
So if you're asked to design something
new, you're not just copying something,
you're thinking about how this might
relate to the problem you're trying to
solve, how you combine new ideas. And so
you do compositional reasoning um really
breaking it down and synthesizing
something new. So this is in a nutshell
what we're trying to build and teach AI
models to do. Now the question is how do
we do it and why? Well here's an obvious
example right? So current AI models
really look like sort of thing on the
left. So they remember you know they
look at an apple falling and they say
yeah it falls pretty fast. They look at
a feather and might say yeah it falls
pretty slow and it might look at a a
different problem like you know dropping
a glass and it shatters. Okay, well the
AI can remember this and it can give you
answers. But we know in physics, you
know, there's actually all of these
problems, there's an underlying theory
which is Newton's laws in this case. And
you can actually describe all of these
phenomena and many more by knowing this
fundamental theory, right? And so now
you have a true understanding and you
can make predictions and this is what
really the limitations of AI are today.
You can't make these kind of fundamental
predictions. Um, so in category theory
and this is how this looks like. So
we've done this work about 105 years
ago. It's mathematics on piece of paper
of a system you understand and you can
kind of write down how things relate. So
on the left you have spider silk protein
and on the right you have music and we
can build theories to relate these two
concepts. That's pretty exciting but
it's manually made. You know we made it
took months and years to do. Uh it's not
scalable. So what we really got to do or
we'd like to do is to build systems that
can make these discoveries on their own
from observations. And this is where
agentic reasoning AI comes in. So we are
basically teaching these models to look
at information which is sort of
measurements of the world and
observations and make connections
between them at a very basic level. Sort
of understand how things are related. Um
and then hopefully we'll make actionable
outcomes. So like if you're in
healthcare we might you know help AI can
help us with administration automation
to drug discovery can discover proteins
and molecules and things like this. Um
and so I I'll talk about this process in
quite some depth and then we'll show
examples and sort of talk about some of
the applications of course but um the
beauty of AI today with even the models
that we've seen in the previous
presentation we have is multimodality
and that's really important for science
and engineering and tech many other
areas too um because if you think about
machine learning maybe in your
businesses in your companies a lot of
times you need perfect data right you
need a table basically you have labeled
data here's a molecule a molecule be
these are the properties. The world
doesn't look like this, right? It's
incomplete. It's imperfect. You might
have handwritten notes. You might have a
video. You might have interviewed a
machinist who worked on a machine for 30
years and they figured out how to how to
do this really well. So, you have all
these different modalities and what we
really want to do, you want to integrate
all of these modalities, digitize them,
tokenize them, and make sense of them
and build abstractions. And the the key
idea, the takeaway from this talk really
is going to be in order to us to do
this, we got to build something like
Newton's laws. Um obviously not Newton's
laws again might be boring, right? But
other fundamental principles um that you
know that are underlying relationships.
And so now you're able to connect
principles from biology to art,
creativity to industrial processes and
many more. Right? So that's sort of the
promise of this. We're building this
essentially by thinking really deeply
about how models work and not just AI
models or machine learning, but any
model, right? So a finite element model
in your company or fluid dynamics model
um or a climate prediction is going to
be one like on the left. It has no
awareness of its own prediction. You
your company humans assess the
prediction, right? And and you you
decide it's a good prediction, bad, new
boundary condition, new new measurement.
So what we really going to do is to have
models assess their own predictions to
be have to have some awareness in
quotation mark okay awareness in a sense
that they can assess what they do um
they can reason over this they can
correct their own mistakes they can
correct logic they can make new ideas
and new suggestions and sort of iterate
through and this idea you know actually
it's been around for a long time you
know in the uh 60s uh included MIT um
people have worked on what they called
at the time artificial intelligence of
course and these systems were um built
sort of hard-coded logic right so they
try to mimic how intelligence works and
that didn't actually work because they
became very brittle you know you needed
to know everything these systems would
do and that's not how the world works we
have to have autonomous assembly of
relationships and understanding and so
this really took you know another 60
years or so until we really had agentic
models that cannot rely that do not rely
on preconceived notions of how these
individual ual components of
intelligence interact but they can self
assemble right and so I'll talk about
this in in more depth of course because
self assembly is fundamental to biology
you know we study biological materials
and any protein in your body is self
assembled right it it it's not told to
assemble in a certain way it has a
memory an ability to do this naturally
and it's a concerted action that happens
an emergence of properties and so this
is what we're beginning to see with AI
and that's really the direction my lab
has taken
um pretty pretty intensely in the last
couple years and I'm giving you sort of
a story of how we got to this. Okay, so
here's an example. Again, for many
years, machine learning, AI, you ask the
question, you get an answer. Most
answers were wrong. And even if they're
correct or wrong, the model had no idea,
right? I mean, you would ask a
regression model, make a prediction
about this amazing new molecule, and you
had a kind of, you know, is it really
true? We don't know. So, um, we built a
few years ago when GPD4 came out, and
this was, I think, the first model that
sort of had capabilities of of thinking
about a problem more deeply. uh we put a
bunch of GPD4 models together and made
them work as a group. Right? So this was
sort of the innovation, you know, we
instead of having one model that you
talk to, we had a bunch of AIs talk to
each other. And what the model did, we
asked the question about creating what
we call force field, which is a kind of
description of the relationship between
uh geometry and energy in physical
chemistry. And again, any other AI model
like graph neural network would have
just made a prediction and it would have
probably been wrong, right? This model
understood that it cannot make this
prediction because it never seen this
data. So what it did instead wrote code,
it executed the code and it produced the
data by running a DFT simulation which
is the first principles quantum
simulation. And so this pretty exciting.
So now once it had the data from quantum
mechanics, it did a regression problem
and fitted this curve, right? And that's
the beauty, you know, is that the model
really had an ability to make its own
data and solve the problem. And so this
was kind of like the moment where we
really thought this is really cool
because you know we want to solve
problems and design and understanding
and now we have a tool we can actually
build towards this end. So I'll s so to
go through um a couple of examples um to
to highlight this and obviously there
you know too many I think the time is
ticking here so I'm going to go quickly
but so there's biology assembly you know
collective motions emergence in ants
they're building bridges they don't know
about bridges they're building them um
bees can build honeycoms and proteins
can be built with AI now is a similar
idea so you can kind of take a bunch of
these individual AIs like like a chat
GPT if you wish simplistically. It's not
actually like this, but and you put a
bunch of them together, not just four or
five like in the previous example, but
hundreds, thousands of them, and they
work together on a problem. Um, and this
is, of course, something we see in
biology all the time, right? We have
building blocks that make larger
structures. We see this in swarming,
right? So, not just in ants and
honeybees, but in many other phenomena.
And so, we're building these systems.
We're building sort of two components
here. One is we spend time in our lab
building these integrated AI systems
that can sort of think and organize
themselves. But we also need to build
individual models that solve specific
tasks. Like for example, we might want
to build an AI model that can design
proteins. This is really an expert into
protein design, right? Because a general
purpose AI today at least can't quite do
this yet. So you have to train AIs to
become very good in specific tasks. We
can make AIs that can make graphs that
can understand forces and mechanics and
chemistry. So these are special purpose
tools which we're building and then
we're putting them together in groups
right so now we're building a team and
so we kind of have okay so we have a
bunch of different components there we
have uh general purpose AI that can plan
we have AIs that are specialists and we
have even physics simulators and so
that's really the key right so now um
when a prediction is made it can
actually assess the prediction by
running maybe a molecular dynamics
simulation or DFT and if all fails as
you've seen in the initial example it
can even write its own code to run its
own simulations. So this is kind of like
where the world lies. It's incredibly
exciting. We can solve problems we've
never imagined being solving like
protein design and their physics
verified because the model isn't just
predicting. It assesses its prediction
and improves the prediction. We can do
alloy design. So I'm just going to flash
through a bunch of examples here. Again,
proteins, alloys. Um we can make
scientific discoveries. We've built
models that can actually form hypotheses
themselves. and solve them. So instead
of just starting with something you come
up with a problem, the model can
actually come up with its own ideas or
what it might want to study. And we can
do this through what we call graph
reasoning. So we can build very large
representations of knowledge from papers
and books and build graphs that describe
the ontologies of how knowledge is
organized essentially. And this can be
fed again into a solution uh agent as
well. And so now we can do both
formulate the problem and solve the
problem. So this is sort of the how the
future looks like. It's very exciting.
Um, this is the swarm example of
designing proteins using hundreds of AI
agents that each works together on a
particular part of the protein. They
don't actually know about each other.
So, we're formulating this as a problem
from reinforcement learning where we're
basically just telling the models each
agent what its actions does for the
objective. And the model figures out on
its own each model how it can best act
to make a better outcome. So, this is
really cool, right? So um kind of kind
of really really fun to think about and
you know this all again is sort of in
this picture here right so we're looking
at relational modeling we're looking at
models they can think we're looking at
isomorphic mapping so we're forcing
models to kind of reflect their own
strategies into these shared spaces in
which knowledge can be abstracted from
which we can then make much more general
solutions. And we're doing this
essentially by forcing models to put
their thoughts into graphs and symbols.
And so those of you who've been around
for a long time, you know that this was
one of the early ideas in the 1960s
actually. Symbolic AI again at that time
the symbolic AI was pre-programmed by
humans. Here the AI learns symbolic
abstractions by itself. And it actually
is is sort of does this using what we
call reinforcement learning. So instead
of teaching the AI the outcome, we're
actually letting the AI figure out the
right abstractions to get the best
possible answer. And we can let the AI
kind of do this for many, many days.
Here's an example where the AI has been
thinking for five or seven days. And it
can create a very deep reflection on the
world. So again, this is an AI in this
case talking to another AI where the
reasoning steps are used as a way to
critique itself, right? And so the AI
can kind of bootstrap itself. So this is
really kind of where the field is going
and you can really teach models of
course to um you know become even better
at innovating even better at making
connections and here's sort of how this
graph looks like. So this is how the the
world model built by the AI itself by
basically asking itself questions and
reflecting on it and building more
abstractions over and over for many many
many days and um at the end you know we
create we see these graphs which
actually and it's surprising uh never
end never saturate so the AI never runs
out of ideas in fact there's always a
reservoir of semantic entropy meaning
capacity to discover new relationships
which are then realized
through structural connections. As the
AI sees these opportunities, it
logically draws connections between
these ideas. And so this is sort of how
innovation works as well. And also sand
piles of course and criticality in
physics is a related concept here. Um so
this slide actually I think you saw it
in the previous presentation. So
underlying all of this of course is how
long can AIs work. So they can work for
days some but generally AI systems in
agendic frameworks can work for about an
hour or two reliably. And you can see
this here and this is a scaling law. I
think it's going to be really really
important for this field as these AIs
can work for longer not just for an hour
day you know two three days 5 days maybe
um they're going to become very very
powerful. Um how do we do this? We built
lots of technology to make this happen.
We built models. We built inference
engines. Everything open source.
Everything at MIT we do is open source.
So you can access this on GitHub and and
hugging face. Um, we've built inference
engines for very large models that we
need to serve these large AI systems, of
course, on a local computer. Um, we need
access to data. One of the things we can
do at MIT, and you might have heard
about MIT Nano, um, is an amazing
facility where we can actually automate
some of those processes in the future.
So, this is an exciting opportunity here
at MIT. You need of course have an idea.
Of course, you can do a simulation, but
sometimes you need to go to the lab at
the end, right? And test some of the,
you know, collect new data. So this is
really how we think we think the web
look like. It's going to change the
world. I think you know we um we're not
using these AI systems in this way today
obviously. So this is I think a study
entropic did um mostly done for simple
office tasks today. Still makes our
lives easier but there's a lot more room
of course to grow. Um the expertise you
need of your staff is going to change
right? So, you know, in the future, um,
you know, the role of an engineer is
going to change. And I like to remind
us, if you think back, um, sort of in
the 1980s and 90s, so I grew up in the
'9s with computers, uh, you know, but if
you look back to the 80s when PCs came
out, and I've been watching a lot of
these, um, sort of historical accounts
at that time. If you listen, for
example, uh, computer chronicles, I
don't know how many of you know that. I
did not know it obviously, but I came
across it. I was too young. I was like
six years old at the time. You can you
can watch it on YouTube. And they
discuss PCs like C64, Apple, you know,
MS DOS, Windows, and they were kind of
wondering what can these things do?
They're very brittle. And they were
advertising them kind of like they had
the guy from Microsoft come in and show
the new machine. And it seemed so um
pedestrian if you look back at this
time, but fascinating. And I think we're
in the same point at AI today. These
things are very brittle. Lots of
questions. Um and we kind of look sort
of ahead a couple years and we're going
to see some really amazing developments.
Um if you're interested in learning
more, I mean I teach classes in
professional education, one in June here
at MIT on campus and one in July live
virtual. So some of you or your staff
want to come. This is obviously much
more in-depth discussion than what I can
do in 20 minutes here. Um yes but so
with that yeah thank you so much. I mean
this you know I like to think about this
as thinking machines. I've been doing
modeling simulation my entire life. In
fact, actually almost my entire life
because when as a kid I was programming
computers to simulate the world and and
it's sort of to me a dream come true
that I have computers can actually
think. They can really think and build
their own models um write their own
code, collect their own data and um
yeah, we're using it for some really
cool applications. I didn't talk about
all the fancy stuff we can do in the
application side. I wanted to kind of
convey some of the technology uh and
possibilities, but I'm happy to talk
about any of the applications with IoP.
I talked to a lot of companies and many
others around this. So if you're
interested in learning about specific
applications and materials and what we
can do with it, happy to discuss. Thank
you.
So you can read your question first.
So do I have to read question? So how
difficult is it to implement high level
material characteristics like conduct
conductivities on all mechanical
properties so they can be predicted by
model? Well, so you know, you you need
um some
observations and if you were to go, you
know, with an AI model that has no idea
about any, you know, any kind of
mechanical properties, you traditionally
do like a regression model, you need a
whole ton of data. Now, if you're
starting with these agentic AIs, they
have some understanding usually about
the problem at hand. So, they know
something about mechanics, they know
something about uh connectivity. So the
way we're approaching this is by using
models that we call pre-trained. They
understand something about the world and
then they learn. They can learn from
papers, sub literature. They can learn
from simulations. They can learn from
experimentation. And often times we need
very little data and or because these
models are trained using reinforcement
processes, we can also teach them to
make better predictions by letting them
basically fail. And that's the point,
right? We want the models to make
prediction, do reasoning and make a
mistake and then the models will have to
figure out a pathway to make better
predictions. So all of this is and I
actually I think I went through this
very quickly but is that we are not
we're really trying very hard to make
models not remember the answer. We're
we're forcing we're encouraging the
model very strongly to understand and
learn the path to get the answer. Right?
We're doing this through symbolic
abstraction. So models in the reasoning
steps are not allowed to just remember
the answer. They can if they really if
it's trivial, but we're making it really
hard for them. So we're penalizing
penalizing them for this. And so um you
know in a way yeah it's like you you
want to find these hidden laws these
hidden Newton's laws doesn't have to be
quite at the level of Newton's laws but
you know these these relationships that
are foundational to describing your
properties and so you can get away with
reasonably little data. So that's a real
game changer. So to traditional machine
learning of course. Yeah. Um another
question um how would you validate?
Yeah. So you know you validate it in in
you can give different reward functions
right. So one could be let's say you're
designing a protein. I mean it could be
the patient response right and that
could be your your final outcome. But
usually you have intermediate steps like
for example you want activity you want
stability and you want to get something
like you want to get proteins that are
stable and that are active and
ultimately the reward will be does it
actually work in a patient. So I would
say you know there's different levels
and the beauty of these agentic models
is exactly that they can do this. You're
not limited to one thing. You're not
training models to be have one outcome
that you know in fact um you know what
we find in in these agendic systems is
that they will define their own
intermediate steps. So they will say I
have to design a protein. Okay, I I
don't know the answer to this problem.
Let me find a path to get to that
answer. And they will actually define
their own merit. So they might make a
plot and they might analyze the plot. I
didn't really get to this either, but um
you know the sort of the the design of
what validation looks like could be part
of what the agents can do on their own.
Now that being said, you're not out of a
job yet. No, I'm kidding. Um especially
if you're here, you're in the right
place. And but you you we we can
supervise this process, of course. And
you know, there are there are you know
human interventions we can have. You
know, we can say, okay, we um here's an
intermediate result. How does it look
like? And we do this all the time. And
then you say, okay, I I like it, but um
you know, I don't like this. I I like
the general direction, but I don't like
this chemistry because it's actually
toxic, right? And so we can give this
feedback to the model, of course. So you
are one of the team members, if you wish
in the agendic AI system and um we're
building these in of course um because
there's a lot of human domain expertise
of course that we don't want to um you
know uh get get rid of. Yeah. Thank you
very much. Thank you so much. Thank you
so much.
[Applause]