the MIT skydiving Club just jumped out
of an airplane it might seem like a wild
adrenaline rush but actually there's a
lot more to skydiving than just jumping
out of a plane and pulling a rip cord
when you're just falling a few feet
there's not much you can do on the way
down so how is falling thousands of feet
through the sky any different you learn
in school that things accelerate towards
the ground because of
gravity gravity pulls skydivers toward
the Earth but as we fall tiny air
molecules bump into
US each tiny bump causes a little bit of
force against our bodies the hit from
one air molecule may not seem like a lot
but when you add all those tiny forces
up you get a big Force called drag which
pushes up opposite to gravity skydiving
may seem like it defies the laws of
physics but in the end it's just playing
with the wind for more MIT moments from
MIT open learning like subscribe or
follow