okay welcome everybody wonderful uh warm
February Friday here and we're uh
continuing with our second topic for the
class first one being about um notes
pitches durations and now we're getting
to how to represent um bigger music SCH
scores
um I'm going to start though by jumping
back to uh topic one for a second I want
to uh talk through a couple things
first great job on pet one uh there I
can and I can say it's nice when you can
say that to the whole class without
putting uh for the most part P set one
was really great no every single P set
one was was very strong um there when
and that's that's my quick to second
overview of having the computer
automatically go through and just um
spit out every error that it detected
and I'll go through it by hand because
um and figure out places where there
might be partial credit where a mistake
early on was causing cascading problems
and uh things of that sort but um some
really really great things happening you
guys seem to be uh really strong on um
on Pitch names on representation on
manipulating transposing some really
really good work with inversions for the
most part which is some of the most
challenging parts of the problem set and
um yeah
so I'd love to dwell for the next hour
on everything you all did right uh give
yourself thumbs up for that but let's
let's talk a little bit on a couple of
the things that were challenging on the
problem sets some of them that um you
know that maybe I could have done better
some of them maybe you we could have
just thought that one one little bit
harder let's start with um the concept
of pitch class
um how many pitch classes are there
let's shout it out on three one two
three 12 12 and they're what 1 to
12 to 11 0 to 11 great super so we
almost all got that so and uh what's
what's a note that's pitch class zero c
c good good
so um let's see see if we know our major
scales pretty well pitch class uh four e
e good so four is
e e
flat
three e double
flat great triple
flat quadruple
flat quintuple
flat 11 so this ends up being this was
one of the things uh challenge that
there's a modulo operator right the you
know trying to make sure everything is
between 0 and 11 at first when you're
looking at the names see and so almost
everybody somewhere encoded right a a
array that looks something like this I
think 5 S I'm getting this right
91 who did something like that at some
point yeah and then um so if you didn't
do that and you encoded all of them then
the hard part was uh
nhar monx yeah if you said that one is C
sh o it's also d flat okay I think I've
got it but it's also you know very very
odd notes like um b double sharp oops I
should do a proper double sharp and not
a programmer's double sharp right
yeah things like that that's correct
right yeah um so if you did something
like this there's that weird thing that
almost that a lot of people um forgot
that when you get your modulo to get
everything into 02 4 5 79 11 by
stripping off the accidentals then you
start adding what is it you subtract one
for every Flat add one for every sharp
so you can do you can have your computer
be very smart at first with things that
um that's a e double sharp my
handwriting will get better um uh and
you can do that but remembering at the
end that oh if B is 11 that B Sharp is
not 11 +
1 but 11 + 1 what do I want to put after
that mod 12 yep good
good um so that was that was one thing
the other thing that came up quite a bit
and uh you're going to think that this
is a like a pretty dirty trick for me
let's start with this
um this is pitch set one this is pitch
set two is there a way we uh is there an
axis inversion somewhere that will let
us transform pitch set one to pitch set
2 no I'm seeing seeing some some nose
Matthew what you you had the first head
uh shock head head Rock what what how
did you compute that very fast did you
try all um all
132 possible axes of rotation and saw
that there were none uh the way that I
did it was I made sure that the
intervals of one were the negatives of
the intervals of the other great so what
when we're talking about the intervals
of one intervals pitch set one what's
the interval that we're looking at
here what do we call two and what's the
interval here two one if we're thinking
of chromatic what if we're thinking of
it in more of our traditional tonal
space what do we want to call this
one what's that whole step whole step
good another word for whole step usually
major second good and here half step
right or minor minor second good so you
knew that you weren't going to be able
to find that you didn't need to do all
the computation let's do one that's a
little bit
harder is there
something like that and can
we find some sort of an inversion ex of
inversion that allows us to transform it
into
that
why it's pretty obvious so go ahead take
always take the easy participation
points um when you when you
can one has four notes and the other has
one has four notes and the other one has
five notes
good uh I believe 15 out of the 17
problem sets turned in found that to be
acceptable because you weren't comparing
first the obvious thing that they had to
have the same number of notes um which
does happen quite often right that
you're going along and you're thinking
of here's a Triad here's a Triad here's
a seventh chord here's a Triad is there
a way that we can manipulate the first
Triad to be the second Triad yes is
there a way that we can manipulate the
second Triad to be the um the uh the
seventh chord the four note chord not
with the tools that we've learned so far
right so those are some things and a a
very very very small um th this one I
think is important because this will
come up in real music
everywhere very very very small problem
in this one this one you might hate your
professor for doing
that can p set one be converted to P at
two by
inversion yes because there's nothing
here you don't need to do any operation
or any operation you do to nothing can
transform it into this right if you
think about the reciprocal of or you
know the Nega negation of an empty set
it'll be sort of the empty set and that
that one I think I I put like one on10th
of 1% on because it's it's kind of a a
nasty thing but it was one of the cases
where uh unlike the fornote thing where
uh a lot of times the pro programs your
algorithms were returning the incorrect
answer uh this one was uh causing the
programs to crash quite a bit um couple
years ago I I didn't my uh automatic
assessment system didn't that was I I
stole it from gozi he's very generous
with that uh did not handle crashes very
well now you know it does so um we'll
we'll see that
so that's a big parenthesis around um
the fact that the pets were great we're
very very strong I think you should all
be uh proud on that but but keep keep
thinking of the corner cases uh I
especially liked how many um test cases
that I didn't write that I saw I mean I
was really really fast through the code
because you all just uh turned it in uh
this morning or late last night but for
the most part but I was I was very
impressed with how how much people were
trying to get at the corner cases and
things and that's a good thing to um
feel free to you know use that kind of
collaborative discussion and we're going
to encourage some collaborative
discussion uh in the next problem set
coming right up there was one other
thing besides U some reading and video
watching um that uh I asked you all to
do and I got some really great answers
and that was talking about um various
kinds of pitch representations what you
might do and uh what some of the
stakeholders um might be who who might
want a particular pitch
representation um and that might be
different from somebody else so anybody
and I read through them I'm going to um
you know say say some things too
especially uh things I found really
great and um if you know but but anybody
find anything that you thought was was
interesting to different groups or
audiences or stakeholders that that
might prefer very different
representations of
pitches yeah Vanessa I think it's
interesting to think like people that
are more into like editing and like
really analyzing sound files might be a
lot more interested in seeing like
frequency values suppos to if you have
like a musician who's reading sheet
music they look at a frequency value
doesn't mean anything to them yeah so
they would want one of and vales to be
able to understand what you're talking
about yeah yeah totally nobody nobody's
going to
see and uh I don't know
59.8 I'm just making these up
947 82 and be like that's my most
beautiful chord I just I just love that
it's very hard to do on the guitar but
when you get it just right yeah yeah so
definitely definitely different
stakeholders for different um for
different uh for different places
different agendas good um other um other
C so we have uh people sound editors and
um and musicians and we can refine that
either way thanks so that was great um
anybody else I
think yeah Matthew some people care
about anharmonic spelling and for some
people that's just access information
that's useless yes the big fight on N
harmonic
spelling yeah I just um got a bug report
in music 21 uh on Wednesday that music
21 was not properly calling uh this
um let see if I can even do it no um
maybe it was
here was not properly calling this a
dominant seventh chord I was saying it
was something
else but if we flip
this here actually maybe I hope I
actually wrote a dominant seventh sign
that sounds like a dominant seventh
chord um that's right right not I'm not
too far away from teaching music theory
for a year so yeah yeah
so I've am a stakeholder in enharmonic
spelling the bug report was from
somebody who um wasn't a stakeholder in
inharmonic spelling
great who who might not care about
inharmonic spelling yeah go ahead uh we
could say like a guitarist who doesn't
know sheet music yeah totally totally or
who or who's doesn't who who's TR maybe
if they they just be a little more inous
maybe
they they know something but it's
translating from the sheet into the
tablet or into the position before
translating to the next stage of mental
processing right I mean we do that a lot
people who are native speakers in um in
two languages don't translate from one
language to another before there's um um
before there's you know some kind of
conception whereas when I'm learning a
new language it's always going through
English before it has a meaning to me
yeah so so that uh somebody who plays
guitar might be translating what they're
saying to a fret position and then
saying Ah that's great you see that uh
quite often in um in a lot of fake book
scores in things where you'll see um I
don't know well same same type of thing
you'll see like E flat minor on
something and then you'll read on that
the the chord
I think that's right
um quite often you know or some
something like that in a melody and well
obviously the that's not but because
it's all about translating it uh first
that's good good other
stakeholders or other interesting people
who might use pitch in a different
way yeah I've heard there's like people
who like make incredible music but they
don't even know music theory at all it's
just like yeah know that yeah totally uh
there's a big um big area now of study
on um implied cognitions of music theory
that um the idea being for for some of
the people who are working on this um
that nobody who's making absolutely
amazing music um has no conception of
what they're doing they might not have
the vocabulary to share it with us but
there's some sort of underlying
conception and how do we get at that um
one of my colleagues one of your uh
fellow professors you can take a class
with Leslie Tilly uh who teaches rhythms
of the world and the Bolognese gamon uh
Sor and music of Bali and Indonesia
things she just uh wrote a book that won
um that just won the big big award in
music theory which was on trying to
figure out what the conception of
Bolognese musicians who play these two
people who play these improvised drum
patterns interlocking at huge super
super fast intervals but sometimes they
one of them stops a bit and does the
other one and they you almost almost
never miss and when they do you know
just like a flub note they you know they
laugh and say oh oh how do how do we it
up but you know they say and um her book
begins with asking people how do you how
do you do this and said oh you just play
whatever you want and so of course she
plays no no no not that not and so how
do you get at the implied uh the implied
music theory conceptions super great uh
question Jordan I keep saying uh who are
the people who do this but some people
uh some people in this class identified
um stakeholders that weren't
people one yeah go ahead like do did
digital audio workstations yeah yeah so
we we can give autonomy to a digital
audio workstation or to a computer in
general or to uh a neural network um
there's been a a lot of talk about
autonomy and sentience in neuron
networks this week um and
uh and you know so so why not talk about
them as stakeholders what makes it
easier for a digital audio workstation
to process pitch probably usually uh
eliminate enharmonic
spelling helps quite a bit um yeah great
uh anything else that came up that that
you found especially if you if you read
something and even you don't remember
who it was but somebody else's that you
read and and liked and you thought oh I
wish I had thought of
that ah I'll I'll see it when we go
through the the sheets and stuff so so
that's that's great that's um mostly
leaving aside topic one now there's one
more thing in topic one and I've put it
on a video to watch this weekend you
will have unlocked your first music 21
module so now in any problem set from
now on it is will be fair game to say
from music
import
pitch and the video will go into more
detail from this pitch is lowercase in
Python what's that
signify if you're importing science
lowercase probably
well actually well okay there's a
there's a there's a pitch. capital pitch
what what's the distinction between
those
two in this
case yeah one is like a class one is a
class and the other one is a
what a
folder it acts exactly like a folder
great answer there's specific name that
that's used in yeah Jason mod module yep
so which one's
which that one's a class that one's a
class I'm I'm I'm very bad at I turn
around and you're Point capital P is a
class and lowercase one is the module so
you have everything
module module y everything that's in the
pitch module is done because you will
also find in there things like
accidental which is pretty helpful so a
module group together a related set of
classes if you yeah sorry just going
back to the umentation thing I was
wondering if there are any studies on
people who don't have perfect pitch but
only Val pitch like take the same piece
of music and then just transcribe it is
there any emotional difference like to
the doesn't matter if it's like you know
starting on D or starting on F some
doesn't have who doesn't have perfect
pitch uh I'll have to look that up I
imagine I mean uh the I don't have
perfect pitch but uh absolute pitches is
the term that we're using more often now
uh I don't have perfect or absolute
pitch but um but there's definitely
pieces that if you play you know some
song that I know really well and you
play it up a half step or up a whole
step it's going to you impact me now if
it's a song I don't know I'm not not
entirely sure but I'll I'll I'll see um
let me just make make a note on that um
I found in one one unscientific study
did that um in uh for a paper I was
working on that there's a particular
case where um you can uh very strangely
the rep the number of notes within a
repetition of Contour is decreasing but
the number of um repetitions of that
Contour before something changes is
increasing so the tempo depending on if
you hear
the harmony or the when the harmony
changes the harmonic changes as
determinant of tempo or if you hear the
repetition of Contour as determinant of
tempo you can hear the same piece
speeding up or slowing down and um a lot
of people were like oh yeah I I hear
this and things but um in that uh
unscientific experiment people with
absolute pit um
said I don't hear repetition of Contour
when the notes are different
that that doesn't seem to me a kind of
repetition so there's there probably
different ways we can do that great
super great question um we'll put that
aside when we edit it we'll edit that
about 10 seconds back and we'll jump
back to here just for a second U don't
don't be afraid of of of doing that if
if it's something you know and if if
it's something that I think it's going
to be super confusing to everybody if we
jump back I'll say we'll hold that for a
bit but I think we we can still code
switch which we can switch back and
forth between what we were talking about
30 seconds earlier and what we were just
talking about right good okay so you're
going to be able to import and use
anything in the pitch module as long as
it doesn't have the word
transpose in it somewhere because
certain kinds of transposition will be
uh things for us to work out in the next
couple problem sets good good so that's
that's what's coming up and then we'll
be done with with
that now uh so last class we were
talking a lot more about moving from the
representation of individual pitches
individual notes into larger things we
might call it representation of a score
or simply representation of Music
something of that sort I introduced a
term that some of you already knew from
other classes uh that come goes back to
uh philosophy but has a inter Twist of a
meaning in um in computer science anyone
remember that term without looking down
at the outline ony ontology
good and last class we explored um some
of the things in the Phil philosophical
thing definition of essence of of what
something is I remember some of the
things that we we had trouble defining
when something ended and became
something
else yeah we talked about notes we
talked about notes that we can't really
tell is is this one note is this two
notes is this six notes is it Infinity
of notes or 14 or um yeah then a larger
system um of musical notation remember
we called it used in used in uh one part
of the
world yeah common western music common
western music notation yeah and we had
we had some trouble distinguishing when
what was common or what was Western
about it or I suppose in one case what
was music about it uh seemed to be um
you know uh on the edge good then we
also brought up a little bit the
computer science
definition and that's what we're going
to be working looking at a little bit
now but always feeling like we want to
jump back to the philosophical
definition because we don't want ideas
from computer science all always to um
what what is easy to conceive of we
don't want that to limit our imagination
of what we might be able to conceive in
the
future so we talked about uh so in the
computer science definitions uh there
are various ones there's ones that are
more formalized there's ones that are
less one that I can't of keep in my head
because I can remember it when I come uh
come up is when we're trying to
represent something like music or you
know you can be your ontology of um of a
website or something but when you're
trying to think of a particular object
that's either conceptual or or you know
rified uh really real want to think
about how is it made up of what objects
are in
it what are the
relationships
ships between
objects and what are they called or what
are their names
what was it there was something it was
like first or second class that we had a
real oh I remember now really hard time
figuring out the name of it and it had
to do with the well this is a this is a
eighth note and this one's a whole note
and so the blank of the note is eighth
the blank of the note is whole what what
did we what did we come up with we had
some the Almond of it yeah we we had the
um so sometimes sometimes pushing it way
out there can make that um I mean some
of you all have taken physics you know
that uh probably subatomic particles do
not have a charm a color uh things like
that but these kinds of names can help
us conceive of some property of
something so we might have the Almond of
a note I think I went with something
very generic the type of the note but uh
always avoid type if you can come up
with something better because a type
it's it's too valuable to use if you can
and too generic so good so what are
things and what are they called and I'm
spending notice what are the objects
you're going to be thinking about that a
lot what are the relationships what
you're always going to be thinking about
that a lot but the name of something can
really really help somebody un somebody
else understand how you're conceiving
something and it's can be very very hard
U some of you have probably heard the
computer science joke that there's only
three really difficult things in
programming what to name something and
off by one
errors good good good some people hadn't
heard that and some other people have
yeah so what is something called and um
and that but we're going to jump now to
what are the relationships between
objects um what are some things in music
that we might consider an object let's
just let's let's rapid fire just shout
out over each other note note good
always take the easy one get the easy
participation credit great rest rest I
heard yep me measure oo that's good
phrase phrase
ah
good articulate Artic
articulation good let's I'm going to
stop writing down unless I hear
something that I've never never thought
of and um good what else
there Cliff Cliff good the whole score
the whole score good the score
the
dynamic the instrument
Tempo name of the
performer Concert Hall that was P
performed in maybe maybe not we can we
can kind of go but these are things we
might represent when we're thinking
about a performance of a music um good
anything else on people's jumping on
people's mind Angelica do you have one
that you haven't
heard beat or something beet oh yeah
beat
see that that's great because that's
something we don't see on the score but
we're thinking all the time right yeah
tamber good the instrumental
color
tamber great so so these are all
different things and um that might we
might think of as as objects one of the
things and some of them we might not
represent in every programming language
as an actual you know object class
depending on your programming language
but you know there things we can think
of that have a
particular um
nness can you say nness that they act
like nouns that they have the essence of
a noun um as opposed to a verb nobody
said that a fundamental object was
transpose or
perform right that that those those
verby things so when we want to think of
various ways that objects can be related
as any um we talk often about taxonomies
and
momies any has this come up in anybody
else's in computer science classes think
doesn't come up in was it 69
6101 okay good who has but who has heard
of a taxonomy in another concept yeah
yeah K what where have you heard it um
like animals animals Kings play cards on
fat green stools do they still teach
that or uh Kingdom film yeah I mean now
there's all these they keep rearranging
it right they're keeping sub classes and
super kingdoms and and things like that
but yeah so we can have a taxonomy that
way so taxonomy is one that we're um
we're useful for text on I
can when you're too close it's hard okay
taxonomy um in this definition in
ontology it's something is
something
else so um give the example here that
um that a a minuette is a
dance um for those who know the minuette
style in the early 18th century the
minuette is a triple time dance which
means it is a dance um or it is a um or
that I don't know what's what's
something else in in music that is
something
else yeah aletto is a Tempo aletto is a
Tempo working good I put up this what
what do you call this one in this
context Stato Stato now now you'll
understand when when we do Optical music
recognition how the context is so
important otherwise you'd say
augmentation dot right so staccato is a
articul articulation good is there any
higher level thing that we might say it
is musicians probably not but when we're
thinking of representing for computer
yeah John a half note is a note a half
note is a note good half note is a
note great uh I was just going to go
back to the articulations also but we'll
jump to half note is a note in a second
because that's a pretty fundamental one
um sometimes with with your own
representations you might think of um
for
instance is Trill an
articulation who votes yes who votes
no who votes I I have never thought
about this and I hope I never have to
think about this again in my life okay
good A lot of people call a tra an
ornament a turn an ornament something
like that so you might need what is the
class of but but we know that a Trill is
more related to an accent mark than it
is to a half note or to um a jaizelle
right so so we might think of what's
some some kind of slight just like some
kind of slightly bigger thing that holds
um that holds articulations and
ornaments what might we call that and
when we come up with a name for that
yeah Jason first then modifier a
modifier good that's what a lot of
people um that's believe what it's
called in the um Vex flow notation
software so somebody yeah I think maybe
you could kind of throw under envelope
if you're thinking about synthesis
envelope they
on are they
envelopes they might
be envelope envelope Changers envelope
there they in themselves the staccato
doesn't does the stado have an envelope
maybe it does I'm not I don't work in
this as much but it's like it's just
they attack
the the second thing
sustain uh attack no attack d k s
sustain r residen or release yeah not
this class not not what we're talking
about but some people have that
Knowledge from doing electronic music
things yeah so that so this is something
that changes how we attack how we Decay
how we sustain how we release right so
so yeah maybe that that is a very good
term we're going to be coming up with a
B bunch of these conceptual grouping
things because of um of something that
you can do with
um with uh with things that are in a
taxonomic
relationship and I'll write that out and
and while while you all think what might
be in those missing letters uh had a had
a question had a comment on the previous
one I say like augmentation there there
might be an augmentation or in the case
of a staccato Maybe a negative
augmentation or something yeah a length
reducer
good what do you think the that in
computer speak when we say that
something is something else we can
represent it
with subclass relationships who uh
subclasses is something that comes up
I'm 99% sure in the prere for this right
you guys deal with classes and subass
classes and things so um quite often
there there a bunch of builtin sub
classes in um in Python that you have
various um a lot of things are uh that
we think of things are subclasses of
number complex numbers oh yeah we all
learned uh taxonomies in in our math
classes too right complex numbers
floats ins
things like that and quite often for
different purposes that's why we thought
about stakeholders for different
purposes different um different sort of
taxonomies can be created right I mean
in certain case you could think um well
in integer is a special kind of float
that has nothing past the
dot and that's a very great mathematical
way of thinking of an integer if you try
to implement it that way in your
computer
programs you got some slowness going
because you have a whole bunch of added
baggage that you wouldn't need or you
could think of if you are uh I don't
know if you're when you're in third
grade fourth grade when's the first time
we learn about decimals we don't know
the word in but we know that there are
integers we know that there's five and
seven and things and the first time that
you see
5.2 you would think oh well this seems
to be a subass of this because it's a
different kind of number so depending on
how our ontology how we're
conceptualizing the world taxonomies
could run in two different
directions so let's um well we'll get
back to I just want to make sure that we
can get through this a certain amount of
time
um then there's something
called what did I write it down did I
not write it Y no something called a
momy
an
aeronomy something that instead of is
it's something that something
has um Michael CER is a human most of
the time and therefore he is an animal
because all humans are animals therefore
he is a living thing or that is because
that we can think of that as a
taxonomy uh Michael is an arm he's
actually two arms and he's also two legs
no that doesn't make sense there's a
relationship between my arms and my legs
and me but it's not the is relationship
or at least not the way I conceive of it
but it's something that I
have so what is something uh oh sorry I
meant to leave up John's great um half
note is a note thing so a half note is a
note what is something that a half note
has that it is
not uh Jason first almond almond it has
almond which we used for the type right
that's the Almond great I'm going to I
already have chives as a vocabulary
later now we have almonds so it has a
particular type great what else does a
half note
have duration duration good might have a
duration um what does an eighth note
have that a half note
lacks flag
flag call that a
flag and what might two eighth notes
have that um one eighth note doesn't and
yeah uh bar or what do we call that
thing beam good good I'm gonna the
center of the room has been really
active I'm going to focus over here and
over here for a little bit for the next
couple answers good so it has a beam so
we can think of this um and here's where
your conceptions go uh eighth note has a
beam um 16th Note have a beam or 16th
notes have a beam yeah do they have do
16th notes have a beam that has two
lines in it or do 16th notes have two
beams you can imagine you're going to
encode this very
differently if you encode number of
things and some eighth notes don't have
beams they have Flags instead um but
they have the potential for gaining a
beam perhaps if we think of um you know
Mommy I always want to grow up and be a
beamed uh eighth note not not a not a
flaged eighth note so you might you
might say well we're not going to have
um certain eighth notes that have no uh
now now we get to computer speak rather
than philosophy speak that have no
attribute that where a beam could go
because that's just silly I don't want
to have unbe eighth notes and beamed
eighth notes maybe as two different
concepts as two different objects maybe
you say well I'll have one type of
eighth note and it has either has or
doesn't have
beams then in your representation you
might be asking yourself oops leave that
up you might be asking yourself does it
make sense to say that eighth notes 16th
notes 32nd notes 64th notes whatever go
on to the highest power of two you can
think of have beams but quarter notes
and half notes and whole notes
don't or do we say that whole notes
notes have the potential to have beams
but we you better not put any
on I don't know there isn't a correct
answer for that and so sometimes what we
conceive of we I cannot conceive of a
whole note with Beams I I can conceive
of a half note with beams but um you
know I can think of it I don't know what
it
means actually it means I tremolos D but
but for but that's something else that's
something maybe that's playing visually
that looks just like a beam but means
something or maybe it's
not um so some of the things that come
up in music musical forms give so a
Sonata is a type of musical form it's
used quite often in the 18th and 19th
century um and it's a musical form that
has an exposition the thing close to the
beginning and the exposition has a first
theme group and a second theme group and
the First theme group has a phrase and
that phrase
has measures and those measures have
notes perhaps is one way of conceiving
it it would make much less sense to say
um well it has a phrase and a phrase is
a measure and a measure is a
note right
so this is going to be part of your um
the big part of problem set to in fact
uh we're going to skip um some other uh
things we're just going to do a little
bit of the the cook discussion um and
then um then I want to give you time to
start thinking about problem set two uh
in problem set two you're going to think
of a type of music that is not common
western music notation might not even
have to be a type of music some people
have done um have done things related to
music such as there was a chess playing
music generating system in the 1960s
that somebody uh decided to work on or
it might be the the structure of a
concert or something like that and I
want you to come up with the kinds of
what's the taxonomy in the ontology in
the in the conception of the system how
does this work and what is what are
these relationships what's the meton uh
morony and the taxonomy there over the
weekend we're going to be going
through some of the past notational
formats for
um western music notation for common
western music notation some of the
representations the ontologies the file
formats that um that have sort of come
up over time um one of the things a lot
of the pieces the discussions that
people were talking about have some
connection to Common western music
notation things I was hearing but are
not themselves common western music
notation right they they might have you
know oh yeah well well the rhythm is the
same as you know but as common western
music notation but something else
anything that you think um is just part
of common western music notation assume
that part of the um of the rep of the
ontology of the file format has already
been solved so you know what saying if
it's sort of like you're doing something
with oh this is a dance Groove and
here's and the Baseline is stored this
way it's it's represented in this way
and the notes of the Baseline are just
put stored in you know C CW
um MN or something and or stored somehow
stored in music XML stored something
you'll you'll get some formats and but
don't uh the only the only way that
people have uh Gone really wrong on on
similar assignments to this in the past
is spending too much time thinking about
the things that have already been solved
if you need to your format needs to
encode in images at certain points just
say the jpegs don't invent your entire
New Image format don't invent a new you
know things things that you already know
that's have spend your time on
conceptualizing what hasn't been
conceived
before um I just want to uh point out a
little bit oh sorry that is completely
illegible always feel free to tell me
when something is completely illegible
is that there we go now it's not um
we're going to go through this more
slowly uh I think I I can um can't
remember over the weekend or on
Wednesday um I should have my syllabus
in my head but I write it down so I
don't have to memorize it um but we're
going to be going through something
called the Rosetta Stone of digital
music representations uh by a really
really smart guy uh Craig sap who
realized um anybody seen uh know what
the Rosetta Stone is it was the same
text written in three different
languages uh in especially in Greek and
in ancient um
hieroglyphics that allowed hieroglyphics
to finally be um finally be decoded
Craig saps Rosetta Stone takes the exact
same little
Melody I can go
over what is it
[Music]
um my rhythm was pretty bad on that
should um but that exact same Melody and
shows
how that Melody is encoded in I think he
has like 32 on his website I have edited
it down to about eight but so that you
can see what different representational
choices people have made and what kinds
of ontologies they make um for instance
I remember in this case
beams are high L things they are
represented by these braces and so
therefore they they enclose things beams
in this case seem to have um a morony
that beams have
notes not notes have beams so we'll try
to see some of these things it's another
format uh called ABC one of the ones
still in use even though uh quite a bit
old because it's very very simple we'll
be looking at these in more detail
various formats that at some point were
very big B um but have mostly faded this
is one that we saw once before M's data
where um the Q was quarter and the eight
um was a certain number of durations and
F5 do you remember that from class or
two ago yep and we'll see over
time how the formats have gotten to be a
little bit
more
complex here we
go this is music XML which we're going
to be talking about quite a bit of
course uh invented by Alum of MIT
Michael good and um and one of the great
formats for representing music notation
uh the first one with enharmonics that
just was taken and used by almost
everybody's about 20 22 years old a lot
of us thought this is the final format
this is the representation that really
really works even if there's some weird
quirks we use it forever and then a
terrible thing started happening to
music a great and terrible thing started
happening to music about uh 10 years ago
12 almost 15 years ago but um we started
looking at music sheet music on various
sized screens and therefore where it's
too the screen is too small to look at a
whole page at the time or or you turn it
sideways and suddenly your page has
changed so the notion that music cannot
just be represented by where is on a
page but has to be able to keep
continuously reflowing has caused um a
big change to people today trying to
come up with what is the optimal format
for representing music whose
presentation might be different for you
because you have an iPad it might be
different over here because you have a
15in um Monitor and it might be
different for somebody else because
you've just printed it out in the
oldfashioned way how do we represent
music that way I wanted to point out
because um there is a huge debate so
there's a big discussion happening right
now on what the music notation next
format will be and exactly how it will
what its ontology and morony will be so
that it survives into the next
generation of musical School course and
people you can see are still right now
um some idiots sometimes post but um and
um and exactly what kind of format uh
what the advantages in terms of space
speed various representations are going
on and I haven't checked it this morning
but it seems to just still be going on
so this is a continuous topic of
discussion people are still very
interested in What's um in what's
happening what music representations are
out there and I'm looking forward to
five new music representations existing
a week from now that don't today thanks
everybody