so the clinical genetic testing sphere
is increasingly large these days I live
very solidly in this diagnostic space
where we have a patient with a series of
phenotypes suggestes of a genetic
disorder that is being sent for genetic
testing to try and find an answer either
a unifying diagnosis that explains all
of the phenotypes or maybe multiple
diagnosis that together explain them
however this clinical care Continuum is
AAS basically expanding more towards the
preventive side in genetic testing where
you may have some predictive tests for
susceptibility for adult onset or even
childhood onset conditions in the form
of newborn screening um prenatal testing
or Carrier testing um to help with re
reproductive planning Etc um so in these
different forums of genetic testing well
the content that you might include in
these tests and the types variants you
would report back may change the general
process for classifying Gene disease
relationships and variant pathogen as
they should not change so I'm going to
spend a fair amount of time today
talking through some honestly pretty
onerous guidelines that the field has
developed for classifying variant
cogenic and classifying Gene disease
relationships and before I take you
through those I just want to give you a
sense of why we go through this process
why we put ourselves through this um and
it's really that the results of genetic
testing as with many other medical tasks
does impact lives so it's very critical
that we get these interpretations right
um over interpretation of these task can
lead to a patient for example getting
diagnosed with a disease they may not
have this may then result in additional
follow-up tests that have their own
costs and risks associated with them and
it doesn't just apply to that one
individual who got the genetic testing
originally they may then go and do
Cascade screening and their family
members so it can expand out to impact
the entire family as well and impact
reproductive decisionmaking so the
article at the back here is actually one
from the Atlantic where um they're
describing uh the story of a family who
had some abnormalities reported in a
fenus fetus on ultrasound ended up doing
some pren needle genetic testing related
to that and received a likely pathogenic
variant on their prenatal genetic
testing
report um the lab interpreted that
variant to the standards at the time and
to the best varability given the
evidence they had at the time um but it
turned out that several years later that
variant and the family decided to
terminate the pregnancy based on that
information but it turned out that
several several years later um that
variant was reclassified to a likely
benign variant so that's obviously an
undesirable outcome um on the flip side
the under interpretation of genetic
testing results May lead to a patient
not getting a diagnosis that they
perhaps could have received based on the
identification of a variant and the
evidence available for that variant at
the time obviously this could lead to
missed treatment opportunities again
both for that one patient being tested
as well as their family members and we
already have examples of lawsuits um
related to these kind of mistakes so the
the interpretation does matter and
that's why we spend a lot of time trying
to standardize it so in um a the world
of a clinical geneticist who is trying
to interpret the results of a genetic
test we are constantly considering two
different axes of implication
and that being the variant level
evidence which we're depicting here on a
y AIS and the gene level evidence on an
xais in this figure which was still ined
in McArthur so in this top right
quadrant we have a very wellestablished
pathogenic variant in a very well
established disease genes so the example
here is the Delta 508 variant in cftr
the most common cause of cystic fibrosis
very well
established even in these
wellestablished genes we're going to
encounter some variant for which we have
a lot less information so this would be
a varant of Uncertain significance or a
v us for example in the cftr gene as we
move back down along the xaxis there
you're also going to encounter
especially if you do broader scale
genetic testing some variants that we
have little evidence for and also genes
that we have little little evidence for
so this is a gus a gus or a gene of
Uncertain significance and some
people not much we can do with these
these really don't belong on genetic
test reports at this point until more
evidence
emerges um but what I want to especially
point out in this figure is that this
top left quadent really cannot exist you
cannot have a variant that you are
confident is pathogenic for a given
disorder if the gene that that variant
Falls within or impacts is not
Disorder so let's talk about how we
decide whether a gene is implicated in a
given disorder to set the stage a little
bit here I want to give some um some
framework of where we're at with Gene
Discovery overall so this is a nice
figure from the center brelan genomics
where these kind of blue green Hues are
the subset of the protein coding genes
within the human genome that we have
some evidence have a role in a melan
condition whereas the yellow and orange
shoes are those genes where we just
don't have um any known in uh
implication in a melan condition just
yet so that's obviously the vast
majority but what's really interesting
to see here although we've made great
progress in gene Discovery is that if
you look at human constraint data and
mouse model data there is evidence that
there's still another in the range of
10,000 melan disease genes to be
discovered so as we're working through
particularly in broader like exom and
genome testing the types of variants we
find you're going to see a big spectrum
of Gene Disease Association evidence Lev
from the very wellestablished all the
way down to the
Undiscovered and even if we hone in just
on those genes that have had some
implication in human disease there's a
lot of variability at least historically
in the field in how that information is
integrated and classified ultimately so
as a read out of this this is an
admittedly a bit um outdated chart of
the hypertrophic cardiomyopathy panel
testing um available at 14 different us
clinical labs and hopefully what you can
appreciate um is that the number of
genes that are included on that panel
actually varies pretty widely between
the labs right so you can see that's a
lot of labs are in the range of 20 genes
whereas others are way up over a 100
there are several reasons for this but
one of the main reasons is just
differences in how labs are deciding to
integrate the information that's
available in the literature to decide
this Gene has a worthy enough associ a
with human disease to include it on
their
panel so um to begin to standardize the
field in this respect the clingen group
has put out um these nice uh
evidence-based framework for classifying
Gene disease validity before I go into
that we're going to talk a lot about
clingen today so let me just introduce
what clingen is this is a large nah
funded project um that has three major
centers one of which is led by Heidi
gream here at the bod and really their
motive is to create an authoritative
Central resource that defines the
clinical relevance of genes and variants
for use in both clinical genetic testing
as well as research so clingen has four
major Focus areas Gene disease validity
variant pathogenicity dosed sensitivity
and clinical Astron ability and in
addition to doing a massive amount of
curation work in these four categories
they also committed to disseminating
their knowledge broadly and freely to
the community um so you will see many
examples of really critical cling gen
developed resources that we use in both
Gene and variant
classification um so back to the gene
disease validity guidelines for a
clingen again this is an evidence-based
framework that considers both genetic
evidence the case level evidence family
segregation data Etc as well as
experimental evidence like your mouse
models Etc um and I will say though this
is the original paper on this framework
published in 2017 clinten has iterated
on it a bit um and so you can actually
find their current standard operating
procedures for Gene disease validity
classifications on the Clinton website
which linked at the bottom
here so one of the major contributions
of this paper in addition to the
framework was defining the terminology
we used to describe the strength of
disease Rel Gene disease relationships
prior to these guidelines every lab kind
of had their own way of describing these
right so one lab may have a red to Green
scale where a red Gene is one that is
inated in the z a green Gene is not
other labs also use that red to Green
scale but had the opposite scale so that
a red was not implicated disease so it
was just hard to align on this when we
weren't even speaking the same language
so this is really important to Define
these
terms all the way from definitive at the
highest level of implication and disease
down to no evidence reported and even a
few categories of conflicting evidence
reported as
well it's a points spased framework so
you will see if you look at the top here
that the genetic evidence can be
assigned anywhere in the range of 0 to
12 points the experimental evidence in
the range of 0 to six points and then in
the middle you can see see after you add
those points together the final
classification you end at an important
thing to note is that given that the
experimental evidence is limited to six
points total you cannot get above a
limited classification without at least
some human data supporting the gene
disease relationship which makes sense I
think if you're considering a a clinical
implication of
this um another thing you might notice
looking at these categories is that the
strong and definitive categories
actually have the same number of points
the distinction between these categories
is really that the gene has stood the
test of time as they say that there's
been at least three years since the
initial publication of the Gene and no
significant conflicting evidence has has
come up in the mean
time so in addition to standardizing how
labs are interpreting the relationships
between genes and diseases um this is
very important for how labs are defining
tests as well so shortly after the
publication of this framework the
American College of medical genetics and
genomics Incorporated this into their
technical standards for the design of
diagnostic sequencing panels
recommending that sequencing panel tests
should really only include genes in
these definitive strong and moderate
categories and that limited evidence
genes for the most part do not belong on
these panels and should only really be
addressed in more broadscale sequencing
like Exel and G you
know um so back to our framework let's
walk through what it might look like to
use this framework in the real world so
let's say you were
yeah um about those panels given that
genomics is changing every year do these
under the hood are they running exom or
is it just Gene panels yeah great
question so under the hood the vast
majority of Labs at this point are at
least on an exone backbone and
increasing even going to a genome
backbone and there are huge advantages
to this so that when you want to add
genes as they are discovered it's just a
matter of bioinformatically unmasking
them versus having to create a new Pinel
with new capture
yeah all right um so we're doing an
exone sequence we're analyzing it for an
adult with dilated cardiomyopathy trying
to find an answer for this patient say
you found a variant in the abcc9 gene
right you may say go to Omen see well
you know what is the role of this Gene
and disease and you might be very
encouraged to see oh look there's a line
for dominant dilated cardiomyopathy
maybe this is very important for my
patient you might also do a little
Googling and see that this Gene is
included on some diagnostic panels for
dilated
cardiomyopathy um so you do your due
diligence and you say you'll take this
through the clingen gene curation
framework and I know this text is a
little hard but I will walk you through
the data um what you will find upon
doing a literature search is actually
that there is only really one paper that
convincingly finds variance in this Gene
in a patient with isolated dilated
cardiomyopathy this paper from 2004 and
there are actually two prob bands within
that paper with DCM one of them had a
frame shift variance so this was a loss
of function variant and in the framework
this would normally get you 1.5 points
but when you're looking around in Nomad
you actually notice that there's a
nearby Fram ship variant in Nomad not
the same one but a nearby one that has a
frequency that's a little high that you
would expect for DCM so you decide to
downgrade those points a little bit to a
total of one point
there you also find that there's a
missense variant in a proband with ACM
in that paper reported as well that
missense variant had some functional
studies to suggest it impacted the
protein so that qualifies for 0.5 Five
Points that's all that you found for
your genetic evidence but looking into
some of the functional studies that are
available you find that there is
expression in cardiac tissues which gets
you 0 Five Points you find that there is
an animal model with some cardiomyopathy
phenotype as well as a rescue experiment
done that rectifies that dilated
cardiomyopathy and pond reintroducing
the wild pipe Gene so together that is
going to get you um a 2. Five
Points so overall we have now a total of
four points for this Gene this lands us
very firmly in this limited domain so
ultimately even though it looked
promising at first this variant cannot
be interpreted as a diagnostic variant
for your patient it doesn't rule it out
over time maybe the more evidence will
emerged for this Gene but given that the
first paper was in 2004 and not much has
emerged since then hopes are not high at
this
point so you can probably appreciate
from going through this that this is not
too bad of a process if you have only a
few papers for these jees that being
said it looked much easier just because
we already had the paper summarized and
it takes some time to go and read
through all those papers but as you get
to genes that have more and more
evidence a lot more papers to read this
can be a very cumbersome process so it
really does not make sense for every lab
individually be assessing all of these
genes and duplicating efforts across
labs and so one of the major
contributions of clingen is to kind of
centralize some of this curation work
and also put it in the context of
disease area experts because
interpreting what the functional studies
really stay about the gene can be
complicated as
well um so again clingen has established
these expert panels that are disease
area focus and go in and curate things
like Gene disease relationship ships and
they've made great progress so far this
is a ton of work and as of Tuesday this
week There's over 2800 gen disease
curations available for free for
everyone to use on the clingen website
one thing that I think is particularly
interesting to note if you look at this
little chart here is that those red TO
gray Hues in this top left section of
the chart indicate that overall clingen
is finding about 25%
of the gene disease relationships
reported in the literature are limited
or below evidence so that's kind of a
good warning for anyone who is thinking
that maybe if this Gene disease
relationship has been published it must
be real it's definitely not
true um a little more detail about what
you might see if you went on to this
information on the cenen website again
it's all freely available there you will
note that genes can actually have been
curated for more than one disease
Association and that the strength of the
evidence for each of those associations
can differ so for this particular Gene
it's definitive for hypertropic
cardiomyopathy only moderate for dilated
cardiomyopathy and then has no known
relationship for
arbc there were also additional curation
information on the clingen website in
addition to this Gene disease validity
again we're going to touch on this a few
times but you can see information about
dosage sensitivity curation which is
important for the interpretation of copy
number variation that you might find in
this Gene as well as the clinical action
ability which really reads into more of
the types of tests that this genan
should be included
on so Clingan as I said has done a lot
of curation work all of their
information is available on their
website but they are not the only ones
doing curation work in terms of Gene
disease relationships every lab that is
establishing a panel for example does a
lot of precur work to decide which genes
should be included on that panel and any
lab that is doing exom or genome
sequencing is also evaluating a lot of
Gene disease relationships while they
look through the results of that
sequencing to see if it's relevant to
your proband of interest you have a
question two questions the first one was
what happens if you are hypothesizing
that the variant is maybe impacting like
a gene far away how does that affect how
you interpret disease Gene validity and
the second question was I guess if you
find a variant in your patient but it's
not recorded anywhere else but maybe
there's like comparable variants in the
literature nearby how do you how do you
decide if those V if the variant that
you have and the variant that's in
literature it's comparable or it's like
too distinct to like be weak evidence to
use both great questions so the first
one um remind me again was um variance I
guess in trans like really far away from
the transacting bar yeah so um that is a
great question there isn't definitely
specific guidelines on that um it would
be really a matter of just looking even
if it's far away that the gene that you
think it's impacting has a role in
disease as well and whether there's
other variation that supports that role
and whether you can prove your variant
is impacting for example the expression
of that G and that would be sufficient
okay um the second question which is
about other variants that may have a
similar impact um we'll get to that when
we do variant interpretation discussions
but there are specific codes for
variants that impact the same position
for example that are established as
pathogenic that counts as evidence
towards the pathogenicity of your
variant um we do also very much consider
the variant spectrum of the genes we'll
touch on that a little bit as well
knowing that this sense variance in this
region for example or a hot spot there's
a specific code you can apply for that
to GL to this paper
thank
you all right um so as I was mentioning
there is a number of different groups
doing this Gene curation work and
previously all of this information is
just siloed inside those labs right they
have their own dat databases that
they're keeping so they're not
duplicating their own work but it's not
shared broadly um and so this was really
the impetus for Heidi and Marina dno
who's also based at the broad here to
establish the gene curation Coalition or
the Gen CC which is a clingen supported
public database of Gene disease
curations um the participating members
at present are listed along the top here
and all of these groups are submitting
their databases of Gene disease
durations to the website for everyone to
see this is an important resource
because it kind of democratizes access
to this information but also allows us
to see conflicts that are existing
between these Labs there were always
these conflicts they existed before but
now we can see they're there and begin
to address them which is really
important to improving um the quality of
interpretation across the field as a
whole so if you were to open up the Gen
CC website which again is the Gen cc.org
you might see a page like this if you
search for a specific Gene
gjb3 and you can see every um
submitter's classification for any
submitter that has submitted a
classification for this Gene the
strength level and the disease specific
Association as well as inheritance
pattern you will see that the categories
used on gen CC correspond to those that
were recommended in the clingen
guidelines for Gene disease
interpretation with a few extras so for
example the supportive category is not
something you've seen in the clingen
guidelines but it was designed to be
able to incorporate some databases that
actually are more curating the presence
of a reported Gene disease relationship
rather than evaluating the strength of
that evidence
we thought it was important to bring
that type of information into gen CC as
well so everything submitted by orphanet
we'll have that supported tag and soon
everything from om is going to be in
there as well and these are really
valuable databases particularly for
bioinformatic pipelines because it can
allow you to annotate some of these Gene
disease relationships in Broad scale um
and again the importance of identifying
these conflicts allows us to go in and
try to resolve them so um the Gen CC
steering committee calls Marina will
gather evidence on some of these
conflicting genes from the available
labs and present them together on the
call and then the steering committee
actually goes through a voting process
to decide overall what gen cc is going
to kind of weigh in and decide what this
G disease classification should be we
don't get to the level of um definitive
or strong or moderate we just decide is
it moderate or above essentially should
it be included on a panel test or not
um do you ever incorporate like when the
data was last modified or updated
because I imagine I'm just thinking that
this is ever evolving in terms of the
conflict resolution yeah yes and
especially like on these displays it's
really helpful to know where they differ
but I wonder if where they they say that
there's limited evidence maybe it's just
old so in a different you on the Gen CC
website you can see the submission date
which is very helpful as well or at
least the date that it is last assessed
um and you can see that in clingen as
well actually it's it's not to say that
the expert panel classifications are
right forever right they're going to
change over time so it is important to
think about when that classification was
done whether there's new information
that comes out and we definitely do take
in the age of that classification into
account when we think about how we're
going to go about about um resolving the
conflicts in particular for the oldest
classification will often just go back
to that lab with the older one say like
hey have you looked at this more
recently um and often they will say no
and when they do look at it it it kind
of automatically resolves the conflict
yeah okay um so we're like halfway
through and we're just getting to
variant interpretation so let's move on
um we can definitely talk more about
Gene curation at the end if we have more
time but let's make sure we're talking a
little bit about variant classification
as well um so variant classification a
lot of the themes you're going to he
here are very similar to what we talked
about in gene curation so classification
again especially historically in the
field is subjective equally qualified
professionals can interpret the same
variant differently and this can be
because they may not have access to the
same base of evidence so for example in
my lab I might have seen this variant
Den noo in a patient that was really
convincing evidence for me but another
lab does not have access to that
evidence they may interpret it
differently but even with the same
evidence Labs can wait the evidence they
find differently which can arise um in
different classifications as well so
this issue has become particularly more
apparent in recent decades for two
primary reasons one being that there's
just a lot more Labs doing sequencing so
more opportunity for conflict and that
the same Labs different labs are seeing
the same variant um and that also
there's this database clintar which
we're going to talk more about later
it's kind of the variant version of gen
CC which allows different labs to submit
their classifications for variance and
that has just highlighted the fact that
there are conflicts um and that we can
now see them um so if you look across
clinvar in fact about 23% of all the
variants in clinvar with multiple
submitters have conflicting
interpretation so clearly there's again
some standardization work to be done
here um and I'm not going to dwell based
on the time we have a lot in history but
this this makes sense historically just
looking back and see
what variant interpretation has been
like as clinical genetic testing has
been evolving um there were some
guidelines for the interpretation and
reporting of these sequence Texs back in
2007 but they were very vague it was
kind of the wild wild west back then
there wasn't really any standardized
terminology about how to classify
variants and some of these guidelines
are essentially you know it was what was
available at the time but essentially it
was like you should check to make sure
your variant is in another database for
for example or see if it's in another
database before you go and report it
didn't really tell you how to integrate
that information and how to classify
based on it um so luckily for us a
standard came out in 2015 that was a lot
more prescriptive about how what types
of information you should look at when
classifying a variant and how to
integrate that information together um
and this was a guideline developed
together with the American College of
medical genetics and the association for
molecular
prology um so in addition to telling us
how to classify variants more or less
again this guideline standardized the
terminology in the field which was an
important step suggesting that variant
should be classified into these five
categories that are listed in rainbow
colors here with pathogenic meaning this
is definitely a disease causing variance
theine meaning this is definitely not a
disease causing variance likely
pathogenic and likely benign on either
side which reflect about a 90% comp
level and then everything in the middle
goes into this bucket of what's called a
varant of uncertainty significance or a
v us um before again as with the gene
curation before the existence of these
guidelines there was a lot of
variability in the clinical field about
how the terminology that was used um so
for example a lot might say benign or
they might say polymorphism or normal or
not associated which is pretty confusing
when you get that kind of information
back on different reports um but these
guidelines have really been very widely
adopted in the field since they've been
published and as of 2017 about 95% of
lats We Now using these terms so let's
talk through about a little bit about
how these guidelines work so if you were
to open up this paper you would see this
nice pretty rainbow chart um which is
really the fundamental um variant
classification guidelines here um to
walk you through it I don't expect to be
able to read all the texts in these
cells but just to walk you through it a
bit there is two major categories of
evidence here on the pathogenic side and
on the benign side in the columns you
will see that there are different
strengths of evidence so on the
pathogenic side the strengths of
evidence range from supporting moderate
strong and very strong and on the benign
side we have strong and supporting
evidence now in the rows there are
different classes of evidence that we
considered and interpreting variants for
example population frequency data
computational prediction tools
functional data segregation within
families Etc um so the general process
here when you're classifying a variant
is to go out into the literature public
databases Etc pull all of the
information you can possibly find about
this variant which is a task in and of
itself it's very timeconsuming and then
determine the pieces of evidence that
you can find within those Publications
and databases and how they matap to this
grid and then basically come up with a
list of the criteria codes you might be
able to apply once you have that list
you can go to this table at the right
and determine how the different codes
you have add up to a final
classification so let's walk through an
example of what that might look like
let's have this nonsense variant in the
pH Gene so pah is an established causal
Gene for for phenol ketonuria or PKU an
autal recessive condition this variant
is a loss of function variant a nonsense
variant expected to lead to nonsense
mediated Decay and it falls within a
gene pH in which the L we know that loss
of function causes disease causes fenal
Cuttin area so this allows us to apply a
pvs1 Criterion
here just to give you a little overview
of how the code naming works starts with
p it's on the pathogenic side it starts
with B it's on the benign side and then
the subsequent letters indicate the
strength so this is pathogenic very
strong Criterion
one um you look in the Nomad database
for this variant see what its population
frequency is like and you notice that
it's in one out of almost 75,000 African
chromosomes in Nomad which translates to
a
0.001%
frequency this allows us to apply the
pm2 Criterion which says either the
variant is very absent is completely
absent in Nomad or is at a very low
frequency consistent with a recessive
disorder which is what we're looking at
here so in the 2015 guidelines this
allows us to apply the pm2 Criterion and
caging that a little bit because there
has been some evolution in thinking
about this code and we now only apply it
at a supporting level but we're going to
go with what the 2015 criteria say for
now and pm2 can I ask a question from
online about that um someone anonymously
asked about um how these pathogenicity
and coding relates to genetic ancestry
and they're wondering is there are there
any examples of variants that are
pathogenic in one An ancestry but benign
in another yeah so when we consider AAL
frequency it does not have the ancestry
within Nomad does not have to me match
the patient being studied and that's
really because if this variant is at a
high enough frequency in any population
it suggests that it cannot cause disease
unless that disease is particularly
enriched so this is particularly true
for Continental populations if you have
a subpopulation like the Amis population
the Asad the Jewish population where
that variant where that disease is
enriched as well you have to be careful
interpreting your frequency cut offs
that you would apply um in terms of if
there is any examples of variants that
are pathogenic in one population and not
in others we we actually do not assign
variant pathogenicity in a patient
specific manner in that way if a variant
is pathogenic it's pathogenic for
everyone but the overall interpretation
of that variant in the context your
patient may change there is maybe some
option of um background variation that
may impact the expression of that
condition or penetrants of that
condition and that exists but we still
call that variant maybe pathogenic we
may acknowledge on the report that it
has reduced penetrat in some populations
for
example okay um so then we do a
literature search for the variant we're
looking at and we find that our variant
is observed in a proband with classic
PKU who also carried a second variant on
the opposite copy of their PKU Gene so
another variant in trans and that other
variant this missense variant at
position 408 is a very wellestablished
pathogenic variant for PKU it's
classified as pathogenic for example by
18 different labs in kinbar this allows
us to apply the pm3 Criterion which
states that for recessive disorder this
variant was detected in trans with a
pathogenic
variant so in total after doing all of
this review we find we have one pbs1 one
very strong code and two moderate C
codes applied and if we go back to that
chart on the last slide you would see
that this adds up to a pathogenic
classification for this variant for aomo
recessive
PKU so this is kind of a nice clean
example for the purpose of the talk but
the more you think about these Criterion
and really work with them you'll find
that a lot of them are actually pretty
vague and it can be hard to decide when
to assign each Criterion right so that
is because these um classification
criteria were really designed to be
applicable across all mandelian disease
right so they had to be vague to apply
broadly um but you may look in and you
may see questions like well this code
says a well-established functional study
shows a delarius effect what what does
that mean what's a well-established
functional study or there's a code that
says there's Co co-segregation with
disease and multiple family members so
multiple affected family members carry
this variant but how many do I need to
apply this codee and if I have a lot of
affected family members because I make
it a stronger level or the code saying
that the minor Al frequency is too high
for the disorder how do you decide what
is too high um so you can see there's
more work to be done in terms of these
codes and again this is work that
clingen has really taken on so in
addition to doing all of that curation
work we talked about the clingen expert
panels also work to further specify
these codes to make them applicable to
specific disease areas in a more logical
way um so there are now over 30 disease
areas that clingen expert panels have
designed these um specifications for
they are available in this database
called cpec the link I've shown here and
this is a database searchable by the
either the gene the disease or the
expert panel and what you might see if
you open up one of these for example is
further specification
how to apply the codes in a disease
specific fashion so this is an example
from the myh7 specifications where you
can see that if you look in the 2015
guidelines this va1 Criterion just
States the alal frequency is more than
5% in the databases available at the
time um but for most disorders 5% cut
off is more than an order of magnitude
higher than necessary for most Mulan
conditions so for this m seven criteria
they were actually able to specify based
on the frequency of dominant
cardiomyopathy its prevalence and the
genetic and alic heterogeneity of that
disorder that anything above a .1% alal
frequency in databases like NAD is
actually sufficient to classify that
variant as
benign so um clinten has a group called
the sequence variant interpretation
group that actually oversees all of
these expert panels in specifying the
criteria appropriately but this group
also has published a lot of guidance on
more broad guidance on the use of
specific codes both for example the pbs1
Criterion um what types of loss of
functions qualify for that what kind of
caveats are there to deciding something
as loss of function and how you might up
or down breade that Criterion based on
the type of variant you're seeing so all
of that information
is here on the svi website that you can
access and having spent all of this time
telling you about the um 2015 guideline
Criterion I will tell you that the SBI
is now working on the next iteration of
sequence variant interpretation which is
going to change things up a bit so don't
try to memorize the pvs1 pm2 because all
of those code names are going away in
this next iteration um still in
development so this is definitely not
final but the codes are going to be
renamed based on the type of evidence
that they reflect and it's going to be a
point space system in the future which
is great actually for us in terms of the
2015 guidelines it's very difficult if
you have conflicting pieces of
information both pathogenic and benign
to decide how to integrate that together
but in this points space system you will
have some positive points some negative
points on the benign side and you can
just add those together to end up at a
final
classification um given that we spent
time talking about gen CC and I've
mentioned at clinvar a few times I just
want to highlight a little more that
clinvar is a publicly accessible
database where many groups are
submitting their variant classification
information um the clingen expert panels
submit all of their classifications in
kinbar but also the most variants within
kinbar are submitted by clinical Labs
about 96% at this point and if you
haven't looked in clinvar before this is
what you might see on clar variant page
at the top you get an aggregate
classification of what every lab has
submitted so for example for this
variant you can see the individual
submissions at the bottom there are
three Labs that are calling this variant
likely benign one lab calling it a
variant of Uncertain significance and
again as with Gen CC the existence of
all of this information with one
database has allowed some level of
conflict resolution to go on over time
um there is a star status so one of the
biggest problems with clintar is that
there's not really um a quality standard
that has to be reached to get your
information into clintar so there's very
widely varying quality of
interpretations within clintar but
they've tried to help us delineate some
of that in that in this star status so
um if a submitter has zero stars that
means that submitter has actually not
submitted their classification criteria
that they use um to classify the variant
so it's hard to know what they're
integrating
um once you get up to one star you've
either submitted your classification
criteria or this happens also at the
aggregate level when you have multiple
submitters that are disagreeing and then
as concordance is reached the star
status will go up so a two star variant
has multiple Labs saying the same
classification the expert panels get an
extra star because they've really gone
through this rigorous process and we
believe those classifications a little
bit more um this is an extremely
valuable database in terms of um
bioinformatic processing of data in
clinical Labs so we all Labs at this
point virtually will be annotating their
data with clinvar classifications as a
means of pulling out previously
classified pathogenic varant there
problems with that clear the question
the previous slide after reading several
kinwa and it seems like every lab
adopted the guideline but what was the
hesitant why they don't put in the codes
in these report is it that they are they
don't want to be bound but if they don't
want to be bound it's it's sort of hard
for people who read to know what exactly
is going on yeah I agree so so there are
many answers to that so Labs overall are
encouraged to submit their evidence and
you can see an example of an Evidence
summary here in that uncertain
significance classification for this
parent but it is not required for labs
to submit the evidence they've used to
classify that variant um the reason that
Labs don't do it honestly is that they
often don't have that information
structured in a way to easily be able to
submit it on large scale to Clint bar
it's a lot of work to get that
information in so for the most part you
know giving Labs the benefit of the
doubt I think that is the biggest
barrier to getting this information into
clintar um a lot of labs will have a
contact button or there's emails for
every submitter in clintar so you can go
in and actually email that lab directly
and say you know what kind of evidence
do you have for this I do this fairly
frequently for like in D GDX which are
massive lbs have a lot of data in there
and they will often respond and give you
kind of a summary of we've seen this
variant Den ELO and XR band um so when
you have a very rare variant you have no
other means of getting that information
that's a good resource to try um but
that being said again like it takes Labs
time to respond to these kind of emails
so it's not you know massively scalable
it's a difficult
problem are labs incentivized to because
it's a lot of work to do that so are
there any incentives great great
question yes so we have found over time
that lab submitting to clintar is a
great indication of the quality of their
interpretation particularly as you can
see when they're like just way off on
the vast majority of their
classifications so um clingen has
actually developed they have a site
where you can see a Labs that have um
they have a classification system ENT
ially for labs that um you get a higher
quality rating when youve submitted a
percentage of your varant to Clint bar
and you update it every year so you can
see updates over time so is there's this
lab list that is developed as the
incentive for labs to do that um how
often people who order tests go and look
at that lab list to decide where to
order from I can't say heid you probably
have some data on
that um so as I was saying Clint bar is
a great source of annotation but there
are some problems with doing that and
that again as I mentioned there's a lot
of varying quality of data in kinbar so
examp for example if I filter a genome
for everything that's pathogenic in
clinar you're going to get tons of hits
many of which are way too frequent in
the general population to be pathogenic
some of those were submitted before EXO
exac or NAD were available right um so
we really kind of need a way to clean up
the database to use it systematically in
this way and that has been led by
clingen um which is now Heidi has
spearheaded this clingen curation of
clinvar produ project or CBC in which
clingen cure readers now go in and
review these conflicting um entries in
clinar pick out for example the old ones
that are outliers and flag them so that
they're no longer integrated into that
aggregate classification that's at the
top of the page um so this is something
that can be crowdsourced so if you find
errors in clinvar there's a link on the
Len website where you can go and kind of
flag them for review as well um so I
just want to mention very briefly we
talked about the evolution of the
sequence variant interpretation
guidelines there are also guidelines for
the interpretation of copy number
variation in 2020 this paper came out um
led by acmg and clingen and this is
again a point space system for
classification that takes into account
genomic content overlap with established
half was sufficient triplosensitivity
tripos sensitive regions number of
protein coding genes Etc fortunately I
don't have time to go through that but
clingen has a great web series um that
walks through these criteria and how to
apply them and I blink that at the
bottom of this slide so overall
hopefully the take-home message is that
the design and interpretation of genetic
test really requires a lot of detailed
evaluation of genes and variant and that
the standards and guidelines that have
been established even though they are
timec consuming greatly improved
classification um consistency and
quality in the field I've listed out
some of the guidelines that I've talked
about as well as a couple extras that I
didn't get to um and then finally that
these public databases like linbar and
gen CC are really critical to the field
creating transparency in crowdsourcing
the work um so thank you to you all for
listening a lot of my slides were still
on from Stephen and Heidi so thank you
to them for putting these together and a
huge thank you to everyone that's
involved in these clingen working groups
and doing really the laborious work of
curation