large language models like chat GPT the
open source varieties are rotten Liars
cannot trust them the reason is they're
all sequence-based they've been trained
on the world's data and they're looking
at patterns sequences of characters to
determine what someone is saying and
then spits out the sequence of
characters on the other side to try to
Plate you and give you the answer that
you were looking for unfortunately it's
not based on logical reasoning it's just
B based on these sequences they are very
much
probabilistic um one of the issues here
is that when we're trying to use these
in corporate settings in government
settings we BR we bring them into
workflows where we have to or want to
trust them so what we have done is
embraced various techniques that address
this problem the most popular one today
the all the rage in the AI Community is
this so-called rag technique which
stands for retrieval augmented
generation and what it's doing is
bringing representative data into the
mix as opposed to using the vanilla
large language model it's giving you
representative data as little nuggets of
information relevant to the task at hand
relevant to the use case relevant to the
domain that this particular model is
working within uh it's kind of like a
clue toward the right answer and it
increases the probability
that it will give you a good answer but
there are no assurances it does not give
you proof that you can trust this output
so what we're focused on is number four
here symbolic reasoning tried and true
been around for decades um we are the
bridge between the very powerful large
language models very creative they can
as they describe it hallucinate come up
with fabricated responses what we're
doing is taking that natural language
and turning it into a mathematical
problem something that can be solved for
think back to Geometry where you had a
formal proof and you showed every step
of your process every claim that went
into the answer and there was only one
answer at the end this is the same thing
that we're doing here we take the
natural language we turn it into a
domain specific language powered program
that gets run through these
off-the-shelf so-called solvers solvers
are saying yes or no it does or doesn't
meet all the constraints and assertions
and known facts that you're imposing
upon
it the way we do this is we bring it
into a knowledge graph we turn the
natural language sequence of characters
into a graph structure that aligns to
The Domain that we're working within
it's a process that has a human in the
loop so we can get feedback and
constantly improve the models and has a
path toward this more trusted age a and
that's really the value is that bring it
into use cases where people are
reluctant to use it say clinical
decision support for healthcare or in
the claims adjudication process for
insurance or picking the right portfolio
in financial
services or with us we've started with
the Department of Defense where they
have lots of data that needs to be
properly classified meaning which
security level can uh this particular
piece of data fall into what label
should we apply to this particular email
what marking should we put on this
particular report and everything is
driven by these security classification
guides which are documents that were
written by humans for humans never
intended for AI to interpret so we're
breaking that down into constraints and
rules that we can apply in near real
time to new data coming into our
environment we have a number of projects
with theod we're working across Ross the
intelligence Community as well we are
intentionally now focused on bringing it
to the commercial sector we have use
cases as I've already mentioned in
financial Ser Services Insurance life
sciences and health care we are eager to
find Pilots we would love to work on
collaborative development efforts with
anyone that wants to perhaps white label
the solution and for partners that want
to help us bring this into the the
industries that we feel make the most
sense which are us usually regulated
Industries ones that have laws and
regulations that have to be adhered to
that we can use as guidelines for the
processing of this new information
coming in so you can find me at at
jackson. or email me directly Scott
jackson. and I'll be outside thank you
thank you Scott