All right, let's get started. Uh,
welcome back to 61200. I am the second
of the three lecturers in this class.
Uh, you can call me Eric. Um, and
Binmore will be on next week. Uh so
today we are going to uh continue our
theme of induction and prove some even
cooler and stronger forms of induction.
Just a recap of where we were last time.
As we've seen, we're we're growing our
catalog of different proof techniques of
how to prove uh different types of
theorems almost by like a cookbook. If
you want to cook this, here's how you
get started. And so here's a a brief
summary of this. uh if the theorem you
want to prove starts with there exists
something then a natural way to prove
that is by example or by construction
you construct a particular x star and
prove that p of xstar is true and if you
can do that uh then you've proved that
there exists an x where p of x is true
it's kind of straightforward but it lets
you unwrap if I give you an expression
starts with exist then you know your
first step is try to figure out an x
where this is true um and of course to
prove p of xar you probably recur
cursively use this cookbook. If you want
to prove a universal uh one common way
if you want to prove for all x p of x is
true uh typically your first line is
take an arbitrary x just give it a name
x and then prove that p of x is true no
matter what x you started with therefore
it's true for all of them. Uh come back
to induction in a second. If you're if
the main thing you want to prove is an
implication, P implies Q. This is if P
then Q. And I want to remind you that um
P implies Q is the same thing as not P
or Q. We'll use this a bunch uh today.
Um then uh the direct way to prove this
what we call a direct argument is assume
P is true and then prove Q is true.
Because this implication we only need to
prove that Q is true when P is true. If
P then Q. Uh or another way to prove
that same statement P implies Q is
what's called the contraositive. It
turns out P implies Q is the same
statement. It's equivalent to not Q
implies not P. Remember this uh symbol
is a negation
um flip true and false. So to do that
with a direct argument we would prove
that uh if not Q is true then not P is
true. In other words, assume not Q and
then prove not P.
This may seem kind of magical. Why is P
implies Q the same as not Q implies not
P? But it actually follows directly from
this equivalence. If you look at not Q
implies not P. Uh this is the same thing
as let me go over here. Not not Q or not
P,
right? because it implies is the same
thing as taking an or if you negate the
first the part on the left and not not Q
is the same as Q.
Okay, so this was uh not Q implies not P
is the same thing as this is the same
thing as this and that is exactly this
uh just by switching the order of the
ors and so P implies Q is the same thing
as not Q implies not P uh more uh so
that was contraositive there's a related
notion of contradiction where if you
want to prove any statement P um you
assume that not P is true and then find
a contradiction prove that in fact false
is true or something is both true and
false. All these things are very very
bad because we assume that our axioms
are consistent. And so if you can prove
false that means that what you assumed
must also be false.
Uh and if so if not P is false that's
the same thing as saying P is true.
Feels very backwards. Lots of double
negatives in there but that's the nature
of contradiction. We try to avoid them
when we can but sometimes it's really
the right way to prove something. And
the last technique we saw was induction.
uh where if we have a universal
quantifier over the natural numbers, we
want to prove P of N is true for all
natural numbers 0 1 2 3 and so on. Uh
then we only need to prove it for some
base case P of 0 and then we need to
prove that P of N implies P of N plus
one for all N. So we'll talk more about
induction in a little bit. Uh
today we're going to add to this list
two more proof techniques. One is proof
by cases and the other is strong
induction. So proof by cases is just a
nice general technique to be aware of.
Uh it's can be very powerful. Strong
induction is going to be an even cooler
form of induction.
All right. But we'll start today with
proof by cases. And we'll start with
proof by two cases.
and then we'll generalize to more than
two cases.
So, uh the idea is take any proposition
C
and observe that C or not C is a
tautology
meaning uh always true.
Okay, if C is true, then this whole
thing is true because C is true. If C is
false, then not C is true. And so this
whole thing is true. I'm going to remind
you uh this uh so V symbol is an or.
Uh whereas the opposite symbol is an
and.
I think the pneumonic here is this looks
like a letter A. This looks like a
letter O. I've heard some people say
this looks like a lowercase R for or. Um
anyway, you just remember these things.
This is or this is and uh so C or not C
is the question no is always true. Uh so
we call it a tautology fancy word for
being always true. And so uh
what this tells us is that our
proposition P let's say we want to prove
P is equivalent to
uh C or not C
implies P.
So this is saying if C or not C then P
is true. C or not C is just always true.
So this is saying if true in other words
always P better be true. So P and this
implication are equivalent. Another way
to see that is to rewrite this
implication as uh a negation I guess. So
this is like saying not uh true
or P and so that's just the same thing
as P
because this is true.
Okay, cool. Uh so I want to rewrite this
a little bit and say this thing is
equivalent to C implies P and not C
implies P.
Uh why is this true? Uh it's like a
distributive law. This is saying I want
to prove that C implies P and I want to
prove that not C implies P. That's what
I wrote over there. Uh that implies that
the combination of C and not C implies
P.
Okay. So I claim these are equivalent.
You could one way to verify it is with
the truth table or you can do it with
some manipulation.
All right. So uh we have
uh what this is saying is in order to
prove P we need to prove that P is true
assuming C and prove that P is true
assuming not C. And these are the two
cases and proof by cases. Let me write
out a little template for you.
Let's suppose the theorem we want to
prove
is P.
Theorem means something that's true and
that we're about to prove.
Uh and so we'd usually say proof by
cases
on the truth value
of C. So this is uh for any
uh
statement seek
proposition is what the word I was
looking for. Any proposition C, it's
either true or false.
Uh and so we're going to do proof by
cases on the truth value of C. Case one
is that C is true
and case two is that C is false.
And so what do we do in each case? Uh
well in the case that C is true this
means that we get to assume that C is
true
uh and then use that to prove that P is
true. And so the the missing step in
this uh proof outline or this template
uh is we need to say P is true because
some reasons which we need to fill in.
uh and similarly in the else in the C is
false case we need to prove P is true
uh
for some reasons. Okay, so we need twice
as many reasons but the idea is that
maybe assuming C is true makes it easier
to prove P is true. Maybe also proving
assuming C is false makes it easier to
to prove that P is true. So in these
boxes here we get to use C and in here
we get to use not C. And often this
makes proofs easier. But the challenging
part is to pick the correct C. What's
the right choice of C for this to be
true. Um, and maybe one more line I want
to add to this template, which is pretty
obvious in this setting, but gets much
less obvious when you think about more
than two cases. So a final step in this
proof would be to say uh C is either
true or false because all propositions
are either true or false.
And so uh the cases are exhaustive.
So this is also called a proof by
exhaustion. Not because we're really
tired, maybe we are also. But the idea
is we want to exhaust all possible
cases. And if we prove that we we
captured every possible situation and
all of them P is true then we're done.
Okay. So that's what we'd like to do.
I'm going to give you two examples.
First one is very simple. The second one
is more interesting
questions. All right. Um,
so the claim is this is a general fact
that a implies b or b implies c is a
tautology. So this means it's always
true again. So you can rewrite this as
for all a, b and c uh which are either
true or false
uh we have that a implies b or b implies
c is true.
Okay, fun fun fact. Um let's prove it.
And the proof technique we're going to
use by cases by two cases namely uh on B
B is either true or false.
We could try to do a case analysis in
terms of A or in terms of C. Turns out B
is sort of the right answer here. It
will lead to the fewest cases. We'll
only need two uh intuitively because B
is in both of these expressions. So it
seems good to split on B because it will
impact this one and this one.
Okay. Uh so
case one
is that B is true.
Okay.
uh if B is true, I claim that A implies
B is true,
which is this first half.
Why?
Uh in other words, I I claim that A
implies true is a tautology.
I think another again an easy way to see
this is to rewrite uh rewrite this
implication as not the left hand side or
the right hand side.
Right? Not a or true. Well, that's just
true. True or anything is true. Okay?
So, in particular over here, uh not a or
b is true because we just assume that b
is true.
Okay. So, this tells us that uh a
implies b or anything in particular b or
c is also true.
Okay. So, kind of trivial, right? Right?
If you assume B is true, then of course
this is true and so of course the whole
thing is true.
So easy when you have the correct case.
Uh let's think about the other case.
It's not enough to just have one half of
the cases. We also need to think about
when B is false.
When B is false, I claim that the other
term is true. I claim that B implies C
is true.
Uh this is maybe a little less
intuitive. This is saying that false
implies C is a tautology like for any C
false implies it. Um and this should
eventually become intuitive for you when
you get used to implies and if then this
is saying if false which means never uh
I need C to be true. But if I if this
condition is never true then I don't
care about the right hand side. If it's
if you know if uh pigs fly then I don't
know apples are orange or something. Um
it that's a true statement because it
will never be the case that pigs fly at
least in the present time. So uh another
way to see that is to think about again
not B or C.
B is false so not B is true and so of
course true or C is also true.
Okay. And so that tells us that anything
or B implies C is also true.
So in other words, this statement
maybe I'll call P, I'll say in either
case
P is true. And so I write my little end
of crew symbol. This is QED from last
time. Uh this means that I have
demonstrated the theorem.
Cool. So in one case this part was
trivial. In the other case this part was
trivial because it's an or. We're happy
in either case. And we've done our proof
first proof by cases. Pretty
straightforward.
Let's do a more surprising result
using proof by cases called
mutual
friends and strangers.
This is actually a famous mathematical
problem we're going to solve today a
particular case of it
which is suppose you have six people
um and every two of them are either
friends or
uh and this is an exclusive or so. So
I'm going to write exor. You're allowed
to be friends or or not friends, not
both and not neither. And in the not
friends case, I'm also going to call
them uh strangers.
So this is like extreme friendship.
Either you declare yourself as friends
or as knowing each other or you don't
know each other. In that case, you're
strangers. You're just never both. It's
always one or the other. Okay? So, you
can think of this as I can draw a little
picture of their six people represent by
circles. You can put smiley faces in
them if you want. And maybe I connect
them via a white line if they are
friends and a dotted line if they're
strangers. So let's And every two of
them have one of these two pictures.
Probably missing some
here.
That's them all. Uh then
I claim
no matter how what the situation is,
which ones are friends, which ones are
strangers, there's always
uh either
three mutual friends
for
three mutual strangers.
Okay, in this example,
hopefully I drew enough. Yeah. Uh, these
three people are mutual strangers.
They're connected by a a triangle of
dashed lines. Okay. If I drew some other
pattern, like if they were all solid
lines, then uh I might get the other
situation, at least three mutual
friends. But it turns out if you have
six people, they're always at least
three mutual friends or three mutual
strangers. Let's prove this by cases.
Whenever we apply a proof by cases, we
need to come up with some proposition C
that's either true or false. Well, for a
proof by two cases, which this will be
uh and it's a little work in this case
to to do it. It turns out a useful first
step is to pick any person P.
So just take the first person or the
seventh or the the fifth person ahead of
six doesn't matter which one but label
it P. So now we have a person to talk
about. This is sort of like the proof by
example or by construction right we want
to overall there we want to prove an
existence we want to prove existence of
three mutual friends or existence of
three mutual strangers. So it's a useful
step to either construct one or in this
case we're actually not doing much of a
construction. We're just taking an
arbitrary X, but that will be enough for
this for this problem. Okay, so let me
draw a little circle for P.
Uh, and it might have some friends and
it might have some strangers. Okay, how
many of these lines coming out of P are
there? Five. Exactly. Because there's
six people total. P is one of them. So
there are five people over here.
Okay, so turns out useful case strategy
is to uh say either P has at least three
friends
or it has less than three friends,
right? Either there are three solid
lines like I've drawn here or there at
least three or they're at most two solid
lines. Okay, let's think about this
first case. P has at least three
friends. Let's uh give them a name
uh Q, R, and S.
So uh that's sort of a general picture.
Now we're assuming P has three solid
lines to three people Q, R, and S.
Okay, this is not yet a triangle. We
haven't solved the problem yet, but uh
if we break into more cases, we'll be
able to. Okay. So, uh case
1 A is going to be
uh sum two
of Q, R and S are friends.
Okay. Suppose
uh for example Q and S are friends. Have
I found a triangle? Yes. P Q and S are
mutual friends. If this edge is here or
if this edge is here then these three
people are three mutual friends or if
this edge is here these three people are
mutual friends. If there's any edge in
here that I can draw any uh solid line
between QR and S then those two people
plus P form three mutual friends.
Okay. So that case is actually easy.
Great.
Then uh P plus those two people
are three mutual friends.
Okay, which uh was situation one up
here. There's always either three mutual
friends or three mutual strangers.
Okay, uh so now we need to think about
the other cases. Let's go over here.
We found one case that was easy, but uh
there's case 1B, which is maybe there
aren't two mutual friends, and there's
case two where P does not have at least
three friends. Okay, but it turns out
all of these cases will be easy. So,
let's do uh case 1 B.
Now, I get to sort of freely choose what
case one was, and I get to freely choose
what case 1 A was because whenever I
split into cases, I get to choose my
proposition C to be anything I want. So
this was C in the first case. This was C
in the second case. But generally if
you're doing proof by two cases, you
have no choice at this point. So case 1
A was whatever. Case 1 B has to be the
negation of this.
Okay. So case 1B literally is uh not sum
to uh of QRS are friends. Uh but if you
think about that for a little bit, this
is saying um
Q R and S uh let me let me write this uh
in a couple of steps. No two of Q R and
S are friends.
But that's the same thing as saying QR
and S are mutual strangers.
Okay, we're using this fact or this
assumption that every two people are
either friends or strangers.
Always one or the other. So if there's
no solid line over here, then all of
these are dash lines. So all three of
these are mutual strangers. And there we
found our triangle of strangers.
Okay. So it turns out case 1 A and case
1 B are actually just as easy, just sort
of reversed. Uh so this was situation
two.
So either we got three mutual friends or
we got three mutual strangers, but we're
still inside case one. We just finished
case one. Now we need to think about
case two. So I'm going to unindent here
and go to case two.
Case two again has to be exactly the
opposite of this. So P does not have at
least three friends.
Uh by
number of people being an integer. This
is saying P has at most two friends.
Okay. If it doesn't have at least three,
it's at most two because number of
friends is always an integer.
Okay, great. So that case two is a
negation of case one. Um, and it turns
out that is also kind of easy for a
symmetric reason. Uh, remember there are
six people total. So there's P and five
others.
So uh, how many strangers
is P with or how many people is P a
stranger to?
Uh, well, it's at least uh, all the
others. 5 minus 2 is at most two of them
are friends. The remainder have to be
strangers. And so this is three.
So P having at most two friends is the
same thing as P having at least three
strangers because there are five other
people total. 2 + 3 is 5. Uh so P case
two is P has at least three strangers.
Case one was P has at least three
friends. These are almost the same. I
just have to flip friends versus
strangers.
So the way I would write this in a proof
is uh this is symmetric
to case one
uh
swapping
friends uh versus strangers.
And of course uh case one or situation
one with situation two.
Okay. So case two would be P has at
least three strangers QR and S. Case 1 A
is that sum two of QR and S are
strangers. Then we conclude that P plus
those two are three mutual strangers
which is situation two. Or case 2B would
be no two of QRS are strangers. In other
words, QRS are mutual friends. And then
we're in situation one. So case two
works just like case one just swapping
the words friends and strangers because
they didn't really have any meaning.
They were just words.
Cool. So in all cases
uh we prove the desired result either
situation one or situation two happens.
Um this is a particular case of
something called Ramsey theory.
What we've just found is that something
called r of 33 is uh at most six uh in
general r of f comma s is the number of
people you need uh in order to guarantee
that there's at least f friends or at
least s strangers. So we just did at
least three friends or at least three
strangers. We showed that six people was
enough. It turns out uh six people is
exactly the right number. You need six
people in order to guarantee at least
three friends or three strangers. If you
wanted to guarantee four friends or four
strangers, turns out you need 18 people.
Uh if you want to guarantee five friends
or five strangers, turns out you need uh
somewhere between 43 and 48 people. But
we don't know how many. So while this
problem was relatively easy, three
friends or three strangers, five friends
and five strangers already is an
unsolved mathematical problem. So that's
kind of cool and crazy how easily you
get to very difficult problems. Of
course, people try to compute larger
numbers too, but we don't have tight
bounds generally.
Okay, I want to say one more thing about
proof by cases, which is what if we want
more than two cases?
Uh so
more generally proof by K cases.
So instead of just C or not C, let's
suppose we have a bunch of propositions
C1 through CK. And let's suppose that
this is a tautology.
favorite word for the day. So suppose
that it's always the case C1 or C2 or
dot dot dot or CK one of these things is
always true.
Then uh we can follow this template
which is uh suppose we want to prove a
theorem that some proposition P is true
then we'll say proof
uh by cases
and
there's K of them so I'm just going to
write it generically in case I
is that CI is true. In other words, we
get to assume CI is true.
And then what we need to do is prove
that P is true in that scenario. And P
is true
because
reasons.
Uh and then here it's especially
important to say that the cases
are exhaustive.
uh
because
reasons and exhaustive here just means
that uh C1 or C2 or up to CK is a
tautology.
Okay, so you need to prove that C1 or or
up dot dot dot or CK is is always true.
That's the meaning of the cases being
exhaustive. So there's sort of two
parts. So one is to prove that each case
is okay. The other is to prove that
those cases cover everything.
Okay. So um I won't show an example of K
cases here. We'll see that I'm in
restitation and so on. Uh but I will
tell you a story about one uh famous
proof by cases which is the fourcolor
theorem.
Uh I'll illustrate the four color
theorem with an example. So here's a map
of United States. uh and I've colored
all the states, all the regions of this
map with four different colors red,
green, blue, yellow in such a way that
if you have two regions that share a
positive length boundary, then this
color A is different from this color B.
Okay, it has to be not equal. Otherwise,
if you had two red regions next to each
other, it' be hard to see the boundary.
So the colors illustrate the boundaries
between all the regions. Four colors
seems to be enough for this map. Uh it's
also enough for this map of all the
countries.
Is it true for all the maps? Turns out
yes. This is called for a long time
called the fourcolor conjecture and then
it became the fourcolor theorem at some
date. Uh so fourcolor theorem says you
can color the regions of any planer map
with four colors so the neighboring
regions get different colors. This was
first observed and sort of conjectured
uh in 1852 by a guy named Guthrie who
was a student of deorggan. De Morgan I
think his name will come up in a moment
famous logician. He actually invented
induction as we
one of the first people to he invented
the term mathematical induction at the
very least and really uh sort of made it
more formal.
Uh so a student of him Guthrie said hey
I took all the counties of England and
it turned out I only needed four colors
is this a theorem and he asked uh
indirectly de Morgan uh and Morgan said
hey seems cool I don't know maybe then
the following year 1853
uh another mathematician named Kemp
uh
proved the theorem
but uh proved should be in quotes
because uh 11 years later 1864 before
Haywood found a bug in that proof. Turns
out there were a lot of cases in this
proof and the cases were not exhaustive.
So it wasn't done. Then uh 15 years
later, 1880, Tate proved the theorem.
Then 11 years later, Peterson found a
bug in that proof. Again, not all the
cases were exhaustive. Then uh 85 years
later, 1976
uh Apple and Haken or maybe it's a PEL,
I'm not sure, uh
proved the theorem and I think most
people consider this an actual proof. Uh
but it's a little tricky. Uh just to
give you a sense, this this is where
sort of my started I started hearing
about the problem. I wasn't alive in
1976, but I heard about it later on. Um
there are 1,834
cases in this proof. They occupy about a
400page printout from a computer
program. And so th this is one of the
first mathematical proofs that used a
computer to assist in checking all the
cases because there's so many 8 1,834.
It's hard to do that by hand and be sure
that you didn't make a mistake. So the
computer proof to me is a little bit
more sound. uh also apparently checked
by hand uh by Haken's daughter. Um then
five years later uh Schmidt found what
you could interpret as a bug in this
proof. Let's say an emission or
something uh but a missing situation. Uh
and then over the next eight years Apple
and Haken fixed all the bugs they could
find that one and some other sort of
wording issues and so on and they
proofed they published it in a book but
book isn't refereed. So I don't know how
many people have read that book. Um,
seems like this proof is maybe correct.
It's been many years and no one has
found a bug. Uh, a little bit later
though, 1996, Robertson, Sanders,
Seymour, and Thomas, some of the top
graph theorists in the world, uh, found
a simpler proof. That proof only has 633
cases. So that's a lot less, maybe three
times fewer cases. And also the length
of the paper is shorter, maybe 10 times
shorter. Uh so that's progress but you
know is that proof true it also used a
computer to check the cases. Uh finally
in 2005
uh Verer and Gonier uh developed a fully
computer checkable proof using uh a
system called coaul where you write down
uh every step in the proof and then the
computer just has to check that every u
mathematical derivation like all the
derivations we saw last class modus
ponus and all those things are correct.
this this program has been has withstood
many many years of scrutiny. So we all
believe that it's correct and so the
fact that you can write the entire proof
in this proof language suggests that
this really is a true theorem. Now
thankfully there won't be more missing
cases. I believe that is just an
implementation of the Robertson proof.
So uh that one withtood scrutiny but
it's very tedious to write these proofs
and so uh for the fourcolor theorem it's
uh worth it I would say all right so
that's just an example of in general
proofs by cases can involve a zillion
cases it's very annoying but sometimes
that's the best thing we know how to do
maybe we'll come up with a simpler
fourcolor theorem proof at some point
but best we know so far has hundreds of
cases
all right let's go back to induction
Uh first I want to review induction a
little bit and then we will get a
stronger form of it.
So uh I'm going to call this the
induction axiom. This is what we talked
about last class. Uh we didn't call it
an axiom and in some setups it is an
axiom. We're going to take it as one.
something that we just assume is true.
Uh although as Zach mentioned in modern
times you usually prove this using other
using the definition of the natural
numbers.
Uh but I'll just take it as something is
true. So for any predicate p of n over
the natural numbers if on the one hand p
of zero is true
and on the other hand
uh
p of n implies p of n + one
uh for all natural numbers n
then
uh p of n is true uh for all natural
numbers
Okay, this is the magic of induction.
You should use this probably in every
problem you solve. Not every problem,
but uh extremely powerful tool. We're
going to use it all the time throughout
this class. I want to give you a visual
way of thinking about what's going on
with induction, which I call block
diagrams.
Uh so um I'm going to think of
a block
like a little box here that takes as
input. Think of it as a procedure. You
give it some true uh propositions on the
left and it produces a true proposition
on the right.
Okay? Or you could think of it as if I
give you some proofs of these
propositions, then this block will give
you uh a proof of a proposition on the
right. Okay? So, uh what's going on with
induction is we're given two of these
blocks, these two. So, you can think of
part one P of 0 is true as a block that
has no input. So, this is what we
normally call the base case. So it
doesn't need to assume anything and it
just produces for you a proof that P of
0 is true.
Okay. And the second part here, the
induction step
says that if you can prove P of N is
true and you plug it into the induction
step, then it will give you a proof that
P of N plus one is true. Saw a bunch of
examples of this last time. We assume P
of N and we use that to prove P of N
plus one. Okay. Now the cool thing about
blocks is you can just uh chain them
together.
So if we chain
uh the only block we can place first is
uh this base case because it doesn't
need anything to get started. So we
start with the base case argument that
produces P of zero. Now we plug this
into the step. This step has to work for
all n.
So in particular it works for n equals
z. And so we plug that into the step and
we get uh p of 1. We plug p of 1 into
the step. So n equals 1.
Then we get p of n plus one namely p of
two. And we plug that into the step and
we get p of three and so on.
Okay. Okay, so this just gives you some
intuition for if I can build an argument
for why P of 0 is true and I can build
an argument for why if P of N is true
then P of N plus one is also true then I
can just repeat that argument over and
over with different n increasing N by
one each time and I can use that to
prove that all the P of N's are true.
Okay, this is like visual intuition for
why why this works. Um, of course, we're
not going to actually prove P of N is
true for all N, but uh should be pretty
straight pretty intuitive from that.
Uh or more abstractly
you can actually think of induction
itself as one of these blocks. Uh let me
use another color.
So we have on the one hand uh a block
base which produces P of zero and we
have uh an induction step which given P
of N produces
uh P of N plus one.
So I'm going to think of this as a thing
that's true and this as a thing that's
true. And then what induction gives me?
Induction is a block that given these
two facts, if you can prove each of
these things, then it gives me a new
fact which is uh for all natural numbers
n uh p of n is true.
Okay, so that's sort of the instead of
having to draw out this infinite length
path, induction just does it all at
once. It says, "Oh, I know I can chain
these all together forever. Therefore, P
of N is true for all N." Okay, I don't
know if that helps, but
it's another visual way of thinking
about induction.
Let's um
All right.
Let me tell you another uh equivalent
formulation of induction which I prefer.
starts out starts out the same. Suppose
P of 0 is true. Uh the second the
induction step I'm going to phrase
slightly differently almost the same.
For all n at least one
uh p of n minus one implies p of n.
Then
uh for all natural numbers
uh p of n.
So uh the first and last lines are the
same. We're assume P of 0 is true. We're
going to conclude P of N is true for all
natural numbers. Here we started at zero
and we wanted to show that P of N
implies P of N plus one. Over here we're
starting at one and we're proving that P
of N minus one implies P of N. These are
exactly the same things. I've just
shifted the indices by one. So these are
identical statements or equivalent
statements. Um I like this version in
particular. it will lead into strong
induction. But I like this version as a
computer scientist because I always want
to think about well I want to prove P of
N not P of N plus one. It's confusing to
think about proving P of N plus one. I
always want to prove P of N when N
equals zero. Okay, that's my base case.
I prove that specially when N is at
least one. I'm not in the base case and
I get to assume that P of N minus one is
true. You can think of this like a
computer program. Think of a proving p
of n is like running a computation f of
n or p of n and I get to recursively
call p of n minus one in order to
compute p of n. n is given to me. This
is the one I want to solve. If n is zero
then I solve it one way. If n is bigger
than zero or at least one then I
recursively call p of n minus one or
depend on that proof and use it to prove
p of n. Okay. But you can use either one
whichever is more comfortable to you.
uh but really you should use neither and
you should use this stronger form uh
called strong induction. So let's let's
do that.
Strong induction just gives you more to
work with.
So it's in some sense more powerful
logically it's identical to induction.
You can actually prove it using
induction and we'll do that. Uh let me
first state the theorem. So if
any natural number
this is true
then
uh any natural number p of n is true.
Okay. Uh let me bring this one down to
compare.
Uh
so uh first thing maybe to notice is
there doesn't seem to be a base case
here. uh which is a little weird. It's
just one condition then this let's
compare the steps first of all um so or
I guess let's let's think about the case
this has to be true for all n if we
think about when n equals 0 that's the
missing base case what this is actually
saying is p 0 up to p minus one implies
p of zero okay so this is kind of weird
notation I'm I'm abusing the dot dot dot
a little bit here and uh for when n
equals one this is p of 0 when n equals
2 this is p of 0 and p of 1 when n
equals 3 I mean for a larger n it's very
clear what this dot dot dot means but
when n equals 0 it's confusing so I need
to specify uh this is defined to be true
uh for n equals 0
okay so for n equals 0 what you have to
do is prove that true implies p of zero
in other words p of zero must be true in
all cases okay so there's Um, but then
for larger n, what this is saying is not
only do I get to assume p of n minus
one, but I get to assume all the p of
i's before p of n. So I would I would
normally say uh p of i is true for all i
less than n. This is what I get to
assume.
That's probably actually a better way to
state this this thing.
So with regular induction here, I got to
assume that the previous P of N minus
one was true and I needed to use that to
pro prove that P of N is true. But
actually if you look at this chain like
by the time I'm proving P of three, I've
already proved all the smaller PIs.
So why not and assume that with strong
induction I get to assume that in order
to prove P of N I get to assume all the
PI's where I is less than M. Okay. Now
when N equals Z, I don't get to assume
anything because there are no smaller
I's. Uh but when I get to P of five, I
get to assume P 0, P4, P 0, P1, P2, P3,
P4. Uh so I get to assume more. So this
only makes my proof easier.
Okay. Um to be clear, uh this is usually
proved in cases normally you need to uh
check zero specially. That might be a
base case. Maybe you have to check one
specially. It depends on your
implication argument. this uh often this
implication
assumes that n is at least something and
then you have to prove all the smaller
ns to be true specially but we'll we'll
get to examples in a moment. What I'd
like to do first is actually prove that
strong induction is true.
This is not something you would repeat
in your homework. You should just assume
strong induction is true. But I think
it's instructive to see why it's true
as yet another example of induction.
Okay, so we're going to use regular
induction this version or actually I
think this version the induction axiom
uh to prove strong induction.
Okay. Now, this is a situation where we
need to define a particular induction
hypothesis. This not the obvious one
and this is not at all obvious, but I'm
going to define uh IH of N to be uh this
P of 0 and P of N minus one. In other
words, uh for all I less than N, P of I.
I like that better because it works even
when n is zero because there are no i's
less than zero. So that's just true when
I when n is zero. Okay, so this is the
thing I want to prove for all n.
And how do we do it? Well, uh as usual
with an induction, we have a base case.
Base case is ih of zero.
So uh ih of zero is actually literally
just true.
uh because we defined it to be that way.
We said when n equals 0 this dot dot dot
is true or you could say uh this is
saying for all i less than zero where i
is a natural number but there are no
natural numbers less than zero. So this
is like saying if false then something
and that's just always true. So this is
by definition
uh ih of z is true. Great easy base case
as usual. Uh what's the induction step
look like? I'm going to I get to choose.
I could either assume I of N minus one
and prove IH of N or I'm going to assume
I of N and uh prove uh IH of N + one. So
we want to show if N plus1 assuming IH
of N. Uh
cool. So the key thing is we get to
assume this is true. The strong
induction says if this then this. So
we're assuming the if part we're
assuming that if uh this implication
and this thing here is exactly IH of N,
right? So this says IH of N implies P of
N. So we know
IH ofN implies P of N. That's uh what
we're get to assume in our theorem
statement here. and we just assumed that
IH of N is true. Therefore, P of N is
true.
Okay, but P of N was not what we wanted
to prove. We wanted to prove IH of N
plus1. So, what is IH of N plus1?
Uh let's just expand out this definition
here. It is P of zero or dot dot dot or
P of N minus one or P of N because I've
incremented N by one. This no longer
ends at P of N minus one. It now ends at
P of N. Okay, but this is almost what we
had before. This is the induction
hypothesis of N. That's this part
or P of N,
right? That's just formula manipulation.
And this we assumed is true. IH of N is
true. And P ofN we just proved is true.
Sorry. Uh I wrote or here but I meant
and everywhere. This is and
and
see even professors get the V's and
wedges upside down. So I wrote it
correctly here. It's the and of P 0 up
to PN minus one. Here we have the end of
P 0 up to PN. And so this is IH of N
which we assumed was true by induction.
and P ofn which we just proved using one
induction step. Therefore, the and is
also true.
And I believe that's the end of the
proof,
right? I did a base case, I did a step.
Oh, no. Quite not quite the answer.
Sorry, there's one more step here
uh which I will put over here.
It's a good illustration and not
skipping steps. Uh what did we actually
prove by induction? We proved induction
hypothesis of n is true for all n. So by
induction
like the regular old induction axiom
uh for all natural numbers n uh
induction hypothesis of n is true
induction hypothesis of n is this thing
but that's not what we wanted to prove.
We wanted to prove p of n is true for
all all n. uh but I can do some
manipulation to make that what I want.
So this is like saying for all n
uh
let's see actually probably this is
nicer for all natural numbers
uh ih of n plus one is true okay this is
a shift it's actually a weaker shift
this includes ih of zero this
should not be greater than equal to this
should be an element of uh this includes
zero this doesn't this starts at one and
it goes upwards But this is nice. Uh
this so this implies this, right? Uh
this is what we've shown. This is a
weaker statement because I just threw
away I of zero. I of zero wasn't
interesting anyway.
I of one uh includes inside of it. So
it's an and of a bunch of things. But
then the last term is P of N.
Right? That's if I take Ih of N + one,
the last term in is P of N. So it's also
anded but uh if the and is true then
every term is true and so therefore p of
n is true for all n. Okay, so this was a
final clean up after we did induction.
We didn't quite get the statement we
wanted because we used a more gen a
different induction hypothesis than just
p. Uh and then we needed to show that
that implied p of n for all n. Okay, but
it works.
Cool. So now uh there should be no
question about why strong induction is
true assuming you believe this proof. Um
you can draw a diagram. Uh it's a little
trickier to do. Maybe I will show you uh
in my handwritten notes
here.
Here is a block diagram for strong
induction.
uh it's harder to draw because you
depend on so many things when I apply
the fourth step here when I want to
conclude P of four I assume all the
previous PS so P 0 P1 P2 P3 they all
feed into this box in the beginning it's
very similar I apply a step I get P of 0
then I apply that P of 0 to a step I get
P of one uh but then as I proceed I'm
feeding more and more PI's into the step
and it gives me one more pi. Okay, so
it's a much more complicated diagram
what's going on under the hood. But from
a usage standpoint, it's it only helps
you when you're trying to prove P of N.
You don't just get to assume P of N
minus one. You get to assume all the
PI's uh where I is less than N.
I forgot one part of the fourcolor
theorem story which was when I was
growing up I read a reprint of this
article by Martin Gardner which turned
out to be published on April fools but I
didn't know it at the time uh and in at
that in 1975 there was no proof of the
fourcolor theorem Haken was I think one
year later uh so at this point he
published a joke saying in fact McGregor
found this map which requires five
colors I remember sitting trying to
color it with with four colors and
always failing. It's like, oh my gosh,
fourcolor theorem isn't true. This is or
fourcolor conjecture as it was called
then isn't true. Isn't that amazing? But
it was all a lie. In fact, you can
fourcolor that map. Uh but it's is a
very funny article. If you want to read
it, it's in in the lecture notes or part
of it is there all sorts of crazy things
like oh it turns out if you take uh e
and you raise it to pi time of 163,
the result is an integer.
It's not true. But, uh, all sorts of
crazy things. Also, uh, chess has a
crazy winning move. And anyway,
uh, to relive the youth. All right. Um,
I think I'd like to, uh, yeah, show you
some examples of strong induction, but
maybe first I should show you a template
for applying induction. Strong
induction.
uh we'll repeat some of the things that
I've said but I think it's good to have
it concrete.
So here is a template.
Suppose you want to prove
uh something is true for all natural
numbers. So for all natural numbers n uh
p of n is true. Then here's what the
proof will look like.
uh by proof by strong induction.
Uh
so generally we're assuming p of k uh
for all k less than n
and then we want to show p of n.
Okay? Or you could shift the numbers by
one but this is my preferred way of
thinking about it. uh usually we prove
this by cases
which is the method we just saw. This is
why we're pairing proof by cases with
strong induction. How do we prove p of
n? Well, it might depend. Often we have
some base cases
where n is small.
So uh maybe we have to prove p of zero,
maybe we have to prove p of one. Uh who
knows? Let's say up to P of little B are
the base cases. Maybe you have to prove
those specially for some reason.
Okay. Then we do an induction step.
So I'll say by cases here.
Uh induction step. We get to assume
n is bigger than b because we just prove
zero up to b manually.
uh and then we need to prove in those
scenarios p of n is true because
uh reasons.
Okay. But the the big thing here is we
get to assume in in these reasons uh we
get to use
uh p 0 p1
up to p n minus one.
Okay. So uh that's the big win. And in
the base cases you don't I mean you also
get to assume this but for example when
you're proving P 0 you don't really get
to assume anything because there are no
smaller pis. Uh so often you have to do
these specially because the induction
step assumes somehow that n is bigger
than zero.
Sometimes you get lucky you just need
the induction step but usually you need
base cases. Let's see some examples and
this will become much clearer.
So let's play a game.
called item stacking
or it's really unstacking.
So this is
unstacking game.
So, we're going to start with
one stack
of n
and then a move
uh splits
uh
stack
of s bigger than one items.
into
two stacks
with A items in one and B items in the
other.
And you get to choose these numbers A
and B, but you need conservation. So A
plus B has to equal S.
And uh we also don't want zero height
stack. So we need A at least one and B
at least one. Okay. So you get to choose
A and B however you want so long as
there's at least one item in each stack.
So let's take a physical example
and got lots of blocks here, but I have
no audience, so we're just going to demo
this myself in in real life. Uh this is
actually this was a snow day at MIT and
so we're recording after the fact. So
all the students MIT students have seen
it. This is specially for you at OCW.
Uh so when we do a move uh from S. So
this is we have a stack of size S and we
convert it into a stack of size A and a
stack of size B. We get A time B points.
That's just the definition of the game.
A* B points. When you split into a stack
of size A and a stack of size B. Uh so
how should I maximize my score in this
game? What's the best strategy? Uh the
game ends when all your stacks have size
one because you can't make a move on a
stack of one item. It has to be greater
than one items. So let's try here. I
have a stack of five blocks.
And uh one thing maybe I'll try to split
it roughly in the middle. So now here
I'll rotate this so you can see the
blocks a little bigger. Uh these are
five blocks. uh I split like this. So
that's a I group of two and a group of
three. Product of two * three is six. I
can do this level of arithmetic. So six
is our total so far. When I split this
one, I get one more point. That's seven.
When I split this one, doesn't matter
how I do it, I get uh 2 * 1. So that's
two more points. That's nine. And when I
split this group, I get one more point.
That's 10. Okay. So one approach gives
me 10 points. What if another natural
strategy that was like splitting in the
middle? Another natural strategy is I
just take one off each time. So if I
take one off here, I get four points. Uh
if I take one more off, I get three more
points. That's seven. 4 + 3 is seven. I
take one more off, I get two points,
that's nine. I take one more off, that's
one point, that's 10. Huh? 10 points
that way, 10 points the other way as
well. Maybe there's a theorem here.
Maybe no matter what I do, I get 10
points. Well, that won't be true. But
for five blocks, I will always get 10
points. For six blocks, I will always
get, I don't know, 15, some more points.
Uh, it turns out it doesn't matter what
strategy you follow, you always get the
same number of points for a given
initial stack of size n.
Let's prove that with strong induction.
Okay. So theorem is
for all natural numbers
uh
every strategy
for this game.
Uh starting
uh with the stack one stack of n items
scores
magic formula is n * n minus one over 2.
So that's the theorem and we're going to
prove it by strong induction
in sort of the straightforward way. So
our induction hypothesis is going to be
exactly the theorem statement uh for a
particular n. So I'm going to highlight
this
statement everything except the
quantifier and I'll call that p of n. So
what I want to prove is for all natural
numbers n P of N is true. And so that's
that's just going to be our induction
hypothesis. We're going to plug that
into this template here. Assume that P
of K is true for all K less than N and
then prove P of N is true. So let's just
try to do that.
So what I would normally write here is
assume
true assume that my theorem is true.
Assume P of N is true. uh sorry p of k
is true for all k less than n. I would
say assume true for all smaller n.
Okay, let's uh we need to do something
with the game. We start with a pile of
size n. Let's just think about the first
move.
First move is something. It's takes our
pile of size n and it splits it into
some piles a and b.
So uh we don't know what it is. We don't
know what a and b are. But we can give
them a name. Like this has to work no
matter what a and b are. But let's say
consider first move which we know we
start with a pile of size n. And we
produce piles of size a and b. And again
uh a + b equals n and a and b are at
least one. But otherwise we don't know
what a and b are.
Okay,
so we go down to here. Um,
so we now have a pile of size A and we
have a pile of size B. Again, we don't
know how big they are, but they are
smaller than B. So I want to claim we
are uh left
with two piles or we can really think of
those as two completely separate games
A and B. We're going to get some points
from splitting up A. We're going to get
some points from splitting up B. They
sum together, but the these piles don't
really interact from here on. We got uh
we got A* B points from this first step.
We're going to get some points from the
pile of size A. We're going to get some
points to the pile of size B. How many
points do we get? Uh well, in fact, our
induction hypothesis will tell us
because
uh A and B are strictly less than N.
Why? Because
uh a + b= n and a and b are at least
one.
So there's at least one in each of a and
b. And so the remainder must be strictly
less than n. If there's one in a, then
there'll be n minus one in b. If there's
two in a, there'll be n minus two in b.
In all cases, less than n. Okay? Because
a and b are less than n, they're not
just they're not necessarily n minus
one. So we couldn't just use regular
induction. But we have they're less than
n. And so by strong induction
uh by strong induction
we know that P of A is true and P of B
is true.
Okay, we wrote that up here. So P of K
for all K less than N. So A and B are
less than N. So P of A is true and P of
B are is true. So that means from the
pile of size a
we get uh a * a minus1 / 2 points
from the a pile. We get b * b minus one
over two points from the b pile.
And then of course we got a time b move
points uh from the first move.
And so now we just need to do some
algebra and add up all these points.
So the total number of points that we
get is a * b + a * a -1 / 2 plus b * b -
1 / 2
These two were by induction. This was
the first move. Uh, and now let's just
put everything over two. So this is 2 *
a * b plus I don't know a^ 2 - a + b ^ 2
- b all over two.
Okay. And now what do I want to get to?
This is supposed to equal n * n minus
one over two. And what was n? n was a
plus b.
So, what I'd really like to show here is
uh a + b * a + b minus one over two.
That's my goal. And what I need to do is
fill in the in between.
Uh
but this is not too hard because let's
see. Uh I see a time b here and a * b
here. I mean in fact you can just expand
this out and you'll get exactly the same
thing here. uh I think slightly more
intuitive is to see oh look at this term
this term and this term that is
uh a^2 + 2 a b + b^ 2 that is a + b^ 2
and then we have a minus a minus b over
2 but interject a rule in between we
have a + b^ 2 minus a + b over 2
uh and then these two are the same
thing. I think that's pretty clear. So
cool. We did some algebra and the we
just computed what we get out of
induction and then boom, we get the
answer n * n minus one over two and it
works. How did we know this is the right
answer? I mean, we were just told that
by the theorem. Uh probably you would
try this for very small n and make a
conjecture. Oh, it seems like it's n * n
minus one over two. Let's try to prove
it. And when you assume the right thing,
the proof just works. And it's kind of
magical. And that's strong induction.
Again, we needed strong induction here
because we needed to assume uh what we
wanted for all smaller n because we
don't know what a and b are. This has to
work for all a and b less than n. Um
so luckily strong induction gives us
that.
All right, I have one more example to
tell you about. Uh,
a slightly more complicated version of
the same thing. We're going to use
strong induction. Don't need any of
these.
So, let's
go.
That's a problem called beat ordering.
I guess somewhat relevant today because
uh there's a Super Bowl, but this is
just about
any teams of games. Sorry, end teams in
some game. And setup is that every two
teams play a game
and there are no ties.
One team wins
and the other loses.
Okay, this is sort of like stranger
friends and strangers uh where it's
either one or the other. But in this
case, it's asymmetric. It's not they're
not both happy or both sad. One's happy
and one is sad.
Okay, this is what's called a roundroin
tournament. Most sports are not played
this way unless it's small number of
teams because it's a lot of different
teams. It's actually n * n + one over
two teams uh games which is a lot. All
right. So what we would like
is what's called a beat ordering.
Uh this is
um an ordering of the teams
t1 t2 up to tn
such that
b1 beat
uh sorry t1 t for teams t1 beats t2 t2
beat t3 and so on
and a TN minus one beats TN.
Okay, let's draw a little example. Uh
there's team rock,
team scissors,
and team paper.
Okay, paper beats rock, rock beats
scissors, scissors beats paper. Okay,
this is a possible outcome in a three
team tournament. There's there's not
necessarily one best team here. There is
no best team. But maybe paper and rock
play a game and it happens that paper
won. Maybe rock plays against scissors
and it happens rock one and scissors
played against paper. It happens
scissors one. Okay, you can tell why I
named the teams this way. Uh then one
way I could order these teams is paper,
rock,
scissors
because paper beats rock, rock beats
scissors. Okay, so this is sort of the
input and this is my goal
is to produce an ordering like this. But
I need to do it for n teams not just for
three.
Okay. So let's uh do let's do strong
induction
to prove that uh the theorem is a bead
ordering always exists.
theorem.
And when I say this always exists, what
I really mean is uh for all n
and then for all tournaments
of size n
uh there exists a beat order.
Okay, there exists an ordering of the
end team such the first one beat the
second one, second one beat the third
one and so on. I should say uh for all I
uh t i beat t i + one.
Okay, so we claim this is true.
Proof by strong induction.
So we're going to assume that this
statement is true. namely this statement
uh is true for smaller n and then we're
going to prove it for n.
Okay. Uh let's
pick a team
any team
call it t.
Then I'm going to split everything with
respect to t. So I'm going to define uh
W to be the set of teams that win
against T. So this is going to be a set
of all teams S where S beat T.
So this is one versus T. These teams win
versus T or one versus T. And L is going
to be the set of teams that lose against
T. So this is the set of teams S where
TBS.
So this is a loss versus T. Then
intuitively what we'd like to do is put
the winners first, then put T, then put
the losers.
I claim that works. Okay. But how do I
order the winners? How do I order the
losers? Well, by induction.
I claim uh the size of w this vertical
bar means the size of the set is less
than n and the size of l is less than n
because
uh
uh the size of the winners plus the size
of the losers plus one equals n. This is
a one. Why? because every team is either
T or they won against T or they lost
against T. So this is counting all of
the teams. There's T itself, the ones
that win against T, the ones that lose
against T. Together that ex is exactly
N. Every team is exactly one of these
categories. Uh and there's a plus one
here.
And all of these are non- negative.
These here W and L might be zero, but
there's this plus one. That means both W
and L are strictly less than M. So the
induction applies to them.
So by induction
uh this thing is true for any tournament
of size W there exists a beat ordering
of W. For every tournament of size L
there exists a beat uh ordering of L. So
we get a beat ordering
let's we get two of them really. Uh
let's call it W1
W2 dot dot dot W size of W. This is for
this is an ordering of capital W. And we
get L1 L2 dot dot dot L size of L
as a beat ordering of capital L
and then
uh we concatenate.
So we claim uh
W1
dot dot dot W size of W
then T then L1
dot dot dot L size of L
is a beat ordering
of all N teams.
Again, this is all the teams. All the
teams either won against T or they are T
or they lost against T. And the idea is
this part is beat. W1 beats W2. W2 beats
W3 and so on by induction because this
is a beat ordering of capital W. Over
here, this is a beat ordering of of
capital L. And so by induction, uh all
these are are okay. L1 beat L2, L2 beat
so on, dot dot dot beat L size of L. The
only things we need to check are these
two commas. We need to check that W sub
big W, W subsize of W beats T and T beat
L1. Why are those true? By our
definition of W and L. Everything in W
beat T. So this is by by the definition
of W. We know that all of these beat T.
So in particular, this one beat T. And
we know by the definition
of L,
uh, all of these teams lost against T.
In other words, T beats all of these
teams. In particular, T beat L1. And so
by combining all these beat statements
together, we know that this entire thing
is a beat ordering. each item beats the
one right after it. So it's a little
more complicated, but again, we're just
quite often with strong induction
proofs, you apply induction twice. You
you have some problem of size n, you
split it into two parts. In general, you
might split it into many parts. Then you
recursively solve the two parts or the
many parts. As long as they're strictly
smaller than n. By induction, we know
they work out. By strong induction, we
know they work out. You take those
solutions and you combine them in some
way. Here we concatenated with t in the
middle. Um over here we summed them up.
We summed up the number of points we got
in each one plus the number of points we
got in the first step. Uh and in general
you combine them in some way and you
prove that it's still that you're uh the
thing you want to prove holds for size n
and then you get your theorem. So that
is the power of strong induction.
Thanks.