All right.
Our next session-- our
last session before lunch--
is focused on two
projects involved with AI.
We have Esther Duflo from
Economics and Graham Jones
from Anthropology.
They'll give their
presentations.
Then they'll be joined
for a panel discussion
with their collaborators--
Marzyeh Ghassemi from EECS,
and Arvind Satyanarayan, also
from ECS.
And then Daniel
Huttenlocher, the Dean
of the Schwarzman
College of Computing,
will join to moderate.
So, Esther, thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you very much.
Thank you for being here
in such large number,
and for just the very thing
that it's possible to do this.
Lily and I serve
on the task force
of the undergraduate education.
So these are the idea that
MIT is not just an engineering
school, but has a very
vibrant [INAUDIBLE] program,
and that it's integrated
deeply into the education
experience of the
students, and also
in the research of
various faculties,
of course, very critical.
I'm looking at my phone
because I want to time myself.
So this is an example,
perhaps, of one of the things
that this incredible
place makes possible.
So this is a project
about using--
so most of my work in the
context of J-PAL the Jameel
Poverty Action Lab--
is about designing
and evaluating
policies that improve the lives
of poor people around the world.
J-PAL is actually a network
of faculty across the world,
of about 1,000 faculties
across the world.
It works in various sectors from
health, education, environment,
et cetera.
And our work is really kind of
at the intersection of research
and policy.
In this context, of course,
a very active area right
now is the combination
of AI and [INAUDIBLE].
And we have actually,
we're able to raise money
to do AI and [INAUDIBLE],
which we call AI for Good.
And one of this
is AI for Health,
which has been very
active at MIT way
before we got into it,
in particular with--
but not only-- with the help
of, again, the Jameel family
through the [INAUDIBLE] clinic.
So this project
is a collaboration
of many people with
different hats.
And I think that's
kind of what makes
this wonderful and possible.
One, of course, is Marzyeh
from [INAUDIBLE] and myself.
Marzyeh's here
and join us later.
Ziad Obermeyer is a medical
doctor, a emergency room
physician, as well as
being a researcher in AI
for the longest time.
Frank is also from economics.
Girija Vaidyanathan is both
a civil servant, very high.
She retired as the
chief secretary
for state of Tamil Nadu--
so, the biggest person
in the state in the bureaucracy.
But she is also a medical
doctor and a researcher,
and she's an OB/GYN by training.
And then two students, one
in economics, one in the ECS.
So you can see how it takes
many cooks to do this project,
but this is what makes
it particularly great.
So what's the policy challenge?
The policy challenge is
that countries like India--
but not just India, but
certainly middle-income
countries who are growing fast--
are now kind of trapped into a
double burden of disease, one
being the traditional
infectious diseases
and the other being
non-communicable diseases that
are more and more important
in people's lives.
And of course, a third
thing is coming along,
which is the direct
impact of climate change.
But for the noncommunicable
diseases, there is many--
there are large treatment
gaps which often
stems from a diagnosis gap.
So for example, in a
survey we have of people--
it's a panel study we
are doing with people.
They started 50 and
above about 10 years ago.
So they are now 60 and above.
Many of them have
various conditions
that are non-communicable and
manageable, if not treatable.
But most of them do not
that they have them.
In many cases, this diagnosis
exists in high-income setting.
It's an even--
people in India who
are high income themselves can
easily get diagnosed for this.
For example, one
of the condition
that's going to be really
the focus for today is--
more like as a test
case-- is whether or not
you've had a heart
attack in the past.
So if you had a what's called
a silent heart attack--
I'm not a doctor, so I hope
I'm not saying anything wrong--
but if you had a
silent heart attack had
a heart attack in the past,
you didn't die, that's good.
That's the good news.
The bad news is it makes
you weaker and more
susceptible to the next one.
And the good news again,
is that that's actually
a manageable condition.
You can put people on very cheap
things-- beta blocker, statins,
baby aspirin, and they'll get--
that's really help
managing the condition.
But for that, they have to
know that that has happened.
And many of the
silent heart attack
never made it to the hospital.
So there is no
sign they have it.
How do you diagnose it?
The gold standard
test is an ultrasound.
An ultrasound is
expensive and can only
be done in the hospital.
So our idea was to use--
to see whether it
was, really, it
was to test out whether it
was possible to diagnose
silent heart attack--
not diagnose, but
predict whether someone
might have had a silent
heart attack in the past--
using a simple one lead ECG
device produced by Alivecor.
These are the type
that you might
be given if you have elderly
parents to check that there
are arrhythmia is in check.
So that's what it does.
It's not designed to test
whether there was a heart
attack.
But [INAUDIBLE]
hunch was that it
might be possible to go from
there to a form, a prediction,
that there might have been
a heart attack in the past.
So we are predicting the past,
which is a little strange,
but you see what I mean.
So what we are.
So if that worked, that's
really worth testing,
that there was a good chance
that it wasn't going to work.
But if it does work, then,
because the government
of Tamil Nadu,
where we are doing
this work, in the
south of India,
like many other governments
in the United States,
have lots of people going to
people's doorsteps anyways
for various things, like giving
people diabetes medicines
and so on.
It's very easy to outfit
them with this device, which
is super cheap.
And then they can do
the test, and then we
can run the algorithm,
see whether someone
is above a certain threshold,
and above a certain threshold
of likelihood that that event
has occurred in the past,
we can send them to
get tested in hospital,
get the ultrasound that
confirmed the diagnosis.
So that was the idea.
And so what we're
requiring from the test
is that it gives--
whether or not
it gives us any information that
is better than noise, or better
than age, or better than the
scores that people use today.
So what we did is that we, with
the help of [INAUDIBLE] South
Asia and the government,
we organized these camps
where people were able to come.
And then we gave them
a batteries of tests.
So today, I'm presenting to
you this one, but the hope
in working with Marzyeh's
group is that there'll
be many others, because we
collected all of the tests
under the sun, as long as
we had people available,
both cheap and expensive.
So we have things
that are cheap to do,
like a retina photo, blood
pressure, [INAUDIBLE] of course.
And then we have also ultrasound
and many other things.
And then what we did is,
so our students, Jenny,
who is supported by
this grant, started
working with a lot of people
in the department and EECS,
and to teach herself how you
apply machine learning algorithm
to these things.
We predicted.
We used the data.
So we have the
gold standard test.
That's our ground truth.
We have the cheaper test--
anything that someone
could easily, cheaply
do on the ground.
But in particular, this
one is [INAUDIBLE].
And then the
objective is to form
a model that predicts that
the person is likely to have
had a heart attack.
So that's how we are
building the algorithm.
And we are also using, in order
to be more efficient given
the amount of data
we are using, we're
also bringing in
data from Sweden
to pre-train the algorithm.
And we then fine tune
within our existing data.
So that work happened.
It went pretty well, because--
so this is how the
government is-- how
the collaboration is working.
This work happened.
It worked pretty well
because at the high end,
our algorithm is
quite predictive,
that someone would have had
this, a silent heart attack.
In our high risk
group, 95% of above.
The chance that they've
had one is about 9%,
which is nine times greater
than in any of the other groups.
So what we did-- this
is our economist hat--
is we do a cost-benefit
analysis, which tells us
whether this would be
worth it to deploy this,
identify the people,
send them to be tested
if they are at high risk.
And that's compare the number
of lives you could save.
In this way, with
the cost of testing,
a bunch of people who probably
haven't had that event happened.
And it's super, super,
super cost effective.
And what is remarkable
compared to existing tests
is that it catches
young people who
are less likely to have
had a silent heart attack,
but have many years of life
saved if you can catch them.
And those young
people are completely
excluded from the
current screening
because the screening is
basically based on age.
So something like that
kind of makes it young,
meaning not super young,
but like the 40-plus.
So where the last things we--
this brings me to
one of the thing
we want to do in the future,
which is the student that ECS is
a financing with this grant,
is already starting to do,
is to look at fairness
property of this algorithm.
Like, yes, we
catch young people.
Do we miss people
that we shouldn't be,
that we shouldn't be missing?
And a preliminary result
suggests that this algorithm
actually works better in
urban areas for older people,
even though it does work for
younger people, and for men
than for women.
So one of the things
we can do in the future
is to improve it, to make
it to solve these issues.
And of course, this
is, [INAUDIBLE]
scratching the surface of
what we can do with this data.
What we can do in the world is
also scratching the surface.
We already raised more money
to the AI for Good initiative
at J-PAL to run a randomized
control trial where
these things will actually
be, first, refined,
like one more round of data
collection to make it better.
And then will be
sent to people--
well, people will actually
be outfitted with this,
and we'll see
whether they do it.
And we can compare
whether or not
people get diagnosed with this.
So as my son was
just at Model UN,
I yield my time to the
Chair, but I don't have any.
So thank you so much.
[APPLAUSE]
Oh.
Thank you, Esther.
Let me make sure this works.
Couple more.
Oh, that's me.
[LAUGHTER]
Hi, I'm Graham Jones.
So thank you so much, Esther.
Thank you, [INAUDIBLE] and the
MITHIC team, Jen and Elena.
Thanks to Agustín
and Anantha, Sally
for making this all possible,
and to the generous funders
of this program, and to
all of you for being here.
So my name is Graham Jones.
I am a linguistic
anthropologist,
which means that
I study how people
communicate with each other.
My MITHIC collaborator, Arvind
Sathyanarayan, who's over there,
studies human-computer
interaction,
which means that he
studies how people
communicate with computers.
Our MITHIC projects, spanning
[INAUDIBLE] and the School
of Engineering, focuses on an
unprecedented moment in history,
where large language
models have allowed people
to communicate with
computers as if they
were talking to other people.
So you can see the
kind of Venn diagram
of our areas of expertise.
We wanted to draw on
these respective fields
to understand the opportunities
that LLMs represented, but also
to mitigate harms and
improve societal impacts.
But our collaboration actually
began several years earlier.
And so I want to try to
contextualize it for you today.
So as I said, I study
how people communicate.
And in particular, I'm
interested in how people
communicate information--
valuable information.
Information like secrets.
Imagine someone with a
secret to share and someone
else who wants it.
The secret holder could
just tell the secret
straight out-- here you
go, and spill the beans.
But consider what happens
in the following example.
This is a magician
who I recorded
sharing a secret during my field
work among French magicians.
This is just a small
snippet, a snippet
of a much longer revelation.
And I was one of the people
receiving the secret.
So he says, to you, I'll
give it to you, all right.
But well, um, I'm--
we're not going to make
it official or whatever.
That's it.
It's-- it's his.
It's-- no.
But--
So you'll notice that far
from just spilling the beans
or giving the secret,
this person is stammering.
He's hedging, he's
interrupting himself.
He's imposing conditions.
He's anxious about
sharing the secret.
And his anxiety is not only
palpable but contagious,
affecting the people who
are receiving the secret.
And that shared
anxiety is part of what
makes magicians magicians.
Now from this, I want you
to retain two lessons.
One, the form of talk
shapes its meaning,
and two, meaning is social.
Now here's an example from
Arvind's research, a data
visualization, like one
of many that most of you
probably see every day.
This is also intended to
convey information-- probably
very important information.
And most people think that
conveying information is all
that data visualizations do.
But compare it to this
data visualization.
You'll notice some differences.
The color palette is different.
And in this new chart,
instead of bland color fields,
we have these
colorful green plants.
You'll also notice that
the information has
been removed from these graphs.
We don't what they're about.
But if I asked you where you
thought these graphs came from,
I bet many of you
would have some ideas.
Arvind and I
recently ran a series
of experiments using
charts like these,
and we found that even when
the content of visualizations
is obscured, people have very
strong ideas about who made them
and why.
And this has profound
implications for whether or not
people trust that information--
a discovery with
deep implications
for fighting myths
and disinformation.
But I want you to retain this.
This discovery means that
even for data visualization,
form shapes meaning, and
that meaning is social.
Just a few weeks ago, there
was an article in The MIT News
about this discovery, if
any of you are interested.
But that's not really
why you're here today.
What does this
have to do with AI?
It turns out quite a lot.
LLMs now allow us to
communicate with computers
as if we were communicating
with other people.
Old-fashioned,
rule-governed AI could not
handle many of the things
that humans do with language.
Generative AI has
changed all that.
Consider ambiguity.
In the sentence, "The
peasants are revolting,"
is revolting a verb
or an adjective?
Well, it depends on the
context, which humans
are very good at parsing--
or laughing about
when they can't.
Probabilistic AI can
parse such ambiguities,
and in interactions
with human users
it reflects our key tenants.
Form shapes meaning
and meaning is social.
This is a deep
technological breakthrough.
But like many breakthroughs, it
is far from an unalloyed good.
Consider this transcript.
This is a snippet of many
thousands of messages shared
between a British man
and an AI girlfriend,
that he created on
the Replika app.
Over the course of
months, this AI girlfriend
helped the man
plan to assassinate
the Queen of England.
He was arrested with a crossbow
breaking into Buckingham Palace.
Old-fashioned rule-governed
AI could never have done this.
It used to be the case that
in building an AI system,
a designer would
pre-configure settings
for everything that a human
might do with the system.
This could involve
giving more agency
to the human user for
more manual tasks, or more
agency to the system for
more automated tasks.
But all of this would
be decided in advance.
But as we have shown,
interactions with gen AI
are open ended, and as such,
designing for generative
AI takes a different
form, because what
the system and the user will do
together is not predetermined.
Designers configure
open-ended possibility spaces.
Our MITHIC project focuses
on how best to configure
those possibility spaces.
We approach this issue in terms
of sociocultural awareness
because AI agents communicating
like people with people
are entering into
sociocultural relationships.
We think that making
designers aware of this
will lead to not only
safer systems, but ones
that are better performing.
This is what we proposed
in our MITHIC project.
But at the time of the proposal,
we really didn't how to do it.
And that's one of the really
great things about this grant,
is that it gave us the freedom
to explore an open-ended problem
space of our own.
Working on this
over the summer, we
were captivated by
an emerging trend
in the design of AI agents.
We began experimenting with
building systems in which
each possibility space was its
own independent agent, offering
a much more granular control
over how the overall system
might behave.
This is called
multi-agent AI, and we
decided that the best way
to explore the topic was
by teaching about it.
We quickly put together
a special subject
called Humane User Experience
Design, which we're currently
teaching, in which students are
using a multi-agent approach
to designing AI systems.
The crux of our collaboration
is the term "humane."
Like "revolting," it's a
bit of a double entendre,
meaning both human serving,
or benevolent, and human-like.
What's interesting is that
our students are discovering
that there's a fundamental
tension between building
a system that's good for people,
and one that seems human,
because real people can
develop dangerous dependencies.
We have 40 students
in the class,
and they're currently
working on final projects,
ranging from domains
such as education, health
and wellness, personal
growth, and entertainment.
We're hoping to
continue with a smaller
subset of current seniors
as MEng students next year,
and really, to
see how far we can
push the application
of anthropology
to computer science and computer
science to anthropology.
And incidentally, on
my way out of class
today, I spoke with one
of our graduating seniors
who just had an internship
in New York working
with a startup that's using
multi-agent AI to develop a tool
to help senior citizens
navigate social services.
And he said, it's
just our class.
So that was very
validating for us.
This collaboration reflects the
best of MIT, of mens et manus.
And we are very grateful
for the opportunity
that MITHIC has given us
to pursue it in cooperation
with our wonderful students.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
[INAUDIBLE]
Get myself organized.
I was wondering,
who's sitting where?
Great.
Thank you for these
really fantastic projects.
Maybe I'll start with a
question for Esther and Marzyeh,
just sort of in the order
of presentation, I guess.
So this is an extremely
important problem domain,
of creating new, low-cost
screening methods
to refer people
for further testing
that they might not
otherwise be getting
for very serious but
hidden health conditions.
So my first question is, how
did your multidisciplinary team
arrive at this particular
problem of silent heart attack,
and the approach
that you pursued?
And maybe just as a--
what I find really remarkable
about this approach
is it's technologically
feasible.
There's no human-AI
collaboration in it,
which becomes a gigantic
rat's nest of trying
to get better outcomes.
And then, of course,
it's aimed at treating
a very important issue.
So how did you get there?
Yeah, maybe I'll start with,
because that was before Marzyeh
came onto the project.
And then she can say what--
the various places we
could go from there.
The genesis of this project is--
I was in a sadly, now defunct
NIH PO1, like a center grant,
on health and aging.
[INAUDIBLE] a lot
of different people
were working on
different things.
And Ziad and
Sendhil Mullainathan
were presenting about
overtesting and under-testing.
In the US, we are more
talking about the fact
that they are overtesting.
We're sending people,
referring people to tests.
But they did point out
that even in the US,
there is also under-testing.
And then there were--
Ziad was-- and then they were
presenting the possibility
that something like that
could help pre-screen
who should be tested for what.
And I thought, oh, this
is really interesting,
because I'm sure there is
progress to be made in the US.
But I know for a
fact that this is,
if it's, like, second-order
improvement in the US,
it's first-first-order
improvement in the places where
I work, where people don't
get tested for anything.
In fact, they get drugs before
they get tested for anything.
And so that's how I
approach Ziad to see
if he wanted to work on this.
And the idea of heart
attack came from him.
Again, he is a
practicing physician.
He works in the ER.
He sees them.
And he also has been working in
this space for a very long time.
And he thought it had all of
this virtue that you describe,
which is, there
is no-- we are not
trying to mimic
how a human would
have made a decision, which is
a lot of how the problems are
done.
In fact, we are trying to
go straight to the ground
truth, which is what
would the ultrasound say,
where there is any--
not really ambiguity.
So that would be a great
advantage, something
you can actually, very easily--
maybe more easily do in
India, because people haven't
gotten the ultrasound already.
And it can be done cheaply.
That can be deployed easily.
And that have potential
life-saving virtue.
So that's kind of why we wanted
to try this as a test case.
And our proof of
concept with the idea
that there's no
reason to stop there.
The data is public.
It's on the public use platform.
So anybody can try to
do better, or to do it,
work on other diseases, and
can also go to Tamil Nadu
and work with us
to deploy whatever
their idea is in the field.
And when I heard of
MITHIC, I was like, oh,
that's an occasion to grab the
attention of my ECS friends.
And I had seen
Marzyeh in the context
of talking about these
grants and a future grant
where we were trying
to get at the PO1.
So I thought she will be
really the right person
to lead that effort.
I'm also, just for
people who don't know me,
I'm a noted hater
of AI in health,
because that's my
research topic.
I have seen so many
bad deployments--
so many bad deployments.
It's very bad.
But a majority of
the bad deployments
are actually when
you're trying to not--
your goal is to make
something more efficient,
and your idea for
efficiency is, I'll just
colonize this human-to-human
interaction with an AI system,
thereby taking out the
expensive part of it, which
is the interaction with another
human, which I'm very against.
I don't want AI to colonize all
human interactions in a health
setting.
And I loved this example,
because when Esther approached
me, again, as a noted hater
of specific deployments,
this is such a good deployment.
It's one of the few times
somebody has approached me,
and I have said, this makes
so much sense in every way.
It's technically the right
data to try to use-- low cost--
to project or predict
what high-cost data
would have given you.
It's attacking a problem
that actually matters,
and that we can do
something about.
It's not predicting
some hypothetical thing
that there's no treatment for.
We actually have something
we can do with it.
And it's also
extremely scalable.
So I think this is--
it was one of the best
designed uses of AI
in a healthcare
setting that I've seen,
and I'm very excited
to be part of it.
I have a million follow
up questions from that,
but I'm going to
ping-pong back and forth.
Otherwise, I'll go down the
rabbit hole of one project.
So Arvind and Graham, I think
the question of understanding
what happens when people
communicate with computers
as if they were human has become
incredibly important with AI
advances, as you noted,
and really urgent,
and one that requires insight
from multiple disciplines.
I guess maybe I'll start with
a somewhat irreverent kind
of question.
So people already talk to
their pets like they're human.
So does that mean it's
inherent that people
are going to communicate
with AI as if it's human?
It certainly presents itself
as much more human-like
than most of our pets.
Even if it's made clear
that it's not human.
And currently, of
course, the direction
is it's pretending
to be human rather
than-- but certainly
some people are
advocating for not doing that.
So how do you think about
how we address this,
both with better
human understanding
and with better
AI systems design?
I think either one of those
alone, probably not enough.
And maybe I'll start
with Arvind, since--
He's looking at me
as if he wants--
OK, well then--
--he wants to start with me.
All right.
You guys figure out who starts.
Well, I think, as
an anthropologist,
we know, cross-culturally,
that people
around the world
in various cultures
have the propensity
and the capacity
to personify all types of
entities in the world--
not just animals, but entities
that we in Western culture
might consider inanimate.
And I think that this
traces back fundamentally
to a fundamental mechanism
of human psychology, which
is pareidolia--
our tendency to perceive
animacy in the world,
or to seek out
agency in the world.
It's a capacity that's
necessary for human survival.
And it gets organized
in various cultures
into refined capacities or
refined cosmologies that
allow us to experience
the world as animated
by agents, non-human agents.
So we know that, in a
sense, as you say, Dan,
there's nothing new
about our tendency
to personify or to
personify AI agents.
I think, nevertheless,
given partially
the institutional and
sociological conditions
in which AI is currently
being deployed--
if we consider, for instance,
the crisis of loneliness,
the crisis of isolation in
modern Western democracies,
I think it creates a
very volatile situation
in which the
personification of AI
can have perverse consequences.
And so we need to be very
mindful of the cultural context
in which AI is
activating, summoning,
mobilizing that human
propensity for personification.
All right, so now I'm really
going to put Arvind on the spot.
Yeah, no.
So--
How do we do that?
So I mean, that's
sort of the thing
that we're exploring
in our class.
So just building off of Graham's
response, we even taught this--
I think Graham
taught this in one
of our first lectures,
this human propensity
to personify, anthropomorphize
even, non-human inanimate
objects.
And I think the difference
for me with chatbots
is that this is now happening--
the chatbot can respond back
to you and respond back to you
with language.
And language can be-- it is this
incredibly seductive medium.
We, I mean, even going back to
the early experiments with Eliza
that happened here
at MIT, you don't
need a very sophisticated
algorithm for folks
to suddenly read
tremendous amounts
of meaning into the interaction
that they're seeing.
And now we've got AI
models that can respond
far more contextually,
responsively
to what the user is saying.
And so as a result, I
mean, I'm sure many of us
have been following the news and
seeing all the adverse outcomes
of that, all the way through
to really horrific things
like suicide.
And our goal with our class
is to give our students
various handles into the
design process for how
to contend with that.
So we cover things from
the conversational design--
how these different
multi-agent systems
can take on different
frames, either intentionally
or unintentionally, through
to the visual and interaction
design pieces, because
that also contributes
a lot of the phenomenon that
users are experiencing as they
converse with the chatbot.
And what I think is really
amazing for us to see
is the students came in
already reacting to, or perhaps
against, this phenomenon
that we're seeing.
Many of them-- we just finished
around of presentations today--
are designing
explicitly to make sure
these agents aren't
sycophantic, aren't
telling people exactly what
it is they wish to hear.
Even going back to the very
first reading we set them,
many of them picked
up-- you know what?
We want from our really good
friends, a true AI companion,
is for occasionally that
companion to push back on us.
And what does it mean to design
for that sort of interaction
is really at the heart of our
class and our MITHIC project.
Great.
All right.
Switching context
back to health.
[CHUCKLES] So this one's
maybe a little more
on the technical side.
So the training set
that you had for this,
of about 6,000 individuals,
where you had ground truth data
that you were trying to predict,
is actually quite small compared
to a lot of
machine-learning systems.
So are you developing larger
training sets, especially
as you're looking
at subpopulations,
which is a very important
part of your work.
Very small training set doesn't
represent any subpopulation
well, or might exclude
some completely.
But also, I think one of the
big lessons from, at least one
of my big takeaways from
modern machine learning
is in some sense, the more
data, even that isn't obviously
directly relevant
that you train with,
the better these things do.
So how are you
thinking about that
in the context of this project?
Yeah, that's what
the physicists say.
No more data.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
The rest doesn't matter.
We are about to go to the field,
or maybe in the field in--
with at least doubling
the size of the data set.
Even that is not
going to be gigantic.
But that's why the
Swedish came in.
That helped.
And then the new data
we are collecting,
we were talking about
also being smarter,
how we collect the data.
In particular, we can start by
deploying people in the field
nearby, and see whether
they look like--
they already have our
imperfect algorithm,
already predict where they are
likely to have had the heart
attack, and then, if they
have, say, please, please
go get tested.
So we'll have more
people with instances.
Because it's not just
the size of the data set.
It is how many are
positive, which is an issue.
Yeah, we have a real issue
with silent heart attack
where the rate is very low.
And so if you have anything that
has a very low prevalence rate,
it's really important that
you capture as many examples
of the positives as possible.
And so by doing more, like,
active learning style selection
of more participants, you
can really squeeze as much
as possible out of
the data you have,
because 6,000 samples
is not enough.
But if you select the next
few thousand intelligently,
it can do a lot better.
And maybe, since
switching context again
is going to be hard, because
I see this thing counting down
in front of me.
[LAUGHTER]
So say you're really
successful with this project.
Does that start to overload the
next stage of the health care
system?
Because these people
are not seeking
these more expensive and
extensive forms of testing.
Or how have you
thought about that?
No, I think screening almost
never, never does that.
In any of the
applications I've seen--
and this is a very good
example, because as Esther said,
we do actually have
treatments that are very cheap
and can be used to maintain
the condition longer term.
But even if we think about if
you have a silent heart attack,
then your conditional
probability
of having a second heart
attack is much higher.
And so even just having
more screening opportunities
for those individuals
is a huge opportunity.
And so again, I hate a lot
of possible deployments
of AI in health.
But this is a really good one.
It has a real impact
to do some good.
Super.
All right.
We're going to turn it
to the audience now.
And we'll let Carol
emcee that part.
Unfortunately, [INAUDIBLE]
keeping the trains running,
we don't have time for
any audience questions.
[LAUGHTER]
But we do have time--
Wait a minute.
Then I'm going to go over.
[LAUGHTER]
Sorry.
We have a lunch
actually planned where
we can continue
this conversation
and the other conversations
from this morning.
So I wanted to
thank, first of all,
this panel for their
presentations and conversation.
[APPLAUSE]