(logo whooshes)
(text chitters)
- So next we have, "How do
you weigh the social balances
of equipping AI with
human-like intelligence
and how does your work aim
to integrate AI into
society in a positive way?"
Ultimately, I'm an optimist.
I think that there is a positive future
for AI integrating into society.
I have had the dream since
childhood of, you know, robots
that are human-like that interact with us.
I really think there can be a positive
and valuable future
with powerful AI systems
living alongside us.
However, it is definitely true
that there are a lot of ways
that this could go wrong.
So my own current approach
to dealing with that kind
of trade off is to say,
I wanna focus on
understanding these systems,
not necessarily being the
one who's going to deploy
and make the big systems.
So I get to kind of step back
and just act as a scientist
and try to understand,
what are the principles of intelligence?
How do current AI systems work?
What are they good at,
what are they not good at?
And that's a position that I quite enjoy
and I'm quite comfortable with
because I think that
understanding these things
and developing the science of these things
is just going to pay off for society.
It will allow us to make good choices
about how to integrate
them into the world.
But that is going to be
a hard policy decision
later on in the future.
What do you see as the key challenges
for generative video models
and what other emerging trends
in generative AI pique my interest?
Yeah, generative video models
are really, really cool.
They're the current
thing that's taking off.
So there's maybe two big challenges here.
The first challenge is
that videos are really big.
They are a lot of frames.
So imagine if it's hard
to make a single image,
well, a video is like thousands of frames,
thousands of images.
So the amount of compute
and the amount of memory
and resources required to generate a video
is just a lot more than to
generate a single photo.
So we're gonna have to make
these systems more efficient.
That's one problem.
The other hard thing
about video generation
is physical accuracy and
physical consistency.
So if you've ever seen one
of these video generative models,
like the Sora model, maybe from OpenAI,
what you might have noticed is
it kind of looks like a dream.
It looks like you're in some
dream world where objects
are just kind of popping
in and out of existence,
the geometry changes when
the camera pans around
and it returns to where it started.
You might have entirely new content.
There's a video I saw of the a chair
that's kinda morphing out
of the sand on a beach
and forming the legs and
everything is a bit dreamlike
and physically unrealistic.
These things are
definitely getting better,
but they're not quite there
in terms of their physical accuracy
and that's one of the big challenges
that people are working on now.
There was one other part to that question
so let me go to this.
What generative AI methods
are piquing my interest beyond videos
and the one that I'm really excited about
is what is called generative world models.
So generative world models are methods
that try to make not just
like a video or an image,
but a whole world, a whole
simulation of the world.
So that means something
that I can, you know,
step into and interact
with like a video game.
I can intervene and you know,
throw an object and it
will bounce, you know,
against the geometry in this world.
So think of like a game
or a simulation engine.
And people are trying to
make generative models
where I could like type in text
and it will generate
this whole world for me.
I'd say, "Make me a video game on Mars
where I can, you know,
jump on different platforms
and do a back flip,"
and then it just makes that game for you.
So this is something that's
not quite available yet
but is coming very quickly
and I'm excited about it.
Not just because it could be used
to make fun video games,
but actually because it's like a new way
of doing simulation.
And simulation has a fundamental role
in engineering and in science.
We often use simulation
to test out ideas and to make decisions.
If I have a generative simulation,
I can do that same type
of simulation-based engineering
in my generative model.
So one thing that we've
been doing recently
is trying to train and
develop robots in simulation
and then deploy the robots in the world.
So the robot can interact
with a simulation,
it's safe, they're not
going to break anything.
They can maybe drive as a
self-driving car in a simulation.
It's okay if they get into
a crash in a simulation
and they can learn from their mistakes
how to behave in a safer way.
And then we deploy that
technology into the world.
So, previously, people used
classical physics
simulations of the world.
And now what is happening
is we're starting
to use generative models
as our simulation engine.
We recently have a project
which we call LucidSim,
which tries to use generative AI
as the simulation engine
for training robots.
"Can you walk us through the process
of how an AI system learns
to understand images?"
So there are kind of two different ways
that you currently can train
an AI to understand images.
One way is via generative
AI, via generative modeling.
So the basic idea here
is that if I have a model
that can make images,
then it must have understood something
about the visual world, right?
It's kinda like this Feynman quote,
"What I can't create, I don't understand."
And you know, presumably,
what I can create,
I do better understand.
So if a model has been trained
to be able to make images
and videos and worlds,
then it must understand
something about the world.
And indeed that's what we see happening.
Some of the current really
effective image processing
and image understanding algorithms
work by just trying to
generate visual content
and then by generating the content,
they learn how to interpret
the content as well.
The other way that current
systems learn to process
and understand images is
what I alluded to before,
which is self-supervised learning
where you take an image
and you just try to predict
some property of the image
from some other property.
So you try to predict missing
pixels from observed pixels.
Or imagine a video.
You might try to predict
what is the next frame gonna
be given the previous frame.
If you can make these
types of predictions,
you must understand something
about the world around you.
If I can predict what
I'll see in the future,
I must have an understanding
of how objects move,
the idea that a ball travels
in a parabola when I throw it.
So these types of understanding
come out of making predictions
and that's the second way of
doing visual understanding.
"How is your group working
toward improving the quality
and quantity of synthetic data
to train generative AI models?
And how can this type of data teach robots
to learn visually from their errors?"
Yeah, I'm really excited
about the prospect
of using synthetic data
from generative models
to improve AI systems.
This is an area where there's actually
a lot of confusion right now
and there's a lot of debate
about when synthetic data
can be useful or not useful.
So one thing that people worry about is
that if the internet just becomes polluted
with a lot of output from language models
and just fake data, then
maybe this is going to,
we're gonna lose touch with reality
and the future models
that are trained on that
will just get worse and worse and worse.
And there are some cases
in which that might happen
and we have to watch out for that.
But what I'm working on
and what I'm a lot more excited about
is kind of the optimistic outlook
that models can potentially
make synthetic data
that's actually better
than the data that trained,
the real data that trained
the model in the first place.
Like synthetic data can
be better than real data.
And there are various ways
in which that can happen.
And we're basically working on algorithms
that try to achieve that.
So for example, I might
have a generative model
that can be steered or intervened on,
like a human can actually go in
and change the parameters
of the model to steer it,
to make data that is more positive
or more useful for some
kind of downstream task.
There are methods,
like one called reinforcement
learning from human feedback,
that essentially do that.
They take a model
and they kind of steer it
toward human preferences
of what is considered to be better data.
So this is just one example
of how you can make synthetic data
that is better than real data.
And I think that there's just
a really interesting
future along those lines.
The question was also also asking
about how we're using this for robotics.
And that goes back to
this LucidSim project
that I talked about in the previous answer
where we are trying to create world models
in which you can train a robot.
So it's a simulation,
augmented with generative
models and generative AI,
that can create all
types of diverse content
and imagine all types
of different scenarios
so that if I train my robot in that world,
it will become robust
and competent in all of
these different scenarios.
So this is a place
where generative models and synthetic data
can teach our next
generation of AI systems.
"Looking ahead to the next 10 years,
what do you envision next
for AI in image processing?"
I really think that the future of AI
is much more going to
be about the integration
of all of our sensory modalities
and all of our other problems in AI
into a more kind of holistic approach,
this embodied intelligence approach,
this human-like agent that I
mentioned at the beginning.
So I'm not sure that image processing,
as like a sub area of AI,
will be the most exciting
thing in the future.
I think it's more about how
you integrate images and sounds
and touch signals, all
the modalities together.
You add language to the pipeline,
you get the field of
natural language processing
to talk to the field of computer vision,
to talk to the field of robotics.
So, to me, the future of image processing
and computer vision is
more about integration
with other areas of AI.
And I think we're at a time
when that is gonna be really effective.
So the last question is,
"Are multimodal world models possible?
Kind of combining
discriminative, generative,
and perceptual understanding
in a single model."
Okay, this is perfect
because this follows exactly
on my previous response.
I think, yes, this is the exciting future
is these multimodal systems
and these multi-model systems as well
where there's different
models all interacting,
all becoming more and more unified
in how they understand the world
and thereby becoming more
effective and accurate and robust.
So there's a lot of work in this area
of combining a vision system
with a language system,
deploying that on a robot potentially.
And I think it's just a really
interesting area right now.
All of these different
ways of modeling the world,
like the way that a language
model models the world
and the way that a vision
are becoming more and more
alike in a measurable way.
So the representations inside
the latest language models
and the representations inside
the latest vision models
are becoming more alike in in
their mathematical properties.
So we have this idea
that we call the platonic
representation hypothesis,
that there's maybe some ultimate,
like unified representation,
this platonic entity,
and all of these different modalities
and sensors and problems are projections
and reflections of that
underlying central thing.
And we really wanna find that thing
and that will be a way
of unifying these different parts of AI,
these different sensory processes,
into a common framework.
And that's one of our ongoing projects.
That's it for the questions.
It was really fun to get
a chance to answer them
and think about these
really interesting topics.
So thank you for taking the time
and I'll see you in the next one.