okay um so what is
gkr can you guys read this it's too big
too small
SL okay so the idea is given a circuit c
um we're going to instead of having to
complete the entire c c by yourself you
can delegate it to a who do the comption
for you and prove it the competion is
correct in an interative protocol um and
the main idea of how you can do it so
let's say the depth sorry dep
D and size s
circuit um what you're going to do is
you're going to take every single layer
of the circuit um Extended to a low
degree extension
um so this is going to be
the so basically take all the wire
values on each layer find a LC extension
of it um and then you're going to have
some LC extension of each layer so layer
is going to be v z then it's V1 second
layer and so
on the final layer is going to be and
the way gkr works is essentially as
follows you're going to reduce some
claims about the top layer the out layer
to claims about layers it and you're
going to keep doing this until you reach
the bottom layer at which point the
verifier can check themselves um so at
the beginning you might have that um the
output gate you want this to be equal to
zero um you're going to reduce this um
via SL check protocol um to two claims
um so let's call these
z11 equals maybe the value V1 one um and
also the claim that the L extension on a
second point is also to be a different
value if you want to and this is done
sub
protocol um and then you can do this
again um so left show how to kind do
this in a two to two fashion we're going
reduce two claims to two CLS
next I'm just going to keep going at the
end you're going to reduce your to the
claim about the out layer um so maybe
zd1 okay and at this point in time um
this is just a low deegree extension of
all the input Gates which is size n um
the verifier knows what all these inputs
are so they can compute the low degree
tension by themselves um and so alog
together this is going to take the
prover time polys to prove um the
competition and correctly to the
verifier and the verifier will
run in time um let's see it's going to
be D * poly log
s um plus like n * main poly log s
also okay is this is we did last time
yeah can you go over how using the same
Randomness you to just do the way down
right so the idea is instead of having
to run a different some protocol call
with independent Randomness for each of
these two claims what you can do is use
the same Randomness for both um for both
claims simultaneously and turns out that
the um the G you have to check at the
very bottom at the end of Thum check
protocol will be based on um the
randomness that was used during from the
verifier point of view so as long as the
same Randomness using both of these
things then you'll have to reduce the
same to like final checks at the very
bottom of the S
Check um yeah okay
um cool um and maybe I should also just
tell you um yeah I also wanted to write
out like sort of sub check like equation
just because we have it um for later
because it's going to be important uh
you have this entire board already which
kind of awkward so maybe I'll put it
somewhere
else yeah oh there maybe okay I guess I
told a camera man we wouldn't use that
for but I'll just put it here because it
shouldn't be important I guess um or
like it would be important for us but
like we did it last time so hopefully it
won't be new um okay
so you're checking a element of like the
ice layer you want introduce it to two
things in the previous layer um and so
what you can do is you can take an
output gate and two input
Gates um and it's going to this giant
thing
so so whether or not it was um uh adgate
times one
times whether like times the sum of
[Music]
it and then you need to take the logic
extension
um okay and so as the equation what's
going to happen is you're going to
essentially do a sub check um with this
entire thing here as a polinomial in
your sub check so we'll come back to
this later we'll just leave
it yeah is a polinomial of
degree um want to say it's like the size
of H maybe in each variable so
individual degree size um H minus one um
or is just take it over
which is the m um and it's going to
basically test the quality of Z and P so
if Z if p is in this like hyper Cube um
then it should be one if and only if p
is equal to Z and then L exension of
that okay so today we're going to ask
some questions okay so we show we knew
how to do this um so last time show how
to do this as long as we had Oracle
access to the add in M
Gates okay
so the goal of the first part of today's
class is to remove this Oracle axis
we're going to show how to get these
things um okay actually we have already
a little bit more in this board so I
guess like so question one is um how to
get these um low degree tensions
um okay um maybe you guys can tell me do
you have any ideas how can we get these
so I feel like onon is bouncing which
clearly means he something to
say
circuit description okay good okay so
maybe I'm saying something like maybe
you can compute these things yourself
somehow if you can artize it um um and
we're going to see to do this in a sec
um another way to do it is we already
know how to do gkr like we already know
how to sort of delegate a circuit right
so let's red delegate the Adam mod Gates
um so
so we're going to Red delegate
atote um and this is indeed what they do
in the original gkr
paper um but we're not going to do it
today so this is another thing you could
do but today we're going to show how to
compute them um actually this is a bit
weird because we're actually going to
compute the low degree extensions of
these added mode circuits we actually
can compute like a different somewhat
low degree polinomial on these that
share the same values on like the hybrid
Cube um so it's actually not going to
be the conical
LD um I think last time Leo had said
something about like can you use a
different like low degree polinomial and
the answer here is yes and we're going
to see application today so um
Okay Okay cool so the idea is like okay
so if you want to compute them okay so
you can't compute the actual canonical
low degree extension um so what can you
do well
so
um Okay and like the reason is basically
because like to compu the ad mod case
like the surface is kind of just too
complicated for you to compute yourself
um so maybe here's an idea what if
instead of computing um doing gkr in the
OR circuit we do it on a much simpler
circuit that comp the same functionality
as a circuit you're trying to as you
want um so
so idea um
replace C with a
simpler to describe
[Applause]
circuit um and I guess by simpler to
describe I just mean that Addam Mo
should be easily computable
[Applause]
okay um okay and so let's use the
universal circuit um so universal
circuit is going to be a circuit that's
going to take us inputs the circuit that
you're trying to compute along with the
input and it's going to Output it's
going to simulate the computation of
your circuit C on the input X and then
compute C of
X okay and the claim is going to be that
this universal circuit is going to have
a simpler description at least for the
addom mod Gates than the original
circuit right because it's going to take
us input like the descript Des of the
circuit and then it's going to kind of
simulate description but all these sort
of like simulation is easy to describe
because it's very general and very
easy okay um so maybe let's see how this
will work um
so okay so we have this universal
circuit here it's going to look like
this um and it's going to take us input
a description of the circuit C along
with your input
X um and then it's going to run um The
Hope is that this is going to be depth D
* po
log
uh maybe it should be okay okay we'll
talk about the depth later um so it
should be hopefully not so much bigger
than the circuit C because you're going
to want to do do it efficiently what is
this description C that over here um
this is um yeah maybe I should okay
so okay so what is the circuit C like
how do you want to like like how what's
the input to this be like um where it's
going to take it's basically going to be
a function that will tell you um
yeah so I guess it would tell you um for
every single like May should be an add
one and a mod
one so for both add a mode it tell you
if at a single location in the original
circuit C if there is
a um if there is a gate of that form or
not so it's going to be a pretty large
description um it's going to be size two
to the
s that make sense
yeah so the circuit we're a description
size yes what that um and as said isn't
alluding to so it would not be so good
for us but we'll discuss how to do
another
way just literally just two bit
strings yeah yeah yeah it's just be
really long it's going to tell you what
every gate of the circuit looks like
okay P W1 and W2 range over kind of like
the the horizontal
yeah okay maybe we should um maybe we
have pw1 W2 range over like all the
possible grades say so you can change
the notation a little bit that's
okay okay um sorry yeah I guess this is
a very small detail how you
hand um so what you can do this also
actually issue original GK protocol
right because they only have ADD mode
what you can do is you can have X and
then also the flip of X or the not of x
and then now you can simulate everything
okay okay um okay so how do you so so my
claim is basically that this universal
circuit is going to be much simpler to
describe than the origion of circuit C
and maybe let's just see why is sort of
a hopefully not too in detail um view
but hopefully we can kind of get idea so
the idea is like let's say this is your
circuit C over
here um and it's going to be a bunch of
layers there's a bunch of gates in each
of the layers and they're going to each
have some
functionality okay and so what the
universal circuit is basically going to
do is it's going to say um like I want
to compute this value of the circuit C
gate here let me look at all the
previous ones because you don't know
which which one this is attached to so
you're going to look at all the possible
like values and you're going to sort of
then see what the circuit C saids and
then compute the appropriate um function
of the previous layer based on what the
circuit C says um so in particular
um yeah so in particular in the ice
layer so the value of the of the circuit
of this thing in the ice layer is going
to
be so maybe this is a
layer and this is a
gate um and it's going to be a sum of
possible gates in the previous layer um
of the following thing so it's going to
be whether C
so it's going whether a c has a add gate
corresponding to the three gates you're
picking picking so this is J and then
maybe K and K
Prime um and then times
uh the sum of them so it's like it's
similar thing as in the jpr thing we're
going to have sort of like a add and
like a m condition um and so okay so if
it's add gaate you're going to compute
the
sum and if it's a m gaug you're going to
mode that okay um wait what is the what
is said inside the parentheses on the ad
gate yeah okay so this is going to be
whether the circuit is an ad gate at
this particular three gase JK and K
Prime um and this is going to be the
values v um i+ 1K so what this value is
yeah sorry so maybe this is a little bit
small
um okay I don't really know how to make
this bigger
um um yeah the subscript on the C I
think of it as an input to yeah exactly
so these are both going to be given from
the the description of the circuit C
which is will also have to take um
description circusy and it's also going
to read into here and this the same
thing that's written on the
yeah yeah sorry still hung up on this C
is defined over three inputs all which
range from one to S right sure okay yeah
so why is it of size so is a table size
like s uh good yes yes so we're going to
have to deal with that in a bit um so
yeah saying that the circuit here is
like the description of circuit C is too
big we're going to have to do something
for that wait so why is it two the S
though because we have sorry it's just s
just s you're right you're right just
SB uh s cubed oh
yes that makes sense like um Sor I feel
like I explained the univers really
badly but um you're basically trying to
simulate the computation of c um and to
do that you're going to introduce her
like a new circuit like a new small
circuit for every single um gate in your
universal circuit I will look at the
previous layer and then canus
appropriate functionality based on let's
see it's supposed to
say okay umel yeah what
the Yeah Yeah uh so yeah so these are
all going to be an H to the m h to the m
here is going to be the size of like
layer okay okay so it's going to be so P
you can think of as being in the I layer
and then Omega 1 and Omega 2 are in the
I plus one's
layer oh like
just so that summation there really
represents like a a c like a you're
trying to compute that summation with a
bunch of GES yeah yeah yeah so this is
going to this is going to correspond to
I'm sorry this is really bad um yeah
this correspond to like a sort of a
pretty big circuit here that's going to
look at the previous layer and yeah so
the dep of be like dep of that Min Circ
exactly yeah that's perfect um
so yeah so so as um I don't know what
your name is Gabe as Gabe said um the
depth of the circuit is going to be um
the depth of the original Circuit of c
um times sort of like this like depth
here um so the question is like what is
a depth
here
um
that's like roughly I don't know that
might be very
cck yeah okay something Times log gu
like poly log maybe at worse
yeah and like the reason is because you
can sort of think of this big sum as
like a binary tree of
sums and then at the very bottom of this
binary tree you have like hly as many um
scen you're kind of looking
at so this this entire depth because
it's like a binary tree it's only going
to be like depth like log s or
something um the depths of the universes
are
good yeah
okay and what about the size of this
universal
circuit yeah so it's going to be the
size original circuit um times like
polys it's going to be
polys um and the reason for that is
because the size of this universal
circuit is basically going to be for
every gate of the original circuit you
have this like poly s- size like circuit
get kind of replacing it so you get like
polys size here and then times the side
of toal circuit which is poly
s okay so this is going to be like part
of what the circuit we're going to end
up using to delegate instead of using
the original circuit c um I guess the
last claim that I made is that this um
circuit U is much simpler to describe
than the circuit c um so particular the
adom M Gates um are easily computable or
like describable very
simply um and maybe let's look at this
and think about it for a
minute so I guess like if you're trying
to figure out you know I have sort of
like I'm trying to look at a specific
gate and I want to see if it's like an
add orote gate what you kind of do is
you kind of figure out where in this
tree you are right and you can be like
oh look I'm part of this binary tree it
should be an ad gate right and you're
like okay I'm an ad gate or you can sort
of read maybe in the leaves like you're
like oh this is this this a particular
gate corresponds to you know like some
some ad gate in the original circuit and
sometime some values and you kind of
figure out oh this is supposed to be a
mate or ad gate or something the point
is that this is like a pretty easy
function to describe um in
particular
so there's going to be low depth booing
formulas that compute both add and mod
Gates um so there's going to be a buing
formula
of um let's see so it's going to
be so it's a buing formula
of size poly log
s
um
that I computes to add in MTI
functionalities so it tells you that
whether within you these um like these
are they're small formulas that tell you
whether a particular gate in U is AD or
mod
that good
okay cool
um okay and so now like these formulat
are much easier to compute than the
previous adem mode um so accessibly the
verifier can do it themselves
now okay
so
yeah ah okay so I guess
originally yeah originally so how do you
compute ad a mode we're we're going to I
didn't write it yet but um you're going
to assume that c is a log SP a uniform
um circuit which means that you can like
you do like maybe up to like time like
poly s computation to compute it which
is too much um here since the cir the
formula is only of size poly log you can
kind of just Compu it yourself right so
then when you're doing gkr in the
universal circuit you just have to do
the small computation as opposed to the
big
one yeah are these like Fiat log space
uniform um I they be log log space
uniform oh right is that how it
works I mean there SI fly log right like
the so basically what I mean by this is
like you can feed in any like P Omega
one and Omega 2 and then computer
formula of the size and it'll tell you
what the answer
is right so it's only poly log size so
you only have is there exist a formula
such that for all P1 Omega 1 Omega 2
yeah the for completes itct yeah
yeah right but yeah the naive way I
would do it is like advice of like P
along sides but like I'm assuming
there's a way to make it to get rid of
this
right yeah I think I think it's log log
uniform I think it's just like
Max figure out what level I
oh
the yeah okay okay
understand yeah maybe just to summarize
what we've done um we've essentially
replaced this like C which has a sort of
complicated adote gate description with
a universal circuit which has a much
simpler adote gate description and then
now what we're going to do is we're
going to run JKR on the universal
circuit instead of the original circuit
C the output is still the same because
univers circuit will simulate C and
compute C of X um but now like the
verifier can themselves compute add
ineut have WR descri good good good um
yeah okay
so so now we're going to run a gkr on U
um you call U of C because it's on the
circuit of it's just
U instead of
C okay so
issues um okay maybe I should also write
like okay so issues so one is that on on
pointed out which is that the input is
now really large
so um so in issue one um input is
[Music]
large okay um and if you remember from
the GPR protocol the proof the verifier
at the very end has to compute some
points in the low degree extension of
the input
right before we said okay the input is
only size n so they can compute it by
themselves it's only n * proba log time
to compute it but now the input also has
C which is size s so now you have to
actually spend like you know time poly s
to compute um the the final layer which
is bad right like we wanted the verifi
to be efficient now we're we kind back
to square one okay so we're going to
deal with this um any other issues
sorry in the gkr protocol the end
follow do I only need to comp a couple
bits in theut Lay or do I need
to uh you need to read it all because
because what you're going to do is
you're going to look at the input layer
and then comp something load extension
and the only way you can do something
load extension if you you know
everything sort of like in the coding
otherwise yeah
yeah sorry I just have a question before
even issues is it obvious the verifier
can compute like add or
mlda good good good um yeah
so yeah so Nikon's question is how do
you compute like the low degree
extensions that Addam mod right now I've
only given you a Bo formula to compute
them right so you can compute the values
on the hyper Cube but you can't
necessarily compute the low deges of
them um so we're going to see how to fix
those things um and hopefully if I'm not
mistake these are the only two issues so
we'll
see is this okay so far
okay so issue one the input is now all
of the circuit plus the original input
so it's very large um so right now this
is what our circuit looks like is U um
big part is C and like a small part is
X okay um so here's when the log space
uniformity of C is going to come
in um so if you ever read like you know
GK ments um the the the theorem only
holds for when C is log space uniform
which means that there's some small
description of
it so some small log S
size description of
c um and let maybe let's call this
description this um and there exist a
turing machine m
that
um basically if it reason this this
description it can then output like the
entire ciruit
C and this turning machine should run
in log space um but it can run for as
much as s
time okay um so okay so C is too big
yeah so is like fixed yeah m is like a
yeah it's just it's a fixed training
machine
yeah yeah just to make this
matters structure it on different
Umi oh I think one main thing is that
the verifier needs to be able to like
know what c is right because like in
order to get sort of any hold on the on
the circus C for the verifier that they
need to kind of have some way of like
describing the circuit in some sense
this is like basically saying the
circuit has to be like log size so that
the verifier can hold it and like you
know have some way of knowing what
circuit he is I guess I'm trying to
think about like what kinds of circuits
are exed by this like C that basically
have to write out all like the entire
table to describe is that what we're
trying to get rid of uh so I think um
Ted is our local complexity theorist so
okay you can't
like
right
yeah so C is large um and the problem
was that reading this entire thing is
too much but we have a short description
of C so let's also maybe have a circuit
that compute c um maybe we'll call this
m just because we have a Tre machine
called M but it's not turing machine is
a circuit um and this circuit will take
us input the description C like with the
things around it um and then it will
output the entire circuit description
and that'll feed into the university we
just talked
about okay so this circuit here is our
circuit C Prime that we will actually be
delegating
on um and just to be clear which one are
the inputs inputs are this um this
description of c and also X like this
entire C here is now kind of wrapped
into the circuit right
yeah description the circuit or say run
the circuit any um so it will you know
run and log as space and maybe up as
time and then it can output like maybe
any gate of the circuit you want any
gate of yeah maybe like you know maybe
if you have an output tape that's
separate from like it's actual like
space as all you comp on you can have
like you can just like output the G by
one sort
of sure yeah out put the description of
C so or like description of the gates of
see so like output the
gates yeah if you just unrolling m that
like really deep good good good okay
yeah so what's the depth of this um so
okay M can run in time up TOS so this
could offensively be depth s which is
bad because her verifi run times depends
on um the depth also
um well it turns out you can do it in
depths log gu um and I'm not going to
tell you to do it you're going to tell
me by the end of class so that's sort of
the goal by
3M um and this will also be size
s so we'll get there but um but'll your
job to convince me and not my job to
convince you
um well anything else yeah wait how do
we turn this machine into a circuit good
okay you tell
me don't be hints don't be hints don't
worry so won't be you like I think
you'll be able to figure out what
clost okay and then the other claim is
this is um like has easy added M Gates
um and well also you also tell me he
that by the CL um so basically circuit
is going to have all the nice properties
you want it's going to be depth log S
size s the whole C get now C Prime is
going to be size poly s because you is
also size poly
s which should probably be poly s not
just size s
um yeah and the total depth is going to
be like poly log s so yeah is the
statement the statement is like true
table of M on C equals c on bracket C
equal C so do we need like size of C
different copies of
M
yeah sure yeah or you can think maybe
it's a thing in like you can have like
an output tape right where you can just
like output everything to or that
another thing yeah yeah I just I want to
make
doesn't yeah no it
doesn't okay yeah you might have just
said
this line there say log s description of
C like C brackets like C in Brackets is
a string it's not actually like it's
like S no this is going to be this is
going to be log S
size so the circuit C is size s but
there's like a short description that
can sort of tell you what the C is going
to look
like I guess a family of circuits like
C1 CN the description could be like the
number n that you should something
sure yeah why is that tree there
like
number um so this description is size
log s so an entire sctu is log S
size I guess it kind of goes like this
more than like yes
we don't know
how um okay so the claim is given the
circuit and CLA giving all these
properties you're going to prove to me
later about um then you can do
gkr and okay so according to our let see
be hi I should for okay the pro is going
to run in time polys where s is the size
of this like new circuit T Prime this is
size polys this is size polys so
everything is polys and poly of poly is
poly so it's polys um for the frer um
and the verifier is sort of the depths
of the circuit um plus like the input
lens deps here this is going to be like
I think we said it was like
basically dep original circuit Times log
and this is going to be really small
it's going to be like log s so it's
going to be overall like the same depth
as the original circuit um and then the
input size is now log S Plus n so it's
not so much bigger
either okay input I maybe yeah okay
whatever okay um okay so the second
issue n pointed out how do you compute
these like the low degree extensions of
the added mod Gates whereas we only
currently have buing formulas that
compute them on the I guess in this case
it's even a boing hyper Cube it's not
even like the H hyper Cube
yeah okay so the idea here was like you
wanted to ultimately get like the bottom
layer to be size that's small yeah like
still like this middle layer that you
get to that has like C like when you run
the M like that's big so at some point
you have to be able to like get
valuations in mle there theover would do
it you never have to do it I
see gu I'm just because the G the
protocol we did last time was like only
first circuits exension smaller
right better what what I did is she
extended every every layer to size s
anyway so even if it wasn't s originally
she extended she'd be big so I think
sometimes s can be viewed as like sort
of upper bound of like each layer size
also
okay so second issue how do we compute
at a mod um so we have let me just write
down what I put there I can push this up
so we
have these two Boolean formulas
[Applause]
it's going to compute at aote this
doesn't have a scoll on top because not
the
extension so
[Applause]
okay right this is what um fee of ad
looks like it's a booing formula so it's
like you know big tree um not big
actually it's very small tree it's like
poly log size um and know output at the
end
um yeah what your like
um yeah out of be one of she say um so
here's the inputs are all
bits so so it's going to be 0 one to
the um I guess this should be taking as
input the size of the circuit and
telling you whether or not that
particular game is add or mod G it
should be like size of like log of the
size of the C
Prime so this should
be okay um
cool and our goal is to
compute and so here we have H is going
to be an H um and so here m is
like log base
h of S
Prime this is what we want um and this
what we have
um I want you to repeat again this is
not the low degree extension this is
going to be a low degree
extension
um so what do we do for Sharp set or
sharp
P you guys remember Yeah question is a l
degree extension but our L degree
extension oh okay so it's a it's a
extension that has low degree but it's
not that low it's like somewhat low
maybe low to degree talking about like
just
extension the low and it's not going to
be the lowest degree but it will have
okay like low enough degree we call it
low
enough low enough degree
extension
okay so you can call this like the l e i
d okay that okay so it's not going to be
the low degree extension but it'll be
like kind of it'll be
okay okay so what do we do for Sharp P
the other like the first class this is
like going like three weeks
ago um the idea there we took like a
Boolean formula or like a like a formula
right we like we okay let me maybe Dr
your memory so the idea was um you want
to count the number of satisfying
equations to some sort of like know CSP
you first turn this into some Boolean
formula right and then you
do something to it and then you can
apply the sub check protocol so what do
you do in the middle artize let's artize
this thing um okay so maybe first before
we ariti we should change the input
formats so over here we have H here we
have bling like the one um but what you
can do is you can just take like maybe a
chunk of size like this is sorry this is
a really like Minor Detail I think
whatever it's fine let's do it anyway um
so this is going to be
size um log of size of H and and then so
this this is how many bits are going to
be here and you're going to take H and
you can convert it via some like
polinomial um it's going to be a
degree H minus one poly is going to
convert any element h of your like you
know your bigger set Capital H to a 01
string and they can do this like a bunch
of times
okay so now we have like this like weird
thing where you're feeding in
h and then you get um you use a degree
like H polinomial to convert it to like
you know zero ones and then now you can
feed it up through this bling formula
and for this part we're going to just
Aris matize
it so what is aris matiz um just to
recall so
and replace it with the the polinomial a
plus B minus a * b um and then sorry
this this should be and not add and then
or of a is
just is this right is this no other way
right this is a plus B minus a b and
this is a *
B right so every time there a or gate
here you can like yeah replace it by
this polinomial anate replace by this
polinomial um
okay so maybe this another Lemo that
like y proved during the first class
that maybe it's been too long to
remember but maybe you can try to
rethink about it um so the question is
like what is the degree of the final
polinomial you get here when you've
arith matized it
like yeah yeah yeah exactly so it's a
number of sort of input Gates here I
think that's the way she said it is a
birth class it just number of input
Gates times like I guess here you have
to Times by the degree of each like sort
of thing you're feeding in which is
going to be H minus one um so it's going
to be um log S Prime which is the number
of gates on the bottom um times this is
say h instead of hus one because it's a
little
shorter okay
so this is going to be the polinomial
that we're going to use um for adod and
Moda so it's not the low degree tension
but it's a good
thing yeah over
F2 over is right or is
over yeah so I guess what's happening is
you're first converting your H um over
larger L yeah sorry yeah the way you've
drawn it it makes it seem like you're
converting H into log H bits but
single ah so H is Big right H is like
two chose a log H sort of information or
like okay maybe it's wrong with the
information but like like guess say like
the H comes from um this bigger set H so
you want to convert it to like 0er one
so you can feed it into the boiling
formula otherwise it's not like type
compatible but the Boolean formula only
takes in like like when you fix the
Boolean formula it has a bunch of input
that are but each you
um so like how do you plug in log H bits
into like an input that only have one
bit oh okay yeah so you can convert this
into like a number of bits it's going to
be log H
many yeah so the conversion isn't from
one h symbol to one bit it's going to be
one h symbol to many bits many but many
it's going to be
L I thought we just wanted to find like
big arithmetic circuit that when you
evaluate it when the ages are Z one it's
equivalent to okay yeah sure so if you
want to keep this this in 01 so you can
have big big set here H just be 01 then
this is just identity you can just plug
it straight in I guess this conversion
is sort of like a I don't know yeah
called the thing based on whether H is
like a bigger set so I've just been
covering it to H is to mat that
basically oh okay H is different than F
okay
okay lit just say I'm
Ling yeah it's it's still a determin
procedure so you'll get to like some
unique Point given the same point it's
just
not y yeah yeah but it's low enough
degree um which is going to be this
number here right because it it's a
really low degree it would just be H
degree but this is a log Factor bigger
but that's going to be okay for us
because I guess the verifier that's fine
I guess
yeah yeah I'm still a little bit
confused about like so V is um like
basically computes for one gate right
like that's essentially like comput like
given one gate um SES the circuit for
one particular G right ah no so the this
formula yeah so the the input is going
to be any particular like location in
your entire circuit and it's going to
compute in this log depths like this
proba log size formula to tell you what
that gug should be like whether that
with the add gate or not so the input is
not like the specific gate it's going to
be like any of the gates in the entire
c yeah so so it's okay so it's one
formula for the entire CC yeah one
formul for circuit um but then why are
you but
like and then so we exactly what but
like we have these hes that means that
we have technically like I guess the
same number of inputs but like we have
like blocks of inputs now and like how
exactly does that change because that
means that we have like
technically we we're
combining information it just feels
weird because like
feels like we're mixing up information
because we're saying like we're
assigning one thing one like like one
thing in a large space to like a bunch
of things the
the in the large field H is in the
larger right and we're saying that just
one to this sprad
of
feels not I'm not falling okay yeah so
you confusion is like this part is like
01 it's really just bullying and then
over here we have this weird H going
into it which is like not bullying so
like what is this polom kind of doing
with all this like bullying stuff that's
part of the question yeah so maybe we
should think about it as in like let's
first Aris matize this um circuit here
so we're going to get something over a
large fod already and then now for we're
going to plug in these like pols into
this already arith matized thing which
is already going to be polinomial so we
kind of like like poog
composition but you're but the thing is
you're not doing one to one you're doing
um if you think about the amount of
information kind of conserved because
here this's h options capital h options
for this H1 and then when you pluck it
up here you now still have only h
options for the resulting like 01
string well I mean yes but it also it it
felt that yes but like the but like in
the higher field we only have like now
we only have um you know log log s uh
different inputs from the larger field
now we're jamming them into this
like we only have like a few we have
much less um things from the larger
field and we're ging that in and it's
just kind of like um like each each
element is getting um you know is
covering a bunch of bits in
those so it turns out that there's a
unique mapping from the string of H1 up
to um hm and then this zero one to the
log S Prime string and so it's a
bijection you can go back and forth
between them so there actually there no
like clashing it's going to be just one
to
one I'm I'm sorry I'm just not
following sure okay um yeah I guess
that's sure okay so what's going to
happen is you're maybe let me zoom out
of that it's a little messy so let's say
you have this is going to be
just so this is going to be our Z 0 one
layer over here I'm sorry again yeah no
you're fine it's good to ask questions
um so this is going to be log H number
of
bits and the idea is we're going to take
some
H and we're going to map it here
to um to log H many different bits right
so here like one way you can do this you
write this in binary right so maybe this
maybe H here is like size eight so this
will correspond to like a binary string
I get you can do that but like
why is why are we allowed to do that and
how how exactly why exactly is this
helping us I understand that you can
write it in binary oning that like how
exactly is this helping us again because
it feels like now um each element each
big element in the extension like before
we were just saying that like we're
going to extend um each individual like
like we're going to assume that like 01
values are actually now extended values
but then we're doing it in such a way
that um like before we wereing these
values from the large circuit are um
going
to like we're going to say like um like
if we have an we have say an hand G then
we're GNA have like PL one big value and
another big value and multiply them
together how about do we take a break
now and then we'll come back in five
minutes and then we'll do the second
half of the class I think that's all for
this part and then maybe we can talk
offline sor you're totally fun let's
talk about it
okay okay so how many of you guys know
the theorem like exists or what it says
or
anything okay it's fine we talk about it
again so this is a really famous theorem
it's a great theorem it's very good um
yeah so we should talk about what these
things are so can one of the local
complexity theorist people tell me what
IP
is it doesn't have to be the local
complexity theorist it could be any of
you
stat that proven
[Applause]
interactive
um oh
[Applause]
did see
okay yeah so okay so IP is a CLA of all
statement that have interactive proofs
um interactive that's right okay yeah so
and the rer can be unbounded time um and
then the verify should run po time this
mean interactive proof should also be
poly size right otherwise ver I can't
read it okay and then what is ppace
[Applause]
TM languages great okay poly space
computations yay um
[Applause]
okay okay um and so the easier Direction
so like okay so it was shown 1992 these
two things are actually equal um so the
easier direction to show is that IP is
in ppace um the way you kind of do that
is by sort of simulating all possible
like transcripts and then you can do
some counting stuff we won't go into
details um but in 1992 it was shown the
other direction also held so this is by
Shamir in
[Applause]
1992 so in fact ppace is also in IP
which means that um these two classes
are actually equal um and to do this he
constructed a like a interactive proof
for all any pbas computation um and that
would give you the
inclusion okay so in particular this
means that
um any
pspace
computation has interactive
[Applause]
proof okay so going back to like the
concept of Delegation which is what this
class is entirely about right like how
do you you know delegate a computation
to like a bigger approver while you can
run very quickly well this is delegation
right okay um like it's basically like
you know I want to compute some like
small space computation like PO space
you know and I can like ask the cloud
hey can you run like awesome like should
your interactive proof for me and just
tell me you know like prove to me that
you know you did it correctly and
they're good right okay um so what's the
issue like why why aren't we done like
why did why are all the why did DKR at
all um the reason is because here the
pro a
runtime is 2 to the s
s right so like
um so in ppace like any competion is
doable in time two to the S but here's
this additional like so this is like s
to squar this like is like basically the
time to prove is much more than the time
necessary to Simply compute um which is
why there's all these follow-ups works
and why this is actually so an
interesting question today um okay and
there's some follow-up work U I don't
know the reference and Y didn't either
and I don't know if her memory is wrong
either so it could be wrong it could be
true so it's a possible statement um
okay so it's possible that there's a
followup work that showed how to have a
Prov a runtime of 2 to the S log s which
is like significantly better than 2 to S
squ but it's you know it's still not two
to the S which would be kind of the best
you could hope for for any arbitrary
pbas
computation um so today what we're going
to show
is okay so today the theorem is going to
be as follows um so assuming gkr which
is an unconditional statement so it's
not an assumption it's just this is what
we're going to use in the proof um so
since we have gkr um we can get
IP equals
[Applause]
pspace um with uh
time 2 to the I should probably write
poly 2 to the
[Applause]
S
pro right so okay so what this means is
like so for like maybe the hardest P
computations um assuming that I guess
the hardest things you can do is time CH
to the S then we do have actually
efficient um delegation protocols for
these things and they're in fact also
proof systems so they are like
information theoretically secure um and
maybe I just mentioned like one open
question is what about General time t
space um space computation
so where T is not necess cly s um can
you
do an interactive proof um um a
[Applause]
sufficient I think this is not
known so if you want to think about some
proof systems this is a question you
think about
um let's see are you guys okay about
races this is probably fine right okay
here efficient just like poly yeah poity
yeah and you definitely ask more like
even like stronger questions like can
you do it with like you know linear time
overhead like you know additive whatever
overhead um yeah there's many
questions okay so how do we describe a
uh peace based computation um someone
said that it's a space of all
computations that are doable by like a
touring machine with founded space so
let's say that we have our touring
machine
M and let say it runs in space
s
um and maybe could they on
input 01 to the N okay and maybe that's
the thing we want is
um and maybe we can just say time um and
also
time T unless I just St 2 to the S just
for now okay so let's say that maybe we
have a turning machine and we want to
see that within time T which is two to
the s that eventually it will get to the
like output like the accepting
configuration or not um
so so by this point I
should um get
to accepting configuration
okay
so so here's sort of the trick the idea
here we're going to use GK gkr to prove
the theorem so we're going to have to
construct some circuit to delegate you
know some habitation with gkr with
um so this training machine here it runs
in space s can run timing up to 2 to the
S right so if you notely do this it get
depth 2 to the s c good that's not so
good we want to really be
deps okay so okay so think that down so
the goal is to
[Applause]
convert um to
depths
[Applause]
s has a goal um so here's a trick um the
trick is as follows we're going to look
at the transition Matrix of all the
possible um states of the of the CH tape
basically so um so we're going to have a
bunch of different possible States here
and a bunch of different possible States
here um so how many possible states are
there well there is 0 one to the S
because that's what the state could
actually say on the tape right but
that's also where the cheering machine
is right now so
maybe times the index and S2 to say
where the cheering machine is right now
and then you know it'll do like one
computation move somewhere and then
it'll be like an adjacent place at a
different state and then now the new
state will be like a slightly different
string and it'll be the ter like pointer
will be at different
location so so here's also be the same
[Applause]
States okay and the point is we're going
to
put a one at a location if there a way
to get from this state here to this
state here in one time
step um and zero everywhere else yeah
does the state include like the internal
like
automaton um yes that's a good point
it's actually very good yeah there
should only be like one one in each
row yeah there should be one one in
every row because the the thing you are
going to do after one time step should
be deterministic based on your current
like sort of location or your state
based on your Turing like so your
internal state of your touring machine
as well as what you see around
you so I'm using this as just like those
number of states in the touring machine
um anything else I'm forgetting was in
these states there's just like a bunch
of information that I don't
remember okay so anyway so I guess like
the the key Point here is that this
Matrix is actually very easy to compute
right because given like like maybe a
state here and like a state here you can
like sort of compare very in very low
depth very efficiently so this a very
uniform description of this check that
or the circuit that will generate
whether or not um the particular
corresponding Matrix value is zero or
one that would be important for us
because we want this like add a like we
want we want a uniform circuit I guess
point and this will make it
uniform PR St yeah okay so the Matrix
here is easy to compute is my claim the
reason is you can take any St here any
state here you can do some checks it's a
very a small like formula you can kind
of just check it very easily by knowing
what m is by knowing what you kind of
see you can tell if there's a transition
from that to the next state so the
Matrix here is easy to compute is my
claim
[Applause]
yeah um
okay so maybe let's call this Matrix
a so what I just said is that a i j this
is going to be like the I row and the
J's column and tree of a this is going
to be uh one if theate I goes to AJ in
one time step so
[Applause]
okay and so that's good right um what we
really want to know
is whether I will go to J or like the
starting configuration will go to the
accepting configuration in t time steps
that's what we
want
um for
okay so here we have a copy of a so okay
so okay yeah so we okay so we want to
find what um yeah okay so we want to
let's look maybe let's just do some
computations just for it fun and see
what happens so you have a copy of
Matrix a here copy of Matrix a here
let's multiply them VI have matrix
multiplication um so we have a squ
um what is the value of the entry in the
I row and the J's column of a
squ yeah so I guess right here actually
[Applause]
so so a s um the IJ entry of a squ
is whether I goes to J in two
steps um and maybe for those of you who
haven't seen this before let's just do
it um so you see
why so if you want to look at the ice St
entry of this product of these two
matrices what you want to do is you want
to take the ice row look at all the
entries across it take the J's column
look at all the entries down it and you
want to take like sort of the pair wise
like you want to take the product and
sum so you want to take like this entry
times this entry this entry time this
entry and so on so what's essentially
happening is here you want to take like
U you want to look at the entry um
corresponding you're going from I to K
and then you go from K to l k to
J um and then you do this for k equal 2
also you do it like can you go from I to
K and then you'll do it um from K to J
and so the final entry will some of all
of this these products will be one if
and only if there is a way to go from I
to sum K to J and two types
of okay or I don't know
okay okay so in general then if we want
to look at the transition Matrix of
having after going for T time steps you
kind of keep doing this right and you
get that the 's entry of a to the t's
power
is whether I goes to
[Applause]
J yeah so here H give you like whether I
exactly ke step like no more no less
yeah okay that's a good point um so
maybe we can say this should be an
exactly T time steps and maybe you can
have your touring machine like kind of
stay as accepting configuration already
reached it maybe for instance that's one
thing you could do another way you could
do it is you could have you could change
this Matrix as it's a one along the
diagonal so that you can always like
kind of waste time if you want okay but
whatever version you want is fine just
yeah maybe let's say for now after
exactly T time steps I should reach the
accepting configuration and just have it
Sol accepting
place
okay yeah okay so the point is if we can
compute what a of the input
configuration comma the accepting
configur ation is we'll know if um this
pbas computation is accepting or not
that
good
so so what we want
[Applause]
is okay so we're going to write a
circuit to compute this
um is it okay if I'm very like loose
about this I like I just feel like all
these things about like exactly how
everything Changs up is just terrible
like it's I don't know
um okay so I guess like one thing you
could do is you could just compute a and
then a squ then a cubed and a to the 4th
this is not so good right you're going
to do it for T times your cir speed
depth T okay so what should we do
instead
squaring great okay yay
[Applause]
um okay so the idea is we can compute
this Matrix
a so this is going to be like very easy
to compute because we I we talked a
little bit about how every like entry of
this Matrix is like you can compute it
very easily kind of just by looking at
what the two configurations are that
you're interested
in and then you can compute a squ
from this I just like I guess you
doation
multiplication and then we can do H to
the fourth a to the E and so on um
eventually we'll get to a to the T which
I don't have room
for so this is going to be our Matrix or
our
circuit okay let's look at the depths um
what's the depth of the
circuit okay so it's like log T is wait
but each like thing yeah okay times
something
um like don't you have to
do if like you have to add
up but you can make it a binary tree so
that will have
okay you can say po s it's probably like
log T times like polys
anyway okay so that's pretty good um
means that a verifier when running this
computation with theover in gkr the
scales of the depth depth is not only
polys right what's the size of circuit
[Applause]
yeah so I guess the Matrix itself is
going to be size two to S right or
something time two s yeah two s two to
the
s s 2s so yeah um
yeah
okay okay so if we apply gkr to this um
would be good so let's um let's run
gkr oh and I should proba also say at
the very top we need to then like look
at the input State and then check the
corresponding entry so you want to read
like this particular entry maybe but you
can sort of read it by doing some sort
of like pretty small like computation on
what the input in accepting comparations
are okay so let's run gkr
uh okay so prove a run
[Applause]
time
y
verify yay
okay I guess that's what we wanted to
prove huh okay nice good work um are
there any questions about this or do
this like make sense yeah sorry I might
have missed an important point but like
where is the cost of like actually doing
the
squaring um I guess sort of like the
depth of circuit is sort of like each
Square you do is going to take some more
depths to your circuit yeah that what
you're saying yeah yeah that's the
question oh maybe I didn't understand
the question oh as in like what is the
cost of squaring a like just going from
a to a squ what's the cost sure yeah so
how do you compute a
square you can kind of do every row and
every column and then like mly and add
them so oh in like you're just doing
like you're doing compation I see um so
maybe you can tell me
how supposed to know how that um thing
that you said we need to prove to you
are we supposed to know oh yeah that's a
great question oh yeah so so okay
earlier I already it I
think are any questions about this
before we go to
that um you can't use
IP um or you're allow to use a logic we
just had okay yeah so how do we how do
we construct this
oh so that's reason need
L yeah okay so this is basically a scale
down version of that right this is log
space usern form so you're running in
log space there you're running in times
like space s so this is a exponentially
smaller version of that take all the
parameters over there and you scale them
down so we had a depth over here was po
s the log of that is like log s right
the log of the size here is s so we have
all the things we
wanted
do how do you incorporate the input into
like you need to know what the starting
state is uh was this one or was the
IP um the input State yeah yeah so I
think the way I normally think or I like
to think about it is you only check the
input configuration at the very end once
you competed entire thing so then you
only have to read like the input comma
accepting configurations entry and there
you can just kind of like do like a a
formula like read off what it says and
then look at the corresponding
value that's great so like almost the
entire circuit is just like doesn't even
read the yeah it's only the very
end but I mean this is for accepting
that
accept yeah
um yeah yeah okay so
maybe yeah so I guess like each each
configuration corresponds to like it's a
configuration right so there's like some
like data about like what the gates
output like gate value is or something
andbe you can read off the the value
there each like input comma
is this like an easy situation
right yeah important Point here is that
check like Computing The Matrix a is
very easy that's really the key thing
here um and that's also why um when we
said what we were put behind but when we
said what um a looks like it really had
to be like also where the touring like
pointer was right if you didn't know
where the pointer was you it could be
very large
yeah okay uh so
wa you can like factor out uh what
you're saying into the form of like if
you have a low space computation you can
turn into a low dead circuit is that a
is that a fair you
used yeah it's actually a kind of
interesting statement huh I don't know I
didn't know that this you could do this
in recently
either um so I guess like the the
interesting thing here is instead of
being like a really tall and skinny
computation you can turn it into a
circuit that's really fat and like kind
of short
that's why we're getting
qu wait sorry okay just in terms of like
where we're at in class so we just
proved this theem and is this like the
same reasoning for why the law toity
thing works out too why this thing works
oh you tell
me you tell me I'm delegating the
it's kind of weird right because you you
don't actually take a as input a is like
kind of like hardcoded into the circuit
right like that's why like the input can
still be like the small thing that's
just describing the stting state yeah
like the the turning machine m is sort
of what the term of the circuit actually
looks like so maybe as part of the input
of this you're also going to have a
description like the turning machine
entirety turning machines are like you
know finite size so it doesn't matter
and then
you and that's why we don't need to
worry about complicated
actually just looks like
this I'm still kind of weirded out by
the fact that like all of that up until
the star at the top all of this is like
not even dependent on the input so it's
like in this case it's just going to be
constants like zero than one so then
like why are we go through the trouble
of like Computing all layers instead of
just like using the top layer we like
yeah I mean how do you how do you hold
the top
layer so you're saying that like it's
easier to encode the entire computation
thing than just the result it's easy to
say what you have to do to compute it
than to actually computed
representation but I'm thinking like why
don't you death hard cod in the top
layer well it's just I mean it's just a
string of like size
of you
can't weird I
so we basically went through this
trouble and we're able to go through
this trouble because we assume that c
can be described succinctly like long
space
suly yeah is po
uni I'm going to delate like question
somebody else I don't know how like log
blows
up probably not right because if you if
you take like the transition Matrix a
you have is going to be two to the
description size or whatever like the
space right so if you have like larger
Space is really
bad but like
space um yeah so we
have
um yeah but then the question is the pro
a runtime
right the reason why we're doing any of
this is because of prove a run time you
get you actually get an advantage in the
prove a run time
uh so we're done early um so maybe we
can all go get some corn and
[Applause]