I'd like to welcome everyone. My name is
Rayvon Gardner Williams and I serve as
an admissions officer here at MIT Sloan
School of Management. I'm excited about
the opportunity to host tonight's panel
discussion with a dynamic group of Sloan
who will introduce themselves shortly.
First and foremost, when we are doing
any presentations, we feel that it is
mission critical um for us to start off
each presentation highlighting the fact
that MIT Sloan is indeed a missiondriven
school. Um everything that we do comes
back to our mission and that's to
develop principal innovative leaders who
improve the world and generate ideas
that advance management practices. Um
this desire for our students to make an
impact is central to not only the MIT
Sloan experience but the broader MIT
experience as well. Um we are seeking
out students um who are missiondriven
and students who have a history of
leadership and impact who have the
ability to work with others and think
and act innovatively. With that being
said, I'm sure you are all probably
tired of hearing from me. Um so with
that being said, we're going to
transition to our panelists and have
them all introduce themselves in the
order in which they appear on the
screen. Um, I'm going to go on mute and
then if we can have Manuel start us off
and I'll jump back on shortly after we
conclude introductions.
>> Hi, thanks very much for that, Rayon.
Uh, my name is Manny Montes and I am the
director of procurement for Lineage
Logistics for now Lineage.
>> Hey y'all, my name is Alexa Katz. I am a
manager at Deote where I'm a consultant.
Um I was in uh NBA 2024 and had returned
to Deote after um or sorry I was at
Deote before Sloan and had returned um
just about uh almost a year ago.
>> Hi all. Uh I'm Brian Silverman,
classmates with uh two of these fine
folks on this call. Um since leaving
Sloan uh I've been working at Desire on
the finance team. Desire is a renewable
energy firm. We're a owner, operator,
developer of utility scale renewable
energy projects. And prior to Sloan, I
spent most of my career as an army
officer. So happy to talk about pivots
with anyone on this call.
>> Uh and I'm Jose. I was also um a Harvard
like MIT Sloan class 24. Um I was
actually part of the uh early admission
program which I applied to when I was a
senior at Harvard and then um that gave
me time to start a a company which I'm
still like working on called Zeta
Surgical. Um and I'm also in parallel to
the company I'm doing a PhD right now in
neuroscience at Cambridge.
>> Awesome. And then I'm also joined by a
colleague Morgan who's on the back end
answering any other questions that you
all may have. Uh Morgan, if you want to
just jump on and say hi really quickly.
>> Hi everyone. Thanks for joining
tonight's session. Really excited to uh
answer your all's questions and feel
free to answer or rather ask questions
throughout the session. Um I will be
highlighting some to answer live uh by
the panelists at the end. So uh feel
free. Thanks for joining.
>> Awesome. Thank you for that Morgan. Um
we're going to just jump right into
questions for our panelists and we uh
curated a few questions that we received
prior to the start of the session. Um so
I'll go ahead and get started with the
first one. Um out of curiosity um one of
our our attendees was wondering what
types of events does MIT Sloan have for
LGBTQ
uh plus MBA students?
Rayvon, do you want just any one of us
to take this or do you want to
>> Sure. This can be for anyone.
>> Um, sure. I'm I'm happy to start. Uh,
there's a couple marquee events, I
think. Um, one thing to highlight
MITwide
is the concept of a C function, a
cultural function. This is where every
club on campus
um, basically has a big sort of party.
Uh, the Sloan Pride one is, I think, one
of the more popular events. Alexa, maybe
you could speak to this. I think you
might have actually helped organize it.
Um, but, uh, so big event, super fun,
super popular across the organization.
And then the other one to highlight is
every year
um the whole crew would make their way
out to Petown
um and spend a weekend out there which
was really great. Honestly, some of my
more fond memories uh of time spent with
classmates just kind of getting away
from campus and and getting to know one
another um in a different setting.
>> Yeah. And I I'll pile on there. I love
in general at Sloan. There's a ton of
opportunities for travel obviously
internationally, but some of I think my
fondest memories are the ones that are
closer to home and having access from
Boston to a ton of nature. Um there's a
big uh usually like a big fall retreat
that we take um up in just like renting
a cabin out in New Hampshire or in
Maine. Um, and I think that was really
where I met most of my friends that were
in Pride because it was early on in the
school year and we had a chance to just
like buckle down like cooking at home um
and just having a good time um you know
out in a place that's not necessarily
right on campus. So that was definitely
a highlight for me. And then definitely
echo the C functions across the board
are super fun. I think definitely the
pride ca function is one of the most
attended and most memorable. I believe
we did a drag uh the first year, our
first year. Is that right, Brian? Um we
had a ton of classmates including mostly
allies honestly uh that were performing
on stage. We had this awesome venue and
it was just a lot of fun. So definitely
a lot of opportunities whether you're
into like smaller group settings. Um
there's also uh we did a lot of smaller
dinner groups or game nights and things
like that. Um, or if you're more into
like the big party settings, there's
opportunities uh for that as well.
>> Was there Manny? Did either of you want
to chime in?
>> Yeah. And I think agree with what was
said.
>> Awesome. Um, so I think that actually
segus perfectly into the next question
um, we got was what are ways that the
Sloan Pride um, club collaborates with
other clubs across uh, Sloan and MIT
and this can be for anyone.
>> Yeah, just I'll I'll start here as well
just because the the C function was a
good example of this. Um, right. Like I
probably split my time at Sloan between
three main clubs. Like I was in the
sustainability like energy club, um,
pride and then the vets club. And when
we were doing our C function, which like
Alexa was mentioning, it was big drag
show and like a giant club with mostly
uh, allies performing. like there were I
think two or three Sloan veteran club
like um you know squads that were up
there performing
uh and the fact that like the the vets
club is performing at the C function
um and was like h we were having events
together all the time right like I think
that just speaks to um I mean I guess
I'm I'm sort of alluding to some maybe
implicit expectations about how those
clubs might relate to each other. But
what I'm trying to say is that they
absolutely don't exist. The pride club
was super integrated with every other
organization on campus and over
overwhelmingly just could not have been
a more uh sort of welcoming and and uh
um you know equal environment.
One of I think if you asked most people
that I knew in our class like what my
brand was at Sloan, they would probably
would say beer. Um I started and led our
our beer club. And one of my favorite
events that I hosted was a collab with
Pride. We had uh we went out to
Dorchester to um a gay-owned brewery,
Dorchester Brewing Co. Um the owner is
fantastic. He is just like such a
wonderful human. Um and then brought in
the LGBTQ historical society. I'm
forgetting their name right now. Um but
they document and preserve basically
like Boston and New England LGBTQ his
LGBTQ history. Um so we had an awesome
presentation from that organization and
a presentation from the the owner
himself at this brewery and just a
chance for like everyone to chat. So, it
was a really cool way to like bring beer
people into like the queer space and
bring queer people into a beer space,
which is like two aspects of my identity
and my hobbies that I really enjoy. So,
um that was definitely a collaborative
memory of mine.
>> Alexa, you touched on a really great
point about just being able to utilize
not only Cambridge, but the the larger
Boston community as as as you leverage
your NBA experience. Um, so I was
wondering if anybody else could, Alexa,
maybe you can add on to this as well.
Um, describe the broader LGBTQ community
in Boston and Cambridge, um, and how it
relates to Sloan students. You provided
a great example, so I'm wondering if
there might be other examples that, um,
others might be able to offer or if you
want to maybe further elaborate on, um,
how that came to be.
I feel bad for keep that I keep talking
so other people please jump in. Um, I
think for that event specifically, it
honestly I think one of my favorite
parts about Boston is that it's truly
such a curious city and so obviously so
many top tier universities. So a lot of
thinkers and doers and just people who
are open to collaboration and so I and
with your MIT email address, you can
honestly like cold email people and they
answer which is amazing. So, I just cold
out like did cold outreach to a bunch of
different types of of organizations or
groups and everyone was very excited
about collaborating um and speaking to
students. And I think in general that is
very true across the board, not only
like in the queer community, but also
there's a you know the entrepreneurial
ecosystem is obviously huge, which is
great in terms of um and people are
super open in terms of like recruiting
if that's something that you're
interested in. Um, but there's always
people that are willing to take your
call. And so finding this organization
that had, you know, coming I live in New
York now and obviously like I feel like
there's so much documented history from
like Stonewall. Um, and that's something
that is very accessible. But coming to
Boston, I was like, what is the queer
community like here? It's not as big.
Like let's let's just be clear. It's
like definitely doesn't feel as
in-your-face as other maybe more
queercentric cities, but that's not to
say that there's not a ton of resources
available. And so, as part of this
event, we learned about the history and
historic taverns, many of which have now
closed, unfortunately. Um, but just
being able to hear some video testimony
and take a tour through some of, you
know, Boston's queer history was really
memorable.
>> Yeah. I would say too, I mean I've been
so I'm originally from Spain, but I
moved to um Boston 2014. So I've been
here like for like 11 years and for you
know uh college and then business school
and working like um in between and sort
of during during that time but um yeah I
would say I would say that like of
course like you know especially recently
with like Trump administration not to
get too political but obviously there
seems to be a lot of um um you know sort
of slashing DI programs kind of things.
I've in 11 years Boston has been the
most liberal like gay friendly like city
I've ever lived in. Um uh you know and
Barcelona is very very liberal as well.
Um, again, you know, I think like um as
as Alexa was saying, I think it's
definitely much smaller than than other
um other other cities just like also in
general, but it's kind of like a little
bit of a quirky um like there's a lot of
people here for you know in school um
like you know working in healthcare like
in the big universities and everything
and um yeah I mean I was I just just
remembering like this um this article I
I that I think like again from my
undergrad things that they published in
this um like Harvard like um parody
thing parody journal saying that four
out of three Harvard undergrads were
gay. So I think it's uh you know um
definitely definitely very um you know
definitely care friendly place to to
live in and I think you know from my
personal experience I um you know joined
Sloan with like a very specific like
purpose which was really to get more of
like a business background because my
background in undergrad was um in
molecular biology and I did I mean as
the company was sort of like growing
more and um actually you know starting
to raise like larger rounds of funding.
and it's still pretty early but like uh
selling the system and all this kind of
stuff. Um I think you know I really
wanted to do that and I had this early
admission like um in in there. So I um
you know spent most I mean I was kind of
like working like really full-time
during during during my time at Sloan
which is not not recommend but I think
Sloan is very I think people are doing
each person has their own thing going on
and um I thought it was great great for
that but um uh yeah I thought it was
like a really great experience and up um
you know really getting getting what I
what I want out of that but maybe was a
little less participating a a little bit
less in the in the events that Alex and
and Brian were mentioning.
>> Awesome. Um, the next question I have
is, um, how did you find community
amongst other LGBTQ,
uh, people at Sloan, both inside and
outside the classroom, um, and student
clubs?
I think obviously the the pride salon
pride um for me was obviously like the
biggest community hub. Um
but not everyone was super involved the
whole time nor do you have to be. I mean
I think there's so many I love that
there's so many different types of
events. I was talking about them a
little bit before in terms of, you know,
folks who are tilted more towards
wanting to have smaller group hangs, um,
dinners, game nights, and things like
that or study groups. Um, and then those
who are more tilted towards wanting to
go on trips or to travel and and, you
know, go to parties, like there's it
really runs the spectrum. But I think
even just going to a couple um events or
meetings, you then have a familiar face
that you see in the classroom and maybe
you didn't have a chance to chat with
that person at the event, but you see
their face, you sit near them and then
you have a friend. Um and I think that's
true throughout your time at Sloan. will
find I mean you all the all the alums
that you talk to are going to you know
just go on and on about like the people
because it's true like you honestly can
meet someone one time they'll remember
your story and then you'll sit with them
in class and become actual friends with
them. So I think for me Sloan Pride was
definitely the the place um but I'm sure
other folks had different ways of
building community and sometimes you
find it in places that you don't expect
as well.
Anybody else want to chime in?
All right. Um, the next question that we
got uh from somebody that's joining us
this evening was, "What aspects of
Sloan's culture stood out to you the
most when you first joined, and how have
they shaped your experience both inside
and outside the classroom?
Yeah, I can talk a little bit about
about this because I mean sort of not
not speaking directly about like um you
know LGBT community but just like more
generally just my my own experience I
thought like um you know something I
really liked about Sloan I think is that
it's um I mean obviously from an acade
from an academic perspective like MIT
Sloan is like absolutely one of the best
um research um like you know like
programs in the in the in the world that
check like Nobel laureates receiving
Nobel Nobel Prize in economics. I mean
Sloan is consistently a place where
there's um you know like um Lorettz like
basically very frequently. I was kind of
interested in like you know like getting
a learning more about financial
economics and I really found that um you
know I was very interesting like being
able to take classes with um you know
really world experts. I mean there's um
like Merton for example teaches a class
on on on options which is obviously like
from BSM and it's it's a really really
special experience to to be able to that
or um Andrew Lo there's just like a lot
of very you know um important faculty I
think at Sloan that like uh teach MBA
students and um some so I really like
kind of like the very you know like I
mean I think I remember during my first
week or something at Sloan for the
orientation they were asking like what
do you want to get out of your program
and my classmates each person has their
own thing like for many people it's also
just like meeting new people or like
something like that. I think for me it
was very much like the class I want to
take and sort of like learning that was
sort of like maybe less typical I think
for for many many students. Um and I
thought that like the quality of like
teaching and um the ability of course
registering with other classes and sort
of the fact that like after the first
term you're basically free to take
pretty much any class you want for the
for the last two semesters I thought was
um spectacular and uh I was you know I I
felt I was learning a ton from seme
semester and um you know I basically
yeah I mean when went from really having
absolutely no background in in in
finance and finishing doing like a like
a finance track and taking classes that
were kind of like the the the hardest
class I could take at least at that
point. So, I thought that was like
really really great and um you know
absolutely would definitely go again if
if um if I was back back in 2022.
>> Always excited to hear an alum say
they'd like to come back if they if
they're the opportunity presented
itself. Um it makes what I feel every
single day that much more realistic um
whenever I step foot on campus. Uh
Manny, it looked like you were going to
come off mute. Did you want to say
something?
Yeah. Uh my experience is completely
different from every other panelists
here because I was part of the COVID
cohort uh from 2020 2021. So none of the
things that any of the panelists have
mentioned were available to us.
Unfortunately, because of the pandemic,
MIT did not feel like it would be safe
to, you know, have people in large
groups for obvious reasons. So all of
the infrastructure that everyone
mentioned um which is MIT essentially
creates for students to plug themselves
into was non-existent and so that meant
that we had to create it ourselves and
so I think from that perspective the
real test comes out right you put all
these people in the room and you want to
say okay what's what makes it special
what makes them all special uh
particularly when you don't have the
institutional backing of the institute
Right. Um, and so I am happy to say that
um,
if we're going to answer the question of
what sort of qualities did we see in
Sloan come out immediately, I would say
it was the ability of other people to
see what others before see in you what
others before would not see or could not
see. and then equipping you with the
tools to go out into the world and bring
that version of yourself to a broader
audience.
>> I really appreciate that answer. Um it's
funny. I actually started working um at
Sloan as we were phasing out of the
pandemic and to see just the the
differences from students experiences is
always um interesting to hear how they
were able to make that time during the
pandemic their own. Um, so definitely
appreciate that insight. Um, the next
question that we have before we
transition to the Q&A from our audience,
um, is how does MIT Sloan actively
integrate diversity and inclusion into
team-based projects or the classroom
experience beyond formal statements?
>> I think what I appreciated was the way
that this was done in a really natural
way. It wasn't like the forced DEI day
where you know it's just one day of the
year and you have to teach a specific
curriculum. Like I truly felt like it
was it was integrated into the cases
that we were learning into especially in
like our uh one of the core classes that
you take as an MBA in the fall
organizational processes. Um, I just
feel like the
some like so many of the lessons and so
many of the like business context were
so naturally incorporated into that
class in a way that felt natural and not
forced. Um, so I think that's that's one
thing. And then there's of course
there's intentional days as well where
there is more discussion around um
certain topics. Um, but I think part of
what I really liked about the program
was that it didn't feel like it was just
checking a box. Like it felt natural.
Thank you for that, Alexa. Um, Morgan, I
know we I can see on my screen that we
have a number of questions in the chat.
Um, so I want to spend the time now to
transition to um, questions that we
receive from anybody that's joining us
this evening.
>> Absolutely. Thank you, Rayvon, for
passing. Um, we do have some great
questions in the Q&A, so again feel free
to keep asking them. Um, we wanted to or
some folks in the chat are asking about
SOS or significant others, partners who
they're bringing to MIT. Um, were you
able to bring your partner into any
events or communities that you were part
of at MIT? Um, and how was your
experience?
>> Take it away, Manny.
>> Um, so there's there's a special sort of
um, so I'm in a Sloan Fellow MBA, right?
And the Sloan Fellows, as you saw in the
initial slide, there's a 12-month
residential program as opposed to like a
two-year standard MBA program. Um, a lot
of the two-year MBAs um, are still
single Pringles, right? as we like to
say. So they're not all not all of them
have their significant others yet. Some
of them do, right? It's a broad
spectrum. All the Sloan fellows pretty
much everybody brings their significant
other. Everybody. And so for me it was
interesting because I was like well I
have my husband right and he's here and
you know he makes empanadas and uh we
have a great place to welcome everybody
in. And um I am proud to say that um
during one of the activities that we
were able to have with Sloan, we had the
uh SFMBA Olympics, the virtual Olympics.
And um my husband won he so he is the
like only time in history Sloanfell FNBA
virtual Olympics winner and he is a gay
engineer from Argentina. So I'm going to
think that pretty much says it all when
it comes to Sloan.
Yeah. I mean, um I I I guess like really
um had just started dating my uh my
partner like shortly before Sloan and
then, you know, we were together all all
through the program and still are. Um
but like I would just add on to say that
um yeah, there's absolutely no barrier
at all. There's uh uh I would say every
organization, every social event is like
totally welcoming to plus ones. And
honestly, you know, a half the time uh
he was more popular than I was. So
there's no um
no limitations whatsoever.
>> I would jump on I just want to build on
that the point that Brian made about
your significant other being more
popular than you. Um, that was the case
in my case too. Sergio was way more
popular. Whenever people sort of had the
two of us in a room, they would always
go to him. And so it made you think made
you much more self-aware of yourself,
right? Which is an important thing that
we learn in Sloan. Um, but it also uh is
interesting, right? Because everybody
says, "Oh, well, you know, Sloan is
going to be transformed. It will be a
transformation for you." And it most
definitely is. However, the thing that
nobody says is that it is also a
transformation for your significant
other. When my when we started out, my
husband was, you know, more quiet than I
was. By the end, he was entertaining,
you know, houses full of people,
engaging with people much more. And so,
I think for me, that was one of the most
sort of amazing aspects of the program.
I wasn't just the one impacted. My
husband was too.
We do have some more questions if we
want to continue from the chat. Um I
also I know I not a panelist and you
don't want to hear from me but we do
have um significant others or so um
group group chats or WhatsApp chats. Um
so it is also like a formalized um
community. So, not only of course are
they welcome at any events um but we
also really do try to integrate folks
into the sun culture um and any events
that they're interested in. Um one great
question we had was are there
opportunities for LGBT related community
service in the area or volunteer
opportunities uh through onampus groups?
I'm trying to think about this. I no
immediate experience comes to mind.
Maybe that's just because I missed it or
or didn't participate, but maybe this is
an opportunity to highlight that just
for all organizations on on Sloan's
campus. um just like the curriculum is
uh is structured, it's really a build
your own adventure type place. So there
are resources available for you know if
if creating more opportunities for
community service is something that
you're interested in. There's absolutely
funding and um organizational support to
do that. Uh, and I know for a fact that
there are ample opportunities to get
involved in the community in Boston. I
just have to confess that I I wasn't
particularly involved myself.
Yeah, I I think um in terms of
specifically about you know um LGBT
related uh community service, I'm also
like not that familiar about that. But
um I mean I I like the reason I actually
wanted to really go to business school
was actually because of uh interesting
global health and sort of like seeing
the the ability of um you know my my
background was really sort of like in
research. I mean I was in the same
research lab for you know four years and
now I'm kind of doing PhD because I want
to go go to academia after this company
again. But um uh global health I think
was kind of like what got me interested
in sort of like seeing how
transformative sort of the impact of um
you know technology and like building a
company can be in the sense of going
from like coming up with the idea to
actually um developing it and and spend
some time like around like half a year
in in very rural part of Western Kenya
and working with um with a group of MGH.
So um Boston is a really good place for
if you're interested in just generally
like global health community service
there's like you know mass MGH Brigamin
Women's Hospital Beth Israel three
massive hospitals Dana Farber you have
Harvard has in like Harvard MIT have
like incredible programs doing you know
a lot of global health like developing
technologies for deployments in
developing countries and others and um
there's a ton of opportunities of
collaborating with groups doing this
kind of uh this kind of work. So, I'm
like completely sure that like if you're
looking to do um tackle any specific you
know like more LGBTQ maybe like um
related um you know line of like
research or others there's probably like
a million different groups tackling this
from like a more you know research like
um you know volunteering any kind of
aspect. So it's a really good place to
do this kind of work if um if that's
what you would want to do.
Manny, I think you had your hand raised.
You wanted to say something?
>> Yeah. As a uh was born and raised in
Boston, so I've got a pretty sort of
familiarity of like what sort of groups
are out there for LGBT the LGBTQ plus
community. Um but um Jose and Brian I
think covered pretty broad spectrum in
that regard. you just add my experience
uh during the pandemic. I was also able
to see you know if you wanted to start
something on your own um for whatever
initiative there definitely was there
definitely was the infrastructural
backing support and funding for those
students who wanted to do that. So there
was nothing sort of stopping you from
starting your own thing because you may
have identified a
>> and I'll just add really quickly before
Morgan shares the next question that
still is the case. um you'll find that
MIT Sloan is a very much say yes kind of
environment and I'm sure our students
will will echo this. Um if you have a
rhyme or reason for why you want to do
something um if you can galvanize your
peers to come and help you um whether it
be through the student life office, the
program office, they're more than happy
to allow you to tailor your experience
to accomplish whatever it is that you
are hoping to accomplish um during the
time period that you're with us.
Morgan, the floor is all yours. Awesome.
Love it. Um, we do have more questions,
so please keep them coming, folks, in
the Q&A. Um, now we definitely heard
about quite a few C functions and I'd
love to hear about that Ptown trip. Um,
but this is a great question leading on
to that. What's your best memory in the
program so far?
I want Brian to go first.
>> Question.
>> Yeah, go Alexa, go ahead. I've been
yacking for a while, so
>> No, no, no. Go ahead, Manny. I was just
going to call out Brian, but
>> Okay. Well, it's that's pretty dangerous
question. Um, and you can answer it in a
number of ways. Um, oh, I know. So, we
had uh the the pandemic, right? And so
we didn't have our MIT graduation until
a year later. And so during our year, we
said we're going to sort of hold our own
graduation. And we did. And my favorite
moment from the year um didn't actually
involve me, but involved a it's a photo
um because um uh because we were putting
on this, you know, graduation virtually.
Um there was a sort of speakers room
right in the the venue where we held it.
And um one of the speakers was Stella
Machello and she is a Sloan fellow 2021
from Mosamb beek and she's the closest
thing anyone will ever come to meeting
an actual saint. It's amazing. She's an
amazing person. She's coming to my house
this weekend on her way to Mosambique to
visit her mother. And um the moment I'm
talking about is this very quick photo I
snapped her as she was reading off the
teleprompter here uh her speech for this
graduation. and my husband was holding
up the teleprompter to make it easier
for her to read. And to me, that
encapsulates so much of what um Sloan is
about. It's about putting yourself to
the side and focusing on the task at
hand and doing what you need to do to
get that accomplished.
I I'll I'll jump in with a couple more.
I mean, there's like there's too many
great memories to count. Like honestly,
my two years at Sloan were probably like
the most enjoyable, happiest two years
of my adult life. Like
um
but I'll give a couple of examples. One,
like sort of just routine is, you know,
I loved um just hosting classmates while
I was at Sloan. Like I love to cook,
love to throw a dinner party, love to
throw a party in in the apartment,
whatever. Um, and every year, like this
is just a good example of how nice of a
place Boston, and I lived in Somerville,
um, is to live, but every year there's a
thing called PorchFest where all of
Somerville, uh, you know, camps out on
their front porches. It's all these like
triple triple-decker houses with with
big uh big decks and people play music.
And so I would open up my apartment,
have a million people come through, cook
a ton of food. Um, and that is just like
encapsulates a memory of, you know, how
tight the community was, like how good
of friends I was able to make during
those two years at Sloan. Just a great
time. Then another one is um Alexa and I
did one of these together, but uh
actually both years I went on study
tours um which are subsidized uh
programs for which you get academic
credit as well. um where you travel to
typically a a set of a couple of
different countries. So the first year I
went to Japan and Vietnam and the second
year I went all over Scandinavia. The
first one was more global trade
oriented. The second was more
sustainability oriented. Um and those
were just incredible experiences that I
never would have had were it not for
being um in the NBA program at Sloan. um
just to learn, to spend time with
classmates, to learn about them, and to
have these incredible uh sort of
tailored experiences abroad, learning
about, you know, business context, uh
cultural cultural context, and um you
know, all all manner of things, just uh
really really unbelievable experiences.
I was hoping Brian was going to say this
study tour or else I would have been
really disappointed because um I led
that study tour and we had such a great
time. Um and I think like on on the
organizing front it was just so
incredible to kind of like get a peak
behind the curtain in the like working
with administration and the program
office to like put on a curriculum for
half the semester. Um, so like we we
built a syllabus, we brought in guest
speakers, we taught a class, and then we
got to do this two-eek trip during
spring break where we got to meet with
um different companies and organizations
that we had um been learning about and
got a s just got a chance to actually
like see what they were doing and bring
back lessons learned to the US and also
have just a ton of fun while we were
there. So I think that's definitely a
big um one of my most one of my fondest
memories. And then also sticking on the
international front, uh there's another
class called Global Entrepreneurship Lab
or Gab, which was another one of my most
valuable experiences at Sloan. Had the
opportunity to work with a startup in
Indonesia. They were a glamping
manufacturer, so kind of similar to like
Getaway Cabins, if you're familiar with
those. Um but they have just completely
dominated the Indonesian market and they
were looking to launch in the US. So we
were working with them for the fall
semester to help them build the go to
market and then got to spend the month
of January in Indonesia working with
them in person. Got to do a lot of
travel just learn a ton about the
culture and I think it both of those
classes and programs just really embody
this like hands-on learning men's manus
if you will um at Sloan like everything
is just so practical and I really love
that. And not only are you learning, but
you're also building incredible
relationships with your peers and those
around you.
>> One other point to mention, I can't
believe I mean there were so many good
there were so many incredible memories
during that year, right? But because we
were the sort of cohort, you know,
things got a little bit extended for us.
You know, MIT is very gracious in that
regard. And um I don't know how we man
how this managed to happen but like it
did right
but um we actually got to do um an
economics unit of study in Lima Peru and
uh I'm from Peru my family's from Peru
and um we actually got to have the final
night of the course at my house in Peru
which was like five of the most wild
magical hours of my entire life because
everyone from uh my my came. But then we
also had the EMBAs come and it was just
wild to sort of see both worlds collide
together and two buses that were driving
up the road to my house and everybody
was in them and then you know uh like my
husband was filming everything and
everybody got off and there was like
music and dancers and this and that all
the great food and I sort of thought
like I never would have thought I never
would have thought that Sloan would be
the conduit to bring these two worlds
together and I know obviously as LGBTQ
plus individuals
That's a very fraught tank for a lot of
us, right? Bringing all these worlds
together as opposed to keeping them sort
of compartmentalized.
Um, but Sloan was the key, right, in a
lot of ways. So, um, I think that's also
another important topic to me. It Sloan
does. However, I don't know what the
magic is, but it breaks down barriers
that you yourself sometimes erect in
your own life.
Yeah and if I if I can say one more
thing just like for for for the
organizer I think uh the admissions
committee at Sloan I think I just want
to say that it's absolutely
extraordinary. I mean in my personal
experience I had a little bit of a as I
was doing this like the first admission
program I kind of missed the deadline
for me to um to actually metriculate for
the next year. I was trying to do five
years but I want to do four and um the
basically it was five months late or
something like that and um the for you
know like I spoke with spoke with the
team there and they were able to give me
give me a place at the like 10 days
before the course started and uh over
the program there I've met like other
students doing this the first admission
program through the through the through
the um you know the assistant directors
at the at the ATCOM and the rest of the
team there. an absolutely amazing team
and I think a great resource for um you
know for alumni as well and um but
really really grateful to to to the team
there because I think um yeah made made
at least my personal experience very
different from that and uh I'm not sure
if if the team remembers but 2018 was
the first year in which they were like
allowing like non MIT students to do
that program and uh I think they really
made it work sort of like in the late
decision until September so it's been a
really really amazing team to work with
and um yeah excited for anyone applying
to to interact with that team as
We appreciate that, Jose. Thanks for
sharing. Um, and I do want to give a
little plus one to Somerville Porchfest.
Um, that is a fabulous, fabulous
community event. Um, I think we have
time for just a couple more questions.
We have some questions from allies in
the chat. Um, as an ally, what are some
meaningful ways to contribute to Sloan's
inclusive culture?
I'll I'll jump in there. Um uh so um
it's probably a well-known fact amongst
you know the folks behind the scenes
that you know my house was like party
central during you know co times and you
know so I see Rayvon smiling so I have a
feeling he probably I'm talking about um
and that's okay and so u the question is
you know how can ally support sort of
LGBTQ events and folks at Sloan and the
way that like I guess we didn't have any
like club or anything like that but the
way that folks supported us. I guess
we're just coming to our parties and,
you know, showing up and blah blah blah
blah blah. And I don't know, that's
created this weird sense of community
like immediately, right? And so, um, I
guess just the normality of it all was
something that really stuck with me.
All right. Um, I'm going to give you all
one piece of homework assignment as I go
over the next slide. Um, and that
homework assignment is to um, as I'm
covering the application slide, if you
can think of um, one piece of advice
you'd give yourself
um, as you were in our our our audience,
if you were in their seats, what would
that one piece of advice be um, as you
were preparing to embark on your your
MBA journey or your um, time in the
Sloan Fellows program at MIT? So, if you
could think about what you would tell
yourself,
what would you would tell your previous
self now before you start and join the
program, that would be great. Um, I'm
going to jump over to our next slide
really quickly and then come back in the
future you could answer. That's that'll
be how we wrap up the the presentation
today.
All right. Awesome. So, just really
quickly wanted to cover some information
about um our upcoming application
deadlines. Um, if you found that the
things that our panelists shared with
you resonated really well and you want
to take the next step in potentially
joining the MIT Sloan community, um,
just want to go over our application
deadlines for this upcoming cycle. Um,
as you can see on the left hand side of
the screen, we have application
deadlines for each of the different
programs that were um, spoke that were
addressed today as far as the MBA and
Sloan fellows program is concerned. But
then for the LJGO program and the
Masters of Finance and Masters of
Business Analytics, you'll see that
those two deadlines are going to be for
the LJGO program in early November. And
then for the early career programs, Min
and MBAN, that's going to be in January,
early January. Um on the opposite side
of the screen, you'll see that there are
um the application components. We
require you to submit um pretty much
everything that's standard for uh most
applications. I'll highlight really
quickly something that's unique to Sloan
is the fact that we do ask you to submit
an org chart. Um and that's something
that a lot of times we get questions
about um I'll just say really quickly we
just trying we're just trying to get a
sense of where you fit in the grand
scheme of things as far as your
organization is concerned. Um so
highlighting maybe your team maybe two
levels above or below you and then maybe
to the right and the left of your team
is all we're looking for. Um, if you're
working at a big organization, we're not
going to ask you to name the CFO if you
don't ever, you know, interface with
them. Um, so things to keep in mind. And
then another thing that we typically get
questions about is our 60-second video.
Um, simply the prompt is introduce
yourself to your future classmates. Just
check two boxes, make sure that we can
hear you and make sure that we can see
you. You check those two boxes, you're
off to a great start. Talk about
whatever your heart desires. Um, we'll
have additional um, opportunities for
you to learn more about our community at
other upcoming events um that I
encourage you to join. Um, here's just a
full list of the upcoming community and
culture um, events that are going to be
available to you to join uh, virtually.
And then if you um, want to learn more
about different DEI initiatives and
things like that that are happening at
MIT Sloan, I encourage you to visit this
web page here. Um, but then also
encourage you to visit our events
calendar to see the full listing of
other opportunities that you can
participate in to continue to learn more
about our campus community and ways that
you can um make the most of your time
here should you decide to to join us for
either one year or two years. I'm sure
if I ask our panelists, they'll tell you
that that time flies by. It flies by.
So, um, to make the most of it, it's
always helpful to have a game plan. Um,
and the best way to do that is to just
get an early introduction into some of
the resources that are available to you.
Um, with that said, I'm going to turn
the floor back over to our panelist um
to answer the question that I assigned
to you before um going over that slide
and we're we can go in alphabetical
order. Uh, so Alexa, not to put you on
the spot, but you're going to kick us
off.
>> What is one thing that I would tell
myself? Is that what the question was?
>> Yes. Um, I would say try to figure out a
way to never have to leave because truly
it's like every day I'm like I wish I
was back at Sloan. Um, no. I I mean I
think this is like you're going to hear
this advice a lot but it's worth
repeating like it's going to be drinking
from a fire hose. have your top three to
four priorities or objectives of what
you'd like to get out of the program and
use that as your guiding north star
because in any day there's 10 different
opportun like opportunities that or
events or activities or things that you
could be doing. So having that to kind
of ground you and help you decide is, I
think, very helpful to make sure you get
what you want out of the program, but
also give yourself some grace because
now I look back at it and I'm like, "Oh
my gosh, like how did I not know that
this was a thing? Like I should have
done this or, you know, taken advantage
of these resources." Um, and the good
thing is that it is a lifelong community
and we have this network now. We have
access. Um, so just give yourself some
grace, but just enjoy it, honestly.
>> Ryan, you're up.
>> Yeah, I feel like Alexa basically stole
the thunder there. I would say almost
exactly the same thing. The number one
advice that I give people when they're
about to go into business school is to
try to figure out exactly or as best as
you can what you want to do at the
program before day one. Um
there there really is so much to do. Um,
I think a different way of saying it is,
you know, a lot of people approach
business school, especially people who
are pivoting, um, like I was, with the
intent of using those two years to sort
of figure out what you would like to do
next. That's absolutely a viable path,
but there are tradeoffs. And I think the
experience is generally more productive
if you have as best a sense as you
possibly can of of what you'd like to do
um when you're at the program. You know,
it's like you get in, you think that's
it, and then you show up on campus and
recruiting starts in like October. Um
and and things really do feel like they
move at 100 miles an hour. So
just game planning is helpful.
Yeah, I think um it for for myself I
think one of the the things I've kind of
like wondered is I mean it sounds a
little bit corny but it's sort of um you
know I think the
s like the you know thinking about
whether NBA is like like a good fit for
you sort of like belonging there I think
in my experience particularly with MIT
there's people that have like absolutely
all sorts of backgrounds I mean actually
one of our co-founders a professor at
the bum of professor from neurosurgery
and he was actually part of a Sloan's um
EMBA program a few years ago. William
Gormley, which I'm not sure if like
maybe maybe your team like knows him,
but um I I have a bunch of like surgeon
friends from all the hospitals here that
did MBAs at different programs. Um I
think it's a degree that like I think
with regards to what you would want to
do, I mean like a more traditional
business background or if you want to
you know work in in in in research,
healthcare, it's it's a great fit for
that. And I think another very quick
thing is like really uh you know doing
work with the faculty at Sloan I think
is absolutely extraordinary opportunity.
I mean they're like the best people in
in the world in in in their fields and I
did some work with um Eric so during my
time there which I think was absolutely
like incredible and the Sloan's
librarian team is extraordinary as well.
I mean like very helpful in terms of
like getting to know the research there.
So, um, yeah, that's what I would
probably tell myself for looking back.
And also feel free to add me on LinkedIn
or anything if there's anything any
other questions like, uh, definitely
feel free to reach out.
>> Awesome. Awesome.
>> Go ahead, Alexa.
>> Sorry, I hit that by accident, but I was
just going to plus one to adding on
LinkedIn if if you have any questions.