Hi, I'm Simone and I'm going to be
showing you MIT Learn which aggregates
all of MIT's online learning offerings
and is designed to support learners in
every step of their learning journey. As
we visit the homepage, we can see
featured courses from MIT Open Learning,
Professional Education, and Sloan
Executive Education. We can browse by
topic and you can also see testimonials
and MIT stories and events that might
interest you as a learner. We have a new
AI feature for courses called Ask Tim
where you can ask questions about
different assets within a course
specifically for videos and for problems
within a course. So that was MIT Learn
Lifelong Learning the MIT way.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.