okay so now you're familiar with the
clinical samples that you will be
working with over the course of these
three crunches during the uh machine
learning Challenge and now let's look at
how the data is structured and how it
will be provided to
you so uh for the spatial
transcriptomics measurements here we're
showing uh tissue sections sitting on
the zenium slide and here we're showing
uh the spal transcript omics data itself
all 480 genes where each dot is a
transcript or one of those 480 genes and
on the right we're showing the
corresponding h& image and so you will
be getting paired data like this for all
eight of these clinical
samples and now let's talk a little bit
about how we chose to design these
experiments so at some point you might
have wondered well or is saying we've
measured 480 genes here how are those
480 genes chosen remember there's 20,000
genes in the human genome and we didn't
just flip coins to choose these genes uh
actually what we did was we looked first
of all for genes that are specifically
expressed in cell types found in the
colon so a gene like epcam which you
remember Mark marks epithelial cells
that's specifically expressed in
epithelial cells in the colon is going
to tell us about those types of cells so
that's a gene we chose um so we did that
for many many cell types and chose genes
that Mark those cell types we also chose
genes that have a known genetic
association with ulcerative colitis and
what that means is that patients who
have ulcerative colitis they tend to
have specific genetic variant that
increase their risk for ulcerative
colitis so we think those specific genes
are important in the pathogenesis the
disease mechanism of ulcerative colitis
finally we chose genes that are involved
in cellto cell signaling so this is uh
what what cellto cell signaling is
really is just one cell sends a signal
to another cell and that cell responds
and that's something that spatial
transcriptomic gives us unique power to
look at because to look at a cell that's
sending a signal and a cell that's
receiving a signal we really want to
know where they are in space so the cell
signaling is very important to us and we
know that cell signaling drives
inflammation so that's another uh set of
genes that we kind of pulled from or
ones involved in cell cell
signaling and then the next question you
have is okay what are the data types
provided so we're going to give you
hystology images um prepared by uh
prepared by us we're also going to give
you the zenium data itself the zenium
spatial transcriptomic data that will be
Gene transcript locations in the
assignment of those transcripts to cells
and then finally we're going to give you
the segmentation masks and the
segmentation mask to remind you is going
to be a boundary that goes around every
single cell and it will tell us where
the cells are and which transcripts are
in those cells and ultimately for every
tissue that we give you every tissue
section there's hundreds of thousands of
cells like typically there's three or
400,000 cells that are being profiled in
a single ZM spatial transcript omic data
set okay so how is the data going to be
provided to you so we've structured it
using open-source python packages so
zenium data is uh actually quite
complicated there's many data types that
are needed to fully Express the data so
we're going to be providing to you the
data in an object that can be um open in
the spatial data python pack package and
spatial data is a really new framework
that came out this year for the storage
and process of a multimodal spatial loic
data and this allows you to store images
points labels shapes and tables so
images would be things like the h& image
uh points would be like the transcript
location uh shapes will be the
segmentation masks and labels and tables
are uh essentially metadata that we can
use to annotate the features in the
spatial transcript doic data and so
spatial data is really meant for it's
really a package meant for reading in
the data and organizing it in this
really beautiful modular way and if you
want to do analysis on the data there's
another package that works seamlessly
with spatial data called squid pie and
we encourage you to check that out as
well so that's how the data will be
structured and organized and you'll get
these eight spatial data objects one for
each clinical
sample now there's also the Single Cell
transcript omix data and there's two
single cell transcript omix data sets
we're going to be providing you with one
for crunch 2 and one for crunch 3 and
remember the Single Cell transcript omic
data is going to give us expression
measurements for all 20,000 genes and we
know that different cell types Express
different gene expression programs so
one data set will be giving you is one
that we already introduced from lecture
two this is the one collected by uh Dr
Ron mavier where his group profiled
ulcerative colitis tissue and did single
cell transcriptomics and so there's
information on immune cells in
epithelial cells in stromal cells which
make up connective tissue in the colon
we will also provide you data sets
collected from colon muscle and the
colon nervous system and we provide
these as well because these uh represent
cell types that are not found in this
first space uh single cell
transcriptomic data set so with these
data sets you'll have representatives of
all cell types that are found in
ulcerative colitis
colon we'll also provide you with
metadata for every single sample and
this metadata tells us whether the
tissue came from a healthy individual or
whether it came from a non-inflamed part
of the colon or an inflamed part of the
colon and this is helpful because you
are probably going to be most interested
in those pieces that are from the
inflamed colon because that's going to
tell us about the inflammation programs
but having the healthy there provides a
point of comparison so you can really
look at what genes are differentiating
inflame from healthy colon
and then the last single cell
transcriptomics data set we're going to
provide you comes from a study that was
made looking at the coloral Cancer
Continuum so this was a study carried
out by William Greenleaf and Michael
Snider at Stanford University and they
collected samples from healthy colon
from adomus polyps or precancer and from
colar rectal cancer so polyps are
abnormal growth of the colon epithelial
cell lining into the center of the colon
tube and sometimes they look like um
mushrooms or kind of just these
projections inward into the colon and so
the polyps themselves also have
displasia in them so within the polyps
there's usually or often abnormal growth
of epithelial cells so this is a good
data set where we can actually look at
what displasia looks like at the Single
Cell transcriptomic level so in their
data they collected samples from healthy
colon from colorl cancer and from these
polyps which often have dysplasia in
them and we have epithelial cells immune
cells and the stromal cells which again
make up the connective
tissue and we have a lot of metadata
provided here uh first we have what kind
of what's the status of the tissue
whether there's a polyp whether it's
fully progressed to cancer it's an adoc
carcinoma a type of cancer or whether
it's just healthy so we call that normal
or unaffected in addition we have the
diagnosis of displasia from a
pathologist so we know which pieces of
tissue have displasia in them and that's
going to be important for crunch 3 where
we're focus on displasia and then
finally you know one thing you might
want to focus on as you use this data is
to focus on those pops where there is
diagnosed displasia by the pathologist
so that's going to give you single cell
data from displasia
samples so uh when you're working with
single cell data there's a lot of
packages out there but we have structure
the single cell transcriptomic data such
that you can load it again in another
open source python package called and
data this is a way to uh store the data
the gene expression count matrices in
matrices and also have annotation for
those matrices and then there's another
package called scanpy which you can use
to carry out analysis of uh the
different single cell data sets and so
this is going to be uh very useful for
working with a single cell data and
what's nice is um these packages all
cooperate very well with the spatial
data package that I introduced uh to you
a few slides ear which you're going to
use to work uh to work on with the
spatial transcriptomic data