[Music]
autoimmune diseases affect 50 million
people in the United States with rates
Rising globally an inflammatory bowel
disease or IBD as it's also called is
one of the most common types IBD is
composed of Crohn's disease that affects
any part of the gastrointestinal tract
ulcerative colitis that affects the
colon IBD is caused when the barrier
between our gut and the microbes that
live there breaks down leading to
chronic inflammation and cycles of
flares and remission before modern
treatments mortality was often greater
than 50% common symptoms of IBD include
abdominal pain
diarrhea gastrointestinal bleeding and
weight loss patients often present to
the doctor with a constellation of these
symptoms but the ultimate diagnosis of
inflammatory B disease relies on
performing an upper endoscopy and or
colonoscopy analyzing the biopsies under
a light microscope these images are
essential for patient treatment as they
guide not just the diagnosis of IBD but
also what drug treatments are best
suited for the patient and whether the
patient is likely to develop coloral
cancer the risk of coloral cancer can be
up to two fold higher in IBD patients
but this cancer is actually highly
treatable if detected during early
screening worldwide Pathologists have
collected millions of gut tissue images
across hospitals making these images a
treasure Trove of data and an enormous
opportunity for machine learning to
impact patient Health even more exciting
the revolution in genomics over the past
20 years enables us to measure genes
directly Within These gut tissues
showing us functional details a
pathologist cannot see and providing an
opportunity to uncover the pathways that
really Drive disease spatial
transcriptomics offers a unique
opportunity to look at how these
individual cells or groups of cells
interact with each other allow us to
identify unique or novel starting points
for Dev veloping better choices of drug
treatments but they're very expensive
and time intensive to obtain what if we
could connect the tissue images
routinely collected by Pathologists with
these less available spatial
measurements the resulting
highresolution view of IBD could really
improve patient diagnosis better guide
the choice of drug treatments and help
identify and start treatment of coloral
cancer earlier this is where you come in
we need algorithms that can connect
these different types of images taking
us from the tissue image collected by a
pathologist to the high resolution view
of genes that are active in the tissue
and are really driving disease to
validate your models we will ask you to
identify genes that are markers of
potential cancerous regions in the gut
and we will then perform experiments to
test these genes in patient samples to
make progress for IBD patients and
better detect inflammation and cancer
the Eric and Wendy Schmid Center
together with a clareman cell
Observatory at the broad Institute of
MIT and Harvard and in collaboration
with a crunch Foundation are hosting the
autoimmune disease machine learning
challenge machine learning challenges or
competitions are an increasingly
important way to direct machine learning
and AI enthusiasts towards scientific
discovery in these challenges
participants from academic institutions
and companies they will develop
solutions for data heavy problems in
this specific project autoimmune decease
machine learning challenge we are
inviting participants from all over the
world to design algorithms that pull out
unprecedented information from pathology
images and Aid early detection of cancer
in IBD now this machine learning
challenge is unique in that the
predictions from the top submissions
will be experimentally validated in the
lab so your algorithm could actually
change the course of how we detect
cancer in IBD patients you might be
wondering is biology experience required
for this challenge it is not we're going
to provide a biology crash course
together with the data all that is
missing is you and your
algorithms participants will predict the
expression of genes in IBD tissue
starting from the tissue images
collected by Pathologists and highlight
those genes marking potential cancerous
regions then we will test in the lab
which genes best identify these regions
in the inflamed gut the challenge will
take place in October of 2024 we will
award monetary prices for this Challenge
and the top participants will be invited
to become an author on resulting
Publications the code data and
algorithms from The Challenge will be
made open source for the community to
use our inaugural cancer immunotherapy
machine learning challenge that we held
last year was highly rewarding drawing
in more than 1,000 people worldwide who
appli their algorithms to an important
biological question and we now invite
you to this new challenge your work May
add a crucial stepping stone to the
great scientific quest of improving
treatment for autoinflammatory and
autoimmune diseases visit the Eric and
Wendy Schmid Center website today to
register