All right, let's get started. Welcome
back to 61200. Uh, today we're going to
talk about state machines, which is a
very cool tool for thinking about uh
processes over time. And in because this
is math for computer science in
particular, we're thinking about
analyzing algorithms that do a bunch of
steps and the state of the machine uh
changes over time like the state of your
memory changes and state machines are a
nice way to reason about how it's
changing. In particular, we'll talk
about an idea called invariance
uh which you use to prove algorithms and
programs correct and you or you will in
the future. And so today we're going to
formalize that into uh a kind of
induction actually. Uh you haven't seen
the end of induction yet. Uh so let me
tell you a little bit about what state
machines are.
Then we'll prove some things and apply
them to analyzing puzzles and other fun
stuff.
So a state machine is going to consist
of two things
uh three things
um a set of states
and the idea this is just an arbitrary
set but the idea is that the state of
your machine represents everything that
could possibly be in the machine all the
information that lets you that that's
inside the machine.
uh we're going to start in some state
which we call Q0
that's going to be an element of Q and
then we are allowed some transitions.
uh and we're going to write
a transition as Q arrow R
uh for some
Q and R that are states.
Okay. Uh let me draw you an example very
simple example of a state machine so we
have some idea of what we're talking
about. This is going to be an infinite
counter.
I'm going to draw it visually first and
then we can say what it means with all
these sets.
Just dot dot dot. Maybe I'll do one
more.
Okay, so this is a machine. You can
think of it as a single uh register on
your machine, single variable. It starts
at zero. This little notation here means
start state.
Um there's there's an arrow coming from
nowhere. So that's where you start. You
start in state called zero. So the set
of states here is 0 1 2 3 and so on. In
other words, the natural numbers
Okay. And then when you're in state
zero, the only transition you can do,
the only arrow that goes out from there
is from zero to one. And once you're in
state one, the only thing you can do is
go from one to two. At some point, you
decide to increment, then you go from
two to three. Some point you decide to
increment and you go from three to four
and so on. So this is a very simple
state machine. It turns out it will be
interesting for certain reasons. But uh
in general, you could imagine having all
sorts of arrows. Maybe one has a
transition to three for example or maybe
three has a transition to one. All of
these are possible. You can have one
state that has many transitions out of
it. You can go in loops. You can do all
sorts of crazy things. Uh but let me
finish precisely specifying the counter.
Okay. So we said uh here Q0 equals the
state zero.
And uh what are the transitions?
transitions are all of the um i to i +
one transitions where i is a natural
number. May recall this set builder
notation from lecture one I think uh
where we write an element on the left
and we write some condition on the right
and so the idea is t is the set of all
of these transitions i to i + one for
every i that's a natural number.
Okay, so that's an example. But in
general, we can have all sorts of
transitions from any state to any state,
but you're only allowed to make the
transitions that are in t.
So let's uh
formalize that with the idea of an
execution.
It's going to be a sequence of states
that uh you can reach by a sequence of
transitions.
So uh let's write it as Q0 arrow Q1
arrow Q2
and so on
uh
maybe up to QN.
And importantly, every transition we
make for all I qi to qi plus one should
be in t, not just any set of states
here. We want to start in Q0, our start
state. We want to then make a valid
transition from Q0 to Q1. Then a valid
transition from Q1 to Q2 and so on. So
in this example, the executions are very
simple. In the in the regular counter
without the red lines, the executions
are just 0123, that's one execution. 0 1
2 3 4 5 That's another execution.
There's an infinite execution which is
zero all the way out to infinity.
Uh that's why I put this in parenthesis.
Either it stops at some qn or just or
the dot dot dot continues off to
infinity. So trying to simultaneously
define finite executions where you stop
at qn and infinite executions where you
go forever. When you write an algorithm
or a piece of code, you usually don't
want your program to go forever. And so
distinguishing between infinite and and
finite executions is one of the goals of
this lecture. It'll come at the end. The
other goal is to show that your program
is correct in a certain sense that in
any execution it does the things that
you want it to do. So that's what we're
going to formalize in a moment. But let
me first talk about reachable states.
The idea of reachability.
I'm going to call a state R reachable if
there is an execution that starts at the
start state Q0 and ends at R.
Okay, so in the counter example, every
state can be reached. If I pick a state
I, I can go 0 1 2 3 up to I. But if I
drew some other circle over here like uh
bad with no arrows coming into it, you
can't reach bad.
Okay,
so usually we're only interested in the
reachable states because you can't get
anywhere else.
I feel like I should make a reacher
joke, but I don't can't think of one.
Okay. Um I think
at this point I want to talk about a
more interesting example and then we
will
come back to
uh
the theory.
So the interesting example is this uh
it's called the eight puzzle. You have a
3x3 grid with one hole and one by one
pieces in it and you can slide them
around. And so this is the solve state.
Your goal is to get here. But you start
in some random state and you want to
move the pieces around to get there.
Uh so what we'd like to do is capture uh
how to solve this puzzle or actually
maybe more interestingly is when it's
solvable. So here for example, I'm
almost solved 1 2 3 4 65 78. I wanted to
get into 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8. Uh it turns
out that puzzle is not solvable. I claim
it's impossible to get from here to the
goal.
So let's talk about the eight puzzle.
Uh
so I have some examples here. One,
three, four, two, five,
seven, eight, six.
Going to one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight.
Or
this one. One, two, three,
four, six, five, seven, eight.
Okay,
hopefully the rules are clear. We'll
formalize them in a second. Um, I claim
it is possible to go from this
arrangement to this arrangement. It's
actually quite easy. You move the three
over, you move the two up, you move the
five over, you move the six up. Okay, so
this is possible. I claim this one is
impossible.
And one of the goal, our first goal
really is to prove that that you cannot
swap the five and the six by themselves.
Okay, we're going to build up tools to
do that.
So, let me define let me uh so the
counter was a very simple state machine.
Let me now define a more interesting
state machine which is the eight puzzle.
Okay, remember the set of states Q is
supposed to encapsulate
everything about the puzzle or your
system or whatever. Uh, so this is going
to be all the different arrangements of
the eight pieces plus a blank in a 3x3
grid. So I'm just going to write that in
words. All possible
arrangements
of eight I'm going to call them of uh
one two three up to eight and the blank
in a 3x3.
In later parts of the class we'll be
able to count how many of these things
there are. It's nine factorial, but uh
we don't really care how many there are
right now. We just want to think about
this as a set of all the possible states
of this board.
Okay, our start state, well, that's
either this one or this one depending on
where we want to start. Um we're also
going to define a final state Q subf and
that is uh sorted
uh by reading order.
So this is Q subf reading order like in
English you read the top row, second
row, third row with the X at the end.
That's always our goal in this puzzle.
That's our definition. Uh and then uh
what about the transitions?
Okay,
transitions are going to look like um
some Q to R for two states Q and R. And
it's when you can get from Q to R by
making one slide.
I'm just going to write that in words.
Can get
from state Q that 3x3 grid to state R in
one slide. meaning
meaning you exchange the blank the X
with one of its neighboring cells. So in
particular there is at most four
different uh transitions
from any state.
You could move the thing above the blank
into the blank. You move the left,
right, or below the blank into the
blank. But if it's on the boundary, you
have fewer than four moves. Okay, so
hopefully now I've said it enough times
the rules are clear if you haven't
played this game before. 15 puzzle is
much more common,
but eight puzzle is a little easier to
think about. Smaller pictures, easier to
draw, and I could actually solve it in a
reasonable amount of time. Um, okay. So,
uh, this is a claim
that we want to prove. You cannot get
from this state with five and six
flipped into this state. And so now
we're going to build some some
technology to do that. And that
technology is an uh first part of it is
called a state predicate.
So
we've seen predicates before.
Predicate is just a
uh
a proposition that's depends on some
variable.
And here the variable is a state.
So p of q is either true or false
depending on which state you are looking
at. You can also think of this if you're
comfortable with functions. We'll talk
more about functions later in the class.
This is a function from Q to the
booleans, true or false.
It's an equivalent way to think about
it, whatever you're more comfortable
with. For every state, we're going to
this predicate assigns true or false.
Okay. Now, we're going to define uh two
types of predicates that are
particularly interesting.
A predicate is preserved if whenever
there's a transition from Q to R,
uh, P of Q implies P of R.
What does that mean? It means that if I
start in some state where P is true and
I do a transition, then P remains true.
So it's the truth of P is preserved
along transitions.
Okay, we'll make this concrete in a
second. Second important notion
is called an invariant or invariant
state predicate.
If uh P of Q
is true
for all reachable states Q.
Crucially in this definition definition
we're only interested in the reachable
states.
Uh that's kind of important for the
eight puzzle because we claim some
states are unreachable. Like if I start
here the claim is that this one is
unreachable. That's what we'd like to
prove actually.
Uh so this seems useful.
Um in particular,
let's write this fun fact. Uh if P of Q
is invariant, meaning it's true in all
reachable states.
uh
and
p of q
is false
for maybe I'll write p of r here
then
r is unreachable
okay that's pretty much by definition
and maybe the contraositive this is
saying for uh invariant means that for
all reachable states p of q must be true
so if I can find a particular state R
where P is false. That means you cannot
reach it. And that's what we'd like to
show, right? We'd like to show this
state is unreachable from this one.
So maybe we can use these state
predicates to do that. And indeed we
can.
Okay,
let me tell you another tool.
Uh you know how do we prove that a state
predicate is invariant?
Uh this seems a little bit tricky
because this is talking about all
reachable states. Reachable states is
like huge. I don't know.
Preserved seems relatively easy to
prove. This is just saying for each
transition something implies something.
So I'd like to prove preservedness
and I'd like to use that to get
invariant.
And we're going to do that using
induction. But a particular form of
induction called the invariant
principle.
So this is for a state
predicate
P of Q.
If
P of Q0 is true
and
uh P of Q is invariant.
Get it right.
Observed.
then
P of Q is invariant.
Okay, this is what I said I wanted. Uh
on the one hand, invariant seemed hard
to argue. Preserve seemed easy to argue.
And this is a theorem that connects them
in the way that we want. It says if you
can prove preserved and you can prove
that P is true in the very initial
state, then it must be invariant. I
think this is intuitive, right? If you
start true and preserve says every time
you do a transition you stay true then
you're always going to be true in any
reachable state anywhere you can get.
Okay. Uh in fact this is induction in
another form. So if you recall
in the past which I happen to have right
here induction
we have regular induction says uh for
predicate p of n over natural numbers
instead of states
uh if p of zero is true and for every
natural number p of n implies p of n is
n plus one is true then for every
natural number p of n is true. Okay,
this is saying uh the same thing
actually it's exactly the same thing if
you apply this invariant principle to
this counter
[Applause]
right in the counter the states are the
natural numbers and the transitions are
exactly going from i to i + 1 okay so
the invariant principle is actually a
generalization of the induction axiom
uh the special case here where we plug
in the counter as a state machine. This
is true for all state machines. And if
we plug in the counter for our state
machine, we get exactly the induction
aim.
This is our base case in some sense. We
prove that uh P is true in the initial
state. This is our induction step. It
says that if we start at Q and we
transition to some other R that's
reachable via transition.
uh and in the particular case of counter
m counter that is going from Q to Q plus
one then we get that P of Q is true for
all reachable states and in the counter
everything is reachable.
Okay, so invariant principle implies
induction aom.
Uh, conversely, we can prove the
invariant principle using induction.
Maybe it's useful to see
that proof.
So let's prove the invariant principle
uh by induction.
So it's not so obvious how exactly but
the idea is to specify a particular
induction hypothesis which is
uh for all length n executions.
uh p of qn
is true.
There should be a colon out here.
Uh I think it's intuitive that this is
enough, but we'll justify why this is
enough. The idea is if you have some
state that's reachable, it's reachable
by some finite execution of some length.
And we're going to prove for all n that
all length n executions p of qn is true.
And by by inducting over length, we
essentially start with short uh
executions and then make them gradually
longer. That makes this easy to prove.
So let's pro let's do a base case
uh iH of zero.
Well, that's all length zero executions.
There's only one length zero execution.
uh
that is just Q0. You start at Q0 and you
stay there. That's length zero. Uh and
we claim that P of Q0 Q0 is clearly a
reachable state. You get there via
length zero execution. Why is it true?
this where it's what we assumed
it's by one.
So that's the base case.
Of course, the more interesting one is
the induction step. I'm going to assume
we get to choose. We could follow this
plan. Assume P of N and prove P of N
plus one. I find it slightly more
intuitive to assume P of N or sorry
instead of P it's IH here for induction
hypothesis
uh IH of N minus one and we're going to
prove
uh IH of N.
Okay, what does it mean to prove IH of
N? It says well for all length N
executions P of QN is true. Uh so how do
we prove a for all? We just take an
arbitrary thing in the quantifier. So
take any
consider any
length n execution
and then we need to prove the property
we want which is p of qn. So let me uh
give some notation for that execution.
any length n execution q0
q1
q n minus one
qn
and what we want to show is that uh p of
that's our goal right it says for all
length executions p of qn is true so we
take an arbitrary execution if we can
prove p of qn is true then we're
Well, somehow we want to use induction
here. We've assumed the induction
hypothesis for size n minus one. Can you
see a length n minus one execution here?
That might be interesting.
Yeah.
>> Q1 to QN. That's a good idea. Does that
work?
Is that an execution?
Let's go back and check. Uh,
execution of a state machine
is an infinite or a finite sequence
starting with Q0 and maybe ending,
but it needs to start with Q0. So
there's like two natural choices here.
One would be starting at Q1 and going to
QN, but Q1 might not equal Q0. And so
that might not be a valid execution. So
we wouldn't be able to apply induction
to that. The other obvious choice is q0
to qn minus one. That is a valid
execution of length one smaller length n
minus one because it starts with q0.
Okay, a lot of terms here so it's easy
to lose track but eventually they will
become comfortable. Uh so by uh
induction hypothesis of n minus one
if we apply it to this execution of
length n minus one we learn that p of q
n minus one is true.
Right? That's what the induction
hypothesis says. The last state in your
execution is true. So now we know p of
this is true. We just need to prove p of
this is true. Why is that? Because
property two
P of Q is preserved which we can unroll
over here says for every transition in
particular the one from QN minus one to
QN P of Q minus one implies P of QN.
Okay. So uh
by 2
uh p of q n minus one uh implies p of qn
because this is a transition in t.
So p of qn.
So that's the end of the induction step.
So uh by induction
we get for all uh n
uh induction hypothesis of n. And the
idea is that this uh implies p of q for
all reachable states q.
Because if you have a reachable state Q,
there's by definition of reachable way
over on the left, uh there's some
execution that gets there and it has
some length and so I of that length
gives you what you want.
So that's how we prove the invariant
principle. It's pretty intuitive notion,
but maybe nice to see yet another
example of an induction proof.
Great.
So, how do we use this?
Let's go
over here.
Here is a template
for proving a theorem
which is
P of Q
is invariant. This is the thing I keep
saying is hard to prove
or by the definition it seems hard to
prove but using this invariant principle
it's going to be easy. Here's what a
general proof will look like.
We can say proof by invariant principle.
For the invariant principle to apply we
need to prove two things
number one and number two.
So number one is prove that P of Q0 is
true
and in a template we just say because
reasons which we don't know but we have
to fill in. And the second thing is that
uh P of Q
is preserved.
That's the more interesting thing and
for this we need to unroll the
definition of preserved. says for all Q
all transitions Q to R P of Q implies Q
of R. So how do we prove that? Uh we
just take uh
any transition in t q to r
and because it's an implication
we can assume the left hand if we want
to prove an implication we can assume
the left part this is a direct proof and
prove the right part. So we can assume
uh Q P of Q is true
and then what we need to do is show that
P of R is true.
That's the interesting step which we
need to fill in.
But this is the template we're going to
now use to analyze the eight puzzle. Of
course I haven't defined what predicate
we're analyzing. That's the next step.
Uh but once we have a predicate, we'll
be able to prove that it's invariant
using this simple structure, right? Just
check it. It's check that it's initially
true and check that if you start from
something that's true and you take a
transition out of it, it's still true.
Great.
All right.
So let me define a predicate
for the a puzzle.
I want it closer to these examples
actually.
Yeah. Let's go
here. I think you know definition of a
state machine.
Okay. So for this uh eight puzzle state
machine, I'd like to
define a bit of a bizarre predicate.
So first I'm going to define the notion
of
an inverted pair.
This is going to depend on what state
we're in.
Uh so let's do it. Let's look at uh
inverted pairs in this example
in these three examples.
So an inverted pair is a is a two
numbers. So not the blank but two
numbers between one and eight. And I
want I less than J. And yet I want J to
appear before I in the reading order.
So for example
my red chalk
uh in in this picture this state two and
four are inverted right in reading order
four comes before two yet four is
greater than two.
Uh any others?
Eight and six are inverted.
Six and seven are inverted.
Seven is bigger than six. Eight is
bigger than six, but they come earlier
than six in the reading order. I think
there's one more.
Three and two. Thank you. That one's a
little trickier because it's on
different rows, but in reading order,
three comes before two and yet three is
greater than two. So there are four
inverted pairs in this example. How many
inverted pairs are there in this
example?
Zero.
Zero inverted pairs.
How about this one?
One. Yeah.
I thought you were holding up your hand,
but you're holding up one finger.
Uh, six comes after five. That was the
only thing out of order. That's what we
we started out with. So if you wanted
some, you know, where do you come up
with this idea, it just is fundamental.
You're supposed to magically
uh invent it. But if you fool around
with the puzzle enough, it's actually
somewhat intuitive and that you can get
where it's almost sorted, but there's
just one pair that's wrong. So you might
think, well, maybe there's something
about these inverted pairs. Let's talk
about them in general, not just about
zero versus one inverted pairs, but
let's count them. So over here we had
one inverted pair. Here we had zero
inverted pairs. Here we had four
inverted pairs. And I claim it was
possible to go from four inverted pairs
to zero but impossible to go from one
inverted pair to zero.
Why
pars
par means odd or even.
So uh
P of Q
is going to be uh that the number of
inverted pairs
in state Q
is odd. Turns out to be this proof will
work for either one. But if we want to
prove this particular impossibility
result, odd is what we need.
So, uh, P of Q is going to be true for
this configuration because it has an odd
number of inverted pairs and it's going
to be false for these two.
Why is that interesting?
Because
over here
we said suppose we can show that P of Q
is invariant. I claim that's true. Uh if
we start from here where P of Q starts
true because the number of inverted
pairs starts odd
then uh and we find another state where
P of R is false
because here the number of inverted
pairs is even instead of odd then R is
unreachable. That means it's impossible
to get from this state to this state.
That's what we want to prove. Okay. So
if we can prove this invariant property,
we can plug it into here and get the
puzzle impossibility result that we
want.
Okay, that's where everything's going to
come together. So let's prove that
uh P of Q is
ideally we'd like it to be invariant,
but uh to prove invariant, we're going
to start with proving that it's
preserved.
Uh the reason for the eight puzzle that
I want to talk about preserved first is
to be invariant it depends where you
start and that's kind of particular
that that's a little arbitrary. There
isn't one natural start state for the
eight puzzle. You might start here. You
might start here. You might start here.
That' be a very easy puzzle. Uh and so
but preserved is just a general property
about the system. So I don't need to
assume anything for that.
So we want to do this part. We want to
prove P of Q is preserved. So we
consider any transition Q to R where P
of Q is true. We need to prove P of R is
true. Okay. So here we plug in the
outline of step two there. Um consider
any transition Q to R that's valid. It's
in T. Uh where P of Q is true.
And we want to show P of R is true.
Okay. What do transitions look like in
this game?
Well, relative to reading order, reading
order talks about rows. So, um there's
really two types of moves we care about.
There's horizontal moves left and right,
and there's vertical moves up and down.
I claim those are the two cases, uh that
we need to think about because we're
thinking about reading order.
So, case one
is that this transition Q to R is a
horizontal move.
horizontal move. So this is like
uh we take some number I and next to it
there's an X and maybe if we move to the
right that would be X I or if we move to
the left it would be like that. Okay,
it's one of those two transitions. X
here means the blank. How does that
change reading order?
Yeah,
nothing. Nothing changes, right? The
reading order is the same reading order.
When we're talking about reading order,
we're only talking about the numbers. We
don't care about the x.
So, no changes in reading order.
or in
uh the number of inverted pairs
because that's only dependent on reading
order.
Uh so we have P of R. Case one is easy.
Let's prove case two
maybe over here.
[Applause]
Case two is a vertical move here.
There's actually something to show more
interesting,
but not much harder.
Okay, I'm going to draw some pictures
for intuition. Uh it could be we are
moving I down and there's two things to
the right of I. Uh it could be uh we're
moving I in the middle
to here or could be we're moving I
on the right
down to here.
Okay. And uh this is for a down move. Up
is going to be symmetric. But maybe
let's first think about down moves. So
in order to do a down move uh in reading
order, there are two items that come
after I because we're moving down. There
is something after I, right? There's a
whole row after I until this X. So if we
can move I down, there's two numbers
between I and the X in reading order.
and I starts before those numbers if
we're going down and ends after.
So, uh the move here we can think of it
as swapping
uh we we want to swap I with X. Okay,
but this is equivalent to
swapping I with
uh J first of all and then swapping I
with K. Instead of going straight down
in another color,
I'm going to think of swapping I to
first come after J and then come after
K. That's the same as the X. And it
doesn't matter where we started. could
be here and then we go here or could be
here we go after J and then we go after
K.
The point is if we swap if we figure out
how to swap two adjacent numbers in
reading order and we swap I twice then I
gets to where the X is because this is a
3x3
that's why twice.
Okay. So,
uh, now what we care about
is, uh, what happens
when we swap two adjacent items
in reading order. So not adjacent in the
3x3 grid but adjacent in reading order.
That's what we care about. If we can
solve this and we do it twice then we
will know what happened when we do a
vertical move.
Okay. So what happens when I swap two
numbers I and J? How how does that
change the reading order? I mean it
swaps I and J. That's all. Everything
before I is still before I. Everything
after J is still after RJ. The only
thing is we're change for if they're
adjacent items I and J. We're only
flipping
whether I J is inverted. Right? If I J
was in the correct order before, if I
was less than J, then after I do the
swap, they're an inverted pair. If they
were an inverted pair initially, if I is
bigger than J, after I do the swap,
they're no longer an inverted pair. So,
swapping two adjacent items changes
the uh number of inverted pairs.
by plus or minus one.
If they were inverted before, it
decreases the number. If they weren't
inverted before, it increases the
number, but always by one.
Never stays the same. Never changes by
seven. Okay?
So that when we swap two adjacent pairs,
we change by plus or minus one. when we
do a vertical move, we do we want to do
two of these uh adjacent swaps.
So, let's continue over here.
So if we do two adjacent swaps,
this will change the number of inverted
pairs by plus or minus one
plus plus or minus one.
Okay, where each of these pluses or
minuses, we don't know. They could be
plus or minus. But uh the point is plus
or minus one is an odd number. plus or
minus one is an odd number. When I add
two odd numbers, this is an even number.
Turns out you can draw a little picture.
If we start at zero here and we do plus
or minus one and then from here we do
plus or minus one. From here we do plus
or minus one. This is a case analysis of
all the things you could do. You either
get two or zero or minus two. These
three numbers are all even.
Okay, but I don't particularly care. It
happens to be just these three values.
What I care is that this number is even.
We started with uh
we started with P of Q being true over
here. Uh assume that P of Q is true.
That means that the number of inverted
pairs in state Q is odd. And now we
change that number by an even amount.
Therefore it will be odd
still right? If we take an odd number we
add an even number uh it become it stays
odd. Therefore uh p of r is true.
Question
>> uh so question is why is this two swaps?
Uh
so the the funny thing here you so it's
right if I swap I J then let me maybe
draw a picture
somewhere here.
[Applause]
Let's just go here. Scratch space. So if
we have I J K X and I swap I and J then
I get J I K X and then I swap I and K
then I get J K I X. And you're right. I
is not quite where I want it. Uh this is
funny. I'd really want I to be here
which I can do.
like this. Uh because that doesn't
change reading order.
Okay, it's good that we spell this out.
And also I can do horizontal moves for
free. So J, K uh I this is maybe
a way to think about it. The point is
these three have the same reading order.
So those don't really count. But I'm
glad you had me spell it out.
are not,
>> right? These are not valid transitions.
Uh, indeed, at the end, we get to
something that's a valid transition. So,
the transition goes from here directly
to here, and we're splitting it up into
some sub moves that aren't valid moves
by themselves, uh, but easier to
analyze. First, we think about what
happens when we swap i and j. That
changes by plus or minus one. Then, we
swap, uh, i and k. that changes these by
a plus or minus one. Then we do these
horizontal moves which doesn't change
anything
or kind of horizontal moves. Moving the
x uh in reading order doesn't change
anything. Cool.
All right.
Great.
Feel like I skipped a bit of a step
here, but
[Applause]
So the point is when we swap when we in
case two we do a vertical move
uh the uh we started with an odd odd
number of inverted pairs
and then we add an even number
uh and even odd plus even equals odd.
Therefore p of r is true. That's the
point. Okay. So if we start odd, we will
stay odd. If you swap odd and even in
this proof, you can also show that if
you start even, you stay even.
But what we really want is uh for this
part
here, we want to get uh P of Q to be
invariant and find a place where P is
false and then conclude that R is
unreachable. So let's do that quickly.
So uh
let's define this state to be Q0.
Okay. So for this Q0 we have
or maybe let's say if P of Q0
is true
as in this example because there's an
odd number of of inverted pairs then P
of Q is invariant
and so by this property
uh
if P of R is false
then
uh
R is unreachable.
Oh, so actually what I care about is not
P of R but P of the final state QF.
Okay, so that's that's exactly the
scenario. We start in a state where we
have an odd number of transitions. we're
trying to get to a state with zero uh
inverted pairs and so uh that's not
going to be possible because we start
with P true and we somehow are trying to
reach a state where P is false. Okay,
but if we can prove this invariant
property
and we've basically done all the hard
work here. This is just by the invariant
principle. So now I'm following the
outline over on the left.
Step one is or part one is that P of Q0
is true. We assume that. Step two is
that P of Q uh is preserved
and we just prove that. This is our
theorem.
So maybe you don't know this word
corollary or corollery if you're
Canadian. Corlary means something that
follows. So theorem means something
that's true. Both of these are supposed
to be true. Uh but these are words to
say that okay theorem was sort of the
main thing we wanted to prove and then
corlary is something that follows
immediately from it. It's like almost a
oneline proof here. Once we have the
theorem, the corollary is immediate.
There's some terminology. Okay. So
hopefully you now believe this is
impossible.
Any
questions about the eight puzzle
for fun? Let's solve it one more time.
Uh, I actually didn't have time this
morning to implement the only generate
solvable puzzles. So, I have no idea
whether this will be solvable. It's kind
of exciting. If you can count the
inversions, uh, you'll figure it out,
but I keep moving it, so it's pretty
hard.
And I'm following a particular slow
algorithm for solving this puzzle
which I won't describe but it's on
wikihow if you're interested. Oh, I
solved it. Great. So I must have started
with an even number of inverted pairs.
Uh in a future version I will add that
number.
But there we go. Cool. Uh
question.
Uh so your question is in if in this
state we move six down how many inverted
pairs do we get? Let's draw it.
So that is one two three four five x it
should be two
uh 7 8
how many inverted pairs are there? Seven
is inverted with six. Eight is inverted
with six. And that's it. Okay. So
there's an example in action. Vertical
move changing by two. Sometimes it
changes by zero. Uh if I is sandwiched
in between J and K numerically.
Sometimes it changes by plus or minus
two.
Of course if we do the up move, we
subtract two.
That was another question. Yeah.
Okay, question is explain preserved and
invariant
and where are we using different parts?
If if I can make an induction analogy
for a second. Uh preserved means uh is
like your induction step. It says every
time you do a transition, if P started
true, it remains true.
And invariant is what you get out of the
induction. Let's go over to the
invariant principle here.
[Applause]
The invariant principle basically says
preserved implies invariant except you
also need to check that you start true.
If P starts true and whenever you do a
transition it remains true
uh then it's always true for every
reachable state.
Okay. So crucially in this setup we're
ignoring all the unreachable states.
just talking invariant only talks about
reachable states. It says that every
reachable state P is true. That's what
we're concluding from. We start true and
every time we start in a true state and
we make a transition, we remain true.
Hopefully that's
clear. Takes a little while to get
comfortable with these definitions, but
very important the difference between
preserved and variant. So if you forget,
read the definition.
Uh or just follow this template. This
makes it pretty clear. Usually we just
want a proven variant. And there's a
clear start state. So in fact, the next
example will have a
well no that's not true. But uh if
there's a clear start state, you can
just follow this template. Uh and all
you care about is proving invariant.
Okay,
let's do the next topic, which is
termination.
And maybe I want to start with an
example
which is a simple sorder machine.
This is another state machine
and it sorts and numbers. This is a
problem you study a lot in the follow on
to this class, the algorithms classes.
So suppose we're given a bunch of real
numbers or integers, whatever.
uh want to sort them
in increasing order.
Okay, here is so they're given in some
particular order a1 through a n and I
want to rearrange them so it has exactly
the same set of numbers or exactly the
same numbers but in a different order
and this time increasing order. So I
want a1 to be less than or equal to a2
less than equal to a3 and so on. Here is
a very simple algorithm to do that
which is
while there's some index I where I AI is
bigger than AI + one
swap
AI with AI + one.
Okay, so I'm just looking at consecutive
pairs AI to AI plus one. And if there's
some that's out of order, I is less than
I plus one, but AI is greater than AI
plus one, then I want to swap them in
the right order. We can see this
algorithm in action
for fun. Uh, and then we're going to
convert this algorithm into a state
machine. Okay, so just pretend you
understand algorithms for the second.
Uh, here we have the numbers in a
particular order. Uh the height
corresponds to the value that's written
362541.
And uh we're just going to do uh an
example. U but then we do a swap a swap.
We're always swapping adjacent pairs.
And then Pac-Man comes over to the left
and we get them in sorted order. Okay.
So that is the algorithm. Let's now
analyze it as a state machine.
So first question is what are the states
Q? Well throughout this algorithm so
this is sort of in our head what we're
thinking about doing. Uh and now uh and
we choose I I arbitrarily now we're
going to model as a state machine. This
will make precise what's actually going
on.
Uh as we do this we're we're taking the
original items in some order. We're
always swapping items. So at any moment
in time what we have is some reordering
of the AIS.
Okay, those are our states.
Let's define Q to be all possible
orderings. These may not all be
reachable, but this is the thing that's
easy to define.
All possible orderings of A1 to A.
Okay. Uh this template.
Okay. What are the transitions?
transitions are going to take some ai ai
plus one pair and swap them. So if we
start with them in this order, they're
going to end up in the opposite order.
And we are only allowed to do this when
ai is bigger than ai plus one.
So that's the transitions.
uh implicitly this specifies exactly the
algorithm. The algorithm says take some
i where a i is bigger than i ai plus one
and swap them. That's exactly what the
transitions specify because uh we can
take any transition that's valid from
any state. So with a if we can find any
i where ai is greater than a i plus one
then swapping that pair is a valid
transition. We don't know which one
we'll do. state machine will follow some
execution which will do one of these
until it can't anymore.
Okay,
great.
Can't anymore. Let's define a tool which
is final states.
Let's call a state
Q final
if there's no transition
uh
Q to R in T. If there's no transition
that starts at Q and goes somewhere.
Okay. So, uh in the eight puzzle there
are no final states. You can always make
moves. You never are done. You're done
only when you happen to reach the final
state. But there's nothing in the move
definition that prevents you from
continuing. Uh in this problem, there
are final states.
I claim it's exactly
a z to a n where a1 is less or equal to
a2 is less than or equal to a3 and so on
is less than equal to a n. Namely the
sorted order
why well first of all I claim this state
is final because if you look at any pair
a i ai plus one we have ai is less than
or equal to ai plus one. So we don't
have a transition out of there. So these
states are definitely final. I also
claim that it's all the final states
because if I had some some state where
this is not true,
that means one of these inequalities is
not true. So that means there's some AI
that's greater than AI plus one and then
there's a transition.
Okay, so that was a an argument spoken
argument for why the final states are
exactly this. Uh technically we're
proving uh all of these states are final
and that all final states are of this
form and therefore these are all the
final states.
Okay, cool. Um
so this implies this gives us something
we call uh partially correct.
I'm not going to define this formally.
partially correct machine
is a machine where if it terminates
oh which I haven't defined
uh then
uh gives a correct answer.
What does terminate mean?
Okay. Terminate means uh a state we're
going to say a state machine terminates
or uh really what we're meaning is it
always terminates. No matter how you
execute this machine, it stops. And the
only way it can stop uh is that it
reaches a final state.
If you think about it for a second, the
definition of execution was a sequence
of transitions. And so terminate says
there's no infinite execution. For an
infinite execution, that means every
state qi there's some transition out of
it to qi plus one. Uh so if that's not
possible, that means at some point you
reach a state that's final and from
there there's no uh transition. Okay? So
you could either say it terminates means
there's no infinite execution or every
execution reaches a final state. These
are turn out to be equivalent.
Okay. So now I claim what we've shown is
that for the simple sorter machine it
actually sorts in this partially correct
sense that if the machine terminates
then it will give the correct answer
because if it reaches a final state it's
sorted. That's what we just argued.
Now that's not enough. We also want to
show that it terminates. And so really
the main thing to do
the main thing to do is to prove
termination.
uh and in particular
uh let's say
a machine is correct
uh if it terminates
and produces the right answer which was
partially correct
okay I haven't formally defined right
answer but for the sorting problem it's
clear we want to get them in order so
that this holds
A1 is less than equal to A2 is less than
equal to dot dot dot. Okay, so we've
proved partially correct but we need to
prove correct and uh
in particular we need to show that it
terminates. So we need some tools for
proving termination
for this machine.
Let's go to another board.
We want to make sure that this algorithm
doesn't take forever. It doesn't go in
an infinite loop. Never reaches the
sorted state.
Let me define a general tool for this.
This is how we will always prove
termination in this class.
It's called a derived variable.
Uh this is sort of a reference to random
variables which we will see when we get
to the probability section of the class.
Lots of forward references today. Um
it's very simple. It's just uh for every
state we define a real number x of q
however you want. Okay. In other words,
this is a function
uh from
the set of states to the real numbers.
Okay, in our applications, we're only
going to think of the natural numbers
here, but in general, this could be a
real number.
Okay. And we're going to call it a
derived variable strictly decreasing.
If
uh whenever we have a transition from Q
to R in T, it's a valid transition.
Uh we have x of q is strictly greater
than x of r.
The new value is strictly less than the
old value. That's strictly decreasing.
This is a very strange looking colon.
Okay.
So again this is about a state machine.
So we talk about transitions and every
transition strictly decreases the
derived variable.
Okay. This is going to be our analog to
state predicates and preserved
invariant. State predicates we map to
true and false or zero and one. Now
we're generalizing to allow it to map to
any number, any real number. Okay, but
very similar notion just we're outside
the boolean realm. Now,
uh it's very odd to talk about strictly
decreasing for booleans. And that's we
want we need this.
Okay, here is a wonderful theorem.
It's kind of it'll be obvious once I
state it, but it's very useful for
proving termination. It's how most
termination arguments go.
So it says suppose you have a derived
variable
x of q
uh and suppose it satisfies two
properties.
Property one is it's actually over the
natural numbers not reals.
And property two
is that uh strictly decreasing.
Then
uh state machine terminates.
Okay. So, uh the then is of course what
we want. We want to show that our state
machine terminates. So, a claim this is
all you need to show. You need to
construct some derived variable where
the value is always a natural number.
So, crucially, it's always non- negative
and it's always an integer. That's I I
highlight this instead of putting it in
the definition because this is something
we really need to prove. This theorem is
is false if you allow real numbers. It's
false if you allow negative numbers.
Very important that they're non-
negative integers. So that's something
we need to check. And it's strictly
decreasing.
That's all we need. Then we're
guaranteed the machine will terminate.
Why?
Any guesses why?
Why is this guaranteed that our machine
terminates?
Yeah.
>> Well, when we reach zero, if x is
strictly decreasing, there's nowhere to
decrease. So, there must be no more
transitions.
>> That sounds good. So, when when x of q
reaches zero, I don't know if it does,
but if it reaches zero, you definitely
can't go any farther because there's no
transitions out of zero. You can't
strictly decrease from zero if you're
non- negative. Why do we get to zero?
>> Yeah.
reach a minimum.
>> Okay,
>> we don't necessarily reach zero, but we
get to some minimum. Yeah, I think these
are all in the right direction. I I'll
write down what I would call a sketch.
Uh
that's thinking about it kind of the
other way around. Instead of focusing on
X of Q decreasing,
um I want to think about executions of
this machine, right? We want to prove
that the machine terminates. That means
that there are no infinite sequences. In
other words, all all executions have
finite length. I claim all executions
have length
at most x of q0
because every time I take a step, every
time I do a transition, x decreases by
at least one. If it starts at x of q0,
it can only decrease by one that many
times. At that point it will have to
have reached zero and then it has to
stop. Maybe it stopped earlier. But this
guarantees that it stops. Right? Every
step I make I strictly decrease x of q
by at least one. We start here. We can't
go below zero. So the number of moves is
at most that you can prove this by
induction. Uh but it's kind of
straightforward.
Okay. So you're in the right idea, but
this is a little more precise. Great. So
now let's apply our termination theorem
to the simple sorder machine. Uh but we
need to do that we need to define one of
these derived variables
[Applause]
and
it's actually this one.
I'll be mean and just erase this.
There's our derived variable.
I I'll rewrite it.
So there's a reason these two examples
are in the same lecture. Use the same
idea which is inverted pairs. Oh,
perhaps I shouldn't have erased the
definition of inverted pairs. Sorry. Uh
so back to the simple sorting machine.
Uh we're going to define P of Q to be
the number of inverted
pairs
in state Q.
Okay, that's some number. It's a natural
number, right? It's always greater than
equal to zero. It's always an integer
because inverted pairs were this
discrete object. It was a set I J. Oh,
maybe I need to redefine this a little
bit. Is no longer reading order. So,
what is an inverted pair? This is uh I J
where
uh I is less than J.
uh sorry but
a i is greater than a j so it's a i i i
and j here are indices into this
sequence so in this example uh let's say
uh 62 is inverted because six is to the
left of two but six is greater than two
and that's the opposite of what we want
but also 61 is inverted it's not just
adjacent pairs all the pairs so there's
a bunch of pairs here how many it's
exactly the number of dots in this
diagram. Each dot
which we construct by taking each of
these numbers of the particular height
and drawing a leftward ray a line to the
left and every time we hit another
number that means that number was taller
than I was. So one for example is is
wrong with everybody because it's
supposed to be all the way on the left.
Okay. So with this funny height diagram
you just draw these lines. Those are the
inverted pairs. A nice visualization.
Thanks Zachmore.
and Bmore. Um, so now we think about
what happens when we do a swap. So, for
example, here I swap these two items.
Oh, great. Before six and two were
inverted. Now they're not. And that's
all that changed because we're all in
the algorithm in the transitions, we're
only swapping adjacent pairs. Okay. If I
swap it back, the number uh increases.
Okay. And now if we watch this
algorithm, each time it swaps an
adjacent pair, it decreases
uh by one the number of inverted pairs.
Watch it one more time for fun.
Love this animation.
Okay. So,
I claim this P of Q is strictly
decreasing. Why? because every time I do
a transition from Q to R,
uh, P of R is one smaller than P of Q.
Let's look at the definition of
transition over here.
[Applause]
When I do a transition in this
algorithm, I only swap two adjacent
elements. So the inverted pairs with
everything else doesn't change.
And these guys were guaranteed inverted.
I told you that AI was bigger than AI
plus one whenever I did a transition. So
I decreased by one the number of
inverted pairs here. So uh I strictly
decrease by exactly one every single
time. So in fact the running time of
this algorithm the number of swaps that
we do is exactly the number of inverted
pairs. But in particular it terminates
in finite time. And that's what we get
out of this termination theorem because
we checked uh this function, this
derived variable is non- negative. It's
an integer and it's strictly decreasing.
Therefore, our sorting algorithm
actually terminates. Yay.
Uh
I supposed to do an announcement about
problem sets.
>> Yes,
>> which was
the Oh,
>> yes. We're about to release solutions to
a problem set. Uh problem set one. And
you may recall you can submit your
problem set one anytime between now and
the end of semester. So what do you do?
Are you allowed to look at those
solutions? Yes, you're allowed to look
at the solutions. But you cannot copy
those solutions. You can look at them,
then put them aside, remember the
solution, think about the solution,
write it in your own words how that
solution works, and put at the top of
your document. It says in the
collaboration policy, I looked at the
solutions, but I'm not copying them. If
you copy them, you will be penalized.
Okay? Just
understand how the proof works and then
write down how the proof works in your
own words.
See you next time.