The following content is provided under
a Creative Common License. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
>> Okay, cool. Uh so so we we've uh been
grading the the assignments and uh we
realized that there were a couple of
things about how to write rules that we
hadn't necessarily gone through uh and
uh and one thing that we would like to
see in the next assignment uh are a
couple of uh are a couple of things that
that I'm going to read out now, but
we'll uh we'll probably send out an
email as well so you can have it for
reference. Um, so, uh, having a
paragraph or a overview that broadly
explains what the game is about is
actually really, really useful. Uh, you
know, just jump jumping straight
straight into the, you know, this is
this is how you set up the board and
this is how you, you know, uh, you take
a turn. Um, you know, that's the meat of
the assignment, but just to sort of help
people get a grasp, especially if you
thought about your theme really really
hard in this next coming assignment,
your theme is right there. Explaining
what are you you know, who are you in
this game? What are you trying to do?
Uh, you know, what's your uh what's
what's your overall goal in broad terms,
not necessarily, you know, very specific
game terms. Just having one paragraph is
a really really good idea. Um, and
really like short, concise paragraph.
And that's that's that's one thing.
Okay. Uh, two, a list of components, you
know, uh, in the card game will be like,
you know, we have this many of this many
red cards, this many blue cards, that
that sort of thing, just so that we know
that we've got everything. Uh, it also
helps sometimes to be able to establish
the vocabulary of the game really really
early. So, if all your red cards are
attack cards and all your blue cards are
defense cards and you want to say, you
know, your your deck should have 25 red
attack cards and 25 blue defense cards.
Now, we know if you use the word attack
card and defense card later, we now know
what it means. Um, sometimes it's
obvious from just looking at the cards,
but frankly, you know, when when we are
opening up these cards, usually there's
one person looking at the cards and
somebody else looking at the rules. Uh,
and just having that information
redundant is uh kind of nice. Um, let me
see.
um the the number of players uh uh in
this particular in this particular
assignment I'm trying to remember what
the requirements for it was like two to
four
>> two two to four
>> yeah two uh two to four number of your
of your previous uh projects actually
allowed more more players less less
players we want an explicit line that
says this is how many players your game
supports
just just one line make it like an
ability bullet points and by but by by
the way bullet points being concise um
you know making things really easy to
read uh is a is is is um highly valued.
Um one one thing that you absolutely
should do is make sure that you're
testing your written rules as well as
your game. You know um don't just test
the rules of your game and then you
write it down and you're never actually
testing the written version of your
rules on some one line. Uh you need to
be able to test the written rules as
well. There was some there was some
games that clearly did that and some
games I clearly did. Um and it and it
showed um by the way no one really did
badly last assignment. I just this is
this is I I'm nitpicking because because
this is this is what bumps you from B to
A. Um let's see. Expected playing time.
Um especially in this next assignment uh
you know if your game tends to take 30
minutes uh or your game tends uh tends
to take 10 uh just state it uh if there
if in some games it takes a really long
time to set up and a really fast time to
play then you just state you know
expected setup time blah expected
playing time blur. Um
there was a lot of assumption in the
rules and in the design of the game that
your players are male. Uh this is a very
male
uh uh proportion class right right now.
But uh don't assume that your players
are all male. It's actually really kind
of off-putting to read a set of rules
that just assumes that if you're playing
this game, you are a guy. Um, so there
are a couple of things that people have
done in academia to sort of like address
that issue. I've seen ver I've seen
papers where they sort of use uh
non-specific uh third person pronouns
and just swapping he, she, he, she all
the time unless they're talking about a
specific person. Uh but it but in your
case when you're thinking about your
themes and like don't assume that your
players are male. You can cast them in
the role of a male but you don't say
don't don't assume that a player itself
is male. Yeah.
>> So I'm just going to say put put this
out there in the English language is
actually very masculine oriented. So the
proper way to say in a third person if
you're not saying one says this it's
actually appropriate to say he. That's
actually proper in English language. And
I'm saying that it's off-putting from a
marketing standpoint to make assume that
your players.
>> I'm saying.
>> Yeah. Uh it it goes more to than than
just non-gender
than gender specific pronouns. It it
goes way more than that. There was a lot
of assumptions on like uh
there were specific rules that assumed
that you were a straight male in a
couple of games. Uh so let's let's be
clear about that. Okay. Uh,
>> I was just going to mention that it from
what I've seen in a lot of rule books,
it seems like a lot of people solve this
problem by just
replacing the assumption that the player
is male with the assumption that the
player is female. Like even uh yeah,
I've noticed this even every single
pronoun in every like post second
edition Dungeons and Dragons book is
female.
>> Interesting.
>> And that's actually kind of an
interesting way to deal with it, right?
It's just like you hand the lamp lamb
shader and said we got to use a pronoun
but we don't want to use language that's
going to turn people off the game. So
we're just going to swap all the
pronouns around and all of a sudden you
actually have a more marketable game.
You have a game where someone going to
read the rules and you know and if
they're not a straight male reading the
rules and it's like okay you know uh
clearly this was a gender pronoun swap
but but I can read these these rules
that can make make sense. Whereas, you
know, someone who's not a straight male
reading rules and and going, "Oh, this
game's not for me, so I'm not going to
play the game." You know, that that that
kind of reaction does happen. Uh, you
know, board games are supposed to be
inclusive. Board games and card games
are supposed to sort of like be these
huge socially enabling games uh and and
performance. So, keep that in mind. You
want people to feel welcome when you
read your um if I can just interject. So
something that I've seen um happens a
lot like bridge literature is they make
your partner so one person specifically
is female and the others are male and
that way you kind of have this
inclusivity but then it helps clarify
who you're talking about. So if you are
writing up examples or you know sample
terms or that kind of thing, you can
think about doing it that way as well
because it it does the whole inclusivity
but then again kind of clarifies who
you're talking about in the in the
>> and you know we're at university we're
trying to be like progressive about
this.
>> I find it's generally people's aversion
to writing using
um pronouns which are gender neutral. So
there
um specifically
people worry that there's an ambiguity
between singular and plural and that's
why you shouldn't use that kind of
pronoun. But for the most part it's
always I it's almost always obvious when
you're talking about one person or
multiple people. So
>> I don't even see really why this is
still an issue really.
>> Yeah. It's one of those things where
it's not technically correct to say like
if I'm referring to a single person to
say they or their but like but then if
you if you're reading other things
they'll say do that. Um a lot of people
just are using he or she now. I mean
it's certainly awkward. It's kind of an
awkward but you can also use second uh
if you use second person language you
know you you know when it's your turn
you blah blah blah. And uh also um I'm
trying to think the word player is a
great substitute for a lot. It's like
player one, player two. You can just
revert to those terms.
Um and it's tough. It's tough to write
stuff like this, but you know, sometimes
I find under constraints writing gets
better. Uh because you know, you're more
focused on how your your your writing is
going to be received. And we're trying
to encourage everything in your games to
be better.
Um, I guess this was something that I I
hit on earlier. Um, try to go for short
sentences like not paragraphs of pros.
Those are actually difficult to read
when you're trying to like also process
what the moves are going to be. Uh, go
for active voice rather than passive
voice. uh you know it's I personally
automatically write passive voice when
I'm writing any report and I have to I
have to like physically cheat myself and
you know and tell Microsoft word to
highlight every single instance of
passive voice so that I can actually
correct that um Microsoft Word doesn't
do a great job in highlighting every
single instance but uh you do this often
enough you start picking it up yourself
it's actually easier to read it it's
it's uncomfortable that you're moving
from the from the appeal of writing
technical papers into writing into
writing for general public but active
voice is easier for some of you in
check.
Um
this one I might need more more help and
detail um lists of steps and actions.
So, like if you are
when you're going through the
instructions, it's really helpful to
have numbered sequences. Like instead of
having a a chunk of pros that saying
first do this, then you do this, just
bullet point it or make it a numbered
list. And it's a lot easier for people
to follow. Um, generally speaking,
bullets versus numbers, like you should
use a numbered list if a sequence really
matters, whereas a bulleted list is more
like these are the things that are
important. just not necessarily a
temporal relationship between them.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you know, just just some tips. In
the end, every single game that we
played, we could play. Uh, you know, it
didn't take us long to figure out what
what was necessary. Um, the games were
good. Uh, the games were entertaining
and uh for the four player uh games, we
brought in extra people to come in and
play and we all had had a blast. The
two-player games was just two of us. And
uh yeah um I'm actually really really
impressed because this is the
it's a market improvement over previous
version previous. So
polite golf
y
um all right so so that was uh the stuff
on the assignment and now on to
intellectual property.
This is this is actually um actually how
many people figured out what the that we
had given you the wrong chapter to read.
Okay. All right. For those of people who
ended up reading rereading chapter 3,
I'm sorry. Uh it's not a huge chapter,
but um I kind of want to talk about two
different things. Uh which um both of
which are related to intellectual
property. And one is the version of
intellectual property that presented to
you in the book. Um, you know, in that
sense, that's kind of the game designer
uh um
concept of what intellectual property
is. Often it means a franchise. Often it
means somebody else's story world or
characters. Um maybe it's real people
and their images, you know, like their
faces and and their bodies. If you're
doing sports games, you have to deal
with that a lot. Um, if you there was a
conference this last weekend and uh
there was and one of the the old gardens
of of the Boston game development team
uh who now runs iRacing was talking
about the amount of effort it takes to
actually license a NASCAR car because
it's not just the car but every single
logo that's on that car. um and uh and
and the person who's inside it and the
uniform that they're wearing, every
single logo on their uniform and and
their face, you know, and that's that
that's a lot that goes into licensing uh
for that. It uh it helps that the person
who now owns iRacing is also the same
person who owns the Red Sox. So, they've
got the bankroll to be able to like do
all this. Um but, you know, uh but
that's that's kind of the the idea of
what uh IP is from an industry point of
view. And um that there's a couple of
things that you can do uh that that you
can do and to to consider that not just
all right how do we design this game so
that we can minimize how much IP we need
to license because licensing IP
generally means licensing money that
needs to be exchanged. Um either that
means you're splitting up your royalties
or you're just putting up money up
front. Of course this goes for things
like licensed music for instance. EA has
entire music department. Sega has an
entire music department whose job is
either to create their own music or more
likely license popular music. Um and uh
of course with with harmonics you know
that's half the business right right
there probably more at this point. Um
and then the other thing that you can do
is that assuming that you are working
with a license and the reason why you're
working with license say Lego Star Wars
which came up last in in the last class
how do we do justice to it? How do we
sort of make sure that the fans of those
particular
intellectual property franchises are
going to look at this game that we're
creating and say, "Yeah, that's that's
faithful. That makes sense." Um, we'll
be actually playing a lot more of those
games, I think, later on, uh, for things
like like Battle Star Galactica. Um, but
let's take Lego Star Wars as one
example. You know, the the idea of if
you're a fan of Lego, then you're
probably a fan of building things up
with little plastic blocks. you you like
making stuff combined and um and you
kind of like the whole blockiness that
that look of it. So the folks who make
Lego Star Wars Tra I think they're
called Traveler's Tales um and Lego
Indiana Jones and and those adventure
games kind of had to play that up. They
made a lot of obstacles in the game,
things that were uh that you had to put
together with parts. Um, sure it's just
it's just just holding down one button
to assemble it from a bunch of
disconnected parts. But creating all
that animation and sort of making this
is the main this is one of the main game
mechanics of the entire game was a
decision they had to make and and
they're very consciously making that
because it's Lego where we're going to
assume people are going to make things
and then you find parts in the entire
game that you um can later go back to a
trophy room and you can see your
trophies sort of statues and objects
from the game world that you're trying
to do um sort of build up. So the more
parts you find, they're like the hidden
collectibles that you find in Grand
Theft Auto and they're kind of hidden
away in secret locations and you find
more of them, you know, you go back to
your toky room and oh wow, you have
X-wing, you know, or you have part of an
X-wing. You haven't found half of it, so
all you've got like are the wings and
none of the guns or something like that.
Um, and that sort of, you know, they
they've managed to figure out a way how
that weaves back into basic game
mechanics, but it's still appealing to
uh to to Lego fans. you know, if you get
chopped in half by a lightsaber, you
fall into pieces. You don't actually
bleed, you know, um when the people when
the characters walk, they kind of walk
like that, you know. Um they're a little
bit more flexible than actual Lego
pieces, you know. They don't just move
legs at right angles. Uh but
but they try they try really really hard
to make everything look plasticky. Um
and uh and it pays off. The same thing
goes for Star Wars, right? You know what
are the things that people expect from
Star Wars?
>> Lightsabers.
>> Lightsabers. Okay. Anything else?
>> The Force.
>> The Force. Okay.
>> Darth Vader.
>> Darth Vader. You got to have Darth
Vader. Well, if they're doing it on the
episodes four, five, and six. Actually,
I believe Darth Vader is still an
unlockable in episode 1, 2, and three
because people expect there to be a
Darth Vader. Uh more generally just the
the main characters from the films.
>> Yeah, the main characters from
>> from films.
>> Uh dark fights.
>> Dark fights. I mean like like like ah
that's actually interesting because I
believe they actually didn't do that.
They didn't get to uh they didn't manage
to put that in and but in a lot of other
Lucas games they they they focus mostly
on space flight.
>> Catch phrases.
>> Catchphrases. Uh, I think they weave the
catchphrases into the names of the
levels because they can't because that
that's not actually actual dialogue in
the entire
>> Nobody's Nobody ever says, "I've got a
bad feeling about this."
>> I think I think the title I think that's
the title of the levels and I've got a
bad feeling about this because there's
no dialogue. No one says anything. The
only the only thing that says anything
is R2-D2.
License to voice. Um,
>> actually I have a a really good example
of catchphrases in um I think Rose
Squadron 64. There's this line in one of
the Star Wars movies where Luke is like,
"Our two of my that stabilizer's broken
loose. See if you can't lock it down."
Every like second time you get shot,
they play that recording.
[Music]
And then there's even like a cut scene
where this other pilot is like, "Luke,
my stabilizer's broken, Lewis." And he's
like, "See if you can't have your R2
unit lock it down.
So yeah, I mean a good example like the
far end the worst end was that game.
>> You can overdo it. You can overdo it.
>> Um I'm trying to remember how the force
works. I think you can assemble Lego
blocks from a distance in uh in in Star
Wars if you're playing Obi-Wan. Uh you
can like it's kind of and then like
things just
all Yoda. Um yeah. Uh obviously Darth
Vader's in there. users in the first cut
scene.
>> You know that bear that
>> Yeah. Yeah. You got to have again all
all all all the big characters have got
to be there, right? You got to have your
nuke, you got to have your Z3. And the
interesting thing about that for Lego
game, again, this is this this is a nice
mix between Lego and Star Wars is that
you can play any level with any
character. So, um after you beaten it
once, I think you unlock the ability to
swap characters in, which is more of a
Lego kind of thing, right? I'm just
going to take the characters from this
from the Harry Potter set and put them
into the Lego skip and see what happens.
Um, but you know, uh, that's that's one
thing that you get you get to unlock all
these characters. So, you can play the
whole game with being like the
>> um I think I like
>> you want to have the locals like touch.
Oh yeah, the locations of
on and kind of like some at least some
acknowledgement that there is some
sequence of when people go to each
hotel.
>> Yeah. The Yeah. The game Lego games in
particular basically like follow the
events of the movie specifically. So
it's like each separate event in the
movie is kind of its own level.
>> Yep. Yep. Yeah. Mostly cantina is one
chunk of is one level and you beat that
and you want two. What happens after the
cantina
escape from Tatooine?
>> Yeah, tattoo
after they get off Tatooine.
>> Uh,
>> probably some Death Star.
>> Death Star.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Oh, right right. Right.
>> I was going to say someone should invent
a game where, you know, all the Lego all
the Lego games and you can use any of
the characters interchangeably between
them.
>> Well, there's one company who already
has technology for for for that. You
know, I would love to see Lego Star Wars
slashing the endurance.
you know, and and even better if you can
change the console to Indiana Jones,
which is a budget,
>> like takes off a hat.
>> Yeah. Like blaster whip.
Um, one thing which uh the game these
particular games have done a really good
job with as of bringing music over. Um,
actually, every single Star Wars game
has been very very careful about making
sure that it sounds like Star Wars, the
sound effects and the music as well. Um,
plus a lot of it is actually developed
with the Lucas Arts license. Um, which
is obviously under the Lucas umbrella.
So they they make it makes it a little
bit easier. Lucas is actually the the
the company um of the whole Lucas
family, Lucas Arts, Lucas Film and
everything. Um, it's actually really
really tightly centrally controlled by
George Lucas uh himself. Partly for
quality control, partly for control
freak issues. Uh but you know in in the
end what it does make it really really
easy as for say how many folks played
the force unleashed.
>> Um the live action trails are awesome
>> the second one.
>> Oh I haven't seen live action trailer.
>> They they do really good. They blend the
in game footage live action. They go
back and forth and it's really hard to
tell where
>> you have like really cool lights.
>> I actually wonder whether the character
is actually based on the case of a real
>> It must be because it's the exact same
case.
>> Okay. Um yeah. uh a lot of techn a lot
of the assets that they use in the
movies uh were brought over into the
game obviously with some with some
tweaks to make it run better in the
game. Um a lot of stuff in the uh in the
force unleash like when you use your
force powers and you smash things uh
which is actually most of the game as I
recall. Um a lot of that that same
technology is actually technology that
they use in the films to simulate things
being smashed. Uh, that being said, that
particular example is probably not a
good instance of something that any
player is going to notice. It's like,
why do I care that things that are
breaking in the game break exactly the
same way in the movie, but you know, um,
but they do more more more usefully. You
see art assets, you see the same concept
art, you know, moving between the
between the games really smoothly.
Travis Tales is actually um and the Lego
Star Wars games are uh a little bit
further out. Obviously, those are third
party. Those are separate from the
Lucasf family. They had to actually
license both Lego and Star Wars. Um, but
Lego already had a relationship with
Star Wars obviously because they're
making these toys. Um, so it's a little
bit easier for them to to to negotiate
that. And that's a game developer issue
I believe uh with a post mode of how
they actually manage that. Um, so you
know, uh, but you know, uh, again,
they're going to be very, very careful.
Even Lucas, even though it's not Lucas's
own company, they're going to be very,
very careful that is at least matching
up with Lucas's control of the product.
Um, and if you're a developer working
with a license, often it's just a long
process of just earning trust back from
the uh from the original license
holders. Jason Dean is actually uh our
art director in this lab and he used to
work with um THQ which made a lot of uh
DS and Wii titles specifically on uh
Disney and Pixar products. Um so uh one
one problem with the DS is that it's not
it doesn't have a huge amount of uh 3D
processing quality. Uh whereas you know
obviously the six movies they've got all
the power in the world to do awesome
looking 3D. Um, so some of the tricks
that they had to do to be able to get
the characters, you know, to be faithful
to the characters in the um in in a
movie are kind of interesting. So, um,
do if folks remember Pixar films, you
know, there's a lot of them have these
opening and closing sequences that are
actually animated in completely
different style. Like maybe it's
handdrawn, maybe it's paper cutouts. Um,
and uh, and those are still emblematic
of pixel style even though they're not
super 3D realistically rendered. And a
lot of the DS games that that Jason be
worked on will use those tricks. They
they'll make a game instead of making it
look like it's all 3D, they make it look
like it's all cut out of cardboard. Uh,
because that's that's that's part of the
movies. Um, and the DS has a much easier
time with that.
Um,
one thing that's kind of useful, uh,
when you're thinking about what to take
from a franchise or a license is to look
at the verbs that, uh, that that that
come out from that franchise. Uh, and I
kind of I I think we have enough time.
I'd like to do an exercise where like we
pick up a franchise and um and you just
try to come up with a bunch of verbs
that sort of make that franchise unique
or at least you expect to see in that
franchise. Is there um but I like some
some examples. Um I'm going to just
start with movies and see if we can get
at least one that everyone's fairly
familiar with and uh and and if not then
I'll try books or or other kinds of
media properties. Anyone want to throw a
movie that maybe everyone in here should
be familiar with?
>> Independence Day.
>> Independence Day. Has anyone not seen
Independence Day?
>> Okay.
>> All right. Actually, let's let's just
throw out a few rins. So, does
Independence Day Twilight?
>> Okay. All right. I'm going I'm going to
go this way. Any
>> day
>> Twilight.
>> Lord of the Rings.
>> Inception.
>> Iron Man.
>> The Matrix.
>> The Matrix. Okay, we hit seven and I
think that's all I can remember. So, uh,
Inception, Iron Man,
uh, The Matrix,
>> Paris Day's
Day, Twilight,
>> never seen Twilight.
>> Um,
>> I'm going to pick Inception. How Who's
not seen Inception?
>> Haven't seen Inception.
Which which have you seen?
>> I've seen all
not all the other ones. Yeah.
>> The slight problem is a matrix that
there's already a number of on it. So
everyone seen
>> it
all.
>> Montipython.
>> Does anyone not know Montipython?
>> Holy Grail.
>> But I think Home Alone. Home Alone.
>> Homeown.
It might have been a Home Alone game,
but I but I bet no one here played it.
>> Home is impressive.
>> They were for the original Game Boy.
>> Oh, okay.
>> It's actually one of the first Game Boy
games my brother ever got.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Um
>> I haven't tried Lord of the Rings, but
maybe a specific Lord of the Rings. Uh,
which is the king?
>> I haven't seen
what
>> fashion.
>> No, not really.
>> No.
>> Fashion. I've seen Fellowship.
>> Wait, what about the Matrix? The Matrix.
>> Oh,
>> no. The Matrix. There too many games on
it.
>> Yeah. So,
>> two towers.
>> I'm going to Okay. All right. I'm really
curious how Ferris Builders Day off as a
game. Uh I'm going to if somebody would
like to volunteer a quick summary of
what Ferris Buer's Day Off is about
which is Matthew.
>> Uh well
>> well okay so the basic idea is the main
character Ferris is played by Matthew
Broadick. Matthew.
>> Uh, the idea is that like he's the
infamously super popular clown, like
class clown kid in school, and he
decides to just play Hookie with
essentially his girlfriend and his best
friend. And the whole movie is them
going around the city getting into wacky
misadventures while the principal tries
to catch him playing hookie because he
hates
>> and it's awesome. Yeah,
>> it is incredible.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, so actually that whiteboard would be
>> Has anyone heard the fight club theory
of day off?
>> Best friend.
>> Yeah. Cameron.
>> Um, I'm going to stand up this screen.
Um,
>> wait. Who hasn't seen Fight Club?
>> Fight Club.
>> Has anyone seen Fight Club?
>> That's another one.
today.
>> Yeah, but I feel
that way actually because I think I
think that game would have benefited
from the exercise that we're about to
do.
>> How could that even
>> like both controllers control the same
character?
>> Metal Gear Solid stuff right there.
>> Psycho.
see.
>> So, we're just going to bring up a
notepad thing. And I kind of and I want
people to start thinking about verbs.
What are the verbs that are that either
are make Paris Day kind of unique or
really you that's what you think of when
you think of Paris Day? When you think
of Paris Day?
>> Yeah. Verbs. What do they do? What do
the characters do?
>> Bad karaoke.
>> Sing.
>> They sing.
>> Well, they
deceive.
>> What?
>> They deceive.
>> Let's let me make sure we
>> live life.
>> Lie. They lie.
>> Okay. So, uh they they
deceive or lie. Uh they run.
>> They run or elude.
>> They run.
>> They they definitely do.
>> Yeah.
>> They drive.
>> They do more than what? They trick.
>> They trick.
>> Yeah. Let's deceive you.
>> Yeah.
>> They be spontaneous.
Uh, they improvised.
>> They get in trouble.
>> They get in trouble. There's got to be a
verb for
>> and get out of trouble.
>> They mischief.
>> Mischief.
>> Mischief. That's a word that should
probably be in there. I mean, that might
be actually a back of the box or or
tagline.
What else?
>> Anything else they do there?
>> Behide.
>> They hide. I guess that's that if I run
elude those kind of stuff
>> exploit
>> advantage
>> they take advantage
>> they they take they take take advantage
okay you know uh exploit
>> they may impress
>> they impress
>> relax
>> uh at some point
>> relaxing
basically
>> one guy is very relaxed
>> they is they hack.
>> Do they hack into the computer
>> in the into the uh school computer?
>> Yeah, I forgot all about that. I
>> was going to say board games.
>> There is only board games. Yeah,
>> that that's too easy. That's a movie.
>> That game was that saying the only right
move is not to play.
>> Yeah, that
>> that's four games.
>> Um well, they don't ruin it. Let's see
what else. It's a classic line you hear
that you haven't seen.
>> Do they ever support each other or do
they just like
>> stress each other out?
>> Stress each other out.
>> Scheme is so much better than plan.
>> I don't like these negative words.
This this may not be what the main
characters do, but uh they campaign
uh they they they run a campaign to save
Ferris.
>> Um so Ferris, the idea is that Ferris is
basically pretending that he's ill and
deathly ill. And so so a bunch of the
students in the school are running a
campaign to raise funds for his medical.
>> Well, everyone says in like the police
station police station, she goes, "Oh,
tell your brother to feel better." And
also the water tower scripted on it.
>> Yeah. So, so yeah. And and and you can
think about what those those works
associated with like you know putting
signs up and painting.
Um and you know if you look at this list
and the list can probably get much
longer than this but this is a fairly
fairly unique collection. maybe not so
unique if you compare it to other sort
of high jinks movies, but it's not like
we've had a lot of video games in
particular that are in that vein. Um,
and uh and and we pro probably should
have because it sounds like it's going
to be heck a lot of fun. Um I actually
the one game that makes me that reminds
me of this is actually Bully uh which
was released by Rockstar where you sort
of do these things but it's much more
vengeful. It's it's much more I'm going
to get I I I I'm going to show the other
bullies in in the school how it's done.
Um
>> whereas this one is kind of more good
nature. Um they they parade actually.
>> Yeah.
>> Mr. Parade is also part of the sing
badly part.
>> Yeah.
>> Because they go parade and then they
sing.
>> But singing madly wouldn't have the same
impact if there wasn't a brass band
behind it.
Um,
so you know, you can think about how any
of these verbs, and we we've done this
exercise of like taking verbs and
turning them into game mechanics before.
And you can think about how any of these
verbs could actually be turned into a
game mechanic. The goal, you know, kiss
might be a goal or it might be a rule of
mechanic to be able to accomplish some
something. Uh, parade might be a
setting, campaign might be, you know, a
collection of mechanics uh that feed off
each other. There could be a whole
system that basically tells you how
successful your save ferris campaign is
going. You could make a game just all
about saving ferris, you know, uh as
opposed to playing ferris wheel itself.
Um
uh
yeah, you know, and and and that's kind
of one exercise that you can do when
you're thinking about your real world
systems in all the systems that you guys
are dealing with as far as I can recall.
Uh you don't have to worry about license
of the IP, but you're basically working
with a real life franchise. You know,
it's like if you're doing something
based on political diplomacy or
something like that, you know, then
there are real life
source material things that you're
trying to be faithful to. And going
through this exercise of okay, so what's
the ver what what are all the verbs in
this idea that we're that we're working
with in this system that we're working
with? What do people actually do? Uh
it's a good exercise to be able to try
to be faithful to that system.
Uh and then you don't have to do it all.
because you know you just kind of cherry
pick and maybe you want to prioritize a
little bit and says okay what things can
we get rid of and still very still
clearly a ferris wheel game um you know
running uh I think I think as long as
you have some kind of evasion thing uh
you know physical running may not be
necessary you could do something like as
long as they're not in one location
where the principle is at any given time
you're good but you don't have to
physically move through a 3D space and
all that
>> um
>> drive probably
>> driving yeah it's such a minor part of
the film. Well, it yeah, it it the
actual driving is such a minor part of
the film that that that that you know,
you you can probably uh do without that.
Um and and you and you might actually
want to think about, you know, what if
instead of this being Ferris Builder's
day off into Ferris Builders multiple
days off, you know, it's like you just
play each day differently and you're
just trying to stay out more and more
days, maybe maybe it's a number of days
that you don't go to school or
something. Um so that's that's an idea.
Um but that's that's kind of the
approach that one approach that you can
use in in in your your projects.
>> Great. Um before we hit two, I want to
touch on another point uh be uh before I
transition any questions about
dealing with it franchises. Um, there is
a point that Brenda makes in her book
and the Brenda and Ian make her book
that if you go professionally into game
industry, you will most likely at some
point of time probably many times in
your career work with a licensed product
and it can be painful because you do not
have creative control. Um, yet you're
trying to be faithful to to to to
what you're working with and uh if you
and if you succeed, you make a lot of
money uh and maybe you get enough money
to start working on your own projects.
But um it's it's it's a reality because
franchises do sell and there are a lot
lower risk than uh dealing with a
completely new idea.
Um by the way, if you haven't played the
new Tomb Raider game, uh which is
actually kind of uh interesting because
it's like Tomb Raider meets Diablo. And
uh for people who if people have never
for who's who's played or seen someone
play Tomb Raider before,
>> okay, who knows about this latest game
that I'm talking about? It's kind of
like three three/arter isometric view.
Yeah, it's um it is two raider meet
meets the other with but it still keeps
some of the puzzle solving. It's
cooperative. It's a very very different
game in terms of how you play it. But uh
it would be an interesting exercise to
sort of like play that play that that
game may maybe uploaded up here sometime
and you can take a look and see how does
that really Tomb Raider franchise so
that people who say who look at the game
still say yeah that's Tomb Raider even
though it's a very different game. Um,
you can imagine like a Tomb Raider board
game for instance and how would that be
different and how could that still be?
That's World of Warcraft games and
Starcraft board games I believe, you
know, like that's I can't even think
conceive how that works, but I'd love to
try it out.
>> Um, let's see. So, the the other point I
want to get to is kind of the legalistic
definition of IP. And uh I don't want to
spend an entire class on this because I
know you will all fall asleep. Um, I
just want to point out that there's
quite a lot of different ways that
intellectual property protected. You
know, people who are creating stuff
professionally, creatively, uh, want to
make sure that they can finish their
product, they can make sequels of their
product. They can maybe even license
their their ideas to someone else, you
know, being IP for some other company
without having their ideas copied out
outright and, you know, not seeing any
compensation for that. But there's like
copyrights, there's trademarks, there's
patents.
I feel like I'm missing something.
Well, I I I can speak on those three
first. And and and and if anything,
those are definitely the three big ones.
Um for copyright, copyright basically
protects an expression of an idea. The
idea itself is not protected. Whatever
you know if if your basic idea is you
know in a world where uh aliens are
attacked by space marines um you know
the idea itself is not protected which
is which is a relief because a lot of
people have made games on those on that
idea
>> but the actual expression is so the
actual um say say if you're an artist
and you're creating concept art based on
that thing that piece of concept art is
a is copyrighted to to either you or if
you if you're an employee of a company
then you probably signed over your
rights to the company that whatever
you're creating on day or dying belongs
to the company. Um, and that's
defensible in court. It's actually an
automatic protection, but it's one of
those things where if um it helps to be
able to document that you've actually
created something. there's a copyright
office that you can send things to, but
for the most part, internal company
documentation saying this piece of art
was created on this so and so date by so
and so person um is usually good enough
to hold up uh to stand up in in in court
if there's ever a dispute. Um so
um same thing goes for writing, the same
thing goes for audio and music. A lot of
music is is pro is protected under
copyright. Um, so if somebody creates a
piece of music that sounds an awful lot
like your piece of music, there are
actually rules that there are specific
rules that allow that for that to
happen. But, um, I think if you
completely reperform the piece, you are
allowed to do that, but you may have to
pay the original composers, the uh,
royalties for music. This means that if
person A composes a song, band B
performs
a
performs a song um and releases it on an
album, band C could actually reperform
that song and the only royalties goes
back to composer. Doesn't necessarily go
back to to tok
B. Um however, band u it depends on
really how close they sound to each
other. And of course, if that be happens
to be also the composers, then they're
going to get around anyway. But you you
see the sort of idea that that copyright
protects the expression of an idea. The
composers at some point of time had to
write down the music, the notes and the
lyrics and uh and that that is what is
protected and you can't just copy that
without at least entering into some sort
of contract saying that you can. Um we
have systems like creative comments for
instance uh that basically people who
are creating new IP say under these
conditions I'm letting people do
whatever they want with with it and
there are different kinds of creative
comments licenses some of them let you
do literally whatever you want with it
they're like open source licenses and in
some cases it's like well you can do
whatever you want with it as long as for
non-commercial use and you have to
credit the origin creator that sort of
thing. Um so that's that's why creative
comments kind of evolve. So to enable
people to freely do stuff without
necessarily uh uh without necessarily
having to pay and enter into separate
contracts with everybody who's creating
IP. Um so the problem is with code in
many many if code and game mechanics
actually for this class uh is something
that I want to consider because code you
can think of code in two ways. One, you
can think of it as a chunk of text. You
know, it's a chunk of asky symbols that
you type into a into a development
environment and you compile it and
that's an expression of an idea. But the
other thing the other way that you can
think of it is it's a machine. It's a
bunch of instructions that you feed into
a machine for it to operate in some way.
And those things machines inventions
basically can be protected by patents.
Um that that's pretty much what the
patent system is designed for. patent
systems a lot slower is you actually
have to apply to the central US patent
office to be able to get to secure
those. Um assuming that you're looking
for patent protection in the US. Every
single country, every single region has
its own patent office and its own
process. It's really expensive. Um what
it does is basically give you a
temporary monopoly on that invention. Uh
at least that's what it was originally
originally originally designed for. You
make a an an inventure then you got like
25 years or something. uh to be able to
capitalize on it before you anyone can
use your idea. And the whole reason why
it's invented is that you have now an
incentive to be able to come up with
inventions. You might make some profit
off it. And after the the the the your
patent expires 25 years or something
because you've released your information
to the patent office now all of society
can benefit can make derivatives of your
invention. So in a sense it was invented
to sort of eventually release break
monopolies. I got this idea and I am
going to state to be upfront and very
clear about how I made this thing work.
Say Amazon patents one click and I'm
going to say for the next 25 years
Amazon now has this lock on oneclick
shipping uh and and purchasing which is
really annoying but it's been quite
annoying. Um and uh but after 25 years
anybody can do one click uh uh shipping
but that's the problem right 25 years is
a heck of a long time and by then
whatever is invented it's kind of
obsolete and a lot of the ideas that
tend to get approved by the patent
office are pretty damn obvious. Um I'm
not going to disparage the amount of
work that Amazon's actually put into
oneclick shipping. It's actually a
really complex process.
But I am going to disparage Sega's
patent on the giant floating arrow that
tells you where you are supposed to go
next. They have a patent on this. Namco
has a patent on mini games that you play
while your game is loading. That's why
only Namco games have mini games on
their in those screens because they have
a patent on that. When it comes to game
ideas and game mechanics, I find this
really annoying. It's a personal rant
because uh uh because uh that's I I
think that stifles creation instead of
of opening it up. It's really it really
really sucks. Um I don't really think
game mechanics fit in the in the in the
>> really Apple has is on all the touching
>> on their gestures. So a lot of people
can't
>> a lot of people have the same uh the the
same issue I have with game mechanics
with software in general. You know, it's
like software happens so quickly that
this kind of temporary monopoly
basically means a real monopoly over the
idea.
>> I thought that game rules were not
patentable or covered by copyright. I
seem to remember hearing that somewhere.
So for instance, you can and this was an
issue which came up when Scrabul and
Scrabble were at loggerheads with one
another. There's some weird technical
detail that I don't fully know, but it
kind of comes down to the actual rules
of Scrabble
are not or the the actual game rules
themselves like
>> are not copyrightable, but somehow like
the look and feel of your game is do you
know what the specific details are? I
don't know the specific details, but how
you outlined it is one very clear way on
how a someone who's created a game can
protect the game without necessarily
being protective of the rules. That
Scrabble can protect the layout of their
board because that's because in order to
come to design that layout, they had to
express the idea of what the board was
with graphic design. You know, it's like
here's where triple words are here where
our double words. That's an image.
images can be copyrighted and thus
protected under copyright law not
>> well and I think I think at least with
copyright and trademarks it comes down
to like confusion right like if someone
could if if Scrabulus was similar enough
to Scrabble superficially that someone
could confuse their products I think
that is like a major criteria right it's
about like and and again yeah that comes
down to things like font you know what
color is the title what color is the
word it's even more specific when it
comes to trademarks Yeah. If if if
you're if it's like the name of your if
if if if you can claim that the image of
or or or or say if a a particular saying
or something is closely associated with
your company's core brand, you can
defend that as a trademark if you
register it with a trademark office. So
Gam Gambit, the Singapore MIT Gambit
Game Lab actually a registered trademark
in in Singapore. Um, actually we had
some trouble registering that because
we're clearly not the first company to
come along with the word Gambit. Uh,
there's actually another MIT product
called Gambit. It's u it's actually game
theory bonding system. Um, so so we we
actually had to negotiate some fine
waters to be able to separate what we
were doing was not going to be confused
with what they were doing.
>> Um, are copyrights and trademarks also
for 25 years or are they
>> different? Copyright.
>> Yeah. And copyrights last as long as
Walt Disney is dead. That is because the
Disney Corp keeps lobbying
um the various branches of United States
to extend copyright so that they can
lock down Mickey. Um that's that's
that's that's the easiest way to tell
exactly how long. In other words, right
now you got something copyrighted, it's
in perpetuity until Disney loses.
>> Um, this is actually really annoying,
which means there's a whole bunch of
works of literature, for instance, that
are, you know, that date back to the
early um 20th century that still that by
all means really should be public domain
at this point in time. And again, they
will pass into public use, but they
aren't. Um, I know one thing for sure,
HP Lovecraft is definitely uh in public
domain. That's why everyone that there
are so many games based on HD
material um not that but not you know
whatever's based on Disney material has
to be made by Disney um or will run a
file of corporate
um
one thing um about rules
actually I think I think we kind of
covered that but yeah you know images if
if the scrabble board is um is
identified as being key to the Scrabble
brand. You kind you might be able to
protect it under trademark. Um and uh
tra trademark is one of those things
where all you're saying is that this is
how our company's identifying ourselves.
And if that is confused with any with
with somebody else's product, that
product is now hurting our ability to
make money. Uh so there are laws that
allow you to to fight that. The problem
with trademark is that you have to keep
fighting that. Um so Xerox for instance
constantly fights to keep Xerox as a
trademark because people keep using the
word Xerox to mean photocopy. Um you
know which is a great problem for a
company to have but it's actually a cash
drain as well because you know
everyone's assuming that you know
associating your company's name with uh
you're thinking of Google right
>> I think I think by law actually too many
people use it. Yes,
>> it's a band-aid, I'm pretty sure.
>> So, you have to fight it.
>> As long as you keep fighting it, uh you
stand a chance of of hanging on to it.
So, um but if you you know like like
Kleenex, if you blink, you know, you
know, it might be taken away from from I
remember hearing about this. I was
looking to find it, but uh Richard
Garfield who created Magic
>> has a patent on methods of play for
trading card games
>> like
>> and one of the elements of the patent is
playing a card in a certain orientation
and then turn changing its orientation
in the game field to signify a different
state of that of that character.
>> Now that's
stupid
tapping cards. Yeah, the patent is among
many other things that are basically so
I suspect that he doesn't enforce this
patent or that is not enforceable
because if you try to enforce it, it
gets rubbed out. It
>> is possible that it's not
>> I don't know the the actual
manifestation of that is that um I don't
know whether wizards contested people
over it, but definitely they're anti-
anyone else using the term tap. Mhm.
>> So, which is why whenever you go to look
at Legend of the Five Rings or what have
you, they have the turn sideways
mechanic, but it's called bowing.
>> But, and the same is true of any
collectible card game that has a tap
mechanic.
>> They're not allowed to use the word tap,
>> but that's a copyright
>> except except that Yeah, it's a
copyrighted
tap. The patience.
>> So, I don't know if it's been tested
because def I don't know if that patent
has been contested.
>> I would suspect not.
>> Probably not. But it's it's interesting
that uh however if you look at any of
the Wizards range of products so
including Pokemon and I don't recall
what the others are they all use the
term tap. So and but seems that because
of the copyright which they hold
>> they're allowed to do it but nobody else
>> a copyright violation probably gives
evidence for a patent violation. So, so
you know, um, if you can stay clear of
the copyright vi violation, the case
that Wizards has to be able to contest
the same mechanic in somebody else's
gets a little bit weaker.
>> But they might still have a case. They
just
>> I think that I suspect that they think
that their patent is not enforcable.
>> It's possible.
>> Otherwise, you wouldn't be able to get
away with not even calling it tapping as
long as you turn a card. They would be
able to say, "Hey, we have a method."
>> Ridiculous. entering one or more cards
into the play by playing one or more
cards face up in the first orientation
and the player's option uh you you know
turning the trade card in other
orientation in the playing surface
doesn't even say for any reason just
like they battles you have to turn a
card upside down or like subway uh
submarine cards you can flip them upside
down to change it from
>> um
train card
>> well no it's me a method of playing
games though when two or more players
love the block
>> doesn't say anything about train cards
So you can see how this gets annoying
and quick, but there's actually a
unfortunately actual good reason why
things like a mechanics and more often
implementations of the mechanism code
are protected by patents is in that
because there are already so many out
there. If um if your company is just
trying to make a game, the likelihood
that you're going to run a file of
patents actually pretty high. Um, so
what do you do if you've got something
that you know that you created? A lot of
companies just go and patent that. In
the event that it turns out to be a case
where you run a file of a different
patent, they might actually look at uh
the company that's suing them and say,
"But you are running a file of our
patents because we just also trademark
uh patented something pretty obvious."
Um, uh, EA activation
>> Yeah. What?
>> It's all just mutually assured.
>> Exactly. I mean well it's not
destruction it's what they do is they
trade licenses it's like you know we
will let you use these patterns and you
will let us use that patterns and thus
avoid a legal fight but of course
lawyers are getting paid throughout this
entire process
>> u it's cheaper than actually bringing it
into court because
>> you can get a your patent is validated
if you can if it can be shown that
someone else came up with it earlier
>> in time you have to be the first person
to come up with
>> although there's also a nonobvious is an
obvious clause.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's why I'm sure that that Wizard
has never tried to actually use the
patent against people because they
suspect that it's not going to hold up
an obvious clause.
>> It's possible. You may not want to fight
it, but it's sometimes the threat of a
lawsuit is a big enough threat. Uh it's
like you don't even have to be able to
win it. It just we are a big company. We
have lawyers and we can pay them. Do
you? you know, and it's
um so that's one reason I mean why
companies that are otherwise opposed to
the idea of patents will still secure
patents protect them to protect their
jobs. And it's it's kind of sad. It's
like one of those things where you know
in a city where everyone owns a gun, you
want to own one. You want to own one
too, you know, sort of thing. Um so
that's patents. I've talked about
trademarks. We talked about uh
copyright. And one last thing I kind of
want to talk about is fair use. Um, you
know, fair use is one is kind of the
defense that a lot of schools fall back
on. And the idea is that if you're doing
something for if you're appropriating
some sort of material for uh or some
sort of IP for political or educational
reasons, uh you have a defense. Should
the case be brought to court, you might
be able to defend yourself and win that
case by saying, well, this was the
reason. So if I'm doing something for
satical purposes, I'm doing something
for uh to teach people uh about about
games for instance, you know, and I'm
going to like reprint rules or something
and then you guys can can look at it and
witness of the coast can sue me and I
can claim fair use. I may not win.
That's the problem. Fair use is only a
defense. Fair use is not a law that
automatically
get protects me from being taken to
court. So lawyers fees still get still
have to be um who pays the lawyer's fees
depends on who gets the the the the case
but frankly I would rather not be put in
that position. So there is that chilling
effect you know um
so uh just just just keep that in mind
you know of the games that you guys are
making these are class assignments um
but of course we don't expect you to be
say copying text verbatim from other
rule sets in fact I doubt any of you
will be particularly interested in doing
so um certainly not copying art uh and
uh but also keep in mind that also
applies for things like art that you
find online um you could protect
yourself under fair use. This is for a
class assignment. Darn it. You know, um
and for the most part, no one's really
going to notice, but of course, if you
want to take these games a little bit
further, maybe sell them in the future,
you want to rethink about every single
piece of art, every single piece of text
that you're using in your game, is that
is that coming from somewhere else or
can we claim that?
>> Has any past students or groups tried to
pitch their games anywhere?
>> Oh, you mean like a turn commercial?
>> Yeah. Um, not to my right, but I really
>> Yeah. Yeah. Do it. I mean, like based on
the games that I that that we saw that
that that we played on Tuesday.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Um, actually, one of the pieces of
feedback that we got from the gambit
folks, every single one of those games
does something that not seen before in
in in car game. Uh, so every every one
of those projects had a really
interesting mechanic and as far as I can
tell, they were all really tested. So,
All right.
Okay. So, I'm not going any more into
like IP discussions. My I spent too much
time talking to IP lawyers because we
create IP in this lab. We create games.
Uh if anyone happens to be interested, I
was considering a career in law. Uh you
know, I'll be happy to to to go into
greater detail. Uh but for now, um any
more questions?
Okay, that's just names.