good morning good morning afternoon I
guess technically uh welcome to lecture
15 of 61200 6120 again I still don't
know how to call it um today we are
talking about relations and
Counting um and there's a bunch of scary
stuff on the board ignore that
wonderful so first thing we're talking
about is
relations uh and relations are a very
useful tool U very useful term
generalizing the idea of a function um
so let's see what we mean by that um
let's see
so yes so a
relation R is a subset of A cross B A
and B are sets they can be any sets you
want R is going to be a subset of pairs
um where the first element is taken from
a the second element is taken from B it
might be all the pairs none of the pairs
some subset of the pairs um all we know
is that we need all three of these
pieces of data uh a relation
consists of first of all a
domain a which is any set
a
co-domain b which is a
set and a
subset are subset of A cross
B so you need to know what is your
domain what is your co-domain and which
pairs are part of your
relation um this generalizes the idea of
a function because you can think of a
function as you have your inputs you
have your outputs and your function
specifies which inputs map to which
outputs by just encoding them in a pair
like this um Let me give a more concrete
example here we go so imagine we have
these three sets we have the set of
students that are Luke geralt Quinton
and Willow um and we have some classes
that these magic students might take in
a magic school I guess uh chemistry
Sports literature and
61200 totally makes sense um and we have
some magic profs we have gadriel Zelda
Zelda Ada and Doctor
Strange um so we have some sets we might
specify a relation uh let's call it the
learning relation L which is going to be
a subset of students cross classes so
it's going to be all pairs where you
have a student who's taking a class and
in this case it looks like we have these
students taking these classes it looks
like Luke is taking chemistry Luke is
also taking literature Galt is taking
chemistry and sports and literature Etc
so we need all three of these pieces of
information the domain the co-domain and
the set of pairs in order to specify
this
relation likewise here's another
relation which classes are being taught
by which professors so this is a subset
of classes times professors
and it's saying that um this class
chemistry is being taught by this
professor Ada Sports is being taught by
strange lit by gadriel and 61200 is
being taught by Zach I mean
Zelda thank you
um this might look pretty familiar this
is almost how we Define directed graphs
right um You have some some set of
vertices or whatnot uh and you have some
edges between them this is very closely
related concept um and just like with
graphs
um that representation isn't the most
useful way to represent it it's kind of
hard to see who's taking what and
visualize and and think about it so
let's draw it instead so we already said
uh here we have the learning relation
ill uh we said Luc is taking chemistry
and I'm going to draw it with a directed
Arrow um Luke is also taking literature
geralt is taking
chemistry uh and sports geralt is taking
also
literature then Quinton is taking Sports
and lit Quinton is taking Sports and lit
uh and Willow is taking lit and
apparently no one is taking 61200 at
this magic school uh shame for them but
this is a very clear representation in
my mind but again it's representing the
same information and we can see that in
fact this is
exactly a directed graph where the
vertices are um what is it students
union classes those are our allowed
vertices and it just has the special
form where each one of our directed
arrows always goes from a student to a
class but otherwise it's just a directed
graph does that make sense let's quickly
draw the other one um so we have
chemistry being taught by Ada we have
sports being taught by
strange lit by
gadriel and 61200 by Zelda so this is
the um the teaching
relation are we clear on what these
examples
are um
wonderful
so for notation there are lots of
different notations that are used for
relations because relations are used in
lots of different ways um but here are
some common
notations so if R is a
relation from A to B uh then we might
write um a relates to
B to mean that the pair a comma
B is one of the pairs in our relation
one of the directed edges in our
graph um because like I said the
relation is really about specifying
which pair pairs relate and which pairs
don't it's a yes no question some of the
pairs are yes some of the pairs are no
and so we might write a relates to B
with this infix notation to say that a
relates to B um we're saying the same
thing just with different notation um
and this might remind you of things like
three um like three is less than seven a
sub um a set s is a subset of a set T
this less than relation this subset
equal relation these are relations and
this General notion of relation is a way
to generalize Concepts like this and so
this is why we sometimes have our infix
notation like that so we can think about
whatever other relation we're talking
about similar to how we think about
these more familiar
ones all
right um we
also we can also think of r as a
predicate we can say R of a comma
B so if R is a predicate that takes two
arguments and say and spits out true or
false this is another way you can think
of specifying a subset of
pairs so R AB is true when AB is part of
our relation and it's false when it's
not and phrase wise we might say that
a
relates to B
again means the same
thing means that a B is in
r at its core we we are just trying to
give one bit of information for each
pair either this pair relates or this
pair doesn't this pair is in our set or
it's not this pair satisfies our
predicate or it doesn't all different
ways of saying the same
thing does that make sense wonderful uh
and by the way when we say relation here
uh specifically we're talking about
binary
relation um yeah that should say a
relation but all the relations we're
going to talk about today are binary but
it's the same relation as in relational
database um you can imagine that this
kind of thing is exactly how a database
stores its information in this case
we're only talking about databases with
two
columns um so learning has a column for
a student and a column for class and
there's a row every time a student's
taking a class that's all this is It's a
database excuse me um
yes so I said
earlier that here let's go back up
here that relations are a generalization
of functions and let's see what we mean
by that
so
definition a relation R from A to
B is a
function uh precisely
when
every element on the left
side relates to at most
one
element on the right side so if every
everything in the left set appears on
the left side of at most one pair it's
the source of at most one Arrow so
another way to say that
is
um every a in
a has at most
one Arrow
out all right so these two examples is
this learning relation a
function who can tell me
why yeah we have a student with multiple
arrows going out that's precisely what
we need to avoid it's function says each
each node on the left is supposed to
have at most one Arrow going out uh and
this fails that is this a
function yeah um every class has at most
one Arrow out so it's a function if I
deleted this
Arrow so now we only have these three
arrows and no one's teaching 61200 is
this still a
function yeah it's fine at most one
Arrow not exactly one Arrow so that's
still fine even if that arrow is missing
but I'm going to put it back because
that's our
example uh let's
see when R is a
function uh we'll write R of
a equals B to
mean means that a B is in the relation
and so R of a is the element that a
points to if it exists R A might be
undefined uh if the function doesn't
have any Arrow out at this point but if
there's only one we we can just call it
R of a this is the usual function
notation that we're used to
uh let's make that even more
precise uh let's look at the function
f um from
R to R by the way when it's a function
we can use this more specific notation
um f is a function from R to R we use
the arrow instead of f as a subset of R
cross R um
so let's define the function where f
ofx is 1x^2
the kind of function you might see in a
pre-calculus class or
something um everyone agrees this is a
function well I mean kind of how is it a
function by our definition of
relation um we're supposed to specify a
domain check a co-domain check and a set
of pairs so what are the set of pairs in
this case uh the set of pairs
is going to be X comma
Y in R cross R such that yal 1x^2
is just the set of pairs that satisfy
our
relation um another way to write this x
comma 1 /x^2
where X is a real
number without zero cuz we're not
allowed to divide by
zero all right all right so f is a
function here's a way to write it in
terms of the pairs like we've said
um and it's totally fine that F of zero
isn't defined because again you can't
divide by zero f says each input has at
most one output and it just happens that
the input zero has no outputs which is
fine sometimes you do want everything to
have every input to have an
output uh so we have a different term
for that we'll say that a relation
is
total if and only
if every a in
a
has at least one Arrow
out in other words every a for every a
on the left side there's at least one B
on the right side that it relates to
everything on the left has some Arrow
going out possibly multiple that's what
we call
Total
um are our examples here
total is this one
total yeah everything on the left has at
one Arrow out has at least one Arrow out
here everything on the left has at least
one Arrow out
excellent is this function total
no why
not zero has no Arrow out F of zero
doesn't exist there is nothing that zero
relates to on the right okay let's give
a a different
example uh let's define
G from the set of R without
zero to the set of R without Z
this is supposed to be a
set where we're going to Def find G of X
is 1x^2
all right same function
right same set of
pairs is this function G
total I saw exactly two nods and a bunch
of blank stairs
that is all
right um someone who's oh a couple more
nods U someone who's nodding can you
tell me why G is
total
yes great uh so so they were saying uh
since zero is no longer an option as an
input um all of the inputs that we're
allowed to choose do have a valid output
assigned to them so this function G is
total this function f is not
total even though it's exactly the same
set of pairs for both f and g it's
exactly the same set of real comma real
or X comma 1/x^2 for all the non-zero
values of X all we've done is change the
domain and
co-domain uh and this goes to show that
you need all three parts of that
definition of relation you need to know
what set you're mapping from what set
you're mapping to and what all of your
related pairs are all three of those
pieces of
information are important to determine
things like whether it's a function
whether it's total does that make
sense
awesome uh now
there's oh by the way uh oh also these
often go together uh so
a
total
function means it has uh so total means
everything on the left has at least one
Arrow out function means everything on
the left has at most one Arrow out so if
you put those together total
function um has
exactly one Arrow out
uh for each a and
a and secretly when mathematicians say
function they usually mean total
function usually the fact that some
values some inputs don't have outputs
that's supposed to be sort of a special
case uh and the default when we say
function is that everything on the left
has a a definite output on the right so
when mathematicians say function we
usually mean total function
um when we're not assuming that a
function is total mathematicians will
often say partial
function so partial function means a
function that isn't necessarily total it
might be total confusingly a total
function is an example of a partial
function partial does not mean not total
partial does not mean that it's
definitely missing inputs partial just
means that you're not
assuming there aren't missing
inputs so by our by our definitions that
we've set out today partial function
just means
function and total function means
function that has nothing missing no
inputs
missing um from now on in this class uh
whenever we use the word function we're
going to try to specify whether we mean
a total function or whether we're
allowed to have some missing inputs
because usually when we say function uh
we're going to mean total function and
so let's decide from now on in this
class at least when we give um problem
statements to you that the word function
on its own is hereby
ambiguous whenever we say function we
should really be telling you do we mean
total function or do we mean function
that may or may not be
total
um so if you see it on a problem set or
test and it's not qualified like that
please ask we want to clarify that for
you we're not we're not trying to be
tricky with edge cases of this
definition if you see function on its
own without qualifiers please ask yes
uh so a relation is total if everything
on the left has at least one Arrow out a
relation is a total
function um if it's total and also a
function which means that everything on
the left has exactly one Arrow out great
question
um all
right yeah sorry that partial function
does not mean function that isn't total
even though that's what it sounds like
it should be partial function just means
function that may or may not be total
naming things is
hard um or rather using bad names that
someone else has already defined for us
is hard I would change it if I
could anyway
um great um we have similar not similar
terminology for arrows in instead of
arrows out so so far we've looked at
total and function which are talking
about how many arrows are coming out of
the left side um we can also ask how
many arrows are coming into the right
side so we'll say that R which is a
relation between A and B is
injective if and only
if every element on the right
side uh has at most one
arrow
in and we'll call it
surjective if and only if every B and
B has at least
one arrow
in so injective means you never hit the
same thing twice surjective means you
hit every everything possibly more than
once back to these
examples is L
injective in other words does everything
on the right side have at most one arrow
in no thumbs down thank you um for
example chemistry has multiple arrows in
that alone is enough to show that it's
not injective is it surjective
also no another thumbs down thank you um
it's not surjective because 61200
doesn't have any arrows in surjective
means you're supposed to hit everything
on the right and we don't so this is
neither surjective nor injective whereas
this is
both everything on the right has at
least one arrow in so it's surjective
and at most one arrow in so it's
injective all right
now one of the reasons we're defining
all of these similar confusing sounding
terms apologies for that um is that we
have some theorems that help that these
terms are enough to help us relate the
sizes of various sets so we have our
first theorem of the day um if a and b
are finite sets
and our a relation from A to B is a
total inject in total
injection so if we have finite sets and
a total injection from the first to the
second
then the size of a is at most the size
of B
if we can find a total injection from
one set to another set then the set on
the left is smaller or at most the same
size and let's let's draw a picture to
see
why um so total injection means that
everything on the left has at least one
Arrow out total means that and injection
means we never hit the same thing on the
right side
twice so there's always an arrow out on
the left side and there's at most one
Arrow out on the right side and so all
this is saying is that the number of
elements on the left is at most the
number of arrows because everything on
the left has at least one Arrow out and
the number of elements on the right side
is at least the number of arrows because
everything on the right has at most one
Arrow out so that's why this is true
size of a is less equal to the number of
arrows Which is less equal to the size
of
B so often when you want to show that
one set is smaller than another set you
just Define a total injection between
them and that's your proof
similarly on the other side of
things uh theorem
two let's
see if again A and B are finite
sets and
R is a surjective function
oops then the size of a is greater or
equal to the size of
B and I claim that's just exactly this
picture but in the opposite
direction um instead of total meaning
everything on the left has an arrow out
we have surjective which means
everything on the right has an arrow in
and instead of
injection which means everything on the
right has at most one out sorry at most
one in we have function which is
everything on the left has at most one
Arrow out so we've just swapped the
roles of in and out that's really all
that happened to translate this theorem
to that
theorem all right and by our powers
combined definition
if R
oops
is
injective
surjective total and a
function if it has all four of these
properties then we say that R is a
bje so that's the definition of bje bje
means you have all four of these nice
properties to summarize everything on
the left has exactly one Arrow out
everything on the right has exactly one
arrow
in and
Theorem um if R
oops from A to B is a
bje then the size of a equals the size
of
B all we're doing is applying both of
these theorems and we get both
inequalities so the sets have the same
size
all right so baction is the main tool
that we're going to be using in the
second half of this lecture um to
compare the sizes of sets questions
about
that
wonderful so next I want to talk about a
a couple special kinds of relations so
first of all um I never said that the
sets A and B have to be disjoint or even
distinct uh so let's look at the special
case where a equals
B so R is a subset of a cross
a we call this a binary relation on
a and this I claim is basically exactly
how we Define directed graph
you have a set of nodes which in this
case is a and serves as both our domain
and co-domain and you have a set of
directed
edges between
them and that's it that's that's how we
Define directed graph so a relation on a
is basically identical to a directed
graph whose vertices are a uh which
means that all of the directed graph
examples we've already talked about um
like who follows whom on Twitter like
reachability in Google Maps um all of
those diagraphs are also
relations uh there are relations on the
set of uh Twitter users or locations in
Google
Maps um another good example that I
really like uh of a relation on a set is
the relation of who likes whom not like
romantically or anything just you know
as a person who likes whom fix a moment
in time
everyone measures who they like among
all the other people in the world bam
you have your relation uh and the reason
I like it is that it has tons and tons
of chaotic
structure um for example uh if I like
you that doesn't mean that you like me
back necessarily especially this week
when the problem set's a bit long
apologies um if I like you and you like
them that doesn't mean that I like
them not always right that first example
I like you means you like me that's what
we're going to call symmetry in a little
bit U that second example if I like you
you like them that means I like them we
call that
transitivity so this graph is neither
symmetric nor transitive it's also not
reflexive um there there days when I
don't like myself so I wouldn't have a
self Loop in this
graph now I don't mean that in like a
cry for help kind of way but you know
you know some days you're a little down
on yourself it can happen it's okay if
it happens too much you have support ple
please seek it
out um
so funny story I I gave the same example
a couple years ago I got the same you
know half-hearted chuckle that we got
just now and then someone went home and
wrote about it on MIT
confessions I don't remember exactly
what they said but they maybe left off
some of the
context
um and then for the next couple days I
was getting multiple Facebook messages
from multiple friends Zack are you
okay uh I know we haven't caught up in a
while but I I'm here to a chat and I'd
love to to talk to you if if you're
available I hope you're doing well uh
and I just want to say I I I felt
loved so so thank you to whoever did
that but maybe let's not have a
repeat anyway back to
graphs um so one of the main reasons we
want to look at relations on a set uh is
because we already have lots of examples
and especially lots of examples that we
don't necessarily think of
as
graphs for
example a equals B is a relation that we
use all the time um a is congruent to B
mod 10 is a relation on the set of
natural numbers of integers that we use
all the time and don't necessarily think
of as a graph but it's it's definitely a
relation it's also a graph because
that's secretly the same thing but the
way you think about it can change if you
want to um likewise a less equ B we have
set a is a
subset of set B we have a divides B lots
of examples of
relations um that we want to be able to
talk
about um another good example is um
reachability so if G is a
diaph and if V and W are nodes of our
graph um then we can Define the walk
relation um yeah sorry that was out of
order if G is a diagraph we can Define
the walk relation on the set of vertices
of our
graph where we Define that
V relates to W under this walk relation
that we're going to call G prime or
sorry G
Star um if and only if there exists
walk from V to
W that's a relation we can Define on a
diaph and it's a really useful
one
um uh one thing I want to warn you about
we started with a graph we defined a
relation
gar we know that that relations on this
set of vertices can be thought of as a
graph on that set of vertices we're not
NE necessarily talking about the same
graph right this relation G star is
something we constructed from this diaph
G but the graph we constructed isn't
necessarily the same as the graph G that
we started with so it can be a little
confusing thinking of oh that's a graph
and that's also a graph that was
constructed from this
other it's fun to think about um but
just a warning even though we're talking
about two different graphs on the same
set of vertices they might actually be
two different
graphs um cool so there are two special
kinds of relations on a set that are
especially useful because we have lots
of examples and it's useful to be able
to generalize those examples um the
first one I want to talk
about is called an equivalence
relation and some of the examples I I
wrote down uh for
example a equal b or a is congruent to B
mod
10 these are somehow capturing this idea
of sameness A and B are the same A and B
have the same remainder mod 10 um if
we're talking about connectivity in a in
an undirected graph we say that two
nodes are connected with each other
meaning there's a walk from one to the
other which means that they belong to
the same connected component there's
another idea of sameness
there um so an equivalence relation is
this is an idea that generalizes this
idea of
sameness uh and so let's see if we can
do that what does it mean to somehow
encapsulate that the two things are
somehow equivalent to each other even if
they're not
identical um and it turns out there
there are three easy um by easy I mean
possibly confusing but I apologize um
three easily stated um properties that a
relation might have and if it has all
three then I claim it captures
everything it needs to capture about
this idea of sameness everything I've
just said is extremely vague
um let's make it
precise
so let's say that R is a relation on
a uh we're going to
say R is reflexive
uh this means
that um for all a and
a a relates to
itself reflexive means everything
relates to itself everything should be
the same as itself if sameness means
anything so this is definitely something
we would want to
have in terms of a diaph it means that
every vertex has a self Loop
all
right next one R is um
symmetric if and only if uh for all A
and B in our
set um a relates to B if and only if B
relates to
a so symmetry is saying that order
doesn't matter if if I'm your friend
then you're my
friend so Facebook not
Twitter um cool in terms of diagraph
remember a relation is always a diagraph
um this means that every time we have an
edge in One Direction we also have the
edge in the other
direction all right so symmetric means
order doesn't matter and finally R is
transitive if Only If For All A B and C
in
a if a relates to
B and B relates to
C then a relates to
C so if this is the same as that and
that's the same as this other thing then
this should be the same as this other
thing another thing that we might want
to be true if we're trying to capture
what we mean by sameness
uh in terms of graphs it means that
anytime we
have a walk of length
two then there was already a directed
Edge from the start to the
end if you can get from here to there
and from there to this other place then
you can get straight from here to this
other
place all right and and both of these
examples that I mentioned um all three
of these examples
um same
connected component
component so these circled relations I
claim all have all three of these
properties every number is congruent to
itself mod 10 if two numbers are
congruent to each other mod 10 then
they're congruent the other way mod 10
and if a and b are congruent and B and C
are congruent then A and C are congruent
mod
10 um and you can check that all of
those examples have this property and in
fact I claim that these three properties
are
enough um unfortunately I have to put
the definition very far away
from um or sorry the theorem very far
away from that
definition we'll make it
work bye
eraser okay definition r
is an equivalence relation
relation if and only if R is all three
of those things
symmetric um sorry
reflexive symmetric and
transitive and we have a theorem that
back up my claim that says this is all
we need for
sess
theorem
um if
R which is a relation on a is an
equivalence
relation if R is an equivalence
relation then are partitions
a into some collection of subsets A1
Union A2 Union A3 Union and so on and
this is going to be a disjoint
Union um such that
every a in
a belongs
to exactly one of our
subsets that's what it means to be a
partition that we're breaking a into
smaller pieces where every element of a
is in exactly one of our
pieces um such that a relates to
B if and only if a and b are in the
same
subset so anytime we have an equivalent
relation that satisfies these three
axioms then that exactly forms a
partition which tells us precisely what
our relation is our relation just says
you're related if and only if you're in
the same
subset for example if we're talking
about congruence mod 10 the parts of our
partition are well we have the set 0 10
minus 10 uh 20 minus
20 this is one part of a partition
everything in the set is congruent to
everything else in this set and not
congruent to anything else outside the
set then we also have 1 and 11 and 9 and
and9 here's another part of our
partition all of these numbers are
congruent to each other and congruent to
none of the other numbers and in in
total there are 10 of these
parts so anytime we have an equivalence
relation we can partition our um our set
into subsets uh that exactly tells us
what our relation is is
yes yeah so the union with a DOT here
the dot is there to emphasize that we're
taking the union of sets that are
disjoint uh that no no element is in
multiple of these sets I know I wrote it
out here in words but I like to
emphasize it in the formula as
well um when we're talking about
connectivity in in an undirected graph
um being connected to each other a pair
of vertices are connected if and only if
they're in the same connected
component and so the connected
components form the pieces of our
partition so we've seen multiple
examples of this this is just making
this more General and more abstract
anytime we satisfy all three of those
axioms we get
this all
right so the other kind of subset I want
to talk about
actually before that we had a couple
more examples we had this example
of a less equal B A divides B set a is a
subset of set B these are other common
relations that we work with and these
are not equivalence
relations right um we know that two
divides 10 but 10 doesn't divide two so
it's not symmetric like we wanted with
equivalence
relations but in many ways
a divides B behaves a lot like a less
equal b or a subset of B there's some
commonality
there um and that commonality we're
going to
Define as what are called weak partial
orders
so weak partial order our goal is going
to be
behaves like a less than equal B A is a
subset of B A divides B Etc so let's see
if we can capture what these all have in
common and prove something about
them so
again okay so let's see
R is a weak partial order weak partial
order if and only if R
is are these all
reflexive is a number always less equal
to itself does it divide itself is a set
a subset of itself yes so these are all
reflexive so let's add that to our
desired definition for weak partial
order
we already said it's not symmetric so
we're probably going to have to replace
that
somehow are these
transitive if a less equal B and B less
equal C is a less equal c yeah same for
subsets same for divides so let's put
that so this is looking very similar to
the def to the definition of equivalence
relation we're going to make one tweak
instead of requiring it to be symmetric
we're going to require it to be
anti-symmetric
which does not mean not symmetric it's a
different concept let's define
that so R is
anti
symmetric
means for all A and
B if a relates to B and B relates to a
then a equal
B so the only way that you relate in
both directions is if you're comparing
yourself to
yourself that is certainly True For Less
equal if we know that a is less equal b
and a is greater equal B than a equals B
that's true for subset as well if we
have two sets and each of them is a
subset of the other then they're exactly
the same
set and so this is going to be our Axiom
if R is reflexive anti- symmetric like
that and
transitive we're going to Define that to
be a weak partial order and that's going
to be our notion of behaving like these
familiar
examples and so why is a weak partial
order useful what can we prove about
them what can we do with
them well just like equivalence
relations um had a different
characterization in terms of partitions
of a
set uh we
can prove that equivalence Rel sorry
prove that weak partial orders are
related to dags
claim
uh
yes if G is a
diaph then the walk relation
G
star is a weak partial
order if and only if G is a
dag so the point of weak partial order
is that we can sort of put things in
sort in somewhat increasing order of
size um if a is less than b less equal B
less equal C less equal D less equal e
what we want to avoid is coming back
around and E is less equal
a
um because as it turns out that's going
to um that's going to break some of
these
axioms and so what all we're saying is
that satisfying these three axioms is
equivalent to being the walk relation on
a
dag and dags were defined by not having
Direction Ed
Cycles all right uh we're not going to
prove this but it's true you can come
ask me about it later if you'd
like um last definition for now once
again I apologize there are lots of
definitions
today but I want to bring our attention
to this word partial a weak partial
order just like we had partial function
that might be missing values a weak
partial order might be missing
comparisons for
example um the set
21 and the set um
27 is one a subset of the
other no in neither direction is that
true so here are two sets and neither
is related to the other one under this
subset
relation um so this is a pair that
cannot be
compared um so if R is a weak partial
order we'll say that A and B are
comparable if and only if the relation
goes in in in at least one of the two
directions a relates to b or B relates
to a
otherwise they're
incomparable so these two sets 21 and 27
are incomparable under this subset equal
relation all right and now finally
a weak partial
order is called a total
order if and only if every
pair is
comparable so whenever you have two
elements you can always put them in
order one of them is less equal to the
other one so that's certainly true for
the less equal
relation it's not true for the subset
relation and it's not true for the
divides relation two and three are
incomparable under the divides
relation but if every pair can be
compared uh then it's called a total
order and if you have a total order then
really all you have is just an entire
line of them organized by size a total
order is um the the most structure you
can have it's just everything is ordered
and there's there's no
ambiguity all
right so that is everything I wanted to
say on the relations side of things
today now let's move on to the other
part of today's lecture which is
counting uh and I don't mean counting
like 1 2 3 4 five I assume all of us are
capable of counting at least to like 300
or
so um no but by Counting I
mean counting the size of a
set um if if you want to know like
here's a comically large deck of playing
cards how many different ways are there
to shuffle them how many different
orderings are there for the 52 cards in
the deck here's one of those
orderings here's a different one Etc how
many orderings are there for this deck
of cards does anyone know
yes 52 factorial
absolutely so the number of
orders for a deck of
cards is 52 factorial and we'll see why
later in this course or later in this
lecture in fact um how
many uh
trees are are there whose vertices are
exactly the set 1 2 3 up to n
does anyone
know I'd honestly be surprised it's not
an easy problem um but this is the kind
of problem that we're going to try to be
able to answer and we're going to look
at techniques for trying to answer in
this case the number of trees on that
set of vertices is n to the N minus 2
which I love I find that kind of magical
there are lots of cool ways to prove it
we're not going to prove it together but
come ask me if you're interested but
these are the kinds questions we're
going to try to ask here's a set of
things how many things are there uh and
to get us a little more in the
mood uh for counting I have a short
story I want to tell you uh the parable
of the two Shepherds no one calls at
that that's just
me um so this first Shepherd this first
Shepherd you know every morning has to
let the Sheep out to graze every evening
bring the Sheep back in to protect them
from wolves I guess I don't know what
Shepherds do um but unfortunately this
Shepherd does not know how to count like
grade school style one two three that
the shepherd doesn't have words for
numbers above three so how do they make
sure that all of their 50 something
sheep go out in the morning and come
back in in the evening if they can't
count the
sheep and a classic answer to this which
may or may not have historical Merit but
um all all mathematicians who have
studied counting have heard this story
at least once um the classic example is
every time you let a sheep out of the
pen you put a pebble in your
pocket another sheep another Pebble
another sheep another Pebble at the end
of the day when you're bringing the
Sheep back in every time a sheep comes
in you take a pebble out of your
pocket and when all the sheep have come
in that's the same moment that all the
Pebbles are out of your pocket so when
your pocket's empty you know there are
no more
sheep and VI Versa if there are Pebbles
left in your pocket there are still
sheep out there and you have to go find
them if your pocket's empty and there
are more sheep coming in well something
weird happened and you probably stole
from your
neighbor um but the point is um for
these next couple lectures in our
counting unit we count with
correspondences we count with BS which
we defined on one of these boards um if
we can set up a on toone correspondence
everything in this set corresponds to
everything in this set and everyone has
a partner no one has two partners no one
is missing a
partner then there are the same number
of things on both sides what that
Shepherd is doing is basically making
sure that there's always a
correspondence between sheep that are
out there and Pebbles in their pocket
they don't have to keep track of what
that correspondence is and in fact it
might change if you initially put a
pebble in your pocket for sheep Deborah
um you're not keeping track of which
Pebble corresponds to sheep Deborah so
when Deborah comes back in in you might
remove the pebble that was assigned to
Sandy I I I don't know why I'm picking
these
names um
but you don't care what that
correspondence is as long as there is a
correspondence between pebbles in your
pocket and sheep that are still
grazing um so the moral here is we count
with
correspondences the second Shepherd uh
the second Shepherd knows how to count
that's totally fine not a problem we
have language um but the shepherd has an
overeager apprentice
this Apprentice runs in one evening and
says master I brought all 40 sheep into
the pen and the shepherd looks confused
what do you what do you mean we only
have 38 sheep don't worry master I
rounded them
up thank you no moral I just like bad
puns I heard one groan thank you very
much that warms my heart
and now that we're in a great mood let's
talk about
counting all right so let's actually
counting um
here first of all why do we care why are
these tools that we
need um in a in a computer science class
why do we care about counting things
well often when we're analyzing the
runtime of an algorithm we're doing some
step some number of times and we need to
be able to count how many times we do
that step in order to bound the runtime
of the algorithm and prove that it runs
fast um it's also useful for things like
probability probability is built very
heavily on top of counting and all of
our counting techniques will transfer
over to probability techniques as well
and that'll be useful after Quiz 2 which
is coming up next week by the
way
um but let's learn where my chalk is
found
it let's learn some techniques for
counting the first one I want to mention
is called the product
rule um which says that for finite
sets A and B the size of A cross B
equals the size of a Time the size of B
remember A cross B is the set of all
possible pairs where the first element
is in a and the second element is in B
so the number of ways to choose an
element from a and then choose an
element from B is the size of a times
the size of
B uh and this generalizes as
well if we have K uh if we have n
different sets
and we're looking
at um ordered sequences where the first
element comes from A1 the second element
comes from A2 the third element from A3
and all the way down the number of such
sequences is just the size of A1 times
the size of A2 all the way to the size
of
a so if we're if we have to choose an
element of A1 and then choose an element
of A2 and then choose an element of A3
and all the way down the number of ways
we can make that choice in its entirety
is size of A1 time size of A2 time size
of A3 all the way down for
example the number
of length and
binary
sequences so a binary sequence is a
sequence of zeros and ones just zeros
and ones and we're asking how many
length and binary sequences are there
well the set of length and binary
sequences is 01 * 01
times 01 n
times this is precisely the set of
binary sequences this is what we mean by
binary sequence first element is a zero
or a one second element is a zero or a
one all the way down and the generalized
product rule or sorry the the general
version of the product rule says that
this set the size of this set is just
the size of 01 times the size of
01 all the way
down which is 2 * 2 * 2 * 2 n * so there
are two to the end binary sequences of
length n does that make
sense
wonderful uh next let's look at the
ejection
rule if there exists a
bje from A to
B then A and B have the same
size this is what that first Shepherd
was doing if there exists a bje between
two sets the sets have the same size
because we're just pairing them up one
to one uh no one is repeated no one is
excluded uh and as an example of
this how many
subsets of 1 through n are
there so if we're looking at all of the
subsets of 1 through n of any length um
could be length zero where we take none
of the elements length n where we take
all the elements or any length in
between where we take some of the
elements and not others how many subsets
are there well let's use the bje rule I
claim um set of
subsets of 1 through
n is in bje
with BN and I'm going to Define this um
BN
is binary
sequences of length
n so the thing we counted in the last
example I claim that the set of subsets
of 1 through n is injection with the set
of those length n binary
sequences and to prove that we can just
Define our function and verify that it's
a bje
so given a binary
sequence B1
B2 BN where each of these is zero or
one I'm going to map that to a subset of
1 through
n i in 1 through n such that bi equal 1
we send it to the subset of indices that
have value
one so you can think of this as a set as
a sequence of binary decisions do we
keep element one or throw it away do we
keep element two or throw it away all
the way down for example 0 1
0 0 1 1 if n is
six then this maps to the
subset 2 five and six
because those are the indices that have
ones all right and we're not going to do
it now but you can verify that this
gives a bje between the set BN and the
set of subsets of 1 through
n
claim this is a
bijection you'll see more examples in
your homework of how what details we
would need to check to verify more
carefully that this really is a b
section um but intuitively they're sort
of encoding the same information each
each number from 1 through n is either
included or excluded that's a binary
decision the the I bit is either one or
zero that's a binary decision so we're
just corresponding those two
things all right
next we have the product rule the bje
rule now we have the sum rule
some rule says that if a and b are
disjoint so there they have no elements
in
common then the size of a union B is the
size of a plus the size of
B right
so if I
have five cards in my right hand and
three cards in my left hand and I I
don't have any cards in both hands uh
then I'm holding eight cards five plus
three uh and more
generally um if I'm taking the size of a
disjoint Union of N
Things if all of these AIS are disjoint
with each other
then this is the size of A1 Plus the
size of
A2 plus the size of
a and let's see that in
action
okay so all of us who have not been
using password managers all our lives
have have frequently been told choose
another password that has these specific
requirements it has this length it must
use a special character it has to do all
this other stuff which just makes it
harder for me to remember it um anyway
I'm going to I'm going to play that role
now how
many uh
passwords have
length between six and8
inclusive start with a capital
letter um and the
rest are capital or lowercase
letters and or
digits the digits aren't capital or
lowercase they're just digits so how
many passwords have length between six
and 8 start with a capital letter and
then finish with whatever whatever
whatever letters or digits you
want and with this it's useful to break
it up into cases based on the length of
your password I claim that um the set W
I called it w in the notes for some
reason um W for
password um I claim that W is the
disjoint
Union of the set of passwords of length
six that satisfy the other properties
set of passwords of length seven and set
of passwords of length eight so if we
can count each of these three subsets
then we add them up and get the size of
w and let's see if we can do that so
what is the size of W6 how many
passwords
satisfy this
property well I claim the set W6 itself
as a
set is well first of all the set
of uh capital letters for the first
entry times the set
of letters or
digits to the fifth for the other five
entries this is exactly what this set is
the first entry has to be a capital
letter the other five characters can be
anything from this set
so we have this product of six
sets um and that brings us back to the
regular product rule so by the product
rule the size of
W6 is well how many capital letters are
there I think that's
26 and then how many letters and digits
are there 26 26 and 10 so that's 50
62 to the 5th we just use the regular
product rule to get this
and we can do the same thing for W7 and
W8 W7 is going to be 26 * 62 this time
to the sixth because there are six extra
digits after the F extra characters
after the first one and the size of
W8 is 26 * 62
7 so by the sum rule since W is the
disjoint Union of these three different
sets the size of w is the size of W6
plus the size of W7 plus the size of
W8 which is 26 * 62 5th + 26 * 62 6 + 26
* 62
7th so we use the sum rule to break it
up into three separate cases and then
use the product rule for each of those
cases did that make
sense wonderful all
right
um so this is a a common strategy here
um notice that we're we're using the sum
rule when what we mean is is or you can
choose a password of length six or a
password of length seven or a password
of length
eight so
or means
sum for product rule you have to choose
a capital letter and then choose one of
these characters and then choose one of
these characters I forget how many times
I've said it but you know five times for
this part we multiply when we mean
and said differently if I have 10 shirts
and six pants in my
closet um if I want to choose an article
of clothing I can choose a shirt or a
pair of
pants and there are 16 options 10 plus
6 um or means add on the other hand if
I'm trying to put together an outfit for
the day I have to choose a shirt and a
pair of
pants and means multiply it's 10times
six options so I have 60 outfits maybe
not all of those look good but I wear
the same pants every day anyway so it
doesn't
matter um did does this make sense
generally speaking or means add and
means
times okay uh the last example I want to
talk about
today is called the generalized product
rule
and example first in fact an example we
mentioned earlier how many
different permutations are there for a
set of 52 cards how many different
orderings are there for a set of 52
cards let's talk through this
together here here are the cards I I
can't hold them all at once with with my
notes and my chalk so bye-bye
cards so how many permutations
of the 52
cards well let's think about it let's
choose the first card first which card
is going to go at the beginning of our
list well how many options do we
have we have the whole deck to play with
okay I think I do want to hold the
cards we have the whole deck to play
with we can choose any one of the cards
as our first card yeah maybe I choose
this one I'm doing a magic trick to
myself I don't know what card this is um
so the nine of Spades is going to be the
first card in our
ordering so this was the nine of Spades
and we had 52 options for it yeah great
okay that goes at the beginning of our
order what's the next card we
pick well how many options do we have
left just Shout It Out 51 yeah we have
51 options Maybe maybe we choose this
one without dropping all the others
eight of clubs great that's the second
card in our order eight of
clubs now let's all watch as I do this
50 more times no um but we get the idea
um the next card the third card in my
ordering well I've used two cards
already I have to choose one of the
remaining 50 cards then 49 then
48 then two then one this is the number
of choices I have at each
stage so it feels like by the product
rule this answer should be 52 * 51 * 50
* 49 and so on 52
factorial the weird thing though is that
this isn't the product
rule product rule says you have some set
of options at the beginning which is
true we have the set of 52 cards at the
beginning but then we're supposed to
have the same set of options for the
next entry every time but the set of
options we have in the second round
depends on which card we picked in the
first
round right there are always 51 options
because we've always excluded one card
from the first round but the set of
options changes depending on what we
picked in the first
round so this isn't straightup product
rule the set of permutations is not just
set of 52 cards time set of 51 cards
time set of 50 cards even though though
the number of options at each stage is
always the same and that's what the
generalized product rule does for us it
basically says if the number of options
at every step of the process is always
consistent even if this particular set
of those options might change then the
number of ways to make your choices is
just the product of the number of
choices at each
stage so
this is the gener generalized product
rule if a is a
set
of length K
sequences where there
are N1 choices
um for the first entry for
A1 and two
choices for
A2 no
matter what A1 was
chosen
Etc uh exactly a uh sorry exactly n i
choices
for AI for the I entry in our
sequence no matter what A1 through a IUS
one were
chosen and all the way down to NK at the
end so if earlier choices don't change
the number of options we have in later
steps then the size of a
is N1 *
N2 up to
NK sound
good cool we will get more practice with
that next time uh and I will see you
then thank you