howdy I'm shiv CEO and co-founder of
active
Services that's me on the left uh I come
from Exon Mobile grew up here in Houston
and worked at the US doe before coming
to MIT my co-founder is actually the
smart guy he invented this stuff along
with these prolific MIT professors
Vladimir bovich who runs MIT Nano and
mji bendi who won a Nobel Prize last
year uh we also have advisers like Seth
kolivan who have spun out and sold
multiple deep tech companies so what do
we do who here has seen a solar panel a
ton right there's one meter by two meter
bricks are normally in the middle of
nowhere we think that solar has grown
tremendously and it has this is a chart
of every Year's iea projection of how
quickly solar will be adopted over the
next 10 years and you can see that we've
outpaced it year over year for 20 years
straight but let's put this growth in
perspective right now if you add up the
entire solar capacity of the entire
planet we're at one
terawatt to achieve Net Zero we need the
minimum 20
terawatts this Gap is equivalent to the
world's largest solar farm which is in
India a couple gws it's three times the
size of Cambridge Mass that size being
deployed every single day for two
decades that's what we
need but there's barriers to this level
of scale transmission is a big pain
because people don't want
Transmission in their backyard and it's
hard to get the power from North Texas
to the coast soft costs are dominating
the instulation cost now the modules are
cheap but labor and structural support
is expensive and then energy security is
the big issue because 95% of those 1
meter by 2 meter panels are made in
China all of this is happening because a
core technology that we are working with
is based with silicon it's in a glass
packaged module and it's heavy that form
factor has been the same for 50 years if
you Google solar panel White House in
the 1970s the same exact form factor
existed what we're offering is something
entirely new this is a 100 times lighter
can be integrated into any surface could
be on Fabrics or Plastics and could be
rolled around like a yoga mat and then
deployed on
buildings if you want to come see it
later we're over
there we're not the first company to
think of flexible solar this has been
around for 20 years but we're the first
company to do it at a cost that actually
makes sense for widescale adoption we do
this because our efficiencies are high
our manufacturing input or materials are
low and then we're able to have the
benefit of the form factor without uh
lower
performance we unlock this with three
different Innovations manufacturing
packaging and materials for
manufacturing we do roll to- roll
Manufacturing imagine like a big
Polaroid plant or New York Times or you
print we do that multiple times for each
layer of the semiconductor for packaging
we have innovations that allow us to
decouple the substrate you're printing
on to the final device package which
means that if you print on glass you're
stuck on glass for us you can print on a
piece of plastic and then laminate it
onto whatever the hell you want Fabrics
glass Plastics no other company can do
that and then materials we use commodity
materials that could be Source from your
region so if you build a plant in
America you could bu sorage materials in
America or from Europe or from South
Asia or from East Asia from wherever
you're locally
manufacturing and you could do it using
uh commodity domestically Source
materials that aren't susceptible to
supply chain risks so none of this
together has been
possible in a summary we're cheaper than
solar today we're glass free and
flexible we're locally sourced we're way
lighter same performance and faster
install this can go literally anywhere
from facades to roofs to Shades and this
is what it was look like on a commercial
building like a yoga mat being deployed
and rolled
out in terms of development we spun out
of uh Technologies validated in 22 we
won some prizes and some big checks uh
early 23 got support from climatech
accelerators uh have raised .5 million
dollar and use that to build a
manufacturing research facility and now
we set ambitious goals for this year to
move faster than any solar uh older to
move faster than any Solar Company in
history we try to do these four things
by the end of 24 make a solar module
make a solar roll get some commercial
interest and do an outdoor demo if we
could do any of these that would be
faster than any Solar Company so where
are
we we made our first solar module 3 q24
we made our first solar roll which is
here I'll unravel it as I talk about the
next stuff that's us on a commercial
install and then we also have our first
outdoor demo scheduled for next month or
this month is December
now uh quick history on a connection to
Houston solar is big in north Texas I'm
sure you guys know this uh scaleup
expertise is Big here I worked for Exxon
I've seen these big refineries we know
how to build things and then I grew up
here so I went to CF cyer High U ofh uh
Aon I'm the Houston
Alum so my ask here is if you own a
building or you're interested in the
application of solar in your operations
let me know uh or if you just want to
high five and support a new technology
always down for
that thank you
[Applause]