I think semiconductor technology is
really the key to address like global
challenges for example energy deficiency
and uh climate
[Music]
change. My research is related to high
temperature electronics that can be
operated in a high temperature
environment. So this can um apply to
many fields that requires extreme
conditions. One of the main like
promising semiconductor materials we're
using is gallium nitride which is known
for its ability to endure extreme
environment. So this work is extremely
important because um it applies to a lot
of fields. Um for example uh renewable
geothermal energy is one of them. It
requires drilling technologies and
sensoring systems that often requires
temperatures at range around like 500°
C. So um it is very important to
consider the possibilities of high
temperature gallium nitride electronic
components. It's very interesting to see
how semiconductor materials is
interconnected or related to the
advancement in clean energy fields.
[Music]