thank uh the MIT ILP uh program to have
this opportunity to to speak to you so
my name is Ali uh Merchant and iq3
connect is all about providing scalable
3D environments for Learning and
collaboration and
uh as a startup you know we work we are
interacting with companies in advanced
manufacturing they're building complex
products or they have complex processes
like they operating you know machines or
whatever and this is what we hear from
them you know they're building a product
it's about you know quality timeliness
you know getting more efficiency they're
worried about disruptions and threats
like covid uh but one of the other
interesting areas is also around you
know uh their their Workforce Workforce
Development Workforce training losing
knowledge we heard about you know
retiring Workforce so these are some of
the challenges that um and companies
that we're working with and uh the
question is how do you virtualize some
of these complex environments you're
manufacturing something I can physically
explain to you how to you know
disassemble a machine but if I want to
do this in a virtual environment how do
I do that do I use a PDF do I use a flat
screen a zoom and so these are the
challenges that you know when we talk
about digital how do you how do you
capture these complex environments
whether you're you're bringing in a
supplier uh to to you know in in man
manufacturing or you're training a
worker to operate a machine or safely
operate a
machine and so what we have done is we
are providing highly scalable 3D virtual
environments where uh what you see here
is essentially a 3D workspace and it
works in a browser so there are a number
of companies that are providing 3D
Solutions but what we're doing is making
this extremely fast and easy and very
very scalable and that's really
important for this to be adopted at
scale uh uh in an environment and we
have Global customers that are using
this for for manufacturing uh for
Workforce training and and many other
applications across the the product life
cycle uh and I'd like to talk about a
customer success here uh this is Sierra
space and uh it's very interesting
because in a matter of a few months they
were able to scale this
technology uh into their production
environment and what you see here is uh
you know one of their vehicles and they
were able to digitize this and bring in
bring this into the iq3 environment it
has a million components they can access
it from anywhere in the company and that
completely changes the game so now
instead of sharing documents I can
simply send you a link and you can just
be in the spatial environment with this
vehicle and and that was the a game
changer for them and so what you see
here is an approved image by Sierra uh
space and they're able to you know make
this accessible to the entire company uh
and it had real immediate business uh
outcomes you know so they were able to
incorporate this into some of their
procedures which they did not have any
tool for before so I asked them how
would you do this before and they said
well we would actually have to go
physically and do this on the real
vehicle now we can bring that digital
record of this vehicle to them and it's
accessible all the way from the top
management down to the worker uh to the
to the employee on the manufacturing
floor they have multiple teams
demonstrating this techn you know using
this as a tool so uh very quickly and
very easily just using it as a as a tool
in their daily work and they able to use
this also for solving a number of uh
designed issues and really solve uh you
know address their uh contractual
obligations which was a huge
issue another aspect of this is the
Workforce Development so not only did we
we we have an industrial success but we
were able to put a a high school teacher
with about 25 years of High School
teaching into this complex environment
and now take this tool into the
classroom for really you know teaching
the the kids so K through 12 and this is
creating new Pathways and this was
recognized by the National Space Council
and so we working with the Department of
uh labor and education in Colorado to
really uh you know change how they're
looking at uh uh upscaling and and this
Workforce Development challenge in the
United
States uh minimizing the barriers so so
we're a startup you know how do we get a
tool like this which is completely
changing work because you're going from
documents 2D you know screen sharing to
a completely immersive 3D environment so
we made this extremely easy to use uh
minimal user training it has to just
work uh in your existing
environment uh the web browser access
was a big issue so that's part of our
technology that makes this so as you
know you can just send somebody a link
and as quickly as you can open a browser
you can access this 3D digital model you
can access it on any device you can buy
a $300 meta headset and now you can
immerse yourself in a one to one scale
uh model of this vehicle so it's
extremely easy to access and we've
created a complete uh pipeline where you
can you can create uh these 3D models
extremely quickly so it's a tool there's
no custom development and that made it
very easy for the company to adopt it in
various uh teams and programs it's also
secure so Aerospace environment security
is extremely important and uh we've done
many things to address that as well and
finally the Enterprise Readiness so it
has to you know integrate into
manufacturing execution systems PLM and
other business processes to really
overcome those barriers for scaling uh
and
adoption so our our partnership ask is
we've got this great technology and uh
we're looking for pilot engagements
Aerospace energy I know there are a
number of oil and gas companies here you
have complex products and operations uh
manufacturing as well as government and
education so we'd love to you know uh
talk more you know happy to talk about
uh our experience with Workforce
Development uh thank you very much