The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mit.edu.
Some content in this audio is not
covered under our creative common
license. For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT Open
Courseware website.
>> Okay. So, today uh we have a guest
lecture. Some of whom are pro some of
you are probably already taking her
class. Uh
>> my victims, current victims
>> and past victims.
>> Past victims. Um, I probably need to do
something for the light.
I think it's
>> I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I I'm still
operating on Tylenol and Cathy. Um, so
uh you know to uh today we're going to
talk about stories and games and Clara
teaches uh not just the intro to video
game studies class but also the writing
for video games class in the spring. uh
I kind of uh wanted her to come in and
bring her expertise uh because she's
carefully looked at this problem a lot
more than I have and uh and yeah
everybody
I've seen you know um so yeah Phil asked
me to come here and talk about uh
stories and games and I as far as I
remember you guys had to read two
articles for today chapter four of yes
real and Seren Johnson's um things not
meeting which was what I take this
course to
>> yes but he's late okay
anyway so so this has been preparing
this has been kind of interesting
because yeah there's there's I think
I've thought about this you know quite a
bit because you know is this some part
of the focus of my research studying how
you know games and stories can be
brought together what Does it mean to
have a story in the game? Uh where do we
put the story? Uh but the interesting
challenge was thinking well the guys are
working mostly on non-digital games and
what does it have to do what do stories
have to do with with non-digital games.
So here what I'm going to need is your
input because you guys have been playing
all these board games, card games. uh
and I want a bit of your input on what
you think um you know the how you think
these concepts uh apply to um to
non-digital games and uh because the
part of digital games I I can do pretty
confidently but I don't know as much
about board games or card games so I
need your expertise this is what you
guys are doing uh so the first thing
that I wanted to ask you about you the
we had two different readings one is
talking about fiction and the other is
talking about theme But what is the
fiction of a game according to you?
>> The fiction of a game is well whatever
you want. It could be the characters in
the game. Let's digital game. It could
be a real environment. You just have
fictional characters. It could be um an
environment that may not exist. It's
pretty much it's up to designer to
figure out what they want to like be in
the game that aren't real and what they
want it to be
uh fiction.
>> Well, it's
there's something there, but but it
might be a bit more
if I it might be a bit more intuitive
than that. I mean, yeah, I think that
you're on the right track. Yes.
>> I'd say it's the setting or the universe
in which the user perceives the events
of the game to take place in. or the one
that the designer intends the user to
see the game take place.
>> Okay. So, I mean, you've mentioned
environment is kind of like the the the
what was the word you the universe, you
know, the setting, you know, something
like that back then.
>> Oh, yeah. I think the word you used over
and over was world. It's just a world
>> pretty much
>> and that's the key word. you know when
we when when um Gary was talking about
fiction he's really talking all
throughout about fictional worlds uh and
in a way you know designing games and
designing video games specifically is
always
thinking about what is the world of this
game and at times there might be games
that don't have worlds you know you can
make Tetris you can make there's very
few video games without worlds but there
are some tetra is u
>> peg Well, Pegle has characters, you
know, you were talking about this like
characters are already flying a fiction.
Um,
>> please he says like has nothing to do
with unicorns.
>> Yes,
>> you want to say something. Oh, we have
two hands here.
>> Stealing it. Okay. Um, and particularly
with board games, I think of fiction
much more as the the specific explicit
things they give you. Mhm.
>> Um like the pictures, the the rules and
all of that stuff versus like what it
>> what it feels like you're doing. So if
they don't specifically tell you you're
in blah place, then that's not part of a
fiction.
>> Okay. Yeah. So that's you put your
finger on it that when we're talking
about non-digital games, there are some
non-digital games where thinking about
worlds is a bit shaky. Do you want to
say something?
>> Uh yeah, I was going to add that in an
environment, you have a set of things
you can do. So, you're basically given
rules. Like in a board game, you could
be you could be given uh if a character
has to jump for some reason, then you uh
the board game could say that they could
jump some insane distance while in real
life they can't do that. That's just
part of the fiction. So, it's whatever
laws apply to within that world as well.
So there are this is a very interesting
point because when when you was talking
about um what's the word he uses in
congruous worlds incoherent incoherent
he talks about incoherent worlds and
it's like going in coherent according to
what you know at times you know the
rules are also creating part of the
fiction the rules are also creating that
you know what are um the the gravity the
laws of gravity in the specific world
that we're playing in for example um so
so you know we when we're talking about
fiction we're mainly talking about
fictional world, but how does that
relate to theme? And you were already
kind of hinting at at that, you know,
that that in fiction and board games,
it's kind of like, well, it almost can
be about anything. But what is the theme
of when you, if you remember, sorry
Johnson's discussion, what does he refer
to as a theme? He is not an academic, so
he has a more
>> wobbly loose definition. It was a theme
of a game.
The theme of the game is what the
designer says to the player. This is
what the game is about.
But when Son Johnson is saying theme is
not meaning.
So he's making a point that theme is
might not be what the game is about.
>> Right.
>> It's just what the game designer tells
you.
>> Yeah. I mean this this is what the
example that that he gives is ticket to
ride right
>> and ticket to ride is not about riding
trains is about
>> it's about well
the description is about going from one
end to another right
>> it's building
>> it's about traveling across the United
States
>> but is it really traveling or is it
building the
>> story about traveling
>> yeah the story It's about traveling.
That's the theme. But the you know what
you actually do is
>> the official the official story is that
>> um I think it's some number of years
after the events of around the world in
80 days
>> and to commemorate that the original
people who were involved in that race
decided that they're going to race
across America in trains
>> and that is the theme of the game
according to
>> that's the theme of the game Alec.
>> Well that's that's sort of like drives
to the point of what Senson is talking
about that when theme and meaning are in
congruous as they are in Ticket to Ride
to like an extreme extent. It can
actually turn people off from the game
sometimes. So,
>> well, and it's not War.
>> Well, not necessarily. I mean,
>> on Halo Wars a bit, it sound like you
bought it thinking it was going to be an
action game and got disappointed. It was
like
>> I mean, in the case of Chica to ride, it
is pretty much what we were just saying
there, right? that the theme seems to
just be what whoever it is that wrote
the instruction booklet says that
>> you're doing
>> which may not necessarily have anything
to do with the actual mechanics of the
game.
>> Yeah, I have a game. I don't know if you
guys have played it. And if you want to
play it, I can bring it back.
>> Uh is a Reneia game called Too Many
Cooks.
>> And it seems to be about cooking, but
you know,
yeah, you have ingredients and you're
supposed to have like a you're making a
soup of sorts, but really what you're
doing is resource management, you know,
and exchanging. Like just imagine being
a cook and having like, well, I have to
wait until I get the right ingredient or
like exchange it for another. It's like
that's not how you cook really. Um, so
there is, you know, there's always the
clash of of how how the fiction of the
game relates to the rules and and what
the interesting distinction between
fiction and theme is that theme seems to
be like a layer, seems to be like a a
decoration. Um, at times, you know, it
can be part of of the title. It can be,
you know, how the the tokens look like
or what the board looks like. That is
setting up the fiction uh of the game.
But it's um not the fiction, the theme,
you know, but it doesn't really have a
fictional world. Like when you're
playing Ticket to Ride or when you
playing Settlers is like, do you have
the feeling that you're in a world
more so than ticket to
>> I mean, so the the I will argue that
maybe the world that you feel is not the
world that they're telling you that
you're in, right? when one of the
problems of Ticket to Ride is that you
never really feel these characters
exist.
>> Yeah.
>> Um but the world of the United States is
very very present.
>> It's like you know the the the
positioning of the cities. The fact that
these cities exist and can be connected
>> by man is is very
>> you guys have read the levels of
abstraction talked about levels of
abstraction here at all.
>> Not in great detail what I'm talking
about. So the idea that you know it
might be a it's a world but it's so the
way that it works is so abstracted that
it doesn't really feel like a world
anymore. It's kind of like this little
bits and pieces.
>> Um so okay we have we have fiction and
we have you know theme but we also have
stories. And what do stories have to do
with this? You know how do how do we
have the story in non-digital games? No.
Well first of all you know a story and
I'm going to define it to you to save
time. Uh a story is uh a series of
events connected events that involve
characters. Uh so those characters
perform actions or there are happenings
things that happen to them and those
those actions happen in time and in a
specific setting uh in a in a specific
place. Uh and in the case of games they
also involve objects. That's kind of
like my telegraphic you know um version
of where the story is. So what we do in
games in games we have uh changed of
state right every step of a non-digital
game particularly we can think about uh
non-digital games as changes of state
and having a change of state can
constitute an event uh so that is one
way how do we generate rules that
generate changes of state that can be
thought of as um as an event in the
story but I want to know a bit more of
the games that you've played so far. How
can non-digital games um I don't know
what maybe you've played more than card
games than anything, but how can we have
a story? How can we have those events
happen?
>> So, one of the games that we played that
has a really nice story to it is Balar
Galactica.
>> And the way that works is uh it works
off of what the player already knows.
>> So, it sort of assumes that the player
has like the knowledge of Balar Galact.
And so, it keeps referring to that
whenever you play a that has special
abilities,
>> whatnot. So, it relies on previous
knowledge of play.
>> That's a very good point. I mean, part
of what we do and and it's in in digital
games and non-digital games, but it's
also in digital games. A lot of
storytelling in games happens in the
player's head is is evoking, you know,
certain characters, certain situations
is with tapping on the player's
knowledge. Is not, as we're going to
see, it's not so much about
storytelling, but we're kind of like,
okay, what do you know? we we are making
the player fill in the gaps. So that
designing a game that involves
storytelling is usually giving cues to
the player to create the story if that
makes sense.
>> Um Patrick
>> um I was going to say that uh a lot of
um like board card games all a lot of
the fiction just comes from the
metaphors of the mechanics.
>> So for example in a like settlers when
you want to build a road if you strip
away all the fiction it's just I have
these cards I put them down. I can put
this piece here.
>> But um adding the fiction to it, you say
now putting I'm not just putting cards
down. I'm uh using up resources to build
a road. And so that metaphorical action
is another like event in the story.
>> Well, it becomes a meaningful action. I
mean that's another I'm sure that you
guys have been talking about that you
know what is a meaningful action and at
times meaningful action is it
constitutes like a story event of sorts.
journey.
>> Um, I think that the whole point of
Munchkin and ShaGeek and those games uh
are to construct stories. We
>> when we played it, there was a moment
when someone trashed someone else's
shrooms and then the other person played
a go dumpster diving card to go pick up
the the shrooms and a bong from the
dumpster.
>> And this whole sequence of events, you
know, the flavor text on the cards, what
they were the actions you were taking,
and you put them all, you string them
all together. I did this then this
happened and this happened with these
objects and you've got a perfect story
because you know you're playing a geek
and uh you know
>> well there's that but the other thing
that is good about munch game is that
reading the cards is fun you know there
are bits of the story already in Munch
game like reading the events that is
kind of like engaging already you want
to say something
>> I was just going to say there are some
games which are like entirely about
telling stories
>> role playing games are the number one
and then another example is something
like once upon a time
>> which I think
And then there also the adventures of
bearing wood trousers if you've ever
>> Yes. Oh, I should bring it. Yes, I have
it in my office, but that's kind of
difficult to set up like in half an
hour. Yeah,
>> I'm actually a friend of mine invented a
game which is kind of vaguely based on
the adventures of Barry Mchowen um where
you each person is telling a story and
they have cards in front of them which
need to be flipped over and by
incorporating the elements of the story
that cards
anyway don't worry about
>> yeah no yeah no yeah no yeah no yeah no
yeah no yeah no yeah no yeah no yeah no
no I'm going no yeah you you we're going
a bit faster but that's fine because you
know yeah there are games that are about
storytelling communal storytelling and
role playing games are about that you
know we again as as game designers what
we are given when we have the rule book
from D and D are is a fictional world
that has rules and but then we have as
as a as a designer as a DM uh we are
coming up with what is the situation
what is the world what is the specific
challenges that we're situating in this
world how are we going to do that uh but
is is about communal sorting as as as
we're going to see in a minute there are
also games that are about coming up with
stories like we're being thrown you know
the similar way. Well, in Munchkin,
you're kind of like constructing the
story as you go. But in the games that
we're going to play today, or some of
you are like gloom or once upon a time
is the game is being able to produce a
narrative, being able to make sense
given the specific cues you would have
had your hand.
>> So, I was going to do the opposite
extreme of a game with a very basic
story and you kind of make the story a
little as you go along, but it's not
really that crazy. uh game card game
falling where pretty much the pretense
says you are goblins. Everyone's a
goblin and you're falling to your
demise. And so the point so while you
guys are falling you guys decide we who
let's make a contest of who hits the
ground last. And so it's a real time
game and you're deal cards in order and
you keep going until you reach ground
cards. And so you can uh attack other
people. It's like okay this is going to
happen to you and different effects
happen. And so when you're actually
playing it, it's kind of like the
intensity when you're falling. It's
like, oh, I'm going to die. I have to do
this fast because before you know it,
ground star.
>> It's interesting because it creates a
longer event or something that is
supposed to be got like smashed, right?
Uh but it's kind of zooming in and how
long that would feel if you were
actually flying. uh make it like a mini
story of that or you know I it's
interesting because I don't know how
strong and this is one of the questions
when we're talking about stories and
games is you know what kind of event
constitutes an event in the story know
like is opening a door an event in the
story well in some games it can be
because it might give you access to uh
new areas you know there might be
someone showing up that changes things
uh but in other cases you know like I
don't know in Monopoly getting to um uh
going around and getting the how many
$100 $200 you know is that an event you
know
>> maybe it's not it doesn't seem like a
story event because it's such a mundane
thing that happens all the time although
clearly has given
>> yeah it does have an effect but as a
storytelling you know part is kind of
questionable um the other thing I wanted
to ask you know since you guys have been
playing um particularly board games you
know there are board games that have
similar mechanics. So, I've played Race
of the Galaxy, which I really like, and
I've been told that Puerto Rico is very
similar.
>> Yes. So, does changing the theme I mean
that those games have different themes,
but is does changing the theme affect
the rules in any ways for those of you
who might have played both?
>> Not really. I mean, not Puerto Rico, but
San Juan, I think, is closer. San is
with the cards, but uh it doesn't really
change the game because the mechanics
are almost identical. It's just kind of
covered in a different shell of whatever
it is, whatever the mechanic they're
trying to mimic.
>> So, it's kind of like maybe if you don't
like colonial or, you know, whatever.
>> Yeah. If you don't like if you don't
like the the
>> science fiction part of
>> the science fiction theme, you could go
for this more earth town building theme.
>> Yeah.
>> But if you don't like playing the game
itself,
>> switching to the other game is probably
not going to be all.
>> Yes. Yeah. which I think is kind of
interesting and just kind of like okay
so tug of munch doesn't kind of cancel
>> the interesting thing is that in neither
of those cases unlike say ticket to
right these things like feel like
they're attacked on theme and in each
case the actual mechanics of the card
faithfully represent what they're
supposed to be in in the in the game
fiction right so
>> I feel that this the fact that they the
themes are essentially kind of
interchangeable or like the the same
mechanics underly both games despite the
fact that they have different themes
doesn't necessarily mean that there's
some something wrong with the theming.
It's just that
>> but the meaning is similar
>> mechanics are flexib
what you actually do in the games is
similar you know resource management
planning ahead knowing where you can
deploy a certain you know they are about
the same thing even if they have
different settings uh so that's probably
the connection it's not about oh if you
like science fiction games you can play
the battlest star galactica game and
race to the galaxy whereas I'm guessing
that for most people it's like well if I
like Puerto Rico or Puerto Rico San
Juan. Sorry, I wrong place
>> name. The games are close enough that
>> but but you would play something that is
similar. Does that make sense?
>> If if the meaning of both games is
really
empire building in some sense, right?
You know, in some kind of historical in
futuristic, but they're both empire
building. That's why I mean sure the
theme is very well applied in both of
these games but it will also make sense
that that will make sense because both
themes are about empire building only
you know one to the future and one to
the past.
>> Okay. So you know we have this is taking
a bit of time but these are like the
foundations of the of the concepts that
I wanted to get across today and discuss
today. Uh when we talk about video
games, there's another there's an extra
layer which is you know video games that
are story driven versus just games with
a story. Uh and the example I have here
is uh so this is selfcal 2 as far as I
remember
>> I think I don't know I I looked for cell
caliber one that was familiar um the
characters I knew anyway. So, in
Soulcalibur, we have what's a game
about?
>> Fighting.
>> It's about fighting and kicking ass, you
know.
>> Story that doesn't
>> And it does have a weird story that is
kind of like, well, does anybody know
the story? I know that there's
something. And there's some reason why
[Music]
>> Sophia Sophia, right?
>> I didn't know. I think this is
>> they're like related somehow. They're
like mother and daughter
sisters or something.
>> Oh, okay. That's maybe that's why she's
asking for forgiveness. I don't know. Do
I care? I still like these games, but do
I know the stories? No. Do I Does it
matter? Not really. I mean, not for
these. I mean, for some people, I'm sure
that they do care about the stories of
these or the stories of the characters
in Street Fighter, for example. Yes.
Well, I was gonna say like for games
like this, I actually kind of like the
story because it adds
>> like it the game is not the story. There
are two separate entities,
>> but one kind of like add to the other
for me. Like Diablo, for example,
>> um there's lots of people that have
played Diablo II without really caring
about, you know, like the actual story.
>> The cinematics were so cool back in the
day.
>> True. But the thing
>> but but like even though like you can
you can pretty much separate the story
from Diablo II and people would still
probably play it like the story
definitely adds a layer of like I I am
attached to this game.
>> But Diablo I mean in Diablo is the the
difference is is that Diablo is closer
to being a storydriven game. It's closer
to being like an RPG game where you know
the quests you have to know you know who
you're going to talk to what you're
going to do. Um, I had a friend, we
were, you know, uh, working in in this
game service and we had to test all
these, um, role playing games and one of
my co-workers was like, oh, I have to
play it was Balders's Gate, too. Like
one of the cool ones. And he was like,
"Okay, I have to test this and I just
have to see that it works." And he was
not paying attention to any other texts.
He was just doing the technical testing,
but then he got stuck. I mean, we were
supposed to finish the the games and he
was stuck and he was going slower
because he didn't know what to do. It's
like, well, if he had read what you
actually had to do, but for him it's
like, well, it's just a story. It's
like, well, you're playing an RPG. You
kind of really leave the the story out.
If somebody's telling you that you have
to, you know, squash, I don't know how
many orcs, you know, you have to know
that you have to squash the orcs. You
can, you have to know where to go. Um,
so, so in storydriven games, what
happens is that the story is really so
tied to the rules and the goals of the
game that you have as you advance in the
game, you're also advancing in the
story. That's something that, you know,
here when when you um, you know, you
beat up somebody in Soulcalibur or or uh
or Street Fighter, whatever fighting
game you can think of, you know, there
might be a little uh uh cutscene uh that
tells us who they are. One thing that I
like about is it Soulcalibur? Yeah. Like
there's a bit of taunting like ah you
kind of beat me or something like that.
Um but that you know is is building
character a bit and that needs writing
but really you know is is not really
story driven. The fact that we're
getting big services as we complete
challenges you know it doesn't mean that
if we ignore the game we can still
complete the game without knowing the
story. Does it make sense? So there's,
you know, this is this is something that
video games are doing that to a certain
extent some of the board games that you
might have been playing don't quite do.
Does it make does make sense that it's
kind of like we can still think of and
and there might be you know some people
who play these board games still at a
mathematical level without paying any
attention to what the events that's
representing are. Uh but that's one
potential of video games. you know that
idea of having a storydriven game where
you are playing a game you are
interacting with the world with a strong
and in the cases of storydriven games
you also have a strong little fictional
world that you're interacting with that
you are exploring that you're poking
around um so one thing that I wanted to
make clear here is that you know when we
talk when we talk about storytelling and
I always try to use it the term we're
talking about stories but is it really
storytelling and the thing is that
technically games don't tell stories.
You know, who's telling the story? Who's
the narrator? You know, there might be
games that have the kind of gimmick of
having a narrator like um Prince of
Persia Sands of Time. You know, when you
make a mistake and you know, he's
supposed to be telling what's happened
to him and it's like, "No, no, no,
wait." You know, I No, no, no. That's
not how it happened. Um but really in
most games you know things again like
Balders's Gate or Diablo or more
recently like you know uh Mass Effect
you know it's like what you know who is
the storyteller you know and and the the
thing is that there are also different
types of stories you know when we are
interacting with the game what we're
doing is is performing and as we perform
we're creating a story there's a story
that has been maybe prepared for us you
know kind of going back to the munchkin
thing, you know, in every card we have a
bit of the story and um and we are kind
of like we are putting it together like
laying it out. Um so so the game
designers have designed each game you
know each chunk of the story what are
the cues that we're giving the player
but then there's also what us as player
are are bringing to the to the game you
know as I was saying before you know
there's part that is the game itself
telling its story and the other is what
we're invoking what we are having the
player uh bring uh to the game you know
is the story happening in the player's
head so what I like to say is that it's
not really storytelling it's about story
building and as game designers we are
designing those little chunks you know
or we are uh creating stories that are
uh that are meant to be reconstructed
that are meant to be together. Uh so the
difference between storytelling and
story building you know basically when
we have storytelling we have somebody
who's narrating or uh you know maybe
there's some uh uh someone who's
enacting what's happened. of things like
theater for example but it's continuous
it's something that just happens and you
know is not is not fragmented which is
what what story building needs you know
we have something that is as has already
happened you know is communicated one
way uh and how what those events are and
what order they're told that's
determined by the author. If we think
about stories and how stories apply to
games in terms of story building, we're
talking about fragmented stories. You
know, stories in pieces, stories that we
have to put together like a puzzle. And
you know, we're game designers. We make
puzzles. That's one of the many things
that we can do. Uh what those fragments
are, how we were giving cues to the
player to put together those fragments
or to come up with their own ways of of
coming up with the story. Um, in a way
it's a kind of collaboration between the
the designer and the player because we
rely on the player to put this story
together to come up with their own ways
of filling the gaps um to to really have
a proactive role in figuring out what
the story is uh and what the order of
events is. I mean there are you guys
have seen the the games of progression
and games of emergence.
>> Yes.
>> Discuss that
first.
I'm trying to remember this.
>> It's like the very It's in the first
chapter.
>> I think we had actually did the the
initial paper.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We we had in the paper not
not
>> another
basically the same.
>> Okay. Yeah. No, cuz he he talked about
the same thing totally different places.
Um so so yeah what what happens is that
you know at times there are games that
have a specific order of events and
there are certain adventure games like
uh Siberia for example where you have to
go through a very specific sequence of
events and when you get to a scene it's
like you have to do this uh things like
um Dragon Slayer the the laser disc DVD
like when you go to a place and you have
to figure out what is the action that
you have to do and if you don't do it
you're you know you die in horrible
ways. Um so those are you know those are
games that set the order of events very
very specifically but most of the games
tend to have some more flexibility. You
know let the player explore the world.
You know the things that happen in the
world are generated by how the player is
interacting with the world. So in RPGs
for example, depending on the RPG, there
might be the main quests and the side
quests and there might be flexibility in
what order that happens or even how a
player might solve a a specific quest in
top tabletop. I don't know who here is
has been uh dungeon master. Okay, a
bunch of you.
>> So everybody,
>> okay, so we have the corner of the
dungeon masters. So, you probably know
that when you design a quest, you know,
and then you you set it up and you have
your players and then your players come
up with totally different ways of
tackling your quest you had never come
up with and you have to improvise and
trying to, you know, like you're
building the rails as they're moving.
You know, it's kind of like, you know,
trying to anticipate what they're going
to do. Um, so so that's we're trying to
get that into video games, too, but but
we don't have the improvisational
capacity built in in computers yet. Uh
but but as you see it's kind of like we
the game or the dungeon master as
dungeon masters we're responding to the
actions of the player. Does it make
sense? And then there are you know we
where we're talking about story building
there are games as I was saying that are
about story building where the challenge
is constructing a story improvising as
you as you go. You know you're given
chunks and you have to be able to be a
storyteller. Uh but you'll play that
these later.
Um,
we've actually talked about this before.
So, when we're talking about building
the fictional world of of the game, you
know, I'm going I'm going to go through
through this a bit um fast. We have
until 4:30, right? Yes. Okay. Uh, so
there are also very minimal ways in
which we can, you know, construct our
fiction. uh and these are lessons that
I've taken from digital games but if you
think about it many of these also apply
to uh non-digital games uh so for
example we have um the title of a game
can tell us you know something about the
fictional world right so come what about
uh board games or card games how do the
titles build the fictional world
>> the board game Mafia Wars is pretty
clear about with that
>> there you go so that's a way It's
evoking certain things like the title
can evoke a world on itself and also
certain situations. So we hear mafia
wars is about
>> there's different factions.
>> There's going
>> there's going to be betrayal probably,
you know, shooting down people in
horrible ways.
>> Pretty much any licensed game.
>> Any licensed game. Yes. There were types
of you know things like versions of
Monopoly or true pursuit that it's kind
of like is that
>> Star Wars
>> Star Wars everything
>> risk it's a kind of broad
>> and there are also skinningings of risk
right
>> there like
>> Lord of the Rings
>> Lord of the Rings everything
>> I don't know
>> I've seen like so many this god which
takes place back in like it's like
mythological.
>> Yeah. What other apart from franchises,
what other title? Sorry.
>> The settlers of katan.
>> Settlers of katan which is evoking
>> settling
building cities
>> building.
>> Yeah. I mean it's kind of who you
talking to.
>> Chinatown.
>> It's set from Chinatown.
>> And what do you do?
You build businesses that are
stereotypically associated with
>> one title. It's not only we're evoking a
world, but we can also invoke rules.
What do you have to do here? So if mafia
were to kill people, you know, don't
settle jobs and longer.
>> Uh but you're already implying what some
of the rules are, what the game is
about. Um which is what is important
here. And and again, you know, Seren
Johnson calls attention to the fact that
if you say if you're announcing that
your game is about something in this
trench booklet that people might not
always read or at least the part that
people don't read, you know, you should
you should um follow up on that because
it's kind of helping. He's giving cues
to the player about how is the story of
the game going to build up. you know
what is the cue you I like talking about
giving cues to the player a lot because
I come from theater and and is a is a
very intuitive way of understanding it's
not about us telling the story it's
about helping the player construct the
story so I have two examples from from
video games that I really like about how
to to build a fictional world with with
a title I mean one obvious one in in
video games is Space Invaders right
Space Invaders means we're on Earth
>> and they're invaders from space that we
probably have to fight.
>> Invading our space.
>> Another good one. Zombies ain't my
neighbors. There's a whole story right
there. So, what's the story of this
game?
>> Zombies a neighbor. So, what do I do in
this game?
>> Zombies.
>> So, probably killing zombies.
>> Zombies eating my neighbors. So, zombies
could have eaten my neighbors and then
just left.
>> Maybe the zombies are your neighbors.
>> Yeah. Oh, maybe you have to kill your
neighbors too now.
>> Um, if there's anything left because
they hit them. Um, but it's, you know,
like this is building like a whole, you
know, situation. What do I have to do?
Okay, zombies, walking zombies, I'm
sure. Or run away from the neighbors. I
>> mean, the fact that you have neighbors
implies that there's a neighborhood,
right? It's not like a military zombie
shooter.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. It's not rested.
>> It looks vaguely like 50s.
>> Yeah. I'm not sure about that. I think
this is like a Genesis game.
I was just looking at the old like 50s.
>> I mean, hearkening back to the movies of
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, another great title that I found not
long ago, Earth Dies Screaming.
>> Wow. which is actually
>> is the title is from a 70s British movie
uh that I think has nothing to do with
the game. This is another it's like
Space Invaders in a way. You are
defending the Earth. It kind of like
looks like that. Um you have your
spaceship and you have a one of the
invaders and you have to you just
destroy it before it lands on Earth. Um,
but again, you know, it kind of it's
very evocative. I mean, it's kind of
more memorable than Space Invaders in a
way. Uh, because it's kind of like,
okay, there's people attacking Earth,
whoever it is, and this is going to end
badly. That's another thing that Space
Invaders are things like Miscommand and
all those arcade games that didn't have
an ending. You know, in this, you know,
the ending, you know, you cannot really
save Earth. It's really it's really uh
ominous in a way. Uh but again like you
have a whole world you have a whole
situation is about in the title and it's
also very memorable. I really like this
title. Um, another way in which we can
give cues to um to players to build
worlds. And I had more of this, but but
this applies more to um this applies
more to video games than to board games,
card games, you know, and even role
playing games. uh is character design
because when we are making and and you
know tell me from your own experience
but when you're making nondigital games
and even when you're making when you're
preparing your uh Dungeons and Dragons
campaign you don't really come up with
the characters the characters is
something that the player brings for
card games. If you have any examples
that are counter examples for this
please let me know. Um but character
design is not something that you do so
much in non digital games. If you do you
have any examples of that?
>> Do the NPCs
>> design?
>> Yeah, in a way. Yes.
>> I was thinking
Arkham Horror and other games where you
kind of have a character role which is
assigned to you and often they have a
backstory in Arkham Horror bio on the
back or what have you.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. I was going to say like um the the
game where you're trying to clue clue
where you have like a you choose a
character and they all have their
swords. I'm sure it's similar. Mhm. The
things like are you as a player are you
really involved with those characters?
>> Okay. So I can think of one game which
is an example where you are and it's
called Android.
>> Mhm.
>> This is an uh this game was released I
think two years ago now. And part of the
actually you should probably play it.
Um, part of part of the point is that it
was trying to include like elements of
resolving characters personal stories
through mechanics in the game.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> So, you're actually you're kind of
you're kind of living you're kind of
playing through this choose your own
adventurish type scenario. Um, and the
choices that you make throughout the
game influence like what directions your
character's personal story arc takes
>> a very good game. But
it's interesting.
>> Yeah. So, so there are the what I'm
trying to get at here is that, you know,
at times the characters are and again,
you know, evoking actions, evoking
certain emotions to it. things of that
detachment with with non-digital games
with role playing games is different but
again when you're building your own
character in role playing you have an
investment but you're making it yourself
I'm talking more on the point of view of
the designer here
>> so another I guess game game again
Battlestar Galactica you are assigning a
character and if you know that like if
you know Battlestar Galactica you're
probably going to go for certain
characters cuz like I that character is
hilarious. I want to be him or I'm gonna
be Starbucks. Starbucks's awesome. And
so, and then each one each player
actually also has certain traits which
are characteristic of their um the
player in the show like Tai. He's an
alcoholic. So, there's a certain
negative tribute to him if you are in
certain situations.
>> Okay. We had he had the back. Well,
let's say in in live action role playing
games like uh experience with the
Assassin's C and stuff, the characters
are entirely designed by the game
designers.
>> Yes.
>> But you still you still get the the
players who like take up this character
become involved with it because all of
their actions are based on
>> on what the designer chose to to make
that
>> character. Yep. That's that's true. I'm
>> um two other games. cosmic encounter uh
is where like um probably closer to the
battle situation, you've got you pick a
a race at the beginning of the game. So,
it's not a single character, but that's
effectively the same thing in in that if
you pick something like the humans, uh
you have different goals and different
different powers that you can use in the
game. Whereas if you play a game like
Illuminati again, instead of playing an
individual, you're playing a corporation
or actually your picking is society for
for the most part and your actual
game-winning goals are different for uh
depending on who you pick.
>> And part of the and there are certain
part part of the game is also figuring
out what certain characters are trying
how certain characters are trying to win
the game. Um because not everybody has
the same game for
>> Okay, Patrick, last one.
In and the card game sabotur, if your
role is the sabotur, then it is in the
player's best interest to act in that
role
>> to like perform like one.
>> Yes. To be subversive to the other
players without like letting them catch
on.
>> Oh. Oh. So you see, and this is why I
didn't do this and I was asking because
I know this much better. But yeah, I
think the the laring one is the the
obvious case here. Um, in video games,
you know what we do? you know, we can
build character in kind of like
cinematic ways and cut scenes and
whatever, but really, you know, it's
very difficult to build a character um
that is at the same time you and not you
or the the player and not the player. Uh
and what we can do, you know, is giving
cues about
the personality of that character. And
one of the the examples I want to give
is Sonic because Sonic is not really
you. I mean this is always the a bit of
the struggle in a lot of the examples
that you were doing you know except for
lapping where lapping is bit more
involved is that it's kind of like you
but not you like who am I you know I'm
the sabotur because I'm doing this um in
in in uh in games we have Sonic for
example with like you know we are Sonic
what what are we hedgehog
um and what do we do
>> like run coins and cute animals
>> and liberating cute animals.
>> Yes, that too. Uh and one of the things
so so one of the the the the goals of of
designing character particularly in
video games is making it seem alive you
know making it go beyond the functional
part you know like oh we're the sabotur
we are I don't know whatever character
in a clue for example you having that
emotional involvement that is something
that that we are trying to achieve in in
in video games and Sonic does it in a
very subtle but very cool Okay. Does
anybody know what this picture is of?
What he's doing?
>> Don't do anything. He starts tapping his
foot and looking at you.
>> So, it's kind of like you have no
control of me. Come on. I want to go.
You know, I really have to go. I have to
run cuz what I do is running. So, let's
go.
>> Mario goes to sleep.
>> Yeah, Mario sleep.
starts to
>> and if you remember any of the Earthwork
gym Earthworth gym games like he does
crazy stuff. He's just like he starts
like
>> he flips his head, he dresses up like he
was like in one of like
>> Yeah. or like he gets an afro
uh uh wig at some point and like what
are you doing? You know, but it's kind
of like calling attention to like who am
I? You know, well, you're not
controlling me. I'm going to be myself.
And in the case of Sonic, it's like,
okay, I'm a running guy, but I need you
to run, so come on. Um, and it's very
subtle, you know, something that is very
minimal, but it's it's building
character, but it's also kind of telling
the player who this character is. Um,
the last thing, and this is something
that again video games can do very well,
is something that role playing games can
do very well or or laughing. Uh but I'm
not sure that you know card games or
board games can do this. It's
environmental storytelling. Uh it's
telling the story in the space as you go
around as you're examining the space and
what's going on. You know, a video games
do what they do very well is uh
constructing a virtual world that we can
navigate, that we can explore, that we
can interact with. Uh and one of u those
of you who've been in my classes before,
you know that I love the beginning of
Bioshock as an example of environmental
storytelling. Uh because you know, you
know what is this world? What has
happened before? And they don't give you
they don't tell the word is just going
into the space and figuring out what has
happened. Another example that I really
love is portal.
um where you know a lot of the story is
you know told or you you you figure it
out as you explore the world. So what is
this import? So first of all what is the
premise of portal you know this the
story
>> you're a test subject testing a new
device aperture labs.
>> Yes. So, you're a test subject and but
but very soon you realize that there's
something kind of wrong, you know, you
know, this voice that keeps talking to
you, you know, kind of warps around and
she goes and comes back and like there
is something broken and you just go on
because you don't know what else to do.
But here, what is this? You know, once
you start realizing, okay, there's
something really wrong. What is this?
>> This is when you try to escape.
>> There's a hole in the wall.
>> There's a hole. One of the things is
like stuck forward. You can sneak under
or something.
>> Yeah. And you go behind the scenes and
you realize, okay, so there is something
really wrong here and kind of guessed
it. But here we have what looks like
somebody's
uh refuge like some where somebody was
hiding and they were writing all these
messages and of course you know it's
very funny because the famous the cake
is alive is something is not something
that everybody has to go through. You
have to find it. you have to find it in
the game is is part of the explore in
the game. So, so what the reason why I
like uh I I like Portal for many many
reasons. Uh but one is because the
storytelling is very brilliant and it's
not you know is is not something that
we're told. This is what happened. We
figure it out by listen to to the voice
by listening to Glados by going behind
the scenes. We are piecing the the story
together. Yes. Um, if you ever pay
attention to what's written in the walls
in the safe houses and Left 4 Dead,
>> there's a lot of funny stuff as well.
And I initially hadn't realized that
Left had a story really. And then when
you when you when you actually pause and
read, you know what's on the walls in
the safe houses, there's almost flame
wars between different people who've
gone to the same houses and are writing
facts about the zombie apocalypse and
they'll say, "No, that's not true. That
town is completely overrun. No, you're
totally stupid. I was there last you
have like these things going on and
various you know tidbits of trivia and
facts about the world and it's very very
clever and often quite hilarious
>> because what this is what environmental
storytelling is doing after all we're
telling the story of the fictional world
you know that can be part of the goal of
of speaking or not what is the story of
the fictional world you
guess
>> um was there's
use environmental storytelling as story
What?
>> Well, you mentioned the difference
between storytelling and story building
earlier and you mentioned that that was
environmental storytelling as a story.
>> Yeah. And probably is really story
building. I mean, so the thing is that
environmental storytelling is what
people call it. I'm using a phrase, but
yeah, this is a type of story building.
>> We're building it as designers and we're
encouraging building for the player.
>> But but yeah, this is story building. So
yes or or um more precisely you will see
talks on environmental storytelling if
you go to a conference.
>> Uh but what they're really talking about
storytelling it's just that that term
hasn't really made it so pervasive.
>> Yeah.
>> So maybe the closest to this kind of
thing is in flavor text in CCGs and
other such stuff. So if you think for
instance of Magic the Gathering then
there is a backstory behind each of
these expansions which comes out
>> and that's told through actual fiction
where you can buy really trashy novels
also partly told through like little
quotes between uh by significant
characters in the fiction and also the
the images which presented on the cards
and so maybe that's the closest thing to
environmental storytelling.
>> Yes. Yeah. I mean Magic the Gathering
has this world and the things that it
seems to be very easy to expand it. I
don't know the survival of of the magic
the gathering.
>> Yeah. Like there's an entire creative
department at visit the coast that's
responsible for maintaining the story
and making sure it's all consistent and
stuff.
>> Yeah. So it's not really something new.
Uh it's almost four. So I have still
something but we can go through it very
fast. I would hope
>> I mean if we run out of time we can play
these games on Friday or something.
Okay. Absolutely.
>> So, so we've been talking so far, we're
talking about uh designing the story of
the world, designing the story of a
fictional world, but we also have, as I
was saying before, you know, the player
is also constructing a story as we go,
you know, things that happen to the
player, um things that that happen to
the world because they happen to player.
And again, one of the reasons why I was
talking about games of progression
versus games of emergence is that in
stories we have a similar parallel of uh
stories that have been designed for the
player of things that that they have to
do. uh in role playing games and and I'm
talking about pen and pencil um pen and
paper role playing games we have the
story that is as DMs we have designs and
then there's what the players are trying
to do in in video games because
computers don't have the capacity for
improvisation
what the player has to do is a lot more
constraint in a way uh so what are the
bosses that they have to you know how do
they solve a specific problem or how do
we get over a specific problem? So, um
uh I like giving the example of of um
the legend the Legend of Zelda games
where we do have a story that we're kind
of complete completing a specific uh in
almost in a specific order because if
you don't have certain objects, you kind
of go to the next dungeon until you have
certain properties. So we have even
though we have a really nice relatively
open world of the world that we can
navigate uh we do have a specific order
of events that we have to follow uh
adventure games and by this I mean like
point andclick adventure games uh um
again things like Siberia things like
mess where you know there is a
pre-established sequence of events that
we have to that we have to fulfill and
then on the other extreme we have games
that are closer to you know these games
like once upon a time or bloom where the
system itself is producing stories of
sorts uh like the Sims and in the Sims
the fact that we have a way to record
our own stories and and share them is is
proof that that is that's a kind of
system closer to to things like one song
at a time that is a system to generate
narratives and the playing with the with
the system will generate certain
narratives. Um
so we have um ways in which as designers
we can provide cues or or ways to to
design the story of the player. Uh and
the first one is you know the game
premise you know what is the goal of the
game uh game events. I don't know if I
left that one because that was too long.
Um and we have micro narrative. So the
the the game premise is you know who are
you in the game? What do you do? It's
kind of similar to the to the title, but
in this case is very tied to who is the
player, what is the role of the player
in the game. So things like cooking
mama, for example, you know, you're
cooking mama. So who are you in cooking
mama? You know mama, mom's complaining
all about it.
You are the person who's cooking for
mama. That's the title you should have.
Cooking for mama and then mama getting
pissed off at you because you didn't do
it right. Uh but it tells you very
clearly. Okay, so you're a cook or what
is it that you do? You're trying to
please mama by cooking something nice
and yummy. Usually also kind of weird.
Um, a really good example of of creating
the story of the the player by the
premise of by who you are in the game is
this.
So, I love this example
>> because it's kind of like who are you?
You're a hacker. And it gives you the
cool thing about this trailer. It gives
you a list of what you do. This is your
story. You are framing people. You're
framing innocent people, of course, you
know, changing people academic records,
building viruses, and all those are are
activities in the game, but it's also,
you know, who you are. That is your
story. Those are the kinds of things
that you're going to do in the game. Um,
so again, you know, we were talking
about Sabotur before. Well, as Sabadur,
you already have a series of actions
that you're associating with with your
character. That's the way that we can
design the story of the player at least
at a at a high level and give it that
cue. Um I'm skipping game events because
that's kind of long and it's very based
on too based in video games um and
mostly on cut scenes. Um the other um
example that I want to bring here is
micro narratives. And again, this is
more all these are more a video game
thing, but micro narratives are little
events, you know, they're not like even
cut scenes. They're just little events
that happen as reactions to the player's
actions. In a way, Sonic tapping his
food is a kind of macro narrative, like
you're not doing anything and it's kind
of like, come on, I want to go or or uh
Mario falling asleep. It's it's kind of
like a micro narrative of sorts. Uh but
at times I love this is one of my
favorite macro narratives in the history
of games. This is the game Jack said
Willie which is from 1985
80 something mid80s. Um it was for
Commodore 64. Well it was originally for
the Spectrum. True. Yes. Thank you. He
has
prepared a presentation of the Spectrum.
Yes. uh Commodore 64, Amsterdam. It was
for all the this uh Z80 U platforms in
the 80s. And this was a sequel to Manic
Minor. Uh so in Manic Minor, you wear
minor Willie. Yes, Minor Willie. Uh and
you go down into the earth and you find
a treasure and you become immensely
rich. So, with the money that you get
from from the first game, you throw a
party. And you throw such a big party
that your house becomes invaded by the
weirdest creatures ever. Um, there are
flying
toilet seats. Um, mutant pigs. I don't
know. This it's it's Yeah, it's such a
good party that you get people from
other worlds to come to your party. Uh,
but the thing is like it was such a good
party, you want to go to bed. This is
Willie. This is this is you in the game.
So he jets at Willie. This is the the
day after and Willie is hangover
probably after the super party and he
was under a bed and in the in the in the
game uh to the to the left you have the
picture of a bed and that's kind of like
your goal. Go to bed. But this is your
land lady who's seen how you trashed the
place and she doesn't want you to go to
bed until you've cleaned it up. So, the
cool thing, and I really want to get an
the animation here, um, is that she has
her arms like this, you know, she's
holding her her arms like this, and
whenever you get near her, uh, her,
which which arm is it? Her left arm goes
like, "H go." And it's a reaction to
what you do is with those. It's a few
pixels. It's like probably four or five
pixels. And in four five pixels, this
game is telling you this is what you
have to do. Go that way. This is your
goal. Yes, but you cannot come here. Go
that way and clean it up, you know, and
this is, you know, this is 8 bit pixels.
And she's telling it all bad with just a
few pixels. You don't really need that
much. Um, but it's that kind of
reaction. You know, we always want to to
get again give cues. What is it that the
player has to do? We don't need a cut
scene. only with a few with a few pixels
we know what we have to do right and
it's a very difficult game too for
today's standards
anyway so the conclusion um here is that
you know why do we need stories or why
do we need fictions you know what do
fictional worlds do for us what do
themes uh do for us you know well as
we're saying you know we have humans
have a tendency to storyize everything
we are natural storytellers some of What
these games like Once Upon a Time or
Bloom um are playing up with is because
we are we tell you know other people
what has happened to us. You know if you
complain about something you're
complaining in the in the form of a
story or something that might have
happened to you. uh we understand our
experience as stories and there are you
know different uh disciplines have have
dealt with this you know from cognitive
cognitive science to um psychology you
know how we are so making stories about
ourselves how we making stories about
our worlds. So having a story having a a
a game that has a fictional world in
which a story can take place is a way of
understanding the underlying system you
know by as I was saying you know if we
have a game that is called mafia word
wars we already have a goal we have a
sets of rules you know who we are what
is it that we have to do uh and we don't
have we don't need a lot of you know two
words have been enough to evoke a lot of
those of that information Um, so the the
other the last thing, and this applies a
bit more to video games, is that by
having a story, we're also providing
consistency to the world. You know, when
when um Yesper U is talking about uh
incoherent worlds, he's really talking
about worlds where, you know, there's
not really a story and and there are
video games that have awful stories.
That's true. But when you're forced or
where you're thinking about your your
world as ter not only as a fictional
world as a simulation but also as a
world that has to produce a story that
makes sense you know that is going to
provide more coherence to the world
hopefully if you have good writers too
but that mean you can take the director
for games supposed to uh you know that
there's there's something and and there
are things that that Jper complains
about like the um you know why does
Mario have three lives Well,
well, because it's Mario, right?
Uh, you know, is that part of the story?
You know, that's that's a bit one of
those like no man's land uh kind of kind
of issues like does that undermine the
consistency of the world? Maybe the onto
the the ontological level, the level of
the world uh itself. Uh but really, it's
kind of is more about making sense about
the rules. You know what is it looking
at being able to look at the world in in
a critical way? I'm trying to think of
an example of apart from the three lines
of Mario.
>> What?
>> What he says the plumber? Oh, no. That
was
>> No, but so for example, uh I don't know
Kirby like he eats
other creatures and spits them.
You know what? Where does it come from?
You know, why does he do that? That, you
know, what is what is the story of
Kirby? He's a kind of Yeah, he's kind of
cute, but hey, I would watch out with
him because he can eat almost anything
and then he becomes it.
>> Kirby is a really disturbing character.
>> When you think about it in terms of
stories, like this is kind of wow.
>> I mean, Yoshi, right?
>> Yes.
>> And I love Yoshi.
>> Yeah. That's another
video game charact. It seems like one of
the reasons why these arguments are
being raised is because been this huge
pile of inconsistencies.
>> Yes, but the inconsistencies become
evident when you try to write the story
>> if that makes sense.
>> You know, it's kind of like So,
>> so Yoshi eats creatures and maybe
>> he poops eggs. He hatches an egg.
>> Depends on which Mario you're talking
about. Cuz if it's Super Mario
Yeah. He poops.
>> Yeah. And it's like And then he throws
it and they're like bomb.
>> Yeah. He throws his ank. He uses his
ank.
That's true.
Yoshi is a question.
>> Yes. But yeah, but all those things
become evident the moment that we start
to story. So who is this person? Why did
they what did they do this? And it's
kind of like wow. It's kind of like
falling apart. So the incoherence and
I'm just thinking that I don't know if
like this or not. But the incoherence
comes from the impossibility or or not
impossibility but but the the problems
of trying to make this into a story and
realizing well this has not been this
has been thought out as a cool game and
I love Yoshi's Island but as the story
is kind of falls apart. Yeah.
>> So
I think one of the the really glaring
inconsistencies in a lot of RPGs in
particular is that in most of these
worlds there's some kind of like
resurrection power which exists.
And there are a lot of plots which
revolve around characters dying and that
being a bad thing. And you're like, why
not just use your Phoenix down?
>> Why do we care if the king's been
assassinated? I've got this thing in my
inventory from
resurrecting like a thousand times. And
now because this guy killed it, like
what kind of reason?
>> The actual conceit there is you're not
dead. You're just knocked out.
>> So it's like smelling salts or
something. But there are games like
Plscape tournament where that is
incorporated in the you know you're
immortal and that's the thing that
figuring out why you're immortal and why
you they make fun of of you like waking
up and it's kind like oh my goodness
this is really this really hurts I feel
terrible you know and then they're
making they're making that problem into
part of an essential part of the game.
Yes. So, with the RPG thing, the
incoherency is how so many times when
you're in these battles, you're doing
these incredible things like you're
summoning asteroids or jumping and
destroy people, but then in the in the
game world, you get to a ledge and it's
like, oh, it's a ledge. I have to go
around or look, it's a it's a gap like
this wide. I can't step over it. There's
a bush. Oh, no. I can't what what am I
going to do? There's a bush in the way.
And so,
>> but you put in diagonals, too. What?
>> No, I'd rather do diagonals.
>> I think another egregious inconsistency
that comes up a lot is the uh and I
think it's in the it's it's explicitly
mentioned in the reading that that
you're you're the world savior usually
and on the way you're going to pillage,
steal, kill innocent people, and it's
not going to be a big deal. and and and
even in games where they make the
endpoint variables, they're like, "All
right, you can neither save the world or
be a total jerk, and that fixes one
problem." They still have the problem
that during the game, you can alternate
back and forth between being really good
and really bad. And all it does is it
kind of swings you one way or the other.
It's one, it's one dimensional, so you
just sort of a spectrum, and if you do
five really bad things and then five
really good things, you're back to where
you started. Yes.
>> And that's not necessarily consistent,
you know, uh,
>> in terms of storytelling. There's also
the the classic inconsistency of if I
don't save the world, everything will be
destroyed, but you're still going to
charge me a 100 gill for this Phoenix.
>> It's still inconsistent
>> and and or I have to say to the world
now because bad things are happening.
Let me go do these 20 side quests first.
>> It's still marching. But yeah, I can
>> this cat stuck in a tree.
>> The rat's in the cellar, man. Rats in
the cell.
>> Yeah. It's like the end of the world is
nine. Like in Final Fantasy, the end of
the world is nine, but let me go around
more more random characters so that I
can bump up my
>> So that actually reminds me of I think
it was a web comic I read about a month
ago and it had like it was based around
Link. I was like, "Oh my god, you're our
savior. You're going to help us." I was
like, "Yes, I am." And so the whole
whole time he's just going on Cypus
like, "What are you doing? They're
raping and pillaging everything. They're
destroying everything. What are you What
are you doing?" Oh. I'll do that in a
second. I just have to get this really
fairly cool shield. It's like and then
and then at one point it's like why what
are you doing? It's like I'm fishing so
I can get this litter so I can catch
some other fish. Like why why would you
ever be doing this right now when the
world's about to end and evil is
spreading across everything. It's like
don't worry about it. I'm on it.
>> Well, it's very interesting. And then
this is my last last slide. So if you
want to
>> we can go on discussing. Sure we can
have. Okay. So um at times you know the
little cues that are building world or
building character can also backfire.
So, I've been playing one of the DS uh
Zelda games, and this one of the nicest
touches is that whenever you get near a
character, you know, Link is going to
look at them in the eye like, "Hi," you
know, like you're walking and stuff
like, "Hi," you know, and at times it's
super weird because they look the
characters look at each other like they
acknowledge that they're there. So, they
feel kind of alive, you know, it's very
simple, you know, 3D algorithm like,
"Okay, if there's another character,
they look at each other." It's like,
"Wow, they're alive. Cool." and they
react. But then you go into somebody's
house and they're looking at you and
you're like, "Hi, you know, you break
their pots to get rupees and they're
looking at you and you're like breaking
everything and it's kind of like it's
kind of weird. They should react because
they're looking at you and you're
breaking their house,
you know, and and that's, you know,
again, it's giving a touch that is
giving you making those characters
alive, but it's also kind of like
breaking it like kind of I'm still
breaking your thoughts. That's better.
>> I think that was uh subverted in um what
was it?
>> No. In another Zelda game, um
>> Link's Awakening.
>> You go into the shop and the shop owner
is always looking at you. So, if you
take something off the shelf and try and
exit, he says, "No, you can't do that.
You can't uh steal it." But if you run
around him, he's not fast enough to keep
his eye on you. So, you run around him
until he's looking away and you can
leave.
But if you come back in, he says,
"You're the guy who stole something."
And then he shoots you with the laser.
>> The character in the game calls you a
thief. The rest of
>> the game. That's very funny.
>> That's awesome.
>> I was going to say like Oblivion and
Fallout do the same sort of like where
everyone watches you like if they're
within like
>> they're acknowledging you and then like
you try and take something like they'll
run up and be like why the hell are you
taking my stuff or like start you know
beating you up or whatever. What should
they do? people called the town guard.
>> Yeah.
>> And everyone
>> problematic when you're powerful enough
and you can take the town guard
>> and it's just really annoying cuz
everywhere you go there's like guys you
can kill that kind of there and you're
like all right come on get out of my
way.
>> Yeah. So there was a Mega Man Legends
which I don't know if anybody ever
played. I don't think anyone played
that, but um essentially it was like
Mega Man, but the RPG style game, but it
was actually slightly different from
most RPGs. And that most RPGs, you just
walk around walking into people's houses
looking for loot. But you actually
couldn't just walk into people's houses.
Their doors would be locked and like you
could knock and see if anybody was
there. But it was kind of interesting
because like it was actually consistent
in the sense that you couldn't just
randomly walk into somebody's house and
steal their crap.
>> There's one thing. So one thing that I
wanted to ask you because all these
things in in video games you know after
a while the kind of result evident right
because we have we have the possibility
of having fleshed out uh uh worlds that
we can interact with you know that are
simulated and the the times when those
cracks are showing you know what system
is showing when they're showing that
this is limited that we've chosen a
specific level of abstraction to to
simulate the the world. Um, but do those
in congruities bother people in board
games or card games so much?
>> I I would argue that sometimes it's a
little bit of a speed bump to learning
what's going on. Uh,
assuming it's unmet, assuming that that
that that is incoherent.
It seems like because it's almost
impossible to play a car game or a board
game without first understanding the
rules unlike in computer games where you
can just jump right in. Um
that is usually something that can be
surmounted if people are if people sort
of say oh the rules say this but the
theme says that okay I understand what
the rules say.
>> Yeah. Able to step over that.
>> Yeah. And I think that that's an
excellent point that when we start
playing a board game and probably when
what you guys do in this class is you
get a new board game of what do you do?
You pick up the instructions
>> and you're figuring out the rules first
and not the world. In a lot of video
games, we figure out the world first and
then by exploring the world, we're
figuring out the rules. And even if
there are games that are giving us
tutorials or you know manuals who I
don't know, not many people read manuals
if at all
>> while the game is installed.
>> Yes, if it's fun. Um but but you know
like manuals is not something that even
though it's going to be the first thing
to look at in a board game and a card
game. Um and even well as a player
no as a player you'll also look at the
rule books at least to cons to build
your own character most times.
>> You mean you mean on PC
>> on roleplay games?
>> Oh in in are you talking about tabletop
role playing?
>> Yes tabletop.
>> Oh yeah even tabletop role playing games
you Yeah,
>> chances are people start by looking at
the handbooks before
>> laring might be a good example of how
like laring you just giving your
>> your character
>> your character which is very
interesting.
>> I mean for role playing I know a lot of
people who can't really be bothered to
learn the rules that thoroughly prefer
just to like experience the story and
have somebody tell them how to resolve
mechanics and that kind of thing. Yeah,
>> but even it's funny because even when
you are not when you're building your
character in in a tabletop role playing
game,
>> you still have to have a look at, you
know, what is the race that you want,
what is your religion, what is your
powers that you want to choose. You'll
you kind of really, even if you're only
playing for, you know, for cakes and you
don't care so much about the moves and
I'm I'm the type of tabletop role
playing that prefers the story and I
don't care so much about combat. Um, but
you still have to know the rules even
before you start playing, if that makes
sense.
>> I mean, there are situations like Owens
describing where people don't look at a
rules, but then then they're usually
relying on the GM to tell them what's
allowed and what's not allowed, which
means someone read the rules. It's no
different from someone explaining to you
a card game as opposed to having rules.
>> Actually, kind of makes the experience a
bit like playing a computer game. The
the GM sort of does the blackbox
arbitration for
>> Yeah, the GM is your computer. In fact,
it's more powerful than a computer
because you can sort of figure out what
you're actually asking.
[Laughter]
>> What someone
>> Yes.
>> I I have a question about narratives
actually. So, so one thing about card
games and board games is that almost
everything that gets revealed or that
happens in the middle of the game um is
usually a play of mechanic. Uh sometimes
some sometimes there's some loose
flexibility in like games where they
allow open negotiation in between in
between specific plays. But most of it's
actually in the play of a card and move
of a piece something like that. And
especially when you're playing cards,
you have things like paper text. You
have things especially um for cards
where you can just like play them at any
time. Uh, and um, I've seen micro
narratives done, at least what I think
of micro narratives, seem to be done
really well in those instances. Uh, in
fact, they're instant cards, right? The
the, you know, someone tries to do
something that might win them the game
and you play this card and that denies
them the win
>> and but then that's tied up with some
sort of labor text, some sort of
thematic element to that card.
>> Well, it could be like the
uh, Monopoly. What is the type of card?
There is two type of cards.
>> Go to jail.
>> No,
>> yeah, like the chance and there's chance
is something that happens to you, but
there's also community.
>> The community chest. Thank you. Which is
something that you play. The difference
is in and micro narratives here. What it
means is something it's a reaction to
players
>> events. is not something that the player
chooses to do
>> which is you know that those reaction
cards those are also part of the
player's narrative and in a way you know
is player is choosing this is going to
happen now
>> um this is what gloom is about in this
is what these two games are about most
of the time it's kind of like you're
trying to to construct a story and
you're kind of like trying to tamper
into somebody else's story uh so it's
that kind of reaction but it's yeah we
would have find a name for it. But um
yeah, it's the micro narrative is
referring to something that happens as
reaction. It's not something that the
player does. Maybe that's
>> it's often in reaction to what another
player is doing. So it depends on whose
point of view you're taking. So
>> I've got a community chess card and I'm
holding it until somebody else is, you
know, about to take advantage of a
position and then I n them.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And these ones
>> still in reaction to what we
>> I just going to mention in terms of
micro narrative I don't know would this
be a possible example in the board game
that we're designing there's a computer
incentive that you want to hack and
every time someone tries to hack it it
gets weaker so it's sort of a response
to someone doing it actually
>> would that count as a micro narrative or
was that more of a mechanic
>> it seems I mean as an event
is an important event it's a change of
state but I don't know how much of a
story it is like how you know and this
is there's no science to what
constitutes an event or not. It's
something that I'm that's part of my
research. It's something that I'm trying
to figure out you know what does how can
we identify with an event that is a rule
and it's also an event in the story. Uh
because things like disconnecting the
computer or hacking the computer
yeah that that seems to be clearly an
event. What if we had you know like each
time they becomes weaker there is
something else that you can do. So by
hacking the computer there is a new
action you know you get access to new
areas of the game or you get uh a new
power up or you get you know it's easier
for example if and I'm totally
hypothesizing about what your game is
about but if you have a computer that is
controlling the security of a place
whenever you hack a certain part of the
system it's letting you uh it's letting
you move faster through the board
uh in a way that might be closer to the
a micro narrative because it does have
it's a reaction but it's also
consequences
>> in that case for careers for girls when
you choose to go down a path is that
micro narrative because the player
chooses and then sort of changes the
state slash gives you more
>> I don't know the choices but the events
that happen like what happens when you
land on something might be closer and
again it's kind of like the micro
narrative.
>> I mean the careers and careers for girls
which if folks haven't seen it is really
really apparent um seems to be built on
micro narratives the whole idea that
everywhere you land something's happen
some life event is happening
>> but the choice what I'm saying is that
the choice itself is not the micro
narrative the landing
>> and what happens when you land.
>> Oh wow.
>> Anything else? I actually kind of wanted
to make one last comment about um like
immersion stories
>> in particular with the example of the
Sims. Uh is anybody familiar with
Allison Kev?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So Allison Kev was this really
interesting experiment that this guy did
where um he created two homeless Sims.
>> Oh yes. A father and a daughter.
>> I think we talked about
>> uh just kind of like did a sort of web
comic style display of the lives of
these two homeless Sims like as she grew
up and he got older.
And
it it it almost seemed like it became
like a role- playinging game where the
guy playing the Sims became the dungeon
master who had like, you know, created
these characters and then the AIs were
playing these characters for him. in
particular this there was this one
moment where um he gets to a part of the
story where uh the the daughter has just
gotten her first paycheck and she
decides to donate it to charity and like
he keeps trying to keep her from
donating it to charity but she keeps
saying I want to donate it to charity so
eventually he lets her donate it to
charity and it was almost like it was
the character's choice to donate it and
he's at the end of this this blog post
that he did about this specific events.
He's talking about how like, you know,
what does it mean when a video game
character that you created makes you
question your own life choices?
>> I don't know. It's just a really
interesting thing. If you haven't read
it, you should check it out.
>> I think it's alphanc.com something.
>> It's a starting The Sims 3.
>> Yeah.
>> Talking about like non-digital games
being very involved in your character. I
felt like I feel like the one game I've
played where I've been very involved in
a character is Mafia where like there's
a lot of actual information given to
you. People are young like you're the
mafia. The way you smiled at him like
you know clearly you guys. So I don't
know.
>> So you become the character more by how
people see you than
>> than how you play it.
>> I guess you're also assigning character
to other people
>> reading into their actions. Is it
>> I heard
>> that's a game where the roles are
designed by the designer and
>> there's only two roles. It's like it's
not
>> Well, there can be there's a few
>> I've seen websites with like a whole
list of roles and some of them are
hilarious.
>> Seems good.
>> Yeah.
>> In digital games, I feel like they're
the games where you have a very defined
character unlike this. If you have a
very defined character in the video game
more was like fable your character isn't
defined and kind of like changes based
on the actions you use if you're evil he
becomes ugly and he gets confessed and
things but I never felt like I
identified with the character at all
versus games that already give me a very
strong character and I'm supposed to
play a certain way I feel like
>> that's that's odd because that's
completely
>> that runs against what they were trying
to do or at least that's what their
marketing claims that they're trying to
do is to make you feel closer to the
character because it's the reflection
Yeah,
>> I think like Bioshock does a better job
of that where you never see the guy.
>> So you're always just like looking
through his eyes and he has essentially
no personality.
So at least no personality is displayed
in the game. So it's almost as if you
are directly interacting.
>> Yeah. given a space to be
>> to to actually like, you know, project
yourself into the game,
>> which I think is sort of what Fable was
trying to do, but doesn't really do a
good job of it because you see him right
there and he's clearly not you. I feel
like torment is a really plcape Torment
is a really interesting take on this
where the character is essentially like
who it is that you play him as. But
there's more to it than that because
there's also backstory to the character
which you the character have forgotten
and is revealed to you over time. But
you're you're no more that character
>> that was that that your character was
back then than you are definitely the
character now. So it's kind of your
nature changes over time and you've gone
through several iterations of this.
Yeah. And if you like none of them is
true or more correct you
>> the funny thing about playscape
tournament is kind of like a like a
personality test.
>> Uh because I've been playing it again
and last first time I played through I
was
chaotic good and I was trying to play
different and still chaotic good. So I'm
kind of freaking out.
Oh, like okay, you know, I'm really
trying to do something different, but
I'm still in the same alignment. Uh
because a lot of your definition of and
actually your alignment can also decide,
you know, items that you can get or
things that you can do. Um but it's
based on your choices and how you
tackle, you know, if you do a quest, if
you choose if you lie, for example, or
if you do like crazy things. Um
and and it's not something
Once you realize where you the effect of
your choices is, you can kind of control
it. But this, you know, like playing is
kind of like, okay, it's going to be
about you and how your game playing
style is majoring personality.
>> Yeah, there's an interesting effect in
like Knights of the Old Republic. when
played that.
>> Um,
you you can explicitly make decisions to
become to go to the dark side, but like
I remember when I played it, every time
it came up with a decision where I could
like the dark side has all the awesome
powers, right? So, it kind of funny to
think of like I'm going to be on the
dark side. I'm going to have all the
awesome powers. It's going to be grand.
Um then you get to the decisions and I
was like almost uncomfortable with
choosing the evil options such that I
couldn't actually bring myself to go to
the dark side.
>> We we are actually out of time but you
know but I wouldn't say that
>> the the options of of the republic
actually let's let's take discussion of
the republic
space.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. All right. Well thanks thanks.
>> Thank you.