Welcome, everyone.
I want to thank you
for joining us today
for what will be a
terrific conversation
with our esteemed guest,
Professor Esther Duflo,
here at the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology.
We'll hear from Dr. Duflo about
her groundbreaking research
and approaches to
poverty alleviation.
And we'll also talk in
depth about her teaching
and how sharing teaching openly
through MIT Open Learning,
and more broadly, has had
a transformative impact
on the lives of people at
MIT and around the world.
I'm Chris Capozzola.
I'm our Senior Associate Dean
for Open Learning here at MIT.
And this is the second event
in the Open Conversation series
that Open Learning hosts, that
focuses on how Open Learning can
empower people to improve
their lives, communities,
and the world.
And our special guest today
is Professor Esther Duflo.
And I have the pleasure
of introducing her.
And her accomplishments
are many,
and her achievements
are phenomenal.
I will just briefly
introduce you to her
as a researcher and a scholar.
Dr. Duflo is the Abdul
Latif Jameel Professor
of Poverty Alleviation
and Development Economics
here at MIT.
She's the Co-Founder and
Co-Director of the Abdul Latif
Jameel Poverty Action Lab, and
Chair of Pauvreté et Publique
at the College de France.
In her research, she seeks to
understand the economic lives
of people who live in poverty,
with the aim of designing
and evaluating rigorously
social policies for poverty
alleviation.
She's worked on health, on
education, financial inclusion,
environments and
sustainability, and governance.
And she has been the recipient
of numerous academic honors
and prizes, many of which
are what probably encouraged
you to log in here today,
including, of course,
the 2019 Nobel
Prize in economics,
which she shared with
co-laureates Abhijit Banerjee
and Michael Kremer, a John Bates
Clark Medal, and the MacArthur
so-called Genius Fellowship,
to name just a few among many.
She's the author, most recently,
of the prize-winning book Poor
Economics, A Radical
Rethinking of the Way to Fight
Global Poverty, which I
encourage you to check out.
And near and dear to
our heart here at MIT,
she is a dedicated and
innovative teacher,
not only here on our campus in
both graduate and undergraduate
education, but in conjunction
with Open Learning,
where she shares her teaching
with tens of thousands
of learners worldwide.
So what we'll be doing
for the next hour
is talking back and
forth with Dr. Duflo.
We're going to hear
some of her passions
for teaching and learning, some
of her insights and thoughts
right now about
poverty alleviation
and challenges in economics
as practiced in the world.
And we'll be bringing in
questions from our audience.
Some of those are
questions that have come
to the audience ahead of time.
And some are ones that
you can continue to offer
if you're watching this live.
So I'm going to just start
off by giving you the floor.
And I'd love to just hear
a little bit about you
and what inspired you to
take this path for research
and to focus on
economics, public policy,
and really using data to
advance poverty alleviation.
First of all, thank you.
Thank you all for being
here online and in person.
I know there are so
many things happening
at the end of May on campus that
it's pretty phenomenal that you
made it here.
Most people, I think,
find a field of study,
and then they look for a topic.
And I went the other way.
I had a topic, and then I had
finally found the field of study
that would fit to that topic.
So from really an early age, I
was very exposed to the notion
that there are poor people
around in the world--
poor kids, when I was a kid, I
was more interested in kids--
that had circumstances that
were widely different from mine.
Part of it because my
mom was a pediatrician,
and she had an
office in the city.
But she also was very
involved in an NGO
that was working with
children victims of war.
In fact, the country where she
spent a lot of her time working
is now very much in the news
because it's El Salvador.
But before that, she went
to many other countries.
And she would come back
and show us slideshows
of what she had seen.
And it kind of struck
me that these children,
just because they were
born in the wrong country
or in a different
set of circumstances,
had a life that was so
much harder and probably
so much more
circumscribed than mine,
with so little opportunities.
So I always thought,
this is a gigantic debt
that I have to the world.
Maybe it was somewhat
self-aggrandizing to think
that way.
But this is really how I thought
about it when I was little.
And I have to devote
my life to repay
that debt of the
incredible cosmic luck
that I have to be born in
the middle class in Paris,
as opposed to in the
Sahara or in the DRC
or something like that.
So it always stayed with me.
And for the longest
time, I really
didn't know how to put
that into practice.
And I followed the path
of least resistance
of a good student in France,
studying for exams and so on.
As a matter of fact, I thought
I would be a historian.
And came a time, somewhere
in the middle of college,
where I felt that I was
really so protected,
and I had a life that was so
comfortable, both intellectually
and physically.
I lived in this wonderful
dorm in the center of Paris.
I was paid to study.
I had the best friends.
And we had classes,
like seminars,
with five people
in them and so on.
And it was like, I'm
making no progress
in repaying my cosmic debt.
And it made me a little jittery.
So I decided I have
to change my path.
And so I thought, maybe I
should go into politics,
because I would have
a more direct impact
on the life of people.
But I was a little suspicious
that they would like it,
because I don't
really like shortcuts.
So I thought, OK, let me just
take a step back and move
country and figure
out what I can do.
And it turns out my school
had an exchange with Russia.
So I was like, I'll go
to Russia for a year.
And I went to Russia for a year.
And I was teaching French
in a university there.
And by some really totally
accidental reasons,
I met two economists.
One of them happened to
be a professor at MIT
at the time, Thomas Piketty.
And the other was a
professor back in my college.
And through them, I got
in touch with many people,
many economists in
Russia at that time.
This was the middle
of the transition,
so people were very busy.
And I watched what
they were doing.
They plugged me in to be a
research assistant and so on.
I spoke Russian,
so I could be more
or less useful despite
knowing no economics.
And I watched with
a mixture of dread
and being very
impressed what they
were doing, because I thought
they have a tremendous amount
of influence.
And they were
academic economists,
many of them from Harvard, who
were advising the government.
And they were really
making major decisions
or having their finger on
major decisions on the basis,
I thought, of not
very much knowledge,
because it's not that anybody
had a lot of knowledge
about how to radically
turn the ship.
But I thought, OK, this is it.
I can go back to my cosmic debt.
I'm going to learn
economics, and then I'm
going to be able
to, as an academic,
have influence,
maybe, on the way
that economic
decisions are being
made that concerns the poor.
So with that plan hatched in
Russia, went back to France.
I had to basically cram five
years of economics into one
so that I could then
apply to graduate school.
And then I came to MIT and
started working on this problem.
So I came here.
I think it was incredibly
lucky in a way,
because I think for
many PhD students,
after they are done
with their classes,
they are a bit fumbling
around, figuring out what
they should do research on.
And I was on a mission.
I still am on the mission.
That's the same one.
That's fantastic.
It's great to hear that
story, and I think also
for many people who start their
learning journey not knowing
what intellectual tools will
solve the problems that they
want to do.
And that's a great story.
Let me talk about you
becoming a teacher.
So what inspires you
in the classroom?
What do you get
most excited about,
whether it's an in-person
classroom on campus
or when you're teaching online?
So in the story
that I tell, there
are really these powerful
professor figures.
My professor from France,
his name was Daniel Cohen.
He recently passed away.
He was an amazing
teacher in the sense
that he was able to connect
quite complicated concepts
to real-world situations and
make them speak to each other
in ways that were
really remarkable.
And he was also a great
exponent of writing
excellent popular audience
books for the same reason.
And that was, of course,
very important in my decision
to switch to economics, because
in the course of working
for him, I had
really the occasion
of hearing the way
he was talking.
And of course, at various
other moments in my life,
I was exposed to
wonderful teachers.
So it's pretty essential
to I think the--
people meet many,
many people, I'm sure,
who are able to pinpoint the
one teacher in their life
or the several teachers in their
life, either in grade school
or in high school or in
college, that made a difference.
Teaching at MIT
and teaching online
is, of course, a very
different ball game.
It's a different objectives.
The MIT students
are amazingly sharp.
And especially, I
teach a freshman class,
which I really love to teach
because I assume that nothing is
known and that
it's a blank page,
but that there is no concept
that you cannot bring.
And I think this attitude, I
try to take to all my teaching
and my writing, whether
it's at MIT or online,
is to never, never, never assume
that the person in front of you
is not ultra sharp
and ultra smart
and can't understand
what you're telling them.
So anything can be approached.
And in fact, in
France, you mentioned
my teaching gig in France is
kind of an on and on teaching
gig.
It's totally open.
There are 2,000 people
in the auditorium.
Most of them are above 70,
and they have never done
economics in their whole life.
And I teach them the same
thing that I teach at MIT.
Nice.
But not in the same way.
So it's really lovely to teach
to MIT students, undergraduates
or graduate students.
The undergraduates, what I
like or love with the freshmen
also is I teach a
communication intensive class,
so I make people talk and
prepare things and get engaged
with really practical problems.
And they are delighted to
have a chance to speak up.
So it's very nice to
give them this space.
But it's very few people.
So when I first got introduced
with OpenCourseWare,
I was really excited.
I was like, oh, oh,
we can put what we do.
But of course, at the very
beginning of OpenCourseWare,
they just put the class notes.
So it's not as interactive.
Then I first got
the chance of taking
video tapes of my
undergraduate freshman class
to put on OpenCourseWare.
And in the first minutes
it put, so many people
get to watch the videos.
And you're like
oh, this is great.
This is more people than I
will ever teach in person.
And when MITx came on, and
we could use the same video
to structure something more,
with deeper engagement,
I was even more excited by that,
because I felt I can basically
now almost teach the same way.
The MIT students that
I teach in person
watch the same video
as the online people,
and basically take the class.
And then they come to class and
they do something else with it.
And the people in the world,
they watch this video,
and presumably, they are also
used in a part of their life
that's a different part.
But the core is the same.
And then the spokes are
different in different parts
of the world.
And I think that's very
powerful in the sense
that I don't think the
people who are on MITx
get a less good version.
They just get a
different version.
Yeah, no, that's crucial.
And a lot of the
learners have told us
that they really value
the idea that this
is the exact same thing that MIT
students on campus are getting.
That's literally the
same, because they
watch the same video.
And from time to time, we
teach the lecture again
to the MIT students so that
the class gets updated online
and for the MIT students.
So they can be sure that
what is being taught online
is really the frontier of what
we think the students would
know if they were here.
Yeah, so as if that
weren't enough,
then you went a step
further and have
developed a program,
the MicroMasters
program in DEDP,
Data, Economics,
and the Design of Policy.
Some of those learners are
probably watching right now.
But for those who don't
know much about it,
tell us about it
and how it works
and your reflections on that.
Yeah, so this is a
program that we--
I mean, it's one of the
things that I've done at MIT--
maybe one of the
top three things.
And I don't even know what the
other two are, that I'm, A,
the happiest I have done and
the most proud I have done
and the most grateful
that that possibility was
offered to me, because,
frankly, it was a bit of--
we were all learning.
Open Learning people, from
engineers to leadership,
and us at the same
time, when we were
trying to build this program.
So the gamble of
this program was
if we can select people
to come to MIT based
on what we want them to
do once they are at MIT,
we would be able
to completely break
the mold of
traditional admissions,
admit an entire different set of
people who would probably never
have made it to MIT,
and they would do great.
So this was really the
core of the gamble.
How you make that work is
by having the equivalent
of one semester worth of upper
level undergraduate/master's
classes online through
the MITx classes.
So for us, there
is now a choice.
But there is probability
and statistics,
there is development economics,
or there is microeconomics,
there is public policy, and
so on, political economy.
You have a bit of a choice,
but of five classes,
which people can either do in
one very dense semester if they
want to.
Some people do that.
But most people
take while they are
doing something else on the
side, one by one or two by two.
And then we admit
students to spend
one semester at MIT based almost
exclusively on how well they
do in these classes.
I'm saying "almost exclusively,"
because we get their info and we
are also paying a lot of
attention to what they write,
why they want to come, what
people write about them,
what are their experiences.
But that way, we don't
need to worry so much
about trying to understand what
their grades might be or might
mean.
Or you don't need to
have gone to college.
One of our most
successful students
had not graduated high school
when he applied to our program.
And he's now in the PhD at
MIT, having never completed
an undergraduate degree.
Another person had gone
to college in Mexico,
but he, due to various
difficulties in his life,
never managed to finish college.
But he did great in the classes.
We admitted it.
He graduated with his program.
Today, he's working at the OECD.
Another person who is here
this year is from Somaliland
and had left Somaliland a grand
total of once to go to Kenya,
but had worked in UNHCR
with refugees and so on,
and managed to take all
the classes and so on.
So it's really an
amazingly diverse group
of people in terms
of their experiences,
what they bring to
the table, and so on.
But what have in common is,
number one, extraordinarily
drive, because to finish the
pretty hard classes online
from Somaliland, it takes
more than grit, double grit.
And number two,
of course, the raw
cognitive skills and firepower
to be able to do this.
And so the first
part of the gamble
of having a much more
diverse class, like 100%.
The second part of the
gamble, when they came to MIT,
we now have several cohorts.
They are systematically the
best in the classes they take,
both when they take master's
level, like [INAUDIBLE] level
classes or upper level
undergraduates, which are also
cross-registered master's
students, and even in PhD
classes.
That's because they bring
in a thirst for knowledge
that none of our
other students have.
The undergraduates,
god bless them,
are a little blasé, trying to
check as many boxes as they can.
The PhD students tie
themselves into knots
wondering what is going to be
helpful for their dissertation.
And our master's
degree students,
they just are
delighted to be here.
And they want to take
the most out of MIT.
And they do.
And they contribute so
much to the classes.
And they change the energy
and the dynamic of the class.
Everybody loves them,
in our department,
to have them in the class.
So I think it's
really been amazing.
And again, it wasn't obvious.
We had to shepherd it
through the process,
get it approved in
the faculty committee,
and every step,
people were like,
are you sure this can work.
Of course, we're not
sure it can work.
We certainly hope.
But it's really
been a huge success.
When they come, we tell them
they have to change the world.
That's the only reason
why we took them.
And that's the
metric of success.
And now they really
are busy doing that.
That's awesome.
That's really awesome.
I love that metric of success,
of changing the world.
But let me drill down
on that one actually
a little bit, because in the
field of economics, of course,
you're very well known,
famous for demanding
rigorous measurement
of policy outcomes.
So how does that shape your
approach to learning outcomes?
And how have you used
some of those insights
from your research methodologies
to think about metrics
of success for the
DEDP, MicroMasters,
or even just for
individual courses?
Well, I have to admit,
not so much in the sense
that we know what I do for
a living as a development
economist to set up
randomized control trials,
so to have treatment and control
that are randomly selected.
And we've never done
that with the DEDP
in any way, shape, or form.
We take the best students.
We take only 20 students,
25 students every year.
We take the people
whom we think are
going to make the most of MIT.
And we have no scope to
randomizing, so who knows.
So in that sense, I
don't have a proof
that the DEDP is
making a difference.
But what I can see is
what they do moving ahead,
the positions where they end up.
This is really
what interests us.
The grades are
important, because it
shows that they fit in MIT.
And as I was telling you, the
distribution of DEDP students
creates stochastically dominate
that of non DEDP students,
correct, so that's interesting,
in terms of the selection
being successful.
But what is even more important
is what they do later.
Some go back to their
country where they came from.
Some go back to the
industry they came from.
Many shift or go elsewhere.
Some work in international
organizations.
And we are in contact with
pretty much the entire network.
And I do know that they--
everywhere.
The type of institution
that welcome
them always tell us to send more
or do you have more like that.
And we do.
Every year, we have
one more cohort.
Yeah, that's great.
And here's a question
you may get sometimes
from all kinds of
learners or people
who are outside of
economics and looking in.
And some of your courses--
and I can say this as a
learner, some of your courses
are really hard
and very demanding.
So when someone is
struggling, either to begin
to learn economics or
to complete a course,
how do you get them motivated
and keep them motivated?
So there are two ways
to answer this question.
One is a little
glib, but I'm going
to start with that,
which is we started
at that pretty high level.
We are started at the level
of a master's program at MIT.
So it's not going to be easy.
Mm-hmm.
I'll surprise you.
Yeah, yeah.
I had a textbook in
macroeconomics that said,
some say it's enough to have
high school mathematics to learn
economics, but it would have to
be a pretty good high school.
So it's a little
bit the same here.
It is what it is.
We can't at the same time say,
after this and coming to MIT,
you will be at the top of your
class, and say, by the way,
it's going to be easy.
So in the sense,
that's a program
that's for people who are
reasonably prepared and very
committed.
So that's the glib answer.
And then part of me feels
that therefore we should
have a lot of scaffolding.
And I'll come back to
the scaffolding part
in a moment, which is fine.
You can end there,
but you should
start so that you can bring
more people to that level,
knowing that it's not going
to be like the whole world.
But in a sense, our book
doesn't bear [INAUDIBLE].
It's not particularly
massive, nor is it
maybe destined to be massive.
It's relatively
advanced material.
So that's the glib answer.
Now, the less glib answer is,
how do we do the scaffolding.
So part of it is happening
within the course itself.
So for example, say if the
probability and statistics--
for example, you take
the data analysis class,
it starts from probability
and ends at machine learning,
starting with probability
from the foundation.
So in a sense it doesn't
have many prerequisites
as long as you are
tightening your belt
and ready to stick,
with the exception of,
for the data analytics
exercise, you need
to be able to use the software.
And then, for that, we
prepared a lot of modules
that people can do
before so they can--
before they even
start, so they have
time to familiarize themselves
with R is the language we use.
And they'll get help to do
that and a lot of tutorials.
So by the time they launch the
class, they have that in place.
And we have a lot
of community TA
on the platform that help out.
So that's the within
platform help.
And then, I also realize
that for a lot of people
it's not enough, and yet
a lot of people who could
succeed if they got more help.
I also know that
only very few people
will be able to come to MIT,
because MIT is not that big.
So we won't be able to expand
the program infinitely.
So for these two reasons,
what we've engaged in,
in the last couple of years,
is an effort called ADEPT,
where the A is for Alliance.
And it's now trying to
form a network of schools
that will use the DEDP
material, the DEDP courses,
as a corpus in a way,
in different ways.
And one of the ways in which
they can use it is they
can take the online classes and
teach them as flipped classroom,
using their time in class to
reinforce, help out, et cetera.
So for example, we are doing
that, one of our ADEPT nodes
is the statistical school
in Cote d'Ivoire, ENSEA.
Their advanced undergraduates
can take our all classes,
and they get support.
Right.
And at the end of the class,
they validate the MIT class.
And eventually--
it's not quite done,
but we are moving
towards the fact
that they'll also get credit
for that class at ENSEA itself.
So this ADEPT is now
what we are trying
to create in a lot of places,
including replicating the MIT
model so that there would be, as
the pipeline grows of people who
have taken those classes,
there'll be outlets for them
to go to.
So ENSEA is going to start its
own master's degree in Brazil.
We just launched at Insper.
They are going to start
their own master's degree.
Princeton is now going to admit
into their master's degree,
students who have finished the
MicroMasters, and so on and so
forth.
So in a sense, the idea
there is to use the material,
not just like, this
is here in the world,
if you can swim, swim,
otherwise you sink.
Yeah, that's fantastic.
And in some ways, all of that
gets back to your comments
at the beginning,
right, about thinking
that anyone that
you meet and talk to
has the capabilities to
engage with this material,
even if they may not have
had the prior preparation.
So in moving
forward, I would like
to start earlier, which is,
there are many kids who,
say, for example, very talented
kids who don't get to the level
where they would even
hear of this program,
or they don't have the math
that's necessary, and so on.
And I would like to make sure
that those kids are not lost,
or fewer of those kids are lost.
So one of the projects
I'm working on,
it's in Tamil Nadu in
the South of India.
We work with AoPS, the platform
of very advanced math classes
that many MIT students
take as enrichment.
And they gave us a
bunch of licenses.
AoPS stands for Art
of Problem Solving.
And it's many, many online
classes, very good level.
They gave us access to licenses
that we can give to the kids.
And we are engaged this time in
a randomized controlled trial,
where we give out
those licenses to kids
in the middle of nowhere,
in rural Tamil Nadu,
or on the country, in a
slum, in urban Chennai,
and see whether they manage
to do well in the classes
and do better in
their coursework,
but more importantly,
get into STEM
and so on, whereas
otherwise, they
would have been giving up
school even though they
are super talented.
So that's one other way to
take this problem is saying,
well, we can lift the boats
a little bit in advance
so that more people
would be able to get
into our program or
any other, really,
that would start at the
more advanced college level.
So eventually, there is
maybe a whole pipeline.
Right, that's fantastic.
All right, so what
I want to do now
is switch to some
of the questions
that we've had
from our audience.
And what I'll do is I'll
be asking a few questions
that we got in advance.
And sometimes I'll be
bringing together questions
from people who asked
very similar ones online.
Most of these are questions
people asked ahead of time.
Some of you will be
providing questions
if you're watching online live.
And we'll be sure to get
all of these questions
to Professor Duflo.
And some of them, we'll
be able to answer.
But there's already
more questions
asked than we can ever get to.
So let me just start
with the first one.
And many of them actually
focus on your research
in economics and
poverty alleviation
and what it means to
do that now in 2025.
And then we'll switch
back to some questions
about teaching and learning.
But here's a question.
And this combines ones
from Corinne and Ulises
and Joe, that works out
to something like this.
What are some of the
consistent obstacles
in alleviating poverty?
And how can technology,
funding, and public policy
play the most effective role
in overcoming those obstacles?
This is a question I'm sure
you think about every day.
This is that motivation
question you talked about
at the beginning.
Absolutely.
So I think the
biggest obstacle is
that a lot of
people whose job it
is to do this,
like policymakers,
but also people in NGOs,
activists, and so on,
are extraordinarily
well intentioned.
But the believe they know
significantly more than they do.
So people launch
into massive programs
on the basis of very little
evidence and a lot of goodwill.
And a lot of these things
end up falling flat.
Mm-hmm, or worse.
Or worse.
So that's why I spent a lot
of my energy trying to--
a related problem
is that most people
feel that there is one answer to
the entire problem of poverty,
which of course makes very
little sense because it's
so many different, different,
different problems.
It's the equivalent of saying,
there is one drug for cancer.
That's just not how
it works in poverty.
Likewise, there are
issues with education.
There are issues with health.
There are issues
with the environment.
And they are all
different problems
that we can take one by one.
So that's why a
lot of my work is
to really try to convince people
to say, OK, OK, let's relax.
What's really your
ambition in this program.
Maybe it's ending
poverty, but closer to us.
What's the immediate
outcome that you seek?
And what are the various
ways that you could seek it?
And what's the most
effective, what
are you sure about,
what should we try out,
including different
versions of the same thing,
because often the devil
is really in the details.
So I think the biggest obstacle
to poverty is what we--
with Abhijit Banerjee,
in Poor Economics,
we call the three Is, which is
Ideology, Ignorance, Inertia.
Mhm, OK.
Yeah, all right.
And a follow-up
question on that,
is that how do
the obstacles vary
in different parts of
the world, whether that's
different countries
or regions or even
within a country, urban
areas versus rural areas?
Are there patterns you see?
Or are these just fundamental
obstacles to the tour?
The problems are very different,
often, depending on the context.
For example, if we think about
health, a problem in rural area
might be that people are quite
far from a health facility.
A problem in an
urban area might be
that they are
thousand of doctors
within a space this size,
but none of them is any good.
So those are different
problems that
require different solutions.
So the problems can
be quite different
in different countries,
in different contexts.
Some of them, you can find
commonalities across problems,
but the approach always
remains the same,
which is being open-minded
and curious and experimental
and willing to be wrong.
Mm-hmm, OK, another
question, this
is actually somewhat of a more
teaching focused question.
But it can also affect many
areas that you work in.
So this combines
questions from three
of our viewers, Jose
Maria, Danielle, and Zarif,
who want to understand how
sharing educational resources
can affect change.
So in some ways, it's bringing
these two together, right.
Is this kind of teaching
part of poverty alleviation?
And also, what are some of
the challenges in context
or settings where things like
electricity and internet access
are really limited?
So let me take the two halves
of the question separately.
So yes, I think the
teaching, and in particular,
this Open Learning, and then
the branching out to ADEPT
is a critical part
of the effort,
because I'm just one person.
I'm going to, I don't
know, maybe write,
if I'm very productive, a
hundred papers in my life.
I actually have no idea.
But that's not very many.
And in fact, when we
got the Nobel Prize,
that's immediately what we
said is that that's not for us.
This is for the movement.
This is for all
of the people who
are doing this work of trying
out one thing after the other,
both the people who are
in the field implementing,
the researchers,
who are running it.
So very early on, actually,
almost the minute I
started teaching at
MIT, I was convinced
that what we needed to do is to
not just run trials, but set up
an infrastructure to make it
easier for others to do it.
Otherwise, it would remain
a completely niche activity
that would have no impact
beyond very few people.
Hence J-PAL, which
basically, from the get-go,
it was, let's start a network
of people who do this at MIT--
not an MIT, in the whole
world, to put in common lessons
about how to do things or not
to do things, infrastructure,
recruiting research assistants,
money raising, and the like.
And J-PAL has been quite
successful at creating
this network effect.
So there are now a thousand
researchers all over the world.
And together, the research
is so much more powerful.
And it had affected
quite a few people.
The current number
is 600 million people
who have been affected, not
directly by the research we run,
but by programs that have
been scaled up after we
found them to be effective.
But it's still not
enough, by far.
And many more people need
to be able to do this work.
And many more
policymakers need to be
able to understand
it and understand
why they need to do it.
And that needs to be
really distributed better
geographically, because although
technically our thousand
researchers are all over
the world, in practice,
there are still many
in the US or in Europe.
But the work needs to
be done everywhere.
When there is poverty
in the US, so some work
needs to be done in the US.
But the work needs to
be done everywhere.
And although, of
course, I feel perfectly
capable of doing
research in India,
it's even better if I have
an Indian co-author that
can do it with me.
Or in fact, it would be
great if teams made entirely
of Indian researchers
could have the wherewithal
to figure out the project,
find the money, and so on.
And for that, we need
many more people trained,
because it doesn't
happen just like that.
It cannot happen by Fiat, said
go find yourself a collaborator
in Benin if nobody's
learning economics in Benin.
Hence, the really key part
of J-PAL 3.0, if you want,
is to be able to network,
not just the infrastructure
of research, but
the infrastructure
of teaching, such
that people can
be trained to do
this type of work
from the point of view
of being a researcher
or being a policymaker,
or being an activist
or working in a company,
everywhere in the world, which
is why our ADEPT, we
started with Cote d'Ivoire,
we're going to Brazil.
Now we have several
places in Europe as well.
We need to be all
over the place.
Yeah, that's fantastic.
And then, just on
that second half,
what do we do with
that last mile?
Yeah, it's a really
important question.
So for example, in the
case of the Art of Problem
Solving project, we
realized pretty early
on it was going to be an issue.
We didn't think so because
network connectivity
is very good in Tamil Nadu.
Electricity is not bad.
And we thought students mostly
had access to a smartphone.
But then we realized
that they have access,
but they don't really
have access in the sense
that maybe it's their father's
phone, the father is away,
then can't have
access to the phone.
So we realized if this
program was going to work,
we needed to give them tablets.
And we did.
And that makes a huge difference
to this basic infrastructure.
So the good thing is that
this is only improving.
Most of Africa, the
expansion of cell phone
has been something quite
phenomenal, and most of Africa
is covered by cell
phone connectivity.
So this barrier will
progressively be less and less.
And we're pretty
confident of that.
But for example,
electricity is a huge need.
One of the key need of
many countries in Africa
today, where the poor
have very little access.
Yeah, so this is
another question
that came from multiple people
in different angles, which
is, many are admirers
of your work,
both your academic work
and the work that that
does in the world, and
are just wondering,
what are the challenges
you're facing in 2025,
in a complicated global
environment where you're
adjusting to many different
contexts, constraints,
and policies, of course,
here in the United States,
but really, around the world?
And just how has that shaped
your thinking and also
your practice?
How much time do you have so
that I can list a my issues?
Well, it's been a pretty
wild ride with, of course,
the shutting down of USAID
within days of inauguration.
We had quite a bit
of USAID funding.
So many projects got cut midway.
And to date, a lot of
the bills for past work
haven't even been paid yet.
So that creates all
sorts of issues.
We are assuming that there
are going to be paid.
We want to believe
in the rule of law.
And of course, as you
say, it's not just the US.
It's in general.
So in France, for example,
the foreign cooperation budget
has also been cut in about 35%,
in Germany, as well, in the UK,
about half.
And within that, except
for France, I have to say,
where they really preserved the
research wing of the development
assistance.
In other places,
it's the first thing
to go because at the same time
as you cut the total volume,
there is also a need to
reorient towards priorities,
like either people
literally starving because
of the end of USAID,
or Ukraine, because
of the end of the
support to Ukraine.
So from the point of view
of funding for our work,
it's not the easiest
time, by far.
Not to mention that we
are within a university,
and in particular,
elite universities.
And those universities
are also under attack.
And as part of them, we also
suffer the indirect consequences
of that as well.
So it has immediate
implication of day-to-day life,
what can be funded, what
can be done, and so on.
At the same time, I don't
think it really anything
to the reason why I'm doing
what I'm doing, because aid is
like a microscopic amount was.
Now it's even more microscopic.
You really need a special
physics microscope to see it.
But even before that, it
was a pretty small part
of the amount of money that was
spent on the poor worldwide.
Most of the money that is
spent on the poor worldwide
is the money that is being
raised by those countries.
And so they used to spend
their money and a little bit
of USAID money.
And now they spend
only their money.
Even before, I was mainly
interested in making sure
that the entirety of the
budget of these countries
is spent in the most effective
way possible to serve
their own priorities of each and
every one of these countries.
So I never really saw myself
as having much to do with aid.
I now realize that I had more
to do with aid than I thought,
because I was financially
dependent on it for my work.
But that's my problem.
The fact is, my
work was and still
is relevant to my customers, who
is not the US government, who
is not the French government,
but who are the people who
live in these countries.
And yeah, so we'll find other
ways to make ourselves useful.
When I started doing
this type of work,
USAID was funding zero research.
And the NIH was not funding
any international development.
So it's not that we had money.
We scrambled.
So now we are back into a bit
more of a scrambling world.
But hopefully, the fact
that in the meantime,
I think the attitude in many
of the developing countries
has really changed in
terms of pragmatism,
in terms of identifying the
problems they really care about,
in terms of trying solutions,
learning from other experiences,
and so on.
So we can continue at
least sharing evidence,
trying to generate evidence
locally, and find a way
to finance this one
way or the other.
So it's going to change
maybe my time allocation,
but I don't think
it changes really
anything to what I need to do.
And in a sense, I
mean, the US shouldn't
have to inflate the image
of its own importance
in the rest of the world.
Maybe after some time they'll
realize, everybody is moving on.
Yeah, and that motivating
mission that you talk about,
that debt that you started
at the beginning, that's
something you're still--
That's very much there.
And in a sense, it's
still very, very important
to know for the kids--
say, for the kids
of Tamil Nadu, where
the government of
Tamil Nadu wants
to know whether giving them
access to apps with tablets
makes a difference
to their learning.
And if it does,
they'll find a way
to finance the
program down the line.
Yeah, that's a really
important message
that I think people looking
in from around the world,
and looking here at MIT and at
American universities right now,
will really value
that message from you.
I think what it will
do is to accelerate
the realization, which was
already coming anyways,
that finance is a
little irrelevant,
and that the northern
country were punching
above their weight, given
what they were giving
and the influence
they had in exchange.
And think now that they
are giving nothing,
they are going to
get no influence,
and then they are going
to feel sad about it.
But people would have moved on.
Mm-hmm, OK, so we've talked
about you as a researcher
and as a teacher.
And now it's time to talk
about you as a student.
And so we are all
lifelong learners.
So what's something
that you don't know now
that you want to learn next?
Oh, so many things.
I always try to pick
research projects that
are a little just above my
current frontier of what I know.
For example, I wanted
to teach myself
a lot of statistics and
econometrics and machine
learning, so I
started doing projects
on the econometrics
of experiment,
not knowing really
much about it.
And so I was very excited
to learn this material.
And I'm continuing to do that.
So I have more econometrics,
too, and statistics to learn.
And now I'm very
interested, by force,
because this is such an
important issue looming
in our lives, about
climate change,
because in the next few
decades, that's really
going to be the defining
feature for many
of the poor countries, which
also happen to be hot countries,
and therefore, where
the warming will have
a disproportionate influence.
So a lot of my
advocacy job is really
about compensating poor
people for climate change
that they haven't
caused, but they are
bearing the consequences of.
And that I can do, in a
sense, with what I know.
But there is so much to
learn about this whole field.
Much of it is in
economics, but some of it
is in many other fields, about
how one models climate change
and what we think
is going to happen,
and thinking about the subtlety
about determining the effect,
how we think about how
people are going to adapt.
And so that's
another big things.
Then, nothing to
do with economics,
I used to play a lot of
music when I was a kid.
And then I stopped coming to
MIT, actually, as a PhD student,
until through college
I played music.
And then I stopped, because
well, I played cello,
and I didn't have money
to bring the cello,
because you need to pay
a seat to the cello.
And I don't know.
I didn't think that
I could rent one.
It didn't occur to me.
But I really also
had no money at all.
So anyways, so I stopped
playing music at the time.
And now my kids
are playing music.
And they are
becoming quite good.
So I feel I need to
relearn to play music.
That's another thing that's--
it was in the back
of my mind, but it's
moving towards the front.
That's fantastic.
That's really great.
Any final thoughts or words,
advice to our learners
about what to do next?
Well, I think
finding any course--
of course, this is my course.
I'm very happy.
But any course anywhere,
physics or math
or literature or
language, anything
you enjoy, and try to stick
till the end of the course
is what I would advise,
because a lot of people start,
but then life overtakes.
But I feel this is when you
manage to go above that step,
that suddenly the
perspective really opens.
So it doesn't really
matter what people do
or whatever strikes
your fancy, but just try
to really, really stick with it.
And I don't know if
it's borne by data,
but my intuition is
that once people manage
to finish a course, the
next one and next one
becomes much more
easy and natural.
And there is such a
big world out there,
and the quality is so
excellent that [INAUDIBLE]
make the most of it.
And know that if you finish
the DEDP program, for example,
or another of the
MicroMasters program
offered, and you do
come to MIT, you'll
have so much to
bring to this campus,
and you will get so much
from it, that it will
be transformational both ways.
Amen, well, thank you.
On that note, just a
huge thanks to you.
And good luck with
the cello lessons.
And we definitely will be
expecting a concert performance
next year, all right.
And so, just to thank also
our viewers who are joining us
online.
This has been really an
inspirational conversation.
And we want to thank
you for tuning in
to listen, and encourage you
to share what you learned here
with colleagues, with
friends, with your networks
on social media and elsewhere,
and share your experience
and your own story as a
learner, and as someone
engaging with MIT's
Open Learning resources.
And of course, we also
ask for those of you
who are in a position
to do so, to consider
donating to support our
efforts and to support
the work of your fellow
learners and the impact
that MIT and colleagues
such as Professor Duflo
can share with us.
So until our next
conversation, happy learning.
And thank you for being with us.
Thank you so much, not
only for this conversation,
but on behalf of MIT
and Open Learning,
for making this
possible, because I
think it required an amount
of imagination that's
quite remarkable.
And also, it requires
a day-to-day dedication
and dogged hard work that you
guys online might not realize,
but I can assure you is there.
So thank you so much for
persisting to this and for all
the people who were involved
in this effort, with whom it's
always been a pleasure
collaborating.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]