So,
choose
and options.
So if you have um
so how do we go about choosing okay
things from 10 objects? That's an easy
way to do it.
Choose them one at a time. So
N ways
to
first
because once you choose the first thing
you can't choose again
and two
third
actually k.
So this gives us
n
- 2
n - k + 1. So I guess this should be
plus.
So is this correct?
No. Why not?
>> Yeah.
>> You want to like divide their order?
>> Yeah. It's basically because
we've
you know we've over counted. I mean if
you had a set of one two three four five
we could choose three and four we could
also choose four and three and these two
ways will give us the same set. So what
we need to do is we need to divide by
the number of ways of getting each of
these objects and that's k factorial
because we could have gotten them in any
order. So we divide by m.
So this is m k is equal to
now there's another expression for this
which
is actually
maybe a little simpler certainly a
little bit more. We can multiply the top
and we see that this is equal to
now
one of the
really nice techniques in proving I
guess theorems about binomial
coefficients and other counting things
is to count things in two different
ways. Count the same set of things in
two different ways. These two um
expressions have to be the same.
So what can we do? Well,
let's
let's count um
ways.
Okay, things.
Well,
either the last thing
is in the set or it's not in the set.
If it's in the set,
we have
in the set. We have n minus one things
here and the last things in the set. And
then also
um I guess k minus one things
and the first n minus one things in the
set. And if the last thing is not in the
set,
then we'll color it white rather than
blue. And you get things in the set.
So um
so what's the number of ways of choosing
k minus one things out of n minus one
things?
>> Yeah.
choose.
>> Yeah, exactly. So, we get n -1 k here
and we get n
choose k way of choosing these things
here. So, that shows us that
n choose k=
n -1 choose k
- 1 + n - k
So
see, so we got this expression by
counting
the number of ways of choosing
K things out of n in two different ways.
First we uh
colored one of them and then
did the
you know used induction and the other
way is we just
prove the binomial coefficient and
choose 10. So having things in two
different ways can give you a theorem
and um in fact it can give you very deep
theorems which
as well as
relatively easy theorems
and
you know there's this beautiful proof of
Kayle's tree theorem and then don't
which depends on counting things in two
different ways and I will eventually get
to it. Probably not until next class.
So,
what do I want to say now?
Yeah,
this is
um this formula gives us Pascal's
triangle near um
I'm going to say 1
and
you know if this
row is n.
So n = 1,
n= 0, n = 1, n = 2, etc. And this is k =
0,
k = 1,
k = 2.
Well,
you get this number from adding the two
numbers above it and that follows from
this identity.
And from Pascal's triangle you can see
that n choose kus
k because pascal's triangle is
symmetric.
You know the ways of getting this number
is exactly the same. The ways of
computing this number is exactly the
same way
we comput this number because each
row is a
Hello.
But you can also see this by the formula
n factorial k
n minus k factorial.
Okay. So,
if a + b c = 10, n choose a b c
is equal to
And
this is the number of ways.
Number of ways
of
choosing
a set of size
sets of size
sets of size. A B Crow
and X
and these sets are labeled and but
the things within the sets are um
I mean things within the sets are
interchangeable.
So,
and how do you prove this? Well, there's
two ways of proving this. First, you can
um
use this
to
n
c
n - one choose a b - c
a c.
So that's one way to prove it
because you just ask which set was the
last n and then the n minus one
remaining things.
you know what the sizes of the sets are
or you can prove it
and
sorry
n=
n choose a
* n a b + b.
So here you first choose the set first
set which has size a and now you choose
the second set for the remaining n minus
one a minus things and that has size b
and this is equal to
the
coefficient
n factorial a factorial nusal
times
I guess
n minus a is b + c. So b + c
over
factorial c.
And now remember that b + c plus n minus
a. So these two terms cancel and you get
n factorial a factorial bal.
And of course, there's no reason that
you
would need to stop with three sets.
We get noose
a1 a2 through a k
is equal to n factorial over the product
1 through k a sub
a1 + a2
plus a k.
So this is um multial coefficients.
So now I want to talk about bjections
which is another way of counting things
and
um you know common and tourists really
like finding bjective proofs by
although So
these are not necessarily the easiest
groups.
So um but often they are bjection
function
is bjection
is injective and surjective.
I guess a B or A sets of things
means A1
is not equal to F A2
A1 is not equal to A2.
So you don't get that mapping two things
onto the same
object
and subjective
is if B is on B
then there exists an A.
So subjective means that everything in B
is in the range of
also
f is
um
only
F as an inverse
f. Now for inverse we use f of g of a
g of f of b.
I guess I will prove one of these
directions.
F has an inverse.
It is a function.
So what we need to prove is that it's
injective and it's surgic.
half of A1
= half of A2.
G of half of A1 = G of A2
just because G is a function. But this
has to a2 and this has to equal a1.
So this implies
a1.
So f is
injective.
E is in the range of
f of g of pals.
So there's this element that maps to b.
So it's subjective.
And we've proven that f has an inverse
that has a bjection.
And a nice thing about bjections is that
the size of a is
and so if we counted the things in A
then we will also have counted things B
and we'll see seeing several examples of
this today. And the first one I want to
show you
is another thing with bal
coefficients.
Um let's see.
Oh, many
different ways.
Oh, coloring.
Okay.
and balls with J
and I should tell you what I mean
different here. So
um
so let's do an example
n= 4
and
J.
Well, we could color them all the same
color.
I want to claim that there's only one
way of doing that.
for each color. If there's only one way
of doing that, so there are three ways
TO
color one of them one color
and the other
three
um
one of them one color and the other
three another color.
And I want to claim there are three ways
of doing this because or six ways of
doing this because you choose one color
for the first one and
three colors for the other one. So there
are three ways to choose the first color
and two ways to choose the second color.
So there are six ways.
So note that we're not distinguishing
the coloring red blue from the color
blue red blue.
So these we're just asking for the total
number of balls we colored. And you
could also color two of them one color
and two of them another color.
And I want to claim there are three ways
of doing this
because there are three colors you don't
use. And once you've decided which color
you're not going to use, the rest of
them are
given. So that's 12 so far.
And I'm
Is there another color? Another way I
missed?
Yeah, like 211. Yeah, 211.
Okay, so we could have
red,
blue,
green, green. So, how many ways are
there doing this?
Yeah,
>> there are three ways to just choose
which color.
>> Yeah, there are three ways because once
you've chosen which color you're going
make two balls then the rest is set. So
there are three
and if we up we get 15
and 15 just happens to be equal to
choose 2.
And
you know just from this one example it
might be a coincidence but you can try a
whole bunch of other examples and it
always works out to be a binomial
coefficient. So it turned out not to be
a coincidence and a theorem that would
like to prove
and
find two is a number of ways of choosing
two things out of five things. So, how
can we take
these colorings of balls and turn it
into
finding a subset of two things out of
five things?
And
this is actually a fairly clever
digestion. I'm not going to ask you to
figure it out.
You'll notice I'm going to do this all.
So, let's um
pick one of these. Um okay, we should
pick two of them.
green.
So first step
step
order balls
with some fixed ordering and in this
case it'll be red green.
Okay. Second step
is insert the
So we're going to put a divider between
actually you know what would have caught
my mistake
15 is 6 choose 2 and not 5 choose two.
So because it's 6 * 5 / 2 that's 15. 5
choose 2 is 10.
So I should warn you that I cannot do
elementary arithmetic when I'm
so um
so the second step is insert dividers.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to take this
and dividers between the
So
okay now I want to claim the third step
is the base.
Okay. So now we have two dividers
and six
things
because we had four balls and two bers.
Okay.
And I want to claim that this is a
righteous. Why?
because we can reverse it. If we know
where the divisors are, what we do is we
color everything before the first
divider red, everything between the
first second divider blue, and
everything after the second divider
green. And if we don't have any red
balls, we just put the first divider at
the beginning.
So, um, this can be reversed and this
can be reversed. So that means if this
function that maps from colored balls to
balls and dividers is
reversal is invertible.
So that means that it's a bjection.
Okay.
Okay. So that means that the number of
Maybe I
Good morning.
Um
involves the jars.
So how many dividers do you use
that we have J colors? How many dividers
this?
>> Yeah.
>> J minus one. J minus one because we put
the fire between
all the pairs of colors and we have N +
J minus one
things. These are the total dividers of
the colors and we're choosing Jers.
Okay, so that was a really
and so this shows proofs djection and
this is not a completely real
and I want to claim that there are other
ways you could do it.
done this.
Okay.
So now I want to shift gears and talk
about thick walls which are
capital which are
really very nice um
very nice example and we will see them
again when we do.
Okay.
First, let's
And so
is up
49 0
2 2n
z
and I guess I should call that a path of
length 2n
and each step
is
- one sorry each step is 1us
one
and
it's always
above
X axis
and that's
and for the
numbers
length
2 N
is C subn
the and Cadillac.
Okay.
So
for Yes.
>> So the first step is not legal to have
like oneus.
>> The first step always goes up. Yes. And
the last step always goes down because
it has to come back to zero. And if you
have a big path, the reverse is also
what I'm going to do is I'm going to um
give you some examples.
C1 is equal to
Well, how many paths are there?
The first step has to go up and the
second step has to go down. So
is what?
Now let's figure out
two. Well, you could either go up down
up down or you could go up up down.
So C2 = 2, C3 = 5. And let's um
Okay, so we have that one. We could use
this one. So we go up twice. Twice
and
one more. And we could do the same
thing.
And
We could also go up three
and there's one I'm missing.
Anyone want to tell me what it is?
>> Yeah. Up, down, up, down, down.
>> Yeah, there we go.
Down up down.
So number five
or like six, I should say.
Okay, I did not write these
Okay. And let's
numbers down here. Catalan numbers.
One 2
um
And we do not have to memorize this.
Maybe you should memorize. I mean, we're
going to be doing a lot of stuff with
Cadillac number. So, maybe you should
memorize the first three or four in the
series.
Okay.
So, Richard Stanley was a professor at
MIT before he retired. He was a
cominator tourist and he came up with
something like 200 things that are
counted by the capitalist.
So there are really a lot of I mean they
really appear all over mathematics
and um
>> is there a pattern relating them to the
end?
>> Yes, there is and we will get to that
eventually.
But the first thing I want to do is tell
you two more things that are counted by.
Okay.
So there are plain trees
and
n
groups
n= 1 have a tree
Only one way you can draw a tree really
and two
draws.
So that's one, two, just like that.
And
let's
draw a tree. This
tree looks like this.
looks like this.
We draw a tree just like this.
And there's one
there.
And you'll notice that
these um
left and right count when you're talking
about. So this is the mirror image of
this but they count as two different
trees.
So
which
leaf
or which vertex something is attached to
matters.
And the next one has 14 but we're not
going to draw that.
And
Oh, let's let's do it up here.
I don't know what to say. Last thing
were
every node
two.
So,
so n=
one binary tree
on I guess three bird seeds, two leaves.
We can either add
two
either develop this node or develop this
node.
and three.
Okay. See if I can not
And that is supposed to be all although
it's not immediately clear.
You know, you get one of these by taking
one of these and adding a pair of leaves
to the bricks
and a pair of leaves to a leaf. And
there are only
well you could pair to anything here to
any vertices but you do it to this
vertex and this vertex you get the same
tree. So this is fine.
>> Yes.
letters.
>> N is counting
um
and is number of non
less than
weakness.
And you can prove that every tree has
one more leaf node and
interior node because now this is true
for n= one. At n= two, you replace a
leaf with an interior node and two more
leaves.
So you preserve the number of
leaf nodes minus non leaf nodes.
So for binary trees
every node
the number of non is one
fewer than the number of
okay
number of edges or n is the number of
edges. Yeah.
And there's one equals number.
Oh no, a number of vertices.
And you can similarly prove that a tree
always has one more
vertex than action.
Okay.
So we have three things which counted by
they pass and I think what I'm going to
do is first I'm going to give you the
formula for the catal number
and this is a
really nice
well
this is a really nice proof of the
formula for capital number although it's
a little bit complicated
and
we will
this is one of those proofs that
it's not clearly help anyone come up
with it.
So
C is equal to
+
2.
So that's the formula for the numbers.
So let's try it for n= 3.
So that's 6 choose 3 * 1 4
1 and actually there's four
And we're going to cancel these out. The
fours cancel, threes cancel the two and
we get five.
So it works at least for one case in
that we'll prove it in general.
So how are we going to prove it?
Okay, let
zero
be the number of PS
0.
So this is all paths from
0 0
to 2 Z.
Okay.
E
false.
And let's go R
Pus.
So everything that's notable.
And what we're going to do is we will
count
the number of things in the end.
All right.
And now
to get the number of dick walls, we just
take the number of paths and subtract
the bar and we get to the end. So can
someone tell me what the number of paths
is from 0 0 to 20?
Yeah.
>> 2 n because we need n
steps up and n steps down and we don't
care whether it goes below the x-axis or
not.
Okay. So, what is dx?
Well,
let
B - 2
N
B
from
0 0 to 2 n - 2
and we don't care which way they go.
So
you should
So a path from 2n from 0 0 to 2 n minus
2 is going to have to have one two more
down steps in upstal.
And I'm going to claim that the number
of non paths
is equal to the number of
and that will give us the catal when we
subtract.
I show you that first.
That's pretty.
So, a path from
P nus 2 is equal to 2 to n - 1.
P subn 0 + 2 ch
- 2
is 2 n factorial over n factorial n
factorial
- 2 n factorial over n + 1 factorial
n
is equal to
well this is just 2n choose n and this
if we take 2 n choose n and multiply in
the
denominator by n + one and the numerator
by n
we get
this thing that's minus n / n + one
that you see when we multiply by
n + 1
n in the numerator
will turn n factorial the denominator
one factorial when we n + one in the
denominator turns an n factorial
factorial
So to get from here to here, we multip
and this is just equal to
10 / n +.
So what we have to do now is show that
every nondict path show a djection
between non path and paths from 2
to
from 0 to 2.
And this I think the best way of doing
it is um
best way
is by drawing a picture.
I'm not going to be able to describe it
in words.
Okay.
So we have here
and it goes starts at zero
and it goes up down down up down maybe
at some point it has to go below the
x-axis because it has to end up at minus
two and um
which is why it's not
this I believe is minus two.
Okay.
So this is a
I guess we are six
any difference.
Okay. What are we going to do? What
we're going to do is we're going to take
the
x =
x.
I'm going to reflect this path around
x=us1
from every point after the first time it
hits minus one
from
let's say
x -
I guess
x= -
well
it's going to end up on zero
and
Okay. So now I would claim this is a
nondict path.
So why is it a nondict path? Well,
I mean we have a point x that is x=us
one. So it has to be a nonic path.
because it goes below the x-axis
and
it is a path from zero to to n every
step up
either up or down. So it is in
p 0
and I'm going to claim this is a
bjection between two paths
and
Stro Zus.
Now why is that?
Right? And if you have a path from here,
well, you have a path from
to n minus 2, you take this point, which
is the first point that hits
you around this axis and you get a
unique path. On the other hand, if you
have a path
from x= 0 to x = 2n that goes below the
x ais, you can take the first time it
has
the x= -1 line and you've undone this
function.
So it's a function f which has an
inverse ga
by junction.
Okay. And the number of paths from x=
0us
2 indeed
factorial. So this shows that the number
of nonps
is the right number. So that shows the
number of big pads number. So that's our
that's our proof that big pads are
number.
So
I want to say how would you ever find
this proof?
I really don't know.
However,
if you wait a couple weeks, we will be
doing generating functions. And
generating functions is a completely
straightforward way of figuring out the
formula for the
although it's
actually not as nice and easy as this.
It involves some calculations.
Okay.
And now the next thing I want to show is
a djection between binary trees and
thick paths.
And that will show you that
binary trees are also counted by
Okay. So, how does this work? Well,
let's do an example. So,
Okay. So this is a LIBRARY
and what we're going to do is we're
going to traverse the nodes in that
first order.
And what does that mean? Well,
What it means in this case is we're
going to just run around the outside
and the first visit. This one is the
second we visit. This is the third we
go down up and we visit. So we're only
counting the first time we visit this
node. This is five six.
Okay. Now we go down back down and up
here. This is the seventh note, eighth
node, ninth node, 10th node.
Okay.
So what do we do with these things?
What we're going to do is we're going to
associate
each of the nose
um
INTERIOR
call plus and
we will call.
So what is this? This is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
9 10 11
and one and two are both pluses
because they're internal notes. Three is
a minus. Four is a plus.
Five is a minus and six is a minus.
Seven is a plus. 8 is a minus.
9 is a plus. 10 and 11 are minus.
Okay.
And what we do is we use this path. We
go up with plus and down when it's a
minus.
So what does our path look like? Well,
it starts out twice.
And now we go down and up and down and
down.
And we go up.
- plus - plus
-
one more interior
one more loop interior. So this always
ends up
but the last step has to be a leaf. So
the last has to be down. So we just
ignore this
last step. and the path is here.
So we have to prove this is a d path and
we also have to prove that
every path corresponds to
Okay.
So why is this?
Well,
how many upsteps does it have and how
many down steps does it have?
So, there are 2 n + one
leaves. All right. N plus one leaves and
n interior nodes.
But we're ignoring the last step. So
there are n
steps up and n steps down.
And why does it never go
the x axis?
>> So suppose it went below the xaxis.
Look
at
the tree.
and
and just
well just the nodes up to the point
where it goes to minus one.
I guess 2 k.
Well,
this sub
must have.
Oh, one more
leaf
then interior.
Okay. So, it has one more leaf and
interior node.
It's a full binary TREE
because you know basically if you take a
tree
and you remove
some part of it
before um let's stop when I get to this
thing
some part of
Then
I want to claim this part always has at
least
as many leaves as interpret.
Why? Wow.
If you remove some part of it, there's
always
uh no degree one. It's because if you
have every node has degree two, it's a
complete binary tree and you can't add
anything more to it. So that means that
you traverse the whole tree. So there's
a
node of degree one
and
that
well there's either an inter
tree.
So if you move if you stop at this note
and move these two leaves, you either
have this guy
Or you could stop
here and this leaf. Then you have
this guy which is
just has degree one. So
if you um stop early
you'll always have
more interior doses than leaves. That
leaves and that means you haven't
actually got
to
yet.
So
if you take a tree,
if you take a binary tree and you stop
really
do not get
that little bit, but you can go and
figure it out if you want. And um
and
every
will give you a tree because
you know you just go through this and
you put a plus one. If it's a plus one
two goes on. So minus one leaves on and
eventually
you'll get to the
We'll get the tree cut out.
Suppose you label this one this
one.
Well, either this is a plus one
or it's a minus one case and you end.
And um
now there's always something to do. I
mean as long as
this tree does not have more interior
nodes
does not have
one more leaf than the interior. You can
always add to it and as soon as you get
to the end of the path and it has
as many
one more interior
One more leaf in the interior node, then
it's a full binary tree and we're done.
Okay,
so that is more or less what I wanted to
tell you today. I
also wanted to tell you what Sterling's
formula was, but um
well, I'll just give it to you.
We can next time. Okay, I have time. So
n factorial
is equal to
approximately
2 m
over the
And from this you can get 2 n
approximately
um
I
squared
2 n / b 2
n / b n
because we're just taking n factorial.
We're taking this approximation for 2n
factorial and dividing it by
approximation for n factorial.
And you can see that most of these
things cancel out.
This e cancels the c. This cancels this
time
and
this more or less cancels
and we get
And that tells us that C7.
Okay, so we have an approximation. We
know roughly how fast C
goes.
Okay, so next time I will do more
examples of counting.
Any questions?
Okay, we're not going to give proof of
Sterling's formula, but I want to say
the only hard part about proof of
Sterling's formula is this square of pi.
Everything else
I guess the square root of 2 pi
everything else is
can be done with elementary calculus or
elementary probability but the root pi
this con is tricky. Okay, thanks