Okay. Well, today is our our last day
together. I was remembering the first
day at the beginning. I said to
everybody, you know, I'm excited about
projection theory and these like basic
problems were just solved in the last
couple years and we're trying to, you
know, describe the ideas in this and and
the beginning of the class, you know, I
say all these things I'm excited to do
and I wonder, you know, am I going to
are we going to manage to do this? Uh
and uh yeah, anyway, now it's at the end
and we've been working steadily and done
some of it.
Um
yeah. Okay.
Um yeah. So today we'll try to say um
the finish the story of proving the
sharp projection theorems and uh to say
the last couple of of ideas that go into
it. Um
so the first idea kind of goes back to
the beginning of the class. that goes
back to uh using the the forier method
and getting a little bit more out of it
than um than we had realized at that
time. Um and uh and then after that so
this this thing I'll do sort of by
itself. It's like re remembering the 4A
method and and playing seeing what how
much we can learn from it. Then I'll
remember what was the whole big theorem
that we wanted to prove and what are all
the things we knew about it. The last
the last idea in the class is um uh
combining combining information from
many different scales which allows us to
combine all of the previous ideas into
into one um big argument master
argument.
Um yeah and you know this this way of
combining scales has only been I would
say has only been around for five years
or so and and is also something it's
it's not that complicated and it's al I
think also something you know that might
be of value to take with you away from
the class.
Okay.
All right. So, part one is the well
spaced case
and the for method.
Okay.
Um
so so all of these things that were
these sharp projection theorems there's
some kind of um uh geometric measure
theory analog of the sum troder theorem.
So for reference let's remember first
the saretti troder theorem
and uh here's the version of it that
will be relevant for us. So if E
contained in R2 is a set of end points
and L sub R of E is the set of lines
little L so that little L intersect E is
at least R.
Uh then the question is how big could
this be in terms of N and R. And the
conclusion is that the size LR of E is
bounded by N2.
Actually, let me do a big R to match
some other notation.
N2 / R cubed + N / R.
This n^2 r cubed is comes from the grid
example. And this n / r comes from a
very simple example. You just draw a few
lines and you put R points on each of
them.
Okay. And we're trying to investigate to
what extent this continues to hold if we
replace our our pure points by some
little balls and by our pure lines by
some thin toes. Um and here is one clean
version of that that if the points are
quite spread out, they're what's called
well spaced. um then this holds almost
as real.
So this is a theorem of Hong Guang nom
Solomon and and me from around 2018 or
something.
So E contained in R2 is a set of N delta
balls.
Uh E is contained in the unit of ball.
Okay. And they're well spaced. They're
as spread out as possible. So they obey
the condition that if you take E and you
intersect it with a ball of radius N to
the minus a half, then that's at most
around one.
So in other words, if I take a unit
square and I subdivide it
into squares of side length n to the
minus a half that's been chosen so that
there are n squares in this picture and
then I put one or roughly one point in
each of these squares
uh one delta ball then this is what this
is our
what our set looks like. So this is a
well spaced set.
>> Yeah.
>> For the size of E intersect B, is that
supposed to be a delta ball covering
number?
>> Yeah, let's make that. Yeah, that's
right. That's it's a Thank you. That's a
delta ball covering number.
Okay.
All right. And then there's one more
hypothesis which is Okay. Okay. So yeah,
so then we could say what tr
of E is the set of delta tubes
T so that T intersect E delta is at
least R. Um and here you know if you
take a if you take such a delta tube and
you wiggle it imperceptibly you will
have another such delta tube and we want
to count those as being the same. So
I'll put here essentially distinct
Okay. Now, there's one other hypothesis
which is that R is not too small, which
I'll explain in a minute. The hypothesis
says R is at least a little bit bigger
than delta time E delta.
And then the conclusion is almost the
same as before that tr of e is less sim
sim um n^2 / r cub.
This two tildas here means that it's
hiding something like a uh like a delta
to the epsilon or something like that.
But it looks almost the same as this.
Okay, let's compare these two theorems.
Um, one difference is that in the first
theorem we had an extra term here which
I had not written in the second theorem
and the reason is that this this second
term is relevant when r is bigger than
the square root of n.
So the second term
this um dominates
if and only if r is bigger than square
root of n. But in the wellspaced case,
it's not possible for a tube to have
more than square root of n points on it.
So this case never arises.
Okay. So that's why we don't have that.
Um the other difference is that we added
this lower bound on R. So let me explain
why we did that.
So a remark
um an average
for a
random delta tube t
the expected size of t intersect e to
cover. Um that would be delta time e
delta. This is for each of these delta
point each of these little delta balls.
There are this many of them. um the
probability that a random delta tube
intersects that point is about delta.
Okay? So if you just take any old tube,
you'll have that many uh you'll hit that
many delta balls from E. Tubes that hit
this many delta balls of E are not
special. Any old tube will do. And so if
R takes that value, this upper bound
isn't true at all. This could be way
bigger than that because it could be it
could be basically all the tubes. But
rather remark there's there's a rather
remarkably sharp phase transition that
you increase r just a little bit beyond
this threshold and then you get a bound
that matches some tri.
Okay. So that is the statement of the
theorem. Um and it it says in a nutshell
that seated troder basically continues
to hold if you take a well spaced set E
which is one of the cases we mentioned
last time.
Okay. Any questions or comments about
the statement?
So I am going to do a proof sketch of
this theorem.
So let me first mention the tools that
will go into it. There's the forier
method.
There's double counting. And then
there's I guess I'll call this playing
with different scales.
The theme of this last class is playing
with different scales which is a simple
sounding an old idea which nevertheless
people recently have found a lot of new
um new ways of doing it.
Okay. Um
all right. So let me start with the
forier method.
Let me label this list of hypotheses
hypothesis
um
for method. Okay, so it's been a while.
In lectures three and four of this
class, we developed a forier analytic
method to estimate stuff like this. And
um if we had kept having problem sets
and if I had been really clever, I would
have had you remember it on the last
problem set getting ready for this
lecture. Um anyway, if you if you if you
take the method exactly the way we did
it back at the beginning of the class,
it said it it will say that if we have
the hypothesis,
then the size of TR of E
uh will bounded by delta.
Uh okay, I have to actually check
Okay. Delta inverse
E delta R to the minus 2.
I considered sort of redoing this for in
the last class to remind us all because
I don't expect it really to have it on
the tip of your brain. Um, but I decided
it was not that much fun for a thing to
do in the last class and also that I had
to manage the time to explain the other
stuff. So, I'd like to take this as a
black box that it's the sort of it's
something you can do with the tools that
we've already have.
Okay.
Um,
now how does this compare to our goal?
This e delta by the way is n. So this is
delta inverse n rus 2. Um
well it depends on how delta and n and r
are related to each other. But there's a
particular case where it just gives
exactly the right thing.
Um the particular case
is that if r is um the smallest that
it's allowed to be. So let's say it is
delta to the minus epsilon delta e
delta.
Okay. So in this case if I solve for the
delta inverse the delta inverse would be
around n / r
and then I plug in here um and I get
that one that this is an n / r is n^2 r
cub that's the semi of that.
So this 4A method actually gives the
right answer in an interesting case.
But then if you make r bigger
um then if you do this computation um
this ends up being bigger and and this
this will be bigger than n^2 r cubed.
Okay.
You know another interesting basic thing
about this that is perhaps surprising is
that as delta if delta gets bigger the
right hand side gets smaller.
So as we make our tubes thicker we
actually get a better bout.
Um okay
so
um if r is bigger this is the smallest r
could be. So the other option is that r
is bigger than this. So delta to the
minus epsilon delta e delta is less than
r. And let's say that r is less than the
square root of n because as we mentioned
earlier if r can't be any bigger than
the square root of n. Okay. Then
I'm going to set a scale row
so that
row * n is around r.
So how big is row? Um well row is going
to be r / n. So it will be smaller than
n to the minus a half but it will be
bigger than delta because um
delta n was smaller than r and I'm going
to increase delta to row so that row n
will be around r. So row will be around
there. And then we're going to study
E row which is the row neighborhood
of E.
So let's make a picture.
Here is the picture of our wellspace set
E. And then we're going to have a scale
row which is smaller than this scale n
to the minus a half but bigger than
delta. And we'll look at
that guy row.
Um
and you know originally we're trying to
find
our original problem is to understand
delta tubes that hit a lot of balls.
So
this might be one.
This is a tube delta tube and tr delta.
E Delta is just E, but I put the delta
to remind us. Um, but now that we have
these thicker guys, we could study um
I could study a row tube
that contains a lot of row balls.
So this might be T row. That might be a
tube that that intersects row a lot. Um
and well maybe for the same R but also
maybe for different RS we might be
interested.
So now let's make a definition. Uh
so TR
of TR tilda of E row this is the set of
row tubes
T row. So that if I take T row
intersected with E row and I take its
row covering number, that's at least our
tilt.
Okay. And now the same argument as
before gives us a bound for this thing.
So if we have our hypothesis
and if our tilda um
let's see
well let me not keep track of it. If we
have our hypothesis and arch tilda is
big enough
um
then yeah I'll just yeah here we can put
r tilda is at least as big as r then
t r tilda of e row will be bounded by
um
well we'll have row inverse
* e delta * r - 2 * r tilda 2
and this row inverse
is
n / r.
So that's n^ 2 / r * r tilda^ 2.
Just by thickening the tubes we get
these bounds. And let me mention an
important special case. So eg
tr
of e row is bounded by n^2 r cubed.
All
right.
So, as it's it's uh
it's a surprising thing that as we
increase row, we get a better and better
upper bound for this.
Um now we can't increase it. There's a
limit to how much we can increase it
because we do need
we do need this condition.
So row this this gives some upper bound
for row.
But taking row as close as you can to
that upper bound is a good idea. And
when we when we make row that big then
we get this.
Okay. Now have we proven the theorem
it look so when I got Yeah. Alia.
>> Yeah it's a good question about the
bound theorem you apply uh the same for
method.
>> Yes. Um but um would the E delta stay
not becoming?
>> Uh right. Right. So it would be E row.
Um but
you can um you can maybe see from the
picture where did we introduce E row?
So E row is equal to E delta is equal
to.
But that's a special that's where we're
using that our set is well spaced,
right? So that's a great thing to um
yeah so the qu so the question was you
know should this should be a row instead
of a delta and how does that affect
things and the answer is yeah great
point this should be a row instead of a
delta but for our set it doesn't change
anything
and
um so if you look at our set our set has
only one delta ball in each um n to the
minus a half ball. So when you thicken
them a little bit, the number of balls
you see is doesn't change. It's still n.
So that is where we are using this
hypothesis.
[Applause]
Yeah, great point.
Okay,
so when I first saw this, I thought that
we were done.
Um, but it's not quite true. So, uh, our
conclusion in the theorem is that we're
going to try to to estimate
how many of these guys there are thin
tubes, delta tubes that have R balls in
them.
And, um, we've counted the number of
thick tubes that have R balls in them.
Now, every thin tube with RB balls, if
you thicken it, you get a thick tube
with at least R balls. But inside of a
thick tube with R balls,
there may be many thin tubes with RB
balls. And we've only counted them once.
So, we do we still have an issue.
Doesn't got super difficult, but it's
important to recognize it.
So
issue
one row tube
may contain
many tubes
of
TR delta.
So what would the bad scenario look
like?
We would have
like a row tube here
and inside we would have a bunch of
delta balls. So at least r of them but
maybe more than r of them.
So let's say that t row intersected with
e.
So delta that would be the same as t row
intersected with e row. um let's say
that it's r tilda which is at least
small might be r but it might also be
bigger and then um inside of here we may
have
many delta tubes
that each contain
each contains
Okay.
So,
so now we have some cousin of our
original problem. We have R tilda delta
balls and we want to count how many RI
tubes there are. Um, we don't know as
much about how they are spaced, but also
we don't need to have such an incredible
bound. Um so
so uh by induction
we can assume
or we can reduce to the case
that each uh t and tr of e delta
um has many delta balls
at both ends.
Right?
So
what I mean by that is here's a tube
delta tube. It has a bunch of delta
balls in it. So it means
that there are a bunch at one end and a
bunch at the other end. Maybe also a
bunch at the middle. Um, uh, maybe it's
better to draw what it's not.
What it's not is like they're just all
on the left.
Okay. So, in a nutshell, how would we do
this if this was the situation
that all of the delta balls were
actually in a much shorter tube? Well,
then in my original picture,
I could cut my set E into separate
pieces and just look at um RIT tubes on
each of those pieces and I could do some
induction.
Um so then we do a double counting
argument.
I'm gonna do um
so we're going to count um just pairs of
delta balls.
Uh so I'll have like
um
tr of e delta
intersect tubes in t row.
So the number of yellow tubes in this
picture times r 2. So I take a tube and
I pick two points in the tube kind of
near opposite ends
and for any two points there is only one
tube that joins them. So this should be
bounded by r tilda squ
double count.
So we're counting we're counting pairs t
uh x1 x2
where
t is in this set and x1 and x2 are in t
and they're near opposite ends.
So how many are there? Well, for each
tube there are R 2 choices of X1 and X2.
On the other hand,
there are only R tilda squared choices
for X1 and X2.
And for each X1 and X2, there's only one
choice of T. So this is bounded by this.
Okay. So to double counting and the 4A
method are the two foundational
approaches that we did at the beginning
of the class. This one was short enough
that I thought I could I could recall it
for us.
Okay.
All right. So now um
TR of E delta is bounded by
um
the maybe sum on R tilda bigger than R
diic.
We're going to look at TR tilda of E
row,
but then we're going to multiply by R
tilda over R 2,
right? Why? So every RI delta tube, if
you thicken it up to be a row tube, it
will be an R tilder rich row tube and R
tilda will be at least R.
So they're all in here somewhere.
And um in each one of these guys there's
at most this many uh RI delta tubes.
This is bounded by this. And then if we
plug in our bounds everything will work.
So this is bounded by um
n^2 over r * r tilda squared. And then
we have r tilda^ 2 over r 2.
This just cancels
and we get n^2 r cub. And that's the end
of the proof sketch.
>> Yeah.
>> Where does the sum go?
The sum has logarithmically many terms.
>> Oh,
>> and so it gets absorbed.
Maybe I should write that. Let's write
that. Okay. It gets absorbed in the last
Simpsons.
>> Yeah. is the only part where we use it
is like well
it's like
the delta
>> yeah so the question is where did we use
it's well spaced and I think it's
instructive to trace where we used all
the hypothesis
so let's label this
WS. Well, let's label it well spaced,
which we can abbre.
So, where did we use that? It's well
spaced.
We used it here. And that's the only
place.
So, so
this guy is is N.
That's the only place that we use.
Okay. If I had another hypothesis
um hypothesis that R is bigger than
average
r bigger than average um I have
unfortunately hidden a little bit where
we used that hypothesis but it it was in
this forier estimate.
So here we use r big
and perhaps a little bit we might use a
little bit of well space too although we
don't need anything as strong as what's
what's up there. Um where did our big
come in? Well we had all these tubes and
we took a sum of the characteristic
functions of the tubes smoothed out a
little bit and we did 4a analysis with
them and there was a high frequency part
and a low frequency part and some middle
frequencies.
Um this is the high the contribution of
the high frequency part. If the high
frequency part dominates immediately you
get this
the very low frequencies uh corresponds
if the low frequency dominated it would
mean that r was equal to this
and there are some in between
frequencies. So you have to compute a
little bit to see that they're
controlled by those two cases.
Good. Yeah,
>> I guess the A for method doesn't really
need the well spacing condition, but
would it be possible to use kind of well
spacing condition to put a cap on the
high frequency command cuz seems like if
the the frequencies of the corresponding
to the delta balls should be low if the
delta balls are very well spaced.
Um
so the question is about the
relationship between the spacing of E
and the frequencies in like the 4A
transform of E. Is that the question?
Yeah. Um
yeah. So if if you just took one uh
delta ball here and you smoothed out its
characteristic function, it would have a
4A transform that was supported on a
delta inverse ball.
Now we have a bunch of them and so each
of them has a 4A transform that's
supported on a delta inverse ball and
now we're going to add them all up. Um
now when we add them all up what happens
is complicated and it depends on exactly
where we put them all but absent any
detailed information about exactly where
we put them all. You would typically
expect that they would have maybe square
root cancellation and that the sum would
still be pretty evenly spread over a
delta inverse.
Um and um
um
yeah, so being well spaced, we would see
quite a lot of high frequency, but I
don't know that we could recognize
whether we were well spaced. I guess if
they I guess if we if we you had more
points closer together, you would see
more low frequency stuff.
Good. Other questions or comments?
Okay, I had myself a couple comments.
Uh, so one thing was it seemed kind of
magical to me that we ended up with the
right answer.
Um, and looking back
in in all the proofs of anything related
to saretti trotder, it seems rather
magical to me that we get the right
answer. So the the uh form ready troder
or this theorem there's a construction
you take a grid you take some lines at
rational slopes you compute a little bit
and you see what happens and you get
this n^2 r cubed then independently from
that you look at some cell partitions or
some this or some that or some for
analysis and completely unrelated
argument you get something and if you're
if you're lucky it's n^2 over r cubed
and we declare victory um and yeah in in
all the cases I won't really understand
why it why we are getting the right
answer
and it's perhaps worth mentioning that
summar has many cousin problems which
are almost as simple to state but no one
knows the right answer. Um so for
instance if you replace straight lines
with circles
or degree 2 curves or unit circles or
make up your favorite class of curves um
you get natural questions that people
have studied hard and almost every one
of them we cannot prove matching
examples and upper bounds.
So it is plausible that um
that there is no deep reason why this
bound matches the example that but that
we were just lucky.
>> Yeah.
>> Most kind of put other variations of the
problem. Is it like harder to show kind
of a similar bound or to kind of find
examples
versus different?
>> Um yeah. So the question is for these
all these other variations is it harder
to to prove upper bounds or harder to
find good examples? Um in all these
problems all of the known examples are
look a lot like the grid example there
they they involve grids of points and
you try to intersect it with a lot of
circles or a lot of parabas or what have
you. Um and um and there's some upper
bound and the proofs of the upper bounds
are not so different from the proofs
that we have shown but the numbers that
come up just they just don't match and
popular opinion probably is on the side
that the upper bound should be improved
but we are talking about open problems
so nobody knows.
Yeah.
Okay. So that's one comment. Um, another
comment is that in the context of the
fenberg problem, there was a key
difficulty that the first problem was
false over the complex numbers, the
first inber conjecture, but true over
the real numbers. So, we're always on
the lookout for what steps distinguish
the real numbers from the complex
numbers. This argument does not
distinguish them. This statement can be
you can replace all the Rs with C's and
adjust a few things and it's still true.
So, this part of the proof is not
helping with that issue.
Yeah. Cool.
Okay. So,
so that was part one of the class, the
well spaced case using the forier
method. Um, part two combining all the
stuff we've done. Um, let's start by
remembering what is the big theorem that
we're discussing the proof of and then
like sort of what are all the things
that we've done and the last part we'll
talk about how to put the pieces
together.
Okay.
[Applause]
All right. So here is the big theorem
that we would like to prove.
So if E is a delta T set
in the unit ball in R2
uh and let's say that the size of E is
delta to the minus T
and then for every point in E
um TX
is a delta S set of tubes.
through the point x and there's no loss
of generality in assuming that this is
delta to the minus s put them all
together to make a set of tubes t
okay and then uh
uh thinking about how how how these
tubes intersect e so let's say r is the
typical ical value of e intersect t
delta covering number typical over t and
t
could mean average if you like but they
after after a little bit of um pigeon
holing we can assume that they're all
about the same as each other
okay so then
uh the goal is to say that r is not too
big these tubes can't overlap the points
too much r is bounded by the maximum of
three things corresponding to three
scenarios.
Okay, so A is the stars example.
These tubes have nothing to do with each
other. So the number of of dots on each
tube is just one. That's scenario A. B
is the really interesting one. It's the
integer grid and so this we've written
things a little differently but this
corresponds to the numerology in sem
ready try
um and C is uh the regime where uh uh
random tubes
know if this set E is really large a
random tube will hit a lot of points of
E and this set T certainly could be made
out of random tubes
okay so that is the theorem we're trying
to prove
And we have developed uh many techniques
and tools to work on this theorem and we
have proven many cases of it. And let's
uh document that
[Applause]
Okay. So cases
we have
uh discussed the proof.
Okay. So there are these A, B and C
scenarios and so we should sort of sort
this theorem according to who is bigger
A or B or C. So uh A dominates
that if and only if
uh S is greater than or equal to T. Let
me write it actually as t is less well s
is greater than
um and in this case it's true by a
double counting argument
and c dominates
if and only if s + t is greater than or
equal to 2 and that's also true by the
forier method.
Okay,
so B dominates
otherwise and it's actually important to
write down this otherwise. So S is
between T is between S and 2 minus S.
Okay, that's what's left. And this one
we don't know yet.
But we do know a couple of special cases
of this hard case. Um but we do know
um do know
if E is ad regular
that was by orin we talked about it last
time and we do know
sorry it is true E is a regular and it
is true if E is well spaced
we just talked
And that's striking because ad regular
and well spaced are sort of the two
extremes in the way that E could be
spaced and the other stuff is in the
middle here. Um
now
yeah so actually people in the field
have run into this problem a number of
times and and and it um so there okay so
there are several cousin problems of
this first set problem. There's the CA
problem which is the most famous. Uh
there's also the falconer distance set
problem. And in both of those problems
there was a period where people knew how
to do these two extreme cases and we
thought we hoped maybe we were close and
we tried to do the stuff in the middle
and it was hard and messy and we
couldn't do it.
So when Orbin and Schmurkin wrote their
paper, they said, "We we've solved the
ad regular case and we know that
previously some people solved the
wellspaced case and what's left is to do
the stuff in the middle, but we're not
sure whether that might be very hard.
Okay,
cool. Um,
cool.
Um,
okay. Um and so the last the last idea
in the proof is an idea from Ren and
Wong. How to
um
break up the general case into pieces
that can be handled by these methods.
First part of what they did is they
souped up this well spaced case a little
bit. Um so they proved that it's true if
E is something called semi wellspaced
that I will define for you
def definition um soon. Okay.
So it's a mild generalization of this
and the proof is very is fairly a little
more complicated but it's similar ideas
to what I showed you. Uh it doesn't
distinguish R from C. It's the same
tools that I showed you.
Okay. And then the the really important
thing is how to how to put all these
things together.
Okay. Um so we're going to put all these
things together
by using uh a multiscale argument which
is similar to the sub multiplicative
lema that was one of the key things in
the in the ad regular case.
So let me remind you of that and draw
draw the important picture again. All
right. So
multi-cale
argument,
so um
so we're going to have delta, we're
going to have some scale in between
delta and row. And I'm going to
visualize E at this scale, but also at
that scale. So now we have a general E
but it's uniform
and so I think of it as having some row
balls.
So these circles
are row inside of each row ball we have
some delta balls.
So those are the delta balls and E
delta.
Okay.
And we have some fat tubes
like that. So those are the tubes that
scale row. Inside of the fat tubes, we
have some thin tubes. Um
should draw a little differently.
So those are the delta tubes.
Okay. Now what do we notice?
We notice that the r that's associated
to e delta and t delta can be bounded
by a coarse scale. So this r is how many
delta balls are there in an orange tube
like this. So first we can ask how many
row balls uh does the orange tube hit.
So that would be r of e row t row.
And then we look inside each of those
row balls at this short delta tube and
we ask how many delta balls does it hit.
And let's call one of these balls B the
typical row ball. And that would be R of
EB
TB.
Okay. Who are what is EB TB? Um so EB is
just E intersect B. And then let's
rescale it so that B becomes a unit
ball.
And TB is you take T well you take T
intersect B where T is in T. You take
all these little pieces of tubes and
then again you rescale
so that B becomes the unit ball. And so
EB is a set of delta over row balls
and TB is a set of delta over row tubes.
We do this rescaling. So we can relate
this. Think of this as a case of our
original problem. We can use induction.
Um okay. But this inequality is just how
many delta balls are there in the orange
tube? Well, how many row balls does it
hit and how many delta balls are in each
row ball?
Okay, cool. So,
by this multiscale argument, we can take
our original problem and break it up
into pieces. We get to choose row. So,
we have some flexibility there. Then we
can repeat that. We can break these up
into pieces and so on. And we would be
very happy if all of these pieces
are in the list of things that we
understand.
And then we could multiply go together
all those bounds and get a bound. And in
some cases we'll get the sharp bound.
And and then that's how we that's how
they prove the theorem.
Okay.
Now to keep track of what happens
everything is described in terms of the
branching function. And for people's
intuition, it has been very helpful to
draw pictures of the graph of the
branching function.
Okay. do graph
of the branching function.
So we're going to suppose that E is
uniform
and then I'm going to draw a graph that
encodes the information of how many row
balls there are to cover E at every
scale. So on this axis I want to put row
and what I'm going to put is log delta
of row. So it's going to be a number
between zero and one.
And now on this axis I want to
understand the covering number row. And
I what I'm going to put here is the
logarithm in the base 1 / delta of this
covering number.
Okay.
Um so
uh if
e delta were a delta to the minus t
then when you plug in one here that
corresponds to the scale delta. So this
is delta to the minus t. So this
logarithm would be t
have this. So I'm going to call this
variable t. U I'm going to call this
variable x and this is f ofx. f is the
branching function.
So if e of e delta is delta to the minus
t it means f of 1 equals t.
If e is a deltat t set
then it means that f ofx is bigger than
t * x. So here's the straight line with
slope t
and
I'll put this in blue. f ofx is bigger
than t * x. Okay, there are many things
that we could draw that do that be like
that.
Okay,
so these pictures always start at one
because when x is one, it means we're
talking about the scale row equals 1.
And this is a subset of the unit ball.
So that's the covering number at scale
one is one. So it always starts there.
any questions or comments about the
about these setting this up as a graph?
Okay, so now what do we know about this
function f? Um
so f is monotonically increasing.
Why? Um as we go this way, row is
getting smaller and the row covering
number is only going to get bigger.
but it doesn't increase too quickly. Um,
so f ofx f(x) plus delta x is less than
or equal to f ofx + 2 delta x. So f is
two vectors.
Uh why? Well, if we have a a row ball
and then we decrease row, we can always
cover that with a certain number of rota
balls.
So B row is covered
by row tilda row over. So if row tilda
is less than row then B row is covered
by row over row tilda squared row tilda
and we may or may not need all of them
but the most we could need is all of
them and that would correspond to
equality here.
So f is two lips.
>> Yeah.
>> So the two comes from the dimension.
>> Two comes from the dimension. This two
is this two which comes from the
dimension. Yeah. Okay. That's right. So
let me say E is uniform. E is contained
in the unit ball and E is in two
dimensions. And if you change this two
to a D dimension, the only thing in this
discussion that would change is that
these twos would become D's. Yeah. Thank
you.
Yeah, good.
Okay. So, um to get a feel for this, I
will draw a few pictures of um
uh of the branching functions for cases
that we have considered.
Okay. So for the ad regular set
before I draw it, picture in your mind's
eye what does the branching function
look like.
It is a straight line.
Okay. the well spaced example.
[Applause]
So the wellspaced example
looks like this. It's a straight line of
slope 2
up to the height t and then it's a
horizontal line. It's flatline after
that.
Okay. And now I can tell you what is the
semi wellspace set.
So here's what we do.
So semi wellspace definition is now so t
is going to be in between 2 minus s and
s. That's good. That's the region we
don't already understand.
Um so e delta is going to be delta to
the minus t. So that point there is
going to be on our branching function.
And then what I will do is I draw here a
line with slope s and here a line with
slope 2 minus s. By the way s is between
zero and one. So 2 - s is the bigger
one. And I extend these lines until they
meet. They'll meet somewhere.
Um, okay. And then the branching
function
f ofx has to lie above this stuff and it
has to go there. That's the definition
of semi well spaced.
Um, okay. So, so Ren and Wong, they
proved that in the semi-wwell spaced
case the this theorem is true.
Um and we won't do the whole proof but
you know the proof is a variant on what
we saw here where you combine in a
clever way the forier method and the
double counting method.
And at a very high level you know this
setup is sort of this slope 2 minus s is
the slope where the forier method works
and this slope s is the slope where the
double counting method works.
And so this picture turns out to be the
situation where you can combine those
two methods. Well,
okay.
All right. So now let's think about what
happens when we do this multiscale
argument. What happens to the branching
functions? In other words, I start with
this setup. I want to understand this
guy and and it depends on the branching
function of E delta. And I get these two
new sort of smaller problems. What is
the relationship between this branching
function and these branching functions?
Okay, the relationship is really u
simple.
So,
so this is so f ofx itself this is the
branching function of e delta and it
looks like something
okay could be anything
and then we have this scale row. So over
here is log delta of row.
And if you think about this set e row,
well it's just the branching function of
e row is the same as the branching
function of e delta except it just stops
at row and we don't look at any smaller
scales.
So,
so this here in orange is basically the
branching function of row.
And then
then we look inside of this ball
and we look at all of the start at the
scale row and then we look at all of the
smaller scales of E. So um this thing
here
is um let me say this describes
f.
This is basically the branching function
of EB.
Okay. Okay. Great. So
so what's the situation?
we begin with an arbitrary branching
function that just obeys this condition.
Uh yeah
>> going back to the the uh multi scale or
the simplicity
second why why is it like the second one
like RB TB but it's like the number of
delta balls in the ball like how
misunderstanding
>> right right so
this r of eBT
is supposed to be counting the number of
delta balls in in a segment like that.
Okay. Now, why is it counting that? Who
is EB?
EB are the delta balls in the row ball
in B and TB are I take the tubes
um and I just take the part of the tube
that is in the um
that's in the ball be.
>> Okay. Then
then R E row R E R row that's the number
of
road balls in the road tube. Right. And
the product is just delta tube.
>> Right.
Right.
Right. So a t row is this blue tube and
r of e row t row is the number of row
balls in the blue tube.
And then if we take an orange tube, it
will go through this many of uh of the
row balls. And we want to know how many
delta balls are there in each of those
bits.
So now we have um some tubes at this
tubes inside of B and points inside of
B. And we blow that up and that's over
here.
Good.
Okay. So here's something we might try.
We start with E delta T delta. we don't
know how to handle it. We look at the
branching function. I can cut the
branching function anywhere I like and
produce two two branching functions and
I can repeat that. And then I can take
the different branching functions I get
and hopefully I can put them into the
list that I know how to handle um and
then I'll multiply it together and I'll
get an answer.
Okay,
so let me do a couple examples of this
concatenation method and we'll see how
it works.
Okay,
concatenation method.
All right, so let me do the example
where our graph consists of two lines.
So it has a line of slope t1
up to somewhere. So here's log delta of
row. Then it has a line at a different
slope which let's say is smaller. So
here's a slope t2
to the end.
It's one. And let's say that this final
height is t.
Okay. So how are they related? So delta
to the minus t is e delta which I can
read off from my final branching
function. That's the size of e row times
the size of eB. number of row balls
times number of delta balls per row
ball.
So that is row to the minus t1.
So this is slope t1 time delta over row
to the minus t2.
Okay. So now let's see what happens.
So r of e t bounded by
r of e row t row r of ebt.
Scenario one.
Uh in this scenario one um t1 and t2 are
both in this middle range where b
dominates.
So then
this guy will give me um
row to the s over 2 row to the minus t1
/ 2 because this is option B b dominates
and this guy here will give me delta
over row to the s / 2 delta over row to
the minus t2 / 2 because that's option
B. This is not B as in ball. This is B
as in A, B and C. The three options.
All right. When we multiply it out,
something nice happens. What happens
when we multiply these together? We get
delta to the S over two. And what
happens when we multiply those together?
Okay, at first it looks like an unholy
mess,
but
it's the same as this.
And so it's delta to the minus t / 2,
which is b, which is what we were hoping
for.
This is a smiley face.
But let me mention another scenario.
Scenario two, maybe t1 is bigger than 2
minus s and maybe t2 is smaller than s.
So maybe this first one is really quite
steep and then the second one is quite
shallow.
Okay.
Well,
now this first one,
when I evaluate this, I'm in the C
domain,
I get row to the 1 - t1. And when I
evaluate this, because this t2 is less
than s, I'm in the a domain, which is
one.
And that's not what I'm hoping for.
That's actually much bigger than my
goal.
>> So actually let me add to scenario two.
But T is in the middle. T is a sort of
average of T1 and T2. T1 is bigger. That
is quite big. T2 is quite small. But
this average is going to be in the
middle. Since T is in the middle, this
is the goal.
How does this compare to the goal? Not
so obvious, but it's much actually much
bigger than the goal. What went wrong?
Remember that at each step when I
bounded R, my theorem bounds R by a
maximum of three things.
Maximum of A, B, and C.
So this C is way bigger than B in this
regime. And this A is way bigger than B
in this regime. and B times B would be
my goal. So this is way too big. So it
doesn't work.
Okay. So uh lesson that we learned here
is that we want
to break up f
into pieces
so that okay I'll say it in words. So
first of all we'd like to be able to
analyze each piece. So we want each
piece to be on the list of things we
understand. So if you don't have a sharp
bound for the piece, there's no way
you're going to have a sharp bound for
the whole thing. But also, we're not
happy with just any of these. We really
want them all to be in case B.
So So we So um
right
um so we really want each piece
[Applause]
is either uh ad regular
with t of that piece in our middle range
in the b range or semi-well spaced.
Okay.
Um so the very last idea is that indeed
you can do this. You can start with an
arbitrary
uh branching function and then you can
break it up into pieces where each piece
is sort of like this.
Uh I'll write it down in a sec and draw
an example.
Um
probably the most important idea behind
this is the rodamoker theorem. So the
rader theorem says that a differentiable
function ellipse function is
differentiable almost everywhere
and so this function f we don't know a
lot about it but it we did see that it's
a lipshits function and so it's
differentiable almost everywhere. So we
that means that we can cut up our
interval into little intervals where
maybe you have to throw out a tiny bit
but on almost every little interval it's
approximately a constant slope example.
So you can reduce everything just just
by by rodmacher theorem you can reduce
everything to the ad regular case and
that's an indication ad regular case is
really important. It's not just a
special case.
However, if you do that, we would not
only have slopes in here, we would also
have slopes that are too small and too
large. So, we want everybody to be in
case B. And that's why we need some
extra stuff like the semi well spaced.
Okay. So, I will
write down this last thing.
So the final lema
if f is a function from 01 to r which is
two lip shits and increasing
then we can break up 01 as a disjoint
union of some intervals
maybe plus tiny leftover
and then on each I
either
um F restricted to I either F is almost
linear
um with slope
TI and TI is in our range.
Ah okay I should say one other thing. So
f let's say f of one is t and t is in
our range.
Uh oh yeah and yeah and we should sorry
we should have f ofx is bigger than tx.
So this is our setup. We have a delta t
set branching function. Okay so either
it's almost linear and it slope is in
the desired range or on i f is semi well
spaced.
Okay.
Um it's not so difficult to prove once
you think to try to prove it. And I'm
just going to illustrate it with an an
example.
So I suppose f
looks like this. And so the slope is
increasing for a while. I guess it needs
to start bigger than t. It's a bit
tricky to draw this picture here. Hold.
So it needs to stay above this dotted
line, right?
Okay. So it's going to start tangent to
the line, which is okay. The slope
increases for a while, has a maximum
slope and the slope decreases and it
goes like that. And as this slope
increases, there is a key moment
where the slope gets too big.
Over here, the slope is 2 minus s.
And maybe at the end the slope is too
small, slope is less than s.
Okay, so what should we do?
Well, um, this whole thing here,
this whole thing is semi well spaced.
And at the beginning, we can take very
short intervals.
So, we'll have this guy and this guy and
this guy. And these blue guys are um
almost they're short, so it's almost
linear.
And the slope is not yet bigger than 2 -
s. So the slope ti is less than 2 - s
bigger than s.
Okay, this is not a proof but you know
there are not that many ways this
function could look and if you draw like
five of them you can convince yourself
that if you want you can prove.
Okay. Um so to summarize
um
this picture, this fact is very powerful
because it lets us break up our original
problem into smaller problems.
And the smaller problems in terms of the
branching functions of the smaller
problems are just little pieces of the
branching function of the bigger
problem. And when you do that there
um
uh what originally looked like we just
had a few special cases. Now we can take
any combination of those few special
cases and that turns out to be a lot and
even to be everything.
So that that
that's the that's the last idea of the
proof. The proof how to put the pieces
together. And so these pieces were were
not just special cases. They they they
are really the fundamental building
blocks of the whole story. Um and it's
also is striking to me that this
multiscale argument. It was really
crucial in both the ad regular case and
the notad regular case.
In the ad regular case, these problems
were all the same. And then seeing that
sameness at all these different
situations, it gave us some some extra
rigidity and structure. In the not 80
regular case by definition these
problems are different and that means
that gives us a whole menu of problems
to choose from and then we can sort of
look through this menu and try to find
the things that we understand.
Okay, cool.
Okay, so that was an outline of
projection theory. Uh thank you for
coming with me on this on this outline.
It's been nice talking with you all and
uh yeah, let's stop the class there.