Thanks so much Asia and thanks to um
everyone who invited me here. I'm really
happy to be here and it's a privilege to
be able to talk to you all and I'm
looking forward to hearing your thoughts
at the end about this topic as well. So
I'm going to speak today about
algorithmic monoculture and the ethics
of systemic exclusion. Um so as A Asia
mentioned I am lucky enough to be uh a
computationallyincclined philosopher who
gets to uh exist in both computer
science and philosophy world and I
couldn't do that without my fantastic
co-authors. Um so you see them here in
their full glory but their little heads
will pop up on the slides uh as I've
drawn projects that I've done with them.
So look forward to my majestic
co-authors return m returning and thank
you to all of them for um the joyful
work that we've been able to do
together. So imagine you are a hiring
manager and out of hundreds or thousands
of résumés you have to find three people
to interview and one to hire. And this
in our computer science terms is a very
uh information constrained problem. We
have time constraints. We have
information constraints. There are some
things that we we might want to know and
we're not allowed to know perhaps for
good reason. Uh there are privacy
constraints. And perhaps most
importantly, the future space is really
undefined. We don't actually know what
makes a good employee right now or what
will make a good employee in the
uncertain future. And so into this
morass of uncertainty step, automated
hiring systems. Um most systems will do
this first round screening. So discard
about half of applications before a
human being ever looks at them. Um and
98% of Fortune 5 companies use some
version of an applicant tracking system
which has some kind of sorting. Uh but
many of them use this more extensive
first round screening algorithmic system
as
well. And the hope is that uh these
hiring systems will save time and money
uh reduce bias perhaps choose better
candidates and most importantly produce
more consistent judgments. And it's that
consistency that I want to focus on in
the talk today. So imagine from the
candidate perspective you're applying to
what I hope are three MIT area uh
grocery stores. The Target, the Daily
Table, and the HMart. I'm getting some
of this. So, I'm hearing these are not
the best grocery stores in the area, but
maybe you didn't know that. Maybe there
are yet better grocery stores that you
should have applied to. Uh, I am going
to defend the HMart, however. Um, okay.
So you imagine perhaps naively that when
you submit these three separate
applications to three completely
separate business entities that your
file will be screened by three different
sets of managers, actors, whoever. Um
human beings will look at these files.
But it might be that all three companies
have purchased software from um an
automated resume screening provider like
HireView. And so you are unbeknownst to
you experiencing algorithmic
standardization where decisions that
were previously made by many different
people are now made by one screening
company. And so we can say that whatever
else they do, automated decision-making
systems have the potential to
standardize by enforcing the same
classification on the same token
applicant file every time it's
encountered at
scale. And then we might ask, is this
standardization a problem? um in a
context where the largest algorithmic
screening providers uh have clients that
include 60% of the Fortune 100 and eight
of the 10 largest federal agencies. Is
it a problem if the same applicants
re-encounter the same systems over and
over? And the reason I think this is an
interesting uh AI and society problem,
an interesting ethics problem, is that
standardization at scale is one of the
features of automated but not human
decision-making. Uh if you've ever
worked with a bureaucracy, you know that
it's actually very hard to get humans to
make the same decisions even on the same
cases. Um if you show people whose whole
job it is to make decisions like
doctors, lawyers, judges, um the same
file three months later with names and
other details re removed, they'll make a
different decision about 25 to 30% of
the time. So even the same individual
will sometimes make a different decision
on the same case over time. And that's
not even counting the diversity of
between decisionmaker uh choices.
So this is a case where algorithmic
decision-making and human
decision-making regimes might have
importantly different features uh rather
than cases that we often talk about uh
which are also important in which it's
just that algorithmic decision-m perhaps
exacerbates patterns that are already
present in the other decision-making
regime.
So in the talk today I want to go
through what is it that standardizes
algorithmic decisions when should we
consider standardized decisions to be of
moral concern and when they're of moral
concern what is it that we should
do so in this room I don't need to go
through uh one source of standardization
which is of course just the basic nature
of a deterministic algorithm put in the
same inputs you get the same outputs but
I want to talk about a more uh subtle
source of algorithmic standardization
which is algorithmic
monoculture. So monoculture is a
metaphor drawn from agricultural
science. Uh we have um the case of
industrial farming where previously you
might have had uh gardens that were
intercropped with many different plants.
Each of those plants drew different
things from the soil uh used different
nutrients, put different um fixed
nutrients back in the soil, etc. Then
when we move to industrialized
agriculture, it becomes more efficient
to take a tractor and run it down the
same line of plants and harvest the same
plants at the same time. But we know
that if we plant the same field with the
same crops over and over, eventually we
get uh nutrient collapse.
So metaphorically we might think of this
as an algorithmic monoculture as uh
Manish and co-author John Kleinberg have
said uh algorithmic monoculture is a
state in which many decision makers all
rely on the same algorithm and in this
lovely uh 2021 paper they point out that
this can have medium-term collapse
effects where even though initially it
might be better for the decision m
decision makers themselves it might end
up in the medium-term uh causing them
problems by their own
So what are some other sources of
algorithmic monoculture? So the first of
course is we literally use the same
model uh in the one domain. Um and we're
going to call this mechanical
algorithmic monoculture. So necessarily
you have to get the same outcome. And
this is not as unusual as you might
think given rollups and mergers by uh
various private equity firms that are
trying to create one actor in an entire
domain. But since this isn't a political
economy talk, we will move on uh to
think instead about a relaxed definition
of algorithmic monoculture. So if uh
Kleinberg and Raavon's definition is
this pure algorithmic monoculture where
all decision makers rely on the same
algorithm, it might not not that be that
realistic in all of our decision
settings. So when higher view builds an
applicant screening algorithms for
grocery stores, it's not actually going
to give the same algorithm to all the
grocery stores. Sufficiently big actors
desire customization. It has to be
tailored to them. So instead of this
case, we're going to have a relaxed
monoculture where, you know, these
houses sure look very similar, but if
you look closely, they have different
doors, they have different windows, they
have different awnings, they're not
exactly the same. And in a similar way,
we're going to define algorithmic
monoculture as the state in which many
decision makers rely on similar
algorithms in a way that I'll specify in
a moment.
So here we might be thinking of the same
provider is still building algorithms
but they're slightly different for each
of the grocery stores or even uh there's
a different provider who's providing
algorithms to a third grocery store. So
in that case why might we think that
decision-m outcomes would still be
correlated? So one reason is that
machine learning is built on a wonderful
tradition of component sharing. So uh we
work really hard to get good data sets
and then it would be rational for many
people in the same decision-m ecosystem
who want to do the same task to rely on
the same data set. So for a long time
imageet was the largest labeled uh data
set of images in town. So it made sense
that a lot of computer vision papers
would all use
imageet. Likewise, um for a certain time
period when BERT was the best model, uh
for certain language tasks, a lot of uh
papers at the same conference would all
rely on BERT. Um we might also have
libraries that are best in class at a
moment at a time and evaluations. Um
academics are competitive people. At
least I hope that's not too
controversial to say. So if someone puts
out a big shiny benchmark, a lot of
people are going to try to meet that
benchmark if it gains social prestige.
And so attempts to meet the same
benchmark might also homogenize the
outputs because we're aiming towards the
same
goal. So we have these standardizing uh
forces that are built on the tradition
of sharing in machine learning. And
anecdotally, we've seen that previous
data curation efforts like imageet have
standardized training corpora. And in
doing so, standardized errors such as
reliance on the same spurious cues or
shortcuts like background textures to
predict foreground objects. So here uh
we have an image of a fox squirrel on
the left. Um but imagenet models are
very likely to say that it's a sea lion.
Uh on the right we have a focal image of
a dragonfly, but imagenet models are
very likely to say it's a manhole cover.
So why is that? Take a minute, look at
the
pictures. Okay, great. So we think it's
because of these strong background
textures. The background texture of the
wet rock is similar to a sea lion. The
cross-hatching of I assume the lawn
chair is similar to a manhole cover. And
so what's important here is not that uh
models make mistakes. of course they
make mistakes. It's that training on the
data set means they mean make the same
particular
mistake. Um there can also be
standardization due to use of shared
data in regimes where there's only one
data set. So common crawl is an attempt
to uh compile and clean the data from
the entire internet. But unfortunately
there's only one entire internet. So
even if we had a competitor to common
crawl, it would be attempting to get all
the same data from the same
source. Um likewise, we might have uh
very large models that are trained with
significant computational resources
often across multiod modalities. And I
don't know about you, but if I built a
$10 million model, which I have not, I
wouldn't want to just immediately throw
it in the trash after I used it once. I
would probably try to use it for as many
different things as I possibly
could. So the concern here is that
adapting the same model for many
different tasks could lead to this sing
a single point of failure. And in some
co-authored work uh a paper called
ecosystems graphs we've tried to um show
this by looking at dependencies in the
foundation model ecosystem and showing
that there are significant hubs where a
whole bunch of different models from
different companies will train on the
same data set like the pile um or
different APIs across many different
companies will rely on the same
underlying base
model. All right. Wonderful. So, um I've
suggested that there are many reasons
why algorithmic decisions might be
standardized. But why do we care about
this in this context? It's because we
think that algorithmic monoculture has
the potential to homogenize
outcomes. So what does this look like?
Um so imagine people are interacting
with some kind of deployed machine
learning system. So there are multiple
people and they're interacting with
multiple decision makers. This is
different from the context that we often
look at in let's say algorithmic
fairness where we're imagining a regime
of one decision maker and a population
that has a bunch of subpopuls. Now we're
thinking about what's the cumulative
effect of multiple decision makers on a
population. So we're switching the frame
a little bit.
So now we want to say what is the
cumulative pattern of the outcomes that
they receive. And we can either think
about these just in terms of their
positive or negative aspects. Uh did
they get you'll say the good or not? Or
we can think about these in terms of
their errors. Was the correct judgment
made on them? And is there a pattern of
systemic failure or systemic
error? So we're going to call uh outcome
homogenization when an individual or a
subgroup receives the same outcomes from
decision makers and those could be
positive or negative. Then we're going
to say an individual experiences
systemic failure if every
decision-making system fails for that
person. And in classification settings,
that's going to mean they experience a
systemic failure or error if every
decision-making system mclassifies that
person. So how do we measure this? We
can't just count, right? Because if we
count, we would overindex on the fact
that the systems do make some errors and
those errors would naturally collide
even if the systems were completely
independent of each other. So we just
minimally need to normalize for that
error rate. So we need to say compared
to what we would have expected if these
systems had been totally independent,
how much more homogeneous are the
outcomes than
that? So you can imagine if each of the
systems is very bad, it makes 40%
errors, there's going to be a high sort
of baseline error rate, but we still
might want to know are they more
homogeneous than that?
Now this doesn't mean by calling it a
baseline this doesn't mean that we're
committed to saying that independence is
actually the right uh the right answer.
In fact we suspect in a lot of cases the
sort of right degree of correlation
would be somewhere in the middle. But in
a lot of regimes we may not know what is
the correct degree of correlation. So
we're just you viewing this as a
baseline where we're saying empirically
how much more correlated are they than
this
baseline. Okay. So um in a uh study of
this we looked at the happy data set and
uh we looked at predictions from
deployed APIs in three modalities image
text and speech. Uh we had 11
classification data sets roughly four
per modality and three APIs per
modality. So three predictions for every
data point and luckily we also had this
over time from 2020 to
2022. So what we wanted to find out is
how often were model errors correlated
and it turned out much more than if the
model errors uh were independent which
is what we would sort of expect. So the
observed is the dark blue. Uh you can
see on the zero so all models get it
wrong. There are a lot more all models
get it wrong than we would have expected
based on independence. Now sometimes
when I present this to computer
scientists they say aha that's right.
That's because those examples are hard.
And I say oh great okay what does it
mean to be hard? And they say well
hardness means that all the models get
it wrong. And I say wait a second that's
what I'm showing you. But is there a
model independent property of hardness?
Because if you and I looked at these
samples, they wouldn't be hard for us.
So I think what we're agreeing on is
that there is a model dependent property
of hardness where these samples are hard
for this class of models, but they might
not be hard for us and they might not be
hard for some as yet uncreated or
perhaps not measured uh type of model
that would be classifying
this. Um and what we notice could I ask
one question? Yes.
um were these cases when they're all
wrong, are they all confident they're
wrong? They we don't have a confidence
measure, but that's a great question.
Yeah, thank you. Um I'll get Yeah, there
is a case later where we do have
confidence. So, thank
you. Um we also notice over time that
model improvements don't substantially
reduce these failures. So here again we
have um out of all the samples that
originally uh the models all got wrong
over the next two years how many of them
are improved and compared to the
potential improvements which is the
light blue many fewer of the models are
improved than you would have expected.
So the systemic failures tend to persist
over
time. Um, so in ongoing work that I
unfortunately can't share yet, we are
trying to audit a real algorithmic
hiring vendor and try to figure out uh
how much correlation is in their
predictions. But what I want to get to
now is the moral question. So uh if
standardizing architectures and data
sets improves decision quality, if
there's a reason that we have this
tradition of component sharing and
machine learning, um if it improves
accuracy, when should we nevertheless
think that outcome homogenization is of
moral concern? And I think this is um
this is a question that I found
interesting for some time because I
think the answer is not completely
obvious.
So this is a challenge. So just to spell
it out a little bit more, uh we often
think epistemically, so in terms in our
in our regime of knowledge and what we
should know and what we should believe,
uh we often think that each decision
maker has a responsibility to act on
their best available evidence, all other
things being equal. But what if they
also have reason to believe as I think a
lot of decision makers should have
reason to believe in the machine
learning ecosystem. Whatever data I
have, others also have. Uh whatever
learning strategies I consider best,
others probably also consider best. Um
others are likely to combine their data
and learning strategies in similar ways
and get similar predictive outcomes. And
those same predictive outputs might
include the same mistakes. And so I
should expect that in by acting in
accordance with the predictions produced
by my best data and learning strategy, I
might compound errors on the same
individuals. And these compounded errors
in a high stakes decision-making regime
could systemically exclude individuals
from
opportunities. So that's the kind of
challenge that I want to address in this
next section of the talk.
And when we think about why it's a moral
concern in the algorithmic fairness
space, we often reach first for bias and
discrimination. So you could say maybe
this matters because uh it's a special
kind of group based bias or uh maybe it
only matters when the individuals who
are excluded primarily belong to the
same socially salient groups.
Um so a challenge to this has been uh in
my past work and also in uh other
people's past work. What happens if the
features that end up being the ones that
underly these correlations are not
necessarily standard group based
characteristics? Um so it could be that
there's some kind of consistent
decision-m based on arbitrary
characteristics.
um what the sort of joking examples that
people use are wearing purple shoelaces
or being born on a particular day of the
month. But you could also imagine this I
think more realistically as some
difficult to interpret uh constellation
of features that maybe is just hard to
find and we don't know what those
features
are. So instead of thinking about for
example biases based on a social
characteristic like gender in a large
model. So instead of cases like uh label
prediction where you have two possible
labels is this a portrait of an
astronaut with the American flag or is
this a photograph of a smiling housewife
in an orange jumpsuit with the American
flag? Uh you might look at these photos
as a as a human being who has seen a
NASA formal po portrait before and say,
"Wow, uh she has the orange, you know,
NASA suit. She has a giant spaceship.
She has a giant space helmet. She has
the official NA NASA badge. Seems like
probably an astronaut, but a model might
say no. It's more likely that she is a
smiling housewife."
Um, but we could also imagine name
artifacts that are more individual or
particular. So, because a lot of large
models are trained on data from the
internet that includes uh forums like
Reddit, uh it turns out that one thing
that people like to do on Reddit is talk
about politicians they don't like. And
it turns out they don't like most
politicians. Uh, and so regardless of
party, if your name is Donald, Bernie,
Bill, Hillary,
uh, Donald, Mitch, Chuck, Barack, any of
these sounding familiar, or did you get
that complete memory wipe that I've been
trying to inquire about recently? Um,
okay. So, all of these names have
negative sentiment associated with them.
And uh you can imagine a certain kind of
training task where if you're doing
sentiment- based analysis of someone who
has one of these names, they get a very
slight negative bump. And if they're a
51% candidate, maybe that bumps them
down to a 50% or a 49% candidate. So
we're not talking about effect sizes
probably large enough to move someone
from a 99% candidate to a 1% candidate.
We're talking about small threshold
effect bumps based on sort of arbitrary
features like
names. And then we might ask this
question if name artifacts have some
negative consequences. For example, if
they cause a candidate who is already a
borderline candidate to consistently
drop below a decision threshold, is it
wrong to concentrate these kinds of
errors on Donald's or Bernie's or Bills
or Alys's or Kevins?
Um, anyone who has those names, come
talk to me afterwards. Uh, okay. So, in
the little flowchart I laid out, we can
imagine a couple different responses to
this. Uh, one is we could say systemic
exclusion shouldn't qualify as bias or
discrimination unless it involves
membership in some kind of socially
salient group. So, we could say, hey,
I'm just not interested in this
Donaldbased problem. you know, call me
when we're uh looking at one of the
seven federally protected categories.
Um, and I think it makes sense to say
this is not a case of bias or
discrimination. And the reason is that
if we look at standard definitions of
bias and discrimination,
uh it seems like both the scope and the
scale of the phenomenon we're
particularly talking about is much more
extensive. So, we're talking about
perpetual subordination of specially
disadvantaged groups whose political
power is severely circumscribed. Doesn't
seem like that's happening to alyses.
Uh, discrimination consists of actions,
practices, or policies that are based on
perceived social group to which they
belong. And the groups must be socially
salient. So here the idea is whatever
your group membership is whether or not
we don't care whether or not it's sort
of metaphysically underlying true of you
if it's something that's perpetually
attributed to you across a bunch of
different spheres of your life. It's
structuring your activities in those
different
spheres. But it doesn't seem like these
artifacts are going to swap between
spheres or at least we don't currently
have any evidence that we should think
they do.
There's also this sense of historicity.
So maybe an action is compounding a
prior injustice. Uh so there has to be
some kind of past injustice that it's
building
on. And this kind of anti-donald semin
sentiment would only count as
discriminatory bias if we had a very
permissive definition of bias.
Interestingly, some of the original uh
people to talk about uh bias and
discrimination in computer systems uh
Bach Friedman and Helen Nissenbomb do
have a very permissive definition of
this kind. uh they are thinking about
systematic and unfair
discrimination and they say it happens
when uh a system unfairly discriminates
if it denies an opportunity or good or
if it assigns any undesirable outcome to
an individual or groups of
individuals on grounds that are
unreasonable or inappropriate. Okay, so
that could be anything. It doesn't have
to have this history. It doesn't have to
be across context.
Uh, so if you think that's plausible,
then I think you would think that
anti-donald sentiment is a
discriminatory bias. Um there's also a
recent paper that takes this stance
talking specifically about novel
algorithmic groups and building on uh
some of our recent work suggesting that
uh al algorithmic groups um should be
thought of as being discriminated
against whenever they're systematically
disadvantaged. I don't find this super
compelling personally because I think
we're losing the characteristic harm of
what discrimination is. I think it makes
more sense to reserve discrimination for
cases that have this you know cross
modal cross context timeextended
character where it is continuous with
socially salient discrimination that
structures interactions of human
beings. Um, and one way to talk about
this is to say, look, if we take one of
these overly permissive definitions,
maybe as Karns and Roth say, we're doing
a kind of fairness gerrymandering. So,
we're picking whoever happens to have
gotten left out and we're saying, well,
it was unfair to them. Uh, but really
that's kind of post talk. It's not
necessarily the case that we should
think of fairness as being
um about whoever just happens to be in
this algorithmic
valley. So we have a few different ways
uh of thinking about why systemic
exclusion is a moral concern. So I'm
going to propose that it's not because
it's a type of discriminatory bias.
However, if you decide you want to think
it is, I think I've given you some
resources to structure how you might
make that
argument. Um, you could say, well, it
matters only if bias and systemic
exclusion stack in some way. So, maybe
there's some kind of bias. Uh, we
already think that's a moral concern in
this setting. Uh, there's a
discriminatory um treatment of two
different groups. And then we might
think, well, it's even worse if the
people in the group that are
experiencing the lesser inclusion rate
also it's concentrated on individuals
within that group and not spread evenly
over that group. I think that's
possible, but being a philosopher, I'm
going to try to argue for what I think
is the hardest and the sort of base case
example and then hope that that uh will
um flow upwards to these other cases
because if I can show that it matters
for any excluded individuals but not
because they're subject to
discriminatory bias, then necessarily it
also matters for individuals who are in
these more specific cases.
Okay. So when is excl systemic exclusion
of individuals because of algorithmic
monoculture
wrong. Now uh there are some
philosophers in the room. There are some
non- philosophers in the room. One
interesting thing about uh attempts to
show that something is wrong is that for
most topics we would expect most moral
theories to agree. So if you say uh
should I kick an innocent puppy just for
fun? uh if your moral theory doesn't end
up saying that's probably wrong, we
would we would have this process of
reflective equilibrium where we would
say well something's wrong with the
moral theory. That's a problem with the
theory that like the sentiment that that
is wrong should be borne out by all
moral theories.
But systemic exclusion of individuals I
think it's an interesting case where you
can see quite a spread of opinions uh
from that I'm extrapolating from
different
theories. So at first I thought okay
maybe systemic exclusion is wrong
because it's unjust. So here we're in
the realm of political philosophy. We're
thinking about what do we owe to each
other? Um, and we might think about this
uh first in terms of democratic
equality. So maybe it's fine for
individuals, companies, organizations to
rank candidates for opportunities
uh by their own metrics. And it's even
fine if some people's rankings are kind
of
arbitrary. But it's when the same
hierarchy you're ranking is used across
the whole sector that it sets rules of
interaction with the domain and
monopolizes access to opportunities. And
when consistent exclusion of people
because of this leads to some kind of
pernicious social hierarchy, that is
when it's
unjust. But notice we have to get to the
status of this sad cat. We have to
actually create a pernicious social
hierarchy. Um so it has to be the case
that the people who are algorithmically
excluded are on the bottom of a social
hierarchy.
And that means this threshold wouldn't
support action on most of the
empirically demonstrated cases of
homogenization. So this is one of the
reasons that I think it's really
important to try to do kind of a cycle
of empirical uh study and then
philosophical theorizing because I think
this would be a much more compelling
talk if I could stand up here and say
there's an algorithmic underclass of
people who will never get any
opportunity across any domain of life.
And so yes, Elizabeth Anderson is
correct that it's unjust to them. But I
don't think we see that, at least not
now. And I, you know, I would need that
to be empirically demonstrated before I
said that to
you. So what instead, what if instead we
think about something like uh wallser?
So we say, hey, there are different
domains, spheres of life, different
kinds of social good, and we think that
these spheres should be separable. So
one thing a theory of justice should do
is that it should decorrelate uh social
goods. So if you lack a certain social
good like healthare it shouldn't mean
that it's impossible for you to get a
loan. And that's one of the roles of the
welfare state is to decorrelate those
things. Okay. So, interestingly, one of
the examples Walzer uses is credit
score, which I would think is kind of an
abstract gateway to other social goods,
not itself a social good, but he uses
it. So, let's run with that a little bit
and say, what if there's this property
of being legible to and correctly judged
by an algorithm? Shouldn't that be
decorated from your ability to access
employment, welfare, healthcare?
Um again I think you have to reach a
pretty high threshold where you were
genuinely shut out of employment
altogether. Uh not just barred from
perhaps your preferred employment
opportunities. So this is also a really
high
threshold. Um so we have a
similar worry on a lot of these justice
based theories that thresholds would not
support action on most cases of systemic
exclusion due to outcome homogenization.
In order to make it work, we would have
to move to like an industrial strength
egalitarianism. So RWS, the a person
that liberal political philosophers
often turn to is not good enough because
he says fair equality of opportunity
shouldn't be contingent on social class
or standing. Um well, it would have to
be equality of opportunity shouldn't be
subject to any morally arbitrary
features. But this means you know uh in
a lot of cases where we currently think
that this it would be too cumbersome or
burdensome for the state to intervene
the state would have to intervene. So if
someone at a local hardware store uh
says I'm going to interview all the
candidates and then I'm going to have a
pool of qualified individuals and then
out of those qualified individuals I'm
just going to pick the one who prefers
to talk about fishing because they're
all qualified and I'm that's going to be
my tiebreaker. that would not be
acceptable because that's a morally
arbitrary
feature. Um, so I think not only would
this sort of industrial strength
egalitarianism require much broader
sweeping social revisions, it would also
doesn't seem to capture the important
features of homogenization due to
monoculture which is that there's
something correlated important about the
correlation across multiple actors.
So instead, I think we should look to
theories like uh contractualism. So here
we're imagining we're all considering
adopting some set of rules or decision
principles. Which ones should we think
are acceptable? Well, Scan brings out
the big red hammer and he says, "A
decision-making principle is acceptable
if no one affected may reasonably reject
it." What is reasonable rejection?
Well, it's reasonable when the burden
imposed on the rejector and is
substantial, but alternative principles
don't impose greater burdens on others.
So imagine you're a nimi and you say, I
don't want this cell tower in my
backyard, move it to someone else's
backyard, but it would impose an equally
great burden on them. We can't just like
shift it around the town. There has to
be some reason why it's uniquely
burdensome to you in order for it to be
shifted.
Um but interestingly the contractualist
also has reason to reject a principle on
which the same small group is
consistently sacrifice for the greater
good. Um and that I think is very
analogous to our case
here. Um instead we should accept a
lottery principle where different
randomly selected groups are chosen in
different counters because there we've
reduced the error burden. we've spread
it over more people and so the
reasonable rejection of the concentrated
errors can be substituted for this
distributed error
model. Interestingly, uh I think this
lottery principle is also shown in the
claims framework. So I'll go through
this a little more quickly, but we could
also imagine we're not now thinking
about a theory of justice. We're
thinking about individual fairness
claims. So, um, you have a claim to
something when you're owed it for
reasons of fairness. And we're going to
say that you have equal claims to the
same good perhaps when you have
equivalent properties. So, for a kidney,
maybe you're the same age and you've
been on the waiting list for the same
amount of time or, you know, morally
equivalent. So, it doesn't matter
whether you've been on the wait list for
four years or 3.8 years. We're going to
say those are roughly
equivalent. Or maybe depending on how we
uh choose morally relevant goods, we
might say, "Hey, just being a human
being is the right qualification." And
so everyone is going to be equally in
the lottery pool. And those all work
from the claims
perspective. And the sources of our
claims could be dessert, that you
deserve it, need or
merit. Um but notice these are a little
bit different from utilities. So
utilities, which is something that I
think we're more comfortable talking
about in the computer science context,
uh are comparable similar to claims. Um
but claims can linger even after the
decision is made. So if I take the
greatest utility action, I'm done. I
don't owe anything to the people who
didn't get the outcome. But claims uh
suggest that I do owe something to the
people who had a claim but who didn't
end up getting the thing. And so uh
they're also different from rights um
because rights aren't something that we
can weigh up whereas claims are
something that we can weigh up. So
claims are essentially comparative. And
interestingly um the claims framework
also suggests that we should allocate
undivided undivisible goods with a
lottery. So I think this idea of using
randomization or a lottery to spread
chances over these different groups that
might otherwise excluded is the right
way to go here. And so what should we
do? We should do something like
that. So how are we gonna do this? Well,
uh, when I first started working with my
awesome collaborators Asian Shomik, uh,
I thought, okay, let's just make a bunch
of models. The models are different. Uh,
and then we use those models to make
different predictions. And it turns out
there is a good way for us to talk about
that and formalize it. We can say, hey,
in fact, there are many models that have
the same accuracy, but different token
predictions. Great. Exciting. And we can
even produce them on purpose. So we can
use the phenomenon of model multiplicity
to intervene at many different places in
the modeling pipeline make different
choices and create different models and
this set of models is sometimes called
the Rashimon set. So Rashimon is a
wonderful movie in which uh the same
event is viewed by different people who
participated in it and they each tell uh
materially conflicting stories that all
fit the final facts. So the same guy was
killed, the same murder weapon was found
in the same place, but different people
didn't. So in a similar way, we could
generate a set of equally wellperforming
models that have different token
features. Uh and we can arrange this in
sort of like philosopher logical
possibility style where we can say the
original model that's going to be our at
that's going to be our home model. We
can have a same accuracy model class. We
can have an equivalent accuracy model
class. So close enough. And then we can
think about all the possible models
regardless of their
accuracy. But what happens if we do
that? Well, um we create them multiply
equally accurate models. We choose
randomly among the models. We have this
possibility of being classified
otherwise. Uh looks good so far. We can
have one model that gets nine out of the
10 qualified candidates but
unfortunately rejects Amara and then we
have a second model that again same
accuracy nine out of the 10 but
unfortunately rejects
Josephine. However
uh it turns out that what we imagine
this uh Rashimon set of models might be
doing is not everything that we hoped
that it would. So if we think about the
Rashimon set of models, no matter how
fancy we get with our tricks, we're only
going to recover a small proportion of
the models that you know God or some
better model generating entity could
have made. So that's our dotted line
within the possible rashimon set and we
might hope that we are then uh getting
equal accuracy allocations
um when we end up running the model
forward and doing our predictions.
But it turns out we don't. Uh it turns
out unfortunately um the allocations we
get not only some of them are worse than
others, some of them are not in an equal
utility allocation set uh but also they
sample pretty unevenly from the set of
possible equal utility
allocations. And so it might be that we
don't get uh this even spread over
outcomes that we wanted. we can get to
equal utility allocations where four out
of the five qualified people are
selected. Um, but it might be that there
are yet more equal utility allocations
that we just never find. Um, and we
aren't going to find with the Rashimon
set that we can create with the data
that we actually
have. So when we tried to do this, we
indeed noted this. So if you look here
at the cumulative proportions of
qualified, so everyone on this graph is
qualified. Uh and so you might say,
okay, uh how likely is that they're
selected? Well, there are some people in
this yellow circle who even in our uh
different ways of creating the rashimon
set never get selected. And that's very
unfortunate.
And one way of thinking about this is
that there are some qualified
individuals who are consistently viewed
as riskier than others even within this
rashimon
set. And so our conclusion here is that
multiple models created from the same
data can fail to evenly sample the space
of equally good
outcomes. And so from an ethical
perspective, we have to stop here and
say, okay, this prompts a question. What
were the good applicants owed? Did we
owe them that they actually got the
thing? Uh, did we owe them that they got
it a certain percentage of the time?
Let's say they applied to 100 jobs. What
percentage do they actually need to move
on to the interview stage? Um, do we owe
them a chance at the good? If so, is it
a proportional chance proportional to
their goodness or just a nonzero
chance? And when do we owe them that
chance? So there's an interesting
discussion uh in a paper called good
reasons for losers. I hope to make uh
such a great paper title someday. Uh
where he argues something I think uh
very extreme which is um if you're
giving someone a chance, it's a chance
that you owe them at the time of
decision. So we would have to pseudo
randomly or perhaps truly randomly in
some way choose between our different
allocations at the time that we're
actually deciding. It couldn't be the
case that we uh have already done this
random allocation because then they
never really had a
chance. Okay.
But I think uh the critique of the
multiple model perspective suggests that
we're not going to get the even
distribution of chances that we wanted
out of the rashimon set anyway. So
instead, what if we just do a lottery?
So we have these likelihoods that we
think people are an appropriate fit for
the good. What if we just randomize
based on those likelihoods? So if you
are uh 79% likely to be good, we give
you 79 lottery tickets in our lottery to
get the actual
outcome. I'm fine with this, but this
makes a lot of people queasy because it
means there are some cases where we give
the 1% candidate the thing and there are
some cases where we don't give the 99%
candidate the thing. So depending on
your tolerance for exploration as
opposed to exploitation, we could also
think about having a quality threshold.
So, we could say, "Hey, we're going to
cut off the extremes. We're always going
to give it to the 99% person. We're
never going to give it to the 1% person,
but there's a big band about the middle
that we should admit we're not that
certain about, and that's where we're
going to run the lottery." Now, this is
a little bit weird because from a
normative perspective, uh, we're saying
that we do have beliefs about the
likelihood of these candidates and we're
just kind of arbitrarily, uh,
thresholding them. So this is what's
called a mixed strategy. Um which
philosophers have some opinions about.
Uh but I think it is a lot more
palatable in a lot of actual decision-m
contexts. And as you can see when
compared with uh the dotted line so just
always giving the stuff to the people
and the straight line running um a pure
lottery it's going to be in the middle.
It is going to reduce outcome
homogenization but not as much.
And finally, we could do something that
does respect our evidence. Uh, and we
could use conformal prediction or
variance. So, we could say, hey, uh, we
could set up the model so that we know
which points the model is most uncertain
about and flip a coin to randomize those
points. And it turns out many of those
points are around the decision threshold
anyway. And then maybe uh we don't have
to lose a lot of accuracy depending on
how many points we do this for but we
can drop outcome homogenization faster
than we lose accuracy. Uh so in summary
shared data algorithms and foundation
models can all create or contribute to
algorithmic monoculture. This
monoculture can homogenize outcomes. uh
and we should consider this to be a
problem when it concentrates an
unreasonable burden of errors or
consistent rejections on individuals
compared to other possible models. And
to address it, each actor in the
ecosystem should randomize their
predictions. And with that, we hope that
we can go from the algorithmic
monoculture to a beautiful field of wild
flowers. Thank you.
[Applause]