Yes. So, I'm very excited uh today to
introduce a speaker, Jennifer Lipinot
Schwarz. Um Jennifer is currently the
senior group lead and head of 4D
cellular physiology at the HHMI's
Genealia Research Campus and her group
focuses on using live cell imaging to
study spatial temporal behavior of
molecules and organels across cells
across live cells. Um but before Janilia
she did her PhD at John's Hopkins um
where she looked at subcellular
localization of lysosal proteins and
then during her posttock at the NIH she
looked at novel dynamic interactions
between molecules and organels and their
structures um specifically the
endoplasmic reticulum and the GGI. Um
and then she established her own lab at
the NIH which has pioneered the use of
GFP fluorescent proteins um for tracking
molecules and structures in live cells.
This is using FRAP techniques um
photoactivatable GFP super resolution
microscopy um to study a variety of
phenomena from protein dynamics to cell
cell fusion um yes so for all these
contributions she's been recognized by
many institutions um so she is the
president of the American society for
cell biology she was an elected member
of the national academy of sciences um
she's an academy of arts and sciences
fellow and uh she was awarded the EB
Wilson medal uh of the American American
Society for Cell Biology just to name a
few of the accolades. Um so with that I
just want to say thank you to Jennifer
for speaking today and uh I'll turn it
over to you. Thank you.
Thank you very much Tara for that really
nice introduction and thank all of you
for joining us today. Um it's very
exciting to be here. Um, I really
resonated with what Todd um spoke about
a couple minutes ago, um, in terms of
we're really being at a pivot point, um,
in, uh, in biology, in science, um,
with, uh, really, uh, I think what we
can all describe as an AI revolution. Um
certainly I've experienced it in my own
world of imaging as a cell biologist. I
will be telling you a little bit about
the way we're trying to incorporate
machine learning and AI into what we're
doing in my presentation today. But I
also want to uh just uh uh draw your
attention to at at
Geneia we really recognize this need for
computational um power in analyzing data
sets. Um so we're hoping you know all of
you who are postocs or uh moving on to
your next career after spending
wonderful time here at Broad and the
Schmidz center please consider um Geneia
because we are basically launching a
10-year huge effort in AI uh all aspects
of AI in terms of experimental
interrogation of um you know various
biological uh pathways uh to structural
work. Okay. So, today I'm going to be
talking about um exploring life
structures across scales through
imaging. And um I want to get right to
the thick of it, which is cells. Cells
are the fundamental um entities,
structures that all life is comprised
of. What's quite remarkable is the
ukareotic cell which as you can see is
this intricately organized system of
many different organels can give rise to
all of the life forms complex life fors
that we have on earth and what's
incredible is that this system is
conserved the internal organization of
the ukareotic cell is conserved across
all kingdoms
kingdoms of ukarotic uh
systems. A confederacy of subcellular
structures um that each have specific
cell activities really define those
membrane bound structures that I just
showed you in that EM image in the prior
slide. Uh this includes organels like
the ER and the gold sheet that are
involved in secrettory activities of
these cells. organels like the endoome
and lysosomes that enable these cells to
take up nutrients and other
macroolelecules from the outside to be
degraded and recycled. Um mitochondria
which are the energy powerhouse of the
cell, the nucleus where DNA replication
and storage has occurred. Perox
peroxomes where um molecules are
detoxified uh and finally this lipid
droplet where fats are stored. All of
these organels are interacting with each
other, communicating with each other.
And if we want to understand life's
programs, we need to understand how
these organels are working in different
contexts. So this is um basically one
attempt to really start digging into the
dynamics of these organels. Maybe if we
had the lights down, it would be great
for you to see some of these movies. But
um what we're doing here is
simultaneously visualizing six of these
organels um uh using a lattice light
sheet multisspectral imaging approach.
Um one of the things that you can see
from this movie is that these organels
are highly dynamic and they are all
interacting with each other in one way
or another. Now because these are this
is a three-dimensional
um movie uh where we have uh very high
res we have basically isotropic
resolution across all of those different
organels. We can come in and map out how
these organels are interacting with each
other uh at different times um across
the the um you know any particular
interval in the and the length of time
of that cell. Um and from that we can
create what what we're described here as
a matrix representation of the organel
interactum. Basically um the extent to
which these organels are interacting
with each other over time. And what's
interesting is that even though these
organels are highly dynamic where you
can see these contact sites um forming
and dissolving um dynamically at steady
state over long periods of time um you
have a conserved type of interactum
among these uh organels. And um those
interactions are playing critical roles
for these organels to communicate not
only lipids but also small metabolites
as well as um uh ions like
calcium. Now we can go from the micron
level which that lattice light sheet um
movie was showing you um to the nano
nanocale um using electron micro u
electron microscope approaches. What
you're looking at here is a whole cell
EM volume across a helila cell where we
are acquiring um we're basically milling
across this cell at four nanometer
slices if you will so we can and then
we're imaging each one of the um regions
that we've milled off um with structure
illumination I'm sorry with scanning
electron microscopy. Um so when you do
that you now start you now have the
ability to basically three-dimensionally
interrogate this the entire cell at the
nanog uh nanoscopic
level. So this is a one cubic micron
region of that heliloc that you just
saw. So it's the center of the cell. Uh
you can see there's the centrial. Um
what we we're looking at is just we're
just scanning through this one micron a
one cubic micron region. Um you can see
all of the individual uh slices
basically that we imaged. Um and if we
then reconstruct all of the objects that
we see in that cubic volume, uh you now
have the ability to divine define many
um bio uh cellular structures including
microtubules, the GI apparatus, the
endoplasmiculum. This is the nuclear
envelope. This is the nucleus. All of
these structures become visible at this
nanoscopic level. Now this was not an
easy task. um each one of the four
nanometer slices is only a a tiny part
of any particular structure. You have to
stitch them all together and that
requires hand annotation. So basically
it took a single person um 7 to 10 days
to reconstruct this one cubic micron of
all of these membranes. uh and the way
they lay out over the over this this
volume. So
that led to an immediate problem. You
know, the cell is actually 7,000 times
this size. If you want to see all of
these organels at this scale of imaging,
um you're going to we estimated a single
person would take you 50 years to do
this type of manual segmentation. So
instead um at Genealia we set up a team
to do this using machine learning. Uh
basically individual um annotators would
go in and annotate small subp parts of
the cytoplasm and then feed that
information uh to a a larger machine
learning um algorithm algorithmic
program which then would um basically
automatically search for the objects
that it had been trained on. Um so
basically as a consequence of that we
could uh really uh reconstruct very
quickly um up in this case up to 32
different structures within this heliloc
and we could compare as a consequence we
could do it with different cell types.
You can compare volumes uh organization
uh the way these organels are contacting
each other across many different cell
types. And currently at Genealia, we're
doing this in much larger volumes, whole
tissues uh from uh various uh organisms
uh to uh look at interrogate cellular
organization um at this nanoscopic scale
across um cells within particular
tissues. Now this all sounds really
cool. Um, but it turns out that when you
look at these images, there are many
structures that are unrecognizable.
Like, what the heck is this? Um, and
there's also hard to find structures.
You know, there should be a structure,
but you don't know what it looks like.
And so, how are you going to find it in
these data sets? And so, that's where,
um, basically we're sort of trying to
push uh, new approaches. Um, so here's
an example where um just of a weird
looking structure that if you were going
through these data sets, you could see,
okay, I don't know what that is. That
doesn't look like a gold sheet. It
doesn't look like a loome. Doesn't look
like an ER. The only way that we have
been able to annotate all of the
structures that I showed you is because
we already know what those structures
look like. We have a hypothesis for what
they look like. This is something we
don't know what it looks like. Um and
the problem with our traditional
supervised uh learning strategy is that
uh the way we go about doing our
analysis is we manually annotate things
that we're interested in uh in a and
these things have to be fairly abundant
in order for the machine learning
program to learn it. Um so basically you
annotate something you're interested in
Eey or mitochondria losses uh and then
you uh use a machine learning to uh
basically interrogate the entire sample
and it will very nicely pull out all of
the objects that look like a
mitochondria or look like an ear. But
you cannot train it uh when you see a
weird object that's infrequently um it's
not abundant. Um so it doesn't you first
I mean you can manually annotate it but
you don't have enough examples of it for
the machine learning to be able to see
it within the system. So the approach
that um we're currently trying to do at
at Janilia is a selfsupervised learning
strategy where instead of um manually
annotating and creating training data
for machine learning algorithm, we're
basically having mach uh basically um
the computer train on the entire data
set. Basically put the entire data set
into its head. That takes a lot of
machine time intensity, but that's
better than having a human trying to uh
do uh do many different objects
simultaneously. But once you have um the
program where it has the entire data set
sort of uh at its fingertips, you can
then query it uh for different objects.
Uh and when you do that, it can pull out
weird looking structures um that are at
very low abundance. Now once you have um
once you've been able to identify where
those structures are across a cell or
across um cells under different
perturbation conditions in this case uh
this structures being generated when we
stress cells um you can then come in and
apply other approaches. In this case um
we're um uh using cryo correlative
electron microscopy to show that this
structure is actually an autofagosome
that has engulfed an ER exit site. Now
this cryo cororlative electron
microscopy is really really important we
think uh for really pushing our
understanding of the organization of
these cells because it's also valuable
for trying to look at the structure of
hard to find structures. One of those
hard to find structures are sites where
all secretatory and membrane proteins
exit the the ER. Um proteins secrettory
membrane proteins are synthesized in the
ER and they exit the ER at very
specialized sites that are created
through this machinery COP 2 coat
machinery. Um and the COP 2 coat in
vitro can create vesicles. So everybody
thought oh well let's look for vesicles.
Um maybe we can see uh uh COP 2 vesicles
in our in these big EM data sets. Not so
easy to find. Um but if you do cryo
cororlative um basically you introduce a
fluorescent probe for a component of
this COP 2 coat which you know is
defining that your exit site. You can
then at the light level image where all
those exit sites are localized in this
cell. And then what you can do and this
is uh we're imaging at cryo
temperatures. So we can now take and
this has been high pressure frozen this
cell. So we can now take this cell and
do our fibsim milling through the entire
cell uh and look at interrogate
individual areas where we have the COP 2
signal. And when we do that, uh, what
you can see, uh, this is, so this is a
little cubic volume here. We're we're
going to go up and down through the
different, um, four nanometer sections,
uh, that we've acquired through scanning
EM. Uh, and here's the spot where we're
getting this, uh, sect 13, uh, SEK 31
signal, I'm sorry, sect 23 signal. And
if we then interrogate that spot uh and
basically stitch together all of the
individual um uh uh images uh we can
reconstruct what these ER exit sites
actually look like and surprise surprise
they are not uh vesicles that are sort
of randomly uh butting off the surface
of the ER they are very discrete
structures this is the endoplasmic
reticulum uh there's a tight neck where
this sect 23 uh uh coat complex is is
operating and then spling out from that
neck are uh is a membrane labyrinth uh
sort of like a grape-like cluster of
membranes uh that have a very
characteristic uh uh diameter of these
uh sort of grapelike tubial extensions
as well as the entire structure. So once
we have knowledge of what this looks
like, we can then go back into our data
sets to be able to find your exit sites
in any cell now that we have the
signature of what this structure looks
like. Okay, in the remaining few minutes
I want to move to the atomic scale. So
we've looked at the micron scale, we've
just looked with EM at the nano scale.
Now we're going to go to the atomic
scale. and how uh imaging is
dramatically improving in this area but
also this is a total area where we
definitely need help through
computational biologists and uh machine
learning. Okay, so this is an archa
cell. Um but like every other cell on
earth it is loaded with these small
little structures uh that we call
ribosomes. So this is just highlighting
um ribosomes uh in a archa cell. Uh but
they are found in every ukareotic cell
on the planet because they are what
drive protein synthesis. So the ribosome
is the core machine of translation. This
is how proteins are being made. Um so
it's a macromolecular complex um that is
comprised of a large subunit a small
subunit uh and it's bringing together
mRNA
um that will be decoded uh and uh
converted into a polyeptide chain um as
a result of recruitment of these tRNAs
that are charged with various amino
acids.
Now, this structure has been studied for
decades in terms of what it looks like
at the atomic scale. What we're going to
try to do is to ask whether we can
actually identify these structures in an
intact cell that's been
cryofen and basically get enough
snapshots of this structure to actually
make a movie of translation at the
atomic scale.
Okay. Now this has at some level been
done from in vitro from um uh uh work
prior work where uh various structures
of the ribosome have been identified um
through single particle averaging. Um
what that has shown us is that the
ribosome indeed undergoes confirmational
changes uh during this elongation cycle.
the cycle for moving the mRNA through
that ribosome to allow a polyeptide to
form. What we want to do is to get a lot
more of these intermediates and stitch
them together to see if we can see a
movie of this
process. So the approach that we're
going to be taking is called
highresolution template matching. And I
want to uh shout out Peter Rickau who uh
was one of the pioneers of this approach
um together with uh Winfred Denk uh and
Niko Guggger at Genealia. Basically what
this approach does is um it uses a
highresolution noise-free template of a
macroolelecule and you search for that
macroolelecule exhaustibly in an image
um that's been acquired with minimal
electron beam exposure.
Now key things here one is we have lots
of highresolution templates I mean the
field is exploding alpha fold you know
millions of templates um let's find them
in a cell can we see these things in a
cell um so this is what this approach is
going to be doing now the the approach
is not dependent on the abundance of a
target or averaging which is what
traditional single particle
cryotomography approaches are using
those approaches. Basically look at
abundant structures, pull them out, and
then do single particle averaging to
look at various states of that
structure. We're not going to be doing
that. Um, we're going to just look at
the all of the structures we can see
using the template. Um, and then
basically we're going to use the high
resolution signal in the noisy images to
gain insight into the structural states
of the molecules. So here's the approach
that we're taking. Um cells are grown on
gold grids. Um they are then
high-pressure frozen. And so you can see
here are individual cells that are on
that grid. Um these are the cells that
are going to be examined. Um and uh
we're going to examine them with a
single image uh on our Creos electron uh
uh uh crym uh system. Now this is a uh
an image from the periphery of the cell
where the cell is about 200 nanometers
thick. So we are viewing everything our
electron beam is moving through moving
through that 200 that entire 200
nanometer section. This is the image
that we get. Okay. So you're going to
say wow what what kind of image is this?
I don't really see much in this image.
which is exactly what I told Peter when
I first saw this. Um, but he said,
"Look, the key thing here is that this
image has information. We have not
destroyed information with the electron
beam." One of the problems with
cryotomography is you're hitting your
sample many many times uh with your
electron beam. Every time that electron
beam moves through this tissue, it
destroys information. So, we have a one
one image we've acquired right here and
we're going to search it for a target.
And the target we're going to be looking
for uh is a ribosome subunit. This is
the large subunit of the ribosome. We're
going to search for it in every or
possible orientation that we can find.
This is what this uh ribosome uh
template would look like in our EM
image. If electron beam is moving
through this, this is what this thing's
going to look like. So, we're going to
uh simulate uh this structure. We're
going to rotate it uh in every
orientation and see if we see any
crossorrelation with anything in our
real image. And sure enough, we get
hits. Uh so that spot right there is
precise in here is where this um this
structure is. Um we are very confident
of that. This is the signal to noise. Um
showing that in this image right here is
this structure. Um now we can do this
across our entire data set. And so what
we're doing here and we can do it not
only for the large subunit of the
ribosome. We can also do it for the the
small subunit spec in in particular the
body and the the head of that small
subunit. So each one of these are
different uh molecular weights as you
can see. Um with that large subunit we
have much better signal to noise because
it's a bigger target. Uh we go down to
the body signal uh small subunit body.
It's um we still see very significant uh
hits signal to noise. The head is a
little bit harder. It's only 350
kilodolans, but we can still get um
signal. Um and we're doing this
independently. Um these are separate
parts of the ribosome that we are trying
to look for. And this is just a decoy
where we just put in a 2000 KD structure
that we know is not in in this cell. Uh
and we don't see any
anything. So this is where all of these
um subunits are localized in that image.
Uh here are all the the uh our peaks of
uh correlation crossorrelation. And if
we fit in uh the position of the large
subunit that we're detecting
independently of the head and the body,
you can see where all of these guys come
together in complete ribosomes. Some of
these ribosomes are not fully assembled
and we can actually see that. Um others
are fully assembled, but we're seeing
all of the ribosomes in this data set.
Okay. Well, what can we do with this?
Well, um, and this is just showing, um,
uh, how these things are arranged. I'm
just going to move very quickly to, um,
you can just correlate it onto the, uh,
image. So, what can we do to this? Well,
during translation,
um, the key, first off, the ribosome is
a machine and the way it works is by
rotation of the large subunit relative
to these small subunits. The small
subunits are swiveling. Large subunit is
rotating. The swivel motion is moving
the transcript forward by one codon
during polyeptide synthesis. Um, so we
want to look at all of the ribosomes
that we've seen. We want to know what
rotation swivel angle of these subunits
each of those ribosomes are in. And
that's what this is showing right here.
So this is a um plot uh where basically
we're looking at um the rotation um
we're we're positioning all of the um
ribosomes in a swivel to rotation um
plot. uh each one of these dots uh to
the far left uh is a individual ribosome
in that data set uh where we can map out
what its swivel angle is relative to its
rotation angle. And we can then fit all
of those ribosomes uh in a in a path. Um
and we're just arbitrarily dividing all
of these guys up into 10 different
states of that path.
um
which reflects the elongation cycle. So
basically we can from the data um
basically look at um the populations of
the ribosomes in each one of these
different states um uh we can also uh
look at their relative abundance um and
we can interrogate what these uh states
are uh during this elongation cycle.
Now some of the interesting things that
have come out of this is um
individual oftent times uh individual
transcripts shown here mRNA transcripts
um have many ribosomes associated with
them. These are called polyomes um that
enables efficient translation of this
mRNA. What we found was that the
ribosomes that are attached to this mRNA
which we call polyomes many of them are
actually in the same state of this
elongation cycle path. Um and uh that
was very very interesting um to see this
uh you can see that there um many of
these adjoining ribosomes are all in the
same uh elongation stage of the
elongation cycle. This is not
um colliding of these ribosomes because
we can actually go in and interrogate
the structure um of these ribosomes that
are neighboring each others that are in
the same uh cycle state. Uh they do not
fit with what has been described from in
vitro studies of ribosome colliding.
We're seeing a very different type of
interface of contact between these
ribosomes. So, what that's led us to
speculate is that these ribosomes
aligned along the mRNA are actually
synchronized in terms of their um their
movement. Much like um if you were on a
rowing team, you have if you're going to
row effectively, you're going to be
synchronized with these motions. And
that's what we think these ribosomes
might be doing. Okay, I only have a
couple more minutes, so I'm going to go
really fast to get to um the movie. Um
but basically uh one of the things you
can do is and this is really important
is you can reconstruct molecules that
are around these ribosomes at different
states of the elongation cycle. And this
is I'll just show you this right here.
Uh this is a uh ribosome that we're
looking Whoops. Um so each one of all of
these structures that you see uh in gray
here uh and that are colorcoded
represent molecules that we have been
able to see associated with these
ribosomes um that we can see at
different states of this cycle. Uh so
this these were not any we we were not
interrogating we're not doing template
matching on these structures. they came
out uh because they were electron
densities that were associated with the
ribosome that we had uh uh identified.
Um and this is just showing we can
actually see uh mRNA we can see the mRNA
tunnel. We can actually see um peight
bases uh in this system uh in terms of
the resolution capacity. Okay. Now I
want to just quickly show you a movie
where we're trying to stitch all of
these guys together.
um we have 41 different ribosome states
that we can fit in this elongation cycle
pathway. And so what we're going to do
is just um we can align them based on
what we know in terms of the ch the
changes in the confirmation of the
ribosome and we can then play it as a
movie and that's what we're doing right
here. Um so we have um this is the large
subunit. These this is the small subunit
the head and the and the body. Uh these
are associated stuff. Um right here
tRNAs uh syntheses that are uh carrying
amino acids into this pocket where a
polyeptide is going to be pulling off
from it. These are other molecules that
are associated uh with the ribosome
during this elongation state. So this
clock right here is just running uh to
show the whole cycle. Um so this is just
different types of motions that we're
seeing. This is 20s RNA that's basically
showing rigid body motion. It's clearly
it's tightly associated with that large
subunit. We can also see um a uh
interbridge protein that's undergoing a
type of bending motion that's never been
seen before. um but we can pull it out
from these data sets because we can
we're basically aligning all of these
ribosomal states uh in a movie. And then
finally we can look at these tRNAs
syntheses as they come in and move um
across uh these code the the
the EPA sites uh for stitching together
uh the polyeptide. So this is just
summarizing um the outlook uh for this
approach as well as other uh
cryotomography approaches. This can be
very much integrated uh together uh with
the system. Um I want to point out that
um I think it's super exciting in terms
of um what what we can do with
structures that are coming out alpha
fold uh other types of structures that
we know um it has the potential to be
used in this type of uh system to be
able to uh more fine-tune the way these
molecules are actually behaving uh
within a cell. So with that, I'm going
to end and thank all the people at
Chanelia who've participated in this. Uh
Peter Rickau, I want to call out again,
is the guy who was um critical for this
high resolution template matching. Um
but uh other people in my lab have been
heavily involved in all of this um
imaging at at these different scales.
Um, none of this would happen uh without
incredible support teams from uh crym to
light microscopy uh to computer support
as well as um other uh group leader uh
uh uh interactions at Genealia. Thank
you very much.
All right, I think Oh, yes. Okay, we
have time for one question maybe. Well,
I'm going to really use it as a long
question. First of all, this was a a
really fabulous talk and a great way to
open uh this meeting. Very inspiring.
What can be done now? You know, in in an
attempt to show how cool everything is.
I'm being the, you know, forever skeptic
are always like how accurate is this?
Does it know when it go fails? Where
does it fails? And again, to the this
wonderful audience of brilliant trainees
behind me, where do you need them? Okay.
Okay. So, I'll tell you exactly where we
need you. So, you know, you would think
that there's a we have a lot of X-ray
crystalallography structures. Um,
they've been purified, crystallized. Um,
if you take those structures and you try
to find them in our data set, most of
them we cannot find. What does that tell
us? it tells us that structure is not
the structure that is the abundant form
in this intact cell. Um so the issue is
how do we go about trying to um use the
information from these cryo images and
alpha fold is the same. Alpha fold has
lots of parts of it that you're not
going to see here. The issue is can we
um can we find parts of these structures
that we are pretty confident are going
to be stable are going to be static and
then what we can do is we can actually
just use that as our template forget the
rest of the the protein let's find that
as a template and as I showed just
quickly go I'll just quickly go back
here sorry because this is pretty
significant um this is um we've done
this Here this is the ribosome. Okay,
the large subun of the ribosome. If we
scale it down to only 700 kilodolans, we
basically shaved off um a huge part of
this ribosome and we're going to search
for it within our sample. We can find it
through its we find it and then we look
at the reconstructed density. We get the
ribosome. Uh and we can do this down to
uh this is this right here is where
we've got a um a 700 KD target where
we're successfully doing that. Uh in
comparison cryotomography and spa
approaches you don't get anywhere near
um that in terms of identifying um the
structure within an intact cell. So this
we really need help from people who can
sort of help us. Um well first the
compute time is huge. Um we need we need
to figure out ways to very make this
refined to do the searching uh took us
two months to search um pulling out
those ribosomes in just one simple case.
Um so having better you know
computational sort of uh uh pairing etc
could speed this up. Uh but also um you
know being able to understand what these
structure how to deal with these
structures I think would be really
important. Great
question.
Okay, great. Thank you. So,
unfortunately, we will just do the one
question and I'll pass it over to
Sebastiano to introduce our next
speaker.
[Applause]