And so from last time uh we covered the
ETO formula for the single case
where
we have the integral
or sorry the function of a brownie in
motion
uh function of one variable. And
importantly um with this function of a
one variable, we get that the
differential of the function is equal to
the first derivative of the function
evaluated at the Brownian motion plus a
half the second derivative
uh of the function. And so this is Eto's
formula.
And when we uh apply eto's formula in
one dimension um we can consider
uh defining the anti-derivative
of the function f
and that's capital f. And so eto's
formula gives us this expression for the
integral of f of bs dbs. So this is a
very uh useful uh way to compute uh eto
integrals. Now when we go to functions
of two variables
so case two we're going to have a
function of time
and bt say um when we want to evaluate
this function of time and space as a
function of brownie motion then our
eto's formula
is expressed this way we basically have
the partials of little f with respect to
t and with respect to x and then a
second order term the second partial of
f with respect to x. So this is uh how
eto's formula generalizes.
Now what's really convenient to
highlight is that with eto's formula we
get this top formula for the change in
value of f of tx. So we have um this
theorem
uh which is for how f of bt
changes from an initial condition and in
looking at this expression it's a sum of
two terms. Okay, the first term is an
integral with respect to time ds
and so that function will be sort of
non-random on paths. The second term is
the integral of the partial of f with
respect to x dBs and that will be uh
that that will be random depending on
dbs. So if we have a uh this formula for
the increment then um we basically have
a constant term plus an integral of
brownie in motion which has mean zero as
a random variable. But if the term
that's in the integrant
over time, if that's equal to zero,
then this function f will be a
martingale.
So importantly in quantitative finance
uh we often are interested in solving
for values of functions where the
functions are the price or value of a
derivative over time. And if we can
express it sort of in the right
framework uh where the price function
follows a martingale
then it will satisfy this PTE condition.
Now the notion of the value of some
derivative contract or asset following a
martingale over time
means that it has a constant sort of
expected value over time. So we don't
have sort of the natural growth in value
according to the risk-free rate. So to
set this up, we'll need to normalize the
prices discounted to the present value.
So that comes into play in different
applications.
All right. Well, um there are some
examples of ETO's formula applying it
and with the brownie in motion with
drift. We went through that last time.
And then finally in this section um I
want to sort of highlight how geometric
brownian motion is represented in terms
of the stochastic differential equation
as given here. So dpt is equal to pt mu
ddt plus pt sigma dpt dbt.
Um and importantly
we basically have
these factors PT on both sides which
could be divided in both sides. So we
might think that we're working with the
derivative or differential of the log of
the price. Uh but it's we're it's a
little bit different. Um so with this uh
geometric brownie in motion if we apply
eto's lema
to the function log of pt so if we think
of log of pt is equal to g
of pt
then the partial of g with respect to p
is simply one over t the partial of G
with respect to T is zero and the second
partial of G with respect to P um is - 1
over P^2.
So it's lema gives us that the
differential of log p is the sum of two
terms one that's times dt the other
that's times sigma db dbt
and so um log price
is going to follow a generalized vener
process with a drift rate given by mu
minus sigma squ over two and variance
rate equal to sigma
Now what's important about this
result is that the drift rate
changes from mu to mu minus sigma^ 2 /
2.
Um so the uh basically the drift rate on
the log scale um sort of has a drag due
to the uh quadratic variation.
And if we consider
uh normalizing the uh log return well
actually not normalizing but we look at
an increment of the log return that's
normally distributed
and then um
let's see if we consider uh I guess
looking at what the conditional
distribution is of log pt it's given by
this brownie in motion which gives
normally distributed log values with a
particular mean mu star and variance
sigma star. Um and so the expectation of
our price
at some time point capital t given the
value at time little t. It'll be a
lognormal random variable with
expectation equal to
the initial price pt p sub little t
times the exponential
of uh mu * t minus t. There should be an
e here which um is in that factor. So,
so despite there being sort of a drag on
the drift
um the expectation of the exponential
of the log
doesn't have that drag due to drift. It
actually has the mean uh log return um
in that in that factor. And with uh logn
normal random variables we have formulas
for the mean and variance which we
covered actually in the first couple of
lectures.
Now interestingly um let's see if we
think about just what kinds of results
happen with values of mu and sigma that
we might expect to see in financial
markets. Um here's an example where we
consider um a drift rate mu of.3
per year
a
time period for obser uh the log normal
return of 1/ half year from time little
t to capital t and an annualized
volatility of 04 or 40%. So this is
perhaps reasonable for some moderately
uh risky uh stocks that have a modest
return uh expectation of sort of 30% per
year and a volatility rate of 40% per
year. And when we look compute the
expectation of the price,
it equals the initial price PT * 1.1618.
Now that 1.1618
says that we expect the price to
increase by about 16%.
And if we think of a half year and a
drift rate of.3,
we might have thought it would be 15%.
If we didn't, you know, follow through
the details. So it's it's a bit higher
return. And similarly for the uh
volatility or standard deviation of this
price, it turns out that the volatility
of the or variance of the price at time
capital T is
335 squared
times the square of PT. So the variance
is also a bit higher than you might
expect if you just naively interpreted
the mu and sigma as appropriate
annualized values.
Now with this result we can actually
uh compute the sort of continuously
compounded percent return of a geometric
brownie in motion. So we can look at the
change in value from time little t to
capital t.
The log of that ratio is the difference
in logs
and divide that by the length of the
period capital t minus t and we get the
basically the annualized rate of return
for the geometric brownie in motion. And
what that
rate of return as a random variable is
is normal with mean mu - a half sigma^ 2
and variance sigma^ 2 over t minus t. So
with this
what's
significant or important is that the
sort of rate of return
over long periods of time
converges to a constant average rate and
the variance about that average rate is
going to zero as the time into the
future continues.
So this is an important property of
geometric brownie motion that the
growth of the uh of the process
uh basically grows at a constant rate
with some variability but that
variability
goes to zero as we consider very very
long periods. So um let's see.
So here uh let's say I have a simulation
of Brownian motion um where we consider
the same mu and sigma as the previous
slides and we consider a time period of
capital t equal to four years and we
define increments uh on that interval um
and look at basically brownie in motion
with the appropriate
mu and sigma then geometric brownian
motion which is the exponential
of that brownian motion and then the log
returns. So let's take a look at what we
have. Um
so so
here's some simulated paths of brownie
in motion with drift with those mu and
sigma parameters.
And importantly, we have sort of the
mean return as a function of time or the
mean value as a function of time of the
brownie in motion being given by the
blue line. And then plus or minus uh
sort of two standard deviations is given
by the red uh curves.
And if we simulate not five but say 50
paths, this is what this Brownian motion
looks like.
Um
and if we I guess before doing this I'd
like everyone to just think about how is
this
set of paths going to transform when we
take the exponential of them. So the
basically the exponential of Brownian
motion with constant drift and variance.
Well, here's the geometric brownie in
motion
and uh what I've done is I've drawn the
same sort of blue line and the same red
lines as the for the Brownian motion and
how that translates to the exponential
scale. And what's rather striking here
is that there are paths out of 50 that
really have extraordinary performance.
And so
you're basically growing in value from
by a factor of 10 or an order of 10
basically to an order of 20 um on the
exponential scale. And so what I think
is an interesting takeaway from this is
that if we have a simple brownie in
motion process defining the sort of log
price processes, then with reasonably
modest drift and volatility parameters,
there can be some realizations
that have phenomenal returns. And so
when you look at the price returns of
stocks, often our attention gravitates
towards those that have extraordinary
returns sort of like Nvidia or Tesla say
and over some periods in the past, maybe
not so much recently, but um these
extraordinary returns over a number of
years is actually
consistent with the possibility of sort
of geometric brownie motion models
underlying those. Now if we look at uh
the average log return
we get this graph for these 50 paths
just uh doing the time series of uh
volatilities
of the or sorry of uh returns um average
returns over across each of the paths.
And if we look at zooming in on that
path, this is the uh
space or it's an illustration of the
realizations of the average returns over
time. So over short periods we can
expect
very different
return magnitudes perhaps uh but as the
time period for measuring returns uh
increases it stabilizes to uh vary about
this uh constant level.
All right
so let's go back here. Um
all right so um with stochastic calculus
uh there are many sort of follow-on
topics. We're going to focus today on
stochastic differential equations. Um
but it's important to know that
stochastic calculus and differential
equations apply to other problems such
as population growth um and uh filtering
problems. um optimal stopping problems
and so uh you know it's a very sort of
rich set of applications of of the
theory.
So let's go to stochcastic differential
equations.
Um okay these slides are a bit dense uh
but I've colorcoded sort of some of the
pieces so we can go through it more
slowly. Um so let's go through the
derivation of the black scholes
differential equation. Now you've
already seen this a few times in the
class from a guest lecture and from
Vicil's lecture but I think it bears
repeating here. Um if we have a an asset
price that follows geometric brownie in
motion.
So dpt
is equal to mu
pt mud dt plus pt sigma u dbt. Then
let's consider the price of a derivative
that's contingent on pt
and as a motivating example say a call
option but we could consider arbitrary
options or derivatives.
And if we apply eto's lema to the price
function gt
then eto's lema gives us this sum of two
terms
dt times the partial of g with respect
to p mu pt partial of g with respect to
dt the second partial of g with respect
to p times a half time sigma^ 2 pt ^ 2
Um and then finally this partial of G
with respect to P times sigma PT DBT.
Now if we think about discretizing
the price dynamics
of the stock or the asset as well as the
derivative then we can say okay the
change or increment in PT is a mean
growth rate times delta t plus sigma pt
delta bt. So there's a random term and a
deterministic term given time little t.
And if we do the same for the increment
of the derivative,
we then basically substitute into dg uh
delta t's and delta b's. So we get the
same constant factor times delta t plus
dg dp times sigma pt delta bt.
And the uh sort of brilliant argument
for solving for the uh
option price or derivative price is to
consider constructing a portfolio
VT that eliminates dependence on the
Brownian motion.
So if we eliminate dependence on the
Brownian motion then we basically have a
deterministic
price function for the portfolio.
So one way of doing this is to say let
us short one derivative.
So minus GT.
If we sell the derivative at price GT,
we receive uh GT dollars
and then um the uh we're going to add to
that a number of shares of the asset
given by DGP.
So if we basically take minus1 times
this plus the DGDP times the asset then
the increment
of value
of this portfolio
is simply
deltat t times this factor.
And we've cancelled out
the terms in green when multiplied by
minus1 for the derivative or uh dgdp for
the asset. So we end up getting a
portfolio whose change in value depends
just on this
bracketed term here with no
brownie in motion increment involved.
And so having eliminated
the sort of risk in the portfolio,
arbitrage arguments
say that VT must be risk-f free
and as a risk-free asset equivalent, it
should earn the riskless interest rate.
So our change in value of this portfolio
is simply the initial value times the
rate of return of the riskless asset
over the period deltat t. And so what we
can do then is equate the two
expressions for what the increment in vt
should be.
If it's riskless, here's the right hand
side. And according to our uh ETO's
formulas, the portfolio has a
incremented value given by this factor
of delta t. So if we
eliminate delta t from both sides, we
get this formula
which is called the blacksholes
differential equation. Now what's really
significant is that at least when one
studies blacksholes theory in finance
classes
um one thinks of call options and
deriving their price or put options
through put call parody. Um what's
really important here is that this black
shell's differential equation applies
for those vanilla options
but also for any contingent claim sort
of derivative
where the derivative where where the the
financial derivative GT
uh basically depends upon um the value
of the underlying asset. that.
So we have GT which is a contingent
claim
um and we assume
that GT
is equal to some function f of pt and t.
So we assume that the derivative
depends only on the current level of the
asset and the current time. Yes.
>> So they won a Nobel Prize for it, right?
What what part of the paper was like the
Nobel Prize winning? Was it like the
right? Um I it it really was the uh sort
of extensions of the initial uh papers
to handle sort of uh modeling
derivatives
under arbit no arbitrage assumptions.
And so the the basic theory sort of
extends
amazingly you know to a broad range of
applications.
And um so yeah, I the initial papers
were rather
impressive in terms of solving these uh
pricing problems using
uh
analysis basically. Um and so the
initial papers were really quite
mathematical.
Um and since then uh arguments uh and
developments have been made that make it
more straightforward and what we're
showing here is essentially the uh
benefits from from those later
developments.
>> Yes.
>> Um every time
changing what the portfolio is.
>> I'm sorry. Can you say that?
>> Like the amount of the asset changes
over time.
>> Yes. Um, so then he's like not seeing
why the the value of portfolio is like
BT like is it the amount of PT has
changed and it's going to get bought or
sold some of it or should be that cash
alongside it that tracks what?
>> Well, okay. I guess this this equation
should be um interpreted in terms of
just infiniteesimal increments delta t.
And as you point out as
time evolves the value of the contract
evolves the uh
derivatives partial derivatives of the
asset with respect to time those are not
constant as well. So as as the uh
process increments those will also
change. So it's this is
a a simplification I guess of the
argument. But if we're looking at sort
of what properties must hold in the
infiniteesmal time range then this is
exact.
But okay.
>> Yeah.
Like why can we always say that like
that term after
>> Oh, why can we say that this equals this
term?
>> Okay, I'm just just repeat the question.
So like the expression for DG at the top
like how like
all
>> okay you're saying that the VT equaling
minus GT plus okay that's um going to be
the initial
value of the portfolio at time little t.
So at time little t
we are
combining a short
uh derivative claim
>> ignore what happens
>> exactly we ignore what happens before
and and but this highlights in a good
way you know it's a good question that
when t evolves
or the time involves past time little t
then the partial of g with respect to p
at that future time point will not
necessarily
um equal this. And in order to have a
portfolio that eliminates the Brownie in
motion term, one would need to adjust
the number of shares in the uh asset. So
if we go back to
this argument here where we sell short
one derivative and buy this many shares
at time little t. This cancels out the
brownie motion. Then for increments of
time t or time after t, we still are
short the derivative, but we may need to
adjust the number of shares of the asset
to buy to hedge that derivative. And
that's where delta hedging comes into
play.
>> That expression doesn't mean like we're
not assuming that we've done this
through time.
>> No, not at all. Not at all. Yeah. And
and it's sort of helpful just to see
okay
if at any arbitrary time t you want to
consider buying the or selling the
derivative valuing the derivative how
should that be valued? Great. Okay. So,
so what's important uh with this uh
blacksholes
partial differential equation is that
there are different boundary conditions
that vary by the derivative
that we are working with. And so with
call options we have basically the final
value at time capital t the maturity of
the option is given by the hockey stick
function of pt minus k if that's greater
than zero or zero. And similarly for the
put option it has this this terminal uh
value. Now um what's what's as I said
very powerful about this theory is that
um the partial differential equation the
blacksholes partial differential
equation is satisfied by any derivative
so long as there's no arbitrage in the
market
um and so with different
derivatives
uh contracts there will be different
boundary conditions on those.
So what we now want to do is figure out
how to solve these partial differential
equations. And what we're going to do is
go through the uh diffusion equation.
And it turns out that
the black shaw's partial differential
equation can be transformed into this
diffusion equation by changing the scale
of time, reversing time and doing some
other normalizations.
Um so so this diffusion equation is very
fundamental to solving the blacksholes
partial differential equations and it's
sort of the simplest form of this second
order partial differential equation that
we can uh study and understand its
solutions. So the heat equation
um is a an equation that is satisfied by
um a function u if the partial of u with
respect to t is equal to lambda times
the second partial of u with respect to
x2. So this is the heat equation.
Okay. So,
and um
we're going to give an example here
which is
uh very important and technical. But in
terms of what kinds of functions satisfy
this diffusion equation, we actually
went through
looking at um
the density
um
of a Gaussian distribution
which is equal to 1 / 2 pi
roo P E - one2
X^2 / T.
So if we think of a Gaussian density
which basically is a bell-shaped curve
around zero with some standard deviation
here
given by sort of one. Um
this would be the density perhaps for
t = 1.
The density function and this is the
density of a brownian motion starting at
time zero ending at time t. And if we
consider
increasing time
then the change in P.
So P subt
is equal to lambda * P subXX.
Um
and so the change over time is
proportional to the curvature of the
density. And so if you look back in the
course notes, course materials, we sort
of looked at how the density of Brownian
motion over time it drops where there's
strong negative curvature and it rises
where there's positive curvature and so
we basically get sort of flatter curves
as time increases. So, so the normal
density function follows this heat
equation.
And what we're going to see is that
functions that follow the heat equation
can actually be represented as linear
combinations of these Gaussian
densities.
So the special case of the Gaussian
density is in a sense very very general
in terms of defining solutions to the
heat equation.
So let's consider
um
I guess how the heat equation is often
set up. It says okay let's consider the
temperature in a long thin bar of
material that's perfectly insulated. So
temperature only varies with distance
along the bar at time t. So we have um
the uh
so we have uh so mu of xt is um is the
value of the temperature over over time.
Um and uh
if we consider an initial value
for
the heat in the bar given by u not of x
um then uh what we want to do is solve
for how that heat function changes.
And so some really neat uh sort of
properties to
use are similar properties to what we
have when we're trying to solve for
ordinary differential equations.
So
first observation is suppose we have two
solutions
u1 and u2 then the sum of those is going
to also be a solution. So solutions are
linear
and if we have
a collection of solutions indexed by
little s
um we can consider
taking a weighted sum of those
per an integral and this will also be a
solution.
So the linear
uh linearity of the solution spaces sort
of extends to this integral
of solutions index bys also being a
solution
let's see
okay so um
the simplest initial value
problem
is to consider this u function to be a
direct delta function at x= 0.
So,
so u of x0
equaling the uh
direct delta
direct delta function
at uh t equals z.
Um
and
if we consider this
function which is essentially the PDF of
a normal
with mean zero
and variance 2 lambda t. Then this
density function is um
turns out to h solve the heat or satisfy
the heat equation but it also satisfies
the initial condition where when we let
t go to zero then it equals the direct
delta function. So so what's the direct
delta function? It's equal to zero
for um
it equals zero for x not equal to zero
and it equals um
and the integral of u of x0
dx is equal to 1.
So it's a function that's positive
but has weight under the integral equal
to one. So this is a rather abstract
kind of function to work with. And uh
actually I don't know if
is anyone here familiar with Paul Durac?
there's a great he he was a physicist at
uh Cambridge University
and if you're familiar with I guess
Schroinger
and uh
other physicists he's like number three
or four in the list of top physicists at
the time and um he came up with this
direct delta function as something worth
working with. So it's in a sense an
imaginary function.
It's basically the limit of
this normal density function as
lambda or as t goes goes to zero. So it
becomes totally concentrated at zero.
So um so with this function u delta we
have this uh particular uh
u function satisfying the heat equation
with that initial condition. Now
if we want to generalize from
this
initial function uh or the direct sort
of delta function at zero. Suppose we
consider wanting
to solve where the initial conditions
are given by a function u knot of x. So
in this discussion we can think of you
not of
x the initial value
being some arbitrary known function.
So it's like the boundary conditions of
this function at time zero.
And if we integrate
our
u not function
with the direct delta function evaluated
at x - s
then we simply get back this you not
function at x.
So the direct delta function allows us
to pull out
in an integral
um the uh you not function itself. So
there's like an identity uh relationship
between you not and this transform of
you not with the direct delta function.
Now if we uh consider
different
solutions.
We can
index
solutions to this heat equation by uh
delta
uh or or by s rather.
And then we can integrate this u delta
function with respect to the factor u
not of s and we get this formula for u
of xt. So, so for any initial condition
function u not of s
this integral
will in fact give us the solution
function u whose initial value u of x0
equals u kn. And so for in order for
this to work, we need to have the
integrals existing.
And if we have uh
if the integrals exist and we can take
partial derivatives sort of inside the
integral sign then we end up getting the
partial of u with respect to t is the
integral of the partial of u delta with
respect to dt. That's the only part that
depends on t. And similarly the partial
with respect to x second partial we can
take that under the integral sign and
get this uh expression here. So if this
holds then we have this function
satisfying the heat equation. Now under
what conditions can we differentiate
integrals underneath the integral sign?
And if you remember from calculus
with real calculus how that works.
>> Yes.
When does US converges? when it
converges. Well, the uh
let's see
okay well ux of t will exist
if sort of you knot is sufficiently
smooth
and um
so if the initial conditions are
sufficiently smooth then they're first
derivatives and second derivatives are
bounded and so these integrals are
bounded and we're and they're abs
absolutely integraable and so we're able
to take derivatives sort of underneath
the integral sign. So um so when you
have sort of unbounded functions you not
um that maybe are sufficiently smooth
then one can take limits as sort of the
bound on that function increases and if
those limits exist then these solutions
apply. But what's what's important here
is to see that
we have this u knot of x is equal to
this sum of the direct deltas
multiplied by
you not of s value. So it's a weighted
sum of direct delta and um the uh
so the equation the equation for the sum
of these uh or integral of those
weighted by u you not of s um is given
by this expression here. Now when we can
differentiate underneath the integral
sign then basically um the values of
the or the u function is the
can be represented as um in a tailaylor
series with uh the terms in the
tailaylor series corresponding to these
d differentials and they each of those
satisfy the heat equation alone.
Okay. So let's see how this works with
where you not is an indicator function.
Um
so we're thinking of
let's see let me just write here.
So,
so let's see. For this description, I I
want to um
actually think about
ultimately a Brownian motion process XT
that starts at zero.
And so we have different paths,
possible paths for this brown in motion
process.
And um
we're going to be interested in
basically an indicator
for
the path line between the intervals A
and B.
So let's consider
a uh a you not function for the initial
condition to be the indicator of
um whether a process lies between a and
b. So there will be some paths that
start with the indicator being one and
others with the indicator being equal to
zero.
And
it turns out that the expectation
of you not the indicator function with
respect to this Gaussian density is
simply the probability of lying between
a and b.
So u of xt as defined in the top is
simply the expectation
of the indicator function which is the
probability of lying between a and b
and we can solve for these this
probability in terms of the cumulative
normal
cdf standard normal evaluated at the
upper limit minus the mean divided by
the standard standard deviation
minus the CDF at the lower limit minus
the mean divided by the standard
deviation. So this u of xt which is the
difference of two functions of gaussian
uh densities integrals of them um is a
solution to this uh problem.
So um so now in the next slide um
whoops okay so that's that solution now
um
all right so um so the next uh set of
concepts we want to introduce you to are
solving these equations using properties
of similarity and invariance
And so
we're going to be considering changes in
the time and space variables. So here we
have time variable and here we have the
space variable with Brownian motions.
And so what if we were to rescale time
to a tow
which is equal to alpha t
and we were to rescale x
to a variable y which is equal to some
beta x.
So we're just changing the units of time
and the units of uh space in a constant
way. Well, if we
consider
a v function which equals the u
function.
Then um
we basically
can map u into v
by redefining u in terms of y. and uh
um
sorry u in terms of y and u in terms of
toao. And so if we apply the chain rule
to
utt
[Music]
and if we apply the chain rule to the
partial of u with respect to x we get
beta v y and the second partial of u
with respect to u y is uh beta^ 2 v y.
And so we end up getting our initial
heat equation in x and t to be this
equation in terms of toao and y.
And if
alpha
equals
beta squared. So we could arbitrarily if
we sort of knew the um if we have if
we're free to choose alpha and beta
arbitrarily we could choose alpha equal
to beta squared and we then get va is
equal to lambda vy.
So this
is a heat equation
in terms of variables towo and y
and um
this must solve the original problem if
we substitute back. So we can think of
looking for solutions
that are functions that are invariant
under rescaling time and rescaling the
space.
So we must have that u of xt is equal to
u of root alpha x and alpha t. If we
consider these this particular
transformation
now with the choice of alpha and beta
those are arbitrary.
We can choose alpha
equal to 1 / t
and then that means our u of xt is equal
to u of x over roo t and 1 which is
a function just of x over root t. So we
have a transformation of our original
scales to a problem where our solution
function V um basically or our solution
function U has this form and so it's a
function just of one variable.
And so when this is a function of one
variable, if we substitute that into the
heat equation,
we get the derivative of h with respect
to t on the left hand side is equal to
lambda times the partial of h with
respect to x second partial on the right
hand side. So those are easily computed
to give that top equation.
And then we can say well let's stop
carrying around x over root t
everywhere. Let's just use y / roo
t as our variable of interest. And we
get h prime of y * y /2= lambda hp prime
which
is given by this last equation here. Now
this
second derivative of h / the first
derivative of h is equal to the
derivative of the log of the first
derivative.
So it's one over the first derivative
times the derivative of the first
derivative.
So we have that the derivative of the
log
of the derivative of h is equal to minus
lambda over 2 y. And we just integrate
both sides to get the solution for h
prime is just a constant times the
exponential
of the integral of this
which is y^2 over 4 lambda minus y^2
over 4 lambda in the exponent. And then
we integrate this again
to get a solution for h of y. And
it turns out that we're basically
integrating
a Gaussian
density function.
This is proportional to a Gaussian
density. So it's anti-derivative is a or
one anti-derivative is actually the
cumulative normal uh standard normal
valued at y / 2 2 lambda. So with
this we can substitute in our value for
y
back in terms of x and we get this
formula here for what the
uh u function is. Now with all of this
development we sort of have a formula
for what u is over the entire time
domain. But at time zero, it's the
initial condition. And so the initial
condition is the limit of this f
function as t goes to zero. And so when
uh when x is negative, this goes to
minus infinity.
And so we get zero for the cumulative
distribution function. when x is less
than zero. When x is greater than zero,
this goes to plus infinity. So we get
one. And
if x equals zero, then it's always equal
to a half. So we end up having this
function
uh which uh corresponds to the initial
conditions.
um and uh
this is the solution uh of the heat
equation when the initial condition is
given by this function. So let's see
let's see if we want um
well let let me just write as a function
of x I guess um
the function at zero
um
and then it's 12
and then it's one here. So this is
the function u of x0 for this case.
Now if we um
consider uh different linear
combinations of
this solution, we can actually consider
taking instead of
u of x0 equaling this, we can consider
u of x
um
corresponding to f of x - a over 2
2 lambda t.
And so this basic these first two
bullets correspond to shifting this u of
x0
to a values a and b
and then with other one b
let's see
sorry the uh
so at a we have the same and then at b
we have the same of zero up to b and
then a half at b and then one beyond. So
we basically have sort of two step
functions
centered
where where the steps are at x= a and at
x= b.
And so if we cons both both of these u
functions will satisfy the heat
equation. And uh if we consider the
difference of the two functions
that will also satisfy the heat
equation. And so if we look at the
difference in the initial conditions for
these two
solutions, we basically have the
indicator of being between A and B.
So one function for B you know is one
forever and then the function for A is
uh is one up to uh
or sorry
both functions are equal to one when X
is greater than B in which case we get
zero and otherwise we get uh one when a
is between X and B and a half otherwise.
All right. So, so what we end up having
is uh for any initial conditions
that are representable
as a step function or a sum of step
functions. We can get a solution in this
way. So for our initial conditions
you not we can basically
use limits of these step functions to
approximate any uh initial condition.
All right. Well, with um
stochastic differential equations that
we want to solve,
um we consider generalizations
um
of the drift and volatility parameters
of the process. And so at the top here
is or the general uh a general
generalization of simple geometric
brownian motion where the drift and the
volatilities depend upon time as well as
the level of the process x. And so what
we want to be able to do is understand
when solutions to these uh differential
equations exist. And there are
conditions that
guarantee solutions. One of them is a
lip shit's condition which says that the
change in the mu function
with at a fixed time t
uh
for different values of x and y
plus the change in the volatility for
the same t with different x's and y's
that those are bounded by some constant
times the difference between x and y.
And if we have
um the uh so so this is a sort of space
time condition. And let's see with the
spatial uh growth condition we also want
the sort of magnitude of the drift term
plus the magnitude of the squared
volatility term to be bounded uh by 1 +
the square of the x values. So what we
have here are conditions for the drift
not getting too wild and the volatility
not getting too wild in order for there
to be solutions to this.
And um let's see with uh
a really important theorem that we won't
get into but which are dealt with in
advanced books on stochcastic calculus
deal with the uh existence
and uniqueness of solutions to these uh
stochastic differential equations. And
so if we consider two processes XT and
YT that are both
solutions to the stochastic differential
equation, then subject to the conditions
that we
indicated,
the two solutions are actually equal to
each other almost everywhere. So we
don't get different limits or different
solutions um to the equations.
So they're essentially unique and
essentially means that with probability
one
the paths are the same.
Now um in solving these stochastic
differential equations um a method for
solving these that turns out to be very
useful is a method called coefficient
matching. And so
let's just illustrate coefficient
matching for geometric brownie motion.
So here's the equation differential
equation for um geometric brownie
motion.
And suppose we have a solution
that's some function of time and the
underlying brownie in motion.
Let's apply the uh eto's formula
to x of t
and we get dx of t is equal to this
expression dt plus this expression dbt.
And so um the uh basically this dx of t
is applying the chain rule to f of t and
bt.
And
we can then say well let's match mux oft
with this
red term here
and match sigma x of t the coefficient
of dbt with df dx.
And if we do that well the first or the
second equation there sigma f equals dfd
dx
gives a solution of
f equaling the exponential sigma x plus
g of t.
So um
so this um so this first equation muf
equals um okay or sorry the second
equation sigma fdf dx
um is equal to uh
uh
let me just write that
Okay. So we have
we have sigma f is equal to df by dx.
And so we get sigma is equal to df by dx
over f.
And so um this is equal to d by dx of
log of f ofx.
So f ofx is going to be the exponential
of the integral of sigma with respect to
x.
And the g of t function will just be an
arbitrary constant of that
equation. And then if we substitute this
for formula for f into the first
equation,
we get this differential equation for f.
And um
with this differential equation for f,
mufals g prime f plus sigma square over
2f. Notice that f is a constant factor
in each of those terms. So we can
eliminate that constant factor or term
the same term and we get g prime is
equal to mu minus sigma^ 2 / 2.
So with that we end up getting a
solution for f which is the initial
value x knot time the exponential sigma
x plus this
factor times little t and that factor is
the uh adjusted drift of the uh uh
geometric brownian motion. So we get
that um we basically get our solution
for uh
geometric brownian motion coming out
from that differential equation. Now an
interesting paradox
is that the drift term
is this factor
and the variance is sigma t. Our
standard deviation is sigma t for the
value of a geometric brownie in motion
process.
But if our drift parameter is smaller
than sigma squar over two then this mu
star is going to be negative.
And so
if we have a
Brownian motion process, a geometric
brownian motion process where the on the
log scale the drift is negative, then
this is going on the log scale to go to
minus infinity as t grows large. And so
the probability that
the geometric brownie in motion is
smaller than any constant is going to go
to one as time grows large. So so when
the
mu terms the drift term is small
relative to sigma squar over two less
than
the likelihood of this process
going to zero
is is
uh occurs with probability approaching
one. But complementing that is that the
mean value of x of t
is growing exponentially
at the rate mu t exponential rate mu t.
So with geometric brownie in motion we
have this process that has a mean level
that's growing arbitrarily large. But
the process is
are with probability approaching one
approaching zero for all paths. So, so
that's an interesting um paradox, but it
um it it it appears sort of consistent
with what actually happens often in
equity markets where you'll have some
stocks that do really really well and
others that haven't done so well and go
close to zero. on average maybe there's
a mean growth rate but uh many of them
have uh ultimate values that that
approach zero well in the remaining time
um there's an introduction here to the
Orinstein ulenbeck process which
basically is a stochastic differential
equation where instead of a constant
drift term we have a drift rate that
depends on how far away the process is
from the mean level.
And so um this uh model is one that
arose with sort of physicists studying
this where you look at the average
velocity of molecules in a container
with a certain heat or temperature. And
so particles should be moving around at
some average velocity. Um and this model
is is one way of trying to characterize
that. Um outside the range of physics,
uh people have used this model in
finance. Vasich used it as a model for
interest rate dynamics where there's a
mean level that is expected in the long
run and there's variation about that
when it you when the process is above
the average level it tends to drift down
and when it's below it tends to drift
up.
So, so with this Ornstein ulenbeck
process we can um consider uh a solution
which is a product process. Now you may
recall with some differential equation
problems where you want to solve a
differential equation with two variables
and maybe the solution is a product of
one variable times a product of another
var
times the uh a function of the other
variable. So in this case we can think
of a possible solution being given by an
a of t function times
the integral of the brownian motion
uh process with respect to a little bs b
of s differentiable function. So if we
just tentatively assume this possible
solution, we can apply the chain rule
to get this first equation uh dxt is the
derivative of a times the bracketed term
then plus a of t times the derivative of
the right hand term with respect to t.
And um we can then use coefficient
matching
as per these expressions. And at the end
of the day we end up getting our Orstein
ulc process.
Um if we start at x0
it well let's see if we consider the
process with mu equal to zero and
initial value of x knot then it
decreases or increases exponentially to
zero
and then um the extra term is this
integral of brownie in motion with the
exponential term and What's interesting
about this process is that it has a
limiting distribution
that's not like a non-stationary
random walk of brownie in motion, but
it's centered at the mean level, which
was assumed in this development to be
zero and with some constant variance. So
there's like a an erotic property to
this process. The long-term distribution
is simply this fixed distribution with
constant mean and variance.
All right. Um well just to finish up um
we can extend stochcastic differential
equations in one sort of space variable
and time to multi-dimensions.
And so we can think of having m
dimensional
processes
evolving
for the uh functions.
Uh so XT could be m dimensional and then
we would have a drift rate
corresponding to different components of
the dimensions mu1 to mumm
different brownie motion terms
corresponding to m independent brownian
motions and then a covariance matrix
reflecting the how similar
sort of increments of x are related to
each other um in terms of the
co-variance terms here in this
expression. So so we can have multiple
uh multi-dimensional uh stochastic
differential equations. And so um here's
just an illustration of thinking about
mean reverting velocity and position
uh and how that would be set up. So um
the theory of stochastic differential
equations you know is very powerful and
it's and exploited a lot in uh in
physics and engineering.
So um with that um let's see I just want
to highlight some useful references for
stochastic differential equations. Um
there's this really excellent uh
monograph on uh by Oxendal uh which is
very mathematical
not necessarily motivated by finance but
uh motivated by physics problems as well
and then the other uh references here
are really good ones in quantitative
finance. So um we have our guest
lecturer John Hall to thank for uh
giving us this book on options, futures
and other derivatives.