- Welcome everybody to
the Gardner Lecture.
It's a obviously virtual lecture
and a genuine welcome to all.
Its the 61st anniversary of
the Lester D. Gardner Lecture,
which was first delivered in 1969.
And of course, it's the first
an inaugural virtual lecture,
which shows we're living
in extraordinary times.
Certainly, Grover learning,
who was the first guy,
in the lecture would never
fathom doing this virtually.
But he was after all an
aeronautical engineer.
We know the visionary.
So we're getting some
interference in the background.
I don't know where that's coming from.
But before we get started,
there's a few housekeeping items
that I want to let you know.
First thing is,
we're recording this meeting
and we'll follow you via email
to share a link of this recording.
And we just gonna in just a
moment begin the presentation
and we encourage you to ask
questions in the presentation.
And you can do it by putting
up your hand, your virtual hand
you know, I'll see that
or during the designated Q&A session
at the end of the presentation.
So those are both a Q&A thing on your Zoom
and you can also put up your hand.
So you all in View-only mode.
So as I said, raise your
hand, your blue hand,
not your virtual hand,
because I can't see your actual hand
and we'll call on you and
unmute your microphone.
We will make a submitted questions,
live to all attendees as
we read and answer them.
If we get to the end of the time,
your question hasn't been
answered please submit them,
we'll do our best to follow up
with you in the coming weeks,
so with an answer.
So let me also thank
Sarah Cody, Joyce Light
and Kathy Manal have helped set this up.
This literally would not
be possible without them.
Now in addition to,
making history with
today's Gardner lecture,
we're also marking history.
The Gardner lecture was made possible,
by the request of the late
Major Lester D. Gardner,
a member of the MIT Class of 1898
to sponsor annual presentations,
on aeronautical history.
Over the years we've been
honored by luminaries such as,
Igor Sikorsky, Jimmy Doolittle,
Yvonne Brill, Neil Armstrong,
to name just a few.
A remarkable individual
Major Gardner played not one,
but two critical roles in
the advancement of aviation,
in the early is the 20th century.
First with encouraging
of Grosvenor learning,
Jerome Hunsaker, Glenn
Martin, Major Gardner,
organized the Gardner
the publishing company,
which published, aviation who's
who in America aeronautics
and rubber age
and later aviation and
aeronautical engineering,
which became the predecessor
of Aviation Week.
A magazine that many
of us read every week.
In addition, Major Gardner
was among the founders
of the Institute of Aeronautical Sciences,
later the Institute of
Aeronautical Sciences,
one of the progenitors of the,
American Institute of
Aeronautics and Astronautics,
which of course,
is the professional
society that's associated,
with aerospace engineer.
Anref is an air officer World War One
and he was the recipient of
numerous aeronautical awards,
including the Guggenheim medal in 1947.
Given for Outstanding Achievement
in advancing aeronautics,
particularly for his
conception of organization,
is true for aeronautical science.
Major Gardner's interest in MIT,
especially as aeronautical programs,
continued throughout his life
and is alive today,
not only in the Gardner lectureship,
but also Hunsaker professorship,
which he helped to establish.
So without his background,
I ask you to turn your
attention to the present
and the remarkable individual,
delivering today Gardner lecture,
Retired Marine Corps Major General,
Charles Frank Bolden Jr.
The vast majority of you,
will recognize General Bolden as the,
12th NASA Administrator,
serving from July 2009 to January 2017.
Prior to his nomination for the post,
by President Barack Obama,
General Bolden enjoyed a 34
year career in the Marine Corps,
including 14 years as a member
of NASA's astronaut office.
After joining the office in 1980,
he traveled into orbit four times,
aboard the Space Shuttle,
between 86 and 94,
commanding two of the missions,
piloting two others.
Today he's the CEO
of the Charles and Bolden Group LLC,
an Independent Director of
Atlas Worldwide Holdings
and Blue Cross Blue
shield of South Carolina.
And fortunately for us,
a member of the MIT department
of Aeronautics and Astronautics
visiting committee,
rather than detail his
accomplishments, which would be,
a long and impossible task,
let me just say,
he's an extraordinary
individual, extra ordinary times.
I've known Charlie for many years
and it's been a, good friendship.
For that I invite General Bolden
to approach the Dias virtually,
share his observations on,
the history of MIT's aeronautics
and Human Spaceflight Programs.
Speaking on leading through
unprecedented times.
General Bolden.
- Dan, thank you so very much.
And for everybody who's
tuned in or dialed in,
or called in or whatever we call it.
Thank you very much for coming in also.
I wanna echo what Dan said
about some individuals.
I really wanna thank Sarah
Joyce, Kathy and Anthony,
our technical assistant,
none of without whom,
we wouldn't be here today.
So thanks to all of you.
Dan's already mentioned that I served as,
the 12th NASA Administrator,
so I was the NASA Administrator,
throughout President Obama's two terms.
And during that time,
I was actually privileged
to be on hand for,
some major changes in both
the strategic plan for the,
Aeronautics Research
Mission Directorate which,
is of special interest to people at MIT.
But also, I was there for a
major change in the method,
of conducting human spaceflight,
for the nation's civil space society.
So, my hope is that, Lester D. Gardner,
for whom the lecture series is named,
you know, he could have no way,
anticipated what we're doing today.
I mean, It would have boggled his mind
if he had even thought about it.
And, but it is my hope,
because this is the inaugural
virtual Gardner lecture,
that my presentation will
not cause its namesake,
to roll over in his grave.
So with that in mind,
let me go and I'm gonna talk about,
I'm gonna try to touch very briefly,
on the evolution of aviation,
from the Wright brothers,
first flight it Kill Devil Hills,
South of Kitty Hawk,
North Carolina on the
17th of December in 1903.
Through the establishment of the NAC
or the NASA Advisory
Committee on Aeronautics
and then on to subsequent
aircraft development in, you know,
involving jet engine, supersonic
flight and everything.
What after the NACA was created in 1915
and then kind of flow
into human spaceflight,
which came with the
establishment of NASA in 1958,
by the National Space Act.
Now, I know that's a mouthful,
and most of you say there
is no way in the world,
we're gonna do this.
So we'll try to see if we can do it.
So if I can get the first slide Sarah.
This is what Gardner started
and this is the Wright flyer.
You know, this thing, most of us,
walk from our bedroom
to our door and we go,
as far as the Wright flyer flew,
on those early flights in 1903.
But it was the beginning
of powered flight,
as we know it
and everything started there.
And so it's, that's our heritage.
A lot of what I'm gonna say,
I'm not gonna mention MIT by name.
But if you go through the
history of Aeronautics and Space,
there is a name of an institution
that comes up almost every time
and every page and it is MIT.
So it goes without saying
that what we're talking about today,
is also about that the legacy of MIT
and its work in aeronautics
and astronautics.
As I mentioned, the the old
NAC was established in 1915.
And interestingly, it was
snuck in, if you will,
under as a part of the Naval
Appropriations Act of 1915.
And it was put in by
assistant then Assistant
Secretary of the Navy
Franklin Delano Roosevelt
and it came about,
sort of in the midst of
World War one because,
after the Wright brothers
were unable to get anybody,
in the US interested in, buying airplanes
or picking up airplanes,
the Europeans ran away with it.
And so NACA was established,
in an effort for the U.S
government to catch up with,
Europe's rapid technological
advancements in aviation.
And then, as it progressed
during World War two,
NACA was described by some
people is the force behind,
our air supremacy
and it was primarily
due to its ability to,
adapt to geopolitical and
military challenges coming
from the Germans and the Japanese.
We have established in
and I'll give you their present day names,
the four centers of excellence
if you will have the
four places of operation
for the only NACA were Langley,
what is now Langley Research Center.
What is now,
Ames Research Center out in
Mountain View California.
What is now,
what used to be Dryden
Flight Research Center
and is now the Armstrong Research Center.
And then Louis,
that is now the Glenn Research Center,
in Cleveland Ohio.
When more of a right was put on,
the NACA in 1920 by President Wilson,
they decided to take on a
new and ambitious mission
and that was to promote,
military and civilian aviation,
through applied research
that looked beyond their current needs.
So, they started out with 100 employees,
by 1938 they had 426.
And the big thing that they did,
which I love
and we tried to do it NASA,
just before I left my
tenure as the administrator,
was we actually authorized
Bootleg research.
So it was,
research in areas that
people may not have,
been thinking were of importance,
and it was through the Bootleg research
that we got a string of
fundamental breakthroughs like,
thin airfoil theory in the 20's
NACA engine cows in the 30's,
the NACA a airfoil series in the 40's
and the area rule for supersonic aircraft,
in the 1950's.
So next slide.
This aircraft aircraft on the left,
I think most of you recognize it.
I don't think it's hanging
in the Smithsonian right now,
doing its renovation,
but it will return there
but it's the bill x one.
That was the aircraft in which,
Chuck Yeager broke the speed of sound,
exceeded the sound barrier,
the very first time.
And then down on the
bottom right is the x 15.
This shows us the transition
between the NACA and NASA
because the X 15 actually was among,
NASA's first airplanes and aeronautics.
You know, NASA came into being in in 1958,
when the Congress became alarmed,
by the perceived threat
to national security
and technological leadership,
something that became known
as the Sputnik crisis.
And they urged immediate and swift action
and President Eisenhower
and his advisors,
wanted even more,
I guess deliberate measures so,
January 12 1958,
NACA organized a special
committee on space technology
that was headed by Guy Skifard
and that brought us,
what was later called the,
NASA research program for space technology
that morphed into NASA under
the National Space Act.
So Sputnik, go to the next
one, if you will, Sarah,
I take that back.
This was one of NASA's first
or among NASA's leading
airplanes research,
it's the X 29.
It became the first
forward swept airplane to,
actually fly to exceed
Mach one and level flight.
And a lot of our work with the X 29,
brought about an understanding of,
composite materials in aircraft,
forward swept wing and in,
super critical air foils and
a lot of other things.
So, the next one if you will.
Now we get into some of the
other research that NASA,
began to do which was,
when I talked about stuff
that was out of the box,
they began to kind of
experiment with DARPA
and with Bell Helicopter on,
rotary wing with what we
call two rotor technology.
And that brought us the
XPS 15 up in the top left,
which was sort of the Father,
if you will of the MV-22,
the venerable Osprey which now is a staple
of marine aviation
and about to become the Navy's
carrier onboard delivery
or cod aircraft
and down in the bottom right,
the AgustaWestland 609,
which is one of a number
of different commercial,
tiltrotor aircraft.
So this kinda hows you
how NASA in keeping with,
the legacy of NACA,
while turning to thoughts of spaceflight,
did continue their work and aeronautics,
in tiltrotor Aircraft.
Next one Sarah.
Here will take you through a series of,
conceptual drawings of explains
that came about with NASA's 2014 change,
in the strategic plan for the
Aeronautics Research Mission Directorate.
The ones that I wanna
focus on are the top one
and the bottom one if you will,
because they're actually,
aircraft under construction right now.
The top one is the x-59 queSST,
Quiet Supersonic Transport.
It's a prototype for
that, that NASA is working with,
Lockheed right now.
There's another company called Boom.
That's building both a prototype
and planning to build a commercial or a,
I guess a business-type jet,
but all intended to fly
at supersonic speeds,
overland with a low supersonic boom.
And the bottom one Maxwell X-57,
is an all electric airplane sort of,
leading the way,
working with industry to see if we can't,
in trying to take care of the environment,
move to non-petroleum based aircraft
or propulsion that's based on electricity.
Something that has kinda
stumped us through the years.
Next one Sarah.
So now, we've talked about
in NACA and we talked about,
you know, this thing on
the horizon called NASA
and I mentioned Sputnik.
Just wanted to show you
this is the culprit.
This was, NASA was on its way to try to,
launch a satellite,
we were gonna demonstrate
that we could do that.
And the Soviet Union reared
its head and did what,
became habitual or something
that they frequently did,
in the early days of NASA.
They beat us to the punch,
so they launched Sputnik in 1957.
And it send shock waves around the world,
it really fear,
because we all of a sudden knew
that the Soviet Union had the capability
of putting something in space.
And it threatened America's dominance,
both technologically and strategically.
And so that,
this was the culprit that led
to the foundation of NASA,
if you will.
Next one.
We, you know, NASA thought
about okay, they did that.
So we've gotta speed it up.
And we said,
we're gonna send a human into space
and manned spaceflight program took off.
Before we could fly our first flight.
However, a young man by
the name of Yuri Gagarin,
a young Soviet Air Force pilot,
crawled into the vehicle
that you see in the,
bottom center there, Vostok
and orbited the planet.
And once again,
America's quest to be
first had been thwarted.
And if you look right above it,
you'll see the Soyuz spacecraft which is,
you know, the Russians really believe in,
if it ain't broke, don't fix it.
And so Soyuz replaced Vostok
and that has been their
stock in trading for
decades now and it is the
way that we currently,
get to the International Space Station
and we're gonna talk a little bit,
coming up about how we plan to,
get rid of our reliance on the Russians
for travel to and from space.
On the right I threw it
in just so you would,
have an opportunity to
see what it looks like,
because you don't hear a lot about it,
but it is a very successful
human-rated spacecraft.
It's called Shinjiro.
And Shinjiro has now
flown about five times,
carrying Chinese cruise to space.
It also has docked with
the Chinese space station,
called Tiangong.
Tiangong one and two, have been flown
and the Chinese,
envision having an
operating space station,
here and in this decade,
a difference between the
Chinese space station,
however at presently
and what we call the
International Space is.
The Chinese generally tend to
wanna operate human tended,
which means the station orbits
Earth and humans come in
and do experiments whenever it's needed.
But they're not there all the time.
So if you can go to the next one, Sarah.
Once we figured that Boeing,
we're behind for sure.
We really put the press on
and the Mercury and Gemini programs,
struggle to catch up,
we finally launched Alan Shepard
to become the first American into space.
And then John Glenn
became the first American
to orbit the planet
and we gradually moved into
the two person Gemini program,
which was the stepping stone to Apollo,
where we demonstrated,
the ability to do extra
vehicular activity or spacewalks.
Which we knew we would
have to do on Apollo.
And we also demonstrated
the ability to do,
on-orbit rendezvous
with another spacecraft,
which was something that,
we would have to do with Apollo.
If we were really serious about,
going to the moon
and having a lunar module,
separate from the the
orbiting Command Module
and then have the crew come back
and re-run the zoo
and safely return to Earth.
Interestingly, during this period of time,
the world was focused
on the Apollo program
and then once we landed on the moon
people were just mesmerized
and it was a victory for humanity,
not just America.
It was humanity had done this.
We, the whole world had done this.
Not known to many people.
However, in the background was,
a very strong effort on the
part of the United States
to figure out, where do we what
do we go next after Apollo?
And Many people say that before Apollo 11,
even landed on the moon,
NASA's budget was already
beginning to go down.
And policy decision makers,
were beginning to turn
their eyes away from Apollo
and think about where to go next.
Because I happen to be a Mars guy,
one of the places that we have
almost always wanted to go
from the very earliest of time,
is to send humans to Mars.
So even during the Apollo era,
people were thinking about,
you know, how do we get to Mars
or should we go to Mars?
The Apollo program essentially,
came to an end after Apollo 616 and,
we had one more,
one more shot with the Apollo
with the Saturn spacecraft.
When we flew Skylab that
was America's first,
orbiting space station.
But you know, we only had
three flights to Skylab
and then we had a period of dormancy,
while we went to the next step
and that next step,
was actually decided that
it would be something
that would be called the Space Shuttle.
Now when we go back and talk about Mars,
interestingly, the person
who was one of the leading,
proponents for going to Mars was,
Brenda von Braun.
And von Braun had talked,
long early in the Human
Spaceflight Program,
about a vision that he had for,
getting to Mars.
And it was essentially a three,
a three-step program where we would have,
a launch vehicle,
that would provide,
transportation from
Earth to low Earth orbit,
an orbiting station,
where the crew could,
spend some time,
put together the transport
vehicle that would carry them,
on to the moon or on to Mars or wherever.
And then this transfer vehicle.
So, that was the original
vision of what was called,
the space transportation system
that was sold to President Nixon, in the,
early 1970's about 1972.
It was a vision as I said
and but it was a vision that
would not be fulfilled because,
President Nixon and his money advisors,
the people in the office
of management budget,
figured the program as
proposed was too expensive.
And NASA was told pick one.
And the obvious pick
was the space shuttle.
And as NASA frequently does,
if we can get our, you know,
we can get our nose under the tent,
will make the rest of it work.
So we embarked on the,
design and building of the space shuttle,
which we finally flew in 1981.
The shuttle was,
I don't think was ever envisioned
to be a program that would
survive for 30 years.
But it nonetheless,
it became the premier program for,
really for the world for a while,
over its 30 year tenure.
So, next one Sarah.
This was the venerable
state space shuttle.
I was privileged to fly on it four times,
twice as a co-pilot or pilot
and twice as mission commander.
And this is actually,
the shuttle discovery on my
second flight into space,
but my first flight on discovery,
as we were in route
for something that we celebrated,
the 30th anniversary of earlier this week,
at the deployment of the
Hubble Space Telescope,
so my second and fourth flights
were flown on this vehicle,
the fourth one being the first,
joint Russian American
space shuttle mission.
We kept, as we flew shuttle,
we started thinking about
where we wanted to go
and we kept coming back
to von Braun's vision.
So if you go to the next one,
we kept trying to decide how America,
could fly a space station.
And to be quite honest,
my research is inadequate,
because I have had
trouble trying to find out
where we went from a space
station with the U.S,
as its owner operator and
everything the way that,
we had done in our earlier space programs,
then where we decided that,
it was gonna be an international effort.
I have been able to
track down the fact that,
after the fall of the Soviet Union
and the Berlin Wall coming down,
President Clinton decided
that we needed some way
to capture if you will, Soviet scientists,
particularly people in the aeronautics
and space business,
so that they wouldn't go to bed places.
And he gave the order to
NASA to figure out a way to,
get the Soviet get Russia,
integrated into the international
space station program.
The treaty had just
about been sealed with,
four members of the consortium,
the U.S, Russia, I'm sorry,
the U.S, China, Japan, the
European Space Agency in Canada.
But they went back in and
opened up the negotiations
and after a number of years
of really hard negotiations
were able to bring Russia in.
And that became the
space station consortium
that we know today.
And as we talked sitting here,
we've now had 20 years plus of,
uninterrupted human presence,
in space, on the
International Space Station.
So that is our, that's
the platform in which we,
spend our time in space
today and right now,
that's our outpost to the world.
So when the Obama admit,
well, actually, if I go back,
beginning in a couple
of the, I'm sorry Sarah,
I didn't mean go back on the slide but,
I said if I go back in time,
actually, prior to the
Obama administration,
going back to the Bush and
Reagan administration's
and you can even go back further
that we kept having these,
visions or space exploration or,
the name kept changing but,
it was always we're going back to the moon
and never going on to
Mars in one way shape,
form or fashion.
But, when the Bush administration,
Bush 43 43 decided that okay,
we really are gonna do this
and that administration began
to put money on the table
to try to get,
commercial companies to,
contract with NASA to provide,
transportation for cargo
and then subsequently for crew to space.
So next one, if you will, Sarah.
So now we're getting into,
what we call Public-Private Partnerships.
And the first two to come in were,
Cygnus, this was originally
designed and built by,
well actually proposed,
by a company called Orbital Sciences,
then became Orbital Metric
and then bought up a big,
aerospace company in Northrop Grumman.
The vehicle itself the cargo module,
is built by the Italians
and it goes to space on a
rocket built by the Ukrainians
that's powered by Russian rocket engines.
The next one,
which is the SpaceX Dragon,
everybody knows that.
So these became our first two,
commercially available
cargo vehicles to carry,
things to space.
Next one I'll show you
is the Russian Soyuz,
its main cargo vehicle,
however, is the Russian,
the Progress vehicle,
but you can carry small
amounts of cargo inside.
And then finally,
an example of another
international partner.
This is the JAXA the Japanese HTV.
We also have a European
cargo vehicle called ATV.
And then finally I'm gonna
show you what is about to come
and this is called the Dream Chaser.
A company called Sierra
Nevada from Colorado,
kinda traveled back to
Langley Research Center
and, saw something on the
shelf called the HL-10,
miniature version of the shuttle and,
they kinda took that, adapted it and now,
it is what we call the Dream Chaser.
The Dream Chaser will first fly
as a cargo vehicle for NASA,
hopefully next year,
but it also has a crew variant
that will be able to carry
up to seven crew members.
And as a pilot,
this happens to be I can now say,
since I'm no longer
the NASA Administrator,
this is one of my favorites because,
I really like, I think we should have,
the nation should have
a capability to go and,
return to space to a runway.
We've been fortunate since
we retired the shuttle.
back in 2011,
that we, you know, we didn't have a need
to make an emergency return
to Earth with a crew member,
but that day will come
and it will be nice to have a vehicle
that can come back to a runway
where we can have an
ambulance waiting right there
to take our crew,
because it doesn't do us any good
to be able to get back to
Earth in about two hours,
after an emergency arises,
only to float around in the
ocean or some other place,
so I'm kind of partial
to a winged vehicle.
But that's my impartiality.
Next one if you will.
And it took a while.
This is, you know, the title
of my talk as you know,
is leading through
unprecedented times and,
so let me talk a little
bit about leadership
and you saw it exhibited back in the,
early days of the NACA when,
Congress and the President realized that,
we had kind of fallen behind,
in the area of aircraft and aviation
and we had allowed the
Europeans to take the lead.
And we found ourselves
embarked in World War two
and we really needed to catch up.
So that was, a I would not
call it an unprecedented time,
It was a challenging task,
but the leadership of the
nation decided to form the,
an organization NACA,
which had incredible
advances and achievements,
in getting us back into
the aeronautics game,
again we found that we were challenged
and it call for people to step up,
for American leadership to step up,
when the Russians beat us,
when the Soviets beat us
to the punch with Sputnik.
And we made the decision then
that we were gonna enter the,
realm of human spaceflight.
And we were able to make
some critical decisions,
not the least of which was the decision,
by President Kennedy
that we were gonna send a,
bag then a man to the moon
and bring him safely back to Earth.
I tell people I remember,
one of the people I met when,
I first got down to Houston Texas,
to join the astronaut corps was,
the Gene Kranz who is a
just an iconic figure,
in mission control
and Gene was saying he remembers being at,
Rice University stadium,
on the day that President
Kennedy delivered,
his we're going to the moon address,
and he said he and many of the other,
people from NASA Johnson Space Center,
went home shaking their heads
and presidents lost his mind.
We don't know how to do.
And they woke up, all
woke up the next morning
and said "nope" we misunderstood.
He knows exactly what he's talking about.
He has faith that we
can, in fact, do this.
And so we've got to figure it out,
figure out a way to do it.
So that kind of tells you,
who we are and what we are.
And we're in a time like
that right now today.
The reason we're having this,
virtual webinar for the Gardner lecture,
is because we have something
that is challenging,
not just the nation, but the globe,
but people around the globe
with the Covid-19 pandemic,
but I happen to be one who believes that
if we work together, internationally,
we can tackle this just like
we've tackled everything else.
This is an unprecedented tap
and it will call for
unprecedented leadership.
And I think that is going
to be the leadership
that allows us to come
together internationally,
with multiple nations to solve this thing
that is challenging us right now.
But back to a challenge of the time,
when President Obama came into office,
he decided that we should follow on,
with what Congress had dictated
and what was in the law and that was
that we should retire the space shuttle.
And we should rely on,
the commercial capabilities
of American industry
to get us to and from space,
while NASA devoted its time
and energies to advancing,
spaceflight human exploration,
back to the moon and on beyond.
And so that brought us the three vehicles
that you're looking at here.
On the top left,
is the SpaceX Crew Dragon
and this is actually,
a shot taken by the crew from onboard,
the International Space Station,
last year when The Crew
Dragon made its inaugural,
uncrewed vision or uncrewed journey
to the International Space Station,
went through its paces.
Docked in station stayed there a few days
and un-docked and came back to Earth.
And if all goes well,
which right now we're scheduled to launch,
with the first crew,
in the Crew Dragon on the
27th of May next, 27th of May
and I'm keeping my fingers crossed
that, that goes incredibly well.
So, that's the Crew Dragon.
On the right, is the Boeing CST 100.
It had its inaugural flight,
intended to get to the
International Space Station.
However, because of some of the
software issues that it had,
it did not complete its mission.
And now Boeing is saying that
they will fly later this year
that they'll repeat the non crew flight,
so that they can fly crewed mission later
or early in 2021
to give us two commercially
available spacecraft
to get humans into low Earth orbit.
On the bottom.
The much larger vehicle is NASA's Orion,
which is the crew vehicle
that's supposed to take us back
to the moon and then eventually onto Mars.
So next one, if you will,
As I get ready to close
out let me show you just,
a couple of things that
are on the horizon.
On the left is new Shepard
and new Shepard is,
the entry of Blue Origin.
It has now flown a number of flights.
So Blue Origin and SpaceX
are the two commercial space,
companies that have embarked upon
and successfully flown
re-usable launch vehicles.
And this is sort of the we
think the wave of the future,
whether or not it turns out to be
as economically feasible
as it seems right now.
remains to be seen.
But as you can tell by the big windows,
the new Shepard was built
for, Sub-orbital spaceflight,
with lots of room for
the tourists if you will,
to get a view of our planet,
from the vantage point of Earth.
I am really, really, really excited about,
the first flight of Blue
Origin with paying customers.
And on the right,
the Virgin Galactic spaceship one,
soon to be followed by spaceship two,
which will, if all goes well,
it's gonna be tight for them,
but they could fly their first,
paying customers by the end of this year.
And that would be phenomenal.
Because my belief is
that when we get people who are not,
career astronauts or not
professional astronauts
to have an opportunity
to leave the atmosphere
and look back on this planet
and get a view of it from
the vantage point of space.
It'll change their entire
perspective on the planet.
And it will give us more and
more ability to convince people
of the importance of
preserving our planet.
Next one.
NASA's present plan with
its international partners
and commercial partners,
is to go back to the moon with humans.
And what they will find when
they get to lunar orbit,
should be the gateway,
the lunar orbit gateway and it's a,
smaller version of a
space station but it's a,
if we go back to Brenda
von Braun's vision of,
the space transportation system.
This is a little bit of,
some of the stuff that
he thought about was,
you would take a transfer
vehicle in this case, it's Orion,
going from Earth to the gateway,
where it will dock,
allow a crew to get on board
and make preparations to
either get into a lunar lander
and go down to the lunar surface
or to get into another transfer
vehicle or back into Orion
and go off to Mars.
There are a few things that we need,
before we're able to make
the final trek to Mars,
but I'm one who believes that,
technologically we have the ability
to get to Mars in the 2030's,
if we can keep our pace and keep up,
with what we're doing right now,
in spite of this incredible challenge,
so, it will require
significant leadership.
But I actually think we can do it.
Next slide.
This one is NASA will
announce this week, I think,
the selection of several of their,
choices for commercial lunar landers.
And this is an example,
of one that was proposed,
by Blue Origin a year ago.
It's called the Blue Moon.
And you can see Jeff Bezos, the founder
and owner of Blue Origin
to give you a feel for the
size of the lander itself,
but Blue Origin and a
number of other companies,
are in competition right now.
And NASA supposed to announce
the winners for this, so,
you may see the blue moon or
another commercial vehicle,
maybe the middle of this
decade or the end of the 20's
that will actually come and
take the first humans back
to the surface of the
moon since the Apollo era.
As we go through this,
I think most of you who follow
the space program know that
there is some push and pull right now,
with the National Space Council and NASA
and industry as to whether or not,
we should take the lunar orbit gateway
out of the critical path
and just focus on getting
humans to the surface
or pick up the lunar orbit gateway later.
That is one of those,
challenges that American leadership,
will have to rise to the occasion,
in these unprecedented times.
And I can't predict what's gonna happen.
I can tell you what I
think I would like to do,
but I'm not a decision maker right now.
And then the final vehicle
I'm gonna show you,
is one that's really way out.
All of the students in the audience today.
Probably will go through and are,
because they're in love with this.
Go ahead Sarah, show us the next one.
This is the Starship
and this is,
Elan musk and SpaceX most recent endeavor.
They finally had a successful,
cryogenic pressure test,
this past week
and they're now ready to go
into what they will call,
a hot test where they actually launch
and move over to another landing site
and then come back before
deciding that they're gonna launch
but this is the vehicle
that SpaceX envisions,
putting any number of people in
and sending them off to Mars.
So we're really talking about the future.
Although SpaceX, talks
about being able to do this,
by the mid 20s.
That's a tall order, I'm
not saying it can't be done,
but it will be left up
to the young people,
in our audience today to
really make this thing happen,
because people like me are too far gone.
And then finally,
go ahead to the last slide Sarah.
You know, I mentioned before that,
these are really unprecedented times.
And I show you this slide just to say,
what we can do,
when we are successful,
in bringing together,
international, academic,
commercial entities
to work collaboratively
to take on great challenges.
This was a great day for me
as the NASA Administrator,
because this was a day that I
re-signed an agreement with,
the U.S. Agency for
International Development
and its administrator
at the time Dr. Raj Shah
to seal the partnership between NASA
and the U.S. Agency for
International Development
to work together
to try to solve some of
the problems here on Earth
to enable people to get
clean drinking water
or to get food supplies
or to do things like that.
And so, NASA and U.S.A did
have a program called severe.
It's headquartered in
four different places,
around the world today,
but it's things like severe
and like the collaboration between SpaceX
and Boeing and Northrop Grumman and,
Blue Origin that I think,
are gonna to make it possible for us to,
accomplish some of these
great visions and goals
that we have,
in these unprecedented time.
So, I'm calling on American leadership
to join with others around the world,
because we can,
in fact, tackle the
challenges that are before us.
But it's gonna take
international collaboration
and partnerships among
universities around the world,
as well as commercial entities.
So with that,
I think I'll turn it back
over to you, Dr. Hastings.
And we'll see if we can
answer some questions.
- So thank you very much, Joey.
So for a great talk that
gave us the, you know,
history of both of
Aeronautics and Astronautics.
So we have the first question.
Do you think we are capable
of transitioning between,
administrations, without a major change in
direction of the human space program?
What will it take to maintain momentum,
through the next transition?
- I absolutely think we
can do that, in fact,
I try to say this quietly,
because I don't wanna get
anybody to change their minds.
But, there has been very
little change at all,
between the Obama administration
and the Trump administration
when it comes to human spaceflight.
And the goals there.
If you look at the goal
of getting to Mars,
in the Obama administration,
we always said, we said all along
that the decade of the 20s,
was gonna be the decade
of lunar exploration
and spending time in lunar
orbit because we knew then,
that there were technological things
that we needed to technological challenges
that we needed to solve.
And the moon being only two days away,
what it would enable us to carry out,
experiments and research
that would enable us to get systems,
that can survive the three
year journey to and from Mars.
So we were not,
even in the Obama administration,
there was no plan to go
to Mars before the 2030's.
And then we would move on to the 2030's
to cap off the by then, 60 years
of robotic exploration of Mars.
And you can see what's going on,
we're getting ready to
launch the Mars 2020 rover,
it will have an experiment called Moxie.
That's gonna actually take,
carbon dioxide out of the
Martian atmosphere and
dissociate it into so that
we can get breathable oxygen,
but also, potentially oxygen as a fuel
to get us onto Mars.
So, I think what you're seeing
right now between the Obama
and the Trump administration
and like I say, I say it
quietly because I don't want,
anybody in the Trump
administration to think,
okay, we gotta change.
But there's been no
dramatic change between,
what was being done for the
eight years of the Obama
administration and what's
being done for the first,
three and a half years
of the Trump administration.
And I also if I go back to aeronautics,
they're not putting as
much money as I had hoped,
they would put into aeronautics.
But the the X-59 queSST,
this Quiet Supersonic aircraft,
the X 57 Maxwell,
they're all electric airplane,
construction on both of
those proceeds on schedule,
and we should see them fly here,
within the next couple of years.
And so I think even in
the field of Aeronautics,
we're continuing to move forward
and it can be done,
you know, if you have some overlap,
in the people in the agency,
where the work actually gets done.
- Okay thank you.
So let me just remind the
audience that you can,
use the raise hand thing,
not your physical hands
as I can't see you but the virtual hand
and we can call on you and
unmute your microphone.
Alternatively, you can submit
questions by the Q&A button.
Okay, so here's another question
from the Q&A.
How do you propose that we facilitate,
international collaboration over the space
sector in today's world
after the Covid-19 crisis?
What can we do individually,
as scientists and engineers
to promote this vision?
- I think what we're finding right now
and I think the Covid-19
crisis is giving us a,
perfect opportunity to strengthen
the relationships that,
we have established.
You know, NASA today has
more than 800 active,
international agreements
with more than 120 countries.
And some of those countries
with whom we're involved in,
in human spaceflight and STEM
education and aeronautics,
are the same countries
that are working with us collaboratively,
working with the National
Institutes of Health,
working with the CDC
and trying to find vaccines,
trying to find, you know,
ways that we can combat,
the Covid the anti virus and it's a,
I think as long as we
can convince ourselves
that this cannot be done by America alone
and we continue to collaborate,
with the international partnerships
out there in the fields
of medicine we'll be okay.
If you look at what goes on,
on the International Space Station today.
It is truly international collaboration.
A lot of the research,
is being done in the biomedical area,
pharmaceuticals development,
looking at ways to make life
better here on the planet,
growing plants or growing
food for the astronauts,
but finding techniques that make it easier
for us to grow things
back here on the planet,
kind of in keeping with NASA's vision to
that whatever they do makes life better
for all humanity back here.
So I, think what we're
doing with trying to tackle
the Covid-19 pandemic,
marries very well with what,
we have been doing in NASA,
in the international partnerships
that we've established.
- All right, thank you another question.
How do we reconcile the
enormous carbon footprint
of space exploration,
with the need to reduce eliminate
emissions here on Earth.
- You know, I get asked this
question every once in a while
and the the biggest carbon
footprint with space exploration,
is leaving the planet.
And we all know,
all of us know that a key to,
to truly efficient and effective
deep space exploration,
is non chemical propulsion.
So it's getting away
from what we use today
and moving on to either
nuclear or electric propulsion.
We use electric propulsion
quite a bit today,
with all thrusters in the like,
many of the planetary
exploration vehicles today,
if you look at the ones
that have been successful,
there are electric propulsion,
they use all thrusters.
We don't need to get somewhere fast,
but you need to be able to
fly for long periods of time,
with sustained propulsion,
you know, back in, I didn't mention it,
but even back in the days
of the Apollo program,
the Department of Energy was working
to develop something called Nerva,
which was a nuclear
program to get us to Mars
that was its purpose.
So NASA and the Department of Energy,
were working together on this thing and,
NASA kinda lost interest
because they got tied up
with the Apollo program.
And then where do we go next?
And eventually, the Department
of Energy just dropped it.
When I was the NASA administrator.
I had a lot of old time NASA hands,
propulsion into a knocking on my door.
Why don't we bring Nerva back?
But but the only way we're gonna work,
on the carbon footprint
from space exploration,
is to find alternative
propulsion types to get us, you know,
to help us while we leave the planet.
I have to say, I have to admit,
I'm not very encouraged by that.
But if you look at companies
like Sierra Nevada, you know,
although it's not in their launch vehicle,
because they're talking
about an atlas five
or a falcon nine,
but, their propulsion on the Dream Chaser,
is a non, you know, it's a non
petroleum type of propellant.
And so we need to look
at something like that
to get us off the plan.
Methane is better and
Blue Origin is actually,
they have a methane engine.
Probably the cleanest thing
we've had that I can remember,
was the space shuttle.
No liquid hydrogen liquid oxygen,
but then you had the
solid rocket boosters.
So you the game you got
from the three main engines
and in the lox and liquid
hydrogen liquid oxygen.
you lost with the solid
rocket booster site.
I don't have a good
answer to that question.
- Here's a question from
one of our students,
Emmanuel Chant.
How has NASA's direction changed,
with the appointment of Douglas Barrow,
as the Associate Administrator
of human exploration
operations especially in Ariel,
Lille commercial development?
- That's a good question
that I can answer,
because I'm an outsider and looking in,
but I can give you one example.
I mentioned the fact that,
that there was now some discussion about,
whether or not,
the lunar orbit gateway
should be taken out
of the critical path
for human return to the
surface of the moon.
That is where Doug has asked the people,
he has asked his team to take a look
at look at Gateway and
say, "Hey, is this really,
is this the way we wanna
spend our money initially?
Do we wanna invest in an
orbiting a lunar orbiting vehicle
and maybe delay getting
humans to the surface?
Or do we wanna focus
on the 2024 timeframe,
laid out by the president
and just go Earth direct
to the lunar surface
and put the lunar orbit gateway
sort of on the back burner?
I will be honest with you.
I don't know yet what the
full term effect will be,
but time will tell.
- All right, here's a question from
Corey Fronton, who's one of our,
outstanding graduate students,
who is in the arrow after Organization.
Thanks a ton for the talk
Major General Bolden.
Speaking of unprecedented
leadership in unprecedented times,
you were the first black NASA director,
under the first black
president United States.
Can you talk about a time
you overcame discrimination?
And perhaps a leadership challenge
that came to breaking barriers?
You ever get asked such Charlie?
Do you have an answer?
- Yeah, you know I'm asked
this question all the time.
And I think because I'm..
and Dr. Hastings you know me,
I am the eternal optimist
and I don't ever look back.
And this is maybe bad,
because it won't allow me to
answer the question completely.
But I am not one who looks
back at I wish things had been
or I wish it had been.
People ask me frequently, you know,
if there was anything in my
life that I would change,
to do something.
I tell them not on your life.
I love where I am
and I love having my three
beautiful granddaughters.
And I would not run the risk of,
changing any of that by going back
to try to change anything.
But, you know, I if I think on it,
I, my mom and dad were school teachers.
And so they were my role
models and my mentors
and I tell people all the time,
everything I learned about
leadership that I needed to know,
I learned at my dinner table.
My dad was my high school football coach.
And he taught me he had a saying,
it's not the size of the dog in the fight,
but the size of the fight in the dog.
I was always a little kid
with a Napoleon complex.
And he told me anything you wanna do,
you can do if you decide,
you know that you wanna
study and work hard.
My mother was my middle school librarian
and she drove me as my librarian.
I was a library assistant.
So I worked for her.
And my uncle, her brother,
her oldest brother,
ran the swimming pool where I grew up.
So we had the Dru Park sharks.
So everywhere I turned,
my family was pushing
me to excel and exceed.
And they didn't give me an
opportunity to stop and think
that I was black.
And that there was
something I could not do.
They said you can do anything.
Now, of course, getting
into the Naval Academy,
that's probably the first
time that I actually thought,
there was something I was
not gonna be able to do,
because of my race,
because I couldn't get
an appointment from.
either Senator Strom Thurmond
or Senator Olin D Johnston,
who were my, two senators at the time
or from Albert Watson, my
congressional representative.
But again, in keeping with
what my mom and dad taught me,
I wrote to the President
of the United States
and who was Lyndon Johnson
at the time because,
I had counted on him,
giving me a Vice Presidential appointment.
But President Kennedy was assassinated,
my senior year in high school
and my dreams of going
to the Naval Academy,
kinda went out the window with that, but,
not to be deterred I wrote a
letter to the president anyway
and said, "Hey, I know
I'm not eligible for
presidential appointment this president,
but you know, I've written
you for several years now
and you told me to write
your back when I'm a senior".
I said, this is Charles Bolden.
I'm a senior and I still
wanna go to the Naval Academy.
I need help.
I never heard from him.
But I had a Navy
recruiter come to my house
and then a federal judge
that President Johnson
sent around the country
looking for qualified young,
black men who wanted to go
to the service academies.
And I ended up getting an appointment
from Congressman William
Dawson of Chicago, Illinois.
So my message to kids
the don't waste your time
and the some of the young ladies,
in Dr. Newman's class yesterday,
like everybody in the Dr.
Newman's class yesterday,
heard me say this
and I've told Dr. Newman the same thing.
Don't waste your time,
trying to explain to somebody,
why you're in the room
or trying to justify your being there,
you are good or you wouldn't be there.
So just perform just do
what you know how to do.
And, you know, your performance,
will eventually win them
over or they're idiots
and you can't do anything
to change idiots.
So that's that's what
my mom and dad taught me
and that's kind of overcome, you know,
discrimination and stuff.
- So final question.
How do you see sustainability
aspect in space?
Do you think we should
just keep shooting things,
up in space?
And shouldn't we also think
about how to clean them up?
- Without a doubt.
And you know, one of the challenges is
that all of us recently
in the space program
and it didn't start with me,
but I, you know, several NASA
administrators before me and,
several administrations before me and now,
the International Space clock.
- [Voice] Its five o'clock.
everybody realizes that,
low Earth orbit is,
really, really, really
getting contaminated.
It's got way too much orbital debris
and we've gotta figure out
a way to clean that up.
We've done some mitigation things like,
telling anybody who
puts something in space,
has to have enough propellant to either,
bring it back for, you know,
a landing in the ocean somewhere,
where it doesn't harm anybody
or take it to a parking orbit,
when it's useful time and
space has been resolved.
But there are a number
of small efforts today.
Unfortunately no nation is
undertaking it as a major effort.
They're talking about it
in the United Nations.
But we've gotta figure out
a way to do debris removal
and not just debris mitigation.
So challenge that needs,
some sterling leadership
in an unprecedented time.
- Well, we actually do have some students,
who are thinking about this,
you know, in the Department.
- They can do it like this.
- All right, look, it's five o'clock,
we gotta bring this to an end.
We have a ton of questions.
So we will try to get these
questions actually answered,
but we just can't do it anymore on that.
So, thank you all, thank you
very, very much for a great,
that's the Gardner lecture.
You've given us some both history
and insightful motivation.
So thank you very much.
- Thank you for letting
me be a part of it.
It was, I was nervous but it worked.
- All right, okay, thank you.
I bet we're gonna capture the questions
and then see if we can
get answers out to them.
Right Sarah and Antony.
Okay, all right.
- Thanks very much, you
all be safe and healthy.
Thanks so much.
- All right, bye bye.
- Bye bye.