all right let's get started uh today we
continue probability the last theme of
the class we have three more lectures
about probability um today's lecture is
about expectation which is a nice
summary it's a one number summary of a
random variable remember from last time
a random variable is neither random nor
variable it's really a
function from your sample space to
something usually real
numbers uh so we use this to represent
sort of some computation about an
experiment we had a similar uh setup
with derived variables if you remember
back to um State machines uh which were
also not variables they were really
functions from the state of the machine
to numbers so random variable the same
idea if I give you if I tell you what
sample like what random events happened
you can compute a single uh value for
this variable that's the meaning and we
had a particular type of random variable
that's going to be really useful today
which is an indicator random variable
where the output is always zero or one
indicating something happened that's the
one or didn't
happen so functions are complicated you
know if I want to write down a function
I got to write down a lot of numbers one
for every uh possible sample so uh
expectation is a way to take that
complicated function and reduce it down
to one number obviously it's not going
to tell you everything about the
function but it tells you what you
expect to happen on average what is the
it's not the most likely thing but if
you take all the things that could
happen and you average them that's
expectation so let's define that
precisely match my notation here so
let's call uh random variable X
over uh sample space
s uh then the
expectation of X which we write e x of X
although often it's written just e of X
so if you look at other probability
sources you might see that as well both
of these mean the same thing uh it's
going to be a weighted average weighted
by probabilities so we're gonna sum over
all possible samples which we call
Omega and S of the probability of that
outcome
times uh X the function X evaluated at
that income
outcome Omega for
outcome uh so if
I right so this is a particular type of
average right because the probability
sum to one and in particular if the
probabilities are all equal this is
literally the average value of
x okay but of course we would like what
we care about is the weighted by the
probability if there's something that's
more likely to occur that should get a
bigger multiplier in front Okay so this
is going to be some average of
X sometimes the expectation is also
called the average uh let's do a very
simple
example which is we roll a
fair uh six-sided
die I happen to have such a die right
here so we roll it it has values one to
six each equally likely here I got a
one uh what is the expected
value okay so sample space here is one
up to
six all the probabilities are one six
probability of I occurring is 1 over 6
and so the expected
value uh I should probably give this a
name let's call it D probability that uh
D equals I for any particular I between
1 and six is 1 over 6 and so the
expected value of D the DI
roll is from that formula well it's just
uh the probability that uh we get uh a 1
* 1 plus the probability that we get a
two * 2 plus and so on uh I'm going to
rewrite that a little bit so these these
probabilities are all six so we've got
16 * 1 plus6 * 2 plus up to 16 *
6 these
numbers it's our favorite summation the
Triangular number uh this
is uh gal right so if I factor out the
six in front then we have that times the
sum 1 through six which you should
remember is 6 * 7 over
2 it's getting a little crowded this is
1 over 6 * 6 * 7 over two let me get a
color
chalk it's time
for uh the exciting cancellation moment
the sixes cancel and so we're left with
7 over2 also known as
3.5 which is as you would expect the
average of numbers one through six um
but notice notably a point of this
example is that the expectation is not
actually a valid outcome you never get a
3.5 on a die but you get 1 2 3 four five
and six and the average of those is
three and a
half okay so don't expect don't expect
the expectation to be uh an actual point
in your an actual value that X could
take
on all right let's do a more interesting
example which we're going to use a
lot what if I have an indicator random
variable also X oh call it
I uh for event a so remember this means
uh I is one if event a occurred if what
if the sample that happened is in a and
zero if a did not occur okay so let's
try to compute the expected value of
I okay uh so um this is a little tricky
with this formula because s even though
I only takes on two values s can be you
know size a million who knows there's a
lot of different random outcomes that
could happen and then I kind of projects
them all down to this very simple 01
space so I'm just going to write the
definition first Omega and S probability
of Omega times I of Omega but this thing
is either zero or
one so this is a summation and we
remember one of the techniques for
dealing with summations is to rearrange
the terms in some useful way and given
that every term here is either
multiplied by zero which case it
disappears or multiply by
one let's maybe collect like terms so we
can split this summation into two parts
there's the sum where W is in a
compl uh probability of Omega time0
because I of something in a complement
here is
zero uh or it could be Omega inside a
without the complex
and then we get probability of Omega *
1 so these
disappear and we're just left with and
the one cancels or is doesn't do
anything so we get the sum of uh Omega
and a Time probability of
Omega and this is our definition of
probability of
a so that's nice and simple another way
to write this that's more directly about
I is this is the probability that I
equals 1 so the expected value of an
indicator random variable is always the
probability that that indicator random
variable equals one this is just a fun
fact because I only takes on zero and
one the zeros don't show to disappear
from the expectation formula and the
ones basically add up just the
probabilities of of the event occurring
okay we're going to use this fact
several times today so it's an example
and a useful
LMA all right uh probability I'm told uh
is was originally invented to analyze
gambling so let's put that to good use
and do some gambling so let me Define a
game and then I'm going to need a
volunteer couple volunteers
to play this game with
me it doesn't have a fancy name we're
just going to call it the gambling game
um so we're going to have three
lers and we're going to follow these
sequence of
steps everybody has some pile of money
which we're going to represent by
candy but I'll write it as
dollars so every round every player puts
$2 into a shared pot then um each
player uh
picks heads or
tails you may have played this game in
the single player version you just try
to guess the outcome of a coin then
we're going to flip a Fair
coin okay with with multiplayer it's
more interesting let's say now mult we
could have multiple winners right maybe
two people guessed heads and the outcome
of the coin was heads then what we're
going to do is take the pot of money
that everyone uh added to and evenly
distribute it among the winners among
the people that guess the coin outcome
correctly so we
split
po
equally
among
winners uh there's one special case
which is maybe no one guesses the
correct value
in that case uh we'll also equally split
the pot which is equivalent to just
giving your money back and trying again
so we're going to play this uh game many
rounds and our goal your goal is to of
course maximize the amount of money you
get who would like to play this game oh
so many people all right I'm afraid it's
only a three- player game uh so I'm
gonna pick Jenny my accomplice uh and uh
how about you
yeah uh no totally fair game don't worry
uh what's your name Cleo Cleo all right
so everyone welcome Cleo and Jenny to
the
stage
yeah uh I I want you to be in like
equally hard and uh good good position
so we're going to put you in the middle
the
Cleo try to keep track here and we've
got a
coin uh except I don't have a coin I
have a Giant die so uh we're going to
say was it heads H H is uh huge I gotta
write this down or I'm gonna forget H is
huge and T is
Tiny okay so one two three is a Tails
four five6 is an H all
right so uh I'm gonna guess first then C
why don't you stand in the middle so
we're like in order here uh so I'll
guess Tails my usual
heads
Tails okay let's roll this
die that doesn't feel very fair but okay
well I'll do different types of rolls so
we got a four which is
H clear winds oh I forgot to distribute
the money okay uh these are all equal so
pick your pile of
cash which are uh poker chips and so
it's I think more fun if everyone can
see the pile so let me so uh we were
supposed to start out by putting two in
to the pot and then you are the only
winner for the pot so you get all this
money it's already looking good all
right so I'm going to flip the the we
should I should flip after guessing a
little too Force otherwise all right
I'll try Heads This Time Tails Tails
heads
Heads okay and we
flip okay six is high oh oh I forgot to
do our thing two
in uh and then we evenly split the pot
all
right
great very consistent coin right play
this game properly supposed to put the
money supposed to put your money where
your mouth is before you play the game
all right uh I'll try
heads
Heads yeah three heads in a row is never
useful uh because whatever happens we
will just take our money back all right
so we
flip this is quite fun another heads wow
it's very consistent coin
here all right so you just a St
distribution we put our money back in to
each uh I'll do Tails heads Heads Tails
Tails very efficient this is great I'm
the slow part here
rolling oh yeah another heads
great I love this there's another
problem we'll be working on which is how
many times you have to flip a coin until
you get tails the answer is two
but uh all right so back in and uh I'll
do Tails sorry heads heads
else all
right based on how this D's been
going good
guess all right have we played enough do
you get the idea not yet oh not yet
you're you're you're almost depleted
there Jenny all right let's see uh one
more maybe we should keep going till we
get a Tails right that can't take
forever famous last words I've done this
before all right hey head Tails Tails
heads
Heads now the gamblers ruin would say
we're due for a tails now right it's
more likely than
50%
oh Gambler was wrong it's 5050 every
time all
right uh heads tails
yes finally
aails all right Cleo here has won
basically all the candy you can take as
many as you like because I'm actually
lactose intolerant so I can't eat these
uh so both of you are welcome to take as
many as you like um so that's the
gambling game now is it coincidence that
Cleo won and I lost no Wasing Jenny was
picking the other one the other from you
indeed very observant this is why Jenny
was so fast at guessing Jenny's one of
our Tas by the way that's uh how I
convinced her to cheat uh but she
cheated in order to destroy me uh so
there's this fun strategy which is uh if
you guess the opposite of one of the
previous players which if you guess in
sequence like this is easy to do Cleo
could have done it Cleo actually did it
most of the time I think there were only
a couple times one time when we matched
um and that's a good strategy uh in
particular uh well let's analyze shall
we how do we analyze a game like this so
small we just draw the decision tree or
the probability tree all right now it's
a little bigger than some of the ones
we've done uh luckily um the whole thing
is
symmetric it doesn't really matter which
one you do first uh the whole thing is
symmetric so I'm going to do it in the
order of let's branch on what player one
does player two player three and then
what the coin does and then we're going
to get some outcome uh which I'll Define
in a
second uh so uh it turns out whether the
first player guesses heads or tails but
because the coin is random uh it's going
to be symmetric so let's just ignore the
whole right half of this space and
pretend we're in this left half so
suppose I always guessed
heads uh or somebody always guesses
heads I think it's probably going to be
me that I care about yeah uh then
uh player two guesses heads or tails now
we haven't said what the probabilities
are here right uh we didn't I was trying
to be roughly 50/50 but I wasn't
flipping a coin each time to decide how
I should guess the coin uh I was just
making some arbitrary Choice C was
making some arbitrary Choice Jenny was
making some less arbitrary Choice and
then the coin this part is random so
this one is one half either
way so that's helpful
and then we get some outcome which I'm
going to measure the uh net for uh
player
one that's this number and I wrote it
down here because it's very easy to get
these wrong uh so the first case is that
we all guest heads and then it doesn't
matter what we do just our money is
going to go back or the pots going to go
back to even distribution whether we win
or lose the the money goes uh back to
where it started so the net for player
one in particular is zero so these are
boring uh then we have uh heads Heads
tails for the three players and so then
if it's heads these two players one and
so they evenly distribute so we're
always putting six in each time so
they'd each get
three uh but they started by putting in
two and so the net gain is only one this
is uh 3 minus two we gained three but we
had to pay two to get there okay or we
lose whenever we lose and all of these
Tales branches uh player one is going to
lose because they gu heads and in that
case you get minus two because you had
to put in the two uh so this case is the
same there's two heads and so you each
get three and so it's a net of one and
then there's this case this is the case
you really aiming for this is the best
for player
one uh because in this case player one
is the unique winner so here uh there
was heads uh and and the other two guess
tals and the coin came up heads and so
that's where you're really trying to be
uh the unique winner in this game the
less common winner that's when you get
lots of
points okay so uh let's compute the
expectation to compute the expectation
we need to know what the probabilities
are on these branches or something about
them uh and I'm going to start by saying
let's uh
that uh all
players are uh
uniform and
independent
so so 50/50 on every Branch okay then
the probabilities down here let me use
color are going to
be 116th in the whole tree or 1/8 in
this sub tree so I'm going to just
condition on the H in the beginning and
so I'll write uh 1/8 down here but if
you were drawing the whole tree you'd
have to write
11/16th okay each of these things occurs
with 1/8
probability get yeah each of these 1/8
and so we get the expected value
is uh
1/8 times the sum of these values 0 + 0
+ 1 - 2 + 1 - 2 + 4 -
2 uh which I hope is equal to zero
because it negative is uh six and the
positive is also six so this is what you
might call a fair game right the your
expected winnings are zero so you're
just as likely well it doesn't mean
you're just as likely to go above or go
to below but on average you will break
even okay uh but that's not what we
did uh we considered the case where uh
let's say player two does not equal
player three which is something that
player three could enforce and that's
what Jenny was doing always choosing
opposite of Cleo
here in that
case
uh it's really bad for me right because
whatever I guess out here if there's
both a heads and a Tails out here if
you're if they're always guessing
opposite one of them's heads one of
them's Tails so that means I always
match one of
them guaranteed and the other of them is
in the unique pile and so they have a
50% chance like in this situation Cleo
has a 50% chance of getting that
plus4 there's still a 50% chance that we
uh that it came up tails of course not
with this die but in principle there's a
50% chance that it comes up uh taals but
then we each only get one point so if
you're focusing on my winnings I will
never get
four dollars in a round with uh Jenny
strategy right I will always get either
one or minus two that doesn't sound like
a very good game for me if I randomly
get 50% chance I get a one 50% chance I
get a minus
two um so this this was uh I guess
expected uh net for player one that's
what we've been Computing so in this
situation uh the expected
net for player one uh if you want to be
precise you can say um it's this sub
tree here this is when uh the last two
guesses are heads Tails or tails heads
is the middle part of this sub tree and
you can see uh my possible outcomes are
limited to these
guys and
uh it turns out they're equally likely
uh in fact independ dependent of what
player two does I won't try to prove
that here but um because all that
matters is this last coin flip 50 if
it's heads then I get a plus one if it's
Tails I get a minus two every time in
this half of the tree and so it's it
ends up being half in other words the
average of 1 minus two also known as
minus a
half so given how Jenny played in fact I
expect to lose and you saw that happen
Jenny also happened to lose the way this
is practical if you're a gambler is you
if you have two players that collude
they decide whatever happens we're going
to take our total winnings and split it
evenly between us at the end of the game
after all the rounds are done then this
this is not quite a guarantee but it's a
pretty good bet that together uh Cleo
and Jenny would get most of the coins
most of the money uh because they have a
their their expected outcome is plus a
half I believe should be the compliment
plus yeah anyway it's positive and my
expected expect expectation is negative
so uh yeah don't play this game if you
don't trust players two and three not to
collude all
right cool you might think this is a
silly game who would ever play this game
well the Massachusetts lottery uh played
this game uh it's a little more
complicated there's you I think you had
up to four digits and you uh tried to
guess a sequence of four digits that
would come up randomly I mean pretty
similar to lotteries today they just
have more numbers uh and there's this
great MIT Professor Herman shernoff who
we'll talk some of his probability
results later in the class um and he
wrote this paper how to beat the
Massachusetts numbers game which is what
the lottery was called originally um and
he just looked at some data and it's a
similar situation if there are many
lottery winners they evenly split the
pot also the state takes like 40% or 60%
cut I forget which way it goes um but
even then uh he made money off of the
lottery and there have been more recent
versions of this run by MIT students I
hear uh to make a lot of money off the
massachusett lottery and they've since
changed the rules to make those
strategies hard to run uh but in
particular uh he executed this made a
lot of money the whole the idea is if
you can guess numbers that are less
likely to be guessed by other people and
all numbers are equally likely then you
expect to win and it turns out people
are so predictable uh what's this say
zeros and nines were unpopular smaller
digits were popular and so we ended up
just going with random numbers from like
five to eight I think uh and or and
zero9 maybe um and uh he won not a lot
of money but he wants some money uh you
can read the paper for more details it's
pretty pretty fun read it goes through
all the probability and stuff stuff uh
this is like a simplified version so
cool practical now you know how to make
money uh let's go on
to uh some other ways to compute
expectation and some more examples and
so
on all right um we talked
about so here we computed if we roll a
single six-sided die the expect value of
that single die is 3.5 what if I rolled
two dice A and B and I want to know the
expectation of dice a die
a should also be 3.5 right if I roll two
dice it doesn't shouldn't change
anything but if I computed it explicitly
in this way it would be really tedious
because the sample space would go from 1
through six to 1 through six squared so
now there's 36 different possible
outcomes and for each of them I need to
like write down a term and add it all up
it will come out to 3.5 but that's super
annoying to do so here's a nice theorem
that makes it easy to do this with six
terms instead of 36
terms um if I have a random variable X
and I want its expectation this is equal
to
sum where X is in the range of big
X of
probability x = x time
uh Little X let me erase
this my terrible losing
game how many coins flips till Tales one
two three four five six seven all right
keep that in mind seven coin flips to
get
Tails um all right so here's a formula
um it's really exactly what we did
here so when we we wrote down here are
all the possible outcomes and we
multiply them by what the random
variable could be and when it was an
indicator random variable was either Z
or one so there were two groups in
general there's whatever the range of X
groups okay so if I
um yeah so this is exactly this this
kind of clustering where we split it
into two sums each of them was the
probability of being in that group times
the outcome of that group this sum is
exactly uh probability
of not
a and this
sum is
probability of
a uh and in general if we if we split
into not two groups but all the
different possible values of big X could
be Little X for every little X in the
range of big x uh then this is we get a
sum of uh probability of outcomes which
is exactly the probability that big x
equals small X and we multiply that by
small X because that's what we have
in the definition of expectation okay so
this is an easy theorem I won't write
down a proof because uh it's this thing
generalized a little
bit
uh and let's do an
example maybe on a different
board suppose I want to know
the number of hearts in a three card
hand okay so what that means is I have
52 cards in a deck I randomly choose
three cards without replacement so just
like your drawing from the top of a
randomly shuffled deck I want to know
how many hearts do I get in
expectation let's call this
uh
yeah expected number of
Hearts uh
is if we just use the
definition probability of w times the
number of hearts in
Omega this would be the definition and S
here is uh Size
52 cubed not quite 52 * 51 * 50 it's
really
big uh so I don't want to have to
compute this this explicitly instead I'm
going to use this formula and say well
look the number of hearts in a three
card hand is 0 1 two or three so uh I
can write this as the probability that
number of Hearts equals 0 times 0 okay
that's not very interesting uh we can
take the probability uh number of Hearts
equals
one uh and multiply that by one plus
probability the number of Hearts equals
2 plus probability number of Hearts
equal 3 *
3 okay and the so now I have three terms
relatively easy and these are hopefully
things you know how to compute um for
example probability I get three hearts
I'm going to cheat um this is like 13
choose
3 uh divided 52 choose three
right because uh this is there are 13
different heart cards so uh the number
of ways to choose three hearts out of
those 13 heart cards is 13 choose three
the total number of ways to choose three
cards is 52 choose three and so that's a
probability and you need to multiply it
by three uh to get this formula and
there's some similar things for these
terms I think I maybe won't write them
down
uh maybe I'll write down the middle one
just for KS I went through the effort of
of figuring these out so this is at some
this point should be something that you
could do uh just like on your problem
set these are combinatorics problems you
know how to
solve okay so you get some sum of
binomial terms but hey it has some
reasonably small size of course these
have huge factorials in them uh but you
know it's only choose one two or three
so they're not too big you plug this
into wol from alpha say and you get
three quarters
very nice
number we might come back to
this all right
uh a lot of the time because this is
61200 we're working with integers
natural
numbers you know all of the um random
variables I've defined so far I believe
are
integers we happen to get an expectation
that was not an integer but all of the
values that could take on or or X or
Hearts could take on was an integer so
let's consider the case where uh I'll
say the
co-domain of
X is the natural numbers 0 1 two 3 um
remember co- domain is just what you
declare this function could take on for
values it doesn't have to take on those
values range here the intent is these
are just the values that are taken on by
this function and so I didn't have to
write
uh even though the number of Hearts
could I don't know be 100 in some other
card uh on this sample space we know
it's just 0 one two or three and so we
just need four
terms okay but let's suppose uh
potentially all the natural numbers are
there but not necessarily all of
them then uh expected value of x has a
nice form and this is a Formula I
encourage you not to memorize you should
write it down on your cheat sheet and
always look at it up from there because
it's easy to get uh wrong especially the
next
one one to
Infinity
probability xal I * I okay this is just
uh exactly this theorem nothing exciting
here I wrote a sum over a range now I'm
writing a sum over an explicit range the
one clever idea I had is Skip zero
because zero is going to get the zero
case is going to get multiplied by zero
so that never matters so we get to start
at one wow I saved this one step forever
more uh and then sum up to Infinity if
we might have to go that
high okay so that is true uh but there's
an even cooler form which is sum IAL 1
to
Infinity of probability of X greater
than or equal to
I
or there's no I
here I equal 0 to Infinity
probability X greater than
I okay so this this part is just this
theorem uh this step is I just change
greater than equal to to greater than
and changed where I started I so here it
started I uh one and here it started i0
and so here I'm effectively adding one
to I and so I get to do or subtracting
one from I so I do greater than instead
of greater than equal to so these two
Arrow equalities should be obvious and
this one is the interesting one
so let's prove
that okay proof
okay I want to claim I want to compute
this sum and claim that it equals this
one and I'm going to do it by writing it
in kind of an obvious way first I'm just
going to write out the infinite series
with dot dot dot so we've got x equal to
plus uh X greater equal to 2 plus X
greater equal to 3 just give me a moment
and I'll write all the remaining terms
might take a while um and now I want to
expand these
out
into uh separate pieces in terms of x
equal
I okay so this is what is probability
that X greater equal to one given that
again that they're all natural
numbers uh we know this is probability x
= 1 plus probability x = 2 plus plus
probability xal 3 plus and so
on up to
Infinity okay what's this
one uh well same thing but starting here
probability x = 2 plus probability x = 3
plus and so on this
one uh starts over here
probability xal 3
okay so if I now sum this
way down the columns I get 1 *
probability x =
1 plus 2 * probability x =
2 because there are two values here
there are two ranges here for X that
include xals 2 these two two is not
greater equal to 3 four five and so on
so I get exactly two of them I get
exactly three uh probability xal
3 and so on and if you work out the dot
dot dots VI a proof by induction you get
some I probability xal I and that's what
we
wanted one to
Infinity so that's why these two sums
are the
same so the point is to do this work
once so that in the future uh if you
have a problem you can use any of these
formulas you want you could use the
definition of expectation
which is a sum over outcomes in the
sample space or you could use this
formula sum over all the things in the
range uh with equality here and then you
multiply by X or if in the special case
where your function only takes on
Integer values so this doesn't work if
you have other real
numbers uh then you can use one of these
three formulas probably the last one or
the first one are the useful ones if
it's easy to compute the probability x
equals something then maybe use this
formula if it's easy to compute the
probability that X is bigger than
something this was CDF and this was pmf
remember from last time if it's easy if
you know have have a nice form for pmf
then use that if you have a nice form
for CDF use that provided you work with
integers do not try to mix these
formulas together don't compute like the
the sum of I equal 1 to Infinity
probability X greater or equal to I time
I that would give you something is not
expectation okay but surprisingly uh
stud students try so don't do that use
this one or this one or this
one or the
definition all
right cool let's do some more
interesting
examples lonely brace
those are
questions next problem is called
meantime to failure it's a little
negative uh you can use it to compute
successful things as well um it's
related to this problem of how many
times it is essentially this problem of
how many times do I have to flip a coin
until I get Tails or until I get heads
either
way uh I'll write it as heads because
that's what my not
say uh it's less interest it's more
interesting for a biased coin so let's
say uh you know the
probability of getting heads is
p i want to know uh what is is the
expected number of
flips until I get
heads okay so you could use this if
you're analyzing coin flipping um but
you can also use it for things like uh
my laptop every day there's like a one
in a million chance that the hard drive
dies something so how many days do I
expect until uh the hard drive dies hard
drives are usually designed engineered
to last like I don't know five years or
so and then all your hard drives that's
for spinning discs ssds are probably
different they depend on usage uh so
that's uh you know that's something you
might care about and that's why this is
called metime failure uh it could be
something more positive like maybe you
have an algorithm you're doing
randomized algorithms in the future and
you have an algorithm that either solves
your problem with some probability uh
one minus p no with probability P it
solves your problem and with probability
1 minus P it says I don't know there are
lots of algorithms like this out there
uh how many times do I have to run this
algorithm until it actually gives me an
answer so I can run it and it gives it
might say I don't know but if I run it
again it might then solve the problem
depending on the random coin flips that
it does so that then it's mean time to
success how many times do I have to flip
this coin do I have to run this
algorithm given some probability of it
succeeding that's P how many times do I
have to keep going until I get a
successful answer lots of other uh
examples we will get to them in a moment
um now our traditional approach to
solving tough problems like this is to
draw a tree in this case the tree is
infinite so that's going to be a little
harder to draw we have uh P versus one
minus P whenever we get ahe heads uh we
stop but this tree keeps going off to
the right
okay so that's uh maybe let's not look
at the infinite tree uh let's use some
formulas
so I'm going to call this number the
number of flips I'm going to call F and
then we want to compute remember f is a
function so uh there are various
outcomes here which correspond to um you
know the executions various numbers of
flips it's going to be tals taals taals
taals tals I times and then heads those
are the various outcomes that could
happen because we stop whenever we get a
heads so it could be zero tails and then
heads one Tails then heads and so on uh
so that's our sample space and then f is
a function that maps that sample space
to count how many total flips were there
head anails so it's always going to be
at least one and then expect so f is a
function can take on some integer value
between zero and uh one I guess and
infinity um and now we're going to
reduce this to a single SLE number via
expectation what is the average number
of flips that we expect to take so uh
that's expectation of f now we will use
our latest and greatest
formula this
one let me memorize it for a second it's
just sum of X greater than
I already forgotten it it's too far from
over there to over here uh was it
probability f is greater than I I hope
yes okay so this is that
CDF and I claim uh this is not too hard
to figure out using what we know because
uh we're assuming each each flip is
independent from subsequent flips like
the the flips of this coin are mutually
independent it's not some magical coin
that always comes up heads or always
comes up with Tails or something well
that would be represented by the P but
there's no correlation between the
the different flips so um for the for
there to be at least are greater than ey
flips before I get a heads that means
that the first eye flips are Tails these
are equivalent events this is this this
F greater than I is the same as
first I
flips are tails
right and then after that I don't know
might get a heads right away then f is
i+ one or it might take longer but F
being greater than an i is exactly this
situation so what is the probability
that the first eye flips our
Tails one minus P to the I I saw you
Whispering
it feel like H yeah cool now the hard
part is working out this sum or remember
ing what this sum is right this is a
geometric sum right so 1us P to the I
because this is a chance of getting a
taals and then they're each independent
so we just take the product by a product
rule uh this is a geometric thing sum of
x to the I from uh I equal 0 to Infinity
is 1 over 1 - x so this is 1 over 1us X
here is 1 - P so 1 - 1 minus P that's
also known as P so this whole thing is 1
over p key amazingly simple
formula for the meantime to failure this
is why meantime to failure is such a
famous example because it has such a
beautiful solution so if I'm flipping a
Fair coin
50/50 p is a half I expect to have to
flip it twice to get a heads or tails
now reality is not equal to the average
sadly so I had to flip seven times to
get a heads or tails uh but you know if
I was gaming for heads it would be very
fast it happened the very first step uh
so that's um that's the expectation okay
it doesn't tell you everything about the
distribution this distribution has a
name alluded to by this uh geometric
Series this was the
CDF uh we call this the geometric
distribution
it comes up somewhat frequently in real
life
distributions if I were to write down
the the pmf it's uh 1 minus P to the I
times P this chance that I get ey tails
and then a heads that's uh well okay
it's either that or probability the way
I defined it before it was FAL I + 1
so one of these is true pick one these
are both called the geometric
distribution if you look at the
Wikipedia definition of geometric
distribution it says there are two
distributions called geometric
distribution this one and this one so
pick your poison
uh both are called that uh so here is an
application another application of
meantime to failure uh I don't know
about you but I like collecting
things Everyone likes collecting
something right the the to me the
epitome of collecting things is gotcha
oh that's the video game version of gcha
where you're collecting characters in a
video game uh please do not play these
games they're annoyingly addictive uh I
spend most of my nights these days uh
but the gacha is named after this notion
of uh you can see it in the top right
there is H gasa pan which is like uh
these these little um you know if you
grew up in the US you have uh vend
machines that give you candy well these
are like the really cool vending
machines in Japan this was a gachaan
festival and uh you pick your favorite
weird thing that you can get in a little
ball out of this machine you put in your
200 yen and you get a randomly selected
ball from those sets of uh weird toys so
this is like a toy delivery or not
delivery service it's a toy uh random
selection service and if you want to
collect all the different things on this
list how many times you have to do it
this is a problem called coupon
collectors or the gotcha problem I would
say uh but uh we'll solve it in general
in recitation
tomorrow uh but I'll solve a very simple
version here which is a nice
application of
this of meantime to failure
let's solve the special case where there
are only two
toys gotcha gacha is a sound that when
you crank the things like gacha gacha
gacha PA is when the ball drops
down uh gotcha
with two toys or characters or whatever
you're collecting uh and so you get a
random Choice say let's say it's 50/50
between the two so in your first pull is
what we usually call these at least in
the video game context or first crank in
the physical context uh you get one of
the
toys okay so now it's really just how
many steps do I need until I get the
second
toy two this is the coin flipping
problem so how many more
PS
until uh
you get a distinct
toy and in this case it's going to be
50/50 each each pull and so uh you
expect two
more uh which is a total of
three now when you have K toys you want
to collect it's annoying because in the
beginning it's really easy to get lots
of distinct toys because you're very
likely but when you're trying to collect
the last toy it's very unlikely that you
pull the last toy because there's only
like a one ink chance that you get it so
you end up with some harmonic series you
get a log Factor you'll see that
tomorrow okay uh let's do a little more
Theory and then some more examples where
should I
goas
gambling I feel like I should have a
disclaimer please don't gamble uh it's
not good for you
please just uh simulate gambling that's
better I was writing a simulation uh of
of this game this morning to see like
what were my chances of actually winning
despite the odds being against my favor
and with 10 Rounds uh I had like a 20%
chance of winning so luckily the demo
went in my favor but there was a decent
chance that I could have won even though
the expectation was
against
me so it
go if there is one thing in this class
that you remember about probability I
suggest linearity of expectation it is
simultaneously the coolest thing in my
opinion about probability and the most
useful thing for solving problems
so what is it uh the expectation
function is linear let me formalize um
suppose you have two random variables X
and Y and you take their sum and then
you take their expectation turns out
that equals the expectation the sum of
the
expectations okay uh or uh if you take a
random variable and you multiply it by a
constant uh you can pull that constant
out and so more generally this is the
full linearity form if I have
a where am I here some I = 1 to n of c i
* x i this
is uh the
sum I = 1 to n of c i * the expected
value of
XI okay uh it takes almost longer to
write it down than to prove it I mean
it's actually not hard to prove um you
if you stare at this definition enough
um it's because this is a linear
function right if you look at how it
depends on the X's it's a linear
function in in X you've got some
constant weights I mean they depend on
your probability setup but if you mess
around with X and don't mess around with
with your sample space or its
probabilities then uh this is just a sum
of constants times uh X applied to
things so in particular if I replace X
here with X Plus Y and I just Jam that
into the sum I can split this into two
sums and lo and behold I get expectation
of X Plus expectation of Y and these
other things follow in the same way so I
won't write down a proof there's one in
the notes if you want to look uh so it's
almost an obvious thing once you once I
tell it to you but it's extremely
powerful
um mainly because it has no
conditions you don't
need that the XI are
independent you don't need that they're
disjoint you don't need anything except
that they are uh functions over the same
sample space I guess that's the one
assumption you need uh compare this with
remember uh like there's the product
rule
this only works if a and b are
independent or there's the sum
rule we use these all the time but you
have to be very careful when you use
them you have to check are those really
independent uh for the sum rule it only
works if a and b are
disjoint so like when we do law of total
probability we're using this all the
time but but uh you have to be very
careful that you use it correctly
whereas linearity of expectation you
don't need to be careful other than
making sure you define your random
variables well okay let's um Let's do an
example common one in games gambling
games and other games uh dice games
let's say we roll two
Fair uh two side oh sorry six-sided
dice what is the expected value of the
sum well uh the expected value of the
sum is the expected value of the
individual Parts let let me rewrite this
as a instead of words let's use some
notation let's say D1 is the ren that
just gives me what is the value of the
first ey and D2 is the random variable
that gives me what's the second value
the sample space here is a pair an
ordered pair of first die comma second
die so this extracts the first part and
this extracts the second part the
expected value of the sum by linearity
of expectation is the sum of the
expectations and we already did this
example right this was
3.5 uh 3.5
so to total is
seven easy and what's cool is this
didn't even need that the dice were
independent you could glue the dice
together so that they always roll
together as long as that doesn't change
the probabilities of the outcomes which
maybe a little questionable with gluing
but imagine I don't know they're they're
quantumly entangled and however I roll
this die the other one comes out the
same way this will still be true it
changes the distribution but it does not
change the expectation
which is
cool all right so we just needed the
probabilities of each outcome were equal
to get the
3.5
question gluing dice together uh I I'm
imagining like if you if I take two dice
I glue them together then when I roll
them when I roll that unit uh whichever
however the first die comes up it forces
the other one to come up in a particular
orientation right so they're they're
literally tied together so that the the
D1 determines D2 if they're glued
together but this formula applies in
that situation provided it's still
equally likely that you get one two
three four five or six for each die
individually okay it's maybe a little
clear with coins if I glue two coins
together then whichever one comes up
heads the other one also comes up heads
or comes up tails
depending if I glue the head sides
together or heads to
tails all
right uh
so I want to do more cool
examples and they illustrate how to use
linearity of
expectation uh with
it like the the key to using linearity
of expectation is this technique
if you want to compute the expectation
of some random variable uh decompose
that random
variable
into uh a
sum
of
other random variables possibly
indicator random
variables okay you see it here already I
mean we said what's the expectation of
the sum well let's decompose that into
the first die and the second
and then the sum is the first one plus
the second one and then we could split
it up using linearity of expectation and
then compute each of these individually
instead of having to look at the giant
sample space which is the pairs of di
rolls
okay
so
uh this is a technique we're going to
use now several times whatever remains
our time so first example
so previously we analyzed how many times
do I flip a biased coin until I get a
heads uh now let's suppose I want two
heads natural
generalization uh this seems quite a bit
harder because you keep flipping and
then at some point you get the first
heads you keep flipping at some point
you get the second
heads okay well that sounds kind of like
two steps there's how many times do I
flip until I get the first head and then
how many more times I have to flip until
I get the second heads both of those
problems sound like meantime to failure
so let's write that out carefully with
random
variables so uh let's call this number
of flips
F then uh F equal fub1 plus
F2
where uh
F1 is
the number of flips from the beginning
until uh we get the first
head and
F2 is the number of
flips starting after the first
head
until uh the second
head okay so to be precise the sample
space here is um strings of H's and
T's where there's exactly two hes and
the last character is an H right because
I keep flipping heads Tails heads Tails
heads Tails until I get the second H
then I stop so that's my sample space
and F1 is just counting how many flips
are there up to including the first head
and F2 is counting how many flips are
there starting right after the first
head and counting up to and including
the second head which is the end of the
string so together F1 and F2 count the
total number of flips
right but crucially uh F1 and F2 if you
think about it are exactly the meantime
to failure
problems uh because they were counting I
mean F1 is most obvious it's how many
flips do I get do I do until the first
head so uh we know
here the expected Val value of
f is the sum of the
expectations F1 is almost literally the
definition of meantime to failure so
it's uh one over p in expectation F2 if
you think about it a little bit you this
is the same experiment but starting
after the first heads and because all
the flips are independent it doesn't
matter what happened before now it's
still going to be the same
situation uh for
F2 and so the expectation is 2
p almost as simple and in general if I
want K
heads then uh the expect expected number
flips I need to do is K Over P by
linearity of expectation beautiful so
simple
okay
uh let's do another coin flipping
example
so here I stopped the experiment when I
got a desired number of heads what if I
just flip a coin n times no matter what
I always flip end times how many heads
do I expect to
get that's kind of the Dual problem
what do I want to do uh let's do biased
again and biased coins again
independent
uh let H be the number of heads in those
end coin flips we can rewrite this as a
sum
of n indicator random variables where hi
is uh indicator random
variable uh for the I
coin uh coming up
heads okay uh so expected value of H by
linearity is the sum of the expected
values of the
hi okay but the coins are all identical
because they're independent and they
have the same bias I didn't mention it
but we're supposing again probability of
heads is
p uh so what's the so uh this is just
going to be n times the expectation of
hi because they all behave the same and
what's the expectation of
hi we work that out over here if you
have an indicator random variable the
expectation of hi is the probability
that it equals one so the probability of
the event which here was the probability
of heads so that's just
P so this is n * probability h i = 1
which is n * P okay
maybe obvious but
uh yeah we didn't even need that these
were independent that's where it's less
obvious right it just it all we need is
that for each coin the probability of it
coming up heads is
p but it could be all the coins always
flip the same they're always all heads
or all Tails but heads with probability
P or it could be they're independent
these are different setups but the
expected number of heads will in all
cases will be n * P by linearity of
expectation so that's pretty cool
uh you can do a similar trick for did I
erase it the hearts problem I think I
erased
it yeah
um I'll just tell you briefly so with
the hearts you can say the number of
Hearts is a sum
of
13 different indicator random variables
heart I is
um is the E Heart Card
chosen again this is a setup where we
have 52 cards we choose three without
replacement and I want to know how many
hearts there are so this is number of
hearts and this is just did I choose the
I Heart Card in this setup so of course
the number of Hearts is exactly the sum
of uh one for every heart card that I
chose uh so one one this is like Ace and
this is King and we got all the ones in
between so this is whereas here was the
I coin flip or whatever here's the I
heart that we potentially choose and the
probability of choosing a given heart
is is easy it's
uh it's not so easy it's some some small
expression uh it could be you choose it
in the first step or you don't choose it
in the first step uh but then you choose
it in the Second
Step uh or you don't choose it in the
Second
Step uh and then you'd have to choose it
in the third step those are the three
ways you can get it and
conveniently all the hard numbers here
cancel this is exciting
and you
get uh 2 over 52 3 over 52 I can
count uh so you add them up uh 13 of
them and then so you get 13 * 3 over 52
and that's
3/4 so kind of
nice no binomial coefficients required
all right uh one more pair of
examples I have in my notes that this is
a situation that H happens in all of us
are dead which is a great uh zombie High
School TV show
uh I imagine it just happens in lots of
schools but I never went to school so I
don't know if you can tell me whether
this is the case probably less so in the
US maybe l so when you're older maybe
when you're young and you still and you
have a phone you have to submit your
phone when you arrive at school and
here's the weird part and this is maybe
only in a zombie scenario uh at the end
of the day phones are returned uniformly
at
random I hope this didn't happen to you
uh how many people get the right
phone natural
question you care about whether you get
your phone that's also true that's a
closely we're going to have to solve
that problem in fact
okay so assuming here each there's a one
toone correspondence between phones and
people no
ownership um so the number of kids that
get their own phone is uh we can write
as a sum over all kids we had n kids so
k k for kid one up to n of the
probability that kid K Kid K gets their
phone
okay I'm just writing this because I've
pre preworked out these examples of
course when you're solving them you'll
probably know in this part of the class
that you should use this technique
always if you asked for an expectation
probably you might need to decompose the
random variable into sums of other
random variables you might not have to
like this heart problem we solved in two
different ways but if you can it's going
to be easier so I encourage you to try
to do this but how do you decompose into
some random variables I mean that's
divine inspiration you just got to try a
bunch of things until you find something
that works you that gives you think
about what you know how to compute and
then try to build it up or think about
how to decompose top down whatever uh
but as binmore said what I care about is
whether I get my phone and I'm kid seven
I don't know uh what's the probability
kid seven gets their phone or kid one or
whatever it turns out they're all the
same
because uh
oh yeah prob I I I sort of did two steps
here right this is how many kids get
their phone we can call this uh X and
this is going to be um the sum sorry I I
skipped way too many steps here the
expectation of X is going to be
this uh and but the number of kids that
get their phone is going to be equal to
the sum of XK equal 1 to n where XK is
uh an IND or random
variable uh for
whether uh Kid K got their
phone okay this is important because
this was a random variable so I if I'm
going to write equals I should have some
random variables over there when I wrote
a probability that means I'm working
with a number and so that means the best
I'm hoping for is the expectation okay
so this first equation I wrote is wrong
please do not do that in your homework
it's easy to do as you can see but if
you you should first set up the random
variables which are functions decompose
them into sums of other functions and
then say okay let's compute the
expectation use linearity of expectation
this is equal to this uh by linearity
the sum of the expectations of the
XIs and then by the properties of
indicator Rand variables the expected
value of an indicator ROM variable is
the probability of that
event okay
so then what's the probability that kid
K gets their
phone well how many different
distributions are there of the end
phones help me
out n n great
answer n different ways there's n
different possibilities for the first
kid to get their phone back
and
then factorial yeah there's n factorial
different distributions of the phones
that's I said oh oh you said n really
loud which is n factorial thank you bad
pun uh so that's the denominator right
those are the all the
possible
uh all the possible rearrangements of
the phones to the kids and very
emphatically uh and then how many are
there where Kid K gets their phone well
this is easy right this is just saying
well Kid K gets their phone and then
among all the other n minus one phones
they're whatever they are how many
different ways are there to distribute
those phones n minus
one hopefully I didn't max out the
mic okay n minus one factorial Over N
factorial oh my gosh such big factorials
but basically everything cancels and
this is 1 over
n okay 1/ n summed n
times that's
one one ah one kid expects to get their
phone
back
okay hopefully it's
bmore Who's the I mean it doesn't mean
that one person will get get their phone
back maybe none of them do here's a Rel
game suppose uh n
diners uh put their
phones put
their phone singular uh on a
turntable sometimes call the Lazy Susan
for Distributing
food if you're eating family style and
uh then you spin the
table spin uniformly at random
uh and then you take the phone in front
of
you let's assume that this is a discreet
table so when you spin it there's only n
different rotations that could come out
and so there's always a phone
immediately in front of you this is a
different way to be terrible with
phones in this one you know anything
could happen it could be no one gets
their phone back that's maybe it's not
quite what you expect you expect one
person to get their phone back or it
could be everyone gets exactly their
phone back if you do it randomly
anything's possible it's just a one over
n factorial chance that any particular
outcome happens uh here it's actually
guaranteed either everyone gets their
phone back or no one does right because
if I rotate by zero then everyone gets
their phone back if I rotate by any
other amount then everyone gets a
different phone so it's a different
distribution it's a different
probability setup but the expectation is
the
same expected number
of uh matching people phones whatever
matching
phones it's still one here it's really
easy to compute because there are only n
different outcomes and in one of those
scenarios uh you get um so one over n
chance
everyone gets their phone back and in
all other
scenarios no one gets their phone back
so that disappears you get one over n *
n you get one that's sort of the by the
definition of expectation how to compute
this but you can also set it up in
exactly the same way you can say well
you could sum over all the diners and
check what's the probability that a
particular Diner gets their phone back
but now you don't have to do this n nus
one factorial Over N factorial it's just
one over n by the setup was this term
here so this is also the uh
probability of
XI and so you can also do it with
linearity of expectation so this is a
funny scenario where I have two rather
different setups for redistributing
phones they have very different
behaviors but in expectation they're the
same so expectation doesn't tell you
everything about the distribution and in
the next couple of lectures we'll talk
more about understanding the rest of the
distribution Beyond just the
mean all right