I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob Stoner and
this is what if it
[Music]
works from the MIT energy initiative
this is what if it works a podcast
looking at the energy solutions for
climate change I'm Kara Miller you might
know me from the public radio program
Innovation Hub which I hosted I now
write the big idea column the Boston
Globe and I'm Robert Stoner the
president of the Kendall Square project
and former director of the MIT energy
initiative and today a look at the Epic
challenge ahead keeping the World's
temperature from increasing by 2 degrees
CS we need to really get on the road to
Net Zero within the next 10 years if
that doesn't happen then you can kiss
two degrees goodbye we'll revisit an
enormous environment Al success story
that rarely gets talked about how the
ozone layer was saved which meant moving
away from CFCs
chlorocarbons and back in the 1970s
cfc's were in all sorts of things well I
was about 18 then and I had in my
medicine cabinet some underarm deodorant
and hairspray which Believe It or Not
75% of the global use at that time was
for quote medicinal
purposes which were those purposes
that's Susan Solomon professor of
atmospheric chemistry and clate science
at MIT and she was once an 18-year-old
with CFC filled hairspray and deodorant
but she would go on to become a Pioneer
in understanding the hole in the ozone
layer and she believes that much as we
solved that crucial environmental
problem we can do it again which we will
get to but if you rewind for a minute to
the 1970s scientists were only just
starting to realize the huge impact that
cfc's had the early concerns about ozone
actually came from two scientists Molina
and Roland who went on to share the
Nobel Prize in chemistry for having done
such a cool thing and what they did was
to point out that the
chlorofluorocarbons which contained
chlorine were being used in increasing
amounts and that that chlorine had
potential to destroy ozone so they did a
little simple calculation and showed
that the key point was just these things
live for 100 years we're using more and
more of them so it's building up in the
atmosphere it's very dangerous cfc's had
been an integral part of American life
for decades at that point in the 1930s
they were being used to cool things down
in refrigerators and to cool us down
using early air conditioners in the
1970s it became clear cfc's were
building up in the atmosphere which
which is when Sher Roland and Mario
Molina started to wonder if that buildup
had adverse effects which of course it
did and pretty quickly consumers got
motivated to change overwhelming numbers
of Americans went to their medicine
cabinets and threw that stuff away so
hairstyles changed actually that's one
of the big reasons why the bont
hairstyles of the 70s went away which
was really no big loss I think suddenly
underarm deodorant became rolon with
which was advertised as saving the ozone
layer get on the stick to save the ozone
layer that's what people said yeah
Solomon the author of the new book
solvable how we healed the Earth and how
we can do it again says consumers don't
usually realize how incredibly powerful
they are when you look at for example
the closure of coal plants all around
the country many many of them have been
closed because the consumers demanded
that they close so it's quite possible
for people to have a big influence and
you know I'm not saying we're going to
have a 75% reduction in fossil fuel use
that way but even a few percent gets
Industries attention because nowadays
Industries you know operate on the
belief that they have to keep growing at
some pace and they become you know
really concerned when they see a
difference happening she believes we are
rising to the occasion on climate change
because the stakes are high much as they
were a half century ago she calls the
ozone layer the world's signature
environmental success story so what we
have done is to basically phase out the
bad chemicals that were causing it yet
we still have air conditioning
refrigeration and all that happy stuff
so the concentrations of those molecules
have dropped significantly they do have
those hundred-year lifetimes just as was
predicted you know 50 years ago
amazing but uh so there is still some
left but the ozone hole for example is
starting to form later in the season and
it's smaller in the month of September
Solomon says the evidence is unequivocal
that the ozone layer is recovering and
if we hadn't chose to mostly phase out
cfc's we would be grappling with some
terrible problems the world would be in
deep deep yogurt right now I mean the
amount of ultraviolet light that would
be reaching the Earth causing already
increased numbers of skin cancers um it
it would be astonishingly bad so we we
really did something great on top of
that the chlorofluorocarbons themselves
are greenhouse gases so phasing them out
actually shaved off a chunk of global
warming probably by 2050 it would be
about a degree of global warming think
considerable yeah about that so it's
very very good that we got rid of this
stuff but to phase out a class of
chemicals or technology you have to
change the corporate world chemical
companies have to change what they sell
or fossil fuel companies if you want to
fast forward today and that often is not
easy indeed the battles we've seen so
far may be nothing compared to what's
next here's Rob Stoner in conversation
with Susan and me you talk about these
refrigerants and how we found a
different way a different set of
refrigerants that got us into a
different problem and now we're going to
solve that problem but at the end of
that the same chemical industry emerged
we didn't eliminate them I'm wondering
how that kind of situation contrasts
with the climate situation where we have
these fossil companies whose existence
depends on this and there isn't really
an alternative fossil fuel that they can
create that would allow them to continue
I mean what do you think
yeah that's that is a difference that is
that is fundamental and and very serious
I will point out that another issue
where we did achieve A change is uh the
use of lead and gasoline and paint you
know the the the Metal Industries had
had a fairly big investment in in
producing the lead that went into those
products and they weren't going to be
part of the solution they were not part
of the solution they actually had to
change do do something else with the
lead I'm not even sure what they do with
it anymore it's such dangerous stuff it
wasn't pencils anymore maybe they well
actually one thing they could do is U
Mine zinc instead because zinc is uh is
is not toxic in paints but that's
encouraging because they did have to
write off an asset they had to write off
a big asset I mean they owned mines that
were lead mines but you know they were
not on the scale clearly of the fossil
fuel industry the fossil fuel industry
today is a 40 TR ion dollar industry
that's the value roughly of all of their
mineral rights you know they own
mountain tops full of coal they own the
rights to you know certain oil wells
they own offshore oil platforms every
one of which costs about $200 million
and I don't know how many they have it's
probably dozens so they own a massive
amount of mineral rights and
infrastructure it's worth a lot of money
what are they going to do with it is a
very very important question so what
they could do is carbon capture and
storage is is one thing where you
continue to burn the fossil fuels but
you put the carbon right back in the
ground that's right now too expensive to
be contributing in the same way that
some of the other things can contribute
now and one of the big issues is we need
to really get on the road to Net Zero
within the next 10 years I mean if that
doesn't happen then you can kiss two
degrees goodbye so we should be thinking
about the longer term solutions that
will help us in 20 years and 30 years to
get all the way to nit zero but one of
the big things we have to do in the next
10 years is get halfway there and and so
you know Carbon capture and storage is
great research question maybe we'll have
it ready in the longer term but it it's
not going to contribute right now so I
would argue we do the things we can do
right now the other thing of course that
the fossil fuel industry is interested
in is
you know they know how to do a lot of
things with methane they could learn how
to do a lot of things with hydrogen you
know a gas they can make out of the the
hydrocarbons that they have because they
have hydrogen in them the other thing
that they could do is uh make ammonia
which again has
hydrogen so all those options are on the
table and are being thought about is to
you know whether these really are good
Solutions you know how safe is it to
make a lot of ammonia that's hopeful
important question they many of them do
refer to themselves as molecule
companies now not necessarily fuel
companies and so or energy companies
we're not an oil company we're an energy
company you hear that a lot actually
which is you know what it shows you is
that they have understood that there's a
time scale for this what established
that time scale it's the consumers and
it's the the fact that
consumers realized that this issue was
becoming per personal MH that it was
actually perceptible that Summers for
example are hotter and heat waves are
more severe so these are my three PS
that I love to talk about the issue is
personal and perceptible that gets us
going and we find practical solutions
that gets us the rest of the way there
and so the Practical Solutions have also
evolved tremendously solar has gotten
much much cheaper than it used to be uh
it's now you know well cheaper than uh
than coal and even than gas which is
really quite amazing and that's without
subsidies in most of the country and
most of the world actually so the
technology forcing and steering that we
did when when people demand change and
governments do a little bit of
investment and research and companies
see that there's a Economic Opportunity
that steers technology in a certain
direction you put that together with the
3ps and and that's how we solve
environmental problems in my opinion so
I just want to dive a little deeper into
the fossil fuel question and companies
how much resistance is there because as
you say there's like all these sunk
costs we've already built these
platforms already drilled these Wells
this we spent a lot of money doing this
and we don't want to just like abandon
our investments and how much is it you
know beyond petroleum like are they
actually going Beyond something you know
to some other phase in their
lives they're trying to figure out what
that next phase is and you know I think
one of the challenges they face is doing
something at the same scale as what
they're doing now they think about
getting into electricity
generation okay electricity generation
is Big scale it's practiced everywhere
but it's not nearly as profitable so
they have also a big profitability
problem that they have to you know it
may at maybe at some level that leads to
nefarious behavior and doing stuff they
shouldn't do in Washington but I think
more insidiously it it leads to lethargy
and uh disinclination to do things and
finding excuses stuff we all do when we
don't want to do something we get
something better to do probably stuff we
all do when we're making so much money
doing something that's not that great
that you kind of drag your feet to like
change what like an individual might
have the same behavior yeah so I see a
lack of real Vigor and commitment to
changing on the part of those companies
if I can say that without offending too
many of them you I I I don't know really
what the answer to that is they may no
longer be able to function as companies
that do what they're doing and maybe
they have to become different companies
or smaller companies or break up and
become companies that mine or do other
things some of the some of the things
they do will persist these are also very
large chemical companies in many cases
one of the chemicals they produce is you
know fuel but they also produce a lot of
plastics a lot of lubricants a lot of
other things we use throughout the
economy those things will continue
probably
substitutions can be found so so they do
invest in those sorts of things but I
think the notion that they can become
energy companies in a new energy economy
making solar panels and
windmills the this is sort of a I think
wrong I don't think that's going to
happen yeah and it's good for the public
to understand and think about those
things because it helps you to put into
context how to how to view those claims
and I will say that some of those
companies seem to be more genu about
changing than others so I I kind of
hesitate to put them all in the same
basket there is clearly money to be made
by the one or ones who figure out best
what to do instead and and they sense
that and they're going after it I mean
let's face it we don't have a a history
of doing a lot of protection of
industries that had be have become
obsolete you know we we we didn't
protect you know I don't know the the
buggy whip when the automobile was
invented because you know that was a
transition that had to happen um so
talking about companies that are making
things that are systemically important
yeah you don't need haris and deodorant
to run the economy but we've developed
For Better or Worse you know an 8
billion person global economy that that
runs on these things and simply
withdrawing them is absolutely
economically disastrous if it's done
wrong absolutely agree their best bet is
probably carbon capture and storage done
in a genuine way one of the problems we
have right now is that a fair amount of
that activity is actually using the CO2
then to Frack to get oil and gas out so
they they pump it down and out comes oil
and gas but that means that also the CO2
comes pouring out as well so they're not
really putting the CO2 away they're
capturing it but then they use it for
something that I mean all or you can put
it in fizzy drinks I mean you put in
fizzy drinks it ends up fizzing back out
into the atmosphere so you know you're
going to have to decide to really
capture it and a lot of them are not
really on board with that yet because
there is financial value in selling CO2
so is the carbon capture that's
happening
initially that they're capturing what's
coming from the initial drilling yeah no
well from from say a power plant from a
power plant but then injecting that back
into the ground to produce more oil
produce more oil or natural gas or
something got it I mean personally I
think it takes a village I'm being
totally honest with you when you look at
for example getting rid of DDT it took
Rachel Carson writing a book that woke
people up it took people realizing it
was personal this stuff could be in
their bodies it was perceptible Robins
were falling out of the sky by the way I
remember I was I was a child back in the
days of Rachel Carson and I do remember
finding dead Robins on the lawn and
saying mom what is this why are the all
these dead birds
so the Practical Solutions were pick
something else but a lot of the action
that happened was public interest but
also the involvement of of EDF the
environmental defense fund was actually
founded because of DDT oh I didn't know
that and what the environmental defense
fund sprung from a group of citizens who
were meeting in living rooms of
themselves and their friends and talking
about the fact that there were all these
dead birds and they wanted stop the
spraying of DDT and so they started
lawsuits against the spraying against
their town that was doing the spraying
so this was at the very local level and
what ended up happening was amazing they
didn't actually win those
lawsuits the judges would say we have to
study this so you can't use it we have
an injunction against using it right now
and then you know what happened the
towns figured out they could actually
spray other stuff instead and so they
sprayed that other stuff and so EDF
learned how to win by
losing and how to use the courts in the
DDT story and it's really quite amazing
then they did it actually Nationwide and
eventually they brought a Citizens
petition in the state of Wisconsin to
their Department of Natural Resources
which happened to be a state that had a
law that said any any group of citizens
maybe even any citizen can petition the
state about something that's related to
environmental actions by the state so
that was the question is is it okay for
the state to do this and they actually
got so much public attention that it was
a big part of the why DDT was ultimately
banned in this country so that's
encouraging because we're having all of
these sorts of legal disputes over CO2
emissions and we're losing those too so
uh it takes hand it takes a village to
raise the the the awareness to raise the
questions of what else could be done
that's really what EDF was doing with
the DDT lawsuits people do a lot of
things because they're used to doing
them and consumer groups can force
change same thing is happening right now
with permitting for electric companies
so it's turning out to be very difficult
for companies to get permits to install
as much solar as we would like to
install it's not anything nefarious it's
just that the People Who oversee how to
keep the electricity flowing are used to
doing the things they know how to do and
they're very concerned with reliability
yeah and of course they should be that's
great because you know we don't want the
lights coming on and off so they do what
they know how to do and that has to
change that's a big change by the way
the same things happening in China as
I'm sure you probably know it's it's the
provinces versus the federal government
in China but it's the same thing yeah
the locals want to do what they know how
to do and to there needs to be some
level of pressure to get them to
change that pressure could come from the
federal government could come from
people could come from the courts
there's lots of ways to like I said it
takes a village to solve these problems
you know for many years and this was
something bizarre to our listeners I led
a program here at the request of the
Chinese government to bring State
leaders to MIT to teach them about the
technology options available to them and
excellent policy which is sort of
laughable looking back at it and it was
actually quite a good program we learned
a lot but exactly what you're saying it
was get those provincial guys in there
and train them they loved it yeah and
then they went home and did a better job
yeah
[Music]
exactly so Susan um the current
expectation of um sea level rise my
understanding is is based only on
thermal expansion and does not take
other things into account do you think
we might be underestimating how bad
things might
get um actually we do take other things
into account and those other things are
small glaciers okay and of course the
the great ice sheets of Greenland and
Antarctica I'm not sure I know the
latest and greatest wisdom on that but I
think the estimates are that it's about
550 thermal expansion and all that other
stuff CU you know we we have lost a
massive amount of ice on land so it's
the ice that melts on land and gets into
the water that adds to the fact that the
the thermal expansion is just the simple
fact that it's water and as you heat it
up it expands I mean if you've ever made
a pot of tea you notice what happens in
your tea kettle um so it's it's
fundamentally that same process that is
the easier part to calculate it is true
that getting in an accurate way the loss
of the great ice sheets of Greenland and
Antarctica is a tough problem we do
better probably on the small
glaciers so that's where a big
uncertainty lies but it's not the case
that we ignore that when we give you a
number so take all that together what we
think we're going to see by the end of
this century is something on the order
of a meter of sea level R so about three
three and some feet how would that
affect you if you were in a coastal city
around the you know what does that mean
what is
it means you should look at the
elevation of property that you own and
ask yourself how long do I want to keep
this property you know and decide
whether you think you're safe enough
that's fundamentally where we're at yeah
it's a challenging issue and of course
there are whole parts of the world that
are definitely going to go
underwater you big chunk of Florida will
be underwater the State of Florida I
think the highest point in the state of
Florida Rob might know this answer it's
it's only a few feet it's not a lot yeah
Florida is very low the whole so like
three4 feet is really going to change
things in fora it will change the entire
Coastline it doesn't get everything but
it gets a big chunk of Florida it's
funny to see in Florida people building
houses on stilts with the idea that you
know I'm going to survive the sea level
rise of course they're not going to have
any neighbors so I don't know oh maybe
that's good like to live alone I don't
know even more exclusive middle of AC
yeah what are the indicators that you're
looking for that will tell you if things
are I don't know progressing more
rapidly than you think or deviating from
what you you know what you
anticipate um I'm concerned about heavy
rainfall and
flooding which seems to be on the Rise
um I mean it is on the rise we expect
that to some extent based on on the
climate models but the bad thing about
rainfall is that not only do you get a
change in the average amount but you
actually get a change in the shape of
the distribution of rainfall such that
you're getting more of the heavy stuff
and that's that's true pretty much
everywhere in temperature that's not
quite how it is you shift the average
which in turn means that the hottest
temperatures are hotter than they used
to be and you set new records and you
have new heat waves but it's it keeps
the same shape it just moves over a
little bit so we've seen that you know
and many many different measurements
confirm that but rainfall I think is a
lot more uncertain how heavy it's really
going to get it it it's projected to get
heavier but I don't think we know how
much heavier the heavy rainfall will be
and that worries me and things like you
know what it's going to do with
hurricanes you know we don't have an
infrastructure built to withstand the
kind of changes we're going to see we're
already seeing bad stuff happening there
was recently very heavy rain in Florida
caused a lot of flooding and the
governor as he want to do came out and
of course denied that this had anything
to do with climate change but it was
emblematic to me of of a problem that
you have when you're discussing this
with people and people who should not
say such things will will often
attribute one storm or another or a tree
falling down to climate change I mean it
sounds absurd even to me and so we're
sort of stuck in this world where in
order to make the case that it's
perceptible one of your
3ps we've got to somehow claim those
events for climate and and how do you do
that I mean it's a statistical game yeah
and but you know people again are are
are smarter than I think we give them
credit for yes these are familiar
phenomena in the sense that we've seen
heavy rainfall before but the idea that
not only is it heavier than we ever had
it's also happening more often is
actually not that hard for people to get
are we plotting graphs of these things I
mean so that the statistics are really
excitable where can we find
them I mean they're certainly in the
ipcc reports uh you can certainly find
them there the ipcc tell us more about
the ipcc you've been involved with that
for a long time the intergovernmental
panel on climate change is an
international group that provides
assessments of the state of the science
and of the impacts and of the policy
options there's three different groups
and I was the co-chair of the science
panel in 2007 and we provide those
assessments to the UN and also to the
world so it's a very interesting process
you get to see how the negotiators work
the same people who negotiate the
treaties are the ones who discuss the
science with you it's often accused of
being sort of hij acted by the
negotiators I can tell you that is not
the case you know scientific assessment
is so valuable not only for the
diplomats but also for for the public
because you you you
should look at those if you can you
don't have to go through the big
underlying reports that are so thick but
you know you can look at the the
highlights and and ask yourself how did
this get agreed by 113 governments if
it's not true generally that it is true
because that's what has to happen to get
it agreed you know we're at the table
the Russians are at the table the
Europeans the developing countries
everybody it's quite a process you know
the ipcc did something in its more
recent assessment of climate science of
showing what has to happen in emissions
over the course of the century in order
to achieve one and a half or two degree
temperature rise on average and and what
they showed was that we have to remove
they they labeled as removal of CO2 from
the atmosphere in order to achieve those
things and it was clear why they did it
I mean they they want to make sure you
understand I mean if we continue
emitting at the economic rate that we're
continuing to emit then we're going to
have to pull CO2 out of the atmosphere
to hit these numbers but it implied that
we could in some way you know to see
that on a page make think oh well I'm a
diplomat I'm going to you know vote in
favor of uh having uh removals and it
was something like 10 gigatons a year
throughout much of the middle of the
century and in order to hit those
numbers what do you what do you think
about CO2 removal technology is that is
that really a practical option well you
know we talked about this quite a bit
earlier uh it's not going to be
practical in the next 10 years so it
gets back to if you decide that you're
going to continue to use fossil fuels
you're taking on sort of a carbon debt
that you then have to get rid of if you
want to for example keep the temperature
from going above 1 and A2 deg now maybe
you're going to decide you know 2 is
okay then you don't have to remove it
you know those are the kinds of
decisions that are going to have to be
made and they present those
cases not to say this is the way to go
or this is the most likely pathway they
present those cases just to show what
would happen if you chose this pathway
right they have a bunch of different
pathways in fact so the implication
isn't that you can do it this is an
option that's available to you it's that
if you don't then you need a miracle to
occur and this is how big the miracle is
well or you you need to figure out how
you're going to adapt to a hotter
temperature adaptation that's another
really important topic because in large
part the problem with climate change is
not that two degrees warmer is
intolerable to us as people or that more
rain is intolerable to us as people we
can swim and we can find other plac
places to live is that it's too fast we
can't adapt and the ecosystem can't
adapt and other species with less
technological capacity than us can't
adapt for sure something I think about a
lot I haven't quite bottomed out on it
is how we should think about allocating
resources toward mitigating climate
change trying to reduce emissions and
just saying oh my goodness we better put
more money into adaptation building
dikes relocating populations how do you
think about that are you not prepared to
give up yet oh give up what I mean give
up mitigation definitely not yeah you
know you have to view it as a carbon
debt that you're G to have to pay back
so it's like a balloon mortgage I mean I
personally don't like that so I am in
favor of going all out right now on the
things we know how to do and get our
carbon emissions down I think we can hit
50% reduction by 2035 maybe what would
be like the top two things you would
push like let's say the US government to
do yeah I mean we're already doing them
frankly because the uh infrastructure
Act and the inflation reduction act have
a lot of stuff in there that if we do it
effectively we'll we'll drive down our
carbon emissions a lot so it's uh
electric vehicles certainly one of the
problems there is not building out
enough charging systems we're going to
have to really get going on that but we
could if we chose to um the the other
thing is solving these problems of
connecting the solar that we know we
need to connect to the grid and and also
wind you know there's issues of Supply
chains that are affecting the the
buildout of wind we need to solve those
problems but they are solvable they are
things we could do right now so this is
a really important Point you're making
because the cheapest thing we can do is
simply not to emit CO2 and then we don't
have to clean it up the next cheapest
thing is to quickly develop mitigative
Technologies like electrification of
cars that costs a certain amount and and
certainly affects our economy maybe
modestly
negatively but the most expensive thing
we can do is try to adapt in the future
because we haven't dealt with those
things I mean moving New York City is a
lot more expensive than putting in some
charge points for 100 you know moving
Miami for example which we already
talked about is going to be real
expensive one thing we have not talked
about is the geoengineering piece of it
I don't know how much you've thought
about about this um this idea of like
maybe injecting stuff into the
atmosphere how much have you thought
about it where where's your head on that
I've thought about it quite a bit Yeah
because many of those schemes involve
injecting something into the
stratosphere which I know a fair amount
about they are uh zany I mean they're
that's the only word I can think of for
them really um it's it's so refreshing
to hear that it's not that we don't have
the potental poal to do those things but
you know do we really want to put sulfur
in the stratosphere which is what
they're talking about it's be like like
little volcanoes going all the time that
actually we know from stratospheric work
would destroy the ozone layer it would
be detrimental to the ozone layer so um
it's not going to completely destroy it
but it would give us some ozone loss you
know do we really want to take an action
to to set back the most successful
environmental protocol we've ever had
but more important than that there are
several things that are wrong about it
let me start with with the one of the
big ones for me and that is that when
you talk about it as if it were just a
scientific problem you're basically
normalizing the issue you're you're
making it something that the public is
going to hear saying oh scientists think
they can solve this isn't that great so
now I don't have to worry about it I
mean it's that lethargy problem that we
talked about before it's a perfect
excuse for complete lethargy let the
scientists figure it out and I have a
serious question here is it really the
proper role of science to be normalizing
something that we don't know how to
govern the real problem is there's no
reasonable governance structure for this
who's going to be in charge of putting
all that sulfur in the stratosphere and
how are they going to set that
thermostat for the whole world you know
who's going to decide if it's Russ they
might like to be quite a lot High warmer
they pretty cold country you know make
Siberia you know a place where you can
grow a lot more wheat that might sound
real good to them it's not going to be
any individual country but they have the
capacity to do it and so do individuals
you know is it I have nothing against
him but is it Elon Musk who's going to
set the thermostat for the whole world I
mean governance is a big big issue and
it's not being talked about somehow the
the idea is well we'll figure out the
technology first and then we'll worry
about the governance I think it should
be the other way around let's actually
have a serious discussion about how we
would govern this thing if it was
possible you know it's a little bit like
covid you know people are now very upset
over the idea that really we don't have
enough biosafety in the world's Labs so
are we going to just keep doing
biological research that might be
dangerous without having a governance
structure that actually works at the
international level for dangerous things
you know so now there's beginning to be
a little discussion around International
governance of that kind of of
research I think you have to ask those
governance questions in the in the world
that we have today so geoengineering
worries me that way the other problems
with it scientific ones are you keep
emitting this the the carbon which means
you keep acidifying the ocean and the
dangers of that are big you also change
the rainfall patterns and maybe it's
only one country that suddenly maybe
it's India doesn't get the monsoon rains
anymore and so their agricultural system
is completely
upended is that going to be okay you
know personally I don't think it's okay
you know another problem is how do you
stop once you start if you stop you will
have a response in the climate system
and there's some evidence to suggest
that right now we've sort of done that
experiment when you look at how hot
temperatures are for the last year and a
half or so you know they're they're
unbelievably hot much hotter than we
expected yes it's been an elino but it
isn't that extreme of an elino that it
should have produced this kind of global
massive temperature rise there's some
evidence to suggest I'm not saying this
is proven yet but it's being talked
about that the reason it happened is
that shipping fuels got cleaned up so
the fuels for um boats you know there's
a lot of cargo that gets transferred by
by ship nowadays that stuff used to have
very sulfurous fuels that it burned
which put particles in the atmosphere
not as high up as the stratosphere but
you know enough to make clouds and that
that has gone way down because the
shipping industry decided to clean up
their fuel well it's great that they
cleaned up their fuel but it meant that
the particles went away and that may be
part of what's happening in fact there's
papers that suggest that is the story I
I'm not sure I believe it yet but it's a
certain a viable Theory but the notion
being you you take the geoengineering
away ands away you are going to get
warmer how much warmer is it going to
give you a little you know a serious
thermal shock and all kinds of other
shocks like have happened in the last
two years I mean it's it's been bad heat
waves have killed people right now heat
waves are killing people last summer
heat waves killed people heavy rainfall
has uh has caused a tremendous amount of
damage and
death you know it goes on and on the
world doesn't adapt easily to Quick
changes so once you start you know
you're going to you're going to have to
keep going and boy is it is it messy and
with no International governance
structure are you kidding
me my sense is that this this topic
though of geoengineering has gone from
being a taboo 10 years ago to one where
people are trying to do the experiments
they're talking about it a lot more than
they used to it's almost socially
acceptable that's kind of scary
that is this creeping normalization that
I just talked about and I think it
should not have happened I think more
scientists should have spoken out as I
do and I wasn't thinking that clearly
about it either to be honest with you
five years ago and said let's let's talk
governance first and Technology second
because boy we don't want to invent
something that's that dangerous I think
the media is also kind of fascinated by
it I mean I think partially it seems
like wow like could this be the solution
what an amazing sort of Science Fiction
come to light there's some charismatic
scientists who I shall not name
wandering around talking about this
stuff starting companies that do this
kind of stuff and um I would agree with
you that this this this should not be
going on governance should happen first
and if it's if the governance system has
worked out and it's all clear-cut how
you govern the research and also how you
govern the implementation
then we're ready to actually do the
research but we're doing the research
like like Cowboys in the wild wild west
and so the public is getting a message
that is normalizing the conversation and
that is not good yeah so finally um you
written a book called solvable which
seems like a really optimistic title for
like a tough
subject um and and we know we're in a
country and in a world where people have
a very wide variety of views about
climate change what if anything we
should do about it politicians are all
over the map on that kind of thing given
what we've talked about what makes you
think like yeah this is
solvable I really believe we're right on
the cusp of succeeding with this problem
we are right on the inflection point and
the reason is that basically when I look
at environmental issue after
environmental issue I see the same
factors that
characterize when we start to achieve
success it's the public being engaged
and interested and feeling that it's
personal the technology steering going
on that makes Solutions practical we've
seen all of that and it's not just in
this country I would say I mean you're
you're quite right to point out that we
have a a deeply divided nation in many
ways on the other hand amazingly doing
something good about climate change
doing doing actions to to mitigate to
help climate change not be as bad is
popular in this country when people do
polls so people would like to see that
happen people are in favor of clean
energy and it's getting cheap enough
that it's overtaken a lot of the other
energy I mean you can bang on the table
all you want and say I'm going to bring
back coal no one's going to bring back
coal it's uneconomic it's on the way out
we've seen that for years the number of
coal plants has decreased dramatically
and it's happening all around the world
so economics and public
interest and enough of a push to move
those things along is exactly what we
need we are going to have to change a
big chunk of our infrastructure but you
know there's more and more evidence that
we can do that relatively easily people
used to say oh the Grid it's too hard
we'll never change the grid so that it
can distribute energy so
easily we now have carbon fiber wires
that we can put in place of the existing
wires that will be much more efficient
and will move that energy around the
only thing stopping us from doing it is
doing it's not that expensive to replace
the wiring and it's old and falling
apart anyway that's why the
infrastructure Act and the inflation
reduction act were so popular because
they incentivized doing a lot of the
right stuff and in other countries it
will happen too if if we're not in the
Forefront you know maybe it's going to
be the Europeans this time we were in
the Forefront on solving ozone depletion
it's fine with me if you know if
somebody else carries the the the heavy
water on this one and and to a large
extent they have been carrying more
water than we have the reason is that
they are less fossil Rich than we are
it's the fossil rich countries like and
is mainly China and the United States
that have a big job to
do but you know they're not the only
consumers in the world and the pressure
on industry is enormous to be able to
sell not only in the US but to sell
overseas too that's why all the car
companies want to go electric because
they want to make cars they can sell in
Europe too and you know Norway for
example is already almost all electric
vehicles it can be done Norway is not a
very easy country to get around in
either you know they have fjords and
mountains and you know and yet it's all
good you know so we can do it me like we
we're going through your three PS in in
phases you know we've we've got the
perceptible personal and I think we
really are moving into the practical now
as these things become affordable and we
figure out how to put them together and
that's what's happened in every single
past problem whether you talk about
leaden paint leaden gas DDT the ozone
layer smog you name it we did it and we
moved some big Industries around by the
way yeah you know DDT moved the farming
industry out of its comfort zone smog
moved the automobile industry out of its
comfort zone and the automobile industry
was as big as the US fossil fuel
industry in those days
[Music]
Susan Solomon is Professor of
atmospheric chemistry and climate
science at MIT her new book is solvable
how we healed the Earth and how we can
do it again Susan Solon thank you so
much this is great thank you thanks for
having
me what if it works is a production of
the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend to listen and remember
to subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu
podcasts and you can learn more about
the work of the energy initiative and
the energy transition at energy. mit.edu
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob Stoner thanks for listening