I think semiconductor technology is
really the key to address like Global
challenges for example energy deficiency
and uh climate
[Music]
change my research is related to high
temperature electronics that can be
operated in a high temperature
environment so this can um apply to many
fields that requires extreme conditions
one of the main like promising
semiconductor materials we're using is
gallan nitrite which is known for its
ability to endure extreme environment so
this work is extremely important because
um it applies to a lot of fields um for
example uh renewable geothermal energy
is one of them it requires Drilling
Technologies and sensoring systems that
often requires temperatures at range
around like 500° C so um it is very
important to consider the POS abilities
of high temperature Gan nitride
electronic components it's very
interesting to see how semiconductor
materials is interconnected or related
to the advancement in clean energy
fields
[Music]