Next we have uh someone very famous. I'm
going to talk him up. He's my former
boss egg and he's going to present on
Penn South.
>> Thank you. I've got a lapel also. Thank
you, Nick. And as a matter of fact, Nick
will probably uh recognize some of the
beginning of my presentation here
because he was involved in one of the
first presentations we did on the Penn
South community. As a matter of fact,
was involved in the design and did some
of this 3D modeling. And uh I got to
drop back just a little bit. Um both
Carrie who was on remotely
uh Carrie first of all sits on the IATMO
uniform mechanical code technical
committee. In other words, we write
approve and submit the final codes and
there is a a geothermal code as of 2024
and as of 2027 there will be a thermal
energy network code. Interestingly
enough, Mark Mezner C448 is a basis that
we use for a design. So, a lot of that
is being adopted perhaps uh completely.
So, we have so many players in here and
I can honestly say everybody in here has
had a great deal to do with what we're
going to talk about now. Uh now, first
of all, this is part of uh pawn
NAERTA. That's a public opportunity
notice. Now, what they do is they put
out put these things out and they say,
"We got a problem. Can you come up with
a solution?" And if we come up with a
good solution or a problem to fit a
solution and this was for thermal energy
networks, they award us funding for
this. So, uh, this one started in 2021.
Actually, Penn South hired Egg Geo
before that because they wanted to
convert their campus to um geothermal.
And the reason why is because they had,
let me jump back and make sure I didn't
Yeah, it'll cover it in a minute. They
had this 5 megawatt boiler and in
addition to that, they generate their
own electricity. And so local law uh 91
told them if they didn't fix their
carbon emissions by xy year, which keeps
getting extended, they would get fined
millions of dollars a year. So New York
City is one of those cities that you you
hear about the carrot, you know, the way
to get people to do things. They've got
the stick. If you have too many carbon
emissions, you will get fined millions
of dollars a year. So they hired us.
They're pretty affluent. uh community,
152tory buildings covering five blocks
in downtown Manhattan, home to 2500
families. And they have an 18,800 ton
central chiller plant. You can see the
cooling tower there and a 5 megawatt
central boiler. And sorry about the
overlap here that happens sometimes in
these, so just look through it. Um,
local law 38, local law 97. I won't go
into the details of it, but they needed
to get compliant on these. So, they
hired us and then Nick, when Nick was
working with us, we put in an
application for this pond and we were
awarded this pawn. So, we began to study
how we could take this community off of
these boilers and stop the emissions.
There is a New York City tool and I keep
hearing about this with regard to bore
holes and Brock, you probably know this.
You can go on to a tool online and if
you were to look at the details on these
graphs on the right, it shows you how
many bore holes you need to drill, what
the thermal capacity is under the
footprint of that to do a closed loop
system. So, the first thing we did is
studied that and we got the entire uh
community involved with that. But then
we really started looking at this and
this was not easy. This alone took Nick,
our operations manager, Justin, uh
myself, my wife used to work with us as
our marketing director, and it we put on
our combat boots and we went out and we
beat on doors because we wanted to find
out where to get the energy to do that 5
megawatt load. Well, as it turns out,
this is the US Postal Service across the
street and we worked with uh couple of
the um well with first we tried to get
with the federal government and then we
found out we could use a local property
management company but we got the data
on it and they have about 8 megawatts of
thermal rejection through their cooling
towers. So we said, "Aha, there may and
it's they have data centers and
equipment. So they may have it all year
round." And this particular center uses
this orange building. This is the um
this is the physical plant, the chiller
plant and heating where it provides all
the heating for all these buildings. And
we said, well, if we could get this
energy over here, we could maybe even do
the whole thing without a single bore
hole. And kind of like what Carrie said
earlier, you know, that's the whole
point of this. So, we said, "Yeah, let's
go ahead and look at that." And we went
forward with that. And then we start put
on our combat boots and we went out and
we talked to the State University of New
York. We talked to the public school
over here. We've even got Penn Station
involved now. We're almost all the way
to uh to the to the Hudson River at this
point. We may even be able to tap into
that by the time we're done. At any
rate, we went to work on this and uh one
of the things you'll you'll know and
this is the biggest concern we always
hear about to go underneath the streets
of New York is a freaking nightmare.
This this when when Nick was there when
we presented to KED because KED did a
lot like Eversource did here. They were
directed by the PSC to do these thermal
energy networks. Well, you want to take
any kind of a guess how much this is
going to cost? Try almost a quarter
billion dollars. Okay. So, we went to
Coned and they said if you can get it
down to 90 million, you can have it. We
walked because we weren't going to go
cheap and we weren't done with our
study. We just said no. And Penn South
said we'll do whatever you want to. So,
we walked and we're finding ways to
reduce that cost now. Meanwhile, Coned's
doing great work. I mean, Greg Mullis
and the whole team over there. But we
wanted to do this. And part of what a
nice study does is this. This is very
important. Nothing moves fast with
government. You've heard that except I
got to take it back with Eversource and
heat. It just boom. Before I even knew
what happened, it was done over here in
Frammingham. I can't wait to see that a
week from Saturday after the GR
conference. But for us, we were just
like, "No, we want to get through this."
Plus, Sue Doherty over at Nightert is
our project manager. And for every
problem, they ask a hundred questions.
They said, "Well, how are you going to
deal with that? How?" Because they don't
fund this so that somebody can get
something for free. Why do you think
they fund it? So we can clear a path for
others to do it. And that's exactly what
we're doing. So the amount of paperwork
we do to tread the way for others to
follow is monstrous. Our uh our hat hats
off to our engineers and so forth. So we
move forward. They did this is a
actually from earlier this month. They
turned in task five. We had to model it
without
the post office because what if the post
office decides to move? they're just
renting the building after all from and
what if we don't have that 8 megawatt.
So we really had to look at it's kind of
like the backup boiler scenario. So our
guys really started looking at it and
they said, "Okay, here's where we can
put the closed loop, but we'd have to do
the advanced boring solution like they
did in Frammingham." And so that's
expensive. But we have other
technologies and that involves aquafer
coupled. And by the way, this particular
part of Manhattan has a very robust
glacial till aquifer. So we we checked
that. We got involved with it. We looked
at what's called invective flow. If
you've listened to a lot of what we're
talking about doing these flow studies
shows how fast when we're extracting
heat or rejecting heat, it can be
restored. Plus, we have to show thermal
influence to the neighboring properties
because in New York, they want to know
what you're doing to everybody's
property. So each of these models as
Nick will tell you or any scientist can
take eight to 16 even 40 hours. But we
get through this and we look at the
bottom line is we get a thermal
influence over 25 years. And I think
that's the way we're going to go. We're
going to go with uh four doulets and
we're going to be able to handle the
peak. We're still going to need some
boilers and so forth, but this is um the
Penn South Underground utilities. This
is how it's going to be piped. Uh, and
this is what it looks like. That you've
heard a lot about from Carrie about um
single. These are the singular loops and
then there's a transportation loop where
they can all as a matter of fact right
here in Frammingham they have those two
loops. They'll be able to shed or add
load one to another. All of these
individual loops here will be able to
share energy with one another. And this
is just a picture of the big what we
call the transportation loop. What is it
transporting? It's transporting energy.
It's like
it's like the grid when you take a big
load from maybe in Texas they need extra
electricity and you can get it from
maybe Arizona or something like that in
a much smaller way. That's the way it
works. And that is my presentation.
Thank you everybody.