Okay. Hello everyone. Uh I presented
earlier today in in the the morning
session. I'm a professor in ECS and
Seesale as well as a co-founder of this
company Nectri. And basically the
problem we're trying to solve is that
there's on the one hand so much value to
being able to customize software
solutions in the context of particular
companies, but it's extremely expensive
and slow to do that customization. Today
you can use old school software
engineering efforts which requires
attracting people with with rare talents
who are constantly being pulled away by
by big tech companies. Uh or you can use
AI enabled tools to streamline that
process. You can use uh more old school
low code and no code tools. All these
have some significant challenges. If we
want to make it really streamlined so
that people who are not the top software
engineers can create customizations for
important software packages used within
a company and maintain them over time at
a reasonable
cost. So Nectrie is presenting a
platform to uh kind of get the best of
all those worlds where without requiring
software engineering effort you can
customize the software as a service
tools that you depend on. It's built on
a bunch of really cool deep technology.
I don't have time to tell you about, but
definitely stop by our our table where
my my co-founders will be manning the
the demo since I have to go off and
teach shortly after this this talk. Uh,
but it has Google compilers technology
both streamlines development and
produces higher quality software
solutions in the end and dimensions like
performance and security. But the the
one key idea I I want to get across here
is that the way NERI works is by
developing a novel architecture of
highlevel reusable components standing
for features that make sense to regular
people who are not software engineers.
Every component encapsulates inside of
it the full stack of features needed in
a production quality web application,
front end, backend, and database. So you
can snap them together without even
knowing what those words mean and get
complete solutions quickly.
And these components are very high level
compared to what you'll see in in other
platforms. They can be something like a
connector to an existing SAS tool. But
even more interestingly, they can stand
for a a familiar feature like a ticket
system or a data integration process.
You can just invoke those by name,
explain how to connect them to your
data, and then our platform generates
the rest of the the code for a working
application.
And we of course have our own AI enabled
front end like like uh many other tools
these days. So you can chat with an LLM,
but instead of coming up with thousands
of lines of Python code or something
like that, you're coming up with a very
short description of picking some blocks
out of our library and plugging them
together. Humans can read it and check
that something reasonable came out. And
then once it's written, the process of
producing the production ready
application from there doesn't use AI
anymore. It's extremely predictable and
reliable.
We also have a compiler that takes
applications written in this way where
naively you'd think data is following a
windy path through all these building
blocks you're plugging together. Our
compiler straightens out those paths,
removes the overhead of abstraction and
produces code in line in performance
with what an expert developer would
write. So one example I want to
highlight, we'll be showcasing it at at
our table later. It was for a customer
that uses like so many of us SAP Concur
for handling expense report
reimbursement. and Concur didn't
understand some of the details of how
their company works. So, there were
there were some commonalities in every
expense report that was filed, wasting
the time of their employees filling out
all these highly predictable elements of
of of trips and and meals and so forth.
We worked with them to understand the
commonalities across their expense
reports and build a an AI powered tool
that is able to uh apply exactly the
right rules for their context and save
everyone time.
So overall, we're here looking for
design partners could be from uh
companies around the world who are
interested in using tools like this to
help them maintain internal software
solutions that are perfectly tailored to
their their needs without needing
software engineering effort to make that
work. Uh we're interested in all kinds
of industries though two we've been
looking at especially closely so far are
biioarma and finance. Thank you.
Okay. Um um I have a question. I um work
in fidelity and um there are a lot of uh
frameworks and guidelines when building
individual architectural layers like
um there is a state management platform.
There is context management platform. We
use GraphQL uh to get to data and um
it's just experiencing we use
microservices. We use data jobs how you
can apply the different types of
guidelines and how you can customize it.
Right. So uh Nectri can connect to
existing external services and I think
some of the examples you mentioned fall
into that category. uh our our goal
though this isn't fully implemented yet
is you can point nectry to your say
web-based documentation for some kind of
micros service and then it ingests that
and figures out how it works and then
makes it available within our platform
and then a further layer on top of that
when you think about security and
privacy and regulatory considerations we
have a framework for describing policies
about what information is allowed to
flow between uh those existing services
in what ways and the a small team of
technical experts can curate a library
of policies like that which are then
automatically enforced for the solutions
being created by people who are the
experts on the specific business
processes that they're automating.
We have time for one more
question. Well um professor let me ask
you um how does nectry fit into the
landscape of AI based coding assistance
if you can expand on that a little more.
Yeah sure. So most coding assistants
these days are being used to write
programs in conventional languages like
Python or Java or something where the
artifact that the the the app developer
is negotiating on with the AI is uh
quite voluminous with all these lines of
code going into excruciating detail in
Nectri. Instead, the the app developer
is negotiating on a nice succinct
description of the app as just a
plugging together of a bunch of highle
reusable building blocks, which makes
for an end result that's much more
understandable to people and also more
understandable to machines, which lets
us do things like enforce security and
privacy rules.