just the last year the sharp projection
theorem in R2 was was proven and um the
proof is is fairly big. It's fairly
complicated but for the last three
classes um I'm going to want to circle
back to that and talk about the new
ideas in that proof.
So it's been a while since we talked
about it. So I thought we could start by
by we'll start just by writing down what
is the statement.
Um okay so this projection theory I I
like to think of it as a um geometric
measure theory analog of the sum troder
theorem. So I'm going to start by
writing down the summary TH
start by writing down summary try
and there are a bunch of different
versions and we have I've picked out a
particular version that sort of fits
into the way the proof is going to go
for this sharp projection theorem. Um
okay so it says the following thing. So
if E is a finite subset of R2
um and then L is a set of lines
or let's say it this way for every X in
E we'll have L X E is a set of S lines
that go through X and L uh is the union
over x
we don't need this.
So this set of lines L there's at least
s of them through every point of e.
Okay. Um so then conclusion is that the
number of lines is at least the minimum
of a couple of options. There's the size
of E time S or there's the size of E to
the 12 S to the three halfves. We'll
call this um option A and option B.
Okay, option A. It's very simple to
imagine how this could arise. I have a
bunch of points I set E and for each
point I have S lines through it and
they're just all different from each
other. So I get E * S lex.
Okay, option B
is more more special, more remarkable,
although not not that complicated. It's
an integer grid and we talked about it a
couple times in the beginning of the
class.
Okay. So in the integer grid
that
some sense.
So we might have a lot of lines through
each point but still each line is going
through many points. So the total number
of lines is a lot less than E * S. And
if you work it out you get this.
Okay. So that's the semir trotder
theorem. Um, we saw early on that it
implies a sharp projection theorem for
finite sets in R2. And we're going to
try to do some analog for like delta
balls in R2.
Okay, when we talk about delta balls, it
matters how they're spaced. And the
spacing condition we're going to talk
about is the one that Pablo introduced,
the delta SC condition. So I make a
definition.
So uh, if um, E is a subset of R to the
D Let me say that E is delta S C F. Um,
okay. So, first of all, I'm going to
imagine here that E is contained in a
unit ball
or almost unit ball. Okay. And then um
if you take E and you intersect it with
a smaller ball,
it's basically a new ball. If you take E
and you intersect it with a smaller ball
and take the delta covering number of
that then that should be smaller than C
* little R to the S times the delta
covering number of the whole set.
Um so for any X and for any R which
should be at least delta
so that's a delta SC it's a sort of a
spacing condition on the set E that says
that it's not too concentrated into any
small
okay
so here is the statement of the sharp
projection theorem
theorem of Orpinan Schmurkin Ren Wong
from 2024.
All right. So if E in R2 is a delta SC
set
then um every X in E will have a set of
tubes T subX.
This is a set of delta twos
through x.
Um, and sorry, E is going to be this is
it's just a notation choice, but if I
don't match my notes, I'll go bananas.
It's a delta TC set.
Uh, okay. And so for each point, there's
a set of tubes through it. And this set
of tubes
is a delta S C set
um in in S1. So let's make a picture. So
we have a set E which um you may as well
think of as a as a set of delta balls.
So there's E. And then for each of these
delta balls, it lies in a bunch of
tubes.
Okay. And we'll repeat for all of these
other guys. Maybe this tube keeps going
and goes through there and tube there.
Okay. But so if this is x, those tubes
there, that's TX
and they point in different directions.
We can think of the directions as being
parameterized by S1.
And they are a delta SC set in S1. Yeah.
What if you multiple tubes that are in
the same direction of being offset from
each other that I guess delta contain
the same point? How does that
>> Yeah. So if you Right. So if I had this
point and then I had
those Oh, I see. Um yeah, we'll think of
those as the same tube.
Okay. Um,
so the the question was, you know, if I
have my delta ball, could I have two
delta tubes going through it that are
going in the same direction or within an
angle delta of each other? And I'm going
to think of those as being basically the
same tube.
All right.
Um, all right. Then t is the union overx
tx
which could be smaller than the sum of
them because one tube might be in tx for
two different x's.
And the question is uh in terms of s and
t how how big does this need to be?
Okay. Um
cool. Okay. So then the conclusion is
that the size of t is bigger than okay
there's a little complicated stuff
cepsilon delta to the epsilon big c to
the minus order of 1
um and then
there's the minimum of okay so the e * s
corresponds to delta to the minus t
delta to the minus s the so this is this
corresponds to There's somebody that
corresponds to B. DeltaUS T / 2 Delta
-3t / 2 that corresponds to B. And there
is a new thing delta to the minus1 minus
S that corresponds to C. Well, sorry
that doesn't correspond to anything.
There was no C up there. I will call it
C.
Okay. Who So who is C?
Um,
so C is a new phenomenon that has to do
with the fact that these tubes and balls
have a thickness which we didn't have up
there. So here E could just be a could
be any set
and then T is a random set
of delta to the minus1 minus S or so
tubes.
And the probability that a delta tube
goes through a given point is delta. So
a typical point TX would would
essentially be a random
set of around delta to the minus s tubes
and a random set there might be a couple
that are close together but on the whole
that would be that would be a delta s
set of tubes.
Okay so that's where this new option
comes from. Cool. Okay. Yeah. and option
B or is one of the exponents supposed to
be an S fun?
>> Yes, thank you.
That's supposed to be an S,
right? Okay, so let's put these on top
of each other for a second.
So the size of E corresponds to the
delta to the minus T and big S
corresponds to delta to the minus little
S. And so so those match up
and then C is something new.
Okay, good. Now, I realized I forgot one
hypothesis that I'm going to add and
then we'll pause and you can look at
these statements.
Okay, so
we needed one more hypothesis in our
list of hypotheses, which is that this S
should be bigger than one.
You see, if I just had one line going
through each of these points, then I
could just have one line and a bunch of
points on it and one is not bigger than
this.
Okay, so that's a special case. And
there is an analogous condition here in
our list of hypotheses. We need little s
to be bigger than zero. This corresponds
to having not just one tube through each
of these points, but pretty many.
Okay, so that's the statement of summary
trotder and the parallel statement of
this is the firstenberg set conjecture
um proven just recently.
So let's pause there to digest and see
if there are questions or comments about
the statement of this theorem.
Yeah,
>> I'm still having a hard time
understanding what's going on in
case C. Would it be possible to draw a
typical example?
>> Yeah, let's draw case C. Okay, so E
could go anywhere
and then
um I'm going to draw a random set of
delt of of of tubes a bunch of them. So
um okay, so here I go.
So I I drew these tubes
or I tried to do it without thinking at
all about where the points are. There
was nothing clever going on.
Um but uh I drew a whole lot of them and
uh one over a delta fraction if if I
draw a random tube the probability that
goes through here is delta. So if I draw
uh m o times 1 over delta random tubes,
I'll have about m of them going through
this point. So let's say I do that. So I
have about m tubes going through this
point. Now what directions will they
point in? Well, they'll point in random
directions. And a random direction, a
random set is a is a delta SC c set
where s where delta to the minus s is
the number of points.
So so that's that's why we have this
Okay, other questions or comments?
Okay, so now let's start talk about the
history of work on this problem.
Um, and the going through the history of
work on the problem will also be an
excuse to kind of recap a big section
big chunks of our class.
So
[Applause]
history of work slash
recap of the class.
Okay. So first I'll do what I'll call
classical bounds which are uh
essentially due to calfman and falconer
and they were sort of written up in the
context of this theorem. Calfman and
falconer were talking about projection
theory. This is a little bit more
general um but they were written up. So
this kofman kman and falconer were in
the 60s and 70s. a pretty long time ago
and then um adapted a bit by Wolf.
Okay, the first classical argument is
double counting.
There actually two slightly different
ways of dueling double counting and I'll
tell you what they give. The first way
gives that if s is at least t
um then um the number of tubes is at
least option a
and this is sharp.
Okay. So let's think about what it
means.
So s is at least t. That means that the
number of directions through each point
is bigger than the number of points.
So um draw a little picture to the side
here.
So I have a few points, not very many.
And then through each tube I'm going to
draw through each point I'm going to
draw a bunch of tubes. And the number of
directions is bigger than the number of
points. So I have a picture like this.
So what you see is that most of these
tubes don't go through any other point
besides the initial point.
Uh and that gives an easy estimate for
the number of tubes
has to be at least the number of points
times you know the number of tubes
through.
Okay. There is another way to do double
counting and it says that in general so
just if s is bigger than zero which
we've been assuming then the number of
tubes is at least delta to the minus 2s.
Um
um so
let me just let me just leave this one
as an exercise. We've done we've done
some double counting.
Okay.
Um then there was a forier method
um that we did in in class and the
forier method showed that t was bigger
than the minimum of two things. One of
them is option C and the other one is
delta to the 1 - S times option A.
And um so this number is smaller than
one. So this is smaller than A. So this
isn't sharp uh unless we're so lucky
that S is equal to one in which case
this is the minimum of A and C. And
that's that's good. So this is sharp
if s is equal to one.
Okay. So I won't redo this one but this
is uh just the forier method that we did
in the in the third week of of our
class.
Okay. So the classical methods are
occasionally sharp but usually not
[Applause]
um and um okay so another comment about
this story that about why why why this
is difficult is that some of these
statements are fields dependent. They're
true over R, but they're false over C.
But others others uh are true in all
fields. Um so if we go back to the
beginning,
the summary detrader theorem is true in
both R and C although it's not true in
all fields
and is
all C in some in some finite fields.
Well, it's really it's false in all
kinds of things.
Okay,
this theorem here is uh true r but it is
false over
and that counter examples kind of
haunted all of us who have been working
on this.
And one feature of these classical
methods is that they don't distinguish.
um they work
over R or C.
Okay. Um okay. So to prove this theorem
we have to distinguish R and C. So we'll
have to do something which in some way
is different from these. Um and the next
phase in the history is begins with Bans
projection theorem. And I it's a phase
that I'll label as epsilon improvements.
[Applause]
So for quite a while actually there
really was no progress on these
classical methods. These ma classical
methods are from the 60s and 70s. Wolf
adapted them to slightly more general
setting but um but basically there was
no progress for a long time. And phase
two is the phase of epsilon
improvements.
And the dates of this phase are from
around 2000 to very recently.
Um, okay. Where is the Borgan projection
theorem?
And it implies with a little work but
not that much work an improvement over
the classical methods in a very
particular situation.
So it says if t is one and s is 12
then
this number of tubes is at least delta
to the minus1
minus some epsilon we're g
um so if you just plug in the classical
bounds up there it would give this and
there's an improvement although only for
a rather particular for one particular
choice of the parameters.
Okay. Um so that was uh in 2000
and the next improvement
is a theorem of Orphin and Schmurkin
from 2021.
And you could think of it as a
generalization of this. It gives an
epsilon improvement but in not just for
this special value of the parameters but
for lots of values of the parameters. So
they proved that if t is bigger than s
uh which is bigger than zero
then
the number of tubes is at least delta to
the minus 2s minus epsilon.
So delta to the minus 2s is what you
would get classically by double
counting. It takes half a page and then
uh after 50 years and 50 pages you can
get this.
All right.
So in our class we
said a lot about the proof of the BADN
projection theorem. I don't I wouldn't
actually wouldn't say that we proved
every did every step every detail and um
uh this one. Okay, let me say so we
haven't proven this in but let me just
say something about the proof. So this
is based on reg projection theorem
um plus a bunch of ideas.
Okay. And so an emotional reaction that
I had to to learning this and going
through it with you is that it is it's
hard work
and also epsilon is really tiny. seems
like you know the harder the clever we
are the harder we work we keep making
epsilon smaller
okay so this was the second phase of the
history where people were able to make
epsilon improvements I could also
mention other theorems not about this
exact problem but but in a similar
spirit so for many different problems it
was possible to make an epsilon
improvement um by using burgans's
projection theorem and by using and
developing ideas related to the ones we
put there. Uh okay, so it was hard work.
Epsilon was really tiny. But one
positive thing about it is that it did
distinguish uh R from C. So both of
these theorems are false over C. So we
did start to do that.
Okay. Um cool. So this theorem
represents a third stage in the history
where we didn't just improve by an
epsilon over the classical results but
we improved substantially and in fact
proved people proved the sharp result.
This is so so I should mention this.
This is sharp.
This is sharp
for any essence.
>> Yeah.
>> Is that delicac
or
>> Yeah, it's sharp up to this. So
sharp up to the delta to the epsilon.
In future I'm going to abbreviate that
mess by this. we won't be at the level
of detail to have all of this in.
Okay. So, um so this this the story I
wanted to try to tell to explore over
the last three classes is how is it
possible to get from these epsilon
improvements to sharp theorems. That's
that's our our theme for the rest of the
class. Um, and if I had to say it in a
couple of sentences,
what happened was people found a way
where you can use an epsilon improvement
theorem and you can use it over and over
again and sort of each time you use it,
you improve a little bit the exponent in
your bound until you bring the exponent
up to the sharp value.
Okay? Now, it's not at all obvious how
to do that, and that's what we're we're
going to try to explain. uh um not with
all details but to to make it seem like
a plausible approach that you could that
you could carry.
Cool. Okay. So any questions or comments
before we start? Yeah.
>> Does doing that process make the like C
to the O one constant kind of
corresponding way I guess tiny compared
to the epsilon constant?
>> Um yeah. So I think the question is as
as we as we use our epsilon improvement
theorem many times does that cause this
to become remarkably bad?
I think it does. Okay. I think that this
is remarkably bad.
Yeah.
Okay. Great. So today I my first goal is
I want to describe the simplest example
where you can get where you can use an
epsilon improvement theorem to prove a
sharp theorem.
And then after that if we have time I
will outline the proof of the big thing.
Okay.
[Applause]
Okay. So, simplest
example
where
epsilon improvement
leads to sharp out.
Okay, so this is a theorem of Beck from
around 1980
which is about the incidences of points
and lines. So it's in the setting of the
summary troder theorem.
It says if E is a subset of R2 and it's
not all on a line and in fact I'll say
at most half of it is on a line. So for
any line L
L intersect E is at most half of it.
Then the conclusion is there exists some
point X in E. So that uh all right so
let me make a definition. So I I'll draw
a picture. So this is E.
Here's our set E. Here's a point X.
Starting at X, I will draw all the lines
that start at X and go through some
other points at E.
Okay. So what's that set? So I'll call
it L XE. This is the set of lines. So
that lines L. So that X is in L and L
intersect E is not just X. So it has
size at least two.
Now the conclusion is there is a point
in E so that the size of LXE is
comparable to the size of E.
This is clearly a sharp theorem because
the largest possible size that this
could be is the size of
all right. Um let me do a proof sketch.
Um and we'll so we'll see that this
follows from sem ready troder. Um but
we'll also see that we don't really need
the sharp exponents in semi troder. We
just need to have something that's an
epsilon better than um uh than a than a
simple bound. That's why I've erased it
but than the double counting kind of
bound.
Okay. So here we go. So the sketchy part
of my proof sketch is that I will
suppose that we are in the uniform case.
Namely for every x in E, I will suppose
that lx of E has size around S.
So it's not really the case that they
would all be comparable, but I'll just
explain that special case.
Okay. So now um how many lines are there
in total? We can do a double count to
find the total number of lines. So we're
going to double count pairs um x l where
x is in uh e
and l is in our set of lines.
So our total set of lines is going to be
let's do this.
Okay. So how big is le? Um well we could
count the number of these pairs in two
ways. We could count okay look at all
the points of E and each of them is in S
lines
or we could say look at each of these
and um how many points are in each line?
Well,
the number of the size of
uh S the size of E intersect L
for a typical L and L XE would be the
size of E divided by the size of L XE.
Right? Because I have all the points in
E. They are divided among the lines of
LXE. Again, assuming it's uniform, they
would all have around this size.
E over L XC
which is S.
Okay. So this is the number of points
times they're each in S lines versus the
number of lines times they each have
this many points.
Okay. So when we solve we see that the E
actually drops out and we conclude that
LE is around S squ.
Okay. So um our goal is to have a lower
bound on on S. So we want to have a
lower bound on LE and the semi trder
theorem exactly gives us a lower bound
on LE. So we can use it. So the semi
trider theorem tells us that L
is at least the minimum of S * E and S
to the three * E to the 12. Okay, but
this L E is is S squ. So if you compare
these we can get a lower bound for S.
In in this case we would have S^ squ is
bigger than SE. So s is bigger than e
and in this case we would have s^ squ is
bigger than s^ 3 e to the 12 and with a
little algebra that is again s bigger
than e.
[Applause]
Um so
right.
Okay.
[Applause]
Right.
Now,
now I claim that we didn't need to have
this exact formula here. Let me write
down all that we needed to to know.
So what we needed to know
is just that if E is much bigger than S
um then the size of L E is much bigger
than S squ.
So that's a feature you can read off of
this formula. If E is much bigger than
S, then either one of these is much
bigger than S^ squ. And that's all we
needed to know because we know that L E
is only S squ. So by the contraositive
we could see that E
S is not much smaller than E S should be
at least around E.
Okay. So this thing that we needed to
know
is very similar to the Orpin and
Schmurkin theorem.
E is much bigger. So now let's look up
at that Orpin and Schmurkin theorem says
if T is bigger than S just bigger than
zero.
So T is measuring the size of our set E
and little S corresponds to big S.
So that first hypothesis is saying that
the set is much bigger than the number
of directions.
And then the conclusion is that the
number of lines is much bigger than S^
squ. that thing is this.
Okay. So this matches
the theorem of Orpin and Schmurkin the
epsilon improvement theorem.
Okay. So that suggests an idea that we
could use that epsilon improvement
theorem by Orpin and Schmurkin and put
it into an argument like this one and
prove some kind of generalization of
Beck's theorem that might have a sharp
conclusion even though we stuck into it
just a epsilon improvement
and that actually works. So I'm going to
write it down now for us.
Okay.
So this is called the continuum
or we could call it in our class the
delta ball version of back theory.
Okay. So this is a theorem of merkin and
wong in 23 I think.
All right. So we're going to translate
this theorem into the language of delta
SC sets.
So we're going to say if E is a deltaU
set, I'm going to leave out the C. Uh
things will depend on C, but E is a
deltaU set. Okay, so that's our set. Now
I need an analog of this hypothesis that
E is not too much in the line. And the
analog says that E will be not too much
in any thin rectangle.
So we'll say if R is a row by one
rectangle
um then
if you take E and you intersect it with
R take the delta covering number of that
should be kind of smaller than the total
delta covering number.
Okay so it should be row to the ADA
smaller than constant row to the ADA is
smaller than the total delta covering
number. Maybe we can we can put the C
back here also. So who is ADA? At the
very beginning of the story, we'll say
for every
ADA bigger than zero. So ADA should be a
positive number. Okay. So this is a not
super strong condition, but it's saying
that E is not heavily concentrated into
a thin rectangle.
Okay. And then the conclusion is um
there exists an x in e s so that
um the size of lxe
is greater than um
uh the minimum
of delta to the minus u and one. So this
would be and sorry not one delta to the
minus one.
Okay. So what's going on here? The our
original theorem would say that lxe e is
at least the size of e and that's the
size of so that's what it's doing here.
On the other hand if I had every delta
tube if lxe consisted of all the delta
tubes through x there would only be
delta inverse of them. So it couldn't
possibly be bigger than this. So we have
Okay.
Um cool. So that's the statement of the
theorem and it is again uh sharp because
as we just explained this couldn't
possibly be bigger than this and it also
couldn't possibly be bigger than this.
Okay.
Um
correct.
So this theorem is sharp. It's also
false over C.
Right? So the example over C would be
that the set E
could be uh R2 which is sitting in C2.
And if you imagine R2, if you take any
point in R2 and look at all of the
lines, complex lines that um go through
that point, um there aren't the the each
one of them goes through many of the
points of R2 and um and the number there
aren't that many of them. It would
violate this.
Okay, so this theorem is uh in the
general spirit of projection theory. um
it is a sharp theorem and it
distinguishes R from C and I believe it
is the first such theorem in the
literature. So we were trying for 20
plus years to distinguish R from C. For
a long time we could only do it with
epsilon improvements. But this is not
just an epsilon improvement on what was
known before. It's not just an epsilon
improvement on what's true over over C.
And it's a sharp theorem.
Okay. Any questions or comments about
the statement?
So the problem depends on
>> yeah so if you unpack this it must
depend on ADA. Uh I think it is a
constant depending on epsilon and ada
delta to the epsilon and big c to the
minus big.
So it depends on it depends on aa
it's conceivable that this depends on
ada. I'm not sure about that.
Other questions or comments?
Okay. Okay. So the the idea in the first
place is to imitate this proof of Beex
theorem proof that converts um a uh
a an epsilon improvement on some simple
estimate for sem ready troder into a
sharp estimate for this beck kind of
thing. Um but when we try to do that we
will see that there is an issue with it.
Um and and when we flesh out the proof a
little more, it will involve using the
Orpin and Schmurkin theorem not just
once but many times at many different
scales.
All right. So let's sketch the proof.
So first plan
is to imitate
the proof of uh of Beck.
[Applause]
Um okay. So let's carry that out over
here. I'll put the beex proof up.
[Applause]
All right.
So attempt attempt one.
[Applause]
All right. So let's say that lxe
is a delta SC
set.
Now that's related to the cardality of
LXE. This is a theorem about the
cardality of LXE. What is the
relationship? Well, it implies that the
cardality of lexe is at least uh around
delta to the minus s, but it could be
much bigger.
[Applause]
Okay, so an example where these would be
about the same is if lxe was sort of
like an s-dimensional caner set. An
example where they would be very
different is uh if is if LXE was very
clumped. So here's a piece of S1 and
maybe LXE
is clumped like that. So these dots
represent Lexi.
So if it was if if Lex was really
clumped into a much smaller interval
then um S would actually have to be
zero.
This is not a delta SC set except for S
equals Z.
On the other hand, the cardality of LXC
in this picture is is is large and in
particular, it's much larger than delta
to the minus0.
Okay, so this S is some non-conentration
condition and non-conentration forces
our set to be pretty big. But it could
also be much bigger than that if it was
kind of clumped.
Okay. So let's uh let's try to imitate
our proof. Uh I'm going to suppose that
we're in the uniform case.
So all of the lxe have the same s
and the same size of lx.
Okay, we can do our same double
counting.
That part doesn't change at all. And it
has it gives us L E is at least
L XE^2.
Okay, sorry, is approximately LXE squ.
And so to get a lower bound on LXE, it
suffices to get a lower bound on LE.
What happens here? Um so now we can
apply the uh theorem of Orpin and
Schmurkin epsilon improvement
which I just erased in a suboptimal use
of blackboards. Um but uh what it says
in this case is uh that if u if s is
smaller than the minimum of u and one
but bigger than zero
then we get
le e is at least delta the minus 2s
minus epsilon. So that this would be the
classical bound
and then we have this.
Okay. And then we're interested in lxe.
That tells us that lxe
is at least delta to the minus s minus
epsilon.
Okay, so let's take stock.
If S were equal to the minimum of U and
one, then LXE would be at least delta to
the minus S. That would be the bound we
want to prove. So in that case, we would
be very happy.
Okay. Now suppose S is in this range.
Well, then we get this bound.
This bound is a tiny bit better than
this bound,
but that's all.
This argument didn't work so nicely as
that argument because in that case there
was no distinction between cardality and
the value of s. In that case this was
the same as this. So we would get a
contradiction at this moment and we
could we could conclude that actually s
is the minimum of u and one.
Okay.
Um so we did learn something. Um
you know if if lxe were kind of spread
out you then you might hope that the
cardality would be about delta to the
minus s and in that spread out case then
we could get we would follow that that s
was the minimum of u and one.
So we see so we see this correlary
if um
lxe is a delta s set
and the size of lxe
is around delta to the minus s then we
would get that the size of lxe is
greater than around the minimum of delta
to the minus u and delta to the minus1
and we would be happy.
But it's a big if and we don't
understand yet very well what might
happen if these sets were a little more
clumped.
Okay. Cool.
All right. So um let me put up a summary
of what we've learned so far. So lama
if s is bigger than zero and a typical
lxe
is delta sc.
Um then
size of typical lxe is at least delta to
the minus s minus epsilon or sorry yeah
if
0 is less than s is less than the
minimum of
okay so the proof of this theorem we
don't have it yet we have this lema um
the proof of this theorem is by
bootstrapping this lema using it many
times at different scales and locations.
So we are effectively using the epsilon
improvement many times not just once and
at many scales.
about it.
[Applause]
All right. So, let's do a sketch of this
bootstrap iteration.
Okay. Um so we're going to suppose
that lxe first of all is uniform
and also that it is delta sc for some s
which is bigger than zero. It's the
start of our bootstrap.
So because it's uniform and it's a delta
SC set then it follows that if you take
its sort of its row neighborhood then
this is a row SC set
for every row.
And now we can apply our lema.
And the lema tells us that the cardality
of lxe the row covering number of lxe
is at least
row to the minus s minus epsilon. So row
to the minus s is what we get just from
being a row sc set. But actually has to
be a little bit bigger than that by our
lema.
And that's true for every row.
And now since since we have a uniform
set
and since these row covering numbers are
a little bit bigger than expected tells
us that lxe
is a delta s plus epsilon c set.
Yeah, actually I should here I needed to
put 0 is less than s is less than the
minimum of e1.
We used all of these are hypotheses of
our lema. So we use them here.
Okay. Now this is our starting
hypothesis. So now we can iterate.
[Applause]
So s keeps getting bigger and bigger as
long as it's smaller than the minimum of
u and one. And so it will approach the
minimum of u and one
and then we're happy.
Okay.
So unlike in the proof of beex theorem
we had to use this lama many times. We
used it at many different scales and
also we had to use it over and over
again and each time we used it we
improved this exponent a little bit
until the exponent approached the
exponent that we had in the classical
vest.
And so this is sort of typical of this
new paradigm that you can take an
epsilon improvement result and use it
over and over again to keep epsilon
improving something until the thing
reaches the sharp value.
Okay. Now you might be wondering how we
started this argument. We needed to
start with an S that was bigger than
zero. And not every set is a delta SC c
set for any s.
Um so to start the argument
we observe um that we had this
non-conentration in rectangles
condition.
on concentration and rectangles
condition here that our set is not too
much in any rectangle.
We haven't mentioned that hypothesis
yet. We use it here to get started. So
to start with
non-conentration in rectangles uh easily
implies that lxe is a delta ad set.
[Applause]
Um because so if E looks like so there's
not too much of E in any rectangle
is our X. Therefore there aren't too
many of these rectangles too much. You
can't have if you had a lot of lxe in a
small angular range it would mean you
had a lot of E in a small rectangle. And
that says this doesn't happen.
Okay cool. So now we have sketched the
proof of the continuum beex theorem the
first sharp theorem in projection theory
distinguishing R from C. So let's take a
take a couple minutes to digest see if
you have questions or comments.
Yeah.
>> On the uh I guess kind of the second
step of proof would be Lexe row is that
the intersection of LXE with a kind of
row radius ball or
>> sorry. Um so lxe e row is the row
neighborhood
of lx. Actually you can also you can
also erase the row. Maybe that's the
best thing to do.
Okay. So lxe is a delta SC set and if
it's uniform it's also a row SC set for
all the bigger rows for row delta
>> for yeah for all row. Yeah.
Yeah. Thank you. Thank you.
Yeah.
Okay. Yeah. So, so recap. So, we don't
so we don't Yeah. We don't we don't need
to mention the right. So, so say it
again. So, LXE is is uniform set. If
it's delta SC, then it's also row SC for
all the bigger rows. And so, then we get
these covering numbers and then get
okay. Okay. So let me share a personal
reaction. So when this paper came out
first of all I was very impressed
because it was you know I had been
wondering about this for many years and
it's the first sharp projection type
theorem which distinguishes R from C.
But I also
felt kind of unsure whether this would
open the door to prove sharp results for
things like the first set problem. Uh
maybe it's a sharp result but maybe it's
about a kind of thing that somehow is
more approachable. It was well known
classically that a epsilon improvement
of something implied a sharp version of
the class of the incidence geometry
something here and that's just not the
case for semary trotder. Sem ready
trotder is not known to follow from an
epsilon improvement on on some classical
thing. Um and so it wasn't clear to me
if this would open the door to prove
sharp theorems about all the things we
most cared about.
All right. Um so in the rest of this
class what I want to do is to uh give a
give a outline of the proof of the of
the of the first set conjecture and the
different ingredients that go into it of
which this will turn out to be an
important one.
Okay,
cool. So the the first thing to say is
that this proof breaks into cases
according to the way the the set E is
spaced that this del this delta TC set
that definition on the one hand it's a
good definition but under the umbrella
of delta TC sets there are several diff
quite different ways that the set E
could be spaced and we have to pay
attention to them and we have to treat
them in different ways.
All right. So, let's explain that.
So, we're going to split into cases
according
to how
E is spaced.
All right. So first of all, let's assume
that E is uniform.
And I'll now I mentioned the word
uniform above, but now I'll remember
recall exactly what is uniform.
Okay. So first of all, our delta is
going to be
capital delta to the M where M is a
large number.
And uniform means that for every J going
from one up to M and for every Q which
is a delta to the J cub.
Then when I take my set and I intersect
it with Q and I cover it with cubes or
balls at the next smaller scale delta to
the J + one. Um that is is around RJ. So
um
so I'll draw some pictures in a moment.
The smallest this RJ could be is one and
the biggest it could be is big delta to
the minus2.
Oh
um
actually yeah let me say a little bit
more. So the delta covering number of v
that's going to be the product j = 1 to
m of rj.
Um and another thing we we can say is if
I if I were to take the product J equals
1 to capital J of RJ that would be the
covering number of E at scale delta to
the capital J
and that should be so
um let's say so
so if E is a deltat TC
Then this should be at least 1 / C um
delta J to the minus.
So that gives some information about
these products and
being a delta TC set is equivalent to
this information about these products.
And so there are many ways that they
could look.
Okay, let me put up a couple of examples
which also should hopefully clarify
everything on this board and then we
pause for questions.
[Applause]
All right.
Okay. So the first example that I want
to put up
is that all the RJs are the same. So RJ
is delta to the minus T for every J.
Okay. And then you'll
see that this this will be okay.
Um all right. And I'd like to visualize
this in two ways.
So the first way I'd like to visualize
is as a tree. Um so oh in my
visualization I picked that delta is
four. Delt no delta is uh 16. Um and no
sorry del sorry delta is one pointer and
we and t is going to be one.
Okay. So in in my visualization delta to
the minus one is going to be four. I'm
going to have tree. So that be r1 guys
coming out of it. And then each of these
have r2 which is also four uh uh
branches coming out. I won't draw that
but they're all the same.
Okay. Now let's do the next stage of our
visualization. We started with a square.
and we cut it into smaller squares of
side length delta. So that looked like
this.
This is stage one
and r sub one is four. So we took four.
So maybe this one.
Okay. Stage two.
inside of each of those four squares.
I took each of them and I cut them into
a 4x4 grid of smaller squares. And I
took four of them. So I'll do the
cutting carefully here. Right. So maybe
I took
those four and then down here I took
four
and over here I took four and over here
I took four.
So our set looks something like that at
stage two in a new
All right. So this is the first example.
It's called the ad regular example.
Alforce devided regular. Alforce and
Devid are two people who worked on stuff
that is related to this. And the word
regular I think here refers to the fact
that all the scales are the same as each
other.
Okay.
Now let me show you an opposite extreme.
Okay. So this one is called the well
spaced example.
So in the well spaced example, RJ is as
big as it could be its maximum value for
some range of J
and then RJ is one for larger of J.
Okay. So as a picture it would look like
this. So we're going to visualize
with uh big J is one, big F is two like
over there. So we'll have two stages.
And so our first stage is that R1 is 16.
Draw it off. And then R2 is one. So from
each uh point here, we have just one
going down.
So the tree looks like this instead of
like that. A lot of branching at the
beginning and then no branching after
that.
Okay. What does it mean? Our set looks
like in space. Well, first stage one, I
take my square and I break it into 16
squares of side length a quarter.
And at stage one, I select all 16 of
them. So the picture looks like this.
Okay, now at stage two.
So I have cut my square into 16 squares
of side length a quarter and I look
inside each one of them. I cut that into
16 squares a smaller size and I pick one
of them
and I do that in all in all the ones I
selected at stage one which is all of
them. So this set looks like this.
Okay,
so this is called the well spaced set.
So I could fix a t. I can make a delta t
well spaced. I can fix t and delta. I
can make a delta t wellspace set or I
can make a delta t alph4's regular set.
And they look rather different from each
other. And there's also a gray area in
between.
Um so this one is distinguished by
saying that the points
are the most separated.
So if these points were like electrons
that were sitting in this ball and they
repel each other, they would come to a
position that's sort of like this. It
would be well spaced.
And this one is distinguished by being
this is the most clumped
which is allowed
for a delta t set.
So this isn't the most clumped possible
set. I could take these delta balls. I
could smoosh them all there. That would
be more clumped. But if it's a delta t
set, it's not allowed to do that. And
this is the most clumped that it could
be.
subject to the definition of a delta t
sub.
Okay, cool. So,
so there's a range of spacing conditions
um and and this hopefully gives a sample
of Yeah.
>> Is there some sort of like energy
condition or kind of quantitative
measure of the clumping that would kind
of allow you to separate the two cases
because they're both delta SC,
>> right? So the question is there is there
a quantitative measure of clumping or
concentrating or spacing that would
allow us to distinguish them? Um I I
think the nicest way to do that is this
list of RJS or perhaps this list of uh
this list of these numbers here. Yeah.
So it's not just a single number, but it
is quantitative. And if you're willing
to have, you know, like a a list of
numbers describing your set, then it
does quite a good job.
Um, it's really a modern innovation to
focus on that. In in previous times,
people wanted to describe the spacing of
their set with one number, which would
be like the dimension of the set or the
energy or something. Um, and when they
were describing with just one number,
then it was lumping together these two
rather different behaviors. And it turns
out to be important to unlump them um
for to prove this theorem at least with
the proof that we have.
Okay, good. Uh, okay. So now I can write
down the outline of the proof.
Okay,
so here is the outline of the proof of
the main theorem or let me say of the
first conjecture
first.
Okay,
so first main ingredient
is a theorem of Borpin and a Schwarin
from 24
and they proved that the Fenberg
conjecture holds in the ad regular case.
Okay, so this is based on it builds on
the stuff builds on the stuff we talked
about today. So it builds on the
continuum bec theorem of OSW which in
turn built on the epsilon improvement
of uh or OS which in turn built on the
BAN projection theorem.
All right, it's not at all obvious given
the Beck theorem, just an ingredient.
Um, and um, so there also some great
ideas in that that we'll talk about next
time. But also it involves some special
structure
of the AD regular case.
Okay, we'll talk about that a lot uh on
Thursday.
All right, the second ingredient is a
theorem of Guth Solomon Wong. So I was
involved a little bit. This a slightly
older theorem. It's from 2019
and we proved that the first invert
conjecture holds in the well spaced
case.
Okay. And it's based on the forier
method.
Okay, this is much less difficult than
this. It's the 4A method that we
explored for a while with a little bit
of extra something something. How do you
take advantage of being really well
spaced instead of just ad regular
okay
good. All right. So now um
when I presented these two possibilities
it the way I had thought about them is
that these are just two opposite ends of
a whole gray spectrum.
And so if you have a method that works
in one end and you have a method that
works on the other end,
I guess you might hope to have a general
thing that sort of combines them both
and and works for everything. But um but
there's still all this stuff in the
middle.
Um and it turns out I think this is
surprising and important in its own
right that the proof of the theorem
actually reduces to just those two cases
or or um so the third ingredient
is a multiscale argument
which shows that the first conjecture
actually reduces to
the ad regular case and the what they
call the semi wellspaced case.
So this is a small generalization of
this case that can be handled by more or
less the same methods using for
analysis.
Okay. Um
cool.
Okay. So in in each of these I think
there is something worth talking about
and worth worth remembering an idea that
could be useful in other in other pro
certainly in other problems in this
field and maybe in other parts of math.
Uh we have two more classes so I'll
vigil and wiggle and so my goal is in
the two classes to say something
substantial about each of these three
ideas which fit together to prove the
first and third conjecture.
Okay, good. Any question la last
questions or comments?
>> Mhm.
>> Within kind of each of these individual
cases like how kind of much variation is
there in the structure of the sets? Like
I guess it's not going to be kind of
rearranging kind of certain points
within kind of one of the boxes does a
lot or does a little
Yeah. Okay. So the question is we've t
so we've taken all the delta t sets we
have then divided them according to
their branching function and one extreme
is the ad regular and one extreme is the
wellspaced
and then the question is if you look
among different sets with the same
branching function like among different
ad regular sets how different are they
from each other? Um
well
[Applause]
uh I will try to sort of answer that by
drawing a second ad regular set in blue
that we can compare to the one in white.
So I should pick four uh big squares and
in each of them I'll draw four dots.
Um
um
I would say that the sort of
spacing feel of these dots is is the
same in all the examples that are ad
regular. Um on the other hand actually
let me draw another example. So this
this would be here's another example.
So
something else is a little different
about this example. Um and so yeah, so
there are some more delicate things that
could be different about the different
ad regular examples. Even though so so
what's the same about them is you give
me a radius your favorite radius you
stick down a ball of that radius and
count how many points are in there that
will be the same for any a dregular set
but there are delicate things actually
another very important delicate thing
that would be different is so for let's
now think about the well spaced set an
example of a well spaced set is an
integer grid
that has some special properties. It has
like translation symmetry and stuff like
that. A typical well spaced set will
still have one point in each of these
boxes, but it won't have additive
structure. It won't have translation
symmetry. It won't have and it won't
have uh you know very many lines that go
through many points. So those kinds of
things are different among the different
sets with the same spacing condition.
Uh okay. Well, let's stop there for
today and we'll talk more about these
things on our last two classes.