good morning everyone and welcome to the mpg
primer and today it is my great pleasure to
introduce Mark elosua bayz he is a computational
biologist in the cell Discovery Network an
initiative within Boston Children's Hospital
which I've used for help so many times um he
aims to use the power of single cell and spatial
resolve Technologies to provide Precision medicine
treatments using highresolution Technologies to
interrogate biology he wants to better understand
disease driving mechanisms where a patient
sits within the disease landscape and how
to effectively treat it from the cell Discovery
Network he wants to spread single cell biology
knowledge and help more people to analyze their
data um so today he's going to be talking about
introduction to single cell RNA seek workflow
please feel free to ask questions throughout
there's two mics in the middle of the room and
you can also wave your hand and we'll come over
to you thank you very much so I'm going to be
talking a little bit about the introduction to
single cell RN I don't know how familiar everyone
is so um I just want to like provide General ideas
of how to analyze the data what considerations
and try to like give sort of like an intuition
of why we're making specific decisions that
uh we believe are are very important in the
in the analysis and these are tool agnostics so
regardless of the tool that you want to use uh
you can go ahead and I think we also don't want
to focus on any one specific tool because there
will be constant tools coming up so just providing
the the Baseline of like when I'm doing this sort
of analysis what what should I be looking out for
what are the limitations uh and what is happening
under the hood uh at a at a broad level um so for
the agenda we're going to uh start a little bit
from the basics so once we have our count Matrix
or gene expression Matrix how do we go to the
the the graph representation of the data
uh and then I want to dive deeper into the
quality control and the batch effect and and
integration assessment which I think are are
two of the key parts of the of the analysis
and then just very quickly provide some data
resources and Tool resources um I think could be
very useful um but before we start why would we
ever want to use single cell RN seek and
I think I just put a few things here but
first of all it allows us uh unprecedented
levels uh of resolution so it really allows
us to understand solell heterogen heterogenity at
a unbiased quotation marks um way uh since we're
going very deep into this biology it can allow us
to also detect Noble and rear C States depending
on how we design our experiment it really helps
us map lineages and and development trajectories
um and ultimately can lead into insights um into
how disease progress in the the mechanisms of it
um so basic steps is I want to start by being
like where do we want to get to um once we have
our data I feel like not many people know this
but single cell RN works on a graph structure
and I'm not sure going to try to like put too
much too uh too much math in in here but like
just to get the understanding that we're working
on the kers neighbor graph where or we want to get
to a point where we can build this kers neighbor
graph where each cell is a DOT and these cells are
connected between them regarding on how similar
they are between them um how do we get from our
count Matrix to here is the complicated
part because you can imagine that uh as we
start to have more and more cells um the problem
becomes intractable in terms of like how much how
you can compute distances between these cells so
let's say we start with uh our Gene Matrix which
has 30,000 genes and 100,000 cells um we can't
compute distances in this super high dimensional
space um and it is neither comp memory efficient
or computationally feasible to really just ask a
computer to do this so we need to find a way to
somehow reduce these dimensions and um the way
that we do this is we need to first um select
or most analysis usually start by selecting a
subset of Highly variable genes um in order to
like accurately be able to select these highly
variable genes we need to normalize our data
and I uh some of you might be very familiar but
imagine we have two cells um red cell and blue
cell and let's say uh if we're just looking at
the rock counts we would say okay the red cell
and the blue cell have the same expression of
of the pink transcript and the GRE and the red
cell expresses more of like the the teal and
the orange transcript obviously depends on the
light res siiz depends on the sequencing depth
so we need to normalize this there's many
ways of normalizing it um many different
algorithms see uh normalizing by the library
depth usually works super well and um I that's
what uh we tend to suggest before trying uh
fancier methods um and once we have the data
normalized we can go on to looking at which are
the genes that are most highly variable this is
because we want to subset from our 30,000 Gene
space we want to just do a selection of let's
say which are the most biologically relevant genes
and we Define biologically relevant by genes that
are variable within our data set we can imagine
that if a gene is constantly expressed it's not
necessarily adding any information uh to our data
set in the sense it's not going to tell us allow
us to tell us apart different cell populations
so so we select our most highly varable genes and
we're like we're going to subset from 30,000 genes
we're now going to look at these 3,000 2,000 5,000
genes of Interest feature selection is very very
important because as you can imagine we're going
from 30,000 genes to 3,000 genes those other 20
27,000 genes will be invisible we'll be blind to
them for the rest of the analysis so just keep in
mind that the Single Cell usually is an iterative
process where you annotate the level one then you
subset your data and then you need to redo these
steps redo the feature selection um because at
each level you're only working with these 3,000
highly variable genes anything that's outside the
3,000 will be invisible to the analysis um and
then once we select our highly varable genes
we can scale the data and we can compute PCA
uh and then we go to say 50 principal components
that were computed on these 3,000 veral genes
for 100,000 cells in our data set um this is very
important because these 50 PCS have been computed
on these 3,000 High highly variable genes imagine
if we start with a data set that's let's say a
tissue biopsy that has epithelial cells that has
immune cells that has stromal cells the highly
varable genes will include genes that come from
the epithelial genes that come from the stroma
things that come from the the immune subset if
then you subsets to just your immune cells you
need to reprocess it so now you recompute these
highly variable genes to genes that are highly
variable within your immune subset and that will
allow you to gain let's say an extra layer of um
um heterogen to pull things apart um and I'm
just making a lot of emphasis because feel
like a lot of people miss this step and it's
it's very very important to really nail this
down and once we have our data in 50 PC or in this
reduced Dimension space here and putting principal
components it could be anything it could be if
you compute nmf if you SBI if you do uh single
value the composition if you do any sort of um
integration method it's just a reduced Dimension
space we can then compute distances and we can
then go on and build our uh cell connectivity and
this is just showing on pc1 and PC2 but you can
imagine that this we're working on 50 principal
components or yeah we're working in in that BC
space um once we have our uh graph build our
K&N graph um we usually end up with something like
this it's not that we're looking at it but this is
what's happening under the hood and we want to say
can we cluster this um classical methods like K
means or hierarchical clustering don't scale well
with these super large um data sets especially
when we have hundreds of hundreds of thousands of
points so what we do is we end up using Community
DET Community detection algorithms like luane or
or or lien more recently um and these basically
try to identify communities within our graph
that are more interconnected within them than
outside of them so it's trying to optimize the
modularity of this graph but basically is being
like okay what cells are more interconnected
between them than than outside of them um
here I put that uh snn which means shared nearest
neighbors uh most of these algorithms don't work
directly on the K nearest neighbor graph and K is
whatever number you want to say 20 50 100 nearest
neighbors but more on the shared nearest neighbor
so once you have a cell for each cell you look at
how many nearest neighbors you share with them
and that kind of prunes um extreme points that
might not um be super related but just um because
they they it cleans up a little bit of the of the
technical variability um with these graph
clusterings algorithms we can increase the
resolution and that yeah can split uh further
split the initial subsets that we had um and I
think one of the questions that we also get a lot
is how do we assess if a clustering resolution is
good or bad or when do we call a clustering
um done um there's no clear answer I think
biology is ultimately the the main driver of
this decision but we can use some metrics and
here I'm talking about two of the metrics that
we tend to use um let's say we we have our our
clustering done and uh each column here is one of
the Clusters and here we have our our samples we
have our flu samples in blue our normal samples
in green and our covid samples in red if we
look at clusters four and six we can see that
they're dominated by Just One of the patients
doesn't mean that it's a bad thing could be
biology but there's definitely no sample diversity
Within These clusters um and even cluster 5
seems to be mainly dominated by uh one of the flu
samples so something to keep an eye out something
that could be pointing that there's something off
or different from that one sample and that
it could be worth paying some attention and
potentially removing it if it's if it's not going
to be useful or we think it's low quality and we
can do this based of the ey test and just drawing
the bar plot and being like what does this look
like or for example we can compute the Simpson
diversity index for each cluster and we can see
how diverse is each cluster by um the sample ID
or the batch that we're looking at I have a quick
question yeah so if you get a cluster like four um
how do you go about deciding if that's some weird
batch effect or if it is some unique biology
that's like do I kick it out or investigate
it that's the question that's why I said at the
beginning that we can provide technical expertise
but knowing the biology is the most important part
when making these decisions in this case I believe
cluster 4 ended up being uh platelets so it was
a sample that just had a lot wasn't cleaned up
well in terms of the blood wasn't fully removed
so we had a lot of um hemoglobin uh genes uh in
cluster 6 and a lot of platelets um in cluster 4
so we ended up removing these because they were
not a cell type that we're directly interested
in and that had just missed the let's say the
sample processing quality steps but again just
by looking at this I would not remove the samp
that cluster I would interrogate and be like
what genes are differentially expressed do I
see this in my condition of interest because if I
see this cluster just in one of the patients but
it's in let's say in my disease category then
I might be more inclined and keeping it to be
like oh this seems to be something that's more
dis specific um but I'm going to go over some
QC metrics in in a little bit as well to to try
to um help with that process but again I think
biology if there's one point is that biology
is the key driver of the decision- making we
can provide as many parameters and tools and and
things to look at but laying our decision making
on the biology is the I think the ultimate driver
of of what's going to make a successful analysis
um and another thing that we can do is we compute
the uh silhouette score which the silhouette score
basically means is my cell more similar to the
cells in its own cluster than to the cells outside
of my own cluster um and I'll show the formula
in in a few slides but basically what we can see
is that high silouette scores near one u means
that um the cells within that cluster or that
that cell is very similar to self than to other
and uh scores zero or below means that that cell
is more similar is equally similar or more this
similar to self than to others um so we can see
how let's say clusters 8 7 six 4 3 2 and zero seem
to be very well structured seem to be very similar
to self then all the cells within those clusters
are similar to uh the cells that are also in the
cluster than the rest cluster five for example
which is uh in this case is this one over here
um seems to not be uh doing such a good job
so cluster 5 could be something potentially
interesting to look at because the cells within
cluster 5 seem to be more different between them
um than and more similar to some stuff outside of
the cluster um cluster 5 when we ended up looking
at it um where a lot of polar forting cells so
they got grouped together because they shared
the proliferation signature but there was a lot
of seller heterogenity within them so when you
were drawing distances um the proliferating T
cells were still similar to the T cells the um
um proliferating Milo cells were more similar
to Milo cells Etc so it's just an indication
doesn't mean that it's a good thing or a bad
thing it just means that it's something that
we need to take into consideration and look
deeper into before we make a a final decision
um so once we have the clustering based on this
K nearest neighbor graph we can also compute
our umap visualization of the data which which I'm
sure most of you have seen some sort of uh umap uh
by now um I just want to caution that you can see
that we started from 30,000 genes at the beginning
we subset it to 3,000 genes and then we reduce
that to 50 principal components we built a graph
on that and then we reduce this to two Dimensions
so it's been a long process and a lot of data has
been let's say shed or compacted during these
steps um because we ultimately want to see can
we capture the most amount of variability within
two components this doesn't mean that there
are more sources of variability Beyond these two
components and the distances that we see them that
we see within our our um map don't over interpret
them just because you see the two things are very
close together and one thing is very far apart
doesn't mean that that's necessarily biologically
true it's just a way of visualizing the data
um if we added a third umap dimension Maybe
um the green cluster would be closer to Blue
than um the orange just because with the third
dimensions and Cas cells would go all the way
up um so just to to not over interpret ums they
there're can be useful to look at the data and
just have some visual reference but um yeah don't
judge distances and and relationships and if you
see four clusters right in a row don't assume that
this is one transitioning space that's going from
one to the other um because basically you're just
drawing things to be like um you're you're
compressing 30,000 genes into two Dimensions
there might be a lot that's missing there as well
um and once we have this then we can go on to do
our our Downstream analysis we can do differential
gene expression we can annotate our cell types we
can do some sort of compositional analysis we can
do cell cell communication many many down stream
analysis um that I think that really depends
on on the question that you're trying to answer
in in your data set um for the quality control I
want to spend some time because I feel like it's
a a very important part of the process and some
people sometimes rush through it um I tend to be
way more conservative in the way that I do quality
control um I will only remove something if it's
very clearly obvious that it's um poor quality uh
or an let's say an empty droplet um I will start
with a sample level metrics so once you've done
your sequencing think can we look at the metrics
that you obtain from from uh sequencing your data
and then mapping them to your reference genome and
see what we're obtaining from from them uh here
I'm putting on the left the let's say typical sell
Ranger report that you get uh when you've done a
10x genomic experiment and you run it through cell
Ranger these are the the basic summary statistics
um and basically by looking at these sample level
metrics we're just trying to understand was this
sample good quality was there something off are
we getting the same the expected number of cells
that we were expecting um is the quality of the
sequencing good that the sequencing depth is
it the one that we expected um from the sequin
facility um that mapping these cells or these
reads to the reference genome work well did it
not and try to like get ahead of some of these um
QC analysis QC problems that we might see later on
Downstream but try to identify them U earlier on
at the sample level and be like okay we know that
um anything that happens within the sample could
be biased because it wasn't sequenced properly or
it wasn't sequenced at a lower depth etc etc
uh and this I like to look at it in two main
different ways so one is on the sequencing
and Alignment quality um so we're looking at
the sequencing depth uh which I hopefully you can
read but uh we can get the total number of reads
that were sequenced uh how many of these reads
um or how many of the barcodes Andis that were
sequenced are valid and Andis are unique molecular
identifiers um so when you're doing your single
cell experiment um each individual transcript
will be assigned a unique bar code uh so when you
do the PCR amplification Etc you can correct for
amplification biases um just Umi is is short for
for this unique molecular identifier um and then
we also have the q30 scores to see how good the
sequencing was in the barcode in the RNA read and
the Umi um these usually always look very good but
sometimes you'll see that some specific samples
just look very very poor and that could be like
already an indication that that sample um could be
Troublesome in in Downstream analysis or might not
be worth um adding in the in here and then some
other things that are interesting is percentage
of reads that were mapped to the genome and then
uh reads that were mapped confence to the genome
M to intergenic exonic or intronic regions um I
can't give you a number of what number you should
be looking for here uh it will vary if you're
doing single cell R sequencing um you will get a
a higher proportion of read mapping to the exonic
regions if you're doing single nuclei where you're
really just looking at the stuff that's within
the nuclei then you will get a higher percentage
of reads mapping to um intronic regions um for
the more immature rnas um so just to to keep
in mind how did the sequencing and how did the
mapping of of our reads go and then we can also
go to the sample and cell quality so usually
people tend to load 10 to 20,000 cells um so are
we getting the expected number of cells sometimes
you get 3,000 sometimes you get 50,000 if you get
50,000 you could be like did I overload it did
uh something go wrong and it's considering more
cells than than it should be considering um we
have our barcode rank plot up here that I will
talk in a second but yeah uh this basically
determines uh the estimate number of cells
number of reads that ended up in a Cell uh some
statistics on like um how many molecules how many
genes were detected per cell Etc and I really
like to look at the sequencing saturation and
at the barcode rank plot the sequencing saturation
is this this top plot where we have the the mean
reads per cell and the sequencing saturation in
the Y AIS meaning that as we sequence deeper and
deeper the likelihood that we're going to find new
genes gets lower and lower over so at some point
there's this tradeoff right um around here let's
say where in order for you to get a more let say
complex Library more new information you need to
sequence way deeper and uh in most of these cases
it's usually better to sequence more samples than
to sequence deeper one sample because you usually
end up having enough information um by 6.7 um
and then the barode rank plot is the automated
way that uh cell Ranger has to determine what is
a cell and what is not a cell or what is an empty
droplet versus what is a droplet that has captured
a cell um and you can see that here's the number
of barcodes in the x-axis here's the number of Umi
counts per cell um all the cells that have many
Umi counts end up being considered a cell and then
it usually gets to an elbow Point um and right
after the elbow point it will set a threshold and
it will be like like anything after this is not I
consider to be an empty droplet everything Above
This is considered to be a droplet with um enough
information to be considered a cell Um this can
be misleading um always I like to take a look at
it because sometimes you get a double elbow um if
you have very if you have a gr sites for example
that have very low um uh transcript uh mrnas um
you can get this double elbow and by setting this
automatic threshold it could absolutely just
remove a whole a whole population from your
analysis so if you're expecting to see something
you don't see it um it could be because in this
first step um and this is you what when you run
cell Ranger you get your filtered gene expression
Matrix and you'll get your raw gene expression
M Matrix uh your filtered gene expression Matrix
will have around 10,000 cells uh your raw will
have all of them so will have 1 million cells
it's much easier to just start from the let's say
pre-filtered one but if you see or if you have the
intuition that something's off that you're missing
something you can always access uh all of the data
that's in this tail end over here um and really
try to recover as much as possible um moving on
to the cell level Matrix here we just want to
mainly remove and uh droplets so droplets that
have no genetic material within them or just
have ambient RNA we want to identify duplets
and uh at least label them as potential Duets and
we want to remove noisy artifacts um some of the
key metrics that we look at are the library size
and the library complexity Library size is how
many um umis we detected for that droplet Library
complexity is how many genes we detected for that
droplet mitochondrial percentage is what percent
of genes map to mitochondria mitochondrial genes
and the doublet score um we'll we'll look into
a second but we can imagine that this is our
our all our droplets after running the the micr
fluid section and we see that we have some empty
droplets we see that we have a a cell that's
stressed out and it's sign we see that we have
two cells within one droplet uh and we see some
empty droplet to have some ambient RNA I'm not
going to go into ambient RNA removal because it's
a little bit more advanced and don't necessarily
recommend to do right off the bat but it's a
thing that uh could be happening within your
your data set and if there's just like sometimes
you just find underlying Baseline expression of a
gene throughout all of your cells uh it could
be ambient RNA worth uh removing um but some
of the metrics that we're using are Library size
and Library complexity if we see cells that have
very low Library size very low complexity most
likely they're going to be these empty droplets
we can label them and and start removing them
from from our data set we can look at our mitochon
percentage um it usually identifies dying or
stressed cells uh usually when cells get stressed
they'll like have uh some pores in the membrane
all the cytosolic um uh content will or mRNA will
leak out of the cell but the mitochondria which
are too big will remain enclosed so when you
sequence them you'll see very very high mitochon
percentages uh with within those within those
cells um and again very different if you're doing
single cell versus single nuclei if you're doing
single cell you can get some cell types up to 30
40 50% of mitochondrial percentage I think I have
an example later but like cardom sites which are
muscle cells will have very high M percentages up
to 40 50% that doesn't mean they're low quality
cells it's biologically driven so you shouldn't
remove a cell just because it has a high amount
M percentage um but if you doing single nuclear
or any where you're just working with the nuclei
you really expect to find very very clean um cells
where there's no metacon your percentage related
to single cell versus single nuke we do single
nuke because our cells are often in CA so we need
the separate nuclei but then we we really have to
clean up the ambient RNA I think because the
cytosolic RNA sticks to all the nuclei is that
just us or is that something you see generally I
think with a single nuclei you you can get more
uh ambient RNA just because during the process may
not be fully clean or might be sticking um you use
salender in those I think Sal vender is one of
the the most used tools for for it uh and again
it's one of those tools that works very well but
it really requires a lot of control right because
like if you use it if you're too strict with it
you might start to remove true biology so always
better to start a little bit more conservative and
then bring it up uh more and more more strict as
you go um and with the doubl scores um we want
to identify instances where two cells ended up
in one droplet and we can't um constantly say that
it's a or b because it's a and b together um want
to make an emphasis into to detection algorithms
uh there's many I put four down here in the the
bottom left corner um but just to like get a
sense of how these algorithms are working um
basically what they're trying to do is they're
trying to mimic a a doublet that has happened
uh during the process and to do that you start
with let's say you you have your your PC space
with all of your cells and what you do is
you create artificial doublets so you grab
two random cells from your data set you put
them together and you do that many many times
and you put those cells back into or these
simulated doublets back into your uh reduced
Dimensions embedding and we can see how in some
cases all of these um simulated doublets end up
clustering together meaning that these droplets
that we were seeing here are most likely um AR
technical doublets uh because they're surrounded
by artificial doublets that we generated um
but sometimes it's not as clearcut sometimes
doublets look like a mix of two phenotypes
uh sometimes if you have a cell that's
differentiating from point A to point B
and it has a phenotype That's A and B like
you can find that these cells get very high
doublet scores where that just biology
it's because that cells transitioning
sometimes we see this a lot with uh intermediate
monocytes where they end up usually having very
High doublet scores because they're this mix
of classical and non-classical monocytes for
they're expressing cd14 cd16 um so just because a
cell has a a very high doublet score doesn't mean
that it's a doublet it could be biologically
relevant again it just a moment to make an
informed decision on your biology of of the data
to be like do I expect to see this do I not expect
to see this could this be biologically relevant or
not um obviously if you see Pell and B cell Market
within one droplet that is is very indicative
that that is uh most likely a dlet but in these
like intermediate cases where it look looks kind
of fuzzy and and kind of transitioning be careful
before removing something because once you remove
something those cells are gone you're not going to
remember that you remove them that's gone that's
out of the out of the picture so always better to
be a little bit more um conservative with with
what you keep than with what you're removing um
and when we're looking at these SEL metrics I
mentioned them before one by one just to like see
how they could help us just looking at them one
at a time is not enough we need to see how these
things um vary together so for example we can
look at uh the number of counts so the the library
depth the number of transcript detected for each
cell and the library complexity the number of
genes detected and we can see that as we increase
the number of counts we increase the number of uh
transcripts detected um but some sometimes for
example we see that if we look at the hemoglobin
percentage it's very high down here so if we
were to remove all of the cells that have less
than this number of counts and that less than this
number of features we would be removing all of our
red blood cells we're usually not interested in
red blood cells but if that was your population
of interest and you just set hard thresholds say
bye-bye to your data because you just filtered
it out of your analysis just by setting hard
thresholds um some of the things that you also
see sometimes are these Tails down here uh where
the library complexity goes up but the number of
features doesn't necessarily go up uh and here
the the dots are called by the mitoch percentage
um most likely it's low quality Sol so I'm going
to show an example of when it's not a lowquality
cell um and why we need to be careful with this
and then I also like to in this same PL plot the
scroll the double scores because one of the the
things that we could think is these cells that end
up in the top right corner uh could be doublets
because they have double the genetic material so
we expect slightly higher um uh number of counts
and number of features detected within there but
if we look at an example here from everything that
I just told you um would be like clusters two four
and six potentially right seem to have very low
Library size um very low number of detected genes
compared to the rest and uh again um clusters
2 and six seem to have low monoc percentage and
low ribosoma percentage so what could be going on
with these clusters um are they low quality and
most of these clusters ended up being in this
uh lower tail down here but before we removed
them we just did like the standard differential
expression analysis between our clusters and what
we saw was that uh cluster 6 uh expressed ly6g
and some cxr 2 and cluster 2 expressed a lot of
cxr 2 as well as il10 and and rg2 meaning that
uh for us these were very clearly neutrophils
that were um included in our analysis and we have
we if we had set a big threshold these neutr fils
would have been completely removed and again if
you look at cluster two it has a big expression
of uh il1b argas and and CX2 compared to the
rest of the data set if we go back one slide
um cluster two seems flat as a pancake in terms
of the uh number the library depth um so just
because something has uh low number features
or low Library complexity don't just remove it
automatically take a second to look at what are
the genes that are differentially expressed uh
before kicking it out of your analysis because you
could be missing a population that just happens to
have uh those characteristics uh and the the same
thing with cardom asites they can have very high
Manon percentages if you just set a threshold
of everything that's over 30% man percentage
I'm going to remove you could be missing out on a
complete whole population that just biologically
happens to have high Monon percentage um and the
last thing that I want to do is I don't like to
remove cells with these strict thresholds so what
I tend to do is let's say we have our uh all all
of our cells I will label my cells as good quality
and bad quality depending on on fixed thresholds
but before going on and removing I will do a
differential expression between the good quality
cells and the bad quality cells and just see if
any biologically relevant genes are popping up to
be over expressed in the cells that I labeled uh
low quality and if they are then I will keep those
cells in and I will like in iterative rounds of
the analysis I will be maybe a little bit more um
um I will find a little bit more noise and
Technical noise in in there but I'm making
sure that whatever population was labeled
as poor quality is kept uh within within
my analysis so I really like doing this
uh I think it's called diagnosing cell
type loss um I think it's super important
it can really help keep uh all the biology
that you have in in your data set and
and avoid you removing uh things um
so that's for the QC part moving on to batch
effects and integration assessment um batch
effects will always be there batch effects happen
at any point of the process different location
site different sign signal machine different
person um processing the data um they will happen
um it's just something that we have to deal with
the question is how do we uh go about it um most
important thing is experimental design if you have
a good experimental design it's so much easier to
correct um your match effect so let's say we have
uh two experimental designs this top one uh where
we have um let's say we have control this isas one
this is diseas two and we sequence each one in its
own separate batch and then we see differences
between them we don't know if these differences
are due because of the batch or because of the
underlying biology we can correct by batch which
will tend to homogenize our data set but that
means that we're also correcting for biology
at that step because we don't have any way to
control biology and batch separately in our second
experimental design where we let's say we grab
um our our control disas one dis two and then in
our patches we mix control and disas two control
and this one and this is one and this is two into
three batches then this all this allows us very
much to correct um things that are happening so
we'll see for example these box plots are colored
by batch um here we have a very clear batch effect
right uh where all the samples that were sequenced
in batch one uh have the same so we can say okay
uh proportion of detected genes in this case
seems to be driven by batch this something
that we should be taking into account um something
that can be fixed computationally but it's so much
easier when done already from the experimental
design side um and sometimes when we're fixing it
experimentally what we're actually doing is we're
just killing very important biological signal just
because we were forced to uh correct these things
or if we don't correct them then the results that
we're seeing we don't know how much of them
are true biology versus just technical noise
um sometimes match with single cell looks like
this um this is just looking at it on the um map
where you see how like these populations seem to
be very similar but they're just mirroring each
other so like how do we get them to integrate
uh much better and post integration we want to
obtain something that looks more like this where
both conditions are much more overlapping um I
just want to go about just like let's not just
look at a umap and be happy with how it looks
and assess integration that way but provide
some metrics that can help us um assess how
the integration has has uh gone and and assess
it um is a very um there there's a lot of nice
benchmarking papers um I really um suggest a
mukan paper I think it's from 2021 about the
integration bench Mark um SCV they call it because
they really are um very thorough in in how they go
through integration um but I want to talk about
these three metrics um the I and the C score the
solette score and the PCA regression um there
are three uh metrics that we can use to assess
how much or how well the integration has worked
um if you look at the first one the ilc and the
CC uh they're the same thing um but uh the name
changes because what we're looking at here is is
batch on the left versus Sal type on the right
so if you can imagine where we have a perfectly
annotated data set and we integrate it we would
want batch to be completely integrated while cell
type labels remain distinct between them so all
the cells that fall within the same cluster should
be from the same cell typ cell type label and very
heterogeneous for batch um this is the inverse uh
the local imerse Simpsons index uh we can compute
it from the batch so if we computed it with the
batch variable we want this um variable to be very
diverse we wanted it to be uh very high we want to
find very heterogeneous neighborhoods in terms of
bch within each cluster uh or within each cell um
and we also want to find this C or the cell type
Ley very low we want this cell type heterogenity
to be very low since we usually don't have the
predicted cell type right off the bat what we
tried to do is uh some sort of automated sell type
annotation that gives us broad labeling of our
cells and try to assess it that way so uh the way
that we're trying to assess the integration is we
want to increase the IC increase the the Le score
over the batch covariates and decrease it or keep
it as much as possible for cell type um for the
cell type label so we keep our distinct uh cell
type neighborhoods while we merge them um across
patch um we can also compute the silhouette score
that I mentioned before uh which is basically
the distance of each cell versus the centroid
of its cluster versus the distance of that cell
towards the centroid of the nearest cluster in
our data set if we have clean um uh data um
and here we're looking let's say at the batch
C variat we would not want to find two distinct
clusters if we're assessing a bat Cate because
we would want these to be very merged we would
want to correct that effect um so if we go back
here um this would be an example where the
silouette score would be very high by batch
because each batch is very similar to itself
and very different from the rest um but in
these cases it would be great um so um looking
at the silhouette width by batch we want to have
high diversity by batch looking at the silhouette
width by the predicted cell type label we want to
have very low because we want to still keep the
structure of our biological data together um so
yeah um and then we can also look at the PCA
regression so we know that this is a little
bit more complicated but we know that each
principal component exp explains x% of the
variability within our data set and then we can
draw some kind of model where how much um each
of our batch C variates Express explains uh each
principal component and then we try to get try to
like align these things and we look at it before
integration and after integration and we want to
see if let's say the site of collection was uh
initially explaining a lot of the variance within
pc1 but after correct correcting or integrating
uh this variance has been uh decreased um so
we've effectively removed the effect of set
of collection on on principal component one um
always look at uh positive and negative controls
so always have uh things that you know that you
want to correct for so the sequencing flow sell
the side of collection data of collection person
that handle the samples versus things that
you know you do not want to correct for or
bioconservation metrics so if you have uh a
proted cell type label or you have the cell
cycle score or you have a biological covert of
Interest disease versus healthy um and if it was
a well-designed study you would expect disease
versus healthy to not be corrected because that
is your key question and you don't want to um
confound that biology with batch um so again I
think it's very easy for computationalist to just
run analysis whereas W lab biologists really have
like the positive controls negative controls and
everything and I think we should start doing more
of these in in our tools and like when you're
running any new tool you always need to expect
something that you expect to find something that
you don't expect to find and that uh helps you
or or run a case in different scenarios that uh
you can validate that it works it doesn't work in
in your hands um moving on to uh closing up the
stages uh possible analysis that you can do with
single cell you can do differential expression
analysis between conditions uh usually um people
will recommend to do this at the pseudo level so
let's say you want to find differences between uh
CD4 T cells and disease versus healthy you would
do pseudo by patient by cell type and compare them
them with classic bulk RNA seek um differential
expression tools which are much more robust and
um really once you do this to B you reduce the
sparcity a lot more you can extract functional
Gene programs you can map Gene signatures of
Interest identify Gene regulatory networks this
works especially well if you add other layers like
um single cell attack sequencing you can do cell
cell communication um compositional analysis
lineage tracing single Cel utls if you have
genotyping information um many many many different
things there's many papers out there um tools to
analyze the data in R Sarat and bioconductor
um are the the two big players in Python it's
scampy which uh uh is uh part of the scers family
which is trying to do this bioconductor uh family
of of um suit of packages uh for python which I
think is is very very cool and uh if you don't
have access to your own data there's very large
data repositories such as the cell by Gene um
database data portal which has yeah 107 million
cells over 1,700 uh data sets the Single Cell P
portal from the broad again 55 million cells from
800 studies and the human cell outlas data portal
which only has healthy cells uh and has 63 million
cells from over 9,000 donors um here I think that
this can be shared so I put some resources on on
places to get started or to go more in depth into
what I just explained uh but these I think are are
very three very good resources to to get started
and uh revisit to just say the foundations of
of the analysis um and yeah I would say that
the take home messages from The Talk would be
that the pre-processing steps matter that they
can have a big influence uh so the way that we go
from gene expression to uh our graph structure uh
and the feature selection and the dimensional
reductions are really key into what biology we're
going to see afterwards the quality control should
be carried out cautiously we can't just remove
cells out of a fixed threshold because you could
have um biology that you're missing out so please
do some diagnosing uh diagnosing cell type loss
analysis uh to retain let's say weirdly behaving
cells that you might not expect and that batch
effects can be corrected with integration methods
but try to have some positive and negative
controls of what you're correcting and if you
don't have a good experimental design and you have
to end up overcorrecting your analysis because
your coar of your biological coar of interest is
confounded with a technical artifact then you will
be homogenizing all of that together and losing on
a lot a lot a lot of biology uh so you have anyone
that you can go talk to or even you can come talk
to us at bch we can help in these early stages
of just thinking about the analysis because
sometimes we find that people have already
gone all the way down the analysis and generate
the data and now we're just trying to minimize
the damage um so yeah I would like to thank
everyone in the oras Mones Lab at bch and
uh also the sovery network group uh and all
our our funding Partners thank you very much
do we have any quick questions in the
room um it's 920 but I do have one
quick question with the QC do you
recommend doing like looser thresholds um
first and then clustering and then doing
QC like by each cluster like iteratively
so you don't remove the weird cells yeah
so the way that I end up doing most of the
ansers is I label them as good bad quality
and then you'll go through level one level two
level three integration and at each level I will
keep all the cells unless there's like cells
that are like really depleted of transcripts
but at each level you will identify clusters
that seem to be behaving weirdly and then you
can contextualize them within that level so I'd
say once you get within cd4t cells you see a
weird cluster in there like okay these seem to
be this cluster seems to be enriched in lower
quality cells and then you can remove it there
or it could be yeah biologically relevant and
and you might want to keep it MH it does seem
easier to label them as bad and remove them
later than to go back and start over to exact
Tock get them back oh it's snowing um um okay
that that was great it's just a reminder that
this is um a science but also an art a very
challenging one that requires um computational
skills but also cell biology knowledge I think
cell biology is the hardest part to bring into
your you almost need like a a computational
biologist and a cell biologist this together um
okay uh thank you we'll see you here next week