(logo whooshing)
(gentle music)
- Recently, there's
been a lot of excitement
on using large language models
and vision language models,
these large scale machine learning models
that have been trained
on the entire internet
for robotics tasks.
So there are all these constraints
from kinematics to
reachability to collision.
If we don't properly
consider these constraints,
the robot is gonna fail at its task.
The research challenge we're interested in
is doing decision making
with these models,
but still considering
these important constraints
that occur on the robot.
- In this work, we developed
a system called process.
It uses a language model to
establish a block of code.
In this block of code,
it tells the robot what to
do in a procedural manner.
So once we have a goal that
we want the robot to satisfy,
we query the language
model for a block of code
that defines an infinite
family of solutions.
This infinite family of solutions
is then searched through
using a constraint satisfier.
And what this constraint satisfier does
is it basically can test out in simulation
different possible sequences of actions
and validate their correctness
under the set of constraints.
- So for experiments,
our goal was to test the range of tasks
that we could get our method
to solve on a real robot.
Importantly, we were interested in drawing
and general manipulation
tasks that the robot
should be able to solve
in a zero shot fashion.
So it hasn't seen these
tasks ahead of time.
And the kinds of tasks we tested
were things like draw a
star or some other shape
and take a bunch of objects
like fruits, blocks,
bowls, everyday objects,
and pack them into configurations
like lines, et cetera.
We noticed that a lot of the baselines
would violate constraints.
They would knock into other objects,
they wouldn't understand the goal
and wouldn't actually accomplish it,
or they would fail to reach objects,
whereas because our approach
explicitly reasons
about these constraints,
we're able to solve these tasks
at a much higher success rate.
So here, we're gonna see the
robot try to solve a task
where we've told it stack all the blocks
into a bowl of the same color.
- One implication of this work
is that we can now trust the process,
so we can put robots in
a arbitrary environment
and give them an arbitrary goal,
and have them operate in that
environment in a safe manner,
satisfying all of the constraints
that the human set forth beforehand.
So in future work, we
hope to extend our method
to more partially observable
and mobile-based situations.
- This recipe of combining
large language models
with classical techniques from robotics
like constraint satisfaction,
and putting them together
in an integrated system
is really powerful.
It lets us solve tasks
that are open ended,
but also maintain trust and safety.
In the long term, this could enable us
to solve tasks in household environments,
like cooking and cleaning,
and assist users in their everyday lives.