Uh so today we're going to be continuing
our probability unit. So I just want to
remind you where we were. So you know
when I was last lecturing I introduced
the basics of probability. I told you
what a sample space was and then it led
to things like events where we talked
about what was the probability of
different events. We talked about
independence.
We talked about random variables that
are functions from our sample space to
real values. And once we had random
variables, that allowed us to do a lot
of exciting things like we could talk
about the expectation and the variance
of the random variables. It allowed us
to do things like talk about
conditioning like when we condition on
some event in the sample space
occurring. You know, how does that
change the probability of other events?
How does that change the expectation of
random variables? And then we talked
about this powerful tool of you know
inclusion exclusion. And then after that
Peter gave you a bunch of lectures on
counting methods on generating
functions. And the truth is for the
introductory lectures in this class
there are a lot of tight connections
between probability and counting. So we
really need both perspectives and we're
going to go back and forth between them.
But today we're going to cover uh one of
the other important topics in
probability. something that we're going
to spend a bunch of time on which are
called tailbounds. So the idea for a
tailbound is to get a handle on how much
how likely it is for random variables to
be far away from their expectation. So
remember that we take a random variable
and we look at its expectation and that
tells us you know on average what we
expect the random variable to be. But of
course, some random variables might have
large averages just because they have
some very tiny probability of having a
gigantic value. So then we talked about
notions like variation and variance that
told us, you know, how well a random
variable concentrates around its
expectation. So today we're going to
make that precise. We're actually going
to get bounds on what's the probability
that a random variable is very far away
from its expectation. So let me tell you
you know one simple tailbound in action
and really the theme of today and uh
Thursday's lecture will be we're going
to use more and more information about
random variables to get tighter and
tighter control. So let's start off with
a very basic example of you know what
theorem needs very little information
about my random variable but gives me a
rudimentary baseline of you know what's
the probability it's far away from its
expectation.
So this is a very simple to state and
prove bound. It's called Marov's
inequality.
And here we're going to assume that X is
not just a random variable but it's a
non-gative
random variable.
Then what I claim
is that the probability that X is larger
than some constant C is bounded by the
expectation of X all divided by C.
So this makes intuitive sense because um
you know if I have this non-gative
random variable as C gets larger and
larger I'm going way out into the tails
of my random variable the probability
that the random variable is actually
that large should be getting smaller and
smaller. Right now the important thing
is that you know the expectation shows
up on the right hand side because that
gives us some baseline of like how large
we expect X to be on average. So the
larger its expectation is, the weaker my
bound on this tail probability is. But
as C increases, I also get some win. So
we're going to prove this bound and then
we'll state another correlary, an
equivalent way to rephrase Marov's
bound. And you can go back and forth
between them depending on what's more
convenient. But one thing I want to
emphasize is that, you know, here I'm
crucially going to need the fact that X
is non- negative. So, just as a spoiler,
I'm going to ask you where in this proof
I'm really appealing to non- negativity.
And after I give you the proof, I'm
going to expect you guys to to tell me
where this fact was used. So, let's
prove this.
And the proof for this is really just
breaking up the expectation into
different pieces.
So, let's start off with our random
variable X. We know its expectation E of
X. And I'm gonna break this up using
conditional expectation.
So I'm going to break it up into two
terms. I look at the conditional
expectation
that of X given that X is at least some
value C times the probability that X is
at least C. And then I'm going to add
the other contribution which is the
conditional expectation of X if that
event does not happen if X is strictly
less than C times the probability that X
is less than C. So this should look
familiar. This is basically a random
variable version of something we covered
way back when which is we talked about
the law of total probability. We had
things like the probability of some
event B and we talked about it as the
probability that B happens conditioned
on event A happening times the
probability that event A happens plus
the probability that B happens
conditioned on A not happening times the
probability A does not happen. So when
we talked about conditional probability,
this was, you know, one of our first
applications once we had Baze rule was
we used it to reason using the law of
total probability. And this is just the
same thing, but expectations of random
variables. Sometimes you'll hear this
referred to as the law of total
expectation, but it's just breaking up
my space into two different things.
Either this event A happens, that X is
at least C, or it does not happen. And
then I average the conditional
expectation in those two different uh
possibilities.
Right? And so now what I claim is that
uh you know I can look at you know each
of these pieces. I claim that you know
the first piece right here is at least C
and then I'm going to pick up this
probability of X at least C. And then I
claim that this second piece right here
is non- negative.
So uh that I'm just going to drop and
I'll get a lower bound. Right? So I've
really just used uh the fact that you
know the expectation of X given that X
is at least C had better be a value at
least C because X always takes on a
value that's at least C. And then I'm
still going to pick up the probability
that that event happens. And for this
term I'm just going to drop it because
this term is non- negative. Right? And
so now what I can do is I can just
rearrange to finish the proof.
That's it. So that's our first
tailbound. Our tail bounds will get a
bit more sophisticated from this. But
this already gives us some rudimentary
understanding of the probability that X
is very very large. So now let me ask
you the question that I promised I was
going to ask you. Where in this proof
did I use the fact that X is non-
negative?
>> Yeah.
>> Uh when you were counting expectation X
given X less than C. So we know it's
negative.
>> That's right. That's exactly right.
Because if X were not a you know
non-gative random variable, I couldn't
say that this term is non- negative.
Right. This term is definitely non-
negative. But otherwise, if X took on
negative values, this could be negative.
and dropping it I wouldn't get an
inequality like this. Perfect. Okay, so
we definitely have to use this and
that's crucial for you know marov's
bound at least the intuition behind it.
I mean this is the algebraic proof but
the intuition is just that x if x had a
very large probability of being at least
c then its expectation could not be what
I promised it was because the
expectation would actually be too large.
Okay, any questions?
Make sense? All right.
Okay. So, let me restate this in another
form. Uh I'll state it as a corollary.
This is just a restatement
of you know marov's bound. But sometimes
you'll find it convenient to you invoke
it in one form versus the other. So I
claim under the same conditions if X is
non- negative
then
the probability
that X is at least C times its
expectation
of X
is at most 1 over C.
Okay. So let me make sure we're all on
the same page. So why is this a
corollary?
How do I get from here the thing I
proved to here?
In fact, let me make it a bit easier.
Let me just call this a different
constant C prime.
Why is this a correlary? They seem
related. Yeah,
>> just substitute C prime C *
C over anything else.
>> Yeah. So let me do it the other way. let
me substitute for C is equal to C prime
* E ex right then I get exactly this
bound right here and then on the right
hand side I cancel out the E of X and I
get 1 over C prime so this is very
intuitive because if I have a non-gative
random variable the probability that
it's twice as large as its expectation
is at most a half because otherwise if
that probability larger than a half the
expectation would be wrong. Okay.
So, any questions about this?
All right. So, um just to illustrate my
point that, you know, in tail bounds,
we're going to be, you know, asking for
tighter and tighter bounds that use more
and more information about our random
variable. Let me do a running example,
which we'll use as a way to check how
much progress we're making. Okay. So
let's do the following running example
and we'll come back to it with our next
tailbound.
So in the US
uh the average male height
is about
69 in. Okay.
So we can use this fact, right, to
reason about the probability that
someone is super duper tall, right?
Because X being the height of a random,
you know, male in the US is a random
variable. So we know its expectation and
we can use Marov's bound and just see
what Marov's bound tells us. It tells us
the probability that X, which remember
is our random variable. This would be
the height of a randomly chosen
US male.
The probability that it's at least two
times its expectation,
which is equal to 138 in or 11t6 in.
That probability is at most a half. So,
we've proven this amazing fact, right?
You're walking down the street in
Boston. The probability you see someone
who's above 11'6 is at most a half.
Okay, so pretty good or maybe not. So
see the problem is that Markov's bound
you can actually check really is tight,
right? It's just that real random
variables, you know, a lot of times
there's more information we know about
it. Things like the variation of the
random variable. The more information
you tell me about the random variable,
the tighter my tailbound will be. And
this markov is just the get me over
first warm-up for a tailbound.
So we'll come back to this example. Um I
want to, you know, make sure we still
have the right intuition for this proof.
So let me ask you,
uh, you know, a diagnostic question just
to make sure we're on the same page. I
think probably you can guess the answer
to this but what I really care about is
to find an example. So does Marov's
bound
hold
without non- negativity.
Okay. So in the statement of the theorem
I definitely assumed that the random
variable was non- negative. In the proof
I gave you, I definitely use the fact
that X was non- negative. We talked
about where we used that. But could I
hope for some bound that looks like
this? Even when X is not non- negative,
maybe there's some other proof out there
that doesn't use non- negativity that
still bounds the probability that X is
twice its expectation by a half or
something like this. So I claim that
this is spectacularly false, but this is
good intuition. So how would I come up
with some random variable that you know
is has negative values and completely
breaks any kind of statement like this
that the expectation gives you a handle
on the tails?
Anyone have any intuition?
>> Yeah, maybe you could come up with a
random variable which has zero.
>> Perfect. I love it.
So this is definitely not true. It's
spectacularly false. So let's just
consider some X where the right hand
side doesn't make any sense because the
expectation is zero. So what if X is one
with probability
1/2 and it's minus one otherwise. The
trouble is that the expectation of X is
equal to zero. But the probability that
say X is at least three times its
expectation
which is still zero is definitely not
less than a third. Okay.
So non-activity really is essential and
sometimes these examples are very useful
for both building intuition and
conveying a proof to your reader. So
these kinds of things when you start
thinking about your term paper even if I
didn't literally need to show this to
you this is the good kind of thing to
keep in mind as a pedagogical device.
All right
so let's uh prove our next tailbound. Uh
this one will be fairly simple as well
but it's much more powerful and we're
going to get some awesome applications
of it. And this is called Chbashev's
bound.
Actually I'm not even sure about the
history because I think Chbashev's bound
was proofed uh before marov's bound even
though it's going to use the proof of
marov's bound. So I don't know maybe
Marov just looked at his proof and and
uh you know called the thing inside it
his own bound. So in any case now uh
we're going to start off with any random
variable X. So this is already very
different than Markoff's bound because
I'm not going to assume non- negativity.
I don't even need it for this proof. So
for any random variable X, what I claim
is that the probability that the
absolute value of X minus the
expectation of X is larger than C. So it
deviates not by a multiplicative factor
of C but by some additive factor of C
from its expectation is bounded by the
variance of X
all over C ^2. So this will be my you
know standard form of chebishev's bound
and the same way for marov's bound I
stated it you know in one form and then
I stated a corollary I'll do the same
after we prove this bound but this is
you know what I promised because now
we're going to use extra information see
marov's bound did not have the variance
showing up so you have to actually be
able to compute the variance in order to
appeal to the chebbes bound but as we'll
see it's going to give us much tighter
bounds and some really cool qualitative
corlaries.
So let's prove uh Chbashev's bound and
then I'll state the other corollary. The
proof will also be short and sweet but
it's going to have a really cool trick
to it which is you know a hint about the
tricks to come later when we do much
fancier tail bounds.
So the first thing I'm going to do,
I can rewrite
the quantity I care about. The
probability that the absolute value of X
minus E of X
is at least C I claim is equal to the
probability
that X minus
E of X
quantity squared is at least C^ squ.
Okay, so this is trick number one for
Chev's bound.
It's not a hard trick to explain, but
this is a trick. You know, why are these
two probabilities equal? Why am I
allowed to say that these two
probabilities are equal?
It's because they're the same event,
right? So, at the end of the day, what's
happening in here is I have an event.
You know, once you fix the random
variable, I know its expectation and you
fix C. I have this event whether or not
X is far from its expectation. And I
claim that these two probabilities,
what's going on in here are two
different events, but these events
coincide. The only way that one event
triggers is if the other one does too,
just because, you know, we're taking the
absolute value. Make sense?
Okay, so that's trick number one for
Chbashev.
And now here's the really cool trick. Uh
what we're going to do is we're going to
define a new random variable.
So I'm going to call this random
variable y and it's going to be equal to
just the thing that shows up in here on
the right hand side. X minus the
expectation of x quantity squared. See I
told you in chebesev we're going to
appeal to marov's bound you know in
order to prove it. But if you remember
for Marov's bound, we needed that the
random variable we are looking at is
non- negative. For chevbishev, I'm not
assuming that x is non- negative to
begin with. So what I have to do is I
have to manufacture my own non-gative
random variable. And that's this new
random variable y that I just
constructed right here. This is
definitely non- negative because I'm
taking the square of a value. And now I
can appeal to Markov's bound.
So using markoff
on y we know that um you know this
quantity right here which I'll call star
is equal to the probability that y is at
least c^2 that's literally just using
the definition of what my random
variable y was and now appealing to
marov's bound which is allowed because y
is non- negative
This is at most the expectation
of y all over c^2.
Notice that my threshold here is c^² not
c as in the original statement of
marov's bound. And now what I can do is
I can just remember what y is right. So
y is just the expectation the y itself
is x minus the expectation of x quantity
squared. I still have my c ^2 and when I
take the expectation of y this is
literally the definition I gave you
earlier for the variance of x. So that's
my proof right?
Any questions?
Good.
All right. So, as before, I'm going to
state another equivalent way uh to think
about chbashev which is sometimes a bit
more convenient.
So, feel free to use whichever is you
know easier in a proof. So again for any
random variable X
the probability
that
the absolute value of X minus its
expectation
is larger than C * sigma of X. I'll
define what sigma of X is at most 1 over
C ^2 and sigma of X
is called the standard deviation.
and it's just defined to be the square
root of the variance of x. Okay, so the
same way I had the simple version of
marov that allowed me to remember it,
the probability that a non-gative random
variable is twice its expectation is at
most a half. The probability that a
random variable is, you know, two times
away from its expectation in terms of
its standard deviation is at most a
quarter.
Okay.
All right. So, let's go back to our
running example and let's see, you know,
why chbachev is a lot more useful for
us.
So, in particular, I need to tell you
more information about this random
variable.
about the height of a random male, US
male. And what I claim is that the
standard deviation
uh you know of male height
is 2.7 in. So now we're in good shape
because instead of using marov, we can
instead use chbachev.
We have the probability that x, where x
is our same random variable as before.
The probability that you're two standard
deviations above average, which is the
same thing as uh 6 foot 2.4 4 is at most
a quarter.
So this is still not a great bound, but
it's at least not a nonsensical bound
like our 11t 6 in version before. And so
you can, you know, do the same types of
exercise. Um, you know, when you tell me
not just the variance of X, but you
know, more information about the moments
of X, you would get tighter and tighter
bounds until you would actually get
something pretty reasonable.
Okay.
All right. Um,
so now I want to tell you now that we
have chbashev, it may not be obvious,
but it turns out to be very
qualitatively powerful, not just
numerically in these examples like
height. So let me tell you about one
really cool corollary. Uh, I'll state it
as a theorem and then we'll talk about
some applications to gambling.
Um so chebbesev
allows you to prove you know one of the
most important results in tail bounds
uh which is called the weak law of large
numbers. Now the weak law of large
numbers we're going to strengthen it at
various times and get better
quantitative bounds but already we can
see some of the power of you know tail
bounds. So let me state what this weak
law of large numbers is.
And then we're going to prove it just
using the tailbound technology we've
developed so far.
Now for the weak law of large numbers
there's um you know you have to be very
careful with the quantifiers. So let me
write it down and then we'll talk about
it. So first I'm going to fix some
positive epsilon. That'll be some
measure of how close I want a random
variable to be to its expectation.
And I'm going to let you know x1
all the way up to xn
be independent
copies
of some fixed random variable x.
And moreover, let's assume that the
expectation of X is equal to some value
C. And I'm also going to assume, and
this is critical for the weak law of
large numbers, that its variance is not
infinity. Okay, so just some basic
bounds that my random variable is
somewhat well behaved.
Well, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to look at averages of these random
variables as a way to try and
approximate this expectation C. So, I'm
going to define a new random variable
SN. That's just going to be the average.
It'll be 1 over little N, sum from I= 1
to N of X I.
So, you know, just to make sure that
we're on the same page, let's keep some
mental model of this in mind, right? So,
one of the most important applications
of the weak law of large numbers is to
something like polling.
So, maybe you have some random variable,
which is the probability that a random
person uh selected from the electorate
votes for one candidate, candidate A
over candidate B.
Now you want to know what's the
expectation of X because you want to
know who's going to win the election. So
you want to do this forecasting before
election day. The natural thing you
could try is you can try and get
independent samples from X just by
calling random people and asking them
who they're going to vote for. Now there
are a lot of issues with that. That
won't really give you independent random
variables. But if we pretend for the
moment that it did, you know, each of
these x eyes is a realization of these
random variables, what would my polling
scheme do? I would just choose some
large denominator n for the number of
people I'm going to pull. I'm going to
average up all of their votes, right?
Which way they're voting. Are they
voting for candidate A or candidate B?
And what I'm hoping is that the
empirical average of their votes of
these random variables converges very
well to my true expectation so that I
can forecast who's going to win the
election, right? And so that's exactly
what the weak law of large numbers tells
us. You just have to be careful with all
the quantifiers.
Then what I claim is that
the probability that Sn
is epsilon away from the true value C
that this quantity as you take the limit
as the number of people you're sampling
in your poll goes to infinity is going
to go to zero. So there are a ton of
quantifiers here, right? So let's say
that I fix epsilon at the very outset. I
want to figure out the probability
people are voting for candidate A within
some additive tolerance 0.01. Right? And
so once I've fixed my epsilon, this is
my success criteria is that my empirical
average of the people I pull that that
exp that empirical average should be
within an additive 0.01 of the truth.
And the claim is whatever you fix for
epsilon, there's an n that's large
enough so that the probability that
you're far away by more than this 0.01
is going to go to zero.
So the weak law of large numbers is
deliberately non-quantitative and we
will get quantitative versions out of it
even just from the proof and from
strengthenings of our tail bounds. But
it just tells you some basic conditions
that if you're given enough samples, you
really can approximate the expectation
to any desired accuracy. And in the
proof, we'll see how large little n
needs to be. So this is quite a mouthful
of a statement. Are there any questions
about the weak law of large numbers?
Give me a thumbs up if this makes sense
at least as a statement. Okay, good. All
right, so the order of quantifiers is
super important for this. Now, let's
prove the weak law of large numbers. Uh,
the good thing is that the proof will be
pretty straightforward
now that we have Chebesev's bound.
So you know first I claim that the
expectation of SN remember that's a
random variable itself because each of
the X size is a random variable and I
could first care about is its
expectation correct right so now I can
use linearity of expectation
to write it out as the sum of the
expectations of each of the individual
XI's that form it. Now because each of
these XI are assumed to be you know
independent copies of this fixed random
variable X whose expectation is C. I
know that each of their expectations is
C. So that means when I average their
expectations I get the same thing back
again. I get C. Right? So this is just
you know a basic sanity check. If I'm
trying to approximate the expectation of
my random variable X with another random
variable SN, I better have that the
expectation of SN is equal to X,
otherwise I'm going to have trouble. So
this makes sense. This just means that I
have an unbiased estimator of the thing
that I really care about.
Now the crucial thing is computing the
variance. We're not going to be able to
get by by using Marov's bound. We're
really going to have to use CHBS. And
that's where independence is going to
save us. So remember for chbachev's
bound, I need to know what the variance
of my random variable is in order to
quantify how close a random variable
will be to its expectation because
that's the thing that shows up in my
statement of chbashev. The main action
for the weak law of large numbers is
just computing what this variance of sn
is. So I can do the same thing as
before. I can replace Sn with you know
what it is defined as in terms of the x
i.
And now what happens when I scale a
random variable by some scalar c you
know in this case 1 / n. Well the
variance is going to scale by a c
squared right because I'm taking the
expectation of some quantity squared in
there. So this is the same thing as 1 /
n^2
times the variance of the sum of the x i
from i= 1 to n.
And now the main trick is that I claim
that this is now equal to I'll carry
through my 1 / n^2. I claim that this is
equal to n times the variance
of each of these random variables x. So
this is the key step in the weak law of
large numbers. This is the part that I
want to dwell on. So why is this step
okay? So how did I go from here to here?
We have to remember way back when with
what I told you when we did the
probability unit. Yes.
>> Because they're independent.
>> Because they're independent. That's
right. So remember we had things like
the linearity of expectation. We add two
random variables. Their expectation of
their sum is the sum of their
expectations. that assumed nothing about
the random variables, it was always
true.
But when I talked about the variance of
two random variables, the variance of
the sum of two random variables is equal
to the sum of their variances, but only
if I have independence. So the crucial
assumption that these are independent
draws, you know, I need in order to get
this step and that's where we're going
to be winning because you can see that I
pulled out a 1 overn^ squ and it's only
canceling out one of these. It it'll
cancel out this n, but I'll still have a
1 overn left over. So that's why as I
take more and more samples, you know,
I'm going to get better and better
concentration. Just to completely drive
home the point, right? We needed
independence in order to get this last
step. Right? If I didn't have
independence here, you know, what would
my polling methodology be? I'm trying to
get a hint about who's going to win the
election. And I call the same guy over
and over again and ask him his opinion.
That would be a pretty ridiculous way to
get an idea about who's going to win the
election. So, you crucially need
independence. But now we can write this
out. This is the variance of x over n.
And now we can just appeal to chbachev
right and chbbeev is going to get us our
weak law of large numbers. So by chebbev
we know that the probability that sn
is off from its expectation by an
additive epsilon
is at most the variance of sn over
epsilon squared which our right hand
side is the same thing as the variance
of x over n * epsilon^ 2.
So this tells me immediately that you
know as I want some better and better
target accuracy for how accurate my poll
is maybe I don't want like 0.05 error I
want 0.01 1 right what's going to happen
is that my epsilon is getting five times
as small so what do I need I need my n
to be 25 times as big in order to get
the same bound on the tail probability
so actually in the course of proving the
weak law of large numbers we even got
quantitative bounds that tell us you
know exactly how large our n needs to be
instead of hiding it all within this
limit okay so this is one of
applications. Any questions?
Good.
All right.
So, let's talk about an application to
gambling. Uh I hope none of you all are
big gamblers. Uh actually it turned out
so when we bought our house in Belmont
um we kept getting all these weird
packages and fruits in the mail like
very fancy things. You know around
Christmas time people would spend us
send us these very expensive wreaths and
it took us a while to figure out that
that was because the person who owned
our place before was the CTO of
DraftKings.
Um so now we get a lot of uh you know
free fruits in the mail because of
gambling. So that's good. But um let's
talk about an application of the weak
law of large numbers to gambling or
maybe a caution about why it's not a
great idea to gamble too much especially
in Vegas.
So there's an important example which is
called gamblers ruin.
Uh so the way that it's colloially fl
phrased is that playing a game
with negative expected value.
You'll eventually go broke.
Okay, so this makes sense. You know,
when you play uh when you gamble in
Vegas, definitely all the games aside
from maybe blackjack, if you're counting
cards, have this property that they have
negative expected value.
And intuitively, it makes sense that if
you have negative expected value, on
average, you're giving up some money
every time you play. But maybe you get
really lucky. Maybe there's some
probability that you just keep on
winning, right? Well, Gamblers's ruin is
going to tell us that that's not the
case. That the probability that you
don't that you go broke is going to
converge to one as soon as the expected
value is negative. So, let's do this for
example with a a concrete thing. So, if
you ignore, you know, multiplayer,
um, you know, betting games like, uh,
you know, Blackjack, if you just stick
to the standard ones,
all of the games in Vegas have negative
expected value, but the one that has the
least negative expected value is craps.
Has anyone played craps before?
No. Okay, I'm talking to the wrong
audience. That's good.
So, uh, craps is one where you, you
know, roll dice and then, uh, depending
on whether it lands on like black or
red, you know, you make different kinds
of wagers. And there's basically a bet
you can make that's very close to 50/50.
So, you have to get to that point in the
game first. But, you know, the house
edge, if you play that strategy in in
craps, is just, you know, 0.0141.
So, we can think about, you know, a
simplified version of making that bet in
crops that with um, you know, some
probability you're going to win a
dollar. And what is that probability
going to be? Well, it'll be
0.4929,
right? because you want that the
probability that you know you win uh the
probability you lose minus the
probability you win is equal to this you
know house edge here okay and then
otherwise you're going to lose a dollar
and so what I claim is now that you know
by weak law of large numbers
well you can look at SN which is just
your cumulative winnings right so you
can add up in each game whether you win
a dollar or you lose a dollar. Now the
point is that that average is negative,
right? So the probability that you're
epsilon away from your average is
actually going to zero as you play more
and more games. So on average you really
will be losing some amount of money per
step and you will not get that lucky
with probability converging to zero. So
by the weak law of large numbers except
with vanishing probability
something that gets swallowed up by the
limit.
I claim the winning
per round
will go negative
which of course since it's a average
over your rounds if you play infinitely
long you will go broke.
So this is called gamblers's ruin. Um
and I want to give one more motivating
example before we take a step back and I
tell you about another probabilistic
tool. So you know for us uh so far we've
been talking about tail bounds as a way
to get a handle on uh how likely or
unlikely it is for a random variable to
be far away from their expectation.
Now, it turns out that really the reason
we care about these tailbounds isn't
just for their own sake,
but it really comes up in all kinds of
applications and discrete math. So,
we'll see probability, you know,
throughout some of the later units in
class, but I want to give you a little
bit of a hint about, you know, why we
care about tail bounds, especially when
it comes to algorithm design. Okay,
so let's talk about an algorithmic
application
and this is a real application,
something that gets used all the time.
So let's say that um we have we're given
a randomized algorithm
and let's call it
a Q. So A is the algorithm, Q is the
input.
And let's say this algorithm, this
randomized algorithm has the property
that when we run A on Q, well, its
answer isn't deterministic. It's a
randomized algorithm. And let's assume
that, you know, it gets the answer right
more often than it gets it wrong. So
let's say it outputs the correct answer
with some probability.
Let's just say 2/3.
And otherwise it's going to output
the incorrect answer
otherwise.
And the basic question we can ask is how
many times we have to repeat this
algorithm in order to get a good to
boost its success probability. So one
way to think about it you know our next
unit after we do tail bounds is I'll be
teaching you about modular arithmetic
and you know the basic thing we want to
do there is imagine I'm given some giant
number. A lot of properties of the
factorization of this number are going
to affect you know how it works when we
when we do modular arithmetic.
And you know later on much later in the
class we're going to talk about
applications of modular arithmetic to
things like cryptography.
So communicating securely with a public
encryption scheme. These are things that
get used all the time in e-commerce.
But when I'm creating a scheme for
communicating securely, I have to start
off with some, you know, number that's
the product of just two primes. So what
I can do is I can try and generate a
random integer and hope that it's prime.
And that turns out to work pretty well.
You're reasonably likely to get a prime.
But the trouble is that, you know, our
best algorithms for determining whether
or not a given integer is prime, they're
randomized.
So, you know, maybe I'm running my
cryptographic scheme and I have some
integer Q and I want to figure out if
it's prime so that I can safely use it
in the context of my secure
communication.
So, you have an algorithm that you know
with twothirds probability tells you the
right answer and otherwise tells you the
wrong answer. But if you were wrong,
there's a huge penalty to pay, right? If
you're wrong and the thing, you know,
wasn't prime and you thought it was,
then maybe you've just leaked all of
this sensitive information like your
bank account, your social security
number. So maybe this failure
probability of a third is just not good
enough, right? What kind of failure
probability would you be okay with your
social security number leaking?
Just give me a number.
10us 30. Okay. I was going to say 10 the
minus 10, but that's that's even better.
Uh, you're even more paranoid than I am,
which is a good thing. So, you know,
let's say I want to get a really tiny
failure probability like 10us 10.
So, how many times should I repeat this
algorithm
to make its failure probability
less than 10 the minus 10. Okay, or
maybe even 10 the minus30.
So if you think about it, right, this is
really the setting of the weak law of
large numbers. It's the same kind of
thing. You know, each of my runs of this
random variable is an is a random
variable XI that tells me whether or not
Q is prime. And what I'm guaranteed is
that uh you know that as I take the
limit as the number of repetitions goes
to infinity the average of the number of
outputs right
uh that you know say that it's prime is
going to converge to 2/3 if it really is
prime and the number that are going to
say it's not prime is going to converge
to 2/3 if if it isn't. Right? So this is
the setting of the weak law of large
numbers. I'm just voting with runs of my
algorithm. And we've already seen some
quantitative balance from the weak law
of large numbers about how large n needs
to be in order to get some valid, you
know, epsilon, right?
And if we think about it, you know, if
we just think about applying the weak
law of large numbers, we're actually
going to get very pessimistic bounds
even here. So let's think about what uh
the weak law of large numbers and
chbishev would tell us.
So the weak law of large numbers slash
our chbachev proof that gave us a
quantitative bound.
Well, it's going to tell us that the
right hand side, the probability of
failure is bounded by the variance of X
n over epsilon squared. Okay. And in our
case,
you know, we can take X to be just
whether or not uh the output of our
random of our randomized algorithm is
correct or not.
And you can compute that the variance of
X is going to be 2/3 minus 4 9ths. So
you know it's some constant that's a
reasonable constant. And what we can do
is we can set
epsilon to be something like 1 nth. So
you know X is um supposed to tell us
whether or not the thing is prime or
not. We only have to set our tolerance
really to sort of split the difference
between 2/3 and 1/3, right? That's not
where any of the action is happening.
These are all just constants. But you
know what's going on is that the
probability that you know our average
is you know off from the truth, right?
We can bound it by something like you
know 18 over n. Now none of the other
computations really matter too much. You
can compute the variance. You can
compute what epsilon makes sense. But
the crucial thing is really the fact
that the n shows up in the denominator.
So if I want my failure probability, you
know, to be absolutely tiny, what kind
of n would I have to take? I'd have to
take it to be like 10 the 10 or 10 the
30. That would be ridiculous, right? So
I want to make sure that I have
vanishing probability of using something
that violates security in my crypto
scheme. And I just have to repeat this
so many times that I can't really do a
transaction online because it would just
clog up the computer. Right?
So this takes me to the last main topic.
This is something which I want to
introduce now. You're going to start to
cover it in recitation.
But you know this tailbound is not at
all you know obvious how to prove it and
it'll be basically the full lecture on
Thursday. But this was really just the
motivation for it, right?
So you see that um like I told you the
theme for today's lecture was the more
information you tell me about the random
variables uh the better I get for my
tail balance. So let's you know take a
minute to think about the proof of this
weak law of large numbers.
So the setting for this was that I
assume that the XI's are independent
draws from X, right? But I claim my
proof didn't really use full
independence.
I claim all it used was that they're
pair-wise
independent.
That if you look at any pair of them,
they're independent. But I didn't use
the fact that any triple or any
quadruple of them are independent.
So this requires a little bit of
thinking. Right? So where in my proof of
the week of lo uh law of large numbers
did I actually use independence?
It was only in this step right here.
And I didn't actually need that all of
these random variables are mutually
independent. I just needed that
pair-wise independent.
That's exactly what got me the
quantitative bound. But that's the
weakness in applying chbushev is that
I'm not using as much information as I
could hope to. Does that make sense?
So that's what leads me to the next
bound which is called the churnoff bound
which is not just going to use pairwise
independence but it's going to use you
know mutual independence.
So let's state the uh the churnoff
bound. This was actually proven at MIT
presumably in this building even which
is cool. So this was proven by our
former colleague Herman Chernoff. And
let's assume that X1 up to XN let them
be mutually independent. So this is a
much stronger notion of independence
because I need all subsets of them to be
independent from all other subsets. So
let's say they're mutually independent
random variables
and let's just say that XI is equal to 1
or zero with probability PI and
otherwise it's equal to zero.
Now I'm going to do the same type of
thing I did before. I'm going to look at
some kind of average or sum of these
random variables. So let me look at
capital X which is the sum from i= 1 to
little n of x i
and let me look at the expectation of x.
Let me call that quantity mu. But
remember that's the same thing as just
the sum from i = 1 to n of the pis. So
this is all just setup. I have mutually
independent random variables the x
subis. In fact, they're Bernoli random
variables because they just take on the
value one or zero. And I'm telling you
that the probability that they're one is
pi. So this is already a bit of a
departure from the weak law of large
numbers because in the weak law of large
numbers, I assumed that all of these
XI's were identical. They were all draws
of this random variable X.
Here I'm actually allowing these to be
different random variables. So that's
even one extra layer of power.
But the real power just comes from you
know the the right hand side. So let me
write down one form of the churnoff
bound. So the probability that X is very
far away from its average mu by some
delta is at most 2 * eus mu delta
squared over
3.
I think I need
the average here. Okay. Uh no.
Okay. All right. So this is the
conclusion for the churnoff bound. So
the important thing is really that uh
you know what I had on the right hand
side when I had Marov's bound was a kind
of weak bound. It looked like one over
C. So as you increase C, you just
improve the right hand side by the same
factor. When I had chebashev, I had a
one over c^ squared on the other side.
So the probability that I'm c away, you
know, was degrading still at an inverse
poly rate. The crucial thing is that
here I have an exponential rate. And
this is what mutual independence buys me
is that the probability that you're far
away from the average is just plummeting
to zero once you have this extra
information about independence. So the
churnoff bound you know there are many
different forms for it. Um we're going
to prove this next time but you know it
turns out that if we were to use
churnoff in our numerical example about
uh testing out primes.
Well, we would only have to take n our
number of repetitions to behave like
some constant times the natural log of
you know whatever we want to be in our
failure probability over here on the
right hand side. So if we had 10 the 10
really the number of repetitions would
be much tamer. It would just be the
natural log of 10 the 10. So even if I
put a 10 or a 30 in the exponent, it's
not such a giant overhead, you know, to
actually drive the failure probability
basically to zero. So that's what we'll
do uh next time we'll do the churnoff
bound. But I want to cover one last
topic in probability before we get to
the turnoff bound on Thursday. This will
be something that's going to you know
help you a lot for uh this week's
assignment which is a writing problem uh
that involves using the probabistic
method. So it's something we've talked a
little bit about on some of the pets but
I just want to be explicit and show you
some neat examples. So that'll be our
last topic for today is the
probabilistic method.
So you should think of this as like one
more important application
of probability tools. So so far we
talked about you know probability for
its own sake like looking at the
deviation of random variables. We talked
about probability for the sake of
analyzing the failure probability of
randomized algorithms.
And you know we'll also be interested in
using probability in the context of
combinotaurics.
It turns out that in many applications
there are exotic types of cominatorial
objects that the only way we know how to
reason about why they exist is by using
randomness. So this leads to a very
important paradigm in uh discrete math
which is called the probabilistic
method.
You can take entire classes on, you
know, using sophisticated tools to do
things like this. But let me um give you
the highlevel, you know, bumper sticker
version first before we talk about some
concrete applications.
So what we'll be interested in is we'll
be interested in constructing certain
kinds of
random objects or structures
which are exotic and have some pretty
wild properties. And we're going to show
that these things exist not by building
them with our own hands, but by arguing
that a random object
succeeds.
So that's the highle idea and you know
there are many instantiations of this
probabistic method. It depends on what
kinds of structures I want to prove
exist. We'll talk about some concrete
applications and we'll see how the
probabilistic method helps. But we're
going to apply this to you know another
important branch of applied mathematics
which is called uh Ramssey theory. So
I'll introduce both of these topics
right now.
So what's Ramsey theory? Well, let me
give you a famous example of it.
So in every party
with at least six people.
I claim that either
we have the situation that there are
three people
all of whom are friends with each other.
All pairs of these uh three people are
friends with each other or there are
three people
all of which are strangers
none of which knows the other person.
So Ramsey theory was actually you know
uh first invented or realized in in
Hungary where there was a Hungarian
sociologist who realized that you know
he was studying social groups of uh kids
and he realized that in every group of I
think uh 20 kids there were always four
a group of four people he could find who
all knew each other or who all didn't
know each other. And you might think
that this is a sociological phenomenon.
Maybe it has to do with the way kids
play with each other that they form some
sort of interconnected groups and they
don't know other groups. But he
consulted with his mathematician friends
including Erdos and others and he
realized that it wasn't a sociological
phenomenon. It was just the property of
graphs. Right? So what this is really
saying like the same way that we can
think about representing
um you know friendship relations with a
graph what we're really saying is that
on any graph
with six nodes no matter how I draw on
the edges and the edges represent who's
friends with who there must either be a
triangle where all the edges are present
or there's an anti- triangle where
there's a set of three and none of the
edges are present. So this is the basic
of basics of Ramssey theory is that we
want to show that in large enough
objects
certain kinds of ordered substructures
must appear because they always have to
happen. There's no way of avoiding it.
So in fact there's a pretty famous and
interesting example from like pop
culture. Um this happened like when I
was younger but in the you know mid 90s
there was a lot of um interest in
something called the Bible codes. Has
anyone heard of the Bible codes?
>> No. Okay. Yeah. You want to explain it?
>> Uh I think it's like if you like skip
letters in the Bible you like make
sentences or something.
>> That's right. So basically what happens
if you take the Hebrew translation, if
you take the Hebrew version of the
Torah, what you can do is you look at uh
you know evenly spaced uh characters in
them and if you choose the step size in
the right way, you can find all these
instances in the Torah of examples of
like you know uh words that cross with
other words which have historical
significance. There would be examples of
like famous rabbis names with the dates
in which they were later assassinated
like after the Torah was written. So
this was you know quite amazing because
you know people let their imaginations
run wild. Um you know they thought that
maybe the Torah was predicting the
future right in arithmetic progressions
in in Hebrew like uh you know you could
certainly write some bad movies about
it. uh but it turned out that it was
really just um you know Ramsay theory in
disguise and the the things that people
found weren't statistically significant
that in fact uh you could find the same
types of things in the Hebrew
translation of war and peace. So that
was an interesting rejoinder to it but
that's the kind of thing we're going to
do with it today. Let me tell you about
one example of structure that has to do
with arithmetic progressions and we're
going to use the probabilistic method to
prove type you know types of lower
bounds on these quantities or at least
very strong lower bounds. So let me tell
you the last topic for today is uh
something called Vander Warden's
theorem.
So let me first give you a definition.
So a k term
arithmetic progression
is just a very particular type of
structured subset.
So it's a set of integers
of the following form.
And I'll call it Q subAB because I'm
going to use it later. But it's just the
set of integers that looks like a a + b
a + 2 b
all the way up to a + k -1 b.
So this is an arithmetic progression.
You start off with some base number a
and then your steps are of size b and
then you go for k steps. So that's an
arithmetic progression. This was the
kind of thing that they were using in
the Bible codes because you would look
at arithmetic progressions and
concatenate the symbols you get at those
positions together.
And so now I can tell you this Vander
Warden's theorem. We're not going to
prove it. The proof is in the notes. Uh
but we're going to prove lower bounds
for it. So here's a really cool
statement. So for every k you give me
what I claim is that there is
an n
such that
any two coloring
of the integers one two up to n. So
before I get to the theorem statement,
right? What's going on is I want to find
a kerm arithmetic progression.
Uh and what I'm going to do is you know
you're going to fix some n
and then once you look at the integers
from 1 2 all the way up to n you're
going to color these integers with
either red or blue. And what I'm looking
for is what's called a monochromatic
arithmetic progression. So I want some
arithmetic progression of this form like
QAB but with the property that I look at
the colors of the integers along the
sequence that they all should be the
same color.
So this necessarily contains a
monochromatic
K term
AP arithmetic progression.
So this is the statement right again
there are a lot of quantifiers in this
so let's make sure we understand it I
want to find some k term arithmetic
progression one that's monochromatic for
whatever k I choose there's some large
enough n so that no matter how you two
color the integers from one two up to n
there's no way to avoid it somewhere in
that set is sitting some kind of
entirely red or entirely blue arithmetic
progression. So this is a bit of a
mouthful, but this is one example of,
you know, a much more interesting
version of Ramsey theory is that any
large enough object, which in this case
is a twocoloring of the integers from 1
2 up to n must necessarily contain this
ordered substructure, which in our case
is this monochromatic kerm arithmetic
progression. So this has a lot of
quantifiers. Are there any questions
about this?
Make sense?
Okay, so uh you know that's Vander
Warden's theorem. The proof of it is not
too hard, but it's just doesn't involve
any probability. So we might cover it
later. But um it turns out that
probability, especially using the
probabilistic method, is a great way to
prove lower bounds for this kind of
theorem.
So let's ask for quantitative things.
Let's let W of K be the smallest N
such that the property holds.
Now you have to be careful and unpack
this, right? W of K is the smallest N.
So that which property holds the
property that every two coloring of the
integers from one up to n necessarily
has a k term arithmetic progression. So
this property has an extra quantifier
because I'm not telling you what the two
coloring is. Right? Now um one of the
things you can show
that you can reason about small values
of
these types of quantities. So one of the
concrete things you can do is you can
ask what's the smallest n so that every
two coloring has a three-term arithmetic
progression.
And it turns out to not be super easy to
show this but one side is easy. So the
easy part is just to show a lower bound.
So we're going to prove that W of three
is at least nine. And the way that you
do this is you just construct a valid
twocoloring that avoids having a
three-term arithmetic progression. So
for example, maybe all of these things I
circle are red and everything I don't
circle is blue. So you can check that
this is a coloring of the integers from
1, two, all the way up to eight. And you
can just check by trying out different
choices of a and b that there is no
three-term arithmetic progression.
The fact that, you know, everything
that's larger than this, right, is a lot
harder to prove because I would have to
argue that when I add another number to
this list, not just this coloring has a
three-term arithmetic progression, but
any other twocoloring has a three-term
arithmetic progression. So, it involves
like a huge amount of brute force
computer search to do these kinds of
things.
But what we're going to do instead is
we're going to prove the following
theorem, which is a beautiful theorem in
its own right, which is we're going to
show nice lower bounds on W K that are
going to kick in for large K. So they
won't be tight for small values, but
they'll give us a good handle on, you
know, how large the N needs to be in
this Vander Warden's theorem. So here's
the theorem we're going to prove and
what remains.
Um what I claim is that for any k
w of k the smallest n such that this
property holds is at least of k -1
* 2 to the k minus one / 2.
So that's the thing we're going to
prove.
And the crucial thing about this which I
really want to explain is that is the
strategy.
What we're going to show is that a
random coloring
you know for the choice of n equal to
this has positive probability
probability greater than zero
of having
no k term
a.
So now this is making good on some of
the promises I made here. Right? See the
whole point of the probabilistic method
is that we want to show that certain
things exist even if it's hard to
construct them by hand. Right? So you
know in order to prove this theorem
really I have to choose some n that's
equal to the right hand side that's
equal to the roo of k minus one* 2
k -1 / 2. If I choose this as my n then
the thing I have to construct and build
is what is the valid two color. That's
very difficult, right? I could try some
things. They might or might not work.
Uh, and then I might get stuck. But it
turns out that the way we're going to
show that there is a coloring that
avoids kter term arithmetic progressions
is just by showing that a random one
works with positive probability. So
that's what the probabilistic method is.
And uh, you know, let's execute the
strategy. So just to make sure we're on
the same page, what I'm going to do is
I'm going to consider
a random variable X that's going to be
equal to the number of monochromatic
K term
APS. I'm just going to count. So you
give me a random coloring. The dumbest
thing we could do is we randomly decide
independently for each integer whether
it's red or blue. And we're going to
show that that works. And we're going to
be interested in this random variable X.
That's the number of monochromatic K
term APS in my random coloring.
Now
the basis for you know making the
strategy make sense is really this very
simple lema
that's going to remind you of things we
did earlier in lecture. Right? what I
claim and this is just a general
statement but it'll make it'll explain
why the strategy makes sense in the
first place. Suppose X is a non-gative
random variable
and let's say it's integer valued
and let's say that the expectation of X
is less than one then what I claim is
that the probability that X equals Z is
strictly positive.
So this is the basis for our strategy
because the way we're going to show that
a good two-coloring exists is we're
going to look at this random variable X
that's non- negative. It counts the
number of monochromatic kerm APS it's
integer valued and as soon as we can
show its expectation is less than one
that means that the probability that
it's actually equal to zero and there's
no k term APS is strictly positive. So
this is the basis for our strategy. So
let's prove this lema. This lema is
super simple. But then let's execute
using the strategy in the case of Vander
Warden's theorem.
So we can just write out the
expectation, right? So the expectation
of X because it's integer valued is the
sum from I= 0 to infinity of the
probability that X equals I * I. But
this is less than or this is um lower
bounded by the sum from i equals 1 to
infinity. So I've dropped the first term
and then I'm going to drop the i because
each of these i's is at least one.
Right? And this quantity right here on
the right hand side is just one minus
the probability that x equals zero by
definition.
So now if I rearrange this I'm going to
get that the probability of X uh you
know being equal to zero is lower
bounded by one minus the expectation of
X and the expectation of X is less than
one.
So that simple proof is the basis for
our strategy because all we have to do
now is we just have to compute what the
expectation of X is. I told you what
X represents, what random variable it
is. I told you the fact that we're doing
a random coloring. And I told you what
the strategy is of how to reason about
the probability that X is zero. So all
that's left is really just to compute
this expectation of X and hope that it's
less than one.
So let's just compute
expectation of X. So I'm going to let
I AB denote the relevant indicator
variables. It'll be one if QAB
is monochromatic
and otherwise it'll be zero because
these are just the events that are going
to help me get a handle on what my
random variable X is. X is just summing
up all of these indicator variables. So
in particular then X the thing I want to
keep track of is the sum over all AB
pairs such that QAB is a subset of 1 2
up to N. Those are the only arithmetic
progressions I'll consider
of this quantity I AB.
And now we're good, right? Because what
I claim
is that the expectation of IAB, the
probability that you know this event
happens that this arithmetic progression
QAB is monochromatic.
I claim that this is very simple to
compute. It's equal to 1 / 2 the K minus
one.
So just to make sure we're on the same
page, right? So IB is the indicator
event for QAB being monochromatic.
Remember Q is a K term arithmetic
progression. So why is this probability
true? What's the you know oneline proof
of this?
I'm fixing a particular arithmetic
progression.
Why is the chance that it's
monochromatic going down exponentially
with the length of the arithmetic
progression?
Who can help me out?
>> Yeah.
>> Choose the color of each term
independently with probability half and
then multiply by two because you have
two different
>> Perfect. That's exactly right. So the
proof of this is exactly what he said
which is that once we pick the color
the first color
I'm just rephrasing the proof slightly.
So, we just pick the first color, namely
the color of A, the first term that
shows up in our arithmetic progression.
The only choice, you know, let's say A
was red. Then A plus B had better be
red. A plus 2 B it better be red. A plus
3 B and so on.
Then all the other colors must match.
All the other colors
in QAB
must match.
And that's the proof because they're k
minus one other things. So now we're in
good shape. We just have one very last
ingredient and then we'll get our bound
to follow which is I have to tell you
how many qabs there are. Right.
Lastly, I claim
the number of valid
AB pairs which induce an arithmetic
progression which you know stays in the
integers from 1 to n is at most n * n /
k minus one. So the way to think about
it, remember our arithmetic progression
starts at a and then it goes a plus b
and a + 2 b all the way up to a plus k
minus 1 * b. So in order for this
arithmetic progression to stay in the
integers from 1 to n, I better choose my
a to be at most n otherwise it's not
going to be in the set. And then my b,
it better be at most n over k minus one
because I'm going to add b k k k k k k k
k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k
k k k k k k k k k k k k k k minus one
times. So if it were larger than this, I
would fall outside the set. So putting
this all together, we know that the
expectation of X is at most n^2 over K
minus one. That's the number of valid
things times the expectation of each of
these IABs, which is 1 / 2 KUS1.
And now you can check that that implies
that if n is less than this quantity I
told you k minus one time 2 k -1 / 2
then it implies that the expectation of
x is less than one. So that's our proof.
So this is a very beautiful but subtle
proof right because of the way we're
using probability. I want to show that w
of k is large because I want to
construct a valid two coloring that
avoids all arithmetic progressions. What
I'm going to do is I'm going to reason
about the random variable that counts
the number of k term aps as a way to
argue that there is a good two coloring
to begin with and the rest of it is a
computation using linearity of
expectation. But that allows us to prove
that these exotic objects which are hard
to actually build and construct must
exist even if we can't find them.
So that's one of the cool things about
the probabilistic method. Sometimes you
can show you know very exotic things
exist even though we don't know how to
build them from scratch and we'll do
some more applications of this uh later
too and next time and we'll also cover
the churnoff bound. So we'll stop there
and I'll see you guys on Thursday.