welcome everyone to today's um Sloan
fellows MBA admissions process and
application tips webinar my name is
Maddie Clark and I'm one of the
associate directors within the office of
admissions at the Salone School of
Management before we do dive into um the
content of today's presentation I want
to kind of set the foundation of who we
are as a school within MIT and so here
at the Salone School of Management our
mission is really to develop principled
Innovative leaders to improve the world
and to generate ideas that Advance
management practice and this is C ly
seen throughout all of the activities
that we engage in as a school and
institution but particularly the first
part of our mission you can see within
our portfolio of programs um we're
really looking to develop principled
Innovative leaders um who improve the
world through our program offerings and
so we have a variety of programs here at
the saloan School of Management we have
some early career programs for folks who
have um just a couple years of
experience at the maximum um we have a
couple iterations of MBA offerings and
then we also have one part-time offering
within the Salo School of Management
which is our Executive MBA but the
program that we're all here to talk
about today is our SLO fellows MBA which
is a 12-month degree where students um
earn either an MBA or an MS in
management or an MS in management of
Technology folks who join the program
have at least 10 years of experience but
on average are entering our program with
15 years of experience um so we'll talk
a little bit about the application
process for the slone fellows program
today
before we do so I want to give you a
quick glimpse of who is in the class
this is our current class profile for
the folks who started this past June we
had 103 students start the program 37%
of our students identify as women 77% of
the class is international coming from
42 different countries and 13% of our um
students from the US are
underrepresented students of color as
you'll see here students are coming from
all different Industries with our top
three Industries
um that students came to us from this
past year from Financial Services
technology government education and
nonprofit um but there's certainly
Variety in where folks are coming to us
from and also where they go after
graduation and one thing that I just
want to quickly highlight is that 47% of
our current class has an a previous
Advanced degree as
well so now that you've heard a little
bit about who's in our class I want to
talk about who is an ideal candidate to
join the slone fellows program um like I
had mentioned before we're really
looking for 10 years of post-bachelor
full-time work experience um that
experience we're really looking for
folks who have both leadership and
general management experience so
thinking about folks who are leading
teams leading organizations leading
teams cross functionally um that can
really help folks be successful in the
program and um contribute to the
classroom
setting as I mentioned before we have 42
countries represented in our current
class and so we're definitely looking
for folks who are committed to Global
Perspective you'll be hearing those
perspectives from your classmates as you
sit in your courses um with Sloan fellow
students but other students across the
um Sloan Community um but also within
the curriculum there's definitely a
focus on the global perspective and how
you can improve the world as a a global
leader we're really looking for folks to
push boundaries and challenge the status
quo um again if you think back to our
mission I'm really looking for folks who
um create kind of innovative solutions
to improve the world and so definitely
looking for that in candidates for our
slone pillow program the program does
have um some um rigorous quantitative
aspects to it and so we're looking for
folks who have comfort with quantitative
um coursework that they've previously
taken or other
certificates we are looking for
candidates who are able to communicate
effectively and articulate their
thoughts um to help them be better
classmates but also better leaders in
the world after they graduate and we're
also looking for folks who are committed
to learning and
self-improvement um this program really
allows folks to take a step back from
their careers um they're not working for
the year and they're really immersed in
this program and so we really want folks
who are curious about learning and want
to be here to kind of work on their
self-improvement and um their own
development in the 12 months of the
program
so the ways that we kind of identify um
some of these aspects that we're looking
for in an ideal candidate are through
our different application components um
we require a cover letter resume a video
statement that's an introductory video
statement we've introduced a second
video question that's randomly generated
open-ended we require one letter of
recommendation from a professional um
Source we require two additional
references one organizational chart your
transcripts from any institutions um
that you've previously taken coursework
two professional short answer questions
um test scores are optional but we
accept um both iterations of the gmap
both the focus and 10th edition gr and
executive assessment scores and then um
one final short answer question on your
personal background um you all are here
today and hopefully are applying for our
round one deadline that's approaching on
October 1st um but we encourage you to
apply only when you feel you are um you
your application is at its best and so
if you're not able to apply by round one
we do have a second deadline that will
be um on January 27th in 2025 and one
thing to note um if you are invited to
interview we do require two additional
short answer questions before your
scheduled interview so that is to come
later in the application
process this is a quick glimpse of um
how our our round one timeline will go
like I mentioned before our deadline is
October 1st so in a few short weeks um
immediately following our application
deadline we will begin reviewing
applications and we'll do that for a
couple weeks and release interview
invites by October 22nd with interviews
starting on October 23rd and running
through the early December and then we
will release all final decisions for
round one on December
13th in our evaluation process and like
I mentioned before we start reviewing
the day after the deadline so on October
2nd every single application that's
submitted will be reviewed by our
professionally trained admissions
committee when we're looking at
applications um we're really looking for
um demonstrated success and Leadership
skills so as you're thinking about
crafting your application what materials
you're providing to us um really
thinking about how you might highlight
some of these questions how well do you
work in a team how do you solve problems
how do you communicate and adapt to
change those are really helpful for us
to see um to really see those leadership
skills again thinking back to the ideal
candidate profile that I um showed
earlier we're really looking for those
leadership skills in general management
experience and so being able to Showcase
that throughout your application
materials is really
important so now we're going to dive
into all of the application components
um and provide some tips as you complete
each of the requirements the first one
is the cover letter and this is where
you submit a cover letter seeking a
place in the MIT loon loone fellows MBA
program um it is 300 words or less and
we're really looking for you to use
examples within this cover letter um and
so a couple tips as you're completing
the cover letter this is really your
place to sell yourself you're doing that
on all your application materials but
certainly using the cover letter to do
so this is also the place to talk a bit
about why MIT Sloan and why the SLO
fellow's MBA degree in particular we
really want to see recent professional
and personal examples that demonstrate
why you are a good match to join the
program so really utilizing the 300
words or less to Showcase this and one
um tip for everyone don't focus on your
future goals here there is a specific
place within the slone fellow's
application for that and so here we
really want to see those um recent
examples that you're able to demonstrate
why you're a good bit for the program um
and later you'll detail what you want to
do after the program and why it the
program aligns with your future goals
the next component of the application is
the resume this is um we have a few
formatting requirements for this so
that's the first tip just make sure you
follow these um formatting requirements
we're asking for two pages or less Times
New Roman font size 10 um in either a
word or PDF format um and like all
resumes we're asking that you structure
it in reverse chronological order and so
as you're thinking about your resume and
kind of um detailing different pieces
about your professional and personal
experiences make sure that it is easy to
read and easy to follow um and that
you're following those formatting
requirements we really want to see not
just your we don't necessarily want to
see your responsibilities we want to see
more of the quantifiable accomplishments
and so highlighting those in the
different areas that you're providing
your professional experiences um really
what was the impact of your work again
thinking back to um we're looking for
leadership skills how can you kind of
showcase those in the quantifiable
accomplishments that you're listing
within your
resume a couple notes for each of the
sections that you'll likely include in
your resume um within the education
section um you're welcome to include any
relevant Awards scholarships or
professional Society societies that
you've been involved in with your work
experience um please make sure you're
including um the basics of the company
name your title um and dates of the
employment and again it's really
important to kind of provide bullets
that showcase your skill set so results
oriented bullets are really um helpful
for us to see the impact of your work
and how you might be able to contribute
to the classroom based off of your past
successes the next component of the
application is the video statement and
this is the introductory video statement
where you introduce yourself to your
future classmates but the caveat being
that your future classmates won't ever
see this this video it is just for us on
the admissions committee but this is a
place that you can really let your
personality shine through um we
encourage you to be conversational and
be yourself we're really excited to
watch these videos and get to know you
more outside of what's already on paper
within your application so a few tips as
you are um thinking about what to say in
your video statement or um how to kind
of record it keep it simple and use your
best judgment um we do want to see and
hear you so if you are um thinking more
creatively about where you might be
taking the video please make sure that
we are able to see and hear you clearly
um be aware of your surroundings in that
as well and really show us your
personality um we through your other
application materials we're seeing kind
of your demonstrated success and
Leadership skills this is a place if you
want to you can show kind of more
personal aspects about you um showcase
your personality and how it might
contribute to the Sloan
Community we have second video question
that we introduced this year so for
anyone that previously applied to our
spone fellows program this is a new
requirement that wasn't on previous
applications and this um is a 60c um
randomly generated open-ended prompt
that you're responding to and so a
couple tips as you're completing this
video question first thing to note is
that if you recently opened an
application this does not automatically
appear on the application you have to
complete about 80% of your application
requirements um in order for this to
appear on your leftand side of your tabs
and it will show up under video question
one which is the introductory video
statement that you'll provide and so
once it does appear you don't have to
record it um immediately but you are
welcome to kind of go into the space and
see how it is formatted where your
question will show up um you'll be
you're able to test your mic and your
video you'll see where your recording
sign is how much time you have left and
so really take the time to feel
comfortable with um the software that's
within our application for this before
you start this video question you do
have to click a button saying that you
are ready to begin recording to start
the video question so it won't just
begin without you knowing um when you
are ready to begin uh recording your
video question two you'll have 10
seconds to prepare to the prompt and 60
seconds to record your answer there are
no right or wrong answers to these
questions and there's no preparation
that's required this is really used to
see how you think on your feet and
communicate authentically um and again
this is about your past experiences and
so there are no right or wrong answers
as you're completing video question
to the next component of our application
is the recommendation letter and um we
do require just one recommendation
letter so um we are not looking for any
more than one recommendation letter um
in your application and this should be
from a professional contact ideally a
manager supervisor someone that can
really speak to the impact of your work
and provide additional kind of results
oriented details um and examples in
their letter that they're
providing we encourage you to ask your
recommender early so that they have time
to um really develop a wellth thought
out letter for you and we ask that you
do not write this letter for them um
they should be writing it from their
perspective on um how they would answer
these specific questions about you
there's no word count on the
recommendation letter and your
recommender will upload their letter
directly to your application once you
put in their recommendation um your
recommenders um contact information and
so when you're thinking about who to ask
to be your recommender um really think
about who can answer these questions in
detail about you um we're looking for
how you stand out from others in a
similar capacity um we're looking for
examples of your impact on a person
group or
organization um examples of how you
interact with others if there's anything
else that they want to share with us um
our commanders are welcome to and then
the last piece we're looking for um a
piece of constructive feedback that
they've given you and um looking for
details on that on the circumstances of
that and your response to it and so
really think critically about who can
speak to these best and highlight again
the impact of your work um those
leadership skills and your previous
successes so that we can see um those
throughout your all of your application
materials the next component are
additional references that you'll
provide and these are similar to who you
might ask to be a recommender um a
couple things to note about this when
you go into the application you'll just
list their contact information and these
references may or may not be contacted
if we are contacting them we'll figure
out a time that works for both parties
um to have this conversation but the
conversation will be similar questions
to what we might ask a recommender and
so I'm just
thinking you'll only have one letter of
recommendation but um if you had others
in mind for a letter of recommendation
you might list them as one of your
references the next component is the
organizational chart um in this you have
up to two pages to kind of visually um
represent your role in the relationships
that you have and so when you're
thinking back to what we're looking for
in an ideal candidate um we are looking
for leadership experience and general
management experience and so this could
be a really good way to provide a visual
representation specifically of that
General management experience who's
reporting to you who you're reporting to
um really showcasing who you might be
influencing for decisions who you might
be delegating tasks to or developing um
that are reporting to you and so really
showcasing all of those relationships is
really helpful for us to see as we're
reviewing your
application um so a couple tips as
you're completing this organizational
chart we really want to see your role
within the greater organization so again
who do you work with how broadly are you
interacting with other group so if you
have any dotted lines to folks including
those within your organizational chart
is helpful for us to
um thinking back to the cover letter we
ask for you to be clear in um what
you're providing to us um and same with
your resume and yes the same in your
organizational chart make it easy to
read um easy to find where you are on
this organizational chart so highlight
yourself um sometimes for folks who have
stayed in their Organization for many
years they might be able to provide
their previous showcase their previous
roles within their organizational chart
that helpful for us to see kind of
career growth if it appears within your
organizational chart but it's not um
required by any means thinking back to
the last two requirements that we talked
about the recommendation letter and
additional references sometimes those
folks will also show up on the
organizational chart so highlighting
those for us to um easily find is
helpful as well um so again this is very
much A visual representation of those
relationships that you have and provides
additional information as we're reading
through things like your resume and and
seeing the different results oriented
bullets that you're providing how they
connect to these relationships that
you're showcasing within your
organizational chart and the last tip
just make sure that your chart matches
the resume and the employment section
that you complete in your application um
your organizational chart um needs to be
from your current organization so just
keeping that in mind as you complete
your
application the next component of our
application are test scores and these
are completely optional um but we do
often get a lot of questions about test
scores so I want to talk just briefly
about them um if you have a valid test
score or an expired test score you're
more than welcome to provide them it
just provides an additional data point
for us as an admissions committee to
review when we're looking again for
demonstrated success and um leadership
skills this can certainly showcase
academic aptitude um if you're able to
provide provide a competitive test score
for us if you are providing a test score
you can provide a GMAT score um either
the focus Edition which is the current
iteration of the GMAT exam or the 10th
edition you're welcome to provide either
of those we also accept J scores and
executive assessment scores um and
you're welcome if you have say a GMAT
score and an EA score you're welcome to
provide both of those to us um you can
upload as many scores as you would like
and we do accept in person or remotely
versions of any of the exams and again
valid or expired test scores are fine
for this lone fellows MBA
application the next component um is
related to test scores when we're
thinking about academic aptitude and
this is our academic record section and
a relevant Force work section within our
application so we're looking for
transcripts from all of the institutions
that you've previously attended or are
currently attending even if you've only
taken a course or two there um please
provide all
transcripts and then there's also a
section within our relevant coursework
section where you're able to upload any
additional materials for non-degree
coursework or professional certificates
um so there's space for both of those
pieces of information and we welcome you
um to provide as much as you have the
things we're looking for when we're
reviewing your transcripts and
non-degree course work is again academic
aptitude um we want that demonstrated
success in the classroom so that we um
know you'll be successful in our program
thinking back to the ideal candidate
again um we're looking for Quant comfort
and so um definitely looking for that
through the transcripts and relevant
coursework section I do want to um also
note that we do not have any
prerequisites and so as you're filling
out the relevant coursework it's just
for us to see where you your foundations
lie within those topics but they are not
um requirements to be admitted to the
program um so you'll complete that
relevant coursework section and many of
those courses are quantitative courses
that we're looking
at when we're looking at these um we
really want to see kind of a sense of
intellectual curiosity so how have you
continued to learn and develop um even
if you've graduated a decade ago what
have you kind of engaged with since then
um to Showcase your intellectual
curiosity if you've taken additional
courses trainings certifications um
providing those is helpful for us to see
and this just helps us these materials
help us understand your Mastery of any
subject area um again thinking about uh
your demonstrated success in leadership
skills um seeing if you're able to
master a subject that you previously
chose to study is helpful for us in our
evaluation
process the next component of the
application are professional questions
and so these are two short answer
questions the the responses are limited
to 200 words or less um and thinking
back to when I was talking about the
cover letter and um not listing your
future goals in your cover letter that's
because you'll list your future goals in
one of the professional questions so the
first question is to share your
immediate and long-term professional
objectives and how this slone fellow MBA
program will help you achieve those so
this is the perfect space for you to put
your future goals in the second question
um I keep mentioning General management
experience throughout many of the
application materials but that's
certainly something that we're looking
for in candidates and so general
managers are often responsible for
strategy budget Andor work output from
individuals and teams for at least one
function of an organization and they
have the ability to see big picture
cross functions general managers are
part of short-term and long-term
strategy discussions and work cross
functionally to achieve a goal or
specific strategy and so this is the
space that you'll detail the general
management experience that you have
um again tying back to the visual
representation that you'll provide
through your organizational chart um and
other areas that your general management
experience might show up this is a place
specifically to kind of further
highlight where um your general
management experience
lies and then the last component that
we're going to talk about today is the
short answer question um thinking back
for anyone who previously applied to uh
the SLO fellows program this was not a
requirement in previous year so it is a
new requirement and it is a short answer
question um 250 words or less and you'll
talk a little bit about how the world
you come from has shaped who you are
today and so this is really a place for
us to learn more about who you are um
and an opportunity to expand on your
personal background and again how that
has shaped you into who you are today it
is limited to just words so please don't
include any links or videos um so 250
words or less um for the short answer
question so as you're thinking about
crafting your whole application um a
couple kind of tips for all of the
materials we're really looking for folks
to provide application materials and um
information that complements each other
so as you're thinking about what
information and what details you're
sharing in for instance your cover
letter um How can you further showcase
your skill set outside of what's already
demonstrated in your cover letter
through your other application materials
is really important we want all of the
materials to be complimentary to one
another rather than repetitive so making
sure you're really taking the time to
think about um where you're showcasing
your different skills um and how you can
use the different application materials
to complement one
another we're really looking for reasons
to admit you so as you again think about
these um different components think
about what data you're providing us so
that we can admit you um we want to be
advocates for you and we we are looking
for reasons to admit you and so as you
craft your application application
really think about um what details
you're providing the impact of your work
that you're showcasing your professional
and personal skill set that you're
showcasing all of those materials are
really important as we kind of to gather
different data points on you to ensure
that you'll be successful not only in
the classroom but also at um working
within our community and enhancing the
community aspect of
Sloan our biggest tip is also to apply
early um with that being said if your
application is not ready to go by round
one um definitely wait until round two
and like I mentioned before we begin
reviewing applications the day after the
deadline and so if you aren't applying
for round one um there's no need to
apply on say October 2nd for round two
we won't start reviewing applications
for round two until the day after the
Round Two deadline in January um so just
apply when you feel that your
application best represents your skill
set um but also apply as early as that
um application is ready to
go make sure you're following the
directions um you might have noticed
that a lot of our materials were were
requesting specific word counts or um
Links of videos and that's very
intentional we want you to be succinct
in the information you're telling us and
the story that you're kind of showcasing
and so make sure you follow those
directions if we're asking for 60
seconds in a video provide 60 seconds of
your video we're asking for 200 words in
your professional question um keep it to
200 words or less as required and just
be yourself we want to know who you are
as a whole person um again looking for
demonstrated success both academically
and professionally from the past um but
also your leadership skills in general
management experience experience and so
showcase those skills um showcase that
data but also be yourself and use things
like the introductory video statement to
show a little bit more of your
personality outside of what we might
already see through your application
materials um and try to have as much fun
with the application process as possible
so that's kind of it for the tips that
we have I know we've had a lot of
questions um throughout today's session
so I am going to invite my colleague Sam
um to come off mute and ask some of the
additional questions that we've seen in
the Q&A
feature hi everyone thanks so much for
submitting your questions throughout the
presentation um some of them like Maddie
said we've reserved to answer live
because we think they'll be helpful for
everyone to hear so uh let's just get
into it um the first question that we
have is is there a possibility for
someone with a US stem degree to request
a GRE GMAT
waor yeah that's a great question um
since test scores for this admission
cycle are completely optional there is
no waiver process for the slone fellows
program um it's up to you whether you
would like to provide a test score or
not and there's no negative inference if
you don't provide a test score you'll
just simply click continue through that
test score section um and provide your
application with out a test score if you
do not want to provide
one perfect um do do I need to be in a
leadership or management role when
applying for an MBA or SF MBA yeah so
our slan fellows program is really
looking for mid-career professionals who
have that leadership experience and
general management experience it's the
program and the structure of the
curriculum is really geared to folks who
have been leading teams and
organizations um specifically if you're
leading teams thinking about um the
strategy that you might be involved in
and cross functionality across teams and
so we are really looking for those
experiences um students need them to be
successful in the classroom and to be
able to contribute in um in the space of
the slone fellows program and so if you
don't yet have those experiences and say
you you might be on the cus maybe you're
at 10 years of experience but you um
have fewer direct reports and you're not
U necessarily involved in Big Picture
strategy and things like that you might
want to consider our 2-year MBA deg ree
um that does not require General
management experience and so really
thinking about what the experiences are
that you've had if you have that
leadership experience in general
management experience loone fellows is a
great opportunity but if you don't um
there are other degree offerings within
our portfolio that U might be better
suited to
you aesome um can you share some tips
for sfba
reapplicants yeah um that is one thing
we didn't cover too much of but um when
anyone goes into our application and is
a reapplicant there are specific
questions for you as a reapplicant and
so there is I believe it's 200 words or
less where you'll highlight or provide a
summary of what has changed since the
last time you applied and so this is a
good place to start as you're thinking
about your application materials really
providing those highlevel um details
about what has changed since the last
time you applied and providing them in
that specific space as you're thinking
about all of your other application
materials you should also consider that
question we do not want to see the same
application that you previously
submitted we want to see new information
and new data points what have you done
since the last time you applied where
are those achievements um results or
oriented bullets within your resume of
things that have happened since your
last application we have your last
application and so it's to your benefit
to provide as much new information as
you can through the application
requirements um so that we can see how
things have kind of evolved and changed
since your last application and we'll
look at those two in conjunction as we
review you for this loone fellows
program great um and for qualifiable
accomplishments um Are we more focused
on leadership skills um like growth
within your team or uh you know
management experience or are we looking
for more like corporate performance
accomplishments like the effectivess of
your work and the results of what you've
done grow with a customer base kind of
things like that yeah I would say we
want to see both types of quantifiable
um accomplishments within your resume
and throughout the
application thinking back to kind of My
overall tip for all application
materials we really want everything to
be complimentary to one another and so
making sure that if you're providing
more detail about one specific
accomplishment in one section if you're
able to Showcase a different
accomplishment or um piece of impact of
your work through other applications
materials it's really helpful for us to
see we want to see as much as you're
able to share within um our application
materials and so providing all of those
quantifiable accomplishments and impacts
is really helpful for
us great um and then there's also a
question about someone who has two jobs
right now um one takes up a lot more
time than the other but the other um is
one they're hoping to Pivot
to um what should the organizational
chart cover in that
situation there's two jobs yeah so your
organizational chart if you do have two
jobs um the one that takes up the most
time um that you list as your primary
under the employment section of the
application again thinking about how
you're showcasing your work experience
in the employment section resume and
organizational chart should all match
for your primary um work currently and
so showcasing that where you're spending
the most time um and we'll see the other
work experiences um that you have going
on concurrently through your resume and
employment section as
well
great um another organizational tart
question if someone's held different
roles and functions within the same
organization should they include that in
their organizational chart or should
they just stick to what they're
currently doing yeah if you are able to
demonstrate kind of your career growth
through your organizational chart that's
helpful it's just another um kind of
visual representation of that and so um
finding a way to kind of detail if this
was a position you previously had that
now reports to you um showcasing that so
certainly we encourage you if your
previous roles fall within your
organizational chart it's helpful to
highlight that for us as well
great um all right and now for
Consulting people how should they tackle
the organizational chart yeah um so we
understand folks that come from
Consulting backgrounds even folks from
military backgrounds um they might
approach the organizational chart
slightly differently than um most folks
um and so for Consulting thinking about
your most recent project or engagement
in highlighting that um organizational
chart is helpful for us and again if you
pull results oriented bullets from this
project or engagement it can showcase
that visual representation of those
relationships and so it's your most
recent um if you've had multiple recent
projects and engagements I would pick um
one of the larger ones but it's a recent
project or engagement in showcasing that
um organizational chart and often times
you'll showcase kind of lines to your
clients as well and for folks that um
aren't able to provide specific details
on names or um different um confidential
pieces um please provide as much
information as you are able to within
the organizational chart and we have an
FAQ section on our um website to kind of
detail how exactly to approach that if
you're coming from a consulting or
military background and aren't able to
provide some
information great um
um okay for the general management essay
should you be describing what your
management style is or do you need to
give examples of demonstrating your
general management
skills yeah we're looking for kind of
your general management skills and
experiences um so not necessarily
providing how you manage people but
talking about what those experiences are
um and kind of the respons
responsibilities within those
experiences this is a short answer so
there is not a ton of real estate to
provide every single detail of your
general management experience and so
really um making sure that you're
succinct in the information you're
providing and really getting to what
those experiences are that it focused on
your um General management and
Leadership
skills great um and then can you share
some general tips on tackling video
question two yeah um I think as you're
going into this video question I know
we've we've received a lot of questions
about it and um just because there is
you only have one shot at recording it
so it does seem um stressful for some
folks to complete it but I think the
mindset you can go in when you're
recording this is um how you might be
answering an interview question or
having a conversation with someone um so
the questions aren't tricked questions
they're not meant to have a right or
wrong answer there are no right or wrong
answers it's really just seeing how you
think on your feet and how you would
have a conversation we want to ensure
that folks who are joining our community
are able to contribute um effectively
and communicate effectively and so this
kind of showcases some of those skills
and how you might interact in the
classroom some of the questions that you
might get asked again they are randomly
generated but this is just um an example
of a couple you might be asked what's
your proudest accomplishment um so
that's something you should be able to
answer again you have 10 seconds to
prepare and 60 seconds to record um and
so how if you were just having a
conversation with someone how you would
respond to that question um there are
some questions like tell me about a time
that you failed and how you bounced back
things like that and so it's not meant
to trip you up it's really like to see
how you think on your feet and how you
would have a conversation and so really
utilize the software and make sure you
feel comfortable test out your
microphone test out your video make sure
you know where the question's going to
appear on the screen where it shows that
it's recording all of the different
pieces before you click that you're
ready um so you there shouldn't be any
reason that you feel unprepared for it
going into it because you'll be able to
see all of the the different pieces of
the video question to before you say
that you're ready to begin recording and
just try to have fun with it um and just
approach it kind of like a conversation
or how you might approach an interview
question great um and can you talk a
little bit about some ways that um the
son fellows program supports or support
students with Healthcare
backgrounds yeah um with specifically
within the program yeah yeah um so there
are a few different ways for folks who
have Healthcare backgrounds or are
looking to get into the healthcare space
um within the program that that that's
um an opportunity and so the way the
sloon fellows program is structured
students start in June and their whole
summer term is spent with other SLO
fellow students you're all in a cohort
um taking core classes and really
setting those foundations creating
learning groups and things like that and
so there's not um a lot of formal
curriculum specialization in that first
semester once you get into the spr the
fall and spring semesters that's when
you have a mix of core classes and
elective courses and so this is where
you can start if you're really
interested in healthcare there are a lot
of healthc care electives that you can
take um through Sloan but you can also
take um cross-registered courses outside
of Sloan in the broader MIT Community or
even at Harvard and so you can kind of
develop um your curriculum to match what
you need in terms of your healthare
needs there is a health care certificate
and so that requires um at least half of
your elective credits to be focused on
um Healthcare and it has a few specific
requirements you have a couple required
Healthcare elective courses and then um
you choose from a list of approved
electives and so this is another way
that you can kind of specialize the
degree specifically to healthcare um
that is true also for other six C
certificates so if anyone's interested
in business analytics Finance
sustainability product management
Enterprise management or
entrepreneurship and Innovation um those
certificates work the same and slone
fellows are able to pursue one of those
certificates in their time of the degree
outside of that um kind of more
informally there are a lot of
opportunities through clubs and
organizations um again thinking about
health care um opportunities through the
health systems initiative as well which
is um the health care certificate is
taught and administered in conjunction
with Health Systems initiative and so
there are a lot of opportunities if you
want to kind of have a more specialized
degree in healthcare um there are ways
to do that and a lot of resources as you
think about that there's also the
healthcare um action learning lab which
goes along with the health certificate
Healthcare certificate and so plenty of
opportunities if you're either in
healthcare and looking to stay in
healthcare or in another industry and
looking to get into Healthcare there are
plenty of ways to kind of make that um a
focus of the Sloan fellows degree and I
would say no to Sloan fellows get the
same MBA degree because there is so much
opportunity for customization of the
degree and really catering the electives
um to what you need
personally
awesome and then there's also another
question about individuals who have
worked for the same company but their
company has different locations in
different countries so if you've kind of
bounced around will you list this all
under the same um employment in the
employment section or would you separate
it to say into like three separate
locations if you worked in three
separate cities across the globe yeah um
within the employment section when
you're filling out each of the
employment section entries you will put
the location um and
so if you have more than three entries
if your whole career has been at the
same company just in different locations
I would list them separately as
employment um entries if you have worked
at other companies as well um I would
list them all in the same employment
section so that you can list your other
companies but um you'll also showcase
the locations through your resume and so
we'll have that information um hopefully
in both spots but if not in both spots
then at least in the resume of the
different
locations
awesome okay um and then here's another
one um about someone who might be just
missing you know the 10year fulltime
experience Mark but they can supplement
it with time that they've spent
freelancing how do we view that yeah so
we're really looking for 10 years of
experience and that would be 10 years of
fulltime post-bachelor's degree
experience up until the start of the
program so say you're at nine years
right now or a little over nine years um
and would be at 10 years by June of
2025 then that meets the 10year minimum
um there are always um like we'll review
every application and see what those
experiences are and so sometimes there
are on a case-by casee basis if they're
right on the cusp of 10 years but we
really are looking for that 10 years of
experience in addition to General
management experience because that's
what makes students successful in this
program and that's who this program is
really geared towards and so it's not
just the years of experience that we're
looking for um but also the general
management experience so making sure
that you have both of those and if you
don't have especially the general
management experience but also not the
10 years maybe considering our 2-year
MBA degree as a better option great um
and then can you provide some more
details on what we're expecting to see
from the first video
question where they should record how
deep they should go into their personal
life kind of just a little bit more that
yeah um so you as an applicant have kind
of total creative freedom to provide
whatever information you want in the
introductory video The Prompt is to
introduce yourself to your future
classmates so I think thinking about how
you might do that what information you
would share with them um there is no
right or wrong way to take the video
statement and so you are welcome to
provide only professional details you're
welcome to provide only personal details
it's really up to you to decide what
information you want to share and how
you want to sh showcase your personality
I will say the most memorable um TP
videos that we've seen are the more
creative ones so um a couple examples
that I can think of we had someone who
was an avid hiker and they hiked a
mountain and recorded their video at the
top of a mountain um someone that is
really into um cooking and showcase some
um foods that they were cooking from
their home country those are some of the
more creative ones where people are
showing kind of more personal aspects
than professional you're welcome to do a
mix you can kind of take it however you
want and showcase whatever you would
like but I think really let who you are
as a person shine through and your
personality shine through and have fun
with that video um and so total creative
freedom that you have with that one to
provide um just an introduction of who
you are and um what you might bring to
the Sloan community
great um and then we also have a
question about management experience
again um if would we consider management
con experience um if it's through
individual contributions so for example
um if someone as an individual
contributor was helping manage a program
outside of their full-time experience or
full-time um employment how would we
view that yeah um when we're looking at
General management experience we're
really looking for folks who are leading
others um that have direct reports or
dotted lines to people that they're
delegating tasks to um helping develop
them as professionals but also people
who are at a position where they're
influencing decisions that are being
made for teams or
organizations um that they're leading
kind of big picture strategy
they might be overseeing budgets or
cross functional teams and so we're
really looking for like all of those
experiences within General management um
we want to see that you have kind of
what that sphere of influence is that
you have and
so we are not necessarily looking for
individual contributors for this loone
fellow's degree um to be successful in
the classroom you have to have these
General management experiences and so
really thinking about that sphere of
influences who you're delegating to who
you're influencing who you're
collaborating with we want to see all
those relationships and those
relationships need to be there um so if
you are an individual contributor who
doesn't have all of those aspects of
General management then the spone
fellow's degree might not be the right
degree for
you great um and then can you also just
talk a little bit more about the CDO and
support for employment after graduation
yeah um I'll talk a little bit about it
during the program too but um the CDO is
our career development office and
they're very involved with the slone
fellows curriculum from the start of it
um even prior to getting to campus our
students work on a 360 leadership
assessment um survey and then work kind
of work through that to see where their
leadership skills are um and where are
areas for improvement and they work
directly with um executive coaches as
well as they think about kind of further
developing their leadership skills in
their time and that's through the career
development office as well um the career
development office also has specific
Sloan fellows advisors to really think
about um career trajectory oftentimes um
SLO fellow students might be looking to
Pivot Industries functional area or um
geographic location and so there are a
lot of resources as you're thinking
about which one of those categories you
might fall into um how to kind of
navigate that career trajectory and um
Career Development and exploration and
so there are a lot of um workshops put
on through the CDO during students time
um so they begin thinking about where
they want to be after graduation from
the start of the program and working
towards that um and then there are also
within the CDO alumni experts across 17
Industries right now um and there are
multiple experts per industry that can
provide guidance so that's a really
valuable resource for folks who are
looking to Pivot Industries um and then
after graduation students have access to
the CDO but also um the Alumni network
is a really valuable Resource as things
as students think about their career
trajectories and there are over 31,000
um MIT SLO alums worldwide and so a lot
of kind of human capital to tap into and
um utilize as you think about your
career going
forward great um Let's see we also have
some questions on if you're able to
apply to um the sfba and the regular MBA
at the same
time yep yeah you can submit an
application to both um I think also
attending events for both programs to
see if you're able to kind of figure out
which one might be a better fit for you
having conversations with us but you are
more than welcome to apply to both our
slone fellows MBA and our 2-year MBA
um in the same admission
cycle great um and can you also talk a
little bit about family supports for
slone
fellows yeah um a lot of our students um
come to the slone fellows programs with
their significant others which at SL we
call SOS or families and so there's a
lot of support built intentionally into
the program for that um thinking about
this past weekend uh they did a welcome
back to camp us for the fall and it was
a day that families were invited to so
they had a lunch that was put on by the
slone fellows program office and then
they had the opportunity to go to the
museum of science with their families
and so that's just one example of how
families and SOS are um really thought
of through the co-curricular offerings
for our Sloan fellow students um there
are certainly opportunities that are
just for students as well or just for
students in their SOS um there was a
welcome back at a bar in downtown Boston
um which required all attendees to be
over 21 so that was just open to SOS and
students but um there are a lot of
opportunities for family engagement
through the Sloan fellows program many
students do come with families and SOS
and even outside of the Sloan fellows
program at Sloan there's ano Club um so
SOS are able to join that and um get
involved with other SOS that are beyond
the SL fellows program as
well great and then we have a few
questions about um people who are
entrepreneurs are pivoting into
entrepreneurship and what resources are
available at slan for them yeah um I
would say a lot of folks who join the
Sloan fellows degree have some sort of
um entrepreneurial Endeavor either
immediately after graduation or a little
further down the line and so there are a
lot of resources um within the Salone
fellows program specifically for that
but then also the broader MIT community
and so thinking back to the seven
certificates that I mentioned one of
those is entrepreneurship and Innovation
which is administered in conjunction
with the Martin trust Center which is
MIT Center for entrepreneurship and so
that is a really valuable resource for
folks who are looking to get into
entrepreneurship um getting involved
with entrepreneurship ecosystem from the
start is really helpful they put on
different Accel accelerator and
incubator programs um once a semester
they do a a pitch night where you can go
and Pitch yourself to maybe find another
um your future co-founder or just hear
ideas of others um they do events like
the MIT 100K which was recently um this
past year was won by um one of our MBA
students um and to gain funding for
their um entrepreneurial Endeavors and
so there are a lot of opportunities as
you kind of think about how you're
developing your ideas and um getting it
from ideation into a reality and so
really engaging in the Martin trust
Center is I would say the number one
resource um for folks who are interested
in entrepreneurship there are also clubs
and organizations within the Sloan
Community um to get involved there and
then the broader MIT community so a
wealth of resources for folks who are
interested in entrepreneurship um and
even opportunities to formally kind of
um signify to Future co-founders that
you're dedicated to that area through
the entrepreneurship and Innovation
certificate great and then what kind of
General guidance would you give to
applicants who are involved in family
business yeah um So within the
application materials um in the
employment section um you will signify
that it's a family business in
employment um as you're completing an
application we are not looking for like
letters of recommendation from family
members and that's true for any of our
applicants and so thinking about who
you're asking to be a recommender um
should really be a professional contact
supervisor or manager and if if you're
not able to provide one of those um that
is not a family member thinking about
clients that might be able to speak to
your um the impact of your work and so
um There Are Places to provide those
details of family business but um please
make sure that you're providing a letter
of recommendation that is not um from a
family member
great and then um can you share
some insight about what it's like for
people pivoting more specifically people
pivoting from maybe a more traditional
background to
something like entrepreneurship that's a
little less um
cleancut yeah um I think depending on
like where someone's permitting to if it
is
entrepreneurship um utilizing the eni
certific certificate is really helpful
engaging with the Martin trust Center is
helpful um if you are looking to Pivot I
think knowing that before you start the
program so you can very intentionally
seek out those opportunities to help
with that pivot if you had a specific
industry that you're looking to start an
Endeavor in um maybe connecting with the
industry the alumni experts from that
industry to kind of get their guidance
on it um there are a lot of
opportunities for networking through the
Martin trust Center so thinking about
how you're engaging with those folks um
but there are plenty of opportunities
and a lot of folks in the SLO fellow's
degree are pivoting in some way and so
it's kind of thought of throughout the
curriculum and what's being administered
to students but also the opportunities
outside the classroom and just making
sure that you're thinking very
intentionally about what you're engaging
with to ensure that you can be
successful in that
pivot great um I think this is probably
a good final question to leave with
because it has a little bit more to do
with actually submitting your
application but if your application is
mostly ready but you might be a little
bit concerned about um not having as
many advanced cours work like calculus
on your academic record should you wait
and try and take those classes on your
own or should you go ahead and submit
your application in round one yeah um I
do want to reiterate that those classes
the coursework that we ask you to detail
in the relevant coursework section is
not a requirement by any means and so
folks are admitted to the program even
if they don't have any of that um and so
just thinking about that aspect but also
thinking back to the ideal candidate
profile that I shared at the beginning
of today's session um we are looking for
people who have Quant comfort and so if
you don't think that it's showcased
through the foror that you've taken
thinking about the other application
material that you are providing and if
you feel that that is um sufficient to
Showcase your skill set with
quantitative um aspects and topics and
so it really is up to you to kind of
figure out if you feel that all of your
application materials best showcase um
your skill set and ability to be
successful in the program or if you
would feel more comfortable um waiting
and providing an additional um piece of
data through like a certificate or an
online course or something like that so
it's up to you to kind of figure out if
that if you feel that your application
showcases th those skills but again it
is not a requirement to have any of the
relevant coursework um topics completed
prior to the
program
awesome cool well thanks Sam for um
asking some of the questions and thank
you everyone for attending today's
session we really appreciate the time
you took out of your day to join us um
we look forward to hopefully seeing all
of your applications