I've seen this as a call to action and a
way for me to step up to the problem
with a potential solution.
[Music]
I am researching distributed energy
resources. I'm compiling a data set that
takes the data on wind turbines, solar
panels, electric vehicle chargers, and
power plants and sees how that data is
correlated within counties based on the
different characteristics such as
population, education, and race. I
started off first on doing California in
the hopes of moving on to other states
within the US. The most interesting
thing that I've learned from my research
is about distributed energy resources in
general. I had never understood how they
were integrated into the grid or how
they had such a profound impact on the
energy that we have. I saw this project
and I saw how they are using distributed
energy resources and the data they have
in order to make a difference so that
other researchers and politicians can be
informed and make good decisions in the
future.
[Music]