Episode
8. Are you sure that's a risk?
If something can go wrong, it will go
wrong. This is what's known as Murphy's
law, and it is one of those awkward
rules of thumb that every engineer has
had to wrestle with. Just keep it in
mind for now. The common advice given to
innovators and entrepreneurs is that you
should focus. You're told to pick one
idea or one market or one user,
whatever, and work on it. The advice
makes it seem like this is only your
choice to make. The more focused you
are, the lower the risk. But you are not
being advised to focus per se. Rather,
you're being told to narrow your
options. There is a difference. Remember
the analogy we drew between working on
the problem and what Chris Hatfield said
about the way astronauts prepare for
missions to the International Space
Station. The way you were being asked to
focus is similar to telling astronauts
to pay attention only to problems in
some part of the rocket and ignore
everything else. The problem with that
advice is Murphy's law. It always stands
in the way. If something can go wrong,
it will. And as Chris Hatfield put it,
you just decided to not pay attention to
many things that can kill you. The same
might be true for your innovating.
Narrowing your options at the start to
just the one idea increases your risk
and gives you a false sense of
certainty. That's exactly the opposite
of what you want. Focusing and narrowing
are not the same thing. This is easy to
see in a camera. When you zoom, you
narrow the field of view. When you focus
the image, the image gains sharpness and
clarity, but the field of view stays the
same. Whether you are the innovator or
the capital, you want to reduce risk by
increasing clarity around what you are
doing. Narrowing your options only
increases risks. Like Murphy's law and
the distinction between focus and
narrowing, in the new mindset, we avail
ourselves of several finance and general
engineering principles like preventing
error accumulation, diversification, the
difference between precision and
accuracy, and many more that fall beyond
the scope of this introductory course.
Those principles help innovators make
informed decisions without wasting time
or inadvertently increasing risk. In the
MIT mindset, students do this by keeping
at least three distinct options open
throughout their explorations. They
focus on coming up with next steps and
actions that will help them advance in
all three at the same time. Which three
they focus on might change as they gain
understanding of the problem, but
keeping three options open helps them
keep Murphy's law at bay. Chances are
this is not the first time you heard
about Murphy's law, but it might be the
first time you hear it connected with
innovation. We hear so many things about
innovation that sometimes we forget what
should be obvious. The way I typically
summarize this for my students is that
there's a lot of things you need to
unlearn about innovation so you can
actually use the skills you already
have. The next video tell you all there
is to unlearn so you can actually truly
start innovating.
[Music]