[Applause]
thank you thank you first of all well
good morning everyone I'm gatri shasan
executive director office of corporate
relations MIT it is an honor to welcome
you to our Flagship conference research
and development and where you'll hear
all about the wonderful Cutting Edge
research that's happening at MIT and all
the
Innovations I also want to thank our
distinguished speakers you're going to
hear from all of them and I'm hoping
you're going to be inspired and you'll
hear about a lot of wonderful uh
activities that are happening
there um I do want to emphasize that
your participation and engagement Drive
the success of not only this conference
but also of all the wonderful
collaborative um solutions that we come
up at MIT right we are all about working
with um real problems and solving them
to begin I'd like to um you know um if
we can move on to the next slide I'm
hoping um so I I know you've all seen uh
or many of you know about MIT but I just
wanted to give you a snapshot of who we
are and what we are we have 105 Nobel
Prize winners and two of them were the
most recent winners and I wanted to
highlight those for those of you who may
have missed that news at some point um
but we have uh about 1100 uh faculty
members uh 4, uh300 uh
researchers uh 4500 undergraduate
students and 7500 uh uh close to 7500
graduate students and we have a lot of
international students in our midst as
well I did want to emphasize that MIT is
MIT because of all the industry um
driven uh projects that we do uh we have
65 plus uh departments labs and centers
we have about $840 million in research
out of which 20% comes from industry uh
sponsored
research half of that industry sponsored
research comes from you all IP members
right you all come to these uh
conferences learn about um work that we
do at MIT and solve real problems
engaging with our faculty and
researchers we have about 600 um patents
filed in uh last in the last fiscal year
362 fact uh p PS issued uh4 million in
licensing revenue and about two 23
startup companies that were formed um
using MIT
ILP now I did want to focus you know
about all you're going to hear about all
kinds of research activities that are
happening at MIT in all kinds of sectors
right but I did want to emphasize that
uh when President kluth came she charged
us with focusing on three institutional
areas um climate and sustain
stainability Life Sciences artificial
intelligence to focus on global problems
and solving for them at
MIT now you must have heard about the
industry Leone program right you must be
wondering what is the industry Leone
program the industry Leone program is a
way for you to connect with MIT right
and you can connect with MIT in through
its research through its Innovation
through its students and through its
education offerings right and you can do
it in three uh modes one is you can
understand and learn through developing
your employees through uh webinars
conferences workshops through executive
briefings for your um companies um
through learning Journeys through access
uh to our conferences of course and of
course discount on um you know uh
professional education uh exec education
and open learning you can also discover
and solve your problems through meeting
with faculties labs and centers um
strategic Executive Education um
assistance with identification of
opportunities for sponsored research
right and solving those problems and of
course lastly you can uh Network you can
network with our students you can
network with our um 800 plus startups uh
through our startup Exchange program and
of course you can uh Network amongst
yourself with other ILP members um and
so please go forth and do
that and of course you must have heard
about startup exch ex change what is a
startup exchange it's a program to
connect industry with startups MIT
connected startups we call them and they
are all um we have about 856 startups in
our midst um we have about startups uh
51 startups that joined last fiscal year
and we have had 120 plus lightning talks
and you are going to be uh treated with
um lightning talks today as well and I'm
hoping you're going to enjoy and
discover um uh innovative ideas that
could be helpful for your uh companies
as well and we have had 87 STX event um
lastly uh I did want to um before I
conclude I want to thank hongfan uh and
Natalie Kim you will hear from them uh
they are the um hardworking uh people
behind the content for today's
conference and I do want to thank them
and of course behind all of that I want
to thank the communications in events
team who worked tirelessly behind the
scenes and all that you see today is
because of their effort right this show
is a success because of them and I also
want to St thank the startup exchange uh
team members who tirelessly work to
bring the startups to the midst to
Showcase them and highlight them for
your effort lastly before I leave I want
to say there are a bunch of program
directors in the audience today and so
if you want to learn more about ILP and
our offerings please feel free to reach
out to to them and they'll be able to
navigate uh MIT for you thank you so
[Applause]
much thank you K three for wonderful
introduction good
morning and good afternoon and good
evening for all who are joining us
online welcome to the 2024 MIT research
and development conference I'm najan Kim
Natalie Kim uh one of the program
directors at MIT OCR corporate relations
uh this year's R&D conference is the
ipce flagship event featuring an
engaging two-day program with six deep
div tracks covering Space Tag Mobility
Innovation strategy AI healthc care and
Quantum and this year especially in
celebration of the 40th anniversary of
the MIT Microsystems technology
Laboratories MTL we are also
highlighting the latest research from
MTL honoring the fourth Decades of
innovation and discovery