Wow, that was intense, wasn't it? So,
let me lighten up the
mood. So, I heard that there was a frog
that arrived late to this conference
today. Can you guess
why? I heard that his car was
towed. So, that intensity has gone down
a little bit. Let me first welcome you
to today's conference and I'm um excited
uh about the agenda and I'm uh thrilled
to see you all here and I hope you're
going to get as much excitement and
knowledge from this conference that I'm
hoping I will and um and I'm I'm sure
you'll get back uh with a lot of uh
anecdotes. So I'm Gaitri Shini Vasan.
I'm the executive director at MIT
corporate relations and today we gather
here not just as representatives to our
respective organizations
um but you know also uh as part of the
global community um that believes in the
power of connections and partnerships
and uh at MIT corporate relations we are
committed to um building meaningful
relationships fostering strategic
alliances and creating lasting impact.
acts. As we explore the opportunities
and challenges of uh our connected
world, I am reminded of the importance
of collaboration and mutual
support. You know what we can do is
drive positive change on a global scale.
So that's why these kind of conferences
are important for you to attend and
listen in and spread the word. Let me
start first of all by thanking three
people. um Steve Whitaker um Jim Flynn
and Graham Wrong uh for their tireless
work in putting together this agenda
that uh you're going to be um exploring
uh
today. Um sorry I can you please uh go
to the next slide? I think I forgot
my
clicker. Um I wanted to start out with
the fact what is MIT? MIT is comprised
of 17,000ish
uh employees, um 1,000 uh professors,
4,300 uh
researchers, 105 Nobel Prize winners,
and yes, you heard that right, 105 Nobel
Prize winners, and we have the latest
ones um here on uh their pictures uh
shown to you. Um and of course 4,500
undergraduates 7,300 graduate students
and the composition of our students is
29%
international also at MIT we are a very
researchheavy intense uh uh institute
right so there's 65 plus research uh
centers and programs um 840 million
onampus sponsored research And you see
that I said on campus because I'm not
counting Lincoln Lab, which is a whole
other amount of research that happens
there. Uh 608 US patents, 323 patents
issued, um three $39.3 million in
licensing revenue, 24 startup companies
formed using MIT ILP. Sorry, MIT IP, not
ILP. But I do want to also underscore
the fact that you know of all the uh
industry funded research that happens
about half of them are because of
collaborations with members such as you
who identify places to collaborate with
MIT. I also wanted to share a few MIT's
past AI contributions. You may know some
of them but I just wanted to showcase
this foundations for so from 1950s to60s
pioneers such as Marvin Minsky and John
McCarthy conceived foundational concepts
in AI lisp I'm sure some people have
heard this was in 1958 among the
earliest programming languages developed
for AI Eliza in the 1960s one of the
first chat bots right who would have
thought that 60s we had a chatbot I
didn't know that um Apollo guidance
computer uh 1960s to the '7s. This
helped with the Apollo missions, right?
Um the moon landing uh and then many
other variable computing uh effective um
computing um gesture interfaces,
Mindstorm, smart cities, liquid AI and
many more. I'm just highlighting a few.
And again, all these happen at MIT and
MIT is such an interdisciplinary place.
It's not happening at one place, right?
It's happening through MIT Seale. You'll
see a little bit of some of these people
represented in the other room. So when
you have lunch or networking uh breaks,
please go and meet with them. Schwarzman
College of Computing, Media Lab, Sloan
School of Management, um uh MIT IBM
Watson AI Lab, uh Lincoln Lab, LIDS, and
the MIT Generative uh AI impact
consortium, which you'll hear about
later in the agenda today.
The MIT campus as I mentioned it's very
interdicciplinary right so the campus
and the Kendall square have become very
dense environment often referred to as
the most innovative square mile on the
planet extending from the east to the
west along the Charles River with views
of downtown Boston our campus continues
to expand right once it was an
industrial area I'll show you a picture
later it has transformed into a major
innovation hub lab new now home to more
than 150 high-tech companies including
the most prominent names in life
sciences, technology, and
pharmaceuticals. Our office is centrally
located on campus and offers companies a
dedicated space to collaborate and
explore new opportunities to advance
innovation. But this recent growth um
with this recent growth the ILP remains
committed to enhancing support for
companies to connect with the uh culture
of continuous exchange among uh industry
and academia and
government. With that I promise the next
picture. This is how Kendall Square was
in the 60s and 70s. It was like an
industrial place with surface parking
loting place right? I mean um there was
not that much happening and look at how
it is now. This is how it is in 2025.
It's amazing right the transformation
that has happened. Um so I I just want
you to know that the campus and MIT like
the Kendall Square commercial side and
MIT campus are not two different things.
They are integrated and porous.
This is what uh is the composition of
companies MIT and all um uh surrounding
areas. Right? So Kendall Square is home
to one of the densest concentration of
innovation and entrepreneurship around
the world hosting um the leading biotech
companies. So you can see the different
color codes, right?
Maroon is all MIT. The pink is biioarma.
Uh the blue the dark blue is venture
capital. The turquoise is IT data and
technology. And the green are energy
related
companies. Now let me come to MIT. Uh I
said I'm from MIT corporate relations.
But what is corporate relations?
Corporate relations is all about
connecting MIT to industry and industry
to MIT. And we try to do that through
four um uh pillars research innovation
students and education or upskilling and
reskilling. So how do we do that is
through two integrated programs
industrial leazison program and the
startup exchange and in the industrial
leazison program is a comprehensive
portal to MIT and the startup exchange
promotes collaboration between MIT
connected startups with uh industry
partners.
Um we have 200 plus member companies in
the industrial leazison program. Some of
you are here represented and 800 plus
MIT connected uh startup uh companies.
And I want you to see when I say 200
plus companies, I'm talking about the
breadth and scope, right? We have 30%
representation in North America, 20% in
Europe, 40% in Asia, 6% South America,
and um everywhere else, right?
Um and with that, I'm going to thank
you, but I also wanted to thank um uh
and give a huge shout out to the unsung
heroes that make this conference happen.
So the marketing and communication uh
communication and events team um so they
are all sitting there they are sitting
outside and they are here to help you
and I also wanted uh to take a moment
for to ask all the program directors
from ILP to stand up so that if you have
any questions you want to understand uh
what is the industry leazison program
they are right there sprinkled together
and you will notice that our badges are
different from yours yours are long ours
are wide so if you see a wide
uh name tag, you know who who you want
to talk to. With that, thank you so much
and
[Applause]
welcome. So, good morning everybody. U
welcome to Boston for the uh first ILP
conference of the year. Uh very much
focused on the kind of the
transformative
uh potential of reality of of AI,
artificial intelligence. As Gathri
mentioned, AI really runs through the
veins and bones of the institute and has
done since 1959 when the AI lab was
first founded and then was through the
media lab through computer science and
AI lab and the Schwartzman Center. Um,
I'm Steve Whitaker. I'm one of the
program directors that Gareth just
mentioned. Uh, and I've uh been having a
lot of fun for the last few months
working with Jim and Graeme who you'll
see later on to kind of bring this event
together. Um, we've got a a fairly
packed day for you. We've got 17 faculty
and researchers, uh 10 uh star MIT
related startups. So, we're going to do
some fairly brutal timekeeping, I'm
afraid. So, we'll kind of try to keep
everybody on uh on track.