(bright music)
(motorcycle engines roaring)
(bright music continues)
(upbeat music)
(David laughs)
(upbeat music continues)
(wheels squeaking)
(bright music)
(bird squawking)
(glass shattering)
(students guffaw)
- Oh my God, it's Product Man.
I can't believe it.
(students applaud)
- Product Man at your service.
(upbeat music continues)
I'm David Wallace,
a mechanical engineering
design professor at MIT.
Play seriously?
Now, that's a thought.
And smash through the glass
and then I kinda pose
in my superhero pose.
- Oh my God, it's Product Man.
I can't believe it.
- When I look at my own work
or watch others in theirs,
when really good things are happening,
we're energized, vibrant, excited.
Here's the detonator with the safety key.
- [Assistant] Okay, it wasn't plugged in.
(students laugh)
- [David] We're so serious
about the importance
of what we are doing.
(electricity pops)
- Whoa.
- [Students] Oh!
- And that could be really stressful.
But somehow it isn't.
Product Man at your service.
- The prototype just shorted.
And it scared everyone here.
- It feels like we're solving
a puzzle, like a game.
This is a gag product
and it worked perfectly.
We feel free to have fanciful thoughts
and we're not afraid of a mistake
and we're really determined to succeed.
- Thank you, Product Man.
- Doesn't that sound like play?
I'm here to protect design, debugging,
and the 2.009 Way.
Gotta go.
When solving hard
problems become like play,
good things tend to happen.
(upbeat music continues)
(upbeat music)
(students chattering indistinctly)
(drill whirring)
(upbeat music continues)
In our design class at MIT,
we're very serious about learning
and solving real problems.
We're working to become
better engineers and designers
to do things that matter.
And in the class, we pair all
this seriousness with play.
We're playful, quite literally.
It's serious engineering wrapped in fun.
(students yelling indistinctly)
So, the students come in
knowing we're gonna
have a build challenge,
knowing we're gonna have a theme reveal.
They know there's going
to be these playful events
throughout the entire course.
So, they arrive with anticipation.
They're waiting for it.
(upbeat music continues)
(machines booming)
Whoa!
And so then when it happens,
they're already invested and saying,
"We wanna make this something
we feel good about."
The reveal signals, hey, it's starting.
Now is go time.
And we take this very seriously.
We take it so seriously,
we'll spend hundreds of hours
making a playful reveal
that lasts 20 minutes.
- My opinion matters more.
- Oh, yeah.
(glass shatters)
(students gasp)
We smash a bottle over my head. Why?
Well, we're actually talking
about design critique
and professional ethics.
One step up and whack,
and then I'll tell you
the key on the whack.
- Hit.
(students laugh)
- Another example is design for assembly.
(students yelling indistinctly)
So, it's really important
when we design products
to think about how
they're gonna go together.
So, what we do is a game.
It's a game of who can put
in the fasteners fastest,
but each person has a different setup
that has different problems
related to assembly.
So, it makes it absolutely clear
how bad design for assembly choices
can impact the outcomes in your product,
and even in their case,
how easily they're gonna
get their prototype together
and take it apart when
they need to fix it.
(students yell indistinctly)
We're learning things
that we will apply in our serious work,
but we're learning them
in a way that's playful,
that engages us,
and we'll retain it.
- I'm done!
- Using play, we can
make the subject real.
(upbeat music)
(upbeat music continues)
Hello.
If you think of a lecture,
it's like theater.
Wow, it's a computer.
Whoa, and there's a button over here.
I wonder what this does.
(students cheering)
(machine booming)
You're really putting on a performance
in a very sincere way,
but one that's designed to engage
and draw the interest of students.
(David screams)
(upbeat music continues)
And all the silly characters,
they do have meaning, context.
This fish, for example, was part
of an environmental-like challenge.
But even more importantly,
it gives students permission
to feel free and exuberant in their work.
(upbeat music continues)
(gentle music)
By being playful, by being silly,
but still talking about serious topics,
what we're doing
is we're just giving
the students permission
to feel that way themselves.
It allows them the freedom to
say, "Hey, let's try this,"
to think of new things, to feel creative,
to not feel constrained
that they might just do something wrong.
Can we all learn how to do this?
Of course we can.
Like most things, it just
takes a little practice.
(gentle music continues)
Start with playing.
Find ways to combine
playfulness with what you do.
Perhaps there's a game-like
approach to getting a job done,
even doing a chore.
Give it a go and embrace
the power of positive.
(students chattering indistinctly)
And that's when you can say,
"We're playing seriously."
- My mom gonna see this.
- No, we'll...
- Guys!
- Whoa.
- Whoa, whoa.
- [Student] Whoa, whoa.
(David chuckles)
- [David] Do you wanna do the
bubble talk thing for a bit?
(David's lips smacking)
(gentle music continues)