[MUSIC PLAYING]
I think we're really at the
beginning of a whole new era
of biological
understanding, and one
where I think MIT
is really extremely
well-positioned to lead.
The planet is changing, and
new diseases are coming.
The things that we
thought we were treating
are changing in real time, which
as inventors, is an opportunity.
But it's really
a call to action.
Things that might have
taken years in the past
can be done in weeks,
if not days, using
the power of computation.
And what better place to
invest in technology than MIT.
At MIT, it's not
simply the discovery
that's up at the top
of our ambition list.
It's also applications
of those discoveries
to making the world
better, to coming up
with better products,
better ways to do things.
One of the things that
we're excited always
to collaborate with our
colleagues at MIT around
is how do we make big leaps?
How do we make daring
departures from what
is obvious and adjacent?
And that's where many of
the breakthroughs come from.
We want to find a
mechanism to bring people
from lots of different
areas together so we
can get this synergistic
effect to solve
really important problems.
There's been a
natural confluence
of the science, the
medicine, the capital,
and the entrepreneurs.
And that doesn't exist
anywhere else in the world.
And MIT has been focal to that.
Being in this environment
allows us then
to tie into that ecosystem and
to learn from them in terms
of understanding
how best the work
we do can be applied outside.
But vice versa, it allows
them to have access
to how we're thinking
about pushing
the boundaries of the future.
And so that's one
of the many reasons
that we are launching MIT HEALS.
Anyone who has spent
any time at MIT
knows this place
has a secret sauce.
And I love so much that
we can now combine that
with the strength that
the hospitals, with all
of the remarkable industry
connections in Kendall Square
to really move health and
life sciences forward in ways
that we can only imagine.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right.
Good morning again.
So I'm Sally Kornbluth,
President of MIT,
and I'm delighted to welcome you
to the launch of the MIT Health
and Life Sciences Collaborative,
or simply MIT HEALS.
I'll have more to say about
MIT HEALS in a moment.
But first, it's my honor to
introduce a very special guest
this morning.
Since she was elected to the
Commonwealth of Massachusetts
just two years ago,
Governor Maura Healey
has focused on making the
state a leader in clean energy,
a more affordable place to live,
and a great place for businesses
of all kinds to start,
grow, and succeed.
Here at MIT, we
especially appreciate
her personal
enthusiasm and advocacy
for the state's interlocking
innovation ecosystems,
from climate technology
and advanced manufacturing,
to AI and the life sciences.
So we cannot be more delighted
to have her with us today as we
launch MIT HEALS.
Please join me in offering a
warm welcome to Massachusetts
Governor Maura Healey.
[APPLAUSE]
Well, good morning.
And thank you so much,
President Kornbluth.
Belated happy birthday to you.
Look, I got word that
this was happening,
and I never want to miss an
opportunity to visit MIT.
And I mean that.
So to all of you who are
here, Madame President,
distinguished faculty,
scientists and leaders
from across this
great university,
thank you for all that you do.
And thank you for
all that you're
going to do because today is
about what you're going to do.
And it's so, so exciting.
Congratulations on this
launch of MIT HEALS.
I love that title and
what it encapsulates.
I was also delighted
to have a moment
with your co-chairs of
this morning's symposium,
Dr. Amy Keating and
Katharina Ribbeck.
Lovely to meet you
both, although Amy and I
go way back because we went
to that other school down,
down the way.
One of the things as governor
that I really appreciate
is the opportunity
to see so many
of our state's
accomplished scientists
and brightest minds
come together,
work together, and
forge a new commitment
to improving human life.
It's even more exciting when
you think about this convening
to think about all the
amazing cures and treatments
and discoveries that
will result from it.
And I'm proud to say, and
I really believe this.
This is something that can
only happen in Massachusetts.
There's no place that has the
ecosystem that we have here.
We must fight hard to
always protect that
and to nurture that.
But we have the
greatest scientists
in the world, the greatest
universities, the greatest
hospitals.
We're number one for
innovation, for education,
and for health care.
And we draw top talent
from all over the globe.
We believe in solving
hard problems.
We, in fact, embrace
solving hard problems.
And this university
has always been
about thinking of ways to
reduce suffering, help humanity,
and further the common good.
We also are home to-- and
I find this remarkable.
Four of the 12 Nobel
Prize winners this year.
Four are from Massachusetts
and of course, two
are from this great university.
And it's just another
indication of Massachusetts
and this ecosystem always
punching above its weight,
so to speak.
This is what gives us
and distinguishes us
among global competition, both
for talent and for innovation
and for output.
It's why I also worked hard to
go out and recruit and appoint
Yvonne Hao as a leader
in an innovation economy,
to come and lead economic
development for the state.
I appointed Kate Walsh to be our
Secretary of Health and Human
Services, a leader of one of our
world-class teaching hospitals.
It's why we worked
hard, many in this room,
to go out and get after and
win the Investor Catalyst
Hub in ARPA-H, which is
the federal government's
new medical discovery agency.
And it's why in our new economic
development law that I recently
signed, we are making a
transformative commitment
as a state to the Mass
Life Sciences Initiative.
This has made us a global
leader and our charge
is to lengthen that lead.
And it's one of the
reasons I'm here
to say thank you because
what you are doing
in furthering aligns with
our state's interests
and where we want to go.
That includes also investments
in making Massachusetts
the global hub for climate
technology and for applied AI
and all sorts of things that
you are already ahead of us on.
But we are looking forward
to sync up and support
what you are doing.
And it's not by accident.
This is who we are
in Massachusetts.
We don't just believe in
science, we lead in science.
And we also know that that
requires intentionality
and effort every single day.
And that's what you do in
your classrooms, in your labs,
and other spaces.
And when I say "we,"
make no mistake about it.
I mean, you-- the scientists,
the brains, the researchers,
the students of
the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology.
And as President
Kornbluth knows,
MIT and the state
of Massachusetts,
the Commonwealth
have a long and very
connected history.
So thank you for
all that you do.
I think that the MIT
HEALS initiative really
reflects the strengths
of our state,
in some really profound
and important ways,
and in ways that we
know are particularly
critical at this moment as we
once again affirm collectively
our commitment and indeed
reverence for science,
for knowledge, for
innovation, for collaboration,
and for partnerships
that will really
help us transcend in time.
In this moment in our nation's
history and our world's history,
your leadership and
the work that you do
is more important than ever.
I cannot wait to see
the results of it.
I look forward with my team to
getting out to various things
you have happening related
to this wonderful, wonderful
effort.
And I just thank you for
being here in Massachusetts
and making not only our
state better but our country
and indeed our world better.
So enjoy the rest of this
wonderful, wonderful day.
And thank you,
President Kornbluth.
[APPLAUSE]