Hi everyone. Uh my name is Molly Breen
and I am the CEO and co-founder of
Parig. Uh our MIT connection is my
co-founder uh who went to MIT. I
unfortunately went to Harvard. Uh and I
am here to introduce Parig which is a
new AI native digital fabric. And the
big problem that we solve is that
enterprises are all running on software.
But that software doesn't work well for
those businesses out of the box.
everything from the salesforce like the
CRM system, the accounting system
tracking finance all the way to the ERP.
Uh there's always gaps in how these
things are connecting uh and the
business and the processes that they're
trying to run and it's the team that
ends up having to be the glue between
all of these different systems and
they're manually entering information
into these systems. They're exporting
information and putting it into Excel or
creating PowerPoints uh or they're like
pivoting between these different
systems. It's really expensive. uh it
doesn't work well, nobody likes it, uh
and you still don't have the answers for
how your business is doing. So, PARG is
solving this uh and we're that glue for
all of the data sources within an
enterprise and the workflows that
they're trying to run. And it's really
simple. It's a software that essentially
is integrating across all of these
siloed systems. We're automating manual
work and then we're amplifying them
using AI. And it actually works. teams
say that we are 100 times faster to
implement, 100 times easier to use and
100 times more adaptable as the business
changes.
So as this AI native digital fabric,
it's a software platform where picture a
business process within your company and
all of the IT systems that are related
but also like the nonIT systems, the
CSVs, the questionnaires and then using
a combination of this tool set use um
including interfaces, automations, even
um data storage and this AI co-pilot
that helps you write them teams ranging
from IT and sales all the way to
leadership are automating these manual
work. So just a few examples of this uh
teams take a crawl walk run approach. So
some really simple things would be
moving information from system A to
system B. So when a shipment is created
in the shipping system in the warehouse
uh and a record is automatically created
in the in the Salesforce for example. Uh
or if you're uh you know have a team
that's just like exporting data into
Excel every single week to build a
report like that's something that you
can automate with paraget. in this
walking uh category. Picture places
where you're trying to unify multiple
tools into a single dashboard or even
places where maybe you've overspent on a
solution and you're paying more uh too
much for it. You can uh bring that into
paragy. That happens a lot with like ERP
systems where uh people often overspend.
Uh and then finally, every business is
unique. uh and there's usually some
combination of these existing processes
that are true to their competitive
advantage and those teams in this run
approach are building those types of
software solutions to fill those unique
needs on top of
parig a really good example of this is
par is working with IGPS which is like a
midsize logistics company uh they're
doing reusable pallets between uh the
Chobanis of the world and the Walmarts
and within the logistics industry it is
plagued by a ton of legacy processes one
of which is this paperbased process that
uh confirms whether a shipment is
delivered or not. Somebody has to like
submit this PDF to say it was delivered.
Uh and this is a huge problem for them
because uh all the time these papers are
lost or there's some type of error in it
and all of those errors lead to lost
pallets and lost pallets obviously lead
to lost revenue. So using parig they
essentially trained an AI model on all
of their forms uh and they insert and
then we integrated with their existing
logistic system and we sit in line where
this AI model is essentially detecting
when a new form is submitted if it's
valid or not. Suspicious forms are
flagged uh uh and then a user can come
in and review it and with one click they
can ask a customer to resubmit it. And
this has transformed this process where
we're saving them 80 hours a month. uh
we've improved their cash flow by two
days and we've also improved their
customer experience because there's so
much less back and forth. Nobody's
getting mischarged and they're having
this true competitive advantage through
AI powered
transformation. And so we invite you to
consider what are the manual work or
siloed systems that you're looking to
fix within your company and uh check out
the more than 25 enterprises that are
using Parig uh with our companies
ranging from IGPS but also PepsiCo and
Burger King and more. uh we typically
work with IT leaders at mid to large
organizations uh predominantly in
retail, manufacturing, logistics and
would love to share more uh after the
talk. Thank you. Thank you Molly.