thank you good afternoon everyone um my
name is Dan Meyer I'm the CEO of cell
chorus and we apply machine learning and
artificial intelligence to study how
immune cells function and perform uh we
do this at single cell resolution and in
high throughput uh for some of the top
uh researchers and biopharmaceutical
companies in the world the reason we do
this is if you are re-engineering cells
uh recruiting cells training the immune
system inhibiting immune cells and you
want to understand how your product
works you want to be able to number one
understand how those cells move and
interact because they need to do so to
fight disease and just like every other
area of biology there's W wide variation
in how those cells perform so we want to
look at a lot of them but at single cell
resolution the most common way that our
customers and partners look at immune
cell function today is in a bulk live
cell Imaging assay we put
10,000 t- cells and 10,000 tumor cells
let's say into a vessel and then we look
at them over time to see how many of the
target cells die and maybe how many of
the immune cells die as well we don't
understand which cells perform best and
why and there's a lot of readouts we
don't get the good thing is these are
really well understood assays the
protocols are available and that's a big
benefit to us because we take a similar
approach for the user but we're placing
the cells into compartments that have
thousands of nanow Wells at the bottom
of them so an early version of our
device is at the bottom left and what
you see is an individual well with one
car T cell and three tumor cells and
when I play the video you see that this
cell if it
[Music]
plays I don't know if we can manually
play the video maybe
not thank
you oh maybe didn't come through so um
you can go to our website and I'll have
a link at the bottom you'll see that
this cell has to move form a synapse
with kill the first cell and then repeat
that process To Be A Serial killing T
cell what our algorithms do is identify
where the cells are classify them follow
how they move and then identify events
like cell death cyto kind secretion Etc
the reason we're using the algorithms is
we're making thousands of these videos
every sample we test generates as many
videos as Netflix has in its catalog
available to you as a user we're not
going to watch all the videos we're
going to use u a lot of computer vision
AI in order to do that for us that gives
us number one a lot of readouts number
two they're at single cell and number
three we can filter and just look at
cells that kill or don't kill just look
at cells that form a synapse or don't
form a synapse um and then if you're
interested in a particular cell or set
of cells we can pick them and do single
cell transcriptional sequencing Etc uh
further down the line um so number one a
common question I get is does it work
we've got data in more than 20
peer-reviewed Publications across a
range of cell types and applications
Etc uh number two uh does the market
value the data and we've opened an early
access lab where we are getting paid uh
in order to run assays for Designing new
therapies selecting lead candidates
quantifying responders and
non-responders evaluating potency and
viability of manufactured cells Etc um
we're sometimes a little bit of a unique
startup when we talk about customers the
they pay pay for the data uh we don't do
it for free um and so we do uh we do
know that people value the data uh and
importantly throughout all these
applications so for early research for
pre-clinical development and selecting
lead candidates for predicting response
in the clinic and doing process
development and Manufacturing analytics
these are fundamentally the same assay
so people can under have data to compare
to from early in their process all the
way through to process development uh we
do have have clinical Diagnostic and
prognostic applications which we're not
pursuing now because those have FDA
regulations potentially and take longer
and cost more uh one uh great example of
the platform we published with kite MD
Anderson and others uh this summer where
we took clinical product from um axis
cell ctis cell as well as clinical
development product and showed that
migration and serial killing uh is
associated with complete response
compared to dep partial and
non-responders um it's a short
presentation I would go into that in
more detail um let me know if you would
have any questions on that or other
examples um so we're actively running
the Early Access lab and we're about to
launch product working with uh mostly
Cell Therapy antibody and vaccine
companies there are also applications in
small molecules and other areas and
we're talking to Partners um for
preferred cro relationships um
instrument part Imaging instrument
Partnerships and then uh also
International distribution um and if
you'd like to see a video which is
normally the best part of my
presentation uh uh sor.com videos or
follow the QR code