So again, unfortunately, we have to
stop. It's pretty clear that uh we we
will do more events uh on this topic
because it's it's not just fascinating,
but uh it will affect all of our lives.
Um but today uh we are done. I hope you
found uh this presentation uh
informative and relevant and we would
love to hear your feedback as well as
suggestions about the topics for future
webinars, forums and conferences that we
run. If you would like to learn more
about how we work with companies, please
email us uh at ask-pit.edu.
Again, it's ask-pit.edu.
And with that, thank you again for
joining and I wish you all a very good
day wherever you are. Bye.