hello can people hear me are we good in
the
back are we good can can people hear me
good good good okay so today we are
going to uh move on from counting and
start the last unit on
probability uh probability is uh you
know very important it's one of the most
important disciplines you know not just
in computer science but like in in all
of the Sciences uh please don't tell
your other you know science instructors
that I said this um you know you use it
in like we've already seen it uh in this
class uh with the Miller Ren algorithm
uh you also see it in like you know
other randomized algorithms that you'll
see later in 61210 1220 5220 if you take
that uh we see it in Game Theory
information Theory signal processing
cryptography uh machine learning
medicine Stu
forensics uh you know the list goes on
and on uh but unfortunately it's also
one of the least understood
disciplines uh so there's a a pretty
famous quote attributed to uh Mark Twain
Benjamin Dy you know several other
people uh there are three kinds of lies
right there are lies there are damned
lies and
statistics uh so like you know you can
kind of lie with probability and
statistics by you know saying things
that are true that are you know also
very
misleading uh common sense is often very
demonstrably you know completely
unreliable uh which you know we'll see
in a in a moment uh there are many
graduate students like even in our
department uh again don't tell people
they said this uh you know that they can
they can do all sorts of exciting maths
but you know you give them a basic
probability question and you know they
don't know where to
start uh there are many garbage papers
that are you know based on faulty
understanding of probability uh even
some of our colleagues um have some uh
let's say issues
um today we are going to look at uh an
example um who who is sort of the Monty
Hall
problem oh nice decent number of people
okay um so yeah well we'll basically try
and use the Monty Hall problem to
illustrate that you know it's it's
really best to just kind of throw away
your intuition and just fall back on
rigorous step-by-step analyses okay
so uh the the Monty Hall problem uh it
kind of became famous in 1990 when uh
this this magazine columnist named uh
Marilyn vos Sant uh received a letter
from a Craig
Whitaker uh which read as follows
suppose you're on a game show and you're
given the choice of three doors behind
one door is a car and behind the others
goats you pick a door say number one and
the host who knows what's behind the
doors opens a different door say number
three which has a goat he says to do you
want to pick door number two now the
question is is it to your advantage to
switch okay and uh who thinks who thinks
yes it is advantageous to
switch who thinks no who thinks you're
better off sticking with your original
choice who thinks it doesn't
matter okay so it looks like most people
think that it's advantageous to switch
uh we've had a few extensions uh I'm
going to I'm going to count those as it
doesn't
matter uh so Marilyn replied that it's
indeed advantageous to switch uh if the
car is behind the originally picked door
then you lose by switching but if it's
not which is twice as likely then you
win by
switching uh and you know of course she
soon received a torrent of hate mail uh
including from professional
mathematicians
adamantly asserting that she was wrong
okay uh so the the hypo that was
described in this letter became known as
the Monty Hall problem uh you know after
the the host Monty Hall of the game show
which you know had games like
this uh where where you know contestants
faced very similar
situations uh so today we're going to
analyze it but first can I get uh a
handful of volunteers to come play Let's
Make a
Deal okay so empirically at least it
looks like it's better to switch right
like you know most people uh switched
and you know most people won the prize
when they did that uh so you know even
though there's only one door with the
prize it it seems to be pretty promising
right so let's see if we can analyze
this mathematically okay so we're going
to solve the Monty Hall problem using
what we call it the the tree method
which is a very simple and Elementary uh
approach uh that doesn't rely on
intuition it's just going to rely on
mathematical break
okay so the tree method uses 4ish steps
uh we used to call it the four step
method but like I couldn't for the life
of me tell you what the four steps are
if if uh you know they weren't written
in front of me uh so you know I prefer
to call it the tree method uh oh I can't
even count it kind of has five steps
we've got like a Step
Zero before you even start right you
really want to make sure that you are
like you know what question you're
trying to answer
okay so before we can even think about
uh solving a mathematical problem we we
need to know what the problem is okay uh
we we we need to to understand the setup
make sure we know what we're trying to
ask uh you know before we can start
analyzing it so the the letter from from
this uh Mr Whitaker was not entirely
precise Okay so we've got to kind of
figure out what axium we're working with
okay so we're going to assume the
following
uh prize is equally
likely to
be in any
box
okay so you know in principle it's
possible that uh you know Monty Hall
tries to be tricky and you know tries to
you know get into the contestants Minds
figure out what box they're going to
pick and like put the price somewhere
else or you know alternatively put the
pricee somewhere where they will pick it
because it's an exciting game show um
but you know we're going to assume that
you know Monty is just you know picking
the boxes randomly okay so the the prize
is going to go into into a randomly
selected box like completely uniform and
then the other two will have the goats
okay we're also going to assume that
Marilyn
or you know your colleagues whoever is
is doing the picking is equally
likely to
pick any
ebx okay so for the for the first pick
okay uh she doesn't know anything about
what Monty is doing she's just going to
you know toss some random coins in her
head and you know uniformly at random
she'll just pick one of the boxes it
doesn't really matter where the where
the price is
okay now after Marilyn picks her her box
right
Monty
must
reveal a non
prise okay and moreover it cannot be in
Maryland's box
okay so you know all that all that Mr
Whitaker said was right Monty did reveal
a non prize that wasn't uh you know
behind the chosen door uh it's not
entirely clear that this must happen and
in fact I believe on the game show there
were instances where you know he didn't
right um so we're just going to assume
that you know Monty is going to reveal a
prize you know regardless of whether
picked the correct uh correct box to
begin with
okay and
lastly if Monty has a
choice he picks
randomly okay so if Marilyn has you know
picked a non-price to begin with right
there's only one other non priz so so
Monty has to reveal that one but if
Marilyn has picked the the prize box to
begin with then Monty could in principle
open either of the other two boxes that
would still follow this role okay so
when Monty has a choice like this we're
going to say that you know he tosses a
coin and he's going to you know open one
of them at random
okay so note that these are all axioms
okay we are just you know taking them on
faith they may or may not have Merit but
if you accept them then you also have to
accept whatever conclusions we draw uh
from them okay uh but you know I should
point out that there are other perfectly
reasonable sets of
axioms uh that would lead us to
different conclusions right like maybe
Monty is you know very rude and if
Marilyn has you know uh has picked the
prize then he offers her the option to
switch
and if Marilyn has not picked the prize
then he forces her to go with whatever
she picked okay you know like this this
is you know a totally reasonable uh
interpretation uh and that would lead us
to to a different conclusion okay or you
know conversely maybe as benevolent
maybe if Marilyn uh maybe if Marilyn
didn't pick the prize initially he'll
always you know try and encourage her to
switch uh but if she picked the prize
he'll just be like nope you got to stick
with that okay
so now that we've got these
axioms we can now pose the mathematical
question uh what is the
probability that
Marilyn wins by switching
so uh yes um this is why I I singled you
out I I don't know where where you've
gone um you your colleague who who did
not switch uh you know we're trying to
analyze this probability which is which
is why single you want so I apologize
for that but you know it's for the
mouths don't take it
personally uh
okay
so now we have you know a well- defined
question right so now we can analyze it
using the four step
method the first of our four steps well
the tree method which has four
steps uh we need to figure out what we
call the sample
space
okay uh so whenever we're thinking about
a probability problem uh underlying it
is always what we call a probability
space okay and a probability space
consists of two
things uh these two elements are a set
right which we call the sample
space okay and you know for the purposes
of this class we're we're only going to
be looking at discrete probability
spaces so uh s is going to be a
non-empty and countable or finite uh set
we're not going to look at sets like r
or something like that okay so you know
this could be uh you know a set of three
boxes or it could be you know the
natural numbers something like that
something that's you know discret and
countable uh and then we also have a
function which we're going to denote by
the letters PR
R which Maps
s into the unit interval 0 to
one
okay so this this is going to be a total
function
with uh probably shouldn't use S here
let's call it
X
okay uh and you know slightly oddly when
we're talking about probabilities we use
square brackets instead of uh
parenthesis uh to enclose the argument
um but uh you know this is just a
function you can think of it as like
PR of X
okay uh so we're going to have the
requirement that if you sum up PR of X
over all of the X in your sample space
you should get one okay that's what it
means for this to be a probability
function okay
oh actually why don't we leave both of
these
up and move on to this
board
okay so this is called our probability
function and uh elements of s are what
uh we're going to call those outcomes
Okay
Okay so we've got a sample space s which
is a set of outcomes and we've got a
probability function which Maps each
outcome to a number between Z and one
okay and it should be the case that all
of those probabilities should sum to
one does that make sense to everybody
people people reasonably happy with this
questions comments
concerns
okay so our first objective is going to
be to figure out what our sample space
should be
okay so we're going to do that using
what we call a tree diagram
okay so for the moment we're going to
disregard the probability function and
just focus on S okay and then once we
figured out what s is we can figure out
how to assign probabilities to
everything okay so the tree diagram you
know as you might expect it's going to
be a diagram in the shape of a tree
where each level of the tree represents
some step in the random process we're
trying to model
okay so in the case of the Monty Hall
problem what might be the first
step like what's what's the first thing
that happens in the Monty Hall problem
the the first like source of
Randomness
yeah uh okay there's there's something
random that happens even before that the
answer was you pick a door
yeah yeah so the the first random thing
that happens right is I or or Monty
picks which store the prize uh the priz
is behind Okay so that's going to be the
first level of our tree
diagram okay so let's start drawing out
our tree diagram we're going to have our
root here and let's label this with you
know Monty hides
price okay
and we're going to have three edges
which go to you know the three
possibilities for what happens here okay
so it could be in door a door B actually
why don't I call these you know purple
gold and silver uh where's the
Eraser here we
go Okay so we've got our purple box our
gold box and our Silver Box
okay uh what's the next random thing
that
happens
yeah yeah yeah so as as your colleague
said last time you know the the next
random thing that happens is Marilyn or
you know the contestant picks a door
okay so um oh dear Monty and Marlin both
begin with the same letter okay let's
just call this
student okay so now each of
these is going to split into you know
three more possibilities okay so you
know our contestant can pick purple gold
or silver okay for each of these these
three things right regardless of where
Monty has hidden the prize the
contestant can pick you
know any of the uh any of the
doors
okay okay what's the next random thing
that could
happen yeah
were you raising your
hand oh no
no
okay yeah so if Monty has a choice of of
door to reveal then he picks one of the
one of the two remaining doors randomly
okay so so far we've got three branches
where that could happen
right we've got uh you know both Monty
and and uh Marilyn picked door P okay so
in that case Monty can reveal either G
or S
okay so let's uh you know make uh make a
branch for that uh similarly if they
both pick
G we could have either P or S and if
they both pick
s then here we could have either P or
G
okay now for the remaining ones right
like we we could you know say that uh
there's a random process there where
Monti is you know randomly picking from
a single element set so you know it's
always going to be the same thing we
could consider it a random outcome
though so we can also draw these arrows
here
okay uh uh kind of running out of space
here so let's
uh put this up
here let's label it on this board
so
Monty
reveals a
zon so this is the uh technical term for
a non prize I think the uh the non
prizes on Monty's show were called zonks
uh that they weren't always goats you
know some times it was uh you know
something some other sort of ridiculous
prize like a garbage can or a potato or
something um but yeah they were just
called
songs uh
okay so now are we done is there any
other Randomness that we haven't modeled
yet who thinks yes
oh okay so what are we missing
then everybody seems to think we're
missing somebody or are we just asleep
it is very early in the morning I
understand
uh are we missing
anything who thinks we're not missing
anything few hands okay uh well yeah
turns out that this is all of the all of
the randomness um you know you could
think about uh a different problem right
where where Marilyn has a random
strategy but for now we're just you know
our question right is you know Marilyn's
always going to switch what's the
probability that she wins okay so this
is all the randomness that we've
got so
now now that we have our tree structure
we can label our outcomes okay and
that'll tell us what the set s
is so the set s is just going to be the
set of leaves of our
tree okay
each you know path right corresponds to
you know some way that the random
process could turn out right those are
going to be our
outcomes
okay so formally we could label these as
tuples so let's say that this one's
PPG right so that represents you know
Monty hides the prize behind door P
Marilyn picks door p and then Monty
reveals a zon behind uh door G okay this
one's going to be
PPS this one's going to be
PG and now I haven't actually labeled
The Edge uh but you know if Monty hides
the the prize behind door p and then uh
Marilyn picks door
G where is Monty revealing the
zon s yeah
so let's uh label that okay and you know
we can continue all the way down
okay so
s oh I've just realized that I've
overloaded
it it's it's a script DES in my notes
and so it looks different I'm I'm I'm
sorry uh okay so our squiggly s is going
to be the set of all
tuples uh
so x y
z
in uh
PG s uh
oops cubed right so it's going to be
triples of you know PG and S such
that uh Z is not equal to X and Zed is
not equal to
Y okay
so that's how we're you know
mathematically going to represent our
sample space okay so X is the door that
that Monty hides the the prize behind Y
is the door that Marilyn initially
chooses and then Z is going to be the
the door that Monty reveals which has a
goat and by our rule that door cannot be
either of the first
two okay but anything else is a valid
outcome
okay do we have any questions about the
sample space and and how we computed
it okay so our next
step now that we've got our sample space
we want to figure out our probability
function
okay so we'd like to figure out what the
probability of each of these outcomes
is okay so to do this we're going to
assign a probability to every Edge that
we've got in our tree
diagram okay uh and so that's that's
just going to be the probability that
you know if we get to the source of that
edge you know what's the probability
that we uh you know proceed along that
edge okay so at the very beginning right
if we're at the
root what's the probability that you
know given that we're at the start Monty
hides the uh the prize behind door uh
P yeah one3
yeah so we're going to label this with
one3
okay what about G what's the probability
that Monty hides the uh prize behind
door
G
anybody okay I mean yeah arithmetic is
pretty difficult but uh I I'll just do
it for you it's also 1/3
okay and uh the probability that Monty
hide sit behind door s
also a third okay yeah
question yeah that's a great observation
so all of these three
probabilities should add up to one right
because if we're at this this uh vertex
here we should proceed somewhere
right uh so like you know it it wouldn't
make a whole lot of sense to have like
you know probability 1/3 probability 2/3
and probability one right because then
you're like like you have to proceed
down this path but then you also have to
proceed down one of the others like it's
it's a bit sticky okay so given that
you're at this this vertex you've got to
reach a leaf somehow you you've got to
get to some outcome so you've got to
proceed okay so you know all of these
edges should uh should sum up to
one great
observation uh it's not quite true
though that that holds for the entire
column
okay so what happens if we look at the
next
column so given that Monty hides the
prize behind door P what's the
probability that Marilyn then picks
DP any
ideas yeah one3
yeah so Marilyn picks this with
probability 1/3 right like Marilyn
doesn't know or care what's going on
with where the prize actually is
she's just picking each door with
probability 1/3 you know regardless Okay
so we've kind of got the same thing
going on
here each of these three edges has
probability
1/3 but now the same holds true for this
Branch right if Monty has hidden the
door or hidden the prize behind door G
you know the same logic applies right
Marilyn's still picking each door with
probability
1/3 Okay so we've also got 1/3 here 1/3
here 1/3 here okay so it's not quite
that all of the uh edges in a column add
up to one but all of the edges coming
out of a single vertex add up to one
okay and same thing for this bottom
Branch
okay now what about the last
column if Monty has hidden the prize
behind door p and Marilyn has also
picked door p
what's the probability that we get to
outcome
PPG
yeah one half that's
right
okay and it's also half whoops that's
not a two that's a three there we go 1
half okay so probability one half for
each of them okay we've got probability
one/ half that uh that the zon behind G
is revealed probability one half that
the zon behind s is revealed
okay and as we were saying before uh if
Monty hides the prize behind p and
Marilyn picks G Monty now has no choice
okay
so we're just going to say that this is
probability
one okay and same with this one this one
also has one uh
PSG
okay and similarly for the other three
branches so we've got one 1/2 1/2 one
one one 1/2
and2
okay so did these Edge probabilities
make sense to
everybody okay so now remember what the
probability function was right right uh
we have to assign a probability to every
outcome okay the outcomes right are the
leaves of our tree not the
edges okay so what is the
probability that we end up with outcome
PPG for instance
yeah 1 18th and how are you getting
that yeah 1/3 * 1/3 *
1/3 okay we're going to multiply
together all of the
probabilities along the path from the
route to that to that
leaf okay so Monty hides the prize
behind door p with probability
1/3 and then you know conditioned on
that happening
Marilyn then picks door p with
probability 1/3 so then there's
probability 1 nth that we make it to
this vertex
here and now that one ninth is split
again among these two outcomes okay does
that make sense to
everybody so if we do that for every
outcome we've got uh oops 1/ 18th not
1/8 another 1/ 18th for
PPS then what about pgs
yeah yeah it's just one
nth
okay so same deal for the first two
layers but then in the last layer we've
just got a probability of one we don't
have to split again so it's it remains
at 1
nth
okay and you know once again we can
continue we've got uh 1 nth here 11
18th 11 18th 1 n
and we can
continue
okay so we're going to justify this more
formally later but uh you know for now
just take it on faith that in order to
get the uh probability of an outcome uh
you multiply together the probabilities
along the path to that outcome okay like
hopefully it at least makes intuitive
sense uh but you know we'll we'll reason
about it more formally later
okay so
now we have our sample space we have our
probability function so we've got the
entire probability space that we're that
we're trying to reason about
okay uh the next thing that we want
we want to figure out what what we call
events we care
about
okay so an event is simply a
subset of our sample
space okay
so it's it's a set of
outcomes
[Music]
so up here right we could think about
the event that Marilyn
wins
okay so what is that formally as a set
yeah yeah exactly so the answer was it's
the subset of events where X and Y are
different so the notation that we
usually use for events is is the
following
okay we you know put the description of
the event in square
brackets so this is just going to be the
set right
pgs
PS
g g
GSP uh s
GP s
PG
okay so the six outcomes right where uh
Marilyn and Monty originally pick
different doors and then Monty is forced
to reveal the uh the last
one
okay similarly we could also Define you
know other events like uh you know
uh Monty
opens uh door
P
okay so this is going to be the
Set uh g g
p uh s s
p
uh
GSP and
SGP
okay so does this make sense to
everybody like any subset of
events uh or sorry any subset of
outcomes is called an
event uh we can kind of take our English
description and then look at which
actual outcomes uh this corresponds
to
okay so what we want to do now
is figure out what event we care about
or possibly what events okay so what are
the events that we care about for this
problem anybody
what was the probability that we're
trying to compute
yeah
pardon yeah so that the events Marilyn
wins and Marilyn loses right these are
the events we care about okay so uh you
know we could
say Marilyn
loses is you
know the compx
of Maryland WIS which we denote with an
over
bar
okay so these are the two events we care
about
okay so the final step
is to compute the answer okay we've
identified the event that we care
about okay so now we want to figure out
the probability that that event
occurs okay so we can extend the
probability function to
events so if e is an event right we can
think about the probability of an event
just as we think about the probability
of
outcomes and we're going to Define this
to
be the
sum over all outcomes Omega and
E of the probability of
Omega
okay so you know hopefully intuitively
that makes sense right like all of these
outcomes uh you know exactly one outcome
is is going to happen so if we're trying
to figure out the probability that you
know one of a set of outcomes happens
it's just going to be you know the the
sum of the probabilities that that each
individual one
occurs okay so we know the probabilities
of each of the outcomes right that's
what we just
computed
here so now we can use that to compute
the probability of the events we just
uh we just talked
about
okay so what is the probability that
Marilyn
wins so we have our set of outcomes
here what's the probability of each one
oh what's what's the probability of
outcome
pgs yeah one n yeah that one's written
up up there
explicitly uh what about the probability
of PSV
same 1
nth okay what about the probability of
GPS also a nth right like you know all
of these are
symmetric
okay what's that
2/3 okay
so we've got six events or six outcomes
Each of which occurs with probability 1
nth so if you add those all together you
get
2/3 okay so this seems to support you
know what we found
empirically right Marilyn wins with
better than probability
1/2 right the probability that she loses
is going to be the complement of this
okay so it's going to be the uh sum of
the probabilities of all of the other
outcomes right and we said that all
probabilities uh should add to one so
this is going to be you know the
complement with respect to
one okay so as it turns out Marilyn was
correct okay we didn't have to rely on
Intuition or anything like that no
ingenious analogies Etc it's just you
know arithmetic over Q okay and I think
the the hardest part of this for many
people is resisting the temptation to
jump jump to some sort of like obvious
conclusion right like you know it might
be tempting to you know get to the end
of the tree diagram and be like oh we've
got six outcomes where Marilyn wins six
where she loses so probably you know 6
over 12 is2 right so if we actually you
know set all of that you know intuition
aside go through everything formally
it's all you know quite simple and
straightforward
okay so that makes sense to
everybody okay so let's move on to a
different
example
suppose I have three strange dice okay
so excuse my
drawing whoops nothing
there okay so I've got one die that has
two written on two of the faces so you
know top and bottom uh six written on
you know these two faces and seven
written on those two faces okay
hopefully that you know looks vaguely
cubical okay I've got a second ey which
is
similar uh but instead of 2 six and
seven I've got 1 5 and nine then I've
got a third one
which has three four and
eight
okay so consider the following game
okay uh I pick a die right now you pick
one of the uh other
dies after or dice after seeing what I
pick and we each roll our dice okay and
whoever gets the higher number
wins okay
who should win should I win or should
you
win who thinks I
win okay who thinks you
win who thinks we should just uh you
know do the tree diagram and figure it
out yeah good call okay so let's let's
call these dice like
r g and B okay
so yeah let's let's draw out our tree
diagram
okay so what happens if say I pick the
red D and uh you pick the green
Dy okay who should win let's let's
see so we've
got when I roll my die right there are
three possibilities I could either get a
two a six or a seven
and now you roll the green D and you
could have either a one a five or a
nine not minus 5 five
1 5 9
five
okay and now what is the probability or
sorry what what are the uh what are the
outcomes
we have nine leaves so nine
outcomes how are we going to represent
them well we can do it basically the
same as how we uh represented them up
here right we can uh just look at a
tupal of uh Edge labels okay so our some
space is going to be the Set uh
267 uh cartisian product with uh
159 okay so this is going to be ordered
pairs where the first element is one of
these three things and the second is one
of these three things okay so this one
for instance is 2 comma 1 this one is 2A
5 Etc
okay now what are the probabilities on
each
Edge yeah 1
nth uh so those are the uh probabilities
on the outcomes yeah one3 on each
Edge
right okay so when I roll my die I've
got a one3 chance each of getting two
six or seven when you roll yours you've
got a 1/3 chance each of getting five or
n
okay and you know it's going to be the
same for the other two
branches so when we multiply together
the probabilities uh along paths to
leaves we get 1 nth for every
outcome
okay so when you have a probability
space like this that's particularly nice
this is what we call a uniform
probability
space
uh so let's
say s comma p r so this is our
probability space is
uniform if uh PR is
constant okay so in this this case it's
a constant function that Maps every
outcome to a probability of 1 nth okay
so it's a uniform probability
space okay and uh uniform spaces are
particularly nice because you know we
don't even have to worry about the
addition that we were doing before like
in order to figure out probabilities of
uh of events you just count up how many
outcomes are in the event and then
divide by the total number of
outcomes okay so it just becomes a
counting problem
so using that what's the probability
that red
wins
yeah 5 9ths
yeah so let's break this down a bit so
we're looking at the probability of the
set
right 2 comma 1 red wins 6165 red wins
and 7175 red wins
okay so
21 uh
75 we have five of
these so
that's 5 over 9
okay now what if instead we had red
versus blue instead of red versus green
so if instead of red versus green we
have red versus blue this column now
gets replaced with 348 instead of
okay so our tree diagram is going to
look like the
following so we've still got uh 267
here but this time this is going to be 3
348 3
okay and I'm going to omit the
probabilities because we just
established it's uniform so it's just a
counting
problem but let's write down the
outcomes
okay so in how many of these outcomes
does red
win well not this one right not this one
not this one okay so if red rolls two
right all of Blue's uh all of Blue's uh
numbers are going to be higher so blue
is always going to win uh if red rolls
six uh red wins if blue Rolls three or
four loses if uh blue Rolls eight and
same for
seven
okay so we have
uh four outcomes where red wins so red
wins with probability four
nths
okay
so we just saw that uh red beats
Green but loses to
Blue what does that tell us about blue
and
green if I pick blue and you pick Green
what
happens who wins
yeah Green
why okay so green Beats red
uh so I think we just established that
red beats screen
right so here we've got you know red
beat screen
here we've got red loses to
Blue so if we
have uh green and blue who thinks that
green should
win who thinks that blue should win who
has absolutely no idea who wants to do
the tree
diagram oh still pretty enthusiastic
about that even though we've got some
intuition that's
great intuition is bad dis SC the
intuition okay so if we've got green
versus
blue so this can be the uh green roll
here we've got uh
159 blue roll can be uh 3
48 3
48 okay
uh so in which of these does green win
well if green rolls one then you know
Green is screwed so all of these are bad
for
green uh if green rolls
five well five will beat three and four
but not eight
so green wins these two and if green
rolles nine then green Beats you know
whatever blue rolls
okay okay
so it looks like green is winning in
five of
these
okay so this should
be like
that
okay so red beats green green Beats blue
and blue Beats
red what's gone
wrong
yeah
pardon yeah so nothing's gone wrong all
that's gone wrong is uh you know I I
kind of expected that there would be a
linear order on them right right like uh
you know if red beats green and green
Beats blue it kind of intuitively makes
sense that red should beat blue right
no no no intuition just do the tree
diagram uh so yeah this is perfectly
fine right and in fact it gets even
weirder right
uh what do you think happens if uh we
each choose two dice or sorry we each
roll twice
so what if uh you know what if I pick
the red dy I roll it twice you pick the
green Dy you roll it
twice right red probably beats Green so
is it true that two red rolls probably
beat two green rolls like if we sum them
up who thinks
yes who thinks
no who wants to draw the tree
diagram oh wow so eager I don't
um like uh what is the tree diagram
going to look like if we if we do
that like I'm rolling twice you're
rolling twice each roll can have you
know three possible uh uh three
possibilities right so we're going to
end up with a pretty massive
tree I I don't want to draw that at
least not on the
board does somebody else want to come up
and do it
please no nobody okay well instead of
drawing out the entire tree diagram
let's kind of start drawing it and see
if we can find a
pattern okay so this is uh R2 versus
G2
okay
[Music]
so let's start by
know drawing as we did before okay so my
first roll as was red could be 2 six or
7 second rle could also be 2 six or
okay now for
green right
we're basically just going to be drawing
the same tree nine times so you know
let's
not so green could roll you know
159 and then can also roll
159 for the second
roll
okay and rather than duplicating this
three nine times I'm just going to leave
this as it is and you know we can see if
we can find a
pattern
okay does that make sense to
everybody so an outcome now is going to
be a four tupal right instead of a
pair and in some sense we can kind of
think of it as combining a leaf of this
tree with a leaf of this tree okay we're
going to take a red leaf and a green
leaf a question or
no no
okay
[Music]
so we can then abbreviate it even
further right instead of looking at the
pair of numbers that we've that we've
rolled let's instead look at you know
just the SU
okay so if red rolls two tws we've got
four here 2 and six is eight 2 and 7 is
N9 uh 6 2 is
8 uh 66 is not 9 that's 12 ever trust me
to do arithmetic uh 67 is 13 72 is 9 76
is 13 77 is
okay and if we do do the same thing for
uh green we have 2 6 10 6 10
14 10 14
okay so now we can start counting
outcomes if we take this Leaf of the red
tree how many outcomes are there where
red wins
if red rolls four in total the only way
that red wins is if green gets Snake
Eyes Okay so we've just got
one if red rules eight which could be
either of these
two how many outcomes are there where
red
wins well we've got a two here a six
here and a six here so we've got three
and we've got uh two red leaves that
have eight uh what about nine it looks
like we've got two more that have
nine same deal right we don't have any
eights or nines over on this
side
okay uh what else do we have
okay well if red rolls 12 then red is
good if blue Rolls 2 6 10 but not 14 or
18 so we've got 1 2 3 4 five six
outcomes and we have one red leaf where
red has
12 okay then same thing for 13 there are
no 12 or 13s over here and we have two
13s now what about
14 well if red rolls 14 then you know
same
deal but we've got these two ties
here okay so red
winds draw we've just got two and then
red loses is going to be the complement
okay so has anybody added all of these
up yet I
haven't 5
30 42 43 is that
right
so 43 outcomes for red
wins
uh had something wrong this doesn't
match my
notes
uh let's
see so we've got one for this sub tree
for each of these we have three
for each of the
nines we also have three so that's those
12 13 and
13 oh do I just have too many terms I
just have too many
terms okay not 43 it should be
37 is that
right yeah are 12 13 13 and 14 each have
six
okay okay uh yeah never trust me to do
arithmetic it's always a bad plan uh
okay so red wins in 37 of the outcomes
right there's a draw in two of them and
how many outcomes are there in
total
yeah1 yeah 81 so red loses in 81 - 37 -
which is that 42 I think that's
42 okay
so because this is uniform space we have
37 over 81 42 over
81 which is going to be well actually
let's not reduce it it's easier to see
like
that and two out of 81 for a
draw okay so if we only had one role
red had the advantage right red wins
with probability 5 9ths if we have two
roles right the probability that red
wins is smaller than the probability
that red loses so now suddenly green has
the advantage
instead
okay and um as it turns out you know the
same thing happens with all three pairs
of dice right so uh you know red beats
Green with with one roll green Beats
blue with one roll but Blue Beats Green
with two
rolls right and Blue Beats red with with
one roll but red beats blue with two
rolls and
uh yeah so the the the dice continue to
you know not have this transitivity
property but like every time it's
switched okay and as it turns out uh you
know you can even you know extend this
right right like if you have more dice
with different numbers you can get like
all sorts of weird things that are that
are that that could happen um so there's
a a link to a to a a rather interesting
paper on archive if you if you want to
see it uh in the lecture notes um but uh
yeah for now I think that's all we have
time for feel free to uh come up if you
have questions and otherwise we will see
you on Thursday