My name's Lindseay Edwards. I'm the CTO
of a company in London called Relation
that does a lot of single cell and
machine learning for drug discovery. Um,
and it's a real treat to be here
wherever Caroline is. Thank you for the
for the invite and thank you for asking
me to put together a committee to judge
the posters. I spend way too much of my
time thinking about raising money and
whether our compute cluster is going to
fall over or not. So, it's really nice
to spend several days thinking about
nothing but science. Um, and a couple of
quick comments before we get right to
the business. Uh, the first thing I
would say is the level of science over
the last couple of days has been
absolutely phenomenal. So just to
everyone that's here and and to all of
the students that have presented the
last couple of days um you're doing
amazing work so feel very good about uh
about yourselves. Um we tried to choose
on the basis of three different things.
So the first thing is originality. So
how original is is the work that's being
done. Second thing is scientific quality
and then the third one is a slightly
looser one that I would call something
like scientific communication. And so
the way that you were able to speak
about your work at the poster or just
the presentation of the poster, the
clarity of the language, the clarity of
the narrative, um, all really important.
And one thing I would just add to that
last thing is it feels like it's not
science and we shouldn't care about it,
but my god, it's important. Like if
you're good at speaking, you'll get
asked to speak. And the more you speak,
the broader audience there is for your
science. So please, you know, people who
you see who are really good presenters
almost never got that way by accident.
They worked on it. It's worth spending a
little bit of time on. Okay. So we have
three prizes. Uh we have um £300. Sorry,
dollars. You you might prefer £300.
Um sorry, I couldn't help it. Uh three
$300. Uh so in third place we have I'm
getting so old I can't decide whether I
need my glasses on or my glasses off. So
in third place is um poster 21, an AI
cyborg system for adaptive intelligent
modulation of organoid maturation. And I
think we have Xinhi Jang to to collect
the prize. Amazing. Come on.
Brilliant. Thank you very much indeed.
Thank you.
[Applause]
Okay. In second place and with a prize
of
$400, uh it is poster 31, whisper
inference of contact mediated cell
signaling. And this is for
Annarandrakumar.
[Applause]
Great stuff. Thank you. Thank you.
And then in first place, we're hoping
that
the that the first authors uh made it
back um by unanimous decision is poster
25 mapping the topography of spatial
gene expression with interpretable deep
learning and it's Utsaf Chitra.
Do we have
is
he now? Now I sing. No. Um, okay. What
should we do? Should we we could we can
have a little clap later maybe and move
forward. Okay. Anyway, thank you to
everybody. It's been a brilliant couple
of days. Thank you, Caroline.
Thank you so much for this.
Okay, thank you Lindsay again and thank
you to all the poster presenters for all
of their work that they put into it and
to you know enriching this uh conference
with their amazing science. Um so now
we're getting to the final um panel
discussion. Um so this panel discussion
is going to be on foundation models in
biology. So kind of the computational
counterpart to what we've um seen
yesterday and again going all the way
from all levels from DNA to protein to
cells, tissues and organisms. And um we
have a treat here for you um this uh
afternoon. So I think I will reorganize
the talks a little bit so that we start
with proteins and then we'll go on to
tissues, we'll go on to drug discovery
and we'll go on to organisms and and
hospitals and biases etc. um all the way
at the end. So we'll start with Sergey
of Chinikov um assistant professor in
the department of biology um at MIT. um
his lab studies protein structure and
evolution in all levels. So
environmental, organismal, genomic,
structural and molecular um scales. And
so welcome. And um we'll have your talk
first and then we'll follow up with a
panel discussion with everyone at the
end.
I wasn't planning to be first. Thought
I'd still have a chance to change some
slides, but too late
now. All
right. Right. So, yeah, thank you so
much for inviting me to be here today.
Um yeah so I'll tell you guys about some
of the work we've been doing in uh
trying to understand what protein and
genomic language models are doing. uh
depending how much time we have, we may
or may not skip the genomics. But uh in
big pictures, uh my group uh wonders a
lot like what are big models learning?
Like we we heard today about like the
genome language models, protein language
models. Um but what are they actually
doing? Like what's this blackbox
learning? And part of the reason we do
this is because my lab we don't have
that many GPUs. That's why I'm wearing
this hat. Hopefully somebody would give
us some. But because we don't have that
many GPUs, we try to say, well, what
could we as biologists or a scientist uh
contribute to maybe maybe this giant
field where companies are training these
giant models like maybe we could look at
these models and see are they learning
new biology? Are they learning
statistics? Like what how can we
interpret them? What can we contribute
in that perspective? Um so we all know
proteins, DNA, RNA. Uh this is
essentially a little cartoon picture of
a of a sequence. But when you only have
a single sequence, there's not much you
can say about it. like maybe you know
some physics, maybe you know some
chemistry, but you're kind of stuck
there. Uh but where things become really
really powerful is if you can collect a
bunch of sequences from many many
different organisms. All of these
sequences here uh all share common
ancestry. Um and there's some positions
that are conserved. Um some positions
that are co uh maybe related to each
other due to fogyny. For example, these
two positions are due because of
connections here and some positions are
coaring with each other which maybe tell
you something about structure. Uh and
one thing we always wonder is how do we
capture these constraints and more
importantly maybe how do these
foundational models that we learned
about today are they capturing any of
these constraints at all? Um and so how
do we model these constraints? A very
very simple model is to say well let's
look look at look at these sequences and
just pretend that there's only three
positions three possible characters. Um
and you could try to really model a very
very simple model where you take the
sequence uh one hot encode it because
you need to somehow express blue yellow
green so a computer would understand. Um
then you could say well I'm going to try
to model how the first position connects
the second position how the second
position connects the first position. So
you have like a fully connected matrix.
So imagine like a very simple linear
layer. Uh and then of course there's
some positions that may be completely
conserved. They're not connected to
anything. And so you have some parameter
that models conservation. Um and then
finally all the probabilities that the
end should sum up to one. So imagine we
have a very very simple uh linear layer
where you have activations at the very
end. Uh and then you try to minimize the
inputs and the outputs. Say the inputs
should match the outputs. Um if you
train such a model on all the data that
I showed a little earlier like train a
model on all this data here you might
imagine it will learn a very very
trivial function of just saying I'm
going to learn an identity matrix of
anything mapping to outputs. And so it
doesn't really learn anything
meaningful. Where things become really
really powerful if you say, "Hey, let me
remove self connections." So I'm going
to make sure like the first position is
only connected to all the other
positions but not to itself. And then
you might imagine the model actually
start to pick up on covolution like the
fact that this position depends on this
one and these edges might have that
interpretation. Uh this model that
actually does this uh one of these
models is called gremlin. uh and this is
the model that I'll be comparing to
where I'm comparing the uh these genome
language models and these protein
language models too. Um and so this
model essentially is very very simple.
It just has a a weights and and a bias
parameter. That's all it has. Um but
this model is very very much
interpretable unlike that block black
box I showed at the very beginning. This
one you could actually say hey these
weights you could actually extract them
uh and then maybe take some L2 norm of
those weights to compress each of these
3x3 matrices to one and now you have
essentially a contact map and just to
give you a big picture here you
essentially these two connections these
two residues are connected to each other
and you can extract from the weights the
fact that they are actually connected to
each other and so it's very very easy to
interpret we know exactly what those
parameters mean um but and just to give
you a real example uh here is a protein
contact map um stretching out this
protein from N terminus to C terminus,
blue to red, blue to red. All of these
contacts you see here are coming from
the crystal structure. Um, and if I want
to show how like the cyan part interacts
with the orange part, cyan orange, I can
look up on this matrix here. Um, now if
I overlay these contacts that were
extracted from just this very very
simple model training, I can extract all
these dependencies and the really
exciting part is they overlap on the
gray dots. So this is around 2011 people
got really really excited because now we
without any deep learning this is a very
simple I guess you say simple machine
learning we can extract these contacts
from there and this can mean that we
could start to predict protein
structures um and so we know how to do
it with very very simple models but how
about more complex model like a protein
language model that has maybe many many
layers of transformers as we heard today
from Patrick like maybe some kind of
stripe hyena layers like how do we like
interpret these things like how do we
look inside this model. Um, turns out
there's a relatively simple trick you
can do because essentially the the input
and the outputs are the same. Like you
still have one hot encoded sequence,
you're trying to recreate the sequence
on the other side. Maybe you could do
something much simpler where you just
try to perturb the inputs and see how
the outputs change. Um, but before I go
into that detail just to give you a big
comparison. So these are traditional
models we used to fit. So for every
protein family, we fit one model for
every family. One of the things exciting
about these protein language models like
ESM uh other other I guess related
models uh is that they are trained one
model for all sequences. Um and they're
trained the exact same way. The only
difference is for for a single protein
family you train one model or you say
I'm going to train all the model. I'm
going to put the sequence in. I'm going
to try to recreate the sequence on the
other side. And so one thing we've been
wondering is like are these two models
learning the same thing? Like is there
somewhere inside these parameters these
parameters? Um, and so how do we
actually check if that's actually true?
Um, and so these protein language
models, as I said, train on all
sequences. Um, and so the way we try to
do this is say, well, could we try to
map the inputs to the outputs? Because
essentially this W matrix or this
coution matrix is essentially just a
mapping between the inputs and the
outputs, which is a linear layer. And
and the way we could do that is perturb
the inputs. And here's a quick
illustration here. So I can go to every
single position um and try to mutate it
to some other character and see how the
logits change. So I can compute this
delta logits and I can compute a matrix
of every possible input to every
possible output and then the exact same
way as I did with my really really
simple model convert that into a contact
map. Um and one thing that we found that
quite remarkable was that if you extract
these contact maps or these covolution
matrices from these very very simple
model like Gremlin models uh and then do
the same thing to a protein language
models the the pair parameters that you
extract are very closely similar and
actually very well correlated to each
other. So the parameters actually look
very much similar uh between the two
kinds of models. Um and so this sort of
gives us this hypothesis that
essentially what protein language models
are doing are essentially uh learning
like a library of Gremlin models and
effectively acting as a a very very nice
or cool uh lookup and compression
algorithm. Uh so this could be both a
pro and a con. I guess a pro is like
well now you don't need to make MSAs. Uh
maybe there's some shared parameters
between families maybe it could do a
better job. maybe a con if you were
thought maybe this this model solved the
protein folding problem then you're like
well maybe it didn't um but but still we
were kind of wondering is this actually
what it's doing is it actually taking
the sequence looking up some model
internally and returning the sequence um
and so we tried to design a quick
experiment where we said okay is it
looking up the entire structure or maybe
it's just looking at motifs because
there's proteins have little motifs that
are shared across all proteins so maybe
it's not actually just look storing
entire protein families maybe just
storing motifs Um and so Ziti and my
group uh decided to do some experiments
for this. Uh she's sitting around here
somewhere. Try to find her later. But
essentially we said well well let's take
the protein for example and find a motif
here. So in this case there's these two
helix interacting with the with the beta
strand. Um and then we try to add more
contacts or remove contacts and see how
much of the context needs to be able to
recover these interactions. And the same
thing for let's say two very distantly
related motifs like this motif and this
motif far away and sequence space.
Sorry. I mean uh and if you add or more
remove or remove contacts what happens
uh and so what we find is that as you
start to remove more and more contacts
interestingly this motif is still there
until you essentially remove so much of
the protein that it's no longer able to
so essentially we're literally just
masking out everything around the
sequence and the only thing the model
sees this little motif and what we see
is essentially we can mask almost the
whole sequence and still see that motif.
Um, same thing with the pair like these
two helyses. We could essentially remove
everything except for those two
sequences of those T helyses and we
still see the contacts. Um, and so what
this suggests to us is that the model is
not doing like a full fold lookup but
maybe is doing some kind of motif lookup
instead. Um, and so we we we wrote um a
paper about this. If you guys want to
check it out at some point you could.
Um, uh, so in summary for at least this
part is that um, we we do have a way of
extracting contacts and it's very very
powerful. you could apply it to any
model where maybe you don't necessarily
care about what the inputs are like,
what exactly is in the middle of the
model. Um, and so since then we've been
now applying this model to other models
like EVO, EVO 2 and asking similar kind
of questions. Um, and so maybe looks
like I still have three minutes. Okay.
So, so since we have a little three
minutes, I'll get into genomic language
models. So, as you guys heard about
today from Patrick is this really cool
new model came out where you say, well,
instead of training on protein
sequences, what if we train on genomic
sequences? So the the essentially the
the task is very much the same. You have
an input sequence. You mask part some of
your uh nucleotides. In this case, you
could do it in an auto reggressive way.
Uh and then you recreate the amino acid,
sorry, nucleotides on the other side. Um
and there's lots of cool stuff happening
in the middle, but for our purposes,
like we said, we don't care what's
actually happening in the middle. We
wanted to see does it learn the correct
uh input output mappings. Um and one
thing that was quite exciting, we s we
looks like it's capturing RNA contexts.
like you could actually see if you
perturb the inputs the output logs
change and you could see that for
example in this tRNA structure it is
indeed capturing contacts. Um but when
we applied it to protein structure we
noticed that there were no contacts. Um
so I mean it learned some kind of
interesting patterns that kind of look
like checkerboards. Um but the contacts
for the most part appear to be missing.
uh and so we were kind of wondering why
are they missing for RNA it looks to be
fine but from for protein like this is
an example from a ESM the protein
language model and this is an example
from EVO where we did the same exact
analysis the reason why this is half
blank is because it is an auto
reggressive model uh so you if you
perturb something at the input only
things after get changed but then later
on don't don't really change so that's
why it's only half um and so some
hypothesis we had was maybe the model's
just not large enough um and so we did
look at EVO O2 and it still seems to be
missing contact. So we think maybe
that's not quite the only reason. Uh
another hypothes well maybe there are
other constraints that are overpowering
like maybe there are protein contacts
here. It's just that maybe there's other
more stronger constraints coming from
other genomic constraints that are sort
of overpowering the signal. Um and
finally maybe this we're just doing the
analysis wrong. So that's always a
possibility. Um, one hypothesis that
we're kind of exploring now is maybe it
has to do more with the fact that what
does it mean to encode the nucleotide
sequence for proteins. And so you
probably all familiar, but if you like
change the last codon, the last letter
of a codon, you essentially stay the
same amino acid. But even if you change
the middle codon, like the letter of
this middle codon, you have to either
stay hydrophobic or hydrophilic based on
transitions versus transversions. So you
can maybe already recreate a lot of the
sequence just based on your local uh
signal. Like maybe you don't need to
learn contacts. Um and so one analysis
by Yunha uh who actually is joining MIT
later. So if you guys want to talk to
Yha, she'll be here in June. Um so she's
a new assistant professor in MIT
biology. Uh so one thing she tried say
well instead of using uh nucleotide
encoding could we just use amino acid
encoding? And when you do that you
actually see so this is just showing
control two proteins contacts between
the two proteins. Uh and then when you
look at GLM2 you actually see really
really strong contacts recovered. And
just to contrast that to like EVO and
ESM2, there are no contacts recovered.
And so we think part of the reason might
be because that reason. Okay, I think
I'm out of time. So I'll stop there.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much Sergey. We'll do
discussion afterwards with everyone.
Yep, that would be awesome. Perfect.
Okay, so I think we'll move to Fasil
next. Fasil Mahmud um assistant
professor at Harvard Medical School and
Dana Farber. his lab uh develops
multimodal foundation models of going
from diagnosis, prognosis, biomarker
discovery and all of that particularly
in the in the context of cancer but also
in many other contexts as well. So
welcome.
[Applause]
Um, thank you so much Caroline for the
introduction and for inviting me to
speak. Um, I'll be talking really
quickly about some of the work that my
group has done over the past past few
years and uh, more more recently what
we've done in in self-supervised models,
foundation models to try some to address
some of these questions from a clinical
point of view. Here are my
disclosures. Um, so what my group does
is that we predominantly try to work
with pathology images when glass slides
are digitized. So, so pathology blast
lies really the backbone of of biio
medicine whether it's diagnostic,
prognostic, therapeutic response
related, but it also has lots of
applications in uh in pre-clinical drug
screening um trying to identify
toxicology and so forth for for for drug
discovery. So, a lot of tools we develop
are are more generic and can be applied
to applied to both. But today, I'll be
talking specifically about some of the
work we do in uh in in the diagnostic
prognostic space. So, once these images
are digitized, they are hierarchical.
They harbor informations at many
different scales and they look more like
satellite satellite images and and it's
a it's a very old diagnostic modality.
It's been around for about 125 years but
it's computational analysis is
relatively recent. So there's been
computational analysis for the past 3540
years but really large scale
computational analysis is is relatively
very very recent and it's just recently
begin to be digitized in in in
hospitals. So when we when we're looking
at these large images for some from a
machine learning perspective, what comes
to mind is multiple instance learning.
So we can split them into smaller
patches and then
u use multiple instance learning uh on
top of them. And there's there's a lot
of work that was that was done training
these models end to end which was
computationally tedious and and over
time we started to use these feature
extractors where where we could could
extract rich feature representations
aggregate into slide level
representations and then do whatever
form of prediction we want to do on top
of it. whether it's you know diagnostic
which means you you can you could be
looking at um detection of disease
subtyping grading staging or if you pose
it as a ranking problem it could become
prognostic uh or related rel related to
therapeutic response prediction and so
forth and we sort of used this idea in a
number of different studies over the
years. We we you know tinkered with this
method adding in attention and other
bells and whistles that were being
developed in the in the machine learning
community but then also applying it to
to to more challenging problems like
predicting religions for cancers of
unknown primary and mioardial biopsy
detection uh in or or for for heart
heart biopsies and also build building
large scale prognostic models by
including histologology and and
molecular information. So coming back to
this paradigm so more recently there's
been a lot of work uh using
self-supervised learning to extract
vector feature representations. A lot of
the previous work I showed was all done
using ResNets trained on imageet and
using those features for for training
these models. So, so in this in this
case we we we try to develop some some
of those self-supervised models back
dating back to 2021 and there are a
bunch of conference articles we we we
published just showing how
self-supervised models can be used in in
pathology and then last year we built
you know these these foundation models.
Uh, one of them was really just a Dinov2
using lots of hospital data. And we
learned from Dino V2 that diversity of
data is way more important than than the
quantity of data. And and we we went out
looking at Brigham and MGH what are the
most diverse cases and built those built
those models and and at the at the same
time we also built a visual vision
language model. So just by using the
Koka framework and contrasting with the
corresponding text information to see if
representation would improve. And these
models, we we made these models publicly
available and they've really been
downloaded quite a lot around the world
and have been used in over 400 different
studies over the over the past past
year. And I think one reason for this is
that mythology data is becoming
increasingly more available. And it's
easy to just incorporate this data if
you have rich rich representations
representations available. But if you if
we think about this, we also have lots
of other multimodal data corresponding
these patients. So histologology really
acts as a diagnostic backbone. But
there's also molecular data which has
been collected over the past past 20 20
years and we also do minister chemistry
special stains um other kinds of
ancillary testing corresponding these
these uh these hisystologology the these
patients and and we have that available
corresponding to histologology and we
have seen this from conventional
computer vision and machine learning
that that contrasting against modalities
improves representation for all the
modalities. So that's what we tried to
explore in a bunch of these studies.
This is from ECCV last year where we
where we're contrasting with the uh uh
with with IC stains uh molecular markers
to see if we if by contrasting across
these these stains we can improve
representation and we then we apply it
to a bunch of downstream tasks including
survival outcome prediction as well as
uh just just grading these these IoT IC
slides and then same concept but instead
of using um IC's we use transcrytoic
data. This was sort of a toy example
just done on the TCGA trying to see if
in a few shot setting the representation
would uh would would improve. Um so so
we're essentially had it headed in this
direction where by using more and more
multimodel data we're able to improve
image representation in itself by using
fewer and fewer samples. So this was
first sort of an indication where where
we really we saw a few shot improvement
on some of these more difficult tasks.
This was the first indication that we
should scale this idea. And we used
basically all the molecular data that
was available to us at Brigham and MGH
together with paired hisystologology to
see if we can contrast against them. And
because we're not fusing here, we're
contrasting against them, we could use
molecular data that was collected using
a variety of different mechanisms
including uh the the NGS assay that we
have at the Dana Farber uh Bigham Cancer
Center as well as the transcripttoic
assay that's frequently used at at MGH.
um and then applying it to a bunch of
different downstream tasks, we we we
found that it it improved performance
particularly for some of these more
difficult tasks like treatment response
prediction where it's difficult to get
get these samples. So we have very few
samples available. Um and these are just
you know very very challenging
challenging problems. Predicting
treatment directly from histologology is
is is a challenging problem but for the
first time we we saw a jump in
performance. We've we've basically been
scaling this working together with other
institutions to to get more
corresponding molecular data to to scale
this idea in in general. Um so once we
had these rich representations an
obvious next step for us was to see if
we could build a build a co-pilot or or
a generative model which can synthesize
text corresponding this corresponding
this this this information. Uh so to do
that you need a large instruction set.
So uh the philosophy behind this is that
you know the these images are
hierarchical harboring information at
many different many different scales.
But but the but the the the
corresponding label that we have just
resides in in pathology reports and the
label is often corresponding just the
slide or the all the cases that are oh
sorry all the slides that are in that in
that particular case. But to build a
good useful co-pilot or a chatbot or you
know multimodal large language model uh
we need u instructions corresponding
every level of abstraction whether it's
at the region level at the patch level
slide level or the case level. So we we
started by curating those manually but
quickly realized that this was just not
scalable despite asking so many so many
pathologists to contribute to this
across multiple institutions and
eventually we figured out that that the
best thing we could do was to use
teaching and training materials that we
had at Bigham and MGH essentially using
what's used to teach residents to teach
the multimodal large language model uh
to to be able to build this bu build
this chatbot but this is a a study from
June of last year where we're able to
build a chatbot where you can go in and
ask different questions about um about
the image. In the beginning, this was
just based on 500,000 instructions. We
did try to maximize for diversity trying
to represent every indication that exist
existed in uh at within our Bigham and
MGH databases. Uh but but since then
it's been really expanded to around 5
million cases and it also got FDA
breakthrough device designation uh
recently. Um there are better demos for
this available publicly. We we're also
very interested in building agents
particularly for computational biology
but you know I think this is something
that everyone's interested in because
generative models are getting better and
better and they can make good scientific
plans for what to do and in
computational biology what we're doing
very frequently is bringing new kinds of
data to to existing tools. We we develop
a lot of new tools but a lot of
discovery can take place by bringing new
kinds of data to to existing tools. So
the question is that can you start with
like a good um um just a prompt from a
from a user break it down have a plan
planning agent that breaks it down into
into a schedule and then and a DAC
scheduling unit that schedules which
tools to use when and where and then uh
essentially have a uh have a language
agent uh and a coding agent that
interfaces with this to to eventually
create uh uh create an overall uh
agentic agentic workflow. So this is
what we have done in just for these
tools right here. And this is just a
just a demo of that where we can where
the user comes in and says that well
here I have a cohort of responders
versus non-responders
um and can you go train a model that
would distinguish between between the
two and it can go make a make a plan and
then and then then go and execute it.
This is uh surprisingly very easy to
build technically because now we have
all these uh models that generate very
good uh very good plans. More recently
we have updated this to where you can go
back and sort of edit what the plan plan
should be and we have deployed this at
MGH and given it to all our pathology
colleagues so they don't come to us when
they need to train and train a model and
uh they can just use this this kind of a
setup to uh to do so. Um so once the
model is trained it would you know you
can you can can look at um how well the
model is doing just by looking at the
the AC curve and then you can go forward
by looking at things like uh uh the the
interpretability at the level of the of
the heat map and you know maybe that's
not good enough and and and you can then
ask it to describe what it sees uh
within the high tension regions across
your entire entire test set and and it
can use our our generative model to
describe that. Um so yeah we're we're
continuing to work in this direction and
then there are a lot of interesting
questions when you you know give them
tasks and we're we're trying to assess
how well these models do in achieving
certain tasks and we're realizing that
the models are good but they don't they
don't quite match a graduate student and
the reason is that graduate students are
more hungry and we're we're we're trying
to assess that how do you build in this
uh this ambition hunger into the uh in
into the model and this is like a open
open question other people are working
on on this too. Um uh but I I do want to
touch upon Apollo. This is a new model
that we recently built and would be
coming out uh uh very very very soon uh
where we have used data corresponding
10.1 million patients from Brigham and
and NMGH and really have tried to used
all of the patient record that was uh
that was available to us. This includes
pathology, diagnostic reports, clinical
and laboratory tests and uh uh all the
EMRs. And we spent about two and a half
years cleaning this cleaning this data
made was definitely made easier once all
these LLMs were available and could be
locally locally served. But the idea is
and this is just a distribution for all
the all the uh diagnoses that were used
and then we have the um the oral
architecture where we have built lots of
unimodal models corresponding these
modalities and then we integrate them
together and also have a temporal
component to this where this there's an
essentially essentially a representation
which gets updated from uh uh based off
of more and more information that comes
in corresponding these uh these patients
and there's a temporal trajectory to it
and then we apply it to lots of
downstream tasks. including for early
diagnosis, treatment response
prediction, biomarker discovery,
clinical trial matching, and we're
working with several pharma to to try to
see how well it can work on clinical
trial trial matching and population
health in general. But really the scale
of the data that we have makes this uh
quite quite interesting because we have
accumulated data not only from Brigham
and MGH but we also have data from other
uh institutions around uh around the
country uh to to really in integrate u
these these data sets and build a single
model that can do patient level
representation. So I want to thank
everyone who I mean there are a lot of
MIT students who worked on this over the
uh over the years as well as all the
funding that you know is probably going
to be stopped very soon. So, thank you.
Thank you so much.
[Applause]
Thank you. Thanks for ending on such a
positive note. Um, okay. So, uh, now
we'll talk take it to uh, drug
discovery. Um, Shirley Leu, I'm very
excited to have her here. She was a
professor of bioatistics and
computational biology at Dana Farber and
Harvard School of Public of Public
Health. um where she developed a lot of
statistical and machine learning models
for many important biological problems
and also actually one of the first
single cell RNA seek foundation models.
Um and then in 2016 she co-founded uh
GV20 therapeutics and has been at CEO
since 2022. So welcome Shirley.
[Music]
Great. Thank you, Caroline, for the kind
invitation.
Um, I
think I don't
need Okay, great. Yeah. So, as Carla
mentioned, I've been at GV20 for uh just
over three years now. Um if you look at
the last decade I would say cancer
imunotherapy crisper and AI are the most
exciting uh scientific breakthroughs and
at GB20 our mission is to cure cancer by
integrating cancer imunology crisper or
other kind of high throughput technology
and data and AI or computation. Um and
so we focused on cancer imunotherapy
because it is the only treatment to a
true achieve true cure in metastatic
tumors and if you look at the last year
the highest selling cancer drug are the
two cancer uh the antiPD1 therapeutics
and uh antip1 is approved in over 40
indications because they don't just
specifically target cancer they try to
boost the patient own immune system to
indirectly cure the cancers but Even for
a drug that's like a the most you know
highest sold cancer drug, it only
benefits about 20% of the cancer
patients. So 80% of the cancer patient
still needs better treatment. The
conventional approach for a drug uh
research and development process like
antip antibbody is like this. Uh it's
from gene uh to function to target or to
uh to drug. So first scientists need to
know that there is a PD1 gene or
protein. It interacts with PDL1 to
induce a T- cell dysfunction. Then they
can develop an antibbody to block this
interaction to um uh stimulate the T-
cells for cancer killing. And the drug
discovery, the target discovery is like
three and 10 years. Drug discovery is
another many years and clinical
development just overall very long and
expensive.
So what I tell you what if I tell you
that humans own immune system actually
already produce and optimize anti-tumor
antibodies in their tumors and in fact
over millions of years of evolution
enable the human immune system to
recognize the tumor targets and optimize
antibodies against them um and so they
are usually made within the tumors in
these tertiary lymphoid structures or
bell aggregates
um and it's it's been widely reported
that the presence of these bell
aggregates or tertiary lymph structures
are associated with better patient
response and antiPD1 um uh response and
so you wonder if they already have
anti-tumor antibodies why do patients
still develop cancer um you can imagine
in the lost territory in the war like a
tumor there are still guerilla warriors
that there are still fighting and if we
can have tens of thousands of tumors to
look at even if we don't know why they
are uh they are still persisters. We
know we need to train more soldiers like
this to really win the war and that's
the kind of approach we're taking. Um we
have a proprietary AI platform that can
identify novel cancer drug candidate
directly from these tumor infiltrating
antibodies. Um we actually don't have to
do the tumor sequencing ourselves. There
are a lot of um published the tumor RNA
seek data available out there and when
people sequence the RNA of a tumor, the
B cells infiltrating that tumor are also
making the antibbody RNA. And so we have
a computational approach called the
trust that can assemble antibodies from
these tumor RNA seek. And so at GV20 we
have assembled over a 100 million of
these tumor infiltrating antibodies from
tens of thousands of tumors. um they are
usually coming from the clonal expanded
B cells that are more likely to be
recognizing some tumor antigens. Turns
out we could use AI to predict the
targets of these antibodies and from
there we get to the drug. So intuitively
how do we make predictions? We don't
actually train on a known antigen
antibbody database. Instead we learn all
the features directly from our tumor
antibodies. For example, from the tumor
RNA seek expression, you can tell which
are her to positive tumors and which are
her to negative tumors. And if you see
any antibbody features, these are, you
know, peptide short peptide features
that are enriched in the hero to
positive tumors but depleted in the hero
negative tumors. That's a potential
herto binder. And if you have a
antibbody sequence that have all the
right features, then you know it's a
potential herto binder. And we don't
just do this for her too. Um we have
first of all a huge tumor collection and
we test it on every gene in the genome
and every mutation that's recurrently
occurring in the tumor. And so at the
end for every antibbody we have a
probabilistic assignment of this
antibbody to the protein or genes or
mutations. And so I hope this kind of
convinced you that we can get a
potentially interesting antibbody. Um
but how do we get to the target? Um the
first thing we you know with this AI
approach we we tested was that do do
patient make antiPD1 sorry make a her
two or EGFR antibodies these are drugs
that sell for about a billion dollars a
year and indeed we can make predictions
and experimentally validate that and
then we ask how about the PD1 PD1 we can
also um actually inhouse we have very
very good PD1 PD1 antibody that the PD1
we get we don't even need to optimize it
works from the bat and then we asked ask
how about the CD47 or SIGLA like 15
these are antibodies that have failed in
clinical trials interestingly we don't
see any patient antibbody signals in
them and so we thought oh maybe we can
use antibbody signal to tell us which
targets are promising um and which ones
are not going to make it and so we use
the antibbody signal to help us rank the
targets in addition once we have the
targets we can also use AI to directly
get to the antibbody drugs and so that's
why we call our approach this um uh stat
or simultaneous target evaluation and
antibbody discovery. And so then we said
okay let's try to predict something new
that nobody knows. And we focus on this
immunoglobin super family protein
because currently um all the immune
checkpoint genes belong to this family.
They are known to mediate cell
interaction and we found that this um
IGSF8 gene is interesting. many many
patients made a little bit of antibbody
against it. Um and we also looked at our
in-house crisper screen data. Um GV20
when we started was based on the crisper
screen technology. My lab were also
among the earliest to use crisper
screens for oncology and immunoncology
studies and we found that this IGSF8
gene normally does not influence cancer
cell growth unless the cancer cell is
under immune pressure. for example when
we co-culture the cancer cell with an
ENK cell or when we implant the cancer
cell in a fully immune mice and um so
without understanding the function of
this gene um we just said let's use AI
to pull out the antibbody that patient
made against IGSF8 and fortunately this
target is conserved between human and
mouse so the antibbody we got combined
to the mouse IGSF8 as well so we tried
on mouse tumors right away first in
melanoma but also in lung cancer, colon
cancer, breast cancer and prostate
cancer. And we consistently see the same
phenomenon like what we observe in
melanoma. This drug always have
monotherapy efficacy and very often
better than anti PD1 alone. And when we
combine the two drugs together by
halfing the dose of each, we get even
better
efficacy. So with this, we kind of felt
okay, we have to understand how this
gene work. At that time when we first
saw this gene, there were less than 10
papers ever published on this gene and
little known reported function. And so
we did the biology function of this uh
of this gene at the company. Um this is
also why I left Harvard to join the
company because my lab cannot work on
it. Um and uh we published a biology
study on the first half uh last year. Um
and uh we just submitted a second part
uh on the dendritic cell uh last
weekend. So this gene is kind of like a
PDL1 but for the innate uh immunity. It
suppresses the natural killer cells and
the dendritic cells especially when the
tumors are losing their MHC class one
antigen presentation. So they are
usually higher in the immune code tumors
and they are because when the tumors
don't express MHC class one they're
invisible to the T- cells. um but they
should be recognized and killed by the
ENK cells unless the cancer cell
overexpress IGSF8 and also it is
expressed on DC as well and interact
with dendritic cell to suppress the DC
antigen presentation and the T- cell um
activation and so with this antibbody we
can directly activate ENK cells and
dendritic cells and indirectly activate
T- cells so it's a very very exciting
mechanism um actually at the same time
as We work on the biology of this
target. We uh brought this drug to the
clinic and um uh we have by now finished
the phase one monotherapy dose
escalation. This drug has excellent
developability and really good PK
profiles. Um we have those 42 patients
and um 38 are evaluable. The drug is
very very safe and uh we saw tumor
shrinkage in non small cell lung cancer
and cervical cancer. But the very first
melanoma patient we tried was a partial
responders. And so we asked the sites to
give us more backfill of the melanoma
patients. And so by now we have dosed
the 17 melanoma patients uh with
monotherapy. And interestingly um well
all of them have previously been treated
with anti PD1. 16 has been treated with
anti-Cta4. And then we treated our drug,
you know, just monotherapy. And out of
the nine patients who previously never
responded to antiPD1 with a primary
refractory to antiPD1, we thought we saw
three confirmed partial responders and
three patients with tumor shrinkage and
another patient who are on wheelchairs
before after being treated with our drug
walked again. And so it's really
benefiting the patient. Um, this is from
the CT and PET CT scan. You can see the
very first patient or some
representative uh um tumors this big
foot lesion shrank significantly and the
second and third patients both have
liver metastasis and this one shrank by
uh 58% and a third patient the 24
millimeter um liver metastasis
completely disappeared. This patient
before our drug in seven months used
five different drugs and progressed very
quickly. And initially on our drug uh
the patient tumor was still growing and
then it started to respond uh at month
seven and the patient has been on our
treatment for over 13 months now and
still responding. Um in comparison to
other IO drugs this drug in the early uh
clinical study is actually better than
CT4 much much better than lac and tg
because they don't really have any
single agent efficacy. In fact it's
similar to antiPD1 from BMS. um for uh
for the merc drug you know that out of
30 patients they did have five
responders but these patients only had
2.5 line of prior treatment whereas um
in our phase one uh together with BMS
it's like four prior line of treatment
in imunotherapy every prior line of
treatment reduced the response by about
10%. And so we saw that our drug was
actually having similar efficacy as
antiPD1 in phase one
clinics. We also saw that the tumor have
significantly increased ENK and T- cell
infiltration even among patients who
don't respond to the drug suggesting
that these patient could be reensitized
to antiPD1. And also the responders seem
to have higher IGS8 expression than the
non-responders suggesting that we should
select the IGSF8 positive tumors to
enrich for responding
signals. So how does AI really help us?
If you look at the development of
antiPD1,
um we don't actually know when the
research started, but the very first
publication was in
1992 and uh it took another eight years
to uh for people to figure out the
interaction partner was PDL1 and then
another six years to develop the drug
and three years to do the antibbody uh
phase one uh study. Whereas from the
first day we saw this little known gene
was end of like 2019 to the end of phase
one was uh only five years. And this is
because AI told us how patient is
fighting the tumor without us
understanding why. And um um in in
actually a drug uh development um
trajectory. If you look at the revenues
generated on the KUDA drug um towards
the later years that's when the income
really comes. So if you can shrink the
uh time from patent to drug approval it
can sign significantly increase the drug
uh patent value and we are doing this uh
uh again to build a robust pipeline in
addition to this drug. you know we have
other antibodies and recently we had a a
partnership agreement with Mishubish
Tanab on some other programs again first
inclass novel targets that we have
antibodies for um and so how are we
going to use AI um so the the actually
the AI we use currently is just a deep
learning model um we can use
foundational models uh by pre-training
on all the proteins and all the
antibodies in blood and fine-tune on
antibodies from tumor or from other
diseases. Um but this takes a lot more
money. Um right now you know we we need
more resources to do this more uh
computationally intensive uh exercises.
Um but you know look forward to
collaborating with all of you guys
potentially to find a cure for cancer.
Thank you very much.
Wonderful. Thank you very much Shirley.
And now it's my pleasure to introduce my
faculty colleague uh Marzia Gosi um who
is associate professor at MIT in the
department of electrical engineering and
computer science and also in the
institute for medical engineering and
science. Um her her work is highlighting
how many of our current algorithms can
really fail patients. Uh so we'll go to
the darker side again. Um but then she
also provides new methods for the
ethical and reproducible use of machine
learning and health. So,
welcome. Thank you. There's not a timer,
is there? There is. It's counting down
already. What? Okay. Hi, everyone. Uh in
case you didn't know, there's a large
timer that's already counting down just
to scare us. And so I'm going to talk a
little bit about my research. Um my lab
uh at MIT is the healthy machine
learning lab and we really focus on
trying to construct methods that will
work well in healthcare. Um in some
cases you don't actually need a model.
Maybe you just need to understand that
there's some inefficiency. Um, and in
some cases, if you build the very best
model possible, if you don't deliver the
advice correctly, the best model and the
best person don't equal the best
behavior. So, thinking about that at a
higher scale,
um, the demonstrative example I always
give people is the simple one because I
I think it illustrates the issue. Let's
say that you want to build a system for
triaging patients who maybe have a chest
X-ray. Um, and if they're not sick,
you'd really like to send them home
early. You don't want them to wait
around. And we can build triage models.
Uh triage models are actually uh
reasonably easy to build these days
because you know every person who's ever
built an AI model has gone through this
you know nice pipeline where you pick a
problem, collect data, define an
outcome, develop your algorithm and then
potentially deploy it, right? And so we
can do that too. Uh we did do that. Um,
we chose this demonstrative example with
our faculty colleagues and we took the
three largest publicly available chest
X-ray data sets in the United States,
300,000 or over 700,000 images. You can
train a denset to try to predict the
finding um no finding which is the
person is healthy, they can go home and
then um we get a nice performance,
right? Which is what everybody does,
right? Everybody uh like makes these
really great models. I do this too that
have these really nice performance
metrics. The question is um how and when
should we be deploying these models? Um
there are many many models that have
been developed for a variety of uh
medical tasks across the range of uh
different data sets and both predictive
and generative settings. And when you
look at even just one, let's say here we
focus on medical question answering
which is a popular benchmark task for
machine learning conferences. we see
that models are very performant, right?
And this is across both uh closed and
open- source models um using a variety
of different techniques uh anything from
pre-training, fine-tuning, and just
prompt tuning.
Okay. Um and it's not just that these
models perform well, it's also that we
know that there are uh ways of
officially having models out there uh
for use in clinical settings. So for
example, the FDA can clear AI algorithms
to be used in a uh clinical
setting. So let's look back at uh my
algorithm, right? Maybe maybe this, you
know, performant algorithm is something
because it gets state-of-the-art
performance we'd like to deploy. But the
question is uh often we just look at
these sort of aggregated uh metrics,
right? And we're not thinking about how
that might apply in a wider more
heterogeneous setting. So for example,
let's look at the false positive rate of
this really really performant model in
different groups. And a false positive
rate here would mean that you're
underdiagnosing a patient because you're
falsely positively saying that they're
healthy. And our great model has the
largest underdiagnosis rate on female
patients, young patients, black
patients, and patients on Medicaid
insurance. And if you uh look at
patients who exist in an intersectional
identity, they're doing even worse.
Right? This is not unique to this
setting. Um, and really there's a
variety of reasons that these things
happen and there's also a variety of
ways that we can try to address them,
but it's something to be both aware of
and cautious about. So, I want to talk
briefly about how this happens in
medical data because I think at this
point hopefully we're all aware of how
this happens in natural images. Uh, has
everybody heard of a
shortcut? I'm seeing nods, but I gave a
lecture earlier today where people gave
me that face. And so I'll just briefly
say, you know, a shortcut in uh natural
images is when we know that this is a
model, a very nice well-trained model
knows that this is a cow and this is a
benign mole, but suddenly this cow is an
orca and this mole is cancerous. And
it's not because of the actual
underlying features we might want it to
use. It's because this model has never
seen a cow trapesing around in water. It
thinks that, you know, large black and
white mammals in water are orcas. And
also, maybe it's learned a shortcut
that, well, I know that when
dermatologists mark the area around a
mole, they're looking for growth, they
think it's cancerous, right? These are
things that you didn't explicitly tell
the model not to learn. And so, it
learned it because it's statistically
true. It's correlated in the data that
it's seen. And this is really funny when
we, you know, see that frisking cows in
water are orcas. It's less funny when we
think about features in medical images
that maybe might be used to mispredict
um in certain people. It's even less
funny when we think about things that
machine learning models can see that we
can't see. So, if you take a medical
note and redact all dimensions of
demographics like self-reported race,
human doctors can't predict that about a
patient. We tested them. uh but machine
learning models can with almost perfect
performance and even higher performance
when you take a uh chest X-ray or any
other kind of medical imaging. Um
radiologists cannot look at a chest
X-ray. We we tested them. They thought
they could but uh med radiologists they
are very confident. Um radiologists
cannot predict these things these
demographics but machine learning models
can with extremely high accuracy. So
what happens when you have a model that
can predict something perfectly, a
shortcut perfectly that humans can't
see? Well, what can happen is that it
can use that shortcut to mispredict more
in that group. So here we wanted to
explore this in three settings um in
dermatology, opthalmology and radiology.
These are all settings where we use
medical images to make a a diagnosis and
where we have AI models that do these
tasks. What we found is that in all
cases, models learn to recover
information about demographics that in
many cases would be very hard or
impossible for a human doctor to do. And
the more that they recover this
demographic secretly in their layers,
the worse they are at predicting the
outcome for a minority uh patient group
in that data setting. So, put another
way, the more I know who is female in a
chest X-ray, the worse I do at
predicting cardiomegaly in female
patients.
There are ways to fix this by example
for using robust uh by using robust
optimizers things like um uh group
distributionally robust optimization
where you can get this uh if you haven't
seen a paro plot economists love them
and one of our reviewers was an
economist. So here uh you can see the
overall AU right we want that to be high
of course on the Y-axis we have the
fairness gap and we want that to be low
of course and you can see when we use
vanilla optimization we get these teal
models that are up here for erm very
undesirable it's like lying right it's
saying good overall performance but the
gap is very high and if we use uh robust
optimizers we can shove that all the way
down this is great but this is when we
take data from Massachusetts train a
model from Massachusetts and then we
test it in new data from Massachusetts.
What happens when we test it in new data
from
Stanford gets much worse and the problem
is it doesn't get much much worse
uniformally. We actually aren't able to
predict whether a model will do much
better or much worse in a new setting
and that's a surprising new result.
Usually we believe that the best model
in one setting will sort of you know
it'll be worse but it'll be still the
best model of all the models in a new
setting. And this is not something that
we can get around. It's something that
you have to evaluate in new
settings. Um, so TLDDR1 human data is
tricky. Test models on data from
populations they'll be used on. The
second thing I want to talk about is how
we actually optimize models in
healthcare settings. Well, you know, uh
there's a hot topic about how we use
group attributes. Don't uh talk to
doctors about it or they'll hit you um
or yell at you. One or the other or
both. And so, uh, the problem is often
when you use a demographic attribute
like here, I view sex, um, and age, even
if I use no fancy AI, just a logistic
regression model, this model is 1%
better on average, but it gets that by
being much better in the young female
subgroup and worse in these two other
subgroups, right? And so again, this
happens when we have some sort of
optimization that is tuning for an
overall performance and not respecting
maybe interactions between features. And
while it's easy to point that out in a
logistic regression model, it gets much
harder when we deal with these large
vision language models, right, that have
billions of parameters. And so vision
language models are used for things like
generation, image classification, and
retrieval, but they also have a lot of
biases. And the way that people try to
debias these models is often this really
linear thing where you sort of estimate
where is male, estimate where is female
and then you project out and collapse
that dimension. But the problem is that
assumes linearity and these are really
complex topological objects that are
nonlinear. And so if you collapse male
and female doctor, you might do bad
things to the space for male and female
pilot or male and female manager. Right?
So it has downstream effects that are
hard to quantify. So a lot of what we're
doing in this space is trying to uh
understand how to work with this complex
nonlinear topology. For example, with
negation, uh despite their flexibility,
if you ask models um vision language
models to give you something with
negation, they fail. So if you say, I
want tables with no chairs, you're going
to get chairs. If you ask uh for a
picture of a dog, not on grass, you're
going to get grass. If you ask uh in
visual question answering whether uh
there is grass, it'll say yes, but
there's not. Um, sidebar, did you know
that the most doglike dog is a golden
retriever? If you look at the embedding
space for dog, all the other dogs are
very far away from it and golden
retriever is right on top. So, we have
trained vision language models that
golden retriever are the only dog out
there for us.
And maybe it's cute that in vision
language models we get these pictures of
dogs on grass. But it's not cute when I
want evidence of lung opacity and I
retrieve this image. But I say evidence
of lung opacity with no signs of edema
and I still get this image. Right? It's
very important that we process negation
correctly with medical vision language
models. This is very hard because when
we train large vision language models,
how do we train them? We train them like
this. Uh we always train them on was is
present. We don't, for example, say
black and white dog jumps over bar, no
helicopter. There's never a negation in
the
caption. And so consequently, vision
language models don't know how to
contextualize that. And again, this is
much harder in medical vision language
models because negation is really
present, right? Often we just have a
list of things that aren't present, lots
of negation. And so we made a benchmark
to try to understand how poorly uh
state-of-the-art vision language models
do in negation. And it turns out it's
really poorly. In fact, they tend to
embed things right on top of their
negations. Not a flower is right on top
of flower. And uh so takeaway number
two, uh robustness is hard. You have to
test models on things that they might
fail on even if humans might not. I see
my time is almost up, so I will breeze
through the last section which is about
deployment
considerations. E, you know, the goal is
not to have AI do everything. Hopefully.
Hopefully, unless you talk to Dr. Oz,
that's what he wants. Um, and so I know
he's like agents everywhere. I'm like,
isn't that the matrix? Isn't that what
the matrix wants? And so really what we
want is doctors working with AI
together, right? But if that's what we
want, that's what we need to measure.
And there's lots of good work that has
shown first the losses of bad AI, this
is not my paper, but I love it. It's
from 2020 is much worse than the gain
from good AI. So number one, make sure
that you have a good AI model, right?
That's the base and not all of the
models out there are good. Number two,
humans are extremely susceptible to
incorrect advice. This was even expert
radiologists when we measured. Okay? And
so it's very hard for humans to dismiss
incorrect advice. We're really gullible.
And finally, convincing advice delivery
style worked really well on doctors. So
when we told doctor to do something bad
as an order, they did it. When we told
them to do the same bad thing as a
factual um you know feature, they
ignored it and retained their original
fair decision-m destroying my life work
of making better models. So all of these
things are really important. These are
sort of the human factors that affect
whether a model will be useful or not.
And they're underststudied. So we really
need to understand that humans are
fallible. You have to test models and
humans in these high-risk situations
beforehand. And uh by doing that we can
move forward with ethical AI and health.
Thank you.
[Applause]
So thank you to all the speakers for
some really really wonderful and
thoughtprovoking talks. So I would like
to ask them all to come up here so that
we can have a discussion up here. And
hopefully we have a lot of
microphones. Okay. So I think this was
really really wonderful going through
you know from proteins all the way then
tissues drug discovery and then all the
way to hospital possibly applications
and seeing where things can go wrong. So
I think we have seen like really amazing
positive examples of you know the use of
ML and where we can get to and then also
some scary examples and so I think I
would love to hear from you of like you
know like we see the complexity of
biology and human health and in some
problems it seems like it's still you
know we're still very very far away from
making progress on these very complex
problems uh using AI and others are
totally in reach. So, how do you go
about deciding and and which problems do
you maybe think the ones who have very
positive examples of like what are the
problems that are totally not in reach?
Um, and what are the problems that are
kind of in reach on your
end? Anyone who wants to start?
All right. Well, I guess I'll start. Um,
hey everyone. Um, so I I think for for
us, uh, like we we're kind of hoping
that these giant large language models
will at some point start to generalize
in terms of start to understand what how
proteins actually fold and so on. Uh, at
the moment they're still in this status
where they're essentially storing
statistics of what evolution has tried.
But like if you want to go beyond what
evolution has done, like how do we so
that's sort of it's still an ongoing
challenge and we're still thinking how
to get these models to do it. um or even
if it's possible at all like maybe the
the way we're training them is not the
right way or maybe the architecture is
wrong. So not sure yet.
So when I was a PhD student at Stanford
uh at the time we were taking Deafany
Kohler's AI class and uh uh she was
discussing how deep blue beats the
casper of for chess playing and it took
another 25 years for general AI models
to really benefit you know the
everybody. I feel like for alpha fold 2
to beat um other computational biologist
in protein structure prediction is the
deep bulu moment we are still quite far
away from a general AI foundation model
for uh biology for the whole of biology
and so I think now it's really important
to know um especially as a company for
us you know how much we need to invest
in AI at the same time to ensure that
the company delivers value and move the
company forward. Um and I think we are
still a way to go but at least for
example right now we feel like the the
available data on tumor sequencing is
sufficient but for other diseases for
example neuroscience or Alzheimer we are
certainly very interested and there
certainly is also immune component you
know something in the brain maybe the
immune system is causing the disease and
or maybe there are still residuals to
fight the disease but we simply don't
have enough data there to make uh drug
predictions yet.
So I think that these models are really
um susceptible to all kinds of failure
just like Mars that Marz showed and
we've seen it in real time for some
models that we have deployed over over
the years and uh have assessed it on
actual patients and we've also published
some of those results from a pathology
pathology perspective. Um but
uh I I think there are ways you can make
them more robust. Uh and I think that
some of the more easier problems for
example in pathology were very
interested in having a universal triage
which can triage out all the negative
slides. It h it happened for papsmears
for cytologology in 1998 and there's
been an FDA approved tool since and it
it decreased the amount of work that
that was needed and uh technically we
could do that in in in pathology. It's
been difficult to get FDA approval for
it. Um and that's because uh it has very
uncertain failure modes. Um, on the
other hand, I think that the larger
models, foundation models that integrate
multiple kinds of uh clinical data are
really valuable discovery engines
because you can discover a lot of uh um
combination markers that you uh may not
have thought of otherwise for all all
kinds of complex complex disease and
also to serve as companion diagnostics
together with certain certain drugs.
I think there are really uh exciting
examples of where um machine learning uh
specifically AI generally is being
applied to problems that we're really
bad at. So for example, you know, um
adverse events in cancer, imunotherapy,
those those are things we're bad at,
right? We don't know how to do it. We're
trying to do something new um and
improve. Um there's a lot of uh
interesting applications I've seen in uh
women's health where everything is
trash. And so if you make any advance,
you're doing great. Um I think the issue
is that's not where a majority of the
effort is going in a lot of AI for
health more broadly, right? I think
we're very um benchmark focused, right?
And so if you look maybe beyond the the
cancer space to more broadly where AI is
um already deployed in healthcare,
right? A lot of the examples are
administrative examples, things that are
adjacent to clinical care like insurers
uh making decisions about who gets
different kind of care. Um uh deciding
who gets booked for appointments,
deciding who gets resources, writing
notes on your behalf, writing messages
on your behalf. And I think those are um
sort of uh dangerous use cases because
they mediate who is even able to access
care even further. So, I think there's a
lot of there are a lot of really
exciting things, but as we all just
said, like we need more data. We need
more data. What if we only get data from
certain kinds of people even more so now
that they're predicted that they
shouldn't be part of a trial or they
shouldn't get to see a pathologist or
they shouldn't like those those are very
scary I think examples
and since now this already came up we
need more data or you know what are
really the bottlenecks to making
progress. I mean one could be data. You
also all mentioned we need GPUs. Um you
know for us like building the large
scale AI models would require much more
funding even in industry. Um you also
mentioned the other way around as well
although GPUs are there but maybe you
cannot run the lab anymore. Um so so
what are though the real bottlenecks you
think? I mean yeah it could be that it
could be new algorithms. Um what is it
and which types of problems?
It's capitalism, guys.
Okay, we all know that you all and the
companies, if you're here, I see you,
right? That you have the data that it's
been deidentified via HIPPA and you
bought it. I know because my friends who
work there and are making millions call
me. Okay, we don't have millions. We
can't buy the same data. Um, it would be
nice if we could, right? And so I think
um one thing that would be really
helpful is if we did something as a
nation like invest more in all of us
which is a fantastic platform that I'm a
huge fan of um a lot of the work that is
done a lot of the really like leading
really cool work that's been done in the
past decade is always done first with
the UK bio bank because they invested in
that resource but I think we want to
have you know similar resources um
across the world of course also GPUs
so so I think that we know that there
are three things that you need to to do
this kind of work. You need the data,
compute and the talent. And there's an
abundance of talent in in this town as
needless to say. Um but for for data, I
completely agree. We need like no large
national consorcia. I think the UK bio
bank is a very good example. They did a
really good job at it. Um I mean all of
us is great but it's not as standardized
and integrated as uh as as we've seen
with UK UK biioank. There are really
large efforts. So I I I think ARPA is
leading some really large initiatives
unless they lose funding too. Um but the
they have the index cohort where they're
there's a very large scale goal of
making very large amounts of data just
publicly available. And the motivation
is that the TCGA was a um you know
10,000 case uh example and so much
research has come out of just using the
TCGA. anything in in my field in
computational pathology all the initial
work um the method development the
initial studies discovery was all done
on the on the TCG and that was just
10,000 cases and I think under the
umbrella of something like like like
ARPA they have the ability to uh just
digitize all the glass slides for
example and the rest of the data if you
if you can deidentify it is is easy and
then in pathology we also have the joint
pathology center from the military where
they have the largest repository of
pathology data going back to the civil
war. Uh and they are digitizing it very
very very very quickly and it's a it's a
national national resource and I think
part of their goal is to deidentify that
data and make it available for uh for
for research. So uh I think that would
that would happen. um the compute. So
what we do what we have done in the past
that's my my group had uh grants that
supported supported compute sometimes it
was just us and in other situations it
was together with other other
investigators
um and S10 awards and you know the they
were supporting at state state awards um
but uh uh I think that if if you look at
all major institutions a lot of compute
support has come from philanthropy so we
need more more of more of that and we we
we have that at Harvard. Uh and I I I
think just because these these
infrastructures they evolve so quickly
and how much compute you need to develop
some of these models. I mean uh a lot of
the lobbying politics behind building
the model that we built using so much
patient data was how do we get access to
the compute and data and and just
organize it u across many many of the
Harvard hospitals or or a number of
years.
Uh I would say one bottleneck or barrier
to get better or good data is the
pressure to publish high-profile papers.
Uh for example, tumor RNA sequencing is
really inexpensive. You can do it with a
couple hundred dollars, but people are
not doing it. Why? You you get another
few hundred samples. You can't even
publish a CNS paper. And yet if you do a
newest spatial transcripttoics data with
10 samples you can get a nature science.
And so I I remember Bill Kalin once said
that you know sometimes journals are
interested in seeing a a mention of hay
instead of a house of brick. We need
more house of brick type of data to
really train these really valuable uh
data to train good uh AI models and
because these really mention of hey the
technologies are still evolving the tech
you know like you have a little bit of
here a little bit of other samples they
can never really be integrated together
to generate really useful insights and
you probably only you see batch effect.
Yeah.
All right. Guess it's my turn. Um yeah
so I actually thought the last talk was
quite interesting because I was trying
to connect it back to the stuff that we
do in terms of fairness but when we
think of fairness and proteins it's more
like there's certain proteins families
that actually uh the models really
struggle on like they don't understand
and don't learn anything about um I
don't know if fair fairness is the right
word for it but they're the worst. We
hate them. Those protein families don't
deserve to be recognized.
Yeah. And it is one of those things that
we often like check. we say well do do
these models like they start to work
really well for large protein families
like where there's a lot of data but
then for small protein families very
underst sampled um don't don't it work
so well and uh yeah I think there's a
lot of interesting joking aside it's the
same effect right it's uh there's a
different dynamic that needs to be
captured right um and uh if it's an
under represented sample it's hard to
capture that effect so it's it really is
the same problem y makes sense
Cool. So I would like to since we don't
have that much time left to open it up
for questions. I'm sure this is very
thoughtprovoking and there will be a lot
of questions. Um maybe I'll give this
one.
So I have a question on when for all
these foundational models for OMIX they
are coming and it was good to see the
talk uh but what are the biases and also
the morning started with Anul's work
where he was talking about TNF biases
and stuff. So as a student it seems with
all the foundational models there are
there are sure there are many biases but
as a community I'm not sure we
understand it. It seems apart from
authors people may not understand where
the things so I mean what's your take on
mean as a student it seems that there
should be a s some consortium or some
symposium dedicated to figure out in
what scenario these foundational models
what are the issues with these
foundational models rather than what
great thing these do and what's your
take on it
yeah I mean I I think that there should
be so uh let me let me answer more
seriously
Um it I think that it would be really
valuable if we had a slightly more
invested regulatory landscape. Right. I
think for example if the bill passed by
the past administration on AI um safety
and equity would not have been repealed
or if there were something to replace
it. Um that could be more encompassing
and and cover foundation models in all
settings you know health settings and
research settings etc.
um uh work on understanding AI bias is
actively being defunded. I know MIT
faculty members whose NSF careers were
cancelled because that was their area of
focus. Everybody said the foundation,
you know, the foundations will step the
philanthropy will step up. They have
not. I promise you. Everybody said
companies will step up. Sorry, they have
not. And so this research is actually
uniquely hard to do right now. There is
very little funding. And if you do that
research and you have grants um on other
things with federal agencies, your
grants with federal agencies on those
other things might also be cancelled. So
this is something that I do think we
should do a lot of investment into, but
it is not um being funded right now. So
it's it's hard to do in an academic
setting. Um the play is to rebrand. This
is what I was told this morning. It's
not fairness, it's
safety. Okay. As long as we can get the
EA crowd to buy in and agree that when
AGI comes for us, they'll kill women
first. Makes sense, right? You know,
then we can all be AI safety people and
get some of that sweet FTX money once
they come back. Thank you.
Anyone else?
Um so one thing I've noticed is uh uh a
lot of the discussion about data
generation for these models is a little
bit agnostic in the sense that actually
you know as many of you showed it's it's
actually quite uh feasible to go and
figure out where the models do poorly.
So you may not actually you know if you
just go to the wide and collect data you
may actually be collecting the uh
targeting the wrong density of the
landscape of data. So like do you know
of I I I don't know as many but like do
you know of efforts that are actively
looking to fill holes like uh model
based data sampling strategies data
generation strategies wouldn't those be
more effective than but but I guess if
all of us is what what is the
what is the target sorry they're
oversampling for groups that are under
reppresented in in other studies that's
sort of their contribution I guess in in
in those kind of scenarios it's maybe
easier to tell but in like biological
foundation models and like you know uh
things like that it's it's very hard to
know a priority what it is but you can
iterate through it's sort of like active
learning but uh with a big human in the
loop you know many years of data
collection in the loop it just doesn't
seem like there are big efforts really
pushing I mean people have been saying
this for decades but I've just not seen
big push in that direction yeah I I
think one issue with biological data is
that there isn't enough standardization
in similar to what we get in medical
data, right? So, so, so a lot of people
are complaining about how unstandardized
all the medical data is, but but
biological data is often collected for
studies, it's like a hodgepodge of like
what what it was actually used for. And
when you when it comes to training these
foundation models, you want to use, you
know, every spatial
transcription, right? It was done using
number of different techniques. It's
it's collected for different purposes
was was done to answer completely
different questions. So, the
distribution of the data would be sort
of all over all over the place. So in in
in medical data we have some hope that
you know I mean we know from all these
studies from you know the large
companies that diversity of data is way
more important than the quantity of data
and it's just really difficult to find
diverse data uh for you know more
biologically oriented problems. So I
think what would happen is that there
are a lot of these foundation models for
all kinds of different purposes. The
next step is going to be that they're
all trained on different distributions
of data and they all represent the the
same kind of data. So, so, so because
they're they're inherent training
distributions are different, maybe you
can use multiple foundation models to
see, you know, mixture of foundation
models even using something very
simplistic for your downstream
downstream tasks. That's what would
happen in the in the short term before
we have more standardized data
collection protocols.
Can I just point out also that we're we
really like it when you know large
foundation models find something new in
in some settings and then we slap them
and say don't hallucinate in other
settings. And so it's also unclear what
properties we want for um this kind of
like forecasting without support in in
real data space.
Yeah, I guess I'll add in the protein
world. I mean we we have lots of
sequencing going on um and folks have
been trying to go to weird places like
under the ocean and so on and just
sequencing everything. I think I've seen
a study where somebody actually swiped
the outside of the space station and
found some interesting weird archa
living there. It's probably I mean I
don't think it came from space but
probably
was but but yeah there there's there's
definitely a lot of sequencing efforts
happening in specific um and and we
still see like every two years we're
roughly doubling in the number of
sequences that are quite different from
what we see before. Um so there so in
the protein world I think we're might be
okay for now until the finding is cut.
Thank you. Based on what you present all
all think it's more not if we can model
the
human body and health it's when and if
we can predict model and cure every
future diseases what's next
I'll take this as the last question
then we'll have universal child care
right afterwards that's the that's the
next fun, you know,
I guess I mean I'm guessing you're
thinking human health, but how about
like all the other animals out there? So
in general, we'll move on to the rest of
life, I suppose.
In addition to physical health, I think
mental health will still always be like
how are we going to make people happier,
right? Like there are also some
physiological things. I'm sure we'll
we'll have plenty of good things to work
on.
Basel has something more to add. No, I I
I I completely agree. I I think it'll
take a while to get there, but yeah, I
don't think it's happening anytime soon
like we've got a way many PhDs in front
of us.
So, with this and a lot more work to do,
thank you so much to this panel for
wonderful.
[Applause]
So this brings us already to the end of
this first uh annual symposium of the
Eric and Wendy Schmidt Center. I really
loved it. I loved all the exciting
talks. Um a lot of stimulating
discussions and you know we started from
very basic cell biology, tissue biology
um all the way to particular uh
pathology to um AI models that were
developed for particular biological
applications to foundation models that
are very very broad. So I hope this
meeting was exciting to all of you um
and that you were also all able to build
new connections and had a lot of uh
different discussions. You know ML will
transform all areas of biology and and
the medical sciences and you know this
is so important to bring this community
together to actually really make this
marriage uh become better and better and
stronger. Um so I would like to end by
thanking all the people who made this uh
so enjoyable and really made um this uh
conference and workshop come together.
Uh so that's the amazing team behind the
Eric and Wendy Schmidt Center. So, I
would love if they could all get up.
And so, we have Jennifer, Sue, Samanda,
Leticia, Nadia, Elva, and Ore. I think
they're all there. So, thank you so
much. This was
[Applause]
awesome. And also, Jirro Studio, who
helped us with everything, getting
through so carefully here. So, thank you
also. And with this, I know we still
have a song. Is that right? There is no
sock. There's no song.
I'm putting Lindsay on the spot.
[Laughter]
So then you all have to beg him for a
song before we go outside. But with
that, thank you all for coming.
[Applause]