Before I um pass it over to our next
moderator for the amazing panel on
policy, I just want to do a a brief
moment summarizing um our first two
sessions. Um, and I know we started with
the enormity of the global challenge in
front of us at from multiple
perspectives and I thought that was a
fantastic conversation and then we turn
to people and it's easy um to skip the
people part and uh and to not have the
harder conversations about all the
different stakeholders and viewpoints
and challenges. Um, so I'm I'm glad we
did it. And I also um felt uh the
um
I don't know, I irony isn't quite the
right word. I'm going to misuse it, but
I felt the um the kind of human level of
what it is to be in a conversation about
people. Um our emotions and our beliefs.
um aligning them to take action is
probably the largest challenge larger
than that first panel.
Um and to do that requires a degree of
vulnerability and human connection. I
think it was mentioned by some of the
speakers that um you know
heat likes to say ch change happens at
the speed of trust. Um it is
relationshipbased. And so, um, during
the lunch break, uh, after that
conversation about, um, utilities and
the question about trust, I was, um,
chatting with, um, a leader in a gas
utility. Um, and we ended up, and I'm
going to totally make this incredibly
uncomfortable and call her up. Come on,
Nikki.
>> So, here's what we were talking about.
We're going to just demonstrate um a
little bit of vulnerability and trust.
We ended up in a very um personal
conversation about how to deal with
waking up in the middle of the night
with work issues
and challenges and and you know was was
was diet, coffee, um uh acupuncture, um
other methods the way to cope with the
burden and the exhaustion of trying to
lead in this space.
>> I'm just going to hand you the mic.
Well, I'm sure it's a foreign issue to
everybody in the room. No one ever has
woken up in the middle of the night. Um,
but I think where we we came out is just
uh the enormity of it all on your
shoulders and kind of goes back to what
some of the panels were saying about how
do you break that down and helpffectuate
change where you can. Um, and then kind
of detach really because you know you if
you're working on something that you
love, even if you're exhausted, it feels
a little less weighty than if you're
just putting the paces in, but you know,
you don't really care. Because I'm I get
asked sometimes um sometimes by people I
love, why do you care so much? It's just
a job. Or and I said, well, geez, if I
went to work and I treated it as just a
job, I would be really bored. Probably
wouldn't perform as well. And and I know
I you know not everybody's wired that
way, right? And then you think, do I
have this all wrong? Because then you
could detach a little easier. And so I
know and it's not just me. I mean, I
stand here on behalf of my team, but um
a lot of us are dealing with that. And
and I think it's just thinking about the
global picture and the to use the word
enormity of it all, but what locally can
you control and what can you do and
trying to do the now I sound like a
Frozen movie, but the next right thing I
think was the song. You can tell how old
my kids are. Yeah,
>> I was going to say that.
>> Thank you so much, Nikki, for for
volunteering to do that. Um, and I just
I wanted to do that to bring like that
level of the people conversation in in
response to some of the conversation we
had before is just it's actually just
human. And as you get to know other
humans, no matter where they are in the
system, you will find over and over
again that they are just humans and that
it is the systems that we must evolve
and change to meet the moment. So with
that note,
turning it over to Andrew Eiff who is
going to be our next moderator. And I'm
so excited for this panel.
>> I'm excited too. I hope you all are too.
I think that's a great segue. We spent
the morning, excuse me, talking about
the sort of high level and talking about
people and I think policy can seem like
a sort of depersonified kind of a thing.
It's just out there in the system, in
the atmosphere, in the water. But I
think we're going to hear in this panel
about people making that policy and what
is driving them, what are the
opportunities, what are the challenges
that they see. Uh we're going to begin
with a video from Laurig Shakudian. She
represents district 20 in in the
Maryland assembly and serves on the
economic matters committee. As you will
hear, Laurig is a passionate and
thoughtful advocate and also runs
ultramarathons, which may help explain
her stamina in pushing for geothermal
networks.
>> Delegate Lauren Chudian uh in the
Maryland General Assembly and I am
sending my greetings and a little bit of
jealousy because I wish I was there with
you.
>> Um but I'm here in the Maryland General
Assembly. We are in full session and I
have bill hearings at the time that you
all are meeting. So, I know your
meetings um and your conversations are
probably amazing and I look forward to
hearing about everything that you are
learning from each other as I continue
to be part of this amazing network of
people across the country uh who are
moving legislation and pilots and
programs forward to increase um network
geothermal systems across our
communities. Um last year around this
time I was working to pass the warmth
act which is the um working for
accessible renewable Maryland thermal
heat. A bit of a mouthful but really a
brilliant name. Wouldn't you agree? Um
and warmth like who doesn't want to be
warm? And so with that as our entry, we
were able to educate my colleagues on um
network geothermal systems uh in our
case utility owned systems and we passed
the bill in uh 2024. And so now we've
reached a point where the utilities are
each putting in um their filings with
working with the community on developing
pilot locations um and things are moving
forward. So I'll back up a little bit
and tell you about our process. I became
um really interested in geothermal in
general when I was working both on
building electrification a number of
years ago. Working on building
electrification and also simultaneously
on looking at grid issues and and um
grid stability and the ability of the
grid to handle building and and um
transportation electrification. And that
was even before we were looking at load
growth from data centers and other
manufacturing. Um and it was clear to me
that geothermal had to be part of our uh
transition because of the fact that it
has the ability to um to do the
electrification superefficiently um and
in a way that really minimizes impact on
the grid and long-term as we've seen
from the DOE studies um really saves an
extraordinary amount of money in terms
of uh infrastructure um and generation.
So I got excited about that. I had an
initial bill um in 2021 uh to create
geothermal wrecks in the state. But as I
was doing that research, I ran across
the work that heat was doing and I
absolutely fell in love with the model
because for a few reasons. Um, one
reason is because um, as I work on
energy transition, one of my top
priorities is to make sure that the jobs
that are being created in our new energy
economy are good union jobs and are
equivalent to the jobs uh, that are
being lost as we transition away from
fossil fuels. And so network geothermal
of course is the most perfect of those
transitions because um literally the
very same work working on pipes in the
ground that could be done with gas is
the very same work working on pipes in
the ground that is done with never
geothermal. So that sort of checked one
of my top priority boxes. And then the
idea of, you know, I do spend a lot of
time um with legislation that the
utilities don't like. Um and it's nice
to work with the gas utilities and say,
"Look, you know, like if you want a
future, I don't have a problem with your
future. I just have a problem with your
current business model and your past
business model of fossil gas." And so if
you want a future, like let me help you
have another kind of a future. and um
really an opportunity to take um to take
what it is that utilities do have, which
is an ability and expertise on massive
infrastructure projects and access to
capital to do that um and a system that
lets us spread the costs and the
benefits across all rateayers. And so
all of those things uh made me really
excited about network geothermal. Um so
I went up first and u met with folks at
HEAT myself. Um learned a bunch of stuff
um with um we brought up I went up with
uh initially sorry first I went up with
uh Washington gas uh and we took a look
at the systems and then as I got clearer
about the bill that I was putting
together I started a process that I do
on most of my big energy bills which is
really bringing together all of the
potential stakeholders. So, I was
working with um I was working with the
gas utilities. I was working with the
labor unions, both the labor unions who
represent gas workers. So, the in-house
labor unions uh for Washington gas and
BG and then also the building trades. Uh
so, work that doesn't get done um by the
in-house unions, construction work that
gets contracted out could be done um by
building trades. I was working very
closely with uh the grassroots groups uh
the housing justice folks, the climate
justice folks who are doing really
interesting organizing in my community
where they're going in and measuring NO2
levels associated with gas stoves and
then they're organizing tenants who are
then going to their landlords and asking
for um asking for electrification um for
as a health and safety issue. So working
with Action in Montgomery, Interfaith
Power and Light, those were some of the
groups doing that. grassroots housing
justice, climate justice work, and then
um also bringing into the conversation
groups like the Maryland Energy
Administration, the Public Service
Commission, the Office of People's
Council, and then of course all the
climate groups um that do really good
work in the state, Chesby Climate Action
Network, League of Conservation, Vot
Sierra Club, and others. And so, um I
started working with all of those
groups. And um I I um
brought uh a group of people up to
Massachusetts and thanks again to heat
for hosting us. Um we had a chance to
see um some of the test board holes. we
had a chance to sort of stand there and
look at, you know, buildings really,
right? because um as AB likes to say
there's not a lot to see but um but to
be able to picture I think for folks who
were there to be able to you know learn
about what's happening but also to
picture what kind of neighborhoods um uh
this could be really effective in and um
and then we continued to work
collaboratively and and it was exciting
to bring folks together who often are
not working um in the same direction on
the same policies um working through
building trust across those groups of
people and making sure that everybody
body felt like the bill that we finally
produced really um met the needs of of
the folks who were going to be required
and and necessary for implementation.
And so, uh we had the bill last year in
the 2024 session. Um and I'm happy to
say it passed in the in the first year
we introduced it. Um and really a lot of
that had to do with the fact that we
essentially had no opposition because
everybody was sitting at the table. And
in fact, when we went for our hearing,
you know, I had the the climate justice
groups and the gas workers union and the
utility and the office of people's
council and like that's a set of folks
that I don't know if they've ever been
on the same panel before, but I was
telling my colleagues, I was like, just
go ahead and take a picture of this um
and then move my bill favorable because
um obviously there was still work to be
done and education and and so on, but
most of the work really was the year and
a half of building coalitions and
connecting people with each and making
sure that the language really met the
needs of everybody involved. So that
bill passed and then soon after we
started um you know working with the gas
companies uh to to start to you know
connect them to the grassroots groups
and to start to organize and identify
potential locations. Um and that's
really where we are right now. Um we're
going through that process with
community groups and the the gas
companies are working on um some
engineering studies and we're excited to
have um to have something here in the
next few years. So um I'll stop there.
I'm not I may or may not be able to be
on there for questions. I'm not sure how
that's going to work, but um if anyone's
interested in getting in touch with me,
we'll make sure that you all have my
contact information. Um so I'm happy to
follow up and be supportive um as I am
able. And I do hope to to connect with
folks and and hear more and learn more
about what you all are doing all across
this country.