hi good morning everyone I'm py from M
systems really glad to have the
opportunity to meet all of you today so
um Mobi is also a spinoff from uh MIT
actually from the computer science and
AI lab right across the street so to
today many of the teams still actually
have the route back from the a lab and
Mobi we develop a large scale planning
and scheduling system that can really
solve for large scale planning problems
with uncertainty and more importantly in
collaboration with humans and then
secondly it's not just generating a
static plan but able to quickly adapt to
any changes disruptions in a highly
Dynamic environment so you can probably
already guessed actually our first
vertical to start delivering our product
is in travel and transportation our
launch customer is Tui from Hanover
Germany they are the largest tourism
group in the whole world we are
basically a core among their platform to
operate transfer services across their
uh worldwide business the this kind of
illustration give you an idea of how the
system works where effectly at the
center becomes uh among all the
different parties from The Travelers to
their operation team to the drivers
operating the vehicles that coordinates
the dispatch the decision making the
resource allocation among all of them
hundreds of millions of decisions flow
through our PL platform every year and
you can imagine from this diagram each
part is receiving different information
from the system as well as providing
additional constraints input back to us
to request updates or new plans to be
generated so the operational efficiency
as you may guess is actually not quite
straightforward it's actually com in
three folds first we will actually be
able to greatly lower the planning time
from hours down to minutes and then
sometimes in seconds allowing a way more
IG operation secondly because we are a
central platform connecting all of the
different parties and equipment
operating in the network we're able to
enhance the decision making looking
across all the constraints not requiring
humans to connecting different pieces
together and finally we are also
achieving greater flexibility supporting
more than a thousand different type of
vehicles and even more type of business
constraints to allow the system to
perform differently for different
countries and different
destinations the past 12 months is the
first time we achieve a global roll out
and then we were able to support more
than 25 million passengers throughout
the 12 months as you can imagine behind
the scenes actually hundred of millions
of decisions being made automatically by
our system and then is even during a
peak day more than 200,000 passengers
are supported by platform for their
Journeys through the Tue Network this
platform has also also been proven to be
robust across 4 uh 40 different
countries more than 100 destinations and
then we have successfully achieved more
than 99% reduction on planning time and
a cost reduction from the very first day
we turn on our
platform moving to the next stage we
also recognize the complexity of
deploying such large scale complex
planning systems with thousands of
parameters and constraint types so
really in the past two years large
language model development had really
give us an edge to actually tackle that
by allowing an automated system to work
together with the operators of our
system to actually give them a natural
language interface and then behind the
scene automatically map what they're
looking for into structure query
languages describing the constraints the
objective functions such that people
without much training they can still be
working with the system on day one
let me give you a very um simple example
like a search Cy I want to look for a r
carton by the ocean that's also warming
generate in a city with nonstop flight
from Boston you can imagine you have to
tap into many different system many
different search routing Transportation
Planning functions and then distributed
data set in order to come up with the
accurate answer but now with our natural
language interface and then really the
already powerful platform everything can
be handled in real time and then in a
fully automated way so the reason we're
here is we believe the planning
scheduling and resource allocation
platform we have developed would have
huge impact Beyond travel and all the
work we have done before may have an
similar impact in maintenance repair
Disaster Response Transportation or
manufacturing and supply chain however
we have to make decision in
collaboration with human for space for
time and resource location we're looking
forward to share more and learn more
from you during the lunch break after
this session thank you thank you so much
ping