hi my name is Hana snow I'm a technical
lead on seeker and today I'm going to
walk you through how to load your data
from an anval workspace into
Seeker start out in your anval workspace
and navigate to the files page please
note that this workspace needs to be one
which you have writer or owner level
access to and have the can share
permission for additionally this
workspace cannot be associated with any
authorization domains if this workspace
does not meet that criteria we recommend
you create a new clean workspace and
load your files from
there once you are in a valid
workspace make sure to upload a joint
called VCF with all the samples you wish
to load to seeker and then click the
analyze and Seeker
button this will prompt you to Grant
Seeker access to the data in this
workspace which will allow the Seeker in
process to
begin once that's done you will see a
drop down with a list of all of the vcfs
that are available in your workspace
please select the VCF that you wish to
load and specify whether it is exomes or
genomes and what genome build it is
on you can then enter an optional
project
description which will be displayed in
your Seeker project and can help you
keep things straight if you've done
loading several times you'll also be
prompted to agree that not to load any
Hippa protected data into seeker seeker
is not Hippa compliant and it is
therefore in violation of federal law if
you load any identifiable information in
your pedigree file including using real
names as your family or individual IDs
or including any identifiable
information in the family or individual
notes once you agree to not load any
patient information you will be able to
load a pedigree file you can download
either a blank template with the headers
populated or an example pedigree if you
are not sure how to fill a pedigree
out there is also a description of all
of the required and optional columns uh
and what values to
provide once the pedigree has been
uploaded click submit
this may take a few minutes and we ask
that you do not refresh the page while
this is
loading please note that once this
loading request goes through search will
not even immediately be available in
Seeker it can take up to a week from the
time that you request your loading to
when data is fully available in Seeker
you will receive an email letting you
know know once that data is available
when the data is available a summary of
it will appear in this data set
section in the
meantime you can see the pedig the
families and individuals created based
on the Pedigree you provided and at this
time you can add any additional
information that you would want for your
analysis you can either add it by
directly editing families and
individuals or by using the bulk edit
metadata functionality in Seeker which
will allow you to provide files with
information such as hpo
[Music]
terms and other information about the
individuals in
Seeker if at a later date you want to
load more data to your Seeker project
this is
allowed you will need to Joint call any
new data along with any of the
previously loaded family members one
once that joint call is complete and is
in the same workspace associated with
the Seeker project you can then use the
load additional data
workflow this will take you through a
similar workflow to the one you just
completed to create the project
initially and will allow you to provide
a different VCF and an updated pedigree
file please feel free to reach out to
the Seeker team if you have any further
questions or encounter any
difficulties thank you