The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mit.edu.
>> Anyway, uh today uh we have a guest
speaker who's the audio director for the
Singapore Academy.
That's where we are. And um and he's
going to run through brainstorming uh as
an exercise. Um but we're not actually
planning out the game that you're going
to be doing for your first assignment in
this class. I think this is a you're
doing other
>> Yeah, these will just be just be
practice. So basically the the groups
there will be a group activity involved
in this but the the things that that
that you're working on don't have to be
the same groups that you will eventually
be using for your first assignment. The
idea is just sort of to get used to the
process of brainstorming and sort of a
general rules of thumb uh and before I
spoil the entire talk.
>> Yeah that's okay. So uh yeah just my
name is Apstein. A little bit of
background on myself. Um I'm the audio
director here. Uh I've been working in
sound design uh officially for uh a
number of years now, five some odd
years. Uh unofficially uh way longer
than that. Um uh doing TV TV and video
game sound design. And then uh and then
before that I I was a high school
teacher. Um and so I think you know to
the extent that um uh talking about kind
of creative collaboration uh I have a
fair amount of experience ranging even
back to to when I was uh teaching high
school for trying to uh encourage what
what we might call organized uh
ideiation. Um I guess first I'll I'll
thank you guys for for reading uh
reading the text. Um it is it is funny.
it does have these kind of um I guess
now a little antiquated 1950s sort of
references and um you know some of his
uh some of his uh scientific evidence
for uh for for why brainstorming is good
is is not particularly well supported.
was like, "We got 95 ideas." And I was
like, "Well, how many ideas did you
get?" You know, doing it the other way
doesn't, you know, he doesn't tell you,
but hey, 95, that's a big number, you
know. So, um, you know, a little a
little bit of background about Alex
Osborne. He was, um, he was an
advertising, uh, executive. Um, and so
you can kind of see where brainstorming
and advertising is a is a creative
industry, right? It's a design industry.
And so getting multiple people in
interdisciplinary kind of you know
different skills working together um on
a on a creative project it can be a
challenge. Um and so you can see how
brainstorming came out of the work he
was doing in advertising. So um so just
to get started I I would say you know
you've read it so you have a sense but
but kind of forget what you think you
know brainstorming is. Um some of what
you think it is will apply. um some of
the most fundamental principles um to
brainstorming maybe you don't you don't
realize or you didn't realize until you
did the reading and and that's a little
bit of what I want to talk about. I
think the the foundation for his
brainstorming idea is actually really
solid and it's something something that
you know we should explore today. Um
why why brainstorming for video game
design um is an interesting question. Um
but I sort of touched on that a little
bit with relation to advertising, right?
I mean, we're talking about a creative
industry where you've got people with
various skill sets, whether they're
artists or sound designers or uh game
designers explicitly or producers. Um,
all of these people kind of existing in
a collaborative environment together.
They're bringing different things to the
table. How do you get them to to kind of
work together and and and be
collaboratively creative? And so this
is, you know, a first step in that
process. And so this is this is why
brainstorming is particularly useful um
for game design. And then the other
thing um the other thing that I I think
is important to understand and we'll
talk about it a bit more is is um the
kind of social pressures um that are
created in creative envir professional
creative environments even
non-professional actually I mean it it
would exist in an educational
environment too um you guys are all at
MIT it's one of the most prestigious
universities um you know in the world
right and so you're probably no stranger
to the idea of of kind of social
pressure in uh in the process of
ideiation, right? Um you sit there and
you say if I say this idea, am I going
to look like an idiot? Um and and
usually the outcome from that is if I
don't say anything, it's it's you know,
maybe I don't get the gain of presenting
a good idea, but I don't get the hit of
making a bad idea. And so it's like, you
know, self-preservation. It's like why
take the risk uh if if it's not worth
it. Um and so you know I think MIT is an
interesting place to talk about
brainstorming and and this kind of
organized ideation because there is you
know social and academic pressure here
too. Uh pressure to be right, pressure
to not say something that would seem
wrong and that sort of pressure is is
completely uh antithetical to the idea
of a brainstorming session. Um and so
that's that's kind of a a basis for why
not only it's good for video games but
why it's also good to talk about talk
about here at MIT. So
there are four uh basic principles of
brainstorming. Um you know these were
outlined by Alex Osborne. He he was an
ad agent. Um and uh I guess it was you
know early he says it was like 1938 when
he first started using it. People
started kind of talking about it since
then. Um and and it kind of I like when
he said it sort of spiraled out of
control that people sort of ran away
with it. They're like ah this is a great
idea but then they were they were kind
of practicing it wrong. Um and so uh you
know in in applied imaginations which is
where the text um you know you guys
read. It's sort of him reflecting on
this brainstorming idea and saying this
is really how it how it should be uh how
it should be exercised. Um the first
principle is single-handedly the most
important principle. Um and that's no
criticism. Um, that's a that's kind of a
blanket way of of saying it, but but
really in a more uh in a more um broad
sense, it's it's kind of saying uh you
know, judgment needs to be excluded. Um,
in some sense, it's kind of um kind of
both positive and negative, but but
especially you don't want to criticize
each other's work. Um, you also don't
want to spend time during a brainstorm
session talking about how good an idea
is, right? If if someone throws out an
idea um and and someone's like, "Oh,
this is the best idea. We don't even
need to keep going anymore." Then it's
like, "Oh, no. Wait, now we're not
brainstorming anymore." Um and so
really, you know, judgment is is is
absolutely supposed to be excluded from
the process. Um
I think that uh this is the primary uh
principle that goes against that social
pressure, right? Because the social
pressure of judgment, the people who are
saying, whether you have an executive
who's in charge of you, a boss who's
saying whether or not the ideas are good
or bad, or whether you have colleagues
that are saying whether or not ideas are
good or bad, that sort of social
pressure that forces people to stay
quiet and maybe hold on to good ideas or
throw away good ideas. Um, you know, if
everybody's on board with the lack of
criticism, then you you kind of have
more freedom to to kind of express
yourself. Um, you know, just just kind
of pulling back to the text a little
bit, um, you know, there was this this
great quote um from this vice president.
I just I'll read to you guys again. Uh
you know, he said, "It was hard to get
through my head uh what you were trying
to do with us. Uh my 15 years of
conference after conference in my
company have conditioned me against
shooting while um almost all of us
officers rate each other on the basis of
judgment. Uh we are far more apt to look
up to the other fellow if he makes no
mistakes than if he suggests lots of
ideas." That's something that may sound
familiar to you. Um so I've always kept
myself from spouting any suggestions
which could be sneered at. uh I wish our
people would feel free to shoot ideas
the way we have been doing in these
brainstorm sessions. And so really like
um this this lack of criticism, this
sort of creating a safe environment for
ideiation um is is the most fundamental
principle in this brainstorm. Um and it
really goes right at those social
pressures which which can stop you know
creativity and really hamper creativity.
Um any questions about that? That sort
of makes sense, right? This principle of
of no criticism. Cool. Um,
principle number two, uh, freewheeling,
as uh, Mr. Osborne likes to call it. The
wilder idea the better. This is also
hard, uh, to kind of get used to. Um,
again, it was like the guy said in that
quote, you know, you you resist the urge
to throw out something that's absolutely
crazy and absolutely wild for the fear
of ridicule. Well, if we eliminate the
fear of ridicule and we understand that
we're just trying to get every idea that
we can um then freewheeling is is
absolutely encouraged and you need to
kind of get past that um past that oh
you know this is whatever we're known
whatever like this um and I can you know
I I put up Kadamari dysi up here because
you know that that's the sort of idea
that someone throws out at a at a at a
meeting um and if there's criticism
someone will be like that's the dumbest
thing I've ever heard. you can't just
roll around picking up stuff for the
king of the cosmos. That's insane. Um
and and it probably, you know, it
probably was a synthesis of a lot of
different ideas that that kind of
created that game, which we'll talk
about later, but um really, you know,
having these like kind of wild, crazy
ideas. You may think it's over the edge,
and it might be over the edge. Um, but
it is it is way easier to make something
feasible than it is to take something
that's pretty um pretty normal and make
it make it innovative and interesting,
right? It's it's much easier to kind of
go go in that backward direction. Um,
and so really the wilder idea the idea
you can come up with the the the
stronger. Um,
any questions about principle number
two? Making sense on board? Cool. Uh,
quantity. Um, this is really the the
goal of of a brainstorming session. Come
up with as many ideas as you can, right?
Um, it it stands to reason that if you
have lots of ideas, there's a greater
likelihood that you'll have a useful one
um than if say you have two. Your
choices are limited. You didn't pick the
better of the two, I suppose, but it
might not be the best idea you have. Um,
and so really this is, you know, this
adds on to that wild idea. Throw
everything out you can. you need to just
get everything um out and everything on
on on the page um in order to even be
able to start judging it. And that's the
important thing too that that needs to
be um that needs to be clarified is that
brainstorming is a first step in a
creative process. It's not the whole
process. It's not like, oh, we've got
this creative problem that we need to
solve. We'll have a brainstorming
session, then we'll have it. Um, and
actually that's that's something that
hampers brainstorming a lot is that you
have the brainstorming session, you come
up with these great ideas and then
everybody leaves and you never return to
it or you never kind of reflect on which
of these ideas is going to be best or
you kind of just end up picking one. And
so the judgment needs to happen as well.
Um, but not now, you know, during the
brainstorm session. It's just get
everything out that you can. Um,
it it really just it kind of stands for
reason. And I I kind of made fun of
Storm when he was like, you know,
saying, well, in this inst in the
government they had 95 ideas and we you
know came up with eight good desires
which you know how many did you come up
with before but but it's true just the
more you have the better you're going to
do
and then this one is related to that
which is the idea of synthesis or
building on ideas um which is that often
times the best idea the best creative
idea is not going to be something that's
just kind of a unique idea that stands
alone in this corpus of ideas that
you've collected over the brainstorm
it's going to be an idea that is a
synthesis of of of one idea and another
or someone suggests an idea and then
that makes you think of something else
that's related to it and you kind of
build on that and and you can see in
really positive good brainstorming
sessions um there's momentum and one of
the things that can really hurt that
momentum is when people are starting to
riff on an idea then someone's like oh
but you know in other news you know we
could do this and so it's really
encouraged that you synthesize ideas if
you have that other left field idea
don't throw it away right jot it down so
that you can bring it up later but don't
don't kind of kill the momentum of the
synthesis if that's happening. Um it's
it's you know kind of really important
that you start um it's the collaborative
part of this creative uh ideiation. Um
it's this combining of ideas that's
going to create um good ideas. And
that's that's just um I I think we can
kind of take that as a given that if you
collect a bunch of skilled, thoughtful,
creative people together um combining
their ideas is going to create something
that's better than just the any one idea
that one creative uh professional is
going to have or at least just a
different solution that might be more
ideal given the problem. And so, you
know, you can think of things like, you
know, Lego's pretty awesome. Um, Star
Wars is also pretty awesome,
but you know, Lego Star Wars move is is
also awesome. You know, similarly, um,
you know, Marvel's dope. Um, Capcom's
also pretty dope. Marvel versus Capcom
is tremendously dope. So, um, you know,
building on ideas can create obviously
really interesting things and that's,
you know, it's a good idea to kind of
keep working on that in your brainstorm
sessions, like what can you what can you
put together? Um,
so how is it organized? Um, you know,
we've kind of talked about basic
principles. Any questions about those
four principles? Do they all make sense?
Do they all seem to be grounded in
the greatest? All right. Um,
so the question becomes then, how do you
organize um how do you organize your
brainstorm? One of the points that Alex
Osborne makes is that um it needs to
have a casual spirit or a casual
atmosphere. He refers to it as a picnic,
which is another one of those I haven't
been on a picnic in a really long time,
but um but you know, it's like yes, we
brought our lunches in and then we
talked afterwards. It's like what we
call those lunch meetings now. But um
but he has a good point that if um if a
large part of the brainstorming session
is intended to combat um social
pressures that stop you from being
creative, that inhibit your creativity,
then it would stand to reason that
creating a casual spirit, a casual
environment um for this process is
important. Um, and so I have, you know,
it's hard to most video game processes
and most video game companies have a
pretty casual spirit and environment
because of the nature of the work in
general. Um, so sometimes this might not
be that hard, but um, you know, things
to consider are like what is the makeup
of your team, right? If there's, you
know, if your president of the company
does a really bad job of putting himself
or herself on the same level as all the
people, you might want to exclude that
person from the brainstorming session
because then everybody's going to feel
the pressure of the president, you know,
and we, you know, do we need to make an
idea that makes that person happy. It's,
you know, you have to think these things
through in terms of what the environment
is going to be for your brainstorming
session and and who's involved. Um, so
it it is an important point is an
important step. um you know starting
with a a bad or or a worthless idea uh
encourages that freewheeling sense. Um
you know a lot of times people will
contribute ideas that feel safe. Again
you want to come up with the most ideas
that you can. Um so you know having
someone with the courage or even
bringing to the beginning of it a a
crazy worthless bad freewheeling idea
can help kind of encourage people to
keep doing that. So, um, you know,
either starting with someone who has a
crazy idea or even bringing it to the
brainstorm at the very beginning can be
a really good thing as well. Um, this is
kind of a key one. Don't uh don't
interrupt anyone. Um, it it's really
important in a brainstorming session to
encourage um that every voice is heard.
Um, you know, there's there's these kind
of uh let me see if I can find that
quote from that one guy. Um, yeah, here
we go. Um, it's great. I was think up or
think up or shut up.
>> Oh, well, yeah, there's that one, too,
which is a good one. Yeah, but um uh let
me just It's talking about the spirit of
a brainstorm session is important. Uh
self- encouragement is needed almost as
much as mutual encouragement. Uh a
perfectionism complex will throttle
effort and abort ideas. Uh he says, "One
of the ablest members kept mom
throughout one of our sessions. I button
hold him, never heard that expression,
afterward and begged him to spout
whatever ideas might come to his mind in
our next meeting." And this is this is
where it gets good. this is the, you
know, really able uh member of this ad
team. He says, "All right, I'll try."
Uh, but here's what happened. After our
first meeting, I jotted down about 15
ideas with the thought that I would
bring them to our next session. When I
looked them over, I decided they were
worthless, so I just tore up the list.
Um, and you know, Alice kind of goes on
to say, "It took a while to encourage
this guy to understand that there's no
such thing as a worthless idea. Um, that
that it can either be expanded upon or
revise." And that's kind of that
synthesis thing, right? that that you
know having a wild idea and and um you
know getting back to this idea of the
interruption. Nothing will stop a person
from wanting to contribute if um more
than than not being able to even have
their voice be heard, right? Like
they're trying to say something and then
they just get cut out by somebody else
who's like, "No, but this is better." Um
you know, especially for a shy person or
a person who's otherwise feeling like my
ideas are worthless. Um they they won't
be able to get it out because they've
then been they've then been cut short.
Um so this you know some of this
responsibility falls on what we might
call the leader which I'll talk about
later of of the of the group. Um but
really it it's kind of a collective
responsibility that everybody kind of um
make sure that as someone is expressing
an idea that it's maintained. Adding to
that you know
keep the keep the description of your
idea short. Um you know if people are
sitting here and it's like you've now
hijacked the 30 minute brainstorming
session with your one idea that took
five minutes to explain. um that that
can also hamper it, right? Part of it is
not only don't interrupt people, but
also make sure that when you are
contributing, you are allowing for other
people to contribute as well. Um
something that maybe is not considered
as much. Um for the organization,
designate a leader. I hate that term,
but that's what he used in the book. Um
I I tend to use the term clerk, which is
kind of a quaker idea, which I I kind of
grab on to. A clerk, you know, being
more of a facilitator than an actual
leader. Um you know, leader suggests,
you know, boss. It's always not great
for a for a, you know, everyone's even
sort of brainstorming session. Um, and
then of course the secretary or as he
calls it an associate theater. Um, you
know, this is someone who who writes
stuff down. You know, there's some of
that that good old fashioned hierarchy
going on in this in this text, but um
but you know, obviously we'll talk a
little bit more about what the roles of
these people are, but but having those
those roles uh defined early is
important. Um,
and then this is this is something to
talk about a bit explaining the process
and the principal question at the start
of the session. Um, you know, I don't
know how how many of you had heard of
these four principles of brainstorming
explicitly prior to reading this text?
Anybody? Oh, well,
I know you heard from me. But, um, but
yeah, the um, you know, the process is
something that it needs to be clear
otherwise people won't remember to do.
And you'll see when we do the exercise,
it's it's even hard sometimes to curb
your criticism. You know, it's it's just
when especially when you're comfortable
with people and you may not mean it in a
malicious way. You may not mean it in a
way to kind of uh you know stop the
brainstorming session, but you just be
like, "Oh, that's nuts." You know, we're
laughing and everybody's having a good
time. And then you kind of like think
back and like wait, you know, that was
me passing judgment on an idea and
possibly inhibiting the kind of the kind
of ideation that we're trying to get
across. So, um explaining the process at
the beginning regardless of the group is
really important and that is usually
responsibility that falls on the leader
or the secretary, whoever is organizing
the session, right? They even suggest in
the text have it posted have the four
principles up so that everybody can kind
of remind themselves through the process
what these four principles are. Um but
explaining the process is really
important and this this is I can't even
this is so important. Um having the
principal question and the goal of the
brainstorming session clear at the start
um you know obviously it's it's this is
encouraging freewheeling. It's
encouraging free thought. that's
encouraging this all kind of you know
wide openen creativity and yet at the
same time if you do that in an unbounded
sort of way you might end up with things
that that really in the end you don't
have too many useful ideas you've got
useful ideas for something else not for
the actual creative problem that you
have. So, I mean, you take it from an ad
ad concept, you know, so you've got a
vodka company that's like, "Oh, we need
we need an advertisement for our, you
know, awesome vodka or whatever." And
so, you're like, "All right, well, we
have a brainstorm session." Then a bunch
of people come up with ideas. Now,
you're selling dryers. Um, because it
was wide open, right? And it's like,
"Oh, we've got these great ad ideas for
dryers, but they're just really, really
not going to work." You know, bringing
it back to a video game contest. um you
know, you've got a contract with a
producer to make a first-person shooter,
and in your brainstorming session,
you've designed um a cool cute
platformer. Um neat, but that's not
where the money's coming from, right?
So, so bounding the brainstorm session
is important, too. And and you'll kind
of see that in the exercises that we do
today, how it's important to to bound
that. Um
yes.
Oh, and write down everything. Yeah,
sorry, I forgot about that. This is an
important uh important question. Uh
important point um you know you this
happens to all of us but you have this
great idea and then you don't write it
down and then you you go to bed and then
the next day you're like oh I had this
great idea great idea and you can't
remember it right and so um writing down
everything is absolutely essential.
You'll never you know you'd be amazed
the number of times that you know a week
later you're like oh we could put these
two ideas together um as long as you can
remember what those ideas were. Um, and
so what you think, you know, it's hard
to not mentally pass judgment on things
during the brainstorm session. And what
you think might be great now may a week
later not be as great and what you
didn't think, you know, will be. And so
making sure to have everything written
down is really important. And and they
even suggest, you know, having um two
secretaries if you need if you've got a
large group or lots of ideas and they're
each writing every other one um can be
helpful to make sure that you get
everything right so that you get
everything. So um
next is the question of what sort of
problems are suitable to a brainstorming
session. Uh the great example that Alex
Osborne gives is um setting up a
brainstorm session on whether or not to
get married um is not a particularly
suitable question. I that was sort of an
interesting uh interesting concept. He's
like well to decide to get married you
you apparently list the pros and cons.
That's not exactly the process I went
through before I got married. I was like
well honey I'm going to have to write
this down. Um
but fair enough that that wasn't the
suggestion that he came up with. And he
has a good point, right? I mean it's the
question of whether or not to get
married is a judgment call. Um it is not
a creative uh ideation process. And so
that's not a particularly useful um kind
of uh problem that's suitable to the
brainstorming process. Um you know, you
want you want a uh you want a problem
that is going to be benefited by having
a large uh a large selection, a large
corpus of ideas. And so those are the
kind of problems that are more more
useful. And you know, you'll see when we
do our example exercise what some of
those might be. Um I also kind of put
here that um you know having a clear
definition of the aim is really
essential. It's sort of what we talked
about before. Um you need to make sure
that everybody understands and
everybody's on the same page. Otherwise
you end up with stuff that um that might
be useful for something else but not
useful for what you're you're
particularly trying to do. Um and so
making that clear for everybody is
really important. Um, keeping the
problem as simple as possible, um, you
know, is also really important. Trying
to keep simple language, uh, for the
problem. Uh, keep it, you know, keep it
constrained in a way that that, um, is
simple enough so that people can kind of
work on it as opposed to just feeling
limited by it. Um, if that makes any
sense. You know, something is overly
complicated and overly constrained. Um,
then it becomes a well, how do I fit
everything into this? You know, how do I
match every single one of these things?
If it's simpler, then it's a little bit
easier to kind of work on and kind of be
creative. So, keeping problems simple.
Um, which isn't to say that complex
problems couldn't be dealt with, but
just divide this divide them into sub
problems, right? Divide them into little
little sections. So, there might be
something like, you know, how could we
deal with the UI? Um, you know, how
could it look in this uh in this game,
you know? So, rather than say, well, how
are we going to design our first person
shooter? You've got a brainstorming
session about what the UI could look
like for the first person shooter.
you've got maybe a brainstorming session
for um you know what the fiction for
this first person shooter might be.
You're dividing it into sub problems
rather than having it be this gigantic
you know model of of a thing. And you
can see how that would be a problem,
right? Because if you just brainstorm on
what's our first person shooter going to
be, you're going to get ideas about the
UI. You're going to get ideas about the
fiction. You're going to get ideas about
what sort of guns you should use or what
they should sound like. And it'll just
be lots of interesting ideas but we get
all over the place.
uh and yeah uh problems should be
clearly and simply articulated. I think
that's what I sort of said by should be
simple just you know make sure that
they're articulated in the simple way.
Sometimes you can have a simple problem
that's not articulated particularly
clearly. Um so it's just something um
responsibilities of the leader clerk
whatever um
the first being uh to understand and
explain the problem and the aim of the
brainstorm session. I mean a lot of
times people uh maybe will write a memo
beforehand um you know as the
facilitator of the of the thing as the
person who perhaps wants to see the
brainstorm be a success uh the most
maybe um you know having a clear
understanding of the problem and
explaining that to the group is an
important job for the leader um I use
this term facilitating the session uh
encouraging ideiation discouraging
criticism you're kind of the watch guard
for the process not necessarily um you
can sometimes be a contributor and a
watchdog for the process. But most
importantly is that you are a watchdog
for the process. Um it's you'll you'll
see as we do it, it's just so easy to
kind of slip into these conversational
habits that are contrary to
brainstorming uh brainstorming process
and uh and so having someone who's
constantly like making sure don't
criticize encouraging people like oh I
haven't heard from this person. Do you
have any ideas? You know, even kind of
pulling people out is important. Um and
that comes to that ensuring that no
voices are lost during the discussion,
right? I mean we had that abbleist
member who had 15 ideas that he wrote
down and he's like they're worthless.
Well, in some ways it's the part of the
leader either during the session or
after the session to try to encourage,
you know, those able members to
contribute. Um yeah, I mean it's some of
the most crackpot ideas become the best
ones. So you really want to make sure
every voice is heard. Um and then
encouraging the synthesis, encouraging
people to kind of riff on other ideas.
Um you know, trying to find ways for
people to build on each other even
offering synthesis towards a direction.
So maybe you have a couple ideas you're
like, "Oh, like you know, one and 10 are
kind of similar, but like you know, are
there any ways we can combine this?" And
like, "Yeah, we could, you know, give
him a helmet." Awesome.
So on so forth. I don't know what what
two things can combine to get a helmet,
but can't get shot in the head. How
about a helmet? All right. Um, so
responsibilities for the secretary. most
obviously record every and all ideas.
It's like write it all down. You have to
write it all down. This is so important.
Um this one is often overlooked. Uh
monitoring the schedule and the duration
of the session. Um something I learned a
long long long time ago is one of the
worst things that can happen is meetings
that run over or meetings that start
late or meetings um you know that don't
adhere to a schedule. no no better way
to kind of uh you know lose your
employees or lose your staff um than to
to kind of bite into their time. Um and
so you know making sure that it's
constrained and that it meets the
duration is really important. And so you
know may seem simple but timing the
thing. Um and then of course if
applicable participating in the
brainstorming you know like I said all
voices um all voices should be heard and
that you know oftentimes would mean that
the secretary is a uh is a creative
professional as well. Um And so make
sure that you participate quickly.
So
we've got a few exercises now to get you
acclimated to the idea of brainstorming.
Um the first one is an actual individual
brainstorm. So uh if you have paper,
grab some paper.
If anyone's lacking either writing
equipment or paper,
>> you could use a note card, too. It's
really just something to write on other
than the table.
Not cards are totally fine.
>> Um, I'll, as you guys are getting ready,
I'll continue to talk. This is actually
something that I didn't mention in the
process, but what is actually very
useful to the brainstorming process. I
think doing warm-ups before your actual
brainstorm is useful. Um, you know,
people show up just for lunch,
especially because one of those eating.
Um, you know, people, you know,
sometimes they're tired. People just
might have other things on the brain.
So, getting getting in the habit,
getting warmed up to uh being creative,
um, is important. I I tend to find it's
a rare it's a rare kind of person who
you just sort of give a blank piece of
paper to and you're like, "Ah, make
something. Go be creative." And they're
like, they just like whip something out,
right? You got you got to kind of get
warmed up. Um, you know, visual artists
sketch constantly and that that makes
sense and I make film sketches. Um, I I
just make dumb pieces of music that I'll
maybe never use for anything, but maybe
I will. Um, who knows? I make stupid
sound effects in the shower. Um, I
consider that warming up for work. Um,
so, uh, you know, you have to kind of
get warmed up. And so, this is just a
really quick five minute, uh, five
minute warm up. And the idea is, um,
write anything that comes to your mind
for this specific problem. And I'll show
you a picture. brainstorm possible uses.
It's not really brainstorm. It's more of
just like a you individually come up
with creative ideas uh creative uses uh
for the following item and I'll give you
five minutes starting now.
All right.
Hopefully was good for a warm up. Quick
question and show
and be honest.
This is a safe mind.
How many of you had an idea that you did
not write down? How many of you self
censored yourself with an idea?
Yeah. You're like, "Oh, that's just
dumb." See, it's really it's hard to get
out of the habit of doing that. It's
hard to get out of this kind of this
habit of self- judgment. Um, and it's
really important. Um, you know, that
that dumb idea that you think was
worthless might be a good one. Does
anyone who raised their hand want to
share what their censored idea was? just
to exercise the demons, so to speak.
>> No, nothing.
>> All right. Who wants to share some ideas
that they did write down? All right.
Here we go.
>> See, I have a lot.
>> Yeah. Well, throw throw us a couple that
are your favorite.
>> See, lockpick, MacGyver, connecting
circuits.
>> There you go.
>> Carrying cards, um, a knife, clothes
hanger, chopsticks, a dowster, um, stir.
See, connect batteries. Air of tires
emote tool nose picker
>> staple. A staple
>> and a paper bra. I have a lot of things.
>> Yeah. Good. No, that's awesome.
>> All right. I got Let's see. Um
fingernail cleaner, an eyelash
straightener, basically a rail gun ammo,
a balloon annihilator, and an official
Tamagotchi TM resetter.
>> Yeah. resets a lot of things. How about
over the side? Yeah.
>> Catch fish with it by turning into
scratch messages with it. Use it as a
key ring. Conduct electricity with it.
Make it into jewelry. Um fix umbrellas
and what have you with it, which I've
done before.
Money clip. Use it as a skewer for
cooking.
uh put it on top of a door and so when
people open it falls on the ground you
know somebody's been in your room
>> oil
accessory
that's a good question
>> uh I had a hair styling accessory
projectile something you could mel down
to for metal and porn out stuff.
>> Uh that's something you could bend and
put on chairs and people sit down and
poke them. Um modern art. Um I thought
of you could like try to get a bunch and
fill a dorm room with it as a prank or
something. Um toothpick
hold stuff open for emergency surgery.
>> Cool.
I thought you could uh bend it into an
interesting flat shape and then put it
in ink and use it as a stamp.
>> Very nice. Very cool. Um cool. Yeah. Go
ahead.
>> Uh game bits and tokens holder for
dipping something into liquids. Um pie
clips and keeping small boards together.
>> Sure.
>> Mini rock garden.
Good
>> heat generator. If you uh work hard in
it by bending it and then bending it and
then it gets hot.
>> Very nice.
>> As long as it doesn't break.
>> I think of a souvenir as a totem for a
lost robot.
>> That's good.
>> You say that again.
>> Let's say like there's a robot made by
human but it's lost in space. They have
to remind it become like a secret thing.
>> Yeah. My favorite use for a paperclip is
cleaning the lint out of my uh iPhone
ear jack, which drives me absolutely
nuts. So, I'm running on reserve battery
power and my slideshow has been
suspended on in my office. There's a uh
there's a air.
So, um
so yeah, how did we feel about that
exercise? Got you loosened up a little
bit. Got you thinking about some ideas.
Got you feeling a little creative juices
fine. We've got three more exercises
that we're going to do. Um,
so much brainstorming.
This is the hardest work I've ever done
to get my chicken. No. Um, yeah. So,
we've got a few more exercise to get you
guys kind of comfortable, get you guys,
you know, relaxed with this kind of
brainstorming process. The next one is
going to be a group exercise. Um, I'm
going to wait to describe it until I can
get uh get my slideshow. Anybody else
have any particularly choice paperclip
ideas? Start one.
>> A sign sine wave generator.
>> Very good.
wireframe doll.
>> All right.
>> Hold up. Stop looking at
it like as a spear.
>> Oh, yeah.
Man versus Wild like catch fish with it
or
>> something to chew on.
>> Launcher rubber band launcher
>> letting air out tires.
You heard of the guy who had an
oversized red tape equip and ended up
trading it for a house
[Applause]
towards a house.
>> Pretty cool. So, so hopefully that got
you loosened up. I do want to just
emphasize again for those of you who
raised your hand and even those of you
who did not raise your hand because you
were censoring the truth because you're
afraid try not to self censor. Um really
it's important to brainstorming. I bet
some
>> Yeah, I know. Stop self-centering. I bet
I bet those crappy ideas that you write
down are actually really awesome. So um
activity number two uh we're going to
work as one large group. Um this is our
con shell. Doesn't look like one, I
know, but um you know the principle
still applies. Um this is just to kind
of get us in the habit in the shape of
uh kind of speaking one at a time uh not
interrupting each other. Um and in some
senses building on each other's ideas
too, right? There's something in the
physical kind of passing of the ball
after you've heard someone's idea that
might encourage that sort of synthesis
of ideas as you're going. Um I will be
your fearless leader. Um all that means
is I just kind of make sure you're not
interrupting each other. Um uh and we're
going to brainstorm solutions to uh a a
design problem. Uh this one I think is
actually a lot of fun. Um so I will show
you the design problem. I will maybe
throw out an idea and then I will toss
the con shell to first person who wants
it and then it doesn't have to come back
to me. Just anyone who wants it throw up
your hand and we'll kind of keep moving
around. Please close the lids on your
drinks.
put put away put away your crystal stuff
that you don't want to shatter. Um, so
we will take approximately 15 minutes on
this. We'll see how our momentum goes.
Um, so you just finished updating Tetris
for Xbox Live Arcade. Awesome. I don't
know how you got the rights, but that's
great. Um, Microsoft is demanding a set
of achievements uh for integrating the
game into their online service because
unless you have achievements, it's not a
real game. Um,
so we are going to brainstorm possible
player achievements uh for your new
version of Tetris. You know what
achievements are, right? Those little
things that pop up on your Xbox every
time you do anything. Um, so that is our
idea for Tetris achievements. And I'll
start. Uh, how about for actually
getting four lines? You get a Tetris
achievement must be next.
>> Uh, you get an achievement for losing as
quickly as possible, which I think would
just be like Very good.
>> Getting three lines with S piece.
>> Uh drawing some sort of unique little
picture with the Tetris blocks like uh
you know something perhaps
>> putting one of each block down.
>> Uh lasting for a certain amount of time
without them ever getting above a
certain height.
a certain amount of time without ever
rotating a piece.
>> Modern Tetris games have a system where
you can rotate indefinitely when your
piece is down. So, you rotate
indefinitely for a minute or two or
three minutes.
>> Lasting a certain amount of time without
ever clearing a line with a straight
piece.
Putting your piece down underneath
another piece
>> into a little hole.
>> The teeth.
>> There you go. Spelling USSR with your
pieces.
>> How's the bathroom?
>> Um, making like a congeration of all the
pieces into like the shape of a regular
piece.
>> Very cool.
Uh, basically only moving the pieces in
B to the music that's playing
>> spelling your say with your pieces. I
don't know if it's possible, but doing
it.
>> Uh, high score and high score without
clearing lines.
>> Uh, managing to clear the entire board
in a game that has already reached the
top line but not quite.
putting a piece down without actually uh
looking at the piece at all.
>> Most pieces per time.
>> Sure.
>> One day of continuous tetris
marathon
>> breaking the previous high.
Only ever shifting pieces either right
or the left the entire game.
>> Ah,
>> doing the marathon challenge but only
listening to one piece of music the
entire time.
>> The same
>> clearing a level by dropping pieces
before they fall five spaces.
>> All right.
>> Rotating every single piece that you
play.
>> Oh, very good.
uh never going above a certain line for
a certain amount of time.
>> All of the above but on different equity
levels
>> uh clearing three lines with a T.
>> Sure.
>> Starting up the game,
>> clearing a kind of screen
>> using the L block.
Doesn't matter how.
different color. So, you know, lines
always
>> rotating a piece 720
>> only matching pieces such that the new
blocks that fall down are touching
blocks of the same color.
>> Clear two four block segments with two
consecutive uh lines.
Uh, clearing a level using only
tetrises.
>> Sorry, you can't talk anymore.
>> Challenging somebody on your friends
list to beat the score.
>> Um, fighting against someone on friends
list to lose faster.
>> Having no holes in the block for
Yeah.
Uh, inviting a friend on one of your
Xbox Live friends to play with you.
>> Five consecutive line clears.
>> Beating one of your friends on Xbox Live
when you play with them.
>> Losing to a friend on Xbox Live.
>> Playing with a friend for one hour
continuously one day.
Beating a score set by the original
creator of Tetris.
>> Clearing a line somewhere above the
first line. The first line only has one
block filled in.
>> I think it definitely is.
>> Someone's going to have ideas. There's
an idea.
lose all the telem
>> losing 100 times.
>> Yeah.
>> Playing on increasingly ridiculous
difficulties with achievements for each
four speeds.
using the speed
>> completing a Tetris challenge, which is
presumably some kind of thing where you
have to drop blocks in the right
sequence in order to clear all the
lines. Yeah.
>> Clearing a thousand lines.
>> Uh playing invisible mode.
>> Uh playing for a certain amount of time
while holding down the down key
continuously.
>> I don't know if you only rotating in one
direction always. I don't know if
someone said that or not.
>> Getting 10 achievements in Tetris.
>> Getting every achievement in
>> the Tetris.
>> Oh no. How can you get it?
>> It's a paradox. It's impossible.
>> Always having blocks on the far left and
on the far right column.
Cool.
I think that that had some that had some
decent momentum, but you know, I think
like our mission was accomplished,
right? Like we were really only giving
one idea at a time because it was only
the person who had the ball was talking.
Um that, you know, probably with a
little bit more speed and momentum, but
it was nice. Like we did had a little
building on ideas. You know, we're
starting to get this kind of brainstorm.
There was still some shyness, which is,
you know, people have different
personalities, but stop being shy.
You're allowed to have your different
personalities, but stop it. No. Um, so
that's activity number two. Um,
any questions about that process? How do
you feel about it? Any thoughts on it
before we go on to the next activity?
>> All right, next activity. Actually, this
might be this is our last activity.
Sorry, I said, but there's only three.
>> Um, okay. So, this one is a more formal
uh a more formal uh brainstorm. And
actually, I screwed up that last one. We
didn't have a secretary. So all of those
great Tetris ideas are now lost. I can't
remember any.
>> Oh yes.
[Applause]
>> Do we not have that 1950s or something?
>> Let me just get these waxers.
So uh what we're going to do is we're
going to separate the two design teams.
Um so it'll just totally be by by
location. We'll just kind of get half of
you over here and half of you over
there. Um, I want the team to designate
one leader. That's gonna be the person
who's responsible. Clerk for
facilitating it. Oh, did I say clerk
there? A leader and a secretary. It's
supposed to be a clerk, leader, and a
secretary. Um, so one person to write
everything down, one person to obviously
facilitate and and we're going to do a
we're going to do a kind of a 20 or so
minute uh brainstorm uh for a game
pitch. Um, what do I mean by game pitch?
It's kind of think of the uh think of
the you're in an elevator with Miiamoto
or you're in an elevator with you know
Philip Han and uh you have this game
idea that you need to pitch but you're
only going to the 10th floor or so and
so really you've got like 30 seconds a
minute 2 minutes maybe um to kind of get
the core information about this game
app. Um so that can be something like a
title maybe a tagline for it um any main
features uh you might have for it. Um,
of course it would be way too easy or
way actually crazy for me to be like any
game at all because there's lots of
different types of games obviously. So
it's going to be a game based on the
following constraint. So what I'd like
to do first before I give you the
constraint is let's divide ourselves in
half. We can kind of draw this like
imaginary line diagonally dividing the
two of you back there and and we'll just
get we just get one half here.
And once I give you the constraint,
we'll actually find a separate room for
for the other team for one of the teams.
>> You're stuck on the little wire.
>> That's an achievement right there.
>> I always think that when I'm watching my
like
think like something happens,
>> especially when someone
you watch this movie.
If someone has a piece of paper, they
can down there, right?
>> Yeah, just write out a piece of paper.
So, um, so these are your teams. You
guys will go into that room. You guys
stay out here. Um, as soon as I give you
the constraint, designate a designate a
clerk/ leader, um, leader and a
secretary, someone to write everything
down because our groups are relatively
small, right? We can have the leader and
the uh the secretary involved in the
brainstorming process. Please don't be
afraid of contributing. But if you are
designated as this leader, keep in mind
your primary responsibility is
facilitating the brainstorm. You want to
make sure it runs smoothly. You want to
make sure people are not criticizing
ideas. You want to make sure that it's
going okay. Any questions on this before
I give you your constraints?
Everything make sense? All good. Okay.
Here are the constraints for the game.
Uh it must have zombies. It must have a
love. It must be massively multiplayer.
Um so that those are the constraints for
your game. that's what the publisher is
going to give you money for. Um uh so
you need to develop a pitch a pitch for
this game idea. Um a title tagline what
what have you. All right. So you guys
we'll we'll take you in this room over
here. You guys stay here. Designate a
leader and a secretary and then start
brainstorming.
Secretary
>> Oh, I love this. It's like I don't want
to be the leader. I don't want to be the
secretary.
>> I said I'll do it. Oh
secretary. Wait, he wanted to be the
secretary.
>> Oh, you're secretary.
>> One of your secretary wants to use
leader. So you get a leader then.
>> Because you're interested in those game
and you lost.
>> Brings up the age question.
>> If they're both vampires or they're both
zombies, does it count as necessities
manages to have
>> encompass all of those except the
massively multiplayer parties licensed
title right there. Make it Nazi zombies.
Two Nazi zombie. No, a forbidden love. A
Nazi zombies in love with like an allied
zombie
>> and Jewish.
>> Yes.
>> And then it's So there's two factions.
It could be Well, they're all people
like online. One group there's like two
factions. There's the ally group and the
axis group.
>> What if What if they're all Nazis?
>> What What What if there's two factions?
There's the zombies and the humans and
they're drawn into war because there's a
love there's a love story between a a
zombie and a human and the leaders get
pissed over this and so we're in war
because of of like Rome and Julietesque
zombie humans.
>> What you're saying is we're having
intelligent zombies.
>> Yeah, intelligent zombies.
>> Well, clearly they're semi-intm
Hitler into this though just because
it's Nazis. There must be a zombie
Hitler. Who said this?
>> Wait, what is your name?
>> Bobby.
>> What is your name?
>> What is your name? Jason.
>> Brian. On Jason's idea of is it
necrophilia? I I think because there's a
love story, the title could be necroilia
question mark.
>> Is it?
>> Is it nec?
>> Is it necroilia?
>> Probably. Probably.
>> Is it I like it as a love story, but is
it a sex story?
>> So, wait. How about this?
>> Or maybe even zombie strippers that fall
in love with.
>> Have you seen Zombie Strippers?
>> No.
>> It's a terrible, wonderful, terrible
movie.
>> I'll watch it.
>> You should not. Should
>> um So the actually how about we have the
zombies as the good guys? That way like
the allies are trying to like make a
weapon that will destroy like half the
world and the zombies are like, "No,
that will be bad. Let's make everyone
else obvious so they agree with us."
Well,
>> what if what if
>> what if you're just a zombie and
everyone is trying to kill you, so you
want to make everyone zombies so the
world will be peaceful and happy.
>> You want everyone to love you.
>> Yeah,
>> I like that a lot.
>> And that's then
even better. Love zombies. Like, who
says they have to be undead? They can be
infected by emotion.
>> That's a tagline right there.
>> Nudest zombies. What if what if like 95%
of the world is zombie and so then the
weird creatures that are like scary are
the humans and they're like sentient
they do weird things but the zombies all
are happy and love each other.
>> Maybe the humans have the love disease.
>> They're trying to zombies
like they're infecting zombies with
love.
>> So then each person would be I either
start as a zombie or a human. They have
to complete a bunch of little tasks
before they can come, you know, and they
like play challenges against each other.
So be like zombie against zombie and one
of them is infected, one of them isn't.
>> So humans can infect zombies with blood
that makes them not zombies.
>> What if no zombies? What what if what if
there's a dynamic what what if there's a
dynamic between so there's there's two
factions zombies and humans and every
player is given a match and in this
massive multiplayer world that one of
their main objectives is to find their
match who's in the opposing faction
buried deep among hostile hordes of
either humans or zombies find them and
like live happily ever after together
>> and become either zombies or humans
together.
>> Correct.
>> But love zombies
>> find a cure or just get bitten
>> and become love zombies.
>> Love zombies.
Ask the question. Is there truly a
difference between being in love and
being undead?
>> That's a great tagline.
>> Maybe some task.
>> What's even more blind? Having your eyes
guided out by a zombie or being in love?
>> So, so then we can draw it into not the
actual Nazi zombie game.
>> Maybe the Nazi zombies from the other
point of view. So, they're just trying
to have love and and the humans are
trying to kill them.
Um,
>> wait. Are we having Nazis?
>> We can.
>> Some of the ideas can include Nazis and
some of them can't and we can decide.
>> Should we be getting to the point of
judgment towards the end of the thing so
we can finalize a pitch in a thing or
whatever? Just just come up
>> with just brainstorming. That's awesome.
>> Yeah, it's just fun.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> How about um the player is a human
fighting against the zombies and you
have some kind of companion may or may
not be a cube but that accompanies you
on your journey to defeat the zombies.
>> So companion cube I like better.
>> Do plants love each other?
>> That way that is a heart like that's
like a love story between you and your
cube.
>> But can the can the cube become a
zombie?
>> Yes.
>> I mean it could be a person like Left
for Dead. like four people against all
the zombies that they're always
>> or witches. Maybe you're trying to get
>> the love story is you and the witch
consuming the thing and like
>> what if so all players play zombies and
most missions are stuff like you have to
infect a city and just run around like
binding people into the entire city that
you've like conquered or turned into
zombified. Your ultimate goal is that
your girlfriend from back when you were
human or your boyfriend from back when
you were human is at some place and you
want to infect all cities until you can
get there and then infect her so that
you guys can live happily ever after.
>> A you could also
>> also building on the idea of being
zombies trying to infect cities.
>> Oh god,
>> you are zombies uh with Cupid's love
arrows
>> trying to infect the entire city with
love at which point no no productivity
is all gone in the city. zombie with
love arrows infecting people.
>> It could be set in the 1950s where
everyone's like trying to be productive
and not love each other.
>> No, what if what if you build along the
lines of, you know, having to infect the
city, but you have to do that. One
zombie can't infect an entire city,
right? So, you have to like ally with
other zombies, but they're like
different factions of zombies. Kind of
like two zombie mob families, right,
that are trying to infect. They have two
different, you know, varieties of this
lovely in
>> Oh, wait. Could there be like a drug
trade? So like the like they have to
infect people with like a certain drug.
So it's like a drug war as well. And
this the three swords good swords are
cool.
>> Zombie.
>> What if
>> what if when you have a zombie virus
instead of wanting to eat people you are
overcome with an urge to passionately
make out with them. And if you make out
with somebody then they turn into a love
zombie too. And so there's no like
decomposition going on so much as there
is like hordes of people running through
streets trying to passionately make out
with each other. So wait
>> being decaying and like decrepit. W
zombies suddenly become very attractive.
So you
>> wait and they start like they start like
taking care of their appearance and
stuff.
>> So when is limit is there I'm well after
the zombies make out.
>> What what's next?
>> Well they get for
Okay. So what if we just like make a
like World of Warcraft type of MMO but
every player player humans you have a
zombie companion
>> pet zombie?
>> Yeah zombie
peties
>> no but they had
>> the dead Pokemon. No, they had a pet as
a pet.
>> I think it's called
>> Ph. It's like I think
>> it's a movie called Phto.
>> I've not seen it, but
>> I've seen the trailer.
>> So, what if you have to fight like with
Pokemon zombies
different powerups?
>> Different kinds of zombies like uh like
Left 4 Dead. There's, you know, the big
fat ones that like vomit and you know,
>> spitters. I hate spitters. But smokers.
Smokers are the worst.
>> Well, instead of pyro, you have blood
potions. Man, he said smokers are the
worst. That sounds like a dating s.
I do I like the Pokemon idea. So, you
can have um instead of like you're
humans, but you just have to capture all
the poke like different types of zombies
and then you fight other people with
their zombies and it's like match for
zombie versus zombie.
What if the love story is not for the
player, but is in is in the story of the
game in that the reason that you're
waging war at the moment is because
you're trying to steal a cure to
zombieism because your fearless leader
20 ranks up, you're president of
whatever's girlfriend has been zombified
or his wife has been zombified. And so
the whole game, you're all the means in
a quest to to try to find this cure, but
you don't realize you're trying to find
a cure for it's not for like your use or
your girlfriend's use or whatever of
people you love. It's for your leaders.
>> And what if she is actually the leader
of the zombies and
>> Oh crap.
>> What if the zombies are aliens?
>> Zombie aliens.
>> The blood. What if the zombies are
ninjas?
>> Yes.
>> You can learn a lot.
>> Combine the Pokemon of zombie ID with
like the Sims where you like have a
zombie that's under your control and
you're trying to like teach your zombie
to love and like maybe you're a
different avatar. like a human avatar
and you go through quests where you like
take your zombie places and teach your
zombie things
>> and not to bite people and
>> yeah exactly like I don't I don't know
train your zombie
>> maybe have so with the whole thing with
the ninja pir ninja zombies might not
have pirate pirates as well pirate
zombies maybe
>> pirate versus ninja
>> zombies
>> zombie edition special edition
>> in space wrapped in bacon
>> yes
>> time traveling zombies
I would be a great game to make just
like pirate zombies versus ninja zombies
in space wrapped in bacon and just make
that game great.
>> So is it necia probably
>> pirate edition the ninja.
>> So maybe you should divide into little
sub brainstorms for like a name tagline
all that. Do we as a name do we have
anyone more brainstorming?
I think we should figure out like a
mechanic that works. So far, we have a
lot of ideas about like what the game
world is. We have no idea like how you
play the game. So, maybe more
brainstorming on that then.
>> Yeah.
>> It's massive multiplayer. ones working
such as typical WoW style RPG, typical
passive player FPS,
Pokemon style RPG,
>> Pokemon seem like Pokemon FPS
>> or as we were saying before like The
Sims Online.
>> The Sims Online was so good.
>> Did you play as a Pokemon?
>> Yeah, maybe play as a Pokemon, but it's
a first person shooter.
>> But more like,
>> but you still have like an RPG first
person shooter as Pokemon. Wait
a
>> zombie.
>> Wait, you have to you have to fight you
have battles with uh words like uh
Monkey Island.
>> I like that text based zombie love.
>> Text based zombie love.
>> And then his really really long tongue
down your throat.
>> Zombie make out.
>> Son of a title. So, if it's massively
multiplayer, what if you, you know, you
randomly get paired with five other
players who are playing this game and
you all have some kind of task you have
to complete and you're given these
particular zombie Pokemon that you can
use to complete this particular task.
>> So, you working those with those five.
>> Wait, we have zombie pokeballs.
>> What?
>> We have a title.
>> So, uh, Necroilia
with F E L.
>> The first zombie sex game.
Oh no.
>> What if wait if it's going to be popular
in Japan? You have to have tentful
somewhere.
>> What if you are a zombie and all the
players are zombies and the NPCs are the
humans and you like try to go on quests
to make yourself more attractive and
like learn human customs and you get
points for like seducing humans.
>> Yes.
>> You have to make sure your your brain
speed meter doesn't get too low though.
>> So you have to eat them in seduce them
in. And then if you like eat them with
certain you
>> eat the ones you don't want.
>> You Yeah,
>> that actually sounds like a fun vampire
game. I'm going to put that out there.
You're a vampire. You have to seduce a
human female to bring back to drink.
>> It's like prototype or or you have to
seduce a human because you want to
seduce a human, but at the same time you
have to eat humans. So you have to hide
the fact you're eating humans for the
human decision.
>> Oh, I see. So you have a human
girlfriend and then like you eat other
humans.
>> Like while she's not looking like it's
true.
>> Have you been eating other girlfriends
without me? Where's my stepdad? Uh,
>> about that.
>> Oh, that's who that guy was. I thought
he was the delivery guy.
>> Let's see. Zombies meets American
Psycho.
>> You've never seen American Psycho? Oh,
>> Psycho.
>> He goes around killing random people,
but he has a girlfriend. I bet he's
crazy. That's
psycho,
>> but better.
So necroilia
>> get infected with emotion.
>> Necroilia infected with love. Brains
>> love after.
>> It's a perfect movie. It's a perfect
game.
>> All right, guys. I'm going to have you
uh have you stop. We're going to read
the other.
>> Love After Life.
>> I like it. I like it.
>> That's really good.
I think that was
>> that was good.
>> All right, guys. So, our publisher is
going to give us so much.
>> It may it may seem kind of kind of odd
to have you guys do this brainstorming,
then what I actually want to talk about
is rather than the ideas that you came
up with because I'm sure they're all
really good.
>> I know. So, sad. But what what really
matters is the process, right? Because
um the point of brainstorming is to
withhold judgment. judging judging which
of your ideas is best um shouldn't have
even been happening at this stage. And
so, you know, one one kind of question,
you know, we'll come back to what went
well, but um what what sort of uh
stumbling blocks did you guys run into
in this process as you were doing it?
Did it did it all go perfectly or I
highly doubt, but what sort of things
>> I was going to say like we were trying
to design this whole game. So, sometimes
we say features and they would push
games.
Yeah.
>> So it might have been
like things you want.
>> Yeah. Yeah. In some senses it may have
been constrained in one area, right?
Yeah. Sure. Zombies and a love story but
but then it was like asking for a whole
lot and so it could have been can we
just brainstorm the title or can we just
brainstorm this? Can we just brainstorm
that? What about
>> we very briefly got sidetracked on
Pokemon?
I think I think zombies for a second we
got like it was like Pokemon only
Pokemon first person shooter but that
was like 25 seconds.
>> Any other thoughts? I mean the whole
recruit be like your help you had
personally but if you had any challenges
with like you know
>> so I feel like if somebody says a really
good idea and everyone's kind of stuck
on that idea and you have to kind of get
through that whole idea before any other
ideas can come out.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's true.
like what other kind of noise are there?
>> Yeah. So like a few other ones.
>> Sure.
>> Kind of hard to like jump in my own
ideas.
>> Yeah, it's really hard to brainstorm. I
mean you guys actually I mean both
groups but I I stopped it with you guys
and you guys had this interesting kind
of momentum going and I was watching you
trying to write it all down. It was it
was way hard like because like ideas
were coming in like as you were
finishing the last idea. So it is you
know if a group has really good momentum
it's I I actually I really like the idea
of having two people where each person's
writing every other one. Of course the
difficulty is then you kind of pull two
people out of contributing right. So
it's you know the organization of the
actual group is is kind of important
that works.
>> Do you ever recommend using like a tape
recorder like you're doing for this
class?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. I mean that it's
it certainly makes sense. One of the
things that you know, one of the things
that Osborne says, which I think is
>> can't put a shape or cord down. Remember
that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But he also says like it's
the one of the most important things for
the secretary scribe is to is to number
things so that you know how many you
have. I'm sort of like is that is that
just to support your work? Like be like,
look, you know, we came up with 110
ideas. That's amazing. You know, it's
like how many doesn't seem to matter as
much as the quality of the ideas. So, um
I thought it was weird that you said
that. But um yeah, I mean tape
recording, video recording, any way of
documenting the process I think is the
most important problem. Um and and
actually you know he does make a good
point of saying you know one of the
problems with brainstorming as it kind
of evolved from when he first introduced
it at this one place and when people
started kind of running with it without
thinking about the principles is they
would brainstorm and then that was sort
of it and it was like you really have to
kind of look back at what you've come up
with. Um it's really important to kind
of reflect on what you've done as a
second step. Um, you know, and so, uh,
that's kind of important, too. How about
the judgment thing? Was there I mean,
people I I didn't notice a whole lot of
like criticism, but like I don't think
anybody was really good. I was like, oh,
that's a terrible idea. But did you find
it hard to not pass judgment on ideas as
they were coming out, even your own?
>> Yeah. I mean, I definitely let more than
one like, I like that slip, you know,
like, oh, that's
>> generally that's okay. I mean like you
know it's it's you know what you want to
avoid is like the oh my god we've got to
do this one you know like that's that
will that will derail everything because
then it's like you know just a loud the
loud voice that proclaims that we're
done because we got the idea will derail
things but you know nothing encourages a
person who's shy more than feeling like
their idea actually was good or
meritorious and so yeah you know that
sort of stuff is fine u you know you
want to avoid the stop the process
>> I I think I did say at some point like
We've got our title which is probably
not.
>> Yeah. I mean it's it's really it's just
a hard thing to kind of train yourself
from doing.
>> Come on. Is it necroilia title?
>> How
many self-censorers still out there
where a lot of people thought of ideas
but then just didn't contribute?
It's good if you didn't. It's great. I
mean it's great if you if everybody felt
like a cool that's that's really good.
That's really good. So um so I would say
that's one thing what that went well.
What other things went well you guys?
>> The tagline Yeah, specifically just
coming up with tagline.
>> Well, just in love
life. Is it love after life?
>> Love after life.
>> That's cool. I mean, did you guys feel
like you had momentum? It seemed to me
watching that there was momentum
building that it was
>> I think you did a really good job of
taking a lot of different ideas that we
had and started synthesizing them into
different things. Oh, that idea would
work well if we did this. Oh, and then
we could use like that name and that
would fit there.
>> Yeah.
>> Who are the two leaders for the two
groups? the clips.
>> Did you did you guys feel like you had
to do much facilitating
>> really? So, the hard part is really just
at the beginning where it's like how do
we want to just approach this thing? And
so, I guess we decided to start with the
title or like it was either the titles
or the main features and we were just
like, all right, let's bunch of random
titles, see
>> forgot I was the lead.
>> I didn't lead anything.
you know, if if you don't have a whole
lot of facilitating to do, it generally
means that the group is running. Okay.
Um, you know, I do think I do think you
have a good point. A lot of the
facilitators work comes at the beginning
of the process or even before the
process even began, making sure the
constraints are clear and that you guys
know what you're going to be working on.
Um, okay. So, bringing this back, this
is a game design class, right? I mean, I
sort of touched on it early, but you
know, how how do you guys see this um
being a useful kind of mechanic or
useful tool in you know what it's funny?
I call it mechanic. Maybe you catch that
paragraph in Alex where the guy was
saying when my team feels like they're
playing, it's a way more productive
brainstorm than when not. And I thought
that was really interesting, right?
Because like there are elements of of
giness to this. Um which I think is kind
of interesting. Um, so you know, how do
you guys think this could improve, you
know, the general game design of the
process?
>> I feel like after you you have a game
and you're testing it and there's like a
major flaw that you know it's taking too
long or or something like that and
everyone sits down and brainstorm like
okay this is exactly what our problem is
fix it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Kind of overcoming
roadblocks. Yeah. Sure. never to have
come up with half the cool ideas that we
came up with in the process and just me
thinking alone never to come up with
like Pokemon zombies.
>> Well, this is good just in general make
to think up a game because maybe it's
like oh every single game has been
decide people made games of all types.
How am I going to make an unique game?
It's brainstorm like hm those two things
I've I've never seen that before. That
could be interesting. Yeah, and that's a
really good point actually. The
synthesis
thing is is actually I think something
that's really important, right? Because
um we do we tend to see a lot of recycle
mechanics and what what becomes an
interesting thing in a game often times
is not that it's a completely new uh
rule, right? It's the way that rule
interacts with the other rules in the
system. Um and and you know in some
instances also how that rule is read and
interpreted by the player or perhaps
intended to be read and interpreted by
the player. So um yeah, I think the
synthesis is actually an interesting
part of it where people can bring a lot
of different ideas from a lot of
different experiences with games um to
kind of fuse these ideas together. Um
just uh
when it comes to coming up with ideas
for games, nice thing about
brainstorming is that it gets past the
good idea that everyone happens to like.
uh which is uh a problem that we
sometimes have in the SP is people the
people will find one idea they will
never think past it that's because they
were happy to find one that everybody
>> yeah and so you guys are dividing into
design teams and one of the things that
I would encourage I don't know how it's
set up schedule-wise but try to try to
divide the brainstorming process from
the judgment you know like I kind of
said it's it's true like even even if
you do the brainstorm it can help you
get over. But a lot of times whatever
had momentum during that brainstorm or
whatever got the most yuck during that
brainstorm, right, is going to be like
the popular strong idea. And then when
you come back to it with a little space,
you might be like, "Oh, you know, like,
yeah, that is a really good idea, but
there was this other thing that got
mentioned like a half an hour earlier
that's really interesting. Maybe we
could incorporate that somehow." And so
kind of, you know, making the judgment
happen in a in a separate phase can be
really important. Um because it's true,
creativity is like this, it's a little
bit more organic. It's not necessarily a
a strictly logical process, right? Um so
applying logic later can be a good thing
I think to the creative process.
Cool. Any questions about brainstorming
at all? You are incredibly enlightened
by Alex Osbor
on the forum actually people reading
about using things like Google or Google
Docs where things are automatically
recorded because everyone's basically
typing in their years.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think it's interesting.
I I don't have a whole lot of experience
with Well, I should reframe. Um I I
Well, I don't have a lot of experience
with remote brainstorming, but I did
have a um I did, you know, so one of the
games I worked on this summer was this
game called Yet One Word where um you
were asked a lot of personal questions.
And so, we had to think of personal
questions. And at one, so we were like,
well, if you have ideas, write it down
in Google Doc. And at one point myself
and two of the other designers were all
in the Google doc at the same time. And
you could actually see it that sort of
brainstorming momentum happen. Someone
would type something in and then like
someone would type next like a that's so
funny and then like write an idea that's
related to that, right? And and you're
kind of seeing it happen in this digital
space. So I think it can we've gotten so
accustomed to having these kind of um
digital personalities, right? these
digital personas in IMing and text
messaging and all that other stuff that
I I think we've gotten pretty adept at
typing fast enough to get ideas out. But
I think it could totally work. Um
there's something to be said for like
the momentum that gets generated in
person. Um but yeah, I mean
>> yeah I mean I was it's so funny. I was
going to say like no that's a terrible
idea you have to be around each other. I
was like actually it worked. Um, I mean
I think it all depends a little bit on
personalities and people that are
involved.
Certainly for a prolonged brainstorm you
one of the things Alex Osbourne says is
like time box it if if you you know if
you don't time box it's going to be a
problem. I think for in person that's
true. Um you know it's so easy to get
onto a Google document now whenever you
have an idea that actually having kind
of a long phone brainstorm where anytime
someone has an idea over a week or
something like that write it down. um
you know that's also useful too because
then you know you separated the
processes collecting and then but you
still should do that sort of building on
ideas.
>> It's probably easier to do those
synthesis when you're at least
simultaneously on the line online or in
the same room.
>> Yep. Yeah. Yeah. And to see the ideas
come out as they come out.
>> Yeah. It's it's kind of it's a little
uncommon to just read something and be
like, "Oh, yeah. What about this when it
first shows up?" When it first kind of
comes into existence as you're trying to
think of things that can spur ideas, you
know, the other danger about doing it
like, "Okay, this document is open for
the next 24 hours. Everyone throw your
ideas in." Is that then people start
spending too long on any one idea
thinking about what they're going to
write down before they write it down and
it's like, "No, that's not the point."
>> Yeah. Yeah. Think of the paperclip
experience and those of you that raised
your hand for saying that you were
self-censoring on your own. Like you
didn't even have to I wasn't going to
make you all hand in those paperclip
ideas and you were self-censoring,
right? So yeah, the same same sort of
thing applies. Like you might you might
censor yourself or spend a lot of time
on ideas. So
yeah, any other thoughts, questions?
Cool. Well, I hope this was helpful. I
hope it'll be helpful for your game
design stuff. Um, email me if you do
have any questions about this stuff. I
mean, I can try to try to help out, but
you know,
other than that, good luck on your your
game design for this class and for the
rest of the cool.
I do like that on the the keynote
things. It says end of show.
>> Uh let's see now. Uh we're going to play
some card games, but before that, just a
little bit of admin. Um on Monday you'll
notice that uh we had two readings, one
of which you've already done. So it
doesn't matter. Um this is the other
reading. It's a little bit dry. Tough it
out. Caffeinate yourself reading it.
Tough it out. It is worth it. It's
translation. So
uh let's see now. Um
there there's at least one person um
who hasn't form that we need to fill
out.
So just just come up here
if
at least four
more time.
>> Yeah, I'm not sure if we have enough to
get through all of them, but most of
them are pretty short. Uh uh a lot of
them the delay is going to be set up
which is why they couldn't first because
uh uh that takes a lot of set up. That
being said, um if you do get a chance to
look at a rule and study the cards, um
what like even though they've done a
bunch of really really smart things on
the cards just to make it easier for you
to set up uh and you want to kind of
paying attention to that, but the the
the aim of the today is pretty much just
variety. We have four fairly different
kinds of games that use cards in a very
different way. Uh and if you don't get a
chance necessarily to play all of them,
at least get a chance to look at other
people playing with them and if you
wanted to like check them out in the
middle of the week or something just
kick around the office but you know your
time to come back here next week or
something
but uh that's basically it if we can
just keep um uh if we can clear the
tables we need them for the cards uh