We're actually going to have uh Yakir uh
speaking up next and he's going to be
talking about powerful and accurate case
control analysis of spatially resolved
molecular data. Um so thank you for the
flexibility. Thanksir and let's welcome
him up.
[Applause]
All right. Uh thanks. So I'm a computer
scientist and a physician who sees
patients with autoimmune disease. I work
in the Ray Chadri lab here in Boston.
And I want to tell you about a method
we've developed for finding disease
associations in spatial data. As has
been already described, spatial data are
advancing very fast. We can now profile
really quite large numbers of proteins
and genes at very high spatial
resolution. And as you've already seen,
this has been a really rich area for
methods development. And there are some
really sophisticated approaches now for
analyzing spatial data. many of which
use advanced ML approaches. Um, and
thanks to these methods such as what
Donna just showed you, we can now
annotate tissue at really, you know, we
parse out tissue structure really in
quite granular detail. Today I want to
talk specifically about finding disease
associated spatial structures and I want
to do this in a statistical framework.
Given a spatial data set with many case
samples and many case and many control
samples, are there patterns that are
statistically significantly different
between cases and controls after
multiple testing correction? And while
it might seem like our ability to
successfully parse out JHU structures
and spatial data should translate
intuitively into wellpowered statistical
case control analysis, we found that
these are actually two quite distinct
problems. There's issues like batch
effects and finding flexible
representations at the sample level that
allow samples to be compared to each
other. These are crucial for case
control analysis. And so even though
some existing methods have been used in
a case control setting, it wasn't clear
to us how effective we should expect
them to be in
general. To look at this, we used
several existing tissue annotation
methods to analyze a spatial
transcrytoics data set of 75 brain
samples from 27 donors in a dementia
cohort. Now, doing benchmarking of this
type is challenging. uh not all the
methods necessarily output p values.
Some of them don't even allow multiple
samples as input. So what we did was we
chose five methods that were efficiently
runnable on a data set of this modality
and sample size and we used each of them
in this standard way. So for each method
we annotated all the samples at the
level of small spatial neighborhoods. We
then merged all the spatial
neighborhoods across samples and
clustered them. And then we tested each
cluster for basically whether it was
over represented in cases compared to
controls or vice versa and then
accounted for multiple
testing. In this data set, we were
unable to use existing tissue annotation
methods to sort of adapt them in this
way to find a case control signal. This
bar chart shows the log P value we got
with each method and the dash line is
the significance threshold. And
paradoxically, the more sophisticated
methods on the right actually maybe do
even a little bit worse than the simple
baselines on the left, which just
represent each spatial neighborhood
using its average expression profile or
its cell type abundance
profile. And as I'll get to later, this
data set does contain case control
signals. We found those signals using
the method we developed, which takes a
bit of a different approach that I'd
like to describe to
you. Our method is called variational
inference-based micron analysis or
Vimma. And in developing it, there were
two key intuitions that we tried to
incorporate. First, if embeddings of
spatial neighborhoods are dominated by
batch effects, then case control signal
might be obscured. And second, if tissue
regions are forced into mutually
exclusive clusters, then case control
signal might also be obscured because
the reality of the tissue biology might
be richer than that. So here's how we
operationalize these intuitions. First,
we take each sample, we split it up into
patches, and then we take those patches
and feed them into a variational
autoenccoder to learn a latent
representation of the patches, treating
the patches as simple images, sort of
pixel level representation. Um, this is
in keeping with, I think, many, you
know, some themes that you guys have
seen today already. But we found that
when we used a vanilla variational
autoenccoder, the embeddings were really
heavily influenced by just which sample
a tissue batch came from. They're
basically capturing a lot of technical
variation in addition to the biological
variation that we were after, even when
we did aggressive batch correction
upstream. To solve this, we made our
autoenccoder into a conditional
variational autoenccoder, meaning that
both the encoder and decoder are given
access to sample information to sample
ID. And together with the variational
penalty, this basically encourages the
encoder and decoder to remove technical
artifacts from the latent space. This
technique isn't new. It was used by a
nearsef and the SCVI team who used it in
the single cell space. And here it made
a really big difference for
us. The second innovation in Vimma
relates to how we do the case control
association test. Here we compute a
nearest neighbor graph of the patches
using the patch embeddings, but we don't
then cluster the patches into you know
what people might colloquially call
niches. uh in the field right now.
Instead, we define for each patch what
we call a microniche which is composed
of patches that are close to that patch
in the nearest neighbor graph and
ideally come from many different
samples. Belonging in these micro
belonging in these microniches can be
fractional and the micrones can overlap.
So the idea here is really to build a
redundant and flexible representation of
what's going on in each part of the
graph. We then represent each sample
using the abundances in that sample of
all the microniches in the data set and
we find the case control signal by
testing each microniche for association
to case control status across samples.
The result is uh does this work? Yeah,
you know an overall p value for the
presence of an association in general
and then also a measure of statistical
significance at the level of each
microniche that tells us whether that
microniche is not significantly
different between cases and controls.
those are in gray significantly enriched
in cases those are in red and
significantly enriched in controls those
are in
blue there are a lot of technical
details I'm eliting here for instance
you have to contend with the fact that
there's usually tens of thousands or
more of microniches this can hurt
statistical power because it makes
things really high dimensional you also
have to think about how to get rigorous
p values in a way that accounts for the
existence of technical replicates which
are very common in spatial data and also
the possibility of other sample level
confounders that you might might want to
correct for our method does have some
nice features. Uh first, it's fast. It
takes just a few hours to compute even
on the large uh dementia data set that I
described. Uh it doesn't require cell
segmentation. So it's applicable easily
to many different kinds of to really any
kind of sufficiently high resolution
spatial data. Uh and it doesn't require
extensive hyperparameter tuning. And
you'll see in the examples I'll show
here across many different modalities,
we were able to run this method with
identical hyperparameters.
And I won't show this here, but you
know, because we're thinking
statistically, we did do simulations to
make sure that the p values this method
gives are well calibrated. You know,
that 0.05 really means 0.05 and so on.
Uh, and we verified that the method is
well powered and that it accurately
identifies the parts of each sample that
contribute to the case control
association or the case control
signal. We applied our method to three
data sets that I want to show you here
briefly spanning three really different
modalities. um all the way going all the
way from simple immunohysic chemistry to
to murfish you know which is spatial
transcrytoics the first data set is the
dementia data set that I described uh
and this is the result of the vimma
analysis of that data set so in this uh
picture what you're seeing is a um where
every point is a patch and the red
points are patches whose microniches are
expanded in the dementia samples and the
blue points are patches whose
microniches are expanded in the
controls. Now when we saw this we the
first question we wondered was what does
this look like at the sample level? Like
is this a signal that is maybe
significant statistically but rather
weak? Is it a signal that's really
driven by a small minority of the
samples or something like that? And so
to get at that what we did was um look
at the fact that every sample in
principle can contain patches of all
three kinds right every sample can have
blue patches, gray patches or red
patches. uh and so we wondered whether
the relative proportions of blue patches
and red patches in each sample could you
know how how closely they relate to the
true phenotype label of that sample. So
what you're seeing here is uh a plot in
which each dot is now a sample and this
is what we're measuring. The y- axis is
the fraction of patches in each sample
that come from these red dots. The
x-axis is the fraction of patches in
each sample that come from the blue
dots. And then the color of these dots
is the true phenotype of those samples.
And so what we see is this really is a
signal that's robust and sort of exists
across the data set across all the
samples and uh and is able to separate
cases from controls quite well. What are
these patches though? Uh to look at that
I want to show you a different view of
the data set which is a spatial view. So
now you're seeing a subset of the
samples. Uh and they're sort of arrayed
in space. And in each sample I've
indicated uh some some of the cortical
layers. Uh so cortical layer 2 three or
cortical layers 2 three are indicated in
green. cortical layer six is indicated
in blue. And the reason I'm doing this
is because when we overlay the control
associated patches onto this image, so
now they're outlined in blue. What we
see is that they correspond really
cleanly to the to cortical layers two
and three. And this turns out to
actually be a known thing. Um thickness
of cortical layer 3 has been associated
with cognitive ability, you know,
positively associated with cognitive
ability in neuroiming studies. Um it's
been negatively associated with dementia
uh in single cell studies.
So, excuse me. This is an example where
our method is recovering something that
we already know. Uh, and it's, you know,
and it makes us happy that our method is
finding things that are known. Um,
certainly, uh, in a scenario where that
maybe wasn't obvious that it would, uh,
work out with this modality. What about
the dementia associated patches? Well,
they uh, overlay like this. So, they
correspond to a subset of layer 6, not
the whole thing, but a subset. And so,
the first question that we asked is
like, is this subset biologically
meaningful? Is it different in any way
from the rest of the cortical layer 6 or
are we just sort of finding some random
subset of layer six because we're not,
you know, because of some statistical
power issue. And so to get at this, we
looked at cell type abundances in these
in the basically the the red outlined
patches compared to the rest of layer 6.
And that's what you're seeing here. So
for a subset of the cells, what I'm
showing you is the distribution of the
abundances of these cell types across
the um dementia associated layer six
patches. That's the red histogram on the
right versus the non-dementia associated
layer 6 patches. That's the histogram on
the left. And you see that some cell
types really don't change much like L6B.
This is a neuronal cell type that lives
in cortical layer 6. It's basically
identically distributed between what
Vimma picked out as dementia associated
and the rest of layer 6. But other cell
types like oligodites show really quite
large differences between the patches
that Vimma picked out as being typical
of dementia in layer 6 and the rest of
layer 6. And you know this is
interesting because uh there's actually
work uh you know current work uh from
Evan Costco here at the broad and others
talking about the potential role of
oligodenderites in Alzheimer's uh
theorizing that they might actually play
a role in producing amaloid. Obviously
it's quite speculative for me to say
that that's what these oligodendrites
are doing but nevertheless this was an
exciting example to us because it's
showing a case where vimma is finding a
relatively granular association uh and
it's doing it where you know in a place
where other methods were unable to do
so.
The second data set uh is a codex data
set in ulcerative colitis and I'll speak
briefly about it. Uh what we you know
the signal I'm sort of the the most uh I
don't know excited about from this data
set is is a signal of TNF inhibition
versus not. So TNF inhibition is the
dominant treatment modality in this
disease. And we were able to find
basically a spatial signature that
corresponds to whether patients are on a
TNF inhibitor or not. And when we looked
at the micrones driving this association
we saw a very striking pattern. So these
patches here that uh vimma annotates as
being typical of patients who are not on
a TNF inhibitor they have uh you know
this sort of stereotype pattern of
clumps of B cells that's the red
staining here surrounded by uh T- cells
here in green these are basically
lymphoid aggregates and these lymphoid
aggregates are completely absent in the
cells that are annotated by vimma as
being typical of TNF inhibition. Um when
we again tried to you know we wanted to
get a sense of how strong of an effect
this was uh we made the same kind of
plot that I showed you in the dementia
example where each dot is a sample and
on the y-axis is the fraction of patches
in each sample that come from this type
of category and on the x- axis is a
fraction of patches that come from here
that are uh typical of the TNF naive
state and then we colored each sample by
how much TNF exposure each patient h had
uh and what we see is a really nice dose
response relationship basically uh these
you know, these two types of patches are
separating uh patients that have never
been on a TNF from patients that have
been on a TNF inhibitor for a long time.
So, we thought this was really neat. Um
the in the rheumatoid arthritis data
set, our goal was to take this, you
know, imuninohistochemistry, which is a
relatively simple modality. It's been
around for decades and to see whether
our method could rediscover known
disease subtypes that have only um that
were only determined recently using much
more advanced single cell type
technologies and then to leverage the
fact that this is a spatial modality to
see if there was any extra insight that
we could
add. So we did see that Vimma found a
very strong uh spatial signature of a
known subtyping of rheumatoid arthritis
into two disease subtypes. a stromal
subtype uh in which fibroblast activity
is high and an immune subtype uh in
which T- cell activity is high and I
won't go into the details but Vimma
found this signal actually in an
unsupervised way using um essentially a
type of PCA applied to the sample level
representation that it builds using
micronese abundances and so in a sense
what this is telling us is that Vimma
was able to sort of rediscover um a
known signal in this data set uh but to
do it from a modality that's been around
for many many years and that's much
simpler than the single cell modalities
that were used to actually you know um
uncover this distinction for the first
time. Uh and the neat thing is that
because this is a spatial modality we
can actually look at heterogeneity
within samples. And what um what's neat
about this is that Vimma actually showed
that although there are samples in the
data set that are composed entirely of
immune type patches, that's the sample
here on the left. And there are samples
in the data set that are confused
composed entirely of strromal type
patches. That's the red the example on
the right. There are also many samples
that are mixed that have some strromal
patches and some immune patches
coexisting in the same person and
actually the same joint. And because
this um subenotyping of stromal versus
immune is thought to actually uh predict
be be predictive of treatment response
in rheumatoid arthritis. These results
have real implications for how we think
about precision medicine in this
disease. like does one patient really
have one sub phenotype of RA or could
there be multiple types of biology
happening even within a single joint of
a single person which is obviously not
great news for precision medicine but
it's important to know if that's what's
going on. So what I hope I've shown you
today is that uh statistical case
control analysis in spatial data is um
really a bit of a different problem that
has different requirements than some of
the other things that we're talking
about in the spatial realm. If you want
to do this, you really need a
representation of spatial units that
gives you consistent semantics across
samples. And you need a flexible
association testing strategy that can
represent samples in a very rich way.
Uh, and I hope I've shown you that our
method Vimma enables powerful
statistical case control analysis of
spatial data and that it finds new and
interesting signals across a range of
data modalities. So with that, I'd like
to thank my collaborators and especially
Lshay Sud and Michelle Curtis. Lakshay
was part of the benchmarking effort. I
showed up front and led the application
of Vimma to the ulcer colitis data set
and he's actually here uh in the
audience. Um as well as Michelle Curtis
who led the application of Vimma to the
Alzheimer's data set and Shar Chadri
who's my research mentor. Um feel free
to check out the preprint with this QR
code. Uh the method is up on GitHub uh
and we'd love any feedback on it if
anyone chooses to use it. Thanks very
much.
I think we have a question in the back.
So yeah, I only showed it uh you know
when you do the section samples and then
you uh you know engage in the uh using
the orodocite
uh why you pick the orodite instead of
some other associ.
Yeah. So I guess I I might be
misunderstanding but to to clarify we
didn't there's we didn't choose all the
goodender sites uh when we were choosing
what to input into the method. Um, so
there was no there's no bias in that
sense. Uh, I'm showing you and and what
we did was compare the dementia
associated patches to the other patches
across all of the cell types that were
annotated by the authors of the original
study. And I'm just showing you sort of
I just showed a subset for space
reasons, but the alligender sites are
the clearly um they're sort of the
largest effect size and um and sort of
there's a statistically significant
difference there. So it might be that
there's other cell types that differ as
well and I'm not sure that I you know
I'm the right person to really fully
understand the biology there. You sample
from Huntington disease or Alzheimer
disease? No, this was Alzheimer's
dementia. Okay. And actually you p you
picked the right cell because uh
actually last week you know there's a PC
dissertation you know across the street
you know they presented in Oracle
dandelai you know has some dysfunction
in Huntington disease and also uh to a
lesser extent in Alzheimer.
Yes. Um it's certainly
thanks for that info. I think uh if
maybe I'll talk to you later and see if
there's a citation or something I can
get for it. Yeah.
Great. Let's thank the speaker one more
time.
[Applause]