What I'm going to do now is going to
reach in here. I'm going to take a
dollar bill and I'm going to put it in
the flame. Just like that.
>> Was that too fast?
>> How is that dollar bill burning up so
quickly? It's actually not a dollar
bill. It's called flash paper. And
[music] it's paper that has been treated
with chemicals to make it burn quickly
and leave no ashes. Practically, what
that means is that you soak [music] the
paper in a mixture of concentrated
nitric and sulfuric acids. The cellulose
in the paper then reacts with the acid
to produce nitrated cellulose and water.
Now the nitro group, the NO2 is the
reactive group and it can be very
reactive depending on the molecule that
it's in. You've no doubt heard of
nitroglycerin
or [music] TNT. All of these molecules
have nitro groupoups in them. [music]
And it's the nitro or NO2 groups that
make these molecules explosive.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.