[Music]
it's a hard thing it really takes your
measure to be a part-time physician
that's not a job you want to do anything
less than your absolute best but one of
the things that I think lets me do
science better is because I'm a
physician every question that I've
chosen to pursue is deeply informed by
what I see in the clinic whatever I had
learned about an illness during the med
school years it was so much more
crystallized when I had a patient in
front of me who had it when I did and I
had a face and a set of feelings to
connect that to they just stayed with me
so much
[Music]
more I lead a lab that's now eight
people and we study antibiotic
resistance and sepsis we study both
mechanisms of antibiotic resistance we
try to develop molecular Diagnostics and
apply them to to Patient samples for
antibiotic resistant bacteria and we
study the immune disregulation that
occurs in patients with
sepsis
I grew up in the Chicago area I was born
in the western suburbs a town called
neille Illinois my parents were both
scientists and so I'd often go into my
mom's lab I was mostly like bouncing a
tennis ball off the walls or doing
whatever reading I could do but I do
remember getting the sort of energy of
the lab I don't think it was until
junior year in college that I first
heard that mdphd programs even existed
pretty much as soon as I heard that I
thought well that that's it that's what
I want to do towards the end of my res y
I had a decision to make about where to
do fellowship and I hadn't actually done
any genomics at all but I could see the
power of it and I felt like we need to
bring this sort of
sequencing technology in a in an
informed and sort of clever creative way
into the understanding of infections and
the bro was at the
Forefront I connected with Deb hung who
was a core faculty member here at the
bro and eventually my postto adviser and
really it was you know sitting and
chatting with her that got me really
excited we started to drill down into
specific specific projects that could do
this and what I thought was a really
cool way not just to understand disease
better but also really to make the full
transition from things that we learned
at the bench actually affecting patient
care I saw the possibility of that in
those conversations what I've seen of
the broad is absolute cuttingedge
Technologies but applied to questions uh
that are really fundamentally important
to human health our societies have been
shaped by infections and I I find that
really fascinating and I find trying to
understand that a really interesting
thing