But the first thing I want to do is
explain
the kaly tree theorem.
And
so the question is how many labelings
labelings
of
um a tree
on n vertices.
And what I want to do is I want to um
give you the first few elements in this
few first few numbers in this sequence
and
let you guess the answer. So the first
one
is a tree on two vertices.
And if you want to label it with
um
with one and two, there's only really
one way of doing it, which is that. And
now so that's um n = 2 n = 3
1 2 3
which is clearly the same as 1 3 2
because these trees
actually
and 312.
So there's one way of doing this, three
ways of doing this. N= 4.
Okay, this time I'm not going to list
them all out because they're too many to
count, but I'm going to list them
in,
you know, the form of the tree. So how
many ways are they doing it? are they're
labeling a tree which is a path. Can
anyone tell me?
Yeah.
>> Maybe like four choose two to choose the
two middle ones and then two.
>> Yeah. 4 choose 2 * 2 which is 12
because you get to choose which two are
the middle ones.
And
um then there are two ways of completing
that.
And how about
a tree that looks like this? Um wait, I
drew one too many leaves on that.
How many ways of there of doing this?
Four. because the only thing that
matters is the middle one. So four and
this becomes 16.
And let's do n= 5.
And there's one of these. Um oops, I
drew I drew an extra leaf on that one,
too. Sorry. There are five of these.
And
there are five factorial over two ways
because there are five factorial ways of
labeling the vertices from left to
right. And
but
this tree is symmetric in left and
right. So you're double counting if you
do that which is 60.
And then there are
again five factorial over two because
um
you can
label these 1 3 2 4 5 but you can swap
five and four and get the same tree. So
there's a extra factor of two and this
is 16.
and you add these up, you get 125.
So, does anybody see a pattern?
>> Yeah.
>> Like multiply by three, then by four,
then by like I guess like like within
the sequence.
>> Yeah. Well, I mean, yes, that's
essentially the right idea. This is 3 to
the 1. This is 2 to the 0. This is 4^
squared.
And this one is 5 cubed.
So the kay tree theorem says there are n
to the n minus2 ways of doing this.
So that's the statement of the kay tree
theorem.
And
there are lots and lots of proofs. So
one way you might think of proving it is
to find a bjection between labelled
trees and sequences of the numbers 1
through n of length n minus2.
And you can do it that way. But this
bjection is really incredibly
complicated and completely
non-intuitive. So that's not really the
right way to do it. So what I'm going to
do is try to explain
a way of doing this by counting these
certain object twice or certain object
in two different ways. And how do we do
this?
So
let t subn be number of labeled
trees
on n vertices.
And the first thing we're going to do is
change the thing to
number of lab of labeled rooted trees on
nver vertices.
[applause]
Okay.
So, what do you do to get a rooted tree
is a
tree
with
uh specified vertex called the room.
Okay. So
um
if t subn is the number of labeled trees
on nver vertices,
what is the number of labeled rooted
trees on n vertices?
Okay. Well, what you do is you start
with a tree. Let's do this tree. 1 3 2.
And now you pick a vertex to call the
root. So in this case you can
you can
do this is the root and three
one two this is the root or you could do
two
3 one this is the root.
So
to go from a label tree to a root tree
labeled rud tree we just pick one vertex
and so there are n * p subn of these
and now
what we're going to Count.
What we count
in two ways
is labeled
rooted trees
with ordered edges.
So, let's pick the um middle one there.
One, three, two.
So, we need to order the edges. And we
can either order this one and then this
one and then this one and then this one.
So, I'm going to use letters to order
the edges because otherwise we have too
many numbers floating around and it gets
confusing. So, 3 2 1
A B.
So
how many labeled trees
in terms of t subn the number of labeled
trees? How many labeled rooted trees
with ordered edges are there going to
be?
So there are n minus one edges. How many
ways are there of ordering n minus one
edges?
n minus one factorial. Very good. So
this is t subn * n * n minus one
factorial.
Okay.
So
if we can count this in a way that tells
us the answer is n to the nus2
* n * n -1 factorial.
Then we have proven the theorem.
Okay.
So
the second way of counting
there
are
n
to the n minus
2 n factorial
labeled rooted trees with ordered
Good.
So how do we prove this lema?
What we will do
proof method
um
construct
a labeled
rooted
tree.
I'm going to say via labeled rooted
forests
by adding one edge at a time.
So back here we have
this n minus one factorial which is the
order of the edges. And this order of
the edges is just going to be the order
that we add the edges
to get to
via labeled rooted forest to get to the
label rooted tree.
Okay.
And I'm going to do it by example, but
well basically because it's much easier
to see by example than if I try to
describe the process in words. So we
start
with a forest. I never told you what a
forest is. A forest is a collection of
trees
which
I'm going to say that this makes perfect
sense. So, start with a forest with
n trees
with one vortex each.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Choose
one of these trees.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to add it to a vertex
and add
it
on top of a vertex
in another tree.
And let's see.
So,
so let's take one of these trees
and stick it on top of a vertex in
another
So this gives us
one two
um four five
three six and we want to label this with
the letter A because it was the first
thing we did. Now let's take a different
um different tree and stick it on top of
another
you know vertex in a tree and we get
one
four five six two
and here this was three and this was a
first step. This was our second step.
Okay. And we keep on doing this. And
maybe the next step is we pick
this tree
and stick it on top of this vertex.
And we have 1 4
5 6 2 3 [sighs]
and
B
A and C.
And we keep on doing this until we get
until we've used up all the trees except
one. And we have a labeled rooted tree
with an ordering on the edges.
So,
how many ways are there of doing this?
Oh gosh. This is
this is one of these um hard to erase
chalks.
Okay.
Well,
how many
configurations are there to start with
anybody.
How many labeled
How many labeled forests with n trees
with one vertex each are there?
I can see nobody's answering it because
this question is too easy.
There's only one of them. There are n
vertices and they have the labels one
through n. And since order doesn't
matter, there's one of them.
So one
after
K steps
have
well each step
we have
n each step we reduce one tree. So we
have n minus k
trees.
Take one node
um
add
a different tree.
We take one node, we add a different
tree on that node
to that node.
So for example
here
um
here we chose node number five and we
added the fourth tree to that node. So
how many ways are there of doing this
step?
How many ways are there of choosing a
node? Anybody?
Yes.
How many nodes are there?
N. And we can choose any one of them. So
there are n ways of choosing the node.
And now we have n minus k trees. And we
want to choose a different tree to add
on top of the node. So there are n minus
k minus one trees we can add.
So there's n * n - k -1
ways
to do this.
[clears throat]
So number of
okay what was it labeled rooted trees
labeled
rooted
trees
with edge ordering
is the product.
Well,
so after k steps, so after we want to
start with how many ways there are after
zero steps. So zero
to
well there are n minus one steps
altogether. So n minus 2 I believe
um
n
- k - one.
Um
[clears throat] so
this is equal to
from 0 k = 0 to n - 2 n * from k =
0 to n minus 2 of n - k -1
which is equal to well there are n
um
there are n minus one steps and each of
these you have a factor of n. So this is
just n * n minus one and this is should
be n minus
factorial
which
if I haven't erased it
yeah we wanted to so show that there are
n to the n minus 2 n factorial, but
that's the same as n^ the nus1 * n minus
one factorial. So this is the number of
labelled rooted trees with an edge
ordering.
So this implies that
t subn
* n
times
um
n minus one factorial.
So this is the number of labeled rooted
trees on node
and this is the number of edge orderings
is equal to n -1 * n -1 factorial which
shows you that p subn = n - 2
to the n to the n minus 2
which is what we wanted to prove.
Okay. Yes.
>> And then isn't the second one just
picking like which like a tree that's
not as trees you already picked?
>> That's right. Well, is tricking a tree?
No, because you can pick a tree that
you've already picked. You just cannot
pick a tree. You cannot pick the tree
that that node is in.
>> Yeah.
So, we pick a node here and then we pick
a different tree to put on top of it.
And that's five, six, two.
>> Doesn't it [snorts] matter like how you
connect them like with the other tree
because you're just picking like another
tree to
>> Oh, we're always going to put the root
of this tree
>> on top of this note.
And
you can see that the process can be
undone because if we have A B C, the way
we undo this step is we find the last
edge and we cut it and we have a tree on
top of that edge and we have the tree
that's left when you remove this edge.
So that undoes the step. So the whole
process is I'm going to say that there
is uh you know this function that takes
you from
trees
trees on k n minus k nodes to trees
[clears throat] or to forests of n minus
k trees to forests of n minus k minus
one trees is reversible. So it's a
bjection.
But yeah, that was a good question.
Okay. So,
and last year we actually used
this theorem for one of our term paper
projects.
This year we're not. But um
I I wanted to tell you this at the
beginning of the um class, but I forgot.
So what we're going to do is tonight,
assuming all goes well, I will put up
the term paper projects and their
assignments to students. And tomorrow in
recitation
um the
you know the recitation leaders will
discuss them a little bit. Although most
of the recitation tomorrow is going to
be devoted to writing.
Okay.
So the term paper projects are hopefully
coming out tonight.
Okay.
So now we are going to switch topics and
go to generating functions.
Okay.
And generating functions
are a very useful concept in mathematics
and you can use them to count things.
I mean there are proofs of the kaly tree
theorem that use generating functions
and there are
proofs of probably nearly everything
we've discussed in terms of counting
that use generating functions. Although
often the generating functions proofs
are more difficult than the
non-generating functions proofs. On the
other hand, there are cases where
generating functions are really the only
way to do it. And the other advantage of
generating functions is that they're
mechanical. So given uh say cominatorial
identity and you look at it and you say
what can I what things can I count in
two different ways to prove it or
something else
well it's um
no you have to use some creativity to
find this but if you have a generating
fun uh combinatorial identity with
general generating functions. Often it's
fairly straightforward to prove it using
generating functions although it
involves actual algebra. So it's
maybe more difficult.
So
why am I
let a1 well a z a1 a2 etc be a sequence
of numbers
The generating function
associated with a C sequence.
is
f ofx
is equal to sum a sub i x to the i
= 0 to infinity.
And
so this is a
an algebraic function and that means you
can use all the tools of algebraic
functions to manipulate it and this we
will find is going to be very useful.
Now um
you can ask what does X mean here? And X
doesn't really mean anything. It's just
a tool for keeping track of what the
what the I is on AI X to the I. So it's
key way of keeping
um
the E
AI from different distinct from the J
AI.
So it usually doesn't really mean
anything.
So the example
um
well one example is we'll take the
sequence
of binomial coefficients.
So what is this f subn?
All right.
A subn is equal to k choose n.
[snorts]
So the generating function for this
f ofx is equal to sum
and here n is what we're summing over n=
0 through infinity
and
you know this is zero if n is bigger
than k. So that's sum n= 0 through k
a
um k
choose n.
Let me write a n x to the n k
x to the n.
And you should know what this is.
This is a binomial theorem and it's just
like 1 + x to the k.
And one way of thinking about this is
f ofx
equals
1 + x
1 + x.
Okay. So for the kth term
no for m term I'm sorry
choose
n x's
k minus n ones.
Good. So we need to choose whether we'll
use the x from this one, the x from this
one,
the x from this one, etc. So we're
choosing k x's. We're choosing n x's out
of k things,
which is just n choose k or k choose n,
I'm sorry. And so that's why a subn is
k.
Okay.
So, example two.
Um,
the
A subn is the probability
of
of N heads.
When you flip a coin,
a biased coin,
K times,
and we'll let P equal probability of
heads
and Q
= 1 - p.
So a of x is equal to summation a subn x
to the n is equal to
k choose n p to the
k q to the n minus k * x to the k x to
the n
x.
Ah, I keep mixing up my K's and my Ns.
Let me apologize for that. There we go.
And this is equal to I forgot the sum
here.
This is equal to
um
q + px
to the n
again by the binomial theorem.
So
hopefully I will have time to do a real
example that shows you why generating
functions are useful
at before the end of class. But if not,
we'll get to it tomorrow or not
tomorrow, Thursday.
Okay.
[clears throat] But I want to say a few
more general things about um generating
functions.
Let
A
B be disjoint classes of objects
and C
equals A union B where
U is disjoint union.
So that just says that A intersection B
is the empty set.
So I'm going to say the generating
function for C of X.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to express the generating function for C
of X in terms of A of X and B of X is
equal to
A of well
it's going to be some C subn X to the N.
Well, c subn is just a subn + b subn
is equal to sum a sub n + b subn
x to the n
which you can see is the generating
function of a of x plus b of x.
Okay. So the next one we want to talk
about multiplication of generating
functions. This is actually first pretty
straightforward and second
is not really that useful in
manipulating generating functions.
Multip multiplying generating functions
is incredibly useful and we'll do an
example.
So let's do the example first and then
we will do
the
the formal um
the formal um explanation
So, let's say we have a six-sided dice
and an eight-sided dice.
Eightsided dice.
And we want to know what
is the
probability
of rolling.
Okay,
let's call it
n.
when we add up the numbers from the two
die
and I should
you know specify that the six-sided dice
is numbered 1 through six and the
eight-sided die is numbered 1 through
eight.
[clears throat]
So
let
c subn is equal to number of ways
of rolling n.
Claim
C subn is equal to or rather C subn
C of X is equal to sum
C sub N X to the N is equal to
X + X2 + X cub + X 6
+ X2 + Xub 2 + dot dot dot + x to 8
equ=
x + 2 x^2 + 3 x cub + dot dot dot
+ 5 x 5th + 6 x to 6 + 7 x to the plus
sorry 6 x to 7th
plus 6 x to the 8th plus
6 x to the 9th
+ 5 x to the 10th plus dot dot dot
plus x to the 14th.
So, how do we get that?
So you can see from this that there are
five ways of rolling a 10. You can roll
a six and a
four
and you can roll a
five and a five. A four and a six. a
three and a seven and a two and an
eight.
And
you know and this works because
C subn is equal to summation.
[clears throat]
J = 0
J = 1 through N.
Um,
okay.
A subj
B sub N minus J.
So if you want to get an N, the first
place has to be J and the second one has
to be N minus J.
And [clears throat]
AJ equals
1 if one is less than J is less than
six, zero otherwise, and B subj = 1 if
one is less than J is less than 8, and
zero otherwise.
Is this clear? I mean, to get an N, you
have to roll a J on the first dice and
an N minus J on the second dice. And you
can only roll a J on the first dice if J
is between one and six. And you can only
roll an N minus J on the second die if J
is between one and eight.
So
if
a of x is equal to summation
i = 1 through 6 x to the i
and b of x is equal to summation i = 1
through 8
x to the i. That's not a very good
eight.
Then
c of x = [applause] a of x
b of x
because this is the formula for
multiplying polinomials.
So we have the generating function for
the first die and the generating
function for the second die. And we get
the generating function for the sum of
the two dies by just multiplying them.
And let's make this rigorous. Let A
Let a
B
be two classes of objects.
[sighs]
A of X and B of X
be their generating functions.
Then
oh well
the cartisian product
product
A cross B
is
A B
A N A B and B.
And we want to claim
that size
of a b equals size
of a
s plus size of b.
Then
the
cartisian product
A cross B
has
generating function.
A of x B of X equals C of X.
poof.
Okay.
C subn equals summation
K = Z through
N
A subk
B sub N minus K. So we want to look at
the things of size n in the cartisian
product. Well, they're the things of
size
k
in the first
um
generating function and the thing times
the things of size n minus k in the
second generating function. And when one
is sum this over all k.
And now
we just need to check that summation c
subn x to the n is equal to
summation k = z to n a sub k b n minus k
x to the n is equal to some k = z
or rather
and = 0 to infinity. I forgot the second
sum here. n = 0 to infinity. k= 0 to n
which is just sum k= 0 to infinity a
subk x to the k summation
j = 0 to infinity b subj x to the j
because [clears throat] you know when
you multiply these
you group the things that have the same
k + j= n and that gives you this term
sum k= 0 to n a sub k b subn minus k.
Yeah.
>> What does size mean? Size is
[clears throat]
size is just an arbitrary
function on these objects that
correspond to the
the the
n here in summation a subk x to the k.
So
when you have generating functions,
you're grouping objects into
things that go with x to the k and um
those
are what we're calling size.
>> So is it the power of x?
>> It's the power of x that is associated
with the object. And I think we should
look at a actual example.
So this is a simple example.
[clears throat]
example.
Okay. Suppose
you have
one penny.
No, six pennies.
Um, one nickel,
two dimes.
How many different ways
can you
make
an
[sighs]
claim? name
the generating function
let's call it
um c of x is equal to sum cn x to the n.
So we'll let C subn be the number of
different ways
CN be number
of ways to make N cents with
six pennies, a nickel and two dimes.
C of X is equal to 1 + X + X^2 + X cub +
X4 + X 5th + X 6
1 + X 5th and 1 + X 10th + X to the 20th
Okay.
So, when you multiply these things
together, let's look at the x to the 20.
Let's look at the x to the
I'm thinking
x to the 21st term.
So it can be get got from x to the 6th *
x 5th * x 10th
and we can also get it from x times x to
the 20th
and those are the only two ways you can
get it. So there are two ways to make
chain two two
ways
to pay
21 cents.
[clears throat]
So here the size is just the
number of cents.
Okay, let's do something a little bit
more complicated.
How
many
ways are there
to pay
let's say n cents in
an arbitrary number of pennies,
nickels,
dimes.
[clears throat and cough]
Well, I want to claim that it's 1 + x +
x^2 + x cub + dot dot dot * 1 + x 5th +
x 10th + x 15th
plus dot dot dot * 1 + x 10th + x 20th +
x to the 30th plus dot dot dot
which is equal to 1 1 - x 1 / 1 - x 5th
* 1 / 1 - x 10th.
So cn x to the n is equal to that.
[clears throat]
Okay. So now I want to
give an example for how you would
actually use a generating function. I
mean, we have not gotten to the end of
our, you know, overall
description of generating functions, but
I want to give you an example first of
how you would actually
calculate something with them.
And
I want to claim this is really pretty
neat.
What
is sum
k= 0 through n k n choose k.
Okay. So the first thing is you can do
it by counting something two different
ways and I want to do it with generating
functions first and if I have any time
at the end of the class I'll check it by
counting by using the technique of
counting in two different ways but I'm
not sure I will. So what is it? K = 0
through N
choose K * X to the K is equal to
Does anybody want to tell me what this
is?
>> Yeah.
>> Um
no because we want this as a function of
something with x's in it.
>> 1 plus x.
>> Yeah. 1 plus x to the n. That's right. 1
+ x to the n. Excellent.
Okay. Now, and this is
we should call this f ofx.
Now, how can we get this out of that?
Well, let's differentiate.
dx
f ofx
is equal to sum k = z through n k
n choose k
x to the k minus one.
Right?
Okay. And now let's differentiate this.
Well, that's just n * 1 + x to the n
minus one.
And now let's substitute
x = 1.
Well, in this we get sum k = 0 through n
k k n choose k
and in this we get
n * 2 to the n minus one.
Okay,
we have our answer.
And [clears throat]
I I want to say
that
we kind of skipped a step here.
Um
generating function
for
K N choose K
um is
some K N choose K X to the K
K = 0 through N.
And [clears throat]
what we calculated here
was just k n choose k x to the k minus
one. So this is actually
n x 1 - x to the n minus one.
But since x if we're substituting x= 1,
it doesn't matter if we have
x to the k or x to the k minus one here
or if we have this extra
sorry plus or if we have this extra x
here
it will if x is one they're the same.
So to get so to multiply
the
nth term
in or to multiply the k the kth term in
a generating function by k, we just
differentiate and multiply by x.
And this is a very useful trick playing
with generating functions.
So, how would you do this with counting
two different ways?
Anybody?
>> Yes.
>> Is that
like what what's the question? Is it the
line about it or
>> you mean this?
>> Yeah,
>> it's [snorts]
K.
What you ask like what's like
um we want to answer what question are
we answering
>> = n 2 n minus one where we're answering
what is summation k and
>> I mean like you just asked counting two
ways like which
>> oh we want to answer this question by
counting in two different ways. Oh okay.
So it's like you pick you have a set of
A elements and you pick K elements out
of it and then from the K elements you
pick one special element.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
So we have
set of n elements
choose
K elements.
one of the K elements.
So we have a special element
and then we have a subset of K and a
subset of N minus K minus one
and sum over K. We just have a special
element
of um
k
n choose k.
We have a special element
and a subset of the remaining subset
of n minus one other elements
and you know you can pick the special
element nways.
other elements
are the subset sorry
the subset of other elements
elements
is 2 the nus1 ways
and this gives
n * 2 the n minus one
which is what we wanted in the first
place.
Okay, so that's two different ways to
solve this problem.
And I want to say that, you know, so far
we're only doing things with generating
functions that we could have done more
easily some other way. But there are
things that you can do with generating
functions that are much harder to do
other ways. And we will eventually get
to those
when we start talking about Fibonacci
numbers.
And um
I think the next thing I want to do is
too long. It didn't do three minutes. So
I will let you go and see everyone on
Thursday.