Welcome everyone to today's Sloan
Fellows admissions process and
application tips webinar. My name is
Maddie Clark and I'm excited to be
joined by you all um wherever you're
calling in from today for today's
application tips webinar. So thanks for
joining us. Today's session um we'll
talk a little bit about the Sloan
Fellows MBA application um and talk a
little bit about the program. We'll
leave plenty of time for questions that
you all might have throughout today's
webinar. If you do have any questions,
please use the Q&A function to pose
those questions to myself and the rest
of my team. I'm joined by a few of my
colleagues who will be answering
questions throughout the webinar and
then we'll save time to answer some
questions live at the end. So again,
thank you all for joining us and we'll
get started.
Before we dive into the specifics of the
Sloan Fellows MBA program, I want to
talk a little bit about who we are as a
school. The MIT Sloan School of
Management's mission is to develop
principled, innovative leaders who
improve the world and to generate ideas
that advance management practice. This
mission is really at the heart of
everything that we do within the Sloan
School of Management. And if you think
about the first part of our mission,
developing principled innovative
leaders, that is really done through the
opportunities and experiences that are
available throughout our portfolio of
programs. We have a number of programs
offered for various points in your
career. Um, from early career programs
or traditional 2-year MBA. Um, but we're
here today to talk about our Sloan
Fellows MBA. This is a 12-month degree
that culminates in either an MBA or an
MS in management or an MS in management
of technology. The students who pursue
one of the master's programs um will
complete a thesis during their 12-month
time. For the Sloan Fellows MBA, we look
for a minimum of 10 years of experience,
but folks enter the program with about
14 to 15 years of experience on average.
And we'll talk a little bit about what
the class looks like.
Our class that just graduated this past
May um was 103 students. 37% of them
identified as women. 77% of the class
was international. Um within the
international folks, we had 42 countries
represented. again about 15 years of
experience when folks enter the program
and the class that just graduated about
half of them had a previous advanced
degree. You'll note here that um the top
three industries that folks entered the
program from were financial services,
technology, government, education, and
nonprofit.
So, as we think about the Sloan Fellows
program um and thinking about who is the
ideal candidate, a few things kind of
come to mind that we're looking for in
the application and admissions process.
Like I mentioned before, we're looking
for a minimum of 10 years of
postbachelor's degree full-time work
experience. And within that experience,
we're really looking for folks who have
both leadership and general management
experience. And so here at Sloan, our
the way we define general management
experience is beyond holding just a
specific title. It's folks that are
leading teams or leading functions have
responsibility for strategy and budget.
And these experiences are really
important for students to have prior to
the program to be able to contribute
effectively in the classroom. We're also
looking for candidates who are committed
to the global perspective. If you think
back to just the previous slide, 42
countries were represented in our class
that just graduated. Those experiences
that students bring in based on
geographic context that they've lived
and worked is really important and
helpful to enhance the experience and
learning for everyone in the classroom.
And so we're really looking for folks
who are excited to learn from other
perspectives and have their own
perspective challenged by the viewpoints
and experiences of others.
We're looking for candidates who push
the boundaries and challenge the status
quo, who advocate for their ideas in
their workplaces and create better
environments um within their
organizations.
The Sloan Fellows MBA program has um
some quantitative rigor to it. And so
we're really looking for folks that have
shown that they're comfortable taking on
that quantitative aspect of the program.
An important component that we're
looking for in the application process
is folks that are able to communicate
effectively um so that they can
contribute to the classroom but also go
on to be leaders in their field after
graduation.
And the last piece that we're looking
for is folks that are committed to
learning and self-improvement. We look
for this throughout the application if
you've continued to do this since your
undergraduate degree. And again,
thinking back to the previous slide, 47%
of our class that just graduated had a
previous advanced degree. And so folks
that are always looking to continue
learning and growing um is really
important and those are the folks that
we want in the Sloan Fellows program.
So I want to talk a little bit about our
our evaluation process and the timeline
for that for our Sloan Fellows program.
Um, we have two application deadlines,
which I'll talk about in a few slides.
Um, and we begin reviewing all
applications the day after the deadline.
All applications are reviewed by our
professionally trained admissions
committee. So, we do not have any
students or alumni involved in our
evaluation process. As we're reviewing
applications and again thinking back to
the previous slide, who is the ideal
candidate? We're looking for evidence of
all of those pieces in addition to um
past successes, your demonstrated
success and leadership skills. So, we'll
look at things like the impact of your
work that you've had um within the past
few years. We'll look at your previous
academics, if you provide any test
scores. Those can all demonstrate your
past successes. We'll also look for
evidence of leadership skills. So
finding ways to figure out how well you
work in teams, how do you solve
problems, how do you communicate and
adapt to change. So we'll be looking at
all of your application materials and if
invited to interview in an interview,
dig deeper into these questions to learn
a little bit more about your leadership
skills and what that could contribute to
the Sloan Fellows program.
And the last piece, um, we're evaluating
candidates for general management
experience. In a bit, we'll go through
every single application component and
talk about the general management
experience question in some more detail,
but that's definitely something we look
for throughout the evaluation process um
as it's a key pillar of this loan
fellow's program.
This is a highle overview of the
timeline for round one. So, we hope um
you all are getting started on your
applications now and applying for our
round one deadline, which is on o
Monday, October 20th. Following that,
immediately the next day, we'll begin
reviewing all applications. Um and we'll
take a couple weeks to review
applications. By November 4th, if you
submit your application for the round
one deadline, you'll have an update from
us, at which point you may be invited to
interview or receive another update on
your application. From there, we'll have
a few weeks of interviews starting on
November 10th with final decisions for
round one being released on December
12th. Um, we really strongly encourage
international applicants to apply by
this round one deadline to allow ample
time for the various onboarding
processes. And one thing I just want to
note, um, you are welcome to submit your
application on the day of the deadline.
We ask that if you are submitting all of
your final materials then um please have
some patience with the system. Um it can
sometimes slow down with many people
uploading their videos and uploading
their different application components
all at the same time.
So now we are going to kind of get into
the heart of today's um presentation and
talk about all of the application
components. I'll provide some tips on um
completing each of them and then we'll
get to any questions that you all have.
So the Sloan Fellow's MBA application
requires the following application
components. You'll provide a cover
letter, a resume, a video statement, a
second video question, one letter of
recommendation, two additional
references, an organizational chart,
transcripts, two professional short
answer questions. Test scores are
optional and then you'll respond to the
question, the world that shaped you.
Like I said before, we have two
application deadlines. The first one
being October 20th and then we have a
second application deadline in late
January on January 26th. We invite you
to apply when you feel that your
application is at its strongest.
So now let's talk about each of the
application components in some more
detail.
The first one is the cover letter. The
prompt for this is to submit a cover
letter seeking a place in the MIT Sloan
Sloan Fellows MBA program. You have 300
words or less to um submit in this cover
letter. A couple things as you are kind
of approaching your cover letter and
deciding what to put in it. Um this is
really the place for you to sell
yourself and talk a little bit about why
MIT Sloan. As you think about all of the
application components, it's really
helpful when you're able to provide
specific examples and details that
really showcase your past successes and
your leadership skills. And so the cover
letter is a great opportunity to provide
either a recent professional or personal
example that further demonstrates why
you're a good match for the Sloan
Fellows community, the Sloan Fellows
program, and the Sloan community. One
thing that's really important within the
cover letter is that you this is not the
place to be focusing on your future
goals. Within the Sloan Fellow's
application, there is a specific
question focused on your future goals.
So, please use that space in the
application to detail future goals.
There is limited real estate across all
of our application components. So, it's
really important that you are answering
the prompt or question that's being
posed for that specific application
component. Please keep the the future
goals in the future goals question and
leave this space to really sell yourself
and talk why talk about why you are a
good fit for the MIT Sloan Sloan Fellows
MBA program.
The next application component is your
resume. Um there are a few restrictions
for um the format of your resume. So,
we're asking for a two-page maximum,
Times New Roman font, size 10, um,
uploading either a Word or PDF document,
and we ask that you structure this in
reverse chronological order. Um, the
biggest tip for completing your resume
is to make sure you're following those
formatting requirements. There are just
a couple of them. Um, so please make
sure that you follow those as requested.
The next tip, um, making sure that it's
easy to read and easy to follow. We want
to be able to see your career
progression um and easily be able to
follow that. And so making sure that you
on your end have um provided a concise
story within your resume is really
helpful. The next piece um oftentimes
when you're writing a resume, you might
be including your job responsibilities.
We really want to see quantifiable
accomplishments in this resume rather
than your job responsibilities. So
really highlighting the successes and
the impact of your work and the v
various roles that you've had in your
resume is really important. In the
education section, you're welcome to
provide any additional awards or
scholarships or professional societies
that you were involved in. For your work
experience, um please make sure that
you're including your company name,
title, again, resultsoriented bullets
that demonstrate your skill set that you
would bring into the program. um the
dates of your experience and then you're
welcome to provide additional
information outside of your professional
and academic experiences. We really want
to get to know who you are as a whole
person. And so if you're actively
engaged in um extracurricular
activities, community service, if you
have continued learning with any
certifications, have any special skills
you want to highlight, um you can
certainly use space on your resume to
highlight that. Again, we're looking for
who you are as a whole person. And so
the professional and academic aspects
are definitely important, but feel free
to use a little space to provide
additional detail about what you do
outside of your professional work.
The next application component is a
video statement. The prompt for this is
for you to introduce yourself to your
future classmates. Um, this is really a
great place for you to share a little
bit about who you are personally. Um, we
encourage you to let your personality
shine. Um, this can help put a little
bit of color onto who you are and how
you might show up in the Sloan
classroom. And we really enjoy watching
these videos and getting to know you
more personally. So, feel free to share
whatever information you would like to
to introduce yourselves. Um, I will note
that these videos are not ever shown to
your future classmates, so it is just
for us on the admissions committee. Um,
but we're excited to get to know you
through this video statement. A couple
kind of tips as you're approaching the
video statement. Um, we're asking for
you to provide a 60-second video
statement so you have um kind of limited
time to share whatever details you would
like to. We encourage you to use your
best judgment and be aware of your
surroundings when you're recording your
video. Some folks might um record it
outdoors or in a space where they um
might be doing one of their hobbies or
um engaging in one of their personal
interests. Some folks might record it um
sitting at their computer. All of those
are fine. Um just make sure that we can
see and hear you clearly regardless of
where you're taking your video. And
again um show us your p personality. We
want to get to know the whole you. Um,
and so this is a great opportunity to
share a little bit more about that.
We have a second video question that
you'll also complete, and this is a
opportunity to respond to a randomly
generated open-ended prompt. A couple
things to note with video question two.
As you first open the application,
you'll notice that it's not immediately
available. um you'll have to complete
some components of the application
before you're able to view the video
question two um tab in the application.
Once you are able to view it, a couple
things to note as well. Uh you will have
to test your video and your microphone
and you'll go through that series of
tests and have to click an additional
check box saying you're ready to go and
ready to record your answer. Um so
please use the test environment to feel
comfortable with the software where your
question will be prompted um where it
will show the time that you have to
record or if it's recording um and
really ensure that your video and
microphone are ready to go for the
recording. So please use the test
environment um so that you are
comfortable before you start recording
because you do only have the one chance
to record this video. Um the video that
is recorded is the one that will be
uploaded into your application. So you
do just have the one chance. When you
decide that you're ready to record your
um question, you'll go through the test
environment and click the check box
saying you're ready, at which point your
question will appear. And you'll have 10
seconds to prepare for this question and
60 seconds to record your response.
There is no advanced preparation that's
needed for these questions. They're all
about your experiences and so there are
no right or wrong answers. We're really
looking at these videos to assess how
you think on your feet and communicate
authentically. It's a really good
indicator of how you might show up in
the various Sloan classrooms. So really,
you can approach it like you would a
conversation or how you might be in the
mindset for an interview question. But
again, it's all about your experiences.
Um, an example of a question you might
see is to tell us about your proudest
accomplishment.
So, we hope you have fun um recording
these videos and sharing a little bit
more based on the question that you're
prompted with. Um, but again, there is
only the one chance to record this video
and the video that is recorded is what
will be in your application.
The next component is your
recommendation letter. We require one
letter of recommendation letter and just
one letter of recommendation. Um, as
you're thinking about who to ask to be
your recommener, we um recommend that
you give whoever you're asking at least
6 weeks in advance of the application
deadline so that they have ample time to
really write a robust letter that
answers the questions that we're asking
of them. Ideally, this is coming from a
manager or supervisor who can really
speak to the impact of your work and
again provide specific detailed examples
of your experiences.
One really important thing is that um we
ask that you do not write the letter for
your recommener. This should come from
their authentic voice based on their
experiences with you. And as you think
about who who can be the person to write
your letter of recommendation on the
right hand side of the screen, you'll
see the six questions that we're asking
a recommener to answer. So, we'll just
read through them quickly. We want to
know how long and in what capacity the
recommener has known you as the
applicant. We want to know how the
recommener sees the applicant stand out
from others in a similar capacity. We're
looking for a specific example of the
applicant's impact on a person, group,
or organization.
We're looking for an example of how the
applicant interacts with other people,
space to tell us anything else that they
think we should know about the
applicant, and then detailing a time
that they gave you constructive feedback
and what you did with the constructive
feedback. So really think critically
about who can answer these questions and
provide in-depth um responses to all of
them is really important and helps us in
the um admissions process.
First loan fellows oftent times you
might be leading um organizations and so
you you might be wondering who to ask to
be a recommener if you don't have any
one that you're reporting to directly.
Um, sometimes folks might ask clients or
mentors that they work with closely if
they are leading their organizations.
But again, thinking critically about who
can provide these examples and details
to these questions is who you should ask
to be your recommener. Um, for folks
working in family businesses, please do
not have your recommener be a me a
family member.
In addition to the letter of
recommendation, you'll also provide two
additional references. And so these are
similar to a recommener um where they
should be able to speak about your
professional experiences and
professional aptitude. The questions
that we would ask a reference are very
similar to what we ask a recommener. Um
and one thing to note with the
additional references is that we may or
may not contact them during the
admissions process. If we are looking to
get additional data and information on
your candidacy, we will contact them to
schedule a time that works um for both
parties. And so, please make sure that
you have notified your references if
they will be included in your
application. And um oftent times we get
questions from applicants who have a
couple people they might want to write
letters of recommendation.
As you approach our application, again,
we just have one letter of
recommendation that is required and
allowed. And so, as you think about who
else can speak to your professional
aptitude, pick the person that can
really provide those specific examples
in a recommendation letter. And then
other folks that might still be able to
speak about your professional aptitude
can be listed as the two additional
references.
The next component of the application is
the organizational chart. And for our
Sloan Fellows application, I would say
this is really a great visual
representation of the general management
experience that's hopefully highlighted
throughout your entire application. We
really use this as a visual to
understand your role within your greater
organization. really defining where your
sphere of influence is and the
relationships that you work with in a
day-to-day basis. We want to know who
you're working with to influence their
decisions and who you're working um with
to kind of develop more professionally
and folks that may be reporting to you
as you complete your organizational
chart. Um if you're working for a large
organization, you may just include your
function. um some organizations if you
have 20 folks you'll be able to include
everyone on your organizational chart.
Um but really just using your um best
judgment to showcase all of those
relationships that you're able to um
feel free to uh highlight any indirect
reports as well in the organizational
chart. Those are helpful to see. We ask
that you circle yourself in red so that
it's very clear where you sit in the
organizational chart. And um one key
thing as you're completing the
application, all of the components
should align. So thinking back to the
resume, whatever you list as your
current employment should match what you
upload in the employment section of the
application and that should match what
your organizational chart is. It should
be from your current organization. Um,
so keeping that in mind and a couple
things as well within the organizational
chart, you might be able to highlight
your recommener or your references. And
so finding an easy way um to point that
out for us is really helpful. In some
cases, you may be able to highlight the
past roles that you had in your
organization to show your career
progression. That's helpful to see as
well. And so again, this is just a
visual representation that um can
further highlight those relationships.
Um and we will look at it in conjunction
with all of your other application
materials to kind of see the impact of
your work and where your sphere of
influence has been in general
management.
The next component we'll talk about are
test scores. For the Sloan Fellow's
application, they are completely
optional. Um, if you choose to submit a
test score, you can submit a GMAT, focus
or 10th edition, GRE scores, executive
assessment scores, in-person, and remote
options um are all accepted. So, if
you've taken a a test and you would like
to provide the score, you're welcome to.
Um, again, it is an optional component.
Oftentimes, we get questions about when
it's best to provide a test score. I
think in looking that at our class
profile, um, you can find a way to kind
of benchmark yourself and where you fall
in that class profile based on test
scores and we encourage if you have a
competitive test score to upload it as
an additional data point. Um, but again,
it's up to you in your judgment if you
would like to provide a test score or
not. If a test score is provided, it
will be considered in the application.
The next component of the application
are your academic records and relevant
coursework section. Um, so we ask that
you provide transcripts from all
institutions that you have attended or
are currently attending. If your
transcripts are in another language,
you'll also provide um a certified
translation um in English.
There is also space for you to upload
additional non-deree coursework or
professional certifications. So, please
use that space to show how you've
continued learning um since your
undergraduate degrees.
When we're looking at these application
materials, we're really looking for your
academic aptitude. So, again, thinking
about how we are evaluating candidates,
we're looking for your demonstrated
successes professionally and
academically and your leadership skills.
And so these components really help us
see your past successes in an academic
environment um and really help us
understand your mastery of a subject
area that you chose to study. We're
really looking for your comfort with
quantitative work. We don't have any
prerequisite courses required for this
loan fellow's MBA, but there is a
section where you'll detail what
quantitative if if any um courses you've
previously taken. This is helpful for us
to kind of gauge how you would perform
in the Sloan Fellows core classes in
addition to the elective offerings. And
again, like I noted, um we really like
to see a sense of intellectual curiosity
and that you're committed to continuous
learning. And so if you've taken
additional courses or certifications or
training, please use the space to
highlight those trainings or
certifications for us.
The next component of the application
are professional questions. So, you have
two professional questions that you'll
respond to in 200 words or fewer. The
first one is the space where you'll tell
us about your immediate and long-term
professional objectives and how the Loan
Fellow's MBA will help you achieve them.
Um, so again, if you think back to what
we were talking about with the cover
letter, I said that's not the space for
future goals. This specific professional
question is where you'll detail those
future goals for us. The second question
is where you'll detail your your general
management experience um and really
defining
what those experiences are. Oftent times
it will show up in various places
throughout your application in addition
to this area that you explicitly detail
your general management experience.
These questions um are limited to just
words, 200 words or less. So keep that
in mind.
And then the last application component
is the world that shaped you. We're
really excited to learn more about how
the world that you come from has shaped
who you are today. This question, you
have 250 words or less to tell us about
that. Um and this is a really great
opportunity to expand on your
background. So again, I've said this a
few times, but we're really looking
forward to getting to know who you are
as a whole person. Um, and this can
really provide that opportunity to
expand upon that. Again, this question
is limited to words only, so 250 words
or less. And it's a great opportunity
for you to just share more about what
makes you you.
So, I have a couple kind of overall
admissions tips as you're thinking about
the application and um getting started
with it. The first one is to follow
directions. Um you'll notice throughout
our application there are limited word
counts or seconds on your videos or page
counts or we're asking for specific
formats of materials. Make sure you
follow those directions. we've very
intentionally created the application
and so please we're really looking for
you to follow the directions as
intended.
The next thing I want to say is that
we're really looking for reasons to
admit you. So throughout the application
we're really looking for those data
points to showcase your demonstrated
successes and your leadership skills and
what that would contribute to the Sloan
community. So find the ways and use the
real estate to really highlight those
experiences and what you would bring
into the Sloan community. Um, think of
us as your advocate. So really help us
gather that data that we need to move
you along in the admissions process.
After you submit your application, the
first step would be giving us enough
data and information that we're excited
and want to learn more about your
experiences through an interview. From
there, it would be to admissions. are
really helping us um help you.
We encourage you to be yourselves. We
want to get to know who you are. Um so
really share your authentic voice
throughout the application. Um find the
spaces to share both personal and
professional aspects to your candidacy
and who what makes you you. Um and
really really find those opportunities
throughout the application. And then the
last piece is applying early whenever
your application is fully ready to go.
Um again we encourage international
applicants to apply by the round one
deadline if you are able to um to allow
ample time for the onboarding processes.
But um if your application is ready to
go in round one, we certainly encourage
you to apply for round one. We do have
two application deadlines in the event
that your application is not ready for
October 20th.
So, I know my colleagues have been
answering um a lot of questions
virtually for you all. Um but we have
some time to answer some questions live.
So, I invite my colleague Ally to join
me for any other questions that we have
in the Q&A.
Awesome. Thank you, Maddie. Um yeah, we
got some great questions in the Q&A. Um,
but a couple of things that popped up a
little consistently I think are going to
be great to answer live. Um,
>> could you talk a bit about any
recommendations you have for
reapplicants? How can they best um,
submit their application this year?
>> Yeah, that's a really good question. Um,
we have reapplicants every year who are
successful in their reapplication. Um,
and a couple tips as you're approaching
the application process as a
reapplicant. um know that we still have
your previous application and all the
information that you submitted um the
year prior and so it's really important
for you to provide as much new
information and details and examples in
your new application as possible. Um
we'll look at both your previous
application and your current one at the
same time. And so we're really looking
for those new details. What has changed
in the past year since you applied? Um,
finding new examples to highlight on
your resume and really sharing the
impact of your work within the past year
is really important for reapplicants.
Reapplicants also have a dedicated
question where you'll highlight or
provide a summary of what has changed
since you last applied. And so that's a
great opportunity to kind of summarize
everything that has happened and that is
shared throughout your application
materials for the admissions committee.
So again, you should provide all new
materials and provide as much new
information as possible throughout the
application, new examples and new
details so that we can review that in
conjunction with your previous
application.
>> Awesome. Thank you. Um there were a
couple of questions about the org chart.
So, I'm wondering if you give some more
detail on some scenarios specifically if
someone is maybe um doing some freelance
work or is an entrepreneur, what can
they submit? And then also, if someone
has an employer that maybe has some
confidentiality um guidelines to follow,
what would someone do in those
situations?
>> Yeah, absolutely. Um I will note briefly
that we have a sample org chart on our
website. So, feel free to take a look at
that. um and that showcases that many of
the names of folks are redacted. We just
show titles of many of the folks on the
org chart. Um so provide as much
information as you're able to, but if
your organization um does have some
confidentiality concerns or um
information cannot be shared more
broadly, you are welcome to redact
whatever information cannot be shared
with us. Um, for folks that may have um
be doing freelance work or consultants,
um, we're again looking for an
organizational chart from your current
work. And so you might highlight a
current project that you're working on
or an engagement that you're involved
with and highlighting those
relationships, even if it's outside of
your organization. Um, if you're working
directly with a client, you might
highlight their organizational chart and
how you relate um to those roles. And so
really um highlighting your current work
and what you're doing and showcasing
those relationships is what's most
important. Um and for some it might look
slightly different than others um but
that's what we would recommend as you
approach the organizational chart.
>> Awesome. Thanks.
Um another question we got was about how
we look for managerial experience in the
application. Um, does someone have to
have direct reports in order to have
that managerial or leadership uh,
experience shown? How do we evaluate
that?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Um, it is
not a requirement of the Sloan Fellows
MBA to have direct reports. Many most
times our applicants do have direct
reports or indirect reports that they're
working with. I think what's most
important is what the experiences are
that you're having in the leadership. Um
so if you're leading a specific
organization or leading specific teams,
maybe you're not leading um individuals
in a direct way, but you have um
responsibility for strategy or budget of
a function um or of an organization.
Those are that's the experience that
we're looking for, that general
management experience where you have
kind of large scale impact on an
organization or a function. And often
times that means that you have direct
reports, but sometimes you don't. And
that is perfectly fine. Um, in your
organizational chart and the employment
section, you'll be able to detail how
many direct reports that you have. Um,
so if you have any, highlighting them
for us. If not, that's perfectly fine.
And we'll really use the organizational
chart to see those relationships that
you have. Um, whether you have direct
reports or not.
>> Makes sense. Thanks.
Um along similar lines, how do we look
for um the words used before were quant
comfortable? What exactly does that mean
and how would one demonstrate that if
not including GMAT or GRE scores? What
are some other ways they would be able
to um show that on their application?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Um if you
look on our website, we have a few
different relevant courses that we're we
ask you to detail in the application.
Things like if you've taken a calculus
course or a statistics course. And so
this is one of the ways that we can kind
of determine your level of comfort with
quantitative work if you've previously
done any and how you performed in those
classes. Oftentimes students might not
have taken any of those classes or it's
been many years since they were in those
classes. And so there are variety of
other ways that you can demonstrate your
comfort with quant work um outside of
the relevant coursework section. One of
the ways is if you've taken any
additional certifications, um done any
professional trainings or non-deree
coursework, there's space in the
application to detail any of those. Um
sometimes we might have students who
maybe complete MBA math as they're
preparing for an application just to
refresh themselves on those topics.
You're welcome to provide details of
courses like MBA math in that um section
of the application. Outside of that, um
the work that you're doing um may also
be quantitate. You may have aspects of
your work that are quantitative. And so
if you highlight those on your resume,
that's helpful for us to see. We're
really just looking for evidence that
you're prepared to be successful in the
classroom. And that can show up in a
variety of places. The previous um
academics that you've done, any
non-deree coursework, your professional
work that you've done. And so if you
don't have specific courses, um just
making sure that it it's shown somewhere
in your application materials your
ability to be comfortable with
quantitative coursework um to help us
kind of um identify if you're prepared
for the the rigor of the program.
>> Sounds great. Just going to keep
monitoring this chat for a little bit
here, looking for some other themes that
have popped up.
>> This is just like a general resume
formatting question. Um, should like the
formatting that we include on the
application be followed directly? Is
there any um room to include an intro
paragraph at the beginning? What are
your suggestions for formatting that
resume?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Um, we
only have a few different a few
requirements for formatting. Size 10,
um, Times New Roman font, two-page
maximum, Word or PDF document, reverse
chronological order. So, if you want to
include a little introduction paragraph
in your resume, you're more than welcome
to. Um, just make sure that you're
following all of those other formatting
requirements and keeping it to a maximum
of two pages.
um you're welcome to include that, but
at a minimum, we're looking for you to
include your academic history, your
employment history, and then um space
for any additional information you want
to share about extracurriculars or
community organizations that you're
involved in.
>> Um is there any place on the application
where students should apply for
scholarships or fellowships? How does
that work for Sloan Fellows?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Um,
within our application, we have a
funding page where you'll read a little
bit about what opportunities are
available and what resources are
available. Um, for the Sloan Fellows
application, you'll indicate if you are
or not interested in being considered
for a fellowship. All of the fellowships
that are awarded for Sloan Fellows are
merit-based, and it's based off of
everything that's included in your
application. So, you just check a check
box within the application. Um, but I
will say all admitted applicants are
automatically considered for the
merit-based fellowships. And then if
you're interested in considering other
opportunities, um, please use the
resources that are linked within our
application to, um, websites like the
Sloan student funding website, um, to
explore other opportunities.
Um, I know we are nearing the end of our
time here. Um, I think we covered just
about everything that I'm seeing in the
Q&A function. Of course, if we missed
your question, we have the email up
there, so please don't hesitate to reach
out. But I think that'll be it for the
Q&A.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Ally. Um, and thank you
everyone for joining us for today's
application tips webinar. Like Ally
said, if you have any additional
questions, feel free to email us at
sfmbba admissions.edu.
We're excited to answer any questions
that you have throughout the process and
get to know you through the admissions
process. Again, we thank you all for
joining us today and we look forward to
reviewing your applications in a few
months.