Hi, I'm Mark Lindseay and I'm a
cardiologist specializing in genetic
arterial disease at the Massachusetts
General Hospital.
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Praep Nodarajin and I'm the
director of preventive cardiology and
genetics researcher at Mass General
Hospital and the Broad Institute of MIT
and Harvard.
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Tiffany Bellamo and I'm a
vascular surgery resident at the
Massachusetts General Hospital.
Spontaneous coronary artery dissection
or SCAD is defined as a tear or a
separation in the wall of the coronary
artery, but it's not associated with
athoscerosis or trauma. It's an
emergency health situation where blood
flow is slowed or obstructed that can
lead to a heart attack or sometimes even
sudden death.
>> SCAD has been known to affect men and
women. However, SCAD most commonly
affects women. SCAD patients are often
healthy and without risk factors of
heart disease such as high cholesterol
or diabetes.
>> SCAD is a rare condition linked to
arterial fragility sometimes caused by
well-known genetic disorders like
vascular ellers stanlo syndrome, morphan
syndrome and loystein syndrome. These
conditions involve mutations that weaken
blood vessels and increase the risk of
arterial tears.
Researchers haven't yet found all the
genes that clearly increase the risk of
SCAD. We can increase the discovery of
genes associated with SCAD by collecting
health data and samples from larger and
more diverse patient groups. The
scarcity and unpredictable nature of
SCAD make it challenging to study. But
with the GVAS research study, we can
make significant progress.
>> GVAS is short for genetics of vascular
disease. This is a research study that
is designed to gather health information
from patients who have been diagnosed
with SCAD or other vascular
abnormalities. The study operates out of
Massachusetts General Hospital and the
Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard.
Participation in the GVAS study includes
completing surveys online about your
health information and providing a
saliva sample which can be mailed to
your home. All information will be kept
confidential and in a secure database
and will never be sold for profit. GVAS
study staff and researchers abide by the
policies and guidelines instilled by the
Mass General Bighgam Institutional
Review Board.
The GVAS study aims to perform the
largest sequencing project to date of
individuals with SCAD. We are working
together to create a research community
of individuals highly motivated to
investigate the genetics of SCAD and set
the foundation for future research. This
community is enhanced by the
contributions and partnership from the
ICAD registry and SCAD Alliance which
also aim to better understand and
support patients with SCAD.
>> We invite members of the SCAD community
to join the GBASK research study and
share it with others. Your partnership
will be key in understanding why SCAD
happens and how it can be prevented and
treated.
>> Visit gvasstudy.org
to learn more and enroll into the study.
And visit scadalliance.org to find
resources and support groups for members
of the SCAD community.