Good morning everybody. Welcome to the
MPG primer. Today it is my pleasure to
introduce Pamela. Pamela is a genomic
specialist for Clinen at the Broad
Institute and an expert in variant and
gene curation. She co-chairs the Clinen
ClinVar curation working group advancing
accurate var variant classification. Her
background includes germline and somatic
curation for an Australian childhood
cancer program and a biotech startup
where she also developed genomic
training workshops. Pamela serves on the
board of directors for the federation of
American societies for experimental
biology, the education committee of the
cancer genomics consortium and the
professional relations committee of AM.
She earned her PhD studying microRNAs in
head and neck cancer. and today she's
going to give us a primer on clinical
genomic resources. So, thank you very
much Pam for speaking today.
>> Thank you. Um I want to start off first
by saying it's my pleasure to be here
today. Um I could talk about Clen
Clenver genomic resources all day. I
won't do that though. I will stick to
the 45 minutes. Um but before I get into
the deep dive on genomic resources, I
wanted to start off first with a story.
Um, so this is a story about a disease
that's been a defining challenge in
medicine for over the past century,
which is cickle cell. And this is a
life-threatening genetic disorder that's
associated with anemia, infection, and
episodes of pain. If you look at the
figure on the right, it shows how red
blood cells are in the sickled cell
shape, hence the name, that can cause
them to get stuck in blood vessels,
blocking blood flow and leading to
really serious downstream health
consequences.
Now, this is caused by a single base
pair change in the hemoblobin gene, and
an individual with cickle cell disease
has both copies of that gene mutated.
And this is the most common uh variation
of cickle cell disease.
So it is known that it affects millions
of people throughout the world and is
particularly common among those whose
ancestors came from parts of the world
where malaria was or is still common.
And so cle cells are really classic
example of a monogetic disorder where
you have a change in a single gene that
leads to really profound clinical
consequences.
Now, in 2023, the narrative did change
and some of you might notice um so what
I've got here is a press release from
the FDA where they had approved two
milestone treatments. So, this was Kazvi
and Lisgenia, which were the first
cellbased gene therapies for the
treatment of cickle cell disease. Um,
also really cool is that cuz Jeevy was
actually the first ever FDA approved
therapy that was developed with crisper
technology. And it's my understanding
it's actually the work of one of the
broadies that also contributed to this.
So that's just a really great example of
seeing that bench to bedside happen in
action.
Now I do have a bit of a personal
connection with this disease. I actually
recently found out through carrier
genetic testing that I have cickle cell
trait which means that I carry one
abnormal copy of the betaglobin gene and
the gen genetics behind that is that I
have what we call a missense variant. So
in the gene on the DNA level at a
specific position instead of an adinine
I have a thymine. So going from A to T
and on a protein level that's going from
glutamic acid to veiling.
Uh what does that mean in terms of
symptoms? Honestly, I have never really
felt any symptoms throughout my life. Um
I wish I had known about it a few years
ago when I was in Bali worrying about
mosquitoes and malaria. Um and not
knowing that all along I kind of had the
superpower essentially. Um there are
some serious implications if you are
planning to have a a family. Um, so if
my partner is also a carrier, and I've
just got a little diagram down there,
then our child has a one in4 chance of
developing cickle cell disease.
I'm going to be honest, we weren't too
worried just because my husband does
look like this. Um, but it's not zero,
so we still got him tested. Um, and what
I want to now show is our first genomic
resource, which is Nomad. Um so this is
a huge resource of the general
population um with exo sequencing and
genome sequencing data and you can
essentially look at a variant and see is
this a rare variant or is it common in
the general population and you can even
look at it further by ancestral groups.
So I've highlighted two. I'm in the
African African-Amean bucket where the
frequency for the variant that I have is
about 5%. actually turns out because I
have generations of Nigerian heritage um
it's more like 25% for me. Um but my
partner who's of the European non-finish
background you can see it's quite low.
It's like 0.004%.
So um it's always worth to check and do
your genetic testing if you can. Um but
it really starts to be this is my segue
into the rest of the talk showing
genomic resources, why they're
important, how we use them.
Um, so there's heaps out there, lots of
resources. Um, I'm just going to speak
about some of them in a broad level and
just show some examples as well. Um, so
grouping them into three different
buckets. We've got like the gene level
associations where we're trying to
figure out, you know, is this gene
actually linked to this disease? And you
can see some examples along there. And
then there's the variant level side
where you want to know are there
interpretations that have been made
about this variant? Is there any kind of
functional data that can be used or a
little frequencies in databases like
Nomad? Um these can be publicly
available so anyone can access that
information or it can be commercial
where you got to pay a little bit of
money to access that database. Um or in
some cases a lot of money. Um and then
there's the case level side where you
have deidentified patient information um
and you're looking into that data
identifying varants and the phenotypes
the observable traits and trying to make
associations there.
So it is a clinen clinva other genomic
resources talk which means there's going
to be a heavy um talk on clinen um so
this is short for the clinical genome
resource and it's really the purpose
behind it was to and is to create an
authoritative central resource that
defines the clinical relevance of genes
and varants for use in precision
medicine and research. Um, this started
back in September 2013.
Um, and it is primarily funded by the
NIH, which in 20125 in the states.
That's a fun time as I'm sure you're all
aware. Um it's covered by three core
grants throughout the US um with PIs at
multiple sites including at the broad um
one sematic cancer grant, one
pharmaccogenomics
and um just over 20 disease focused
grants as well. And all of this is
fueled into this mission on the left um
which is a infograph depicting what we
do. So we have our stakeholders at the
top where we're able to aggregate
deidentify genomic and health data um
and use that to answer Clinen's four
critical questions. One, gene disease
validity. Does variation in this gene
lead to disease? Two, variant
pathogenicity. Is this variant disease
causing? Three, dosage sensitivity. Does
copy gain or loss of this gene or
genomic region lead to disease? And
four, clinical actionability. If this
gene was significantly altered, could it
confer a high risk of serious disease
that could have been mitigated if that
disease risk was known? And so we do
this in the form of our expert panels is
what we call them. Um, which consists of
scientists and clinicians around the
world who are experts in the field. and
we come together on a frequent basis um
focusing on a series of diseases and
answering these questions using
established frameworks that have been
created and then this information is
disseminated to the public. Um and it
fuels back into these questions and we
have this feedback system and the end
goal here is really just to improve
patient care through genomic medicine.
Additionally, Clinen also has um the
honor of being a global core biodata
resource, meaning that it is considered
of such fundamental importance to the
biological and life sciences community
um for the preservation of biological
data. So, it's a cool honor to have.
So this paper came out last year from
the Clinton consortium and really just
shows the progress of the past decade in
essence. Um and the figure on the right
really shows the explosive growth of
Clinen's expert panels over time. You
can see in pink the gene curation expert
panels and in blue are the gene
curations and then in orange are the
variant curation expert panels and in
green are the variant curations. And
we're now at what we call phase three
which is all about scaling and
sustainability. So we have so much data.
How do we continue to maintain this in a
feasible manner? And also how do we
scale our efforts? There's still so much
to do and how do we do that in a
resource sensitive and mindful way.
Um here I've got a slide showing Clinen
leadership who are responsible for
oversight and the direction of Clinen as
a whole um and they're all around the US
and then additionally
um we also have 100 plus staff members
such as myself um who are involved in
additional leadership roles,
coordination. Clen is a beast. It's a
fantastic beast, but there's lots of
moving parts, so coordination is
necessary. Um, biocuration,
software development, and many other
roles. We also have over 50 working
groups that manage standards,
operations, and software, and also over
140 expert panels.
Wanted to highlight the Clinen team at
the Broad site, which is where we're at
today. Um, so this is co-led by the PIs.
You can see here professors Heidi Ree
and Marina Dfina at the top. Um and then
this is a diligent hardworking team that
um really make sure that we keep clinen
running from our side.
Okay. So let's start to talk about
Clinen's expert panels. So in order to
do that um we have what we call our
clinical domain working groups. So
there's 15 of them. You can see them on
the left there. um focus on specific
disease areas essentially and then that
leads to 58 gene curation experiencation
expert panels and another thing that I
really want to highlight is that yes we
have about 100 or so staff but the bulk
of Clenen is actually our 2,800 plus
volunteers all around the world from 74
countries that actively contribute to
our extra panels in our working group.
So, Clenon wouldn't exist without them.
Um, so we're always very thankful for
that.
So, today I'm going to be focused on
gene and variant um curation. I'm not
going to talk about those clinical or
sematic um but before we can define a
variant's role in disease, we first must
assess the gene level evidence.
Um and so I want to show another
resource which is Omen. Um this is a
absolutely comprehensive resource for
finding claims that have been made
between a given gene and disease. Um
looking at recent stats from Omen, they
have over 7,000 phenotypes or observable
traits for which there is some sort of
molecular basis known. Um which equates
to about 5,000 or so genes that are
associated with a phenotype causing
mutation. So that's a lot of data,
especially for very um uh other
comparative resources that do the same
thing. Um in order for a gene to enter
this database, it does need a minimum
level of evidence. So it's not just
anything and everything. It's really
genes that it seems like there there
could be something there.
Um and OM includes variants for a given
gene and disease that are kind of like
exemplar variants for that. So it's not
a complete catalog either of every
variant that has been reported in
association with that disease.
Now there's lots of ways to use Omen.
I'm just going to show a really simple
way um where you can put in a gene and
I've put in here MSX1 and you can have a
look and see okay um what diseases have
been asserted for this gene and then you
can click into them and look into it
further and see okay what are the
phenotypes associated with this disease
that have been reported. um if you got
patient data you're looking at, does it
match your patient? Um if you're trying
to figure out more about the disease and
figure out if it's part of a spectrum,
um you know, you can do comparisons
there. There's lots of different things
and it's a really great starting point
for that.
Okay, so now I'm going to start to talk
about um gene disease validity, which
I'm using interchangeably with gene
curation um from the Clenen side of
things.
So on the top left there is the
publication that came out a few years
ago describing the evidencebased
semi-quantitative framework that Clinen
uses for gene curation. Um and
essentially this is subdivided into
genetic evidence and experimental
evidence. So when we're thinking about
genetic evidence we're thinking about
things like case reports, case series,
case control data, family pedigrees. um
and we have a point system that we use
as a scoring metric. And then similarly
with experimental evidence, we're
looking at things like biochemical
evidence, expression data, um animal
studies, all of that to support the gene
disease relationship as well. And so the
points are added up and then based on
the amount of points you get, the more
points you have um the more evidence
supporting that gene disease
relationship. So at the top we have
definitive if I can get my mouse to go
there. Um, as the most amount of
evidence and then at the bottom we have
refuted as the least amount. Basically
saying that at this point there is no
substantial evidence at all supporting
that gene disease relationship.
Okay. So there are implications
downstream on what the final class is
for a given gene disease relationship.
Um on the right uh technical standards
that came out a few years ago from the
American College of Medical Genetics and
Genomics ACMG
um basically giving guidance around how
to diagnose a sequencing panel and um
report variance um from that. Now um in
essence if you are in the kind of
discovery stage research settings you're
going to identify genes and diseases
that meet that entire spectrum of uh
classification.
However, as soon as patients are
involved, you need to have a pretty good
amount of confidence that that gene is
actually associated with that disease.
And so when you want to design a
diagnostic panel, the recommendation is
to have moderate or above as the
evidence um strength for that gene
disease relationship. And then the next
tier above that is predictive testing
where you have an asymptomatic
individual who wants to understand their
risk of developing disease. And so for
that we use the highest tier of um
evidence for gene disease validity
classification.
So this is just showing the data from
Clinen's 58 gene curation exop panels.
That's just a subset of them there. Um
colorcoded by the final classification
that they received. Um when I last
checked it was 3,331
total gene disease curations. Um three
is my lucky number. So I was kind of
hoping it'll be 3 three3 by the time
this talk came around, but no such luck.
That's okay. Um and then this is just
showing at the top the distribution of
the classifications and you can see the
vast majority are definitive. However,
there is a subset of the insufficient
evidence about 23%
which don't have enough claim. And
that's kind of concerning because a lot
of the times when we're looking at these
genes in our expert panels, it's because
they're on diagnostic panels. So we
shouldn't be seeing them. you know, they
should be having more evidence. So, it's
it's a little bit concerning. It just
highlights why it's important to do gene
curation first.
All right, this is our golden example of
like why you need to do gene curation
first. Um, so this was a paper that came
out a few years ago from the Bata
syndrome expert panel. They were looking
at 21 genes that are commonly found on
diagnostic panels for Briata syndrome.
So they applied the gene curation
framework and lo and behold to their
shock and horror only one gene just one
gene had definitive evidence for bata
syndrome. The remaining 20 genes were
actually disputed meaning that the
evidence was conflicting at best and yet
these were appearing on diagnostic
panels. Right? That's a worry. Um, and
so it just really highlights why we
really encourage gene curation to be
done before designing a diagnostic panel
and using it on patients.
So these are just a few screenshots
showing the clin knowledge base. It's
honestly quite huge. There's no way I
could show everything in time. Um, but
there's lots of different uses. If you
haven't used or been on this website
before, it's a treasure trove of
information. I recommend you use it. I'm
not just saying that as someone who's
paid to work for Clinen. I said that for
years prior even, you know, receiving a
single paycheck um from the place. Um
but it is genuinely a fantastic
resource. Um you can put in your gene of
interest and you can see if there's any
kind of curations in the gene space, the
variant space, the CNV space, um sematic
clinical actionability, all of that and
um see what evidence that has been
expertly curated towards it. Um, so
everything we do, we're all about being
thorough and transparent. And so when
you click in into any gene, disease, or
variant, you'll find out the evidence
that we use to score it, how we scored
it, and why.
So just here is just an example of the
my gene and you can see from the gene
disease validity perspective that the it
has been curated against four different
diseases. um the final classifications
are different especially for that last
one there. Um and you can click in
further and find out why
um if any kind of CNV uh review has been
done that will appear under dosage
sensitivity and then similarly
actionability will have a report if
that's available.
I'll talk about our variant curation
exop panels later but if one exists and
they've started they've created
specifications and curated variants
you'll find that evidence there as well.
Um, so I want to talk about the curation
ecosystem now. So I've talked about
clinen quite a bit and the consortium
and what we do, but we also work quite
closely with two other resources. The
first one I'm going to go into is gencc
or the gene curation coalition.
um which is a database for sharing gene
level knowledge and this is supported by
clinen.
So gencc is actually co-led by two of
broads pis that I introduced earlier.
So, Marina Dust Stefano and Heidi Ree.
Um, and so their vision before Gen CCC
became a reality was based on the fact
that for a while you had lots of groups
out there who were also doing gene
curations all in isolation and not
sharing their data. And as we know at
science, collaboration is key, right,
for scientific progress and and
discoveries. And so they envisioned
essentially what could be a one-stop
shop for gene curations and convinced
quite a good number of submitters which
you can see up there um to come together
and share it in this database. So this
is a combination of public and private
resources
and part of creating genC and getting
them on board was also developing
consistent terminology for gene disease
validity assessments. And if you think
about it, right, if we're calling
something with the most amount of
evidence definitive, another group needs
to have the same name or we need to come
to an agreement as to what that name
would be, right? We need to be speaking
the same language. We don't want to be
comparing apples to oranges.
Um, and so this has led to the public
sharing of not just published curations,
but also unpublished curations from
these groups. um and they now meet
frequently to collaborate and resolve
discrepancies um on gene curation.
Um so in terms of overall stats from
dencc they have over 24,000 submissions
in their classifications on over 5,000
genes. So very similar to Omen and 16
submitters that actively contribute
their gene curations. Um and on the
bottom you can again just see the
distribution of those classifications
where similarly to clinen about 17% of
those have insuff insufficient evidence
supporting the claim.
Um so one thing that you can do with
gencc there's lots of things actually
but you can put in like your gene of
interest or disease or you can even look
by submitter and basically you can see
what information is out there. Um in
this example here we have GJB3
and you can see that it's associated
with eight diseases from seven different
groups. And so you can just like have a
look and see okay what are the
submitters diseases and what
classifications did they come through
and what's concordant or discordant
between them.
So I want to move on now to variant
pathogenicity. Can I can I ask a
question before you move to the next
part online? Um, someone was thanking
you for bringing up OM and they just
wondered why there's no OM numbers or if
it's possible to add OM numbers to
Clinen
as in in our Clinen curations also have
Omen numbers embedded within them.
>> That's what it sounds like.
>> So, you can actually see um in one of
the sections where if you click down,
it'll say what disease entries were used
and so Omen links would be in there if
if um if used.
All right. So, where was I? Baron
curation. I need to go back one slide.
There we go.
Um, okay. So, when we're thinking about
variant classification,
um, there's a few considerations, right?
Um, so you want to have a set of common
standards for variant classification.
Um, if you think about it, you want a
group in Japan or a group in Australia
or in Germany to see the same variant
from a patient and review the evidence
and come to the same conclusion about
the variants pathogenicity,
right? Um, in order for that to happen,
they need to be using the same
framework. Additionally, you want them
to have access to the same pool of
evidence. Similarly, if you have one
group that has access to internal
patient data, another group that has
access to some functional assays that
Jay just have, another group who has
access to neither, you know, it's a for
sure they're going to come to different
conclusions on the variance
pathogenicity. And so what we really
want to encourage is a breakdown of
those silos and a sharing of evidence so
that we can try to come to a harmonized
classification on a given variant. And
so part of that is having a shared
evidence base which I will talk about in
a bit. Um we also want the public
sharing of variant classifications right
um if there different groups have
different views and there's discordance
we want to know why so we can see what
those discrepancies are. And then
finally, we want to have expert
consensus on these classifications. Um,
one to help resolve discrepancies, but
also for those groups who don't have the
bandwidth or the resources to go and do
those deep dives into the evidence to
support them and which is what our
clinen variant creation extra panels do.
Um, so I'll get into all of that, but
you can see on the right, um, just a
subset. There are so many resources out
there and they just keep growing day by
day. But um these are some very commonly
used ones for variant classification
purposes.
Okay. So common framework. Um so we have
the ACMG AMP standards and the paper
down there is just showing the paper
that came out in 2015. to about a decade
ago um which really is a cornerstone of
variant curation um and describes this
common framework um it acknowledges the
complexity of curation right cur um
classifying variance isn't black and
white I mean sometimes it is but a lot
of the time it's not right it can really
fall on a gradient and so they developed
this five tier classification system
where you had pathogenic likely
pathogenic Um so these are variants that
are considered um reportable and you can
return them back to the patient. Um
there's a variance of uncertain
significance or the vos's and um anyone
in this space would know they are the
bane absolute bane of our existence um
and how labs can treat reporting them um
can be quite different depending on
circumstances of the patient that
they're dealing with. Um but there is
guidance coming out to help with this.
Fingers crossed. Um and then we have
likely benign and benign um which is
considered not reportable because the
variants are not disease causing.
So this is the table of evidence that we
use for variant classification. It
summarizes things like you know is a
variant common or not in a general
population like I showed with Nomad. um
what do the computational predictures
predictors think um of this variant um
are their functional assays out there?
What about the family data? What is that
showing? So using all those pieces of
evidence to then combine them and come
to a final classification which is shown
on the right. Um now those combining
rules have over time proven a little bit
tricky to remember. So we have started
to shift towards a point system which is
quite intuitive. Um and we're expecting
next year, we've been expecting this for
a while, but we've been told it's for
sure next year we are having a long
overdue update to the 2015 standards and
everyone's waiting with baited breath.
Um, and this should really just resolve
some of the issues we've had um with the
current standards such as subjectivity
of um interpreting some of the evidence.
So with Clinton's variant curation
expert panels or VSAPS, their goal is
essentially to take those 2015 standards
which are generic in nature and that's
intentional so you can plug in a given
disease or gene but they take it and
they're focusing on a disease area and a
set of genes and they capture that
information and account for the
biological nuances right that are
associated with diseases. So that's what
they do. um can take a long time, right?
It can take a couple of years at least
to put that together and then those
specifications once approved are made
available um by Clinen for public use.
So genetic testing labs, research labs
can just go on get that information and
use what they need like okay what is the
threshold of population frequency to
consider this rare or frequent like they
don't need to do the research we've done
that for them. Um what we also do is
that vets then publish curations um on a
database called clinbar um to classify
difficult variants and resolve
discrepancies. So it's on climber but
it's also um can be found u within
clingen one of our portals also takes us
to that. Um
the work of clinen beps is a FDA
recognized process um because of how
thorough our curations are um and how
transparent we have to be um in terms of
what evidence we use and why. Um so at
this stage we have 38 fully approved
vsaps associated with 89 gene disease
specifications
where 82 vips in total in various stages
of development.
Um so this equates to almost 12,000
variant curations that have been
published. Um and this is just showing
down here the different um
classifications that they've met.
So going back to curation ecosystem I
now want to talk about clinvar. So this
is a database for sharing variant level
knowledge and is supported by the
national center for biotechnology
information.
So clin has been around for as long as
clinen and at this point has over 6
million submissions and that number
keeps drastically changing. And I feel
like every time I talk about Clinbar,
it's, you know, 3 million, 4 million, 5,
now it's 6 million. Um, and on 4 million
variants and over three, 3,000
submitters from 92 countries. So, the
amount of data in here is unbelievable.
Um, by far the vast majority of
submitters are clinical labs, as you can
see. Um and then a smaller subset are
researchers, clinen expert panels,
patient registries and clinics. Um so
over time has really proven to be a
critical resource for the global
clinical and research genomic
communities.
Um very quickly just for anyone who's
not familiar with ClinVar and what that
looks like. So this is just showing a
variant record for a missense variant in
the MIBPC3
gene. Um and I'm going to try to click
and see how I go here. Each row is a
different submitter, right? Um so on the
left you have information like uh what
classification they gave the variant. Um
if they used a framework, what we call
the assertion criteria, they provide
that. um what condition it was curated,
classified for um and who the submitter
was
um and when that information was put in
in ClinVar and if it's been updated um
if they have evidence that is shown. So
if you see the second submitter, we have
it under comet. Um we love to see
evidence by the way. Um it's important
to know why a group came to a
classification
um and what evidence they used. And then
all this information from the submitters
is then aggregated at the top to a final
classification.
Um and Climber uses a review status to
indicate their level of confidence on
that variant record. So if there's and
review status is just
at the top there.
Okay. Let's see. There we go. Okay. So
if you get zero stars, it means that no
assertion criteria was provided. So you
don't know what framework they use to
classify a variant. Um they get one star
if only a single submitter provided a
submission or if multiple submitters did
but they disagree which is the case here
where you can see it's conflicting um
classification. So that gets a one star.
Um, two stars if multiple submitters
agree, three stars if it's a clinion
expert panel because of our FDA status,
and then four stars if it's a practice
guideline like CFTR, CFTR in um, cystic
fibrosis.
Um now if we start to think of the
landscape of rent records in ClinVar um
the vast majority of them only have a
single submission. It's about 76%.
um 9% of these are actually associated
with conflicting classifications
and of that 1% which equates to 44,000
at the time because this is based on the
June data set from Climbber. Um 1% of
these are considered clinically
significant conflicts, right? These
these are the ones that kind of worry
you a little bit. um they're they're the
ones where um in a variant record you
have a submitter or submitters that
think the variance is reportable path
likely path and then submitters who
think actually the evidence isn't enough
it's it shouldn't be reported it's a v
likely benign benign so you can
understand that that would be quite
confusing to someone who's gone into
clever looked at the variant and
thinking so what is it which one is it
um and when you look at it subdivide
further on the top right um the majority
ity of those clinically significant are
actually at the border of being likely
pathogenic versus a vis. So the ones
where like there's there's just enough
evidence but also for some not just
enough like it it could go either way
and those are the ones that really can
be quite challenging um to know which
bucket they should be in.
Sover's goal was never to actually try
to pass any judgment on the accuracy of
the submissions that they receive. They
just house them. Um, and neither were
they planning to review them over time.
Um, but it's become clear that some
submissions are just inaccurate or just
really old and are missing newer
evidence has come out. And so there's
been calls over time to essentially
clean up Clinbar.
So that's where Clinton steps in.
It will step in in a moment.
Let me do it from the computer.
Okay, there we go. Um, so this is done
in the form of what we call the Clinen
Curation of ClinVaver or CBC working
group. So this is Heidi's brainchild. um
this project
um and it's a group that her and I
co-chair together um where we review old
and outlier submissions in ClinVar to
improve the accuracy of the content in
there. Um and this is just revealing the
team that uh work spent a lot of time on
this project. It's it's complex so it
does require quite a bit of um scientist
power behind the scenes. Um, and it also
includes Melissa Landram, uh, who's the
PI of ClinBar. So, it's something we
really do handinhand with them.
Um, so a little bit more about this
project. Um, so we're focusing on really
obvious issues here. We're not trying to
do any kind of variant classification.
That would be a mammoth task for such a
small team. Um, and also somewhat
redundant when we have our variant
creation expert panels. um what we're
looking at are things that are what we
consider clearly inaccurate, right? Um
so a submission in order to meet that
category typically needs to meet two
qualities, which is that it's either
quite old. Um it's an outlier, so it's
causing conflict or it's lacking
supporting evidence. Um and so we review
those submissions. Uh we apply a flag
that those flag submissions are passed
on to ClinVa. Clever passes it on to the
submitter and basically the submitter
has 60 days to contact us or update
their submission with more evidence or
change their classification
before the flag goes live on Clenbar.
Um, and so what happens is that once a
flag is live, the submission is pushed
down to the bottom of the varant record.
It doesn't disappear. That information
in there can still be useful. It's just
pushed to the bottom and the
classification is removed from the
overall classification. So there's an
example down there where you can see the
flag submission and so that was a V that
was causing conflict but you can now see
after being flagged the classification
has now gone to just path likely path
essentially and gotten a two star. Um
so this project has been going on for a
few years but it officially went live
just over 2 years ago um in ClinBar. And
so in that time um almost 18,000
variants have been reviewed um leading
to just over 4,000 variants um
containing a flag submission in ClinBar.
Um so that's the amount of variants that
have a flag submission. But in terms of
the amount of actual flag submissions,
it's 5,222.
Um, and what we've done, because we want
to know what the community thinks of
this, right? This is a community
database, so we want to make sure
they're receptive and that this is
something they feel is working and
useful. Um, and so we've kept an inquiry
log to keep track of issues.
Um, if there are any, Clville will reach
out to us and connect us with the
submitter. We then investigate on our
end and respond.
Um, and so out of the 5,222
submissions, only 26 of them actually
were challenged by 21 labs. And
challenge is too combative. They really
were just like, "Hey, why was my
submission flagged?" Um, so that's
about.5%.
And a lot of those were actually in the
early days. Um, and so out of those, we
retracted seven flags on our end, and
then the remainder, the submitter
updated their uh submission with more
evidence. Um but again that was more at
the start when we were dealing with some
of the teething issues um as you can
imagine with a complex project. So it
still appears to be really well received
by the community. Um and we're now at a
stage where we're trying to think how do
we scale our efforts um with this
project.
Uh if you do find an error in ClinVar um
please send us the variant. We're always
happy to review them. We have a request
review form on the web page that you can
click in and put in your um the
information and details about the
variant.
Um so in the last little bit of time I'm
going to go through very two very quick
case studies um and the application of
the CBC project. Um one of them you need
to understand that there is a
relationship between gene curation and
variant curation. Gene cation needs to
be done first. And the reason for this
is that if you do curation, gene
curation and a gene gets limited or
below variance in that gene should not
get for that condition should not get
anything above a vos. Um if it scores
moderate the cap there is likely
pathogenic and if it gets strong
definitive then the full spectrum of
pathogenicity can be used for the
variant. Um so this is an example of a
gene curation on the FAM gene that was
done by our cancer expert panels. Um
there's three diseases, three different
classifications. Um I'm using the Fonei
anemia as an example where this received
a refuted classification meaning
variance in this gene for that condition
shouldn't get beyond a vos.
When we went and looked in ClinVar, that
is the case for the vast majority of
submissions, but there is a smaller
number that have uh classified their
variance as pathogenic and likely
pathogenic. And so this is obviously
very confusing um for outside um people
who are using ClinVar and looking at
Fonia anemia. And so we have a side
project going with the CBC work where we
actually review these low evidence gene
disease relationships and see if they're
path likely path uh submissions in clin
that need to be flagged when
appropriate.
The second case study is from the rare
genomes project um which is at the broad
and it's a patient-driven research study
led by genomic experts and clinicians
using genomic sequencing data to find
answers for families with rare and
undiagnosed conditions. Um and so in
this example we had two siblings here a
male and female in their 30s with a list
of phenotypes that you can see there.
and we used Seeker to analyze their
genomic sequencing data. Quick plug for
Seeker for anyone who's not familiar
with it. Um it's a web-based resource.
It's um publicly accessible and it's
fantastic if you have genome exom
sequencing data um for a given patient.
You can put it in there and there's some
preset filters that you can use to try
and identify, you know, what varants
could be um causing the disease being
seen um in the phenotypes in in the
given patient. So
we used that and from that we identified
variants in the KFBP gene. Um when we
look at Gen CC there are multiple
submissions including Clinen saying
there's a definitive gene disease
relationship for autotosoma recessive
Goldberg sprintson syndrome which when
we checked out that disease the
phenotypes were a fantastic match for
these siblings and so um we'd found what
we call a genotype phenotype match here.
I won't go into the variants too much um
in interest of time except to say that
with so there were two variants
identified the first one um a nonsense
variant had all the hallmarks of clearly
being pathogenic
um and in clin it was supported um with
multiple submitters saying yep that's
pathogenic. The second variant was a
little bit trickier.
um the team was able to put enough
evidence to get it at likely pathogenic.
But in ClinVar, this was one that was
calling a causing a clinically
significant conflict um with some
calling it path likely path and one
calling it a V us.
So this is a great case study for the
CBC project. Um when you look at the
path likely pack versus VUS, we wanted
to know why and what was going on there.
So we looked at all the submissions um
and the VS is at the top one wanted one
wanted the likely path at the bottom and
basically we ended up flagging the V
essentially for three reasons. One it
was an outlier was a lot older by
several years than the other
submissions. Two it was an uh it was
causing the conflict and then three it
had insufficient supporting information.
It didn't have as much evidence as some
of the newer um submissions did. So that
met all the criteria for flagging um the
submission and removing it from the
overall variant record.
So I hope I've convinced you in this
time on the power of clinical genomic
resources. As I said there's so much out
there um just chose a subset focusing
mainly on clinen and climber but there
is a lot out there um and they're
absolutely essential for diagnosis and
discovery.
um you know there's gene level, variant
level, case level, there's also therapy
level which I didn't get into as well.
Um I always have to do the final plug at
the end. Um if you are interested in
volunteering for Clinen, there's the QR
codes. We're always interested in having
more biocurators and experts. Um but you
can also find those forms on our
website. Um and then I just want to
finish off on this acknowledgement
slide. Um including the translational
genomics group which is where the broad
clinen team is situated.
Thank you. All this work is based on a
consortium of people. So it is it is a
lot.
>> Great. If you have a question, come up
to the mic and I'm going to quickly read
one online first. Um for individual
clinical labs, how do they get
information for individual diagnostic
test panels? Does each lab create their
own panel or is there some sort of
central database or guidelines? for
example, which genes or broco mutations
would be included on a cancer panel?
>> Um, so one of the most commonly used
ones at the moment and you can find that
through Gen CC actually is panel app.
Um, so they have like a traffic light
system um for a given panel. So they
have lots of panels in there saying um
you know high level evidence is green,
amber, yellow, I forget the three colors
of the the traffic system essentially.
Um and so that's a a great way to like
get a preset pedal. Um and then
obviously you can also cross check with
GCC to see if there's agreements about
the final classification for those genes
and a given disease as well.
Thanks for such a beautiful clear talk.
Um I have two questions. One is the kind
of obvious one about how is AI going to
transform all your processes? And the
other one was I've noticed in the
screening world um people are like well
actually the model that we have of like
we've got genes linked to a disease
we've got variants linked to a disease
is like not sufficiently rich because
you might think you people know oh but
those variants in that part of the gene
they tend to be much less penetrant than
these ones that are over here. So I
think there's like a felt need that we
don't have a rich enough scheme to
capture what we might want to pass on to
patients particularly in the screening
absence of phenotype world and I'm
wondering if there are any thoughts
about like making that underlying model
richer
so penetrance is a challenging thing to
deal with um in our space um and I you
know definitely for genes that uh really
suffer from that um I can understand
from a screening perspective if
something has such low penetrance
It's more a combination and within the
same gene you they they know the
clinicians know that some are low and
some are high.
>> Yes. Agreed. Um and so you know with the
ones that have the the high penetrance,
right? There's less concerns there. it's
it's the ones that are are lower
penetrant and um in terms of framework I
should say that there is uh so clinen
does have a working group focused on
like dealing with risk alils and
penetrance and they've um started to
work on and they've got two public
they've got a publication and a white
paper that's come out really providing
guidance on how to deal with that um in
terms of classifying but also reporting
so I think there's more to come in that
space but like agree that it's it's a
common challenge especially in the
cancer space as well um and then sorry
what was First question,
>> what's AI going to do for you?
>> AI,
it's the buzz word, AI. Um, I mean, we
are working on that. Um, as I imagine
every group is and I I think the hope is
that a lot of what we do is so manually
intensive.
Um, and there's so many areas in there
that really have the opportunity for
automation, right? and and and um using
uh int artificial intelligence to really
do the work that we don't need to do
like still have a human like overall
review but there's just so many things
that are quite tedious. Um so we're
looking into it. There's definitely lots
of places along there that that could be
done for sure.
>> All right, thank you Pamela for a great
primer.