okay can people hear in the back are we
good yeah thumbs up okay nice one so uh
you you've already seen uh a couple of
lectures on on number Theory now and uh
so we've already uh some of you have
been asking like why are we doing this
why is this in
61200 and uh today we're going to see
how gcds and modular arithmetic uh can
be very important for uh you know
something that you that you use every
day computer security uh so cryptography
has been uh uh you know very important
uh subject for you know uh for for daily
life for like the last 20 odd years uh
you know any time you uh do an online uh
like credit card transaction or anything
like that like that's using uh you know
modern
cryptography um we'll see some uh some
examples from history where it was quite
important uh it's it's you know very
much a computer science topic not uh not
just math and uh but but it does use all
sorts of uh exciting mathematics
including you know number Theory okay so
can anybody tell me you know just in a
nutshell very informally uh what is
cryptography anyone
yep okay secure information over an
insecure Channel yeah that's a that's a
pretty good
description uh so I I would say that
it's uh you know the art or science of
of you know dealing with with such uh
dealing with protecting
information
um so like the the basic idea right uh
well at least for for what we're going
to be looking at today is suppose you
have an insecure Channel and you want to
send some message to uh you know a
recipient but you don't want other
people who might be uh EES dropping on
your channel to to know what you're
doing okay so basically you're going to
want to garble a a message that you send
privately in such a way that only
certain parties can read it okay so
let's uh you know take a look at at uh
what we mean
okay so the art or science of protecting
information so our uh you know our setup
the convention right is that we're going
to have uh two parties Alis Kazam and
and
Bulbasaur and they're going to be trying
to communicate over this communication
Channel which you know may or may not be
secure okay so maybe Alis Kazam wants to
send a message it's it's Pi Day so she's
going to send a pi
uh over to Bulbasaur right so you know
maybe she puts it in an envelope uh pops
it in the post and you know Bulbasaur
receives it he can open up the envelope
and and get the message okay so does
that basic setup make sense to
people okay so nothing too fancy yet uh
but what could go
wrong can anybody uh tell me a problem
with
this yeah
yeah somebody could come and steal the
message right so like maybe we've got uh
some Eve stopper Eevee right and uh you
know Eevee wants to uh wants to Eve St
up on their conversation wants to figure
out what they're talking about okay so
it's it's quite possible that you know
maybe Alex Alex Kazam pops this in the
mail Eevee then opens the mail puts it
back in the mail sends it along to
bobasaur but now Eevee knows what the
message is okay so this is a problem
right what else could go wrong any other
ideas
yeah yeah like what if what if Eevee is
is not just an eavesdropper but like
some meddling adversary okay so you know
maybe maybe Bulbasaur now wants to say
thank you for the pie Bulbasaur you know
puts this in an envelope sends it over
to all gam but you know E's intercepted
along the way and so now when uh when
alexam gets it it's not quite the same
message as Bulbasaur sent okay so that's
also a problem we we'd also like to
prevent this
okay so what can we
do well if we think about you know the
actual Postal System we could uh you
know basically put a put a seal on it
like a an oldfashioned Wax Seal uh but
you know basically
Alice gazam and Bulbasaur are going to
share some some key okay
so they they have a a message that
they'd like to share it's supposed to be
secret so instead of just you know
putting the envelope in the post they're
going to put it in a locked box right
and alas exam will will lock it with her
key and now when she sends it over the
channel Eevee can't do anything with it
it's locked Eevee doesn't have the key
okay but Bulbasaur has the same key so
he can now remove the lock and open the
message and everything is awesome
okay so key Concepts in
cryptography oops that all
work okay so the the basic idea you know
we're we're trying to send private
messages right so we're going to want to
what we call encrypt a message so this
means just garbling it so it kind of
looks like random
noise uh so only parties who share your
secret key will be able to read
it
okay uh decryption is the reverse right
you're going to take one of these
garbled messages if you're the intended
recipient and hopefully you can Ungar it
to recover the uh the original message
but also you know hopefully nobody else
can do the same thing okay and in order
to do both of these things uh the the
two parties are going to share a secret
key which is some data that that only
they have nobody else should have it and
it should look random and it should be
hard for for somebody else to to derive
or guess
yeah that's a great question so like
that yeah they have to meet up and and
actually share a key uh but then that
allows them to you know share messages
uh over this insecure Channel later okay
but they they do have to establish a uh
you know a secure way of sharing the key
first uh so we won't be talking too much
about how you can actually do that
nowadays uh but it is in the notes if
you'd like to read it
okay
uh okay so a cryptographic scheme is
basically just you know these things
right it's a it's an encryption
algorithm paired with a decryption
algorithm and they should you know use
the same secret key to uh you know
invert each other
okay so can anybody give me examples
historical examples of cryptographic
schemes does anybody know what the first
one
was
yeah uh yeah the Caesar
Cipher so what was the Caesar
Cipher how do you encrypt a message yeah
okay so the answer was you offset every
message in the letter by you know n
letters after
it uh not quite you are thinking of
something very slightly different the
Caesar Cipher was specifically using
three not not like some some key n okay
so you take every letter shift it over
by three letters so like you know C
becomes D EF right uh and you know you
shift every letter uh individually and
then send the shifted message okay and
to decrypt it you do the reverse you you
kind of subtract three modul
26 okay does that make sense to
everybody now what you're thinking of is
the Caesar
shift which is slightly better right so
one problem with the Caesar Cipher right
is um you know you're not you don't
really have a key right like uh
it's kind of what we call cryptography
by obscurity so the only reason it might
be secure is if nobody else knows you're
doing
it uh unfortunately you know if uh you
know if you're a Roman Emperor Legion or
whatever using the Caesar
Cipher
uh you know it doesn't protect against
say maybe one of your generals defects
and uh now goes to the enemy and is like
hey they're using this cryptographic
scheme here's how you can break all
their messages right and so then from
that point forward you know nothing you
send is secure okay so one way we can
fix that is you know by as you said
introducing a key okay so the Caesar
shift is you know very similar but
instead of just shifting by three you
shift by you know some secret key K okay
modulo
26 okay does anybody see a problem with
this
MH yeah that it is
so oops let's not caps lock
that
uh okay so here is a um oh
that did not work what is going
on okay so here's uh an encrypted
message it's been encrypt encrypted
using the uh uh the Caesar Cipher sorry
Caesar
shift
uh as you said right it's fairly easy to
guess what the key is right so does
anybody have any guesses before I start
just you know putting in
values
yeah 13 why 13
yeah that's uh that's a very good
guess so yeah no knowing some
information about the message right like
this is probably in English right uh you
have a a standalone n in that first line
right that's probably an A or an I right
you you've already got lots of
information that you can use to narrow
down the key and even if you don't right
like if we just start putting in random
values here right like most of them are
going to look like garbage right
okay uh but like one of them is actually
going to make sense okay so when we try
all of the possible values we're going
to you know figure out something that uh
that is almost certainly going to be the
the correct key
okay so how can we avoid this
problem any
ideas yeah
change the encryption method based on
the index of the letter okay uh so what
you're describing is uh what we call the
onetime pad um that is a good idea we
will not be covering it just yet
yeah okay um similar idea uh let's let's
start by making a a smaller more
incremental change
yeah okay include
numbers uh
well the idea that I had in mind was to
just use a larger key
space uh use a permutation instead of
instead of just a shift okay so that
this is something that was done you know
in medieval times uh instead of Shifting
every letter over by the same amount
right you'd take a random permutation of
the letters and so you're kind of
Shifting each letter
differently okay now can anybody think
of a way that you could attack this
oh why is this not
working
H sorry technical
difficulties oh well I guess it doesn't
matter too much uh I can describe what's
going on um so yeah uh what what your
classmate suggested was that you know
again we can use uh the known plain text
attack that that we described a moment
ago with the um uh with the Caesar shift
okay if we know something about uh about
our message right like uh for instance
if we know that it's it's probably
written in
English then we can count how many times
each letter appears and whichever letter
appears most frequently probably
decrypts to e because e is the uh most
common English letter or even if not
we've got a decent guess right like uh
you know it's probably not going to be
like X or Zed it might be S or t or
something like that uh but the point is
it's very easy to start narrowing down
the key
space and you know once we have a guess
we can then start building on it so
similarly to what your colleague did
earlier right like if you have e and you
see threel words you know ending with E
that might be the right so then you've
got two more letters okay does that make
sense to people so you can like knowing
a little bit of of information about
your key you can kind of incrementally
figure out the the rest of the key and
decrypt the message
yeah that's right so it is a permutation
so uh you know it's a it's a onetoone
map it's a
bje okay uh other questions
maybe I can just post this demo on the
website so you can uh play around with
it uh sorry it didn't
work
um
okay so the next example comes from
World War II has anybody uh heard of the
Enigma Cipher yeah few hands can anybody
tell me what it
did mhm
okay uh so the answer was it changed the
encryption method every day uh that's
not quite true it changed the key every
day it didn't change the algorithm that
they were using uh
yes yeah so it it basically oh so the
answer was it it changed the permutation
every letter uh so yes that's that's the
the basic idea behind uh
Enigma um it started with some you know
permutation of the letters and every
time you uh encrypted a letter it would
then you know apply some some uh change
to this permutation so that the next
letter would be encrypted differently so
that made it resistant to a frequency
analysis um but you know unfortunately
for the for the Germans it was still
viable to do a known plain text attack
right so basically the the way that the
Allies ended up breaking this uh
encryption scheme was you know they knew
something about uh about the messages
that were being sent every day right
like many of them were weather reports
or
something uh many of them had like you
know the phrase H Hitler or something
like that um but like if you know that
you're getting a weather report from a
certain location you know the weather in
that location like you've got a bunch of
information about what you know how this
message might start right and so this
you know similarly to to to a a
frequency analysis attack you can kind
of use this information to narrow down
your key space and uh figure out the
secret key and once you've got that you
can decrypt everything that's being sent
that day uh and so you know this is what
the Allies were were doing uh uh in
Bletchley Park to to win the war
okay
so Enigma kind
of uh Enigma was kind of the the last
uh major example of of what
we or what I call kind of um
cryptography by hubis uh like basically
the the security relied on on you know
some German engineer being you know
smarter than everybody else on the
planet right like you know he he came up
with this uh encryption scheme and was
like okay this looks uh this looks you
know weird and random I can't figure out
how to break it I bet nobody else can
either okay and so the the Germans kind
of worked with this assumption for the
uh duration of the war and it was wrong
right so nowadays we like to uh you know
try and you know prove Security based on
you know more reasonable assumptions
than
that so uh one example which is in the
notes that we won't be uh covering too
much today is uh called Diffy Helman uh
the one that we'll be focusing on though
is uh RSA
so RSA was uh you know it's it's a a
modern cryptographic scheme named after
its inventor Clifford
Cox um that's totally a lie uh so
Clifford Cox did you know in some sense
invent RSA but uh he made the rather
suspicious life choice of working for
the
government uh so his work was classified
for like 2025 years something like that
and in the meantime you know rsna came
along uh and you know Ed his same scheme
they did it here at
MIT uh so this was uh Ron reest Addie
Shir and Leonard Adelman uh they got all
the credit for it they won a cheering
award and you know poor Mr Cox uh was
kind of screwed um so more of the story
don't work for the government um just
kidding but uh yeah kind of sucked for
him uh but yeah let's uh why don't we um
why don't we get into uh to what RSA
actually actually does
okay so RSA is an example of what we
call a public key crypto
system
okay
so okay so before right I described uh
what we actually call a a a private key
crypto system right where both
encryption and decryption use the same
secret key okay in a public key crypto
system that's no longer the case so we
actually have two
keys so let's call them uh KP and
KS okay so KP is going to be a public
key which everybody can see okay and
then it's going to be paired with the
secret key KS which you know you keep to
yourself okay and now the encryption and
decryption
algorithms uh each of them uses a
different key Okay so we've got
uh
encryption okay so our encryption
algorithm
is going to be you know e of some
message and our public
key okay and this will output you know
some Cipher text
C okay and then we're going to have a
different decryption
algorithm D which will you know
hopefully take this Cipher text uh C and
this time the secret
key and it should output the original
plane text message
M
okay so slightly different from the uh
uh uh from the the crypto system that I
defined earlier right in that one these
two keys were the same and so you don't
you you can't publish uh you can't
publish KP okay so only people who share
the same secret key can actually
communicate here this allows you know
any body to uh to to send a message okay
so you can kind of think of this as you
know suppose Alex exam wants to send a
message to
Bulbasaur uh so she's going to use
Bulbasaur's public key to send him a
message you can think of this as
Bulbasaur's like Gmail address right
this is something that you know anybody
can
find uh but then Bulbasaur has his Gmail
password which he can then use to read
the message okay
okay
so now we are ready
to actually Define how RSA
works
okay so the basic idea behind
RSA is that uh the encryption and
decryption algorithm together
uh should basically make use of phos
little theorem to to make sure that we
get back to the same
message okay
so we're going to try and come up with
uh you know some e and d
right and some n such that if we you
know
exponentiate right first raised to the
power of of uh e then raise again to the
power of D we should get back to to
where we started okay so we're going to
want uh you know for any m m to the E
raised to the power of D should be
equivalent mod n to
n
okay so let let's just start with
correctness for now let's let's not
worry too much about security just yet
but uh how could we achieve
this how could we choose uh n and D such
that this will at least work even if
it's not
secure any
ideas so what what did FMA tell
us so phma tells
us right that uh m to
the uh you know P minus one is congruent
mod P to one
okay so how can we kind of massage this
into
this well first time might we choose
n
yeah
sorry
okay
so the idea was to you know let e and d
uh be factors of n so like e *
D sorry equals
n
okay uh does anybody see a problem with
this
yeah uh so that's not the problem right
so we uh remember the exponent here is p
minus one right so you know if you
multiply both Ides by m you get m to the
p is congruent mod P to M okay so that
that is actually what we
want what assumption did we have on
P
yeah P ISE yeah p is prime so we can't
do
this
okay it is close though
so maybe I should rewrite this as the
suggestion was e * D should be equal to
p
minus1 +
okay does that make it any more clear
what how we can uh iterate on this
what other things would work here
instead of P minus one +
one yeah
yeah uh yes that's right
sorry so the answer was we can multiply
this by whatever we want right like any
K here it'll still work right as long as
e * D is equivalent to 1 mod P minus one
so e d equivalent mod P minus one to 1
right as long as we satisfy this
right we get
this okay or sorry we get
this okay
yeah uh so the the the question was like
what are we multiplying by K we're
multiplying this P minus one right uh
yeah so the the reason right FLT says
that M the P minus one is congruent to
one so m to the K * P minus one is going
to be 1 to the K right so that's just
one okay so no matter what K we put here
this will still work now when you
multiply by m that's just adding one
onto the exponents okay so then you'll
have you know m to the uh K * P - 1 + 1
should be congruent to to
n
okay does this setup make sense to
people yeah
question uh so the the question was why
are we adding one onto the end so the
answer was you know FLT tells us that
we're going to get one what we really
wanted was
n okay so you know what what we want is
uh you know m to the Ed is congruent to
m not congruent to one so that's why
okay so as long as we choose Ed
congruent mod P minus one to one
right we'll get
this okay so you know more practically
speaking how can we generate e and
D like how can I find uh a solution
to this uh
congruence
yeah
sorry okay so the answer was TR
different values of
K uh okay
[Music]
so we're going to want to be using very
large numbers here so that's going to be
intractable we want to be able to do
more
efficiently so recall from uh Tuesday
right this is saying that e and D are
modular inverses modu P minus
one okay how can we compute a modular
inverse well one way is to use the
pulverizer okay so if we choose e
randomly and then
pulverize this will give us
D
Okay Okay so we've got a way to generate
Keys we've got a way to encrypt we raise
m to the E we've got a way to decrypt we
raise C to the
D can anybody tell me a security
flow why is this
insecure so remember for public key
crypto system right everybody knows the
public
key right and we don't want anybody to
be able to figure out the private key
from
that so in this case our public key is
going to be you know KP is going to be
the pair uh P comma D oh
sorry P comma e and our secret key is
going to be the P the pair P comma
D okay so this is what we need in order
to encrypt this is what we need in order
to
decrypt I claim that this is
insecure
yeah yes so the answer was can't anybody
else do exactly what we did right we
started with the public
key and then use it to to derive our our
secret
key if we then share that public key
with everybody else everybody else can
do exactly the same thing okay so our
secret key isn't exactly
secret
okay so we would like to try and do
something similar to this but in a way
where other people can't you know repeat
our
computation can anybody think of how we
might do this
how can I make sure that nobody else can
do the same
pulverization
yeah okay so the answer was choose a
random D and then pulverize to find E I
claim that this is exactly the same
right it's it's the same process right
um
so you know like these two are basically
symmetric okay so like if I share one of
them then anybody else can can then find
the
other okay so the idea behind RSA right
is that this modulus here the the thing
that we're trying to pulverize with
right and
the modulus here the part of the key
that we're
sharing you know here they're off by
one but in some sense they don't have to
be okay so we'd like to find a way to
share
this but like not have this be so easily
uh so easily computable
okay how could we do
that well instead of using a single
Prime suppose we have two
primes so let's call them p and
Q
okay and
now uh our
n is going to be their product P * Q
okay so that's going to be what I want
to share
here okay
uh but now this no longer quite
works so instead of pulverizing with uh
n minus one we're going to pulverize
with you know uh sorry P
minus1 * Q
-1
okay why
well suppose like you know suppose we we
we have done this already suppose
that
Ed is congruent mod uh let's call this
uh say m no M is for message let's call
it n
Prime congruent mod n Prime
to
one
okay what happens if we take M and raise
it to the Ed
power what is this equivalent to mod n
y okay so the answer was M yes
why don't
know fair enough I mean this is kind of
you know what we were aiming for so you
know very good educated
guess uh how could we prove
this
yeah uh so this is supposed to be an N
right so remember that uh you know when
we encrypt and decrypt those
computations are being done mod
n it's only the pulverizing that should
be done mod like using uh n Prime okay
so we're we're trying to so we're we're
assuming that Ed is congruent mod n
Prime to one right and so we find that
by pulverizing with with the N Prime but
you know after that we can forget about
NP Prime right we don't need nime
anymore we're just going to do all of
our computations mod n using you know e
and
D
okay so does anybody have any ideas how
we could prove this this statement
here what exactly is the statement
saying if we go back to the definitions
yeah yeah exactly so you've skipped a
couple of steps but um yes I will get to
that in a moment uh so this is saying
that you know uh n
divides m to the E
D minus uh
M
okay now at this point we can break
apart this n so all we really need to do
is you know prove that P and Q
separately divide m to the Ed minus
M or
equivalently that uh m to the Ed is
congruent
mod P and Q separately to
M
okay so if we prove these two things
then we're
done okay so p and Q are
symmetric so so you know let's let's
only prove it for p the same same exact
proof will work for
Q
okay
so how do we prove
now that m to the Ed is congruent mod P
to n how could we do this
any
ideas yeah
that's right okay so the answer was
basically that we've already done it
okay so remember that uh Ed is congruent
mod n Prime to
one okay so this means that n Prime
divides Ed minus one
okay well what is n Prime n
Prime equal pus1 Q minus
one so in particular Q minus
one no P minus
one divides Ed minus
one
okay so set otherwise e is congruent mod
P - one to
okay so that's exactly the uh condition
we had over here yeah
question uh so the question was how do
we know P minus1 divides edus
one uh P minus1 divides n
Prime right we defined n Prime to be the
product of Q -1 and P minus one okay so
we know that n Prime divides this and
one of our rules of divisibility was
that you know then any factors of n
Prime also divide
it
okay so we know that P minus one divides
Ed minus
one so that's just saying that Ed is
congruent to one mod P minus
one right and that's the condition we
add
here
okay so now by FLT
m to the
Ed is congruent mod
P to
M
okay so did people follow
that so we've got congruence mod
P by symmetry we also have congruence
mod Q right p and Q are you know they're
basically
symmetric
okay and now because they
Prime right we can say that if you know
p and Q both independently divide this
difference their product must divided as
well so that gives us congruence mod PQ
okay
questions
yeah okay so the the question was can we
uh you know go into this this step here
in more detail okay so remember that's
what we were doing over here right so
fma's little theorem right says that M
the p
minus1 is congruent to one mod
P okay
so if we raise these to any power K
right it's still going to be congruent
to one okay so m to the K * P minus1
will also be congruent to one right so m
to the K * P - 1 + 1 will be congruent
to one
okay this here is saying that Ed has
that form it's some multiple of P minus
one +
okay so basically we're applying FLT
repeatedly just as we did over here
okay are people reasonably happy with
this
yeah okay so why are we using p minus1
and Q minus1 in the first
place uh in short I pulled them out of
my house so it would
work uh
so this is um you know it's basically a
generalization of of FLT uh called
Oilers
theorem um it turns out that uh you know
this P min-1 * Q
-1 is what we
call V of n where V is Oiler to
function uh this counts the number of of
uh you know numbers up to n that are
co-prime with n
so basically we can we can use the same
proof uh as we did you know
Tuesday uh to show that you know if we
want to get rid of this assumption that
P is prime over
here uh we can replace this this P minus
one with P of
n uh and then then we get congruence mod
mod
n
okay uh we just kind of proved the
special case where n is the product of
of two
primes
um but uh yeah basically it's it's kind
of it's kind of a guess and check right
like all we all we really need to know
is that this works we don't really need
to know how we got
there okay
Okay so we've proven that uh you know if
we encrypt something by you know raising
it to the uh eth Power mod n and then we
decrypt it by raising it to the D power
mod mod n we're going to get back to the
same thing we started with
Okay so this crypto system is at least
you know correct right we can uh encrypt
a message and then decrypt it again
is it
secure oh
sorry actually why me
just do
that
okay so uh is RSA secure
right we we said before that if we're
just using a prime instead of this
product of two primes then uh anybody
else can can computer secret
key okay what are we doing
now
well one we're choosing random
primes large primes so think of these as
like having hundreds of digits okay
okay uh next we're going to set n equals
their
product
and uh let's just call it f of n
nowal p -1 * Q
-1 and next we're going to choose a
random e
co-prime with
this and then we want to pulverize it we
want to compute an inverse of
e so why don't I write it this this
compute a multiplicative inverse
modulo uh F of
n
okay now what is the public key public
key is going to be oops K sub p is going
to be n comma
e k sub s is going to be n comma
D
okay so before when we had uh oh
question
okay uh how hard is it to choose e
that's that's co-
Prime uh it's actually not that hard uh
so in practice usually you would you
know not choose it totally randomly
you'd have a fairly small e so that
encryption is
efficient uh but if you wanted to do it
totally randomly right like how many how
many things are not co-prime to
uh so yeah multiples of the prime
factors yes um so let's see have you did
we do the carmichel numbers yet no okay
so uh well it turns out that if you
choose a random a random number it'll
actually be co-prime with reasonably
good probability okay uh but you know in
practice right we're going to just you
know choose a fairly small
e
okay
okay so we said that if if we just you
know forget about Q use nals P this
doesn't work because anybody else can
then you know compute our our secret key
in the same way as we computed it
ourselves why does this not happen
here why can nobody else compute the
secret
key given the public
key
yeah yeah so the the basic idea is that
we're relying on factoring being hard
okay uh so the the basic idea right is
that if you have n it's it should be
hard to to come up with with p and Q
okay and I claim that this is actually a
much safer assumption than was used with
Enigma uh because this is a very well
studied problem like people have been
trying to factor things more efficiently
for you know hundreds of years right and
you know mathematicians have not found
an efficient way of of doing this so in
particular the adversary will will also
presumably not be able to do it right
it's not just saying like I personally
couldn't come up with a with a good
factoring algorithm this is you know
relying on you know many years of of
work by many mathematicians okay it
still is possible that that factoring
isn't hard like you know and in fact
maybe maybe somebody already knows how
to do it they've got they've got their
algorithm they just haven't published it
uh but the assumption is basically like
if one could do it then one of these
mathematicians would have would have
figured it out okay like one of these
World
experts
okay uh so more formally though
if we could compute the uh
uh ah okay question was isn't this just
cryptography by
huis okay I claim that I'm not relying
solely on you know my own intelligence
I'm relying on you know everybody else
like the the entire field of mathematics
okay like like many mathematicians have
spent like their entire careers trying
to you know Factor things
quickly and nobody's figured out how to
do it yet it's not just like you know I
was spending half an hour in my basement
and you know I I couldn't figure out a
good algorithm in that time you know
like the the the Enigma engineer right
like you know he just came up with
something and then couldn't figure out a
way how to a way to to break it and so
kind of just assumed security from that
right so it's it's kind of you know me
versus the entire field of of
mathematics
okay okay so yeah I guess the question
is you know given uh so if we had an
algorithm that would you know compute
the secret key from the public key how
would this Factor end
right notice that the uh secret key
doesn't actually contain p andq
so I suppose as described we aren't
quite relying on the hardness of
factoring we're relying on something
slightly different
yeah oh sorry
uh no how do how do we um so if we could
find the uh the private key the secret
key given the public key how would this
then factor
in right we we would like to rely on the
the hardness of factorization
okay so the the answer was basically
that that you have to come up with the
prime factors p and Q before you can uh
before you can
compute uh D from e
uh we would like to say that you know no
matter how you do it you're still
basically going to end up with the
factors p and Q right like you will have
solved the problem even if you didn't
intend
to does that make
sense okay so suppose I have n e d
okay so suppose I've I've used the uh
the public key to come up with the
secret key so now I have these three
pieces of
information right does this now allow me
to factor in
does anybody remember the quadratic
formula from uh from grade
school it's okay I don't
either
okay
[Music]
so if I have end d
right Ed minus one
should
be a multiple of P
-1 * Q
-1
okay what happens if I reduce that mod
in
hm I get one uh if I reduce it mod P - 1
* Q -1 I get
one
yeah get p and
Q okay let's let's make it a little bit
simpler suppose I actually have p minus1
and Q -1 or P -1 * Q
-1 if I had that could I factor in for
so if I had that I could oh yeah
mhm yeah so if we actually had P min-1 *
Q - one we could use that to figure out
the sum of p and Q we know their product
we can use the quadratic
formula
okay what happens if we just have Ed uh
sorry e and
D can we do something similar
oh actually I'm running quite short on
time okay uh why don't we hold off on
that uh let's just take it on faith that
we're relying on factoring being hard
let's move on to
uh the last thing that we wanted to
cover
today which is a uh slightly different
application of uh of number Theory which
you may find useful in uh you know
throughout computer
science um notice where is it
uh okay
here so here we kind of
uh we're trying to work mod n right n is
the fact or n is the product of two
primes and we said that it's easier
instead of working mod n we're going to
work mod the two primes
individually okay so it turns out that
this this is something that you can do
in general right uh this is what we call
the Chinese remainder theorem right uh
if you have uh in fact if you have two
co-prime numbers p and
Q working modulo their product is
equivalent to working modulo each of
them
individually okay and often working
modulo you know the the smaller numbers
individually is going to be you know
much easier than working modu the the
large number okay so as a very simple
example uh suppose we
have the
following uh actually strictly less than
55 okay
and we know that X is congruent mod 5 to
4 x congruent mod 11 to
okay I claim that we have enough
information now to Unique identify
X okay can anybody do it
how might we do
it
yeah okay uh so the answer was you know
try everything between 0 and 55 uh see
what they're con to mod four or Mod Five
see what they're conent to mod 11 and
see whether it satisfies both of those I
claim that we can do it slightly faster
than that uh why don't we enumerate
everything that satisfies uh this
congruence
first okay so what is congruent to seven
modul 11 in this
range right so that tells us that maybe
I should write it down here oops X is in
the following
set 7 18
51 and if we add 11 again we get past
okay now we only have to check uh five
numbers to see which is congruent to uh
uh to four modul
5 and if we look at them 29 is the only
one that
works okay so it turns out that there's
a unique answer modulo
okay and we can actually do this in
general and in fact even more
efficiently so Chinese remainder theorem
often abbreviated
CRT so
suppose p and Q are
co-prime okay and a and b
are
integers
okay and we have the
following system of
congruences
okay so if we have this then there is a
unique solution there's a unique X that
satisfies this modulo PQ
okay so how might we prove this what
what are the elements that we need to
prove
yeah
sorry oh here
fien uh here
fien yeah so you don't have to worry
about what this is actually called we
could call this n
Prime but
yeah sorry this was just following up on
on what one of your classmates asked uh
earlier
okay so what are the elements that we
need to prove in order to prove this
this theorem
here well we need to prove existence
and then we need to prove that there
don't exist two
solutions okay so let's start with let's
start with
existence why does there exist a
solution maybe we can start thinking
about a special case so
suppose uh suppose for for a start that
a equals
Zer
okay how could we find a solution
uh to X congruent uh to b modul
q and x congruent to zero modul
P
yeah
sure yeah
so the relation here is that uh you know
we've got our p and Q are 5 and
11 right our A and B are 4 and
seven and so we're saying that there's a
unique solution to to you know this
system of congruences modulo 55 which is
their product okay or you know you could
also phrase that as there is a unique X
in this range like a unique integer X in
this
range
okay so we're just kind of we're just
kind of G to generalize this kind of to
um you know
a more General p and Q more General A
and
B okay question or oh
sorry
okay well if we look at the special case
where a equals
z why don't we start by defining
uh P minus
one p
inverse uh to be a modular
inverse of p
modulo
q
okay and now let's multiply that by P to
get the
integer uh e
subq
okay now what can we say about e subq
what is it congruent to modul p
yeah yeah so we defined it to be a
multiple of P so e
subq is going to be congruent mod P to
zero okay what about modulo
Q what is it congruent to modulo
Q
yeah one yeah so by definition
right P inverse is a multiplicative
inverse of p modul q so when you
multiply them you get one mod
Q okay so how can we use e sub Q to get
X remember remember we're thinking of
the special case where a equals
z so we're trying to find a multiple of
P that's congruent to b modu q
anybody yeah
yeah so the answer was multiply EQ by B
okay B * EQ now is congruent to zero
modul p and 1 * B which is B modul
Q okay does that make sense to
everybody so for the more General case
we are going to
Define uh e subp
analogously
okay now how how do you think we could
solve the more General
case instead of just B * zq
how do we then you know fold EP into
it
y
yeah so
claim X
equal a e p + b e
q is a
solution
okay so we can verify each of these two
congruences
separately right so if we look at the
first congruence what happens if we
reduce this x modu
p well modulo P this EP here is
congruent to
one so this term becomes
a uh we said that EQ is defined to be a
multiple of P so the second term just
goes
away so modulo p X is now congruent to
a modulo q it's exactly the opposite
right this term goes away because the
the EP was defined to be a multiple of
Q right and
uh
sorry yes this is defined to be a
multiple of Q and uh I've done it the
wrong way around haven't I
Q mod
q no no we're fine
okay so EP is a multiple of Q the a term
goes
away uh B * EQ is going to be one
okay sorry B * EQ is going to be B
okay so what about
uniqueness how might we prove
uniqueness what is the what is the setup
going to look like
yeah okay so the the idea was show that
any candidate solution so let's say x
Prime is actually the same solution okay
so let X and X Prime be
to
Solutions
okay now what are we trying to
show
yeah uh not
equals so we're not trying to we're not
trying to prove there are unique
integers right we're trying to prove
that it's Unique modul PQ so we want to
show that they're congruent modul
PQ
okay how can we do
this well what is the definition of this
equivalence we could do this by showing
that uh you know PQ
divides x - x
Prime now in order to do that right we
can look at p and Q
separately okay so why does p divide the
difference
well both of them satisfy that first
equation or that first
congruence okay so both of them are
congruent to a modulo p if you subtract
them you get
zero okay so P divides the
difference now because they both satisfy
the second
congruence right uh you subtract them
you get B minus B right so there so the
the so Q divides the difference as well
okay so p and Q
individually
okay and by assumption they're co-prime
so their product must then also divide
the
difference okay
okay so that means that x and x Prime
must be congruent modu of
PQ okay so that's all we have time for
today um yeah you'll see you'll get more
practice with uh RSA and CRT in uh in
recitation tomorrow and uh yeah feel
free to uh come up if you have questions