[Music]
Don't
baby
what
I don't
[Music] I've become
prettier
.
[Music]
Engrave it
[Music] You
idiot who only shows off his strength and can't change your mind because you like me
[Music] Come at me
[Music]
[Applause] Neun-la
[
Applause] Lalala [Applause] Lalalala
Lalala Lalalala
la
[Applause] La
[Applause]
Don't
B
[Music] I'm getting
prettier
.
[Music] Taking a
bite of the celery that's being raised
[Music]
Lalalala
Beautiful
[Music]
Ah, I'm getting better because you
saw me You idiot who never gives a damn
[Music] Come at
me
[Music]
Lalalala
[Music] I have a
feeling Look at the water now Superhi
I won't let that guy be different
Lalalala Lalala Lalalala
Lalalala
[Music]
V
[Applause]
app for B