thank you very much uh for the kind
invitation as well to present my work
here today with all of you so uh this
presentation will focus on this new
invitra model of human skin vasculature
for the subcutanous
space about that um so before we start
with the details uh for the project uh
I'm going to share some details about
this Consortium so it's actually the
same general Consortium with Frances as
well that she just presented but this
time we're focusing on the skin project
so it's called humanizing drug
development skin these are the member
companies that we have we are currently
are collaborating with five uh major
Pharma companies this project started on
February 2022 right when I joined as
well MIT and it's still ongoing we are
currently phase two and we're discussing
a phase three so um it's going really
well uh the main goal of this project
was and still is to de velop an inv
vitro model of human skin skin
vasculature for the subcutanous space
and I'm going to S more details later on
um and then use this model to understand
and hopefully predict drug by
availability of uh mostly monoc
monoclone antibodies or other protein um
therapeutic drugs and um yeah as we have
already noticed this is uh the me
mechanobiology lab uh lead by Roger C
and I'm working in this project to
together with another post talk uh sangu
Kim so uh I'm going to start with some
things that you probably already know uh
but uh this is kind of an introduction
uh the variability in drug
bioavailability that's a major um factor
in drug development um the drug by
availability the numbers that you get
for each specific drug uh and also at
another point of view there is an
increased interest in peptide and other
protein protein based drugs such as the
monoclone antibodies nowadays the market
is increasing a lot and it's projected
to also increase in the next 10 years as
you can see from the right uh
plot and also they growing efforts to
increase the number of maps delivered as
subq injections instead of uh like IV
injections and there are multiple um
advantages in this uh subq
Administration through skin it's easily
self- administered by the patient uh of
course in improves patient compliance
and quality of life uh it comes with
decreased cost and a lower risk of
systemic infections as well so um
nowadays as you can see in the lower
plot um it is uh really used the sub
injection of these drugs however one of
the big issues is the vi vi availability
values that come with this subq
Administration can be very variable with
values from 50% actually I recently
found
25% uh all the way to 100 so that's
that's really a big Randomness so it
makes thre development uh more difficult
so here we come here is when this
Consortium comes and we're like okay
let's try to create to develop a
microphysiological system of human skin
vasculature that maybe could help
understanding better where is this
variability coming from and then like in
terms of the drug by distribution uh and
then hopefully uh help to try to predict
uh later on drug by
availability so um we have already held
uh many nice details from my colleague
about them these microphysiological
systems um these are nice in vitro
models that can replicate real organ
Form and Function they are based on
microfluidic Technologies they include
3D cell structure of multiple organ
specific cells like primary or iepc
cells
uh you can apply flow and you can mimic
the actual what's happening in the real
um tissue and also they can be used for
drug drug screening studies or you can
move to disease models with these as we
just saw with the brain disease
Alzheimer disase
model um yeah
so okay so as I said our goal was to
develop a microphysiological model to
study subc drug biodistribution so the
first step to that was okay how does
this subcu space look like and um the
subcu space is this uh hypodermis layer
of our skin uh it it it has uh blood
vessels lymphatic vessels adipocytes
everywhere uh and also ECM as well so
you have all these different 3D
compartments that we're trying to
replicate in our invitro system so we
want a model that we replicate this 3D
subc morphology we'll have enhanced
recapitulation of this complexities of
the envious tissue um will allow for
solid transport measurements across the
different compartments the different
blood and lymphatic endothelium for
example and then later on with these
measurements that we will get from the
different compartments um these data can
be informative on the drug by
distribution across the different um
structures so that's what we did um so
you have at this point you have he many
times what is our goal to develop this
micral iCal model of human skins vascul
for the subcu space uh but the main
thing that we wanted here for this
particular model is to have blood and
lymphatic vasculature at in the same
chip allowing for S inter signaling so
um in at least in our lab and actually
in general these invitra models have
usually only like blood vasculature
that's the most common thing so it's um
to my knowledge it's the first time that
we also combine blood and lymphatic
blure in one device so that was really
the challenge of this project uh so we
wanted to have these Mo these components
in our system blood microvasculature
lymphatic vessels adipocytes fiber
blasts and ECM in one device and you can
see in the center uh how our device
looks like uh we have this lengthy
compartment that has the blood uh
microvascular and then we have the
lymphatics lymphatic vessels uh and also
another compartment that has the ECM
where we actually introduce the drug for
measurements from ECM it goes to the
blood vascular and then lymphatic
vessels and we uh make various
measurements I'm going to talk about
right away um yeah so that's how it
looks like and also I'm want to mention
here that there are multiple open ports
where you can sample uh at any time any
time point of the experiment so that's
pretty nice because you can do all these
tests uh that Francesa just talk about
uh with all the different cell types
um so uh a couple of things of how we
develop this very briefly we start for
the blood vascul we start with dermal
primary dermal endothelial cells uh
primary dermal fiber Bloods and
adipocytes that we actually
differentiate from adus derived stem
cells in our lab it takes about three
weeks and then we combine these cells
with fibrinogen and we see these in this
compartment that you see um and then
after about four or five days these all
these cells self assemble into a very
nice perfusable 3D uh blood
microvascular uh and then once it's
perfusable I also incorporate add the
lymphatic the dermal primary lymphatics
uh in the system and then they also with
a specific application of flow they
create this nice Lumen so you can see
also lymphatic vasculature in the system
so the result is that we have an
integrated device with these different
compartments and now we are ready to
introduce our drug from this ECM
circular compartment that you see in
dark green and uh measure whatever we
want to do um so the first oh yeah I
forgot about that so I have showed you
um schematics but let's look at actual
images of our networks um you can see
how the blood vasculature looks likees
looks like uh this is St with lectin so
you see the AC ECS but you also can see
the adipo sites um and there also
fiberblast there as well and then you
can also see the lymphatic networks in
red um in the on the bottom image um and
then you can see another image on the
right that has uh both the blood
vasculature and the lymphatics and you
can see how these are close we didn't
want to have them all together for now
we start with the system because we want
to uh take different measurements like
separate measurements of the two but in
the same device we have low so all these
are interconnected pretty much the the
cells um um so we start uh our
measurements with the blood vasculature
we call this measurement blood
endothelial permeability this is
actually a technique that is well
established in our lab and pretty much
everyone is using so what we do is that
we need a conf focal and we are taking
images of our networks at a specific
time Point time Point Z let's say and
then after a couple of minutes usually
10 or so we take another image of the
same position so then we can compare the
permeability of the drug uh I forgot to
say that we have perused the vessels
with a drug um so that you can see how
much of this drug going outside to the
interal space from the vessels now in my
particular space because I'm doing the
skin it's a little bit opposite so
because it goes from the ECM to the
vessels so I try to replicate that
process so I actually have to Exon
everywhere like in the vessels and the
Matrix as well and then I peruse the
vessels with media which is black it's
not fluorescent so um the vessels clear
out so then I can measure how much of
the drag that is in the interstial space
comes into the vessel so that's a
measurement of the permeability from
Matrix to the vessels and um we have
actually started many experiments
experiments with our device and here you
can see all these drugs that we have
used and our results we do see a
molecular dependence which is pretty
nice and we think that this is a control
of that the system works um lower
molecular weight drugs
uh give higher permeability which makes
sense and it's also in agreement with
previous studies as well um so then we
also look at the role of the ECM in
terms of Matrix binding and diffusivity
for all these drugs we the technique we
used is called frap uh fluorescent
recovery after photo blitzing so photo
Blitz a specific spot in The Matrix and
then we see down the road like over time
how much uh of the diet goes into it
well uh and we measure the diffusivity
and the immobile fraction of various
drugs um also I have um done some other
measurements with a control device that
has no cells at all and a device that
has all the cells and uh in for the
diffusivity we don't necessarily see a
big difference but the immobile fraction
uh so it's a big difference and we think
that's a result of the of this
reorganization that the cells are
causing throughout the the whole week or
10 days that we have actually uh the
device going on and you can see also the
diffusivity and immobile uh measurements
for all again these different drugs that
we are using we uh do see a molecular
dependence uh which is also nice um and
we also all these values we're going to
test them um like correlate with other
um uh characteristics of these drugs as
well to see if there is a correlation so
that's how we're going to approach the
bi availability and bi distribution and
hopefully predict it in the future as
well um and also so the last measurement
we're doing right now is regarding the
lymphatic Network as well that is
growing in the integrated device um as
you probably many of you know the
lymphatics are a network of vessels that
serve as conduits for fluid protein and
cellular transport they regulate fluid
and osmotic pressure homeostasis in
tissues so they are really important as
well uh for drug absorption and uh
bioavailability so these are how the
lymphatics look like um and also I have
an orthogonal view here that you can see
actually that they are really 3D you can
see the lumens the
cross-sections um like this circular U
are they and they as we move they become
bigger so um what we do is that we
introduce the dexam from this circular
compartment and hopefully you remember
that uh in the device and then we
measure over time um the fluorescent of
the drug after the lymphatic so in a way
we measure the drainage rate of the
drugs uh for in the lymphatic
compartment so these are ongoing
experiment so this is the data that I
have right now but I'm running more and
more to get the whole panel of the drugs
that we tested for the others as well
for the
lymphatics um and with that uh I would
like to summarize my our work so we have
developed an integrated 3D model of this
human human skin vasculature for the
subcu space with blood and lymphatic
vasculature this skin model can now be
used for subcutanous delivery of
molecules and provides blood vasculature
lymphatic drainage and ECM measurements
and as I just said uh we hope to
colorate all these measurements for the
10 different drugs that we use with
known PK values for these drugs we
actually selected these drugs um having
that on our mind so they are really
heterogeneous one to one other like in
terms of bioavailability molecular
weight and other things uh in the future
we are going to do some single cell RNA
sequence I think it's pretty nice with
such a system complex system that you
have all these different cells uh
proteomics analysis as well H we also
probably that's not sure but we may add
also immune cells into the system um and
another idea could be to also as I said
we have many open compartments in this
system so that gives us the opportunity
to alternate a little bit the model so
maybe we can add an epidermis later
layer later on like
keratinocytes or we can use this model
to study human diseases uh as well uh I
really want to mention as well that my
collaborator in the project uh Dr sen
Kim have developed um a digital twin
model for this uh device so that's
that's pretty cool because we can
compare uh and then my experimental
measurements will inform this model
aiming for prediction of drug by
availability down the road which is our
main goal um and with that I would like
to thank you all thank you thanks to uh
my adviser Professor Roger C all my
collaborators uh um of course the
companies that fund this project and are
members of this wonderful Consortium um
thank you very
[Applause]
much thank you Maria for giving us that
overview any questions from the
audience thank you beautiful talk so can
you comment uh the possibility to
repurpose the SK model to cosmetic
applications yeah yeah that's a that's a
great application um that's a great
application I have actually thought a
lot about it uh you can you can use this
complex uh model for um investigating uh
many things in coneing or trying to find
new bioactives or something like that uh
I'm not sure if this particular
Consortium will go down the road on this
because it's funding by this big Pharma
companies I'm not sure if that's going
to be a goal for them but this can be
used definitely for for cosmetic uh
research as well that's a great idea
thank
you two in the back we'll come to one
and then the other thank you this is
this is great stuff um so maybe first do
you mind going back to slide nine you
had two I couldn't read from here sorry
uh you had two colors on the on the top
plot yeah uh the brown and the green
what are the difference between those uh
oh so these actually are plots from
other paper papers um I have included
the
citations um so these particular are
coming from different sources like they
are different cells so they have
Incorporated these as well these I think
the brown are huex and the green are
from animals um but the reason why I
have these plots here is to uh have an
idea of the permeability values that we
we get and to show that my system also
is very close to these values um but
yeah this is the difference in
and and uh maybe this is a question for
more more Downstream once once you have
a you know agreement with the digital
twin model um very excited to see what
happens with that but are you already
thinking about I don't know how the
Consortium governs the the licensing of
these uh MPS systems or how do you plan
to U sort of uh commercialize this or if
you plan to do that yeah so um yeah I
guess I forgot to say that we have
annual trainings for our member
companies we have already done two of
them and in actually two months they're
going to be another so all the member
companies come here at MIT and I
actually see together with their
representatives in the hood and I'm
teaching them how we develop the model
we got the microscope I'm doing all this
so they have access to everything we're
doing so they can actually recreate that
at their side so they already can do
that now this particular model though we
have separate systems with
commercialized M fluidics that they can
buy and they can do it but this model
model is a custom customized microle
device that they have developed we have
developed so they don't have access
right now but uh this is actually an
idea that a my advisor and actually
everyone is thinking about like
commercializing this device down the
road so every can can can buy it thank
you oh yeah thanks for the talk there
there's all kinds of organoids that seem
to be limited by the lack of a
vasculature like there' be a neural
organoid or an embryo model or you know
any kind of number of organoids that can
only grow so far so long because they
don't have a vascular so does this does
this system in any way uh could it be
generalized to these other organoids to
allow them to you know have a blood
supply yeah I think so and actually I
think our lab is a great example because
uh pretty much all the models we have
have a blood
vasculature um so yeah I think uh you
can grow a blood vascular it takes more
time than just a monol layer of cells uh
but I think it can be Incorporated in
many system many systems depending on
the organ you want to
test sorry I'm just interested in your
data here why do you think the V EGF m m
doesn't follow the size rule or my the
Bea SZ M why the permeability is quite
High there sorry which one did you say
the one the large molecule your far
right the VF an body
bmab just quite High permeability
despite being okay so this is again uh
from another
study um yeah maybe I mention that
better but yeah so these are from other
studies like um that have been done in
the past so for this particular one I
have never tested the my results are
this main plot here so um I'm not really
sure as I haven't tested why this has a
higher permeability that could be due to
many reasons like I don't know nonp
specific endocytosis maybe could be one
or others um yeah I guess I'm not sure
about that since I haven't tested that
problem thanks