All
right. Uh let's get started. So today
we're going to continue our discussion
of you know algebra. Uh so last time we
talked about modular arithmetic and I
introduced you to the basic notions. We
talked about the uklidian algorithm, the
extended uklidian algorithm and uh
multiplicative inverses and it turns out
that um there are some really powerful
abstractions that can give us a useful
way to think about modular arithmetic
and these come from really the starting
point of group theory. So group theory
is something that you can take you know
a whole class in multiple classes in and
it goes quite deep but we're going to
introduce you to the basics of group
theory and you know why this abstraction
is powerful. So let me start off from
where we left off last time. So we had
this notion of you know multiplication
in modular arithmetic and one of the
questions which was on our mind was you
know whether an element has a
multiplicative inverse. So given an
element a is there's some other number
element we can multiply it by so that
mod n we get back one and we showed that
this was always true whenever n is prime
and a is non zero. And in fact um you
know what we really showed was that even
if n is not prime the critical thing is
whether or not the gcd the greatest
common divisor between a and n is one.
So we showed in particular that there
was this equivalent way to think about
the gcd as the smallest integer you can
get nonzero integer where you take you
know s * a plus t * n and you want to
get that to be equal to one. So if the
gcd is one then that gives you the
multiplicative inverse and if you can't
get one you can show directly that it
has no multiplicative inverse. So this
is where we left off last time. But now
I'm going to tell you one very powerful
definition and it'll take us you know uh
all of today's lecture to really
understand why this is such a powerful
notion which takes us to what's called a
group.
So a group is just a pair G. It's a set
of elements potentially infinite along
with a binary operation star. So this is
some set potentially infinite and this
is just a binary operation
and the critical thing about a group is
that it has to satisfy a whole bunch of
properties. So the first thing we need
is closure that we can apply this binary
operation to pairs of elements and get
back another element in the group. So
this is really just the statement that
for any pair of elements AB that belong
to the group the operation of A* B is
well defined because it sends us back to
some group element.
Right? So last time when I wrote down
for example this table we got with
modular addition I was really just
showing you for every row that's a
choice of a different element for every
column that's a choice of a different
element. And I told you in the table you
know what particular group element that
pair adds to or multiplies to. That was
just the closure property. We also need
associivity
which is also familiar from before. So
for all triples a b c that belong to
your group doing the operation of a star
b and then taking the result and doing
that with star c is the same thing as
parenthesizing the expression a
different way.
Okay.
We also need the existence of an
identity element
which means that there is some element
which we'll call E that belongs to the
group with the property that for all
elements of the group day doing a star E
gets back the same element I started
from and that doesn't matter whether you
apply E on the right or on the left
either way you get back your original
element and you do nothing to it. So for
example in the case of the group being
you know when we were working with this
um set of moduli
uh when we had addition the identity
element is zero and when we had
multiplication the identity element was
one. Okay.
And finally the last property we need
from our group is the existence of an
inverse.
So what this means is natural we want
that for all a belonging to our group
there is some element which we'll call a
inverse with the property that a inverse
applied on the left versus a inverse
applied on the right both of them send
you back to the identity element. So
this is the notion of a group. This is
just formalizing
you know algebraic structures that we've
already seen in action. We've already
seen groups but we didn't think about
them as abstract sets you know abstract
uh properties.
Um and I'll also mention that you know
additionally
if we have commutivity
so if commutivity holds that you know a
star b is equal to b star a then what it
we we say is that we call g
a billion so it's an aelion group So
these are the key definitions for today
and what we're going to do is we're
going to understand why this is
powerful. So are there any questions
about the definition of a group
this makes sense hopefully.
Uh so next let's go through some
examples. We've already seen groups in
action. Um and let's see some examples
just to you know get a feel for what
these definitions are. So one simple
example is you know an infinite group.
you've been working with all the time.
You can look at the set of integers
under addition.
Right? So we can check in that case our
set G is just an infinite set. It's the
set of all integers positive and
negative. Our binary operation is
addition. And you can check that all of
these properties hold. I take two
integers, I add them up, I definitely
get back an integer. Uh, when I add up
three integers, it doesn't matter the
order that I add them up. I have an
identity element that's zero. I have an
inverse that's just the negative of the
number I started off with. And in fact,
it's also commutative, so it's an aelion
group. So, this is a very simple example
of, you know, a group is just the set of
integers under addition. Uh just as a
pop quiz, what about the set of integers
under multiplication?
So what if I take the same set but my
binary operation is now multiplication?
Is that a group?
Why not?
>> Because zero doesn't have [laughter]
zero doesn't have an inverse. And that's
true of all kinds of other elements too.
when I take, you know, the element two,
well, I can talk about multiplying by
that element. That'll still send me back
to another integer, but I don't have the
existence of an inverse because that
would be 1/2 and that's not in my set.
So, a non-example of a group is, you
know, integers under multiplication. So,
it's not just about the set, but it's
about how the set behaves under the
binary operation I've chosen.
We can do another example with
multiplication. We can take the set of
uh rationals minus 0
and we can take
our operation to be multiplication.
So now we do have an inverse because we
just flip the numerator and denominator
and we once again have a group. Right?
So these are all examples of infinite
groups. And what we'll be particularly
interested in today are finite groups.
That's the part that's going to collect
uh connect with modular arithmetic.
So what about you know finite groups?
In fact I claim we've already seen some
examples of uh finite groups in action,
right? So we can take another example.
This will be a very important example
for us which is we can take ZN which is
just um you know addition
we can take it with the binary operation
of addition uh you know modular
addition.
So for example when n equals two this is
just you know two elements we're looking
at evens and odds and for that you know
finite group just the set of evens and
odds you can check that you know when
you add up two elements it makes sense
you know an even plus an even takes you
back to even an odd plus an odd takes
you to even and an even plus an odd
takes you to odd right so in fact um
we've already seen examples of finite
groups in action that's what we did last
time, right? But let me give you a a
more interesting example which is going
to show up
okay.
So actually let's do a simple corlary
first and then we'll get to that
example.
You know this will be a correlary of
that key lema I wrote up there. So let's
look at the set ZN minus 0. So I'm just
looking at the remainders when I take
mod n but I'm removing the zero elements
and if I look at this finite set with
multiplication
I claim that this is a group
if and only if n is prime
and I'm writing this as a correl
because really it's a corollary of this
key lema that we showed last time.
So let's prove this lema just to get
some familiarity with groups.
So this is an if and only if statement.
Uh let's prove the reverse direction
first. So let's suppose that n is prime.
Then uh why exactly you know is this a
group? Now some properties you know a
bunch of properties of the group are
sort of tedious to check and they're
very natural. So you know if I take
multiplication mod n it's definitely
closed. You know that's what it means to
do modular multiplication. We talked
about that last time. You just multiply
the two numbers and subtract off as many
multiples of n as you can and you'll get
back to some remainder. No big deal.
It's associative because really
multiplication is associative and we're
just subtracting off multiples of n. Uh
you know the main question and the
identity element is easy. That's also
one. I take any remainder multiply it by
one I still get the same remainder. The
tricky thing is really the inverse right
that's where this corollary becomes
interesting. So the key thing to check
is that uh there is an inverse and
really from our lema. So if n is prime
we know by the key lema from last time
that every element
has a multiplicative inverse.
So that proves one direction you know of
our corlary.
Uh you know the converse is equally
simple. So let's prove that you know uh
if n is com we'll actually prove it in
the contraositive. So let's suppose
that n is composite.
So what I just proved was that if n is
prime then it's a group. But let's prove
that you know if n is not prime if it's
a composite that we don't have a group
right
and how am I going to prove that this is
not a group what I'm going to do is I'm
going to construct an element that
doesn't have a multiplicative inverse
because that's where all this action is
happening in the proof of this
corollary.
So any guesses for what kind of element
might not have a multiplicative inverse?
Any good ideas? We already know this
lema tells us a bunch of things do have
multiplicative inverses. So where should
I look for something that doesn't have a
multiplicative inverse? I should look
for an element A where the GCD between A
and N is not one. Right? So let's just
take any old
element A with the property that the GCD
between A and N is not equal to one.
Right? And so you know the lema tells us
already you know the work is already
done for us that that element does not
have a multiplicative inverse. So it
fails our property four of being a
group.
So when we were doing modular arithmetic
and we were worrying about
multiplicative inverses really what we
were doing was we were characterizing
when exactly we had this group
structure.
So that's the first point is that we
were really doing group theory last time
and you know what we're going to do now
is we're going to understand some of the
implications of having this abstraction.
All right.
Uh actually let me make one comment
first. So just as a quick comment this
will be very useful for later. So
imagine that uh we take n which is
composite. We now know that the nonzero
elements of ZN do not form a group. But
it turns out that even though it's not a
group, there is a group hiding inside.
So this will be very useful for us. So
there is a way to fix the failure of
this group property. What we can do is
we can let ZN
star
just be the set of elements A belonging
to ZN with the property that the GCD of
A and N is equal to one.
So what I claim and I'll just assert
this but the proof is very simple. It
just again follows from this key lema
last time. What I claim is that ZN star
equipped with the multiplication
operation is a group.
So that's our key fact that we're going
to be using. So even though there are
elements, you know, belonging to ZN that
are not zero that do not have a
multiplicative inverse. So we failed to
be a group, we can just take the set of
elements that do have an inverse. the
set of all elements a where the gcd is
one and what I claim is that that's a
group sitting inside this other thing
that failed to be a group
so the main point for today's lecture is
we're going to uh develop some
understanding of you know properties of
groups we're going to prove something
called lrangees theorem which is going
to have a ton of cool um you know simple
to understand applications
So let's go a little further with you
know group theory.
Let me give you a key definition.
The order of a group
of a finite group
G
is just the number of elements
and we denote it by size of G this way.
So we're just measuring the number of
elements in G. Okay?
And you shouldn't yet see why this is a
very useful notion, but that's where
Lrangees theorem is going to kick in.
But let's do some examples just to make
sure that, you know, we're on the same
page. So we can look at, you know, ZN
with multiplication
um for prime n.
So we already proved in our corollary
that when n is prime, this is a group.
So what's the order of this group? Well,
the order of this group
uh you know ZN sorry ZN
uh minus 0 because the element zero
doesn't work.
Well, this is just N minus one for this
group just because I've uh uh removed
that element.
Okay. So now um the key property we're
gonna Okay. So then let's do one more
example and this will be a a crucial
example that we use for later. So let's
imagine that M is composite. We can look
at Z MM star again with multiplication
and let's assume that you know M is
equal to P * Q where both P and Q are
primes and they're distinct primes.
So this is one simple example. you know
m is composite so zm you know minus0 is
not a group but if we only look at the
set of elements that have a
multiplicative inverse we know that it's
a group the question is what's the order
of this group so how many elements are
actually in the set zm star so this is
really just a counting argument right
because what we want to do is we want to
count the number of a's such that the
gcd between a and m is equal to one.
So now what I can do is I can use my old
friend inclusion exclusion. Right? So
what I can do is I can overount. So I
can start off with you know PQ minus one
because those are all of the elements
that are in consideration you know in
the set and then what I can do is I can
subtract off the things which fail to
have gcd1.
So what are the ways that a could fail
to have gcd with m uh one? Well it could
have gcd equal to p or it could have gcd
equal to q. So the question is just how
many elements you know how many choices
of A are there where the GCD between A
and M would be P? How many are there
where the GCD would be Q?
Because that's the amount by which I've
overounted. So I should subtract off
those things. And you can subtract off P
minus one. This is just you know the
number of A's where the GCD
of A and M is equal to Q. In particular,
A should be a multiple of Q in order for
this to be true. And then there are P
minus one possibilities for what that
is. And I can do the same thing the
other direction. um I can subtract off
the things which are multiples of P and
I'm going to get q minus one of these
elements and there's nothing that's a
multiple of both p and q because the
largest my remainder gets to is pq minus
one. So this even though it sounds like
a pretty you know tedious example this
turns out to be an extremely important
example. So just to write down what the
expression is, it's p minus one * q
minus one. And what I promise you is
that this expression is going to come up
in a very magical way later. In fact, I
claim that this expression is the key to
RSA encryption. So we'll see a bit of a
hint of that. But this expression is
very important. It's just the order of
this group that you know has fixed the
fact that our original attempt was not a
group. So are there any questions about
where we are right now? The notion of
groups makes sense and the order makes
sense. Hopefully
any questions.
Good. All right.
So
I want to get up to Lrangeas theorem.
But next we have you know one more
abstraction before I can tell you
Lrron's theorem.
This is our last abstraction for today.
We can also talk about the notion of a
subgroup. So imagine I gave you a pair G
and star. So G is the set and we'll be
interested in finite sets for today. And
then we have this binary operation star.
And let's assume that it's a group. So
it satisfies all the axioms one through
four of being a group.
And let's imagine that you give me some
subset of the group. You just keep some
of the elements and let's call that H.
Well, if
this pair H and star is also a group.
Then what we do is we say that H
is a subgroup.
So this is our key definition. So not
only you know do we have a group but
sometimes inside a group we have other
smaller groups sitting inside them.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to show that whenever we have a
subgroup, we can say something very
interesting about the relationship
between H and G. So that's where we're
headed. But let's do, you know, let's
just be explicit about this, right? So
what does it mean for HAR to be a group,
right? So in particular what this
definition is really telling us
is that we better satisfy a stronger
closure property. So when we have any
pair of elements AB that belong to H,
we need that A* B belongs to H as well.
See A and B are both elements of G. So
we're automatically guaranteed that Aar
B belongs to G. But this is the stronger
statement that when A and B are actually
not just in G but they're sitting inside
H then the result of you know
multiplying them should be something
that's in H2. So the critical thing here
is that this should not just be in G
but in H itself. And the same thing is
true for the inverse too. Right? We need
that for all elements A belong to H.
Well, a is in G, so there is an inverse.
But the key thing is that this inverse
actually belongs to H and again not G.
So somehow when you're doing the binary
operations or when you're looking for
the inverse, you never have to go
outside of the set you started from even
though it lives inside a much bigger
group. So that's the idea. So this is,
you know, a key definition. This is very
subtle. Uh, are there any questions
about the definition for a subgroup?
All right. So, I'm going to state
Lrange's
and then we're going to go through some
examples
and we'll prove Lrange's theorem and
then I'll tell you some awesome
applications of it.
So what I claim relating all these
concepts we've done so far. So if G is
finite, it's a finite group and
H is a subgroup.
Then what I claim is that the order of H
divides the order of G.
This is why we care about orders
already, right? See, when you tell me
the group and you tell me the order, you
know, how many elements belong to this
group,
well,
that imposes some restrictions on what
kinds of subgroups you can find.
Say if I have my original group is you
know order six this tells me no matter
where I look I cannot find a subgroup of
order four because it wouldn't divide
it. So this is a really beautiful fact
even though it sounds like we haven't
assumed very much just G satisfies these
simple axioms and H is a subgroup
automatically we can say something very
striking and powerful about the
relationship between H and G that tells
us something very important structure on
what H could be. So we're going to prove
this but first let's give you know some
examples.
just to make this explicit,
right? So let's let G denote Z7 minus 0.
7 is prime. So this is a group. It has
six elements, right?
And now what's going on is that uh you
know the subgroup H we can take to be
the elements 1 2 4
and what you can do is you can just
check that when I take any of these two
elements you know 1 * 2 1* 4 I go back
within the subgroup right and 2 * 4 I go
back to the subgroup because it gives me
one
um and uh you know you can check that
every element has a multiplicative
inverse because in fact the
multiplicative inverse of four is two
and similarly the multiplicative inverse
of two is four. In fact one of the
elegant ways to see that this is a
subgroup is actually by realizing that
you know there's a way to express this
subgroup in a different way.
So an easy and powerful way to see this
that'll be very useful for what we do
later in terms of applications of
lrangege is that all of these elements
of the subgroup are all powers of two.
So 2 to the 1 is 2 mod 7.
2 3 is 1 mod 7 and 2 to the sorry 2 to
the two is 4 mod 7. So all of the
elements we got 1 2 and four they were
powers of two. So why do we have the
closure properties? is just because when
I take different powers of two and
multiply them, I'm just adding their
exponents.
So really this is the set of remainders
you get from taking powers of two and
looking at the remainder mod 7.
So this is one example of how to build a
subgroup is really with powers of some
element. And this will be a crucial way
that we we use lrangees theorem, but
I'll have to explain that later.
And of course you can check the obvious
thing that Lrange's theorem checks out
uh in this case because you know the
size of G is six the size of H is three.
So you know three really does divide
six. Okay.
All right. So, let me pause here and ask
you guys if you have any questions again
because if not, we're going to do the
proof of lrangees theorem. And that's
where we're going to assemble all of
these definitions from groups and
subgroups that we've been talking about
so far. So, uh, ask me questions to slow
me down. They should hopefully be about
the course material, but if not, that's
fine.
I'm just going to stare awkwardly until
someone asks me a question. Everyone
understands everything. You promise?
Yes. Okay. All right. I'll take it. So,
let's prove Lrron's theorem. This will
be the main proof we do today, but then
we'll get a whole bunch of amazing
applications out of it. And this fact
that I promised you is going to come
back later on. Okay, but we can already
see some hint about why this fact is
powerful. Counting the number of group
elements tells us something very
powerful about the types of subgroups we
can expect to see inside.
All right,
so let's prove it here. I think I should
have enough space.
Now this is really just a counting
argument using the group structure.
After all we just want to prove some
statement about divisibility.
So you know really what's going on here
the way to prove lrangees theorem at a
high level is to break G up into
different pieces.
You know we already have a subgroup
which is one piece of G. But the
question is how can I translate that
subgroup around to cover all of G in a
nice even way. So that's the intuition
behind Lrron's proof and you know making
this precise we have to talk about you
know what are these translates and this
takes us to the notion of a co-et. So,
as I promised you, the main idea
is to partition G.
And we're going to build up this
partition one by one. And we're going to
partition it into something called
co-sets.
These are really just translates of my
original subgroup. So, if you take any
element belonging to the group, what
we're going to do is we're going to
consider the following set. It's called
XH
and it's really the set of all XY where
Y belongs to H. Right?
So what's going on is for the definition
of the subgroup we needed the property
that when I take a pair of elements
belonging to H we go back within H. Here
I'm taking a pair of elements one of
which belongs to H and one of which is
general. And these are my different
translates. So I'm not just considering
an X which belongs to H. But as I
arrange X over the group, I'm going to
get different pieces of the group,
right? When X belongs to H, I'm just
getting back H. And when X is something
else that does not belong to H, it's a
translate of the thing I started from.
So these are called co-sets. In fact,
this is called a left co-set because the
element that um you know I'm taking from
G is multiplied on the left and right
co-ets would be the same thing but on
the other side.
So now uh you know here's our plan. This
is our plan of action is what we want to
do is we want to show that G can be
written as X1H
union disjoint union X2H
all the way up to disjoint union X KH.
So what's going on is I have K different
co-ets one for each of these XI. I
haven't told you how to find them. We'll
talk about that in a minute. But I want
the property that I can choose X1
through X K so that their resulting
co-etss together make up G and there's
no overlap between them. So what this
symbol means is it's not the union, it's
the disjoint
union. So I want all of these things to
have empty intersection.
Okay, so that's my plan. And if this
were true, Lrange's theorem would be
done, right? Because what is the s you
know each of these elements right here?
We're going to prove that each of these
co-ets has size order of H. And then
we've written G as K copies of H. So
that'll be our plan.
So here are the things we need to show.
And I haven't even told you, you know,
how to build up this set.
uh what I want to show is that the size
of each of these co-ets you know XH is
equal to the size of H. And I want to
show that the way that I've built it up
the intersection between any pair of
elements of any pair of co-etss is uh
zero. And this should be true for all I
not equal to J.
So in fact we're going to have a very
simple plan for how to generate these
XI's.
All we're going to do is you know we're
just greedily
pick an uncovered XI.
So I start off before I've built up a
single co-et. I have nothing. I've
covered none of the elements of G. I
take any arbitrary element X belonging
to G that's not covered which is all of
them. That will be my X1
that defines a co-et. I pull that co-et
out of G. All of those elements are now
covered. And then I take any other
element that's not yet covered. That's
my X2. It defines a co-et. I pull it out
and I keep recursing
in this way. But I have to prove that
this really does create a disjoint union
of G. Everything is covered at the end
and it's covered once and only once. And
I have to prove that each time I pull
out a piece, a co-et, it has exactly the
same size. So if we can prove these two
properties, we're done. And we've proved
lrangees theorem. But now proving these
two properties will just be about using
the axioms of group theory. So this is
where group theory is a powerful
definition. We haven't seen it yet but
we will in a minute is to prove these
two properties.
So let's show these two properties. So
first let's show
one.
Okay.
And
let's suppose
that
X H1 equals XH2
for some H1 and H2 belonging to my
subgroup capital H. So what is the way
that I wouldn't get the co-et has size
order H? Really the way that the co-et
is defined is once I fixed x I look at
you know xar y
for all y and h and if for different
choices of y I get the same element when
I do that multiplication I get a
collision that's the only way that I
don't have an equality here if that
doesn't happen then I really do have
that my co-et equals the order of the
subgroup every distinct choice of y is
going to lead to a distinct product.
Right? So let's imagine that we had two
elements H1 and H2 that X * H1 and X *
H2 were the same thing, right? And now
you know what should I do? I claim that
you know the way that my proof strategy
wants to work, right? This you know this
won't be a very complicated proof but
the logic is subtle. So what I want to
do is I want to show that h1 and h2 must
be the same thing.
I want to show that the only way that
you get the same element when you get x
* h1 is equal to x * h2 is if h1 equals
h2. So how should I do that?
How should I conclude that h1 and h2 are
the same thing?
And you know my hint is that you know
the critical thing in Lrange's theorem
is if G is a group so what should I use
about the group axioms in order to
conclude this fact?
That's my key question. You promised me
you guys understood everything up until
that point. So which axiom should I use?
I got you guys on the hook. Now
who can make me happy?
People
are not making eye contact.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Maybe we could use like the
existence of X inverse.
>> Yeah. That's right. That's a great idea.
Let's use the existence of X inverse,
right?
And that'll work. So now what we're
going to do is we're going to left
multiply
by X inverse. See this is where I need
the group structure is that X inverse
exists. Right? So once X inverse exists
then what this is going to imply is that
uh you know uh X inverse
X H1 and now I can use associivity
is equal to X inverse X H2. And when I
use associivity and the property of the
inverse that it equals the identity and
that identity times an element is the
element, it's going to imply that H1
equals H2. So in fact the critical thing
was the inverse but we really used all
of the properties like you know the fact
that we have associivity, the fact that
we get back the identity element and the
fact that the identity element doesn't
change any of those things. So in this
one step we've used you know all the
properties of groups which is great and
it implies the thing we're after but
this finishes this first part in the
proof. Every co-et has the same size
because when I take different elements
of h I cannot get the same thing because
of the inverse. So we're halfway home.
Right?
So let's show property two and then
we'll be done with Lrron's theorem.
So now let's show two.
Okay. So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to suppose that
they're not disjoint these co-etss we
get. So let's suppose for i less than j
we have the property that x i h1 equals
xj
h2 and this is true you know for some
h1 and h2 belonging to h. So we just
proved that you know we don't have any
collisions within the co-et we don't get
back the same element.
Now what I want to do is I want to
suppose for the sake of contradiction
that you know there's some co-et i and
there's some co-et j that intersect and
that means that there's some element I
got out of one which is you know x i *
h1 and that's the same as the element I
got out of the later coset which is xj *
h2. So this is what it means for the two
co-etss to not be disjoint is that they
have a collision for some H1 and H2. And
now we're going to try and get a
contradiction. Right?
So what I want to do I'm going to ask
you guys to help me out is that I want
to show that you know XJ actually
belonged to an earlier co-et.
So I want to show that XJ belongs
to an earlier co-et.
This would let me be done, right?
Because what is the way that I built up
my co-etss? I started off with any X
that was uncovered and I chose it as my
X1 and I pulled out the entire co-et.
And then I took any x2 that was still
not covered. I used it to find a co-et
and pull it out. So if some xj later
down the line actually belongs to an
earlier co-et, then that means I
shouldn't have done that. It should have
been pulled out before. Right? So what
I'm really saying logically is that if
this weren't true, if the intersection
were non zero, then I actually haven't
implemented this procedure I told you
correctly because xj was already
covered.
So now you know same question right I'm
telling you what I want to show this is
what we're assuming for the purpose of
contradiction
how can I show that xj
belongs to an earlier co-et and I'll
give you a hint it should be the co-et
defined by x i and same thing is going
to be true here we just need to figure
out what property of a group or subgroup
we should apply right so what should I
do to this expression h uh Xi H1 equals
Xj H2
to try and derive an expression where XJ
belongs to a co-et the coset of XI.
What about
right multiplying by H2 inverse?
Okay, so let's see what happens.
So let's
let's write multiply by h2 inverse. So
we get x i h1 h2 inverse is equal to xj.
I wanted to show that xj belongs to an
earlier co-et. Why is this expression
showing that xj belongs to an earlier
co-et? So what can I say about this
element right here? H1 H2 inverse.
Yeah,
>> it's an element in H.
>> It's an element in H. Right. Why?
Because H2 inverse belongs to H. And
then I'm multiplying two things
belonging to H. So we've used the two
key closure properties of the subgroup.
Right? And so what this means
is that you know XJ belongs to the set
XI H.
And that means that XJ should have been
covered and we shouldn't have considered
it to begin with. So that's our proof
like this is not a long proof but the
logic for this is very subtle. We used
everything that we could have used about
groups and subgroups just to prove these
few lines of this logical argument. Once
we had the strategy of how to partition
it into co-sets and we had this
definition of a co-et where we needed
the group theory and the subgroups was
really the structural properties that
forced these properties one and two to
be true. So this is a tricky proof. Uh I
will ask again any questions.
Is everyone comfortable with this proof?
So I can give you my pop quiz now.
That'll count towards 50% of your grade.
I'm just kidding.
Boy, would the people who didn't show up
today be upset. We should do that at
some point.
All right. Uh, so let's, you know, now
that we've done this hard work of
proving Lrange's theorem, let's see some
payoff.
So let me tell you some
awesome statements that are going to
follow as you know an application of
lrangees theorem
and it's going to connect all of the
tools we talked about subgroups powers
of elements
uh the order and everything.
So this is a theorem called uh format's
little theorem. We're not going to prove
for's last theorem.
Uh so what I claim is that if p is prime
and a
is not divisible by p.
Then
a to the p minus one is congruent to 1
mod p.
This is a beautiful identity, right? In
particular, what this means is really
that a to the p minus 2*
a is equal to 1.
So this gives me an explicit algebraic
expression for what the multiplicative
inverse is. Last time we talked about
how we could compute the multiplicative
inverse by using the extended uklidian
algorithm. It turns out you can also do
it by powering.
If you give me a and I know that p is
prime, all I have to do is raise a to
the p minus2 power and that is the
multiplicative inverse. You can check
that all of our examples satisfy that
property. That's why two and four were
multiplicative inverses of each other.
Uh was just that you take one and you
raise it to the p minus 2 power and
that'll give you the other one.
So this property it doesn't seem like
it's connected to lrangege but it is.
So it turns out that uh we're going to
prove it through lrangees theorem.
Right? So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to have a key definition which is
I'll let K be the smallest integer
such that
a to the k is congruent to one mod p.
So now uh the basic idea is that I have
to prove that such a K exists. It's not
obvious that there should always be a K.
And once I know that there is a K, I'll
relate it to the order of the group
because this is going to define a
subgroup. And that'll tell me something
about you know when I use Lrangees
theorem and I relate that to the order
of the actual group which is P minus
one, that'll tell me that the same thing
holds with P minus one instead.
So really you know this is the plan.
First I have to show that such a K
exists. So you know why is there any K
and now we get to use a lot of the tools
we've talked about in the class so far.
So we get to connect it to a lot of
earlier tools right I claim we can prove
this by pigeon hole principle.
So let's assume that there is no K.
Suppose there is no such K. Then what I
claim is that by the pigeon hole
principle,
there must exist some I less than J with
the property that A to the I is
congruent to A to the J mod P.
So what I'm going to do is I start off
with A. I raise it to different powers
and I stop at the first power where what
I get is congruent to one mod p. Let's
suppose I never stop. What if I just
kept going? Well, there are only so many
other values for what the remainder when
I divide by p can be. And eventually
when I consider high enough powers, I
must be getting some kind of collision.
Right?
So once I get this collision that a to
the i equals a to the j let's figure out
you know why there must exist a k such
that a to the k is congruent to one. So
what we can do is we can just divide
through by a because there is an inverse
to a right because p is prime and so we
can write this as a to the j minus i is
congruent to one mod p. This is just
because a inverse exists and we can get
rid of powers of a
right. So when we get rid of i powers of
a from both sides, we get the identity a
to the j minus i is congruent to one mod
p. And that shows that there must exist
some k just by pigeonal principle. So
this is the first thing that I owed you
is that k exists. Right? And now we're
going to relate k to p minus one. And
that'll be the proof of vermont.
So this is the first step. And now what
I claim
the powers of a
form a subgroup
and what is the order of this subgroup
right
it's K because that's the first time
when I got back the identity element so
it was the same way when I did that
numerical ical example up here. I had a
subgroup that was really generated by
powers of two. Now I have a subgroup
that's generated by powers of a. And my
order is just the first time that I
return back to the identity element.
That's what K is. So I have a subgroup
which is the powers of a and it has
order K. So what I can do is you know
now I can appeal to Lrange's theorem. So
by lranja's theorem
we know that k the order of my subgroup
must divide p minus one.
You remember when we did all those
computations of what the order of a
subgroup is when you know n is prime
when n is the product of two primes. We
know the order is p minus one because of
that first example we did. And now we
can appeal to Lrron's theorem and we
know that k divides p minus one. So now
we're golden because a to the p minus
one, you know that's the thing we want
to show is congruent to one mod p.
And what are we going to do? We're just
going to write this as a to the k raised
to the cth power. If for example P
minus1 equals C * K because K divides P
minus one. So I'm just rewriting it in a
different way. And now what do I know
about A to the K? What is it congruent
to? Mod P. It's congruent to one. So
this is the same thing as raising one to
the power C,
which is the same thing as one.
So that's the proof.
So this is for Mott's little theorem and
even though the statement of it had
nothing to do with groups right I could
have stated this for you at the
beginning of lecture today because we
knew what modular arithmetic was we know
what it means to take powers of a but
somehow the cleanest proof of theorem at
least one of the cleanest proofs really
goes through the fact that sitting
inside the powers of today is some
understanding of a group structure and
how that relates to you know the larger
group that it contains.
So are there any questions about
lrangees theorem? H sorry the
application of lrangees theorem to
format's little theorem.
Who's comfortable with the proof? Give
me a thumbs up. Okay.
All right.
So, one of the uh really cool things you
can do, let me just take a brief
digression for a minute.
Uh which is that you know something like
for Mott's little theorem there actually
tons of proofs. So, we gave a group
theoretic proof right now. Let me give
you a totally different proof just
because
and this will connect back to some of
the earlier topics we've seen. I claim
there's a purely combinatorial way
to prove for uh little theorem and we'll
prove it in a particular case for a
particular setting of you know a and p.
So let me give you a combinatorial
proof.
And let's do the proof specifically in
the case where a= 2 and p equals 5 just
to be concrete.
So the way that I'm going to do this is
I'm actually going to think about a
counting problem under the hood and
it'll involve something called
necklaces.
So the idea is that um you know when I
take the statement of you know Vermont
right it's the statement that uh a to
the p minus1
uh is is congruent to one but you know
another way to think about this
statement
is really the statement that a to the p
minus a is divisible
by p. That's really what this statement
means because I can take this identity
and I can multiply it through by a. So I
get a the p minus one is congruent to a
mod p. When I move the a on the other
side, I get this quantity a the p minus
a. And the statement that that's
congruent to zero mod p is really the
statement that that is a multiple of p.
Okay. And I claim that there's a
combinatorial proof of this fact which
will give us you know another way to
think about you know what format's
what's happening in for's little
theorem. So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to count certain combinatorial
objects and I'm going to prove as a
corollary that statement.
Right? So what I can do is I can think
about strings with different types of
beads. A is two. So they'll have two
kinds of beads, red or blue beads. And
their length will be P, which is five.
So I can look at the number of strings
of length
five over an alphabet.
Those are just the bead types of size
two. So how many strings are there of
length five that are composed of, you
know, red and blue beads? That's very
simple. It's uh 2 to the 5, right?
That's my a to the p right here is 2 to
the 5. It's just counting the number of
these strings.
But what I'm going to do instead of
counting these strings is I'll be
interested in the number of necklaces.
So I'll take those strings which are
length five and I'm going to tie their
ends together.
But now the point is that it doesn't
matter you know for the necklace whether
it's you know when you take that
necklace and rotate it it's still the
same necklace.
So now I'm losing some information.
there are fewer necklaces because some
of them are the same thing, right? So
the question is, you know, how many
necklaces are there?
I don't know. It was very easy to count
the number of strings I can get out of
two beads of length five.
And you know the way to think about it
is that um when you take an example
let's say right which is a necklace that
looks like red blue red red
well there are actually many strings it
could have come from right in fact there
are five strings it could have come from
which all depend on where the B is.
Maybe the B was the starting point of
the necklace. Maybe it was the second
and so on. And there are five
possibilities and five is my P. Right?
So in fact some of these necklaces
really come from equivalence classes of
strings that could have generated them.
Now there are some necklaces which don't
come from five different strings.
Uh, can anyone give me an example of a
necklace that can only come from one of
the uh 32 possibilities?
>> All reds.
>> All reds. Perfect.
You know, there are all of these other
examples. Well, there's two of them. We
could take all red
and we could take all blue. This it
doesn't, you know, any way you rotate
it, you get back the same thing. So what
you can show is that these are the only
two possibilities that you know the
proof is using the uh uklitian algorithm
again amazingly
but um you know here the number of
necklaces really the way to think about
them is in different groups either it's
a necklace which comes from five strings
or it's a necklace that comes from one.
So you know this gives us our proof
right is because you know the statement
is that if we look at five this should
divide 2 5th minus 2. So these are the
number of non monochromatic
strings.
And if we just remove all of the
monochromatic strings, the all red and
the all blue, the rest of the strings
have this property that they come in a
5:1 relationship with the necklaces.
So in fact, the necklaces gives us a way
to group the set of strings into groups
of five. So what does this statement
look like more generally? This is just
the statement that P divides
A to the P minus A because you'll have a
monochromatic necklaces and that is
exactly what format's little theorem is
telling you.
So you know once we have enough tools in
uh discrete applied math there's this
amazing nexus between these things. This
was a simple statement related to
modular arithmetic. I can prove it using
group theory. I can prove it using
combinotaurics
and you know there are maybe half a
dozen different proofs of format's
little theorem. There are many routes to
this theorem and they all lead to
different kinds of abstractions in
different mathematics.
All right. Any questions about this?
All right. So
I will tell you uh one other statement
which I promised you.
This is due to oiler
and this is the thing which is going to
have you know amazing applications on
cryptography when we get to it in in a
bunch of lectures time we'll do that
we'll do a whole unit on it later
this is due to oiler
So let's say that uh so we're in the
same setting of format's uh little
theorem except for the fact that we have
a composite. So if m is equal to p * q
where p and q are distinct primes
and a
has
gcd
between a and m equal to 1.
Then what I claim
is that a to the p min -1
* q -1 as congruent to 1
mod m.
So this takes a minute to digest, right?
So now I'm working modulo m that is not
prime. So we already know that it's not
a group and not every element has a
multiplicative inverse
but some elements do. In particular,
what are the elements that have a
multiplicative inverse? Those are the
A's where the GCD between A and M is
one.
So what I'm saying is that all of these
elements that have a multiplicative
inverse, a version of Format's little
theorem holds even though we're not
working over a prime. The difference is
that I'm raising it to a different
power. It's not, you know, p minus1,
you know, anymore where p is the
modulus.
It's now, you know, p min -1 * q -1. So,
we've changed the power we have to raise
it to in Oilers's.
It turns out that this is really a
correlary of the proof I already gave
you.
There's actually nothing that's really
specific about the fact that P is prime.
We're just using groups, right?
So what can I do? Like how does this
proof change?
Where did I use the fact that it was
prime?
Well, uh let K be the smallest integer
so that a to the K is congruent to one
mod M. Right? I have to prove that you
know such an integer exists
and uh you know if not then there'll be
some collision where a to the i is
congruent to a to the j and then I can
still rearrange things because I'm
working with an a whose gcd between a
and m is one so it has an inverse so I
can pull out i powers of a and I'll get
a the j minus i is congruent to one mod
m. that part still worked. It was
literally the same proof. So such a k
exists.
And now uh that's still a subgroup,
right? When I look at the powers of two
uh look at the powers of a that's still
a subgroup. I still know its order
because that's the first time I have a
collision is at K.
And then uh by lranjes theorem I know
that k divides not p minus one but the
order of the group. So what did I
promise you we were going to use was
this simple example. This computation
right here. What is the order of the
multiplicative subgroup sitting inside
ZM which is where the structure is
really happening? It's not M minus one.
It's P min -1 Q -1. So what do we know
is that K divides P minus1 * Q -1. So
then uh you know k is uh p minus1 * q
minus one is equal to c * k. Same thing
happens here. This is p min -1 * q -1
which I'm writing as a the k raised to
the cth power and that's still one.
So in fact what's really cool about this
right I could have told you all of this
at the beginning of lecture. We knew
what modular arithmetic was. I could
have stated for the I could have stated
Oilers's
and they might have seemed a bit
mysterious like why is the power I'm
raising things to different depending on
whether I have a prime or I have a
product of primes
right and it turns out that once you
have this group theoretic proof of it we
can see that the reason that we have a
different power is because you know it's
no longer a group and we have to look at
the order of the subgroup that's inside.
So that's really what's going in the
exponent is just the order of the
appropriate subgroup.
So this is one of the amazing things
about, you know, group theory um is that
uh it can demystify a lot of these
statements that otherwise look like
they're, you know, not quite the same
thing. In fact, here we had literally
the same proof. It was 100% the same
proof. I just had to cross out a bunch
of things and replace them.
So, are there any questions?
All right.
So, very last thing I'm going to tell
you
uh one more abstraction and then I'm
just going to tell you a theorem because
we're going to use it later, but we'll
just take this for granted. So it turns
out, you know, a group has a decent
amount of structure, but not, you know,
not everything.
[clears throat] So there's actually
something you can do which imposes even
more structure than a group. Actually,
there are many things you can do. Uh
there are things called rings. We won't
be interested in those, but we'll be
interested in something called a field,
which has a lot more structure than a
group. And when you're dealing with a
field a lot more nice things can happen.
So uh last bit of you know abstract
algebra is you know a field
is a set f potentially infinite which
now has two operations addition and
multiplication
and it satisfies a bunch of properties.
So first of all we need that f and the
operation plus the binary operation is
an aelion group
and it'll have identity
which is some distinguished zero
element.
We're going to need that multiplication
is also a group. We need that f minus0
when we remove out the element that's
the identity for addition. We need that
the binary operation on whatever remains
is a group.
We need that it's an aelion group
and it'll have identity
one some special element. And the very
last property that we need is we need
that uh it satisfies the distributive
property.
So we need that uh for all
a b c belonging to my field a times b +
c is the same thing as a * b plus a * c.
So this is a field. A lot of times we're
not just dealing with groups. We're
dealing with fields like the field of
you know rationals where we have
addition and multiplication and
everything behaves nicely.
And now here's an amazing theorem which
we're going to use later on when we uh
do more crypto.
Uh what I claim is that any polomial
of degree
D at least one with coefficients
in my field can have
at most d roots
in f. So what this means is you can
consider some polomial
p of x which is you know p 0 plus p1x
and so on all the way up to pd you know
x to the d and the crucial thing is that
you know all of these pi's belong to my
field
and I'm only going to consider values of
x that belong to my field. So a notion
of a root is can I find an x that
belongs to my field so that p of x
evaluates to zero.
And now it turns out that uh you can
show you know this basic statement we
know and love about real valued
polomials that they if they have degree
d they have at most d roots. Well that's
actually a property of a general field.
So it's not just a property of the
reals. It generalizes even in this
sense. So just to give you a hint about
what we're going to do later. We're
going to do an application we talk about
crypto called secret sharing. What we
want to do is we want to take a secret
and divide it up among a group of n
people so that any k people can recover
the secret but any fewer than that
cannot recover the secret. So they can
together share their piece of the key
and find out the answer. And what we're
going to be interested in is the way
we're going to build up our secret
sharing schemes is we're going to be
working with polomials not over the
reals but over finite fields. So roughly
what's going to happen is that the
secret will be something like you know
the constant coefficient of my polomial.
So it's some finite value from some
finite field and then what each of the
parties are going to have is they're
going to have the evaluation of this
polomial at some point and together when
they have enough points and evaluations
they can interpolate the polomial and
find the secret and otherwise they
cannot. So I'll just give you the hint
of that for later. But you know stay
tuned when we do uh cryptography. We're
going to see how this identity namely
Oilers's theorem is the basis for modern
cryptography in the RSA encryption
scheme. And we're going to see how this
uh statement about polomials and the
number of roots is the basis for modern
secret sharing. But we'll get there. So
let's stop here and um I'll take any
questions you guys have offline.
Otherwise, have a great uh spring break.
Hope you guys do something fun.