a lot of you um you're interested in
knowing not only what we're expecting to
see in the application components but
again how the the whole admissions um
process works and I think you know this
is something that we talk a lot about um
and it can be viewed in a sense of being
um a little bit of a cliche but we
really do take a very holistic approach
to the evaluation or admissions process
when we're considering candidates um
meaning that we look at all pieces of
your application and we use them to
better understand who you are as an
applicant. Um we are looking for
students who are missiondriven. Um
students who have a history of academic
success. So if you look in terms of this
first group being um I will mention and
pull out that mathematics or elemental
fundamental mathematics in some of these
courses that are also what we ask about
in the application are going to be
really important and are going to help
to for you to be able to succeed in the
program because when you think about the
coursework and against again the rigor
of it um the the quantitative finance
courses and everything else that's built
in you're going to be doing a lot that
will draw upon any of your knowledge in
these fundamental mathematics. Um,
computer programming again it is not re
it is not required but it's highly
recommended that you have some
familiarity and this is at a basic level
in Python. We're also going to teach you
Python as part of the course. Um, and
then STEM backgrounds or disciplines. So
the science, technology, engineering,
mathematics students have found that
that has really been helpful to them in
thriving and doing well in the program.
um coming with some background in
finance, statistics, accounting and
economics is also really valuable. And
then as we think about you know what why
would you want to pursue a master of
finance or an MIN program you know
certainly having some work and or
internship experience in the field or
related is beneficial but let me
emphasize this it is not required.
Um, we're looking for individuals again
who have those strong academic records
and are good problem solvers. We can
teach you finance. So, um, I think
that's important to note here. Um but
understanding of finance career paths is
also extremely helpful for us to be able
to to see what is your passion for the
field, what is your motivation, how do
you want to make an impact, and then
last but not least, um excellent
communication and interpersonal skills.
um written and spoken English language
if English is not your native language
um coming to MIT and expecting to be
able to learn it um once you get to
campus is is not going to work. You need
to really have those strong written and
communi uh spoken and communication
skills before you get to campus. uh team
player. Um it's a term that's thrown
around a lot, but we also want to know
not only how much you are um
participating as a team player on
whether it's university projects, work
projects, but also do you recognize the
successes of others on your team? Um how
do you demonstrate that? And really a
desire to become an active member of the
MIT Sloan classroom and community that
is integral. When we talk about it, we
talk a lot about the clubs, conferences,
other ways that you can engage in the
community and it is really a huge part
of your network that hopefully you will
take with you for a lifetime. So, you
put all this together, these are some of
the things that we're really going to be
focused on as part of admissions.
So, hopefully that's given you kind of
at a high level what we're looking for.
Here is the application checklist. We're
going to go through each of these one by
one. Um the deadline and let me just
mention this upfront is January 3rd for
anyone who is planning to enroll uh in
this July of 2025. Um what I will tell
you is that we do not have rolling
admissions. It's one cycle or one intake
and I promise you we do absolutely
nothing. I say this all the time when
I'm out on the road talking to
prospective students. We do nothing with
your applications until after the
deadline of January 3rd. So, please do
not rush to submit your application
unless you feel that it's as strong as
it should be and that you've answered
all the questions and submitted all the
documents. That being said, though, if
it's ready in 2 weeks and you want to
submit it, absolutely go right ahead and
do that. But nothing will happen to your
application. So, let's start going
through some of these application
components.
Uh transcripts, of course, we want to
see, you know, as I mentioned earlier,
what are some of the things that we're
looking for? It's definitely the
strength of your academics and your
background. So, um, an important note
here or notes is that all applicants to
the program must hold a four-year at
undergraduate or bachelor's degree. We
know in some countries it's actually the
three years that you earn that um
undergraduate or bachelor's degree, and
that's fine. We accept them. You must
have completed all your undergraduate
and bachelor's degree requirements by
the time you start the program in July.
And this is very important because while
you may not in some cases there are
schools where you complete all your
degree requirements in time to start the
program, there may be an extra paper or
some other document that you need to
submit and you may not have your trans
final transcripts until a little bit
later. That's okay as long as you are
not expected to go back and finish an uh
a paper um on your c you know
undergraduate campus or take a test or
um have to go back is not permitted. So
you will you absolutely cannot leave the
program once you started in July to go
back and fulfill your degree
requirements. So I just want to make
sure that's clear because it does come
up um a lot every year from prospective
students. So if this is not the case for
you, you may want to think about is this
the right year to apply and maybe think
about a ne the next year. Um these are
just some additional details. All of
this that I'm talking to you about now
and that we're going to be continuing to
review in this session are available in
the application itself. So you can see
all of these instructions and details. I
will tell you please please just follow
instructions, answer the questions. Um,
and if you have any specific situations
that you're unsure about, you absolutely
can write to us separately or questions
that are coming up now um, in the Q&A,
but please make sure to scan and upload
your transcripts from all colleges and
universities you attended or currently
attending. Um, we also want to make sure
that anything that is not in English. We
do actually want to see the original
versions in the foreign language as well
as translated versions. up to you who
you have do the translation. There are
many services out there, West and
others. Fine with us as to whichever. We
don't have a preference. Um do not mail
any hard copies of your official
academics or uh uh records or
transcripts, excuse me. And then once
you are admitted to the program, you
will be required to provide an official
signed and sealed transcript from all
the schools that you have attended. So
that is something that you know we'll do
um in addition to verifying anything
that you tell us in the application.
test scores. So, um I want to be clear
about this. While test scores are
important, um and certainly can be one
of the many different things that we're
reviewing, um it is optional for 2025 to
submit test scores. And this applies not
only to GMAT and GRE, but also to the
English language ability test, TOEFL and
IELTS. Um if you have a GMAT or GRE
score, certainly submit it. if you think
um it's an additional data point that
you would like the admissions committee
to consider. Um that being said though
again those without a test score will be
reviewed as is and there's absolutely no
negative inferences. We have a lot of
information about you um in terms of
your academic background and strength.
We're going to be looking at the courses
you've taken. We're going to be looking
at how well you've done in the u more
substantive and quantitative courses.
We're going to be looking at what your
academic recommenders, which we'll talk
about in a minute, are going to say
about you. So there are many different
components and aspects of your
background that will contribute to how
we view overall your academic strength
and whether you're going to thrive in
the program. Um we will accept
self-reported test scores by the
application deadline and welcome either
the traditional or online version of the
exams. Um please only input accurate
test scores. Do not use estimates or
approximations. Um that being said
though again with the application you
are going to self-report. If you do
submit GMAT or GE score GRE scores, you
are going to self-report them. We will
verify all that information later on.
So, employment and resume information.
I'm going to actually turn this over to
my colleague Ally. She's going to talk
to you about this.
Hey Diane, sorry. Um I was thought I was
going to do um letters of bre. Okay,
I think the resume anyway. That's okay.
No worries.
Um, yeah, happy to talk about our um
employment and resume information
section. So, there are actually two
different areas on the application where
um we do ask you about your past
employment. So, we're going to walk
through both of them right now. Um, the
first is the employment information
section. So, this is where we'll ask you
to list up to three of your most recent
employment experiences. Um, it's
important that these are verifiable. So,
it means that you must have been hired
by HR. If we contact um your employer,
they should be able to confirm that you
did in fact work there um and talk about
your experience there. Um in this
section, we ask that you only include
examples of um full-time or internship
experiences. Um and we define full-time
work as more than four months of paid
postderee work. Um, if you have
nonofficial work experience, um, for
example, if you weren't hired by HR,
maybe you were working with, um, you
know, a mentor, um, to do projects like
that, we do want to hear about that.
That it is of course very important
experience. Um, but we ask that you
include that on your resume or in other
points in the application and not in
this specific employment section. Um,
now in the resume, um, we ask that you
submit a one-page resume that follows
the following format. Um, we need it to
be in Times New Roman font. um uh size
10 and in word or PDF format only. Um
and you'll list your experience in
reverse chronological order. Um and this
is where you can include um other points
of reference um in addition to your
full-time and internship experiences.
So, of course, your education, um any
other work experiences you've had, as
well as additional information, any um
extra skills that you might have,
technical abilities, extracurriculars,
um that can all be on here as well. Um,
if you have any questions about how we
define some of these other sections, um,
there's a very detailed description on
the application itself, um, about how we
would define other work experiences,
additional information as well. So,
please do read that carefully, um, and
be sure to give us the information that
we are asking for.
Thank you, Hie. So, that was great. Um,
I think that hopefully we've made it
really clear. Um we've worked very hard
to ensure that people understand what we
mean by full-time work versus um you
know multiple part-time or internships.
And again um as Ally mentioned, it's
really important that um you make sure
that what when we do admit students, we
are going to verify all of your
information and it's important that
we're able to easily verify any kind of
internships or work experience that you
have provided in your application. So,
can't overemphasize that enough.
Okay, Ally, do you want to pick up here?
Yeah. Yeah, I'll keep going. Um, so for
letters of recommendation, I do know we
get a good amount of questions on our
letters of reck, so want to make sure
that we're really clear about um what
we're asking for. So, first and
foremost, every applicant should submit
three letters of recommendation. Um, if
you are currently a student while you're
applying, we ask that two letters come
from an academic source from your
current school. And one letter should
come from a professional source, um,
like a recent internship or a co-op, um,
preferably your most recent internship
or co-op experience. If you're applying
while you're working full-time, you
know, you've already graduated, um, we
understand that you may have, you know,
a bit of of a gap between, you know,
your past academic experience. And for
that reason, only one letter is required
to come from an academic source. Um, and
then one letter should come from your
most recent employer. And the third
letter is up to you. It can be from an
academic source or professional. Um,
whatever you think or whoever you think
will be able to best speak to your
abilities.
Um, regardless of if you're applying as
a current student or working full-time,
it is important that at least one letter
come from someone that can speak to your
quantitative abilities. So, be sure to
consider that when you're thinking about
who you're going to be asking. Um, and
an additional note is that we do ask
that all letters be submitted using the
link provided in the application. Um, as
you're sending out your request, the
recommener will get a link sent to their
email and we ask that they use that link
to submit it and not just send us um,
you know, their letter to our email. Um,
a couple of tips to share about the
recommendation process. Um, first I will
note that you can see the questions that
your recommener will be asked when they
get the um request from you. So um take
some time to look over those questions
and think intentionally about who would
be a good person to ask who can actually
speak to all of those topics. Um, it may
also be helpful if you have time to meet
with your recommenders and talk about
um, you know, why you're asking them
specifically for a letter, why you want
to apply to the MININ program, what
you're hoping to gain from it. Um, and
just kind of walk through that whole
thought process with them so that they
might have more content for their
letter. Um, especially if you're asking
a professor that maybe has a large class
or they haven't had contact with in a
little while, it's great to reconnect
and kind of remind them um, you know,
about who you are and have that
conversation so that they're able to,
you know, talk about you as accurately
as they can. Um, and this brings me to
my next tip, which is to ask your
recommenders for these letters as early
as you can. If you haven't started that
process yet, I would strongly encourage
you to do so. Um, they are busy people.
The deadline is approaching quickly. Um
and especially if you want to take some
time to uh you know sit down and talk to
them about this at all, you will need a
little bit of extra time. So would
encourage you to begin that process now.
Um and then my last tip for letters of
recommendation is just a reminder that
we are not evaluating your recommener.
So there's a tendency I think for people
to want to ask someone that's high up at
their organization or you know the dean
of their school and even if they've only
met them a couple of times or you know
worked on one project with them. Um, and
at the end of the day, we're not looking
at the recommenders title, um, you know,
or who they are at the, um, company, per
se. We're looking at what they say about
you and how well they can speak to your
skills and your skill set. So, um, you
know, be intentional about who you're
asking. And, um, you know, if you work
at Amazon, we don't need Jeff Bezos to
write your letter. Please just pick
someone that can really speak to the
contributions you've made um, and get
help us get to know you as best as we
can.
Those are great tips. Yes. Thank you,
Ally. And I would also just add um I
know for some individuals if your um
recommener if English is not their
native language you know they may want a
little help but please you know try to
make sure that they're getting it
translated from someone else other than
yourself. I think's tip about, you know,
wanting to ensure that your recommenders
understand um beyond just the request
why you're asking them to provide the
information and answer those seven
questions that are really important for
us to because we look at everything. Um
but keep that in mind as well. So all
great tips. Thank you.
Okay, video.
Yeah, of course. So the video questions
also ones that we get a couple of
questions about every year. Um, so happy
to share more info on this too. So
really the videos are a chance for your
application to really come alive is how
we see it. Um, video one is just a
chance for you to introduce yourself to
your future classmates. It's a chance
for us to really put a face to the name
of the application that we've been
reading, you know, so intensely. Um, and
have your personality really shine
through. So um, this video can be
conversational, relaxed. We want you to
be yourself. Um, again, you're
introducing yourself. So, what would you
share with someone if you were meeting
them for the first time? Um, it does not
need to be overproduced. You know, we
don't need movie quality videos here.
Um, you can definitely just be sitting
at your desk recording it with your
phone, camera, whatever is easy and
comfortable for you. Um, you are
welcome, if you choose to do so, to film
it in a different environment. Um,
however, we do ask that wherever and
however you record the video, please
follow the guidelines we share about,
um, you know, what the video should be
like. Um, so first and foremost, you
only have a minute for the video, so
it's relatively quick. You know, please
stay within that time frame. Um, please
let the video be all in one continuous
tape. So, don't edit together different
snippets of different videos. Um, it
should be one solid video.
Um, but the most important thing I would
say about the video is that we need to
be able to see and hear you very
clearly. So, um, please speak directly
to the camera and make sure that you're
in a quiet place with no background
noise or distractions. Um, there should
be no music that you put over the video.
Um, if you're filming outside, let's
say, there should be no wind that, you
know, we aren't able to hear you over.
So, um, before you submit it, please be
sure to watch it back and make sure that
we can see and hear you clearly. Um, we
just want to be able to, you know,
really meet you.
Um, one tip that I would share about
video one is that I think that you might
want to um, and absolutely can share and
talk about pieces that you know are
listed on your resume or experiences
that are touched on in other parts of
your application, but you also can use
the opportunity to talk about things
that maybe haven't been mentioned on
your application yet, like hobbies or
activities um, or other passions. So,
feel free to share um, those too in this
video. Again, it's an introductory
video, so we want to get to know you.
Um, video question two. Um, I will the
first thing I'll note is that video
question two does not appear in the
application until you're about 80% done
with it. So, it's kind of a popup that
appears, um, towards the, um, end of
your application. So, um, be on the
lookout for that tab to appear. Um, the
style of this video question is more of
a question and answer. So, you will be
presented with a prompt that is randomly
selected from a list of over 200
possible questions. Um, and once that
question appears, you'll have 10 seconds
to prepare a response and then you'll
have one minute to record your answer to
it, which the recording will begin right
after that 10 minute, sorry, 10 minute,
10-second um, preparation period. Um,
the question that will appear is not
going to be a technical question and
does not require preparation. Um, an
example might be something like, uh,
what's an article you've read recently?
Um, what was it about? How did it impact
you? So, there's not really a right or
wrong answer. We are just looking to
learn about how you communicate, how you
express yourself, what your thought
process might be. Um, and again, just a
chance for your application to come
alive and for us to get a better sense
of you as a person as a whole. Um, one
thing I will note about video question 2
is that before you record your response,
you do get to kind of go through a bit
of a test run. Um, make sure that your
video is recording properly, that your
microphone is recording properly, so
that there should be no technical
glitches. you'll get a good sense of
what the platform is like. Um so please
do use that test environment to make
sure that you feel um ready to move
forward and actually see the question
and start recording. Um this is because
you only have one attempt to record this
and we are unable to offer you a redo.
Um if there is a glitch or something
goes wrong. So please make sure that
everything is functioning properly
before you start to record. Something
doesn't look right, you can email us but
um you should be able to navigate
anything through that test environment.
make sure that your, you know, video is
clear, that there's no background noise,
your microphone's functioning, um, and
then record it because just like video
one, most important thing is that we're
able to see and hear you. So, um, please
just be sure that that is all
functioning properly before you record.
I think that's video question two.
Yeah, great. I mean, I love the fact
that we have these videos incorporated
into the application and you should see
it as a very positive way to a positive
aspect and component components because
it really is again, you know, how we're
able to really put a face with the name,
get to know your personality, let it
shine through. Um, and uh, it really is
again one of the, you know, things that
I think is um, a great way to express
yourself and it goes beyond just seeing,
you know, pieces of paper with writing
on it. So, thank you Ally for those. So,
let's talk about a couple of the short
answers. I'm want to be cognizant of the
time. So, I'm going to go through these
a little bit quickly. Um, but here's
another way that we want to be able to
get to know you a little bit better. Um,
each of you has your own journey and
story to tell. And so, we're going to
ask you how the world you come from has
shaped who you are today. You know, it
could include something about your
family, your culture, your community.
you know, what has helped to shape
aspects of your life experiences thus
far and your perspective. Um, it's
really um, again, another way for us to
get to know you a little bit better and
it really does speak to the things that
we look for um, from an admissions
standpoint is how much will you engage
in our community um, and the larger MIT
ecosystem.
And then we have a few um, what we call
professional questions. Um so just you
know discussing your past academic
professional experiences and
accomplishments um include achievements
and then we have a second question about
your short-term and long-term
professional goals. These are
non-binding. I promise you we are not
going to hold you to what you tell us in
these but it helps us again get a sense
of you know if you don't come from a
background of having some finance or
finance related courses or internships
what is it about you know the finance
field that interests you and the infant
degree and helping you to achieve those
goals and then the third one is what
personal qualities will enable you to
contribute to the advancement of our
mission um and the mission is really an
integral part of being at MIT
So, we've given you a lot of information
about the application and the
components. Um, some tips. I hope this
has been really helpful. Let me just
tell you what's going to happen next.
Um, so as I said, absolutely nothing to
your applications will happen before the
January 3rd deadline. January 4th, we
then have an admissions committee and
professionals who are going to review
applications. um a lot of you know what
we're going to be looking at is based on
all of the things that we've just talked
about. So everything in the application
all the components really are um you
know they're developed to measure your
attributes and that what we feel will
make you successful MFIN candidates. Um
and so we we really are interested in
knowing what you have done thus far. um
how are you looking towards the future
is certainly something where we also
want to know about but we also want to
make sure that you know what you've done
thus far is going to set you up for
success and to thrive in the Min
program. Interviews are by invitation
only. So once we review applications
then we make decisions and then then if
you're advancing you're going to be
required to um have an interview. They
will be conducted via Zoom. It's
typically one-on-one with an admissions
professional. Um, there will also be
some additional aspects to an interview.
You'll have to complete a virtual
quantitative assessment uh and submit a
pre-in essay question. All of the
details around this and the interview
you will receive um once you're notified
about an interview invite. So, the
interviews from a timing standpoint, I'm
going to share with you just what
everything looks like. Important dates.
Again, can't mention this enough, but
January 3rd is the deadline. make sure
everything is in by then, including the
letters of recommendation. Um, late
January to Febru February is when we
conduct interviews. So, it all happens
in a very um what I'd call condensed
time frame and they are all virtual um
on Zoom. And then we will let you know
our decision on the 7th of March and
then you will have until the 15th of
April um to let us know if you're
planning to enroll. And again, um it's
important that you apply in the year
that you intend to enroll. So we have
one intake cycle January 3rd, which
means that you're applying now in
January because you intend to enroll
when we start the program in July of
2025.
Okay. So with that I am going to stop
sharing and look to my colleagues to let
me know in the time that we have left if
there are any questions that um would be
great for the general population that we
should answer live.
I'm going to just scroll through some of
these too.
Everything's been answered. You guys are
great. You've been
Hi Diane. Um I do always I know we
always get this question, but uh we have
some questions about the West and if
people should use that to translate
their transcript or if there's any
preference and and how the process goes.
Yep. Yeah. No, we um absolutely have no
preference. Um Wes is fine. Uh as I said
though, you make sure you include both
the the transcripts in the original
language as well as the translated
version. Um some universities actually
provide that as a service to their um
graduates. So you might want to check
with your own school to see if that's
something they'll do for you. Um but
absolutely no preference.
And on that note, should people um
convert their GPA or give it as is in
the application?
Yeah. No. Um it's a great question. So
no, you do not absolutely do not need to
convert your GPA. We have systems in
place for being able to do that. As you
might imagine, we get um applicants who
have graduated from universities all
around the globe, many different um uh
grading scales. Um so you absolutely do
not need to do that.
Great. And I know um you all went over
this very well, but um we've had a
couple of questions around any tips to
make folks stand out in their essay of
what they should include.
No, it's a great question. So, um, I,
you know, look, we want this to be about
you. This is your story. And so, what
we're looking for is authenticity. We're
looking for you to be genuine. Um,
there's a lot out there to tell you what
you're supposed to be doing when you
apply to schools and how you should be
answering, but you really want to just
tell your story. And keep in mind, you
know, you're applying for a master of
finance program, a highly specialized,
deeply rigorous program that's going to
set you up to launch a career, whether
it's in quantitative finance, financial
engineering, we're investment banking.
So, you want to make sure that you know
anything we need to know about what you
have done thus far that's going to
contribute and going to help us to
understand um everything about why you
are pursuing this master's degree is
really important. So, answer the
question. um is the best answer I can
give you. Make sure you're answering the
question that we we set up. Um but be
yourself. Be genuine. It comes through.
We know we're admissions professionals.
We, you know, we we understand when it's
really everything has to sort of connect
in terms of what your recommenders are
saying about you, what you're saying
about yourself, and how we're looking at
um all the materials and information you
provide us.
Thank you. Yeah.
Um Ally, this may be a good question for
you. So, it's about the relevant
coursework and professional
certifications piece of the application.
I I've seen a few questions asking, you
know, should they list it out as a truly
a list? Should they have a portfolio?
Should they share certifications? Do
they put that they've been on the deans
list? What what all are we looking for
in this section?
Yeah. So, there is a specific relevant
coursework section and that's kind of
the only place that we would ask that
you would list that. So, you'll be
asked, you know, do you have, you know,
a course taken in this subject? If yes,
please insert all the information about
that. So, that should certainly go
there. Um, you can also acknowledge if
you are, you know, on the dean's um
honor list or or, you know, whatever the
equipment will be at your institution,
that can also be listed on your resume
under your education section. So, that
can be included there. Um, there also is
a specific area for academic awards and
achievements. Um, I believe you can list
up to three. Um, so feel free to include
those there as well. There's a lot of
different spaces on the application and
I would encourage you to you know use
them all as best as you can um to take
advantage of all the space that we
offer. So um you know if there is an
academic award that you were able to
list um in the specific section then
that can be maybe not on your resume to
make room for something else. So um you
know just be intentional about what
you're putting where and I'm sure
there's plenty of room to get um in all
the incredible things that you've done.
Um, but yeah, I would just encourage you
to put it in the section that
specifically asking for it if you can.
Um, and if not, then hopefully there's
room on your resume as well.
Thank you. Um, we've gotten a couple of
questions, too, or Diane, if you saw one
you wanted to highlight.
Yeah, I was just going to actually No,
thank you, Katherine. This is great. So
I think um one question that I noted um
a couple questions actually one on um
the test scores which again are optional
um but certainly if you feel like it's
important to uh include it you
absolutely can do that and whether
there's a preference between the GRE or
the GMAT and the fact that we do list
the GRE it just happens to be that what
we have discovered um in the past you
know or more recent years is that the
most of MIN applicants actually submit
and seem to be gravitating ating towards
the GRE. And so it's just by mere fact
of the statistically the numbers are
really small for individuals who do
submit test scores and have taken the
GMAT. But we have no preference. So you
absolutely could submit either one. And
then I think there was one more that I
saw about part-time teaching
assistantships considered work
experience. Um, it really I mean it's
great if you have that experience, but
it's really not part-time again is not
necessarily something that we that you
would want to put in the employment
section. So, I would say for a teaching
assistantship um on your resume is is
probably the best place to put it.
Okay. Sorry, Katherine. Go ahead. Was
there another one?
Great.
Yeah. I I see a couple questions around
any tips and advice for relicants.
Yeah. No, great question. So, um
certainly, you know, one of the things
that we want to know about is what have
you been doing in the past year since
you last applied. Um you know, maybe
you've taken additional coursework. Um
I'm making it up now. Perhaps your um
coursework didn't include as many of the
relevant ones that we talk about or um
ask about in the application and you've
done something towards that um effort or
initiative. Um or perhaps you didn't
have any finance related coursework or
internships and you've been able to do
that either a summer or some other type
of work. Maybe you've even done research
with um within the field of finance. So
we're looking at what have you done in
the past year to further support your
background um and experiences that's
going to help you again to really thrive
in the Minim program. And if I can add
on to that also, Diane, um just noting
that the admissions committee will also
be able to see your prior application
too. So um you know when answering the
professional questions, let's say you
don't need to repeat exactly what you
said last time, even if your goals are
relatively the same. Try to share new
information because they will also be
looking at your past application. So you
kind of have double the space. Um so
just try to um share anything new or um
you know what's changed like they said.
Yeah. Yeah. Great.
We definitely probably take one or two.
Oh, sorry, Catherine. Go ahead.
No, yeah, yeah, we've definitely
answered a lot of questions. I'm just
scrolling through.
I do want to note we've had a few
questions about submitting some
components of the application after the
deadline, perhaps a letter of
recommendation or test score. Um, we
really would love for you to try to get
everything submitted um by the the
deadline date of January 3rd. um we
start reviewing the applications the day
after on January 4 and it's on a rolling
basis. So if we read your application
and completed it and pushed it on down
um we may not be able to you know go
back and review and add that
information. So uh as best as you can
and please try to have it um submit it
by January 3rd.
Yep. Great.
And this may be jumping ahead a bit. Um,
unless there's another question that we
see some, uh, people are asking about
the math evaluation test and tips for
the interview.
Yeah. So, well, again, once we establish
what those are going to be, I mean,
there'll be a little bit of math,
there'll be a little bit of coding, um,
but, you know, again, we'll confirm all
that once the interview invite um, is
extended. So, um, nothing to be overly
concerned about at this point. So,