And without further ado, uh Demetus uh
is going to Demetrius Betsimus who is um
among many things he's the vice
president of open learning but I think
uh here he's the associate dean of
business analytics and Boeing professor
of operations research. Demetrius take
it away. Thank
[Applause]
you. Uh good morning. I'm here as a
professor not the other titles which is
in fact u you think about it the most uh
important aspect of um my experience
here at the MIT. So I'm talking about
creating fair and efficient transplant
allocation policies.
Um this is uh work jointly with my
colleague uh
Nikoshakees, our doctoral students Eli
and Mora, our uh postoc Tommy and
recently graduated uh Angelos and our
master student Jaun. So uh just as a
historical note um Nikos and I have been
working in transplantation areas for
about 15 years.
um although the focus uh today what I'm
about to present is work that we have
very much completed in the last year
after the circ
uh who here knows much about
transportation raise your hand not so
much I thought so so uh let me give you
some some perspective transplantations
in the United States last year we had
about 50,000 transplants about 27,000 or
so were kidney
transplantations. Uh these are people
who die and donate their organs. There
are also live transplantations but this
is less far less common. More than
95% are um are from somebody who donated
the organ um when the person died. You
see 11,000 livers and so forth between
uh kidneys, livers and hearts. This is
the lungs. This is the majority. There
are some others as well. So
um clearly in many organs uh this is a
matter of life and death. If somebody
for example does not have needs
transplantation on the
liver, you either get a get a liver or
or unfortunately you you die waiting. So
I'd like to give you some background of
the of the process. Um so imagine uh
Jane Jane is 34 years old and has an
autoimmune
disease. Uh the disease recently damaged
her kidneys leaving her dependent on
dialysis
uh so the the the blood can be cleared.
Typically this is a three times a week
endeavor and in need of a transplant.
to receive a transplant she must enroll
on the national waiting list along with
thousand other
patients. So now this is a list and uh
when a kidney is offered meaning that
somebody has died and the kidney is
donated. Uh so according to some
criteria that we will discuss uh a list
is formed a queue is formed and Jane
enters that queue based on her
characteristics.
uh it's not a typical line in in the
sense that a new kidney changes the
priorities because the biological
matches are not the same from kidney to
kidney. So as a result uh when a kidney
is donated all compatible patients are
prioritized according to a policy a
national policy. So it acts more like a
pool.
Uh so
so now the kidney is so there is an
ordering developed by national policy.
We'll discuss about these matters. And
then the kidney that is offered is
offered first to the first the first
person waiting in that list. The person
has an hour to accept or reject. If the
person does not accept because he
doesn't think that the quality of the
organ is appropriate or for other
reasons, it goes the offer goes to the
second person and at some point the
order the the kidney is given to a third
person. Jane didn't get it this time. So
it re-enters the the the list and so and
so it goes. Okay. So just to give you a
sense uh there were about
27,000 last year successful
transplantations. The waiting list was
about a 100,000. So it's the average
waiting list can be in people can be in
the waiting list for five years. It's
not
uncommon. So
uh so what is the key concept? The key
concept is that of an organ allocation
policy. So this uh policy determines the
priority of an organ
transplant. It critically drives
aggregate clinical benefit of
transplantation and also shapes how
benefits are distributed across the
population. What is the significance of
that? By altering who is likely to
receive a transplant, policies might
affect reducing the weightless
mortality. what is the principle
um so and I'll see you a concrete
example based on some of our earlier
work that changing policies might
actually affect how many people live and
and die
uh or it could be affect how fairly you
distribute transplants across the nation
for
example here's a a simple example should
distance play a role in that if you have
a kidney
that uh needs to let's say travel 200
miles or 3,000 miles, does it matter?
And how does it matter? And also it
might increase the policy on the number
of usable organs. Why is this so?
Because as you start offering offering
the kidney
um I mean they they have a useful life
about 24 hours. If the kidney is not
donated within 24 hours, then it might
not be um viable anymore and is
discarded. So if you have a policy that
you have very few discarded organs, this
might actually affect lives in the
future.
So clearly you you observe that policies
might have
uh implications on life and death
ethical aspects. Who should have
priority sometimes who should have
priority affects who like who lives and
who dies. It's not a a nice to have is a
is an important aspect. Just to give you
an example from some of our earlier
works, Nicholas and I and our former
student Ted. Um so this was the this is
time and this is the count of
um weight list removals
uh that are too sick to transplant or
death let's say decreased small numbers
is a good thing it meaning that more you
know less people die in a way so we have
worked some of the tools we use we use
in this presentation were used for this
is for lung transplants
It's about 3,500 a year. So the land
policy based on some of our work was
started in 2000 March
2023 and you so it has been going on for
two years and you observe that this new
policy decreased very unfortunate
outcomes death from around 300 to
about60 or so. So just to demonstrate
that these are not innocent aspects.
Okay. So, uh a 38 um decrease reduction
and this and and lung is about maybe 9%
of the total transplantations in the
country. So, how is a national policy
created? So national committees made up
of doctors, patients, ethicists and so
forth develop policies and these are
dedicated people with uh a committee
involves you know multiple times
Nicholas and I have presented in this
committee of the order of maybe 20
people. There are six such national
committees. There's a committee on
kidneys which is uh as as you have seen
the majority of the transplantations, a
heart committee, a lung committee and
more ethics committee that talks about
uh general principles and tradeoffs, a
multi-organ committee and a liver and
intestinal committee. Each committee is
separate. It is supported by u several
uh entities that hersa the health um
department in the United States has
formed that have certain roles. UNOS
which is the u a very important
committee and very incorporate unit that
um in many ways implement the national
policy. This national policies develop
guidelines. UNOS
implements uh and then there is another
important entity SRTR which uh does the
analysis of these uh of these aspects
you you will say you will see today now
what is the vision of what we try to do
I gave you this was a preliminary to
give you a little bit of a sense what
transplantation is and some of the
issues that arise so we have the
following objectives in this work as you
will see these objectives are not minor
in my unbiased opinion
So we would like to decrease the time to
design and evaluate organ allocation
policies from years of what it is today
and I'll tell you more detail two
seconds. In other words, we would like
to build a system that once
completed, people in the committee while
the committee is happening can use the
system and and when they propose
policies
uh they can figure out the effects
without having to wait months and years
for the results to come back which is a
current
situation to allow the
committees UNOS
Congress and the public to evaluate
these policies and understand
trade-offs. So currently that's not
true. That is all this knowledge
um is within the committees and so
forth. But you know let's say for
example uh the public wants to
understand the effect that's not
feasible. Very importantly would like to
decrease weightless mortality. I saw you
before an example of such a policy would
like to unify the design of policies for
all organs simultaneously.
Currently, one committee meets about
kidneys, another committee meets with
completely different on on livers and so
forth. There's no unifying theme. So
even the ethical aspects of what we are
doing is
uh is not by the same people in other
words. And finally would like to enable
the ability to design and evaluate
multiorgans to today it's completely you
know when somebody passes uh there are
multiple organs that can be
donated but currently if somebody needs
a lung and a heart for example how do
you evaluate this relative to a lung
alone a heart alone two people will be
the recipient but one per so this is
there are serious just ethical issues as
well as efficiency issues. A very
important component of this is the
simulation of the transplant um system
because if you want to do something from
months to seconds, it has to run very
effectively and and and this is not a
trivial matter. The reason it's not a
trivial matter because when you see a
simulation, you know historical data.
When this historical data is available,
you have you have to say if the the
policy changes different orderings will
happen and you need to understand what
you know is what had happened what you
need to find out what would have
happened for a new policy. So there is a
so-called notion of counterfactuals and
estimating and so forth. you know we
won't uh I won't bother you with all the
details but this is not a this is not a
trivial story as indicated the fact that
SRTR which which uh simulates
um it's takes typically six months to
complete an investigation of five to 10
policies so in other words the story is
as follows the committee meets five to
10 minutes five 10 policies are
contemplating they are simulated by SRTR
after six months
you get some
results. Quite often new analysis is
initiated, new another six months. Often
changing a policy is a long long
multi-year process. That's the current
story. That's the current story. So of
course they have limited policy may have
limited information takes about six
months and only few policies are being
evaluated and definitely definitely not
online. So of course
um there's the idea is to simulate more
policies to also trying to explore
uh far more than that and much more much
faster. So what we've done is we
developed a novel algorithm for
simulation. This is about a thousand
times faster than the existing. It goes
from six hours to 14 seconds. 14 seconds
is online. If you have a
simulation, if you you can while the
committee is meeting, it can run if you
have an appropriate way of um of
evaluating. So, and it also allows not
one policy, thousands of them. So, if
they have various ideas, uh this is
where AI can help. Um this is not just
because hardware is faster. You have to
to organize it in a way that is uh far
more intelligent and then we have we
have generalized my time is closer but
but we also have a way of designing
policies and I will do it in this way.
So here are some things we'd like to
minimize weight lift mortality. We have
to have uh many transplants. We have to
have pediatric access. you'd like to
reduce geographic disparity to reduce
blood type disparity and so forth. The
way we do it, our simulation keeps track
of all these measures by thousands and
thousands of policies and by having
weights you can optimize this using
optimization to be able to uh to
optimize that. So it's a this is a
system that
optimizes the simulates optimizes and
because we have already pre-calculated
thousands upon thousands of policies the
optimization is much simpler to to build
this offline it might take a long time
but online is seconds and the way to
support all this uh is a website which
uh by the end of the month will become
available to the nation.
and the committees that basically allows
all these calculations in a in a way
that makes trade-offs and so forth
um and
gives you know various metrics for which
ethical questions can be addressed. For
example, um the question I was asking
you the tradeoff between if you allow
transplantations for longer longer
distances maybe the weightlift mortality
will go down
um on the other hand the discard might
be possibly higher because they have to
travel. So how do you optimize all these
things and this is because one you have
the metrics then you can possibly
optimize that. So this is uh James
Alorn. It's a short video. I don't know.
I hope it would work sometimes.
One of our key partners in this has been
MIT or the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology. And what MIT has brought to
the table is they have brought their
expertise in mathematical optimization
to the table. MIT is able to radically
change the turnaround time for
evaluating these different simulations
of policy scenarios. What would normally
take a couple months to look at a
handful of different policy scenarios,
MIT is able to let us look at thousands
upon thousands of different policy
scenarios in a matter of minutes. And so
we are able to make these changes much
more rapidly, which ultimately means
that we're able to improve the system
for transplant candidates much more
rapidly. One of our key partners in this
has been MIT.
To conclude, we have completed this uh
aspect of the design to to being able to
evaluate tens of thousands of of
policies. We build this website which we
plan to make available in the end of the
month uh for kidneys and in the end of
the summer for all organs. Uh we I gave
you an example of weight list mortality.
We have completed and implemented this
in the nation not uh for writing papers
um for lungs and we are in process
because we are in dialogue for all the
committees. We're optimistic that this
will also go on for for the other
organs. Uh we are in progress of
designing these policies simultaneously.
In other words, the website you click
the organ and then all of the analysis
is unified. And finally, uh we have
started more will start working on it on
how to evaluate given you have all these
data. How do we evaluate and make
ethical uh decisions between uh
multiorgan transplantations? Thank
you. Um awesome. Uh thank you so much
Demetrius. So we're going to take
questions quick. A couple of ground
rules. We'll get two mics going. Nikos,
is it gonna be you or Angela? Uh,
perfect. Okay, so I'll maybe start with
this side of the room and what we'll do,
we'll have a quick ground rules. Um, I'm
afraid it's going to be no follow-ups.
It's gonna be a single question and then
yeah, we'll try to get through and I'll
try to answer them quickly, please.
Yeah. Uh, questions. Questions for
Demetrius.
There was a question. Yes, we'll start
off and Angela, could you get somebody
on deck for the moment?
Uh, thanks very interesting talk. Uh I'm
wondering if your simulations have
revealed some new interesting trade-offs
which were previously unknown. There are
many but to be able to
answer there are many in fact the
discussions in the ethical in the ethics
committee discuss exactly that and the
beauty of this is because the you have
all these data in front of you uh it it
generates new ideas. You say for example
let's say the pediatric use is lower.
What would have happened? Can we do
something else? Of course there's no
free lunch. You cannot do anything that
fulfills every single obligation, every
single thing that you try. But people
now have a system that online they can
make these decisions. I'll be glad to
point you to some papers where all these
discussions otherwise will take us all
the time. The lady here. Yeah, I was
curious. Um, obviously with simulations,
one of the challenges is the data you
put into them and the assumptions about
the equations that you're using. So I'm
just curious how you got the committees
to buy into that or or how that process
worked.
uh years of effort. Uh but uh this is
the data that the nation has. This is
UNOS data. This is every single thing
that has happened. We also simulate it.
You can simulate and then see the effect
on things that you do know. We obviously
we increase credibility on that. I mean
as you know you build credibility with a
lot of evidence and so forth. I told you
15 years we have some credibility on
that. uh and good results. Um that I
mean I I saw you when you have a policy
that we predicted the the the mortality
would would drop 200 deaths and it
happened. Well, that's pretty credible.
No.
Oh, okay. I have one question. Where are
you? Oh, okay. Yeah. I have a curious
one thing now. In my country, I am from
Mongolia. In my country, we have a very
country Mongolia.
We have a very big uh scandal in my
country currently because one doctor is
the president due to the harvesting the
many argans from the person who is the
donated and then how it will be
regulated by if it's involved in so many
stakeholders for example doctors and
other uh some how it is this is a highly
regulated story that has the attention
in the high echelons of the government.
So the the committees design a
policy these policies as implemented in
UNOS. UNOS is the the regulator in a way
the the one that
uh obviously I do not know what happens
in every single country in the world but
in the United States
uh I have not people disagree
scandals I have not heard. Okay thank
you. So therefore I do not know what
happens in other countries.
Other questions? Yes sir. Yes. Um uh my
understanding is that you have a large
amount of um uh policies you're looking
at and and you make that simulation or
decision based on the smaller amount of
criteria criteria such such as like the
uh reduce the mortality of the travel.
Yeah. You have that that list and what
if the the priority of the requirement
the criteria changes and that would
change a lot right? So that the whole
thing simulation will change. U my my
question is that uh when that happens
are somebody uh adding some other
criteria and and how would that thing
change everything and would that be
still like ethical? The what we have
found that this has been going on for
some time. We know the criteria. There
are about 20 of them. Right? Now on
these 20 criteria, we have mapped
thousands upon thousands of policies to
this criteria. Right? So then we try to
optimize according to this criteria. We
have some weights. They can change. Let
us empa build a policy that emphasizes
uh weightless mortality. This is much
higher weight than before. We can we can
do that. On the other hand, if on if at
that point they design a 21st criterion
that it was never before, we have to go
to the drawing board, we cannot, you
know, we do many things. Coffee we don't
make. So I mean you realize this is uh
if if it is within what has been uh
analyzed in the past and it's it has
been my experience that is always like
that to find a a brand new criterion
that nobody has ever thought about. I
have never seen it. So
You see what I'm I'm saying? Other
question? Yes.
Um my question is um your criterias are
fact or subjective. Um like weight list
mortality is a factual how many people
died? Um no what is the average waiting
time? You said there are at least 10 to
20 criterias apply for the each
candidate. So I don't believe all for
those candidate. No, no, no, no, no.
These criteria are for the policy. For
example, if I change the ordering Mhm.
there are 35 more deaths, but the the
the but people have to travel 21 more
miles and the number of pediatric
transplants goes down. This is not only
the patient. This is you know as you
change the national policy you affect
the the aggregate behavior of the
system.
But on the slide you show it some
criterias like most of them ob for me
it's a fact like the blood group you
cannot change the patients this
is how the weight list for example uh
how long have you been waiting for a
kidney transplantation matters in your
ordering the the sensitization of the
characteristics of the organ and
characterics of the patient also also
matter. So there are criteria of how to
order and with what significance but but
how the national policy is thinking
is what is the effect if you change
something to the overall national
effect. I hope I hope I'm making myself
clear. Not really. Thank you. Well, but
your question is also not as clear as
well. I'm sorry you say so. Okay. Thank
you. Are we having a sense? I'm just
going to close out. This will be the
final question. Are we have a sense of a
sense of what policies are winning out
when um when people are able to identify
precisely what their priorities are and
then simulate the effects of these these
we have look the class of policy we are
consider continuous distribution
policies. There has been a lot of debate
for decades of what is the class and so
forth. the the nation has converged on a
particular way with um what's called
continuous distributions with a
geographical aspects and so forth.
There's no time to explain but within
this class which is a broad class this
is where we optimize this is where we op
and and I think there is significant
convergence that this is the class now
the specific parameters you know that's
another story but that's what the where
the nation has converged. Awesome. Well,
thank you so much, Demetrius.