Our
next speaker is uh Kevin Bradshaw. He is
senior vice pres president of data
center strategy at FM which is an
insurance company that is an ILP member
and I work with FM actually had the
original idea to put on a workshop
dealing with data centers because it's a
obviously with Kevin it's someplace they
focus on and uh it was supposed to be
one company and then it turned into a
much bigger thing. So thank you Kevin
for giving me something to do all
summer.
>> No problem.
>> So let's hear it for Kevin Brad.
>> Yeah. Thanks.
So, I'm uh Kevin Bradshaw. Um and I work
for FM. And a lot of people probably
wondering who's FM? What's FM? So, FM is
a commercial property insurance company.
Uh we we don't insure cars. We don't
insure liability or personal. It's only
commercial property. Primarily focused
on the bigger industries. Uh we ensure a
lot of uh paper companies and and power
generation companies, tons of
manufacturing companies, uh lots of
mining, lots of real estate, and yes, we
do insure MIT. That's one of our clients
also. So we just ensure the the
commercial property and uh we provide
services for it, which I'll get into in
just a minute.
Um,
so you're probably sitting here
wondering, well, before I go there, I
just tell you on from a market size,
we're a little over10 billion a year in
annual premium
and we have um the u about 40% share of
the US market. We're the largest in the
in in the US and uh and then worldwide.
We're also extremely large uh company
for commercial property insurance.
So, you might be wondering, well, why
what in the wide world of sports is an
insurance guy after that as that
presentation? What's what is an
insurance guy doing up here talking
about data centers? Well, I got some
good news. I'm towards the end of the
agenda and the day is almost over
and I'm going to even better news is I'm
going to do this in 15 minutes. I've
already taken a couple. All right. So,
I'm going to leave you with three
impressions related to insurance of
these physical assets that are being
built out there.
And um I mean, you've probably been
reading the press. I mean, I just the
last one I just saw as they're
estimating by the end of the decade over
7 trillion dollar of investment into
building out of data centers around the
globe.
So, there's a ton of money pouring in.
There's a lot of l new construction
going on and these things are getting
bigger and bigger and bigger.
So the first impression I I want to give
you from an insurance, a property
insurance
is you can have losses, you can have
fires,
you can have equipment breakdowns,
um, and you can have big storms come
through, you can have earthquakes,
wildfire, and all this. And guess where
they're building a lot of data centers
in a lot of those areas. Okay? So they
obviously they need insurance.
So when it comes to losses um if you
only go back because this is a really
young industry to be relatively okay you
go back you know last 20 25 years and we
have about 50 clients right now 50 data
center companies um and we have uh um
you know several thousand locations that
we insure. Um, but they're not that old
and it's the good news is they've
they've built them to modern
construction techniques, modern and
they've got really nice clean
facilities. Um, they put good fire
protection in. They put gaseous systems
underneath the subfloors. They put all
kinds of protection in. So, they know
what they're doing when they build these
facilities, which has led to pretty
benign loss history. Haven't seen a lot
of losses. Not a lot of really not a lot
of big fires, a lot of big equipment
breakdowns. You're not seeing that. And
you know, we haven't seen a lot of
NATCAT, you know, the wildfires and
winds, none. They haven't really taken
out much data center. So, the loss
history
is uh is pretty good in this industry.
And it's because I think that these
things are built pretty resilient to
begin with.
But there's always a butt.
But we did have a big loss this year. We
had some um lithium ion batteries and a
an exterior battery banks or whatever
caught on fire and the loss is well over
hund00 million.
So these big fires can happen. So if you
start marrying up how many new data
centers are being built, where they're
building them, even though we've got
good not much frequency in loss, and
we've finally had a severe loss, what do
you think insurance companies are
predicting for the future when it comes
to losses?
Then we're going to be paying clients a
lot of money if we start having losses
in this industry.
So, I want to leave you on that
impression is is right now, keep
building them safe. Keep building with
all the protection, good construction,
be mindful of where that where you're
putting it, and you can get away pretty
good without having huge huge insurance
premiums, and you can have your your
property insured.
Which brings us to the next impression I
want to leave with you.
And that is the in my 39 plus year
career,
the the biggest challenge I've seen the
insurance industry ever have is going on
right now. And that's the ability to put
enough capacity
on a program to be able to actually
ensure the exposed risk for these
companies that are owning and operating
these equipments.
I'll tell you a little story.
6 months ago when I was working on this
strategy and um a typical company like
ours will put on a on a contract policy
will have a billion dollars of capacity.
Your limit of liability for the policy
for a fire, an explosion, billion
dollars pretty much covers any single
location having a bad loss. You know,
you got enough insurance to cover the
whole loss. Okay? You're not left bare
when the insurance company finishes
paying.
So, a billion dollars, maybe a billion
and a half. Some companies maybe a
little bit more than that, up to$2
billion. That was pretty much the
industry standard.
And then two months ago, I was giving an
update to our executives
and one of the things they wanted me to
do is what are some of the biggest
challenges you're having as you stare
into the future for ensuring these data
centers and all this construction going
on?
And I put on the board, I said, 'Well,
we're starting to get requests for 5
billion in in capacity.
And um
that is hard to put together right now.
Near impossible.
You can't get enough insurance companies
and reinsurance companies who are
reinsuring the insurance companies. You
can't get enough capacity built in the
entire insurance market to be able to
put $5 billion of limited liability on a
policy. Okay.
Now, two weeks on or well two months on
today, we're getting requests for 10,
15, and $25 billion in capacity.
And folks, it's not out there. There's
no way you can put it together. So, the
CEOs of all the insurance companies and
the reinsurance companies and the
private equity uh groups and the brokers
are all getting together trying to
figure out what kind of solution
without god forbid asking the government
to pitch in would you have if you had
really catastrophic losses.
Now, the reason you want this capacity
I'll give you an example of a location
million square feet. Now, that's a big
building, right? one story big million
square feet that's a big building you
can shove about 300 to 400,000 GPUs and
about 10 12 15 20 halls into a million
square foot building
but think about it it's one building one
exposure
if you had a fire run away and ran out
of water you could spread it from hall
to hall to hall you could actually do
that and that's how insurance companies
view the maximum foreseeable loss
so this particular facility has about
$20 billion worth of value in just the
GPUs. Not counting the building, not
counting the infrastructure, the
cooling, not counting the the the the
gas turbine sitting outside, none of
that. So the overall site is 30 $40
billion
and that's a million square feet.
But if you've seen some of these other
projects like Fermy south of Amarillo,
they're going to invest $250 billion
into a single campus full of this stuff.
So the biggest challenge in the
insurance industry is coming up with a
solution.
Okay? And I and I don't I don't know
what it's going to be, but so so what do
you do about it? Well,
you know, the big companies, the big
alphabetic companies and the and the
developers and the architects and all
them, they need to start, you know,
thinking about how do you
compartmentalize a campus?
How do you build more buildings? And I
know nobody wants to hear we got to
build more buildings. We'd rather just
put it in a big building because that's
more expensive.
But what are you going to do if you
can't insure it and you have no
insurance? You're bare.
What happens is whoever's loaning you
the money to do it isn't going to give
you the loan.
So that's the dilemma that we're facing.
So insurance capacity is the impression.
Someone was telling me just a little
earlier that the limiting factor on data
centers is power. It might be insurance
before long.
>> And lastly, I think it's it's is to
build these facilities very very
resilient. I already said that they
build them pretty good now. They're
pretty well put together. They're clean.
They put protection. They don't fuss
about getting protection in there. Um,
but you got to but the the the industry
is evolving. And I'm sure all day long
you heard about what's coming next. What
what's what's the next thing in cooling?
What's the next thing in Well, every
time you introduce something new like
that, you're creating a new exposure
that our research people, we have a
couple reps from our research people.
What we do as our research group of
about over a hundred research scientists
is we look for loss prevention and we do
research to figure out what kind of
protection or what kind of construction
materials or what kind of things you
could do to make it resilience to loss
whether it's fire loss equipment
breakdown loss wind loss on the roof
whatever. So we're we got a lot of
research going on. Matter of fact, these
guys have 21 over 20 research projects
specifically for things that are going
into data centers right now that we're
working on. Now, how does that get to
you? Pretty simple. Once we do the
research, we give it to our engineering,
which is represented here, and they
develop guidelines and data sheets and
standards on how best to protect it,
which materials not to use, which
materials to use, and then how to
protect it.
And if you go on uh correct me if I'm
wrong, but if you go on fm.com,
those data sheets are available to
everybody. We don't keep those
confidential. We share them with the
world. We got data sheets on um data
centers, on turbine generators, gas
turbines, roof systems,
fire protection, gashes, fire protection
systems,
um gas detection, you know, those
things. So we got full of data sheets.
But with what's changing in this
industry so fast, we have to have the
research because we got to keep evolving
the protection guidelines for that.
Once we have the standards and we put
together our procedures, we have a over
a thousand engineers who go out in the
field and help clients uh understand the
hazards they have uh give them
recommendations, challenge them. And we
got a lot of people now starting to work
on construction projects trying to get
in early to make sure the developers and
the designers and the builders are
putting in the right protection, using
the right materials, using the right
equipment to make sure it's well
protected.
So with that, I got those three
impressions.
Losses aren't happening. Haven't been
happening, but they're going to happen.
Second impression is we're running out
of insurance capacity. And the third one
is build it right. Build build it
resilient to loss.