Hello everyone. I'm Jeff Felgo,
co-founder and CEO of Get
Intro. And if any of you like myself
have um ever done any sort of um
business sale or partnership deal, um
you know that having a personal
relationship makes everything easier.
Um, we're building on that truism to
create valuable business connections
through warm
introductions. The problem that we're
solving is that for sales teams, the the
vast majority of leads that sales teams
work on uh are never going to go
anywhere. They um they just don't close.
Why is that? Well, sales teams are using
tools like LinkedIn um to do
prospecting. They may be enriching leads
with tools like Apollo and and others
and and they may just be um searching
around the web looking for signals to
try and figure out um who might be a
valuable prospect for their company.
What does that result in? It results in
a huge top off of funnel, lots and lots
of leads that are just not going to
close. And those leads get worked for a
very long period of time. Um, in
verticals like healthcare, the average
sales cycle of selling technology into a
healthcare organization is up to 19
months. So imagine sales teams spending
all this effort on leads that just
aren't going to close for months and
months. The end result, unfortunately,
is low conversion rates and we have um,
as I said, long sales cycles, massive
effort by sales teams and um, the
results just don't show. There is a
better way. Um, we believe that having
an AI agent that introduces sellers to
prospects who are both receptive and
reachable is the right solution. So
imagine a top of funnel, a top of a
salesunnel that is much narrower, much
more focused with accounts that are
actually interested in the offering that
is being um being pitched with folks um
that are also going to be um ready to um
ready to receive the information that
you're um that you're sharing with them.
And it's not just about being receptive.
Are they actually reachable? So, are
there um are there connections into
these key decision makers and can those
folks actually be found both offline and
online? And then having all of this
information automated through an agentic
AI
process. Where things really get
interesting though is when you start
thinking about enriching the data with
vertical specific information. We are
focusing on the healthc care vertical
and we're building the world's best
healthcare enrichment data. This data um
is being structured based on the
conversations we've had with hundreds of
healthcare sales executives and the
types of things that they look at today
from um what is the tooling that is
being used today within these buying
organizations all the way down to things
like um where are people attending
certain conferences. This information
enriches the um data that is available
for the agent to be able to find those
right people who are
reachable. So how does this look today
in our application? Well, it's really
simple. You simply describe the types of
customers, partners, and um other folks
that you would like to reach in natural
language. The system searches out across
your network and your team's extended
network, finding those people who are
going to be interested in what you are
talking about. And not only interested,
they're reachable through somebody in
your extended
network. And then once um that pathway
has been selected, we go ahead and build
out the communication stream reaching
out, gathering um interest from that end
person and facilitating the
introduction. Let's look at a real
example. Today we're working with a
business-to business startup networking
hub in Boston called Venture Lane, which
has approximately 75
startups. 150 of those members on our
platform share a network of over
250,000 people. That's a network that's
reachable by any one person within the
community through our platform. What
does that equal in terms of actual
introductions? Around 500 introductions
per month. All of this is extremely
valuable to a young startup company
that's trying to reach the right
customers. One of the business founders
um just told me the other day that 75%
of his current business comes through
warm introductions and he's doing this
in a very manual process today. He is so
excited to be on our platform because we
are automating a process that he knows
delivers business results
today. So what are we looking for? Um,
we're looking for partners who share our
vision that these types of relationships
drive business results. If this sounds
interesting to you, please scan the QR
code and sign up for our weight list.
We're currently taking um companies who
are interested in um being early
customers on our platform. Specifically,
we're looking for customers um um that
are selling into the health care
vertical today um specifically into
provider organizations and who believe
in the value of relationshipbased
sales. An added bonus would be if you
have a sales team that has a strong um
point of view on the types of sales
signals that you find most valuable in
bringing um in those business sales. So,
thank you very much. we're in the other
room and have a a table. Please come um
come see me if you'd like to uh hear
more. Thanks very much. Thank you, Chef