and I'm very happy to kick it off with
what I think should be um a wonderful
panel I will turn it over to our
moderator Antonio Regalado from the MIT
technology review who covers the area of
biomedicine and he will introduce
today's panelists thank you Antonio
great uh thank you so much Rebecca I'm
glad to be here I do work at MIT
technology review some of you might be
surprised to know that this ecosystem is
big enough that it has its own
journalists um and not just me there's a
whole bunch of stat news Etc and so I
just want to relay an anecdote before I
introduce our wonderful panel is that uh
well actually bill here in the middle
asked me you know what kind of stuff do
you cover I said biotech uh um crisper
gene therapy that kind of thing um but I
realized you know what I really am an
ecosystem 30 years ago in 1995 I applied
for a job and I included a vend diagram
you know University industry capital I
actually put this in there as my huge
Insight when I was 25 I was like this
place is not just an idea it actually
exists and I'm going to go work there um
and so it's funny to think that my
career has uh actually started with such
a vend diagram our panelists are three
people who manage the inside of that
space right the
collaborations uh and the Strategic
Partnerships and they are from uh left
to right SEMA Basu uh head of strategic
Partnerships at Mass General Brigham uh
Bill kubasek who is a director of uh
strategic Partnerships at the broad
Institute uh right around the corner
here right down the street and Colin
staltz who is co-director of the Harvard
MIT Health Sciences program and MIT does
not have a medical school so you can bet
that he is also a professor in the eeks
Department electrical engineering and
computer science um so it's wonderful to
have you all here now even today as a
journalist when I write about the broad
Institute or someone who works at MGH it
can be hard even to write their titles
right they have so many titles and
affiliations um so we're going to be
able to sort some of that out learn a
little bit who's who about these
complicated and overlapping institution
so uh SEMA could you uh introduce your
institution and give us a picture of the
kind of things that you work on yes
happy to it's a pleasure to be here
thank you to you and backa for inviting
us um so my name is Sima Basu and like
he referred to I have two titles
strategic Innovation leader and head of
strategic Partnerships they actually
have some meaning in organization so
I'll take a step back and first tell you
for those who don't know what masteral
bream is and that will help so masteral
bream is an integrated academic Health
Care system and it has five Howard
Affiliated hospitals two general and
three specialty the two general aass
General and bream and Women's Hospital
and when I say we're an integrated
academic Medical Center that means we
have a fullart mission you know one is
uh Health Care delivery patient care and
related to it Community we care about
Equity equity and Health Care access and
then there is education because we're
affiliated with Harvard we have about
4,000 trainees that go through our
system on an annual basis whether
they're phds MDS MD phds and then we
have research and we call that pillar
not just research it's research and
Innovation because that is in our DNA to
not only just do research to build for
the future but also to innovate along
the way and so my title is strategic
Innovation leader because we're trying
to look internally always to see how
might we organize ourselves better right
for that mission and then head of
strategic Partnerships because I'm
trying to little part of my career I
spent at a Pharma company so I do have
you know the little bit of experience
having seen it from the other side and
I've been at Mass J Brigham 22 years now
almost so I can actually help bridge
some of those and know what how we can
structure for success with our industry
Partners as a win-win and so we have a
small Alliance team that is a Continuum
of trying to bring from what's
strategically important for us where do
we have a strengths how do we Bridge how
do we Bridge with our academic uh
partner uh research with industry
Partners in so many different ways
because as an academic institution we
have clinical insights based on which we
do research we do clinical trials
translational research but we in that
entire cycle need industry partners
because we're never going to make the
product the device the drug but if I
want to impact patient care I do need a
partner who can help us along the way
I'll stop there terrific uh Bill let's
hear from you I just want to uh it's
great to hear learn about the
institution you told me earlier that the
broad has does have a budget of $700
million a year 2,000 employees and later
on today I'm going to go check is is
that like the largest scientific
nonprofit in the world uh in this city
or or what we don't we don't know but
I'm going to try and figure it out later
on so well let me know what you L learn
I will okay um yeah the broad Institute
is actually a lot larger than most
people think and actually is the broad
Institute of MIT and Harvard so it's
really a combination of MIT Harvard and
all of the surrounding hospitals right
and you know uh believe it or not we're
actually going to be celebrating we're
celebrating our 20th year uh at this
point so it's been around for for quite
a while and actually the precursor of it
was even started at the whitee head even
before that focusing on the on the
genomics so you know the mission of the
bro is really to advance uh you know to
to get therapies to people to find
therapies to people and sort of the
Cornerstone of the broad and hence it's
uh sort of unique structure is all about
collaborations right the idea is is that
great science big advancements all come
through big collaborations big
collaborative efforts uh no barriers uh
things like that um and so for example
you know the building is designed to
Foster bumping into people right um even
that we don't have departments we don't
have a Department of Chemistry we don't
have a department of biochemistry and so
on and so forth um you know we have
programs we have a cancer program a
metab a metabolism program uh and
cardiovascular so we don't you know we
really try and pull down all sort of
these artificial barriers to Foster this
Innovation we you know we have big
collaborative consortiums with groups
all over the world um and also another
unique uh feature of the broad is is
that there are
2,000 uh full-time employees but there's
also about 4,000 members in the
community so we have different levels
many of them are at MGH for example or M
you know um in the surrounding hospitals
um we also have uh a lot of professional
scientists which adds a continuity
because we have a number of platforms
that really help enable advancing
discoveries uh identification of tarvi
development of Therapeutics you know we
have a metabol platform um we have a
proteomic platform we have the gene
pertubation platform we have the center
for development of Therapeutics which is
about 50 people that you know can
actually you know develop assays do drug
screening we have a number of compound
libraries do drug screening uh uh
chemical opt optimization and so we try
and you know pull all of this together
to really Advance um to advance
Therapeutics and then the sort of the
the critical thing here is this that we
have a number to do that we believe that
we have to partner with industry sort of
the vend diagram that you talked about
so we have collaborations with Deerfield
management which is uh a big investment
fir healthcare investment firm in New
York buyer Calico Labs Novo uh Novo no
disk Novo Foundation um and so we have a
number of different uh collaborations
where we work very closely and
collaboratively with them to advance
these things to get them closer to the
patients teric uh thank you Colin your
turn um tell us about the programs that
you run uh n MIT and what they're about
so I'm I'm I'm uh oh this is very loud
I'm I'm a boot on the ground and I think
while I can opine about the programs I
think there's another perspective here
that I think is um upo so I'm a
cardiologist at Mass General Hospital
and uh computer scientist in MIT and we
think very in a on a very granular level
about how we can take Technologies from
infancy to the patient and the steps
that are required therein and uh so some
of that involves fundamental science
that happens on MIT side some of that
involves clinical trials that happens on
the Mass General side and then lastly
bringing these things to fruition right
what what guides myself and the scholars
who I am privileged to Mentor is doing
things that will benefit patients at the
end of the day and how we can do that in
uh in an impactful Forum with with
respect to the uh HST program it is an
educational
program that combines uh both Harvard
and MIT we teach MD students and we
teach PhD students um who aspire to do
quantitative work at the intersection of
medicine and um Health Sciences our our
Scholars go on in a wide array of of
fields some of them in in the academy
many of them in Industry many of them in
startups so I can speak to either end of
that as you wish okay terrific I mean we
want to talk about Partnerships uh had a
partner with the ecosystem so I think uh
journalists like me were very example
driven so I'm definitely going to ask
for examples I think we just heard about
Deerfield that's an interesting one uh
there was a press release initially that
Deerfield um the initial value was $50
million it's been going on for a while I
understand that they get to uh pick and
choose different things that they work
on so what is actually how does that
collaboration work Bill what is the
outcome like what is the deliverable in
a sense uh of it right um well let me
just say on the outside each each
partner has a little bit different
objective of what they want out of these
collaborations of course they all want
to get to Therapeutics in the case of of
Deerfield I would say it's not so much
technology deriven it's more therapeutic
driven um is you know what what we're
looking for is they want to tap into
this great ecosystem uh that we have
that great expertise and work sort of
hand inand to you know take early stage
targets you know find you know validate
them develop all the tools and reagents
that you need to do drug Discovery as in
addition to further validation and then
the end goal is sort of to be able to
get them ready to go you know to be spun
into a company or to be licensed to
another company for the drug development
and you know if you think about if you
have a great thing in your lab and you
want to go to a VC they'll say oh you
know this is great but come back you
know you need more this sort of fills
that Gap it's already sort of a plug
andplay way to sort of fill that sort of
that bridge you know between the basic
you know Grant funded science and
getting it ready for a real drug
Discovery effort I would say uh Colin
let me just go to you and I get back to
you Sim to to Anchor this um at your at
MIT are you are you working in
Partnerships I mean you you're working
computer science AI but obviously all
this has to be deployed into medicine
which is kind of a different space so
what is what are what is the role of
Partnerships in your daily well I think
a seem as intimated these things don't
get to the people who really need them
without industrial support and buyin and
uh and collaboration and and there's a
long process and I think it's often
times not recognized the the
peculiarities with respect to
Technologies and Healthcare that have to
that have to be addressed to get it from
the conception of idea to the point at
which it gets deployed to um um a
patient and so we have had
collaborations we have an ongoing
collaboration for example with quantum
computers and that's something I can
talk about later on I think suppose that
that's that if there's interest in
developing technologies that help
patients with heart failure and it's an
interesting discussion about the idea
the fundamental research that happened
at MIT and then the clinical trials that
are ongoing at Mass General and then the
desire for Quant to roll out some of
this technology at least in in in Taiwan
what was imperative in that and is is
getting early buyin and early engagement
with potential industry partners and
that has worked that has worked uh and
that General approach how to do that is
something I don't know the answer to and
I think it's a caseby case sort of
discussion I'm sure somebody here
probably will tell will tell me the
answer get the solution I can take back
to the people who I collaborate with but
it's it's a longer discussion and I know
that SEMA is very very very very
familiar with terrific SEMA can you in
introduce us to one of the
collaborations that you manage and what
what what are
people what are the what are the
objectives of of the Barner okay so
maybe three-part one to Sure save you
time to look up if you maybe I should
have mentioned so we're the largest
employer in Commonwealth of
Massachusetts as Mass General Brigham
and out of that about I would say we
have over 7,000 clinicians and over 6
and a half thousand Howard appointed
research faculty right and that doesn't
even include faculty like him who are
actually MIT faculty that also have
appointments uh with us anyway so I just
wanted to say that with that U what Bill
said you know should resonate and all of
you should take away that each
partnership is a bit different you know
the biggest thing I tell our partners is
let's have a shared Vision that means
like what is it we're trying to achieve
what might be things it's a journey what
are you going to acheve achieve along
the way what's the long-term goal what
are short-term deliverables and each
we're very intentional because our needs
to partner with industry just like I
said in that cycle are in so many places
we're happy to find a partner that would
go the entire Continuum we're happy to
find partners that will just go one
segment with us right we're happy to
find Partners who work in three
indications with us we're happy to work
deep into one indication so we it is a
bit what each partner wants how are we
going to reach short so I really want to
leave everybody clearly with that
philosophy that we're very intentional
we're happy to take small sponsored
research programmatic approach but we do
encourage industry to think in terms of
themes and programs because it allows us
to be more meaningful and intentional in
how we bring our academic partners
because it's hard for them to do
something for three months four months
they really can't build on anything you
can't take people on and off NIH grants
you can't really h or somebody so the
more intentional you are in a little bit
longterm the better we can partner so
with that kind of contacts just to
Showcase we have many different
Partnerships my background because I
came from Pharma as and Therapeutics so
maybe I'll not talk about a lot of the
um um algorithm AI diagnostic but maybe
um of a and not even of the past ones
but ones we're actively working on right
now
which is uh we're a member of the lab
and square program that is uh between
academic institutions uh noo NIS and
evotech and the reason I bring that
because the topic here Rebecca really
wanted to say how does the whole
ecosystem work together and so for
example there you know it is in the area
of novo's Interest Novo is trying to
identify potential drug Discovery
projects but as you think in my job to
think with Nova what would make a
success successful program because at
the end I want the ecosystem to be
successful right for Massachusetts for
our investigators and for the patients
so in that we said we need maybe more
than one academic institution each
working to in their own capacity but for
the program that Noble wanted to build
and to Noble's credit they agreed to
have um Yale Harvard and uh MGH be the
initial party with whom they built what
would be the nuts and bolts of the
program how would we implemented what
would it cost what would be the uh legal
contract right and so and to be able to
bridge that Academia to um where would
be to bring resources one was funding
and the other was evot as a partner to
both Novo and US of course it adds
complexity when you have uh three
Partners but I just wanted to bring that
that you because resources are not
infinite for any industry how do you
operationalize it for Success right
there's a whole Mothership Nova nois
doing its thing but how does it create a
program that sits adjacent but can be
nimble can be fast can be tailored to
work with academics so that's one of the
ones I wanted to highlight it's only in
its first year so a long way to go
before we get to
outcomes um you know we're talking about
the ven diagram which I encountered 25
years ago so uh in a way it seems very
very static right uh the the the
institutions and the way they're
organized can seem static over the long
term but also things change like there's
uh boom and bust and and these sort of
cycles and especially since Co I wonder
if uh you can comment on whether what
industry wants is different um is it
constrained in different ways or is it
expanding into new areas like uh
thinking of them as your customer like
what what are how are their needs
changing what what kind of things are
you hearing maybe we'll just go straight
down the row here okay um so of course
um actually amazingly the immediate
pandemic years were not did not see as
much churn other than everybody adapting
amazingly well uh but it's been the post
this last year but it's a convergence of
a lot of macroeconomic uh things that a
lot of our larger partners because of
patent Cliff strategy changes R&D are
themselves going through a lot of
reorganization our industry Partners
it's harder they are a bit more
constrained and reorganizing so it's uh
we have to wait for them to come out of
that
strategy um to reorganize before we can
really be able to articulate there's
there's always been constraint on
resources but the constraints are
different to re understand what is going
to be different but there is definitely
some churn and I think it's driven by
the macroeconomics what is churn just
people
just changing what is early stage for
them which are the early stage programs
they want to get in and out of you're
hearing big headlines out of this in
this a lot of layoffs but I think it's
all driven by it's a cycle in when they
come out of it they will again be
focusing resources but at this point
sometimes it's hard to
Pivot
okay yeah I I would agree with SEMA I
mean we're experiencing similar things
all due to the same things I think
largely driven by the economics you know
there's been a contraction uh in biotech
funding and and so you know I you know
you see that partners are more hesitant
to pull the trigger on something they're
a little more risk adverse they know
they're going to have to fund this thing
deeper into the cycle you can't just get
a you know a lead and then license it
it's going to have to go deeper but I
agree that it's that it's a cycle and
and and things but it it is a little bit
tighter right now Colin you're closer
what is called AI which has to be in a
boom uh a boom Trend now it's going to
solve all the world's problems bring
world peace and uh so forth but but but
I think and we all can sit on the beach
while AI does of course where else would
we be um so I I I do think a common
theme that underlies this is you know so
uh Acom additions like to opine about
stuff but we don't always opine about
stuff that's important important and I
think the industry perspective is is is
unique in that they identify sweet spots
and special problems which necessarily
inquire new new new approaches and
finding these two individuals to come
together and communicate is challenging
and I have to say the MGB model at least
from the lowly boot on the ground like
myself is the NIH funding model right
and our lives are dictated by how and I
and that model is not necessarily
conducive for impact in the real world
mhm I think one of the things that that
Co that I took away from Co is that
people don't necessarily need to be in
the same room in at at at the you know
at the same time in order to have
impactful discussions moving forward and
and um I'm not quite sure if this is a
direct answer to the inquiry that was
that was that was made but I I think
something I do want to I do want to
stress is that mechanisms that allow
individuals with different expertise
somebody who has a a a um a method a
solution of thought and somebody who
knows how to do that and is willing to
support that together in an in in some
ecosystem whether they don't have to but
they're in different places or not I
think is essential to driving to driving
uh um a progress forward I hope that in
some way shape or form addresses a
sentiment you it does it does well
actually some of these people that
you're talking of might be in the
audience some of these potential
Partners so I would love to just throw
it open to see if we have questions for
our directors of strategic Partnerships
anybody anybody have a question that
they'd like to
ask any Brave questioners no okay um
maybe can oh if no question I was going
to say so while there is a constraint
you ask what am I seeing I'm also
seeing um for example some of our
partners um that do have um pipeline but
they do need to prioritize that pipeline
they need to be more resource efficient
for their clinical development because
it costs a lot should we're we are
seeing some newer interest around more I
would say early development just before
getting to clinical trial because a lot
of the Innovative newer pipelines like
cell therapy and all require a lot more
thinking on the what are the biomarkers
what might be the end points and so
we're seeing a little more uptick and
collaborations around that because as
Mass General Bram we do have a lot of
clinicians a lot of patient clinical
data longitudinal data she was like can
we actually work together to use that to
come up with things that would make
clinical development the future clinical
development a bit easier so while we
might be seeing things that may start in
early
research kind of not clear right now
because a lot of partners are redefining
what their research programs are things
where they're already in advanced
pipeline we're seeing a little more
robust collaborations of really trying
to um put that Pipeline with them in
collaboration for
Success when I uh when I read a
scientific paper like uh maybe like a
lot of you I I read who the authors are
what the title is and then I go straight
to the conflict of interest section
right because I want to know like what
the company is and what the patent
number is um so you know it's kind of
interesting to think about um what are
what are
the rules or the guard rails that exist
when sort of collaborating with or
through sponsored research to some
degree employing academics whose primary
goal is concept is NIH grants and being
an academic so can you speak to um kind
of like H how that works within your
institutions what the guard rails are uh
and also whether they're changing
because I think there has been some
changes recently uh that people may not
appreciate so conflict of interest is
always there I'm a BD person so I think
of compliance after the fact but um
uh we have very clear Pathways that's
the point whether you're MIT Harvard um
broad mg R because all the academic
affiliations are through MIT or Harvard
so it's pretty aligned what those uh
guardrails are everybody's aware from
The Faculty onwards to um our compliance
office for industry interaction to the
BB people so generally there are no no
immediate barriers for working with uh
industry when you're working in your
institutional hat in your research
capacity right because that's an
Institutional you're playing a role as
research my personal advice to
investigators is you're not ever
spending 100% of your time on an
industry collaboration you're going to
continue doing your teaching your um NIH
grants you know you think of it you have
one hand you're doing administrative
work part of your career you're doing
teaching maybe you have two uh NIH
grants or Foundation grants and then
maybe one part of what you're doing is
with industry and there's no conflict
when you're doing it that way some of
the conflicts arise when you already
might have a startup and an equity uh
position and so those but we have very
specific detailed ways of managing that
and also very upfront so people are very
cognizant and know exactly when the
guard rail is going to be right up and
some of those are
you just can't do that and that's it
right well actually MIT is famous for
its spinouts I mean they're all
clustered all around here uh aami and
all these other ones so it's it's uh
it's nothing shameful it's like the
badge of honor you know to start a
company so uh Bill how does that work at
the broad Institute because there's
certainly a lot of activity around um
some of the technologies that have been
developed there and lots of startups
coming out so how how do you manage when
the when the in investigator herself or
himself sort of is involved in the
startup and is a key a key person yeah
well what one thing let me just uh State
at the beginning is that um P the
ability to publish is a Cornerstone that
is a
non-negotiable uh aspect every
collaboration we have right up front
don't don't you might as well go home if
you're not going to let us publish this
um so so that that is one thing and also
like data we make data public available
you know that's that's another
Cornerstone for example all the data
from the cancer uh dependency map is is
publicly available um in terms of uh you
know faculty being involved in startups
there's a conflict of interest committee
which I actually happen to be on a
member of uh that reviews all of these
things and we're very careful to make
sure especially that for example
students aren't directed to do things
that would benefit the startup that the
p is starting in fact there are even
examples of where you have another
faculty member watching out over uh that
that uh student or postdoc or something
like that so you know we we always um
you know every every situation we look
at we look at very carefully to make
sure there's no conflict of interest or
even perceive conflict of interests in
fact you know one of the questions like
could this end up you know on the cover
of the Boston Globe you know as a
potential conflict of interest so so we
have a lot of guard rails I would say in
that way but just very fundamental
cornerstones of publication we're
nonprofit um you know you have to be
very careful about you know the
government gets the same deal as you
know Deerfield gets for example um so
we're just we're we're very very try to
be squeaky clean about all of
this Colin how about you what are what
are the guard rails that are around you
or or that you use up here uh in your
own work so I think the guard rails that
have been that bill is articulated very
much mimic the guard rails that are at
um MIT in terms of the ability to
produce
scholarship um avoiding conflicts that
involve
students and and so forth I think the CH
it's it's much more mysterious to me on
the MGH side than it is on the Mi MIT
side I think the culture of of MIT which
has been to uh you know recognize that
that um uh intellectual the valuable
intellectual property and bringing that
um out into the into the into the public
at large is much easier to overcome
we've had faculty on on the uh MGH um
side at Harvard who want to start do a
startup and were told by Department of
his you can keep your Harvard
appointment oh if you if you if if if
you want to whether that's typical I I
mean I just I just just I just don't
know but but having gone through this
exercise on both and that's that's not
see I know that's not your I'm just
exciting the data as as as I as I know
it and having tried to go through this
on the MGH side the the the pathways are
much more obscure uh even in in terms of
having funding from from outside of the
NIH um or you know some of the the
specialty organizations the American
Heart Association or or something is
always a challenging thing thing to
maneuver and I think it's an obstacle
because ideally you want all of these
all of these parties that have unique
things that they could contribute to the
development of of of Novel therapies or
Pharmaceuticals come together and shake
hands and be amiable you know but but
that that is a that is a difficult
optimization problem that I have yet to
solve yeah yeah well associate
professorship at Harvard uh versus
equity in a startup of unknown you know
uh prospects be a difficult one uh to
measure please a little bit
so just to be clear masteral Brigham
actually has a lot of spin outs so
unlike uh MIT or the broad we actually
have our own fund what that means is we
make investments and startups that come
out of our technology that founded
actually we have a core team that helps
build the company spin it out and we
take Equity so actually we're very well
wored at being a able to do that um
extremely knowledgeable team we're on
fund three we have external Partners
it's actually and we syndicate with all
the VCS in this area and internationally
and so we actually have a tremendous
track record so I would just want to
balance that conflict
aside tremendous like probably beats
everybody in the Boston ecosystem at
what our startups have raised and
successful products that have come out
of it hands down you can look it up so I
would just say balance that with the
fact that we actually know how to
navigate that but we our faculty as I
said our Harvard appointed faculty so
they have to meet the academic criteria
set by Harvard and the bar is a bit
higher because of clinical research so
when you're doing fundamental research
making technology Tech development it's
considered very far from patient impact
right the the biases would have to be
pretty far out but when you're doing
clinical research and clinical trial
your patient facing your biases might be
a bit more Aver to taking that risk so
that's where the difference between MIT
and not just Harvard but Harvard when
you're in a um academic Medical Center
because a lot of our researchers do very
close to Patient clinical research it's
very close to human impact and that's
why the bar might feel a bit different
to you yeah well Bill mentioned the
front page of the Boston Globe of course
as a journalist I mean we are hunting
for these conflicts of interest of
course because
actually I can't even keep track they
make better stories but no they people
people from the highest uh echelons of
cancer research and stuff uh get toppled
uh even for just you know what they put
in those little conflict of interest
disclosures they forget to mention you
know fiser blah blah blah blah blah and
uh wow you can have uh it can have
consequences so seems like a weighty
subject matter um our goal is to keep
people like Anton away from us so but
they have but their first priority is to
publish so they keep giving me the
information so that's bance we have a um
yeah love hate really so uh I think uh
one of the things I was really uh
promised to ask about is
silos my business we might call it like
a rats hole or something uh it is a
place where things get stuck and they
don't work and uh you know your ideas or
your Investments somehow you've gotten
into a corner of the ecosystem and
you're not really benefiting from it so
the question I've been given for each of
you is what advice do you have or how do
you
avoid silos and what does a silo mean we
know what it is this a metaphor but what
does it actually mean in
practice
um I can take start and take a shot at
it um so you can think in silos in many
ways silos can exist so forget the whole
ecosystem and the different
interinstitutional even within semestral
breum because we have five hospitals and
integrated system obviously they're
silos people have built Things based on
NIH grants careers you know but because
our mission is patient care um community
research and Innovation and education
the way we train our trainees is by
doing patient care and uh doing research
so we do have each of those vertical is
constantly intersecting with each other
right so that's one way organically you
know the silos are not there if you're a
fellow who's also doing research in a
lab and also seeing patients with one
division more intentionally at M General
Brigham like for decades we've been more
intentional of saying well how do we get
more multidisciplinary or how do we like
deliver on a focus that might be a
research area so for research we created
things called do we just label them but
it helps us internally be able to create
Pathways to avoid what might get stuck
so for example um we have thematic
centers should we have a regener
medicine thematic Center that means the
people do their research in that
thematic Center because they're with
other people their resources built to
drive regenerative medicine research but
their clinical appointments one is in
Psychiatry one is because it's the
different organs the different parts
that regener medicine could be should we
try to bring multidisciplinary in a
research base where all the clinical
appointments and the clinical care they
do each one of them in that department
is in different um clinical vertical um
so those are maybe an example of where
intentionally and organically we've
tried to break
silos yeah I mean the bro is set up to
avoid silos right but that said because
when you have a large group of people
you sort of naturally at times drift
into silos not by intention but I think
it's more like what you were saying see
but and so what one thing we try to do
is make deliberate efforts for example
to make sure you know like we'll have a
project where work's being done at the
broad and at MGH or at Dana Farber is
that we have to set up meetings where
everyone meets right at least by Zoom um
and so we there's a real deliberate
effort to bring everyone in and it's
really tough with you when you have
multi-institutional uh collaborations
going and you know there's always a
commitment like we've got you know like
for example we we have a commitment for
example with our Calico partnership they
come here once a year and we go there in
once a year where every you know the
joint steering committee everybody gets
together to try and break those those
silos down but it's more of a natural
segregation because you can only meet so
many and work with so many people and
keep track of so many
things so I I I think oh I'm sorry you
going so I I think um Sil in part arise
from just human nature and and and I
think especially in the you know in the
academy when one has something they find
that's interesting especially if one is
trying to build up their promotion to a
professor they want to have papers that
are identified with their uniquely
identified with their work similarly
institutions want work identified as
coming arising from from there so I
think Silo is something we're all silos
are something we're always all always
fighting and I think in in so far
uh we can incentivize individuals early
on to see the benefit the tangible
benefit to them from from actually being
open in their Communications we can get
people in a in a room and to talk and to
do such things in my my experience but
you know how far that gets to removing
the siloed thinking I think is the is is
is the barrier and so I think early on
this this
incentivization as in as much as we can
do it is is a is is a path forward
interesting well silos can't be that
they're built to keep things safe it's a
safe place to be um any questions can I
add it's more than safe it's really to
build that deep expertise sometimes you
can't unless your self aggregate so it's
not intentional but the deeper you go
sometimes harder to go broader right so
but I would just like to say it ech goes
everything but especially even like he
mentioned with Calico I mean that's one
of our thesis if you come work with us
and you want to be in a strategic
partnership there's a Cadence of
meetings and the meetings aren't just to
get the people to talk the Cadence of
meetings are to take some decisions to
get different input to go noo decisions
for projects to kind of get you know uh
and especially for example I'm thinking
of one project where we started with a
lot of Technology development with the
company it's an engineering device
company but then as the product got to
where it needed a lot of user needs a
use case you know we're working with a
thoracic surgeon So within the system
the focus of the project moves from
technology development of a robotic into
really being driven by using a lung uh
setting and so but the team meets as a
whole should the PHD and the MD the one
who's doing the surgery and the one
who's thinking about software and
clinical engine they are all meeting
together but it's in different phases
right you first had to do some tech Dev
before you could get there so when
there's Catalyst to make that the silos
actually just different subject matter
experts that if there is a reason they
will work together and I think as long
as we facilitate what that reason is you
know why you should work together
because it'll bring to you some output
and then of course you have to Resource
it that becomes the challenge if you
cannot resource people people have their
daily commitments you got to be able to
Resource it free up some time articulate
what you can do what it's going to take
to do and why you're doing it and I
think then people want to contribute to
something tangible that can come out so
I've actually found that the silos are
great subject matter experts if you can
articulate and be a catalyst to bring
what
that joint expertise could do we've seen
it work tremendously well just just a
point of clarification um so so um it's
not my statement that silos represent
nefarious Thinking by individuals my
statement is that um individuals have to
prioritize the things that they do every
day and and and and and this speaks into
all aspects of their life in terms of
where they put their intellectual
efforts and their intellectual cycles
and and I think that uh you know in so
far as you could have all
participants um have the same vision so
in the last 35 years I've seen lots of
people get together you know depends on
what what's your metric of success for
what these and what what does it mean
for it to work right and in my view it
the work it means that it solves a real
problem and it comes forward with some
with something and and if using that as
my metric that's where my statements are
applied terrific hey thanks to all three
of you uh Colin Bill and SEMA it's time
for the networking break and you can
grab the speakers um hear more from them
and from one another and we'll be back
at uh 11:35 for humanizing drug
development thank you thank you