thank you startup exchange for having us
I will jump right into it um I am an
Alum from the slone School of Management
MBA 23 and I lead SOS carbon uh I will
be focusing on um one of our
Technologies the most cost effective
technology for invasive seaweed
management and Marine debris management
but I will briefly also showcase other
areas that we have been developing and
already work so many of you probably
already heard about um seawe invasions
not only in the Caribbean but globally
affecting Co Coastline Marine ecosystem
tourism dependent economies and even um
human health so at MIT at the mechanical
engineering department we developed a
Innovative but very simple um Hardware
that allow us to retrofit local
infrastructure local boats
to harvest a seawe in the ocean before
it makes landfall this device um is
already patented and we have deploy it
in several countries not only showcasing
again the high capacity that we have to
prevent the seawe from making landfall
but also um in terms of employing the
local communities and basically how this
works is that we again Harvest a seawe
in the ocean and then we have develop a
series of processes that um accommodate
to the local conditions Bas if it is a a
tourism location or if if it is like a
power plant um or again depending
depending on the customer
profile uh for this equipment we have
been able to deploy it as I um
highlighted in four countries Dominican
Republic Anan baruda Mexico and Puerto
Rico with with operational permits um in
in all of them and has enabled us more
importantly as well to develop a supply
chain uh develop a supply chain from the
seawe as we also now work in
transitioning other Industries away from
petroleum based from chemical based uh
products into uh being CU based um we
have already developed a vertically
integrated operation from the seaweed
man man agement uh to seaweed seaweed
sales we have already chipped to more
than 10 countries um we also have been
developing and commercializing uh
several products our first entry point
has been in agriculture through a seawe
based bio stimulant called Marine
symbiotic and we are now also working on
carbon credits uh quickly to wrap the
idea or the concept around the carbon
credit carbon offsets basically when the
seaweed makes landfall it rots and
releases back the carbon and methane
that is that it once capture so taking
it through our vertically integrated
operation we can also account for those
carbon offsets um basically what we're
looking for not only Partnerships around
you know U groups of interest in the
tourism industry power plants affect the
stakeholders from from the invasive sewe
but also um industry leaders on
agriculture and bio Refinery looking to
transition again away from uh polluting
based materials into SE based um
materials so with that said again
looking forward to connect thank you
again startup exchange and and here my
contact information as we move away from
um you know petroleum base into
sustainable materials from invasive sewe
mitigation thank you and thank you so
much and great to see all the progress
and um excited about uh the news that
everyone um has to offer so um can you
tell us a little more about um your
competitive advantage or how you
differentiate from anyone else out in
the
market sure so as I already share we
we're working on technically four
business segments um quickly on the
cweed management our equipment you know
is a at least 10 times a fraction of the
cost of other other competitive
technology like conveyor based machines
that are very complex and costly to
deploy in Ocean based environment and on
our end as well we have been able to
develop through our system to integrate
the local communities and offer uh foral
jobs today we have been able to
integrate and and Empower in different
levels more than 120 fish
with that said on the um agricultural
side for example our seawe based bio
stimulate we are already at a commercial
level employing it or applying it in
over 15 crop types from rice to avocado
to tomatoes and we have seen um increase
in yield up to 60% in in several crops
um and we have also been working on
reducing synthetic f fertilizer putting
all that together also improving soil
Health um so again couple benefits
across our different uh business
segments yeah that is great to hear and
how um are you working nowadays with a
corporate for example or a government
agency what's the business
model thank you so again kind of
highlighting or partitioning it over the
different business segments very quickly
on the sewe management side we provide a
service or a licensing to affect the
stakeholders this could be the tourism
sector hotels um also like power plants
we have been also partnering with uh
government agencies across the Caribbean
and now looking for Europe as well where
where sewe has been affecting the the
coastlines of of various countries on
the um agricultural site we have been
working with um you know the different
farmers at a Industrial Level
incorporating our product as we then
form alliances with Agro Distributors
that's also the Partnerships mainly that
we're looking forward in the US and
Europe as we scale up the the
commercialization of our
products okay thank you very much thank
you