No, thank you very much. I have the the
pleasure of introducing a a section
here, a session that will focus on
sustainability across two somewhat
disperate uh industries, telecom and
aviation. But I think you'll find over
the course of the session that they
intersect uh quite nicely and we'll be
able to leverage some of uh the lessons
we learned from this. Uh so the next
speaker will be professor Masha Fox.
She's an assistant professor of
aereroastro. She is a true scholar
practitioner who spent several years
prior to this at Rolls-Royce. Masha,
thank you.
>> All right. Thank you very much for
having me. Um so I'm an assistant
professor at MIT. I work in the gas
turbine lab in the lab for aviation
environment and my passion is
sustainability and sustainability in
aviation. Now, at my core, I'm a
fluidamicist and a and a
thermodynamicist. And I've but I'm
really interested in connecting the
science question to the engineering
question that can make a difference in
our world. And so, that's what I wanted
to talk to you about today. Uh,
sustainability in aviation is really
difficult and the challenges that it
poses go beyond any single individual
contribution. That's actually why I'm
really excited to be here today. It's to
to sort of talk about the need for
collaboration. collaboration that that
we've heard about this morning between
uh entrepreneurs, government driving
policy uh investment and the science and
the engineering technologies uh behind
that that that really requires uh all of
us coming together to solve the
challenges. And the second is you know
sustainable aviation uh is is not
impervious to the laws of physics. uh
lest we are seen to be greenwashing, we
need to be very rigorous in how we
account for the technology that we
invest in. So we need to understand the
physics, the science so that we know
what are the levers, how do we invest
and how do we communicate what we're
doing in the world of sustainability to
take people the community along that
journey with us. So when I teach
thermodynamics and propulsion at MIT, I
begin with the range equation, the
airplane range equation. And it relates
how far an airplane can go uh with with
a few other parameters. For example, um
what kind of a fuel is it carrying and
the energy content of that fuel, how
efficient that uh propulsor is at
converting the energy stored in that
chemistry of the fuel to propulsive
thrust. That's the efficiency term.
something about the aircraft
aerodynamics. So that's the lift to drag
ratio uh and how much fuel has been
burnt. So the log of the the weight of
the initial aircraft uh divided by the
final weight of the aircraft. So
assuming conservation of passengers, the
only thing that changed has been the
fuel that we burned.
So let me set the stage for aviation. In
the past, uh, emissions of CO2, which
are the direct byproduct of combusting
fuel, of releasing that heat energy,
have been relatively constant.
Uh, the CO2 emission is about 2.5% of
global emissions. Now, why have they
been constant? In general, every year
the fleet improves in efficiency. Older
airplanes are retired, new airplanes
come in. So, why isn't this curve going
down? Well, at the same time there's a
growth in aviation
uh and the two have historically offset
each other so that emissions from
aviation have remained pretty constant
and today they're at about 2 and a half%
of global CO2 contribution. Now that's
important because CO2 has radiative
warming impact on our climate. Um as the
earth reflects energy in the atmosphere
CO2 in the atmosphere uh captures that
and sends it back to the earth. of
warming the planet and that's measured
by effective radiating force. So we know
CO2 in the atmosphere uh which is the
direct result of combustion of that
those hydrocarbon fuels uh contributes
to radiative forcing. But that's not the
only thing going on in an airplane.
There's also emissions of NOx which have
a contribution to global warming and
contrails. So contrails uh sort of act
as a blanket again when the earth wants
to cool off. uh the presence of
contrails sometimes um doesn't allow
that cooling off to happen. So so
warming up the environment. Now there's
a lot of uncertainty and different time
scales associated with this global
warming. But by and large these are the
three major impacts of aviation on
global warming.
Today if we account for contrails NOx
and CO2 the impact of aviation is
between 3 and a half and 6% of the
overall global warming. But we're at a
precipice
tomorrow. The growth of aviation is
going to take off in a way that we
haven't seen it before. And this is a
good thing, right? It's going to
encourage uh globalization. It's going
to give more people opportunities to
travel, to connect. And that's very
important. But at the same time, um the
the sort of efficiency gains that we've
had historically are going to be
outpaced by the demand for aviation. By
2050, the CO2 emissions from aviation
are going to more than double. Uh and
that goes for contrails and and NOx
effects as well. So uh so growth of
aviation is going to continue to grow.
So why can't we just decarbonize? All of
the other sectors that are emitting CO2
and and global warming effects will
begin to decarbonize. Why is aviation so
difficult to decarbonize? Why can't we
just electrify it away? Let's go back to
that range equation. Turns out the most
emissions from aviation occur on long
range flights.
So that's important because batteries
for example can only displace a very
short amount short duration flights
short range.
If we look at the the range equation for
an electric propulser the equation
changes slightly. First of all there's
no longer a log with with the weight. So
even as we're using power from the
battery, the battery weight does not
change. Uh and the the specific density
so so the energy per kilogram of a
battery is about 50 times lower than
that of a hydrocarbon fuel. So the range
for a battery powered aircraft is very
short. So even if we electrified as best
as we could, we would only displace 5%
of aviation emissions. We might think
about electrifying using other
technologies such as fuel cells and
they're a little bit better at that
energy density problem, but still
they're limited in range. Really 2,000
maybe if you're really pushing the
boundary 4,000
uh uh kilometers in in range. That
accounts for 20 to 40% of aviation
emissions. So where do we need to focus
our research on? Well, the bulk of
aviation emissions are going to continue
to come from gas turbine engines
converting energy which is stored in a
fuel into heat which creates useful work
in a braen cycle which is a gas turbine.
So if we think about making the most
amount of impact that's the technology
we really need to think about. Now the
other challenge in aviation is that
airplanes have a very long time scale.
Airplane lifespan is about 25 years.
That means the airplanes that are coming
off the production lines today will
continue emitting the same exact
emissions in 2050. So understanding the
time constant in in the aviation
industry is also really important in in
thinking about making a difference. So
it's important to think about aviation
both in the near term and in the future
term. So improving how we fly today and
thinking about designing better
solutions for the future. And that's
what I wanted to talk to you about
today. So sort of some of the research
MIT is doing in both fronts and how
that's going to be able to make a
difference.
Um so so let me begin with the the today
factor.
The first thing we need to do is improve
how efficiently we fly. In general
there's about a 7 and a half%
inefficiency in managing airplanes. Now
an airplane uh to fly efficiently it can
take advantage of the winds. there's an
optimal altitude and speed which
airplanes should be flying but sometimes
they're not able to. Sometimes it's
geopolitical reasons, right? We might be
avoiding regions of no flight. Um we see
a lot of inefficiency there. Sometimes
it's due to weather and other times it's
just due to um policy. So so airline
policy, we might want to get from point
A to point B faster and that costs us
more fuel. So in aggregate that's about
7 and a half% in efficiency uh in
aviation today is just due to operation.
Now the interesting thing is this
doesn't require a technology change to
fix this. The technology is already on
board all the airplanes. It's it exists
in satellites. Uh this requires a policy
and and a global buyin uh to to actually
make this change. So again sort of
explaining how challenges in sustainable
aviation are more than just one
technological solution.
Part of the efficiency story is also
maintaining the fleet. So the fleet has
a lifespan of 25 years and we can't just
ignore that. So it's really important to
think about either accelerating the the
turnover of the fleet if there are
airplanes available to replace them or
modifying existing engines to inject new
technology as there throughout their
lifespan. So a continuous improvement in
a way. Uh we know a lot more about the
physics of of inside the the heat engine
than we did 25 years ago when some of
these airplanes were first developed.
why not inject that now as these
airplanes are are uh serving the world.
Um and that just that sort of drives a
different business model that that
hasn't really existed before.
The other important aspect of what we
should be doing today is around
sustainable aviation fuels. Now, where
in my range equation does sustainable
aviation fuel come in? Any takers?
It doesn't. It actually doesn't improve
anything in that range equation. But
what it does is it uh changes where the
carbon that's released into the
atmosphere comes from today. It comes
from the ground. So we dig up fossil
fuels, we combust that energy and new
carbon goes into the atmosphere in the
future. And what sustainable aviation
fuel allows us to do is to capture that
carbon either from the atmosphere uh
directly or through uh bios through
plants photosynthesis convert that into
fuel and combust that fuel and release
it back in a net zero way. Now it's
really important to track the entire
life cycle of sustainable aviation
fuels. um for some processes that's
actually very carbon intensive and
sometimes even worse than just using
traditional jet fuel. So we have to be
very rigorous in accounting for the life
cycle of sustainable aviation fuels.
And the other thing is putting together
hydrogens and carbons in a lab to make
this hydrocarbon sustainable aviation
fuel. Well, it requires energy and
energy costs money. So scaling up the
production of sustainable aviation fuel
to meet the demands that we will see is
going to require uh a a cost premium and
that cost premium is not going to go
away. So we can think about uh
technological challenges to improve that
uh synthetic manufacturing process but
we also need help from policy and from
markets to incentivize the development
of the sustainable aviation fuel
economy. Now, saps are beyond just
carbon. What most people don't realize
is they're expensive, but they can
actually be very clean. The chemical
composition of of when you put hydrogen
and carbon in a lab together is very
different than sort of the cocktail of
molecules you dig up from the ground in
fossil fuel. When you dig up the the the
mixture, uh there's a really key
component called aromatics. It's it's a
circular hydrocarbon and when combusted
it creates this black smoke soot that's
actually very bad for human health and
can affect uh communities near airports
London. Uh sustainable aviation fuel on
the other hand uh does not have that
compound if if we decide not to make it.
We can make a purely paraffhinic
synthetic aviation fuel which when
combusted lacks that that uh soot and
lacks the the health implications. This
might also have implications for
contrails. So so we need to be bold in
taking advantage of this ability to
synthesize hydrocarbons that in a way
that's not just easy to implement but
that's the right way to to do it. And we
need to be ready to fund the cost
premium that's going to be associated
with it.
But those are all technologies that
exist today. What are we thinking about
in the future?
Here is a comparison of airplane
silhouettes for the past 60 years. Tuban
wing has looked like tuban wing for
since 1960. Is that how they will always
look? Well, actually no. Aircrafts of
the future might look something like
this. This is a a concept called
boundary layer ingestion. boundary layer
is a boundary layer is a low momentum
fluid that occurs near surfaces. So on
the body of this aircraft, the low
momentum fluid is actually being
ingested intentionally by the
propulsors. Now by accelerating low
momentum fluid um it it not only reduces
the overall sort of drag and force
required to propel that airplane but it
improves the propulsive efficiency of
these engines.
It might look something like this. The
concept here uh proposed by Electra is
distributed electric propulsion. So
instead of two propulsers on on the
wings, we see 10 propulsors, 10 small
little electrically driven propulsors.
Now the ability here is each one of
those propulsers can blow on the wing
increasing its lift. It's it's a concept
called blown lift in fluid dynamics.
That increases the L over D in our range
equation. So, all of these technologies
are addressing the different factors of
the range equation. Um, and if we keep
range the same, we can use less fuel.
Core to all of this technology is this
idea of hybrid electric. But wait a
minute, you told me electric airplanes
aren't going to take off. Well, that's
true. That's true. If we're only talking
about batteries, hybrid electric is when
we have some sort of a fuel on board,
but instead of using that fuel to
directly propel the aircraft, we're
using it to generate electricity. And
then we're using that electricity to
drive some sort of a new airplane
propulsor configuration like a boundary
layer ingesting fan or distributed
electric propulsors.
So the the intersection of how these gas
turbine engines which are powering
generators is really important to
understanding what the overall
architecture looks like because they're
the ones that are actually burning fuel.
Uh but the propulsors are the ones
creating thrust. So decoupling the fuel
burn from the propulsors and integrating
them with an aircraft uh is is going to
be the forefront of of future airplane
technology.
What about other fuels? We might have
heard about hydrogen. Let's unpack
hydrogen using our range equation. Well,
hydrogen is great because it carries a
lot more energy. In fact, it has three
times more energy per per kilogram than
uh jet fuel. So, that's great, but it's
a gas. So, so it takes up a lot of
volume. We might compress it to to take
up less volume. Uh we might liquefy it
so so that it takes up even less volume.
But even in the mo most optimistic
scenarios where we've cooled um the
hydrogen, it still takes up about four
times more volume which has to be
carried in very large tanks. So the site
the the promise is there but the
technology that's needed is this
integration of being able to carry that
hydrogen in in an aircraft and making
sure that the entire CA uh system
closes.
So, six things. These are the six topics
that people are talking about in
sustainable aviation. Now, if I didn't
talk about the the midterm, the new
airplanes that are going to come out in
2030s, 2040s, the new engines, those are
important, too, but I'm really
interested in straddling the little
eyes. That's what we do today. And the
big eyes, and that that's what we do in
the future. And and that's where I think
a lot of the research is is happening.
But none of that research can happen in
isolation.
It requires collaboration, discussion,
incentivization,
um, and and really interesting
strategies to go from fundamental
science, the fluid dynamics that I'm
really interested in and exploring in my
lab to the engineering solution, uh,
which is these airplanes that we see as
safe and critical, uh, to to policy. So
something that the, uh, the community
buys into and and believes in. That's
why I'm really excited to talk with you
all today and I'd welcome any questions
about this. Uh I'm going to turn it over
to Sar who's going to talk about the
sustainability of digitization
uh and and that aspect of it.
>> Thank you. What I would like to say is
if you have questions for Masha, please
use pigeon hole. But keep in mind that
we will have a chance to ask Sarwalk
questions as well. But then more
importantly, we'll have a chance to ask
them both questions for a bit of
dialogue. And if you remember nothing
else from today, sorry presenters, but I
would like to say having done this now
facilitation between corporations and
faculty members, the one bit of advice
is the discourse is what matters. So
think right now what will I remember in
five years. Sorry Masha it won't be the
formula but it'll be the discourse you
have between each other and perhaps what
they have between each other. Sawir um
we're blessed right now to have saw who
has worked in a large corporation who's
worked in small startup corporations and
more importantly I believe gives back to
the smaller corporations in which BT is
working. So the director of
sustainability for BT group Sarah Khan.
>> Thank you so much Steve.
Welcome to BT first of all. Hopefully
you're having a a great day and the team
are looking after you. So um I'm Saw
Khan. My background very much has been
uh more than a decade in the energy
industry, five years, six years in fact
in the telecoms industry and I've also
got a background in AI. So um following
on from Masha, you might be thinking
about what's the similarity between the
telecoms industry and uh the aviation
industry. Well, the the fascinating
thing actually is uh both industries are
experiencing an increase in demand for
consumption. In the case of the aviation
side, it's obviously passenger flights
and and uh wanting to travel the world.
In our case, it's the thirst for data.
Um and you've probably heard and maybe
you can't get away from it. Um there's a
big word at the moment which is AI. Um
and in the context of digitalization,
that's where the demand for um or the
thirst for data comes from.
Um first of all, I'd like to start off
by saying it's really important to call
out that actually digitalization and AI
can be a force for good and will be a a
force for good. And we've already seen
some real life examples across industry
where organizations are already driving
increases in productivity, increases in
efficiency and reducing waste. So um I
just wanted to call out a couple of my
personal uh favorite examples actually.
So uh when we think about smart energy
and I know Masha talked a little bit
around the the demand for energy in the
aviation sector. We have the UK power
networks uh which is effectively a
distribution company uh in in the UK.
They're utilizing machine learning to
scan rooftops and they're doing that
because they want to identify
opportunities to deploy more solar. So
accelerating the transition to net zero
for the UK, but also they're using the
same technology to uh identify something
referred to as invisible energy and that
is people who've already installed solar
panels on their rooftop but the uh
energy consumption is sat behind a smart
meter and that data is not filtering
through to uh the grid and the UK are
not able to report on it. So they
already utilizing AI as a way of solving
both problems. The other one, which is a
personal favorite, and that's only
because my wife is constantly on my case
for uh putting uh putting the the wrong
item in the recycling box, um is a
company called Litter Lotto. So, um
Litter Lotto have a an application where
anyone can upload images of their
rubbish. Really interesting in in from
the starting point. Um and they will
give you some guidance as to where to
place your litter. And the the ambition
there is to try and uh encourage
individuals to increase their recycling.
Uh but also it has a knock-on benefit
for local authorities where they're able
to reduce the cost of recycling um
because there's there's a it costs a lot
more to be able to sort out at the
recycling facility items into the right
um facilities and and so on. So really
great initiative and little Lotto
encourage individuals to do that by
entering them into a monthly draw where
they can win a prize. So there's also a
local uh benefit um to to that as well.
So um absolutely we believe AI can be a
force for good. Uh but it's it's
important to call out that it also comes
at an environmental cost. So there are
some trade-offs to think about and I
think this graph uh shows that really
nicely. Um and it's from a recent uh
piece of work uh under the AI index 2025
which shows uh the carbon emissions
associated with training some of the
larger language models. So uh chat GPT
or GPT for the specific uh open source
model is there and you can see there's
been an exponential increase over the
last couple of years um very much
associated with the growth of large
language models and you can see Llama
3.1 there really taking off in terms of
carbon emissions. Um so what is that
associated with and and what's changed
in the last two years when it comes to
AI is predominantly the way AI has
advanced to uh deep learning models deep
learning neural network type models and
these models are super complex. In fact
they they're built to imitate the brain.
So they're built on many many layers and
it's very difficult to enter the layers
and understand what's happening there.
But as you feed more data into an AI
model, um the layers just continue to
expand. Um the second thing is these
this new generation of AI models, they
tend to utilize unstructured data sets
and that's where a lot of compute power
actually is is consumed. It's it's
processing unstructured data. So what is
unstructured data? without being going
too much into the detail that's
effectively where the data is not
labeled prior to it entering the AI
model and therefore the AI model has to
uh you know compute what that data set
actually looks like what it is etc and
assign a label. Um, additionally the AI
model has to continuously iterate itself
to ensure that the output from the AI
model and the recommendation it provides
is accurate and there is an accuracy
trade-off as well when it comes to
sustainability because the more you
iterate um the more compute power again
that it consumes and then very finally
um if we think about AI we're not just
thinking about the chipset that it
resides on um it actually has we have to
think holistically about the
infrastructure that sits that's behind
it. So typically compute will go into
a a server which may reside in a data
center and if you take into account the
full life cycle impact and the energy
associated with it that's where the the
big concerns are.
So if we think about specifically what
is the impact if we take these models
and bring them into the UK where large
language opensource models become the
basis for industries and public sector
deploying AI models um at scale. Well
there's there's a potential energy
challenge even before we enter the
sustainability uh uh domain within the
UK. So uh the government this year
launched something called the UK AI
opportunities action plan and
underpinning that is a promise that
there'll be a 20fold increase in compute
capability within the UK enabling the UK
to be an AI superpower.
Um so in terms of what it means from an
energy perspective you can see in 2024
the total demand in the country was
approximately 319 terowatt hours. um 285
terowatt hours UK generated domestically
but quite a large proportion of that is
coming through the interconnect. So the
UK is effectively importing electricity
from our neighbors France, Belgium to
cover the deficit in terms of the
electricity consumption today. Now if we
take the ambition by the UK government
to have a 20fold increase in compute
power in the UK then roughly that goes
from 3.6 6 terowatt hours today to
approximately 72 terowatt hours by 2030.
So pretty significant increase in
digital demand and that is to fuel the
data centers that will enter this
country. Um if we then combine that with
the energy outlook provided by um Nesso
for 2030 and that is part of the UK
government's plan to decarbonize at the
same time. So um achieving 95% clean
power in the UK by 2030. You can see
pretty much in this space that um we get
pretty much there in terms of fulfilling
the demand. But actually there's around
50 terowatt hours that's accounted for
and that's because the Nesso plan
accounted for a five-fold increase in
terms of electricity consumption
specifically from data centers. So
there's a significant gap left there.
So why does that leave a challenge?
Well, um the first thing is there's 50
terowatt hours potentially unaccounted
for. So there's an energy security uh uh
issue straight away there. But that's
potentially over we can overcome that.
Um but there's some serious
considerations that need to be taken
into account by the the government and
and industry as a whole. So what are the
options available to do that? Well, the
first one is the country increases the
interconnects and continues to take more
from the neighbors such as Belgium and
France. But obviously the big
consideration here is in terms of uh
energy security. The second one is uh
could we retain gas for longer? Um the
the consideration on the back side of
that is actually that pushes out our net
zero ambition as you can see from the
the gap there. Um third one is to
increase dispatchable power. Um so that
could be maybe combining gas with carbon
capture and storage and having it um sat
available. So if the wind didn't blow as
hard as it should or the sun didn't
shine as much as it should, then you
call upon the dispatchable power unit to
turn on and provide the the power to to
cover that. that comes at an increased
cost because you've essentially got
power capability sat redundant for most
of the time. And then the fourth option
which is to increase uh the percentage
of offshore wind in the UK but obviously
uh building an offshore wind farm
doesn't happen overnight. There are some
long lead times associated with it. So
um some smart decisions have to be made
now in terms of heading down that route.
So the UK has a challenge today in terms
of fulfilling the ambition to be an AI
superpower and also being net zero in
terms of our energy supply by 2030.
However, this is where there's an
opportunity because as we see demand for
AI grow, I come back to my first point
where AI can be a force for good and
we'll see it in terms of increasing
productivity and so on. then naturally
this is an opportunity for the UK to
also double down on the green growth
agenda to back and fuel the growth of
AI. So um in terms of making the right
decision uh there's a potential
opportunity arising here where we see
the 50 terowatt uh hour gap in energy
demand being filled through a
combination of both offshore wind in the
UK and a smarter grid and the benefits
associated with that is an increase in
green skills so more technicians more
skilled engineers um coupled with that
we'll also see the emergence of storage
technology so CC CS, battery, uh
whatever it is, we'll we'll see um that
potentially emerge. And then finally, uh
the big aspect here, which is about
energy resilience and a secure energy
system.
On the other side, um there's a bit of a
dependency here in terms of AI itself
becoming efficient. Otherwise, there's
the risk where we'll continue to see AI
grow, put more energy strain, and you
know, there's a limit in terms of how
many offshore wind farms we can spin up
in a set time. So, um we need to see
some innovations happening on the AI
side and we're we are starting to see
that on on the fringes, but what are the
big topics that are under research at
the moment? Well, the first one is
something called zeroot or federated
learning. So this is the ability where
an AI model effectively doesn't have to
iterate or reiterate as much to
understand the context and give an
output. Um it's smart enough from prompt
engineering to make an informed decision
to provide an output. So reducing
iteration obviously reduces compute
power. So that's something being looked
into. The second thing is um
quantization and distillation
techniques. So this is um removing the
fat essentially. So data going in just
making sure it's the right data and
therefore the compute capability only
has to process exactly what it needs. So
again reduces compute power. Um
neuromorphic computing. So this is a
really interesting area still very much
under heavy research under academia.
This is the ability to combine compute
and storage together. Um obviously from
a e-waste perspective that's great but
uh overall in terms of power consumption
you can drive some synergies because you
remove something called a digital clock.
And then very finally really interesting
look from big tech companies but also uh
corporations is dynamic AI load
management. So this is where you match
um your workloads for AI with
availability of green energy and you try
to do that on an hourly basis. So we're
starting to see that emerge. Some tech
providers starting to provide solutions
and software that enables companies to
um program and schedule their workloads
to match. But that's all great, but
there is a dependency on a few things.
So the first one is um if we are to have
green growth and we're about to have it
in terms of being ready for 2030 where
we're going to expect the AI boom then
we have to back something called um uh
contracts for difference and this is
basically the government's way of
procuring renewable energy and it sends
a price signal to organizations. It
gives them the reassurance for a fixed
term that this is the price the
government will pay for a certain type
of technology. And um to get to that 20
target, the uh the auction that's due to
happen uh early next year has got to be
the biggest auction for offshore wind in
the history of this country. So we're
waiting to see what happens. um a lot of
um discussions being had around that and
a lot of advocacy going into helping the
government understand you know what's
the right strike price that they need to
set to make sure that they are able to
do that. Um I would say although it's a
huge ambition the government have
successfully managed to um drive
adoption of offshore wind over the last
couple of years by altering the strike
price under the contract for difference.
So it is possible so that level of
ambition should remain. The other thing
is uh investment into building a smarter
grid. So whilst we uplift our energy
system and we bring more renewables,
more electric vehicles etc onto the
grid, without a smarter grid, you have
some flexibility uh challenges and um
you still got copper there in terms of
the distribution network. So you know
being able to do things like um dual
management, flexibility, demand side
response, etc. does require an
investment into a smarter grid. And then
very finally as Masha uh called out and
maybe you've heard it already throughout
the day, increased collaboration between
academia, energy and the tech sector.
And you can pretty much see why, right?
Because on one hand you've got AI
growth, on the other hand, you've got an
energy dilemma, you've got a
sustainability challenge, and then
you've got uh innovation challenges in
terms of early research within AI
itself. So um lots of opportunity to to
collaborate and drive this agenda for
good. So again getting back to that
point of reducing waste, increasing
productivity but doing it powered by
green growth.
Thank you very much.
Oh no, that's mine. You mine.
Thank you SA. Um so if we can put any
pigeon hole questions on the screen, I
would appreciate it. I'll sort of start
by saying Chancellor Nobles um indicated
earlier that part of MIT student success
is due in part through collaboration and
I think you heard both speakers say that
just now. Um in order to get to a
technological question, may I ask uh to
start this off, what is one of the
biggest misconceptions
to your path to net zero in your
respective industries?
>> Would you like me to go first?
>> Yeah.
Great question. Very challenging. I I
think I'll go back to the earlier point
I made around consumption. So there is
the uh misconception that we can't
decouple growth, right? That's the
starting point for for a lot of people
particularly within the the telco
sector. Um but we are starting to see
some early shoots and and and and green
shoots and that is backed by things like
renewable energy starting to to grow
across Europe and and and the UK. So we
we do believe that you can decouple
growth. So what by the way what does
decoupling growth mean? It means you can
you can continue to consume more but at
the same time the um the carbon
footprint associated with that goes
down. Um so uh that's usually the
starting point but we do believe that
you can decouple both and and and
achieve both at the same time.
>> Do you find it challenging in that the
growth seems to be in different
directions as well? It's a very dynamic
area that you live in, whether it's the
grid, it's computing at the edge. Is it
hard to focus on an area while everybody
else is growing in a spiderweb?
>> Yeah, it's it's a tough one and in some
cases where we're seeing um AI being
deployed, you know, um pretty much
entering the the scale phase. So, uh,
the industry as a whole, particularly
when it comes to energy and
sustainability, are trying to keep up
with that. And historically, there's
always been that disconnect between
understanding the the hardcore
engineering element of AI and the
traditional sustainability folk. You
kind of think, oh, well, you know, they
don't tend to go hand in hand, but
actually, we're going to have to bring
that together to to achieve growth in in
both industries.
>> Thank you,
>> Marsha. I would say from aviation the
biggest misconception is that it's not
really a big deal. Um the uh it feels
like there isn't enough urgency but it
really is an urgent problem. Um so right
now the aviation contribution to to
global warming is really small. Uh but
it's like I pointed out it's it's going
to astronomically grow and it takes a
really long time to penetrate into them
that that market. Uh and I think
unfortunately what we've seen is is sort
of a stalling in investment in in the
aviation sector. So the biggest
misconception is it's fine. It's it's
not fine. It really is at a turning
point right now. Um and I I would say
one one thing I would I want to ask
about is a lot of people whether it was
this morning that had spoke to me about
this potent your talk was they were
looking at leisure or business travel
but there's also a big push to go to
space and I feel that the need for fuel
going to space is a much larger quantity
than you would have for a flight from
the US to England.
>> Yeah. So, so, so that that that's a
whole different challenge. And actually
in this the space industry is thinking
about reusability as well and the
reusability of technology. So, with
space, we've treated um the rocket
engines themselves sort of expendable.
You use it once and it's it's done. Uh
so, thinking about um extending the life
of of space rockets and and airplane
engines, there's actually a lot of
synergy in the technical challenges
there, not not just the fuel.
>> Thank you. Um, all right. I want to give
due respect to the audience here and
we'll just maybe take the ones with the
highest votes. So, number six votes. Do
we think that the government or NESO
others will manage to deliver the net
zero goals that have been set by 2030?
No.
>> So, how how would the lack of green
energy impact sustainable AI growth?
>> Great.
>> I'll let you digest and then answer
will. I guess the starting point uh is
with the with the no from this whoever
asked the the question. Um I'm I'm on
the opposite. I'm I'm a lot more
optimistic actually because I've I've
seen um the energy industry in the UK um
go through the ups and downs. Um but I
think with with the Labor government's
agenda in the UK, there's an opportunity
to grow two industries at the same time.
Um, as I said, the key enabler will
actually be the contract for difference
auction coming up early this year. If we
can put the right market incentive in
place for offshore wind, then I do
believe we can get to the 2030 net zero
target. Um, so it it is a bit of a you
know, we got to watch and wait. Um, but
as I said earlier, early indication, the
government has done this before. They
have sent the right price signal. we
have seen offshore wind come online over
the last two years which is a great
starting point. So um yeah let's let's
see but I'm I'm I'm very much optimistic
on on that front. There is a lot of work
being done behind the scenes. So it's uh
not just government and the energy
sector. Um a lot of the big tech players
are investing in some of the innovation.
So we have seen uh significant
enhancements in things like data center
efficiency. You know, historically pee
factor, power utilization effectiveness,
which was the the metric that was
historically used for u measuring the
efficiency of data centers, has gone
from something like 1.8 and we're on the
verge of, you know, 1.2, 1.1,
best-in-class, even potentially at one.
Right? So in the background, we're
starting to see things um um improve and
we're starting to see other players
within the ecosystem act and and
recognize the importance of this. Um
because everyone wins, right? If we
manage to um drive sustainability and AI
growth, then the guys who want to push
out the the tech and the AI systems will
have less barriers to adoption. So
there's a potential synergy there. So
yeah, more optimism. Do you think that
uh the big tech companies will have to
become more diversified in their
offering then so as opposed to being
onedimensional historically speaking?
>> Um it yeah what what is interesting is
we have seen and you may have caught in
in in the news a lot of the um
hyperscalers so they that's the likes of
Amazon uh Google and Microsoft they're
already starting to think about how they
diversify their business. So um we've
seen a recent spree in terms of their um
shopping for SMR technology right so uh
which then creates an interesting
conversation because that's very much
focused around energy um they are
historically and still are very much
cloud AI technology focused but they're
having to diversify their business and
understand the energy sector a lot
better and as a result they're starting
to to buy into the SMR technology to try
and fuel that growth. So, what you might
see over time potentially is some form
of premium offering where you have a m a
sustainable option for cloud computing.
We'll wait to see um when that happens
and if it does happen, but we're
definitely seeing some form of
diversification there. Thank you. Uh I'm
going to skip the next one, but since
they're tied, but this one's from Masha
since we've given her a moment to to
take a break here. Uh do we have or
should we have a right to fly? It's easy
to hop on a plane, but should we all be
made to comfort the ethics of this? A
cap on personal flights? It sort of ties
into what we were speaking about
earlier.
>> It it does. That's a really difficult
question to answer, isn't it? Um on on
one hand, we've sort of had the luxury
of of being able to apply to be
connected. Uh how can we say at this
point now that you know the the emerging
economy that are going to have that
opportunity to to sort of limit that? So
so that's a really difficult question. I
I think being connected should be a
right that everybody's
entitled to. Um but but also I I think
that connection increases productivity.
So So I uh I was thinking of these
numbers last night. I I traveled over
here to London and from from Boston. So
so obviously that flight had some
emissions. I I did my my range equation
and calculated how much fuel was burned
and the CO2 emissions. Um but I spent
the week actually traveling to um
Rolls-Royce who who creates the jet
engines who create these missions and
spending time speaking with their
fundamentalists uh on whiteboards and
sort of understanding the challenges to
implementing the the science and the
engineering solution that then is going
to go back into my research and the
efficiency that's going to come from
those conversations far outweigh the CO2
that I contributed on the flight over.
So I think that is really important and
that physical uh human connection should
not go away because that will continue
to drive our growth
>> and and in a way um your two respective
industries are at heads in a way because
you want to potentially create more
content virtually and yet aviation wants
to fly more people around. Um, is there
a way you can leverage each other's
technologies to both be sustainable, get
people together and offer accessibility
to people in remote areas?
>> Absolutely.
>> Yeah, I think we discussed that actually
um last week didn't where we were seeing
there's potential to use digitalization
and AI as a way of helping the aviation
um industry become more operationally
efficient which would reduce the impact
of fuel going in. So yeah.
>> Yeah. Exactly. So, so there's a lot of
um you thinking about how to use AI to
make um better fuels, right? So, how can
you use AI with synthetic biology to
drive the cost of some of these
sustainable aviation fuels down, the
energy intensity of those fuels down? Uh
how can we develop different materials
that can withstand higher temperatures
and enable more efficient propulsion?
So, I think there's a huge opportunity
for for using AI to to decarbonize in
the aviation space. And then again,
connecting people together to to
um to improve
>> um a question for both of you. We're
switching gears, but to an older
technology, nuclear. Uh are very small
micronuclear reactors the answers to
both sustainability challenges.
>> I'll uh I'll I'll mention it from
aviation first. Absolutely. I we are
considering this. Um so so nuclear
reactors have come a long way. You can
now sort of 3D print the casings that
the nuclear fuel is in, increasing the
safety. So, so there's a lot of work in
policy and the technology of putting
nuclear on aviation, but it's it's not
science fiction. This is uh an active
area of of research and watch this
space.
>> Yeah. And ju just to add that I guess
it's very similar from a technology or
tech sector as a whole because as I
mentioned earlier uh the the big tech
companies are investing in this
technology as a way of decoupling
themselves away from from the from the
grid. So there's potential there but I
think still a lot of research going into
that space. So longterm I believe it's a
big part of the energy mix
>> but in terms of the the the short term
we might see some smallcale deployments
until it becomes a bit more commercially
feasible to scale. Um there might be
more appetite I mean some countries
actually ban uh this the technology as a
whole. So there's there's some other
barriers to to overcome but is it part
of the equation? Absolutely.
>> Yeah. So from a portfolio analysis
perspective it's good to diversify.
>> Yeah. for both of your respective
industries. Is there one of these either
renewables or older technologies that
you would prefer or think is the the key
to advancing it?
So I think I think it's actually really
interesting the growth in demand for
digital and the growth for aviation they
both at the heart of it require energy
and we have a lot of renewable energy
and uh so so so thinking you know I
spoke a lot about making sustainable
aviation fuels it requires investment in
renewable energy but it does that for
for digitization too. So actually this
this growth in AI coupled with this
growth in aviation uh I think enables
larger investment together for for these
renewable energy sources. Um so I I
think in the future uh countries that
have a lot of renewable resource will
will take advantage of that to make some
sort of a fuel that's able to be stored
whether it's uh hydrocarbon fuel or
hydrogen fuel and that will sort of
become the new currency of um making and
exporting energy. Uh but that's going to
benefit both aviation and
this need for digital AI.
>> Absolutely. And I think going back to
your point around storage, that could be
another the key enabler because if we're
going to have gas in the short term and
we're just thinking about how close we
are to 2030. You do have that
dispatchable power at your source, but
how do you make sure you you're meeting
the demand now? You you look to retrofit
options and I know you discussed that on
one of your slides and it's similar.
There could be an opportunity here for
for gas storage potentially to to be
part of that overall mix.
So if I may, I think the next three
questions are somewhat related. Um
trends suggest sustainability is losing
popularity. Um so is there oh sorry
would you mind going back to the the
list for a moment? The reason is so the
first one is asking about losing
popularity. The second one is about
public and political discourse turning
away from the green agenda. And lastly,
if as a aviation is expected to grow, um
why are we
uh when advancements in technology
should be making remote collaboration
better? So, I feel that they're there's
somewhat connected from a a public
policy standpoint um and where we're
going with either the support and I
think the discussion about potentially
data centers and nuclear sort of both
tie into that nicely.
>> Yeah, I mean happy to start. Yeah, go
back and just talk about trends overall.
So, um, again, we've kind of seen this
cycle before when it comes to
sustainability. Um, we went probably
just around COVID, we saw a peak in
interest in sustainability. Um, and very
much after that, we saw a phase called
greenwashing, right? Everyone wanted to
be a frontier in in sustainability.
um regulations came in uh and and things
a lot more controlled and then we've got
the geopolitical issues. Um what I've
noticed over that 5year period is
actually the demand has not changed so
much but the narrative has gone from the
greenwashing to the green hushing. M
>> so what's essentially happening here is
organizations are continuing to do what
they do but they're just not talking
about it as frequently as they used to
or they're using a different form of
language you know instead instead of and
I'm sure you may have seen this across
your organizations um instead of netzero
you may be talking about energy
resilience they're both very
interrelated by the way and maybe that's
what's required to um deal with some of
the the the political geopolitical
challenges that that we face so uh from
what I see and I speak to customers on a
regular basis the the trend still
remains and what drives that by the way
is the end consumer right there that's
still being driven what's good for
business a lot of private corporations
is still driven by the end customer you
know the the appetite for sustainable
products from the end consumer is
growing evidence shows is still growing
so you know how do you capture that
market segment to continue growing in a
very complex um industry sector etc um
that has to be a position of growth for
a lot of companies. So yeah, very much
on the trend side. We're still seeing it
remain. It's just a change in terms of
the language.
>> I I think there needs to be a role in
government for this both in
incentivizing the markets um through
through some sort of market incentiv
incentives or um mandates. So so I think
there's there needs to be a clear
direction from from government uh but
also as as a thought leader and as as an
idea. So, so I I'll give you an example.
Um, when I first came to MIT and started
teaching thermodynamics and propulsion
in in the aerrowastro department, uh, I
asked my students, why are you here? And
a really large part of them said, I'm
I'm worried about sustainable aviation.
Um, and then sort of over a year, the
national conversation about
sustainability changed. And I asked the
new cohort of students, why are you
here? And not so many of them said that
anymore. Now they said rockets, they
said space. Uh but but that didn't seem
to be a pressing challenge.
Sustainability sort of left the national
conversation and it left what our
students were sort of uh passionate
about and and I find that very very
worrisome. So I think the role of the
government is both to sort of help drive
the markets, put those incentives in
that that otherwise um wouldn't get
people to change. Uh but but second is
to to set an example for for where we
should be going.
Um, thank you. I want to I want to
continue that thread, but we have about
a minute left and I want to I want to
end on a bit of a technological
question. When quantum computing
solutions emerge at scale, what will
happen or what will that do to power
demands?
>> Yeah, that uh similar challenge. I mean,
quantum's a big part of the the AI
solution, right? We get more compute
power. You can do things at super low
latency, etc. Um, in terms of scale,
we're not there yet. So, it's difficult
to say, but again, we go back to the
graph that I showed earlier in terms of
the gap from the energy demand. That's
going to be a decision for uh
governments ultimately to to to decide
what's the right incentives that they
put in place for green infrastructure to
support support that growth. But the
idea is if the right incentive is in
place, let's say come the the CFD
auction this year and we see a growth in
renewables come online then the cost of
renewable energy continues to go down as
the technology advances. We'll see uh
other forms of technology come online at
the same time. So in the UK we've got a
nuclear power station due to come online
in the midterm. SMRs are are evolving.
So I believe at that point we'll have a
plethora of options available. there
won't be as much of a dilemma
particularly from a cost perspective.
>> All right. Well, I think that brings us
to time. I want to say thank you very
much to our speakers. Um, and I just
want to say I think that some of the
cross threads here was that we are
living in an interdisciplinary world
where a lot of these major thrusts are
connected and collaboration is likely
the key. So, thank you very much.