Okay. So, um so the topic of today is uh
civ theory and the the large civ um
which was the first place that I know of
where proofs like the proof that proofs
that we've been talking about appeared
and it appeared in the context of of
analytic number theory. Um, we'll talk
about that and then if there's time I'll
try to show you like a really very
closely analogous thing in the context
of real analysis. Um, and we'll compare
it.
Okay. Um,
all right. So the setting of the large
civ is that we have a function on the
numbers from one up to n. So remember
that that notation is the integers from
one up to n and I have a function.
Okay. And then I'm going to think about
what happens when I
reduce these integers mod p.
So um
uh
so I'll have pi p of f that's a function
from z mod p to c and the definition is
like this pi pf of a is defined to be
the sum over all the n= to a mod p of f
of a.
Okay. Um the setting of the large civ is
I have I have one function f but then I
consider this is sort of a projection of
f and I consider pi p of f for many
different ps and see what sort of the
typical behavior and how the different
the different ps are related to each
other.
Okay. Um
okay. Now, as before, we've seen it's
sometimes helpful to separate a function
out into its constant part and its mean
zero part.
So,
f0 would be so the take the average
value. So, 1 / n=
1 to n.
So, that's the average value.
And then maybe still
I still have a function on on numbers
from one to n.
Okay. And then the high part of f is f
minus the constant part. So subn
f high of f is zero.
So this is the dangerous notation with
the I'll make it a capital h.
Okay. And you can do the same thing with
the with the projections.
So if I take the projection of f zero,
it's 1 / p
sub a and z by pi
p f of a. It's a constant function
and pi p of f pi is pi p of f minus pi p
of f.
Okay, a little tiny remark is I was sort
of careful about where to put the
parenthesis, but it doesn't actually
matter. So,
um, pi p of f high is the same thing as
pi p of f high and
pi p of f zero is the same thing as pi p
of x.
>> Sorry, could you just explain what the
bracket means on the definition of zero
again?
this one here.
>> Yeah.
>> Um so f0 is a function of let's say m
and
inside the large bracket is a number
which is like the the average value of
f.
>> Oh those are just parentheses here.
>> Those are just parenthesis.
>> Okay.
Okay. So the the theme of the large civ
is that if you take a almost arbitrary
function here and you look at many
different projections then the um
uh the oscillating part of the high
frequency part of the projections will
on average be pretty small whereas the
um the constant part um well it only
depends on the constant part of f but it
will be it could be typically bigger. Um
okay so let me write a theorem which is
makes that sense
I might need just a little more notation
to state our theorem.
Okay. So let's say capital P M is the
set of prime numbers P prime in the
range M / 2 less than P less than.
Okay. So here is the main theorem which
was proven by Linu
says that if you have a function
n goes to c um and we have an m which
goes up to square root of n.
Then if I take um
the the sum
p and pm
of pi p of fi
l2
and that is bounded by
n / m times the sum on n of f of n^2.
Okay,
so it takes a little bit of work to uh
digest the statement of this theorem and
like what kind of a bound this is giving
us. So let's digest it together and and
by doing we'll digest it by doing some
applications and then after that we'll
come back and we'll prove this theorem.
Okay.
So,
so there are the character in our story
is the primes of size about M and it's
useful to know about how many there are.
So, a background fact from analytic
number theory is that the number of
primes about M is around M over log M
which very roughly I'm just going to say
is about M.
Uh, okay. So, there are about M terms in
this sum and it sometimes is helpful to
replace the sum by an average.
Um so correlary
is that the average
P and PM
of pi P of FI
L2
is less than N / M^2
times the sum on M of FI N
Okay.
So as a first application of this, let's
um prove an estimate about uh so so we
so last time I gave the example of the
square numbers. Square numbers have the
interesting property that if you reduce
them mod p for any p you get the
quadratic residues and they're only p+
one over two of them. Um so let's think
about a situation like that. Suppose you
have a set and when you reduce it modulo
P, you get significantly less than all P
of the of the residue classes. What does
that tell us about the set?
So there is a corlary
if a is a subset of 1 to n
and pi p of a is significantly smaller
than p. So I'm going to say it's less
than.99
* p just some constant that's less than
one. Um, and
for all P would be interesting, but but
I'm going to say for all the P in P n to
the 1/2. So we only actually are going
to use the primes of size about n^ the
1/2.
Um, then the conclusion is that the size
of a is bounded by around n to the 12.
So this would be the this would be the
case if a was the set of square numbers.
A was the set of square numbers. would
be basically half of P. This would be
all the primes. So in particular all of
those primes and this set of square
numbers would have cardality n to the
1/2.
Okay.
So let's make our function a
characteristic function of a.
All right. Um
okay. So
if I look at the sum uh a and z mod p of
pi p
f of a squared let's so let's say that p
is in this pn to the 12
okay so how big would this be well if
each of these entries if each of these
guys were the same as each other then
the size of this thing would be a / p
and it would be squared and I'd be
summing over p terms.
Right? So if all these values pi pf of a
they were all equal to each other they
would each have size size of a over pum
and then the sum would be like this.
They could be unequal to each other and
then by koshi schwarz argument they
would this would be even bigger. Okay.
And then simplifying this a little bit,
it's
it's around a^2 n to the minus a half
because p is around n^ the half.
Okay. Now what happens if we take the
high part?
Um well
because
pi p so the support
of pi p of f that's contained in pi p of
a
um so the size of the support
pi p of f is less than.99
*
That's enough to say that this function
is not super close to a constant
function in L2.
So that implies
that um the sum and cp
pi p of f high
squared is around the sum without the
high.
[Applause]
So, so all of these L2 norms they're
they're all big.
Does that feel intuitive to people?
Should we talk about that more?
>> Yeah. Okay. So, let's call let's call it
a lema.
So, lema is that if I have a function G
um CP to C, it's not really important
that this is CP. It's just a finite set.
Um
and um
uh and the support of G has size
significantly less than P.
Then the conclusion is that the high
part of G L2 is around the same as GL2.
Um okay. So, um,
okay. So, G is G knot plus G high. And G
knot and G high are always perpendicular
to each other.
Um
so
so the sum
so gl 2
is around
g2
is equal to g l2 2 plus g high l2.
Um okay.
Um
um so okay if if GL L2 squared was much
smaller than G L2
then clearly G high L2 squ would be
bigger.
So
if G knot
L2 2 um is less than half of G L2.
We're done.
Otherwise, we go the other way.
Um
and um
so
so um
let's say S is the support of G
complement and notice that S is at least
some definite fraction of P
and on S
uh G high is equal to I guess negative g
because they have to add up to to zero.
G vanishes on on on s.
Um so we get
g high l2
is at least um the sum the sum in s of
of g
squ.
But since g is constant
um this is at least s over p times
g l2
which is then at least uh
so s over p is on the order of 1 and g
l2 is on the order of gl2.
So that's
okay.
Okay. So the high part of this
projection has an L2 norm that's
comparable to the L2 norm of the whole
projection which is at least this big in
terms of the size of A.
But the L2 norm of the projection high
pride of the projection shouldn't be too
big by our theorem.
So the theorem
implies that the average over p^
12 of this same thing is bounded above
by
n / m^2. My m is the square root of n.
So this just cancels and then I get the
sum of f of n^2.
So this would be bounded above by the
size of A.
Okay. So to summarize this is bounded by
this is bounded by this a^2 n^ the minus
a half bounded by a a is bounded by n^
the 1
Any questions or comments about it?
Okay. Okay. So, um, so I feel like it's,
you know, it's interesting that it
matches the examples of of the square
numbers. So, it's sort of sharp in that
context. Um
uh but also it would be nice to discuss
more and look at more examples to try to
get a feel for sort of the numerology of
the equations. And a helpful reference
point for me is to look at a random set.
So reference point
be a random set.
Okay. So here we're going to take a
subset of the numbers from 1 to n and we
include
each number in a
with probability 1/2.
You could also as an exercise play with
this probability but let's just talk
about 1/2 and you know independently.
Okay.
So um
so
what would we expect
pi p characteristic function at a what
would we how would we expect this to
behave?
So this is the number of n uh from one
up to n. So that n= a mod p and n is in
capital a
and each one of those candidates was
chosen with probability a half.
Okay. So,
so the expected value over our choice of
a so over the random choice of this set
a of pi p1 a little a would be half of
the number of guys here.
So that's essentially um half of n over
p.
Okay.
But um well you you wouldn't necessarily
expect this number to be exactly n over
2p every time. If we choose randomly
you'll see some ups and downs. Um and um
uh
um so the standard deviation of the
number that gets picked here would be
the square root of the size of this.
We also would see
that with high probability
the size of the actual size of the
projection minus
the approximate size
would be bounded by like the square root
of the um of of this
um and it typ typically would have size
around this square root.
Okay. So for example
uh if if p is in capital p n to the 12
then the actual size of the projection
minus its expected size would be around
n to the
Okay.
So let's compare this with what our what
our what our theorem says about an
arbitrary set.
Um
so so what we concluded is for every P
in here and for every A in C mod P
we would have this. So if we took a
random set um and then for every P and
every A
the difference between the actual size
of the projection and its expected size
would be a square root of the of the
number of choices which would work out
to n^ the 1/4.
We're going to compare this to um what
what our large civ tells us about an
arbitrary set.
Any questions or comments about the
reference setup?
So corollary three. So a is any um a is
any subset of numbers up to n.
Then um
if I take the average
over primes of size around n to the half
um and then I take the average over a z
mod p. I take the actual size pi p 1 a
and I subtract off the expected size. um
a over a over p.
So this is this is what so we have this
many elements and we reduce them all mod
p. I would expect on average that this
number of them would be congruent to
little a mod b.
So then this is bounded by n to the one
and this matches this
Okay.
Um, so
so the proof is uh coropy down what
corlary one tells us and it basically
tells us this.
So we're going to plug in corlary one
where um p is pn
um where where m is n to the 12. that
will make this disappear.
and cor so corlary one tells us that the
average
p and pn to the half sum a and z mod p
of pi p1 a of a minus a over p^ 2 um is
bounded by the l2 norm of f which would
be the size of a
Okay. Um, and that's smaller than n.
Then if I want to replace this average,
this sum by an average,
then I'm going to divide by p, which has
size around n^ the 1/2. So I replace the
sum by the average. Then this is bounded
by n^ the 1/2.
And there's a square here. So I want to
get rid of the square. I would use Koshy
Schwarz. Get the average on P, average
on A.
Get rid of this.
So that's the proof of the coral.
Okay. Um
so so the large civ is telling us that
if you look at a residue class with a
random P and a random A
then it behaves a so you take an
arbitrary set a worst case complicated
any set at all but then you look at a
random residue class with a random P and
a random A then it behaves a lot like
you had taken a random set.
Um, okay. So, a cute application of this
is if a is the set of primes and there's
a fun question as a interesting question
in number theory. How many primes are
there in some arithmetic progression?
Um,
so that that's exactly this thing. A is
the set of primes and this is telling us
how many primes there are that are
congruent to A modulo little B.
Um and um
and
so the question is how evenly
distributed are the primes among these
different arithmetic progressions? And
the conjecture would be that for every
little p and every little a that's not
zero, this is always true.
Um, and this corlary actually makes some
progress towards that. It says we don't
know that it's true for all the little
P's and all the little A's, but we know
it's true for most of them.
Now, it's a little bit silly to call
that a correlary about about the primes
because it uses nothing about the
primes. It just uses the fact that the
primes are a set of numbers. Um but um
uh okay but but that line of reasoning
is actually important in some of the
some of the things we know about the
questions how well are primes
distributed modulo p okay okay so next
class we'll come back to the question um
how much do we know about uh about this
function when a is the set of primes um
and we'll do the the bombiier venogradov
theorem which is not quite the
state-of-the-art but for many many years
was the state-of-the-art about about
this question. Um
and well yeah any it uses these ideas in
a crucial way.
Okay. So that was my survey of some
applications of this large civ
inequality and next we'll prove the
large civ inequality itself.
Oh, there's actually there was one other
thing I wanted to say. So, okay. So,
imagine that a was a set of size n /2.
Then,
um this thing here
would have size about n over p which
works out to about n^ the 1/2 and this
thing has size about n to the one half
and the error is about n to the one
quarter. So this thing here is the pi pi
p of f sub0.
And so what what we're seeing here is
that the um the pi p of f0
is much larger than pi p of f high at
most of the points. So say in L2.
So when we we take a set of size n /2
and we look at all these different
projections, a typical projection looks
almost constant. it's a constant
function plus something that's much
smaller.
Um, so this process of taking a random
function takes a set with with no
structure and it produces something
that's almost constant. And people
sometimes use the word that the
projections are getting uh smoother. And
when we do the real analysis version a
little bit later in class, we'll see
that smoother is is exactly the the
right word.
Cool. Okay. Um yeah so I think that's a
good way to summarize what the largest
div is telling us it says if we take a
set A which is a pretty decent fraction
of the numbers from one to n and then
when we look at all the projections of
it most of those projections are almost
constant
and that's relevant for this question up
here because um you know if we
hypothesize that pi subp of a is has
size smaller than.99 of p that's telling
us the projection is really not very
constant
And that's only possible for small sets.
So that's where we get that upper bound
on the size of a. If a was bigger than
that, then it would start to be the case
that the projections of A would have
pretty would would look pretty constant
and it would then it would be impossible
that the support would be that small.
>> Yeah.
>> What does P tell the capital P to the 12
mean?
What does
>> under the average
>> this one
>> oh sorry that's P in so capital P n to
the half is the set of primes of size
about n to the half and this is this
prime is one of them yeah thanks for
thanks
okay
so next um let's prove Linux theorem
[Applause]
Um so the proof of Linux theorem is
based on the forier transform. So we're
going to take the fora transform of all
of these characters and then we're going
to see how the different fora transforms
are related to each other.
Um so first let me remind you how the
for a transform works for uh functions
on the integers and functions on z mod
p.
So f is going to be a think of it as a
function on the integers which is
supported in in this set one of tan
and so if I take its fora transform what
does that mean the for transform is
going to be a function on r mod z and
it's defined by f of c is the sum on n f
of n eus 2 pi i c do n c that's the for
transform
And it has a forier inversion and it has
a planter route. And they go like this.
Forier inversion.
It tells us that
f of n is the integral from 0 to 1 f of
c e 2 pi i cn dx.
And there's a planer.
And it tells us that the sum on n of f
of n^2 is the integral from 0 to 1 norm
of fat x c^2 dx.
Okay. So this is probably most familiar
backwards from the way I've written it.
If you started with a function on r modz
z a periodic function you would take its
forier series and if you sum the forier
series you get the function. This is the
same thing. We've just chosen to label
the for a series by f and the uh
function on the circle by fhat.
Okay. And then
we will also have a function on z mod p.
So suppose I have a function z mod p
goes to c. Then its fora transform will
also be a function z mod p goes to c.
And the definition is ghat of uh alpha.
So I'll say that this variable is called
a and this variable is called alpha. So
ghat of alpha will be the sum a and z
mod p g of a eus 2 pi i a alpha over p.
And then we have fora inversion
which tells us that g of a can be
recovered as 1 / p sum alpha and z mod p
ghat of alpha e to the 2 pi i a alpha
over p
and uh and planer
that tells us that the sum on a norm of
g of a^ 2 is 1 / p * the sum on alpha
norm of g of alpha square.
Okay, so that's how the for transforms
works for each of these worlds.
And now we're going to put it together.
So if I start with a function on the
integers, I reduce it mod p to get a
function on z mod p. How does this for a
transform relate to this for a
transform? Okay.
[Applause]
Okay.
So, lama I'll call this lama dictionary.
This is a dictionary between the integer
world and the mod p world. And it says
that if I take pi p of f hat of alpha
that is fhat of alpha and vp.
Okay the proof is just unwinding the
definitions of what all these for
transforms mean. So what does it mean pi
pfhat of alpha? Pi PF hat of alpha
that's the sum a and z mod pi
pf of a e - 2i i a alpha over p
okay now who is pi pf of a
sum a and z mod p open parenthesis sum
n= a mod p of f of n
e - 2i i a alpha.
All right. Now, if you look at this
double sum,
we're just summing over all the x.
And now let's look at the thing that
we're summing.
So
uh n= a mod p that tells us that e to
the - 2i i n alpha / p is the same
as e - 2 pi i a alpha p.
Why? I have different ns that are
congruent to a mod p. So I think of
adding a multiple of p to this n. that
multiple of P the P cancels with that P.
So we're changing this by an integer and
it doesn't change the value of of it.
Okay,
so this is just the sum over n f of n e
to the - 2 pi i n alpha p.
Cool.
Um, another little remark, this is
something we basically saw last time
that if you take the high part of pi p
of f and it's l2 norm squared. If you
take the high part of it, what it means
is that we removed the zero frequency.
So I guess I'll also call this a lema,
but it's very similar to things we've
already proved.
So pi pfi
L2 squared is the sum on the nonzero
alphas.
Okay.
Um, so,
so now we have a way of writing. So,
let's look at the theorem we want to
prove. We're going to take a sum over
different ps of the L2 norms of the high
parts of pi p of f.
These lemas give us a way of writing
that and translating it into a sum that
involves the for transform of f.
Yeah, I guess one last remark is um
so so pi p of f hat of alpha is fhat of
alpha over p that's for any function f
and so if I were to take pi p of f high
hat of alpha that would be fi hat alpha
Okay. So now let's let's write out the
left hand side of Linux theorem using 4A
using the 4A transform.
Okay.
Um, so the left hand side of our
theorem, I'll just copy it. The sum p in
primes of size m
pi p of f high part l2 squ.
Okay.
So that's now some pinp
on the nonzero alpha n cp
um
pi p of fi hat of alpha squared
which is equal to some p of pm
some alpha not equal to zero np
of fi fi hat of alpha over p
norm
cool. Okay, so we're taking the 4A
transform of the high part of f and
evaluating it at a set of points norm
squared and adding them all up. Uh let's
visualize that set of points.
So let's say qm is the set of uh alpha
over p where p is a prime of size around
m and alpha
is strictly positive and less than or
equal to p minus one.
Okay, so um the size of qm is roughly m
squ. So we mentioned before how many
choices are there for this prime p? It's
about m over log m which is roughly m.
And then for each prime there are
basically p choices of alpha which is
also around m. They're roughly m squ of
these um quotients.
Um and an important fact about these
quotients is that they're distributed
quite evenly on the real line. So
they're about m^ squ of them and the
distance between any two of them is at
least m^2.
So here's a lema.
Um, if alpha 1 over p1 and alpha 2 over
p2 are in qm and they're not equal to
each other,
then the distance between them
is at least 1 / m^2.
Okay, proof. Um, we're just going to put
it over a common denominator.
Alpha 1 P1 Alpha 1 over P1
minus Alpha 2 over P2
is alpha 1 P2 minus alpha 2 P1 over P1
P2
by assumption there the difference is
not zero um and so this numerator is not
zero um and so this it's an integer so
it has norm at least
some say at least that big.
Okay. Um I guess to be careful I should
also say that if you know if P1 is
different from P2 then these two are
never equal to each other.
So we never so the importance of making
these primes is that um we never have
the same number written as a fraction in
two different ways here.
So let's also make the remark
that um
uh
if alpha 1 over p1 equals alpha 2 over
p2 um in qm
then it must be that alpha 1 equals
alpha 2 and p1 equals p2.
Okay. Um,
cool.
[Applause]
All right.
So, I'm going to erase the dictionary
lema and I'll make a picture of this set
and of what we're what we're doing.
Okay,
here's a picture.
So, here's the line from 0 to one. And
on this line we have this set Q subm
which is maybe not quite that evenly
spaced but it's it's quite evenly
spaced. So that's Q sub.
Okay. And then we have we're interested
in the uh our formula involves the the
norm of squared of the 4A transform of
f.
Let me put that on this axis.
Okay. So, um, so this will look however
it looks.
Okay. We'll talk about this a little bit
more.
All right.
So what what we're taking in that sum is
we're finding the actual values at these
points and we're adding them up.
And this sum might remind you a little
bit of a remon sum that would help to
give an approximation of this integral.
And indeed we're going to compare this
sum to this integral.
Um,
okay. Now, there is a way that the sum
could be a lot bigger than the integral,
which is a narrow peak like this. You
know, if if the function is very big at
this one point, but the peak is
extremely narrow, then it wouldn't
contribute much to the integral, but
it's still there as part of our sum. So,
it's important to know sort of how
narrow a peak like this can be. And the
heristic
which is similar to heristic we've
talked about before is that the function
fi hat of c is roughly constant
on intervals of length 1 / n
because remember that f is supported on
the numbers from 1 to n.
Okay. So we'll make this precise in a
moment. Uh so I'll draw in what it means
that this peak here should have width at
least 1 / n.
Okay. And I'll also make a remark that
um m is less than or equal to n^ the 12.
That's one of the hypotheses in in Linux
theorem.
And so that guarantees
that the spacing between consecutive
points of QM
is smaller than this one overn.
So the picture is sort of right that you
know this 1 / n is smaller than the
distance between the different points of
Q.
Okay. So this is just a heristic but
let's follow it for now and we'll see
that it basically gives the inequality
that we want and then we can come back
and prove things rigorously.
Okay. So the heristic tells us
that um
the sum
c and qm
fi hat of c^ squared
um
is bounded by
n times the integral from 0 to 1
fat high x^2
y. So take a one term of this sum say
from this point that one term is bounded
by n times the integral on this um
interval around here of of side with 1 /
n
which is a piece of this integral.
Okay.
Okay. Okay. So, the rest is just
algebra. And it's a little bit um
annoying to get all of the constants
right in the algebra, all the exponents
right. And in fact, I have already
messed it up a little bit.
So if we go back here, um the left hand
side of the theorem is indeed this sum.
I would just copied that correctly. Um
and then for the sum, I did planer. But
when you do planer mod p there's this
factor of one over p that I forget
frequently. So there's a one over p
there. Now the one over p the p has size
about m. This is around 1 / m *
all right. So the left hand side of the
theorem is actually around 1 / m * this
sum over here. So that would be bounded
by n / m * this integral
and then we use plan again and this time
there's no factor that I have trouble
remembering. So that's n / m sum n f of
n^2.
Okay. So this is the lin theorem.
Okay.
Yeah, let me mention in this picture uh
so we had this theme that if you you
take one function and you reduce it mod
p for many different ps most of them are
almost constant.
So why the constant frequency is special
compared to all the other frequencies in
this story?
Okay. Um so
um so let me shade in for one particular
prime the frequencies alpha over p.
So that would be frequencies alpha over
p1 alpha and zp1.
Let me do it for another prime.
So, and the color blue, I'll draw alpha
over P2.
Alpha and Z mod P2.
What would that look like? Well,
crucially, it would still have zero,
but all the other ones would be
different.
Okay. So now imagine doing this with all
the different primes in our set of
primes. P subm I would get a whole
rainbow of different stuff. Zero would
be in every color. But other than that
each point is only one color. There are
no other overlaps.
Okay. Now fhat can be distributed
anyway. We've assumed nothing about the
function f except that it's supported
from one to n. So we know nothing about
its fora transform except for this
heristic.
So fhat could look like anything
but um
well most of the places that you put
fhat. So okay so one thing we do know is
let's say we know the sum of f the L2
norm of f. So we know the L2 norm of
fhat.
If you stick some mass of L2 norm of
fhat over this point, it will contribute
to this one prime but none of the
others.
But if you stick some mass over zero, it
will contribute to everybody.
So zero frequency is being counted very
differently from any other frequency.
Every other frequency only contributes
to one prime, but the zero frequency
contributes to all primes.
Okay. So therefore, if you if I start
with my function f, if it has a decent
amount in the zero frequency, then all
the different ps also will see a decent
amount in the zero frequency.
And then my function may have a bunch of
other frequencies, but each one of them
is only contributing to one prime. So
kind of uh if I average over all the
primes, those get damped down a lot
compared to the zero frequency.
So that's what's go that's a
possible a possible intuition about
what's going on in the large s.
Okay. So the last thing to uh to round
out our proof of the large s is we'll
actually rigorously prove this heristic.
Um any questions or comments before we
do that?
Well, it seems like we have more freedom
to choose f here than in the like
reality.
We always just choose fing.
>> Yeah. So the question is um do we do we
choose f? So here f doesn't have to be
the characteristic function of a set.
We've often talked about f being the
characteristic function of a set. What's
up with that? Um
uh we'll also do something at the end of
class we'll mention something in the
real setting where f doesn't have to be
a characteristic function. Um so
yeah so there so there are there are
some theorems that become interesting
where f is a is a characteristic
function of kind of a sparse set and
that sparity comes into play. Um and
there are others where f could just be
anything there.
They're both they're all part of the
theory.
Okay.
Um
So this heristic, this locally constant
heristic is similar to the one that's on
the homework that you're thinking
through that's due tonight. And by the
way, there are office hours after the
class for anybody who would like to talk
about that or anything else. Um so yeah.
Okay. So I'll also prove this in class.
Um and um yeah. All right.
So how does it work?
I'm gonna choose a function CN. It's a
function Z to C. So that CN of little N
is one if N is an integer from 1 to N.
And CN is also um smooth and rapidly
decaying.
Okay.
Um so then when I take the fora
transform of CN behaves like this
so it's around n if the frequency c has
size less than 1 / n and then it's
rapidly decaying.
So in pictures, so C is only well
defined modulo one. And in this context,
it's nice to draw the modulo one as
going from negative a half to positive a
half. Here's zero.
So this axis has the norm of CN C. This
is N. And this distance here is one N.
That's what it looks like.
Okay. And rapidly decaying could mean
rigorously
n*
c * n. So once c is bigger than 1 / n,
this thing starts to be bigger than one
and kick in. And we could throw in that.
>> Yeah.
>> What does smoothness mean for a map from
the integers?
>> Yeah. What does smoothness mean? Um,
>> right. Um you you could think of C as a
map that's defined on the whole real
line and it's smooth on the whole real
line and then we happen to be evaluating
it at the integers.
Okay.
Um okay. Now this is helpful because
f is equal to f * cn.
If so, if the support of f is contained
in integers up to n.
Um and then when we take the for
transform we get that f hat is f hat
convolved with cn hat.
And so in particular um so fhat at a
particular frequency of v is c is fhat
convolved with cn
c. Chat looks like that.
And so the norm of fhat is bounded by
the norm of fhat convolved with cn hat.
And also the norm of fhat squared is
bounded by the norm of fhat squared
convolved with cn hat by koshi schwarz.
So what actually one feature of this
formula is that the integral of cn hat
xc dx c is bounded by one.
It has height one and it has width
height n and width one n.
>> Sorry. So head is the for transform of S
in the sense of real function and
or is the form in the sense of
>> okay yeah there's a good question
there's a good question okay so um
all right so there's so I originally
said is a function on the integers But
in answer to the question, what does it
mean to be smooth? I said we should also
think of it as a function on the real
line. So I'll call them SN integers
that's our function on the integers and
P n real line that's a function on the
real
and they each have a fora transform
s on the integers hat of c is the sum
over integers s n of n eus 2 pi i n c
and s n if you think of it as a real
valued function It has a 4A transform
and XC that's defined to be the integral
over the real line s of x e - 2 iix
xc dx
okay so the question was um when I write
n hat which one of these two things do I
mean
okay so I mean this one but they're
equal to each other so the
summation theorem
says that
C and Z hat is equal to of C
is equal to
right is that right
wait
so these are closely related
for a
Yeah. So this guy is the sum uh Z and Z
of C and R hat of C plus Z.
Okay.
Um, so we should make two pictures
in yellow. I will draw C and R hat.
Let's extend this.
It looks basically the same.
And then it gets really small
and it stays really small.
And
what does so in blue I'll do at z hat.
It looks really almost the same
except
this one is periodic. This 4A transform
is defined on R modulo Z. So it's going
to be periodic Z periodic. So then here
at minus one,
it's going to go up again. So there's
going to be an identical copy. The blue
one is Z periodic.
Okay. Um so if you compare so then if
you know if you look at this formula it
is also it's taking this function and
turning it into a z periodic function by
periodizing it and since this function
originally was extremely localized to
between minus a half and a half. It
almost looks like I took the yellow
function and I just took copies of it
and put them here.
Um so the you know the the the copy over
here can
Yeah. Sorry. Okay.
Anyway, so that's what that's what this
one that's what this one looks like and
what this one looks like.
Okay. Um so to prove this estimate first
you prove it for C and R and you can do
that using rate for analysis over R and
you use the smoothness and you integrate
by parts many times
and then to study the one over Z you use
this formula and because this guy is
decaying so rapidly the contribution
from the so if C if if if this C is
between minus a half and a half then the
contribution coming from integer Z other
than zero is incredibly small.
Anyway, so so the bounds for this one
you use to give bounds for this one.
Okay, thanks for those questions
everybody. That was helpful.
[Applause]
Okay.
So now we're going to do a slightly more
rigorous version of this argument.
So rigorous proof.
So the left hand side we decided was
around 1 / m times the sum over the
frequencies in qm
of
f fi of c norm squ. That part was
rigorous before. We didn't need to make
it rigorous. But now we need to relate
this sum to an integral
and we use this fact here. This fact
encodes the idea that this quantity is
locally constant at the scale 1 / n.
So this is bounded by 1 / m
sum c and qm of the integral
f^ 2 of um
omega time cnhat
of c minus omega.
So this is just writing out the
convolution as an integral.
Now we can bring this sum inside.
So this is 1 / m integral
fi hat of omega^ 2 times the sum over c
in qm
of
cn hat of c minus omega omega.
Okay. And this sum we can bound by n.
Why? Because each each term in the sum
has size at least around n. This term is
a bump essentially a bump of height n
and width 1 /n around c. And the
distance between any two different is at
least one overn. So those bumps don't
overlap with each other.
Now the bumps aren't quite compactly
supported. They have the the tails that
you can see in the picture, but the
tails are incredibly tiny. And so if you
just plug in the rapidly decaying bound,
the tails don't contribute anything and
you get this bound.
Okay. Then if you take out this n, you
have what we had before.
n / m integral from 0 to 1 f^ 2 c
uh
n / m
sum f of n squ
and that's the proof of of linux Good
stuff.
So, we only have a little bit of time
left, about five minutes. Um
in
e we could either if people have things
you want to talk about we could just
talk for five minutes
or I could set up the next thing and try
to try to give a feeling of how
something in real real variable setting
is analogous to this thing in a kind of
number theoretic
Okay. So, I I give a little try to give
a little teaser preview foreshadowing of
how the same idea occurs in real
analysis. I want to keep this picture
[Applause]
Okay. So the the um the thing that we
proved is if you have a function on the
integers from one to n then when you
project it mod p most of the projections
look almost constant. They look smoother
than the original function. And there's
a totally analogous phenomenon in R to
the D. If you have a function on R to
the D and you consider projections onto
lower dimensional subspaces, then almost
all of them look smoother than the
original function. And like we mentioned
on the first day, if you're in high
enough dimension, if you take a a
function and you project it onto a
typical line, even if the initial
function is only in L2 and is nowhere
continuous, the on a typical line, the
projection will be continuous and even
C1 and even C2, right? So the
projections are much smoother than the
original function.
Okay, so uh here is a setup for this
that's kind of analogous to the large
sip. we have a function on R to the D
and then we'll have V contained in R to
the D which is a subspace.
Um and if if you have a function so so
pi V of F is the projection of F onto
this plane. So that's a function from V
to C.
Okay. So now I have a remark that if you
have any function of this vector space V
then it's for a transform is also
defined on the vector space V.
Okay. And there's a dictionary lama.
How is the 4A transform of the
projection related to the 4A transform
of the original function? And it says
that um
pi v of f hat
uh is just fhat restricted to v.
So this is a function on the vector
space v. It's for a transform is
supposed to be a function on the vector
space v.
fhat is a function on r to the d. But
this for transform is just fhat
restricted to that to v.
Okay. So now make a picture. Um
uh so here is r to the d and inside of
there
there's a space v1 and there's another
space
uh v2.
Whoops. And okay. And I let you imagine
other ones. They're all subspaces. So
they all go through zero. Although my
picture was not perfect.
And I want you to imagine this as 4A
space.
So we have a function f. F is just an
L2.
Uh say it's an L2 function on the unit
ball. So its 4A transform could be
anywhere here.
Um and all we know about it is say say
we know the L2 norm of f. So we know the
L2 norm of fhat could be anywhere. If
you happen to put some L2 norm of fhat
near zero then that will be part of the
for transform of pi v for all the
different v's.
But if you put some of the l2 mass of
fhat over here that will contribute to
pi v1 but it won't contribute to most of
the other pi vs.
Um so therefore uh when you take a
random projection the part of the for
transform at low frequencies is uh kind
of more highly represented and the part
at high frequencies is less highly
represented.
So a typical projection so initially the
for transform could have been anywhere
but then a typical projection will now
have its fora transform concentrated at
low frequencies which makes it look
smooth.
Okay. So here's a statement like that
that we will prove next time by the
analogous reasoning.
theorem.
If f is an L2 function on R to the D
supported in the unit ball
and if D is big enough
um then
for almost every so then um if I take
the average over theta in the d minus
one sphere
of um pi theta of f. So this means I
take f and I project it onto the line in
the theta direction.
The ck norm of that is bounded by the L2
norm of fition.
[Applause]
Okay. And so the to so we'll prove that
next time but to end I just wanted to
have everyone look at the analogy
between these two pictures. So in fora
space when we project our function onto
different um subspaces then that we have
these different uh pieces of the fora
transform that we're seeing and in for a
space in the large civ when we take our
function and we project it mod p for
different p we have these different
color pieces of the 4 a space that we're
seeing and the different color pieces
intersect at zero
and they don't intersect anywhere
or they don't intersect very much
anywhere else.
And that has the effect that when you
take the projections, it emphasizes the
zero frequency or the low frequency.
And and that plays out slight in
slightly different ways in the different
settings, but but morally very similar.
Okay, cool. So, let's stop there for
today. I will hang out afterwards and
office hour, make office hours talk. Um,
and I will see you next week.