All right. Well, we have two more
classes and this is uh day two of trying
to grapple with the recent big
breakthrough in projection theory. So,
this is sharp projection theorems part
two. And in part two we're going to talk
about the ad regular case. So let's
first remember our goal and remember
what is the ad regular case.
Okay.
So our goal is the first set conjecture
which is a theorem of Orpin and Schmurk
and Ren and W says if E contained in R2
is a delta T C set
and then for every point in E there are
a bunch of delta tubes going through it.
So t subx is a set of delta tubes
through x
and the the directions if you like of
this set of delta tubes is a delta s c
set.
Okay. And parenthetically we can assume
a couple of things. uh we can assume
that this is uh is uniform
and also that the number of them it's
like delta to the minus s and s should
be bigger than zero.
Okay, so we put all of these tubes
together to get one big set of tubes
and the question is how many tubes are
there?
Um so then the conclusion is
that the number of tubes is at least a
little fudge factor.
So this whole thing I'll abbreviate like
that and then the minimum of a few
options
which we'll call option A, option B and
option C.
Okay. And these exponents are hard to
remember, but I would prefer to remember
for everyone to think of them in terms
of three different scenarios.
So option A that corresponds to the I
call it the stars scenario. Have a bunch
of points and through each you have a
bunch of tubes and they're just
unrelated to each other.
Option B is more intricate. It's the
integer grid scenario.
Um and option C is a kind of random
scenario. So E is arbitrary
and T is random.
Okay. Um
now it's it's really a good idea to
think about this theorem in these three
different scenarios. So it's good to
separate out the case where each one of
those things is the minimum. Um, so let
me do that and recall for you how much
we know about each case so far.
Um, and I said something about this last
time, but what I said wasn't uh the best
thing to say. So I wanted to do it again
and get it right.
All right. So there's the case where a
is the minimum option. And if you do a
little algebra that corresponds to s
being at least as big as t.
Um and in this case
so if s is at least as big as t then the
uh the theorem is is true the first so
first is is true
and it follows just by double counting.
So we did it very early in the course
like on the second one.
Okay. Then I'll come back to B which is
the most interesting. C is the minimal.
If you do a little algebra it's if S
plus T is at least two.
Um and in this whole range where S plus
T is at least two the theorem is is also
true true and it's true by the forier
method. So it follows from the theorem
we proved in the second or third week
using for a analysis. So the whole case
where C is minimal uh we we also already
understand that
okay and that leaves a case where B is
minimal and that's like otherwise if
neither of these things are true then B
is minimal and um and so that's that's
the content of this theorem. So this is
the hard new thing
in the uh OSRW thing.
Okay,
cool.
Another little comment is that the the
number of tubes is not my favorite
parameter to keep track of. Um, my
favorite parameter to keep track of is
I'll call it R
of of ET,
[Applause]
which in words is like the typical
number
of delta balls
of E on a typical tube of T.
Um so let's make a uh
let's make a picture. Um so we have some
delta balls and then we have some delta
tubes going through them
and in in an interesting scenario each
tube will have many balls in it and r is
this number of balls in a tube. Okay.
So algebraically
by double counting
number of balls in a tube would be the
number of points times the number of
tubes going through a point divided by
uh the number of tubes. So that would be
the algebraic definition of r. And then
it's easy to convert bounds for t into
bounds for r. So our theorem is
equivalent to
um that r is upper bounded by the
maximum of three things. Scenario one is
a. So scenario one the number of balls
per tube is one which is always easy to
arrange.
Uh b you have to do a little
computation. It works out to this.
I don't really care what the exponent.
It's not important what the exponents
are. And C is delta to the uh t + one.
Okay. And this delta to the t + one has
a nice interpretation which might
clarify a little bit what we mean by
this random case. So if um e is a set is
a delta tc set. So the size of e is
delta to the minus t. Uh let me say it
this way. Suppose that E
is a set of delta to the minus T delta
balls in the unit ball.
And then I take the average over any
choice of delta by one rectangles of um
the number of delta balls that the
rectangle covers. You would get delta to
the minus t + 1.
So it's not difficult to locate
rectangles with that richness. Almost
any rectangle would do the job. And
scenario C is when the rectangles just
have this average richness. There's
really nothing special about them.
Okay. So next let's remember. So their
goal today is to talk about the ad
regular case. So let's remember what
what is the ad regular case.
Okay. So we're going to suppose
that E is uniform.
So that means that our delta is some um
capital delta to the m where m is a
large number
and the uniformity is that if I take e
and I intersect it with a cube of side
length delta to the j and I ask about
its delta to the j + one covering number
that's around some uh beta j
for all the iatic
Q delta J um that intersect E.
Okay, so these beta J are the branching
numbers. We drew pictures last time to
illustrate what they mean. Um and so
definition would be that E is C L4 is to
be regular. So actually let's say it's a
delta t c a d regular set
f um has a this branching structure like
above and um if I take the product j = 1
to capital j of beta j. So that would be
the delta j covering number delta to the
j covering number of our set.
um
it is at most C * delta to the J to the
minus T and it is at least 1 / C * delta
to the J to the minus T.
Okay.
All right.
So, let's label all these hypotheses in
our theorem by each our hypothesis.
And what we'd like to understand is
given these hypotheses, how big could R
be?
And for for today we're going to talk
about the AD regular case. So let's give
that a name. So R A D of S T delta C
that is the maximum
over E and T obey our hypothesis
and E is a
delta T C a d regular
of R of E and T. How big could it be in
in this case?
Okay, there's really a mouthful of
parameters. So, let me just say to uh
reduce a little bit for today, we'll
have C equals 1. Um so, that means it's
you know really ad regular and
everything we say actually um will work
for small C that are bigger than
that will allow us to not write the
letter C. And then s and t will not be
changing through our arguments. So I
won't write them every time. So now I'll
just abbreviate it
as r a d of dot.
Okay.
All right. So um
so the theorem that orbit and smirkin
proved is that they they proved this
thing in the ad case. So r a d s delta
is indeed bounded by
that.
I'm not sure I computed right.
Got the minus signs wrong.
So that's our goal for today is to
understand this theorem which is a
really important special case of that
theorem.
Cool.
So maybe so it's clearly a special case
of that theorem. Um and at first it
might seem like a very special case
because these branching function
basically there's a huge range of what
the branching function could be and ad
regular is just one particular choice in
this huge range but it's a particularly
important case and we'll see tomorrow or
next class that that this is really a
crucial case plays a big role in
understanding the theorem in general.
Okay,
cool. Um, yeah. So, so it was a really
it was a really important realization in
thinking about this theorem that we
should break it into cases. The
different cases have their different
things that are useful and their
different things that are difficult um
and um and and so that recognition is is
key. So the next thing I want to try to
talk about is like what is special about
ad regular sets that we could use to to
get a handle on them um that we couldn't
use just for the for the general setup.
All right.
Okay. So this proof is is quite
difficult. We won't do all of it, but I
would like to share some key ideas about
it which I think are really cool and and
are like sort of worth taking with you
away from this class.
All right.
Okay, so in a nutshell, the important
special thing about ad regular sets is
in this lema that has a one board proof
which is called the sub multiplicative
lema.
Okay, so it says that RA a delta, let me
put it this way. If delta is delta 1 *
delta 2, then RA a delta is bounded by
with a little bit of fudge RA a delta 1
time ra
delta 2.
It is sub multiplicative.
Okay.
and
it follows from understanding thinking a
lot about a picture of an ad regular
set.
Okay. So
remember that E is a set of delta balls
and T is a set of delta tubes and we're
going to imagine thickening them.
So, so in this setup here, um, delta is
smaller than delta 1 and delta 2, which
are smaller than one. So, delta 1 and
delta 2 are each bigger than delta. So,
I'm going to thicken them, and I'll get
E1,
I'll call it, which are the delta 1
balls around E, and T1, which are delta
1 tools.
All right. So, what does it look like?
Let's think about E and thickening E.
So here is E1 is this bunch of circles.
Each circle has radius delta 1
and inside of those circles there are
some delta balls
and those guys are my delta balls E.
Okay. Now,
um, T1 are some delta 1 tubes.
So, they might look sort of like this.
Let's put one more ball up here.
That looks like that. So, those are my
fat tubes. T1
Um and then there are inside of them
there are some delta tubes T2
that um
there are too many but I'll try to give
some idea. So,
so through this point here,
there might be a couple of red tubes
that are inside of that orange tube. And
then there might be a couple of red
tubes
that are inside of that orange tube.
Okay? And I just drew the ones through
this point. Experience has taught me
that if I draw more, this picture will
get too messy. But you should imagine
that this is happening at every point.
Okay.
So
first observation is that E1 and T1 obey
the hypothesis of our theorem
because actually if so if you take a
delta t set of balls and you thicken
them up to radius delta 1, you get a
delta onet set of balls
at least if because if it's uniform
and um if you Look at who's going
through this point. Uh we have a delta s
set of directions leaving that point.
And if you thicken them up a little bit,
you get um the directions corresponding
to the orange tubes. And that will be a
delta 1 s set of directions.
Okay,
great. Um then
yeah. Okay, so
let let me put the punch line and then
we'll think through why this works.
So R A D of delta that's the number of
white balls in a red tube, but that's
bounded by the number of delta 1 balls
in a delta 1 tube.
Right? So I look in this orange tube, I
see how many of these balls there are
times
the number of delta balls
in a delta tube within
one delta 1 bar.
So if I'm looking at this at this red
tube here, I want to know how many delta
balls are in it. It's bounded by the
number of big balls that it enters
times the number of little balls in each
of the big balls.
Okay. So, we'd like to relate these two
things to our problem at a coarser
scale.
And this one here well E1 and T1 obey
our hypothesis. So this this one here is
bounded by RA a D of delta 1.
Now here
if you take E and T and you restrict
them
to a delta 1 ball
and then you magnify it to bring it up
to scale one. Um this also obeys our
hypothesis.
So if you look inside of here, you see a
little delta TC sat a little a little uh
you know this this this
and and these red tubes. That's the same
situation on a smaller scale or on a
coarser scale. So when you when you blow
this up um uh if you blow it up then you
get delta 2 balls
and delta 2 tubes
in the unit ball.
So this guy is bounded by the uh ra of
delta 2.
Okay, I'm going call this claim one and
claim two.
All right,
so this picture is perhaps the most
important thing uh to take away from
this proof and this class. So take a
moment and see if you have questions
about this proof.
ready to verify.
>> Yeah. Okay. So the question is do we
need to check that everything is ad
regular? Yeah. Okay. So let me add to
these claims and then if we want to
we'll we'll prove we can add details to
the proof of these claims. E E1 and T1
obey the hypothesis and they're ad
regular. And we need that this blow up
here obeys the hypothesis and it's ad
regular. And if you believe those two
things, then you can plug you just plug
in and you get that.
Yeah. And we we can talk a little bit
more about those two things if you want.
Are there other questions or comments?
Okay. So, I'll probably add a little
more, but actually I wanted to ask you
all a question. Um, in this argument,
where did we take advantage of the fact
that the original E was ad regular?
Yeah. Jonathan,
>> is it like picking one delta one ball
and magnifying it?
>> Yeah. So, it's related to when we picked
this one delta 1 ball and magnified it.
Yeah. So, so let's talk about one and
two a little more carefully. Um,
all right.
So let's discuss
one and two. Okay. So point one if e and
tx are uniform which we can pretty much
assume in the which we can assume from
the beginning with a little pruning
um then um
e delta t implies that e1 is delta1 t
and
tx
um
delta s implies that t1x
is is delta 1x.
Okay. And also uh if E is ad regular
it implies that E1 is AD regular
because this is saying all the branching
numbers of E are the same as each other
and this is saying that all the
branching numbers of E down to the depth
of delta 1 are the same as each other.
Okay,
we didn't need E to be ad regular to do
this or this,
but it comes in in part two. So
because E is a deregular
then we get that if you take E and you
intersect it with a small ball and
magnify it
then this is uh a delta I guess delta 2
t and a d regular.
So let me illustrate this with pictures
instead of equations. So what does it
look like? Let's draw an ad regular set
and a not regular set and we'll look at
both of them. Okay. So if E is ad
regular
what I do
I pick say four of them.
Let me do this in the color.
Okay. Then for each one that I picked, I
subdivide it
uh and I pick four of them.
Okay, I'll stop drawing. You get the
idea, right? Okay, now this is a self
similar construction. If I take this
thing in here and I blow it up, it's
just like what I started with. So it
will be a dere regular and it will be in
particular a delta it will be a a delta
t set for the appropriate delta.
Okay what would it look like if e was
not a d regular?
Well,
for example,
I might do the following thing. Might
cut it into a 4x4 grid. And I might take
all of the boxes. And then I could cut
each of each one of them into a 4x4 grid
and pick just one box.
So this was the, you know, the well
spaced example that we drew last time.
Okay. So this whole thing is a delta t
set. But if I took just one of these
boxes, what I would see is much more
concentrated. This is not a delta t set.
So if I were to take this guy
and take it out here and magnify it,
then inside of here, I would just see
this. This here is a blank T set. But
this here is not a blank T- set.
Whereas in the AD regular case, if I
were to take one of these and bring it
out and magnify it, then what I would
see in here would be very similar to the
original set. This is um
similar to B. So this here is a
blank T set and it's a dregular. And
that thing in there is still a blank T
set and it's still ad regular.
Okay, so this is the special feature of
ad regular. The word regular refers to
the fact that all the different scales
look the same. And so when we uh look
inside this ball here, we have another
example of our original problem at a
coarser scale. And that feeds into an
inductive argument and we can say for
example we can say this sub
multiplicative lema.
>> Yeah first inequality over there do you
need some sort of uniformity on the
number of
cuz like the average and you're saying
something like the average.
>> Yeah that's right. That's right. So so
um
yes that is a good point. Okay, so the
comment is that RA was defined as an
average number of delta tubes per delta
ball. And here I was pretending that all
the tubes are average. Um so
let's call this a proof sketch.
Um you do need some uniformity. If you
think back to the original setting, you
know, you have the set E and then you
draw all these tubes. You can sort them
by how many delta tubes are in each one
and you take the category that has the
most delta tubes and that will still you
can work with that. So you can do it you
you you're correct. You we have to
uniformize it. Um and it is possible to
uniformize it.
Okay. So let me scribe that. So um
um
can do some
uniformizing
so all tubes
have the same number of balls.
Okay, other questions or comments?
Okay. Cool.
All right. So, this little lema is very
important. Um, for people who have some
seen some other things in harmonic
analysis, there's a submative lema
that's sort of like this in decoupling
theory and it's the beginning of what's
special about decoupling. If those words
don't mean anything to you, don't worry
about it. Um so let me show you some uh
corlary some applications of this lema
and then we'll um and then we'll sort of
go in earnest into using it to prove
this theorem.
All right.
[Applause]
All
right. So the first application is sort
of tongue and cheek
but uh also I I I think it's
philosophically important. I'm going to
call it so applications.
[Applause]
I'm gonna call it uh brute force proof
of a theorem of theorem um of the the ad
regular case.
So here's how it goes.
Um
so for some
for some specific delta knot
we check by brute force
that r a d
s delta kn is bounded by um the right
hand side
and we won't be able to get it perfectly
but we could get something like
Okay. So, how could you do this? Once
you fix a particular delta knot, like
one over a million, there are really
only finitely many different ways you
could arrange the delta balls. And there
are really only finitely many ways you
could put the tubes. So, there's a giant
brute force calculation that you
couldn't really do, but we could
imagine. And you could just check this.
Once you have this then you use the
submultiplicative lema
many times.
Um and so you know when you used it once
you would get ra s delta kn squared that
would be bounded by right hand side
times delta kn squar to the minus
epsilon
because the the right hand side is just
a power delta kn. So it multiplies
everything fits and you you keep going.
Okay, so of course this so this brute
force computation is so large that it's
out of the question to do it even with a
supercomputer etc. Um, nevertheless, it
is worth noticing that this very
difficult theorem has a one blackboard
proof up to a brute force computation.
Up to a finite computation. Most
difficult theorems in math, it's not
obvious how to reduce to a finite
computation. I wouldn't say this is
obvious either, but for most difficult
theorems in math, there's not a
half-page argument to reduce it to a
finite computation. For this one, there
is, but it shows that this is quite
important.
Okay, let me give another application.
Um, second application is the general
case
general ad versus the projective ad.
Um, okay. So, the course was called
projection theory. Uh, and at the
beginning we talked about problems about
orthogonal projections. And this theorem
is really more general. I guess I've
erased the theorem. The theorem we're
talking about today is more general than
just orthogonal projections. Um, and if
you had some orthogonal projections, the
way you would get all these tubes is you
would pick a direction from your
direction set. And then you would get a
bunch of tubes in that direction that
cover your set.
So um, so I make a definition.
Let's say that ET is projective
If
for every X and E,
the direction set of the tubes TX, let
me put it this way, for every X1 and X2
and E, the direction of the tubes
through X1 is the same as the direction
of the tubes through X2.
In other words, you have just one set of
directions and TX is all the tubes
through X in that set of directions.
Okay, so if you think about the general
the problem that we wrote down, this is
a very special case. So it used to be at
every point you picked your own
independent set of tubes, but now
there's an extra rule that that the
directions have to be the same at each
point. It's a very special case.
Okay, so
let's say RA a projection of delta is uh
the maximum over the usual stuff. So ET
obeys our hypothesis. Uh E is a regular
but also ET is projective.
All right.
Cool.
So um
in general that you know that we're
taking a maximum and this is a
restricted maximum. So we clearly have
that ra a projective
is smaller than rather
more cases
but it turns out that they're basically
equal to each other. So let's make that
a lema.
So r a d of delta is less than here
there are some fudge factors so I'll
write something like this c epsilon
delta to the minus epsilon
actually let me I don't quite say that
that's true but
let me just say something uh okay so
here so here's a cool observation based
on that diagram and that proof
so notice
that in the uh sub multip applicative
lama.
If um delta 1 equals delta 2= square
root of delta,
then
the
inner uh the the small ball problems are
all projective.
Okay.
So in this in this problem we sort of we
have a a delta scale
>> fenberg problem and we broke it up into
two pieces a coarse piece at the large
scale and a piece a small piece inside
each small ball. Okay so I claim that
this piece inside the small ball is
projective.
Why is it? Well,
so pick one of these points and I'm
going to look at the directions of the
red tubes going through this point.
Um, now I'm working in this small ball,
so I can only distinguish them up to an
angle of square root of delta.
So what directions will they be? They'll
be the directions of these orange tubes
going out through here.
So, so there there could well be two
long red tubes going through here in the
that are in the same orange tube, but
inside of this small ball, they'll just
be on top of each other. I won't see any
difference between them.
So, the directions that I'll see within
the small ball, they just correspond to
these orange tubes.
And if I look at different guys inside
the small ball, I have the same set of
orange tubes.
Okay, so that gives me an inequality
r a delta is bounded by
R a D delta to the half times R A D
projective
delta to the 12.
Yeah,
>> I thought that you were writing
projective,
>> right? Only the inner one is projective.
The outer one is arbitrary.
However, we can repeat this.
So now that's bounded by RA a delta to
the quarter R A projective delta to the
quarter
R A projective
delta to the half.
And now you can keep going.
Okay, so you do this many times.
There'll be a T appendix left here that
is still has no projective on it, but
it'll be very minor. And the rest of
them all have projective. And so the
conclusion is that to prove the theorem,
it suffices to check the projective
case.
So that's a cute application of being
submitted.
Okay.
So those are a couple of cute
applications of this lama. Yeah.
>> Is that like extra r that kind of went
over epsilon
uh kind of where the delta epsilon kind
of error term final or is there as well?
>> There are several places where we might
incur a delta to the epsilon in the
final thing and this is one of them.
Yeah.
Okay. Um,
so let's say something big picture about
trying to prove this theorem.
So we were saying yesterday that for a
while in this subject there were only
kind of there were only epsilon
improvements on some classical things.
And what was very striking to me is to
go from just making epsilon improvements
to go to making to to proving the sharp
theorem.
And while Pablush Murkin was visiting, I
talked with him a lot about all this
stuff. And he said to me something one
day that really stuck with me. He said
sort of philosophically.
Um
that here, yeah, here's how I would like
to put it. Um
that in order to prove this theorem,
what we need to do is make an epsilon
improvement on the submicative lema.
So let me write that down because I
think it's worth taking with you out of
this class.
So
philosophy
to prove the theorem
what we need
an epsilon improvement
on the sub multiplicative length.
Okay. So in other words, we'd like to
say either
one possibility is that ra a d square
root of delta is already obeys the
bound.
Okay. Well then we're happy and you know
by by the sub multiplicative lema our
ide of delta also will obey the bound.
So we'll be happy
or
we have so I'll write down the um sub
multiplicative lema.
So that's the sub multiplicative lema
but or we have not not this lema but a
little tiny improvement on it.
Okay, so in this case of course we're
happy and in this case we can iterate
and so you can think of ra of delta as
being some power of delta
and then every time we do this that
power goes down
uh or some negative power of delta.
Every time we do this, that power is
going to go down. Um and um uh and so
it'll keep going down until we get into
this case and we're happy.
So
so let's illustrate that. So if say we
have ra a delta
um let me write it this way be easier as
delta to the minus gamma then we'd have
ra a d of delta squared
would be bounded by um so this would
give us delta to the minus 2 gamma but
plus epsilon
Then we would do this again.
RA a D delta 4th would be bounded by
delta 4 to the minus gamma plus epsilon
plus epsilon. We keep going and this
exponent keeps getting better and better
until we can't make an epsilon
improvement anymore. So if we have this
dichotomy then we can get um the
theorem.
Okay.
Cool.
Um
all right. So so then you might reflect
well you know why is it easier to make
an epsilon improvement kind of theorem
than it is to uh you know prove a really
sharp bound straight out. Well, there's
a thought process for that. If we have
we already have a result and then we
want to make an epsilon improvement,
then we say to ourselves, you know, what
would it look like if the result we have
is sharp
and maybe there's a lot of specific
things that have to happen for the
result we have to be sharp. So, we get a
lot of structure and then we have then
we have to get a contradiction and that
shows you can do just a little bit
better. That's why an epsilon
improvement result is is easier than um
than just getting a a great balance
straight away. And you know and when we
so you know if if we go back to Bans's
projection theorem and we tried to make
you know epsilon improvement in a in a
projection theorem well we we didn't say
this at the time but it might have been
good to say you know what would it be
like what would it mean if the bound we
have so far is sharp would mean we have
this structure and that structure and
eventually we have this subset that is
almost closed under addition and almost
closed under multiplication anda d
Okay, so the idea is we are going to try
to do the same thing. We're going to
think about what would it mean if the
sub multiplicative lema was sharp and
we're going to see that it just means
the set has to have a lot of structure
and eventually we'll get down maybe not
today but eventually
orin and smirkin uh got down to to the
structures got down to the banan
projection theorem or um and got a
contradiction
okay
so let's talk about what would it mean
if the sub multiplic Licative llama is
sharp.
Okay. So let me draw a couple pictures
for you. And one of the pictures it
corresponds to the sub multiplicative
lamina is sharp and in the other one it
it it's not.
Okay.
So,
so we'll have some fat balls in a fat
tube.
And
then in each fat tube, in each fat ball,
we have some little balls.
And the little balls are in little
tubes.
So there's your typical little tube and
okay in each of these balls there are
some each of these back balls there are
some little balls.
Okay.
So in the scenario in this picture would
the sub multiplicative lema be sharp or
not sharp?
Stand next to the picture
in this picture. Would the sub
multiplicative lema be sharp or not
sharp?
I don't think it's sharp because there's
just one tube for the like coarser
scale. that could be consist of several
tubes for the fine scale.
>> Um, okay. So, let me clarify what this
is a picture of.
So, so there are many coarse scale
tubes, but I just drew one of them. And
I'm just drawing what's happening inside
of one of them. So, inside of that one
coarse tube, this is what we see based
on this is the
>> So, there's only one fine scale tube. Um
there could be more fine scale tubes but
this is a typical one. Yes, there are
many orange tubes and many red tubes but
I'm drawing uh only one of each to
direct your to focus our attention.
Okay, so let's review for a second the
proof of the sub multiplicative lama uh
because it's really important and maybe
it'll go in a little deeper and then
I'll try this again. Okay, so our goal
is to estimate ra of delta, which is the
number of delta balls per delta tube.
So I picked a delta tube like this red
one here. I I have to estimate the
number of delta balls in it. First I
estimate the number of fat balls that it
intersects
and then I multiply that by the number
of delta balls that it intersects within
each fat ball. And that was my bat.
And that each one of those things I
bounded sort of by induction and I got
those two members. All right. So
if I take a particular fat tube and
inside of it a particular thin tube and
I see this would that argument be sharp?
Right. Okay. So so the suggestion is
that this is not sharp because uh inside
of this red tube most of the fat balls
are contributed nothing.
And only this one fat ball is
contributing.
And it would be sharp if the number of
delta balls in the fat ball was the
number of sorry the number of delta
balls in the delta tube was the number
of fat balls times the number of delta
balls in one of them. So let me show. So
this is not sharp. And let me draw the
one that's sharp. You'll see the
difference. This is not sharp.
Delta tube
should look like this,
right? So the delta tube should
intersect a bunch of fat balls. It
should intersect that many fat balls as
many as possible. And inside each one of
them, it should intersect a lot of delta
balls, as many as possible. That's what
it takes for the sub multiplicative lema
to be sharp.
So it should look like this. So this is
sharp.
[Applause]
Okay.
Um,
and this is a kind of striking picture.
right. So
in this ball, these points are in just a
few tubes in a certain direction. Could
also imagine we're in the projective
case. And in these other balls, the
points are in those same tubes.
Goes all the way across. Of course, the
balls don't have to look exactly the
same as each other. So maybe a better
picture might be like so.
But the the tubes are exactly the same.
Okay.
Okay. So,
let me pause. I'm going to erase a
little bit to make some space around
here. Is that okay with everybody? that
if the sub multiplicative lema is sharp,
it has to look like this, not like that.
Okay. All right. So, let's erase around
here a little bit.
Okay. So, um we already reduced to the
projective case.
So let's say D is the set of directions
which is the same everywhere as our
projections
and so D is a delta S set in the circle
and here I fixed a typical fat tube. So
here's a typical
root delta tube.
Um, and I'm going to look at the angles
that are within this fat tube.
So, um, so let's say,
so here's our circle and, um, there's a
little range of angles here. This is a
delta to the here's theta, which is a
delta to the 1/2 arc that corresponds to
the that tube.
Um okay
and so D is some delta set delta SC set
in here and let's say that C is D
intersected with theta. So it's just
these directions.
Okay.
Um so
so the red tubes correspond to one of
the directions in theta. So this one
there red tube.
And um so when I project the set in the
red direction, I just get a small set.
But it's not just the red direction. I
could draw some other directions inside
of the tube also. Let me do one more.
I'll take here a blue direction inside
of here.
So I draw the tubes in the blue
direction. What would it look like? I
think I need to make this picture come
out nicely. I need to add a few more
points.
And then so there'll be one more red
tube.
Oops.
And now I'll draw a typical blue tube.
The blue tube also manages to intersect
our points a lot. So it should look sort
of like this.
Okay, I don't think I can draw anymore
without making a complete mess, but get
the idea.
So the blue tube passes through all
these balls also. And each time the blue
tube passes through a ball, it manages
to line up with one of the red tubes.
All right. Okay.
So, we have a kind of special situation
here with a product structure.
So, what is our set? Um, so let's say
over here
these dots this the projection in the
red direction. Let's call this A.
And then um down here we can make a set
that illustrates where the fat balls are
in the fat tube. Let's call that B.
And so what we see is that for every C
in C
the projection
uh in the C direction or I'll write it
this way. A + C B that's the projection
in the C direction
is not much bigger than A.
So
the you know the projection in every one
of these directions is small. They're
all about the same as each other. A was
the projection in the red direction. B
the blue one is just as good. So A plus
CB should be not much bigger than A.
Okay.
Okay. So, let me summarize what we have
seen here.
Okay.
So
f sub multiplicative lama
is sharp.
Um
then
we get sets A and B and C which are
subsets of real numbers.
And in the main case,
a is a delta a a set.
Well, it's a row a set. Uh size of a is
like row to the minus a.
B is a row B set. Size of B is like row
to the minus B. C is a row C set.
size of C is like row to the minus C.
And
for every C in C,
A + CB is not very much bigger than A.
Okay. Now, the size of A and B and C can
all be traced back to the numbers in our
problem.
Um and
we find that if uh
if a is smaller than b + c that's
equivalent to saying that ra a d square
root of delta is good
a sorry if a is larger than b plus c
then that means you do a boring
computation.
Um so there's a
intermediate result maybe I'll call it a
key lema which is called the ABC sum
product lema
which is goes into this paper of open
schwarin. Uh, and it says if you have
all of this stuff, um, then indeed a is
bigger than b + c.
Okay, let's yeah,
>> good means that it obeys the theorem.
Um so the theorem's up there. So smaller
than the maximum of one and
root delta to the minus t / 2 + s / 2
and root delta to the 1us t.
So if if that's the case, we're we're
happy. And otherwise uh yeah. Okay.
Right.
Okay. So, let's go back to our general
strategy, our big our big picture
strategy. We'd like to prove this
theorem that RA of delta is always
smaller than that.
And we consider the sub multiplicative
limit which doesn't give us the theorem
yet, but it's an important tool.
And we'd like to say
um
uh
if if the if we can have an epsilon
improvement in the sub multiplicative
lema then that's great. We go to the
next scale and we have a better bound.
So you keep doing that until you stop
and we must stop in a situation where
there's no more where the sub
multiplicative lema becomes sharp.
And maybe that's a better way to say it.
We have the sub multiplicative lama. we
use it. It's either sharp or it's not.
If it's not, we get a, you know, a nicer
exponent at at delta squared than we did
at delta. We keep doing that and the
exponent is not going to keep getting
better forever. So, we stop at some
moment where the sub multiplicative lama
is basically sharp.
But the fact that the sub multiplicative
lama is sharp gives us a lot of
structure. It gives us uh the structure
of being projective
and it gives us this kind of product
structure and it leads us to this
problem which looks a lot like additive
combinotaurics and which is very special
problem compared to our original setup.
Um okay and then the bound we need to
prove for this problem if you just
unwind the computation we need to prove
this bound for this problem and if you
unwind it it will tell us that um that
ra obeys the desired bound
yeah row I guess row is also row here is
square root of delta
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay. So this situation
is now a lot more structured than what
we started with and it looks reminiscent
of uh additive cominatorics maybe of
brian projection theorem and so on and
indeed they were able to deal with it
with that toolkit.
I could say a little I don't I don't
want to write too many equations so I
won't say the whole thing. I could say a
little bit about it. Um, but I I think
that what we've done so far is what what
I feel is most worth remembering about
the proof of this theorem. So, let's
pause here and see if people have any
questions or comments about
Let me let me summarize it.
So the ad regular case is special
because all the scales are related to
each other and so we can break it up
into problems at different scales and
put them together. And by doing that we
get problems that are somewhat nicer. So
first of all if we look at the problem
in a small ball instead of the original
problem it becomes nicer because the
directions through any point are the
same for any two points. the directions
are the same because they correspond to
the directions of the fat tube through
there. So this already made it a little
bit nicer.
Then moreover in order for the sub
multiplicative lema to be sharp. So if
the sub multiplicative lema is not sharp
then you just keep going down scales and
you keep getting better exponents and
eventually that has to stop when the sub
multiplicative lema is sharp. when the
sub multiplicative lema is sharp,
there's even more structure because
these different balls have to talk to
each other. Um, and so if you know
there's a if if you see in this ball,
you see a tube here, then you have to
see a tube in the same place in that
ball.
Um, and that means that this set of
points has kind of a product structure.
And in particular if you what what's
literally true is that if you take this
uh well anyway so if you if you take the
set of red tubes in this ball and then
in this ball and then in this ball that
is a product which is very helpful.
Okay. Um
cool. So,
so the the the ad regular case allows us
to restrict to a situation which has a
lot more structure and uh it restricts
to to to this lema about projections of
a product set.
>> Okay. Yeah. Um, so the argument like can
continue sort of until the
more is sharp. How do you know that kind
of sharpness corresponds to kind of the
sort of
delta to the epsilon factor rather than
just kind of something much smaller?
It's seems like I don't I don't
understand how to kind of get a
quantitative bound kind of a more
qualitative proof by contradiction.
>> Yeah. Okay. Okay. So the quest this
question is about keeping track of the
small parameters. So every time I apply
the sub multiplicative lema
I was using the word sharp or not sharp
but of course there's some kind of a
gray zone and I have to decide where I'm
going to cut how how what am I going to
consider to be sharp and what is not
sharp. Um and um then
in this analysis um
uh
um yeah okay so so actually so in in
order for this to stop in a reasonable
amount of time I'm going to have to have
a cutoff that's a tiny power of delta
otherwise this would go on too long
wouldn't work. Um, so my so I would say
um
uh
so what would the definition of sharp
be?
Keep that.
[Applause]
All right, let's get rid of this stuff.
So we're going to we're going to use the
sub multiplicative lama
repeatedly.
And so if ra a d of delta is bigger than
I need to put something here ra a d of
root delta squared and here I'm going to
put delta to the epsilon kn where
epsilon kn is a tiny parameter then I'm
going to call this sharp
and I'm going to stop and analyze
the Other possibility is that RA A of
delta is less than delta to the epsilon
KN RA a
root delta squared. And here I'm making
progress. So I'll keep going. So this is
the not sharp case.
So now I'll keep going.
Okay. So that's that's if we're more
careful about what is sharp and not
sharpening. All right. So here um if I
keep going every time I make a definite
amount of progress and so uh this this
actually cannot keep going forever
because eventually the exponents would
be negative instead of positive. So it
will stop. So we will end up here. Once
we end up here we have to analyze the
sharp case and we do have to remember it
wasn't perfectly sharp but we had a
fudge factor of a tiny power of delta
and that complicates all the pictures
that we have drawn. So in this picture
here,
this tube goes through many fat tubes.
It doesn't have to have many delta balls
in all of them. It has to have many
delta balls in a fraction like delta to
the epsilon, not fraction of them. It
makes the picture a little bit more
complicated. Um and actually because of
that in in this theorem,
if we're honest, it's a little bit more
complicated. It's not um so it's um
this would actually be pi c of x where x
is a subset of a cross b and it's like a
delta to the epsilon subset.
So we wouldn't have to fill the whole
product. we'd only have.
Okay. So for that's what how we would be
careful about sharp and how we would
have to be more careful here.
Okay. Um let me tell you just the first
idea of the of the proof of um of this
key lama.
So um so we have
just a step proof
um so we have a plus cb is only a little
bit bigger than a
um that reminds us of plunicus. So an
appropriate version of plunicusia
well okay we have this big subset x we
might want to get rid of that by doing
bix gowers. Um so a val 80 hours would
reduce
to um a prime plus c b prime smaller
than a prime we actually have all of it
instead of just a big piece of it and
then uh plunicus
[Applause]
would give us so this would be true for
man c and c
and that would give us a prime prime
plus C1 B prime plus C2 B prime plus C3
B prime would still be smaller than A
prime could get that from plunicus
okay and so now you we're not done yet
but you sort of have the feeling that
we keep using these tools from additive
commentary we keep having stronger and
stronger sounding uh information about A
and B more and more suspicious
okay And it definitely takes some some
skill and some some good ideas to to
finish from here. But we're in a setting
where the tools of additive
combinatorics are quite powerful and
they're able to analyze what happens.
Okay, good.
Any final questions or comments?
>> Yeah.
>> How did we reduce the projected case? we
reduced to the projective case at the
beginning. Um we said uh so after we had
the um sub multiplicative lama we
reduced to the projective case by saying
that um this ball is in the projective
case.
Um and so using that we were able to
show that it suffices to prove it for
the projective case.
How do you put that? How do you chain
that argument?
>> What's that like? Like like I I don't
understand how you use uh like that kind
of argument and the and the reduction at
the same time.
>> Ah um so the question is about how we
put together reducing to the projective
case with all the other things that we
did. Yeah. Um
um okay. So,
so using this lama, we had an argument
that if you could prove a good bound for
the projective case, then combining it
with this lama and and noticing that
this is projective that then we get a
good bound for the general case. So now
we just imagine we're trying to prove
the theorem in the projective case.
Um so we can assume that we're in the
projective case
and then we start applying the sub
multiplicative lema.
Um
ah so you're wondering when we do this
yeah you can so you can think of this in
this picture um where over here we have
um not just some abstract thing but the
this would be the R in the small ball
and the R for the fat tubes. So, we look
at those and if if the R if the R is
better than multiplying the small balls
times the fat tubes, then we keep
breaking things up. Take the small balls
and break them into smaller balls. And
otherwise, if if they're comparable,
then we look at at what's happening.
>> Yeah, that's a good question. Yeah.
>> So, I understand uh what's going on. Is
this example uh supposed to be similar
to the case B that we had at the
beginning where like for instance if we
started with tubes and points on a
bridge would we kind of immediately fall
just into the situation and what we're
doing is blowing things up until we get
there.
>> Yeah. Okay. So the question is how how
these pictures and these examples relate
to the the the three examples that we
had in mind at the beginning. Um so the
three examples we had in mind at the
beginning were there was a simple one
the stars example there was the grid
that was interesting and there was like
the random example
and a funny thing is that none of those
is ad regular
right and now the the the
random one we could fidget to make it ad
regular if we wanted to um and the stars
we we could make it ad regular if we
wanted to but the grid is is actually is
really not adular
Um and so that is a little bit funny
that in the most important example is
not in this case. Um even though this
case is very important in the final
proof.
Um so you can't really start with the
grid
and it is
not at least until recently it was not
known what is the actual worst behavior
in the AD regular case. It may be so it
may be that RA a is much smaller than R.
Um uh although but the argument so far
doesn't prove that and that's a little
it's a little bit funny because it means
there's not an example that you can keep
in mind when you go through the ad
regular case.
>> Yeah.
>> What what goes wrong with trying to kind
construct an ad regular grid where you
just kind of have a grid wherein each
point has a lot of sort of nested
subgrids within it.
>> Yeah. So the question is could you make
an ad? Yeah, I guess that's true. You
could make a roughly a somewhat ad
regular grid by taking a grid of balls
and then in each one of those balls you
put a grid of balls and you repeat like
this. Um uh but it's not since the grid
itself is not a dregular. This this is
only a it's only a dregular with a big
c. Um could you do that? Yeah, I guess
you could do that.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So you could do that.
And then what would happen here? The A,
B and C would be like sets of integers
except they would have this ad regular
structure. So A would be like take an
arithmetic progression of intervals and
in each one of them put an arithmetic
progression of smaller intervals and so
on. That's what A and B and C would look
like.
>> Can you cancept them?
>> Yeah, it's kind of like a caner. It's
like a counter set but the but with but
in order to make it make the numbers
come out well you you need to have a lot
of intervals in an arithmetic
progression in each step. Here I'll draw
it and then I'm over so I'm going to
stop.
So the example is um for a big line you
make an arithmetic progression with a
lot of intervals.
Okay? Then you look inside of each one
of these intervals and you repeat what I
just did. Um and for for this to for
this to be a kind of sharp interesting
example, it needs to be a lot of
intervals.
Okay. Okay. Good. Sorry for going a
little bit over. Um, those are great
questions. Let's stop there and I will
see you next week.