the MIT energy initiative presents
Franchesco Benedetti building
communities founding a startup with
people in mind written by Katherine M
O'Neal MIT postdoctoral researcher
Franchesco Benedetti admits he was not
always a star student but the people he
met along his educational Journey
inspired him to strive which led him to
conduct research at MIT launch a startup
and even lead the team that won the
2021 MIT 100K entrepreneurship
competition now he is determined to make
sure that his company osmosis succeeds
in boosting the Energy Efficiency of
traditional and renewable natural gas
processing hydrogen production and
carbon capture thus helping to address
climate change I can't be grateful
enough to MIT for bringing together a
community of people who want to change
the world Benedetti says now we have a
technology that can solve one of the big
problems of our society Benedetti and
his team have developed an Innovative
way to separate molecules using a
membrane fine enough to extract
impurities such as carbon dioxide or
hydrogen sulfide from raw natural gas to
obtain a higher quality fuel fulfilling
a crucial need in the energy industry
natural gas now provides about 40% of
the energy used to power homes in
industry in the United States Benedetti
says using his team's technology to
upgrade natural gas more efficiently
could reduce emissions of greenhouse
gases while saving energy to power the
equivalent of 7 million additional us
homes for a year he
adds the MI
Community Benedetti first came to MIT in
2017 as a visiting student from the
University of bolognia in Italy where he
was working on membranes for gas
separation for his PhD in chemical
engineering having completed a master's
thesis on water desalination at the
University of Texas at Austin he
connected with University of Texas Alum
Zachary P Smith who is the Robert and
noise Career Development professor
professor of chemical engineering at MIT
and the two discovered they shared a
vision we found ourselves very much
aligned on the need for new technology
in Industry to lower the energy
consumption of separating components
Benedetti says although Benedetti had
always been interested in making a
positive impact on the world
particularly the environment he says it
was his university studies that first
sparked his interest in more efficient
separation Technologies when you study
chemical engineering you understand
hundreds of ways the field can have a
positive impact in the world but we
learn very early that 15% of the world's
energy is wasted because of inefficient
chemical separation because we still
rely on centuries old technology he
says most separation processes still use
heat or toxic solvents to separate
components he explains still Benedetti
says his main Drive comes from the joy
of working with terrific mentors and
colleagues it's the people I've met that
really inspired me to tackle the biggest
challenges and find that intrinsic
motivation he says to help build his
community at MIT and provide support for
international students Benedetti
co-founded the MIT visiting Student
Association or Vista in September of
2017 by February
2018 the organization had hundreds of
members and an official Institute
recognition in May of 2018 the group won
two Institute Awards including the
golden Beaver award for enhancing the
campus environment Vista gave me a sense
of belonging I loved it Benedetti says
membrane
technology Benedetti also published two
papers on membrane research during his
stint as a visiting student at MIT so he
was delighted to return in 20 2019 for
postdoctoral work through the MIT energy
initiative where he was a 2019 through
2020 xon mobile MIT energy
fellow I came back because the research
was extremely exciting but also because
I got extremely passionate about the
energy I found on campus and with the
people he says returning to MIT enabled
Benedetti to continue his work with
Smith and Holden lie both of whom helped
to co-found O mosis Li a recent Stanford
PhD in chemistry who was also a visiting
student at MIT in 2018 is now the chief
technology officer at
osmosis co-founder Katherine Mahi
Rodriguez
2017 an MIT PhD candidate joined the
team more
recently together the osmosis team has
developed polymer membranes with
microporosities capable of filtering
gases by separating out molecules that
differ by as little as a fraction of an
angstrom a unit of length equal to 100th
of a
CM we can get up to five times higher
selectivity than commercially available
technology for methane upgrading and
this has been observed operating the
membranes in industrially relevant
environments Benedetti says today
methane upgrading or removing carbon
dioxide from raw natural gas to obtain a
higher grade fuel fuel is often
accomplished using amine absorption
which is a process that uses toxic
solvents to capture carbon dioxide and
burns methane to fuel the Regeneration
of the solvents for reuse using osmosis
filters would eliminate the need for
such solvents while reducing carbon
dioxide emissions by up to 16 million
metric tons per year in the United
States alone Benedetti says the
technology has a wide range of
applications in oxygen and nitrogen
generation hydrogen purification and
carbon capture for example but osmosis
plans to start with a $5 billion market
for natural gas upgrading because the
need to bring Innovation and
sustainability to that space is urgent
says bened Didi who received guidance
and bringing technology to Market from
mit's Desh Pand Center for technological
innovation the osmosis team has also
received support from the MIT sandbox
inov a fund program the next step for
the startup is to build an industrial
scale prototype and Benedetti says the
company got a huge boost toward that
goal in May when it won the MIT 100K
entrepreneurship competition which is a
student run contest that has launched
more than 160 companies since it began
in
1990 90 teams began the competition by
pitching their startup ideas 20 received
mentorship and deved development funding
then eight finalists presented business
plans to compete for the $100,000 prize
because of this we're getting a lot of
interest from Venture Capital firms
investors companies and corporate funds
that want to partner with us or to use
our product he says in June the osmosis
team received a 2-year activate
Fellowship which will support moving its
research to Market in October it won the
northeast regional and carbon
sequestration prizes at the clean tech
open accelerator and in November the
team closed a $3 million preed round of
financing fail naturally Benedetti hopes
osmosis is on the path to success but he
wants everyone to know that there is no
shame in failures that come from the
best efforts he admits it took him 3
years longer than usual to finish his
undergraduate and master's degrees and
he says I've experienced the pressure
you feel when Society judges you like a
book by its cover and how much a lack of
inspired leaders and a supportive
environment can kill creativity and the
will to try that's why in 2018 along
with other MIT students and Vista
members he started fail inspiring
resilience an organization that provides
a platform for sharing unfiltered
stories and lessons leaders have gleaned
from failure we wanted to help
destigmatize failure appreciate
vulnerabilities and Inspire humble
leadership ship eventually creating
better communities Benedetti says if we
can make failures big and small less
intimidating and all consuming
individuals with great potential will be
more willing to take risks think outside
the box and try things that may push new
boundaries in this way more breakthrough
discoveries are likely to follow without
compromising anyone's mental health
Benedetti says he will strive to create
a supportive culture at osmosis because
people are Central to success what
drives me every day is the people I
would have no story without the people
around me he says the moment you lose
touch with people you lose the
opportunity to create something special