okay um let's start our last session of
today um so um we have uh Professor
Jacob uh he's a assist associate
professor in um um at the Department of
Mathematics and computer science at
Aloma University of Technology in
Netherlands and he's also the gener head
of the generative AI group there and um
okay uh can you pull up the slide please
yeah so um and today um uh so um I'm
sure that you'll um uh before we pull up
the slide uh I just want to um just say
that uh if you have any question you can
feel free to come up to the the speaker
uh the two microphones here and okay so
now we have the slides available right
and is this your uh not yet not yet not
yet okay um yeah uh so after this we'll
have a poster session and networking
with uh we have a re
um you feel free to um stay and enjoy um
um networking with your fellow
colleagues um I think um there's um lot
of exciting talk today um kind of uh
span across you know small molecule drug
Discovery and we'll um also have we also
have some um our Kyo speaker on a
protein design and we will have um we
are kind of trying to sample across
different drug modalities and and um
okay so and without further Ado uh I
would like to just leave the stage to
you yeah thank you very much so first of
all thank you for the invitation it's
great to be here it's the first time for
me in Boston so it's it's really great
place and uh uh I am actually a computer
scientist I work on generative modeling
generative AI for over 10 years so
before the hype I think it's good to
mention that these
days uh and also I happen to be a
program chair of newbs this year so I
really liked all the comments in the
morning a bit sour comments it's
actually good to listen to them as well
uh and I hope that I can also meet you
in Vancouver this year or maybe the next
year uh and so as I said so I'm a
computer scientist I'm not a biologist
I'm not a chemist I'm not a physicist so
you can very easily kill me with any
simple question probably but I will try
to do my best to tell you a little bit
about how we can use generative AI to
accelerate drug Discovery so a little
bit different perspective so we listen
to many many different uh aspects
already today um and uh I will try to to
point out a few other interesting
applications in my opinion right so
first I would like to say a few words
that you probably know about it but it's
good to always start with why right and
first why is uh uh very shameful serf
advertisement so I I I
just finish my second edition of my book
on on deep generative modeling and uh
for me gen geni is not not equivalent to
llms it's really about probabilistic
modeling so I really loved how Jennifer
said in the morning that it's about
density density about probability
distributions because this is exactly
what generative AI generative modeling
is right and uh we talk about geni it's
actually about parameterizing
probabilistic models with deep neural
networks right and we have many many
different classes of deep generative
models SL gen models like what we
listened today already so diffusion
models um latent variable models energy
based models Auto aggressive models like
llms nowadays right and also maybe what
is not mentioned here is uh the another
class of so-called Foundation
models that are not necessarily
probabilistic models but they can use to
to to build more sophisticated
generative AI
systems and uh talking about drug
Discovery so like focusing on the R&D
part so of course this is always very
lengthy uh very costly process right and
from Target identification and
validation to lead identification and
optimization in vitro studies and so on
so on so on right so there are many many
many aspects of
R&D uh before even any drug candidate
enters clinical trials right so where I
see a computer scientist right where I
see that gen can help uh in this process
so of course at this R&D especially
right so probably I I again I don't need
to convince you about it the hope is
that we can shorten all this this pretty
lengthy
processes and as and as an outcome we
can get something faster as well and and
and and cheaper right we saw multiple uh
talks today multiple great uh success
stories actually right uh and uh but I
what I want to highlight is that we can
use broadly speaking gen AI not only to
get for instance molecules but we can
also use it at different places so for
instance we can use for Target
identification and validation we also
listen to that today uh and also for
understanding mechanisms why something
happens what how a given given
disease evolves because generative
modeling we need to remember is about
actually generative
processes we can say that this is in
some sense how we think our reality is
like we can Sample about our reality
right so what is like what kind of
condition what is conditioning what is
condition on on this and so on so on
right so this is like a generative
process uh but also of course we can use
gen for do NOA drag design so I said we
listen to that maybe some phenotypic
profiling etc
etc and so what we can do with
Gen uh again so we can look at this uh
in different from different angles so
one we can use gen for Target
acquisition or like for instance with
Alpha fault or
Rosetta uh it's good to remember that
there is not only alpha alpha fault
right so there are also other approaches
uh we can also use data analysis so
sequencing data Imaging data network
data simulation data there are plenty of
amazing simulators that can help us with
uh yeah understanding what are the the
the mechanism under the hoood of of
given disease for instance and of course
we can use gen for molecular docking the
NOA drug design but also we can look at
some properties so this is what I I I
will try to cover to some extent today
so for instance about uh enzyme kinetics
right so we can also use gen for that we
can help Chemists in wet Labs we can
help them with some tools that that
speed up uh they work work right so this
is very interesting and there are pretty
old Concepts actually but they come back
so very
recently uh many researchers from
Stanford John Zuckerberg initiative they
they they they they they published a
paper on archive about virtual cells
organisms so to to create something in
silic like an organist or a cell in
silico that such that we can play with
without even touching anything in a wet
lab right so this is of course very very
challenging task because if you look at
a cell it is like extremely complicated
system by itself and yet we we have
organis that consist of this cells so
are built of this cell so this is like
crazily complex right but so this is
very interesting uh uh where we can use
AI actually right in so many different
places so okay so how we can how we can
use a gen so first I would like to start
with one example of uh understanding
regulatory mechanism of diseases so this
is a project that I'm I'm involved in uh
with a startup in Amsterdam in the
Netherlands so the idea is that by
Regulators we mean some natural
compounds that control biochemical uh
reactions uh and disregulation results
in let's say disease right uh
or some unhealthy State an example is
vitamin
B12 again what is in this uh uh in this
block so I can't fully comprehend but uh
for me what is important is that input
is uh like some deficiency of vitamin
B12 and output is anemia right so
basically the first and the last word
here and but there is a some complete
system that we can actually understand
biochemists can understand and explain
it pretty well but this is exactly what
we mean what we mean by
regulators and so we can actually look
at diseases from this perspective well
maybe perhaps instead of Designing uh a
drug we can first look and we can try to
understand why a disease occures right
maybe we can be lucky enough to find
that there is some uh compound that is
this natural compound that regulates
some process right and then based on
that we can start optimizing that and
this is the approach that we uh we use
for very challenging uh problem of
Alzheimer's and we used a database of
over
220,000 uh candidates Regulators that
that that are naturally occurring our
bodies and we used generative AI based
on deep learning uh so some Foundation
models we created a pipeline in-house
pipeline uh that allowed us to actually
highlight some potential leads then of
course it's not don't get me wrong I am
a huge Enthusiast of AI but uh of course
at the end or in this process must be
Human Being Human expert right So
eventually medicinal chemist looked at
this potential candidate and said yes we
see in this list some potential uh
candidat right then further it was
optimized in a wet lab but at least this
this uh uh this step was definitely much
faster than studying literature of for
this
220,000 potential compounds and so on so
on so we can uh make it more automatic
right so this is first example very
interesting in my
opinion uh another example is uh like
let's say this was the very beginning of
the whole pipeline of drug Discovery now
we are entering like this almost like
preclinical uh step right so let's say
that we have uh identified some
inhibitor or a candidate uh drug
candidate and now we need to check
different uh properties right uh so for
instance enzyme kinetics is one of those
steps uh so like the M Menan model right
so let's say that we like you know more
how how it works than me but there is a
system of differential equations this is
what I understand at least and uh what
we have to do we have to check how
enzyme behaves with and without uh
potential inhibitor we try different
concentration levels right and this is
the the most basic approach this is the
the a right so this is this let's
so-called standard approach you try
different concentrations you you measure
it you you make the mement and plot and
then you get your uh parameters right
values you estimate your
parameters so our question was can we do
it faster by just having one single
measurement instead of multiple like
typically eight or so right so then we
of course don't waste money for startups
is super important we don't waste time
again for startups super important right
and then maybe we can get very quickly
ER some uh maybe rough but at least some
estimate right of the value so this is
what we use so I call it like a local
model because this is like for one given
case we can use some computational uh
models so here we use approximate ban
computation uh so you can use
uh if we bend the definitions a little
bit gen for that right uh and this is
this approach gives you very quickly
some
posterior over your parameter value
right for this enzyme paramet entics
parameters
so does it work well we applied it to uh
to uh to the case of uh
uh uh
covid-19 so with this approach uh we
were able to actually very quickly check
something and put a paper on bio archive
uh two months after the first uh First
cases in the Netherlands right so it was
like around March and in in uh in in may
we already had some first uh write up
right and this was possible because
actually we applied this computational
approach so we really sped up everything
and then uh the paper was then late
published one year later right because
we had to do everything properly but at
least it helped to very quickly navigate
to say hey it's actually Worth to pursue
right and after all this is what we do
care about right we want to quickly
proceed uh like you know like I always
joke that uh in AI if a paper is one
month old it's pretty old if it's one
year old it's like ages old right so I
think it's getting like that everywhere
right in in uh in Medicinal Chemistry
it's getting similar
right uh so this is uh uh this is an
example that actually we can we can use
that uh and very recently so this is a
preliminary uh works it's unpublished
very
preliminary again with enzyme
kinetics and what we try to use here we
try to look at the problem as uh time
series forecasting SL generating right
Right Time series and the case is here
that uh we assume that we don't know for
a second that there are some ODS there
is some m m model we just have some
measurements so what we can have we can
have uh substrate concentration enzyme
concentration and then we observe uh the
curve for product right how it changes
over time right and we can phrase it in
in two ways so first we can say that hey
we have some initial measurements and we
stop it right and we say now given those
data this and this concentration initial
concentrations predict the remaining of
this curve right it could be useful but
typically we are more interested in
another scenario that we only have the
initial condition for the product which
is zero and we don't do any measurements
in the wet lab and we want to generate
or predict the remaining of this time
series right
uh and I'm for our initial experiments
we use M Menan model to generate like
synthetic data but of course in practice
we can say that hey we are now agnostic
to to this enzyme kinetics model under
the hood it could be anything just
provide me a lot of data also this is if
this
works it it has this very nice property
that since this is a deep learning based
model we can can now add many other
modalities right so we with Odes we need
to stick to Odes with deep learning
models we can attach many different
components and and as I said modalities
so for instance we can now give uh
structures of enzyme and ligant and we
can train such a model right so but
first comes first so first we wanted to
check if even uh this this neural
network based approach works
and in the first case we are pretty
positive that it will work in the second
case we were something like probably it
won't work right I as a I work with my
PhD student as a good supervisor I said
it probably won't work but let's give it
a try anyway right and uh additionally
so we wanted to check if giving this
initial condition
give some uh information it should
because this is how the the OD works
right but we wanted to check it as well
we picked like state-of-the-art
model again state-ofthe-art in terms of
uh AI it's bit tricky so in April they
were state-ofthe-art not anymore but
they were pretty good and so these are
some results uh by the way I hate
looking at tables but this is the only
table here so so bear with me so so if
we this scenario one is this let's say
we have more information and scenario
two is that we don't give any
information of the of previous
measurements right and so if we don't
use any external information so we only
give uh no initial conditions are given
uh so the model performs extremely
bad which is a very good information for
us because when we uh give this
information initial conditions suddenly
everything works pretty well right and
here is some very chped
example
uh yeah sorry so this is actually
scenario one I mix mixed them up so this
is scenario one so if we you give some
initial information it is capable of
predicting uh everything very well uh if
you don't give this external information
the the prediction is pretty bad and
then uh as I said so this is unpublished
so unfortunately I don't want to show
too many information uh with you s guys
but uh if now we we updated the model in
some way and first of all it worked
better in this scenario one but also
worked better in this scenario two and
this is actually very very interesting
and very promising and this is actually
how uh like I think that very skilled uh
uh specialist expert would work so how
it works it like if you give initial
conditions and if you know a bit how
this OD works so the the initial uh
value of the substrate will be the upper
Bound for the maximum of the product
right because
of well you cannot get more product than
your initial substrate right so then
what we notice is that exactly by giving
this information so you can see that
this this uh or this this green and and
red so these two curves so they exactly
like go to the the to the maximum right
if you don't give this initial condition
for a substrate the model goes
completely bananas right it it goes
somewhere and we notice that by giving
this external information so this model
worked a little bit like that it figured
out the curve so it was always something
like this this logarithmic let's say
right and then by giving these
conditions it was just shifting it up or
down and then when we discuss that we
realized that probably this is how we
would work let's say you are given 1,000
examples you see that all these curves
are a little bit like that and then by
having different initial conditions you
just move them up or down so you have
something like an average of your curve
and then you're moving up and down and
this is actually very cool because now
maybe if we give extra information like
for instance what is the structure of
your enzyme what is structure of your
compound maybe the model will start
figuring out the Dynamics like the Cur
the the the rate right so maybe it will
start moving left or right so this is
like this is our stage at this point so
we are working on that I think it's
super super
interesting uh and it can like at the
end of the day if we can create this
let's say foundation/ gen model that you
don't need to run in a wet lab you can
run on your laptop it's like amazing
right because you can very quickly
verify for given enzyme and compound
what is the enzyme kinetics of
that right and the last example sorry
when I'm getting excited I don't know
how much time do I have I I should
finish probably yeah all right sorry so
very quickly so this is about mechanics
of action uh uh so phenotypic profiling
with images so we used a data set that
was actually uh prepared here here in in
Broad
Institute and this is an example of uh
like a follow-up paper of uh a platform
or framework that we developed earlier
in Amsterdam at the University of
Amsterdam on attention-based multi-
instance learning for histopathology
slide we use it for for other data uh
and we used uh like pre-trained
embedding model so like a foundation
model on top of which we created a a ban
model right not going into the details
what was interesting is that oh sorry
another table I li to you so there are
two tables in this presentation another
table so we have uh obviously sorry guys
like AI spirit in me so we we got
state-ofthe-art
obviously uh H but what was interesting
is that because it has this attention
mechanism for everyone who is familiar
with attention mechanism so we can
actually use attention mechanism to
highlight which uh parts of the input
are important or not so where the model
uh puts some emphasis on and our model
this is uh it looks like a chair picked
it was but in general it it worked
pretty pretty this the same way so you
can see that actually our model put a
lot of emphasis on these small images
with some cells inside
and put very low for the background
basically so this is again how you would
expect this model to work right so
really really interesting uh part and so
to conclude I I I don't want to go
through that but in my opinion this is
very interesting how we can use gen for
really different applications not
necessarily only molecule generation but
really in many many other a part of the
the pipeline and I personally I believe
that this virtual cells organis is like
probably the way to go i' would like to
thank everyone and if you are
interesting we can talk more and uh in a
month I'm I'm moving to San Francisco
I'm joining Chan Zuckerberg uh
initiative so maybe we can also
collaborate in this
continent thanks
all right thank you so much uh given the
time maybe can we have one question uh
if you have uh can you uh come to the
stage while maybe um um can you the ab
team can you set up U put on J and the
zoom on the on the screen thank
you uh hi hi was it yeah hi my name is
no from Brown University uh I don't know
much about like enzyme kinetics but I've
seen your model I don't know why you
call it generative AI because it's more
like neural operator or like the
foundation model yeah but uh I I have a
question that what is the input of your
model that you get get the kinetics
right so thank you very good question so
indeed uh it's a little bit how you look
at the problem so like in general time
series forecasting is a perfect example
of an autoaggressive mod model and an
autoaggressive model is a generative
model but I'm not so like you know to me
it's tomato tomato a bit so you can call
it whatever you want right uh but uh
what is different here is because I saw
your poster by the way so very cool uh
one so it's a we we assume that we don't
know what is the OD so we don't use this
neural OD kind of ideas yes we really
want to be like fully data uh like uh
what is the input of your model is it
like the like initial conditions and
maybe some the parameters of the model
no no no no no we don't know we don't
know the parameters that's why it's not
working so well maybe right uh but we
have only the initial conditions and
part of your time series and that's it
so you don't know what is under the
hoood I see of course if we know it and
we should use it so this is but this is
for our future work yeah thank you so
much I have a similar work on like the
uh effect of the drug on two more growth
so we have state space model Mamba for
predicting the efficacy so in that case
we have like more feature uh and not
initial at all but like more feature
about the patient nice very cool I I
will come back very interesting talk
thank you thank you thank you very much
okay yeah with uh let's give the speaker
one more round of applause