Hi, I'm Mark Lindseay and I'm a
cardiologist specializing in genetic
arterial disease at the Massachusetts
General Hospital.
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Praep Nodarajin and I'm the
director of preventive cardiology and
genetics researcher at Mass General
Hospital and the Broad Institute of MIT
and Harvard.
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Tiffany Bellow and I'm a
vascular surgery resident at the
Massachusetts General Hospital.
Spontaneous coronary artery dissection
or SCAD is defined as a tear or a
separation in the wall of the coronary
artery, but it's not associated with
aththeroscerosis or trauma.
>> Scad has been known to affect men and
women. However, SCAD most commonly
affects women. SCAD is a rare condition
linked to arterial fragility sometimes
caused by well-known genetic disorders
like vascular ellers stanlo syndrome
marfan syndrome and log gene syndrome.
Researchers haven't yet found all the
genes that clearly increase the risk of
scat. We can increase the discovery of
genes associated with scat by collecting
health data and samples from larger and
more diverse patient groups.
GVAS is short for genetics of vascular
disease. This is a research study that
is designed to gather health information
from patients who have been diagnosed
with SCAD or other vascular
abnormalities. The study operates out of
Massachusetts General Hospital and the
Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard.
Participation in the GVAS study includes
completing surveys online about your
health information and providing a
saliva sample which can be mailed to
your home. All information will be kept
confidential and in a secure database
and will never be sold for profit.
The GVAS study aims to perform the
largest sequencing project to date of
individuals with SCAD. We are working
together to create a research community
of individuals highly motivated to
investigate the genetics of SCAD and set
the foundation for future research. This
community is enhanced by the
contributions and partnership from the
ISCAD registry and SCAD Alliance which
also aim to better understand and
support patients with SCAD.
>> We invite members of the SCAD community
to join the GVAS research study and
share it with others.
>> Your partnership will be key in
understanding why SCADAD happens and how
it can be prevented and treated.
>> Visit gvasstudy.org
to learn more and enroll into the study
and visit scanalliance.org. org to find
resources and support groups for members
of the SCAD community.