okay today we're going to do our second
lecture on
monopolies uh remember once again to set
the picture if we want to figure out how
much producers are going to produce we
need to know what Market structure they
sell into that's the sort of final
condition we need to pin down how much
producers produce we started with a
particular Market structure which was
perfect competition and showed how under
perfect competition with price equals
marginal cost we can pin down how much
producers produce we then turned last
lecture to an alternative Market
structure really The Other Extreme which
is Monopoly with only one firm in the
market and we showed how that can pin
down what producers produce but we also
showed that monopo breaks the link
between the positive equilibrium outcome
and the normative concept of efficiency
that we have an equilibrium outcome that
unlike with perfect competition is
inefficient we create a dead weight loss
because monopolists don't sell units
that they can produce more cheaply than
people are willing to pay for them and
they don't do that because they don't
want to poison their sales they don't
have to lower the price enough to get
additional
sales now what we're going to talk about
today is a couple topics within Monopoly
the first topic we'll talk about is
where do monopolies come from from so
how do monopolies arise or the origin of
Monopoly If you're sort of a marble fan
well this is our origin
story okay no no radioactive spiders or
anything okay but rather we're going to
talk about markets where Monopoly is
sort of inevitable and natural in
particular we'll talk about today
natural
monopolies natural monopolies
arise whenever there's a market
where for all relevant
quantities average cost is
falling in other words fixed cost is so
large relative to marginal cost you
remember our typical average cost curve
Falls and then
Rises we're going to have an example
where fixed costs are so large average
cost is always falling so for example
the classic example we' use is is like
producing Rock from a rock quarry you've
got to dig up Rock from this rock quarry
it's one resource there's one sort of
for historical reasons there's one
geological site where we can dig up
Rock okay it's a huge fixed cost finding
it digging it
out but the truth is creating a second
Rock cor would be incredible fixed cost
so the fixed cost of doing another one
is small relative to the ongoing
marginal cost or more generally this is
something where basically uh you would
see this in any sort of
utility like delivering water to houses
if you deliver water to houses you have
this incredibly expensive Enterprise of
laying all the pipes to deliver the
water and then the marginal cost is
pretty trivial you just pumped the water
through so the fixed costs are so
enormous that they're going to dwarf the
marginal cost for any relevant
quantity and we'll see what that looks
like in figure
121 figure 121 is a picture where the
average costs are everywhere above the
marginal
cost for all relevant quantities now
it's true could produce enough there's
some quantity for which average cost
will fall below marginal cost and start
to rise again but basically idea is the
range where average cost is falling
extends to the entire relevant range not
just the beginning as in previous
examples why is this cause Monopoly it
causes Monopoly because the it creates
such a barrier to entry that no one else
can enter imagine you tried imagine you
saw this Market you saw this water
utility okay and you said look there's
profits be made average costs above
marginal
cost okay is is is declining above
marginal cost there's profits to be made
because average cost is falling I'm
going to enter okay what would the
existing firm
do what could the exist the ex existing
firm that's already invested in the
water pipes you say I'm going to lay a
whole new set of water pipes and sell
water more cheaply what would they
do what would existing firm do
well you're an existing firm you've laid
these water pipes you have this graph in
front of you you're setting your price
at some level well above marginal cost
what do you
do yeah lower your price if you lower
your price to marginal cost no firm no
other firm can make money because then
price is below average cost and you lose
money but for you you've already paid
the fixed costs so for you you're still
making money in the marginal unit so
yeah the existing fir just lowers its
price towards marginal cost below
average cost any other firm looks and
says look I can't make back my average
cost I'm not going to enter once you
scare them off you raise your price back
up so in a market like this it is
natural it's indeed proper to only have
one firm it makes no sense to have a
second set of pipes going all the way
through the town delivering water to
houses it just makes no sense so in this
case a monopoly is
natural and this is basically an example
where a fixed cost
creates a barrier to entry the fixed
cost is so large that you never enter
remember I talked about how we never
have perpect competition because there's
always some slight barried entry someone
can beat you up if you try to L sell
additional you know uh little eiel ta
Tower figures or whatever there's always
some fixed always in bar entry here the
bar entry is so large because the nor as
fixed cost basically no one's ever once
someone's in no one else is ever going
to enter and therefore it's a natural
monopoly
yeah well with there's nobody delivering
water there's money to be made because
the first room is Monopoly we know
monopolies make profits so if there's no
one they can come in and lay the pipes
and make and make money now you might
say how do they know someone else won't
come in lay and faster that's an
interesting that's exactly the kind of
fun stuff we don't have time to get into
in this class but if you take Game
Theory
1412 uh they'll teach you all about how
we think about these different things
and I'll get into that I'm going to do a
couple exra in Game Theory but not
nearly enough but think of it as one
firm just sort of happen to go first and
they own it
okay other
questions so that's one reason One Way
monopolies can arise another way
monopolies can arise so one way is a
natural monopoly another way monopolies
can arise is the government can create
monopolies the government can actually
create monopolies one is by actually
literally delivering the service so in
most countries when they're young
governments do a lot of things we think
is private now like they run the
airlines they run the steel industry
they run the banks and even in mature
economies governments still do some
services like run the Postal
Service there's activities that
governments can just do and say we're
goingon to have the Monopoly on them and
we are going to deliver these Services
now as as economies mature typically
those get shifted off to the private
sector okay and we'll we'll come back a
little bit to that but basically uh that
is sort of one way the more common way
that so one way of government Crea
Monopoly is through
delivery but the more common way of
government cre Monopoly is through
property rights in particular patents
and
copyrights we talked about copyright
last time with huckin and Fahrenheit
451 but a patent is basically an
exclusive right to sell a good for some
period of time in the US 17 years
typically so the way patent work you
file for a patent if it's granted then
you are essentially a time limit of
Monopoly you have the exclusive right to
sell that
good so what how do we feel about
patents well in fact there's a good and
a bad side what's the bad side of
patents what's the bad side of offering
patents yeah it's a monopoly you create
deadweight loss it's inefficient what's
the good side offering
patents
yeah yeah you basically why invent
something if you can't make any money
off it they create incentives to
innovate and invent because there's no
patents the me you invented something
someone to just steal it and produce it
at marginal cost or marginal cost plus
Epson you wouldn't make any money so why
put the work in so it's a tradeoff with
patents between incentives for
investment for
Innovation and Monopoly costs to uh
to Consumers so basically the optimal
patent trades off these concerns you
want a patent that gives enough rights
to incent
Innovation and not so much rights that
you overly hurt
consumers so for example let's take
Pharmaceuticals developing a new drug is
incredibly
expensive roughly speaking um about one
in every
10,000 compounds you try is going to end
up working in terms of being effective
drug once you have a compound that you
think works you do animal testing in
Phase then you have to do three levels
of human
testing the best estimates although
they're rough is that developing a New
Drug in the US today costs about2
billion
doar about2 billion not not not if you
knew ahead it was going to work but if
you take all the failures along the way
on average by the time you develop the
drug you spent $2 billion that's a lot
of money okay so basically um what we do
is we give a patent for 17 years and
then when the patent expires other
companies allowed to enter brce what's
called generic drugs so you have a name
brand drug you invent it you get 17
years and then after those 17 years
anybody can enter it the formulation
becomes public and they just produce it
at marginal cost and your profits all go
away in theory that's how it works and
in theory we'd have an easy solution we
just say well well set up an
optimization problem where you optimize
the incentives to innovate versus the
losses to Consumers clearly the optim
will not be a patent last
forever and clearly optim will not be no
patent it'll be somewhere in between who
knows the 17 years right but you could
you could the economics gives the tools
to think about this trade-off now right
the problem is in practice it doesn't
work that well there's a lot of problems
with the patent system the first is that
companies have a lot of incentive to
think up creative ways to effectively
extend their
patent okay so for example one thing
drug companies will do is do something
called pay for delay let's say I've got
some name Brad brand drug and Pedro is a
potential generic uh innovator he wants
to enter and make my drug and I say
Pedro look I'm making like a billion
year on this drug you're a a generate
guy you're not going to make much money
because you're coming in competitive
market I'll pay you $500 million not to
come in
Pat's like great I didn't do I got
$500 million I'm still making $500
million in
profits so I can effectively extend my
patent or what I can do is I can tweak
the formulation and apply for a new
patent so for example insulin is
incredibly cheap to
make okay and it was invented the
inventors were academics who gave away
the patent for a dollar because they
wanted to be publicly available but it
cost a ton of money why because there's
always Innovations and delivering in
that make it a little more efficient a
little better now they are true
Innovations but each one extends the
patent and makes insulin more expensive
and that trade-off is not really what
was what we're that's sort of a
different way in the system is supposed
to work so that's one reason this
doesn't work the other reason is that
generic markets aren't as competitive as
we'd like to think so
epipens which are now epinephrine is a
generic drug still cost $600
why epens cost $600 because it turns out
it's expensive to make an EpiPen the
delivery device and stuff is expensive
and firms aren't
entering and as we'll talk about
starting next lecture unless you have
perfect competition there'll be profits
and there'll be dead weight
loss okay that's the second
reason a third reason is the biggest
challenge yet which is for the new class
of drugs being made called
biologics which are not stable small
cell stable large cell I'm sorry drug
development but literally drugs that are
developed and injected and are
essentially um formulated they're
biological formulations that are live
effectively it's hard to make an
effective
generic and so generic composition May
simply not exist for these new biologic
drugs which is the new class of drugs
which are making incredible uh steps and
let's be clear the innovation in
Pharmaceuticals is
unbelievable okay just one example
there's a horrible horrible disease
called spin or muscular
atrophy if the baby if your B it's a
genetic disease purely random if you're
born with it your life is brutal
miserable and you're dead by two I mean
awful can't imagine anything worse as
app parent they've cured it they
developed a miracle cure it's a new
called selling gene therapy would
literally inject a virus in the baby's
body containing a new patched Gene it
goes through the body and repairs it
it's a miracle it's the kind of thing
you guys are doing here at MIT every day
and it's only going to get better this
drug cost $2.1
million now on the one hand I say $2.1
million that's a lot of money on the
other hand you're saving a baby's life
you are adding potentially 80 to 100
years of life to someone21 million is
actually a pretty good deal on the other
hand if we develop drugs for everything
like this we'll bankrupt our country so
these are the kind of difficult issues
we raise in wanting give incenters for
Innovation but also being ultimately
affordable uh in terms of what consumers
need to Consumers need to
buy okay questions about
that okay and this is if this is
something that interests you um this is
a big debate in the US right now as part
of President Biden's uh inflation
reduction act the IRA the government for
the first time is actually regulating
the price of pharmaceuticals it's
actually saying to some Pharmaceuticals
that have competitors look you know
we're going to regulate your price
because we think you're making too much
money the government's decide the patent
system isn't working it's out of balance
and so drug companies are making too
much money and they're regulating prices
and that was very controversial and uh a
significant step forward in how we think
about drug pricing in the US and you can
read more about that if that's something
that interests you and certainly if you
want to go into bi biological
engineering or or or any of those fields
this is something important to know
about okay so that's the first topic I
want to cover where do monopolies come
from the second topic I want to cover is
addressing Monopoly because this is
where things get exciting from my
perspective I'm a big government liberal
okay I think government can do good
things yet everything I've taught you in
this course government's the bad guy
okay I don't like that but that's the
way Bates economics works and let's be
clear that that's the proper way to
teach the first half of this course the
first fundamental theorem of what for
economics says government only does bad
things okay but that's not true in
reality and here's the first case we get
to see where government can potentially
but not obviously make things better and
that is through regulating
monopolies so for example let's go to
figure
122 figure 122 is the same figure we
ended with last time you've got a
marginal cost curve a demand curve and a
marginal revenue curve the marginal ring
curve intersects marginal costs at six
units producing six units you respect
the demand curve you charge a price of
18 six units get produced we get a dead
weight loss of C plus
e so as we said the market outcome is
not
efficient what can the government do
well what if the government set a price
ceiling and said we are not going to let
the monopolist charge more than
16 we not going to let the monopolis
charge more than
16 well then the new marginal cost curve
from for the monopolist the new supply
curve
or or the new it's essentially the new
uh marginal revenue curve I'm sorry the
new marginal revenue curve becomes the
flat line all the way to point e what is
that e c it should be that intersection
of the red and blue lines the flat line
all the point that little e e z I guess
it looks like it should be EC and then
it drops the dash line down you go back
to the old margin Revenue curve so you
draw the solid line from the 16 on the
y- axis over to the what looks like e0
follow that dash line down and then
rejoin the original marginal revenue
curve that's the new marginal revenue
curve why well think about what marginal
revenue
is okay if you
produce remember in the old world if you
produce the seventh
unit okay your marginal revenue is your
your profits fall because of the
poisoning effect but now if you produce
the seventh unit you can only charge 16
that's the most you can
charge so you might as well produce it
at if you can only charge 16 if that's
the limit then at that point your your
costs are
below your marginal revenue so you
produce in other words the marginal
revenue in the old point when you went
to the seventh
unit marginal cost was above marginal
revenue now going to the seventh unit
it's not because we haven't let you
raised your price so the government by
regulating and saying the price has to
be set at 16
is essentially taking away the poisoning
effect the poisoning effect
arises because if I want to sell one
moreon have to lower my price well here
your price is already low I haven't let
you raise your price I haven't let you
set it at
18 before you didn't want to sell the
seventh unit you lower your price to 17
right well now your price is already 16
so why not sell the seventh
Unit 16 is still above marginal cost so
why not do it so essentially the optimal
solution from the monopolis then is to
sell eight
to sell the competitive quantity if you
tell the monopolis they can't charge
more than 16 they have they will they
will sell the competitive quantity and
guess what dead weight loss has gone
away we're now selling the
competitive amount and dead weight loss
is going
away
okay
so let's think about an example of this
and how the government could make things
better okay and let's come to a case of
a natural monopoly which is
broadband Broadband
delivery to deliver Broadband it's not a
fully natural monopoly and that multiple
people can lay the lines that come to
your house but it's a big fixed cost if
you want to set up a Broadband
competitor you have to go out and lay a
whole bunch of new fiber cable okay
that's expensive it's not infinite it's
not like a water utility it's doable and
it happens but it's pretty expensive
competition will be definitely Limited
may not be natural monopoly certainly
natural oligopoly you're not going to
have hundreds of firms laying these
wires getting price making prices
competitive okay so for example across
20,000 us zip codes
70% have either zero or
one option for 25 uh for 25 megabytes
per second
service okay zero or one on is that a
megabytes per second I say that right I
think so I hope so Mbps I think I got
that right uh Z One
options okay even at the lowest possible
speed of internet service only 30% of
zip codes have more than one option for
getting Broadband 30% of America has
only one option for getting their
Broadband why because it's a natural
monopoly in many cases the costs are
really high if you're in some rural town
it's not effective to lay a second set
of wires going to people's
houses okay as a result
prices are high and there's Monopoly
power now you might say well John and
the Broadband companies will say well
John because they have deep voices John
how do you know we have Monopoly power
just because there's not that many we
still could be pricing competitively
well economists have developed a very
clever test fors Monopoly power which is
they ask what happens to prices as more
firms
enter if a Market's competitive what
should an additional firm entering do to
the price
no if a Market's perfectly competitive
what should additional firm entering doe
to the price if it's perfectly
competitive price is already set to
marginal cost it shouldn't do
anything price is already marginal cost
so additional firm shouldn't have a
meaningful effect on the price maybe go
down a little but not meaningful if it's
a monopoly market and you add a second
firm price will come down a lot and
we'll TR that next next
lecture so the way to test this is ask
what happens as more firms enter markets
do prices come down a little
or do they come down a
lot and the answer is it comes down a
lot so basically for every um for
gigabyte internet moving from one
provider to two providers of gigabyte
internet lowers the monthly price by 60
bucks a month literally you pay 60 bucks
less a month for gigabyte internet when
you get go from one provider to two
provider that is not a competitive
market
okay so obviously there are huge
Monopoly rents being made in these
markets so what could we do well the
answer is easy we regulate the
price we say look we're going to
regulate the price at a level you know
you can't regulate at truly marginal
cost because then no one will enter it's
the question I got before why would any
enter but you say look marginal costs
this is what we do for example with
electricity and water those are Public
Utilities the way we regulate we say
look you have an acceptable profit rate
will let you make 10% whatever it is and
regulate the price at the marginal cost
plus that profit rate you do the same
thing with Broadband we already do it we
electricity and water we have plenty of
electricity and water in the US why not
just do the same thing in Broadband
indeed that's what they do in
Europe in Europe they have quite an
interesting approach they they have a
different they regul the price but
actually they do a different kind of
regulation in Europe the public owns the
lines and the companies compete on
sending the signal over the lines
it's kind of a clever approach the fixed
cost part is laying the lines right the
marginal cost part is setting the signal
over the lines so the government owns
the lines and companies compete on who
sends the signals and Broadband if you
ever been to Europe is incredibly cheap
compared to
here okay that's when way to do it or
alternatively if we don't like that we
could just regulate the price so why
don't we just do that why don't we just
do what figure 122
suggest well the answer is because it
turns out to be hard because we don't
get these handouts in the real world
okay in the real world we have to figure
out what the competitive price is and
that turns out to be hard it turns out
to be hard because we need to know what
demand curves look like and what Supply
curves look like and both are hard to
measure let's start with demand
curves you might say look it's easy to
measure a demand curve just ask people
they're willing us to pay you say
literally I go and I do a survey of all
the customers are Bron band I say how
much you willing to pay for each of
these different
options for broadband and then I
regulate the price the problem is people
have no idea what it's worth to
them people don't know when you ask
people with stuff's Worth to them and it
is something they buy all the time they
don't know if you ask me what an Apple's
Worth to I say well I've gone to the
store and apple you know Apple cost
that's about 80 cents or a buck for an
apple you know for a good apple per
pound I can get a sense if you said
would you pay five bucks for an apple
I'd say no but I don't honestly know I
mean if you said would you pay $1,000 a
month for internet that's too much and
zero sounds cheap but 60 100 150 I I
have a harder time figuring out what's a
fair price okay this is obviously an
even bigger problem when you think not
just about regulating broad Bend but
they regulating things like the
environment regulating things like U
stopping oil spills or global warming so
for example if you ask people what
environmental benefits are worth they
have no idea so for example if you ask
people what it's worth to save the Grand
Canyon and you first ask as a standalone
question and then separately ask as one
of five questions in the second case
people give a value that's one as big
shouldn't matter right just your value
but the problem is they don't know um if
you ask people how much they'll pay to
save a whale and save a seal if you ask
them how they'll pay to to say a to save
a whale and save a seal they'll pay $172
to save a whale and $85 save a seal that
make sense Wells are bigger okay if you
ask the order reversed
and say that um how much save a seal and
how much save a whale people say they're
about worth the
same okay um if you ask people how much
they'll pay to save a thousand birds or
a million birds or a billion Birds they
give the same answer none of these
things are consistent with any form of
utility that we write down in this class
people clearly don't know so it's hard
to measure demand it's easy to measure
demand when there's a price signal when
you see different prices and you see
well want different prices but when you
try to create a new market and you have
to rely on willingness to pay that's
hard that's the first problem demand
curves are hard to draw the second
problem is Supply curves are hard now
you might say here well it's easy you
just go to the firm and you say well
give me your marginal
cost and that's great and what does the
firm
say when you say give me Marin cost they
say sure what do they give
you if you're running a firm what would
you do
yeah You' give them the biggest possible
margin cost you could ever justify in
the world remember my story about the SE
about the CEO wanted his own plane
that's nothing compared to this okay the
problem is you're trying to regulate an
industry that knows more about itself
than you do so it's hard to know what
Supply is
either so the problem with regulation is
that you're you can't just draw these
neat diagrams you have to guess at them
which is fine except if you get it wrong
you can make things worse take a look at
figure
123 imagine the government
decided that it was set the price at 10
it had some base setting theice it it
got its own demand curves Supply curves
it decided 10 was the competitive price
whereas we know the right competitive
price is 16 what happens this Market
sets the price at 10 well at a price of
10 the optimal Monopoly choice you
should solve this for yourself is to
produce five
units at a price of 10 well that creates
even bigger dead weight loss than if you
just let the Monopoly rip you've lost an
extra that extra shaded
area Okay from regulating the price at
10 so the government's made things worse
it could be even worse if you're at the
price low enough you could just kill the
industry the industry can say I'm not
going to form at all because the price
isn't is too low how would you know the
industry didn't exist how would you know
the regulations killed
it okay so
basically regulation is tricky there's a
recent research paper I learned about
where someone looked at what happened
when the Food and Drug Administration
which regulates medical devices loosened
the regulation categories of medical
devices you want the regular devices
right you want there to be sa you
worried about safety you want some
regulation when they loosen the
regulations they found Innovation went
up a th% and there was no worst safety
clearly they were overregulation
uh what the tradeoff is with government
intervention and this is sort of the
point of my entire course
1441 which is markets typically feature
market failure there's honestly truly
almost no Market in America doesn't
feature market failure of some type if
there's a market failure then in theory
the government can make it better in
practice it's not clear it
will so the fact there's market failure
does not
justify you saying there that a
government regulation it better it might
make it better it justifies considering
the government regulation but you still
don't know it makes it better until you
do the careful empirical
analysis okay questions about
that now let's say you're worried about
that and you're worried you say look I'm
really worried about regulating but
there's this Monopoly and it's consumers
are losing out and I don't know what to
do well there's another option
governments have which which is
governments rather than creating an
creating Monopoly in the way it does up
there governments can reduce Monopoly by
injecting competition into markets and
there's no better example of that than
the market for
Education take a look at figure uh
124 figure 124 is from my textbook it
shows educational
spending in Blue by each country per
student so the US is about
almost 12,000 per student the Czech
Republic is about less than 6,000 per
student in Orange it shows that
country's performance on an
international math
exam Czech Republic does better than the
US indeed the US despite spending by far
the most per capita on education it's
pretty mediocre in international
comparisons of Education
systems now there's lots of reasons that
could be but clearly our schools are not
uh getting it done are not
delivering return for the proper return
for our
dollar one solution to that is say well
part of the reason they're not is
because schools are monopolies how many
you went to public school how many you
went to most of you okay public schools
are
monopolies I live in lexingon my kids if
they want to go public high school go to
lexingon high school it's not like can
say I'd prefer you know to go to brain
tree high school instead I don't have
that choice I have no choice it's a
monopoly now in some cities it's not
quite right some cities do have a choice
of say Elementary School some of you may
have if you ever grew up you grew up in
Chicago or Cambridge or some cities
where you can choose your elementary
school but typically you can't choose
the choice is not a feature of um of uh
Public Schools so the idea is since the
fear is since we've created these
monopolies have we created inefficient
schools that not delivering proper
benefits cuz remember I said when
Monopoly they can make profits well if
it's a monopoly where you can't make
profits but there's no competition the
other way can come out is just not doing
a good not being efficient there's no
incentive to efficient if you a monopoly
we could set your
price then there's every incentive to be
efficient because every dollar
efficiency gains a dollar profits but
imagine your Monopoly that can't set
your
price why work so hard to be
efficient right what's the pressure on
you to do so why not have a slightly
easier life and that's the concerns
happen with schools so that's why
there's a big move introduce competition
into the US public school
system okay one way to do so as I said
some schools have introduced what we
call public school choice they've
allowed students to choose across public
schools and the dollars follow the
students so if you're a shitty
Elementary School and folks leave you
get less money so suddenly it matters
quality matters for how much money you
have to function and that's uh that's
one approach that's been tried generally
does not seem to show it has a huge
effect on student performance
the other approach that's been tried is
to set up alternatives to the
traditional public school and the most
popular those most well known as charter
schools did any goes guys go to Charter
School yeah there's uh charter schools
are essentially non-traditional
Alternatives that are publicly funded so
idea is you've got your Lex in high
school and you've got your you know
achievement Academy charter school and
that Charter School often they're
for-profit sometimes they're nonprofit
are essentially Place students can go
they're still funded by the public
sector but they are not abiding by the
same set of rules necessarily for
instance they don't have to hire
unionized teachers Etc and they provide
a competitive alternative and in fact
charter schools have been shown by my
colleagues here MIT who've done the
leading research in the world to be
generally a very effective alternative
to private to public schools that
students who go to Charter School when
you put in a charter school students do
better okay the competition is working
in the context of Education by having
these educational
Alternatives so here's the case and in
particular let me say in particular for
disadvantaged students the group that
benefits the most from charter schools
are minorities under and and low-income
students they benefit the most from
having this alternative so here's an
example of another way governments can
try to deal with Market power is by
introducing uh introducing
Alternatives so the bottom line is
governments have the bottom line is
monopolies
exist okay governments the fact they
exists creates deadweight loss in the
market in fact it's good that they exist
in many cases like Pharmaceuticals we
want patents but at the same time we
want to figure out the optimal way to
deliver
Innovation but minimize the loss to
Consumers government regulation is one
way to do that okay another way is by
increasing competition in the market
okay questions about
that okay let's come to the third point
I want to talk about which is an
important
concept that is sort of starts to lead
us towards a more subtle way of think
about marks we've thought about two
extremes we've thought about perfect
competition and Monopoly starting next
time we're going to start talking more
generally about oligopoly in between
cases one sort of Bridge to that is the
notion of what we call contestable
markets
contestable
markets a contestable market is one
where there is a monopoly Advantage but
it's not so
big it's sort of like a natural monopoly
but with a natural par isn't so large
with a sunfix costs they're pretty big
but they're not so big that someone
couldn't enter at some point point the
idea here is there will be a
monopoly but it won't make that much
money the idea is there'll be a monopoly
but if it tries to set price too high
then it will cover fixed cost and firms
will
enter so monopolies are sort of in a
contestable market monopolies have
barriers to entry but they're not so
big that they can go nuts and charge
full Monopoly
prices okay and the most famous example
of this was in the era of
Airlines when I was a
kid Airlines were a regulated
Monopoly if you want to fly from A to B
you had to apply to the government they
gave permission to supply from A to B
and they regulated the price you could
charge
okay and um in that World um basically
the view was governments kind of didn't
do a very good job and Airlines made a
lot of money the view is governments
because remember the airlines kind of
lie about their marginal cost and the
view was governments were sort of in
their pocket and the government was
setting prices too highs and making a
lot of money and Economist said you know
what you don't have to regulate this
industry yeah it's a natural monopoly
but it's also a very contestable Market
okay the fixed costs aren't that fixed
cost aren't that huge because there's
lots of planes for sale planes that are
a couple years old still work really
well and other airlines can buy them
this is actually not that hard industry
to enter I mean it's hard I can't enter
it but it takes you know tens of
millions not billions to get into this
industry so actually if we get rid of
Regulation we can actually do better
than if we keep regulation you're in a
case where essentially you're setting
the price so high that if you just let
competition work will do better and
economists actually won the day
economist convinced the government to
deregulate the airline
industry so what happened three things
first prices fell enormously economists
were right prices fell by about a third
the unregulated prices were about
two-thirds of what the regulated prices
were because economists were right the
government had set the price too high an
example is that when I was at MIT in the
1980s I would fly home to Newark on
people's Express People's Express which
sounds like a communist organization was
this new airline that was introduced in
the new deregulated Market in 1984 the
market had only been deregulated about a
decade so so this new Airline and I
would fly from Boston to New York for
$19.99 okay I mean now it's a few
hundred dollars right it was before that
Airline also a couple hundred bucks
literally didn't even reserve a spot you
just literally showed up and lined up
when the plane was full they took off I
I don't know then they went they came
through with the cart and you paid on
the plane I don't know like if you
didn't have money they throw you off I
don't know but like literally it was so
cheap to fly prices came way down from
what they used to
be the second is the number of routes
that were
flown went way
up because it turns out there were lots
of routes that were profitable to fly
the government wouldn't let happen it
turned out airlin say well look if you
let me charge what I want I can figure
out would make this route profitable so
there's a huge increase in Access huge
increase in where planes went at a much
lower
price third
effect service
quality
tanked flying used to be fun when I was
a kid everything was free you got in the
plane free food free booze real
silverware huge leg room no no charge
for anything free bags okay any of you
watch Mad Men and watch you know Don Don
Draper fly that's what it's like he's
not even flying business class in those
shows it was awesome flying today sucks
we all know
that okay so why did that
happen why did quality deteriorate so
much but we deregulate Airlines why did
quality fall so much yeah actually
really funny because we're doing a
project in another CL
okay um long story short like in order
to have such good customer service you
have to through a lot of employees and
so your TR is be really high as a result
as soon as you start getting market
share for like people's econom
people Legacy
carriers yeah I mean that's a little
more detailed answer than I wanted but
basically the bottom line is when you
are regulated on
price but you have different planes
flying the same route how do they
compete on quality right in a in the
markets we've discussed so far the only
way firms can compete is on price but
firms compete in reality along multiple
Dimensions so in the old days if United
America were both flying to
Chicago and they had to charge the same
price how did they get your business by
being a nicer
experience now suddenly they can compete
on price they said we're not going to be
nicer experienc anymore it's too
expensive we're just going to charge a
lower price
now you might say well gee that sucks
that's a terrible thing it's horrible
Airline quality fault why would I tell
you you're wrong why would I tell you
it's good that Airline quality fell why
can I say for sure we're better in a
world with lower prices and lower
quality than we are than we are in a
world with higher price and higher
quality
yeah well I I don't know that because
only because I grew a draft in prices I
didn't draw a draft in
quality I don't know that we got rid of
the Dead weight loss for sure
but I do know something else what do I
know what fact is true
yeah what's
that well it's more accessible we flying
more routes but they're shitty how do I
know people wouldn't
rather do something else yeah you can
still pay for a better experience so the
fact that people are buying a cheaper
ticket yeah because we haven't ruled out
high quality high prices just no one
wants it okay so people who bit
about oh flying's terrible they don't
about the fact it's really cheap
and if you don't like that fly business
class or if you don't like that get
together and form an airline that gives
the old high quality high prices JetBlue
sort of tried to do this JetBlue was
kind of a better experience now that
kind of deteriorated back towards what
the airlines are when jebl started you
get all these free snacks and stuff
which no one was doing okay they were
trying to do that a little bit but the
bottom line is if you want to tell me
gee the old world was better I tell you
fine go back to the old world if it was
better it should exist it doesn't
because while people don't while people
may about flying now they they
aren't bitching about the prices and
we're happier and this is the key
concept once again of revealed
preference this is how economists test
welfare conclusions we use revealed
preference we've revealed that we'd
rather have low quality at low prices
because it's rewarded in the market new
lowcost airlines that suck enter all the
time but high-end Airlines don't so we
we want low quality at low prices I we
i' rather have high quality at low
prices but that's not an option okay
that's the third thing that happened the
fourth thing that happened actually five
things happened the fourth thing that
happened is that safety the other thing
you'd be concerned about is well gee now
there's no one said it to be safe but in
fact it turns out safety didn't
change it turns out there's still enough
instead of to be safe that it wasn't
like the regulation was actually making
flying any safer flying is unbelievable
safe it always was it always
is so this is all great news Economist
for the win except economists got one
thing
wrong we got one thing wrong which we
missed the fact that while there's not
huge barriers to entry in terms of
airplanes there is huge barriers to
entry in terms of what what's the
barrier to entry yeah airport
slots that those are fixed and that it's
incredibly hard to expand an airport it
took Logan airport until about 12 years
ago had one Runway at night one runway
in Boston at night think about that for
the city of Boston we expanded to two it
took 25 years to happen to expand a two
runways okay it is very hard to add new
airport slots as a result there is a
truly fixed barrier which is Airline
slots and as a result competition did
not go up as much as we thought take
Minnesota where I had to fly for years
to visit my wife's family okay Minnesota
was served almost as a monopoly by what
was called Northwest Airlines in our
part of
Delta now why didn't the city of mota of
Minneapolis and Northwest control all
the slots at the airport why does it in
Minneapolis say hey Northwest we're
going to take a a few of your slots and
allow another airline to come
in and create some competition why
because Northwest Airlines was
headquartered in Minneapolis and said if
you do that we'll leave and we'll take
all our jobs with
us and so essentially uh the city of
this city of Minneapolis barely let any
competition
in as a result of this ability to sort
of monopolize slots Airlines set up what
we call the Hub and spoke
system which is if you want to fly from
A to B you got it on the way stop at C
which is their headquarters
airport okay so Airlines funneled all
their traffic through airports where
there're sort of
monopolies and as a result while there's
much more competition prices did come
down a third there's much less than we
thought there would
be because we missed the fact that the
airport slots are truly fixed and aren't
expanding so there a great lesson in the
power of Economics but even the creative
economic aabus can't see the future
industry is incredibly creative at
maximizing its profits
and that they will come up with things
uh to get around almost any well meaning
government intervention doesn't mean
government interventions aren't a good
thing to do doesn't mean we can't do
more but it does mean we have to
consider we think about projecting the
effects of government interventions how
industry will respond what we call the
Dynamics we can't just say this is the
way the industry works today so it'll
always work that way we have to consider
well what are the other angles how's the
industry going to respond and that's
once again a big challenge for
government policy maker is envisioning
worlds that might be under your
regulatory environment not as it is
today