okay good
afternoon so we are
back with chemical
reactions systems subject to chemical
reactions and
today we will uh talk about the
statement of the second
law and a small detail that is in there
that regards chemical reactions and then
we'll
start playing
some uh more
interesting physics of of how chemical
reactions happen
so remember that in order to describe
the chemical reaction mechanism we
Define uh an
equation uh which we can write in
various
forms formally the generic chemical
equation reaction mechanism can be
written this way where these are the
chemical symbols and these are the
stochiometric
coefficients okay and the
proportionality
relations uh
relate changes the possible changes in
composition now uh let's go back to the
statement of the second law this is the
the same slide that we have seen
um long
ago second lecture I believe and
uh or maybe even the first uh where I
added some more specifics
because we didn't stress it then but in
the statement we wrote that
um in the subset of states of a system
compatible with given values of the
amounts of
constituents I sort of skipped
discussing what that compatible means
because now we have the tools so
compatible means
that uh the amounts of constituents may
be different may change according to an
internal mechanism such as a chemical
reaction so in fact when we fix when we
say that there is a stable equilibrium
state for each value of the energy the
amounts of constituents and the
parameters it's
really uh it's it's not exactly the
amount of constituent
but it's a given set of compatible uh
possible U
compositions corresponding to for
example an initial am set of amounts so
for example suppose we say we
characterize a a set of
[Music]
compatible uh amounts of constituents by
a given set of values of amounts like an
initial set we put molecules in a box
then we close the
box but then uh the chemical reactions
can change these amounts due
to the collisions and the and the
reactions themselves so according to
these
relation so that defines what we mean by
compatible and also here it says that
from any initial uh
composition and the values of the
parameters we can reach a stable
equilibrium state by means of a
reversible weight
process uh that's really true also if
you can change the composition
compatibly with the chemical reaction
mechanisms that you have defined as part
of your of your model as being possible
for your system remember that we're
always talking about a model okay so in
a model you specify what the what the
constituents are and also you have to
specify what the uh allowed chemical
reaction mechanisms
are you
change one of these for example you you
add one chemical reaction that is a
different
system so it's part of the definition of
system is also
this all right so what the what does
that
imply well it
implies that since the composition can
change they
become like properties from state to
state you have different composition so
you can measure uh what's the current
composition something that you can
measure uh corresponds to a
property so the amounts become
properties and at stable
equilibrium there is only
one
uh uh stable equilibrium state that
means there is only one composition that
stable that is a stable equilibrium for
the given set of parameters energy and
compatible composition so that means
that within that set of compatible
composition only one for each value of
the energy is a a stable equilibrium
composition all right so we have to deal
with this uh difficulties so we
can somehow
restate uh the the state principle and
the maximum entropy principle
what I just
said is that any property and now that
list of properties includes the
amounts of
constituents uh is
uniquely uh fixed by the state so the
once you once you have a stable
equilibrium State and you have one for
each value of the energy volume initial
amounts and stochiometric coefficients
that defin what the mechanisms are in
play okay for that
one that fixes the state and therefore
fixes the values of all the properties
therefore each property is only at
stable equilibrium because this is true
only at stable equilibrium is a function
of these variables and only
these and among these
properties is the
amounts so we call n Sub Zero the
amounts that Prevail at uh stable
equilibrium so in addition to the
fundamental relation for the entropy
which is this
one with which we have played a lot in
Computing derivatives properties
temperature chemical potential pressure
and so
on we now have also another
we could call it another fundamental
relation for
composition or
equivalently since composition and
reaction coordinates are related this
way you can also write it equivalently
this is not an extra equation in terms
of uh the Epsilon and here I have to
correct this must be
epsilon0 okay
the maximum entropy principle then
says that among all the
states and here in the slide I didn't
write it explicitly so now we should we
we should go back and
correct uh States compatible with given
initial amounts of constituents
parameters and energy so among all these
states and there are many uh the stable
equilibrium state is the one with the
maximum Maxum
entropy and we shall use this condition
of Maximum
entropy in a moment to determine what
the equilibrium composition
is in order to do so we have to Define
better or maybe let's say refine
with an important little detail the
simple system model namely the model
that applies when we have many particles
large
and remember this slide which tells us
how strong the chemical bonds may
be and
yet as a result of
cions these chemical bonds can be broken
to form more stable
ones or in fact also the collisions of
these more stable ones sometimes if the
Collision is strong
enough can produce the breakup into uh
products that are lesser stable and
actually at equilibrium the mechanism
that goes in One Direction equilibrates
uh the rate at which things go in One
Direction uh he equilibrates the rate in
the opposite
direction so this slide you'll read it
later on but simply wants to talk about
collisions I actually added this
Photograph this morning because I was
passing in the
fourth floor Corridor in um building 10
where you probably uh have gone and seen
these photographs by doc
Edgerton
um and you see how uh a
collision uh between a golf club and the
golf ball can
deform the ball which if you take it in
your hands you know it's kind of hard it
looks like a very hard almost a hard
sphere yet
uh the photograph shows that even
in I think uh yeah it says six six
milliseconds uh I think it takes six
milliseconds or less to uh during that
impact which is very
short
uh the
particle gets deformed so much so it
since it is elastic it absorbs the
energy kinetic energy that comes from
from the club and it becomes the
formation energy like a spring and then
that energy stored in the spring uh will
be
released very quickly so in the case of
the golf Bowl it
[Music]
will hit it at a very long distance in
the case of
molecules it may
generate uh the breaking of some of the
weaker bonds and uh the formation of
other more stable
bonds there is also this other video in
YouTube which shows you
again
um the impact of a golf club of a
golf bow into a rigid really rigid wall
it's see how it it's impressive how it
deforms it becomes almost flat and then
it begins to oscillate as it goes
away very impressive so this is uh
collisions are play an important role in
chemical
reactions now so let's introduce now
this
concept that we will call
the activated
complex as a result of a collision
between
molecules
typically as you
know uh by thermal agitation molecules
are move around and have many
collisions per second billions and and
um as a result of these collisions they
get deformed they do what we just said
sometimes uh the combined kinetic energy
of the colliding uh atoms or molecules
are enough to
form um
a sort of an unstable
compound which we will call activated
complex and uh call it with the star on
top and this compound
is momentary is
momentary lives it's very short lived
and uh it's
unstable and uh and this is where if it
decays the proper way in other words if
it if the uh elastic energy the
vibrational energies get the get um move
to the right uh to the right bonds so as
to break them and to uh so so that the
atoms are free to recombine in a
different way then you'll have an
effective Collision that will transform
your reactants in
products
uh of
course this is um Contour through
Contour plot of a of
a of a diagram that wants to represent
uh
here the most stable
potential configuration that represents
the potential energy of your say uh AB
plus C is the products okay and
here the in this bottom of this other
Valley uh you have the potential
energy combined of the uh reactants
and
um so typically if you are at zero
temperature particles don't move no
collisions no chance to reach uh uh
enough energy to overcome because you
see this is a it's like two
valys and this is a subtle point that
connects the two valys okay and this one
which is uh this dashed line
represents the like the
bottom let's say the steepest ascent and
steepest
descent uh path uh from the reactant
Valley to
the product Valley of the potential
energy so if energy is only potential
you are at zero
temperature and the particles will like
to stay in the
bottom but as soon as the temperature
increases the collisions the kinetic
energy uh allows for collisions and the
collisions allows particles to put
energy together and therefore they can
uh move
around in these valleys and uh and find
themselves in configurations that are
not not the most stable but momentarily
they can live also in very unstable
situations along the sides of the valley
and sometimes they can even reach the
subtle
Point perhaps also with additional
energy than just what is barely enough
to be
there so this
plot uh represents along this dust line
potential
energy and here we are assuming that the
uh reactant Val is uh deeper than the um
product
Valley okay what is important for the
moment then we will when we do kinetics
um next
time uh we will also talk about how to
to model the rates at which this uh
climbing of the valley to the sdle point
happens but uh for the moment all that
we need to to know is
that this activated complex uh can be
treated can be it's literally a a new
compound so a super molecule in which U
all the atoms that are in in play are
very close to one another and they share
a lot of elastic energy exactly like the
golf bowl is uh deformed and then it
only depend in the and then NE once
you're there that thing could decay in
One Direction or could decay in the
other
direction so there is a chance that it
you are up here and you Decay down this
Valley or you can Decay the other Valley
after all this is an unstable
Point
okay so in principle
see in principle if you have a
box
uh in which you have
only say suppose you have just two
hydrogen
atoms so this
is and U now as a result so this is a
time say T1
at a later time as a result of
collisions they find
themselves in a highly deformed
situation uh like this very close to one
another this is the
activated
complex
and there as a result of the Collision
you could have two possibilities maybe I
should do this uh
that the thing
breaks back to having two hydrogen
atoms so maybe these ones were moving
this way they Collide here they form
this activated complex let
me put that just to say well it's it has
a lot of uh stored elastic energy in it
so one way is that that elastic energy
makes it explode in two uh two other uh
atoms that will move far away or it
could
also
uh if the angles of the collisions are
appropriate and so on you can also form
just a single uh single molecule that
would move away this way of course you
have to conserve also momentum so uh
this molecule will have the same
momentum that the sum of the two
momentum okay so this would be an
effective chemically effective Collision
that produces the chemical reaction and
this is an ineffective chemical
Collision
just this kind of collisions the
ineffective ones are the ones that are
um also uh
responsible if you don't have to have to
go to this kind of extreme uh they are
responsible for redistributing the
energy between uh the various atoms in
your system and if you have enough
particles that will give you uh produce
the maxwellian distribution Maxwell bman
distribution of velocities okay
now you see here that uh for a system in
which there are only few particles like
two literally two particles here we have
those two particles have disappeared at
this moment in
time
uh in order to describe the the Dynamics
of this system or the properties as a
function of time we need to know also
the properties of this activated complex
because for some time it's the only
thing in our
box so if we want to describe properties
uh we have to know what the structure of
this molecule is and what's the specific
Heats and so
on uh so we treat this activated
complex as as a molecule in
itself however
yeah
uh okay let's uh uh do the the formal uh
discussion about
this so
essentially what this says is that
we we can
split
the uh reaction mechanism into two
parts a forward half
reaction that that
takes uh the
reactants
and forms as a result of collision
between the reactants forms deactivated
complex and the backward half
reaction which is a result of collisions
between product molecules also gives
right uh gives rise to
this so you notice that we can write our
original overall reaction in this
way and by our rule since we have put
the positive stric coefficients for the
products and negative for the
reactants if you want to start from the
products and form the activated
complex you have to put this
uh put them this way and and so the net
uh stochiometric coefficient of the
original reaction is given by new minus
minus new plus the
the stochiometric coefficient eent of
the backward reaction minus the
stochiometric coefficient of the forward
reaction so now we have two reactions
instead of
one and
that's going to be very
important as we see here uh in order to
describe the
possibility for the reaction to
occur so this activated
complexes are fundamental you have to go
through that subtle point in order to go
from one Valley to the other other
Valley you can also go through higher
than the sdle point or any any path that
takes you from one Valley to the other
but the most probable is uh going
through the SLE
point
and so each reaction for each reaction
we have defined
properties like the enthalpy of the
reaction so the enthalpy of the re of
the overall reaction if you remember the
other time is the weighted sum on the
stochiometric weighted on the
stochiometric coefficients of the pure
component uh uh property at standard
U pressure in this kind in this in
this instance and and The Temper the
generic temperature T well we can
also apply this definition to this
reactions the half reactions in order to
do that I have to make the uh a half
reaction with all the components to the
left according to our rule so so if you
take this to the left now you see this
the product is a
star and the reactants are the AI with
this stochiometric coefficients A+ I
mean new
plus so in this summation I have to
take uh with the plus one coefficient
the enthalpy of the activated complex at
standard pressure and temperature T and
then put the stochiometric efficient
therefore minus these
things okay so that defines
the property of the forward half
reaction and this is the enthalpy of
the forward I mean backward half
reaction in order to Define them you
need to know your to have characterized
your activated complex because you need
to know its enthalpy at standard
conditions treating it as a
molecule so in a sense
because people don't really do
this um this is just a sort of a
hypothetical it's a way of looking at it
which will allow nevertheless to
uh Define a lot of useful things that
then people do
use okay
so in spite of the
fact that we have just
said that that the activated complex is
fundamental in order for the reactions
to
occur next we're going to neglect
them so but it is not contradiction
we're going to NE neglect them neglect
them uh for just one aspect namely for
calculating the properties of our
reacting
mixtures and only in a limit in which we
have many particles so this is an an
addendum to the simple system
model it amounts to saying uh the
following yes if I have a situation in
which I have only two particles this
passing through this is fundamental and
also when I take a photograph at this
instant of time
uh the 100% of the scenario is made up
of the activated complex there's
only but if I have many
particles it's true that there are many
collisions but they do not occur all at
once so that means that if I have many
particles uh in this box in addition to
the two particles that are going to
collide and form these there are also
large amount of other particles that are
not colliding in that
moment and since they form the
majority the mo fraction of the
activated complex is so
small that we can neglect its
contribution to the properties of the
mixture so in that
sense we say for many
particles and when we are dealing with
just looking at the properties for
making like energy and entropy balances
uh so properties like the entropy the
enpy and and the energy uh or the volume
we can we we we compute them by
neglecting the minute uh amounts of
activated complex that are there
so essentially what we're what we're
saying is that neglecting the activating
complex is like neglecting the existence
of the chemical reaction for the purpose
of computing the
properties in other
words
uh we assume when Computing properties
of mixtures that are reacting we assume
that they have the properties of the
mixture with the reactions so to speak
turned
off if I turn off the
reactions I stop the formation of
activated complex so there is no
activated complex in play and I'm in the
usual uh situation in which I have only
my
um original
particles although
uh we're not actually turning reactions
off but it's as if you
could uh although the reaction is
occurring and also what we are assuming
is that
um the
you see with the reactions uh uh if I
have this situation here and I turn uh
off the reactions and I still have an
activated complex that was already it
was already there because it was just
being
formed uh that
complex sometimes will break up like
explode so that
explosion uh delivers kinetic energy
locally so produces a non equilibrium
situation that amount of kinetic energy
which is concentrated here in this
bullets that go away from the
explosion and they are they have a
velocity which is much higher than the
typical
velocities it will take a
while for a the other collisions not of
the chemical kind to redistribute that
excess in ktic energy due to the
chemical reaction in redistributed to
the other molecules
around
okay well we will we also
assume that the
uh that this
non-chemical uh coll Vision
redistribution
mechanism is very fast so
fast that as soon as we turn off the
reactions or as soon as the activated
complex has decayed into its fragments
of of the Decay uh that energy gets
almost immediately redistributed among
all the other uh molecules so that they
reach immediately uh the stable
equilibrium state with with their with
the Frozen composition that they are in
at that
moment okay so these are all the
concepts that go
into the idea that then we are going to
uh model the properties of our system
with chemical
reactions as if they were not reacting
but in stable chemical I'm sorry in
stable
equilibrium uh for the instantaneous
composition talking in terms of
characteristic
times the chemical
reactions we think we consider them much
slow slower
than the redistribution mechanism by
Collision uh but chemically ineffective
collisions which instead are very
fast
and and therefore the chemical reactions
change the composition and according to
the
um proportionality relation
so the the the reaction coordinate does
advance in time but we assume that each
instant of time the system immediately
redistributes the energy caused uh the
the local excesses or defects of
energies produced by the chemical
reactions and the activated complex and
so on
and and therefore keeps uh the
state almost close to what it would be
uh stable equilibrium if you didn't have
chemical
reactions okay so that's the
scenario and of
course this formula is going now to be
our uh head of the
game
because for
example uh
we can Define we can
compute the equilibrium composition by
maximizing because the maximum entropy
principle does
apply in
fact that same expression here it's
written more even more formally saying
that
uh yeah this is the S of the off
system with an N that is now variable
and it depends on the initial amount on
the chemical reactions that are in play
and on the uh reaction
coordinate so if you look at it this way
it's going to be easy to do uh the
partial derivatives that we have to do
for example here because for example
with with we like to be we are
interested in taking the derivative of
of the entropy with respect to the
advancement of to the reaction
coordinate of one
reaction because that derivative is
going to be called the Affinity of the
reaction they they don't there uh
Affinity of the
reaction so we have to do that
derivative but before we do that here's
the graphic graph graphical
representation of what we're doing
here for if you fix the value of the
composition so fix an Epsilon say
epsilon
one you you have fixed the composition
and this blue this blue curve represents
the stable equilibrium state of a
mixture with that
composition now you change the
composition and here you have another
stable equilibrium State curve and
another
yet
okay these
curves they do not represent all the
states of your system they represents
this family of
States uh Frozen equilibrium stable
equilibrium states that we have chosen
to describe the
properties but this family is Rich
enough that it can uh span
essentially uh all the allowed region of
the energy versus
entropy
diagram for the reacting
system and certainly these are allowed
States so when we want now to
apply the maximum entropy
principle the max maximum entropy
principle says well I fix the value of
the energy I fix the value of the volume
the initial amounts and the reaction and
the stochiometric
coefficients and the stable equilibrium
state of the chemical reacting system is
the one that has the highest
entropy so you see along this line it
this black line crosses many uh of these
EPS blue
curves until it reaches
one which Beyond which there is
nothing and if you do the same at
another level of energy you're going to
highlight this other equilibrium State
and again this
one so the envelope the red curve the
envelope of these blue curves
represents the stable equilibrium States
the maximum anthropy so those are the
stable equilibrium states of the
chemically reacting
system so that dotted red curve is the
fundamental relation for the stable
equilibrium uh stable chemical
equilibrium
States whereas these blue
ones represent stable equilibria only if
the reactions are
Frozen
Okay
so this derivative is the
affinity and uh now let's uh
uh go into a little more details of the
same same
graph same definition of
affinity what's new here is only a more
explicit expression for this uh red
curve which is a stable equilibrium
State fundamental
relation with the CH with the c in front
which stands for
chemical chemical stable equilibrium
States
you see uh uh at each level of energy
there there is one particular Epsilon
which we call Epsilon
zero that corresponds to the composition
at chemical
equilibrium and that's the one that
appears
here so the entropy of the red curve the
entropy of of the stable equilibrium
with chemical
included uh
has this um shows for example the
dependence on
energy is not only from the original
dependence of the Frozen
equilibrium mixture but it's also
through the Epsilon
zero because as you change the energy
Epsilon zero changes and so energy
influences the the maximum entropy not
only through the properties of
regardless the chemical reactions but
also through the composition at chemical
equ all right so that means that when we
need to
compute derivatives for example the
temperature you remember the temperature
is the derivative or actually the
inverse of the temperature is derivative
of fundamental relation respect to
energy
well if I have to take this derivative
with respect to energy I have to
contribution from here but I have
contributions also from
here the first
one is what would be the temperature if
the reactions were
off and these other contribution is a
summation because these are vectors and
so this a summation of over all the
chemical reactions from J that goes for
J that goes from one to Z how the
derivative of s off uh with respect to
Epsilon in here you could also do it
with respect to n and then with respect
to
Epsilon uh times the derivative of EP
with respect to
U however
since at chemical
equilibrium the entropy is maximum
maximum so if the entropy is maximum it
means that it's derivative with respect
to these variables here must be zero
including this derivative the affinities
that is what we call the the condition
for chemical uh equilibrium the
affinities must be equal to
zero and in these
summations this derivative is precisely
that one so it's the
affinity
and maximum it's equal to zero so this
summation is a bunch of
zeros and it turns out therefore
that the temperature so the derivative
of the red curve
is equal to the derivative of a blue
curve in other words they have a contact
of first degree they not only they touch
but also they touch with the same
tangent and this is true not only for
temperature but also for pressure and
for the chemical
potentials okay so we have essentially
already said what the condition the
necessary condition for chemical
equilibrium is is that the affinities
must be equal to
zero
okay so now let's compute those
affinities again that's the derivative
we were talking about and here is a
summary of what we just said
now the derivative of s we of the
off system the off fundamental relation
with respect to n is the chemical
potential divided by the temperature
with the negative sign in
front so when I do uh this derivative
the result is a weighted sum of the
stochiometric coefficients because here
uh you're taking the derivative with
respect to the Epsilon of one reaction J
is the label of the reactions and I is
the label of the
components so these are the
stochiometric coefficients of the J
reaction for the I
component and so it's the weight
sum of the chemical potential divided by
the temperature
that's the
Affinity of reaction
J now we
can uh use the tools that we uh have
already developed in order to uh
describe um chemical potentials of
mixtures because we spent half of the
course on
this for example assume an ideal G
Dalton mixture of Ideal gases
off so these are the off allows us to
use anything that we know of the system
without chemical
reactions if we it's remember it's like
the chemical potential of the of the
pure component at T and P plus RT log of
y y being the mole fraction of that
component if we want the reference to
the standard pressure p not
then here we have to put that integral
from P not to P of the partial of new
respect to P which is the specific
volume and for the case of gas this
gives the logarith
contribution okay so we have seen this
several
times let's substitute it up here up
here okay so if you put it up there you
will that end up with a a summation of
tetric coefficients times this mui mu I
double eyes and this summation you may
recognize is the Gibs free energy of
that reaction because you remember that
the chemical potentials of the pure
components are equal to the GBS free
energies of the pure
component and it's the Delta G zero the
zero here it's because we are doing it
at the standard pressure and a function
of temperature all right so from this
part from this thing we obtain a
contribution like
that uh
from this other
one see there is no subscript I here so
it goes uh off the summation sign and in
the summation sign can remains only the
summation of the stochiometric
coefficient
of which we're going to denote as new of
J so that's the total stochiometric
coefficients of of reaction
J and the last
term it's okay
RT but the T goes away with the T at the
denominator here and then it's the
summation of
stochiometric Times log of
Y okay you can see that you can put
the the preactor of the logarithm inside
it becomes an exponent an exponent so
this it becomes the summation of log of
Y to the new new
subi and then you so you know that the
summation of the logarithms is equal to
the logarithm of the
products of the arguments of the
logarithm this is simply a property of
the
logarithms
okay all
right so that that equation is like that
we now in order to sort of get
rid of the logarithm we can take the
exponential uh so so if you take the
exponential of this expression of
Y actually take the exponential of Y
divide also by R and change the
sign okay so that can comes from
here uh the exponential of the
logarithm they cancel each other so I'm
left with this product of the mole
fractions to the power of the
corresponding stochiometric coefficients
and then I have the exponential of this
Delta G which is divided by T and also
by R because we divided also by R and
change
sign all right we call that exponential
it's actually written
here the equilibrium
constant of the
reaction um yeah here I should also
correct it should be for precision it
should be K Sub sub J now it's the it's
related to uh the J uh label of the
chemical reaction so this is the
chemical reaction constant e to the
minus the GS three energy over
RT
from uh this term here the log of P the
log is gone away and the coefficient
multiplying the log was the total so
coefficient which goes inside the
logarithm becomes an exponent
okay and the product of this pressure
dependent and temperature dependent is
also called equilibrium constant so
these are really not constants because
they depend on temperature they depend
on pressure what they don't depend on is
composition that's why it's they're
called in traditionally equilibrium
constants
so so far we have made no other
assumption that than the modeling
assumption so this is not yet the
equilibrium uh law of mass
action so we call it the non-e
equilibrium low mass
action it relates this that and that but
of course since we know that at
equilibrium the the affini are equal to
zero and so e to the 0 is one so this
take if you cancel this you have the
equilibrium law of mass
action here since we've always work with
mole fractions the Y sub eyes it's
written in the most natural way for uh
for our treatment so
far often
in the practice of U
chemical
engineering instead of mole fraction one
uses the
uh um
concentrations the molar concentration
so the number of molecules per unit
volume and sometimes you denote that by
c c
Sai concentration
sometimes you denote it by this n in
square
brackets of course there is they
related and therefore if you if you take
this one and do this substitution you
get the law of mass action written in
terms of
concentrations what changes is uh the
constants so for example the pressure
depend then goes
away the P you see the P the total P
disappeared and uh so this equilibrium
constant based on concentration the the
C up there is there just to distinguish
between these equilibrium constants so
you have to be careful when you are in
this business to understand which
equilibrium constant you're talking
about there is also this
last way of writing it also has an
additional difficulty that has to do
with the dimensions because
whereas the top one is
dimensionless because the M fractions
are
dimensionless p over p is
dimensionless and Delta G over RT is
dimensionless so everything is
dimensionless up here down here it's not
because this is n over
V and so these equilibrium
constants depend for example this is a
this is
a these as dimensions
of moles per cubic
meter so if your chemical reaction has
the stochiometric coefficients that are
equal that sum up to zero then this is
dimensionless but if they don't sum up
to zero then these as Dimensions that
depend on the sum of the tetric
coefficients so that sometimes it's a
cause of little errors in
computations
clearly you can redo
what we've just done also for
liquids if you instead of having a the
reaction occurring in the gasos phase
you have it in the liquid phase and you
can assume ideal Solutions solution at
all compositions for all
components which is rare but it's a
starting
point then of course you remember that
integral when you write the chemical
potential instead of the RT log of the p
over P it's simply P minus P times the
specific volume of the pure component
liquid the pure liquid component
I then you substitute up there then it
appears also the weighted sum of the
volumes that's the volume of the
reaction
and U when you
do so when you go back here the non
equilibrium law of mass
action this side has the same uh format
except that the equilibrium constant uh
is different it has also it has one
contribution which Remains the Delta G
over RT that's the equilibrium constant
k k of JT
what what differs is that the other
thing that you could also separate and
make it two separate exponentials like
uh this could be the
preactor of the uh of the standard
equilibrium con constant and you can
also write it in terms of uh
concentrations for a liquid of
course uh the
concentrations
uh the relation between Mo fractions and
concentrations are this
way and
again by
setting
all the affinities equal to zero your
system is at equilibrium chemical
equilibrium all the reactions have zero
Affinity at equilibrium so you can set
zero all these ones and with this law of
mass action you can compute the
equilibrium compon
position if instead of
having
ideal um M gas mixtures or Solutions you
have a uh
real uh mixtures that you
model according
to Mar goues van are all those models
that we have introduced for the models
of nonideal behavior of
mixtures
then you can always put that um the
expression for the chemical potential in
this way in
terms of the
affinities which which become Mo play
the same role as M fra fractions for the
uh ideal
Behavior instead of calling it yabi you
call it aabi and it becomes non ideal
but the mathematical steps are exactly
the same so here is what you
obtain uh but then obviously you need to
know to have those van or marulas or
whatever relations that allow you to
write the affinities in terms of mole
fractions and then this will be a set of
equations that will allow you to compute
the mole
fractions now the main part of the
equilibrium constant that exponential of
minus Delta G /
RT is something that
we have uh already encountered at the
beginning of uh last
lecture when we talked about
the the the role of the Gibs free energy
in determining when a reaction is react
reactant favored or product
favored because it turned out that
the uh entropy produced by
irreversibility is related to
this okay so if I take this expression
and take the logarithm and actually take
the logarithm in base
10 I can plot that
logarithm versus the inverse of the
temperature and we already proved last
time that this derivative with respect
of this logarithm with respect to 1 / T
is related to the enthalpy the Nega is
the the negative of the enthalpy of
reaction so when a reaction is
exothermic Delta H is negative so that
means that this slope is positive for
the exothermic reactions so for example
this reaction is exothermic this one is
endothermic because it goes down with 1
/
T so you see that the
chemical equilibrium
constants
span over a wide range
[Music]
of of
um how do you
say the senior moment uh uh orders of
magnitude okay
thanks um so you
see so it can go from from very high to
very
small and the reaction in equilibrium
constant is what
determines uh the
compositions if it is very much so if
the equilibrium is very much uh towards
the products
when the chemical equilibrium is uh if
you go back here if the equilibrium
constant is
large uh it will make uh uh Prevail the
um the mole fractions that have positive
stochiometric coefficients so it will
make Prevail the uh products whereas if
it is small it will make Prevail the one
that are at the denominator so they have
negative stochiometric
coefficient so what how do we how do we
compute the equilibrium
constants yeah they are
defined for each reaction but since they
related to the Gibs free energy of
reaction
we
can uh use the S relation that you
remember allows you to compute the
properties of reaction from the
properties of formations of your
constituents so all you know all you
need to know is uh the properties of
formation but you need to know them as a
function of temperature
so for
each component in principle you should
know you should measure it as a function
of temperature however there's a
simplifica
So based just on that turns out
that the equilibrium constant for your
reaction can be computed as the
product of the equilibrium constants of
the reactions of formations of your
various constituents that that appear in
the chemical reaction mechanism to the
power uh of the stochiometric respective
stric
coefficients okay and this is
General
now if we use that derivative that we
done in the previous slide and also
earlier to show that this derivative is
equal to the minus of the enpy of
reaction and then if we know notice that
the enthalpy of
reaction seems to be pretty constant
with temperature how how how do I why do
I say that because if you look at these
uh curves here they look like almost
straight
lines so straight lines means that the
slope is almost
constant so if you assume if you make
that
approximation if you look close it
they're not literally uh straight
lines so it is an
approximation but if you make that
approximation it means you can do can do
this integral you assume this is
constant and and that integral therefore
it's like an integrate integrate of D of
one / T it's uh it's like a linear
relation between the logarithm of of KT
and one / T these are exactly the
equation of those line lines of the
previous
plot then if you notice that this one is
still the the concept of integration is
the equilibrium constant evaluated at
standard temperature and so that's also
related to Delta G over uh I think
there's a t missing here this is should
be rt0
and U yeah I have to correct that so if
you substitute that up here and remember
that Delta G is Delta H minus t Delta
s you finally get this expression which
gives the logarithm of KT as a linear
relation in one /
T and those Delta s and Delta H are the
properties of reaction at standard
conditions of temperature and
pressure so essentially by just
knowing the entropies the entropies of
formation and the enalis of formation of
your virus
constituents this expression gives you
the chemical equilibrium constant at any
temperature
and if you if you want to correct for
that
minor uh difference that is due to the
fact that those lines are not exactly
straight lines but you want to do the
approximation instead of using those you
can use those from a table which does a
at least square feet which does a better
job for example this table uh gives you
good numbers in a wide range of
temperatur from 300 to
5,000k which is
plenty uh what you need uh for for
example combustion
applications all right so we know the
the chemical equilibrium
constant so let me give you an
example you've probably seen these kind
of things in the previous course 2452 I
mean two um
242 in any case suppose we
consider the reaction of dissociation of
CO2 which is important in combustion
because CO2 is a product of combustion
and at high temperatures uh this
dissociation may occur so let's assume
the temperature is of the is three
3200k and that we are at atmospheric
somehow using the previous um U table
you can compute the equilibrium
constant
um which is
64 and so in order to do the calculation
we need to apply the law of mass action
and the law of mass action says that the
product of a mole fractions to the
stochiometric
coefficients it must be equal to to
equilibrium
constant the equilibrium constant that
depends on temperature and
pressure uh now in this case the
pressure is is equal to P not so this
preactor
uh is equal to one so it cancels out so
you're left with K of T which is e to
the minus Delta g/ RT okay so we know
the value of the right hand side now for
the left hand side
we need to express we need to find the
mole fractions and the mole fractions
they're not all independent of of one
another because they are
related through the proportionality
relations so Mo fraction is n over total
n so n of component I is equal to the
initial amount plus the stochiometric
coefficient times the reaction
coordinate Epsilon
and the denominator is the sum of the
numerators so to speak uh so it's the
total n initial the total stum
coefficient and the uh reaction
coordinate if we divide by N Sub
a denominator and
numerator above I get the mole fractions
the initial mole fractions below I get
one and Epsilon over n sub a I call it
C okay so each Mo
fraction depends on the initial mole
fractions and on a
single variable
C so if I substitute that in the low of
mass
action this gives us one equation in the
single variable
C and therefore I can solve for
C given the initial compositions and
theal composition for this problem is
given somewhere uh here can look up the
details so once I know C I go back here
and I have the entire composition so I
have the M fractions of all the various
constituents so that how that's how you
compute chemical equilibrium uh
compositions using Mo fraction
clearly if you have more than one
reaction in
play you have one law of mass
action per
reaction so each reaction brings in a
new unknown which is the reaction
coordinate so if you have three
reactions or five say for the example
that will follow we have five reactions
so you have five know which are
the uh reaction coordinates epsilons or
the CES which
are the per
mole
coordinates uh five unknown but you have
five equations which are the the
corresponding to setting equal to zero
the five um
affinities of each of the reactions
so of course you have to compute five
chemical equilibrium constants but then
you have a system of five equations in
five unknowns which gives you uh all uh
that you
need this is for
example I think we we' have seen already
part of this table when we did a diotic
flame temperature for an internal
combustion
engine so here is the is that
computation that
does at the same time it computes
the uh the energy
balance that gives you the adiabatic
flame
temperature in terms uh but
also at the same time it you compute the
five
equilibrium low of mass
actions and therefore as a result you
can compute the compositions of all the
various
components notice that these numbers
this is in mole this is in Mill moles
and this is in
micromoles uh turns out that U the first
two reactions here the dissociation
reactions are important in
determining um the thermal aspects of
the
combustion they will affect the thetic
flame temp flame temperature if you
don't consider them you overestimate
it
whereas the last three um give you an
estimate of the uh formation of
the nitrogen oxides that are pollutants
as you know uh of combustion of
combustion products
that correspond to various ways in
which nitrogen and oxygen molecules can
Collide and at high temperatures and uh
combine to
form these various
oxides now I told you that um
uh life is not that uh
simple I
remember collaborator of Professor kek
downstairs who used to say that uh what
I just told you so far is Disneyland
with respect to the real world
because even for the simplest uh uh Hy
carbon which is
hydrogen in order to describe the
chemical reactions in play and these
activated complexes and so on you
need this is the official scheme 24
reactions and eight
species and these are the parameters
that allow you to compute the reaction
rates this is a diagram
which shows for
various hydrocarbons for example ISO
octane which is like gasoline say you're
here methane is
here uh and it it gives you in a log
scale the number of species that are
that you need to consider and the number
of
reactions turns out that the number of
reactions is time is about five times
this straight line is an equation uh it
says that I need five times the number
of
species hydrogen is really a bit of an
exception because uh 5 by 8 is not 24
but uh in any case hydrogen would be
here in the skin uh and you see for
example for a uh
methane I think you need the
um yeah 50
something um species we could read it
here and
reactions at least this is for is true
for kinetics whereas for
equilibrium uh we can avoid this kind of
complication but but for the
kinetics it's not so simple actually if
you look up uh even this is not a
settled uh issue because people are
still working on determining these
detail mechanisms for new fuels but also
for old fuels and now uh there is a lot
of uh the artificial intelligence is is
playing a game also here because
developing these schemes with so many
reactions is first of all
complicated second it makes life uh
uh
very
uh difficult because you how do you know
first of all if I have 5,000 uh
reactions to be considered how do I know
that the 5,000 parameters that that
Define the reaction right Ates are are
correct uh
and and what if are they all
important so in fact many people are
working on uh and artificial
intelligence may help in model reduction
schemes so you say you start with the
complete uh scheme but then you you try
to cut out at least for ranges of
conditions and do a simplif simplified
model that allows you to to do a good
job anyway so uh a lot of and again
mentioned Professor kek because he was
one great contributor uh to this issue
through the rate controlled constrained
equilibrium method that uh you might if
you're interested you should uh should
read
about okay now so the affinities at
equilibrium are equal to
zero uh here is a another way of of
saying
it which gives us a
chance know I should say a again or
first chance to use the method of lrange
multipliers for maximizing
functions subject to
constraints because after all the
chemical equilibrium condition comes as
a condition uh from the maximization of
the
entropy of the entropy of our uh system
with chemical reactions so therefore
this is the we adopt this model model
for describing its
entropy where the N the
amounts uh can be varied but only in a
constrained way constrained by the
proportionality relations so we
consider maximize this
function
subject to keeping energy volume initial
amounts stomri coefficients fixed and
varing the constituents only according
to these equations so this is a
constrained maximization
problem and as you may
know I'm sure you've seen it somewhere
else
uh
um the method of lrange multipliers
consists in taking the the function you
want to maximize and
subtracting uh uh the constraints each
one multiplied by its own undetermined
parameter
Lambda and so I write the constraint
constraint by putting everything on one
side and setting it to zero and that
that thing on the one side is the thing
that is multiplied by the lrange
multiplier so now I have a
function in which I have the R
multipliers I have the N I have the
epsilons and I want to maximize this uh
function so essentially need to take the
derivative with respect and set it equal
to zero with respect to those the
derivative with respect to those
variables that
are um
undetermined so the n and the Epsilon so
I take the derivative of L with respect
to n
so uh I get one contribution
from s from the entropy the derivative
of s with respect to n this is equal to
the minus of the St of the minus equal
potential over the
temperature and then when I take the
derivative with respect to N I also have
a contribution from here because this is
an
N which is minus Lambda and that's this
minus Lambda
here this has to be set to be equal to
zero for this Max this lran function to
be unconstrained maximum so apply the
rules of maximizing function so you set
the derivative is equal to
zero so this
says Ah okay the lrange multiplier must
be equal to uh the chemical potential
over T fine
then I take the derivative of L with
respect to
Epsilon okay I pick up nothing from here
because the Epsilon doesn't appear here
Epsilon is only
there so it it's with a plus because
there's two minuses here and the Epsilon
J picks
up uh the stochiometric coefficients of
uh of the J
reaction multiplied by the lrange
multipliers so this is what we get but
since the LR multipliers is minus mu / T
we can
substitute and
that is the expression of what we called
the Affinity of the
reaction and taking the derivative equal
to zero and therefore imposes the
Affinity to be equal to zero okay so
just another way of deriving the
chemical equilibrium
conditions however this is useful also
to introduce
another
possibility precisely
because we have so
many chemical reactions and and chemical
species in
play
uh maybe we can
also uh work and people do work in fact
uh uh in all the simulation softwares
commercial softwares that have
properties for uh
Computing
equilibrium uh they are based on this
concept of complete chemical equilibrium
what what is it
the idea is all right why should I
list uh such a large number of reactions
couldn't just just say that uh all
reactions are
possible all conceivable
reactions so instead of listing the
reactions let's assume that all
conceivable reactions are possible in
order to compute chemical
equ so what would be the only constraint
in chemical
reactions chemical reactions the only
thing that they cannot do is to change
the nuclei so the inventory of nuclei in
your mixture is
fixed so the constraints here is count
the number of nuclei in your mixture
initial you you must be sure that they
remain what they were otherwise you
would be doing nuclear uh
equilibrium
okay so the idea is uh you want to
maximize is usually the entropy because
we are applying the maximum entropy
principle now the constraint is that I
want to con constraint the this c subk c
is the
number of uh nuclei of a given
type and they are given
initially this way and at a generic
composition this way so what are these
coefficients a sub I
K let me explain it with this table
here a sub by K represents for each uh
for the molecule for example uh I say
methane it gives you the number of of
nuclei of each type so the first type is
carbon yes in methane there is one
carbon so I put a one here there are
four
hydrogens so I put a four there are no
oxyg no
nitrogens okay so these are the uh
Matrix of um com nuclear nuclear
composition of the uh of your various
constituents so you list the
constituents and you for each one of
them you put how many nuclei of each
kind there is it turns out that for a
very large number of organic
molecules uh the number of nuclei is
very
small carbon hydrogen oxygen nitrogen
what else yeah maybe argon because it's
present in air
but um
okay so that means
since the index that runs here so the
number of constraints is that you have
is the count of the nuclei in these
columns so you have few
constraints just as many at kinds of
atoms are around
okay so with the initial composition and
sub a
uh sub a and with this table you compute
how many you have
initially and you have to make sure by
this maximization constraint
maximization that also at equilibrium
you have that same number
of of of of
nuclei everything else is allowed so
that means you assume that there will be
some chemical reactions that will do
that change will take you to that
equilibrium because everything is
allowed provided the nuclear
conservation is is done is
satisfied so again to proceed we we we
assign a lrange multiplier to each
constraint and the constraint here uh is
written uh by taking on the same side
here these two so it's n i minus initial
n i * a
summation and then you multiply each one
by the L
multiply and now you take you
impose that this function be
uh
maximum so you impose the derivative
equal to
zero with respect to the only variable
which is the NS the an
subbi so you do
that and of course the this one still
gives you the chemical potential over
the temperature and this uh
here and gives you the summation over K
of Lambda K time a i
k
now for example let's
assume uh ideal gas
mixture or ideal
Behavior like this chemical potential
goes with the logarithm of
Y so you substitute it up
there and so you obain an equation since
this must be equal to zero you get an
equation that gives you the log of Y in
terms
of this chemical potential of the pure
component and this summation of the
lrange
multipliers times these coefficients of
the
Matrix so this is the this gives you the
composition but it is in terms of lrange
multipliers so you need in this case
four lrange multipliers how do I
determine the lar multipliers as
typically in the method uh you to
substitute the solution back into the
constraints and that will give you an
equation that allows you to compute the
uh multipliers so I take this
expression and put it here in order to
compute uh
the uh the amount of nuclei that it
implies okay so this is the ends then
the ends can be m can be n n subis can
be computed as n times the mole
fractions all right so this is an
equation or actually it's a system of
four
equations because I know the initial
amounts of the of the nuclei so I know
the left hand
side and the only unknowns are the
um lrange multipliers so I can solve
this four system four by four system
four equations in four unknowns and get
the lrange multipliers as a function of
the initial composition I plug it back
here and then I have the mole fractions
and
notice
that uh it's very interesting
because uh we didn't put any limit to
the number of chemical compounds that
you can
consider so this L list can be
as long as you
please you could take the entire J of
tables uh or uh you can just consider
the ones that you want and uh and this
expression will give you the mole
fractions of anything that you're
interested
in
and this
method was is was implemented by Gordon
and McBride uh in the 50s I believe and
it is still um the method used um in
almost all
softwares I know it very well because
when I started when I did my masters uh
with Professor
kek uh I worked for one year uh and
those times we didn't have a
uh easy computerss the computer building
was uh like a building uh near the
nuclear engineering department and uh he
gave
me this computer program was a set of
cards like a thousand or 2,000 cards in
a box for the program something that
today I think stays in like uh maybe
28k
kilobytes and another box
with the properties of the
various
constituents and uh and he asked me to
implement his model reduction uh method
constraint equilibrium method into that
software which was very nice
start uh here and now I notice also that
there is something I have to correct
here because is it plus or is it
minus I'll figure it out and let let you
know okay so I think we are done for
today