For our final panel
this afternoon,
we're joined by the Living
Climate Futures Lab.
This is a project that received
seed funding from MITHIC
through its faculty-driven
initiative program.
So we have two presenters,
Chris Walley and Amah Edoh
from anthropology.
After they present,
they'll be joined
on the stage with
Kate Brown from STS,
Janelle Knox-Hayes from
Urban Studies and Planning,
and Laura Frye-Levine
from anthropology.
And they'll be moderating
their conversation
by Evelyn Wang, the MIT
vice president for energy
and climate.
So, Chris and Amah.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Hi, everyone.
I'm Chris Walley from--
sorry, Professor.
Professor and Head
of Anthropology.
And I'm Amah Edoh,
research scientist,
and serving as managing director
of the Living Climate Futures
Lab.
And we just wanted
to say thanks so much
to the donors who have
made MITHIC possible,
and to the SHASS Dean's
Office and the whole MITHIC
crew, who've been so fabulous.
We're truly honored to be the
recipients of the first MITHIC
Faculty-Driven Initiative Award.
So we are a
collaborative initiative.
There are 20 people, 20
researchers currently involved
in the lab.
And folks have been
coming in and out.
But maybe the LCFL members
who are here, if you can just
wave so we see who you are.
There you go.
Very few of us are here, but hi.
A number of folks are teaching.
Yep, and there's Chris.
And so we wanted to
start with the video.
It's a short five-minute video
that we made with earlier MITHIC
funding to show the
foundations of the lab
and tell you a little bit
more about how we came about.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
When we think about
climate change
as a scientific problem or
a technological problem,
we often forget then that
climate change is also
a social problem.
It's a cultural problem.
It's a political problem.
It's an economic problem.
MIT students come here
wanting to change the world
and wanting to come
up with solutions
to impossible problems.
When I was a student, what
felt like that was missing
for me was constantly
asking the question,
how does this relate to
what's happening in the world?
Social scientists
can serve as a bridge
among different communities
of scholars, communities
of engineers, as well
as Native communities,
agricultural, urban communities.
What the Living Climate Futures
Lab is going to do is listen,
and to ask questions, and to
learn the ways in which people
are grappling with this in
their everyday lives right now.
There are populations
that have been grappling
with these issues for
a long time already,
and that have developed
a lot of knowledge.
And this lab is an opportunity
to invite that knowledge
and help grow that
knowledge in a way that
can benefit all of us.
We decided to do this
conference a couple years ago.
And the idea was, can we
bring these community partners
that we're working with
to MIT, host this space,
and see what comes out
of this conversation?
Ohio has a very certain
idea of what farming is,
and it's not what we're doing.
These changes take time,
and they take effort.
And they need true dedication.
Change happens at
the speed of trust.
And that speed of trust
has a lot of different ways
to get to it.
We had Indigenous leaders
from the Pacific Northwest
and from North Carolina.
We had environmental
justice groups
from Chicago and from Boston.
We had urban farmers from Ohio
and from the New England area.
When I deal with
communities that
are on the front line of
an environmental stress,
they often feel alone.
And so when we brought
people together,
I think that really
gave people of boost.
It told them that
there's all kinds
of other people and resources
out there to help them.
When
You look in Indigenous lands
that Indigenous peoples
have stewarded, we see
much greater biodiversity.
It hits on a lot of what
Indigenous peoples' knowledges
have said for millennia.
It's about relationships.
It's understanding how the world
works in an interconnected way.
Working with communities,
it is really important
to build long-term
relationships and not
create extractive
forms of relationships.
[INAUDIBLE] photograph.
Professor Mike Short
with Professor Munkhbat
has this molten
salt heat bank that
has been produced in the lab.
But we need to make it work
in people's homes in Mongolia.
So anthropology steps in.
The intention is to learn about
how Mongolians use technology
and what could work in
a particular setting.
We have the opportunity to work
with students at the National
University of Mongolia,
and it was honestly
one of the greatest
experiences of my life.
We debriefed almost
every night about what
has been discovered, what
is the engineering side,
and what is the
ethnographic side,
to the point where students
gained this fluency
to merge two
disciplines together in
such a smart,
culturally-sensitive way.
So much of the MIT education
this is the way the world is.
It's very black and white.
It's so common to say,
well, I see a problem.
I can come up with a series
of technical solutions
that, if everyone behaves
I think they will, then
it's going to work.
And yet, when students get
out into the real world,
they realize nothing does.
It takes cultivating
relationships.
That's what our students
have learned, too.
I learned so much
more about the project
and about what the
future of this project
could look like than I think
if we had just gone alone.
The discourses of urgency,
crisis, speed and scale
in the context of solutions
just keeps coming up.
Who are those partners
in communities
that we want to engage,
and what should be
included in this conversation?
Why aren't we training students
to work with communities?
Why aren't we training
them to understand
different ways of knowing?
It's a really good
example of something
that we should be
doing across the board.
The Living Climate Futures Lab
is a unique opportunity for MIT
to stand as a leader in the
response to climate change.
It's extremely meaningful
for a school that
is known for STEM to
say, hey, the social,
and the cultural are as
important as the technological
and the scientific.
Yeah.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[APPLAUSE]
Maybe you could leave it
on the picture of everybody
until the post comes up?
Oops, nope.
There you go.
Great, thank you.
So, as mentioned
in the video, we're
committed to thinking
about climate change
in the more holistic
terms of how
it plays out in everyday life.
And by partnering with community
environmental organizations, who
are themselves living through
the effects of climate change
and developing
their own solutions
for how to mitigate
those effects,
we recognize that in order
to do this effectively,
we need to bring together
different forms of knowledge
and partner with those in
other fields, including STEM.
So this lab came about
because many of us,
as researchers, have for many
years, been working already
at the community level, not only
in the US, but internationally.
And we've seen how
well-intentioned policies
and programs by international
organizations, national agencies
and other institutions
too often fail or leave
behind a trail of
unintended consequences.
There are many reasons
for this, but the lack
of familiarity with particular
locations or populations,
or lack of substantive
or equitable partnerships
are some of the key factors.
As a consequence, many of us
have experienced firsthand,
as researchers, the often
enormous disconnect between what
such interventions
are assumed to do
in the abstract and the reality
of how such interventions play
out or fail to play
out in everyday life.
So our intent is
to think about how
to achieve what is often
referenced as scale and impact
differently.
So first, our focus is on
building long-term research,
partnerships, and connections
with community organizations
as a basis for building trust,
as was referenced in the video.
So we're operating with
different kinds of time frames
than are commonly used,
for example, in developing
technologies for markets or
generating venture capital,
where the assumption is that
showing immediate returns
is a key sign of success.
Taking time is part
of our secret sauce.
In the model we're developing
for the Living Climate Futures
Lab, we seek to
generate impact not
by replicating what
works in one location
and transferring that
to other locations.
Our goal is to
generate conversations
among those living in
very different places
that help push forward
thinking about what works,
without presuming those
solutions will look similar
across different locales.
So for all of us, what
we seek to scale up
is the process of
learning how to listen
across different groups, and to
explore place-based solutions
through collective
conversation, and by generating
what STS scholars call
a community of practice.
We envision the
community groups that we
partner with as similar
to a series of sensors
spread out across national
and global landscapes that
can tap into and offer a
reading of what is happening
in different locations.
To make this work,
we need to partner
across disciplines and
schools within universities.
We also have to learn to partner
with community organizations
in ways that are co-designed
and fully collaborative,
and that our community
partners themselves consider
to be ethical and equitable.
For example, while
marketable technologies
to address climate change
are absolutely critical,
our own path takes a
different orientation
to arrive at similar goals.
The emphasis for the
Living Climate Futures Lab
is on scaling knowledge
and showing impact
by extending out
horizontally to create
a more vibrant and equitable
research commons in often
overlooked locations.
And so to this
end, the lab's work
is articulated along two axes.
So the first one is
for the lab to serve
as a research hub,
where members can form
a community of practice,
as Chris was mentioning,
across SHASS and
STEM disciplines,
where they can learn
from one another,
develop new collaborations.
And you'll be hearing
more about some
of the research that's
happening during the panel
after this short overview.
But here, we just
have two examples
from the anthropology
department, Professor Amy
Moran-Thomas, who's working on
co-creating sensors in old coal
mining regions of Pennsylvania
that are being heavily impacted
environmentally and health
wise by natural gas extraction.
And Professor Sonya
Atalay, who is graciously
allowing us to learn
from the network
she's been developing-- the
Center for Braiding Indigenous
Knowledges and Science.
And we're learning how
to do just that, how
to bring these
different knowledge
systems into conversation.
In addition to a
research hub, we're
also generating a suite of
experiential learning classes
to train the next generation in
how to work across disciplines
and how to collaborate ethically
with community partners.
And those of you who've
been here all day
have heard again and again this
emphasis on returning to the
or enhancing the
MIT mens et manus
and teaching students by doing.
And so we wanted to
illustrate that it's late.
You've been here all day.
So we're showing videos because
it's easier to integrate.
And so we have another short
video from one of the classes,
Lab to Land.
And we're creating a
series of these minute
and a half, two-minute videos
to make our approach more
legible to students, but
then also to colleagues
across SHASS and STEM fields
and community partners.
And so.
Brianna Meier and I wanted to
create a class where students
have the possibility to
engage with communities
that have actually come up with
solutions to climate problems.
We piloted our field
school this summer.
We took two students out
to the Pacific Northwest
to engage with the actual
cultural landscapes.
One of our community partners,
Se'Si'Le are an Indigenous-led
environmental nonprofit that
has been dedicated to teaching
people about ancestral
Indigenous knowledges.
Se'Si'Le focuses on land,
water, and human rights,
in particular protecting
the Salish Sea.
Our legend goes our first
mother came from the water.
What does a mother do?
A mother feeds you.
So we start working with that.
That's the beginning of our law.
The communities that we work
with follow that same law
and want to give back to the
things that provide for us.
It was really grounding,
just meeting a lot of people,
doing really good things,
doing good work, who just have
such a community base value.
There is a tendency
that the people
that you're learning
about, you learn
to see them as these symbols
versus actual people.
Living with them,
you get the chance
to actually meet them
as people and for them
to meet you as people,
as well, and to actually
form a connection.
One of the key concepts in the
class that we're engaging with
is the concept of
infrastructure,
and the notion that
infrastructures don't only
build physical and
material worlds,
but also build social worlds.
The best work that we've been
doing is in our own backyard,
and we continue to do that,
to be stewards of our land.
We've always been that
way, and we are now.
And we always will be.
That's who we are
as [INAUDIBLE].
Anybody can make a difference.
And that's the same at MIT,
whatever you're doing in school.
Let's create to enhance
with technology,
to make a world a better place.
This is something I
wrote in my field notes.
As a mechanical
engineering student,
I've been searching for
solutions, trying to problem
solve a way out of the hole
we seem to just keep digging.
But this trip helped me
organize my thoughts.
There's no engineering
without people,
no people without community, no
communities without the planet,
and no planet without balance.
[APPLAUSE]
So, you see, we
have a whole series
of courses that are coming.
And these videos will
be up on our website.
The next one that's coming up,
and that's just about done,
is for a class called Green
Steel, Green Jobs, which
is a course that explores
developing collaborations
across anthropology and
engineering to simultaneously
work on decarbonization
while also
trying to design for good jobs.
And with that, we
will transition
to the panel, where you'll
get to hear a bit more
about some of the research
underway in the lab.
Great.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Oh.
Sorry, sorry.
Are we supposed to
sit in this order?
Oh.
Are we--
We'll mix it up.
Keep everything a
little more confusing.
[LAUGHTER]
Great.
Well, good afternoon, everyone.
I know we're the last
panel, but hope you'll
find this extremely exciting.
I think certainly from
the videos that we saw,
I think the Living
Climate Futures Lab
is such an inspiration.
And as I'm leading
the Climate Project,
I see so many synergies
and opportunities
to really collectively work
together, which I really
enjoy just hearing about
really the opportunities
for partnerships at MIT.
And I think the
more we can engage,
the more we can actually
affect and impact
people and communities.
But maybe we'll start, and just
with a round of introductions,
and maybe sharing a little
bit about what each of you
are working on in the context of
the Living Climate Futures Lab.
And I know Professor
Chris Walley has already
shared a little bit, but
maybe I'll ask you to start,
Sure.
Just super quickly, in
the interest of time,
so I Amah had mentioned the
class Green Steel, Green Jobs.
My work for many years,
I did earlier research
on environmental
issues in East Africa.
But in-- later after
that, I've been
working in the area
where I grew up,
Southeast Chicago, an old
steel mill neighborhood.
My father was a steelworker.
My grandfather
was a steelworker.
And so this class,
Green Steel, Green Jobs,
that's partnering with Elsa
Olivetti, and the Climate
Project, and others
is really, again,
as Amah mentioned, trying to
think about this question,
can we decarbonize?
At the same time, we don't
just automate away jobs.
How do we actually try to
create good jobs for people?
And so that's a lot of the
focus I'm bringing to this.
Hi, my name is
Laura Frye-Levine.
I am a research scientist
in anthropology.
My PhD is in sociology, and
I study sociology of science
and sociology of collaboration.
So I have a connectivity grant
from MITHIC to pilot integrated
research hub in SHASS for
conversations and research
engagement to integrate
across social science
and humanistic
disciplines, but also,
as well, to build community and
build research infrastructure
to solve climate
problems by bringing
in engineers and
scientists to figure out
how to integrate research.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Janelle Knox-Hayes.
I'm a professor in the
Department of Urban Studies
and Planning, and I direct
the Resilient Communities Lab.
And so a lot of my
research projects
are about bringing
a community focus
into both thoughts of climate
mitigation, adaptation,
and then also thinking about
energy systems and transition,
and how to bring a
socio-technical lens
into technology development.
One of the things I
wanted to highlight
is our Indigenous
Environmental Planning class.
So we've been building
for the past five years
an Indigenous community
planning program within DUSP.
And this has probably been one
of our most successful efforts.
We now have three classes.
We've partnered with the
anthropology department
to bring incredible scholars
like Leslie Jonas, who's
a Mashpee Wampanoag
Eel Clan elder,
in to co-teach these
courses with us.
And Indigenous
Environmental Planning
is an amazing course in
that we bring together
multidisciplinary students,
and then pair them
with client projects.
And so we've worked
over the last five years
with more than 20 communities
around the United States.
And the student teams have
an amazing opportunity
to learn firsthand from
these Indigenous communities
to think about their lifeways,
their knowledge systems,
and how to bring that into
a focus in different facets
of urban planning.
So we've had really
successful projects
with the nation of Hawaii,
for example, exploring
their ahupua'a system, which
is reimagining or rethinking
planning from the standpoint of
from the mountain to the sea.
So the way in which
aquifers and watersheds
guide different thoughts
about economic transition
and economic integration.
And then, working with the
Shinnecock Indian Nation,
we've done a number of
projects over the years,
including redesigning
energy systems,
and thinking about
different forms of land use
planning, where students have
actually gone in and done
participatory action
mapping with tribal elders
to think about not just the
physical resources on-site,
but the cultural heritage
sites, and how to preserve
and integrate those.
So that's been probably a
really successful example
of how to take what we're trying
to do with the Living Climate
Futures Lab, partner with
the students, partner
with the communities, and bring
all of those different knowledge
systems together.
Hi, I'm Kate Brown.
I'm an environmental historian
in science, technology,
and society.
And I came to MIT as a historian
working in nuclear disaster
zones.
And at one point,
I realized, and I
saw thousands of people going
into the radioactive pripet
marshes around the zone,
picking blueberries
on an industrial scale.
I thought-- first
I thought, what
a shame to send these
radioactive blueberries
into global markets to end
up on your breakfast table.
But then I also
started to think,
these blueberries are doing
what an army of scientists,
and engineers, and Soviet
soldiers could not do.
They're cleaning
up the environment
and handling radioactive
waste to humans
in a neat little blue package.
And so I started--
I mean, I tried to advocate
that we pay these pickers
and dispose of the blueberries,
the mushrooms, and cranberries
as radioactive waste.
But that got me
thinking about how
plants can be our
allies in ways that
offer low-carbon, low-tech
solutions to the problems
that we have in the
anthropocene today.
And so then I got interested
in big cities, and the history
of big cities, and
self-provisioning,
and how as farmers exhausted
soils in the countryside,
they were impoverished.
They moved into cities
starting in the 1850s or so.
And when they got
there, they saw
all the nutrients they had
been growing in stripping,
mining from their fields, were
all sitting around as garbage.
And they're like,
don't throw that out.
I'll take it.
And they started building
these human engineered
soils that are the most
productive agriculture
in human history.
And so I'm just finishing
a book about that.
It's coming out in February.
And that got me into teaching.
I was like, oh, there's so much
more to explore about this.
So in January, I'm going to
teach a course in Spain, an IAP
course.
We're going to take
about 15 students
over to look at
regenerative agriculture,
which then leads to regenerative
economies in the Catalonia area.
And then in the
spring semester, I'm
teaching the second part of
a MITHIC-funded course called
Urban Resilience,
with an instructor
from architecture
and another one
from Art and
Agriculture Institute.
And together, we're going to
work with two urban farms who've
asked us for help.
And what the students
are going to do is design
and build capital-shaped
capital coops,
chicken coops in the
shape of the US capital.
And on them will be history
exhibits of the food sovereignty
movements, especially in
East and South Boston,
that have been really
powerful since the 1970s.
Great.
Well, thank you for those
great introductions.
Maybe, Chris, I'll
start off with you.
I certainly appreciate
the lab's focus
on the impact of climate change
on people's everyday lives.
And at the MIT Climate Project--
and we're very
much thinking also
about the scale of
communities, because we
think that is the unit of
change that will really
help us really think about
this holistic global challenge.
But the one question we're
always grappling with,
what is really a community?
And what exactly is a scale?
It could be a small town,
say, at the Coast of Cambodia.
It could be a very
large city like Chicago.
So how do you think about
that in terms of the diversity
of contexts in your approach?
Yeah, that's a great question.
And anthropology, actually,
when we use "communities,"
we often use it in quotes.
And actually, in
my first book, I
had a whole chapter on taking
apart the concept of community.
But it can be a
helpful one, as well.
I mean, communities, as we
know, they're heterogeneous.
People move around.
They're diverse.
You can't bound something
easily as a community.
But nonetheless,
climate change effects
play out in people's
everyday lives.
And so what are the
place-based ways
in which these things play out?
Who are the leaders
who are already there?
What are the community
groups already at work?
How can we bring
those in to partner
with in ways that they're
also translating for others
in the places where they are?
And so hopefully the
focus we're bringing
is both the kind of power
of working at this level,
but at the same
time, recognizing
that kind of diversity
and heterogeneity,
and how that's also a source
for thinking more creatively
about these kinds of questions.
So I don't know if other folks--
there's plenty in the room also
who work on at
this level of work,
if others have thoughts on that.
But anyway.
Any others you want
to comment on that?
Just speaking as a
sociologist of science,
working at this intersection
of collaborative, large-scale
efforts that involve
multiple kinds of expertise,
I think it's very
common, and there's
a big literature on
this in social science,
for social scientists
and humanists
to be called upon
at the end of pipe,
to implement a prefigured
technology or research
agenda in a community.
And we know that there are
counterintuitive effects
of these technologies that
reverberate when they're not
designed in tandem with the
people who are the intended
users and with the relationships
that those technologies can
configure.
So we're really
excited to partner
at the outset of
some research design,
in terms of our
collaboration within MIT,
to build MIT's climate-wide,
MIT-wide climate
paradigm of research.
And I think one of
the definitions,
in addition to community,
is frontline communities.
So we're talking
about people who
feel like threatened by climate
change or other problems,
environmental problems.
And so a lot of
these communities
start in a living room,
where people get together
because they're upset
about something,
they're worried about
something, and then from there.
So they tend to be
self-appointed communities.
And, and in our ethics, we want
them to come to us to ask for
help.
We're trying not to be the
parachuting social scientists
that go in and
extract knowledge,
but we're there to exchange.
And I think that's a good point.
I think thinking about
frontline communities,
certainly there's still a
lot of diversity of that.
And there's so many that
you can try to work with
and to help solve
their problems.
How do you pick where to start?
And we've heard a lot
of examples of this,
but there's so many.
And how do you think
about approaching it?
How do you pick the
ones that you decide
to work with in that context?
I mean, I would
just say in my case,
that was the other way around.
I mean, because I grew
up in this old steel mill
community that was
heavily polluted,
I actually became
an anthropologist
to try to make sense of
why the experience I had,
where I was growing up--
I went-- after all the
steel mills closed,
and my dad was out of
work for a long time,
I went off to a fancy
boarding school.
And becoming an
anthropologist was a way
to try to understand
my own background.
And the relationships
with the community groups
I work with actually began
before I was an anthropologist.
So I didn't choose the place.
I chose MIT as a way to continue
that relationship there.
So that's somewhat different
than a lot of folks,
but that was kind
of the route in.
Any other comments?
Janelle, do you
have any thoughts?
Yeah, I mean, I think that
part of what you're hinting at,
Evelyn, is that you
don't have to have
interaction at a really large
scale to have meaningful impact.
And I think that's where
communities can be so important.
So many of our climate
mitigation or adaptation efforts
tend to take this state
top-down, forcing approach
that we need wide scale
energy transition.
And we do.
We absolutely do
need all of that.
But I think that, as
academics, and serving
in a bridge capacity between
the science, and the technology,
and the community values,
and needs, and objectives,
we can have a really
meaningful role working
with those communities to which
we already have connections,
or working where, locally, at a
smaller scale, that kind of work
can be really impactful
and meaningful, as well.
And I think that's
absolutely true.
And I think that's how we're
also very much thinking
about it.
But I think the
questions that continue
to be kind of front and
center is like, well,
since it's such a
large problem in--
Chris, as your case, it's
been part of you in some ways.
But as engineers, we're
trying to really take
advantage of our
skills, but also
being respectful of what
communities also want.
And how do we really
engage effectively?
And I think that speaks to,
Laura, your point, as well.
Because I think there's
a lot of well-meaning.
However, sometimes
the well-meaning
doesn't translate into how
communities kind of really
interpret kind of
that well-meaning.
And I think that's always
this ongoing challenge
and opportunity for us to
learn from many of you that
really look at these
aspects in detail.
Absolutely.
And I just might throw out
that one orientation of the lab
overall is, again, really
the focus on the long term,
so that it's not one-off
relationships like, oh, we're
going to work with this
community this semester.
And next semester, we're
going to do something else.
This is our long-term.
And the partnerships,
for many of us, were--
even mine was an unusually
long relationship.
But in many instances,
people were already
working with particular groups.
So the idea is we are in it for
the long haul with the groups
that we're partnering with.
And the idea is to keep
going back to those groups
and make sure that
it's long term.
So I think that's one of the
ways, a different kind of time
frame, is something it's key
to building relations of trust,
as you heard one of the folks
say in the video that you saw.
Kate, I'll turn to
you in terms of you
just mentioned a few classes
that you're teaching.
You talked about
this Urban Resilience
that you're teaming up
with architecture to teach.
And you also teach a class--
you've taught a class with
Susan Solomon on 20th century
environmental programs.
And you shared a little
bit, but I was curious.
What can we learn from these
efforts that would specifically
guide how we work today
across areas of MIT generally?
That's a great question.
These are challenging
relationships, I think,
across social science, and
science, and engineering.
Because we don't always
immediately speak
the same language, and we don't
always have a level of trust.
And so I think what's
been so great--
I've taught a course with
Susan Solomon in EAPS
now for the last four
or five years, and now
with architecture and art,
is that by working together--
and we have what--
the goal in mind is
students and their learning.
And working together, we
develop both a common vocabulary
and a sense of trust.
And then from there, we
start to do other things.
So Susan Solomon and I
write right op-eds together,
and we get involved in this,
and so on, and so forth.
So I think that's one of
the real values we have.
And thanks to
MITHIC for allowing
us to be able to-- in
the social sciences,
to start to ask the questions,
and to set the first parameters,
and invite others to come in.
I think that's really helpful.
Yeah, that's great.
And, Janelle, I have
a question for you.
You mentioned in your
introductory remarks
that you spent a lot of time
with Indigenous communities,
and you talked about
the opportunities.
But where do you see there
are still challenges and gaps
by which how we
really can effectively
engage with them, that
we can help them and work
with them effectively?
Yeah, I think, I mean,
the last few months
have been really challenging
with all of the federal impacts,
different regulatory pressures.
And so I think capacity
is a huge issue that
is-- as academic institutions,
it's really important
that our engagements
are not extractive,
that we're actually
going in and that there's
a mutual exchange or mutual
facilitation of benefit
in these exchanges.
And so funding is a huge
issue, trying to find--
we never-- when we were running
the Indigenous Environmental
Planning practicum
course, we actually--
we provide honoraria
to the communities
to work with our students.
And that's really important.
It's acknowledging the
time and the effort
that they're putting
into the projects
and what they're
bringing to the table.
And so I think that
kind of level of support
can't be taken for granted.
We've seen in the
last few months
where we have a more
difficult budgetary situation,
how that can make that
kind of work challenging.
And then it's also
just a capacity issue.
The often Indigenous
nations, you're
looking at smaller
groups of people
that are fulfilling all of
the functions of a government.
So any kind of
engagement with us
is an extra level of engagement.
And sometimes the
ministers or secretaries
that we're working with in
these governments already
have multiple jobs.
And so it's kind
of that recognition
that any kind of
academic engagement
can take time and resources
away from them, as well.
And so I think it's
to Chris's point.
It's important that the
relationships be meaningful
to both sides.
They're absolutely
invaluable to our students,
but that we have sustained
funding and resources
to support these programs
where we want to build them,
and that they're also long term.
I think some of our most
successful projects,
like with Shinnecock
Indian Nation,
we've done multiple projects
over and over again,
and they develop really
meaningful relationships
with our students.
Our students have an
appreciation for the communities
they're working with.
And then the projects
themselves can actually
take work that's somewhat
restricted by being
in a one-semester context
and expand it over time.
So that they can do, actually,
really deep and meaningful work
for these--
or with these communities.
Well, thank you for that.
Laura, I'm very excited
about MITHIC in general
and the opportunities
for cross-pollination
with what we're trying to
achieve with the Climate
Project.
You spoke to this a little bit
in your introductory remarks,
as well.
And your research really
has included an examination
of the challenges faced by
these interdisciplinary teams
and seeking these collaborative
approaches to developing
these climate solutions.
And I was wondering if you
could dig in a little bit more,
because I think this is
really the crux of it
all as we're trying to think
about how do we really engage
across the ecosystem to
really move the needle in some
of these solutions in impacting
and helping communities.
Absolutely.
Thank you for that.
I think that is the most
exciting and potentially
generative challenge.
When we crack that is
an MIT hard problem.
My colleagues have
spoken to some
of the collaborative
environments
that they've been involved
in, in terms of collaborating
internally to MIT.
And I'm hearing
a lot of emphasis
on trust building,
capacity building,
and working together to
identify some shared language.
And these are all
excellent tools for us
in terms of individual
collaborations.
And I also want to point out
some what's under the hood
a little bit in
these challenges.
So we are often presumed, in
social science and humanities,
to have different
objects of study.
And that can be true.
But as we've heard from
all these wonderful videos,
we have a lot of
shared interests
in terms of how to address
climate as an object of study.
So we may study
people in communities,
but folks in engineering
study efficiency,
and mechanical processes,
and technical innovation,
and all these things that are
exciting and at the forefront
of climate work.
But there really is a gap
in research investment,
in terms of social
science, of climate change.
So only less than 0.25%
of research funding
goes to the social science
of climate mitigation.
So that's a really exciting
opportunity for us.
And integrating across these
expertise-- areas of expertise
is quite difficult. We need to
learn how to get comfortable
with indeterminacy, with
speaking in different paradigms,
and with having different
kinds of empirical toolkits.
I think our empirical
toolkits are often
not legible to one another.
And we also really
need to figure out
how to think differently, and
thinking in terms of impact
differently, I think we've
heard a little bit of--
I'd love to continue
this conversation
because impact is such a--
it's a watchword, and
it's so motivating.
And I'm going to oversimplify
engineering a little bit,
I realize.
But when engineers
think about impacts,
they're thinking
about optimizing
within a particular technology
or a particular technical
process, and optimizing
within the boundaries
of a specific condition.
But as we know from a lot
of research in engineering,
as well as in social
sciences, when
you expand that area of
analysis, impacts in one area
have counterintuitive
effects at larger scales,
at longer scales, not just
in other technical arenas,
but also for social
relationships,
for communities, for receiving
communities of pollution,
and things like this.
So I think this is a
really powerful opportunity
we have to, at MIT, situate
technical innovation
within its
sociotechnical context.
And so I'm really excited
to be involved in that.
And I think the theme
here is a lot of learnings
across disciplines
for us to really
be able to really appreciate
all these different nuances
and opportunities.
I'm starting to realize,
I'm out of time.
So I'm sorry.
We do have time for questions.
Please, Kurt.
Thanks.
Laura, you actually started
to get into this a little bit
in your last response.
I'm curious, while across
all of these great projects,
you're investing in the
heterogeneous nature
of each community, what kinds
of interesting entanglements,
especially beneficial or
particularly interesting ones,
might be coming up because
you're gathering all
of these projects together
under the Living Climate Futures
umbrella?
Yeah, and if there's folks--
where did [INAUDIBLE] go?
Amah might have
thoughts on this.
Just to throw
something, if nothing
comes to mind quickly
for somebody else,
I was just thinking we
actually did a symposium.
This is actually where the
idea for this lab came from,
was a symposium we
had back in 2022.
And it brought together
different environmental justice
groups, different urban
farmers, Indigenous groups
from different parts
of the country.
And they all got together.
And there was one
moment where we
had-- there were these
young teenagers of color
from a high school in
Southeast Chicago who
were dealing with all these
kinds of toxicity issues.
And they got into
conversation in the audience
with some of the leaders
of the Lummi Nation
from the Pacific Northwest.
And one of the leaders of
the illumination, Jay Julius,
said to the student--
you know, I dreamed you,
and had all this amazing--
and those teenagers were
just like, oh my God.
They were just so amazed
by this kind of connection
across groups.
And so there was
conversations that
were happening across
different kinds of groups,
very different kinds of
groups in different parts
of the country that
kind of sparked
whole other kinds
of relationships.
Some of those folks are still
in conversation with each other,
just a generativity of bringing
these different stuff together.
And so there's something, in
some ways, that's imposing,
we kind of thought
of it as a happening.
You bring these people
together, and it
was about putting
them into conversation
and seeing what
comes out of that.
And that was just
really super exciting.
I don't know if others
in the group, in the room
have thoughts on this.
But anyway.
You have a question?
I have a question
that goes crossing
between the Living Climate
Futures and the Climate Project.
Because it seems
as though impact
might mean something
very different
between the two projects.
And would anyone do-- does
anyone perceive that and want
to comment on it?
I'll start, if you
might, if it's OK.
I actually think there's--
actually, I think they're
the same, ultimately,
at the end of the day.
And the Climate
Project is very much
focused on building wellbeing.
And that means both human
wellbeing and planetary health.
And I think that
impacts on communities,
and how we want to
think about how do we
build, empower communities
so that they can have
these lives that are
sustainable, resilient,
and prosperous, I
think it's synergistic.
And so it's not just about
say, CO2 abated from--
that's a very
technological perspective.
It's also about jobs.
It's about job creation.
It's about bolstering
local economies.
There's a lot of this, I think,
that is hopefully resonant.
Welcome your thoughts
from this team.
I think this is such an
important conversation
for us to continue to have.
I think when we crack that MIT
hard problem of impact that
is locally situated, and
desirable, and climate
solutions that are not just
durable in the long term,
in terms of planetary health,
but also welcomed and integrated
into the prosperity
of local communities.
And being invited
into that process,
we will generate some
really cool solutions.
Yeah.
OK.
We have a flashing
red light here,
which makes me think
that we're out of time.
Let's thank our
panel one more time.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
You can stay all the way.
That's the end of our
programming for today.
I just want to thank, one more
time, all of our presenters
and all of our moderators for
the wonderful panels today.
If you're--
[APPLAUSE]
So to produce an event like
this requires a lot help
from a lot of different people.
And because we are a
human-centered entity,
I'm going to name them all.
So I'd like to thank a lot
of people who have helped out
either today, volunteering,
or in the lead-up to today
in terms of the planning.
So a big thanks to Tia
Griglio, Michael Brindley,
Liam McDonnell, Megan
Hinkley, Anne-Marie Michael,
Handley Valentine, Jennifer
Guarino, Maeve Downey,
MF Geddes, Jana Green, Carly
Sol, Benjamin Daniel, John Van,
Britta Bell, Rosie
Dicostanzo, Liz Kazakh, sorry.
And then the lovely people from
MIT AV and Video Productions.
Thank you to all of these.
[APPLAUSE]
And the biggest thank
you goes to our MIT team.
This is Jen Altan.
I think you want
to take up a bow.
And Elena Nosiglia.
[APPLAUSE]
I mean, we're very fortunate
to have Institute support
for MITHIC and such amazing
faculty producing this work.
But we're also very fortunate to
have a team like Jen and Elena
supporting everything
we're doing.
I have some closing words,
but I'm not going to say them.
I think instead, we're going
to go down to the sixth floor
and have a reception.
Because I think
community building
is a large part of MITHIC.
So let's go talk
and build community.
Thanks, everyone.
[APPLAUSE]