[Music]
tonight I want to try to pose the basic
assumption behind the idea of
facilitative leadership in the public
sector and share a few terms a few
Concepts I want to give you a problem to
think about at dinner then ask you at
your table to pursue the questions and
then save about 10 minutes at the end to
see if something different was happening
at the different tables but the key idea
tonight is raise this question and offer
some terms some Concepts the goal is to
begin a conversation if I had these
ideas all worked out for myself I would
have written a book but I definitely
don't have all these ideas worked out so
my goal is to share some thoughts
provoke some
conversation ask you to continue the
conversation in small groups and then
all together and I'm hoping that I can
get you to write a couple Pages at the
end of the fourth week or sooner should
you be mo motivated and that I can take
all of those and work them into the kind
of uh summary or synthesis I will draft
something and then encourage anybody
that contributed to continue to work to
take that draft develop it further and
have it be a departmental publication
which we don't have but I don't see why
we can't do that because I think the
question will continue um to be of
interest and concern so all
started last spring at the end of uh the
semester my course on negotiation and
dispute resolution in the public sector
uh said you know I've looked around for
leadership courses they have them at the
Kennedy School they have them at the
business school at Harvard they have
them at
Sloan but they all seem to assume you're
somebody working in a private
organization it's not the same thing as
leadership in the public context really
the assumption is you're in an
organization and it's a private
organization how do you manage as a
leader there's nothing said differently
about being in a leadership role in the
public sector and I think it's very
different that's the what I'm trying to
work out in what ways is it different
should all the basic assumptions be
questioned about leadership SL
management of groups organizations
networks um in the public sector I've
spent 50 years working in dispute
resolution in the public sector in 30
countries um I want to think
comparatively about this so please do
not constrain yourself unnecessarily to
imagine only something in a US context
when we're talking um at table
conversation if you're thinking very
much in your culture your context your
country just say so don't not do it but
let everybody else know that you're
starting from a different point in the
conversation and I don't know about how
far generalizations can go about the
public sector when we switch from
country and culture to Country culture
we'll see what you think about
that imagine a city government has
appointed a task force to give the city
advice regarding the decision the city
has to make regarding the use of a
particular piece of public land that was
abandoned not used and now there are
multiple proposals for how it should be
used within that neighborhood within the
city within the metropolitan area and
the cities asked a task force of people
the uh the usual the Blue Ribbon
committee was announced and a lot of
folks yelled about that and so more
people got added that was the solution
to representation that that mayor chose
okay fine we'll just add more people
especially the ones who've made noise
you be on the
committee begging the
question of the representativeness and
thus The
credibility of this group and whatever
it
recommends but since the city wasn't
giving away final decision-making
Authority was just asking for advice
from a task force didn't worry too much
about
representativeness it didn't worry too
much about
credibility in the eyes of the groups
that weren't at the
table and so this task
force has been
meeting it didn't have much of a mandate
just we like your advice about this
undeveloped parcel that's been sitting
here for a long time what do you think
City should do with it and my question
to you
is how would you know who's the real
leader of that task force they've met
multiple
times they have whatever mandate they
had from the mayor's office how would we
know who's the real leader of this 25
person group you could clearly tell that
a couple of people had way more
knowledge and experience with regard to
the city city politics City Planning
City development real estate development
and they were showing it off in the
conversation did that make them the
leader or maybe we're listening and one
person soft
voice not pushing hard at all on the
substantive question but says well I've
been on a bunch of task forces like this
before in the city and my sense is we
ought to do this this and this and use
our time this way way and get the
involvement of other people like so and
so and so and so with the fact that that
person had the most experience in this
kind of a role would that qualify them
to be the leader would that make them
the
leader is one person who clearly is the
Workhorse on this committee they're
saying oh I'll take the notes I'll work
the flip chart and they're making very
clear that they're taking care of all
the
housekeeping chores and activities
almost like a secretary keeping track of
the ideas and offering their own views
along the
way is the person willing to do the most
work the leader who's the
leader or are there just these
leadership
functions and different people can all
choose on their own to play different
functions as long as the rest of the
group accepts it if we're in a corporate
context I promise you everyone would
know who the leader of the group is
because whoever said there would be a
meeting whoever said there would be a
group
appointed the person who was the head of
the group
right doesn't happen that way most of
the time I'm talking about when the
larger
network of
the
public is
tapped and trying to organize in cities
trying to organize them don't we need a
theory of
practice as urban
planners with regard to how this
leadership question should be handled in
the public
Arena just whatever happens mayor says
it's fine with me it's a whole group can
just collect their suggestions and send
them to me that's
fine as practitioners I think we need a
theory of practice could be our own it
could be the MIT theory of leadership
facilitative leadership could be you
know your tables Theory but I don't see
how as planners we just wander
forward and we're going to be in so many
situations in which OD hoc clusters of
people are supposed to be doing the
Public's work we're usually supposed to
be involved in such things and I think
the key to that is to see yourself as a
facilitative leader providing a
service a service it's a service model
of leadership which I think is necessary
in the public sector but you can
convince me that that's wrong you have
plenty of alternative models and that's
why we're going to be having
conversations about this they need to be
empathetic to the interests of the other
people in the around the
table if you can't Jin up empathy for
the others and their quandaries with
regard to this you'll never be a leader
of that
group you have to be a capable active
listener if you can't hear how far off
you are about what's going on by
listening to people talking to each
other or to you you won't
succeed you have to be able to read the
group to recognize underlying
dynamics that let you know more about
the interests of the
participants this is not people raising
their hand and saying something reading
the group over many occasions Coalition
building you can't keep treating it like
a set of individuals who are only there
for themselves you have to help them
begin to form
coalitions you cannot function in a
service role if you cannot put aside
your ego you need to be able to take a
Long View the group needs you to do that
they're focused on the short term I
would argue the facilitative leader has
to constantly be thinking about the long
term you have to be able to write the
group's victory speech you have to be
able to draft that as the facilitative
leader because it has to take count of
how it looks from all of their
standpoints you have to promote
organizational learning along the way
what didn't we do well what did we do
well how would was that just this one
time or is there something there we can
change about how we're working so we do
better next time but if someone is not
focused on organizational learning it
will not just fall out
naturally now when I look at that list
of let's call them skills not micro
skills but capabilities capacities leads
me to the conclusion may lead you to a
different conclusion that facilitative
leaders are made and not
born I believe that the
charismatic
leader who provides Vision who provides
inspiration uh you you might try really
hard to become that my sense is that
carismatic leaders are
born it's not that they don't do
anything to improve themselves I just
don't think you can build yourself up
piece by piece to become
charismatic I really do think that's
either lucky or not lucky to be endowed
with
that ability as an inspirational
leader charismatic leaders I think are
more likely to be born than
made paternalistic
leaders that you we can train them I
think Sloan and H BS do a great
job I can't deny they've made a whole
lot of people like that I would like to
think that if we
tried D USP could make a whole lot of
facilitative leaders people who are
collaborative service providers in the
public sector on this question of our
facilitative leaders made not born I I
think facilitative leaders can be
made and there are people who
when it comes down to it say yeah a
facilitative leader can provide
Direction without taking
control they know that everyone has to
be involved in all the decisions
leadership in the public sector requires
different kinds of skills orientation
and a different Theory from leadership
in private organizational contexts I
counting on the
conversation over these uh four weeks uh
to maybe make a case the beginning of a
case to take to the department and say
what what exactly are you hoping I'm
going to turn out to
be don't tell me planner that do doesn't
do it it has to be more than
that so we break for dinner and then um
I will ask you uh to uh consider some of
the questions from within what I've
presented I'm hoping to get from each of
you by the end of week four some
reflection on this proposition that I'm
[Music]
offering so public private any
important difference always sometimes
maybe second question facilitative
leaders are made not born does that
sound right to you and anybody become a
facilitative leader I mean leader I
don't just mean a facilitative person so
made not born public versus private and
can you cons really construe leadership
as service
you say I'm a leader I'm providing
service that's what I'm doing service in
the public interest that's the dominant
consideration in thinking about
leadership in the public sector can you
imagine yourself in a service role
someone who's recognized for the service
they provide in the public Arena so I
offer those three points um see where
the discussion goes take 20 minut
minutes meet somebody you don't know
talk to someone you do know and you
never get to talk
to one of my managers was like you need
to have the confidence to like assert
that make a decision and move forward
with it rather than trying to make
everything a collective decision when
you're like there's a group and I do
think there's kind of a gender Dynamic
involved in that where and I felt like I
was younger in the office I felt like oh
I should be deferring to all the other
people in his group uh in order to make
decisions I do think like women maybe
socialized to be more
facilitated uh rather than like turtle
or top down I don't want to say like a
taping role but it does begin to feel
like you're nurturing consciences sort
of timing to every news as opposed to
achieving the best station it kind of
feels like hurting cats sometimes and
there is a lot of emotional labor
involved understanding
social dynamics and power and political
Dynamics sometimes even like I don't
know like
babysitting you know it doesn't feel
like a sexy leader
role like it's definitely not I think if
you're delivering a product as opposed
to a service you don't have to have much
of it within just Mo drive and ambition
but if
you're leaning into
process which I think is like the nature
of filation like you need to be patient
with folks to provide the service I feel
like this can be very easily under
appreciated that's kind of service I
feel like maybe leadership does contain
a meaning of achieving a consensus like
we still need to lead people to
somewhere public sector is trying to
achieve our best to serve public
interest uh in public different voices
from multi stakeholders but for private
corporate they have a Clear Vision or a
clear goal that I want to create this
product there is no involvement of the
community in what we are doing the
corland is different than probably the
skills that you may need in terms of
leadership they may have commonalities
but I do believe that there are certain
differences my perception is that the
private sector is it's more it's more
Bur fault and it's more based on on
appointments and authori and in the
public sector in my experience you may
need a little more influence in the
public sector what's more dangerous is
that you're kind of putting on this
facade of like this is the public but
then the mechanisms there don't allow
people to equally come to the table the
of the public and private sectors are
different the the nature of leadership
should be different how do you think
like managing people differs the public
sector in many South European countries
you have to play a a low profile Asad as
no as an individual that wants to Aspire
as a leader I I have a heart type here
uh in the US in the US particularly yeah
I mean I've been working 20 years with
an Anglo Saxon organization that is the
UN and I think that this doesn't work in
other cultures in many cultures I think
it's very difficult to transpose these
styles of leadership wholesale but by
developing skills you can eventually
bestowed the power by the community
because they see that you are ready to
show up and you are aligned to their
values and that's very important is in
Japan for example they have a hard time
partnering and negotiating with
Americans they are self-confident and
spoken and and they are bold yes and
this boldness which here is considering
a skill and something positive you are
confident with yourself which don't take
me wrong it's not bad in certain
cultures could be considered arrogant
and it's important to play a more low
profile role so how was that very when
you're in that give it that's that's one
of the things is is empathy you reading
the room and you understand that for
example in the noric countries people
don't want to shine Ah that's people
don't want to shine the power of the
many noric countries is the community
itself while here in the state I can see
that this distinction you can see that
in movies and narrative a leader is
someone that shine that concept of
leadership doesn't apply every for us
reades working in Japan is perfect but
Americans they always have a CL septum
communities are are more like silent so
you don't have to discuss and I'm not
saying that they are better or worse
there are certain communities that they
have other value than a
financials this goes for public Evans I
think a lot of times you're rewarded for
just like doing your Curr job well which
a lot of just start out as like a
technical skill and then you can get
promoted to a manager role of people who
do that technical skin
but you're not taught how to be a
manager how to support people how to
develop their skills you're just like
really good at that
one things like empathy and being a good
listener are things that you know might
get I don't know kind of not embody
those qualities as much I'd honestly
like love to talk about the like
efficiency piece in the public sector
because cost efficiency is usually one
of the biggest conversations that
efficiency isn't articulated as like
anything come up that anybody felt
strongly about on any of those three
issues the concept of leadership as
service and we kind of had a maybe this
is a philosophical question about
whether there's a such thing as like
selfless leadership or is everyone
always at the back of their minds doing
something for their own benefit even if
you are facilitating trying to be a
facilitative leader do you get a little
ego Rush when you like make something
happen you know are we all at dust
because
we truly want to change the world or
because we think that we're important
enough to do that thank you thanks
Cris those who have some CTIC
characteristics will naturally be deer
so we opened up by discussing the
question of whether facilitative leaders
are made or war and uh we talked a
little bit about the role of gender and
race and sexuality in this question just
kind of speaking from my experience
being a woman in the public sector I
found myself deferring to a more
facilitative form of leadership when
maybe being a little bit more assertive
or um taking on more of a
decision-making role would have been
better um so I think that yeah kind of
thinking about the social dynamics
around whether someone is innately
facilitative is important a lot of the
time in public settings there's
apprehension to take that more
decision-making position just
because that's maybe not like the the
role that we've like historically
occupied and so we defer to potentially
more caretaking more
nurturing uh I guess like function in
decision making so we tend to build in
consensus rather than delegating respons
responsibility or asserting expertise in
a realm um because if you don't look
like the decision maker often times your
credibility could be reckoned challenged
pushed back against and so the next best
thing is often to maybe opt for
facilitation instead especially in a
public setting when when sometimes it
can be hard to Corral really cating
interest okay we have a very interesting
discussion on we may have in our minds a
concept of leader that perhaps is not
share with other parts of the world and
I think that this is very important
where we are defining some of the skills
that makes a leader because we are still
especially certain communities certain
societies create a sort of a narrative
in certain communities what leadership
should be we discuss that leaders are
made by the legitimacy that the
community give to someone what
legitimizes the leader and gives them
that capacity that authority to
influence all those folks usually we see
the arrow going the other way which is
the legitimacy of the leader is a
function of the support of the
population in the public Arena so the
arrow goes from the
constituency to the leader it all it's
providing
legitimacy and yet we're crediting the
leader with providing Direction and
helping everybody see what they're going
to do
so if we talk about legitimacy and
sources of legitimacy and we talk about
Authority and the sources of authority
and we can certainly compare public and
private there are very different sources
of legitimacy sources of authority if we
talk about responsibility comparing
leaders in the private sector versus
leaders in the public sector what's
their responsibility clearly this
there's different right so if you begin
to pile up these differences and you say
all right so how is this public sector
leader
leading to get a different source of
authority different source of legitimacy
different nature of responsibility
forget about the skills they have or
don't have there's a big difference I
think now we can say oh you're just
saying that because you're looking at it
from a a a western perspective or you're
looking at it from a a US perspective uh
and that may be although
when I look at the sources of legitimacy
for leaders in some different countries
I can't find out I can't figure out what
they are I mean people have taken
leadership and it legitimacy wasn't the
issue they sort of took the leadership
I'm not saying they worked against an
electoral process in a democratic
context I'm saying but what gave them
credibility as a leader wasn't just that
they were elected my goodness
that something else gave them
credibility gave them the right to
exercise
Authority and I'm wondering what their
sense of responsibility was I know that
those three things are different when I
talk to and watch leaders in the public
Arena versus leadership in a private
company and we didn't get to discuss
what you mean by the public interest
right we're we're presuming the
responsibility partly to the Public's
interest as part at least of what a
leader in the public sector has to do
and then where do they get satisfaction
the questions that you raised first what
do they think success means and what
does it give them what does it generate
for them I said earlier that if you take
service seriously as a model that you
would include in that ability put your
ego aside I don't mean you have no ego I
mean the issue is when I rank my
responsibilities what's first and when
there's a tradeoff what's dominant and
over time
consistently and my sense is that we've
got to talk about being an effective
leader who can meet the public
interest but also this satis action that
comes from being effective in that role
and that's for that person I don't mean
to erase any of that when I talk about
Service as the primary model yes people
still will
pursue the things that satisfy them that
they're going to be motivated not just
by being in service not just by meeting
the public interest but by doing a good
job being recognized for that it's just
what's got priority when tradeoffs have
to be made what's the
primary objective will come back to them
but born versus
made public versus private when we make
these distinctions do we end up with a
model of a leader that we would admire
in any country in the
world Maybe not maybe there's just
radical differences by culture and
context and location I'm very prepared
to hear that that's a view that's come
out of everybody the levels of
governance uh Power relationships and
power dynamics responsibility and even
impact that the public and private
sector may have they also would be
reflected on some skills and
characteristics that we be shared by
both of them them there are certain
characteristics and skills and nuanced
and in even political sense that you
will need in the public sector more than
in the private sector in order to move
forward initiatives in order to create
consensus in order to engage with
different communities um so we thought
that it could be a little bit more
complex in the public sector and
therefore those skills must be
enhanced something that we just
discussed is the difference in the
public sector versus the private sector
of the accountability measures and how
in a lot of different
contexts across the world the public
sector a big fault is that you might
have a good relationship with people
that you're interacting with through a
public process but if there is no
tangible outcome that people see from
their time and efforts people are going
to be frustrated and disempowered by the
process and then they'll be much less
likely or even ref used to participate
again and in the private sector that is
just not really something that people
have to navigate because the
accountability is already built into the
leadership role and then we talked a
little bit about the leaders
facilitative leaders are made or born
and I think collectively we did talk
about they're mostly made because a lot
of qualities that you did point out like
empathy or active listening or putting
your ego aside or organizational
learning I feel like are things you
learn by actually interacting with
people by doing this again and again
this process we need to stop thinking of
this one person needs to have all of
these qualities and maybe just think
along the lines of how you can continue
to do it better thank you okay um we'll
meet again same time next week think
about your own view of what makes a
leader in the public sector successful
okay so do think about that thank you
all so much for coming and we'll see you
next week
[Applause]
[Music]