So today we're going to do a simple
little demonstration we're just going to
work out how big a voltage we can get on
this vandag graph generator when I have
the belt on the belt is pulling
electrons out of the vandag graph and
when I have the grounding rod here as it
pulls electrons out of the Vander graph
the electrons are flowing back in
through the grounding rod now as soon as
I take the grounding rod
off the only way that the electrons can
get from the grounding rod to the vandag
graph is via making a lightning bolt and
right there there's a lightning bolt
that's going about 15 cm through dry air
and the breakdown voltage of dry air is
33,000 volts per centimeter so that's
roughly 500,000 volts if I come in
closer they'll become much more frequent
because the vandag graph discharges when
it's picked up a much lower voltage
right now it's discharging when it's
only about 100,000 Volts for more MIT
moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow