hi everyone good morning very excited
for this uh discussion where we're able
to have three terrific industry leaders
here who are dealing with some of the
generative AI uh challenges that were
coming up in earlier presentations in
their everyday uh lives and careers so I
just wanted to um start by asking our
our three panelists we have uh Lisa
gelber here who's the founder of grow
with Google and the chief marketing
Officer of Google in the Americas we
have Marco who's the global head of the
CIO office for ING uh a large global
bank um which he'll he'll describe in
more detail and then finally PR
natarajan from um from Capital One who's
the chief scientist and head of
Enterprise AI which I think is probably
the most fitting title we could have for
this for this discussion PR um but just
a a question for all of you to get us
started and and to dive into some
details I'd love to hear a little bit
about how in your roles you've been
dealing with generative AI applications
where you've seen kind of a no-brainer
or a slam dunk case of using these tools
and where are you thought that the tools
would be useful but it turns out we're
not there yet and maybe starting with
you Lisa and your role with grow with
Google sure
um uh good morning
everyone um so on in my world um growth
Google is really about digital Equity um
we're focused on how do you make sure
that the opportunities that are created
by technology are truly available to
everyone and that's really relevant in
the case of AI
um so we've been focused on how do you
give everyone the basic skills for using
these tools to improve their performance
their knowledge and their
productivity um so we've been talking to
a lot of employers um and hearing basic
use cases and and you can look at things
like even the McKenzie study from May of
this year and basically what people are
saying is there's great use cases in the
place of things like HR where people are
finding real cost savings phenomenal use
cases in customer service higher
resolution faster and then um in the
world that I work in um for the other
half of my job really good use cases on
the marketing and sales side as well
better ability to reach customers with
more personalized messages leading to
more efficient and effective marketing
and better sales
pipeline terrific Marco how about in in
the world of High Finance
the world of High Finance or digital
Finance for that matter there we go yeah
um well for us this is a logical next
evolution in in banking we've served
some some waves whether it's process
automation or the internet wave or the
app wave or the cloud wave modular
architecture wave so this is the obvious
next wave in banking probably leading to
new business models or business
propositions for that matter um and the
last couple of years we've been
experimenting a lot with the with data
usage how can we use it what really
delivers value uh one obviously is there
it's it's a massive use case that's all
the reporting that we need to do to all
kind of
stakeholders you need to do it it
delivers a certain value but I would say
the the most value we get out of
increasing customer experience in
customer interaction getting providing
better insights for example having a
better conversation more relevant and
the other one is the developer
experience um so really making life a
bit easier and faster for our developers
turning into a better time to market for
example um before getting into the use
cases Ben uh maybe just I'll make a few
comments on like what makes you ready
for uh AI um and I think there are a few
prerequisites um one is uh the talk that
you all just heard from Barbara uh the
state of your data
infrastructure um AI brings to life the
value that is resident in your data so
if you don't have your data act together
that's kind of the first thing to do and
what is the state of your data stack as
well the second is the overall Tech the
modernity of your Tech stack and your
Tech
infrastructure um are you you know
ideally you know Capital One went all in
on the Cloud 5 6 7 8 years ago before my
time uh that's a state of excellent
Readiness in my mind when I joined a
couple of years ago I was surprised by
the Readiness of the tech infrastructure
um versus are you fragmented across many
different Tech Stacks ETA are you Cloud
native or not uh the third is the state
of your talent uh what is the state of
your in-house Tech Talent what are your
gaps what do you need to bring in a lot
of this um the system integration
approach doesn't work work you know
classic it Enterprise it has been a lot
about integrating systems in third
parties uh but in this case you really
do need to have some practitioners uh
and so Banks uh we're not the only one
but we're certainly one of the uh first
ones uh having a history of practicing
machine learning uh in their decision
processes or putting them uh to work um
are are in a better state of Readiness
having said those I'll say uh the two
ones it's not going to be a big reveal
for anyone I mean if Jim Kramer is
talking about it on CNBC and saying
customer servicing is a big opportunity
for AI it's not like the best kept
secret in the world um but the way I
would look at it is take a look at where
is The Leverage where are most of your
opportunities uh use it as a test and
learn approach early on so uh customer
servicing is one uh we certainly uh put
in place systems uh these are early days
for everything you're asking about
what's working what's not working I
don't think we've proven anything is
actually working massively yet right we
just have a lot of conviction around the
areas where they're going to work um AR
you were talking about the software
piece I think globally everybody's
making a big bet across Industries where
technology is used at scale uh that
software development is going to be uh
another place but it's about the full
sdlc a peace meal approach to just
authoring or just testing or this or
that doesn't actually give you that much
of an unlock but our early experiments
on both are super promising we're
already seeing lift but it's too early
to talk about actual numbers but I'll
say like in the customer servicing in
certain areas you can see uh pretty
substantive lift in terms of the agent
experience definely to stay with you PR
for a second you know we hear in earlier
presentations about the democratization
of technology and that generative AI in
particular could be a democratizing
force putting more um potential in the
hands of individual users but what you
said at the beginning I found
interesting where you need to have the
infrastructure in place to really make
use of these tools and not everyone has
that infrastructure so it seems like it
might take a while to get to the actual
democra so I wonder how you feel like I
think it's two different things I mean
the fact that the goal is
democratization yeah but we all know
democracies require a lot of work and
they require a lot of infrastructure and
they require a lot of scaffolding to
work right so I'm just talking about
what is is your state of Readiness yeah
to be to be practicing or pursuing the
stated goal of democratization of AI I
mean I think I don't think you'll find a
single Enterprise leader who says um my
goal is to make sure only like a small
fraction of my users can benefit from
this right we really do want everybody
to benefit and you create mechanisms uh
those mechanisms include education at
one end resources for experimentation
and learning somewhere in the middle
ready to use tools somewhere in there
but the maximum leverage you know to the
extent that everybody believes that your
data Advantage is your AI Advantage
right uh I certainly believe that uh you
can't be practicing the and your data is
proprietary and I think the future of AI
is also proprietary for Enterprise and
it's not proprietary in the sense that
the algorithms are particularly
proprietary so it is democratic in the
sense the tools Technologies and the
platforms are available to everyone but
that doesn't mean everybody's going to
be equally proficient at practicing how
to bring things to life that's where you
have to make investments yeah fully
relate to that and with that respect
highly recommend also one of the books
of Caesar by the way uh become how to
become Future Ready highly can recommend
that
but in indeed what you stress as well
you need to be ready to work with to
tools like this and it's not isolated uh
you work together with your Tech
ecosystem for so for example in our
customer interaction yes we've seen uh
we've seen the value but not let's say
from the data on its own but working
together with our friends at gcp for
example or working together with our
friends at Adobe George was touching
upon that it only works if the whole
system works same applies for the
developer experience yes thanks thank
you for co-pilot but it's all about
making life easier for developers so we
work together again with our friends at
Spotify to really improve let's say this
developer experience and bring the data
in otherwise it's just another
tool so to shift gears a little bit Lis
you know you've made these speaking of
democratization you've made resources
for learning about AI more available
through Google's AI Essentials course it
builds on a series of courses you've
already developed around data science
and you know we talk about maybe the
infrastructure for an organization is a
a data stack here we have something like
a training St back I wonder why you felt
like at Google this was important and
what skills are really necessary to
learn in order to use these tools
effectively yeah so um so we spent a lot
of time talking to organizations about
how's it going uh what are what are you
actually seeing your people do and the
other day I was talking to the head of
AI for a big multinational company and
he basically said I just can't get
people to use it and I was like what do
you mean and he said well people don't
know how to use it so they're basically
treating it like search they're doing a
crappy query they're getting crappy
results and they're going ah it is all
hype and they don't really appreciate
the value so one of the most important
things I think is teaching people to
prompt well these tools are amazing when
you know how to use them but it is
garbage in garbage out um and so one of
the things we've created at Google is a
short form course called AI Essentials
um and it teaches you all the basics
what is AI how does it work what do you
have to be careful about and then kind
of the art of prompting um and then we
put that course online and made it
available to everyone because one of our
core principles is that AI can be a
great equalizing technology and I can
talk about that in a second um so I have
kind of an evolving mental model of um
how we can get individuals to be
productive in our organizations around
using Ai and because I'm a marketing
person I call it the four C's the first
is Clarity do people in your
organization understand what the
parameters and guard rails are around
how they can use this stuff do they know
what information is okay to put in what
tool Clarity the second is critical
metrics are you um clear on which
metrics you're going to use to evaluate
success so as you go into building out
these projects everyone knows what
you're shooting for the third is
community how are you helping people
share best practices across the
organization um and the fourth is
credentials so one of the things that I
was talking to this person about was how
do you motivate people to educate
themselves and fortunately or
unfortunately people are a little
motivated by having a credential they
can show for what they've learned they
can put it on their LinkedIn or
internally use it as a badge and so
that's why things like our AI Essentials
program are also useful is because
Google is giving you a credential
certifying that you have learned the
basics so I think in in my mind these
four C's are kind of in addition to the
tech and data infrastructure that
they've been talking about kind of the
change management part for getting
people to embrace these tools so did
they sign up to put their people through
the course or what was what was the end
of the story there yeah so lots of
companies are signing up to use RI
essential City group was actually the
first um company to sign up their whole
organization um so any company can use
it please check it out Google AI
Essentials but also um individuals can
use it so if you're personally
interested um all of our courses are
hosted on corsera it's really easy to
find the Google AI Essentials course and
of course we have a whole stack of ways
to learn if you're more advanced or more
technical learner as well and I wonder
at at in in Capital One what has been
the approach to learning have you seen
something similar to this executive like
resistance to I know that there's a
group probably of power users who are
early adopters and excited to use these
tools and then as as we've seen in our
research a majority of people still have
yet to adopt or maybe curious but
resistant type attitudes what have been
your experiences you first okay thanks
um I'll say actually it's more about
keeping the floodgates closed so it
there's no there's no lacking of
excitement like there's a tremendous
excitement across the Enterprise whether
you're whether you're a tech associate
or Tech employee or doing other kinds of
jobs like business analysis and stuff
like everybody thinks that jobs are
going to be transformed uh by AI I will
uh say um uh I agree with the first
point I think you do have to Define what
are your metrics for success or like
what does success look like even if it's
not a metric metrics are pretty hard
right now like take software development
there's a fair amount of debate going on
around what's a real metric is it the
speeding up of the release cycle is it
the shortening of the Agile development
it's just it's not clear that any of
these are clear signals but you want to
have a sense of what success looks like
uh before you start beyond that you also
want to take a look at uh kind of the
state of the Readiness of the different
places along the three things I were
talking about how ready are you
especially on the talent side uh in
terms of absorbing uh some of these
things maybe the highest leverage use
cases are the most complex in some sense
and maybe the way at least the way we've
fashioned it um internally and the way
that I U most comfortable with is to
take a test and learn approach right
like slope your way up right find the
things where there's leverage start
small bring people into the process by
having small groups of test users bring
their feedback into the design show them
how your design is adapted to their
feedback on the change management piece
change management is not like a it's not
like here's my project plan for change
management it's it's a bit of a cultural
thing as you know and so you have to
build into the cultural values of the
organization that you're in you have to
tap into that and say how am I going to
manage this process but no we're not
lacking for excitement in fact we have
to hold back and say let's do the
thoughtful thing
here um yeah well in the ing there's a
also a DNA uh thingy so we're always
embracing new technologies and want to
be first and want to experiment with it
uh we are very agile but specifically on
the autonomy uh part so we love autonomy
not so much alignment so there's a lot
of autonomy around yeah let's experiment
and coming back to George point
yesterday what we need to bring in right
what we are bringing in right now is a
little bit more governance and alignment
on okay now let's join forces and and
and really accelerate um and we see a
lot of uh spontaneous
upscaling in in in all aspects you were
for referring to the licenses I see it
also are people on LinkedIn I have a
Google license oh I didn't know that you
were interested but okay cool uh Gardner
conferences not so much about ceso
whatever you see some applications and
then data analytics everybody wants to
go there so it's it's obviously hype
everybody wants to learn and I would say
it's it's also something to embrace and
encourage but with a little bit of
governance and
Alignment you know maybe Ben if I may go
out of cycle just add one thing I'll say
like I think to the extent that we all
believe I think most of us do that the
geni
transformation is going to be an
enduring it's going to be a
transformative force in the long run
it's going to create an enduring
transformation of the business Etc to
that extent I think if we really believe
those things it doesn't go hand inand
with a gold rush mentality that we have
to mine it now if this thing is truly
transformative is truly enduring take
your time think this through figure out
how to do it thoughtfully and resp
responsibly build the scaffolding to
bring everybody along either you or you
think there's all of the competitive
advantages are in the next 6 months and
you have to rush to it so I I think
there's that balance that needs to be
struck like where you say what is my
hypothesis it's a fundamental
transformative Force fine then let's
treat it like one with the respected
deserves approach it with the right uh
mindset that makes sense and one thing
Marco brought up earlier was customer
facing tools you know we can talk about
workers and work adoption but I wonder
if customers particular banking
customers are ready for a personalized
experience that is you know influenced
by generative a in my banking experience
that's not necessarily what I'm looking
for and and I wonder if you're seeing
different customer profiles or you know
if customers are looking for this next
Generation technology and how they're
engaging with your services well we do
uh we do see the the the differences in
different countries so for example in my
home country nland is very let's say
adaptive to new technology so it's it's
99.9% digital uh and they really love
insights insights like this in Germany
perhaps a little bit less it's more on
on on sovereignty in Australia bring it
on uh so you see the differences in
countries
but we do have a common Foundation that
we work with or a common data capability
Foundation or platform to work with that
and let's say to keep up with the pace
of the respective countries uh and
coming back to your earlier question
what is a use case or value case that
hasn't materialized yet as much as I
would love to that is more in the kyc
fraud area uh where I I see a lot of
value in let's let's call it contextual
banking bringing all the data that you
can gather to prevent fraud um but for
that we need some sort we had a small
discussion about that we need some sort
of Tim at consent customers aren't there
yet which makes sense the villains they
just take your consent so to prevent
fraud it would be helpful to get all
kind of data in to prevent to prevent
this these fraud
schemes uh that is still something that
we haven't Harvest uh to the max right
anything else yeah I can um I think um
in general uh sloping your way not just
in terms of learning how to scale your
application but sloping your way through
risk is crucially important especially
in a regulated industry like Finance um
uh there is the Instinct of course let's
just put it out there customers will use
it but you can introduce all kinds of
risks in the system I mean I'm sure all
of you are tracking how these things can
make offers that don't exist or that
offers you can't back up Etc even though
those are not white spread in the case
of banking Finance is so Central to all
our lives access to managing our
finances responsibly and enablement of
Finance is so Central to our lives that
we do have that additional burden of
responsibility in the finance industry
to make sure whatever we're putting out
there in front so our approach to
sloping the risk in this case is that
pretty much everything we do will be
with a human in the loop to start with
and for the foreseeable future until we
can have the Telemetry and observations
that tell us this is working well enough
here's where we can automate more right
so take customer
interactions uh customer interactions
are a huge area of investment for most
companies like ours well you know you're
interacting with customers the daily
transactions Etc so we have a lot of
agent Associates Associates is our term
for employees who interact with the
customers how do you make to me the
noble aim of AI is to transfer the
cognitive burden from the human to the
system
right so my agent Associates have a lot
of cognitive burdens they face when they
have to get information in the moment to
answer a customer query how can we make
their lives that much easier that much
simpler while they're helping these
systems while they're leveraging these
systems to help them in their jobs uh
same with software development right
like despite all the predictions um I
think we're trying to bring in these
tools to make our software Engineers
more you know focus on the more creative
aspects of their jobs uh try to automate
the more routine aspects like testing
and things like that and some of the uh
boiler plate code generation Etc so I
think that's kind of the sloping I see
like figure out for your particular use
case what is the risk slope and how do
you progressively go up that risk slope
in a responsible way just to follow up
quickly on that because you talked about
Shifting the cognitive burden which I
think could you could interpret in one
of two ways one like you mentioned you
can introduce this tool into your job
and then you could take on more skilled
higher value ad tasks as an individual
maybe that translates into higher pay as
well and we've seen that in some cases
like HR taking over routine interactions
and then having HR workers move into
more critical thinking problem solving
type tasks you could also imagine it if
it takes over your cognitive burden you
end up deskilled in the tasks of
checking the you know whatever the
algorithm's producing to make sure it's
accurate or doing more rote tasks that
the algorithm can't take over yet so I'm
wondering how to guarantee in in this
question to everyone how do we ensure
that this is actually creating higher
quality jobs for workers versus just
increasing the
drudgery would you like to go first go
ahead please go um I was actually
thinking you know we've been talking
about very big corporate um highly
regulated uh use cases but one of the
places that has tons of democratization
I think already um are small businesses
and I think it's a great example of you
know the vast majority of small
businesses in our country are um sole
Proprietors it's a one person show right
80 plus percent of them um and if you
think of all the drudgery tasks that go
into running a small business you can
take AI you can create an entire new
product line overnight you can name it
you can come up with a logo you can come
up with a tagline you can come up with a
marketing plan A business plan a
promotional plan a targeting plan in AI
in a very very short period of time in a
day call it maybe less in a way that you
could never do before as like a small
business owner so I also think we've
been talking about very corporate
examples probably that's resonant with
most of the audience here but if you
think about drudgery versus empowerment
there's all these additional use cases
that I think is are just worth
mentioning where all these things you
could not have found even the time to do
as an entrepreneur and now it does it
with you human in the loop um to empower
you to you know expand your product line
and do more in your business than you
could ever do before I think that's also
an interesting um use
case um yeah in general what we see is
in indeed it offers a lot of benefits uh
which which are valued so for example
you for our developers it takes away
some of the heavy lifting not only AI
takes away lot of heavy lifting also
marketplaces or Plug and Play kind of
kind of
tooling as a result their time to Market
uh massively improves which they love so
they there are better things that come
to life and they have all kind of
analytics to see okay this is really
working let's let's do some uh some
further AB testing so basically they get
more out of their work that's the good
the good side of it and we also see that
let's say in our marketing area so they
can really play with the numbers instead
of writing a text basically I'm
exaggerating a little bit that's what we
see happening on the one side what we
what we what we also see at the a very
same moment is that there's uh we had
the discussion also before for example
for our talents that just come out of
University I think it was also topic
yesterday normally or typically you give
them the easy work to gain some
experience and then move on there's
there's not a lot of easy work around
anymore so how do you educate let's say
your new uh you're new to the company
people that is a bit of a of a challenge
and especially in that area we see some
challenges not so much with the let's
say the the current
Workforce yeah you on this is I mean
there are two aspects of this one is uh
the intensity of your concern on that
fund it depends on which articles you
read right um and which which uh
thinkers you follow there's one end
where that says AGI is already
here the actual codes right from people
we all know to um people thinking it's
out there 2 to three years away all the
way to somebody like Yan who will say
there's no human with AGI why do we
think systems will have AGI right so
there's a whole Spectrum here my view
you know grounded in the Here and Now of
these things is that um and also I said
it transfers cognitive burdens not the
cognitive joys my view is we enjoy the
creative aspects of our world I think
that requires reasoning that requires
planning now you can read some things
that say all of these things are
happening but then when you start
actually trying them out you know
there's a difference between something
working sometimes well enough to kind of
grab our attention and say hey this is
coming sometime in the future versus
this is here and now and I can use this
at scale and it's good enough and
reliable enough and people can count on
it that's uh that's one uh one the other
part is for the most uh in most cases is
is definitely true where uh I'm working
right
now
are we're not lacking for ideas or
products that we want to develop our
biggest uh limitation is the bandwidth
of the resources we have so every year
our list of things that we want to do is
growing it's not shrinking so when I
look at it from that if this allows me
to limit the rate of growth of that list
uh by using using technology to
accelerate that development that just
allows us to accelerate the speed with
which we can provide services and value
to our customers and our Associates so I
don't necessarily there is a zero some
view of it which is different the way
we're working I don't see it we're still
hiring we're still not able to keep up
with all that we want to do technology
better help us because otherwise we're
going to continue to fall
behind and just to to follow up you know
we this is is something consistent with
what we've heard from a lot of companies
that this isn't necessarily um Zero Sum
where you're trying to reduce headcount
to solve the same number of problems
instead it's enabling you to solve more
problems with the res do more with the
same or more with more um one question I
have about the ways that you're
deploying these tools um you could
imagine you're deploying these tools in
a way that is top down that has kind of
Executives choosing High leverage use
cases and then asking individuals to to
use them this particular way and kind of
narrowing individual discretion and then
we've seen some companies do a very
bottom-up approach where they give an
internal version of a let's say a chat
GPT to the individuals so that they can
use it as they wish and then they can
track use cases to understand which are
the most effective I wonder how you see
the trade-offs of these different
approaches in in your organizations and
and what you've seen effective in in
different contexts you want us to
talk I can share an anecdote is it
recorded okay let's see uh
um I think you signed away the right
otherwise I will apply as Capital One it
was
uh was it that was already last year of
course with the with the Big Fuzz about
Chad DPT 10 10 billion so I got a call
from the board asking Marco are we
missing out why do you think we're
missing out ah there's a big thing going
on and we're missing out well at the
very same moment there was a was also a
survey in the financial t
times banks that are doing the most with
or are fur the furthest with with their
development of of AI in was globally on
number seven so so I replied apparently
the outside world actually think that
we're doing quite a lot already but
let's let's let's give some context to
it and some educational stuff so
including the supervisory board and said
okay this is what we are doing already
because we have we have attracted great
talent that are let's say that that are
open to fur to new developments they are
simply getting out there getting this
knowledge implementing testing it this
is what we already have so at least
within Ing and perhaps partly uh uh
because of our DNA and we're open for
new technologies it was already
happening before actually the board
became aware of it so I I really do
encourage this this this learning and
this experimentation this part of the
agility the autonomy part just go out
learn and at a certain moment put some
governance alignment on it otherwise it
will really go ballistic but uh at least
within in it was a bottomup
approach i' say I think
um I always hate it when somebody says
both but I I am going to say both and
but I I hopefully I'll articulate why
and it's it's concrete
um it all starts with finding out where
is is the maximum leverage in your
company or in your in your industry or
in your business some of those areas of
Leverage especially maximum leverage
take software development which
everybody's aligned huge leverage there
those end up being cross cutting across
the company things doing bottom up
doesn't really help you don't want like
six different Sol if you have if you're
a if you're a company that's practicing
software development uh as it should be
you have one as TLC framework software
development life cycle framework you
have one set of tools that allow you to
go all the way from planning and design
to development to testing to moving into
production and then post- production
monitoring and everything you want to
have an sdlc that's integrated you don't
want everybody to be going and getting
it because that actually makes your
systems less secure less maintainable
increases cost Beyond uh sustainable
limits Etc there are other areas where
there are a lot of people practicing
things like you know there's a business
analyst who's working on certain things
or all the reporting you were talking
about and those reports are so stylized
different Regulators want different
types of reports they are asking
different types of questions there is
really no le so what is the leverage
there The Leverage there is in providing
a set of platforms and tools that people
can most easily develop applications and
customize them for their if they have to
do it from scratch it's too hard that's
where the platform story comes in so one
you have platforms as Solutions the
other is where you have platforms as
building blocks and that platform as a
building block is where the bottom up
thing becomes uh that's what enables the
bottomup development we have tremendous
number of use cases in development right
now we know every single use case that
is in development because we have a
central use case review and approval uh
mechanism regulated industry you have to
do it Regulators will come and ask tell
us all the use cases you have to be able
to produce a list and show them the
other hand that also makes sure
everybody's thinking about things in the
same way that eventually when you have
an Enterprise that is very AI
transformed the look and feel and the
experience they're all seamless so I
think it's it so I'll just say it's both
but hopefully I gave you exact and I
think it might come up in a different
context when you're working with small
businesses or or
entrepreneurs yeah I was just um I was
also just thinking about some of the
surprising use cases so the other day I
was reading about one of the things that
Walmart is doing um so they they
actually created a bot as I understand
it to NE negotiate with with vendors so
um this is obviously everyone wants to
sell their stuff at Walmart um and
that's a bandwidth constrained thing so
they actually made a bot that negotiated
with vendors um as an experiment so you
could um you know pitch your idea to the
bot and the bot would negotiate with you
and their results were that people
preferred negotiating with the bot over
negotiating with people and essentially
Walmart still got the same high quality
deals out of it and if if you had
thought about this you would never have
imagined either that it would work as
well or that people would be as
satisfied negotiating with a bot right
so I do think also there's these
interesting use cases that people
wouldn't have thought of or wouldn't
think would work that we're all going to
discover over time are actually um kind
of fascinating so um it's good to be an
observer and see like what are all the
things that other people are doing it
might spark also creative new ideas well
and to follow up on that it's always
exciting to be at a university because
you're in learning mode but what is
great about the university convening
folks like yourselves is I feel like
we've all been in learning mode for the
last 18 months or so and being able to
share experiences like this is is really
exciting one of the surprises that that
we got we recently did a survey of about
9,000 workers in in nine different
countries and we thought you know
consistent with some observations that
um those most optimistic about tools
like generative AI would be highly
educated knowledge workers but actually
people without a college degree were
more optimistic about the benefits for
their work than college degree holders
so maybe you know last question for you
before we head to some of the questions
from the audience is how do you see kind
of uh the the jobs that are most open to
to change the types of jobs within your
um communities you know there's some
economists a big hypothesis being that
this will be a skill leveler more
beneficial for low skilled low wage jobs
and we really see mixed evidence that
for some expert developers it seems to
be a superpower whereas for junior
developers might be harder to use um I
wonder how that shakes out in your
experiences well I don't have empiric
evidence here but what what what we do
see happening is I think you touched
upon that as
well the the the number of fases are
actually Rising so we need more people
perhaps a little bit more in in the data
area obviously but also work with that
you see some spontaneous upskilling of
people and perhaps in that indeed even
in the what you might call lower skilled
areas but somehow it's now much easier
to keep up with the pace because we we
also deliver some tools to actually
apply it so it's not not only having the
the AI knowledge but we also provide the
tools working with that and in doing so
uh learn learn some new techniques or
skills here so at least from although
it's indeed not not scientifically
proven but I do see see some upskilling
of of lower lower skilled jobs yeah okay
so I'd like to democratize here to the
to the audience and allow each of you to
pick uh you know we we can go around at
least once a question that you find you
most interesting from this um this
audience uh collection
system Lisa do you want to start
can you scan that down a little bit to I
can take the one about uh
education great um so I think education
is a really fascinating um AI use case
and I'll take two different parts of it
um so one is I want to talk about
teachers um as we all know um there was
kind of
a panic in the world of Education around
um AI as a cheating tool and um it made
teachers and and parents and others uh
quite um anti- AI for a period of time
um which I think actually did a real
disservice both to the educational
system and to teachers themselves and
what we see now even in our search query
data at Google we look at queries that
start with AI for blank and actually AI
for teachers is now one of the top
queries on on
ai4 on Google and this is because
teachers are starting to realize that if
students understand something at a
minimum they need to understand it too
and they're just starting to realize
what a powerful tool it can actually be
for a teacher so one of the courses
we've created is Gen AI for educators
and it's a course specifically for
teachers to learn how to use
AI um because actually AI can be a
really incredible teaching assistant I
just give a few quick examples
a teacher could take their lesson plan
say a science lesson and say help me
teach this lesson this science lesson
using Sports analogies and the AI will
craft a a way that that teacher can do
that to meet students where they are you
could take your lesson plan for a
certain age group and convert it to
different reading levels or different
levels of understanding take the entire
week's lessons and summarize it for the
kid who was out sick write the class
newsletter on and on and on it's
actually an outstanding uh tool for
teachers and actually we built our
teacher course with MIT with a
responsible AI in society and Education
team and I think um we're going to see
it be a really powerful tool for
teachers um and for learning but I also
think what we're realizing in society
more broadly and even beyond the AI use
case is that there is absolutely no way
that all of us will be able to learn
everything we need to know for our
careers in the Years we're in school or
in College we are way past the point in
society where at whatever 22 years old
you've learned everything you're going
to need to know and people are going to
need to be constantly
reskilling um that's one of the reasons
we created the Google career certificate
program is so that people could easily
change careers and make pivots so we'll
teach you to become a data analyst Marco
was talking about the vast need for data
analytics or to be a cyber security
analyst or an IT support professional
and you can do it all online on demand
and this is the way I think people will
res skill in the future um working
people need ways they can access real
training when they have time it has to
be available to them and so all of our
Google career certificates are therefore
online on demand and allow you to Res
skill into these professions in a pretty
straightforward way learning from Google
experts and giving you as I was
mentioning before a real credential you
can you can point to
and the the first or the one on top uh
organizations are never ready for for
Change Is Never necessary to create a
sense of urgency definitely
not I would rather say uh start thinking
beyond the hype uh uh uh and and put
some some more perspectives to it like
having a value based approach to it uh
because the let's say AI on itself
doesn't deliver that much value you and
we had that discussion yesterday what
problems are we solving here what
business are out there are the new
business or new business models and and
how can it can iI enable this uh are you
ready as a as a company to even start
thinking about it or working on it or do
you have some other problems to solve
first so it's not so much a sense of
urgency uh people do want to change uh
they do like to embrace it but hold your
horses a bit uh uh it's it's not the
holy Grill and you really need to have
your act together so it's perhaps uh the
opposite
great says you're looking Prem we have
one uh organization we've been working
with that um is doing exercises uh with
learning about generative AI realizing
that they might need to abandon whatever
applications they build because there'll
be a vendor that can do it better in six
months so that for them it's maybe the
option isn't to wait and just hold on
entirely it's to keep learning but
recognize that you might need to change
what you're doing as as you learn the
technology evolves but I think your
point is really well taken that urgency
doesn't seem helpful in in this case yes
I'm going to present a challenge for
your presenters I'm going to pick the
most popular remaining question but also
the one about four big areas of impact
because I think I see ativity there so I
want to see say it out for the I want to
see if you can actually show two
questions at once on your screen that's
the challenge here if not maybe that's
the next AI generated U ux that uh you
can go for
um but you know this whole thing I'll
focus on that four big areas of impact
I'll start with the secret source for I
think the generic business processes
radical transformation personal
productivity radical transformation is
not a category of its own in in other
sense it's a horizontal that we're going
to radically transform the other three
areas generic business processes secret
Source personal productivity a software
development is about as generic a
business process as you can get and and
the reason we're seeing a lot of
progress there is because there's just
so much code available in open source
which means there's so much training
data that's available this is the
connection I was seeing with the garbage
in garbage
out it's a lot of code and a lot of good
code we now know there's a lot of
emerging literature showing that more
important than perhaps the sheer volume
of data is the quality the cleanliness
of the data the relevance of the data so
whatever you call Quality is making a
bigger difference to the performance of
AI systems now uh than the sheer uh
volumes uh in fact most of the best
performing things all of us use have
invested disproportionately in improving
cleaning the data that they're using to
train to get some of these advances and
so the secret Source in a data and AI
Enterprise and you know Ali who leads
data Brooks often say every company of
the future is going to be a data and AI
company and the secret Source what is
our secret Source our secret source is
really the data that we have have that
represents our interactions with our
customers what do our customers want how
do we support them best what are their
intents and needs how do we serve those
best Etc if that's kind of the key
ingredient of the secret Source then you
have to have a data operation that
ensures that you have high quality
complete data that you can then use to
train your AI so I do think when I look
at destination a few years down the road
the biggest transformation is going to
be that the company companies who can
use their proprietary data to create
proprietary AI that differentiates their
services from what others in their
industry are able to uh offer that's one
part of it there's also a part where
generic business processes are going to
those are going to be table Stakes
everybody better be using all of these
things for the generic business
processes otherwise you're going to
create negative differentiation for
yourself simply because the crowd is
moving ahead of you in general and and
for all of these I think it's important
for the quality of data uh to be good
and from the end user perspective I
think they really two things if you need
to use prompting or in context learning
to improve performance that's a
diminishing number of use cases because
performance out of the box will continue
to become better for places where it's
just the in context learning from
prompt-based tuning that helps I don't
think that's necessarily going to be
huge but the place where it will help is
where you have to really tune with your
data great and I think that's a
wonderful place to leave it and and just
a common theme Here here about how
organizations and individuals are are
climbing the learning curve and just it
aligns with this new data set that we
have that shows that workers who are
most motivated by learning and upward
Mobility are also the most open to using
these sorts of tools and see them as
beneficial in their work so um a big
thanks to Lisa Marco PR for for joining
us today and sharing their experience
thank you thank you