Um, okay. Everyone can hear me? Uh,
how's everyone doing?
>> Good. Great. Um, so my name is Chris
Rae. I'm the education program director
here at MIT's environmental solutions
initiative. Um, it's really important
for me to talk about that quickly that I
come at this from an educational lens
and a lot of my projects are about
trying to integrate climate justice or
environmental justice into educational
contexts both at MIT or in other uh
institutions of higher education and
even in K- through2. Um, so this is a
really high level discussion on how
geothermal energy networks or genens can
meet environmental justice priorities.
So, uh, just a quick overview. I'm going
to go over like an EJ framework define
environmental justice. I'll probably say
EJ a lot right now. Um, I'm going to
review EJ concerns with existing gas
networks, talk about how genens can meet
a EJ priorities, and then really briefly
talk about some next steps. How can we
better integrate EJ into this kind of
work? So, let's define environmental
justice really quickly. Uh, what is
environmental justice? I think it's
important to remember that environmental
justice is a movement that started in
the early 1980s. um as people of color
and other vulnerable groups like
indigenous people protested the
inequitable placement of environmental
harms in their community uh and this was
happening in the United States and all
around the world. Uh here you can see a
really famous protest in Warren County,
North Carolina where African-American
communities uh tried to block the
delivery of toxic PCB waste into their
landfills around them. Uh so that famous
protest is cited in a lot of uh
environmental justice studies and it led
to these two uh landmark reports that
used uh like GIS technology to show and
prove that yes environmental harms uh
were inequitably placed in communities
of color and low-income communities.
uh that led to the environmental
protection agency and a definition of
environmental justice like this is sort
of a basic definition that all people
have the right to a healthy and safe
environment regardless of their social
identity. Um there's been a lot of
theory new work on defining
environmental justice. So I would
recommend checking out uh David Pell who
has this term called critical
environmental justice or looking up
Kimberly Krenshaw's notion of
intersectionality if you want to go like
do a deeper dive on new definitions of
environmental justice. Um so those two
landmark reports helped uh form a field
of environmental justice and maybe some
of you are are familiar with things like
climate justice or maybe energy justice
which is most you know directly
connected to today and tomorrow's uh
class. Um so you can see you know you
know this movement has like splintered
into different areas and fields. um it
has expanded in in breadth and depth and
methodology and so like the
environmental justice work that was
being done in the mid1 1980s is totally
different from the work that's being
done now. Um I I like to point out that
uh environmental justice helped redefine
the environment. So I think if you look
at American environmentalism uh you know
the environment was pristine natural
wilderness and a lot of focus was on uh
nature preservation. Um but uh the
founder of environmental justice uh
Robert Bullard always talks about how
the environment is where we live, work
and play or study or worship and the
environment is all around us which I
think is so connected to the built
environment uh in these in this two-day
conference and also environmental
justice helps theorize or conceptualize
think about what is justice or what is
equity. So uh I kind of want to talk
about network geothermal through this
prism through sort of different forms of
justice. So I think a lot of people
think about social justice. They're
thinking usually about distributive
justice. How are we allocating
resources? Um but they often don't think
about participative justice, right? Who
has a seat at the table? Uh whose voices
are being listened to? Uh and I think
this is a critical component as we move
forward with, you know, uh addressing
the climate crisis. Or there's also
procedural justice, right? When you
start a project, you know, what are the
different checkpoints of the project to
sort of check in to see like are we
involving everybody? How are laws and
policies, you know, uh going forward?
There's recognition, right? Who's
getting recognition for this work? Uh,
you know, who's involved, etc. I think
recognition is very connected to
participative and procedural. Uh,
there's historic or restorative justice,
right? Acknowledging the problems of the
past and then when we're engaging in
projects, focusing in on groups who
haven't historically been included. Um,
and then there's epistemic justice,
which I like to just say knowledge
justice. uh are we making sure we're
listening to the voices and experiences
and stories of those who have been
historically marginalized in
discussions.
So let's talk about some EJ concerns in
the energy transition or in relation to
gens through that prism of justice that
I just mentioned. I won't mention all of
those in these concerns, but uh you can
see sort of how they're intertwined.
So, uh, I think it's really important to
just point out that, uh, buildings
account for 30% of US emissions and half
of that comes from on-site combustion. I
think Christopher Reinhardt talked about
that, Jason Jay already. Uh, this is
sort of like an injustice for all. Um,
also I think discussed by Christopher
Reinhardt was sort of how right now we
have an individual home market model
where if I want to redo my energy system
at home, it's under my kind of
discretion or responsibility to learn
about that and go through the process.
And it's pretty challenging, right? I'm
still working through that. Like, no one
tells you that when you put in heat
pumps, there's no heat for the bathrooms
or there's uh no heat for your basement.
This is just a little silly example, but
I think that a lot of people uh in
Massachusetts, around the country sort
of lack literacy about this and this can
exacerbate inequity.
Um as people make the transition to
renewable energy, um the co the gas
customer base will go down and this has
showed that this will put a burden on
low-income communities because their
rates will go up. So you can see one
study showed that this will double the
economic burden on low-income families
by 2050. Um as the gas uh customer base
you know goes down this can also make
gas utilities vulnerable. And finally
there are gas leaks which have already
been discussed right so this is a health
and safety concern. So how can
geothermal energy networks meet those EJ
problems that I just discussed? So I
think this this slide is sort of like
almost like a justice for all slide. Um
which I think there's always like some
tension in the EJ movement is like we
need to acknowledge that there the
injustices have been inequitable among
different groups but then there's also
injustices that we all face. So um you
know network geothermal can uh decrease
uh carbon emissions by a lot and then
also it can uh lead to a lot of savings
at a community level uh and also uh have
an increased energy efficient efficiency
where there's less peak demand on the
grid or significant savings. Um also
just mentioning again like gas leaks are
really problematic for our health and
the environment. Um and we can move to a
self safe and healthy reliable heating
and cooling uh system which is a better
model for gas utilities and we can
better address urban heat islands where
I know here even in Massachusetts
there's a ton of communities that lack
you know uh you know adequate access to
cooling.
Uh so like thinking a little bit more
about the distribution uh and sharing of
energy resources. Uh I think one thing
that's really interesting and I'm just
learning more about is how uh a
geothermal loop can share heating and
cooling across different kinds of
buildings. So there's one ongoing
project in Chelsea, New York, uh where a
data center is on a loop with a public
housing community and data centers will
like release extra heat and that can be
used by another community. So here you
see like uh building infrastructure with
different kinds of resources being able
to sort of more equitably share that or
uh one of the first or the first uh
network geothermal or geothermal project
in Boston is in Dorchester in the
Franklin Field community and um so
network geothermal allows us to
prioritize EJ communities when we can
provide heating and cooling to every
building on the network regardless of
the resident's income level or home
ownership status which I think addresses
this idea that only sort of wealthier
families or families with literacy can
redo their appliances in their home.
Finally, I don't know, I think this one
is the most interesting to me. Uh how do
we engage the community and make sure
all stakeholders and all groups are
involved in the process? Uh when we're
engaging in network geothermal work, so
this again goes from the individual to
the community level. Uh we need
community engagement. This is the the
project in Framingham, the Framingham
loop uh where a number of different
communities um from different contexts
had to be involved in the project. And
then we need to engage in stakeholder
assessment and engagement. Uh there are
renewable energy projects all around the
country that get halted because one
particular community blocks the project
because they hadn't been involved in the
process until later on. So there's
actually a course here at MIT called the
renewable energy facility sighting
clinic. That's quite a mouthful. uh
where they actually teach students how
to do that sort of stakeholder
engagement and I'm trying to learn as
much about that as I can. So I guess
maybe you could see a little bit how
these like forms of justice
interconnected and sort of those
solutions um and sort of thinking of
this as a framework for future
geothermal work. So just really quickly
uh what do we do in the future? Uh we
need more legislation. I got I've got
tons of time. We need more legislation.
uh you know I think environmental
justice has has a uh like historical
roots in uh law and policy. Um so we
need to do that. I think we need
improved participation across sectors. I
think uh the heat the work that heat
does is so incredible where uh the the
energy utilities are involved,
government is involved, education is
involved, uh community organizations are
involved and then individual residents
are involved. This is incredible work.
It takes so much uh you know thought uh
and process to do that and we need
education and awareness. So um most
people are still confusing the different
kinds of geothermal. They're confusing
uh deep geothermal with shallow shallow
geothermal. A lot of people don't know
that this is a viable um you know energy
resource moving into the future. And so
like we need that at the K through2
level and at the level of higher
education and then also in informal
spaces. This is a term used in the
literature, right? Where we're just
working with individual people and
community residents. And then we need
action at all different kinds of levels.
Um, so that's political action and
communication. And so I just kind of
have this reflection question here is
how can we make sure that an EJ
framework, right, or a framework of of
different forms of justice uh is
included in future geothermal energy
network projects. uh how can we make
sure that all forms of justice are
considered? So, thank you for your
attention.