CAROLYN TIERNAN:
Without further ado,
I will hand the mic over
to Bill Bonvillian, who
will be the moderator
of this session today.
Many of you will know Bill.
He's a lecturer at MIT
and senior director
for special projects
at Open Learning,
and he will introduce our
guests, Eric and Kate.
I'll hand it over to you, Bill.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN: Thanks,
Carolyn, appreciate it.
And let me just introduce
briefly Kate and Eric.
Eric is a professor at MIT and a
director of the Scheller Teacher
Education Program and the
Education Arcade at MIT.
He's head of MIT'S Department
of Comparative Media Studies
and Writing.
He is an expert on the
application of technology
to education, and his
research has really
focused on computer
gaming and simulations
for building understanding
of science, technology,
engineering.
He's the author of four
books on these subjects.
And Kate Moore is a
research scientist
who studies how to teach
middle and high school
students about
systems and ethics
behind artificial intelligence.
She earned her doctoral degree
at Columbia University's
Teachers College, and before
entering the field of education
and research, Kate had
on-the-ground experience serving
as a middle school science
and special education
teacher for 10 years.
So we've got two very
talented discussants today.
Let me give a
brief introduction.
We've discussed many topics,
as Carolyn suggested,
in our J-WEL series
on AI and education,
and now we turn to
a crucial one, which
is how teachers in
classrooms are using it
and the challenges they face.
So the availability of
generative AI tools like ChatGPT
is, as we all know, a new
disruptive force in education.
And MIT's Scheller
Education Program,
which Eric directs and where
Kate is a research scientist,
this program is engaged in
activities to both understand
how teachers are impacted by
the arrival of AI and help
prepare them and their
students to use AI tools
both ethically and effectively.
And they see generative AI as
offering real opportunities
in education, yet
many first attempts
will miss opportunities
for connection as well.
How do teachers and school
districts use generative AI?
Well, the way they
use it, it's going
to affect gaps in education.
Those who know how
to use the tool
effectively could show
significant, remarkable gains
even in learning.
Those who don't may miss
out on these opportunities.
So that's why teacher
and student AI literacy
is so important.
And Kate and Eric are
both deeply involved
in a series of AI
fluency projects
that support students and
teachers in their creative and--
then the connected use
of AI for learning.
So let me turn first to Eric,
and then we'll turn to Kate.
ERIC KLOPFER: Thanks, Bill.
I'm going to share
some slides here.
Great.
So thanks for having us here.
I'm going to give a
quick overview of some
of the frameworks we use to
think about AI education,
and then I'm going
to turn it over
to Kate for some more deep
dives into some case studies
that she's been working
on as part of her work,
working deeply with
teachers in schools,
thinking about both
those opportunities,
as Bill was just talking
about, as-- opportunities
that they have as well as the
challenges that they face.
And this slide here, I think,
really summarizes also--
and where Bill was going, it's
sort of about the opportunities
and the potential costs.
The bottom line here is that
we work from the premise
that we don't think
that people are going
to be replaced by AI
in many professions,
but we do think that people who
know AI will replace people who
don't know AI in many places.
And so our goal is
to prepare everybody
to really be able to
use AI effectively
and creatively and ethically
as part of their work
and as part of their lives.
My work is part of
a larger initiative
at MIT called RAISE, Responsible
AI for Social Empowerment
and Education.
I'm one of the co-PIs
along with Hal Abelson,
and Cynthia Breazeal is
the PI of this project.
And this is a
comprehensive project
across many
different subprojects
where we're working
on both AI education,
teaching people about
AI, as well as thinking
about ways that we
can use AI to help
people learn more effectively.
The goals of RAISE,
just real quickly,
are to advance equity
in learning, education,
and empowerment through AI.
We do this by rethinking and
innovating how to holistically
and equitably prepare
diverse K-12 students
and an inclusive workforce.
And we want them to be happy,
engaged, and successful
in an increasingly
AI-powered society.
So this isn't just
about career readiness.
That is one component
of it, because we also
want them to be sort of happy
and engaged citizens and people
in the world.
I'm going to lay out
some principles here,
which I call the Roadmap
for Transforming Education
with AI, which is just
some principles about how
we think about using AI in
schools and in education.
And I think this will help
establish some baseline stuff
when I turn it over to Kate.
And many of you may know
Bloom's taxonomy, the idea
that we have--
at the baseline,
we have remember,
and we push this
all up to create.
And we really want to be pushing
people up along this taxonomy
in many activities that
they do, including the ways
that we use AI in schools.
So we want people to
know and understand AI.
We want people to
use and apply AI,
and we really want them
to evaluate and create AI.
And in talking with Kate about
this diagram just yesterday
or the day before, she said,
the interesting thing about AI
is that creating
and evaluating is--
we should put it at the top,
but it doesn't necessarily
require people to analyze
and apply and understand it
as they're doing that.
So we really need to
think about taxonomy maybe
more as like a pillar,
that they really
need to be able to do
all of these things.
They need to be able to
create, evaluate, and analyze,
but they also need to be able to
apply and understand it as well.
And I think that's a
really important comment.
As Bill mentioned
our word fluency,
we're trying to move
away from "AI literacy,"
even though people use that word
a little bit more frequently
than "fluency," but we really
want people to be much more--
have a much deeper understanding
than just literacy, which
is maybe a superficial
understanding, where
they'd be fluent with it.
So they're using it
readily in activities
when it's appropriate, figuring
out when it's not appropriate
and not using it
in those places.
And we think about these
different components
about ethics and AI, core
concepts, creativity,
career readiness.
All of these are foundations for
what we think about as fluency.
I do want to--
this is a common metaphor
that we see a lot now,
a professor in every pocket
or something like this,
a tutor on everybody's screen.
Everybody's going to be
able to get much smarter
and do better because we
have tutors that are going
to be available to everybody.
And this is something
that's pushed
a lot in a lot of
different-- from a lot
of different companies and
a lot of different sources.
I think we need to think
about, in this model that we're
going to have a professor who's
going to be able to teach us
everything in our
pockets, we need
to ask fundamental questions
about, does AI improve learning?
Can we define learning
in that context?
What does it mean to learn?
And how do we think
about these tools being
used in association with
those different definitions
of learning?
One important thing--
it's maybe a little hard
to see on your screens here.
At the beginning of the
semester, my colleague,
Justin Reich, who runs the
Teaching Systems Lab here
at MIT, posted some
information about a new poster
that they developed, and I'll
have a link to this later on.
It was some guidelines around
AI for schools at the beginning
of this current year.
The very first one of those
things was that AI will not
replace teachers, and right
above that, in my Twitter feed,
where I saw this, was this
commercial for a tool that says,
"One app replaces teachers,
tutors and textbooks."
And this is really not
what we're thinking about.
This is not our design.
We're not looking to
replace teachers or even
textbooks perhaps.
We're thinking about,
how does these tools
get integrated into an ecosystem
that involves teachers, that
involves peers, that
involves traditional media
but also involves AI
along with those things?
One of the reasons I
think that people are so
attracted to this
idea of the AI tutor
that can teach you
everything is that we
need to move beyond retention
to much deeper learning.
Yes, I think you can-- if you
want to think about quick recall
and understanding
of some math facts,
probably some of these AI tutors
can get you there very quickly.
But we need to be
thinking about learning
that's much more
durable than that
and that's much more
comprehensive than that.
Again, with AI tools readily
available and computational
tools more generally available,
we need to be thinking about,
what's the value
added that people
will have inside lots of
different kinds of ecosystems?
And those are not going to
be to do the kinds of things
that tutors can teach
you really quickly.
We need to be able to design
things for the whole student.
As we think about designing
educational technologies,
we often think about,
OK, this student
needs to learn this thing to
get past this benchmark here,
but we really need
to be thinking
about who that student
is, what position do they
have in their
community, in the world,
with their friends and peers.
What kind of identity
do they have?
Thinking about
that whole student
can really help
transform the way
we think about these tools that
are not just delivering facts
to them but helping them
understand deeper concepts
to develop identity about who
they are and what they're doing.
Those kinds of
things are actually
much more difficult to do.
I think we can get there
with a lot of these tools,
but it's going to require
a much deeper thought
than just getting people to
respond to math questions.
We do need to do research.
I run a reading group here on
campus around AI education.
Kate is a part of this as well.
And one week we read two papers.
These are paraphrases
of those two papers.
One was called "Large Language
Models," or things like ChatGPT,
"May Harm Learning," and the
other one was called "LLMs
Perform as Well
as Human Tutors."
And these were both papers
that were peer-reviewed
and published, and they both
have some merit to them.
There's qualifications
around a lot of the things.
As you can imagine
in research, there's
a lot of qualifications
of the things
we might think about in these.
But the fact is that we don't
know a lot about where and when
large language models and
AI can work effectively
and where it works
counterproductively.
And we need to be thinking
about doing research
that helps us understand
that space about who, when,
and where these different
kinds of things can be useful
and when they can be harmful.
The ways they're
harmful is sometimes
it gets kids to think that
they are good at something
because they have this AI help.
When the help is
withdrawn, they actually
don't understand it very well.
So sometimes it
provides a false sense
of understanding to them,
which can be harmful.
A quick example
from my own class--
we did a little
activity in my class
where we gave a programming
assignment to students,
and we gave three different
groups-- a group with ChatGPT,
a group with Code Llama, which
is an open-source large language
model, and a group that
could only use Google,
I first gave them
a task where they
needed to do a
programming assignment
and they could use these tools.
And then I told them I
was going to give them
a test afterwards where
they couldn't use the tools.
And sure enough,
the ChatGPT group
got it really quickly
on the first activity
where they could use the tools.
The Code Llama group struggled,
took a little bit longer,
and finally, the Google
group took the longest
to solve the problem.
But then when I took the tools
away and I gave them a test,
the ChatGPT group all failed.
They could not understand--
they could not repeat what
they had done with ChatGPT.
The Code Llama group--
about half of them got it
right, and half of them didn't.
And the Google group
all got it right.
So there's something
about struggling with this
and taking a little bit
longer that can actually
be really helpful
and effective when
you think about where we use
those AI tools to help people.
AI must support educators
in supporting students.
Teachers are such an important
part of the ecosystem.
We need to think about
how we integrate teachers
into the process and not
remove them from the process
by replacing them with tutors.
Learning is so much more
than just learning facts.
It's about those
social relationships
and about caring
mentors and teachers.
We need to think about how
we make those people more
empowered to do their
job and not remove them
more from the process.
That means educators need to
be part of the AI conversation
as we're designing tools.
Sometimes tools are designed
by technology companies
without really thinking about
who the educators really are,
and those educators
really need to be
a part of the conversation.
They need to stay
up to date on AI.
This is a course we developed
with Google, Generative AI
for Educators.
It's a two-hour course open
to anybody who can just
learn from the fundamentals
of learning about AI,
and this was really effective.
We've had many, many people
from around the world take this.
It's now available in several
other languages as well.
But this has been
really a nice experience
to help people stay up to date.
And it's going to be
something that people
need to do regularly.
AI is not going to
be the kind of thing
that you learn once and then
can sit on for five or 10 years.
It's going to be
the kind of thing
that teachers need to stay
up to date on a yearly basis.
I think one of the most
important things about learning
about AI is to create
communities, experiment,
and share.
The best way that
people can learn,
educators can learn is
from other educators,
so really thinking about
ways that teachers can create
communities, share their
experiences with each other,
learn from each other
what worked, what didn't.
It's going to be
really important part
of advancing our understanding.
And policy, educators being
an important part of policy
as well, we're going to see
policies at the school level,
district level, state
level, federal level
emerging over the coming
years, and really, teachers
need to be a part of
those conversations
because they're the ones
who really understand how
this is working in a classroom.
I'll just quickly mention
a project here just
to give you the kinds of
things that we're working on.
CAIL is a project we're
working on in our lab.
It's really thinking
about, what happens
when we move from an AI
tutor on a one-to-one basis
where an AI tutor is
actually now part of a group?
As I mentioned, I think
that collaborative learning
and learning with
peers is so important
a part of the process
for so many students.
And CAIL is a way
of thinking about,
how does an AI agent become
a member of that community?
How does an AI agent actually
help the group work together
so it's not just about
people learning from AI
but people learning
from each other?
I do think-- I won't spend
a lot of time on this.
I do think the future is
bright if we think about this.
I don't want to sound
too negative about AI
in the future of education.
I'm very optimistic about it.
But we need to be thinking
about it carefully,
with research behind
it, and thinking
about ways that we can advance
this in an evidence-based way.
This is, just real quickly-- and
I can share these slides later
so you can see these things.
This is Justin Reich's
poster on "Teachers on AI."
This is a report that we
released on "Generative AI
and K-12 Education--
An MIT Perspective," which
was released this past spring
or summer.
And we also have a policy paper
that we released this past fall,
"How Policy Can Help Ensure
the Proper Use of AI in K-12
Education."
These are all available.
I can share the
slides and the QR code
so that people can
download those later.
With that, I will
turn it over to Kate.
KATE MOORE: Hi, everybody.
I'm Kate Moore.
Thank you so much for
the introduction, Bill.
I'm a research scientist
focusing on AI in education.
I work with Eric and many other
researchers at the STEP Lab,
and I've been invited to speak
a little bit about the work I've
been doing with Irene Lee,
who is at the Education
Arcade, the MIT
STEP Lab with us,
and also at New Mexico
State University,
and also with Dr.
Helen Zhang, who's
at the Lynch School of
Education at Boston College.
What I wanted to speak
about was a project
called Everyday AI,
which I've sent a link to
in the chat for you.
Everyday AI is a middle
school curriculum
that focuses on developing AI
literacy for middle school,
and we've also seen it
applied in high school.
But we're very open to receiving
the term "fluency," Eric.
It's just that we've been
working with the word
"literacy," and it's
in the title now.
So we're going to stick with it.
And on top of that
curriculum, we
have been working
since 2021 on a teacher
professional
development project.
What that means is
we've really tackled
this problem in education
where teachers are putting out
dumpster fires every day.
They're working.
They're fixing.
They're building.
They're creating.
They're innovating.
And they do not have time
to learn how AI works,
how to teach their
students about AI.
And what we've done is
tackled that problem
by creating a professional
development program that
connects teachers who are
often isolated with each other
through a book club and
then through a opportunity
to practice during a summer camp
where they can practice teaching
this curriculum.
And we've been working on
this for three years, four
before I joined the program,
Irene and Helen working on this.
And since then, we've
reached almost 70 teachers,
2,000 students all
across the country.
And what we're learning is
that teachers, once they
are connected to a community
of people who are all chatting
and learning about
education and once they
practice teaching AI concepts or
AI fluency in their classrooms,
they outperform expert
curriculum developers
and experts in machine learning
when these experts taught
the same curriculum.
So what I mean is teachers
have the pedagogical wisdom
and the insights into things
like culturally responsive
pedagogy, what their students
love and are interested in that
makes these challenging topics
really accessible and meaningful
for their middle
school students.
So what we're finding, just
to put a fine point on it,
is that teachers are great at
advancing middle and high school
AI literacy.
What they need is proper
professional development
to help them get there.
I've had the privilege of
interviewing about 65 teachers
across the country to
ask them about their work
teaching AI concepts to
their middle school students.
And talking to them
about this work,
I've learned that
some of them are also
trying to work with
large language models.
Working with the PD has made
them feel comfortable with AI.
So some of these teachers are
using large language models
today for their own
work, such as ideation,
developing ideas as if they're
working with a colleague,
developing lesson
plans, rapid creation
of differentiated materials.
And all of this is--
I'm just hearing
from some teachers
that this is helping
them feel like they
have an extra ear that they
can bounce ideas off of.
And maybe, although I don't
have any evidence of this--
maybe this is tackling
one of the great issues
in teachers' work,
which is isolation.
Particularly teachers
who are teaching
about artificial intelligence
as part of their class,
they're probably the only
one in the building teaching
this content.
So it's hard to find somebody
they can connect with to feel
that they're not alone in this.
I'm at my five minutes.
I'm just going to take two
more to emphasize a few things
that we've also found
from the research
by interviewing and measuring
teacher and student learning
from this project.
One is that we've learned
that as teachers participate
in this program, they start
to see artificial intelligence
education or understanding
how AI works as not just
about learning the
technical content
but as something that's
important for a person
to learn as part of
their being a citizen
and part of their
engaging in society.
And what that's shown
us is that AI literacy
is interdepartmental.
We started thinking
about this as something
that would be championed by
computer science teachers,
but what we're seeing is that
teachers in the Everyday AI
project, they're librarians,
they're English teachers,
they're social studies teachers
and math teachers and science
teachers.
So teachers of any discipline
can introduce their students
to AI concepts with
great efficacy,
and their students report having
positive experiences with it.
One thing I'm also
hearing from teachers
is that there are ways
that they have learned
to identify bias in AI that have
been really helpful for them.
For example--
actually, I'm going
to give a personal example.
I was teaching a class--
this was last year--
to graduate
students, but we were
doing an activity where
you generate a movie
poster with image generator,
generative AI tool.
And one of my
students was trying
to create the movie poster for
the movie Barbie, which had come
out then and was very popular.
And when we created
the movie poster,
we noticed that Ken
was driving the car.
And I don't know if you
guys have seen Barbie,
but one of the main
things in this movie
is that Ken does
not drive the car.
Barbie does.
But because the
model was trained
on this overrepresented--
this dataset that
had an overrepresentation
of men driving cars,
the movie, one of the
main points of the movie,
was misrepresented.
And teachers who go through
professional development that
helps them be prepared
to speak about these ways
that bias can emerge
in generative AI tools
are ready to jump
on those moments
and speak to their students
about some of these ways
that bias can emerge.
And teachers without that
training might miss it,
and that's where the harms might
come in, where students start
noticing that information
that's generated by these tools,
they might think
that this is normal.
One of the things
that we've noticed
is that there's an
overrepresentation
of some groups over others
in the training dataset,
and the risk is that students
get the idea that the people who
are marginalized in
the dataset are also
marginalized in society.
And that can give really
difficult messages
for young people who are trying
to find their place in the world
and see themselves as leaders.
So I'm being a little
bit vague because there's
so many different ways that
bias can creep in and give
confusing messages to
our youth, but that's
one of the reasons AI
literacy is so important,
to help teachers be prepared
to have these conversations
about bias and I.
So I think I'll
stop there because I
did want to just emphasize
the fact that we wanted
to have teachers
come to this talk
to share their experiences
introducing concepts
to their students.
And just because of
the time of this talk,
they're all in the classroom
right now, so what I did
is I went in and I interviewed
three of our teachers.
These are teachers who have been
participating in our project
since the first or second
year of its beginning,
and I'll ask Eric
if I could trouble
you to share your screen.
Yeah, so these
are three teachers
who kindly let me chat
with them after school.
You'll see some of
them in the video
I'm about to play are
actually in their classroom.
And I want to introduce them
because each of these teachers
not only went through the
PD that I described earlier,
but then they returned
in subsequent years
and led the PD themselves.
And what we've found is that
when teachers teach teachers,
we have the greatest impact on
student learning of AI concepts,
and we have the greatest
growth in AI literacy,
according to our measures.
So it's these teachers
who are really
showing that it's through
educators that we might
be able to advance some of
the difficult conversations
about AI.
So let me give each teacher
a quick introduction,
and then I'll ask Eric
to play the video.
So on the left here
is Phylis Wilson.
Phylis is a veteran teacher of
over 10 years with experience
teaching in middle and high
school science and computer
science.
She served, as I said, as
what we call a facilitator
during the Everyday AI project,
where she introduced teachers
to AI concepts.
Phylis is a master of strategies
for integrating AI education
into STEM education.
And she's presented her
work at several conferences
as part of our
Everyday AI project,
and she's presented
her work on AI,
for example, at the National
Association for Research
on Science Teaching, or NARST.
Jesse is also an experienced
classroom teacher,
with nine years of
experience teaching in middle
and high school media arts.
He teaches graphic design,
yearbook, film, esports.
His school, with some
of his assistance,
was awarded the state
Innovation Zone grant in 2023
for exceptional
work, in part because
of the work he's doing in
his film and media classes.
Jesse served as a facilitator as
well in the Everyday AI project,
and I consider him a
master of strategies
in integrating AI education
into digital media education.
And lastly, Kelly Powers--
but certainly not least--
Kelly is a veteran
teacher of 25 years
of experience teaching middle
and high school computer
science.
She is a leader
in the development
of strategic pathways
in computer science.
She was formerly working
at IBM, and she's
left industry to
come to the classroom
and served as a facilitator
in the Everyday AI project.
And fun fact about
Kelly is that she
was one of the
teachers who initially
advised the AI4K12 working group
in 2018, which has become--
will inform the AI4K12
frameworks and learning
standards worldwide.
So with that, I'm going
to ask Eric to play--
it's just a seven-minute video
of these teachers sharing
their insights on, first, how
they are using large language
models just for their
own personal use
and then reflecting on some
of the challenges and benefits
and future of large language
models in the classroom.
Thank you, Eric.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- So I use it in work.
What I've been doing is any
time I have to write an email--
I think I do pretty well
with writing anyway,
but when I'm doing
a parent email,
sometimes I'll send
it out directly.
But other times I'll put
it into Chat and say, edit
this draft to a parent
regarding the student's warning,
just to make sure my
tone is coming across
and my message, intent is there.
And so I'll feed it
through there just
to see if it makes it better.
And sometimes I
keep the original,
but normally at least
I change a few things
because l like having some of
the verbiage the Chat uses.
It's like, OK,
that sounds nicer.
That sounds better.
So I use it for that.
And I did that to create
a template, basically,
and I shared it
with my department
to contact parents about
violations of the cell phone
policy.
- So for my educational
practice and how I'm using LLMs,
I'm using it a lot
for my prep work,
creating assignments, not
necessarily analyzing work just
yet but mostly just getting
assignments to a point
where I can come up with an
idea for a creative assignment,
and I have a master prompt.
- I use it for lesson ideas.
If I have an idea
of what I want it
to look like but I don't really
have it spelled all the way out,
I'll ask Chat for--
just to come up with
something and see
if it's in line with
what I was thinking.
- So professionally, I must say
I haven't really used it a ton
because the lessons--
and this is where
I get confused.
A lot of these tools create
amazing lesson plans,
amazing activities, but if
you think of the public school
teacher, not me but the
public school teacher,
they're usually
given a curriculum
that they have to follow.
So do they really--
if anything, maybe
differentiation activities,
that would be a use case.
But we're not really
writing curriculum so much.
- But I know that students
right now are using it
as a big crutch for just
turning in projects,
and it's not necessarily
learning because that's
the issue is that schools right
now are focused on, do the task,
get the grade, not find--
I'm telling kids, you
can find the answer,
but are you understanding
the solution?
And that's the biggest
part of learning.
And what made it
worse was Google.
You can Google a question
now, and now Google
has an AI response.
But now no one's actually
clicking on those links
of where these are coming from.
- I definitely see the
middle school brain--
I see them using these tools
to get their homework done
and not really thinking like we
would want them to think, think
thoughtfully and thoroughly and
spend some time with the model
to engage in back-and-forth.
- Because I don't
think everyone has
the discretion needed to go
back and evaluate the product.
You have to be able to
say, OK, this was my idea.
This is what prompted.
But is it actually doing
what it was asked to do?
And is it my work?
Is it speaking the way
I want it to speak,
or is it just saying
something random?
I think that part
takes time as well.
You have to evaluate
what's there.
Very rarely.
I haven't had-- we haven't
done that because even
at the school that I'm at
it's still kind of in between.
And I don't want to--
I don't want to step on other
teachers toes who are reaching
against it because we have--
I really, really--
I am super, super on board
with classical learning,
especially with reading,
writing, especially writing.
Learning how to write
and synthesizing it,
that's how your brain functions.
- We're still limited by
lots of tools being blocked,
so they're not in
schools lacking policy.
How are we going to integrate
AI into the curriculum
so it's thoughtful and it's
just right for the kids--
it's age-appropriate?
And a lot of schools are
still struggling with what
that should look like.
- So I think it's kind of crazy
that some teachers are going
to be able to
develop their skill
set because of the district they
work in and benefit the kids
and make their workload easier
and all this kind of stuff.
And then you're going
to have, once again--
not a technology
divide, but it's
like some people are
getting left behind,
and they have to do
with the regular way.
And I just don't think--
I'm happy that the
district I'm in now
is not on the downside of that.
But I do think about
what that means
for other teachers in
other school systems
who are not being taught
anything about AI, who are not
allowed to use it at all
for their personal work
or with students, and what
that will mean for them.
The whole point is for
everyone to get better.
- So that's where
my jam is, really,
is like, how can
I expose students
to how AI works, how
AI presents some harms
and benefits to society, and
as we prepare our students who
are in my classroom to become
creators of anything, how might
what are some of the
questions they're thinking
about when designing tech?
What are the harms
their tech might
have on society or
people in our society,
and what are the benefits?
So they are getting a real great
sense of how these technologies
work and doing a lot of--
getting feedback
from their models
and then making
adjustments, going
through the problem-solving
and design cycle.
So we are doing a lot of AI,
just not prompt engineering
so much with my students.
- AI at this point
is going to make sure
that everyone has their
own production company,
everyone is able to
make all these things.
I'm watching these interesting
videos of-- there's one
good writer, and
you want to say LLMs
are going to replace writers.
And I'm like, no,
LLMs are just going
to be a catapult for
writers because because--
- But some of the tools are
having AI buddies inside
of them, and in
that case, then you
will be creating certain
prompts to interact
with the tool embedded in
the curriculum resource
that you're using.
I can see that blowing up
beautifully in a great way.
- I feel like a lot of--
not a lot.
A lot of people want to be
on the PD train, I would say,
when it comes to AI,
but everybody is not
teaching teachers how to help
students use AI or teaching
teachers how to integrate
AI into their curriculum,
even more importantly.
That's not what they're doing.
It's more about, this is
a tool for teachers only.
That's kind of what you get.
This is a tool for teachers
to write learning objectives.
You know what I mean?
It's not necessarily
helping me to deliver
the content any better or
to teach children content.
So I feel like that part
is not being addressed.
[END PLAYBACK]
So I'll close by saying
these teachers highlighted
some areas of concern.
One is that they're concerned
about a digital divide
between teachers who
have training on AI
and don't, and they're not
yet seeing the connection
between the LLM tools of
today being useful immediately
for them in their classroom.
Happy to take questions.
I'm sorry I went a
little bit over time.
I'll pass the
microphone back to Bill.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN: Kate
and Eric, thanks very much.
This is really a
real helpful session.
We will have a few
minutes for questions.
Let me just tell the group, if
you could post your questions
in chat, then I'll
try and field them
so we stay within
our time limit.
Let me start with a
question I've got,
and I'll ask it
really of each of you.
Eric, what are-- you've
given us a lot of insights
in your presentation.
What are the best
practices that schools
ought to be thinking
about for AI
and its application
to education?
And then, Kate, let me ask
you, with all your dealings
with teachers, what do you
think the best practices are
that teachers ought to
start thinking about?
ERIC KLOPFER:
Yeah, it comes back
to that comment I made earlier
about creating communities
of practice.
I think the best thing
to do is to have people
who are willing to experiment
and share with other teachers
to figure out what's
working, what's not working,
what's working for whom.
And it would be a waste of
time to think about everybody
trying everything and not
sharing it with each other.
And I also think
that there's going
to be people at different
levels of readiness,
and so the people who are
ready to test things now
can learn and share that
with the next wave of people
who are maybe a little bit more
reticent to use the technologies
in their classrooms.
I do think that one piece of
advice is to not ban things.
There's a sense that, well,
if we just ban everything,
we just put up a big
gate at the door,
we will not have any problems.
We won't have to
think about this.
We can just ignore this
problem, and we'll just say,
you can't use AI.
I think really that's the
"sticking your head in the sand"
solution, and I don't think
that will be effective.
What that does is
create disparities.
It means that people who
have more access to tools
outside of school will use
those and benefit from those,
and the people who don't
have access to those
will be hurt by not
having access to those.
It's really important to have
people learning how to use them
effectively and
ethically, and I think
that that's only going to
happen through practice.
But I think teachers
need to have policies
that they feel like that they're
comfortable with as well,
and they need to be a part of
that process, which says, hey,
if we say you can't use the
AI on certain assignments,
we need to assume
that that's the case.
And if we find out that you
are-- and I don't think that
should be done through
AI detection tools.
I think through
conversation with students
that you find out whether
that's happened or not--
then there should be
consequences to those things.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN:
Thanks, Eric.
Kate, how about teachers
and best practices?
KATE MOORE: I just
agree with everything--
I agree with everything
that Eric just said,
and I think it's all
relevant to teachers,
particularly staying
connected in a community.
We found that teachers who are
connected do the work longer
and feel more
refreshed and involved.
Staying isolated,
not connected, just
trying to bulldoze through it
on your own leads to burnout.
I also really
appreciate Eric's point
about the disparity, the risk
of disparity if we just ban.
And the one thing I'll add is
that the research is still not
out yet on this, so
I'm just speaking
from my own personal work
interviewing teachers.
But it seems that
giving students AI tools
and treating that as the
educative experience leads
to confusion, misunderstanding.
Perhaps start by talking
about how AI works first
with your students, giving
them a sense of what's
happening under the hood,
using some of the curricula
that Eric shared, that I've
shared that's already out there.
And then give them the tools.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN:
Great points.
And again, if folks
have got questions,
just please post them
in the chat feature.
There's been a lot
of talk, obviously--
and you all have both
raised it at some length--
about the application of
AI-based tutors in education.
Where are we in that process?
How are these
tutors coming along?
What are some of the
problems we've got with them?
And what do you think
their potential role is?
And let me turn to you,
Kate, and then to Eric.
KATE MOORE: Well, Eric's
certainly the expert on this,
but I did make a few--
I do have a few comments on
this, and I'll pass to Eric.
One is, as I said before,
teachers are having a hard time
connecting the pipes.
They're using tools like ChatGPT
but also Khan Academy's Khanmigo
to create materials
for their students
if they have a membership,
and the materials just
aren't quite landing.
They're great at
differentiating.
There's opportunities to
really make materials quickly,
but the opportunity to
put in meaningful images,
relevant content, and have
tutors that are actually
responding to where the students
are in their needs as learners
isn't quite there.
And there's a few concerns--
I don't think they made
it into the video--
that students might
feel if they're just
working with a tutor
or just working
with AI-produced materials
that they might feel isolated
or like they're not connecting
with-- the social learning
that's so critical in education.
And I know you
were probably going
to say the same thing, Eric, so
I'll pass the microphone to you.
ERIC KLOPFER: Yeah, I'll
definitely agree with that.
I think that's the
key is that tutors
need to be part of
an ecosystem of tools
and used at the
appropriate times
for the appropriate activities.
So much of learning is social.
It's about connecting
with other people.
It's about developing
my identity.
It's about having relationships
with a teacher who
I feel like cares about me.
A lot of this stuff from tutors
comes from the 2 sigma result
of many years ago where
if you give a kid a tutor,
you can make a 2
standard deviation
difference in their learning.
And I think there's evidence
that some of that is true,
but that's not all
about the tutor can just
deliver them facts.
It's about a real
tutor, a live tutor
who can understand the student,
think about their relationship,
think about who how they
develop as a person.
And that's what a tutor
does, and AI tutors
don't do that even if we try
to pretend that they do that.
But I do think that they
can play an important role.
You just have to think about
how the other people are
using that tool as part of
that ecosystem of things.
So as I said, in
our examples, we
use it as a member of a group,
so as a way to connect people
within a group.
We have a project
going on in MIT
where it's helping students
learn software development.
But it's integrated into
the software development
environment, and they
can ask questions.
It's things like
professional programmers use,
except it's so much more
Socratic method of doing that.
So I think there's really much
more better contextual ways
of doing things like this.
There's better social ways
We're using it in
games, for example,
where it's supporting some of
the gameplay that they're doing.
So I think it's about thinking
about where to apply it
effectively, but I think
the idea is this is
a tool that's just going to--
if we give this to
everybody, they'll
make 2 standard
deviations of differences.
It's a little bit shortsighted.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN:
Great, thanks
for those thoughtful responses.
Eric, let me ask you a question
and then Kate chime in as well.
MIT RAISE has been--
the effort you mentioned at MIT
to confront AI in education,
MIT RAISE has been
collaborating with Google
for teacher professional
development,
and where does that stand?
What's going to be
the results of that?
What can we hope to see
from that collaboration?
ERIC KLOPFER: Yeah, so one of
the courses I mentioned is--
there's a two-hour
course that we have
that people can take that's
an intro to AI for teachers.
The rationale behind
that one was we
want people to
just understand AI.
Don't immediately
understand how you're
going to apply this to
students and apply this
in your professional practice.
Just understand what
it is and how it's used
and how it can help you.
We think that's a really
important step because I think
teachers often jump
too quickly about,
how am I going to use
this with my students?
And so that's our first step
is that we've done that.
I think now we're
thinking about expanding
that kind of
professional development
to provide other kinds
of tools, to provide
more in-depth learning
experiences for students.
Google themselves has developed
a special large language
model for education--
I think it's called LearnLM--
that they announced
recently, and I
think we'll start to see some
interesting results from things
like that where people can apply
that in different contexts.
I think it's going to be
really important to then do
some research on that and
understand where it's succeeding
and where it's not succeeding.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN: Let me just
ask one closing point here.
Could you give us maybe a couple
of sentences from each of you
on what you think the most
important kind of applications
of AI are going to be
in education in this K
through 12 kind of realm?
What do you think the
really significant things
are going to-- contributions
that AI could make?
What might they be?
Kate, can I start with you?
KATE MOORE: Yeah, yeah,
and I'm excited to hear
what Eric's going to say.
So first, I'll just
resonate with what
Kelly Powers said in
the video, that she
sees this opportunity with--
she calls them "buddies," but
it's actually kind of like what
Eric was saying, too, where you
have an AI agent who's inserted
into an ecosystem that's
designed for a collaborative
learning experience or it's
part of this model that
you're exploring and you have
a buddy or an agent jump in.
I do think there are
opportunities for personalized
learning, but I'm hesitant to
say we're anywhere close to that
now because we have to think
very seriously about what it
means to personalize
what kind of data
security risks are
involved in that
and what does it mean to have
a personal tutor know you
very well, for example,
like surveillance issues.
So I do have
hesitancy about that.
But I do think those
are two opportunities.
I hope I didn't take
too much time from Eric
because I'm very excited
what you're going to say.
ERIC KLOPFER: No, so
I'm going to agree
that collaborative learning
is a really important place
that we'll see AI.
I think ways that can help
teachers support teachers
in making sense of student data,
those kinds of things as well.
But I also think that we'll
see it integrated more
into other tools, so rather
than seeing the standalone tutor
where I come in and
I ask questions,
I think the Python
Tutor that I mentioned
is a good example of this.
We'll see it integrated
into other tools.
So things that people
are already using
as part of their practice--
it could be a game.
It could be a simulation.
It could be a development tool.
It could be a creative tool.
Things like that where you have
AI integrated into those to help
provide students with
feedback, to help provide them
with guidance, those
are the places where
I think we'll see a lot
of interesting results.
WILLIAM BONVILLIAN:
Thank you both so much
for your really
terrific insights.
Obviously, the role for
AI for teachers in schools
is a crucial question for
everybody participating
in this event, and
you've really given us
some great thoughts about
how that might work for us.