well it's a pleasure to uh have the
opportunity to tell you a little bit
about our work in Silicon photonics
specifically for trapped ions um I think
maybe to start us off we could do a
little show of hands who's familiar with
integrated photonics or silicon
photonics Kevin's waving in the back
okay we have a couple here wonderful
Well what we'll start off with today
then is an introduction to silicon
photonics and maybe I can uh introduce a
lot of you to this wonderful field of
integrated silicon photonics we'll then
take a look at what we can do when we
use integrated photonics to address
trapped ions and then I'll um briefly
mention some of the other group other
work happening in our group The fonics
Electronics Research group so this will
be a little bit of a switch and topic
the last speaker was really uh talking a
little bit more about algorithms and and
how you do these uh you know Advanced
gate operations things like that now
we're going to switch more to the
engineering side of things how can we um
deliver light to interface with
different types of cubits and
specifically trap ions in this case so
let's start with an introduction to
Silicon
photonics so for those of you who are
not familiar with silicon photonics the
general idea behind our field is that we
want to take standard seos fabrication
processes and repurpose them to create
optical devices and systems on chip so
on the left left hand side here you can
see a standard bulk semos transistor you
know normally when you have a seos
process you would use this process to
fabricate these transistors that are
going to do electrical switching and do
the standard computation that we have in
our you know classical computers here so
you'd have a silicon layer here this is
if you took your computer chip for those
of you that are maybe not as familiar
with the the hardware side of things
this would be if you take your computer
chip and you cross-section it in half
this is what one of these like little
nanoscale transistors would look like so
you have the Silicon over here uh then
you would have regions of what's called
doped silicon that's where you take the
Silicon you bombard it with dopin and
then you'd have metal coming down into
contact with those doped regions and
what that allows us to do is on those
metal lines actually apply voltages and
uh get switching of the transistor
that's what allows us to do our normal
classical Computing Gates right that's
what allows us to to do classical
Computing so what we can do is we can
take all these layers that you would
normally use for your transistor and
repurpose them to create optical devices
on chip so for example here you would
see a cross-sectional view of a silicon
photonics Optical wave guide what this
is going to look like is here in this
cross-sectional view it's a little
rectangle if you actually took a top
down view on your chip what this would
look like is you'd have that little
rectangle and it would be a long strip
of that rectangle on your chip and if
you took maybe
electromagnetics uh at some point in
your engineering career um you would
have learned that if you have this strip
of dialectric material here and you put
in some electromagnetic wave in this
case it would be an optical wave into
that that wave guide that wave guide is
going to confine the light on your chip
in that little strip of silicon and it's
going to guide the light down the chip
so we have this way of confining and
Guiding Light on our seamos chip here
okay so we're confining and we're
guiding our light but we don't want to
just have the light on the chip we want
to be able to do operations with this
light so we need to have some way to
modulate the light on the chip so what
we would do is we could maybe take this
wave guide and we would create an active
electrooptical modulator so you'd have
your wave guide here that's confining
and guiding your light and then you
extend it on either side and then on
either side there maybe we'd put some of
those dopents in that allow us to have a
uh electrical properties in this silicon
and we place metal down into contact
with those dopin and now we can apply a
voltage across that wave guide and
through things called uh the thermal
optic effect or electrooptic effect
you're going to apply that voltage
across that doped region and it's going
to change the properties of your wave
guide and now when the light goes
through the wave guide it's going to
either slow up uh slow down or speed up
so you have this way of changing how the
light passes through the wave guide uh
we call these electrooptic phase or
amplitude
modulators and then okay we can guide
the light on the chip we can modulate
the light on the chip now we want to
interface with the surroundings of the
chip uh so to do that we would pattern
some more interesting more complex
devices maybe something like these
grading antennas which we'll talk about
in a few slides again um the idea there
is you have your wave guide on the chip
now all of a sudden you want to scatter
the light up and out of the chip to
interface with different things in the
environment for Quantum Computing that
thing would actually be the physical
Cubit that you're trying to interface
to so by uh taking these seos processes
and using them to create Optics on chip
we can take Optical systems that once
complex and bulky maybe they would take
up an entire Optical table in a research
lab or a ton of optical fibers all
connected together well we can take
these Optical systems and now we can
compact them down into these little
millimeter scale Sil photonics
chips a very small form factor also by
taking advantage of seos fabrication
processes right seos uh chips are
fabricated on the wafer scale you can
see up on the the top left here is a
photograph of a seos wafer that was
fabricated in our lab for silicon
photonics um well these seos fabrication
processes they're fabricated on these
large 12-in Wafers which allows us to
really scale up how many of these chips
we can fabricate at at a time so it's a
uh way to scale up the manufacturing the
both the yield and the
number and then uh finally by
integrating these optical devices onto
chips we can enable new functionality
that was never before possible with bulk
Optics or fiber optics and you'll see
why this is so important when we start
interfacing with these different types
of
cubits um maybe I'll pause here if
there's a question or two just to make
sure uh we're kind of catching think
everyone in the audience that maybe
hasn't seen this field of integrated
photonics
before
absolutely so I understand how you get
the the wave to go down uh of that and
because I've seen other
areas radar systems oh yeah that's
that's essentially wave guides for RF
yeah so
um how does that become a cub
my understanding of that is missing and
that's key to almost everything we
talked about tonight oh yeah so far no
cubits this is all classical so so far
we're just putting classical laser light
on this chip um you'll see in a few
slides how we can actually use this then
to interface with cubits so hold that
thought for for maybe five
minutes forgive me but if I could talk
with you on another day that would be
appreciated awesome yeah absolutely
thank you any other questions before we
keep
going you essentially creating like
Gates through this you're essentially uh
you're trying to take functionality that
you would normally use that you normally
use maybe an optical fiber or uh bulk
lenses and you're taking that and
putting it on the chip so so far we
haven't yet touched the quantum side of
things we're just thinking about how can
we get light on a chip and create these
Optical devices on the
chip so maybe let's keep let's keep
going and see uh how is quantum
Computing going to come into this field
of silic and
photonics so uh in general this field of
silic and photonics actually came up
because of the problem of optical
interconnects there was a need to take
data uh move around lots of classical
data to uh move data on and off the chip
in large volumes um and silicon ICS
really came about as a field because
there was a need to do all this data
movement in the optical domain where we
could have faster speeds and and lower
losses and because of this uh the field
of silicon photonics kind of rose up and
there's a lot of infrastructure put into
place on how can we fabricate these
chips how can we create platforms for
silicon photonics um all still classical
uh but there's a lot of money and
infrastructure poured into this field
and now we can take this idea of
integrated photonics and apply it to
many different other application areas
so things like lar sensors or ar
displays uh free space classical
Communications biophotonics interfacing
with the bi uh with the body with Optics
but relevant to this Workshop today is
that we can actually use this field of
silicon photonics to interface with
different types of cubits optically and
the Cubit that we're going to talk about
now for the next 30 minutes is the
trapped ion
so that's where uh now we're actually
going to bring in the quantum Computing
side of
things so who's maybe show of hands
who's familiar with trap
ions okay so now we have about maybe a
third of people um so trap ions are a
very promising modality for Quantum
Computing because they have very long
coherence times um they're fundamentally
identical and they enable High Fidelity
gate operations so um maybe before I
switch to the next slide just cuz uh a
good chunk of people didn't raise their
hands for famili familiarity with
trapped ions let me step back and just
introduce you to what a trapped iion
would be so if you think about back to
um kind of your basic quantum physics
class or maybe your chemistry class when
you have an atom right there's uh
neutral particles here in the center and
um you might have an ion where you have
some charged particle that's hanging out
on kind of the highest bands
of this
atom and this little charged particle
this ion that's hanging out here um
depending on what band this ion is
sitting at depending on what that state
of that ion is is it sitting at a a
lower energy level or higher energy
level that's effectively going to be the
one or the zero in your Quantum bit your
your quantum computer made out of these
trap ions so we have this ion sitting
here and it's going to be in these
different levels there's going to be
different states it can be
in so there's this little charge charged
particle this ion it's going to be in
these different states how do you
actually switch between states how do
you read out what state this ion
actually is at you need to be able to
use um or these states are separated in
energy by exactly Optical wavelengths so
you need to have some way to interface
with this little ion Cubit optically to
actually switch between the zero and the
one state or to read out when this ion
drops down between states it's going to
emit a little Photon you're going to
need to be able to interface with that
ion optically to even read out what
state that ion is in so there's this
this need for trapping that ion there um
to actually create your Cubit and then
some way to interface to this ion
optically to actually uh do all the
different operations for this quantum
computer so now let's take a look at at
what does this physic physically look
like so at first um you know we need to
have some way to take that ion and to
trap it in space so the first
demonstrations of this look something
like this this is called a pul trap uh
these are metal long metal rods um that
have DC and RF Fields actually flowing
through them and they're oriented like
this where this would be a
cross-sectional view if we cut this guy
this physical guy here um you'd have
these metal bars here uh red is the RF
potentials gray is DC potentials and if
we um apply just the right voltages here
we're going to create the correct
potential to actually trap this little
charged ion here in the center of this
trap this is great as a first demo right
but if we want to create a real quantum
computer we need a way to take this
system and create it in a more
integrated more scalable way so the next
huge innovation in this field of Trapped
iion Quantum systems was to take this
really bulk system system this this P
trap and integrate it down into a chip
so the idea is can you take these uh
metal bars these electrodes and actually
kind of flatten them down and pattern
them on a little chip this isn't
necessarily now at the stage yet where
we're at seos level uh complexity but
this could maybe just be a little
silicon chip here and these could be
little metal electrodes now on top of
the
chip these electrodes are now going to
be powered with those same fields to
create the potential to trap this ion
now above the chip this is physically
what that looks like we have this little
chiplet down here this is from uh an
image from Duke University a lot of this
work is transitioned to ion Q which is a
a big uh um company operating in this
space so they have this this little um
chip down here that's holding all of
these these traps and they set the Trap
potentials just right so that they can
actually trap a chain of these little
ions Above This
chip okay so this um area of thinking
about how can we actually get the
electronics to trap these ions in an
integrated a scalable way that's been
pretty well explored but now the
question comes as we just talked about a
couple of minutes ago is we have these
ions here now we need to actually switch
their states we need to read out their
states we need to do these operations
and all of that is done optically and
the problem is so we have this nice
little integrated way to trap the ions
there but we still have a huge Optical
table multiple Optical tables of bulk
Optical components that are going to be
required to interface with these ions in
this ion chain so now if you go into
kind of a state-of-the-art uh trapped
ion lab this is kind of the view you'd
see there would be an an optic lab about
the size of this front area here and in
the center Center there would be a cat
which I think you guys have already
talked about a little bit uh this
cryostat would be cooling ions down to a
very low temperature and then there
would be little windows on the side of
that cat literally Windows um and then
we have a whole room filled with Optical
tables with bulk Optics that are taking
different wavelengths and polarizations
of light phase stable light and bringing
it in through those windows to interface
with the ions that are sitting in this
cryostat quantum computer
right um it looks super cool it's also a
little bit scary you know I go into our
collaborators Labs that are working on
this and you're like don't breathe you
know there's all these bulk Optics all
perfectly aligned and and you know
hundreds of components all required to
interface with these ions so the problem
is that how is this scalable right you
have a whole room worth of bulk Optics
just to interface with maybe tens of
ions in this uh cry stat if you want to
scale up to tens of thousands of ions
many cubits just like uh was um really
emphasized by our previous speakers that
we need to scale up the number uh this
is not going to be a scalable way to
interface with those ions right the
hardware is not scalable it would take
like a M's worth of bulk Optics to
figure out how to do that also the more
pressing problem right at the moment is
that uh you know when we talk to our
friends in the atomic physics world all
these Optical tables are vibrating
slightly differently they're all sitting
in the room vibrating slightly
differently the bulk Optical lenses are
all vibrating slightly differently and
when all these different uh wavelengths
and polarizations of light now come in
to interface with our ion the coherence
of those Optical beams is going to be
messed up so you can imagine if things
are vibrating slightly differently the
light as it's coming in is going to have
a slightly different phase as it hits
your Ion it's going to mess up the
coherence which r produces the Fidelity
of your Quantum operation on that
ion so there's really a need to to think
about a way we can take all these Optics
and make them more scalable and also
phase stable to improve the coherence of
this uh of these
operations and the solution to that is
what we talked about right at the
beginning can we create computer chips
now these photonic chips that have
integrated photonics components that
have all those Optics but now integrated
on your chip to interface with your Ion
maybe we're seeing where the this uh
field of integrated photonics can come
into play so what that looks like is now
we have this this chip here you can see
these metal lines the the yellow those
are going to be those RF electrodes that
are actually going to trap your Ion
electrically above your chip the ion is
shown here in light
blue so we we've again like I mentioned
before this is a pretty well-known uh
technique this Paul trap on chip but now
we need to have all these Optical beams
interfacing to the ion also coming uh
from our chip so here we would have our
integrated silicon photonics wave guides
coming
in these would be our tiny little
Optical antennas that are going to emit
the light up and out of the Chip And to
the the point where the ion is trapped
there above the chip you'll notice that
these um in this this rendering here
from our friends at Lincoln Labs uh
they've colored the beams in different
colors and that's because we actually
need different wavelengths or different
colors of light to interface up to the
ion to do different operations on the
ion so this requires uh the different
operations that we're thinking about
here is cooling the ion so you trap the
ion there now you need to cool it down
to kind of stabilize its motion then you
have to do state preparation so
initializing what state is it a one or a
zero that that ion is initi
in um you need to do state excitation
right when we actually want to perform
operations on that Cubit we need to
excite different states and then also
optically we need to read out when the
ion actually um fluoresces out in uh
Photon when it drops down between states
we need to read that Photon out and also
capture it optically these are all
Optical operations then now we can think
about doing on one of these photonic
silicon photonic chips so we'd have this
chip here uh what this is going to
physically look like in our larger
system is this photonic chip would be
sitting down here this would all be in a
uh cry
stat um your Ion actually is is flipped
down underneath the chip here and then
you'd have some Optical fibers bringing
light from an off chip laser and
coupling it onto this photonic chip and
then you would do all your operations
that you need to do on your chip doing
all that light delivery to uh in this
case this would be a single ion but of
course we can also scale up to multiple
ions and one of the very key components
for this is uh these Optical antennas on
chip so what that would look like is
you'd have your your silicon photonics
wave guide that dialectric wave guide
that's confining light on your chip and
then you'd have some little what we call
grading coupler or grading antenna that
is going to take that light off the chip
and then scatter it up to your Ion what
that physically looks like is you have
your wave guide and you patter these
little pertubations in the wave guide
that causes scattering at each of the
pertubations if you design them just
right you can get all that light to emit
up and uh to the ion through those um
metal electrodes that we patterned
earlier um so how do you actually make
this concept come to life is again you
need platforms to actually fabricate
these photonic chips in uh so what that
could look like is you here's an example
Le of the platform that we fabricate in
um you have different wave guiding
layers this is a silicon nitride wave
guide uh you could have multiple layers
that would allow you to maybe cross the
wave guides once you start scaling up to
larger numbers of cubits uh have
different operations happening in these
different wave guides then you have
these emitters that are emitting light
off the chip up to the ion that's
sitting above the chip uh you could have
some modulator layers like we talked
about earlier maybe modulating the light
that's actually in that chip and you
could even
um uh have these modulators connected to
integrated Coss control Electronics on
that same chiplet so really thinking
about how can we scale up these trapped
iion quantum
computers so the advantages of moving to
integrated photonics for this uh like we
talked about is the coherence and the
scalability so here um this is nice work
coming out of uh lincol Labs a couple of
years ago they actually did an
experiment
um where you can see if you have a you
know your your Ion trap chip sitting
here it's trapping your your Ion in this
case below the Chip And then you have
free space beams coming in um from all
those free space Optics those free space
beams are all vibrating differently than
your your uh trap chip and that's what's
going to cause this um reduction in the
coherence reduction the fidelities of
these operations when you move to
integrated now you have uh the light
coming in and it's actually emitting off
of the same chip that the ion is
registered to the ion is trapped to that
chip and now we're going to emit all the
optical beams off the same chip
everything is going to be nicely
vibrationally stabilized you're going to
improve your coherence you're going to
improve your
Fidelity and then I just love this video
um showing how we could think about
scaling these systems let's see if we
can play it
so so far we really thought about um
just interfacing to a single ion that
would be like a single cubit in the
system we want to really scale up to
multiple cubits so here would be our
single ion it would be sitting above all
these grading couplers that are emitting
light off the chip then you could
shuttle that ion between these different
SES
right and now you could have gradings
that are interfacing um to this single
ion and now you can Envision creating a
a kind of grided up version of this
where you'd have multiple sites your
ions are shuttling between these SES and
that's really what's going to get us to
the point of scaling up this this uh
trapped iion um Quantum system concept
so would be really hard to do if all
that all those light beams were coming
from off chip um bulk Optical components
so of course we can never talk about um
research without sending a big
acknowledgement to all the the other
work happening in this field um so I I
you know kind of highlighted uh here the
work Happening by our collaborators at
MIT Lincoln Labs initial work um kind of
spearheading a lot of this integrated
photonics for trapped isons was done
here at MIT and Professor reiv rah's
group in collaboration with it Lincoln
Labs the team led at that time by uh
Jeremy sage and then we have seen an
explosion of excellent results coming
out of many groups um around the world
some uh great work coming out of eth
Zurich and and Jonathan Holmes Group uh
an Oxford Group doing excellent work
also an integrated photonic Sandia has a
lot of efforts in this space um Cornell
there's a new Pi uh that's working in
this space and then even when we look
more broadly we have all this research
happening but now there's been an
adoption of these techniques in the
indust industrial space so we see
companies like ionq coming up um that
are uh not just thinking about scaling
up ion traps but also bringing in the
integrated photonics to interface
optically with those uh trap Dions
quantium is another company Honeywell
all doing excellent
work um I wanted to highlight really
quick the work happening in our group
here at MIT uh by all of my excellent
students this is all done uh in
collaboration with MIT Lincoln
Labs um so all the the previous demos
that we looked at were all thinking
about interfacing with these ions with
just maybe a single beam of light uh a
single
polarization uh which limits the
functionalities that we can get out of
these trapped ion uh Quantum systems so
what our group has been focusing on in
collaboration with linking Labs is
enabling polarization diverse
integrated uh photonic beam delivery to
enable more advanced functionality this
has been done in bulk Optics but so far
hasn't really been touched by integrated
photonics so the first thing that we are
looking at is um what are different
architectures where we have these
multiple polarizations of beams coming
out what can they actually enable and
one thing is I I mentioned that one of
the main functionalities of Optics in
these trapped ion system is cooling the
ion to low temperatures to stabilize the
ion um fundamentally this cooling is
usually limited to What's called the
Doppler limit if you've heard of Doppler
cooling there's going to be a floor how
cool that ion can actually get what you
can do instead of being limited by the
stop low limit is if you have multiple
polarizations of light you can
incentivize cooling to subd Doppler uh
uh floors and what that would look like
is you'd have this chip sitting here
you'd have these gradings emitting light
out of the chip but they won't just be
emitting a single polarization you'd
have two different polarizations of
light coming up to the ion this creates
what's called a polarization gradient
which induces different transitions in
the ion and enables this subd Doppler
cooling using a technique called
polarization gradient cooling or
electromagnetically induced
transparency to enable that we have to
think about devices on chip that uh are
going to prepare these different
polarization States so here's nice work
led by my students um Ashton and Tall
where we showed the first integrated
polarization Splitters and rotators on
chip that operate down at the visible
wavelength that's required for
this then um my student Sabrina with
help from Ashton and Mila designed these
grading couplers that now don't just
emit te uh polarizations of light but
emit both te and TM so you have to do a
lot of different electromagnetics device
design to enable this and again this is
the first uh gradings that can actually
emit both polarizations to interface
with ions
uh Sabrina then uh took these chips
where we have these these U multiple
gradings emitting different
polarizations and with the help of the
MIT quana group of postto Ethan and and
graduate student Felix they took these
chips put them in the crat and actually
trapped an ion above the surface and
then induced this polarization gradient
using these multiple polarizations of
light uh to show the first polarization
gradient um result with integrated
photonics and here we're actually able
to now cool four times below the
fundamental Doppler limit um with this
kind of system which we're really
excited
about and then also uh you know we
mentioned how another um operation that
we need to do with uh optics for ions is
to not just uh excite different
transitions for cooling and state
preparation and excitation but also to
be able to collect photons that are
emitting out of the ion and to do that
we have to design uh we call collection
grading so your Ion is sitting up here
uh it's emitting a photon out um you
need to be able to collect that photon
with some integrated device and then
bring it to a detector to be able to
understand what the state of that ion is
so here again in collaboration with the
qu group we showed the first um
integrated collection gradings for
ions um I hope this gives you a flavor
for for where we can go uh with this
field in general
um maybe now for the just the last
couple of minutes I'll uh briefly switch
gears and just U mention very briefly
some of the other research directions in
our group just to give you a feel for
what else you can do with silicon
photonics Beyond um interfacing to these
uh Cubit trap
Dions so one of our research directions
is thinking about can you create these
silicon photonic chips that emit light
off the chip scan those Optical beams
around light gets reflected back and is
received by the same chip to enable a
non-mechanical solid state-based liar
for autonomous vehicles this is work LED
uh by my students Daniel and Ben with
the help of
M another area where silicon photonics
can have a huge impact is in displays so
here uh Mila with the help of Andre and
Henry is creating a chip that can is
actually transparent and can sit in
front of your eye and it has all these
integrated photonic components that emit
light off the chip and actually project
3D holographic images um for the user to
see for augmented
reality to enable this um we need to
think about how can we uh create these
chips that can actually sit in front of
the eye um before everything was uh all
these silicon photonic devices were
focused on Silicon Wafers that are not
transparent so here we showed the first
demonstration of 300 mm silicon
photonics platform that's actually
transparent we also have to think about
modulators for all of these applications
and even for trapped iron Cube uh
Quantum systems so here uh mil led the
demonstration of the first liquor
crystal-based modulators that enable
compact uh visible light modulators on
chip we can also think about silicum
photonics um to create 3D printers so
the idea here is to have a chip that
sits in the palm of your hand and
actually projects three-dimensional
hologram into a vat of resin to cure 3D
objects without needing all the complex
Optics that's normally required for
highresolution uh resin based 3D
printers so this was uh creating a
portable chip based 3D
printer we can also create chips that
emit light off the chip to trap and
manipulate biological particles here um
work led by my student t with help from
Sabrina Mila we are actually trapping
and manipulating cancer cells on
chip uh when we think about bi photonics
we have to create Wafers that don't just
sit on the body but that mold to the
body or maybe get integrated in textiles
so they have to be flexible so here
we're showing the first 300 mm flexible
uh
Wafers and then finally we can create
chips that actually going to Comm uh um
uh transmit data highspeed data uh
through free space channels so here um
work led by uh Daniel and mitaa we're
actually creating chips that emit light
through water and enable um underwater
Communications so again just to give you
a flavor for the the uh work that we can
do with silicon photonics impact we can
have outside of just uh Quantum
Computing and Quantum
sensing so with that I'll wrap up and we
started out with just giving you a
flavor for what is silicum photonics we
then took a look at silicon photonics
for trapped ions right motivated by this
need for interfacing to ions optically
to enable these different
functionalities how we can can create um
these devices and platforms to enable
integrated um addressing of ions to
improve uh scalability Fidelity and um
really find a way forward for trap IR
Quantum Computing that's that's truly
scalable and I just very briefly
introduced you to some of our other
research directions of course I could
never give a talk without giving a huge
shout out to all the wonderful students
in my group um all their wonderful work
is really what enables all of uh this
work to move forward and specifically
for this talk I'll highlight our
collaborators at MIT Lincoln Laboratory
um led by uh John Trini um and John also
spend some time here at MIT in the
quantum group led by Ike Chang uh so
it's been a pleasure also collaborating
with the students in that group in
addition to the team at lincol
Labs so with that maybe um just because
we started a little bit late maybe I'll
just pause for one or two questions and
then hand it over to Kevin so we can get
back on
time How are um TR how do
trap encode Quant qits and how do you do
one and two gate
um operations Yeah question yeah sure
I'll repeat it uh so the question here
was how um how is the actual encoding of
uh these operations done on the ion and
maybe how you could scale up to multiple
uh two cubits Gates or things like that
um so the way that we actually encode
information on these ions is in their
state so uh like we were very briefly
mentioned earlier you know normally this
ion is sitting here in some band on your
atom and depending on what band that ion
is sitting at that's going to
essentially correspond to a zero or a
one in your quantum computer it's going
to correspond to the state of the ion so
how you encode where which state this
ion is sitting in
is exactly with these Optical beams that
are going to kick that ion up in energy
to higher further away from the nucleus
or they're going to kick it down pH
sorry what about phase yeah so so you
would you would kind of uh create these
um uh you you would encode the state
using these Optical uh beams and then if
you actually wanted to go in and create
higher order Gates then you could take
two ions bring them interact them
together just like we saw in that that
quick video I showed um so the the two
ions would then be shuttled together
they would interact and then they' be
shuttled back and then they could kind
of go in and interact with other ions in
this array of uh cubits there how you
control what what what it is that how
they interact right because that's
obviously what the gate is yeah and
that's that's all done optically so
that's going to be um often you would
even have two different species of ions
so you could have for example strontium
and barium and these two different ions
they're going to require slightly
different Optical frequencies to switch
between their states and so how you
actually excite these different
operations is you would choose which
Optical frequency you actually excite up
to the ion to decide what operation
you're doing yeah maybe just for the
sake of time Kevin maybe we should
switch just uh since we got started a
little bit late here but I think there's
going to be plenty of time for more
discussion later on when we sit together
as a panel wonderful well thank you so
much
[Applause]