[Music]
uh my name is corad and I'm the
executive chairman and founder of AMD
Amity Solutions uh to be honest uh I was
not exactly fully aware of the format
until um but I was anyways asked to
present talk a little bit about uh what
we do and what Amity is um so actually
we started amate in 20 2 um I was 17 at
the time um and uh you know since then
we've been building uh software and
Cloud products uh from here in Thailand
um to basically Ser help with call
centers customer Communications customer
engagement that's the sector that we are
in um throughout our time we've raised
about $100 million um and we have about
600 colleagues across the world today um
and basically in the last two years
we've shifted our business model
significantly um our objective is very
simple our objective is to be a global
leader um in AI gen applications so
obviously you've all heard of the llms
and the large on all the foundation
models you know which sit at the very
you know bottom of the funnel uh we aim
to be the best at applying those
Foundation models and those large
language models um for usage especially
around customer communication and
customer service so we actually are a
rollup play uh what we do is we grow
through acquisition
um and what we do is we essentially
acquire uh Legacy software companies
where we see huge
potential um for generative AI to create
uplift and upsold so this year we did
four Acquisitions uh most of them in
Europe and we deployed about $200
million um to acquire a few software
companies in the call center and
customer communication uh space so for
example we acquired one company in the
UK called toing they serve 20,000
businesses in the UK and Europe and
they're a market leader in call
analytics so what they do is they
basically uh provide analytics on all of
your calls inbound and outbound and do
uh give you all the qu do do quality
assurance do analytics um you know and
before generative Ai call analytics is
very boring right because it just uses
keywords it just checks your sentiment
and it tells you what it can do but with
generative AI you know we see the call
analytics and call Center management
space is being
revolutionized um and so that is why we
acquired this company um and what we
have in Thailand is we have something
called our AI lab and what our AI lab
does is essentially um study do deep R&D
in order to be the best at applying
generative AI um into this use case so
now we work with the companies that we
acquire to apply generative AI um into
their offerings into their products uh
and to make it you know competitive and
create value for them um so today uh we
are based in Bangkok uh but we generate
about 80 90% of our um profit uh from
the European and UK Market we believe
that Thailand is a really really great
place for production um and so here
where we have about 300 400 Engineers we
produce uh build help to build and and
invest and research on generative Ai and
work with our portfolio companies to
apply them um so that is the the model
that we do and here in Thailand we
service almost every uh we service the
majority of the largest the 40 largest
companies uh we provide everything from
uh generative AI debt collection uh to
call center inbound um to you know for
example if you go to San Paragon or icon
sayam you can find our AI machines that
you can ask for recommendations or
restaurants so anything uh customer
facing we we you know I I believe that
we do uh most of you are our customers
um so uh I think that you know our goal
again just to uh our goal is to build an
AI Champion for Thailand um today uh we
we do about $120 million in run rate um
and we are uh in fact uh probably the
largest software company in Southeast
Asia now um and our goal is to you know
develop the AI ecosystem here in
Thailand and we're always open to
partner we work with many big companies
um in the country uh and I think and and
you know we're always open to partnering
to develop different gen uh generative
AI Innovations um different uh
applications for llms uh and uh yeah um
that's pretty much it I uh apologies
didn't uh didn't have any slides or
anything but always open to discussion
and I think that uh you know uh we look
forward to working with uh all all of
our partners and customers to advance
generative AI in Thailand thank
[Applause]
you thank you very much