so welcome everyone uh my name is
Terrell Williams and I serve as the
associate director for diversity equity
and inclusion here in the office of
admissions I am excited about the
opportunity to host tonight's panel with
our Dynamic group of sonies who identify
as veterans and I will now pass it over
to our moderator for the evening William
who will be uh able to share some uh
brief introduction about himself but
also introduce our panelist for the
evening William the floor is yours hey
charl thank thanks for that warm
introduction um yeah so guys my name is
Will CH I'm a current second year in the
full-time MBA program I am one of the
co-presidents of the Vets Club this year
I spent eight years in the Army I served
as a menac pilot which I know obviously
bias think it's h one of the best roles
there were I did my summer internship at
Microsoft and then I'll be going back uh
next year and then we'll start with uh
uh Andrew if you want to just go with
you know name program year and then what
you were doing before and then kind of
what you're doing now yeah hi everybody
my name is Andrew chanski joining you
from beautiful Medford Massachusetts
little North of Boston stayed here after
I graduated I was a submarine officer US
Navy for seven years um I went to uh lgo
I studied mechanical engineering along
with my MBA and did an internship at am
gen while I was there focus on
operations Robotics and now I'm at a
company called zuk uh that is working on
self-driving cars Robo taxis and I'm a
product manager there working on their
internal tools for
perception okay awesome and and now that
this slides up let's go left to right so
it makes a little bit more sense so
we'll uh go to
Mike hey everyone glad to be here my
name is Mike Morino I was a loone fellow
MBA um graduated in 2023 so just a
little over a year ago I did 22 years in
the Navy uh I was a Navy SEAL and um
actually came from the enlisted ranks
retired as a Senior Chief um I retired
in 2022 and um started the program
really the day the same day that I
retired um so after Sloan um I went and
did a post MBA internship uh at a
private Equity back Manufacturing
Company in Cincinnati uh while I was
looking for full-time work here in the
Boston area and I did Lander roll um
running a um a solar construction
company that serves both the uh both the
residential and Commercial and
Industrial markets uh called the Boston
Solar
Company awesome thanks so much Mike
Justin hey everyone my name is Justin
Mueller I uh am at NBA 2023 so a little
over a year out um I did the full-time
program uh I did my internship at
BCG uh and as you'll see I'm not there
now uh but I uh still have the option
available to me uh sometime soon if I
decide to take it uh in the meantime I
actually decided to take a senior
manager Business Development um role
atomium which is a green hydrogen
company and I'm actually in Houston
right now at a conference called gtec uh
representing Om I'm setting a com from
meetings things like that so um
yeah awesome thanks Justin we'll move to
Christopher hello uh hi everyone and I'm
happy to be here and happy to chat with
you and uh learn more about all of you
um so I'm Chris Chris uh Banks I am a
army reservist and I was a reservist
during Sloan so happy to talk about that
uh Military Intelligence officer um I
graduated NBA 2022 I my focus at Sloan
was entrepreneurship Innovation and I
was I did the product management track
there uh or the DPM certificate as it
was called when I graduated uh like will
I actually interned in Microsoft as
product marketing manager over the
summer which was a great experience um
but I decided to go back to deoe
Consulting uh because I was sponsored so
I came back I actually don't work there
anymore I actually now work for the
government um but that is it's it
literally happened a few weeks ago so uh
yeah super excited to be here and thank
you awesome and then last but not
least awesome hi everybody my name is
Valerie coach um I'm in Denver Colorado
moved here after um I finished up the
full-time program I was class of uh 22 I
was an Army intelligence officer before
I was in for five years active duty
stationed at JBLM my full-time and then
I went into the reserve for a little bit
at Sloan so happy to talk about that as
well uh I stopped doing it though so I
might have a different perspective um
than Chris but um I interned at McKenzie
uh during my summer and then I went back
full-time I've been there now close to
two years um but I'm doing something a
little different I'm on a fellowship
with McKenzie um I'm working with a
nonprofit so it's a certainly a
different um different experience so
happy to chat about all of that awesome
yeah thank you all for the introductions
I know you guys bring a ton of wealth
and knowledge and good background back
here I think one of the first questions
I kind of wanted to jump into here
is the transition right you know we all
were in the military and we left so I I
I wanted to start with a volunteer who
maybe wants to talk about what was the
most difficult part of transitioning
from you know being in the military to
full-time student life and how can
others in the seat be the most
successful I'll jump in um I was
reflecting a lot about this um in light
of this panel and I I think back to that
fall when I started so I think similar
to Mike my etss date from active duty
was the first day of class at Sloan so
it was just jumping right in and I think
one thing that was challenging is I
didn't really have time to reflect and
and think about um what I wanted to do
uh when I got to school and so um that
was something that was a little bit
challenging but one thing that was
unexpected is how much time you have if
you structure it sort of correctly I
think coming from working full-time you
know you're really busy obviously
military is really demanding and I think
I was surprised by the amount of free
time I had and what's so exciting about
that is you can fill it with too much
stuff I mean you're G to have so many
opportunities and options and so I think
it's just important to be uh prepared
for the amount of um um options and then
just be really intentional about how you
want to fill your
time yeah I know
absolutely anyone else want to jump in
there yeah I'll just say real quick um I
think it was a little bit different for
me I I'm married to have three kids and
um obviously I think the challenging
part is is you're making this transition
from a
lifestyle um that You' that you've known
for a very very long time coming up to a
new city um and and trying to balance in
my case I didn't have a lot of free time
um because because of my family
commitments so certainly just trying to
figure out how to to balance that um and
and knowing that it wasn't just me going
through a transition um it was my family
as well um I think that was probably the
most the challenging thing um you know
for for me and and and the family alike
um yeah we but it can be done and it's
just a matter of just expectation
management and uh you know getting into
a routine um you know we we happen to
live an hour an hour away from campus so
I was commuting every day um not
something I would necessarily recommend
but but it it it kind of allowed us to
to we we bought a house when we moved up
here we knew we were going to stay um
allowed us to be kind of out away from
everything um which which was important
to the family but it was at the same
time meant that um I was doing a lot of
commuting and pulling some really long
hours so just just trying to figure out
how to manage that um and and be present
for both um I think was the most
challenging aspect of
it no def
the
uh so they definitely deserve way way
more credit than they get um anyone else
Andrew Justin Chris you guys wantan
to talk about your
transition uh similar to Valerie's point
I think for me one of the things I found
hardest was um feeling you know there's
the obvious imposter syndrome of all
these people who have like come from
various business I mean even Chris at
least had like deoe before uh you know
but you feel very behind like oh I don't
know I haven't done this math
calculation I don't know anything about
economics I don't know this I don't know
that or I don't know these people or
these types of people um and so you feel
like you need to catch up and at least I
know I did like definitely signed up for
way too many things and just like
overstretched myself um uh which had to
slow down very much my second year CU my
wife and I had a kid over summer uh in
between my two years so uh that was
definitely um something that was
challenging for me was just trying to
overcome that feeling and and you'll
find you know especially as you kind of
get towards the end that everyone kind
of feels that way no matter where they
come from so uh you know don't feel like
you're the only one because you
def yeah well if if I I mean I kind of
had the deoe as Justin mentioned I kind
of had the deot experience beforehand so
I kind of knew what I was getting into a
little bit um I would say from my
perspective if I was like thinking about
the transition it would be like okay
what does it mean to be an NBA but also
choose to be a reservice at the same
time uh and I I think I think that was
probably one of the hardest transitions
because I think you know wanting to be
an active participant making sure I'm
still doing what I need to get done to
help out my soldiers was really
important to me it's something I valued
I mean I actually went away uh to
Germany for a few weeks and this was
like right as the Ukraine right before
Ukraine was kicking off so it was a it
was a very different time so um it it
was tough but I was able to prioritize
the military and school and my family uh
not well sometimes but I I tried to do
my
best yeah know that's that's great uh
Andrew you wanna finish it off here it
was great I wish I could go back I loved
it no no I I love it um okay Andrew we
we'll start with you for here you know
when you're when you're looking at all
these different schools you know
obviously there's a ton of incredible
programs out there just curious you know
on your thought process on how you ended
up at Sloan and you know obviously
you're the one here who did the uh LGL
program as well
yeah
um for me it came down to fit and that's
a kind of mushy thing to say like what
what is fit to me fit looking backwards
means that you got to spend two years
with these people schools have different
cultures um you should want to go enjoy
those two years with those people so uh
talking them ahead of time I think for
me I landed on lgo because I really did
want that engineering degree I wanted to
go spend some time studying engineering
I wanted to dig deep into Ai and
Robotics uh I got the chance to do that
and the fit part of that too is that
there were a bunch of other people who
wanted to do that as well that I get to
spend my time with um you'll probably
hear from everybody here in one way or
another that you there's way more
commitments than you have time for
and the the the the cool part of the lgo
group is that those are people who have
decided they're going to spend a decent
chunk of that time doing doing
engineering work um I liked that it made
it a fun place to spend two
years yeah know the I feel like the LG
cohort definitely has a very busy
experience for sure but man they you
know I'm not jealous of them uh yeah
anyone else would like to kind of talk
about why they ch slan
yeah I'll I'll go ahead and um you know
specifically for me you know the the the
appeal was the Sloan fellows program um
you know I joined the Navy when I was 19
I didn't go to college beforehand I did
my undergrad online while I was um while
I was working as a
seal which which what really wasn't a
fun thing to do and I knew that I wanted
the full-time experience and uh really
what this uh offered me there's really
nothing like it out there uh was an
opportunity to to study at a top MBA
program and to do the full-time
experience um without being out of the
workforce for two years um part of that
is just the opportunity cost with
associated with having a family needing
to you know provide for them but also
you know I'm also in in the in the
program already in my 40s and I'm ready
to get out and and and and start a new
career so uh for me you know it was um
really a
no-brainer no yeah that's that's
awesome uh yeah to Andrew's point for me
it was definitely fit I realized in my
intro I didn't even tell you guys what I
did in the n in the military but I was
in the uh Navy for eight years I did uh
was a Navy nuclear surface Ware officer
so um for me I wanted to leverage you
know I was a math major undergrad uh did
the new filler thing but uh I wasn't
sure that engineering was something I
actually wanted to do like forever um
and so but the MIT MBA you know had kind
of the balance of I would even say a
balance because it's not even
necessarily like a curriculum thing but
it's more of like the people who go to
MIT typically have some sort of
association with being technically
profession I mean it's literally in the
name and so for me that was like
something important um to kind of like
focus on and and and be able to use
moving forward even if I didn't do the
lgo program um also even know from
Montana I'm a huge post of Celtics fan
so that was like a second second huge
point for
me yeah that's
great um yeah I'll say for me I think it
came down to three things the first was
I was really interested in the lgo
program totally candidly I didn't get in
and while I was bummed by that what's
really neat about Sloan is you can still
take a lot of classes from other um
disciplines and so I was still able to
take a lot of the engineering classes
that I was really interested in even
though I wasn't in the lgo program so
that was um that was huge for me and
that was really that that really swayed
my decision I think my second Point here
is just I had a very specific interest
um I did a lot of supply chain and
humanitarian assistance in the army and
that's something that Sloan actually and
MIT generally they have an ecosystem
that does a lot of research and support
into that so after hearing that I was
like wow this really just seems like a
natural fit and then I think third to
just cap it off and Echo what everyone
says the conversations that I was having
with people just it felt like this was
going to be a place where I could Thrive
like it sounded like it was going to be
challenging but you form really strong
connections and I think I would just
suggest maybe don't overthink it and
just go with what feels like like where
do you think you're going to fit in and
and where do you think you're going to
be able to be the most successful and
get the most
support no yeah Valle that's that's such
a good point too and I think that's the
one thing that I didn't know coming into
MIT is that you could actually take
courses at other you know programs and
I'm I'm currently in a course to AI
machine learning for engineering design
getting my ass kicked next to phds and
graduate students but you know it's it's
it's been really a amazing to be in the
classroom as these amazing people and
learn so definitely if anyone needs to
challenge thems it's definitely one way
to do it and then uh Chris you wanna
wrap us up here yeah yeah I'll do my
best to close out and I I'll lay out my
three reasons um I think for me one was
the the technical aspects I kind of came
in knowing that I wanted to make the
switch to product management so it kind
of made me think about okay what schools
to me based on my back background being
a liberal arts major beforehand and
having some you know military military
experiences would best position me to
get a role in and in product dur in Tech
and Sloan was like at the top of the
list um I also I think I also had Square
this with saying like if you're applying
to Sloan you're probably applying to
more than one school and if you get into
Sloan you're probably gonna get into
more than one of the school so it CES
down to a choice right um and the choice
for me was made
immediately after uh I did uh admitted
students weekend where I stayed with the
president of the Vets Club who actually
was my friend from
Roc um who I met when I was deployed in
Iraq and he's like apply and it just it
felt like the right place to be um and
so that was one of the big reasons for
me and um yeah I mean I just I can't
speak highly enough about the quality
and the the the the Brilliance that
people bring to MIT and it's just it it
was astounding so that again of seed the
deal for
me oh yeah Chris it's definitely echoing
all that you said and you know I'm I'm
definitely gonna miss this you know
place next year um and then Chris I I'll
come back to you on like and you kind of
alluded to the community at slan but you
know if you had to describe that in a
sentence and then during your time there
like how did you get plugged in you know
into that Community you know whether
that was through clubs or different
ORS yeah yeah um I think the this the
classic saying about SLO SLO helping
slon um so it is very common and I don't
know almost expected when I went into my
Microsoft interview for this my summer
internship I found out everyone every we
all know where we're interviewing and I
just gave the questions to the next
person that I just so they know hey this
is what they've been asking so just kind
of lean in on some of these things from
your experiences and that's normal to me
and that that was completely fine so
it's it's not a competitive environment
at all and that's what I really enjoyed
it was mostly about helping each other
um but things that I got involved in um
one of the things that I wanted to
prioritize was building black
relationships um at sloom so I decided
to become um the treasurer for the black
business Students Association and that
was important to me uh to give back to
the black community not just uh for in
at Sloan but for the Institute because
we all work together um to create our
the black community uh which um is which
was growing uh which was fantastic to be
a part
of that's
awesome Justin you want you w to jump in
here as one of the
of the Vets Club yeah um I was actually
going to be part of my answer so what
are the uh wait was there a first part
of the question as well that I that I
missed involvement no yeah it was mainly
just like you know in a sentence if you
could kind of describe the community at
Sloan oh yeah Chris nailed it so I don't
need to expand on that
um uh yeah and then in terms of things I
got involved in my first year I did the
Sports analytics conference uh like
actually worked on it second year I
volunteered recommend the ladder
um and then one of the things I did not
expect to get as involved in uh and as
Will William just mentioned is the vet
club uh I was not expecting to be as
like involved in that uh you know one of
the things I think a lot of veterans do
and some and some do uh and it's totally
fine is they go to this you know they go
to this new this a new chapter of your
life and you know you may want to keep
as close Ties on you know this past
chapter you're now leaving um but I
found the you know that that Community
was even more uh you know I connected
with them so much better overall right
than some of your classmates not that
any of those other connections are bad
it's just it's so much easier and fluid
to connect with other vets because you
have similar backgrounds or you know um
you know you might be looking into
similar things and you just have so many
other things in common with them uh and
so yeah that was probably for me
ended up becoming like one of the most
important groups for me and yeah
obviously I became a co-president my
second year so uh obviously enjoyed it
enough um but yeah that was probably the
biggest one and then yeah joining like I
joined a couple hackathons that's where
you really start to see like the true
genius of a lot of your classmates I
think I just realize like oh yeah the
guy can actually use Excel out a mouse
like it's pretty crazy uh stuff like
that um you know that I thought was
really really uh kind of
rewarding yeah I know for sure and then
Justin you want uh you know you
mentioned the sports uh analytics
conference is that is is that a big
conference or you know does that
generate a lot of attention yeah yeah
yeah Sports anal Le conference is huge
for those who don't know um it's I think
there's like 70 students a year 70 75
students a year that work on it um and
we do it in conjunction with Daryl Mor
darl Mory and
Jess I remember last name but um yeah I
did like the marketing I was on the
Marketing Group um yeah it's just it's a
really really big event and you yeah you
don't realize it until you like go uh
and just all you know subber jig retic
all these like random people are just
like walking around you know like normal
people um and it is very cool that
recommend attending even if you don't
work on it or trying to
attend yeah Justin thanks for sharing
and and then Mike you want to kind of
you know I'd love to hear kind of your
experience you know being being a slone
fellow and because kind of
how yeah yeah absolutely um you know the
community is is really diverse um at
Sloan um for example the the snba
program uh itself is is 75%
International um so having been in the
military for as long as I have been and
having you know I've had the opportunity
to work with teams and and folks from
all over the world um you know I really
appreciated that um but but at the same
time it's really a small community um
and and I think it was mentioned before
or it was mentioned about the impostor
syndrome um I I I think you know it's
obviously in full force it's MIT no one
thinks they're smart enough to be there
uh including myself but I think that's
what really connects us all um in some
ways it kind of level sets um us and
when we all realize that um you know I
people open up and become more
vulnerable and and that's where the real
relationships are built and um so yeah
if you know the community itself's just
very tight very um you know um very
diverse and appreciative of of people
with different perspectives and
backgrounds even Within Myself you know
myself being you know uh or or the the
veterans in general you know you have
you have look at the panel here we have
like we come from all walks of life you
know in the military and so it's not
just you know different Moss's it's it's
officers it's enlisted um it really you
know it's really representative of of
more um during my time um I'll kind of
go back to what I was saying before you
know the one-year program is fantastic
it's um it's not easy trying to cram uh
two years worth of credits into one year
um and and again being where I lived um
it it's one of my biggest
regrets is not being more involved I was
in the entrepreneurship throughout
acquisition club which I thought was
really great um I had involvement with
the veterans Club as well um but I I
would say that you know one of my
biggest regrets was not getting more
involved on thing in things on campus I
was I was almost taking my coursework
too seriously and um you know I I was I
was focused on trying to get to school
you know before anybody else because I
out of necessity had to beat traffic and
you know I would I had my routine and
and before I knew it uh the year was
over so um you know I I was involved in
things but but certainly if I could
offer anybody advice it would be to to
Really you know take advantage of of all
the things that are on campus I mean the
cours work's important but but there's
so many more things and so you know that
you can take advantage of and that you
should take advantage of um that you
don't want to let that pass you
by no definitely thanks Mike for that
and then hey Andrew can you talk about
you know the I feel like the lgo's have
a have a community within the you know
the or can you kind of like talk about
that a little bit sure yeah so to
squeeze uh the engineering degree credit
requirements in with the MBA credit
requirements over two years uh we start
our uh class early so we come in there
may uh and then we have all of the first
summer
uh doing what we call the lgo core a
bunch of operations engineering Focus
classes the fall We join the rest of the
slown community uh after getting our
butts kicked all summer you know nice
good military kind of team uh and then
we have a couple of uh trips out to
different manufacturing operation sites
uh during the program as well as an
internship and a thesis that um we all
kind of uh not collaborate on our thesis
but be doing at the same time so that
builds that Community inside the
community because you get to know these
people first and uh then you get to go
Branch out and meet people who are
working on a lot of other things and
from a lot of different backgrounds um
and it's the best of both worlds I loved
it
um you also get a chance to go and meet
the engineering community and go take
classes with folks in The Graduate
School of Engineering which is uh a
chance to learn a lot a chance to dip
your feet in a bunch of different things
and a chance every now and then to watch
like a 17-year-old ASA test that you
struggle to get a 60 on which you know
kudos to them because they're probably
gonna you know cure cancer and I I I
want them to be
challenged no yeah definitely that's
that's awesome and then
Valerie yeah I so I was doing the um
stainability
certificate so I was pretty involved
with some of the sustainable clubs um
one comes to mind we do a pretty pretty
big sustainability Summit every year so
I was pretty involved with that I also
mentioned earlier that one of the
reasons I was interested in Sloan was
because of um sort of
humanitarian um Logistics and supply
chain and there is a club at Sloan the
Sloan entrepreneurs for International
Development so that was really
fascinating I got to work um
unfortunately it was during Co otherwise
I think we would have been able to
travel but that um gave me a ton of
exposure to um entrepreneurs overseas
and in a completely different context
from which um I was familiar um but
honestly one of the ones one of the
experiences I look back most fondly on
is I'm a big skier and we have a really
big ski club we go on a lot of trips um
and I think uh that that's one of my
favorite memories that and um as sort of
Will and Justin I was also so involved
pretty involved with the Vets Community
um I I think it's really important to
have a lot of um more female
representation in um female veteran
representation so I spent a lot of time
um sort of like mentoring and reviewing
um in assisting with admissions for the
Vets Club um but yes overall you're the
issue is you're gonna have too many
things to get involved in um so like I
said good luck figuring out what to
do no yeah that's feel like
the if you can figure out how to say no
quicker that's kind of the you know the
magic there
um Valerie I have a question uh here for
you and you obvious for the rest of the
group as well I
think everyone a lot of people who apply
to NBA programs you know like Mike
mentioned you know we have impostor
syndrome but I think sometimes as
veterans we are like oh man like we
didn't come from a business background
like we not a consultant or or like a
banker and sometimes maybe we feel even
more inadequate compared to our
classmates so would love to hear your
your experiences on how you know the
veteran and military background how they
help shape discussions and and decisions
you know whether that's in group
projects or case studies
Etc yeah know it's a great
question you know I think the value that
a lot of veterans bring is leadership
experience and I think it's one thing to
keep in mind as you know as applicants
you're thinking about crafting your
narrative that something that is really
distinctive about military applicants is
the exposure and the experience that you
have managing teams and that's something
that your classmates will really value
as well because a lot of them have come
from very diverse backgrounds but not
many of them have led organizations at
sort of the level and the positions that
you all will have so while it does feel
like often how are you here and are you
doing and what can you contribute you
really you do have a lot of experience
that is really valuable and people want
to hear about it so I think it's worth
remembering that while your experience
is different it is just as valuable and
people will want to hear about it um I
think the other thing to remember as
well and this is something that I still
have to remind myself but just because
you may not feel like you are qualified
or that you should be there don't self-
select out like have someone tell you no
don't tell yourself no because you know
I think this often happens with with
military applicants is is maybe you just
feel like you don't have the relevant
background or you're not really sure how
to craft your narrative but like I
implore you have someone tell you no
don't don't self- selck out because um
like we have really special and
important experiences that need to be
shared and Sloan really values that and
I think that it's important to make sure
that you're giving yourself a shot at
anywhere you want to go
yeah know that that was a awesome
response yeah if anyone would like to
take it back off that and have any
opinions I'll I'll I'll Echo what
Valerie said I I took a semester class
on power negotiation which I loved and
one of the lessons from it was the
answer is always no un let you ask so
ask apply um but I'll also Echo the uh
piece about leadership it's it's give
and take right like um you can give your
classmates a lot of examples of tangible
leadership of like ethically challenging
situations you have navigated through uh
and your classmates are going to be
Future Leaders of corporate America
there there's going to be CEOs from your
class right they're going to have huge
amounts of of power in the real world um
you have a chance to shape their ethical
decision making for the better that's
really cool that's the the give I think
the take is um I mean I didn't know what
Revenue was uh my accounting test kind
of proved that to me but when that
happened right there was a uh you know
an accountant in my core team who was
more than happy to explain that to me
and teach me
so that's something that I think the
military prepared you all for is if you
don't know what you're doing like you
are ready to admit that and go ask and
get help and learn it uh so that is um
that's the superpower to tackling ult
things to learning to trying hard
classes all the things that slan is that
you succeed at because you're willing to
go work in a
Dean yeah know
it's yeah it's just a different
experience we that we bring to Sloan
yeah and then Justin yeah
just kind of like another Nuance on on
what they've said but one of the and
it's been it was asked in the chat um as
well but the like at least and this is
this was my experience but the way
respect and like curiosity from my
classmates about what I had done in the
military far surpassed anything I
expected um you know I expected most
people to like not really care or maybe
you know on the impostor side of things
like yeah you're just a vet you don't
you've never done any of the things
we've done um or you know you're coming
in from like a basis of much a much
lower like knowledge basis than I have
you know or something like that it was
the exact opposite I thought and I'm
sure this is true in a lot of other NBA
programs but I was actually really blown
away at like oh no people care about
this people care about what I have to
say about you know this example of some
yeah to Andrew's Point like ethical
leadership question I had to answer um
they don't just tolerate it they like
actively seek it out and I think that
was something that um really surprised
me and you know made me feel better in
that imposter concept right because like
I do have something to bring here or I
have some experience that is valuable to
my core team to my ocean to this
particular class discussion or whatever
the case would
be yeah I know that's that's awesome and
and uh I want to set aside some time for
some open Q&A it looks like there's some
questions from Rachel one of the
classes uh one of the her questions was
you know what class was the most
memorable or kind of helpful you know
that helped you throughout your career
and uh Chris would would love to hear
what what your thoughts are on
this um yeah yeah happy to elaborate so
I said
op um and I so op is our class called
organizational processes uh we take it
during our first semester as a part of
core um the class
covers um how organizations function and
work and
uh it's really a series of case studies
on culture on uh how to design a company
you know what's your or organizational
chart um how is power distributed
there's so many different things it goes
into um what I think was important about
that and I think how I related with
veterans is that like there was a
particular case we did Mount Everest I
don't know if you guys remember that the
high stakes Mount Everest case um where
the Vets kind of just took over because
you know it's it's it's a case about um
uh having to make tough decisions to
save people's lives and we were
explaining how through the military
experience how we kind of did the same
thing and how decisions should be made
within a company and how they were made
on Mount Everest so I thought that was
great yeah and I've used that all of
that uh what I've learned in the actual
workplace um very very important stuff
to kind of take with you I open my
casebook every now and then like if I
have a rough employee I'm like a what do
I need to do how do I change the culture
so it's it's great
stuff yeah Mike any uh classes from your
your year here that's
memorable yeah I'd have to say um
healthc Care lab so I actually there was
a there was a um semester that I went
heavy on the health care classes because
that interested me and and I wanted to
to learn more and um you know I was part
of a team um our project involved
working um with an outpatient clinic at
a major Hospital in downtown Boston um
and we really got to use some of our um
some of the the the uh experience and
coursework that we had learned modeling
in during operations management and we
got to apply it to a real world
situation um that was pretty cool um to
actually see that in action but part of
it um was also because um it was a
situation where
um and this is to kind of go back on
what we were talking about before with
leadership and and you don't you don't
really value the leadership experience
that you bring um when you realize that
that you have a lot more experience than
other people and I ended up um
ultimately stepping into not because I
wanted to but because we needed it um
into a project management role and and
it was important for me because it gave
me
confidence um you know to know that I
could take the skills that I had learned
in the military
um and apply them in in a you know to a
essentially a private sector
um um uh situation and be successful so
so you know it was it was uh important
from from both the you know perspective
of of being able to use what what I had
learned um to solve actual real world
problems but also it was a big
confidence booster for me as well yeah
know and you know that's the big thing
about MIT you know that action learning
Labs where you can actually do and learn
which is
amazing for Justin and Valerie um a
question for you and you know I'm
reading this and I'm chuckling
um when you initially applied to Sloan
you
know and you had a plan on what you
thought you wanted to do coming into you
know NBA like did that change post MBA
and just you know if you want to give
some broader you know at least anecdotal
evidence as well from you saw amongst
your your cohort as
well yeah I can
start so I work in consulting which is a
very you know Common sort of post MBA
role that was not initially my plan I
think it is something that a lot of
veterans end up doing uh because a lot
of people view it as sort of like an MBA
2.0 like you go and you learn a lot of
skills and then you are in this kind of
very structured company where you can
then apply those across a wide range of
Industries um so it that did not sort of
align with my initial plan I thought I'd
be doing a little bit more um in sort of
humanitarian International
work what I would say is and what I
would just highly highly recommend is to
spend the time learning in talking to
people about all of the different career
options like this is something that I
did not do enough and I think that it is
like this is part of I mean this is
truly the reason you're going is even if
you have a very clear picture of what
you're doing you're given this sort of
like Halo as a student where you can
reach out to anyone you can talk to
anyone you can LinkedIn DM I mean it's
really I would encourage you all to take
the time to really reflect and be
intentional about what you want your
life to look like post business school
because it can look like a lot of things
and and and and and it's all positive
but it's like you need to be in control
of what you want it to look like and how
you want it to turn out and so I
I I I think that it could be
intimidating to some but I think if you
can reframe it as it's really exciting
two years to figure out what the heck
you want to do with the rest of your
life and you are in no better position
to have all of the resources to to help
you figure that
out um yeah I mentioned it in the uh
like my typed answer but one of the cool
things about Sal is they actually don't
ask you that question
um like other schools do and I think
that's a really unique aspect because
you're going to find you know to the
anecdotal thing will mention like most
of your class friends don't have any
idea what they want to do either um you
know everyone just
seemingly um makes up some sort of path
that they should be on and then tells
all the schools that that's what they
want to do for me that was like I wrote
everything as if I wanted to be a banker
um because for like a brief moment in
time I did uh and you know I just kind
of had to pick one learned as much as I
could about it to explain it interviews
and things like that and then I got to
school and I immediately shifted to
Consulting um and then could not Echo
Valerie's Point more like take the time
to like actually evaluate things even if
you know the the vetsa consulting or
vets the even banking pipeline is like
really well kind of fraud like do
evaluate other things like I'm not doing
consulting now and I will tell you like
from getting the hey you're graduating
in June 2023 but we're not going to
start you until January
2024 so having like eight months of like
oh what am I going to do uh you know and
I was like I honestly don't even know
what like I want to do it all I just
wanted to go do consulting which was the
intent the intent was to like figure it
out there but I could have used the two
years of my NBA to spend more time doing
exactly that um and I'm super happy like
doing what I'm doing now uh just kind of
lefted out to be honest um
and so yeah like use the use the
resources of both being a student and
people being willing to open their doors
and talk to you or answer their phone
and talk to you um as well as like you
know if for those of you who do end up
at MIT like getting to use the MIT
ecosystem to also do the expiration on
that side um and yeah that's like yeah I
could not recommend that more because I
did not do a good job of that uh you
know and I've yeah I would have actually
made better probably networking I would
like you know one of the things about
NBA r two years to network I would have
had a better Network in my current
industry had I actually spent more time
evaluating my industry while at my NBA
um and so that would have been a really
it's been awesome already but like it
would have been
a no Justin that's awesome thanks for
sharing that and for Andrew before we
hand it over back to Terrell we got some
questions here for you so I think
there's a a Common Thread of people
asking
like how was the lgo workload like how
did you manage that personally like you
know what were your kind of techniques
and you know just truly bluntly how how
was it um the second part to that is you
know did you have to have a lot of Prior
technical experience like did you focus
in Ai and in undergrad and I think the
third part is you know if I want to be
an entrepreneur and I want to create a
company should I be going lgo route to
be closer to Engineers or should I be
going the full-time uh NBA
route good questions um maybe the last
one I'll give a very simple answer uh if
you are doing lgo you spending a lot of
time on engineering classes which is
time you can't be spending on a startup
so just from time management you might
not want to do it uh the second one
about technical experience undergrad I
did mechanical engineering that was
mostly heat transfer Statics um Dynamics
I coded a bit I liked it but I it was
not a CS undergrad um I did mechanical
engineering at lgo uh and the really
cool thing about that uh is that they I
didn't have to apply to CS because I
didn't think I'd get in and I was still
able to take a bunch of AI classes
because they're pretty loose on the
credit requirements for mechanical
engineering
um I wish I had taken some even harder
classes I strayed away from and in true
military fashion if you are doing
something with a buddy uh you will
probably get through it and I took that
approach to those classes and it was
fine um learned a lot made even better
friendships by trying to do some really
hard things together uh and
then one more question oh yeah and then
um terms of just managing the course
load uh you I think I said it before but
you spend more time on engineering
classwork than your peers you spend more
time on just class work than your peers
uh
and
that's that's a choice you make when you
go into the program but you still get to
choose how you spend the rest of your
time and you get to choose how much
effort you put into your classes um
classes are pretty easy to pass they're
hard to do well in and as a graduate
student uh you should be mature enough
to choose what it is that you want to
get out of those classes and focus on
that right and that was a little
different from undergrad where I think I
just tried to go and learn what the
syllabus was everything on the syllabus
you get to choose you have a little more
flexibility um you should use that
wisely to prioritize uh social life
clubs exploring career opportunities all
the things that MIT gives you you're in
control that's what's cool about
it awesome thank you guys yeah seriously
thank you again so much you guys come
from such incredible backgrounds and
it's great to hear from you guys again
and you guys definitely B out some
experience on all these prospective
students who hopefully you know we'll
all see in Cambridge sometime soon