Good morning. My name is Stephen Palmer.
I am with MIT's Office of Corporate
Relations and I'm honored to kick off
today's event.
Um, the next generation of global
communications isn't just about faster,
smarter relation. Uh, sorry, let me
start again.
The next generation of global
communications isn't just about faster
connections.
It's about smarter relationships between
people, machines, and data.
We're entering an era where networks
will sense, predict, and adapt in real
time, where connectivity becomes
contextaware.
This shift means the internet will no
longer be a static infrastructure we
use, but dynamic and one that learns
from us and about us.
The same networks that can bring fun and
frivolity will bring precision
agriculture to rural Africa. Real-time
tele medicine to remote villages,
situational awareness the military will
um will use while also amplifying
misinformation
or entrenching digital inequality.
The next decade will test our just not
our engineering skills but our wisdom,
our ability to build systems that are
technically brilliant and socially
resilient.
And yet the future of global
communications won't be defined by any
single technology.
It'll be shaped by the quality of
collaboration.
That's something I'll come back to
later. Between the people in this room,
industry, academia, and startup
ecosystems.
We're moving toward networks that are
intelligent, adaptive, and deeply
intertwined with human behavior both
quantitatively and qualitatively.
systems that not only connect devices
but mediate trust, privacy, and
opportunity across every corner of the
world.
Understanding the challenges and
opportunities that lie ahead requires
both perspectives.
Academia and our startup founders bring
the long view and the curiosity to
explore what's possible, while industry
brings the urgency, the scale, and the
practical insight
into how innovations take root in
society.
When these worlds engage meaningfully,
we don't just make the internet faster
and safer, we make it wiser. We build an
infrastructure that reflects not just
what technology can do, but what
humanity needs it to do.
I'm leaving MIT in a few days for
another opportunity. And someone asked
me recently, what have you learned over
the last decade?
After a few months moments of
introspection, I stole a line from our
former colleague Randle Wright and said
the power of discourse between the type
of people in this room.
So I'm defining discourse as discussion
and debate. We should not shy away from
speaking to people with different views
as it is the only way that we better
understand the opportunities and
challenges that lie ahead. I've
witnessed cutting edge research in the
internet of things when that was a a
term. Uh digitization, AI, sustainable
steel making processes, fast and
inexpensive medical diagnostic tools,
imaging of a black hole, the creation of
high temperature superconducting
electromagnets
and an instrument to produce oxygen on
the Mars the size of a lunchbox.
All these inventions, innovations
require scientific inquiry and rigor,
discussion, investment, validation.
Think that five stakeholder model. I
urge all of you to leverage this
platform that is corporate relations to
further your research, development, and
commercialization of technology that
will shape the way we live. Thank you.
[applause]
Now, it's my pleasure to introduce Dr.
Dr. David Clark, senior research
scientist at the MIT Computer Science
and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory.
For over five decades, David has been
one of the key architects behind the
internet as we know it. From his early
work shaping the protocols that
connected the world's first networks to
his ongoing research at the intersection
of technology, economics, and human
behavior, his insights have continually
helped redefine how we think about
connectivity and innovation. Today,
he'll take us on a journey through the
internet's evolution from days of
mainframes to today's world of
broadband, mobile, and things, and share
what he's learned about the forces, both
technical and human, that truly drive
progression.