Okay, up next is Yuan Bolohan, vice
president of strategy and marketing at
well.inc, a digital health company using
AI and behavioral science to help
employees make smarter health decisions.
Yuan will describe how Wells app helps
employees navigate their wellness
offerings, drawing on insights from the
gaming world to enhance health outcomes.
He'll also share details of their
research collaboration which with HSI
which uses health analytics to improve
engagement. Yuan, the mic is yours.
>> Great. Thanks for the introduction, Jim.
Um, as Jim mentioned, I'm Yuan. I'm the
vice president of strategy at Well, and
uh we're based in Boston, North
Carolina. So, fortunately, I'm just a
stones throw from the MIT Sloan team. I
get to swing by from time to time. And
that's what we'll be talking a little
bit about today. uh our collaboration
with the MIT team and a bit more of a
background on our platform and our our
goals with the collaboration.
So to dive in, one of the core questions
that we're often faced in healthcare
navigation and wellness is why is
engagement so elusive? Knowledge is
available. It's plentiful. Um access has
expanded. And yet many people,
especially those who can benefit the
most from these types of solutions, are
not engaging. Behaviors aren't changing.
And even if they do start, often that
engagement isn't sustained. Ultimately,
people want to follow the path of least
resistance. And that's really what we
have to identify is how to better inform
that path. So if we were to break down
the problem, we can think about
traditional versus modern consumer
engagement solutions. On the traditional
healthcare and benefits side, what do we
generally see? It's often limited
interactions. These are brief and
infrequent, um, often confusing. Adults
are seeing providers about one to three
times per year and almost half of
employees don't actually even understand
their benefits despite the overwhelming
majority stating that benefits are very
important to them in their employment
decisions. Uh we al we also see limited
continuity. Some of those episodic and
transactional relationships with
providers and the these can often feel
generic uh irrelevant and inconsistent
with results being often delayed um no
regular check-ins along the way and a
lot of friction throughout the process.
This can often lead to frustration. So
from this perspective, it's really no
wonder that engagement is is low and and
users and members are reluctant to
engage. On the flip side, if we looked
at modern consumer engagement platforms,
uh think mobile apps, games, um you
know, social media, this often has high
frequency sustained engagement, 11,000
minutes a year. And for those of us who
didn't go to MIT, that's 180 hours um
every single year that they're engaging.
And this approach is really informed by
consumer science. It flips the script on
these traditional models. Um
interactions are personalized, they're
timely, they're relevant, they're
persistent, and really engaging. Um
rather than frustrating, they actually
generate excitement and are actively
enjoyable. Um for people who very few
people get giddy about going to a
doctor's appointment, but they might
light up when they achieve a milestone
on their app or are rewarded for it. So
the tools are there and really that's
why we believe in a trusted always on
personalized whole health partner
something that will meet members where
they are in their health journey and
focuses on personalization at scale
accessible guidance for the individual
um while continuing to offer the
credibility of clinical rigor and the
convenience of a mobile app. Um
important in this is choice architecture
which should be designed to be
convenient, attractive and normative
where engagement is a positive and
considered the social standard much like
what Joe was mentioning a moment ago and
throughout this process it's important
to make members feel cared for and
valued at the individual level. That
individual personalized experience is
very important. So that's easier said
than done. How do we actually go about
doing this? Um and at the core of our
platform is behavioral economics
principles. Consumer science is really
in our DNA from day one. Uh we start
with the data. What do we know about a
me a member uh from their data feeds,
claims, pharmacy data, wearables, and
then what can we learn about them as
they engage from their various patterns,
what archetypes they might fall into,
and then the self-reported information
that they share with us along the way.
At each step of our users journeys, uh
we aim to increase personalization. We
want to learn more about the members and
then play back those learnings to them
uh from their health needs and goals to
identifying opportunities and barriers
that they might face to achieving their
best health. And this ultimately enables
us to achieve this N of one with a
bespoke experience that's relevant,
timely, and enjoyable for each
individual on the platform.
From there, our platform connects with
members in ways that resonate with their
preferences. So with each touch point
we're learning about the individual
member. We're building a profile and
then we're able to dynamically improve
their experience accordingly. Uh we have
a content of library that's thousands of
actions spanning over a hundred
different clinical pathways to find the
most relevant interventions which
importantly um the member has a high
propensity to engage with. It's not good
enough to serve content that they are
not interested in participating with. Um
and a lot of that is thanks to our uh
clinical team that's building all this
um from the ground up. Um I think
several of which are on this call. So
thanks to shout out to them and thank
you. Um and without with all this on the
engagement journey, we really are
looking to overcome inertia. Um
identifying and addressing the barriers
acting on negative signals as well as
positive ones. And that's a key part of
successful engagement flywheel is
understanding what made a member engage
but then also what makes a member not
engage to find those barriers and help
address them. Um we also complement our
digital experience with a human touch
with our well guides. So this helps add
that personal touch where members can be
free to chat, learn, they can ask
questions and share insights that
potentially programmatic flows alone
wouldn't necessarily cover. Um, all of
this is spurred with a responsive
incentive system that offers relevant,
dynamic, meaningful rewards for members.
And this will come as no surprise to
you, but this classic Q action reward
feedback loop really does move the
needle and perpetuates engagement and
this flywheel effect. Um, every action
is tied to an incentive. Every incentive
offers a timely reward and each member
finds that rewards that resonate with
them. Um, those rewards are purposefully
architected to be attainable,
motivating, and engaging. Um, they can
be tangible. Think premium reductions
for long-term motivation or gift cards
for immediate gratification. Um,
sometimes even things like sweep stakes,
auctions, challenges, which gify the
experience. Um, these also have the
added benefit of breaking down the risk
of trying new behav behaviors and
habits. If you think about exercise,
diet, visiting a provider, those pose
potential risks for for users and
creating an incentive helps to overcome
that inertial hump. Um, other users
might find more motivation from
intangible rewards. Think streaks and
leaderboards and badges. And we've seen
really strong reactions on our platform
to social cues and team challenges where
people feel like they're doing something
that's normative. That's just the social
standard and the default. Um ultimately
rewarded engagement
drives habit formation which supports
health improvement and cost savings over
the long run.
Um we've seen the results of this kind
of structure and uh engagement is
important because it reflects success of
other metrics as well. Think of it in
some ways as a proxy, a temperature
check. Uh people engage when they're
satisfied. We've achieved an 85 plus
NPS, 4.9 out of five stars in the app
store. Members are um completing an
almost an action a day on average with
25% being active every single day. And
in turn, this has increased utilization
of benefits um with our uh employer uh
partners um leading to over a 6%
decrease in costs compared to control
groups. And that's before we even
account for things like reduced
absenteeism, productivity gains, and
turnover reductions.
So with this kind of success, we want to
keep the momentum going and we have to
ask ourselves, how do we keep
innovating? What's the next step? And
that's where MIT and the Sloan
partnership comes in. Um MIT is
collaborating with us on several
research topics related to our our model
and our platform. Um, and the focus of
this is really the trifecta of driving
engagement, improving member health, and
reducing costs. Uh, we're using our
highfrequency engagement to develop
these predictive models that create
health achievement scores,
hospitalization predictions, and cost
savings estimates. Uh, imagine being
able to normalize health engagement at
the individual level, contextualize this
achievement score alongside peers within
an employer and benchmark across an
industry in this standardized way. That
goes back to the earlier point about
social cues and team challenges that
really motivates engagement at the
individual level. And importantly, these
aren't just purely academic exercises.
Um after our data exploration and build
phase where we are right now uh we'll be
deploying these algorithms in real world
tests uh with the intention of measuring
impact and um on engagement and health
improvement and we'll ultimately be
publishing these findings um from these
projects.
Throughout this process the MIT team has
been really great partners and we're
excited to deepen our partnership
through projects like this in the
future. Um, our hope is that through our
collaboration, we can advance our
mission of being the world's most
effective partner in advancing our
members health. And, uh, with that, um,
if you're interested, please feel free
to reach out to us at getwell.co.
Um, thanks and happy to answer any
questions.
>> Great. Thank Thank you. That's a lot of
information in a short time, so uh, for
folks who just want to know more, they
should definitely get in touch with you.
Um and I do have one question here about
um personalizing is key but the question
asker is concerned how does that how to
do that according to the European data
protection standards. Um person says I
would never do this only from the chance
of being hacked. So h how do you how do
you respond to that? Well, um there's
certainly a robust team of of
clinicians, data security officers, uh
data scientists, all all working to
ensure that we're compliant with all the
equivalent like SOCK 2, HIPPA, ISO
27,0001 uh requirements. And there's
certainly plenty of regulation, which
makes a lot of the innovation
challenging because you want to be
compliant and protect your your members.
But at the same time, one piece that we
really uh focused on is we don't just
ingest claims and then start um
surfacing content to individuals because
we want to avoid the creepy factor. We
want them to feel very comfortable and
trusted um as our as our health
navigation and wellness partner. Um and
so what we'll often do is wait until a
member has actually reported information
themselves, what they feel comfortable
sharing with us, and then it's just
incumbent upon us to be compliant with
data security provisions. And um we're
primarily based in the US right now, but
we do have a global presence. And so
making sure that we can maintain those
data security frameworks, but then
really um play back to the member things
that they've already shared with us that
also helps validate what we've seen with
other data feeds, claims, wearables, um
pharmacy, etc. Um and what's really
impressive about that, something that
was surprising to me was how much
members are willing to share once you
gain their trust, once they feel like
you're really on their team. Uh we've
had people chat about everything from,
you know, mental health issues,
alcoholism. Um we had people sharing
with us that they were pregnant and they
didn't know who to turn to in in various
situations about how to provide, you
know, formula and food for their family.
And so it often goes beyond just
immediate health uh concerns, but
actually starts talking about what is
the financial stressors, what are the
social situations that they're in, what
what are they stressing out about work,
and this is an employer sponsored
program for them. So we we really feel
like that trusted relationship is really
key and then of course compliance having
the team to back it up.
>> Great. Thank you. Um and one more
question is um and and I'm not sure if
you can answer this. Um are there
opportunities for personal measurement
of body capabilities such as integrating
with sensors?
>> Yeah, so we do have integrations with
things like Apple Health Kit and Google
Health. Um we also have various
wearables integrations. So, we're able
to collect some of those endpoints and
integrate into our platform. We have
these check-ins that you can either um
passively ingest with these wearable
integrations or you can actually
self-report. So, maybe you have your own
tools, you have things that you don't
want to link or can't link to our
platform. Um, but then you can actually
just self-report. Here's my blood
pressure, here's my, you know, resting
heart rate, here's my um exercise, diet,
sleep patterns. And so being able to
collect all those biometric uh data
points and then integrate them into our
algorithm which generally on average I
think for the members processes
something like 25,000 data points we
have about every member to really
surface the right content and the right
um interventions to to every individual
so that they have that personalized
relevant experience.
>> Right. Well thank you so much. I think
our time is up at this point. We have a
couple more speakers. So uh again for
the audience you know contact um Yuan or
contact us and we'll be happy to pass
along further questions.
>> Great. Thank you.