but now uh moving right along and I I
feel like this presentation is going to
bring us from kind of the beginning uh
where John was talking about the
workforce challenges that have bubbled
up from the past uh on to to Bruce and
Chris talking about the challenges of
the present and then uh FZ who's who's
working on such interesting uh problems
in in Ai and generative AI where I feel
like it's it's more futur looking and
and more perspective so um really
excited to hear your uh presentation Fez
and and look forward to what you have to
share
thanks for the invitation Ben um so hi
everyone I'm I'm I'll be talking about
AI for advanced design and first let's
start with what do we mean by Design
because design can mean a lot of
different things for different people
and when we focus on AI for design we
are mostly thinking about engineering
design where you are creating a plan for
either a product systems or Services
based on technical or functional
requirements this can mean you are
designing simple Parts simple assemblies
more complex assemblies or systems and
different networks now when we are
thinking about design like let's take
the case of the car design process and
if I talk to a car designer designer and
think about how they design products
there is the usual standard design
process where they would understand the
user Personnel they would do some
competitor analysis understand the
market basically identify the key design
parameters come up with some conceptual
sketches then do uh refined design make
a 3D CAD model send it to their
simulation friends and they might run
some cfd simulation they might send it
for a wind tanel test and so on and
there is research showing that 70% of
the life cycle costs of a product are
determined by the decisions that the
designers are taking in the early stage
of design so this is what we think the
design process is and what we read about
but in reality the process is much more
complex I mean in the car industry they
call it there is the devil cycle where
you go back and forth between the sketch
and the cad and the simulation and
entire process if we think about the car
design process it can take up to 5 years
uh going from a concept to a market so
this leads to insufficient exploration
there is difficulty meeting constraints
there's also time in efficienc loss and
finally there's a lot of communication
burden but overall when we think about
it right like there is a challenge that
we see where people do not explore
enough because the cost of exploration
is very high and this is something which
we think a lot about and the key
motivation for us is how can AI enable
humans to create better designs faster
and and this is really uh critical for
many sectors we are talking about
whether we are it's Aerospace Automotive
energy shipping uh there's many sectors
where the design process applies to
different products now today's for talk
will focus a lot around generative AI
which has the potential to help with
some of this Mission let's start with
definitions like generative AI is a
field of AI that uses algorithms to
create new and original content such as
text image video and other media this
was written by a generative AI model
having said that most of us associate
generative AI with large language models
but generative AI is much broader than
that and it has been around for a while
from Models like mixtures of goian
variational autoencoders Gans diffusion
models topic models and so
on but at a fundamental level right when
you think about what generative AI is
doing this is a one-dimensional data and
you can see a histogram and effectively
a generative AI model is trying to fit a
curve to this distribution it's learning
the distrib ution that we want to
approximate now it's much easier to see
it in onedimensional data but imagine if
you have a single image that is thousand
by, pixels there is a million
distributions that you're running
simultaneously now what has changed like
why are we talking about it a lot a lot
now I think this is a good example of I
just in 2021 if I want to generate an
image of a group of elephants walking in
muddy water this is one of the best text
to image models 2022 2023 2024 and now
we are also seeing like models which can
generate entire videos based on text
problem so there is a lot of development
that has happened and disruption in
anything which is multimedia related but
the key thing we have been thought
thinking about is what happens in
engineering how does this impact in
engineering and this is a really
important question because at a
fundamental level all these models are
doing are they are learning a very
complex data dri distribution and if
they can learn complex distribution from
text and image modalities can they
actually learn something about
engineering and we see that the
applications have been there across
different sectors from healthcare
industry financial retail and media
entertainment there is uh there is uh
claims that Char GPT and models like CH
GPT will change the word make jobs more
efficient however what we have found
from
Explorations and our thought processes
that the current AI models are not there
yet however there is a lot of promise
that we are seeing in the way design and
Manufacturing is done and I think we are
thinking a lot about at MIT on how can
we create the Next Generation AI model
that can enable us to reshape design and
Manufacturing so why are we talking
about next generation and I think the
key thing is where what are the
fundamental challenges with current
generative a model and a big thing which
I'll be talking about today is this idea
around Precision which is can we come up
with generative AI models that are
designed to produce highly accurate and
specific outputs that meet precise
requirements and this is really
important for engineering because uh we
have to come up with designs that work
and that function in the real
world there are other challenges also I
think in the interest of time I'll only
talk about a few challenges so let's
start with precision ative AI models and
in Precision generative AI models the
first problem I want to talk about is
this idea of structure design using
something called topology
optimization these days a few companies
are offering products around how to do
generative design or topology
optimization and the key idea there is
that you are given some domain and you
you are given some requirements in this
case you have some boundary conditions
like loads you want to use less material
so I want a structure which is stiff but
it's also using less material and there
are solvers like solid isotropic
material and with penalization method
that have existed for some time and I
think they are great for the tasks that
they do having said that they might get
stuck in local Optima and they may be
computationally expensive for expensive
for complex problems so what we think
about is can generative AI amortise the
cost of optimization so can we actually
come up with generative AI models that
can use experience to help these
optimization models do much
better so this is exactly how we think
about is like can we can we create a
data set of problems and once we train a
model given a new problem can it
instantly generate a lot of designs all
right so first let what have other
people done we look at some of the
existing methods and what we found is
that there is some promise in generative
AI models being able to generate
Solutions
so each row you have the ground truth
and then the top row is what generative
AI models come up with but having said
that we see that there's a lot of things
that cannot be manufactured there's
manufacturability defects and they're
not working as well as we would have
expected especially in conditions that
are out of
distribution the key reason here is that
almost all the generative AI models that
are uh imported from computer science
they are often focused on statistical
similarity which is they try to mimic
the data that they have seen But in
engineering it's really important that
you have to understand the performance
and the physics and that creates a big
issue because things that look similar
might all perform very differently so we
looked at we started looking at this
problem again the same idea with where
if you're using a model like di there
are diffusion models which are extremely
powerful generative models and we
started thinking about can these
generative models create 2D structures
and the first naive way of doing this
was like okay you can take a large
collection of designs that are optimal
and we can train a diffusion model to
solve this problem now this does not
work very well for the reasons that I
outlined so the next thing we started
thinking about is what how can we bake
in the engineering so we started looking
at what are our goals our goals were
things like compliance floating material
as a as a proxy for manufacturing and
once we can do that we came up with
methods that can incorporate this
regressor and the classifier performance
within the generative model using
something called guidance and the good
thing about guidance is that maybe you
train your diffusion model today 6
months down the line you change your go
goals you say now I don't care about
compliance I care about thermal
performance you can just change this
module and it's very modular so you can
get new new designs without retraining
from scratch so we do this and we saw
that already we got a lot of improvement
in compared to the previous generative
models so this is a huge Improvement
eight times less error in compliance 11
times more uh better manufacturable
designs as measured by floating material
but we were not satisfied this was like
looking very promising we couldn't see
that many cases it would actually come
up with new designs but we wanted it to
be actually even better we wanted it to
think on like how can we really bake in
the optimization ation performance and
what we started doing was we started
looking at this idea of learning not
only from the best designs but learning
from the trajectory of optimization that
has been obtained and this was critical
because the models can now learn from
nonoptimal designs and this is uh in the
newps paper we showed how you can take
this and bake it into the diffusion
model trajectory by saying the diffusion
model trajectory tries to mimic the
optimization trajectory and what we saw
this led to huge Improvement both in
terms of speed being faster and also
Precision having said that and I think
one of the key things that we liked
about this was the diversity of designs
so in any given row you can see that for
the same problem it can almost instantly
generate many designs that are diverse
for the same problem so it was capturing
some notion of
multimodality having said that we wanted
to go 3D so we started looking at more
complex problems and also multi-domain
so now we are training not on a single
domain but multiple domains and came up
with these ideas around how can you
represent these problems in a in a
domain agnostic way so for that you have
to come up with simulation
representations that can be represented
as Point Cloud invariant Point clouds
and also the geometry as fields and by
doing that we found that this really
accelerated the process now we have
2,000 times faster than Sim which was
the previous Baseline and this speed up
which is 2,000 times comes up up at a
cost but that cost is only 32% accuracy
so given this now you can actually go
and do 3D almost instantaneous design
where you can change the loads and see
what the designs change and if you want
even better performance you can add it
to the optimization five steps or 10
steps and you can get even better
performance with 15 times faster so the
general key message is I think what we
have found is the generative
optimization architectures can really
help amortise the cost of optimization
so things we were already solving but
now we can solve it much faster and much
better and there is uh they are often
domain agnostics so we've talked about
topology optimization with DARPA we are
looking at multimaterial design we are
looking at car design the the same
Concepts can really apply across
different
domains and in the future we expect a
lot of foundation models to support
inverse design tasks now this has been
applied for aircraft design and ship
design where we have looked at different
types of challenges for each field like
data bias and lack of data and I think
the key idea is that u in general the
challenge is we don't have a lot of data
a lack of public data set so if you are
an organization thinking about
generative AI what you should really
think about is how can I invest in data
and create data sets that are useful and
and we have looked at it from many
perspectives we have created large data
sets and made them public I think there
is a lot of Promise around synthetic
data also we've looked at the idea of
negative data where you train the models
not just on good designs but also on bad
designs and finally transferring
Knowledge from other data domains so
this is just some examples of data sets
from cars and turbo Machinery to
topology optimization and ships that we
have created and again the the methods
can broadly apply to many other areas
that are of interest and we have looked
at many of them
ourselves with that I want to change
gears and talk more about design
co-pilots and in the first case we were
talking about accelerating optimization
now we want to talk about helping humans
like if this is problems where normally
people don't use AI at all for Designing
and we looked at the problem of bicycle
design we we teamed up with a company
called bik cat which where frame
Builders from across the world uh go and
create CAD models for bikes and we
started looking at how do you design
bikes for people and it's not just about
engineering performance the cfd or the
structural performance it's also about
things like the ergonomics or kind of
subjective performances like a user may
say I want a futuristic black cyberpunk
style road racing bicycle how do you
optimize for
this so the first way we looked at this
is we started thinking about it as uh
can I actually help a designer
autocomplete a design so imagine that
you go on a CAD software and you design
half the bicycle and you say you know
what can you just autocomplete my entire
design based on things that you already
know so we looked at this problem as a
problem of missing data from an Excel
sheet so if you have an Excel sheet and
your design can be written down in an
Excel sheet imagine there are some
columns that are missing so these are
the values that are missing we can train
a new type of generative model which can
fill in these values of in the Excel
sheet and it doesn't give you a single
value it gives you a lot of values and
this key idea is around this diffusion
imputation model which we work with
Toyota research and we have a Patent
filed for it and we can see that these
diffusion imputation models can really
fill in many values which are diverse so
they don't give you a single option they
give you many options and given an
incomplete CAD model it can complete the
cad model in many ways and it can really
show that it not only comes up with good
designs good ways to Auto comp the
design but it also comes up with diverse
ways so you get a lot of diversity and
also you get low error rates which is
quite promising in helping humans also
we have looked at the idea of the whatif
scenario so if you are a bike designer
and you want to design a bike maybe you
ask can I what if my bike look like this
other bike I found on the internet but
maybe I also want this my bike to be a
futuristic black cyberpunk style and I
also want engineering performance so how
can you really optimize in this
multimodel space where you have all
these competing objectives and we have
looked at that the current AI models
enable you to do it by combining
optimization and machine learning
representations and the key idea is to
think of it as a counterfactual search
question where you're asking can I
actually make a minimum amount of change
to make the designs really useful but
also meet the new desired requirement so
you want to reduce the weight you want
it to be ergonomic and you want it to be
futuristic but broadly speaking like I
think a general question for that comes
up is we are seeing all these Vision
language models large language models
and can they actually help engineering
designers and we did a study on many
many problems in design process from
Material selection understanding
sketches to problems around
manufacturability assessment and a
general takeaway was that for early
stage designs these models are actually
quite good they can really understand
many of the abstract designs which were
surprising we can manufacture some of
the products based on a design sketch
but for more complex designs that
require Precision the models are not
there yet so in this case you're trying
to come up with a cad model with a hole
which is not through and the models
really struggle to do that very well and
this is an area of improvement where the
AI community and the the researchers
should think about how can we increase
Precision on creating better models
and again the key highlight is that we
want to come up with designs that are
suitable for much higher complexity so
we are looking at complexity of not just
chairs and tables but multiple component
designs that we want to aim for to
really help designers and when doing
this like when we are creating these
Foundation large language models
ourselves I think a key question we
asked was can we even evaluate our
designs so given a new AI model like
let's let's say we come up with a new
vision language model how do we really
know it's better and to do that we
started working with the MIT Motorsports
team and we started looking at this idea
that for any designer a large chunk of
their time and a large chunk of their
frustration is based on reading a huge
design rule book and understanding
what's in there so we looked at a design
rule book and we said Can these
generative AI models understand design
rule books and answer questions about
CAD model so for this we created uh
Benchmark problems so based on our
actual mit's Motorsports CAD models and
questions from it we created these
questions on like can you extract the
rules can you actually find what are the
dimensions in this drawing can you tell
me if this rule is being followed or not
in this design and so on and across the
board I think a common message was that
the current generative AI models are not
there yet for very complex
uh questions in this although there is a
lot of promise that we are seeing with
new models performing much better than
the previous
models so that's more about helping
humans so we talked about assisting
optimization helping humans and I want
to wrap up with a third part around much
complex design spaces and these are
problems in very large discrete and
continuous spaces we use the example of
mechanical linkage mechanism design so
for folks who are
new to linkage mechanism design if you
see a robot walking or if you looking at
your car wipers or many other like
robotic designs these are often driven
by mechanical linkages so in this
diagram this is my student trying to
come up with a linkage design where they
have a motor which is running and they
have to come up with what is connected
to what and where those positions are
and their goal is this path following
problem where they want the mechanism to
tr to come up with a
path that can be exactly like this now
this is considered more of an art and
science than science and the reason is
it's extremely hard problem so this is
commercial softwares and how they
perform for a test curve and you can see
that they come up with some solutions
but they're not as good and the reason
is that first many models are restricted
to four bars and six bars but more
importantly this problem is both
discrete and continuous like positions
are continuous connections are discrete
which makes the machine learning problem
extremely hard so we started with
thinking about this problem by creating
a solver which was thousand times faster
than the previous best solver and we
with that we could create a data set of
100 million planer mechanisms and these
are all random mechanisms they don't do
anything particularly well they're just
creating and working uh creating shapes
that are random so this is a billion
curves that we can create with that and
then the interesting part came first is
without doing any machine learning we
can just retrieve from that data set and
you can come up with very fast methods
to do retrieval and that already often
performs better than commercial
softwares but more importantly we came
up with this idea of multimodal learning
where you have to think about different
modalities of design so in this case the
linkage mechanism is a graph and the
curves or the performance are these
curves and this can be incomplete or
complete sketches and you can learn
these joint representations for this
using this idea of contrastive learning
which is the model which is the same uh
similar idea which are driving many of
the text to image models and by doing
that we can uh learn joint
representations and there's there's more
on how to actually come up with better
graph models specialized for these
engineering problems happy to discuss
that in
Q&A but the key idea is that we by doing
these uh joint representations now we
can solve this problem much much faster
so something that took 45 minutes now we
we can take a a few seconds and we can
also come up with mechanisms which are
extremely precise so now we are taking 2
minutes compared to 40 minutes the new
version is actually 20 seconds and we
also have much less error compared to
state-of-the Art so these are existing
designs existing targets that people
have published and we can come up with
designs almost instantaneously we also
found that we can comp generate designs
which are much more complex than
anything that existed and in some sense
this gave us a notion of automated
Discovery because before this it was not
very clear on what is possible with a
single motor so what are the mechanisms
that you can actually create and the
reason why it was not clear is so this
is just my student drawing like showing
you live on how to come up with
Solutions very fast I'll Skip and like
you can see that the method comes up
within a few seconds and you can
download the cad model and look at the
3D structure of the
design but the key idea the key
Challenge on why this is hard is because
of it's a comp mixed integer problem and
if I only give you the entire mechanism
and fix everything except one node
everything in red is where this node
will not work so if even if you change
it slightly and you have some tolerance
errors the mechanism will lock and it
will not work so this shows that for
very complex engineering problems it
almost becomes um a problem of Discovery
because we don't know which problems can
be solved and we can also build in a lot
of manufacturability constraint so that
it can be manufactured it doesn't
collide with each other and the key
ideas again this is a general model so
you can apply it for molecule Design
Network system design and so on so with
that I think I give a quick overview of
helping with Precision generative AI
helping humans and also solving problems
that were not possible to solve to a
large extent ENT uh very quickly but we
are thinking about how the Next
Generation a AI will look like and a lot
of it boils down to of course extremely
high quality data raw internet data
sensor data how can we capture existing
worker knowledge capture physics and
first principles as well as the rules
and designs that humans have come up and
they are extremely good for most
problems and the next generation is also
thinking about how can we really come up
with tools that can help people without
requiring a lot of training so with that
like we think about creating methods
that can create better designs faster
accelerating scientific discovery and
enabling design
democratization and I think when I think
about design democratization I really
want to emphasize this because I've
looked at this idea of kinematic design
and I asked chat GPT to come up with a
poem and it comes up with robotic arms
with joints of fine move with Grace in a
straight line and in some sense it's
democratizing language for people who
are not necessarily trained to write
poems similarly we can do art where you
create a doodle and it can create very
good art for this my question often is
like how can we as a community take
design and think about design
democratization so this is from a
industry problem that I worked on and
can we just ask Alexa to design a stand
for my Railway wagon and it can come up
with CAD models generate preferences
simulate performance and make sure it
can be manufactured with that I'm happy
to discuss questions thank you and if
you are in the area happy to chat about
these
topics so so thank you very much indeed
for like thoroughly engaging talk there
I think really kind of gets to this uh
question of how the new approaches to a
completely changing our relationship
with knowledge of various forms how it's
going to be kind of encapsulate into the
the tools and processes and platforms
that that we all use