so I'm going to take a card at
random um RI rising sea levels uh
flooding yes ha beautiful hi I'm Ali
Leslie and I'm representing uh climate
change charades uh for the day of
climate for MIT basically this activity
is meant to be a bridging activity for
classroom teachers to be able to go from
their lessons on what is happening to
our planet before they start actually
talking about Solutions oil breathing
breathing or carbon dioxide uh
oh at the end of the activity students
are going to take all of the vocab that
they reviewed and create a concept map
um allowing them to link these ideas to
one another to recognize that climate
change is a very very big very very
complex issue and it's not a direct
cause and effect relationship and now
we're going to investigate real
solutions to these real problems for
more MIT moments from MIT open learning
like subscribe or follow