Let's uh let's go back so I want to say
before actually I tell you the just a
high level idea of the other proof I
just want to I got a very good question
in the break so I want to emphasize I
want to answer it kind of for the class
so the question was the following when I
talked about interactive proof I said
sound is half and if you want more than
half do
repetition do par repetition and now
when I talked about argument I went to
negligible so the question is why don't
I do have like why why is the change of
language of terminology why for proofs I
said half and you can do repetition and
for argument I immediately said no I
have I want it to be
negligible and the answer is actually
pretty weird the answer is that for
proofs we can do we can repeat if you
have an interactive proof and you repeat
it in parallel let's say Lambda times
then the soundus goes down exponentially
with Lambda if it was half now it's one
over two to the Lambda like you would
expect with arguments that's not
necessarily the
case once we go to the land of crypto
Things become a little weird and it's
not the case that any argument if you
repeat it in parallel Lambda times if
you had complete if you had sound is
half now it sound is one over two to the
like one over two to the Lambda that's
not the case
anymore now we have examples that show
this is not the case that actually
sounds doesn't go down but these
examples are very contrived very very
contrived it's not natural uh a
arguments my guess is for every for any
natural argument however you Define
natural soundness probably does go down
exponentially when you repeat in
parallel now but but it's not true all
the time so actually we you know this
par repetition you can't kind of rely on
it now we can do sequential repetition
and then the soundness does go down if
you do once and then you do the so you
do the interactive argument once you
were done do it again done do it again
do it l the times and accept if and only
if all of them accept then sound this
does go
uh exponentially like you would expect
however then you increase the number of
rounds by Lambda so you went from
constant maybe to non-constant so
there's a price so it's not like for
free you like in interactive proof
setting it's like for free just repeat
in parallel it's like for free here be
now the round complexity changes it's
not very free anymore so we don't we
that's why we put here
negligible that that just explain the
change of of uh kind kind of language
why here we chose negligible before we
chose half or 1/3 2/3 whatever the
conent didn't matter because you can
amplify a okay questions before I go
back to say a few words about So the
plan for the lesson now we have left I
want to say a few words about the Barak
proof called they call the universal
arguments uh that paper and then we'll
move on to construct hash function
yeah okay so let me just say a few words
I don't want to go into details about
the the but just to tell you kind of the
the H of idea this proof what it did
what it tried to do is to to say look if
there are no collisions I'm going to
construct an entire PCP I'm going to try
as much as I can and now got a
contradiction because there's no PCP and
hence I I get I conclude that there was
a hatch function but for this I needed
to construct an entire PCP and therefore
run in time that's proportional to the
to the PCP size okay instead the pro
what they say they say let's look at
each kind of query separately so in
other words let the PCP let's say has
length M okay let's look at uh the PCP
at location I and I asked the following
query the following question here's the
question they ask
in location I if I run the
PCP I have a cheating prover here yeah
if I run him twice or many times where
all the times have location I in there
one ey not all the PCP for a certain
index ey let me run the PCP verif let me
give the cheating
prover like
a a Randomness from the verifier so that
the queries include index I and let me
take many of them
is there a collision in I or is all the
time he answers in the same way that's
the question so for an index ey does he
always answer with the same bit or the
assuming he answers correctly if he
doesn't answer correctly if he's
rejected then we throw it out but all
the time that he answers correctly when
ask location I does he answer
consistently with the same bit or
not now if if he's answered if he if if
not if some prob probability I don't
know Epsilon he answers with zero and
probility Epsilon he answers was one we
found a
collision that's then we're happy if not
we didn't find the Collision okay now
they ask so let's call an index like uh
good if there's no collisions on that
index like then he behaved like the
prover behaved well he behaved good so
for every index I ask is it good in the
analysis I don't yet I don't have an
adversary yet I'm just saying look
there's a cheating prover for every
index let's look at the
probability that when he answers
correctly he answers always the with the
same bit let's say we the same bit with
probability what condition an answer or
he answers correctly but with two
different answers with probability like
greater than I don't know Epsilon to the
third whatever some some function of
Epsilon that's not
negligible so it's good if if he doesn't
do that he he answers consistently
almost always and it's bad if he answers
inconsistently probability at least I
don't know Epson to the
third and now what they say is many it
must be that many eyes are bad if almost
all the eyes are good like a a
significant fraction of the eyes must be
bad namely there should be collisions on
them why if almost all of them were good
then on the good ones I will in the okay
so first they say many of the indexes I
must be bad once you establish that then
you just you break collisions by
choosing a random eye hope it's bad and
you're
done you you're not doing many eyes like
we did just one random eye with some
good probability or bad if it's bad you
found a collision
done okay but one can say maybe there's
maybe the number of bad is like one over
n maybe you need to repeat it n times
until you find a bad one
so they say no the number of V need to
be like polinomial and
like at least abs like non negligible in
Lambda why if almost all of them were
kind of good where there's no Collision
like every then you can okay and these
reconstruct the PCP and the good ones do
the same
a kind of idea of reconstructing the PCP
but only in the good
indices then they show that if you have
enough good indices then you'll be
accept with non
probability so there there must be
enough kind of bad indices indices that
the cheating prover kind of answers
inconsistently once you have that then
now now once you establish that in your
head that you you we understand that now
here's the adversary just chooses one
random eye he runs the PCP verifier
twice kind of he generates two two
Randomness that generates two kind of
fresh index set that include I so they
had one assumption that they needed
about the PCP that given I it is easy to
cons to find R so that the PCP verifier
and input R output to set that includes
I and turns out all pcps we know or all
pcps I know satisfied this property so
you know that's kind of it turns out
it's a natural property it's easy given
I to find randomness kind of uh true
Randomness that is generates this a set
of queries conditioned on I being in in
that
set once you can do that then he choses
two RS Randomness that have i in the set
and hope for collision and then you can
argue that you get collision with nonnal
probability because non-n fraction of
them are bad and the bad ones are
defined so that when you choose two
random kind of invocation that include I
you find a collision so they found a
collision so they just did it kind of
the difference is they did it index by
index they said does he find Collision I
have a cheating Pro P star does he find
the Collision on index one does he find
a collision on this two this is an
analysis once and then they establish he
must find collisions at many indices and
now they're ready to break the Collision
the hash function they just chose the
random ey and break by running the
cheating Pro
twice so so it's just a more uh
efficient way of of breaking it instead
of the prover running in time n their
prover instead of the adversary running
in time n because they in this proof we
ran the cheating prover end times or
size of the PCP times at least times one
over Epsilon they run it only security
parameter times divided by Epsilon with
polinomial overhead but inde pend ofen
is the point
AR
Universal okay good you're asking what
why what what what's that related to
Universal yeah because uh the the reason
they call Universal is because uh yeah I
guess the fact that it doesn't depend on
N It's really because they they talked
about like the universal language that
has like a tring machine x and t and
it's in the language of there a witness
for that this twing machine runs in time
te and they didn't want things to blow
up with t like they want to this
Universal did so they want kind of one
hash function that works for this
language and T now is given in binary in
this language so how can you have one
hash Function One universal hash family
and that's why the name
Universal yeah what is it name the paper
the name of the paper is universal
arguments I I'll I'll link to it in in
the website yeah it's not there yet I
only linked mikali but I'll link to it
it's a good it's a really nice it's a
really really nice especially the
overview explains it very nicely it
explains the proof I gave here and it
explains their proof in a very nice kind
of way so I'll add a
link okay uh any any other
questions before we go and construct the
hash function so let
[Applause]
me this is what I want to construct but
any questions before we go ahead and
construct
it okay let's do
it okay so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to first
construct a hash
function that's not quite what I want
but it's going to be a building block to
get what I want and this hash function
first it doesn't have a local
opening so it doesn't satisfy that and
second it's not even goes from 01 star
to 01 to the Lambda which is what I want
it actually goes from 01 to Lambda to 01
to the Lambda so it just shrinks a
little bit it doesn't shrink like by an
arbitrary amount it just shrinks by a
factor of two that's it and it doesn't
have local opening so it's a bit of
pathetic uh but uh we'll do that first
and then we'll show how to use that to
get what we
want okay so the first so now we're
going to talk about Construction
so let me first show you a construction
based so all all of cryptography in
particular cry and hash functions are
based on assumptions an assumption that
some math problem is hard and uh we have
we know how to construct Collision
resistant hasch functions from a bunch
of assumptions many many assumptions I'm
going to show you one that's just very
simple and based on the discrete log
problem so the discrete log problem just
says that there's some group you can
think of zp star so uh everything
multiplication mod
P uh but in general there's a group such
that so this is the discrete
log uh
assumption this is what we're relying on
the hardness of this on the hardness of
this problem that says that given a
group a group
G of
order a number order meaning number of
elements let's say two to the Lambda so
it has like two to the Lambda elements
so I have like a you know a family of
groups and given a
generator G so so every element think of
multiplicative multiplicative groups
okay so any this group is like G to the
x uh so uh for every you know all the
group is of form G generates the entire
group the assumption is so uh given a
group of order so it's a finite group
with two to the Lambda elements so order
more or less to the lambas and the
assumption is that given a random given
G to the x for a random
X take a random X in the group like a in
the size of the
group given G to the X it's hard to find
X that's the Assumption so in other
words for
any po
Lambda adversary a the probability there
exists a NE ible
function the
probability that a a knows G and P the
then the and the group these are kind of
fixed okay the generator the group are
fixed he gets G to the X for a random
X and the probability that he can find X
is
negligible okay usually we think of
these groups as an element of the group
is described by so any group any element
of the group you can describe as a
element every uh for every H in G you
can think of H as being in 01 to the
Lambda you can describe it as kind of
efficiently in Lambda bits and just
think of zp star if you want as a you
know all the elements mod P with
multiplication mod P that's kind of an
example so this is the Assumption now
some groups this all some groups it
doesn't hold okay for example you can
think of it as in a group in the
additive group mod P this is false but
in the multiplicative group we believe
that it's true is it really true we
don't know we don't actually know we
believe it's true and we base
cryptography on this assumption okay so
we base cryptography on the fact that in
zp star in the if you take elements um
in the multiplicative group zp star mod
P then if I give you like a random you
know if you take a a generator of this
group and you raise it to the power of a
random element uh if I give you a random
element in the group essentially then
finding the discret log we believe is
hard yeah we know
like quantum's EAS good yeah so okay I
say we believe it's hard why we believe
it's
hard I have no idea I think the only the
only reason we believe it's hard is
because we don't know how to break it
that's really it because quantum
computers can break it there
subexponential algorithms like if and if
you you know if we didn't think we were
that smart we would have think it's easy
because every evidence we have is that
it's not that hard but because we don't
know how to break it and we think we're
pretty smart then we you know but no the
truth is really I have no evidence for
why this that why this problem is hard
the only evidence we have is that we
didn't succeed in breaking it there's no
other evidence like the fact that it can
be broken it can be broken pomal Time by
quantum computers
yeah and even classically we have
subexponential algorithms so we have
some non-trivial algorithms for doing it
like but uh a but not in polinomial time
the best algorithms like something like
time two to the end to the thir
something like
that so uh but this is the problem okay
so now let me go to the construction of
our hash function
so I'm going to fix a group of prime
order okay for the construction I'm
going to assume that I have a group of
prime
order I'm going to tell you how I find
the group in Prime order in a second but
think of a group that has number of
elements in the group as Prime so let
G be a
group of Prime
order which just means that the number
of elements in G is
prime that's all it means and now here's
my and now every element except for the
unit now is is a generator so it's easy
to find generators here and now here's
my hash function my hash
function um depends on G and H okay so
what's the key the key is a so there's a
Okay so so we have a generator G you can
think of G is fixed that's just a
generator if you want you can choose it
also randomly because any element is a
generator here H has a key so okay so
now the hash function so
gen and one to the Lambda this is like
sub Lambda what it does is it chooses
random H and
g a random element that's what it does
that's the key
okay so hash key is just H just the
random
element
eval okay so IAL takes his input before
we said IAL takes his input uh hash key
anyx any X now no now less so that's
what I'm saying it's not let me denote
the number of elements in G by Q now IAL
takes his input a hash key and X but now
X is not everything it's just in zq * zq
so it's it's bounded later we'll show
how to get everything but for now I'm
bounded okay it goes from zq to zq and
what it does uh it generates so so let
me call it x0 and
X1 because it has a pair and what it
does it gives you g to the x0 times
H to the
X1 in the group multiplication in the
group that's the hash function so this
is an element in
G okay this is the hash function now why
is it even shrinking because this is
kind of the the group has only Q
elements so it's like this is Q elements
and this is two Q elements like this
this is one out of Q and this is you
have one out you can think of G as like
uh embedded in like you can like think
of G as isomorphic to kind of uh you
know
zq you know you can so this you know if
if if you think of Q if you can think of
Q as like a in you know 0 one to the
Lambda then here you have two 01 like 0
one to the two
Lambda but let me actually make it more
concrete for you so it'll be just easy
to think about it cuz I said a generator
and let me just Prime let me just give
you the concrete example you can think
of look at zp star so just
multiplication mod P okay where p is a
safe Prime safe Prime I mean it's 2 Q +
one where Q is
prime okay there's a lot of safe primes
so it's easy there uh you know choose
one at random check if it's safe you can
check check primality and if you choose
enough times you'll hit a safe one
they're there uh there enough of them to
hit one with good probability okay and
now G is just going to be the set of
quadratic residus mod P so this is all
the kind of X
sared mod
P for X in like one up to P minus
one all the
squares okay how many squ squares are
there like half so z p star has P minus
one elements one up to P minus one and
half of them are square so the number of
quatic residus is p minus1 / 2 which is
exactly
Q so really one can think if you want to
be think of the Quad residue is mod
P okay that's
um so this great so now you can think of
this is all the quadratic residues this
is all the quadratic residus and uh
sorry so this sorry this isn't zq this
is zq this is quadratic residus mod P
and you can you can embed the quadratic
quadratic residus mod P very easily you
can kind of embed them in zq you can
represent each element here in zq how
take any quadratic residue look find the
two square roots so if you have X it's a
quad residue so look at plus minus
square root of x one of them is going to
be
smaller than Q one's going to be bigger
one's in the upper half one in the lower
half write the one that's in the lower
half that's kind of a way to express the
quadratic residues as zq the reason I'm
telling you that is because I want you
to think that you can this is you can
think of it as a hash function that goes
from zq * zq to
zq okay because you go from zq to zq to
quadratic residus mod P and then just
efficiently kind of convert this to the
square root which one the one that's
smaller the one that's between one and Q
and that's that that would be the output
it's you could it's you can go from one
to the other very efficiently so does a
way to represent the quadratic residue
so it doesn't really
matter okay and the reason I'm I'm
representing the quadratic residu is an
element in zq is just so you see that
it's really shrinking that you can see
okay I have from zq to zq from zq * zq
to zq that's my hash
function okay the fact that it goes from
zq to zq time zq to Q I'm later going to
use this fact to kind of increase the
the the domain to 0 one star okay but
before I increase the domain why is this
a hat
function so in other words why is it
what do I need from the hash function
well there's no opening here so it's not
local opening so this doesn't hold but I
want to make sure that uh it's Collision
resistant why is it Collision resistant
so I want to argue that I cannot open if
someone gave gives me if an adversary
gave me a uh
uh a value a hash value he cannot he
cannot open in two different
ways so let me actually try to argue
that you cannot open in two different
ways do it
here okay so
why suppose there's a cheating prover
that can open in two different ways then
I argue that I can break the discrete
log problem I can just use them to break
the discret log problem
why so let's say I get H I'm an
adversary there's this G and there's you
know uh and I got hash
key sorry I'm going to the discret log
so I got H which is supposed to
supposedly like G to the X I'm G to find
X okay here's how I find
X I got H I'm going to give this
adversary here the so if I can find a
collision so suppose
there exists a collision
finder let me call him B then I I
construct a that uses B to break the
discrete log how do I break the discret
log what he gets H he needs to find
X yeah he has G he gets the input H he
need to find the discret log of H how
does he find the discret log he goes to
the Collision finder let me write him as
a c for Collision it's better he goes to
the Collision finder and he tells me oh
here's your key hash key equals
H Now find the
Collision now we find the Collision it's
a V and two inputs so I don't know uh
um two he gives a V and two
openings so two inputs so let me call
one x0 X1 and the other x0 Prime X1
Prime such
that
a this is a pre-image and this is a
pre-image so G to the
x0 H to the X1 is equal to G to the x0
prime H to the X1 Prime that's a
collision now I can I claim if he gives
me this I can use this to find the
discrete log of H with respect to G how
I just what is this this is just gx0 -
x0 Prime equals H X1 Prime minus X1 I
just moved uh arithmetics and now g a h
is nothing but G to the x0 - x0 Prime
divided by X1 Prime -
X1 this is the discrete
log done
so what is the discret he gives me a
collision what is the discrete log of H
with respect to G it's just x0 - x0
Prime divided by X1 Prime minus
X1 now where did I use the fact that the
G remember I said g needs to be a prime
Order Group where did I use the fact
that it's a prime order because this you
compute this mod
Q mod the order of the group if it's not
a prime order it's not clear you can
divide not every element has an inverse
if you're not in a prime Order Group so
I want it to be in a prime order group
so that every element has an inverse now
another thing you need to make sure is
that one you can say wait X1 Prime may
be equal to X1 and then again you can't
you're out of luck but if this if X1 if
this if these are equal then these have
to be equal because if these are equal
means this is one and the only case
where G to the power is one if it's the
power of zero because it's a generator
any other element is not zero is not
one so if they're different if if these
two are different that's what a
collision means then X1 Prime must be
different from X1 and therefore we can
divide and we're
done so this is why this is the proof
that this is a collagen resistant
okay any any
questions yeah do you have a way to
sample
H during J do I have again a way to
simple H during the generation what do
you what do you mean to simp what do you
mean to just take H the element
without learning something about so H H
is just I choose it randomly from G the
the key generation the key generation
algorithm of the hash function H is just
a random element in the in the group so
if you use kind of this specific group
you choose zp star all the elements mod
P and where p is a safe Prime you make
sure p a safe Prime and the way you
choose H is a random quadratic residue
so I choose a random x and x squ is my H
so it's a the key gen algorithm is very
simple and note by the way here you can
indeed it's it's also random there's no
secret going back to the uh kilan mikali
protocol that the first message hashy
it's just random it's random uh quad
resid there's no secrets you can send
the randomness it's not uh there's no
secrets in the hashy or anything like
that it's a very very very simple
construction this is by the way known as
Pon commitment for those who studied
cryptography
um uh it also has some hiding properties
which are nice but we're not we only
care about Collision resistance here so
we don't care about
hiding any any qu any other questions
about why it's Collision resistant
about the
construction okay so let me just say by
the way as a side note uh these kind of
groups of Prim order in particular kind
of quadratic residues mod P uh where
pizza safe Prime is a very useful kind
of group we use it a lot in cryptography
uh a so it comes up in many many
Primitives we all working with groups of
primot is very comfortable and the
examples we have often is either quad
res mod P where p a primot group or
elliptic curves which is a whole
different
story okay so the ne oh yeah so all
order are isomorphic right they're yeah
so like the special thing is in the
actual structure of the group it's like
the representation of elements something
and the way it's like yeah like you
can't evenor to group definition like
you can't compute that exactly exactly
exactly yeah isomorphic is a is an
information theoretic term it's not
clear that you can efficiently go from
one to the other yeah exactly exactly
good good point yeah okay so uh if
there's no further questions let's just
go to the to show how to go a how to get
local how to uh go for from Collision
resistant to one with local opening so
okay this fell short in two ways first
this construction goes only from zq time
zq to zq it doesn't go from 0 one star
to zq Second there's no notion of local
opening which is also a problem so what
we're going to do now is we're going to
show actually a generic transformation
from any hash function that goes from zq
time zq to
zq with that's Collision resistant to
the one to to what we want okay so now
we're going to do the construction from
loc with local opening and arbitrary
domain and here is how it
goes okay so a
and this is from I'm going to assume I
have which is Gen and
eval like above but eval goes let's say
I said zq * zq to zq let me just write
it as 01 to the Lambda time 01 to the
Lambda to 01 to the Lambda I'm writing
it because that's how we usually write
it but if you want to think of zq zq zq
that's Al that's totally fine it's uh
because that that's what we saw it's
just um most constructions of hash go to
we think of it as 01 to the Lambda
that's why I write it this way but
everything I say you can replace 0 1 to
the Lambda with zq and it will work okay
so I have that I want to now get an
entire family of of hash functions from
like I want to make the domain much
bigger and I want to get local
openings so how do I do it actually I do
it in one shot okay I get the domain
bigger and get local opening at the same
time and here is the idea so I do it via
what's called Merkel hash it's idea by
Merkel it's really beautiful clever and
simple and here's what he does he says
look you want to Hash something if it's
less than two lamb bits long done you
have a hash use your hash but what if
it's longer if it's more than two Lambda
bits okay okay so do it iteratively what
does that mean take your
input let's say so I'm okay so sorry
first J so let me the Gen is exactly the
same as J the same
thingal is so I need to give these
algorithm Jal open and verify J is this
gen you have a gen for this algorithm
use this now you have a hash key what
about IAL IAL well if your input is
small smaller than two Lambda you can
use this algorithm you're done what if
it's
bigger so if it's bigger the idea is you
know if you have only so convert your
input to
blocks if you have only two blocks or
less you're done we have a eval
algorithm for you we're
good but what if you have let's say four
blocks what do you do so the idea is oh
don't worry apply eval to these two
so you have a hash key compute
eval with hash key and these two you get
a value comput
Val with hash key same hash key and
these
values now I don't want to open I don't
want to Output both of them that's two
Lambda I want to get Lambda okay so no
worries apply van
and this is your your
value now you're saying wait what I have
if I have more no worries you have two
more sure apply Val you have more apply
Val now you can apply
Val and you can apply
Val so just you know you can just apply
value Val Val and you're done that's
really the
algorithm now there's two problems with
the the okay what I I didn't tell the
entire story for two
reasons so first of all there's an issue
of how many blocks are there really so
usually what we do we say let's assume
that the number of blocks is two to the
L for some L just to make this tree
complete okay so usually what we say we
don't actually do X from 01 star we
assume that all the inputs are of size 2
to the L for some L now you're saying
wait but that's not the case oh with
padding you can make it the case so the
idea is given X always put like so you
want to do EV Val X don't do eval of X
put eval x aend with one and
zeros how many zeros as the minimum
amount that will give you size two to
the L
forl it increases the length of it yes
but only by by you know factor of two so
it's not that bad so now one what okay
good good good great so's like why am I
putting here
one exactly otherwise you don't know is
this part of X or so this you know so
now when you have padding you know all
this is padding until the one including
and this is the X so this is just to
make it kind of one to one great
question yes cause issues that if you
like take this tree and you Pat in this
way you were like very close but only
barely above the power like the entire
right hand side will be a ton of like
yeah you're right so here's the thing if
this is exactly a power of two exactly
I'm always going to add a one and depend
as so it's some like I shouldn't have
added a one but my algorithm is always
append the one and make it a power of
two so if it was original Power of Two I
unfortunately I had one now I'm stuck
need to add a bunch of zeros so all
these are going to be zeros yeah you has
that okay I guess like it just
seemed okay never mind maybe the rest
the construction will make it clear it's
you okay so there's there's another part
of the construction that's missing and
I'll tell you but let's uh there was
another question
or this not impct the okay good so so
the question will it impact the
correctness and the answer is it won't
impact the correctness if the eval
algorithm now so let me be clear on what
the eval algorithm is the eval algorithm
takes his input
X it adds a one and as the minimum
amount of zeros to get a power of
two once he has X that's the length is a
power of two like two to the L then he
does
IAL in a treewise
manner and now he's just going to have
one root the reason I made it because if
it's not a power of two then there's
kind of dangle Roots hanging hanging out
right and I don't want to deal with
these dangling Roots so I'm just going
to make it a power of two now what is
the output the output is the last hash
value usually we denote it by root
because it's the root of the tree so
often if you see hash you'll see they
denote that hash instead of V for Value
they denote it by
root but the output is not only root and
I think that goes back to maybe your
concern the output is not only root it's
also the depth of the tree
okay so the hash value so
eval given given hash key and x what it
does is one uh
compute let me call it X Prime which is
X One 0 like the padded this is of
length 2 to the L for some L then
to compute
root via
tree so you compute all these hash value
hash value hash value hash value hash
come all these hat until you get to the
root and
output
root and depth of the tree this is very
important I you have to Output the depth
if you don't output the depth then it's
easy to find collisions the reason it's
easy to find collisions is I can let's
say generate this
randomly compute comp and then I can
either open to these two say oh I just
hash to these or say I hash to
this
and you know it's it's a collision both
of them has the same value they're
different
sizes so without the depth one can argue
you can you cannot finding you cannot
find collisions of the same size of the
same length
but it's easy to find collisions for
inputs of differing
lengths by just that ATT that I said I'm
an adversary I'm going to choose a
random long input honestly compute the
root and then open either to this layer
say or open to this layer open to this
layer all them are going to be kind of
valid
openings so I found collisions once I
have the depth I can't do that anymore
because it won't correspond if I open
this
well it's it's it doesn't correspond to
this depth this is a depth one and I
I'll put it depth
yeah is that this is no longer
L good okay okay very good what you're
saying ah yeah you know you lied because
this root is of size
Lambda this depth can be actually even
bigger than
Lambda yeah you promise Lambda okay so
let me let me tell you how I deal with
it if
you okay this is a nitpicky I can make
it Lambda how do I make it Lambda you
know what I'm going to run here's my new
gen algorithm the Gen algorithm on input
one to the Lambda will run the original
gen algorithm with Lambda over
two and then this is a size Lambda over
two a root now is the size Lambda over
two so now have I have Lambda over too
spare to play and I can use it this for
the depth but actually you know what let
me make it simpler you know what if
you'll excuse me I'll write V to be two
Lambda make it two Lambda let me allow
myself here
[Applause]
slack can't the be good you're right
you're saying wait but the depth can be
unbounded so you know what if it's more
than two to the Lambda
sorry if the depth is more than
Lambda I will
output a you
know
fail the point is okay so
okay let's do two to the Lambda
here I always think of I always think of
everything the inputs are always at most
size two to the Lambda that's the truth
so just think of the input that we also
have correctness only for inputs of size
two to the Lambda like our guarantees
hold only for inputs of size two to the
Lambda so let's just think of it as t
two to the Lambda you're right if it's
not two to the Lambda I don't have any
guarantees so why even talk about more
than two to the
Lambda so I guess the way to think about
it you can handle any input length but
the security param the hash function
will grow with log the
the input
length so you're right you're right if
you want to use any Star you should
let's think of that always Bound by two
to the Lambda anyway we'll need it for
completeness we'll need it for soundness
we need it for everything so just assume
that it's two to the
Lambda
uhuh so you're saying you can Mark each
node but for what what's your purpose
for so we Mark
leaves that's one
uhhuh zero
okay oh you're thinking there's an
attack
no oh Sol solves solves which problem
the deps oh you're saying okay okay yeah
yeah yeah what you're saying is uh maybe
we can uh solve okay so you're saying
maybe we don't need to get the depth
here and instead what we can do is
you're saying the honest Pro the honest
person he will add zero to everything
here and he will add a one to everything
here
and yeah okay yeah so you need to make
sure one bit is probably not good
because uh I guess
my concern is if you're not this is what
I'm going to do if I'm honest but I'm
not honest so I'm I'm going to go ahead
with my original
crazy thing you know and of uh you know
you okay fine if you one I'll I'll put
here zero and I won't put ones I'm just
going to compute not without your tags
because I'm malicious and now when I
open maybe some of them are going to be
one and I'm
lucky you see what I mean are zero and
I'm lucky no but if you add different
tags for the you add tags of zero on the
very bottom row you also add tags of one
yeah but you're right okay but now I
don't do that's what I should do but I'm
malicious I don't do
that so what um what two inputs would
you give that give the
same so so I I mean if I'm allowed to
put one or not put one I'm always going
to put
zero oh okay okay sorry what you're
saying okay okay now I understand you're
saying if I want to open it this has to
be a one okay therefore okay now I
understand what you're saying okay got
it so you're saying this may solve the
problem
um it's a good
suggestion you
like he
yeah sorry I'm yes to increase the
length of block at each level by one
would get the exact same
thing the opening will be well the
opening will grow with the
depth like if
we're we need to have a hash function
which will allow us to walk in the this
is not a leaf intermediate thing so the
hash function needs to now take like one
bits in oneit level
two oh you're saying it will grow I see
presumably the is still like K to K goes
to K but in order to keep adding
additional pad so you're saying if you
pad here this will go to k+ one if it go
to Lambda plus one and then you add one
it'll go to Lambda plus two yeah so
you're just got LDA
plus can you I wonder if you can get
around this though don't to power don't
make it a complete tree make it like you
know it's a good question if you could
do it like with complete like without
blowing up full
completeness what the domain extension
have like Mir Dam construction can with
two Lambda plus two bits can still
shrink it that into like two and then do
right that's yeah yeah yeah you can prob
that's what I was saying you can go you
write that it grows but you can maybe
shrink a little bit and then continue
shrink a little bit and then
continue not have
open okay so we didn't talk about
opening yet
H look you gave really interesting idea
then I'm trying to think if I can make
it into pie something in the pie
[Music]
set okay I'll think about offline anyway
let's we have five minutes so let me
quickly talk about like how do you do
local opening and about Collision
resistance of this thing so this is so
first we managed to do domain extension
okay so now the domain can be up to two
to the Lambda and the hash value is just
Lambda plus Lambda because we assume
that the in size to the Lambda the depth
is the most
Lambda yeah so we're happy with the
size how do you open so let's say I want
to open to one point here I want to open
to this bit how how do I open to this BD
only well what I do is I identify the
block that it sits on okay so now I know
what I want to open is this I'm going to
open to this entire Block it's not it's
only Lambda bits so I can remember the
opening is poly Lambda bits I can allow
poly lamba bits in my opening so I'm
going to just open to the entire
block okay so I can give you the block
but how do you know it's the right
block so what I do I give you you know
what I'm going to give you the block and
The Sibling block that is needed to
compute the
parent so I'm going to give you both of
these now you can compute the parent and
then I'm going to give you the sibling
block that is needed to compute the
parent and then I'm going to give you
the sibling
block that is needed to compute the
parent so for every
layer I give you the sibling block that
you need to compute the parent so the
number of blocks I give you is like the
depth at each layer I give you a sibling
block so it's depth number of block each
block is size Lambda so I give you po
like Lambda squared
bits okay so this is the opening the
opening just contains the block of the
bit you want to open with all with the
sibling blocks of each layer The Sibling
blocks that of of the parent yeah the
The Sibling corresponding to the
parent all the way up how do you verify
it well so that's that's the opening so
the opening are all the kind of green
well this green you can on your own so
you don't give it but you know think of
it all the green a blocks
here how do you verify you just verify
you check you check that this these two
hash to this these two hash to this
these two hash to the root where the
root of the that's the hash value
so actually like this you don't need to
give because you can compute this you
don't need to give because you can
compute but this you need to give and
the point is you re you can Rec you can
ask the the verifier to recompute this
recompute this but at the end he needs
to make sure you consistent with the
root with the with the hash value that
he committed to you say you just need
the siblings you just need the siblings
but it doesn't matter yeah you can just
give the kind of one sibling you can
give D instead of 2D
that's the opening that's the
verification yeah how do you sure like
this opening doesn't like it's
consistent like it doesn't say one block
is different next time say open a
different block so oh okay there's a
so the the only thing I need to check is
Collision resistant I don't know what do
you mean by
consistent like give like a differ BL
next fine I can do whatever I want look
I can do whatever I
want like I can I can do whatever look
I'm cheat I'll I'll do whatever I want
whatever I can whatever I can do to get
and I get away with that's what I'm
going to do okay the question is I'm
what the honest Pro what the honest
prover should do like what the honest
the honest open algorithm he should give
all the correct blocks now you're saying
he won't what if he
doesn't so now I'm going to tell here's
what I want to argue look he may not I
don't know what he's giving okay all I
need to argue is Collision resistance I
mean first note
completeness correctness is I said we
get if you're honest you're going to be
accepted if you're honest you generate
this gigantic thing like you should have
you have the entire tree and when you
want to open this you actually give all
these everything should hash the hash is
good it computes correctly and you'll
get you'll accept with probility one
okay always that's not a problem what
you're concerned like wait okay I tell I
tell the cheating person who wants to
find collisions this is what you should
do give the opening you say he won't
give he won't give this he will give
this BL or who knows what he's going to
do who says he can give whatever he
wants so how do you know that this is
how do you know that this is Collision
resistance you're not
happy yeah yeah I was more um concerned
about like the soundness like the
soundness that we get from there like
yeah how how do we know like um he can't
like each time you query he just kind of
like for his proofs of those siing
blocks he can just construct them in
such a way that it ends up um at your Ro
I how do you make sure that he can't
just construct them so that you know
fir you you should be concerned so first
when you say sound is human Collision
resistant I wrote soundness but right
that's the yeah that's kind of thing
yeah and you're right you're saying how
do you know he givs he does whatever you
want he wants how do you know that at
the end of the day somehow he doesn't
man man maybe manages to mix Max and do
it and magically get to the root in two
different
ways so the answer is he can't actually
the only way he can generate two
different openings for the root like the
only way if you could generate two
different openings for this one block
and a different block with the valid
openings I argue I can find collisions
to the original hash function that I
started with
from like two Lambda to Lambda the
reigon why I'll find collisions we're
out of time so we'll have to do it next
week so Friday at same time next week
finally we have consecutive weeks