Whatever I've done, I've had to explore
through myself, through my own experience.
So creating my own path has been rewarding.
But has been challenging
also because you don't have
a straightforward line to follow.
I am from Coatzacoalcos, Veracruz, Mexico.
It's a coastal city
in the southeast of Mexico.
growing up there really changed me
or really put,
a stamp in my,
in my growing up. For example,
seeing all the inequalities that existed
shaped me in a way that I wanted to,
to help, to improve that.
I've always wanted to
and thought about being an entrepreneur.
the logic was you will create a company
that will do good and will help people.
I understood from the beginning
that in order to help, you need resources.
The way of being an entrepreneur was a way
of creating those resources. So I think
creating a company in my hometown
was important because I had the chance
to do something that could be meaningful
to the ecosystem and to the local economy
and be able to, in that sense,
try to help improve something.
I knew no women in my hometown
that did a master's degree in,
in an institution like MIT.
I couldn't relate myself
to someone that have been here
before that I could see myself in the future.
So I had to figure it out.
How to do it by myself.
And it took me some time.
My presence here, it's a privilege.
I would like that privilege
to be shared with other young women
and not so young women
that have the curiosity
to explore this path.
Your talent combined with your passion
are the best recipe to bloom
and to flourish in an ecosystem like this.