okay so let's start uh thank you
everyone for coming uh this is going to
be a advanced class on cryptography
those who do not have background on
cryptography it's okay it's not actually
hardcore cryptography this is actually a
class on the evolution of proofs in
computer science so this class is really
about proofs uh that's what we're going
to learn and kind of how kind of proofs
evolved with the years starting from
kind of the 80s mid 80s all the way to
today and how we think about proofs
differently today so this is uh what
this class is about actually before I I
go into kind of the content of the class
and what what I'm going to be teaching
first of all quick question how many
students here are not MIT students but
cross register students okay h a bunch
so you guys have access so I hope I made
the the website public it's on canvas uh
but now I think it should be public so
uh you know you should have access if
anyone has problems with accessing the
website just let me know I'll try to fix
it um so this class is meeting once a
week weekly from 1: to 4: p.m. uh in
terms of expectations or what uh so you
know the expectations that you'll enjoy
it I hope you will I think it's really
really beautiful material uh but beyond
having fun uh I want to ask uh I have uh
two uh kind of uh requirements from you
guys so one I want to have scribe notes
for the classes uh I I have written
notes I can give it to you uh to help
you out but uh so we have about actually
we we have 11 classes total in in this
class but uh we're going to have a bunch
of uh like one one day we're going to
have a guest lecture uh by odv who's in
he has a beautiful result he's going to
come here uh on October 6 and presented
to us so uh we won't H that won't need
to be described and then there one day
there's a crypto day which also won't
need to be described well uh there's
more anybody wants to
sit uh but for the rest we'll need
scribe notes I'm happy if you want to do
it in pairs uh to describe unless will
run out of people and then we'll need to
keep it for one uh so that's one
requirement and then I was told that I
need to do something more you know
that's not enough so we'll do a p set
sometime in the middle of the course
okay uh it won't be anything too
difficult it's mainly to make sure
you're on board uh but I really do
recommend that before class every time
before so here's a real homework okay uh
every time before you come to class in
the website there's reading I really
recommend you look at the reading and
try to read I so there's beautiful uh
survey by Justin Taylor uh there's a
link uh on the website uh the survey is
on proof system it's more of kind of the
applied side of proof system this is a
more Theory class but he does have
really beautifully written sections that
are very theoretical that I'm going to
link to uh so I recommend or I you can
think of it as informal homework before
class to do the reading I think it will
be very helpful to uh for understanding
this class and also after the you know
the lecture to look at the reading and I
think it'll be very very
helpful okay so uh any questions about
bureaucracy
stuff okay so let me tell you a little
bit more about about what the class is
actually about so you know proofs is
something that has been studied in
mathematics for thousands of years uh
and usually when people think about what
a proof is uh you know a proof you write
kind of line by line and you can verify
it kind of line by line to make sure the
proof is correct that's how you know
most people think of what a proof is
okay starting from the mid 80s in
computer science and particular Le in
cryptography the way we thought about
proofs changed started changing this is
uh came uh about because of the idea of
zero knowledge proof so there was a hope
to kind of construct proofs that reveal
no information about why the claim is
true and uh in around 85 uh godas M and
roov kind of constructed the first zero
knowledge proof by the way this class is
not about zero knowledge actually it's
not about crypto per se it's just about
kind of coming up with new proof systems
you have a
question um but they constructed they
want to construct these proofs that
reveal no information and to do that
they needed to change the model turns
out they could not do it using kind of
what we think of a classical proof and
the way they changed the model is by
defining a new uh proof system a new
model uh which is called interactive
proofs we're going to talk about this
today okay but they Define this notion
of interactive proof so the we're going
to start this course by talking about
what interactive proofs are okay uh and
we're going to construct interactive
proofs in the 80s and 90s when people
thought about interactive proofs usually
the model is we think of the verifier as
being efficient for us efficient means
polinomial time okay but of course uh
you know in practice it has more
specific meaning but for now think of
efficient as being pomal time and the
verifier can be all powerful so the the
time complexity of the prover was not
even a consideration actually they
called the prover Merlin like he's a
wizard can do whatever the hell he wants
like in infinite
power what we're going to talk about
about after introducing this model and
giving some protocols we're going to
talk about the model of doubly efficient
interactive proofs and here what we we
say no the appr is not all powerful we
don't have all powerful machines in the
world every machine is bounded so what
we want yes the verifier should be very
efficient but the Prov should not be all
powerful either so we care about the
Prov running time too that's what called
double efficient interactive proofs
we're going to construct double
efficient interactive proof uh we're
going to show the GK protocol specific
protocol and then we're going to show
application of this protocol and we're
going to see application to really nice
kind of models such that PCP which is
probabilistically checkable proofs nip
multi prooof interactive proofs and
particular we're going to show how to
use this to get a a kind of we proove a
celebrated result which is the IP equals
ppace theorem of Shamir okay so this if
you don't know any of these buzzwords
I'll explain everything this is I'm just
kind of doing a very quick overview for
those who kind of heard these buzzwords
a little bit and so you'll know what to
expect okay so up to here no crypto at
all this is not at all about crypto it's
just about proof systems then we're
going to show how to use cryptography to
get our proofs more succinct okay and
then we're going to kind of uh leave the
idea the stand the classical idea of a
proof that if the theorem is false there
you can't cheat it's possible to cheat
like there's no fake proof there's no
false proof okay every there's no if the
theorem is incorrect there's no proof
period we're going to use crypto to say
ah maybe they're false proof but they're
very hard to find so the only way you
can find a convincing proof to a false
statement is by breaking kind of a hard
uh cryptographic problem you can Factor
large numbers you can break latus
assumptions and so on okay so we're
going to use a cryptography to make our
proofs more succinct but then what what
going on here is are proofs who can make
them succinct but they're still
interactive and then we're going to show
how to use this beautiful F Cham
Paradigm which is a paradigm for
reducing interaction and we're going to
kind of study the security of this
Paradigm and show how to make this
Paradigm secure okay so these are kind
of results that have happened very
recently actually one of the students
here Alex Lombardi at MIT uh was V not
student was uh one of the people who
came show kind of the security of this
Paradigm so we're going show it we're
going to use it then to show how to get
our doubly efficient interactive proof
how to make it non interactive anymore
so make it completely
non-interactive we're going to also show
to use this fimir Paradigm to do kind of
batch proofs uh non-interactively in
very succinct way so taking a bunch of
claims and kind of giving one uh short
proof from them and finally we're going
to show how to use that to go all the
way to what's called a snar which is a
succinct non-interactive argument
argument is just another word for a
computationally soundproof so this is
kind of very very high level of what you
should expect uh uh to learn in this
class if you didn't understand a word
what I said then this is what the hope
the goal is that you will understand
this by the end of this
class okay uh questions before I start
okay I need a volunteer to scribe for
today oh fantastic thanks okay so with
that let let's start so let's start with
the notion of of interactive proofs and
before I go to interactive proofs let me
just you know even before intive proofs
let's look at the class NP
non-deterministic pomal time even this
class is about proof system right so
what is this this class is trying
to by the way there's another chair here
for those who don't have a chair there's
one right here
great great so even before we go to the
interactive setting let's even think of
the class NP what is the class NP if you
think about it it's all the
languages that have a proof that's the
witness that can be verified by
polinomial time okay so we want to think
with the here's the the framework for
this class is the following we want to
ask I we have the verifiers are pomal
time or even like there there you know
they're very efficient what can you
prove to these
verifiers okay so that's exactly what NP
captures NP is all the
languages that you can prove membership
in the language to pomal time
verifier okay so NP is exactly the
set of
languages m
ship can be
proved in poly time so for or can
prove or can prove to a PO time maybe I
should say can proved
to a polinomial Time
verifier so uh poal time verifier can
verify membership in the language so far
so good okay but NP is not that rich
okay so we want more more than NP okay
so let's so okay so one thing we can add
so what is the class IP the first thing
that so IP interactive proofs and two
components so in NP the proof is
classical it's the class of languages
for which a membership can be proved
using a classical
proof okay like a proof that you know
you can verify just like running a
touring machine okay interactive proofs
are different in two ways first of all
we
allow
interaction between the prover and the
verifier they can talk back and
forth
importantly we allow
randomization now note what do I mean
randomization the verifier can be
randomized and there can be some chance
that the theorem is uh false and he'll
accept but that's very very small okay
we can make it kind of if the
communication complexity is let's say n
we can make you'll you'll accept the
false statement probability something
like 2 Theus n so we can make it very
very small but there is a nonzero chance
that you'll accept false statement okay
so in that sense we weakened the
model now note if there's no
randomization if we force the
verifier to be deterministic if the
interaction so again the interactive
proof is a kind of
interactive protocol between approver
and verifier if the approver knew what
the verifier is going to send if he was
completely
deterministic then the pro can just
generate the entire transcript and give
it as a proof so it will really be
NP there's no point of this
interaction so really the power of this
IP comes from the fact that the verifier
is interacted it comes from the fact
that the verifier is interactive is is
randomized sorry is randomized and the
pro doesn't know what this Randomness is
going to be so if I'm trying to prove to
you a
statement I send you my first message I
don't know what question you're going to
ask me you're going answer some random
questions and I'll need to give an
answer and then I don't know what the
next question if I knew all your
question in advance then there's no
point it's like it loses the power okay
so really the power comes from the fact
that there's interraction in the PO
cannot predict ahead of time what
questions he's going to get from the
verifier okay so any any
questions Okay so
I can I did Define this formul yet I'll
Define it formally in a bit but I hope I
convinced you that like without
Randomness this model is really useless
okay there's no point how about just how
about without inaction let's say I had
only
Randomness do I get more and actually so
what what if we allow only
Randomness so
proofs so let's talk about
non-interactive proofs
where the verifier V is
randomized by the way I forgot to say
please stop me at any point and ask me
questions I like questions questions are
good for me to kind of SL me down it
gives you an opportunity to digest so
it's a great thing so please just at any
point stop me with questions
questions okay so uh good so what what
about if we so we said if we get rid of
Randomness we get nothing what if we get
rid of interaction and we just allow
Randomness do we get more and actually
we do get more okay and actually this
complexity test is a name this is ma for
Merlin Arthur Arthur is known as a
verify Merin is known as aover so kind
of the approver sends a message Arthur
the verifier can kind of toss coins and
based on that decide if to accept or not
but anyway the non the non-interactive
randomized version is uh believe to be I
mean it may be more powerful than NP we
actually don't know but it seems there's
some more power and actually let me give
you an example this is example that will
kind of be useful for us later so it's
not only an example but let me give you
an example where kind of Randomness can
be helpful for us okay so suppose you
want to
verify let's say you have two n byn
matrices A and B these are n byn
matrices let's say over Z1 or over a
finite
field and let's say you want to verify
suppose you want to
verify that some Matrix C is equal to a
*
B so you're also given let's say
C you want to so you you need to verify
task of matrix
multiplication okay we can do it
efficiently in general the best known
algorithm is something like order uh o
of n to the 2 3 6 maybe something like
that that's the best known matrix
multiplication
algorithm why you looking me the number
yeah close uh let but turns out that if
using randomization
you can do it more efficiently okay so
let's show how you can verify that a
matrix C is a product of two matrices A
and B in time order and
squared okay so kind of the best you can
do because you need to read the the
input okay so how will you do that
here's the idea so here's a
randomized algorithm for verifying this
so let's assume that F first assume this
is kind of without lots of
generality that f is much bigger than
n if not you can take kind of an
extension field of that okay embedded in
a much bigger field so just let's assume
if those who are not kind of comfortable
with extension field let's assume it's
just much
bigger okay then what do you do here's
my algorithm what I'm going to do I'm
going to choose a random element in the
field I'm going to consider X which is
just uh 1 r r 2 up to R to the N minus
one okay so all the powers of R I chose
a random R in the field I look at all
the powers of
R and then what do I
do yeah
exactly and then I'm going to
check if C * X I guess
transpose because I wrote it is equal to
a b *
X that's my
algorithm okay so note
uh yeah
so so note this is just a vector and
Vector times Matrix mult so to multiply
a matrix by Vector is time n squ as
opposed to you know the N to the 23 six
so this is more efficient why is it okay
why why so of course it's complete if
these are equal I'm going to accept Okay
but if they're not
equal so so why why is it uh sound so
maybe you can convince me let's say
they're not equal maybe you can still
convince me that they're equal that
would be a problem
so let
yeah the size of the field iser than n
it's that like fantastic fantastic so
here's let me just repeat what you said
a b bit more formly so suppose they're
not equal there's one row that they're
not equal on right let's focus on that
row so you can think of what when I do c
* X let's let's say C1 like the first
row of C when I do c *
X this is you can think of this as I
take I look at this the row as a polom
so if you look at the first row maybe
I'll write it as C11 up to or C10 up to
C1 n minus one okay let's look at this n
row when I multiply by X which is one r
r squ this is nothing but some C 1 i x
to the I or sorry R to the
I so now what do I check so now you know
if this row let's say it is different
than the row
here then I have two different
pols right so if I write if I write the
row there let's say as I don't know D1
d0 or d10 up to D1 n minus one let's say
this is the row corresponding to a *
B if these are different if these are
different then I have two different
pols that agree in a random out two
random degree n minus one pols so the
polinomial is defined by this row these
are the coefficients of the polinomial
they're n coefficient so it's a degree n
minus one polom so
when when would I S when would I accept
a false claim if there exist two things
that are equal that are different to
there exists a row in in C that's
different than a row in a *
B so there exists a polinomial degree in
minus one here and a different
polinomial degree and minus one and
these two pols are equal and this
are but what is the probability that two
distinct polinomial of degree n minus
one are equal it's just this happens
with
probability at most n minus one the
degree divided by the field
sides right two pooms agree two distinct
pols agree on at most or the fraction
not they agree on at most n minus one
points and which is nus one over F
fraction of
the of the field
so so that so I'll I'll reject with this
probability and if we're not happy with
this F is f is not big enough for us
then we do everything over a bigger
extension field so we can except so our
rejection probability will be uh high if
if if the claims
Falls any any questions about
this okay so so far what we saw is that
when oh yeah oh yes please thank you
is this is not short zipa short zipa is
similar but in a multivariant setting so
this good so let me that's a good
question so thank you so uh I just want
to say oh by the way I should tell you
guys this this uh this is being recorded
I hope it's okay with you you're not
being recorded it's supposed I'm
supposed to be the one being recorded
but I think you should know that there's
a cameraman behind you uh but actually I
don't I don't think I'm going to put
this public I mean it's in the website
for us well now the website is public so
it will be public
I I can make it private if you prefer if
if people come to me and ask for it to
be private I'll make it private um okay
uh so uh good so the question was was
this short zipa and the answer exact
short zipa is a multivariate version of
this okay this is for the single variate
case so the fact that two univariate
polinomial of degree D distinct they're
equal and a random value their equal and
most D element D being the degree uh is
uh is kind of I don't remember theorem
like basic something
M you say interation yeah but CH is
exactly that but the multivariant
setting so a generalization of exactly
exactly the tral is exactly
generalization of this the it will come
up actually later in this class so yeah
we'll talk about that great any other
question
yeah good good good very good question
so the question is can are do we have
examples where Randomness gives you more
speed up than just kind of pathetic this
is not very interesting right so or in
other words let me rephrase your
question is the class ma different than
NP that's the question we don't
know so ma said that the
verif yeah so the yeah so all and okay
so yeah so let me explain uh there's a
kind of there's this class called like m
a m a ma a as many as you want and the
idea is m means Merlin speaks mlin is
the approver he's the wizard a means
Arthur the king he's the verifier
answers M speaks a answers M speak a
answers so there's kind of these classes
uh you know Ma a ma ma ma
uh here ma a means M the Merlin speaks
Arthur kind of uses Randomness and then
kind of sends Randomness well he doesn't
speak mlin doesn't speak again so but
Merlin speaks Arthur chooses coins and
then there's a verdict function that
decides to accept or
reject okay and we don't know if ma is
different than NP yes so this actually
is a you know po identity testing right
right like you saying this is like poom
identity yes I give you a circuit
supp I claim
that you can check it
clearly right right
right right but uh oh you're saying
you're saying sorry you're saying to
test whether a circuit is a identically
zero but wait oh you're giving us just
as as a circuit as a circuit testing if
it's identically zero
but if it needs to be low degree because
otherwise so like it's syntactically low
degree right low dep or something right
low depth aritic CC low depth like log
log depth arithmetic circuit then you're
saying it has polinomial degree it has
polinomial degree you can test it by
taking a large field it's sent field you
can test you don't know how to predict
if it's yes good we don't know how to D
randomize it how to Der randomize
randomize it then there are circulars
which means you can randomize everything
probably right more
less you
get yeah yeah
Al no why why is it n so so you look at
the
CL also right okay okay yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah you're right it's in BPP
yeah so I just wanted to make the point
that I describe is essentially the the
only canonical problem in okay yeah yeah
up to up to details which I
think thanks thanks yeah okay so uh okay
so now let's go in ahead and just Define
this class of NP
uh of of Ip are interactive proofs so
and then we'll show how kind of uh an
actual uh to and we'll actually show why
we believe this class is more powerful
then NP will give kind of a a protocol
that solves a problem that seems pretty
hard so let's
see so here is the so what is an
interactive
proof an interractive proof
IP this is a
[Music]
protocol
between and
possibly all powerful okay I'm
not
aover
P okay so P can be run as long as he
wants and a poly
time
verifier
v such that here's the requirement want
from from the protocol we want to say
that a so interactive protocol let's say
for H sorry between a
p for a language l
for some
language or some problem l so the
problem correspondent is membership in L
that's a problem is X a member not a
member so an interactive proof should
satisfy the following so it's a protocol
such that it should have two properties
completeness and
soundness completeness says
that if x is in the language the PO
should convince you to
accept Okay so if for every X in the
language if you look if you denote let's
say by T the transcript so let's say
p uh and V which has secret Randomness
the prover doesn't know what it is ahead
of time and input X let's run this
protocol we get a transcript
okay so the it's an interactive protocol
it actually think can think of it the
protocol consists in two phases first
there's interaction between the they
talk back and forth let's denote the
transcript by T okay often denot like
like PV that's kind of the protocol the
Prov has are both of them know the input
X they generate a transcript and at the
end the
probability that V with his input with
his uh he gets the transcript the r
Randomness in X the probability that he
accepts outputs one when we say output
one we usually mean he
accepts is large okay let me call a
least
C so and C is going to be a completeness
parameter so a protocol between p and v
for language L with completeness
C and
soundness
S ah yes I do mean all AC now oh thank
you thanks
L okay so if it's in the language he's
accepted with high probability there's
some complet this parameter C and most
of what we see in class that AC is one
okay you accept with probability one and
sist
says
this sist says that for any X not in the
language
for every X that's not in the
language no matter how you try to cheat
you'll fail okay so for any cheating
prover or for any P star because it can
be any any Prov that tries to convince
me to
accept if we the probability for the
same t as above the probability that the
verifier given the transcript the
randomness in X outputs one accepts is
at most
s okay so that's if you if it's in the
language you should be accept with high
probability C is high if it's not in the
language you should accept with small
probability s is
small
okay question about the
model
yeah is there any restriction on S and C
or they just right great question uh
what are snc are they constant so that
was my next remark which means that the
question was right in place uh so often
if you look at the literature there
won't be a mention of s and C and C will
be taken to be 2/3 and that's will be
taken to be one3 that's kind of a
canonical so when people say there's an
inter here's an interactive proof often
you think of s as 1/3 and C as 2/3 and
this seems like very arbitrary and you
should be be alarmed so what what you
know where do this PL come
from I don't I think it's
theed
exactly exactly so the reason why we
don't care so much about these constants
is because if you have an interactive
proof with a gap between CNS so for
example 1/3 and 2/3 what we're going to
do is repeat the protocol so let's say
that it's 1/3 and 23 let's repeat the
protocol let's say n times and then
we're going to accept if you're closer
to C and reject if you're closer to to s
or if so in other words if you if more
than C uh plus s over two like right in
the middle if more than C plus s over
two are accepted you're going to accept
if less you're going to reject in in
this case of 2/3 and third if let's say
more than half repeat it many many many
times you should accept if it's in the
language you should expect to see about
two3 acceptance if it's not in the
language you should expect to see one
third of them being accepted and if you
repeat enough times by the laws of large
numbers you're going to kind of get
closer and closer to the expectation so
you're going to be either very close to
the 2/3 if you're in the language or
very close to the one3 if you're outside
the language and the the uh like the the
there's very strong concentration so if
you repeat it let's say n times then now
you're can to be accepted or your the
soundness and uh completeness Gap would
be something like 2 the minus n versus 1
minus 2 the minus n so you can really
kind of uh very fast make these things
go to zero and one which is why often we
don't really care about these and you
can think of them very close to zero and
very close to one so if it's in the
language you accept probability almost
one if it's not the language you reject
you accept probility almost zero
okay great okay any question about kind
of what an interactive uh proof
is okay I just want to mention one thing
uh this
notation like PV on input X is
overloaded we use this notation to
denote the transcript we also use this
notation to denote the verdict function
whether V accepts or not and also I'll
use that in class and also wherever you
read you'll see both of them kind of
used so it's good to get used to so this
sometimes denotes the entire transcript
sometimes it's just the notes the
acceptance or ejection bit of of the
verifier and it'll be clear in the
context okay so now the question you
should ask is okay is this uh is this
model more expressive than
NP what can we do with this model how
can what's the power of this
m so let me actually go to the punchline
and say there's a celebrated result by
Shamir from 92 I
believe and he showed ex he oh this
model is very very powerful and actually
you can prove any P space computation in
this model namely if I want to prove to
you any language in P space take any
language in P space I can prove
membership in this language to a
verifier that only runs in polinomial
time so that's sh so b space we believe
is much much kind of more expressive
stronger than NP we actually don't know
how to prove it by the way but we
believe that's the
case uh so we believe this is a much
stronger kind of uh proof
system okay actually before I I'm going
to show you actually now I'm going to
give you an example of the kind of the
power of this proof system but before I
go into kind of the technicality I want
to step back for a second and kind of
think a little bit about the story here
which is a very nice story so you know
this introduction of uh interactive
proofs this model came about for the
goal of doing zero knowledge nobody
thought at that point about whether you
can prove more languages not more
languag which is the only thing you want
is to hide okay I just want to hide why
a theorem is true I want to hide the
proof I want to convince you but hide
that was the only goal uh that kind of
introduced this model and it's kind of
interesting how kind of very F like also
who cares about zero knowledge this is a
really interesting model let's see what
we can do with it and this kind of open
our eyes just the idea that we can shift
from the traditional way of thinking
about proofs to this attractive and
randomized randomized land kind of
brought about a lot of really really
beautiful and fascinating results
including the fact this is the first
time to realize wow we can prove a lot
of ver to a polinomial Time verifier
much more than what was believed to
be a what we believed we can do with a
classical
proof so this was kind of really I think
eye opening and very interesting so okay
so now I'm GNA convince you try to
convince you of why this
a proof system this model is so powerful
by giving you an example of things of a
problem that I can prove to you using an
interactive proof that we really don't
know how to prove using a classical
proof okay so let me give you the
example
so here's the
example so the protocol is called Su
protocol and this I'm going to give you
an interactive this is an interactive
proof for the following problem so take
any degree
fix or okay
given a
polinomial
F let's say from F to the N so
multivariate
polinomial of let's take degree D in
each
variable okay I want a proof
that sum of f B1
or let me just make sure how do I wrot
it
down okay
sorry so take any fix
any subset h and
f you can think of H 01 you can think of
a bigger
set I want to I want you to convince me
that Su F of H1 up to hm
for all H1 up to
hm in
h is equals some value
beta okay so there's a fixed polinomial
F let's say I know this polinomial I
either it actually has a succinct
circuit or maybe I have Oracle access to
it so I'm a
verifier I'm a verifier I have let's say
I have Oracle access to this polinomial
or there are some sync way to compute it
so I can compute this polinomial easily
let's think for now I have Oracle access
to it so I can kind of query it in some
point and after that and get back an
answer I want you to I want prove you
you're going to prove to me that the sum
of this polinomial and H to the m points
and all the points there some set H you
can think of H as 01 you can think of it
bigger and I want you to sum this iial
on all the elements in the set H to the
N okay all of this is done over some
finite field
F and there's a result beta I want to
prove that this sum is
beta okay that's that's I I'm going to
show you an interactive proof for this
langage now before kind of you guys are
like seriously why do I care about this
language is it interesting where did I
come up with this thing let me tell you
I think this is
the most important protocol in all the
literature and pro systems okay we all
use this protocol all the time it turns
out to be super super influential okay
every single thing we'll use from now on
relies on this protocol okay so it turns
out and I'm going to convince you that
later uh but that this is a very very
important actually problem okay if you
have interactive proof for this problem
you it kind of gives you rise attrative
proof for many many many other
problems okay actually we use this if
you give me an interactive proof for
this problem I can use it to get an
interactive proof for all P
space in kind of a blackbox way so
really this is the heart of coming up
with interactive proofs this is the most
important interactive
proof okay so with that let me show you
the interactive proof for proving
this okay any questions before we jump
yeah just H is like one
dimension exactly H exactly you can
think of H is 01 for example you can
think of H 012 yeah I mean if two is in
the field yeah it's a onedimensional
thing right and you sum over so as a the
you sum here over H to the m sides of H
to the m elements
uh it can be you sum over all of them
you sum over also like z z z z z one
yeah all yeah H one and each2 do not
need to be distinct at all yeah exactly
over all possible yeah you Su over H to
the m elements each one all all the
possibilities good other
questions thank you yes so degree D in
each variable just means like any
variable is exp exactly so yeah let me
good good great so degree D in each
variable means f is a polinomial so you
can write it as a sum of monomials each
monomial each uh H variable has a degree
so I want say if you look at all the
monomials each variable has a degree and
most be in each of the
monomials okay great questions thank you
any other
questions okay great so let me give you
uh the protocol a
so let's do
it by the way I want to tell you I get
such satisfactions from your questions
so if you just want to make me happy
which is a great goal on its own and you
should ask
questions okay
ready for the protocol okay Pro
convinces a
verifier that the sum F on H1 up to
hn is equal to
Beta where the H is are all elements in
this set H which is in the field we have
some fixed field that we're looking over
okay how would he prove what would what
would he do so here is the idea the idea
is the prover will first
send this sum this polinomial but where
the first variable is EMP is open so he
will
compute he will compute some only over
H2 up to
hm f of x this is a variable H2 up to hn
and he will send this over let's call
this G1 of
X so he sends a univariate
polinomial okay where he sums over H2 to
hm but leaves the first variable
open okay what is the degree of this
polinomial D very good so this is a
degree d
polinomial the verifier
checks that G1 is of
degree at most D if not he rejects
because he knows that this is a degree D
polinomial multivaried
polinomial so he knows that each
variable is the degree most D so if you
s something degree like you're cheating
here so it's going to be reject
you he he will also
check that
some G1 of H I guess one let me call
H1 that if you take G1 and you sum it
over all possible H's in
h what does he expect to get what would
he check
for exactly beta
because the claim is beta so he checks
that this is a degree
mosd that when you sun over hes you get
what was
claimed okay if he's if this does not
hold then he reject he say b i reject
you not going to continue if this holds
then he chooses a
random T1 in the
field this is often a notation left
arrow that we use for choosing a random
okay so he uses a he chooses a random a
T1 a random element in the field not an
H but in The Big Field okay you need to
think of this field as being big well
that will the bigger the field the
better the soundless will
get okay so he chooses a random T1 in
the
field good then what happens the the PO
in some sense this reduces the problem
from checking that this sum is beta to
checking
sum let me WR here to checking that sum
of f t t is fixed or T1 you call it and
then H2 up to
hn is this fixed I don't know G1 of
T1 we kind of reduce the problem to this
problem which is of one dimension less
because the sum is only over M minus one
variables
yes good what what are we going to put
polinomial in very good question when I
said that verifier is polinomial time
polinomial in what so he's going to he's
going to be polinomial okay we think of
F I said f can be as Oracle axis to it
so what poom what so he was he what
we're we're going to analyze his runtime
in a bit but his runtime will depend
polinomial on M which is the number of
variables and on the
degree and we think of a in these in to
today and act like throughout the course
and it's common in this field we think
of f like that he can add and multiply
things in or order one time like it's a
constant uh and typically these fields
are going to be take polylog but we
don't want to run you know chase after
these polog terms so we're not going to
consider them really sometimes we do
sometimes we don't depends but beyond
the so if you want to be kind of very
pedantic then
you log
F also H maybe yes thank
you yes of course thanks sua the size of
H and log
F that's what's going to happen but you
right that here the polinomial time
doesn't really apply here because you I
said that he has oralis so we polinomial
over so this is this is what he's going
to be after but when we're going to use
him for applications you'll see it will
correspond to polinomial time but we're
going to go over this uh when when uh
when we analyze the
protocol okay so let's uh okay so let's
just uh uh continue so where let me
actually start it so what's let me even
say before I continue the protocol let's
continue the protocol with kind of a
high level idea of what we're trying to
do here the idea is the
following we want to catch aover
cheating that's the goal of a proof
right we want to catch you if you're
cheating so suppose aover is cheating
here how will how will he C we catch it
the way we're going to catch it is when
tell you know what give me this
G1 okay now he cannot give me an the
actual true G1 Because the actual true
G1 will not sum up to Beta beta is the
false thing so right so if it if a po
cheats if he try let I'm trying to kind
of let's come up with this protocol
together with kind of the goal of trying
to catch the the approver so how do we
catch aover cheating so the IDE is will
tell me you know what give me this some
with this
open I'm going to check that this sum
with like that the sum of G1 is equal to
Beta and then it's low
degree if it passes then this G1 cannot
be the true true G1 it can't actually be
the real sum of f because the real sum
of f is not beta he's cheating so this
must be a
cheat now when we send in
T1 and we consider kind of so now we
send T1 and we kind of reduce the claim
to claiming this
but with very high probability G1 is
also a cheat
because G1 G1 T1 is a cheat so G1 T1 is
not really the sum because they're
different G1 is different than that so
we know that if they're different they
agree only on D elements okay two
distinct polom age only on D elements
what's the probability that this1 is one
of the D very small
DF Okay so think of is really large
great so this is also false actually you
know he give me G one it's actually not
the real life he's going to claim it's
the real life but I know it's not now
I'm going to tell him next thing I'm
going to tell him okay give me G2 G2 is
G2 of
X is some it should be some f T1 I'm
going to only sum over H3 up to hm
the X2 the two is going to be open and
then H3 after
H okay so we started by getting rid of
the summing over
H1 we gave him the univ pomal or we
chose our R T1 now we're getting rid of
summing over the second
coordinate we're asking for a univ
polinomial G2 what do we check we check
so the verifier checks that
G2 is of
degree and most D and what else does he
check very good so sum G2 and
H maybe I'll write H2 is equal to what
exactly G1 of
T1 so essentially we kind of you know we
check this for exactly as we did
before okay so now note if in the honest
case of course that's that's the case G2
of course is degree at most D because f
is degree at most D and when you sum
with over over all of H2 you should get
exactly G1 and T that's how
we
great if he's if this does not hold he
immediately aborts and say I reject you
if he's happy he's going to send T2 at
random from the
field what am I going to reply with what
what should the Prov reply with
so let's see
G3 of X is
what very
good very good F of T1 T2 X and H4 up to
hm yeah again we take essentially what
happened here we reduced after T2 we
reduced the problem to proving a sum
check over sum F1 T1 T2 H3 up to hm and
we need to check whether this is equal
to a G2 of
H2 of T2 sorry
okay so again each time we kind of layer
kind of get rid of one variable in the
sum check we start with an narate sum
check and each round we get rid of one
variable okay last one what do we check
here we got G3 what do we check
what is the
g33 exactly so first that G3 is low
degree is
degree most and some
G3 is
G2 and we continueing this way until we
continue continue continue until we got
rid of everything so in the last round
what will happen in the last round in
the last
round we will send
g m minus one
GM of like
GMX which is f of T1 up to TN minus1
X that's what he should check that's
what you should send if you're honest
that's what you send you peeled out off
everything
finally you're left with a with a GM
which is F and M minus one X and then
the verifier is done he'll choose a
random
TM and he will check whether this is
indeed F of T1 of the TM we assumed he
has Oracle access so we can check if
this value is T1 of the TM okay so
finally this is this and
verifier I'm out of room but maybe I'll
write
here V
chooses uh random TM
and
checks that g m of
TM is equal to the Oracle he has F on T1
up to
T that's the
protocol I'll give you a minute to
appreciate the beauty while I eras the
board
you have
a you're asking can I have a different
set I can I can have a different set yes
yeah so the question was do do the hes
have to be identical and the answers
they don't have to be identical you can
take a we didn't use that anywhere and
yeah it's somehow yeah somehow we always
use it when it is but uh
but but that's a very good point because
it's like it seems more General it seems
like it can be useful but somehow we
don't use it
uh but that's a very good good point
yeah you can the hes does not have to be
the same age you can be some over H1 of
hm so particular H would be equal right
okay H could be equal uh to F yes H
could be equal to f um
how do you
do
G1 sorry first line Su G1 H1 you will
take time propal yeah but let's say
that's
okay again
s yeah so let's we'll talk about
soundness in a minute uh actually
um if f is degree D the sist won't
Decay I actually I think actually a okay
let's talk about soundness and then
we'll see actually the soundness won't
uh in general usually when H is big in
applications what happens often is when
you take big H the F turns out to be
degree H or H minus one so when we use
this protocol so you know as I said this
problem I'm say why do I care about this
problem who cares about this problem so
it turns out we care a lot it comes up
all the time the way we use it in pra
like the way it comes up is the F that
we use usually is of degree hus one and
each variable we use it in a way that
that turns out to be the degree of F and
the soundness decades with a degree so
if the H is Big the soundness if the
degree is Big the soundness is big but
actually if your promis that the degree
is small then we're good we we'll
analyze it right now yeah can you say
something about like what's so special
about
yes yes great question love the question
so what what's so fascinating about
polinomial that comes up here so the
what it's kind of why is this so
interesting why is colonial so so
important you know that this comes up
everywhere so here's my take and uh on
this
question everything can be okay first of
all pooms are and St they're very very
useful because of their their power of
error correction so in other words what
happens if you cheat it once we're going
to amplify your cheat that's kind kind
of what we do here right you cheat it
once we're g to like for a random Point
T you're if if you're low degree this
we're assuming that this Pro gives kind
of low degree low degree low degree all
the time if you give low degree low
degree low degree and you cheated then
the cheat must be kind of corresponding
a che a random Point like at the end a
random Point T1 the TM you should be
different and that's kind of we'll
analyze this this is just intuition but
that kind of the beauty of polinomial
that if you're wrong you're wrong almost
everywhere because if if it's not the
correct polinomial then it's different
from the correct bomal almost everywhere
that's the short zip for the multivaried
case for the single varied case it's
just the the interpolation I guess it's
called but okay now you're saying okay
but that just pomal why am I saying
comes what's so special about polinomial
like why why are they so General okay if
you happen to have a polinomial good
good for you you won because it has such
air crafting guarantees you're you're
lucky it's your lucky day but what if
it's like why is every day a lucky day
kind of thing why is the poal come up
come up everywhere and the answer is
that you can actually embed many many
problems into pols so there's a way
there's a technique which we'll call low
degree extension we'll see that pretty
soon soon if not today then tomorrow
then next week where uh a a you can kind
of convert many problems into
polinomial and then use the sum check so
that's often what we do we take a
problem we embed it into a polom we kind
of extend it to look like a polinomial
of low degree and then we use subject to
it so that's how it will come
up any any more questions before a
before we analyze the subject protocol
questions on the protocol
itself
or oh oh you're asking what you're
asking you're saying this sum check do I
really need this specific kind of a
polinomial code or can I do using
arbitrary codes kind of thing okay so
actually this is a great great question
uh there's a paper by or
from several years ago I remember
exactly where he shows how to do a sum
check over more General codes not any
kind of code but more General than that
thing like tensor codes or Rachel do you
remember you looked into it yeah t
tensor
codes yeah so so he generalized it not
to any code but he G the generalization
this OC to work for big for a larger
family
of to ask the question what does it mean
for the subject protocol to work for
okay more good good good so you can
think of it is I'm proving something
about uh I don't remember exactly how
his formalization was but it's like uh
I'm proving something about a code
word and I want kind of reinterpret this
you can reinterpret this as a because
you can think of the this F as being an
aircraf in code so does it work only for
this kind of read M this is called the
read does it work only for read can you
do it for arbitrary codes uh and he
proves it for for arbitrary codes so
this is kind of there's kind of a any
polinomial is an air correcting code
it's a type of air crafting code H for a
multivaried case it's called read Muller
for univ case is called re Solomon and
so when the subject protocol for V think
it is this protocol for read more codes
and then you can ask is there a analog
for other codes and actually there is
there are analogs out there
yeah okay any other questions
yeah making the
of that wouldn't like point of doing
this because of like the size of H the
log okay you're right so okay you're
right so if there okay so the let me go
back so the question is what what should
this H be you know what is this H and
the answer is this H can actually be all
of f of course if it's all of f the
verifier runs in time which is like the
size of f because he checks you know Su
over H if it's all of f you run the time
all of f but maybe f is not that big
maybe f is polinomial even if f is
polinomial size still checking this sum
is much bigger than F right it's like H
to the n like f to the m m can be big so
the the hardness does not come only from
f it comes from M it's exponential in M
it's the M that kind of makes it very
hard and so H can be as large as the
entire field and you can run some check
over that too there's um it's still an
interesting protocol yeah but if we that
would we need to do an extension or
something that good so okay the good so
the question is wait do we get any
aircraft in guarantees here because uh
if we're doing over all of that and I
think the answer is yes we we don't need
to extend it further because as we see
now we'll see now when we analyze it the
soundless error goes down with something
like d over f h does not come into play
there but we'll see that let's let's see
that together I I right I agree when you
say that yeah that should right it
should things should degrade with age
but actually they don't so we'll see
that now when we when we analyze
it okay okay any any these are great
great questions so thank you any other
questions before we go to the
analysis okay so actually before we do
soundness let's just first do a sanity
check on the com on the kind of
communication complexity and the the
runtime and so on so first let's see
this protocol has n rounds each round we
kind of get rid of one VAR one sum in
the sum check right so
the so uh the communication complexity
so our round
complexity is M rounds M back and forth
M to m i don't if you want to count each
one or round is one two so let me just
say
[Music]
order uh the the communication
complexity is what um uh so each time uh
po one polinomial is s and one field
element so it's really a polinomial is a
degree d right so it's just uh D field
elements each time times
n so fine we can do times you know log F
if you want
to so that's the communication
complexity okay what about the verifier
run time
so the
verifier he gets a polinomial degree D
polinomial so D essentially field
elements or D plus1 field elements and
he just sums them up he checks that it's
a degree D and sums them up that's all
he does so it's really essentially the
same for M rounds he has a degree D
polinomial and he sums them I should put
here maybe po log then because the sum I
I'm assuming addition multiplication
take poly log F again as I said often I
think maybe even in the notes justtin
Taylor's notes this is omitted it's like
the feel thing of is one operation so
just so you know if you read things
often you won't see this part question
ver the verifier also needs to choose
the
T yeah exactly so some over H is like H
additions okay okay yeah he you sorry
yeah so okay good uh you're saying he
needs to compute uh it's still yeah so
right so the the ver far he gets a
polinomial he needs to evaluate the
polinomial in h so yeah so for M rounds
he gets a degree D polinomial he needs
to evaluate
it oh sorry this does not have
H yeah you need to evaluate it in in uh
H
points the degree D polinomial and then
a
log thanks
good thanks a lot good catch that's
awesome okay great so that's the
verifier as I said the PO we care less
about but just you know if you want to
just
and and by the way this is assuming the
verifier has access to F he knows f f is
kind of he has Oracle access to it
because of course at the end he needs to
check equality with f so this we just
assume he has oral access to F and then
the prover what he does he need to do
well he needs to do this computation so
he runs in time like H to the m he needs
to do all the sum he needs to run so the
polinomial so it's called a t subf is
the time to run uh to compute F so we
need to compute F uh he needs to uh do
the sum overall fs and he does that kind
of a d m times right something like
this A and polog H polog F
sorry
yeah so that's the pro ver test
okay
yes no good good good good good great
question no so you're okay so even if V
has random Oracle access to F he can
compute this entire thing but it will
take him time H to the end because he
needs to computer some so the the goal
he needs to check so let's say Computing
F once it takes the one time you can
kind of ask but to check the sum he
needs to
ask this an H to the m question now
think of H of them is
huge even if a even if H is two think of
M as being Big M is like n variable so
it's like exponential that's it great
question but should I think of the
description of f Pol or good so you can
okay there's two options you can think
of the description of f as being
polinomial that's one option or that you
can compute F in it's like described by
a polinomial size circuit or you can
think it can be large but the verifier
has access to it somehow the verifier
has like a trusted Oracle that computes
app for
him
okay great okay so now the
so
yes good yeah this is just sorry this
it's just the time it takes to compute
F thanks
yeah because he needs to comp the
approver supposedly doesn't have he
needs to actually do the
computation okay great yes um whereing
that into account the theover finding G
of One X like don't they have to combine
a bunch of terms order of oh yeah but uh
he runs in time F anyway f is much
bigger than D so the degree is also
always much smaller
F so it's I'm kind of lumping it in yeah
thanks great question
yeah something else again you're saying
if you you want to be even you you're
saying let's say the verifier wants to
be even more efficient than this then
what can you do can I choose H to be
like special structure okay but you're
changing the problem you what you're
saying is so the problem is H is given
to us and you want to prove now you're
saying maybe if H has a special
structure maybe we can be even more
efficient is what you're saying
a good question a I haven't thought
about
itation yeah like you can probably uh
yeah yeah probably you can you can so V
not was saying you can probably batch
things or probably yeah I think if you
can choose H if H is of a certain
structure then I think you can do better
but this is kind of your the verifier
doesn't choose it like that's what's
given them great okay
great okay any more any more a
questions
yeah oh okay it's degree D but it's m
variables so in General Degree D
polinomial with m variables can have
size like m to the D so which is can be
very big great question a d to the m
sorry yeah great great
question okay okay so let's go to
completeness and soundness then so what
is the completeness of this protocol if
let's say the pro is honest the
statement is correct with what
probability will the verifier
accept one exactly because you'll just
be honest you always give the C nomial
always be Lo degree will always sum to
what it should be and you always going
accept it that's easy the hard part is
soundness so let's do the soundness and
then after soundness we'll take
a okay so for sound this here's the idea
suppose so let's look at it fix suppose
there's a cheating
prover that generates a false clip so
suppose
that the claim is
false mainly this sum of
f is actually not
big okay so we start with the false CL
the first thing we know is that and so
fix any so you you fix a claim that's
false fix any piece
he tries to cheat let's show that he he
fails like he won't succeed or succeed
very small probability the field is
large enough so let's
see first the first thing I want to
point out which I mentioned before is G1
must be false G so it must be the case
no matter how he cheats and he gives me
a bad G1 okay it cannot if he's accepted
if the Prov is accepted then G1 cannot
be sum of
a call
g1x is not sum of f H2 up to
hm because I'm going to check that it's
equal to Beta but the sum of f is not
beta so the G that he gives me cannot be
the correct F like the correct
G okay so in other words he starts the
protocol by a cheat a the first message
is not the correct
polinomial okay because the correct
polinomial if you Summit you'll get the
real beta not the fake
beta okay that he
claimed okay however at the end of the
day if you're
accepted the final check when you check
then you check with respect to the
honest F right and that verifies so at
the end of the day when you left with G
to the like the last one GM to the TM
that's actually
honest so somewh the protocol you had to
move from a
bad G to a good
G okay so again here's the
claim so I want to argue if so let there
I want to argue there must exist a round
such that around let's say I so to Pro
to cheat
there must exist around
I such
that
GI is false so GI is not sum of
T1 t i-1 x h i +1 up to hm this is what
it should be but it's not
and yet at some point but g i +
one is actually equal to oh I forgot
f is actually equal to some f T1 up to
ti so to cheat you must go so you start
with with you start with an
incorrect A A polom we know that's for
sure because you assuming you're you're
accepted if you're accepted G1 is false
now either now G2 is true and then I'll
show that happens with very small
probability or G2 is also false if G2 is
false I G3 is true I'm going to show
that happens with very small probability
or G or G3 is false until we're left
with
GM which again let but it's still I'm
going to argue that if G minus one was
false GM is also false with very high
probability but if GM is
false you're not going to be if GM is
actually not
F then for random T the probability that
you'll get f is very very you'll be
consistent with f is very very small
because these are two different
polinomial and they agree only on D
points so what's the probability that I
chose one of these D's one of these
points D over f
okay so let me let me be a little more
formal
now okay so I want to argue that part me
argue that so first to cheat there must
exist some round where we go from F from
from false to true because the final
final check must be true otherwise
you're I'm going to check you with the
true so there must exist a around that
you go from false to True let's see
what's the probability of going from
false to true
so good so what's the probability so
let's denote this event let's knowe this
event by
bi now let's see what's the probability
that this events happen this is kind of
a bad event an event that you go from a
bad incorrect a false to true that's for
the ver part it's a very bad event
because then he accepts a false
statement what is the probability that
this bad event happen so the
probability of
B I want to argue is that
most D over F let's see
why
so when is let's see when is GI + one
true we're sending here like the very
the probability let's fix like we fixed
already T1 of the ti plus1 that's fixed
okay so fix and I don't care how t one
up to t i minus one this
defines like the what the prover
gives GI in the protocol the cheating
prover gives in the
protocol okay
now now the verifier chooses a random t
a random uh so good so this defines GI
which is uh okay this is my G now the
prover the verifier the probability over
TI that the verifier
chooses This Ti tells you if GI this
defines GI +
one but when it's
if what do we know about when
if we know that because the verifier is
accepted we know that some g i +1 of
H is equal to
GI which is the wrong
polinomial
so
uh sorry
NTI and this is the wrong polinomial so
what is the probability that for so so
in other words J + one is the wrong
polom
what is the probability that for a
random T it will be the right
one D over
F because two polinomial that are
different agree on it most D points I
chose a random point the probability
that it's one of these D is D over
F so what is the probability that you
cheat at this is the
probability that there exist some
I such that bi holds a bad event holds
namely there exists an eye that you go
from True from false to
true and that IE by the union bound this
is at most M number of rounds Times the
probability of one of a specific b b me
which is D over
F so just just note H actually doesn't
come
up in the soundness this is the
soundness okay so the sinus needs M time
D to be significantly smaller than the
field
size that's all that's important for
sence yeah so Point like
the
have exact exactly the point is if
you're not happy if f is not large
enough if it's not much bigger than m
the m * D then you just make it bigger
you can take you can take extension
Fields you can take so you just kind of
artificially increase F so that F will
be much larger than M * D and hence
you'll get a small
s
applications what happens is given H
right and the degree happens to be uh H
ESS or h that's why it doesn't make
sense for H and to be the same but you
can dis exactly can dis 100% so let me
repeat it because I'm recorded you're
not yeah because that's a very good
point the the point is for Su in general
it makes sense to consider any ag even H
which is of size f is interesting for
the Su protocol okay in application
because as long as the D is small of
course in applications often it turns
out that the when we use the sub check
it turns out that the D is often equal
to the size of
H okay because we kind of do the slow
degree extension which makes the field
as large as
H and then if a if if we take H which
becomes the degree to be F this is
Meaningful
meaningless so for
application often indeed H is small but
for the sum of prot it's own you can
make you can take eight to be the entire
field yes is it that find F like it's
easy to put another yeah okay good good
good yes exactly so let me yeah so it
there's kind of uh you can take so this
is a fact from mathematics you can take
any finite field and embed it into a
bigger finite field and how big is the
bigger finite field kind of as big as
you want so you can take any Loosely
speaking you can take any F and embed it
into kind of a field F to the
N uh so when you can take n as big as
you want so you can kind of that's
what's called an extension
field so you can kind of extend it to as
large size as you want while still
keeping f as a sub field so operations
in F kind of behave exactly as they did
before so without ruing the sum or
anything like
that this Anis right is it really the
case that there is actually a chea
strategy that succeeds with yes this
yeah this good this analysis is really
tight so I mean if if I'm malicious you
know I can always hope for the best if
it happens to be I'm malicious I give
you the wrong polinomial look you may
find so I want to go from the wrong Pol
to the true polinomial that's what to
cheat right that's what I want to do now
the the my wrong poal and the true
polinomial they agree the points any two
pomal can agree on the points so as long
as the verifier I'm lucky enough that
this T is one of the deep points I mean
look I got a good pomal I'll continue
with a good pomal till the end of now
I'm I'm in kind of a h La La Land you
know I'm happy uh the problem is the
chance each one the chance that you'll
give me a t that's one of the D points
is only D over F and a union bound over
everything it's n times D over F and if
f is much much bigger than n times D
then you know uh the chances that the
Prov will Su will be in this L land is
very small
okay any any questions further questions
about the subject
protocol okay so let's take maybe kind
of a five minute break to stretch and so
on and then we'll show application we'll
start showing applications for this