[Music]
so our final uh session of the day today
is going to be a panel discussion that
includes representatives of Industry
Academia and government the three-legged
stool that brings our society together
here they will be introduced by our
moderator Dr ksac Putra former Minister
and now director and Senior Executive
Vice President to Bangkok Bank and yes a
proud MIT Lum awarded the PHD and
economics in 1997 I'd like to invite Dr
copsac and all the panelists to please C
up on the stage
[Music]
CRA good
afternoon the last session is us the
hardest uh you have listened to the
whole day seminar and learn a lot of
things but you still
are here and in Thailand people always
say that people still here at the last
session are the true
love you must be real fan of AI who
would like to understand more and in
fact we have learned a
lot Professor have talked about AI is
everywhere in fact there has been some
mention about um AI winter but the more
I listen today the more I feel that it's
not AI winter that is coming it's more
like AI Golden Age there will be so many
opportunities available and in fact this
is probably very early part of the whole
thing I think um there are so many
things that can be done like noat just
mentioned before we are at the beginning
of the most important
transformation that we are facing
so basically
today we will definitely get the last
panel Who coming from both the business
Academia and also from the government
segment to talk and discuss exactly what
can we do to really fast forward the AI
implementation in especially in Thailand
I think the more you listen you are
having the same question that what is
the opport for Thailand can this thing
happen in this country and what can be
done right so today we will would like
to talk to the four distinguished
panelist I probably would like to do in
two round um uh we'll
be on some question that we are
preparing and then the last 20 minute
will probably be in question and answer
in the first round we will ask question
on the use case I mean what are the use
case in Thailand we have listened in the
morning on blockchain in term of GTM in
term of um
the AI and also in term of customer
services but we also would like to know
how company in Thailand have adopted AI
into their operations
and at the same time we would also would
like
to talk about the
challenges what are the challenges
preventing us adopting Ai and finally on
the question of incentive what kind of
incentive what kind of infrastructure
that we can put in place to making sure
that AI prosper in Thailand and finally
if we have some time we will talk about
the consequences there are some
consequences that we have to deal with
especially people who become unemployed
and also in term of um the ethical and
equality questions so basically let's
manage this in um for row of questions
and uh that we we are
planning now um let me begin from the
business side um I would like to ask
Dr Nat on um from through on what is the
use case of AI in your
organization thank you very much thanks
thanks to uh allow me to be here um I
think we we let me categorize it in
three ways one is the direct Service uh
to the customers uh second is um you
know our own efficiency the business
efficiency and third one is the customer
understanding so direct uh Service
Direct product and service would
certainly include the customer
interaction call center automation I'm
not just talking about customer talking
to chatbot which may not be satisfactory
to everyone but right now customer
service people are using AI as their
Helper because phone's coming out all
the time every month every day and um
they lose track of all the details
instruction for each phones so when
customer calls in asking the details of
the phones and and how they use um they
can use AI as their helpers so that's
very real very practical ways of of
using it right now without sacrificing
the direct experience of customers
talking to people um that's the Direct
Customer uh impact um company efficiency
business efficiency we are using them on
the smart Telecom Network um Telecom
network using a lot of uh Power and um
AI help our Telecom Tower reduce power
usage they know in what time what angle
of uh the tower protected to the
community which angle have low load you
know at what time and they can kind of
customize that based on based on the the
uh actual load the third one um let me
just take the example of uh customer
understanding right um data uh we are
using data to understand 300
360° um customer knowledge um so to
offer a credit line to customers to do a
credit uh scoring for the customer and
also to collaborate with our uh business
partners to create that understanding of
customer so that we can you know upsell
or help customer personalize their you
know their content consumption things
like that that that is uh we are using
some of those for uh our u customer
understanding oh let me just mentioned
the last one um for for True uh we are
also building um AI compute
infrastructure so we are have we we are
facing um you know opportunity and also
challenges to equip our um data center
to accommodating the the the water cool
liquid cool um ships um such as Nvidia
for example um that that would be a a
huge investment
and and I might touch on that a little
bit more in in the incentive question
thank you thank you um let me move on
toak from cbx um on the use case of AI
in your
organization um I guess um SBX as you
know is a financial institution right um
and financial institution Financial
Services is known as one of the areas
where AI is actually quite primed to uh
to transform but on the sort of
perspective of of how AI will be used I
I guess I have a I have a little bit of
mixed feeling right I I I am optimistic
hopeful but at the same time very
concerned about how a will be used and
you know the impact and elaborate the
use cases uh much similar to K I think
we we trying to incorporate AI into
every part of the um the business from
decision- making data driven insights
you know help identify New Opportunities
manage a risk uh as any banks would do
uh improve the customer service you know
shorten the time to Market reduce the
cost all these things are uh in fact are
happening and we even set the target for
for the group right we say that 75% of
our businesses should be enabled by AI
in some way shape or form in three years
and that there's some clear measures
around that there's some some examples
of how how we're using um a couple of
examples right uh right now when you
when we um one of the concern as being a
bank is that we heavily regulated and
every time our sales agent try to do
something or try to sell a product there
a there's a thing called Market conduct
the bank of Thailand would actually
govern that essentially you need to say
certain things right in the past what
happened is that uh you know there'll be
mystery shopping right some people will
go and try to uh pretend to be customer
and see what the sales agent is actually
saying according to the script or not
the the way to do that is highly labor
intensive right mystery shopping and you
only do sampling so right now with with
AI right with the collaboration within
the group we actually uh designed using
language model uh and all these things
that you're familiar with to essentially
do a realtime uh transcript of what the
agent has said and right then and there
you can actually send out an email
whether you've actually completed
according to what you should say and it
it takes quite a bit of compute
resources and uh you know kind of the
the algorithm behind as some of you who
familiar with would would know right so
that that is a you know qu kind of one
good use that we're using there are a
few more use cases but the the reason
why I'm concerned that I mentioned is
that it it certainly feel that for our
organization uh we feel that we actually
doing a lot right but we barely
scratching the surface and every time
when you in the morning when you get up
you hear about new invention new AI
coming out and you can't help but feel
that you're actually uh falling behind
right in that sense and it's actually
quite challenging because
in a way for for it to happen our
current infrastructure and processes are
I would say analog right a lot of human
involvement and AI feeds on digital
infrastructure and companies like ours
even they considered relatively advanced
in in many areas still very much um sort
of got slowed down by that right and
there s the thing around data that
everyone essentially AI need to have
data and and the the quality and the
quantity of data is actually also a CH
CH I'll you know I I'll say something
that perhaps I shouldn't be saying but
I'll say it anyway you know a customer
who is actually holding a multiple
products within the organization because
they run by different business units
sometimes you don't even know that they
are actually the same Customer because
the customer ID is different and before
you know it the customer 360 that could
not is talking about is a Holy Grail
that we're trying to do it takes a lot
of time to even try to clean up that
kind of data and if you think about it
even step one is so difficult in that
sense right and you have a lot of
Promise around AI coming out which we
are very excited about and we're trying
to we have tens of use cases actually
rolling around and within the
organization but at the same time I
think it's it's the rating is so
organization and we touch on the human
capital later on in terms of the riness
other the people right in the end I
think uh this is where an area where as
a company as a country I think we can
use AI to Leap Frog uh where we are
today but you got to do it right and you
have to um sort of plan it and it's not
just going to happen by just seeing the
examples elsewhere and trying to imagine
that it could happen in your
organization you actually need to do a
lot of ground work uh behind the scene
and that's something that um you know we
are excited by but like I said also
concerned if we're not uh putting the
right infrastructure in
places thank you in fact I also come
from banking business also I can confirm
what could arak have said we we failed
the same way we just scratching the
surface so many more thing to be done
and in fact a lot of a lot of our
customer now U using the interaction
through the mobile banking almost 90%
that's very very much lending itself to
the AI um technology that we can help to
service the client more now let me turn
on to Professor crimson's um we have
listened the whole day in fact on the
use cases
from the business segment and in fact
now two more from Thailand um I would
like to ask you I mean we have seen a
lot of Advance a lot of thinking in the
University level um but how can Academia
and business can work together to bring
about the implementation of AI better
from the idea from the University into
the business from your experience please
I love getting easy questions um but
it's an important question and I'm going
to highlight two places where I think
Academia can can
help one
is there are lots of academics that take
on interesting problems and their goal
is to write a great paper helps you get
promoted but I think the real Advantage
is to take on problems where you not
only solve the problem but you think
about the impact as my colleagues know
I'm it 's mission statement says we
educate students we create knowledge and
we apply that knowledge to the great
challenges of the nation and the world
and so I think universities not just MIT
but other universities really ought to
think
about not just tackling new problems not
just coming up with new Solutions but
hearing from the potential place where
there's the impact of so what is the
real need um you know what's the thing
that you really need to make this go and
I think if I look at experiences from
MIT I think the opportunity for Thailand
is to help identify unique opportunities
here where you could use help from
Academia to think about Solutions we've
seen that with interactions with other
countries where it's something specific
to that situation that really makes
things interesting so it's a high level
answer but I think many of my colleagues
at MIT are interested in understanding
specific problems here where our
if you like our experience in creating
Solutions can work with colleagues in
business here um to try and find ways to
find
Solutions I think the second place if I
can really quickly we've talked about it
during the day I think upskilling is a
real challenge for companies jobs are
going to change um you've got employees
that are no longer going to be able to
do the things they did in the past and
how do you help them deal with that and
I think universities have an opportunity
to create educational experiences that
aren't just the traditional MIT class
but they're aimed at helping deal with
upskilling and for that we need help
from industry to understand so what is
the new rule going to be you know a
worker that's I'm going to use if I may
the banking example I'm sure you have
employees that are um you know
traditional tellers traditional
accountants those are going to change
help us understand what the new jobs
will look like and then how can we help
do the upskilling to make it happen but
I think upskilling is real challenge for
AI is it changes the job situation
Academia has a role to play in trying to
help adapt to
that I I think our our accountant will
be G will be gone very
soon and but but then but then can you
give us some more example where MIT have
been working with business in term of um
helping with AI projects or how can you
collaborate
so we can see more and
clearer so unfortunately the examples I
think of are less focused on business my
colleagues can probably do a better job
of that but I think there are great
examples of
MIT interacting with companies to think
about how to use the new tools to create
new opportunities so I'll I'll give you
just one example I don't mean to isolate
it but it's one that I know MIT has a
partnership with IB m u IBM in fact
moved its Walt its Watson health unit to
Cambridge in order to be close to MIT
and we have a series of projects where
MIT researchers and IBM researchers get
together every year to propose a problem
and to find places where there's an
overlap and then to work jointly to come
up with Solutions so I'm hesitating
because it's not a solution to a
business problem but it's a solution to
new opportunities in business it's a
5-year project IBM is very happy with it
um and um you know we're continuing to
use it I said one I'll give you a second
one quickly um MIT has a partnership
with teada the um the teada the the what
the I think of it as a Japanese although
it's International but a but a a an
international if you like um
pharmaceutical company and again what we
do is we have MIT researchers talk with
teada researchers where the teada folks
provide input on specific problems of
interest to them and then they partner
with MIT researchers to come up with
projects that we'll try and find
solutions to it so they're generic
examples but they are really places
where the business is providing input on
specific challenges and they're finding
MIT colleagues to come up with Solutions
thank you we we definitely looking
forward to working with MIT on some of
these problem uh I I bet that there will
be a lot of business who would like to
work with MIT now let me turn on to
katai katai come from our government
agency DEA um which is support digital
economy in Thailand um what is your view
on AI um this application of new
technology artificial intelligence in
business uh what is the stance of the
government how you look at
it okay thank you kapan um I would like
i' like to um give my recognition to Dr
vet as well he has founded Deepa the
organization where came from your boss
my my boss um well um The Stance of the
government I think has been far beyond
the the the boom of AI um in recent
years uh we have the national AI um
master plan which spans from 2021 to
2027 so sixe spans um in that spans we
focus on two phases of uh the
development the very first phas will be
the fundamental aspect of it uh which is
the um the data Covance the um the
framework the participation from the
public and private Partnerships and um
all that uh we are drafting uh laws Al B
it will be uh quite slow um um in
drafting the law in Thailand but um
there are two laws involved in AI which
is the AI business laws and AI um
promoting uh promotion act uh well why
that is being delayed I think it's a
good sign um that um the Pioneer in uh
developing or uh uh implementing the AI
technology we have some head start on
that because uh the laws can sometimes
times uh uh shoulder you with like some
of the weight that you have to take care
um a little bit extra carefully um and
also uh besides the law that is being
delayed um there are the guidelines that
um Eda uh another agency is uh uh
putting up the framework uh which is the
AI governance Center uh this Center is
uh responsible for giving consultation
to public and private um sectors to like
who would like to implement the AI
projects so it it are it is a very good
foundation that we have to work with but
um on the second phase uh which is like
starting very soon will be the expanding
the research expanding uh the
applications that AI has to offer across
various um sectors in Thailand um and
and in Thailand there are a few um
prominent um verticals that we can uh
have a very good and uh extensive data
from uh first one being tourism the
second one uh being the healthcare and
the third one being agriculture which I
think uh we can we can explore more in
the in more interactive rounds but um
from uh Professor Grimson said the
upskilling the workers the workforce uh
it is exactly what um Deepa has been
tasking to do um we are proposing to the
government and get the the the approval
of having the the tax deduction for the
corporates who would like to upscaling
their Workforce so the corporate income
tax will be deductible up to 250% of the
expense and for the people without uh
like who works in freelance without um
uh uh organization they can enjoy up to
150% of personal income tax so um if
that skill um matches the the road map
that we are putting in forth um they are
entitled to that tax
benefit thank you seem like the
government is now preparing a lot of
support um let me turn to kunak on the
question of
challenges I think along the way that
you try to implement AI um AI adoption
there there will be a lot of challenges
uh can you share with us exactly what
are the challenges that you are facing
so far and I will turn to goodat to
later on please so I I I would say that
if you know in the spirit of um I guess
being analytical that I would say the
way the four things that we need to put
in place to get the the impact right one
is essentially the the AI the model
itself uh second one is the
infrastructure underneath that you can
actually run uh the AI on top the
processes and everything right the third
one is the data and the fourth one is
the human you know it used to be very
difficult to actually uh we used to
operate under the assumption that you
know we have data we and not we don't
have good algorithm we can't run the
model so on and so forth with AI with
Gen coming out I think that first parted
equation is actually considered solved
and is it's actually uh becoming an
issue where you ride on the global
capabilities coming out from open AI
coming out from a lot of places where
you you feel that okay at least the
algorithm part they brain the AI part
you you you you have it
right the the the other three though
remains a challenge right uh the
infrastructure I mentioned in the
previous
discussion uh the systems are still not
100% digital and when it's not digital
there's disruption it's very difficult
to actually deploy uh meaningful
processes uh AI enable processes
optimization on top so that's that's one
thing that we need to fix and the longer
the oranization in our organization
turning 118 years this year so you can
imagine the kind of and Bangkok Bank is
also
not doing so differently in that sense
uh we have quite a bit of Legacy
processes and system so I think those uh
probably can appreciate that uh data uh
mentioned the quality and quantity
that's actually quite uh quite difficult
but I think the last one which is the
human is the one that actually I foresee
to be the the most difficult one it's
not so much in the past we were
concerned about how many data scientist
we would have and you know things of
that nature because we're worried about
the algorithms right but right now I
think think is more of the broader
Workforce are you able to uh you know
kind of fully Leverage What AI has to
offer is becoming a question of can you
develop the new skills for the future uh
the skills that you know around asking
the right questions having the
creativity and having imagination to ask
the AI to do something which is
unfortunately the the skill that that
critical thinking that creativity is
something that's actually unfortunately
lacking quite a bit in in in Thailand
and perhaps in other part of the world
so where I I think this is uh when we
need to invest a lot of time and
resources I'm glad that GBA is actually
having when when is that the tax coming
out that would be good it's coming up
okay good so 250% I I take note um the
you know because I I I'll give you
examples of how we we think about we
have what we call AI literacy program
where you know for we aim 100% of our
employees need to actually have basic
rudimentary AI skills and not to say
they can program right they need to know
what it is what it can do what it cannot
do how to use it you know so on and so
forth so everyone has to kind of know it
the same way they use computer in that
sense but the the next one is the one
where we talk about you need to actually
process abilities to interact and use AI
this is a low code no code type of uh uh
access you'll be able to fully leverage
whatever is solutions that out there and
the last uh much smaller percentage is
in uh research and development where we
need to actually uh Advance the skills
at one point we need to actually have
our own each company I believe you need
to actually have your own competitive
advantage and you need to actually
develop that from the ground up right
and we have actually a few two team
members uh sitting in this room as well
from R&D where they focus on building
that advanced skills so I would say uh
to make the impact in the long run it
starts from The Human Side of Things
where the the tools the capability that
the brain I think you will catch up it
will become more of a commodity product
but the people who's actually using it
is the one that I think will will proven
to be um the biggest challenge that we
need to
overcome thank you Dr not come from
another industry do you have the same
challenges or a different one please
very much the same I I think um I Echo
every Point um that arak said um you
know data um algorithm um and compute U
infrastructure and um I just want to add
maybe some ankles to the data um more
and more data cannot be just internal
data it it has to be collaborate uh with
outside organization or even public um
organization or public data um how to do
that while um uh respecting the the
privacy and anonymizing the data It's
Tricky right to say the least I think um
how we can do that that I think in at
least in my view that is still a
struggle um but if the customer uh um uh
can benefit from from doing that I think
uh the industry is is you know basically
going that way right but how to do it uh
while keeping that respecting that uh
right I think I think that is something
that we need to maybe put our heads
together and try to to crack that maybe
there's some best practice out there um
but but that that's one ankle that um
that's a challenge the second one I
think the compute side um we are still
quite you know very slow in in in that
in that side in Thailand um we have yet
to have a lot of compute um
infrastructure for for AI training and
influence and uh when right right now
while we are using the regional um
infrastructure it's very expensive it's
very expensive for training and for for
actual use so having a local computer
infrastructure is one of the most
important uh um element um and one of
the key uh uh driving force for that is
is the power um it's power cost uh to
the infrastructure because
infrastructure use a lot of uh Power
that would be something that we also
need to to to crack uh before we we
getting more and more um compute coming
from whether it's from Nvidia by
themselves or they're going through
hyperscalers you know and other AI uh
Compu infrastructure that that's going
to be a challenge for
us um I we we listened from two business
already they have very similar problem
uh what are the main Challenge from the
government point of view in adopting AI
what what you feel that that is need to
be done the obstacle from preventing
business in Thailand really move toward
more AI adoption in Thailand well uh the
challenge just for the private sectors
um to to adopt AI would be the the
workforce probably number one because AI
is changing um every night um every
morning we wake up we have a new
technology coming up um so um that's a
part that the upscaling is the of the
utmost uh importance um the second one
would be the data um I agree with Dr n
that U the data from one Corporation or
one organization alone probably not be
able to train uh decent AI um of today
um just forget about the future but um
we will need to find the framework for
the government data to uh desensi uh Des
sensitiv um all the data um remove all
the sensitive items um and then share it
with the the
organization um that probably be the way
that we have to with we have to crack it
and work it to to uh together to to to
train a better AI for tomorrow and one
area that we need to focus on is um
thees because um everyone here is coming
from the very big corporations and thees
the small and medium Enterprises are the
one that uh probably get trapped into
this U technology Gap um and the
government will have to find a way to
subsidize um to be able to um allow
thees to access the AI with the tools at
the reduced cost to help uh I think
sharing some of the burden of upfront uh
investment fores so I think the money is
probably be the very very important
thing and the people
drak thank you I want to turn to
Professor Grimson um how about your
experience I mean what are the
challenges in other countries Now you
listen to type person three already
right what are the challenges that you
have seen in other country that prevent
adoption of AI and then um we would like
to also come back to the question of
reskilling the workforce preparation
please I love I love being the last
person in the group because all the good
answers have been given so I'm just
going to I'm just going to highlight
them I totally agree on data and I would
add to it and I think it's it's you know
implicit in what you said
it's making sure that the data is of
high quality dealing with bias in the
data is really important uh in order to
um make sure that you're training a
system in a way that is actually going
to be valuable and I appreciate the
answer from the government perspective I
totally agree with you that one of the
worries I have about the data is small
and medium-sized Enterprises may not
have access to it you can already see
this in the US right I mean a Microsoft
and Amazon and Google can really
dominate in this space because they've
got massive amounts of data and open AI
has has done that well so I think the
idea of a government thinking about how
to make that data accessible to other
partners really is crucial so I think
data is really important and bias and
data I think is is really important um
one of the places where I think Academia
can help with a challenge we've talked a
little bit about um upskilling workers I
do think that's an important part
but I think there's another opportunity
maybe a little smaller but I still think
really important how do you get an
employee in a company to actually trust
the answer that the AI system comes up
with um and sorry what I'll point back
to the study I mentioned earlier the
Sloan study that showed that when users
were using
gp4 um they their performance on a task
that gp4 did well improved by using it
if they were using gp4 and they had a
guide on how to use it it improved
either more but when the task was
something that was not well suited to a
large language model their performance
declined because they didn't question it
oh it's an AI system has got to be doing
the right thing so point of this is I
think Academia can help by providing
training components that help people
decide when has this passed the smell
test the smoke test when do you really
want us to decide to use it that will
improve the the incorporation of AI into
system but when it comes up with a
really bad answer and it changes what a
company does it's not good so I think
that's a challenge is how do you decide
how to evaluate the performance of the
system and I think Academia can help
provide things in that space But but you
also mentioned early in the day about um
education for K12 I think that also will
be interesting thing to to to talk about
because in fact AI can be trained early
on in life so people become more AI
literate and then be able to adapt it
later on can you can you give us some
more example and understanding yeah I I
think K12 is a place where um Academia
can actually have an impact I'll give
you a very specific example it's just an
example I have a colleague um in open
learning um faculty member in media lab
Cynthia Brazil who's created a program
called day of AI and the idea of day of
AI is they create curricular material
four different versions one one aimed at
elementary school students one aimed at
middle school students two aimed at high
school students one for students that
are stem oriented one for students that
are not a lot of hands-on experience but
the idea of day of AI is it's a day in
which teachers with help from these
materials can talk to those students
about so what is it how's it going to
change your experience when you graduate
and if you're an elementary school
student that's 10 years now it's going
to change it a lot um what can it do
what can it not do Dave of AI last year
had um schools from a 100 different
countries with several hundred, school
students impacted in terms of getting
that sense of experience now that's a
day it's not changed the curriculum but
it's a valuable way to actually think
about getting students to think about
this I think on top of that we can build
curricular material that actually can be
used by school teachers um to
encorporate into other kinds of classes
and I know it's not related to this
topic but by the way having done day of
AI we're in the process of doing day of
climate with the same idea how do we get
young students to understand the impact
of climate change the impact of
sustainability as we deal with
it University professors are probably
not the best people to create curricular
material for for younger children but we
can partner with people to create those
pieces and I do think there's an
opportunity for us to actually change
K12
y I cannot
resist I I remember when I went to it
there was away a picture of student
sitting under the fire host and then
learning from the
professor so you DP so many idea and
then we have to learn quickly and I'm
thinking MIT Professor teaching
elementary school so we have to training
very hard okay but but but you really
think that we should begin from early
age not not just um 18 years old 16
years old so
as early as possible on AI I
think so if you don't know the comment
the comment is getting an education in
MIT is like trying to tr trying to take
a drink from a fire hose uh you can
imagine how painful that is uh
and so to that point I think MIT and
other places need to work with education
experts to understand the level at which
you can do that but to your question I
actually think that it would be very
valuable to introduce simple concepts of
AI to first graders to second graders
there are things that they can
understand um they're not well I was
going to say they're not going to
program we have occasionally people who
show up at MIT who have been programming
since they were six but I think we can
have impact on very young children to
think about what is AI what does it do
when should I trust it and how is it
going to change my experience moving
forward yes I think we should thank you
I think I think um now we probably have
a new generation they said generation
beta but I think it's probably
generation AI um that all the kid have
to learn and then live with AI since
early age and then the more time passed
by AI will become even more importance
now let me turn to the last round of
question on the incentive what what can
we do I think everyone who in this room
probably feel that so many opportunities
so many thing to be done so many things
to be captured but how can Thailand
become the leader in this field right I
think um many country have been
progressing very well in in the area of
AI what can we do together to really put
Thailand on that map I now I would like
to begin from Kai first uh let's give
the government um the first comment on
what can the government do to to Really
create the right ecosystem for AI to
prosper in Thailand Okay um apart from
the upscaling um package that we
prepared um I believe the government uh
by the board of Investments have already
introduced the package I think way
before like maybe seven eight years ago
about um AI being included into the A1
package A1 package means the highest
incentives that um any Corporation will
get whether it be the um investment from
abroad or within the
country um A1 package allows you to uh
have up to 13 years of tax holiday with
no cap so um there's no tax for you for
like 13 years and if you are in um the
specific areas for for example eec or in
the special economic zones uh that the
government's announced um you be
entitled for another five years of 50%
corporate income tax so that is a I
believe it's it's very generous package
and for the eec package itself um if you
have experts coming in to Thailand and
worked in uh let's say the eec area um
that expert is entitled for 177% flat
rate of personal income tax so it's
going to match the neighboring uh tax uh
benefit from from our neighboring um
countries so that's a tax incentives um
not just only those two that I have
mentioned um there are several more um
for the usage of the package as well the
government is also giving the grants um
and also with the matching funds for
example if a company is investing in Ai
and uh the company think it's going to
be eligible for for the matching fund
they can apply for the fund uh for up to
um 50 million B per
company okay and that is through the
competitive funds that has set up since
um uh former cabinets so it's 20 billion
BS funds that are sitting there and
waiting for uh companies to like have
cool projects to come in and claim that
uh that fund and also the government has
uh the cloud first policy um which is uh
implementing but uh we are seeing some
of the uh use case from the government
from the public sectors uh utilizing the
data and with the AI coming in so um the
cloud first policy will uh probably help
speed speed up the the transformation to
AI uh with within the public sector and
we have the digital skill road map uh
that uh we set up a list of uh courses
and syllabuses that uh we we would like
uh the corporations and thees to to to
look at and if it matches some of the
skill set that the corporations would
like to uh Empower their Workforce then
it's entitled to the tax benefit as well
so that'll be four of these okay I I
want to turn to Professor first um what
kind of policies that government can put
in place to really Foster AI I mean um
in other countries that you have seen
sorry say again um what kind what what
are the set of policy measures that the
government can put in place to in
incentivize the adoption of
AI and then I will turn toak and then
now so I have more time to think about
but
just so I I think first of all I mean
I'm struggling because I don't know the
tie system well no but in in other
country not no need for Thailand or
maybe in America I mean what what do
what do they do that we can learn from
them I mean what what is the role of the
government in the AI adoption yeah so I
think three comments two of them I think
we've already heard I think this idea of
encouraging upskilling is really
valuable I think this idea of providing
incentives for for companies to move
forward I I think is really valuable I
think the third place where I the
government can work with business and
Academia but especially with business to
really encourage AI
is to think about the safeguards on the
regulatory side of um when is a product
safe to be used what are the standards
that a product needs to demonstrate
before you you decide that and I said it
earlier in the day I look at what the EU
has done and think it's a really good
start it's not perfect but it's a good
start on saying for these kinds of
products here's the level of concern for
these kinds of products here's a higher
level of concern so I think to the
extent that government can work with
businesses together to say here are the
regulatory issues here are the
safeguards in use that will make it
it'll help users accept it more readily
of saying yes this is something I trust
to use and it'll protect the businesses
from um you know if you have that
disaster if you've met the regulations
hopefully you've got some protection
around it as opposed to if there are
none and I would say as a last comment
you know in the US I think the major
companies started this Microsoft
partnered up with with Amazon with
Google with Facebook to say what are the
initial levels of performance that we
need how do we get that into regulation
I think that's a place where it can
really help that's very insightful um
now let me turn to uh Dr n first I mean
you have listened to K chai already
proposing what the government can do do
you feel it's enough I mean do you want
something
[Laughter]
more okay you can choose me which one go
first um okay um I think certainly
incentive to upscale is very important
um and and we looking forward to to work
as a PPP as well um there's a lot of
tremendous opportunity for uh to to do
PPP in a certain pilot zone for educa
specifically for education for example
uh which is the right formula um I'm in
connect ed uh program which BBL also
part of of many organization here also
part of where it's PPP between um um
Ministry of Education um corporations
and also um the um schools um work
together some of the projects or
districts that implemented uh create
their own type of upscaling it is
Grassroots and that kind of various
projects that free form project was
created some are effective some is not
but it's excellent to be able to free up
the imagination and see which project
Direction approach it's working so when
when we funding this type of
upscaling uh I think uh the the the
Forum where we allow creativity for for
for this type of format I think that's
important on funding certainly
corporates uh wants to uh wants to help
as well
uh not just to train the students but
also to uh helpme adopting AI that is
win-win right I mean if is using
corporate also uh have opportunities to
work together and and win more as well
um so incentive to helpme adopting AI is
the second thing I want to uh touch on
as well um yeah and and and and I think
um for the rest I'm I'm totally agree
with with with all the points I think as
also very important because they don't
have the resources I mean to really
implement this AI really need people and
also resources right can can I just
elaborate because I I missing um the the
When you mention the small company
there's a lot of good AI um companies in
Thailand
startups uh who who have that very
specific products on in verticals
various verticals
government and corporates can help and
and also education can help play
important role of to to identify those
startups and allow them to work with the
corporate you know the the the
corporates who have you know various use
case opportunity Market access if we
allow those uh and and work together
with those uh startups we can create a
lot of a successful um you know new
generation of of AI Entre entrepreneurs
and I think that's very important I mean
we talk about big tech and and those
coming with compute and everything but
vertical algorithms vertical you know s
SRM small language model very critical
for our future and I I think we I want
to Advocate to to make sure that uh we
have the opportunity to uh AI startups
for TI AI startups to to flourish thank
you kunak we have the last word on this
round before we start a Q&A session we
only have eight minutes and many
questions
so I I think you were asking about how
to essentially if I paraphrase right how
to accelerate uh Thailand using with AI
I think you know coming from
corporations we always need to Define
measure of success right we need to
Define who or what Thailand uh is I
think the who they the the general
population I think the concept of
education is is what uh we need to put
in place and you know before back in the
days kak could not you only could get
MIT educ ation if you go to MIT but here
you can actually be anywhere and get MIT
level of Education fire host equivalent
uh from anywhere so I think we need to
take advantage of that from you know
kind of from from the education
standpoint but if you talk about the
other part essentially the corporations
right Thailand 95% of companies are so
if we cannot solve problems then there's
no hope that we can actually solve
Thailand problem
UMB uh we can see either AI s a as a you
know kind of opportunity or or a threat
I am a little bit pessimistic on this
one where I I think the the Gap the
inequality The Divide between the large
corporations and thees will only get
wider unless gets help and therefore we
need to actually help uh smmes the large
corporations struggle as they are I
think they'll find ways because they
have sufficient means and resources but
smme I mean we we're talking AI but
reality is that if you go and askme to
do proper financial accounting is a
challenge for them today right I mean if
you think about in that sense I mean AI
is this thing like in a light 5 10 years
from now but unfortunately AI is here
and unless unless you do something about
it you they'll be left behind even more
so so program like know the government
is putting in place uh I think it's
important but I I guess the the the
house and the what uh I already
mentioned won repeat but the measure of
success to me I think you ought to be
able to make sure that leverage AI to
improve things such as productivity uh
improve things such as the value add
that they could actually do within the
product not just producing some basic
Commodities those are things that we I
think we should find a way to AI to to
help and if we can do that then I think
we can create an uplift in in in the
competitiveness and and and once that's
the case I think there there's a hope
for the country overall and I I'm quite
hopeful about the the various programs
that the big companies and the
government is actually putting in place
so so all very supportive and in fact we
we need to be rooting for
ourmes okay thank you I think it's loud
and clear so we hope that Kun chatai
will take the message back to the
government really cons a large portion
of our company and they need really need
help um if we can work only with big
corporate there will be even larger gap
between this company now let me turn on
to the question
please can make it can you make it
larger okay oh that one that cannot see
from there um Can which uh the first one
how do you want to solve privacy and
ethical data sharing can SEC multi
partic computation and privacy
preserving blockchain create trust with
users
for sharing confidential data for banks
and health um yes
please I was gonna ask okay
please so okay I I'll I'll answer so now
I think solving I think the technical
mean to solving confidential and data
proper data sharing is indeed required
and whether blockchain is the the
solution it has has a prospect of being
a solution right we need to look into
the um the the Computer Resources
required behind that but there are also
other techniques right the things being
popularized like Federated learning
where you don't really need to see
actual Source uh of the data you can
actually leverage the data and make use
of it as much as you like so in in that
sense you know data from True could be
used by data uh combined with data from
scvx to do something even combined with
a BBL but there's some framework around
that so I'm totally in agree with and
with the the the person who asked this
question that we need to solve the the
problem and it's considered a technical
problem so we could actually use a
technical solution be it the blockchain
or other emerging Technologies and uh
Solutions which I think Academia is
actually working actively in this area
because they know cracking the data is
is what need to be done and I think uh
it's the right area to to look into if I
could add I agree I think it's a really
crucial area I think there are
blockchain's one but there are other
Solutions will point to one other one
it's in early stages it's not ready to
be used in prime time but there are
people working on it and it's an
encryption system called homomorphic
encryption where the idea is that you
encrypt all of the data into a database
and you can actually query it without
ever decrypting the data sounds a little
strange but there are ways to do it and
so I think if that becomes practical
it's as I understand it not yet there
it's a way to protect the data protect
the privacy and yet still let you use it
to get out the broad information that
you want from that so something to watch
in the future I I think kunat already
already mentioned about this um data is
very important in fact it's not only
internal data but it must be data from
outside but to to put the two together
that they needs some protection some
rule of law to govern the an
anonymization and the creation of this
big data that way we can share and we
can learn from it and and I think the
government is now working on this topic
now let me turn on to the next two
question it's very very similar um the
first one uh intend for DEA now you
cannot um is Thailand planning any
universal basis income if let's say half
of the workforce become Obsolete and
without any income and Social Security
is this a topic at all and and and let's
move on to the next one also um the next
question please
with AI replacing lowlevel task pushing
human to higher level works is there a
limit to how far this chift can go could
we eventually hit a wall when human
capability can keep our place I I think
this is the question about the AI
replacing the workforce right what this
is the consequence that we have to face
later on even though today we have
listened to many people said AI is
helping human but but in fact when we we
think about robot when you put robot
with AI there will be a lot of job
losing to this kind of human humanoid
robot right um in the warehouse It's
Already Gone um now byd Factory is now a
lot of humanoid robot walking around and
and many more so basically a lot of job
will be
disappear what to do I mean do do
government have some scheme preparing
for this change I think the we have seen
the change throughout the history for
several times we see the um the
Industrial Revolution for a a couple of
times already and I think this one is
going to replace some jobs the low level
um the repetitive um task as well um and
the the best thing that we can do right
now is upskilling the workforce to be
able to move on to the um upper chain uh
of the the the the industry so um they
can do a a much more uh
human uh worthy worthy job in the future
um I would say that um it's going to
replace a job and it's our of probably
our best interest to keep our human kind
uh move up the value chain um and the
thing is I saw one question about you
Universal basic income um I I am not
aware of that like is it going to be the
10,000 B scheme that the government has
produced but um we would love to have
all humans on Deck um to to help U with
the Aging society that we are facing in
Thailand so um we would not have the
scheme that have the people um take
advantage of the the universal basic
income in the future I this is my
personal view okay I think we of time
but but any participant the panel would
like to um chip in on the question of
the human losing job because of AI what
can we do what how can we
prepare no
okay okay so today we have listened
to very interesting and insightful
discussion on the use case of AI in
Thailand the challenges the incentive
the infrastructure that we can put to
adopt AI I think everyone would agree
that there are many things to be done
and especially listening from Professor
Crimson at in the morning
session three key important component
deep learning data Computing cloud is
all there I think with all this
component in place we probably will have
the golden golden age of AI later on and
Thailand cannot miss out so let's work
together and try to solve the problem
and put Thailand in the map thank
you thank you
[Music]