the arrival of artificial intelligence.
Uh Justin Reich is the principal
investigator. Uh he lives here. He's
presenting in California today. I live
in California. I'm presenting here
today. It's not the most efficient way
to do it, but here we are. Um I'm a
journalist by background. So, um Justin
is the social scientist, the researcher,
the educational technologist.
uh but it turns out there's a lot of
overlap between qualitative research and
journalism and I want to start with a
anecdote uh as a journalist I tend to
think in terms of narrative in terms of
anecdote so I want to start with an
anecdote that I think expresses why
we're using the term arrival in the
title uh so this is from Steve by the
way I just I really enjoy playing around
with the older generation of dolly to
make my slides sides. So, uh, forgive
me. I just I I find them kind of
hilarious. Uh, Steve is a technology
director,
meaning he doesn't, you know, he's not
just managing laptops and Chromebooks
and things like that at at the school,
although he probably does that, manages
the servers, but he also part of his job
is to help teachers think through how to
use technology to advance their
educational goals. So he's here in
Massachusetts and this is a story he
told about uh November December of 2022.
So I think it was it was December 8th
and I was home sick with COVID. I got an
email. I'm on a list serve, you know,
with all the tech directors in
Massachusetts and I got an email that
said have AI write your next uh English
paper or something. And then uh the
subcaption was buckle up, here it comes.
And I someone had basically shared a
video of this thing called chat GBT that
was generating an essay about I think it
was about raising in the sun and I was
like what is going on
here? So Steve uh sees that email
realizes this is going to be a big deal.
This is, you know, a week or two after
uh chat GPT or GPT3.5
uh dropped and people were just starting
to figure out its capabilities. And so
he wrote an email, in fact, he got chat
GPT to write an email to all the
teachers in that school district uh to
say, "Hey, there's this new tool. Uh it
may end up being very helpful to us as
educators. It can also do uh your kids
homework assignment for them, so you
might want to know about it." uh they
very quickly put together some
professional development
uh gave some guidelines to the teachers
and they've been sort of working to
catch up ever since then but I like this
idea of buckle up here it comes I think
it gets to the idea of uh arrival
technologies versus adoption
technologies and this is something that
Justin and I came up with as far as we
know we originated this idea at least in
the context of education um we may be
wrong about that so um school districts
throughout history. Um, there's been
various technologies present in schools,
in classrooms, things like chalkboards,
pencils, textbooks, all sorts of other
kinds of technology. And generally, um,
most of those technologies that are
present in learning environments are
adopted by the schools, by the school
district, by the teachers. Uh,
educational technologies can cause harm
to educational systems as well as
benefits. Uh they technologies can cause
distraction, academic misconduct,
reduced instructional quality, cyber
bullying. Uh but with technology
adoption uh schools can introduce new
technologies when they are prepared to
manage the risks. They have policies in
place. They have data privacy agreements
in place. They have updated their
academic integrity policy. um they can
make sometimes the wise, important and
prudent and ethical choice not to adopt
a particular technology if they decide
the school's not ready for it or if they
decide the technologies affordances are
not worth the risks or the challenges.
But in the case of arrival technologies
um they bypass the planning, the
assessment, the policym the professional
learning um and uh they crash the party.
they show up and in the case of
something like chat GPT, the students
have access to it irrespective of any
policy that the school district is going
to put in place. They might try to ban
it at the server. Uh but kids with
laptops um will have access to it at
home. Also, uh students are pretty good
at getting around uh bans. They can
figure out how to use things like VPNs.
Maybe they have a phone, maybe they have
two phones uh where they can access chat
GPT. So it's very very hard to ban the
technology. Uh pocket calculators a kind
of canonical
uh arrival technology cliff notes or
spark notes uh the books that students
use to bypass uh the learning and the
thinking their uh their teachers want
them to engage in. Uh smartphones
arguably are something of an arrival
technology. And actually many many
school districts right now are in the
process of thinking about whether they
need to restrict uh mobile phones. Um so
we wanted to understand how teachers are
experiencing all of this and also
students and actually we started with a
grant from the Spencer Foundation in
Chicago and then uh the CIRC uh grant
really allowed us to expand what we were
doing to diversify our cohort to
diversify geographically. Um so we
talked to I think yeah 85ish uh we're
always doing a couple more interviews. I
think we did a few more this week. uh
teachers about 40 students um we didn't
want to just ask them hey what do you
think about chat GPT is it making your
life great is it making your life
terrible we wanted to understand what
was top of mind for them before
introducing the concept of AI so you
know what's your school like what's your
job like what's going on what are your
top challenges right now sometimes they
would bring up AI chat GPT in this list
sometimes they wouldn't um and then
after we got sort of that baseline top
of mind information we would ask if they
had noticed AI
in their school. How is it being used by
whom are students using it? Are teachers
using it? Are you using it? Are you
using it to support learning and
education? Are students using it in ways
that you approve of? Are students using
it in ways that you disapprove of? And I
would say that probably the most common
story we got is something like this. I
think probably we're still coding the
data, but I would just estimate
something like threequarters of the
teachers we spoke to had a story like
Alec who's an eighth grade social
studies teacher in Chicago. So, you
know, if I'm used to looking at a
student's classwork and uh they sound
very much like an eighth grader, you
know, in the way that they structure
their sentences, the vocabulary that
they pick out, and then I, you know, I
receive an assignment, most likely an
assignment done at home that is, you
know, you can pick it out almost
instantly. Uh, you know, the the
manifold differences between the south
and the north, you know, during the
reconstruction prompted, you know,
whatever. it's it's not it's not eighth
grade language or it's not these
students eighth grade language. And so,
uh, that's something that I would
probably have a conversation with the
student and I would say, "Hey, look, you
know, um, this doesn't sound like your
usual voice. Uh, when I looked in your
edit history, I saw that this paragraph
had just kind of popped up in, you know,
in a split second. You know, can you
explain to me how that happened?" Going
to move to the next one. Uh you missed
unfortunately when the audio dropped
out, you missed the kind of hilarious
uh um the manifold differences between
the north and south uh during the uh
postbell or antibbellum period led
inevitably to the conflict. You know
that there was this very kind of
academic language used used by an eighth
grader who probably doesn't normally
speak that way. Uh we got a lot of
stories like that. I think most teachers
in K12 schools have experienced
something like that. We also got a lot
of stories like that from students uh
some of whom um well they were on
different sides of uh of sometimes
they're talking about what they're
doing, sometimes they're talking about
what their fellow students are doing,
sometimes they're concerned about it,
sometimes they're excited to have a new
tool that um you know allows them to get
their homework done quickly so they can
go hang out with their friends. Um we
also heard some stories like this one.
This is Eric Timmons. Um, and he's
talking about he'll start by talking
about the challenge of generating uh
discussion questions and other kind of
curriculum for his students who are film
students. So, he's often getting them to
watch uh movies and that or read things
that aren't in the textbooks and he
wants them to engage in certain kinds of
discussions. I'll be honest, like as a
teacher, there's like sometimes a
feeling of like, well, you know what,
like I'm not a curriculum designer.
Like, should I be going and doing all of
this work for free, you know? Um, but at
the end of the day, it's not going to
happen. So, I have to do it, right?
Right. So, uh, um, so I, uh, um, being
able to work with the smartest
curriculum designer that's ever existed
and have that at at my disposal, it
means GPT. And being able to take
designer that's ever, Project Zero's
thinking routines and apply it to like
every assignment that I have is
remarkable. I remember I was at a PD and
someone introduced it. I'll stop that
there. Um, one thing I'll say about Eric
Timonss, and I think this is a general
observation. I think that somebody like
him is able to use chat GPT effectively
to design discussion questions for his
students because he already knows how to
do that. He already has that domain
knowledge. Uh, that's just an aside, but
uh, an aside, but that's another pattern
we've noticed. Um, and from the
students, this is probably the most
extreme story, but I find it kind of
amusing. Uh, Woody is an eighth grader
in the Northeast. We talked to him about
a year ago. I think he's in nth grade
now. He did he he described his science
class moving through topics more quickly
than was comfortable to him because he
felt like his teacher was getting an
illusion like a mirage uh in terms of
what the students understood and he
thought this because he sits in the back
and he watches his fellow students type
prompts that the teachers are giving
them in the chat GPT and the teacher
can't see but he can. If you had to
estimate, say in a classroom of 20
students, how many were using chat GPT
to cheat the way that you're describing,
how many would you say? Okay. So, I'd
say that there's 10 people in that class
using it for everything, like cheating
on the whole paper is AI. I'd say
there's another five that probably half
of it's written by AI, but they do
actually read it through and go, gee,
maybe I don't want to include the part
that says as a large language model, but
they like read it through and copy parts
and splice bits and do whatever. Then
I'd say of So you've got five remaining.
I'd say probably four of that five do
the paper legitimately
and then there's another one
that's going and I'll skip the rest of
the of of his answer just what he's
going to say is that there might be
students who are using chat GPT to
supplement their work maybe as a
research tool or something like that. Um
so overall lots of concerns about
cheating or bypassing learning lots of
discussions of enforcement cat-and-
mouse games. There are some examples of
teachers saying I I is helping them
support their work as teachers. I would
say it's probably twothirds the top one
to maybe one-third. Um we're we're
coding the data. That's my sense of it
right now. Uh some examples of AI
helping with administrative tasks. Uh
teachers role model modeling uses of AI
by students to support um student
learning. Uh perplexity use perplexity
as a research tool. It searches the
internet. That's a good example of that.
Um some experimentation with AI powered
edtech. Um and uh most teachers feel
that the support and guidance from the
school and district has been inadequate.
We fielded a study with Rand last fall
with their national teacher panel. They
talked to a thousand or so uh teachers.
25% said they've gotten any guidance or
support with regard to the arrival of
generative AI in this is in public
education in the United States. 5% say
the guidance or support that they've
gotten is adequate or good. Uh that's a
year ago, so it may have gotten better.
um lots of lots of examples of building
the plane as they fly it. Uh ethical
challenges in the age of generative AI.
The two at the top are the ones that I
would say we found evidence of uh
students bypassing learning. The teacher
has designed a activity, homework, you
name it. Something like that for the
students in order to get them to think
in a certain way so they will learn and
they use AI to bypass that thinking. How
big of a problem is this? We're not
really sure. There's there's been some
disputes on it. I can talk about the
Stanford study and what the latest
research shows. We don't know. Seems
like it's a problem. Teachers think it's
a problem. Students think it's a
problem. False accusations, harsh
harsher discipline. I have a slide I'll
share about that.
Um, students who might present as less
academic to their teacher are less
likely to be trusted or more likely to
be accused of using AI to get schoolwork
done. Um and that can have consequences.
Uh another ethical issue, um are the
students who are using AI actually
getting better grades? Um what if if
that's the case, what does that uh teach
our youth? Um sorry I didn't word this
in more um researchy phrase, but we're
already starting to see crappy AI for
poor kids. We're already starting to see
differentiation between the models that
we pay for and the models that we get
for free. So, if AI is in fact going to
be useful for students and uh for
teachers, who's going to get the good
models and who's going to get the free
models? Um AI replacing human
instruction. We're not seeing that yet,
although people are talking about it.
Um I'm going to skip this because I'm
running out of time. Uh black teens are
more than twice as likely as white or
Latino teens to say that teachers
flagged their schoolwork as being
created by generative AI when it was
not. That's a result from a common sense
media survey in
2024. Um, that's something we're
interested in trying to find out more
about. Um,
[Music]
and yeah, I already mentioned this. I
just want to make I I think our
hypothesis is though that the ethical
concerns we talked about will be better
addressed by schools that have made an
effort to respond coherently. To me, the
fact that teachers say only 25 only 25%
of teachers say that their district has
given them any policy guidance when it
comes to AI to me is shockingly low.
Although, the more time I've spent
talking to public school teachers, the
less shocked I am by that statistic. Uh,
we also think that districts with
wealthier students and more resources
are more likely to have put clear,
coherent, and wise, responsible AI
policies in place. That's my sense of
the data, but again, we're still kind of
coding it for that. Um, so we have an
article we're submitting to the British
Journal of Education Technology this
week. Um, to me the signature thing that
we're working on because I'm a
journalist and a podcast producer is a
miniseries scripted narrated podcast
within the Teach Lab podcast called The
Homework Machine. That's coming out in
July that will feature many more voices
like the ones I shared with you, plus
some analysis. We're also maybe going to
make a responsible AI policy handbook
for teachers or schools or districts who
don't have a policy in place and would
like some guidance. Um, and we're
thinking that maybe the next thing is to
look at schools that are adopting AI
powered edtech because there's a lot of
that going on out there. But I will stop
there and I'd love to take some
questions if we have time.
[Applause]
Thank you, Jesse. There is absolutely
time for questions.
So, I I just wondering if you know based
on your talk, it's about those uh um
pre-ol students. Do you think that those
students doing that right now will bring
this into college and into the graduate
school?
My understanding talking to college
professors is there's quite a bit of
bypassing learning that is happening at
the college level. Um Justin thinks so
if we have chat GPT is released you know
GPT 3.5 in December
2022 that we might notice something when
a gener when students who have spent
their entire four years of high school
uh relying on chat GPT to do say writing
assignments and that sort of thing show
up uh in higher ed that we might notice
it it'll be anecdotal because We don't
necessarily test these things, but we
might just notice some real diminished
capacity for reading and
writing. Students have expressed to me
that they're worried about that
possibility. I talked with a student who
said that she's been relying on chat GPT
to do a lot of her essay writing for the
last two or three years and she's
nervous. She she likes writing. Uh she
likes reading and she's nervous that
she's relying on it too much and she's
losing her ability. U but we're not
really paying attention to what's
happening in higher ed. So anything I
know about that is anecdotal. Um but
from what I understand it's something
that professors are aware of. Uh I want
to ask about thank you for this this
wonderful talk. I want to ask about a po
popular
possible positive effect of AI uh from
the students side which is kind of an
always available very patient tutor that
you can ask questions of. Did you hear
any of that coming out of your student
interviews that they were Yes. they felt
more comfortable asking the AI questions
or that they didn't need a tutor or they
stopped their parents didn't hire a
tutor or anything like that? I think
there are stories about that and I think
part of I mentioned this idea of
researching the schools adopting AI
powered edtech. My sense right now, this
is just a hypothesis, but from talking
both to students and from talking to
some teachers who are experimenting with
AI to support that the work they're
doing, that the most
innovative examples of teachers or
students, but students using AI to
support their
learning. Those are not happening with
these companies that are creating
purpose-built purpose-built AI powered
edtech like Conigo, Magic School or
School AI. It's students who have gotten
very comfortable and familiar with chat
GPT playing around with chat GPT and
prompting it to be the kind of tutor
that they want in that particular
moment. So, I've talked with a lot of
students who talk about using it to
prep, study for tests, practice writing
essays, that sort of thing. There's a
great story from a young woman, I think
a 12th grader, who described herself as
dyslexic, who got a writing assignment
that she found very intimidating and
challenging. And she went to her
teacher, who she had a very trusting
relationship with, and say, "Look, can I
use Chachi PT to get some ideas for
this? I'll do the writing, but I'm stuck
and I'm kind of intimidated by getting
started." and they had a discussion and
together they came up with a protocol
where she could use chat GPT to kind of
help her break the ice of the project
that she felt intimidated by but he
still felt like he was getting his
learning goals across uh in terms of how
she did that assignment. I thought that
was a great story. I also thought what
was kind of powerful and important about
that is the social dimension to it. She
she told me she probably wouldn't have
asked that teacher that question if she
didn't already have a pretty good
relationship trusting relationship with
him too. And I think that's vice versa.
So you see this example
of the social relationships between
teachers and students mediating
responsible uses of AI and those two
parties working that out together. And
I've heard of a few other stories like
that too. I I mean I think I think
there's tremendous potential for
positive use of AI in education and many
many teachers think so too. I mean I if
you get anything from the talk it's that
this technology which is quite
disruptive hit very suddenly and schools
do not adapt very very quickly and they
weren't necessarily prepared and that's
where a lot of the harm comes from.
Thank you. One last question.
Hi. Yes. Thank you so much for this
talk. Um, I was curious, um, although
I'm not a big fan of things like
standardized tests, um, I was curious if
there was any impact on like average,
uh, like scores and those kinds of like
state-run tests or things like the SAT
um, since the advent of things like
CHPT. It's a really good question. It's
better question for Justin than for me.
uh I really have focused on talking with
the teachers and he's really the
education researcher. I think you can
find his email uh online and he'll he'll
respond to it if you want to ask him or
I can try to remember to ask him. My
sense of this though is that
standardized testing is really murky
right now because there are other crises
happening within education emerging from
a pandemic that really did have bad
impacts on learning particularly things
like reading and math particularly for
younger students um who if you think
about a three-year-old trying to learn
reading and math over Zoom that's
particularly challenging maybe 11th
grader sorry not three-year-old a third
grader it would be very hard for a
three-year-old. Um, but if you think of
a yeah, like you know, like a
10-year-old or a nine-year-old uh trying
to stay engaged in a Zoom math class uh
a couple years ago, that would have been
very hard. Um, so that's a complicated
factor. Um, I do think we've seen scores
uh drop in the last few years, but it's
hard to know if that's pandemic. We also
are in the middle of a attendance crisis
in schools right now, too. Um, and
schools, our public schools in
particular, are just generally
belleaguered. teacher burnout has never
been higher. So, it's kind of hard to
figure out, well, what's what's AI?
What's one of these other historical
factors?
Thank you very much. This great