My name is Tabitha Wanjira.
I am the  founder of IConnect
Kenya, based here in Kakuma refugee camp.
I would say one. I'm hardworking.
Two. Ambitious.
Three I'm very corroborating.
We thought about coming up with Kakuma
Digi Connect to bring together
people who are leading media houses,
and also people who are leading different
digital hubs here in Kakuma.
There's always a gap when it comes
to innovation and creativity.
It's the high time
we think about creating platforms.
As Iconnect
to where people can come together.
I have seen a lot of support
also coming in
for refugee sessions because they are
people like the Migration Summit.
They fund people directly
to be able to do their own events
and different action to rally up
conversations
around migration, which is very good.
You find that most of
the times when working with these
individual people or working with groups,
you'll find some of the people we work
with, they do not have formal registration
when it comes to like having legal
documentation.
It's a challenge
for some of these creatives.
Also, when it comes to business
registration and without the refugee ID,
you cannot be able to open KRA Pin.
You cannot be able to register a company
and the agencies around here,
they demand that you always
you have to have the form or registration.
So this becomes a hindrance
for these people,
even if they're in a position
to work with agencies.
The opportunity goes to someone else.