Okay. So,
uh first let me look at a curb and
plate. Talked a little bit about this
last time at the very end.
Okay. So, so let's first talk about
curves in the plane.
So we have uh
um we have functions uh f and g
on some interval say from a to b
uh into r and they are uh I'm assuming
that uh f and g are differentiable
[Applause]
and uh and that the derivative
uh are continuous.
Okay.
And then I'm thinking about uh so I'm
thinking about the curve. So gamma here
of s is a curl
and it's given by the gamma of s is f of
s comma g of s
and I want to look at the length of this
curve right so s here is running in the
interval from a to b
and so the length and this is the
definition of the length But then we
will justify it. So the length
of gamma
um so L is equal to the integral from A
to B of square root of F prime of S
squared plus G prime of S
squar
DS. Okay. Now why is this the case? So
so why do we why is this a sensible
definition?
So suppose that this thing here is f of
a comma g of a. So this is the starting
point of the curve
and suppose that the curve looks like
this. So here is here's the end point.
And now imagine that you take the
interval from A to B
and you partition it into a lot of
small. So so you have this partition of
this interval
and then you're looking at so so again
so we have the curve here. This is maybe
x i minus one. And here I have x i
and under the the map gamma this little
interval here is mapped maybe into this
piece of the curve.
Right?
Now this piece of the curve I will then
approximate it by the line segment from
here to here. Right? So if you do that
then it means that you are looking at so
you have that you're looking at right?
So you have that. So here you have x i
minus one. Here you have x i
and you're looking at the curve on this
little uh uh interval.
And so
and there the curve goes from so the
initial point is
is this right? That's the image of that
point. And the image of this is gamma of
Xi,
right?
And so the line segment from here to
here,
right? So this is so the length of this
line segment if you have this point
here.
So this is gamma of x i minus one and
this is gamma of x i.
Then the length here is the this the
vector here. So gamma of x i minus gamma
of x i -1
the length of this. But this thing here
is
right. This is the end point is this.
Sorry. Yeah.
And the beginning point is this.
So this here. So it's the length of
this.
But the length of this by pyagoras
is um is the square of the coordinates
and then taking the square root of that.
So this is what the length of this of
the line segment here is.
Right?
And now, but now like the mean value
theorem tells you that this thing here
is essentially
the derivative
at some point in between these two,
right? It's it's there's the it actually
is equal to if you will uh the
derivative at some intermediate point
um times times the length of that little
interval
right this is this different here and
likewise so this is
u x like this some intermediate point
and likewise for this there's some
intermediate point
times the length here.
So this means that this little line
segment here
the length of this little line segment
um is equal to and you see that when you
take this thing here and you square it
then you can factor out. So let me just
write it out. So you take this thing
here. So it's f prime
like this squared delta xi
squar plus
and then g prime
squar delta x i
squ. Okay. But now you can factor this
out. So you can write this as square
root
of uh delta xi
squared and then frime
like this squared
plus g prime in this intermediate point
squared
right and this factor out both of them.
And so now you can just take when you
take the square root it actually goes
out as the this is anyway positive. So
it comes becomes like this.
And now
the functions g prime and fprime are
both continuous.
So this thing here is like roughly what
it is at one of the end point right. So
this here is like roughly equal to
right like this and then it's like one
end point or you can even take like the
Yeah. So it's like an end point.
And so you see that this thing here. Now
when you sum up
when you sum up all of these over this
partition and you let the partition the
the the delta xi goes to zero, then this
here is going to converge
to the integral from a to b of the uh
square root of frime of s squared plus G
prime of S
squ D S right so so that's why so you
take this little curve
it's parameterized or you take the curve
parameterized by a to b you're looking
at this uh at at a partition
and then on each of these little
intervals you approximate the curve by
the by the line segment
And then you let the as you let this
refinement
uh the length of these individual
interval goes to zero then actually this
approximation will have a limit and that
limit is this integral right. So that's
why we define it to be the arc length.
Okay. So that's our arc length. And so
let's look at an example of this.
[Applause]
So we look at two examples. Let me first
look at case where f of s is equal to s
and uh g of s
uh is equal to
uh s squared.
Then I have that. So then the curve is
uh so the curve gamma of s is is s comma
s 2 and uh frime of s is equal to 1 and
g prime of s is equal to 2 s and so this
means that um and let's say that it's
parameterized s here
from 0 to one. So then the length here
of this curve is the integral from 0 to
1 and then square root and then you have
to take this thing here squared. So
that's one plus this here 2 s squared
ds. So this is and is this integral here
1 + 4².
So that's the arc length. just given us
this integral.
The second example I want to look at um
about for aren
[Applause]
uh is uh if you you have the unit
circle. So suppose that you have the
unit circle.
So here you have one.
So this is supposed to be the unit
circle. So it's x^2
+ y^2
= 1. It's a unit circle centered at the
origin. Okay.
Now this means that um that if you take
a point right then um then y here is so
this here means that y is given in terms
of x with that y^2 is equal to 1 - x^2
and so if you're assuming that you are
in this upper where y is positive so if
if uh y here is positive positive then
you're looking at y =
of 1 - x square.
So in this part here where y is positive
you have that you have the curve uh this
part here of the this part here of the
unit circle this one here is given by
the parameization
gamma of s equal to uh s and then square
root of 1 - s² right and s here is Now
running uh right s is the first
coordinates so it's between minus1 and
one so s here it's between minus one and
one
okay
now suppose that you take some x here
and suppose that you want to look at
what is the arc length of this part of
the circle right
Well then uh in this case if you're
looking at the arc length of this part
of the circle let's call that arc length
uh teta theta
um so theta here is equal to this part
it's now par metricized like this but x
here is so this here is this length
of gamma. But now gamma by now s here is
running from x to one right because x is
the first coordinate and it's running
from
the first coordinate is running from x
from this point right this here to to
one right
and so now let's try to calculate this
length or at least write it up as an
integral
So if we write it up as an integral um
we have that so in this case so gamma s
is equal to s square of 1 - s²
and so if we define f of s = s and g of
s=
to square of 1 - s²
then we take f prime
well that's equal to one
and uh g prime
right so there we use the chain rule so
this is equal to 1 / 2 square of 1
- s^2 and then we have to take the
derivative of this also so this is times
-2
uh s like that right
and so this here is of course then equal
to the two cancels and you're getting -
s over
of 1 - s 2.
Okay.
And so now if you're looking at so f
prime squar + g prime
squared this is equal to f is one. So
this is one plus this thing here
squared. So this is s^ squ and then the
denominator squared is just of course 1
- s squ
and we can now put it on a common uh
with a common denominator right and so
you see that this is 1 - s^ 2
1 - s^ 2 that's how you write 1 and then
plus s 2 1 - s 2 and so you see that
This whole thing is the s squ cancel in
the denominator and so you're getting 1
over 1 - s^2
right
and so this means that the integral
so this means that the integral
[Applause]
so this length here
um and
the length uh is so actually uh we call
the length theta
and uh it will be clear in a minute why
I do this. So the length here is then
the integral from x to one right and
then it is uh of the square root right
so it's supposed to be the square root
of this thing here so it's the square
root so if you will is one square root
of 1 - s^2
ds Right?
So that's the length, right? But if you
think about it, so you have here the
unit circle again.
What we now calculated was that we take
some x here and then we calculated the
length of this piece here, right? Well,
that piece is um this here is also the
this is how you define this is if you
will this is the angle,
right? So theta is the angle, right?
And um and so you see that so theta here
is the angle and x here
x here is so and and and this point here
sorry this point here is uh is cosine
to the angle comma sign
to the angle right that's piece so this
means that X is X is actually cosine
to the angle.
Okay.
So, so this means that that uh theta
here in terms of X
uh theta is the inverse function. So
it's what's called arc uh co cosine 2x
right. So this arc cosine it means that
it's the inverse function. If you take
the inverse function on both sides of
this right then um so if you take the
inverse function so arc cosine
so you get r cosine to x on this side
this side you're getting arc cosine
and then cosine
to theta but these two functions
together gives you the identity so this
is to theta
Okay.
Okay. So, so in other words, in other
words, what you have is that arc cosine
to x is given as the integral from x to
1 /
of 1 - s^2
ds. So you have this formula here
which is not so so surprising but anyway
you can get it from this and so now you
can get it. So now the fundamental
theorem of calculus. So by the
fundamental theorem of calculus
of calculus
then you have that. So if you have a
function that is given like a integral
like this
then this thing here is the derivative
right the one thing you that's what the
fundamental theorem calculus say except
you got to be a little bit careful
because this is if the variable is up
here but now it's down here because it's
down here the derivative is minus this
okay let me explain that so you get from
the from the fundamental theorem of
calculus. The derivative of this
function I claim is minus this thing
here.
Okay. And then this should be evaluated
at x. This is the r cosine at x is equal
to like that.
Okay. So now let's just see that. So why
is this the case? So you take
[Applause]
So remember that if you have a function
f ofx
and this is given as you're integrating
from some x some a to some x a is fixed
and then you're integrating of a
function like this right
assuming that the function is nice etc.
Do we then we have that the fundamental
theorem of calculus
fundamental theorem of calculus the
derivative of this function
is little f right
but suppose I now switch so now suppose
I now look so I don't look at this but I
look at at suppose that g of x
is the integral
from X to A
X to let's call it X to B just because
we usually have the end point as the the
the the the last point as B.
So suppose that the function is like
this
what is the derivative right? So but but
this is just the fundamental theorem of
but you know that's one of the rules we
had with writing the integral is we can
write this one here as so here I'm
thinking about that the function little
f is defined on some integral from a to
b
and I can rewrite this thing here in
this form here because I can just think
about this thing here as the integral
from a to b
of f of s
right so sorry let me let me write it
over here so
so I'm just making the trivial
observation that we have that so if we
have a function
from a to b
into r and we have some x that lie
between a and b.
Then we proved that the integral from a
to b of f
this thing here is equal to the integral
from a to x
plus the integral from uh x to b.
Right? That was one of the rules that if
you if you take this if you have like a
dividing point in this interval then you
could integrate over the first half and
then in add integral of the second half.
But this thing here just tells you that
this thing here you can rewrite as this
minus that. So you have that the
integral from x to b f of s d s is equal
to the integral from a to b f of s d s
minus the integral from
uh from uh a to x f of s ds right and so
a and b are fixed and when you think
about this thing here as a function
function of x then it's equal to this is
just a constant and then minus this. So
when you take the derivative of this,
this is a constant. So this derivative
is zero. The derivative of this, well
that is straight the fundamental thermal
calculus. And because of this sign, you
get minus little f, right? And so that's
what I applied over here that if it is
of this form here
then the derivative of this function is
minus little f.
Okay.
Okay. So this was this is so right. So
this is how the angle is defined if you
will right. The angle is defined as the
length arc length of the curve, right?
And we can calculate it using this
formula here. And we're getting a nice
uh uh
nice uh I mean we get you know we know
what the this arc cosine we know
actually what the derivative is just
from this arc length and the fundamental
calculus.
Okay.
The next thing I want to talk about is I
want to talk about uh pointwise and
uniform convergence of functions.
So you have a sequence of functions.
You have a sequence of functions fn.
So suppose you have you have some
interval I
and you have a sequence of functions
fn and you have a function uh another
function f also on this interval.
Then we say so this is the definition.
We say that the sequence here converts
to f pointwise
if for all
x
fixed.
If you're looking at this, so x here,
think about x as x as being x could be
anything, but it is fixed. And then
you're looking at this sequence here,
right? So this is a sequence of real
numbers because x is fixed. Then you
want this thing here to converge to f of
x. Yeah.
>> Sorry, I had a quick question about the
last thing. So how do you know that the
integral of a to bs is zero?
So no uh so so
um so the thing is that what we're
looking at here so I was asking so
um so this here is uh so if you have a
function capital f that's given like
this the fundamental the calculus gives
you what the derivative is so I'm just
asking suppose that the function that
the variable was not up here but it was
down here what is the derivative and so
in order to figure out that derivative
I'm just using that so that if I was
integrating over the whole interval a
and b are fixed right so this is just
some number whatever it is it but it's
probably not zero right I mean general
wouldn't be zero but it's just some
constant right and so for each x you get
the same constant here and and it's
equal to this plus that. And so, but
this is what we're interested in. So,
I'm just moving this one over on the
other side. So, I get this thing here.
But remember, this here is a constant.
So, when you take the derivative, it's
zero, right? And so,
>> okay. So,
>> if you were to set a
goes to zero and then you can get like
But that's but if uh right so but if you
if if if you if B is equal to A
if B is equal to A uh yeah I mean but
it's not I mean so then this interval is
just a trivial interval right
>> right but doesn't allow you to get
identity there
>> right but but the thing is so the reason
why so why did I want to do it yes but
it's like H but but but but it's it's
kind of using something implicitly. You
see what I mean? I'm assuming that X is
between A and B because when we took
this interval, you know, if X is not
between A and B, we had to figure out
what the hell do we mean by this sort of
integral, right? Anyway, and so yes, it
it works even if you re you know if even
if you have the ordering differently but
you just have to all I want to point out
here is that if it is downstairs and not
upstairs you have to you know just
remember the sign.
Okay.
Okay. So this here so so again so I have
a sequence of functions on the interval
I have another function on the same
interval
and I uh we say that this sequence is
converging pointwise to f
if for all x fixed when we're looking at
this sequence it converts to that right
and so let me look at two examples of
that
Um
so the first one
is
so the first example I want to look at
this is where the functions fn of x is
equal to uh x to the n and uh and x here
is between zero and one.
And so this is my fn
and my f
uh my my function f which is now of
course also a function on this interval.
This is equal to zero if um x is uh
bigger equal to zero but strictly less
than one and is one if x is equal to
one.
Okay.
So of course this function f is not
continuous. The other ones are
continuous.
Now
I claim that that this sequence so the
sequence fn
is converging pointwise to f.
So fn
converts to f pointw
right because if you take if you fix if
you fix x let's say fix x and let's
assume uh and uh assume
that that that it's between
sorry it's between
zero it's strictly less than one right
so you're fixing x and let's first deal
with a case where that x is strictly
less than one well if I'm looking at x
to the n so I take some small number by
small just means that it's strictly less
than one and I multiply it by itself n
time well that certainly goes to zero
right
if the if X here is fixed but it's now
one then X to the N. If X is one then
this here is still one. Right?
So you see that in this case so this
here is f to the n of X and this here is
F of X. So these things here I mean
they're actually equal to this. So in
particular they converge right? And this
here is what f of x is. And this here is
again fn of x.
Right? So you have that this sequence of
functions converge to this slightly
crazy function. Um right. Okay. So
that's the first example. They converge
pointwise.
The next example
I want to look at is
um
so the next example
is where uh the functions
uh are you just summing here
you're summing you just take the power
series for for the exponential function.
So you take your summing where k is
equal to 1 to n and that's my fn
of x
and then my f of x
is the infinite sum which is the
exponential function and we have already
proved that if you fix x right so we fix
x then this fn here of x converts to f
of x point you know for each fixed x for
each
fixed x
right
so so this sequence of functions
pointwise converge to the exponential
function
now so this is one notion of convergence
for functions and there's another notion
that is also useful. They're both
useful. Uh the other one is stronger.
And so, of course, if you have the
stronger version, you often get
something much better.
Oh, I shouldn't have erased this, but
anyway. So, uh and so the second the
second notion is uh so this is
is is a notion of uniform convergence.
uniform is is means that it's that it's
uniform in x. So, so we what we have
here is we have a sequence
of functions and f defined on some
interval into R and then we say that
this sequence here converts to f
uniformly.
If
for all
epsilon greater than zero there exist a
capital n. So that if little n is bigger
than this capital n then f of x minus f
n of x
is smaller than epsilon for all x.
And again right the uniformness is that
it holds for all x right
you can use the same capital n for all x
and so now
uh
[Applause]
now what you have is that if a sequence
converge uniformly
then it converge pointwise. So we have
the following lema
that follows directly from the from the
definition.
So lema.
So a uniform convergence
of fn to f
uh implies
point polarwise convergence.
of fn of fn to f to to f okay so uniform
convergence imply pointwise convergence
and that's that's clear that's really
just the definition
if I had written out what it means for
so this here I've written out what it
means to have uniform convergence.
If it was pointwise convergence, right?
Then you have these functions again and
you have that this converts to that
pointwise. It means that the sequence fn
so so once you fix x then the sequence
fn of x right. So once
so once x is fixed
then these here
converge to this.
But saying that this sequence here
converge means that for all epsilon
greater than zero there exist a n
but this n is now allowed to depend on
x. So that if little n is bigger than
this capital n then f n of x minus f ofx
is smaller than epsilon. Right? So you
see that clearly uniform convergence
implies pointwise and again uniform just
means that this capital n can be chosen
to be the same for all x. Right?
Okay. So now let's look at the examples.
Unfortunately, I raised like the most
important one. Uh so I'll just go
through it again. Let me just talk about
the example again and then we'll see why
this um this example here does not. So
we had this example from before
where the sequence of functions
uh was x to the n
and x here was between zero and one
and then we had this function f that was
this function that was not continuous
but this function was given to be equal
to zero if x here
strictly less one
and it was one if x is equal to one
right that was this function f
and we know we already shown that the fn
converts to f pointw wise but we want to
see now so that this so I claim
that fn
does not converge so This does not
converge uniformly
to F.
We know already that it converge
pointwise and I claim that that this
sequence does not converge uniformly.
Okay. So now why is this the case?
Well, this is because
you see by the intermediate value
theorem
the functions
Fn are continuous
at zero they take the value of zero at
one they take the value one so for each
n by the intermediate value theorem
um uh for each
since
since each
uh fn
is continuous
then there exist
there exist a x n but it really will
depend on n
so that f n of xn n will take the value
1/2 right so the functions here this is
the functions oops this is the functions
this is the function fn
it takes at zero it takes a value of
zero at one it takes a value one so
there is somewhere where where
a half is achieved and this is at this
exit
Right?
So you have that and again this xn is
depending on n and the thing is that as
n get large this point will have to move
very close to one. Okay. But if you're
now looking at f(n)
uh of x minus f ofx
right
so we want to we if it was converging
uniformly it would mean that this
difference here would be smaller than
some epsilon for all x right but if
you're just looking at this point Here
this difference here is this point here
xn
will lie strictly xn here will lie this
is where this value here is a half it's
not one so it's lie be strictly between
zero and one right so you see that for
each n this function
f at xn this will always be zero. This
is because the function f is zero except
at one and this point is definitely not
one. Right? So you have that. So you
have you see that this thing here this
is this here is zero. So this is just
the value of this the absolute value but
that's actually a half. So this is
always a half. Right?
So the function would converge uniformly
as long as
that if you right. So uniform
convergence would mean
so uniform convergence.
[Applause]
So,
so now let's show
So let's prove
that
FN does not converge uniformly to F.
Right? And so I just pick my epsilon
So
I pick a epsilon less than half, right?
And then if it was converging and and
suppose
and suppose not
i.e. That is
suppose
fn converts to f uniformly.
This means that for all epsilon but I
just use this epsilon. Yeah, I just take
use this one epsilon.
But then I would have that there exist
capital n so that um so that I mean I
can even take it to to be equal to a
half. So there exist capital n so that
such that if little n is bigger than
capital n then this thing here
minus f of x would have to be less than
strictly less than a half for all x.
Right? If it was converging uniformly
then in particular for this one choice
of of epsilon you would have this for
all x but we already know that if we
looking at now depending on what this is
but that's fine you know if you insert
x= to xn then this is actually equal to
a half right so this is this here does
not hold this is the contradiction
Okay.
Now, uh in the other example that we
looked at before,
um
in the other example, uh we have that um
in the other example which is this
example here.
uh this sequence here is converging and
I'll return to this in in a minute uh
that so in this case the these here
converge to f uniformly
on each
uh interval
on each bounded interval. So in each
interval of the form
minus L
to L. So on each bounded interval. Okay.
And we will talk about this more in just
a second.
Um okay.
Um and right because this is uh this is
this is uh this is the contact uh uh
content of the uh what's called bas
test.
So this hold more generally that if you
take a sequence so you see bias
M test.
So,
so in bio stress end test you have a
sequence of functions fn
and you have that this sequence. So fn
sorry is functions on some interval into
r
And then you have that the fn
uh is are bounded by some
some constant mn
and then you have that the mn. So these
are clearly non- negative numbers and
you have that this that this series here
this here is um is uh is is finite right
so this is a series of non- negative
numbers so to say that it's that this
series is summable is the same as saying
that it's finite
and now the claim is so then bias M
testers.
So,
so this is that if this is the case then
this
sequence converts to some f uniformly.
Okay. So that's why M test.
>> Yep.
Oh yeah. So this here so this here means
this here just means that fn of x
is lesser equal to m for all x.
Yeah, that's a kind of you know quite
common used.
Okay.
Uh so let's try to prove that.
So we are looking at
so suppose we look at suppose we define
sn of x. So this is just when you're
summing
from k = z to n of fk
of x. Suppose you're looking at this and
we want to prove so want to show
yeah sorry about that this is not what
we want to prove. Sorry this is uh sorry
I should have said
yeah this it's not these functions that
converge it's a sum of them. So what I
want to prove is that I want to prove
that this thing here as
k equal to zero to n that this function
here converge
uniform. Okay?
Right? So think about it. You want this
to kind of probably apply to a to to
some power series. Right? And so the
individual
uh fk is like this polomial it is you
right it's some of some degree
okay
so so we define this function sn and I
want to prove that this
sn and then converge
and and and and and if It's okay. I said
it's better to call this something else
than little f to call it s, right?
Because it's not these guys that
converge. It's a sum of them that
converge, right?
So we want to show that these guys here,
the sn
converts to this s uniform.
Right? That's what we want.
Now
let's look at the difference between Sn
of X
and SM of X. And so here I'm going to
think about N as being larger than M.
Suppose I'm thinking about this thing
here.
Well, this here is when you're summing
the first
I guess we're starting at k equal to
zero. So then we're summing the first m
+ one, right, of those guys here. We're
summing more. We're summing those guys,
but then we're also summing some some
more, right? And so this thing here, so
the the let me just write it out. So k =
to zero to n of f uh k of x and the
second one is when we're summing right n
is bigger than m. So here we are
actually summing fewer
and so of course the differences
between these two are how many more of
these guys are
there than those guys. So this is
summing absolute value where we're
summing from k = m + 1 up to n of fk
of x. Right? So that's what it it's
equal to. And we didn't even have to
have absolute value, but in a minute
it's useful to have absolute value
because now of course this sum here is
less than than the sum of the absolute
values.
k = m + one to n and then we take the
absolute value in under the summation
sign like this right but now we can use
our condition here so this thing here is
less or equal to
the sum here from k = m + one up to n of
m k Okay.
But but those guys,
right? This is just a sequence of real
numbers, right? This is not a function.
It's just real numbers and they
converge. So this means that that so
this means that given
this means that you have that you can
make this saying here as small as you
want as long as m is sufficiently large.
Right?
So
so given
So given
epsilon greater than zero there exist a
capital n such that if m here is bigger
than capital n then the sum here of the
tail
this thing here up to anything else,
right? Right. Uh is of this MK that this
is less than epsilon,
right? And so you see that this really
say that the so this implies that the Sn
for each X for each X if you can think
about this thing here as a sequence,
right? And so you have that that now
this sequence here is a cushy sequence,
right? For each x this is a cushy
sequence.
So this means that these sn of x they
will actually converge to something and
that's something I call s of x. So that
gives you a function s of x but it gives
you more because you see it's uh right
it actually show you something about
because this inequality here
[Applause]
that this difference here is less than
that that hold for all x right
so this means that
this means that as you're sending
that you have
right. So now let n go to infinity. If
you take this inequality here. So you
have we have this inequality sn of x
minus sn of x
is less or equal to the sum here k = m +
one to n of mk.
So we have this inequality and we have
in fact you can write it as if you're
summing over the entire tail
right and so now this side of it this
side does not depend on little n right
this here hold as long as all here we
required was that this here was bigger
than that
and so as n go to infinity. You have
that s of x
minus s m of x
will have to be less or equal to this
sum.
And the key point here is for this for
this size m test is that this here holds
for all this inequality holds for all x.
Right? You see the little n is gone.
there's only this capital N uh this
sorry the the M right
and so now we again we can so if you as
long as you choose some n sufficiently
large then if little m is bigger equal
to this n then you can make this sum
here that have no reference to x you can
make this less than epsilon
right so this here is less than epsilon
And you have this inequality for all x.
So you have this one here less than this
for all x. And that's exactly uniform
convergence. Yeah.
>> Um where did we get the first um like
when we said that the sum of these k are
less than ep.
>> Yeah.
>> Where did that?
>> Okay. So the the the
right so let let me just let me just um
I I'll get to this in just a second but
let me just say what is the strategy
here so you have so we have this
sequence
uh maybe I erased the statement
unfortunat So we have this sequence of
functions on an interval
and you had that this function here was
bounded like this and then you had that
these these are just real numbers and
you had that these real numbers here
was summable.
So these are non- negative real numbers
of course right
and so then and I claim so the claim is
that these that the sum here of these
guys these here
I claim that these guys here converge
uniformly to some function s of x. The
first step is to say that they actually
that there exist some function s and
they converge to that function
pointwise. Right? In order to prove that
I proved that this se this the this
these these sums here for each fixed x
is a cushy sequence. Right? Once there
sequence for each fix x then they will
be convergent and the limits I now
defined to be s of x right. So that
gives me a function and then the thing
is that I have to upgrade this
convergence which initially is pointwise
to uniform convergence. Okay. And so now
you were asking so now
>> like why did so we got the sum of MKs
but then
>> where did we like how do we
>> that's fine and so now so so this here
was just very general and it just used
this inequality that's all it used right
now I'm using that these guys are
summable so this means that if I'm
starting this summation sufficiently far
out then I can make it less than a given
epsilon.
>> Oh it's like
>> because it's just like that these are
non- negative number and that they are
summable just means that if I go out
really really far then from there on and
out it makes very little contribution to
the total sum. Okay.
Okay. So uh right so
right and so right so so you see like
the first thing is
for each fix x
I prove that these sn of x is a cruise
sequence that then allow me to define a
function uh s of x and I get that the
sequence sn of x is converging the
sequence function is converging
pointwise and then again Then once I
have that then I need to upgrade it to
be uniform convergence and that's what
we did. Yes.
>> Okay.
Um okay. So now let's try to uh apply
this.
>> Uh yeah.
>> So what if the MKS are a kind of
converging sequence that
>> but in like the small side the zero side
is on a low index.
So then like as I go further out,
>> it's getting bigger.
>> Um
>> can can we look at an example and see if
it become clear? Um so let's look at a
sort of
um let's look at an example.
Let's look at it very yeah let's look at
at an example.
So in fact let's look at the function
the example we just looked at but we
said that it followed from stress M
test. So what was the example I just
looked at?
So I take a function fn of x this is now
x to the to the n divided by n
factorial.
Okay. Now I define uh sn of x. So this
is now the sum from k= to0 to n of this
fn of x f k k of x sorry. So this means
that this thing here is the sum from k
=0 to n of x k over k factorial.
Okay. And I want to show that this. So
want to show
that this Sn of X converge to the
exponential function
uh uniformly
on on an interval of this form.
So L is some fixed number and I'm
looking between minus L to L. Right? And
I claim that they converge. Okay? Now
let's try to apply Bas M test. Right?
And so what are the MN?
The MN in this case the natural one is N
to the power N*
N factorial.
Okay. If I'm looking at those numbers,
these are just these are non- negative
numbers, right? And we already know that
this sequence of non- negative numbers
is summable that these non- negative
numbers like this that they are
summable,
right? And so then and suppose now I
have suppose now I take this
f uh n of x. So this is this function x
^ n over n factorial. x here remember is
in this bounded interval.
Well, let's look at fn of x.
So this is x n
/ n factorial.
But this thing here, so this is just x
to the power n factorial. This is right.
It's lying in here. So it's it's the
absolute value is bound by L. So this is
L n / N factorial.
Right? So I have that this sequence is
less than these m MN
right and so now bias stress but it is
it we restrict to this interval here and
so now based
M test tell you that that this that the
sum here when you're summing from K to
zero to N X K over K factorial that
these actually converge
to the limit uniformly
on but remember we we are restricting.
So and the limit here we already have
defined the limit to be the exponential
function.
Okay. Does that is that clear or not? Uh
does it answer it or not really?
I'm not sure.
>> Okay.
>> So I guess my question was y
>> is is it that mn must be a convergent
like series like
>> Yeah. So mn that's right. So mn
m uh you know in this example or in the
general example it's it's it's
you know so why so why is the mn so much
easier to determine because they are
just numbers they are just non- negative
numbers and you're just asking if the
series of non- negative numbers is not
function it's non- negative numbers if
that's convergent or not right and so
since they're non are negative, it just
means that the sum is finite, right?
And so that's that's much easier to to
determine.
Okay,
right. So now we can do this sort of
same argument more generally.
So this lead us to the following
[Applause]
that suppose you take a power series.
So suppose you take a power series. So
you summing here n = 0 to infinity a n
xn. This is a power series right? So
power series remember that a power
series is where you're taking a sequence
of fun of numbers real numbers and you
think about these as coefficients in
this polinomial and then you're summing
o over them right but it's like you know
the it's the a n is the coefficient to x
to x to the power n
okay so this is a power series and a
power series again means so like you
think about it as a series because like
for each X it's like a regular series
right but then it's like the value of
that you get depends on X right and so
for this we define the radius of
convergence
and let me remind you how this radius of
convergence was defined
you take the AM
and you take the absolute value of it
and then you take the n root of that and
then you're looking at lean soup
as n goes to infinity
right
that gives you some number that number
potentially it could be infinity
it's always non negative but and it will
always give you a number it could be
zero it could be infinity and It could
be anything in between.
And then the radius of convergence
of convergence
of the power series
is um
so this is what I write by r and this is
one m
and where where there's this convention
in this case usually you you know don't
let divide by zero or infinity but in
this case if m here is zero this means
that the radius of convergence is
infinite if m is uh is uh is infinite
then it means that the radius
convergence is zero
and now this sort of slightly surprising
fact but we proved this but I'm just
reminding about it that that the the
thing is that that the power series is
convergent. So here you have zero is
convergence
inside. If this has the if this here is
r it's convergent inside here and it's
divergent outside but it's not
completely clear what happened on the
boundary. Right?
So you have to check the boundary uh uh
you know in you know
separately and that that depends on the
power you know there's no general
formula for that.
Okay. So now the theorem here is
that
so the theorem is like this and this is
just generalizing this example that we
just did and the theorem is the
following
that if you take a power series.
So if you have a power series
and um
and R is the radius of convergence
and uh L here is strictly less. It has
to be strictly less than than the radius
of convergence.
Then um
then these functions here k= to zero to
n a n a k sorry x k
that these functions here converge
to uh to this to the limit
uh uniformly
on on this interval here from minus L to
L. But remember that L had to be
strictly less than the radius of
convergence.
Okay. And so so this is like extremely
useful like if you have
um and and and it will be clear next
time why it's useful because if you have
uniform convergence then it becomes very
easy to if you have uniform convergence
then you can argue about if you want to
take the derivative of integrating this
thing over here. If you have uniform
convergence
then it will say that it's then a lot of
operations
we'll be more precise about that next
time but a lot of operation like
integration and differentiation you can
do that over here and then go to the
limit. So instead of you know if you
were to integrate this thing here right
so just say that but this seems maybe
very very hard but the thing is if you
can integrate here then you can just use
the usual sum the usual formula for the
sum that you it's just a sum of the
integral and likewise for
differentiation okay
and so uh okay maybe I will just uh
uh yeah maybe to stop here. I wrote out
the but the proof in the notes. Uh I
already posted the notes the lecture
notes. Are there any questions?
Okay, great.