[MUSIC PLAYING]
ANDREW BENNETT: SeaPerch
is really a system
or an approach to learning.
It's in the form of a
small little vehicle that
drives around underwater, but
it's a lot more than that.
We are trying to disseminate
love of the ocean
and teaching about the
ocean as broadly as we can.
And SeaPerch is
meant just for that.
DIANE BRANCAZIO: SeaPerch
is a fabulous project
for middle and high school
students developed at the MIT
Sea Grant college program.
TEAGAN SULLIVAN: The SeaPerch
was made in about 2000.
It's not outdated per se,
but there's definitely
a lot of stuff that's
come around since then
that could be added to it.
ANDREW BENNETT: We specifically
wanted MIT students
to help us create the SeaPerch
II and the SeaPerch II concept,
because they're bringing a fresh
set of eyes to the problem.
TEAGAN SULLIVAN: I
love seeing people
get excited about engineering
and get excited about learning.
MAN: Oh, wow.
DIANE BRANCAZIO: Now it's
a robot that's not just
going underwater and
just driving around,
but now it can sense things.
Now it can grip things.
Now it can do many more things
that the original SeaPerch could
not do.
ANDREW BENNETT: There is
an international SeaPerch
competition every spring,
and last year there
were 144 teams from
all over the world.
DIANE BRANCAZIO:
Kids will have teams.
They'll build something
and they'll practice
and practice and refine.
They make the robot
frame out of PVC pipe.
They get motors, make a cable
that goes to a control box,
so now they've made a robot
that they built. And they
can change the
design of the frame
and they can change
its performance.
TEAGAN SULLIVAN:
From the get-go,
SeaPerch is about
exploring design.
You have to think
about buoyancy.
about how am I going
to make everything stay dry?
You have to think about the
placement of your motors,
because when you're
driving underwater,
you can move in any direction.
So if you want to
drive straight,
you have to really
think about how am I
going to make this robot level?
DIANE BRANCAZIO:
The SeaPerch project
is really outreach for the
Sea Grant college program.
It's really great to have MIT
students working on the project,
because they're able to bring
their passion for engineering
and put it into a
project that is going
to be used in the high
schools and middle schools
that they went to.
TEAGAN SULLIVAN: Developing
an educational tool
for other people feels
really rewarding.
I love trying to make the world
a better place by educating
others and helping people learn
through learning yourself.
[MUSIC PLAYING]