So the first thing I I promised to do
today was to do the last problem on the
first problem set with you all. And so
for context, this was like pretty
difficult problem. Um and a lot of
people didn't get it fully right or or
made a mistake. And actually even the
people who did get it right tended to
write something that was pretty long and
complicated. Um so so I spent a while
thinking about it. I think I could have
set up the problem with a little more
direction. Um but anyway, but I will
explain uh explain it to everybody and
um and try to say sort of what were the
issues and what like what's what's what
do you need to know to do it cleanly.
Okay. So the set the the the the
background of this problem is that we
had done a bunch of stuff in class about
lines in the plane say in FQ2 and the
problem was to try to do something
similar for lines in FQ3 but it is a
little more complicated. So let me first
remind everybody what we did for lines
in FQ2 and then we'll go up to three
dimensions.
[Applause]
Okay. So
general setup.
Okay. So first of all if we have a
function on fqd
then fnot will be the constant part.
So fnot of x is 1 / q to the d some y
and fq to the d of f of y. And then f
subh f high will be the rest of it. So f
is f not.
Okay. Um so first we studied lines in
fq2 and this is just going to be a recap
of what we did in class.
So we noticed um so let's say that l1
and l2 are are lines or characteristic
function of lines. Um okay so there are
two cases. If L1 and L2 are parallel
um then you can easily see that their
inner product is zero. Parallel means
they don't intersect.
So you get this.
Okay. And you could also look at the
high part and if you look at the high
part it will be negative. The inner
product will be negative. L1H L2 H will
be negative.
It's easy to compute but let me there's
something I could say out loud. Um uh so
one one would one always has that fg
is f gn plus fi g high.
You can see that from the fora
representation of these things. So in
this case l1 l the inner product of l1
and l2 is zero.
Ln l1 kn and l2 kn are both positive. So
their inner product is positive. So for
this all to fit together this inner
product should be negative.
Okay. So that's what happens if they're
parallel. Now at the time that felt
parallel felt like sort of a special
case. Two lines are usually not
parallel. Once in a while they're
parallel. So maybe the more important
case is if they're not parallel.
L1 and L2 are not parallel.
Okay. So if they're not parallel then
they intersect and therefore the sum L1
of X L2 of X is one.
But if you take the high part
L1H L2H you get zero. So the high parts
are orthogonal.
Okay. And we discussed a couple ways of
seeing this. Um so one way to see it
is based on the fora transform.
[Applause]
So if you take L hat of C its norm is Q
times characteristic function of L perp
and so in particular
the support
of L1 hat intersected with the support
of L2 hat is L1 perp intersected with L2
perp which is just the origin. if the
lines are in different directions.
So this is all under L1 and L2 are not
parallel. L1 and L2 are not parallel. L1
hat and L2 hat also are not parallel and
they intersect only at the origin.
Okay. And then by looking at the high
part we leave out the origin. So there's
nothing left where they intersect and
that gives us the orthogonal out.
Okay. So once we had this we used it to
prove a proposition
that said if f is the sum over some set
of lines of l
then
f high l2 squared is bounded by the sum
over the lines of l high or not high
l2 squared which then you could work out
easily as bounded by the number of lines
times Q. This is almost an equality.
Okay.
Um so this was really the key thing and
this came from orthogonality. You can
think of it as taking this sum and
expanding it out. So this is the sum L1
and L2 in our set of lines of the sum
L1H L2 H.
And for each of these we plugged in
that.
Okay. So now let's go to three
dimensions. See what's the same and
what's different and and most
importantly what should be the analog of
this proposition.
[Applause]
Okay, so lines in FQ3.
Okay, so they could still be parallel or
not parallel. So if L1 and L2 are
parallel,
um then everything is still true.
They're parallel, then
this is zero. And if we wanted to take
the high part,
it would be negative.
Just the same as before. Okay. What if
they're not parallel?
Okay. If they're not parallel, there are
still two possibilities. They could
intersect each other or they could not
intersect each other.
So I guess there are sort of sub cases.
If they intersect
um then the sum on x l1 l2 would be one
intersect at one point.
Okay, that looks like before and we
could take the high part
um but the high part isn't zero.
So this is an important thing that's
different.
So one one common mistake was not to do
this computation carefully and just
assume it should be zero like it was in
two dimensions.
But it's not
um there's not that much difference
between one and 1 - 1 over Q. So it's
not clear that we're accomplishing a
whole lot by focusing on the high part.
Yeah.
Um okay. Now we so to see this we could
do this computation. It's elementary but
it's a little bit tedious.
Um but let me see if I could say
something conceptual. Um
so the the reason that this happened
here is that the two high parts are
independent of each other as functions.
That's like a high a highbrow way of
saying what's going on. um and um that's
not true anymore. If you have two lines
that intersect in three space, um
they're not is not independent of each
other. So if you know that you're in the
first line, then you're much more likely
to be in the second line than if you
were just a random point.
Okay, so you can I don't know if that's
helpful, but you you could also just
check that
that's how it goes.
Um, okay. They could also not intersect.
If they don't intersect, then everything
is the same as the parallel case
actually. So the that's going to be zero
and the sum of the high parts in a
product the high parts will be negative.
If you do it carefully, it's negative 1
over Q. Same thing would be true here.
Okay. So, uh, another direction that
this suggested to some people is that we
ought to try to think how many pairs of
lines intersect as opposed to the pairs
of lines that don't intersect.
And that is a totally reasonable way of
thinking about this from the beginning.
But it's not ob not obvious how to
figure that out. Um it is possible for
every pair of lines to intersect and
there are there are two significant ways
that that could happen. One way is you
could take all the lines through the
origin. You just pick a point and take
all the lines through that point. Then
every pair of lines will intersect at
that point. Have like a porcupine shape.
A second way that almost all the lines
could intersect is to choose them all in
a plane. So if you fix a plane and then
you choose lines in the plane, a few of
them might be parallel, but almost every
pair of lines in the plane will
intersect.
Um
anyway, so so people try to explore this
a little bit, but it's not so clear how
to uh put a bound how about how many how
many pairs will intersect.
Okay. So then another thought is that
instead of instead of try focusing
on this we should focus we should look
at the for transform and just sort of
see what the for transform tells us. So
the for transform does have a nice
description in any dimension like you
did on the first part of the problem set
and it it tells us something.
Okay. So let's think about the forier
transform
for point of view.
Okay. So if we take the 4A transform of
our line and look at its absolute value,
it will be Q times the characteristic
function of L perp.
But notice, so the L is still a line,
but since we're in in three dimensions,
L perp is two dimension.
Okay. So then if we were to take look at
the so if L1 and L2 are not parallel
not parallel I if I look at the support
of L1 hat intersected with the support
of L2 hat
well that's L1 perp intersected with L2
perp
so I have a two plane and I'm
intersecting it with a different two
plane and that will make a line
a line.
Okay, so a third common mistake was to
not do this so carefully and think that
this intersection was just zero. And if
the intersection was just zero, when you
take the high part, you would get rid of
the zero and that would show that L1 and
L2 were orthogonal, which is not
actually the L1 hat and L2 hat were
orthogonal, which is not actually the
case.
Okay.
Okay. Cool.
All right. So, to prove some kind of a
estimate about how these lines
intersect, we're going to try to combine
um this information and this
information. So, if they're parallel,
they actually are orthogonal, which is
very good. If they're not parallel, um
they're not fully orthogonal. But the
forier transform of the intersection of
for transforms is kind of small and
special. We'll try to use that.
Okay.
Um so here's the analogous proposition
and I think it would have been helpful
if I had stated this in the problem set.
Um okay. So here's how how it goes. So
if L is a set of lines in three
dimensions
and F Q3
um um and F
is the sum
lines
then
um
F L2 squared is bounded by so what we
had before was something like
orthogonality
um
some L and L of F L or this is with the
high part the high part L2 and that's
not true anymore but it is true if we
put an extra factor of Q.
Okay. Um and so then that is around um
the number of lines times each one of
these is around Q and there's another
factor of Q which is around there.
Okay.
So if you compare these this is like an
orthogonality proposition. This is
clearly much weaker than orthogonality
because we have a big factor here.
uh nevertheless it's stronger than
nothing. Even though there's a big
factor here, this proposition has some
meaningful information in it.
Okay. So, let me explain how to prove
this proposition. Um and then we'll
digest it and and say argue that that it
does tell us something interesting even
though it's a lot weaker in some sense
than the two dimensional proposition.
Okay. How do we prove this?
[Applause]
All right.
Um,
so
for parallel lines, we have a really
good information. So let's first think
about all the lines in a given direction
and add those up. And then after that,
we'll add up the different directions.
So we'll label the directions by W. So W
will be a one-dimensional subspace
direction and then LW will be the lines
in our set of lines that are parallel to
W.
Okay. And we can also make an FW. That's
the sum over the lines in LW of L. So F
itself is the sum over the different
directions of FW.
Okay, so the first thing that we will do
is um prove some estimates about FW.
Um and this part really is not that
difficult and we're adding up functions
with disjoint supports. So it's not that
complicated what happens. Um, okay.
So, FW
L2
is the size of W sorry the size of uh LW
* Q.
Why is that? We're we're
because the Okay. So proof
uh so the sum f w^2 is the sum lw
sum on x
l of x
squared.
But these lines are parallel. They're
disjoint from each other. So there's
only at any given x only one of them is
making an appearance.
So this is some l
sub x l of x squ.
Okay. And then that's the right hand.
[Applause]
Okay. And if you, it's not clear yet why
we would want to look at the high
frequency part, but if we did, it
wouldn't change much. So FW high L2 is
less than FWL2.
And so the proof is that this is this is
true for any function.
We have have it over over there. Um
for any function g2
is always g l2 2 plus g high l2 squ. So
it's at least as big as g high2.
Okay. So you can do it with the with
furry transform. You you could also do
it by hand.
That's a it's
call it an exercise.
Okay.
Now um the more tricky and interesting
point is what happens when we add
together the different W
and when we do that the way their fora
transforms behave will come into play.
All right.
So I guess that this is lema three but
I'm going to put a star because this is
the important lema. This is where the
interesting stuff is happening.
Okay. Important lema says that f L2
is bounded by Q + 1 times the sum on W
of FWL2.
Okay, here's the proof. Oh, and sorry.
And now I need to put high everywhere.
All right. So,
f high l 2 is by planer. It's the sum on
the nonzero c fhat of c squ.
So remember that f knot is the zero
frequency part of f. f high as all the
other frequencies in F. And so this is
planer.
Oh, okay. And I guess because of the
finite field normalization that I always
have trouble remembering, there should
be this.
Okay. Now f is the sum of fw.
This is 1 / q cubed times the sum in the
nonzero c sum on w of fw hat of c^
squ.
Okay.
Now in two dimensions we could have done
this and gotten to this point and then
we would have been very happy because
the different FW hats have different
supports. They're supported on on
different lines through the origin. So
we would have orthogonality.
So the way it would the way it would
have worked in two dimensions is that
for any particular C there is only one w
which is non zero in this sum and so we
could take this square in inside.
Okay but that's not true anymore. So fw
hat is supported on wp
and in any in any uh in any given
direction any given any given c there
are many different two planes that
contain that c.
So let's write that down.
So we're going to note
that the support of FW hat is WRP
and um so for any C um
uh the um FW
the the set of W so that f W of C is not
zero is contained in the set of W. So
the W is in C per
yeah
>> did the we we still need the high part
right on the
on the F hat.
>> Yeah. So the question is I think the
question is so on the left hand side I
put the high part of F and the question
is do we need the high part here? Is
that the question?
>> Zero. No. Um so we so we don't need that
but but I should have said it uh
clearer. So let's all remember that if
you take the high part of f hat c what
you get is fhat of c is non zero and
zero if c is zero.
So this is this is f fihat.
Okay. So for any given frequency C, I
only need to include the W's in CP.
So actually I can write
this
and there aren't as many there. There's
more than one of them, but there is a
non-trivial bound on how many are terms
are in this sum. So the number of W
in C perp so this is a two plane we're
talking about how many lines through the
origin there are in this two plane
that's Q + one
so for so there are something like Q ^2
different W in total but for any given C
we're only including Q of them in the
sum here that's not as good as
orthogonal ity, but it actually is
helpful information.
And the way we can exploit that
information is by Koshy Schwarzing this.
So I'm going to think of this as the sum
of this thing times 1. Of course, I
didn't change anything. And now I can
apply Koshy Schwarz
one over Q cubed sum over the nonzero C.
Okay, the first term will be
some W in C per
FAT of W of C norm squared
and the second half will be some W and C
per of 1 2
okay and this is Q + one
so we bring that out to the front. And
after that, what we have left is a sum
that just involves each FW one at a
time. So it's Q + 1 1 over Q cubed sum
on the nonzero C. Um
actually I could put well I'll put the
sum on W here. F WW hat C^ squ but I can
switch the order of these sums.
And now if I plan your back I have Q +
one times the sum on W FW high L2.
And that's the statement.
Okay. Any questions or comments?
In that case maybe I have a question for
you.
In this proof, what was the purpose of
taking out the zero frequency? What did
we gain by doing that?
>> Yeah,
>> the zero frequency
equals 0 every
W contains equals Z. So the bound would
be Q.
>> Good. Good. So the comment is that C
equals 0 is special because and when C
is zero every W per goes through zero.
So um every every there so there are Q2
different W's and every one of them has
a contribution at zero. So if we wanted
to do Koshy Schwarz we would have Q ^
squ terms here. Um but at every other C
we have only Q W per going through it
and so we have to pay only Q over here.
That's what's different about zero and
not zero.
Yeah. Good.
Okay. Um so now the proof of the
proposition over there is just
assembling these lemas. So the
proposition says that I I want to bound
the L2 norm of f high.
How do I do it? Uh, lamma 3 says the L2
norm of fi is bounded by q + one times
the sum on w of those. And llamas one
and lamas 2 tells me how big each one of
these is.
If you put that all together, you get
you get proposition two.
Okay.
Okay. Um,
great. Okay. So, now let me erase this a
little bit and let's think about what
what proposition two tells us about
lines in free space.
Okay.
Um, so actually let's let's uh first
review what proposition one tells us
about lines in the plane.
So f is a sum of lines.
fnot is always the number of lines
divided by q. And so f L2 squared is
works out to be the number of lines
squared. It's not hard to check.
And proposition one,
it tells us that fi L2 is bounded by the
number of lines times Q. So if you put
these together, you see that if the
number of lines is much bigger than Q,
then F is mostly constant.
So then uh the L2 norm of f_subi is much
smaller than the L2 norm of the constant
part. The sum of lines looks almost
constant with some small perturbations.
Okay. What's the analog of that in three
dimensions?
Lines in FQ3.
Okay. So in three dimensions fnot is the
number of lines over q ^2 because each
line occupies a 1 over q ^2 fraction of
space.
And so then you can compute the l2 norm
of f^ 2. It's not difficult. It's number
of lines squared over q.
And on the other hand we know that fi l2
is at most the number of lines times q
^2.
You can put these together. If the
number of lines is large enough, then
this is way bigger than this.
If you do a little bit of algebra, you
see that if the number of lines is much
larger than Q cubed,
then the high frequency part is much
smaller than the constant part. So if
you add up more than q cubed lines in
three-dimensional space, you'll get
something that's mostly constant with
some small perturbations.
Okay. Now these are both the correct
thresholds for this behavior. Why? So in
two dimensions suppose I add up less
than Q lines. Say Q over2 lines. Well
they only fill half of space. So there's
no way that that thing is going to look
constant. So this will certainly not be
true with Q over two lines.
All right. Now in three dimensions
suppose I add up less than Q cubed lines
maybe half of Q cubed lines.
All right. Now this is a trickier
wicket. It depends which lines I pick.
If you were to pick half of Q cubed
lines randomly and add them up it would
be quite close to constant.
But if you pick them cleverly you can
make it not look like a constant. And
here's how to do it.
Um
so example
of 12 q cubed lines
in fq cubed.
Okay, here's what I'm going to do. I'm
gonna pick one half Q aine two planes
uh capital PJ
and then um in each capital PJ
I pick
all the lines
which is basically Q^2 lines.
So two dimensional plane has about Q ^2
lines in it. Q2 + Q.
Okay. So you put this all together.
That's about half of Q cubed lines. Um
now f which is the sum l and l is
supported
on the union of the pj
and the size of the union of the pj is
uh is clearly at most half of the space.
So the size of the union of PJ is at
most 12 Q the number of J times Q ^2
number of points per plane 12 Q cubed.
So this thing is only supported on about
half of space. There's no way that it's
approximately constant.
Cool.
Okay. So in a certain sense this is the
right threshold. Uh although you could
also imagine asking some more refined
questions.
Okay, I guess looking back at the
homework, I mentioned a few a few things
that people tried that didn't work. And
um I think the most common thing that
people had a tricky time finding was
that they should first group the lines
in by their direction and have these FWS
and then group the FWS together to make
F.
Yeah. Um so I think I could have done a
better job giving direction to look in
that look that way. Look in that
direction. Uh but in hindsight, why was
that a good idea?
Um
there's a saying that I like about
trying to learn stuff or trying to
figure stuff out that I learned from a
Taichi teacher. Uh they said do do
what's easy first.
So if you are you're trying to for in
math for example add up a whole lot of
things and understand what the sum is
like. If there are some pieces that you
can add up and you know what those are
like it's usually a good idea to do that
first.
Um and uh you know adding up parallel
lines is fairly easy to understand and
so
it won't always help but sometimes it's
helpful to do what's easy first
actually same thing happens in Fubini
when I teach analysis at various levels
when is it a good idea to do Fubini to
switch the order of integration or
switch the order of summation you want
to put the sum that you do first to be
the easy one that's almost always the
right way to organize
Okay. So that was the recap of the
homework.
Okay. Um cool. So now the now we come to
the the main the main topic of the day
uh which is uh doing some some
projection theory in uklidian space and
thinking about how projections ma makes
functions smoother. So if you take a
function in R to the D and you project
it onto something lower dimensional
um well if you just pick one lower
dimensional projection it might not be
very nice but if you look at all the
lower dimensional projections most of
them will be smoother and we're going to
investigate that phenomenon. And I hope
you'll see that it's very parallel to
the large civ theory from number three.
[Applause]
All right, projections
and smoothing.
All right, so here's our setup. Uh so f
is now a function on r to the d
and v is going to be a subspace.
Okay. And recall but by by the
projection of f what I mean is the
integral over var f of y + z
d volume of z.
So this is a map from functions on R to
the D to functions on V.
Um okay
u and I'm going to mostly focus
everything works for all the dimensions
but for ease of notation whatever I'm
going to mostly focus on projecting to
onedimensional subspaces. So theta is a
direction in the circle. Pi theta of f
is going to mean pi it's abbreviation
for pi span of theta of f or direction.
look at the line in that direction.
All right. So, here is a theorem that
says that if you start with a function
that's very little regularity, most of
the projections are even smooth. So
theorem says
if f is an l2 function on r to the d and
the support of f is in the unit ball
then
um if I integrate over the sphere and I
take um
the projection onto the line in the
theta direction of f and I take it ck
norm
um then that is bounded by the L2 norm
of f provided that the dimension is big
enough. So I add the hypothesis to
dimension uh what should it be?
Dimension
D minus one / 2 should be bigger than 12
+ K.
You can unwind that a little bit. It
says D is bigger than something
right. So for example
D is seven then you can take K equals 2.
So in seven dimensions, take just a L2
function. If you project it down to one
dimension in a typical direction, you'll
get something that's C2.
Okay, I'm actually not sure to whom to
attribute this theorem. So I'm I'm in
the process of doing some historical
research and maybe I'll know next class.
All right.
[Applause]
So this theorem is also based on the 4A
transform and the way the 4A transform
interact with projections.
So now let's think about how that works.
transform
and projections.
All right. So f is a function on r to
the d. It has a 4 a transform. We've
talked about it. Pi V of F is a function
on V. It also has a 4A transform. I just
remind you how it works. So V is a
vector space and it basically works the
same way as on on uklidian space. Um
okay. So suppose I have a function G
from B to C. Um then g hat will also be
a function from v to c and ghat of c
will be the integral over v of uh g of y
e - 2i i y c d y but dy means with
the volume form for my vector space v.
So that's the for a transform.
Yeah.
>> Why do you add the two pi here normally
include the general transform? Is that
just a convention?
>> Yeah. So the question is why is there a
2 pi here? There are a couple different
conventions for the 4a transform. One of
them has a 2 pi here. The other one has
a 1 over 2 pi to the d in the front.
Those are as far as I can tell equally
good. And they both involve some
slightly annoying factors of 2 pi.
There's another convention where you
write neither of those things. Um, that
strictly speaking is not correct, but
it's convenient and it usually is okay.
Uh, okay.
Uh, okay. Then we can do for a inversion
where we recover g of y. Do for a
inversion. That's the integral over v
ghat x of c e to the 2 pi i y c d volume
of x c.
Okay, so that's how the for transform
works on a subspace. Um and um
and now what does projection do to the
for a transform? There's an elegant
formula llama call it a a dictionary
lama translates between
the um projection on the physical side
and projection on the forier side and
it's analogous to something that I
called the dictionary lema when we were
doing large s all right it says the
following thing um if I have a function
on r to the d
then if I project it to v and take its
fora transform it's just fhat of c
for all c and v.
All right, so let's process a second. So
this is a function on v. It's for a
transform is only defined on v. So this
left hand side only makes sense if c is
in v. But it's equal to fhat of c and
fhat makes sense for c anywhere in rd.
Okay, so here's the proof. Um
yeah, let's just expand out what
everything means. So the left hand side
is the integral over v pi v of y eus 2
pi i c doy
um d volume v of y.
But what is the projection pi v of y?
That's also an integral and it's an
integral over v.
So that's the integral over v integral
over vp
f of y + z
d volume of z. So that was this thing
e to the minus 2 pi i y c d volume of y.
All right. So now notice that all
together if you put this stuff together
and that and that together we are
integrating over r to the d.
Um and so more precisely we can do sort
of a change of variables here. We can
say x is y + z and dx is dv volume v of
y dv volume v of z.
So this is f ofx. This stuff is just dx.
Uh now who is this?
Well, because z is in var and c is in v.
Z do c is zero.
So e to the minus 2i i y c is the
same thing as e - 2 pi i y + z c.
changed it by z which was zero
which is e to the minus 2 pi iix x dx
okay so I can rewrite everything in
terms of x and it's just my integral
fx e the minus 2i ix c dx
all right so that's fhatic c and that's
what we wanted to prove
All right. Good.
Okay.
Okay. So let's see what how might we use
this? What might this tell us? Um,
so we're interested in this projection
thing and the projection plays very
nicely with the forier transform. And so
any anything else that plays nicely with
the for transform, we could sort of try
to figure out how it interacts with
projection.
And one of the fundamental things that
interacts nicely with the for transform
is the L2 norm because we have planer.
So we can write F L2 in terms of F hat.
and fhat is closely related to pi v of
fhat. And let's just see what happens.
What does that tell us?
Okay, so I'll call this um
relating
um
f2
and pi v of f via the 4a transform.
Okay. And I'm going to focus on pi theta
of f because that will make this the
easiest.
All right. So
f l2^2
is f l2.
Write that out. It's the integral over r
d f of c^ 2 d c.
Okay. and the different um if I take pi
theta of fhat
that will correspond to fhat on
different lines through the origin.
So that suggests let's sort of separate
this out in different directions by
writing it in polar coordinates.
So this is equal to the integral over
the dus one sphere integral from 0 to
infinity
f of r theta^
2 r dus1 dr r d theta.
Okay. And um
let me do this little trick
to also include negative r so that once
I fix theta I have a nice integral from
minus infinity to infinity.
All right. So this guy is related to pi
theta of f by this lema.
So this is 12
sus1
d theta. So I'm averaging over all the
different directions. And what am I
averaging? integrating from minus
infinity to infinity
pi theta f
of r theta
r the dus one dr r
what is this inside thing inside here
you know at first you might have thought
you might get the l2 norm of pi theta of
f^2
but that's so that would be the L2 of
the F^2.
This has this extra factor here
which heavily weights large frequencies
and gives a very low weight to small
frequencies.
Yeah,
>> that's right. This thing is a soalevn
norm. So what what naturally appears
here is a soalev norm. And now let's
pause and we'll review solev norms and
the and some fact important facts about
them.
[Applause]
All right.
Okay. So definition
if I have a function G on a vector space
um like a like a subspace of well a
space with a with uklidian norm.
>> Yeah.
>> Um this is about the dictionary level.
I'm wondering what class of functions
that applies to because if f is like an
L2 function so f hat is L2 function. How
is its value on a measure zero subset
like be meaningful?
>> Yeah. Okay, great. So the the going back
to the dictionary lema. Um the question
was for which set class of functions
does this actually make sense. And if
you look at what I wrote on the board,
it's a little suspicious. It just says
that f is a function. And if f is just a
function, actually none of the sides of
this equation in general make sense. Um
uh one thing that would that would be
clearly sufficient is if f was a schwarz
function.
If f is a schwarz function um f had hat
is awarz function. The projection is a
schwarz function. It's it's for
transformation. So that's all okay. Um
if f is just l2 it's not immediately
obvious how how all of these things
would be defined. Um so let's think
about this this way for now. Um and
in in in it's fairly often the case that
we can prove things about general L2
functions by first proving them for
Schwarz functions and then proving um
then using the fact that Schwarz
functions are dense in L2.
Okay. Um
okay good
okay okay so we were remembering what
what is a sole fn norm so if I have a
function on v then um g hs dot squared
is the integral over v
I'll take the norm of g hat of c^2
um and then I'll put here the norm of C
to the 2s.
This makes sense for any real number S.
Um and um
and it has something to do with the
smoothness of of of G and in particular
if S is a natural number then it has an
interpretation in terms of L2 norms of
derivatives.
So um G H1 dot squared
is the sum over different directions J
of the J derivative of G L2 at least
approximately maybe exactly um and then
um higher values of S higher values of S
correspond to taking more derivatives so
I'll just put one more and you'll see
the pattern h2 dot squared is around the
sum over J1 and J2 of the second
derivative in the J1 J2 directions of G
L2 and so on.
Okay. Um and if S is not an integer then
there's not a direct interpretation of
this form but it is still kind of
measuring how smooth the function G is.
Okay. There is also a regular. So this
is the sole f norm with a dot. It's
called the homogeneous soalef norm. And
there's a version without the dot which
is defined like this. Um
gh hs 2 is the integral over v ghat of c
^ 2 uh 1 + the norm of c ^ 2 to the s d
c
which is roughly the same um as if you
took out the biggest power. This would
be 1 + c 2s
and the one contributes gl 2^ 2
and the c to the 2s is this thing. So it
contributes
hs dot.
Okay.
Um
cool. So there's a well-known um set of
theorems called the soalev embedding
theorems which imply that if g is in a
soalev space for a big enough s then it
is continuous and if even a bigger s
then it's c1 and so on. Um so I will
write a summary.
So belove embedding. Um
if s is bigger than
1/2 the dimension of v um then
g l infinity is bounded by g in hs
and um and if g is in hs then g is
continuous.
And if we add um if s is bigger than
some k plus 1/2 the dimension of v um
then the kith derivatives
of g are bounded by the hs norm
and if g is in hs then it's ck
Okay.
Um, any questions or comments about sov
spaces?
Okay. Um so
now that we have recalled that
if we look back here
we will recognize what appears here as a
solev norm of the projection.
So the L2 norm squar of f is this
integral and this thing here
is the hs norm of pi theta of f. So this
is 12 integral over the d minus one
sphere
pi theta of f h
d -1 / 2 dot^ 2
d theta.
Okay. Where did this come from and why
does it have a dot? This r is the norm
of my frequency c.
So this is the norm of c to the 2 s. So
s is d minus one over two. And it's
homogeneous. We don't have this extra
one. So there's a dot.
Okay. Cool.
Cool.
Um
okay so now you can pro probably have a
good guess of how we would like to prove
this theorem.
The L2 norm
controls an integral like this with the
soelv norm. Sov embedding tells us that
the soilv norm controls the ck norm.
So that's the plan. Okay. But
technically there is a small technical
issue which has to do with the dot or
the no dot. Dot and no dot homogeneous
not homogeneous are both natural and
important. Homogeneous one will occur
naturally in some places. It naturally
occurred here. On the other hand sov
embedding is a theorem that requires uh
that the non-homogeneous soil of space.
So we need to do a little bit of work to
to get between
Okay.
Um so now we can do proof of theorem.
All right. So integral sdus1
pi theta f c k k d theta is bounded by
integral sdus one pi thetaf f
h dus1 / 2 without the dot squared d
theta so this is so embedded
okay and that hypothesis about d up
there is just exactly the hypothesis
that you need for this to be true when
you plug in so embedding.
All right, now let's open up the
definition of this thing and we'll
almost see the FL2 norm squared but not
quite.
So this is around integral of sdus one
integral from minus infinity to infinity
f of r theta^ 2 and we'll have 1 + r dus
d r d theta.
So we don't have a dot that requires us
to put this extra one that we didn't
have before.
All right. So you have a sum of two
pieces. In real analysis, we usually
think about which of the two pieces is
bigger. So if r is bigger than one, this
piece dominates. And if r is smaller
than one, that piece dominates.
So it's the integral sus one integral r
bigger than 1
f of r theta^ 2 r dus r d theta. Let's
call that term number one.
Plus the integral sdus one integral r
smaller than one f of r theta^ 2
1 * 1 d r d.
Let's call this piece two.
Okay.
So piece one is uh clearly smaller than
what we had before which was f L2 squ.
So piece one smaller than L2.
Piece two.
Okay. In piece two I think it's no
longer really helpful to think of this
as being related to polar coordinates.
We're integrating over a sphere cross
and interval and that's a finite volume.
And so what I'd like to put here is just
that it's bounded by the a constant
which is the volume times the biggest
possible size of this
super.
Okay. So how big is that?
So fhat of c
bounded by the integral f(x) e - 2i
iix x c dx and the most common approach
the easiest approach to this is use the
triangle inequality so we have this
now we have the l1 norm of f okay so we
have two pieces one piece is controlled
by the l2 norm of f the other piece is
controlled by the l1 norm of f um I
could have written the theorem that way
But I wrote it a little bit differently.
I thought it was cuter. Uh I've had the
support of f is in the unit ball. If the
support of f is in the unit ball, then
we can control the L1 norm by the L2
norm.
So
since the support of F is in the unit
ball integral of f ofx
dx looks like that. It's bounded by the
integral of f(x)^2
to the 12 times the integral over the
unit ball of 1 to the 12. So that's
bounded by f2.
Okay. So using using the support I can
bound both one and two by FL2
and um
okay and that was that was what I had
thought of as the proof of the theorem
but now is a good moment to come back to
the question that was asked earlier.
What do you actually have to assume
about f for all of this to make sense?
Um okay. Um so let me add some fine
print. I'll write what we actually
proved.
Um
all right. So the fine print is for for
the time being suppose that f is a
schwarz function.
We needed f is a Schwarz function to
justify our formula about the 4A
transform of the projection and in a few
other places to make sure all these for
a transforms make sense. If you assume
that F is Schwarz, everything we wrote
makes sense. Um and we get this estimate
and and this is an inequality.
And then it is now possible to do some
extra work. If you have a function
that's not Schwarz, just a function in
L2, you could have a sequence of Schwarz
functions that approximate it and um and
for each one of those approximating
functions, this bound would be true. And
then with some work, you could show that
the bound is also true for the limiting
function f.
Okay. So I'll put a remark
um can remove the hypothesis.
[Applause]
Okay.
Um, so any questions or comments about
the proof of this theorem?
>> Is the condition that the support is in
the unit essential to this?
>> Yeah. Okay. So the question is, is the
assumption that the support of F is in
the unit ball essential? What would
happen if we remove this assumption?
>> Right.
>> Yeah. So looking at the proof, we could
um
let me get another color.
Looking at the proof, we could if we
want to remove this assumption. And then
we would need to add the L1 norm as well
as the L2 norm um to deal with um
uh due to my brilliant neighbor labeling
scheme, term one is bounded by the L2
norm and term two is bounded by the L1
norm.
Okay, I haven't thought about it
carefully. You you could ask if we did
this uh would it still be true? I
suspect that's not true and the sort of
natural example to look at is a function
on a really big ball. I haven't I
haven't thought it through carefully.
So, it's good a good little good little
project to figure out what happens.
Okay.
Okay. So the um big big picture takeaway
of this theorem is we take a function in
high dimensions which is not very
regular and when we project it to low
dimensions most of the projections are
much more regular and um I was trying to
think of places that this relates to or
we might have seen something like this
before. Um and one place where we see
something like this is the central limit
theorem in probability.
Um,
so let me remind us how that works.
Okay. So suppose that XJ are random
variables
which are uniformly distributed
in 01
and there are a lot of them one up to n.
Okay. So in the central limit theorem we
might think what happens if we add up
all these random variables.
Um so and we could look at the sum of
the XJ. This will be the random
variable.
Actually let me put it not that
important but going to put minus a half
a half. The central limit theorem is a
little bit nicer.
Uh okay. So what happens when I add them
up? and I add them up. The central limit
theorem
says that the sum of these random
variables
is approximately a Gaussian
with mean zero and um standard deviation
something like square root of n.
And notice in particular that it's quite
smooth.
Okay.
So
um okay. So the probability the joint
probability density function of these
XJS
XJ
is f of x1 up to xn. It's the
characteristic function of the cube.
So this is a sort of typical this is an
example of a function that's in L2 but
is not continuous.
Okay. Uh now what is what is the
probability density function of this
thing? Um well, we have a map. Um I
guess the summation map goes from Rn to
R and it just takes X1 up to Xn and it
maps it to X1 plus F plus Xn. Add them
up. It's a linear map.
So the probability
density function
of um of the sum of the xjs
is the push forward of fdx
and this is a slightly different
language but it is up to a small change
of variables. It's the projection of f
on the main diagonal.
[Applause]
So
actually
I can make we can make this look nicer
if we normalize in the central limit
theorem which is not a which is a fairly
standard way of writing it. So let me
write the central limit theorem this
way.
Okay. So now my function is
that
and let's say that theta is 1 / n11
which is in which is a unit vector. So
this is just the projection I'll call it
theta 1 in the theta 1 direction of f.
Okay.
So I take the characteristic function of
the cube. If I project it in that
direction, I get something that is
almost a Gaussian. And that's the
central limit there.
And notice in particular that the that
that that projection is quite smooth.
So if I were to take the cube and I were
just going to project it onto the x1
axis,
well the other variables would be
irrelevant and I would just get the
characteristic function of an interval
and it would not be any smoother than it
was before. Still be discontinuous. And
that's the same I could project it onto
any of the axes. They're all the same.
That would be uh characteristic function
of an integral. But if I project it onto
the main diagonal then I get the thing
in the central limit theorem which is
extremely smooth and you know the the
the the more I increase the dimension
the more it looks like a Gaussian and in
particular the smoother it gets.
Okay. Now in the central limit theorem
it actually is not terribly important
that all of these are exactly one. It's
just important that they're roughly
equal to each other.
So as long as you take a direction which
is doesn't emphasize any of the
coordinate axes too much, you'll see
something like the central limit
theorem. So in all of those directions,
the projection will look quite smooth
and in fact it will look a lot like a
Gaussian.
Uh or where but if you were to project
it in the bad directions and in a
coordinate direction or combination of a
couple coordinate directions, then
you'll get something that's not so
smooth.
Okay, so that's an example of this
theorem.
And in this special example, we can say
much more refined things about which
directions are good and bad and exactly
what happens. Um, but this theorem is a
lot more general because you don't have
to put in the characteristic function of
a cube. You can put in quite a broad
range of functions
and qualitatively similar things happen.
Yeah,
>> dumb but like this theorem we proved
earlier it's really saying like when you
integrate you make it smoother like it's
a projection is an integration.
>> Yes. Yes. The comment is the comment is
that when we project we project by
integrating some of the variables and so
the comment is when we integrate
something we make it smoother. That's a
really nice comment and it reminds us of
something uh more familiar and
fundamental just like if you had a
function of one variable that was just
in L2 say or L1 if you integrated it it
would get smoother. If you integrated it
a whole bunch of times, then you would
get something smooth.
Yeah. So, this is a little bit like this
is this is a little bit like that. And I
guess the smoothness does come from
doing the integration.
>> Um, in this situation,
>> yeah, what's it?
>> The bounds are interesting. So, like
like how smooth it is is interesting.
>> Yes, the bounds are interesting. Yes.
Yeah. And I guess one of the differences
here is, you know, this this function
depends on many variables. We're going
to integrate some of them but not
others.
Um, and so
yeah, anyway, so it and then it depends
which ones we integrate whether or not
it gets smoother, but it turns out that
usually it does.
Yeah. But yeah, I think that I think
that is a good way of looking at it.
Yeah.
Cool.
Cool. Okay. So let me end by mentioning
so as part of the class I'll try to
mention different ways that that
projection theory is related to various
parts of math. Um and so this reminds me
of something I heard about um which is
about trying to generalize the central
limit theorem. So what if the input was
not um independent random variables but
something somewhat more general? Would
it still be true that when we take a
projection like this, you would see a
Gaussian?
Um,
and so there's a a big a big body of of
work on that. Um, but what one
interesting direction I heard about is
initiated by Keith Ball and it's
connection between probability theory
and convex geometry. And the point of
view is that maybe to some extent what's
important about the cube is just that
it's a convex set. So instead of the
cube, take any convex set in R to the N.
N is large.
Okay. Now there's no distinguished like
there's nothing special about the
coordinate axis anymore. So so it's not
the coordinate axis projections aren't
necessarily the ones that are bad that
this one isn't necessarily good. But the
the question he raised is maybe you take
any convex set and look at its
projections onto one-dimensional spaces.
Maybe most of them are almost Gaussian.
Okay. And that's a recent topic of
research and a significant amount like
that is true. Um, uh, Keith Ball gave an
ICM talk about it and I put some
references in the homework if anybody is
interested in reading about it.
Cool.
Um, okay. Well, let's let's stop there
for today.
uh to to the plan for Thursday is to
come back to the large civ which is done
which is from number theory and I'll try
to tell you some some things what kind
of applications in number theory does
the large civ