so I'm going to uh talk about some space
policy
issues um I I'm going to give you a
certain perspective on Space technology
from some different viewpoints and then
talk about the aeroastro department and
then talk about another issue which is
very important to me which the
demographic issues in the space
Enterprise and finally end it with two
different views of the
future so in terms of space policy
issues you know I I thought rather than
just hearing my perspective
uh what you I should let you know the
perspectives of some of our students
right so we we actually have a space
policy class that I uh co-teach with
Professor David Newman and so at the end
of that class we asked them to write a
set of papers on what they see as the
critical issues in space policy so so
this is the titles of their papers in
addition to that there's actually a
whole policy Club here and I asked them
so what do you see is the big issues in
space policy and they gave me two pages
of list right so that's good this is
what young people are seeing at some of
the issues uh in the space business and
I think what you can definitely say is
that there's just a lot of stuff going
on in space policy and space technology
it's a very Dynamic time driven both by
the rise of entrepreneurial space as in
you know what SpaceX is doing what blue
origin is doing and it's other companies
one web and so on also by the fact
there's now many many countries that are
in the space business it's no longer the
purview of just a few but there are many
countries that launch many countries
that build satellites and so
International um issues have grown
substantially so uh here you see the
list from the from let's first of all
start with space policy class uh you
know one of the the issues for a space
policy is the fact that you know the
outer space treaty comes from the 60s
the outer space treaty which governs uh
international law in space you know was
was negotiated at a time when there were
really only two players in the space
business which was the Soviet Union and
the United States and it it reflects
that and you know many people myself
included think that the outer space
treaty needs to be updated but certainly
one of the things that come become very
current is the whole issue of liability
and claims in space you know if if
somebody's satellite hits something else
who actually is liable I mean what the
outer space treaty says is it's the
launching uh country uh but of course
satellites are now owned by many
different people different countries
different companies and so on so there
are issues there that need to be sorted
out another big issue is the whole Space
Traffic management um development you
know when you're when you're talking
about a very small number of of things
in space you can track them individually
and see if they're going to collide when
you're talking about you
know up north of 50,000 satellites
occupying a band of low earth orbit uh
now you get into serious Space Traffic
management policy issues who who is
responsible for informing you know
SpaceX are going to collide with
somebody else uh who is supposed to move
I mean all of these things need to be
you know sorted out I mean right now
what happens is you know they get a a
message from the from the space force
and they can choose to move or not right
I mean you know so it that's to be
sorted out uh the whole issue of space
sustainability has now become much more
cogent what does it mean to have a
sustainable space
environment uh especially as the number
of satellites goes up old orbital debris
goes
up what what does it mean to have the
sustainability environment go down into
the atmosphere so there are now people
talking about that and developing a
whole set of structures around it um
laser Communications is a particularly
interesting one it it turns out there
are rules about firing lasers
up um but there are no rules about
firing lasers down you you know so
there's a set of policies that need to
be developed there uh um of of you know
we we know there's going to be
commercial space stations so those
policies need to be developed for those
you know the both NASA and the space
force are talking about U nuclear
propulsion uh do the do the rules that
we apply to nuclear materials on the
earth still make sense to apply to
things up in space um I mean is that the
right way to do things or not I mean
there are people discussing those issues
so as you can see there's just lots and
lots and lots of space policy issues and
you see some of some of the uh questions
from the space policy club uh
International cooperation how how to
think about dealing with emerging space
powers like India and China where you
unlike with us companies you don't have
any ability to force them to do things
so you have to enter into agreements
with them
right um um how how does to take the
last one how do you balance Innovation
and regulation with a rapid rise of
price space companies you know too much
regulation will inhibit Innovation so
you don't want that on on the other hand
if you have no regulation then you get
actually what's happening right now
people are just putting up satellites
putting up satellites and there's no
fundamental controls on how much they
put up and where they put them up you
know it is true they have to get
licenses from the FCC and so on uh but
but that's about it right so oh I'll go
to the next one so here's some other
issues the balance of public sector
interest with the dominance of private
space companies um space becoming an
economic
Frontier uh how how should national
government subsidize or regulate the
private space industry these are all
from the students by the way saying this
this these are issues that they care
about um how does policy makers ensure
that commercialization of space does not
lead to environmental degradation like
we've seen on Earth um uh you see the
word sustainability come up there rep L
these students are concerned about these
issues how do we ensure that in the long
term we have something that's
sustainable what are the key
technological innovations that will
shape the future of space exploration
and policy next 20 years what are
policies that govern dual use
Technologies and you know some perceived
as an incre increasing militarization of
space how do we prevent What policies
can we adopt to prevent an arms race in
space um especially as different
countries are are maneuvering for
position there so lots and lots of space
policy issues uh there's no shortage of
opinions these things actually need to
be sorted out I said I thought I'd show
you this because this tells you what
these young people are actually uh
thinking
about now let me turn and give you a
couple of different perspectives um I
I'm currently the president of the aiaa
and because I'm the president I I see
some of the internal documents so the
aiaa has been developing a set of white
papers um for uh actually Aeronautics
what they call Aerospace R&D and and
space so I'm going to show show you
what's in the white papers for Aerospace
R&D and Aeronautics so these are the
things that the aiaa believes are the
the The Cutting Edge R&D um issues uh
across Aerospace digital twins autonomy
AI these things are going to make a huge
difference in the space business
additive manufacturing for for space
system engineering that's transformative
Quantum sensing human robot teaming this
is what they think is part of the future
for for uh space there's an equivalent
list for air but that I'm not going to
show you
that and then for the space domain as
opposed to R&D the fact there's many uh
simultaneously operating systems I mean
you can think of starlink you can think
of Kyper you can think of one web all
all operating to first order in the same
large space um there's the whole idea of
how do we get to routine operations with
these large complex regions of space the
emergence of an independent space sector
that is independent of the government
that's the point independent of the
government um obviously uh maturation of
commodity subsystems I think you might
say many of the Technologies in
satellites are now Commodities actually
and digital management the fact there
fractionation of agency that's actually
implicit in the space policy still who
is the agency that that actually
authorizes everything to occur up there
at least from the US point of view the
answer is there is no one agency
different people authorize different
things right the emergence of potential
space conflicts and of course again
unsustainability of today's civilization
for uh the Earth's biosphere so this
whole issue of space sustainability uh
comes up again in that white paper
uh and and the these are the the areas
of space in the in the aiaa white paper
they call out Earth launch Leo out to
600 kilometers the moo to Geo uh
environment the CIS Luna space going
outside of Geo Luna surface and deep
space what's interesting about this list
is how much bigger it is than something
you might have seen even 10 years ago
it's because you know science is
expanding out there commercial interest
is expanding standing out there uh I
mean just just to take for example um
Luna if you just look at at least what
people say they're going to do in the
next four or five years there going to
be upwards of a hundred satellites going
around the Moon doing interesting things
science commercial stuff and so on right
so it's
expanding and then I I thought I um I
would tell you give you some sense of
what space force is saying I I do
actually see some space force documents
and these are are all public documents
you can go find them yourself they're
saying what the what are the things that
interest them the great power
competition um the space force is very
interested in how to integrate with
commercial space Solutions as opposed to
doing everything themselves game
changers in space they've identified on
orbit servicing as a game Cher and
nuclear propulsion as a game changer um
obviously they need to know what's the
expanded space domain awareness is
um technology maturation and fielding
and again believe or not the space force
itself says sustainable space operations
is of interest to
them um the there's also a list you can
find of technologies that will enable
new capabilities in space what you'll
notice about this list is how similar it
is to the aiaa list what's going to
change the the nature of what's going to
occur in space autonomy trusted AI cyber
all of these things are happening for
ICS uh informetric Imaging Quantum
Communications there are lots of people
looking at those things now nuclear
propulsion and Power on orbit assembly
repair manufacturing and high energy
lasers and power beaming I mean these
are all technologies that over the next
number of years when they come to pass
will make a difference to what occurs in
the space
business so having given you those
perspectives uh I thought I'd now turn
and give you a perspective on what is
MIT aeroastro Department doing uh so the
Engineering Systems lab my colleague
Professor Deek is the head of that uh
there's work going on on space system
architectures to optimize uh system
designs I'll show you some of that we
have a human systems lab that's looking
at optimize human system Effectiveness
uh we have a space repulsion lab looking
at enhanced space propulsion
astrodynamics lab I think Professor
Laris is going to come later and talk to
you about that and then a a a Labs uh
what they call the star lab that does
state-of-the-art laser Communications so
this this of course is not everything
that's going on in space but it's it's
where this department is actually
focused then I thought I'd just give you
a quick perspective of what my own
research group does because I'm going to
take this opportunity to talk about that
so uh we have students that are working
on different a aspects of space
architectures there and I'm going to
show you some of the results
uh the highight band with space
Communications um I I had a student that
took a look at what does it mean to
continuously produce satellites like
Space X does and how does that change
the nature of what you do we actually
are have another student who's taking a
look at uh the commercial space um
augment actually more integration policy
of space force and comparing it to what
the Air Force does uh we are actually
looking at the atmospheric impact of
large scale deorbiting if you think
about all the satellites that are going
up um you know the the current now rule
which the FCC imposed is they all have
to be deorbited in five years five years
after they finish operation not five
years from now uh but which means
they're all going to come back into the
Earth's atmosphere and you're talking
about if you sum them up I said tens of
thousands of satellites deorbiting into
our atmosphere so what's the last SC
atmospheric impact of that I mean they
will demise about 60 km mainly aluminum
some lithium and deposit that into our
atmosphere and it turns out we've
actually done the calculations it's
sufficient mass that it will it's about
the same order as what comes in by
meteorites except meteorites are mainly
of course Stone carbon we're talking
about aluminum lithium now being
deposited into our atmosphere something
that we've never done before it's a
human race so it's the question is
what's the environmental impact of
that um we we I have another student
that looked at iterative manufacturing
system confidence combined with I Isam
in space servicing assembly and
manufacturing of have a student I'm
going to show you some of the results
looking at what value does on orbit
servicing provide uh Space Systems um
and what is utility most
impactful uh and we we took a look at
Luna Space Traffic management and we're
also looking at what can AI do for for
so you know there's a whole bunch of
students all working on a whole range of
issues associated with the exciting
things that are happening in
space so so this I'm going to show you
two sets of results so one is the
question of optimized communication
architectures with deep space missions
so you know right now of course um NASA
communicates with um deep space missions
through the deep space Network it's an
RF Network it's basically at capacity
and as more science Mission goes out how
do they actually get stuff back so we we
we looked at a whole range of different
architectures uh single a laser single
ground station a Goldstone and a raid
ground station multiple
Goldstone ground station in Goldstone
Madrid and Cur putting something out of
The L4 point and putting a space-based
array at moo to then capture the laser
links coming back from these deep space
satellites then down link to Earth by RF
the the trouble with laser Cal of course
from a satellite around around say
Jupiter or around Saturn is you you know
weather the sigma if the sigma comes
back and it's cloudy over Goldstone you
won't get it right so you know how do
you deal with weather so that that's why
you might think of putting stuff out in
space and so not not maybe not
terrifically surprising we we actually
found that a uh a spacebase array
outperforms and data availability that
is if you if you have an array of
receivers in moo uh and then then down
Link in RF you can actually get very
high data Rel be well over 90% very high
data volumes because basically they can
always see the laser signal but not
surprisingly it's the most costly option
of the options we looked at it's the
most costly option um you know if what
if what you want to do is save money
then the least costly option is to put
something at Goldstone to put a laser
receiver at Goldstone and just but you
but you will end up actually not being
able to receive the signals some fair
amount of the
time now of course you could always tell
the the uh satellite to send again all
right once it can see but but you
know and then I'm going to talk to you
about the work we're doing on on orbit
refueling and reposition
so
um you know the the space force says it
is very interested in the whole issue of
of maneuvering in space and the and the
way they characterize it is maneuver
without regret because if you ask the
question why don't they maneuver a lot
of the satellites now it's because
there's only so much fuel on them and if
you maneuver the satellites then you you
basically reduce the lifetime of the
satellites right okay so that's reason
why they're interested in the question
of on orbit refueling and repositioning
and um you know that there is now a a
limited commercial capability North
grman offers in geosynchronous orbit to
actually uh they they don't actually
refuel geinger satellites they actually
attach another satellite with fuel on it
and then it allows it to maneuver to
Contin to maneuver past his uh lifetime
his nominal Lifetime and and the
Europeans have just announced that
they're going to be building an un orbit
refueling system with a robotic arm by
the way uh to go out to geosynchronous
orbit and potentially refuel and with
the robotic arm they can also think
about repairing right okay so we we we
took a look at the question
of when does it actually make sense to
refuel relative to uh the Alternatives
so the alternative of course is you
launch a new satellite right that's the
alternative right
um and so here we construct um uh trade
spaces where you have cost along the x
axis and the and utility along the Y AIS
uh and and basically everywhere you see
color is where it makes more sense to
actually do this right but but here's
where it really gets interesting is if
now you you compare it against um
altitude so we uh we're looking at
utility versus altitude you uh if you
have what they call a a an undemanding
case where you can basically put more
fuel on the satellite you're not
stressing the pay the payload is not so
large that it's stressing the system uh
then refueling makes sense of very low
altitudes and that's because the drag is
very high and if you want to keep it up
there you have to refuel it and it makes
a little bit of sense as you go all the
way out to geosynchronous altitude but
if you have a case which is payload Mass
demanding that is you want to put more
payload on and reduce the size of your
fuel tanks and maneuver a lot then as
you can see again refueling makes a
great deal of sense at low altitudes it
does not make sense at the Leo altitudes
because at Leo altitudes you can always
just put up another satellite relatively
quickly but at geosynchronous altitudes
it's much harder to do and so the
ability to do that gets gets
um uh not the ability but so the utility
of doing it gets much better as the
altitude goes up uh so we we intend to
push this out Beyond goo but this is
this is how far we've got and the
different curves on this is just showing
you know different launch systems Falcon
9 Falcon heavy and so on
right now let me turn to talk about
another issue which I think is really
important which is demographic issues so
so here is the the um demographics the
US population uh percentage of of of uh
of female persons you know white black
Hispanic so this so this is from the
July
2022 uh population estimate
right now let's look at
it uh now let's talk about uh the stem
Workforce especially in Aerospace so if
you look at the the stem Workforce some
uh something of the order of which is 36
million people this is again from this s
uh this is NSL
data um 78% of people in the work that
this Workforce have a bachelor's degree
so so basically the argument is if
you're going to be in the stem Workforce
you need a bachelor's degree it's not to
say there isn't room for people in stem
Workforce don't have but most people
have a bachelor's degree so what it
means is you got to look at the
educational pipeline
now so this is from aiaa it should be
AIA a industry report survey and they
surveyed um um 850,000
employees counting everybody that that
says they're in Aerospace right okay um
and what do you see by contrast to the
what the Census Data I showed you is the
percentage of women in the Aerospace
business is quarter
25% percentage of African-Americans or a
10% um the point is it's very different
from the GL Census Data I showed
you now let's look at the educational
pipeline so this this is from uh Adare
is the Aerospace Department's um
Aerospace Department's chairs
Association
um so th this is data goes up through
2022 and it shows you across uh the
people responded to this with 60 60
different schools with departments in
aerospace engineering okay uh um um what
what do you see you see the percentage
of women uh across those years is is it
the undergraduate level you know a bit
less than
20% uh and underrepresented minorities
goes up and down but it's you know again
about
20% the point I want to make is this is
very different from the Census spir data
um and it's even different from from the
the big uh survey across all of
Aerospace so so this pipeline is just
not producing enough people you know to
uh you know help the Aerospace is
industry actually
Chang here's now the data for graduate
programs through
2022 uh the both foreign students uh you
can see is the order of
30% uh women which actually went up
quite dramatically from 2020 to 2022 and
then underrepresented minorities right
so if if if you're looking for the
demographics of Aerospace to change this
data does not support the notion that
it's changing and I the reason I'm
showing to you is I think it's an
important issue for the Aerospace
business uh this just goes back a bit
further uh both ethnicity and gender
Trends back to 2010 and you can see the
C the curves are basically flat so there
there's not very much progress that's
happening in the Aerospace
field just to give you the contrast uh
this is from the aeroastro class of
2019 you know we here at MIT we do
somewhat better a higher percentage of
women higher percentage of minorities um
not so much better The Graduate students
but the undergraduate level um
so let me just end by saying you know
I've talked to you about space policy
issues I've talked to you about some
technology issues uh I've talked to you
about some of the demographic issues uh
you know I I think this in the space
business this is my take it's of course
we can we can debate this uh there a
tale of two
Futures uh so the pessimistic view is
there's an imbalance of governance and
freedom we either have have too much
regulation or too little regulation and
in the pessimistic view uh space debris
would continue to increase it's
increasing right now but it it continues
to increase we don't develop any rules
of the road or or there's no
standardization um there aren't enough
rules of the road there may be active
warfare in
space uh there's there are large scale
environmental effects both low orop and
down into our
atmosphere uh ISM Technologies which are
underdevelopment or immature maybe
having Aeris using and there's a cooling
off of space interest I mean certainly
if we get to the point where the low
orbit environment is full of space
debris there'll be a cooling off of
space interest because the satellites
will get
destroyed that's the pessimistic
view here's the optimistic view where
there's a healthy balance of governance
and freedom and you know where where
there's enough regulation to keep things
in control but not so much as to uh
inhibit Innovation so uh those rules of
the road that are established not just
for us companies but for us companies
and with other countries like China and
India rules of the road are established
that are agreed to standardization is is
established in order to actually refuel
a satellites you actually need to
standardize the refueling um because
there's no point in developing a
refueler if it can't actually go up and
refuel the satellite because it can't
connect to it right um there's
widespread Commerce uh maybe with space
stations uh certainly with respect to
all the internet in the sky um that you
know SpaceX is developing and Kyper is
developing we we have figured out how to
extinguish space
debris you know what is the case is that
some uh you know NASA now says they have
now establish an office of space
sustainability and they they say that
one of the things they will do is is
understand what are the Technologies we
need to develop to get rid of space
debris I
mean you actually have to probably go up
and grab it and push it into the
atmosphere or do something else with it
but you just can't leave it up there
right uh the Japanese government is also
funding astroscale to do some work on
Space debris and astroscale has a system
up there right now where they've already
shown they can find Space debris and
then the I think the next mission
they're going to try to actually grab
some and deorbit
it uh we have mitigated the
environmental impact of all of these
satellites coming back into the
atmosphere uh either we show that
there's no impact which actually is not
very likely I I'm pretty sure we can
show there is some impact but we we
understand what it is and we've
mitigated it uh we now use Isam
Technologies in space servicing assembly
manufacturing for benefit we we
manufacture things in space we assemble
things in space you know
robotically um and we we we that extends
out to lunar orbit and it extends out to
beyond that and we've developed nuclear
propulsion and nuclear propulsion will
allow us to get human beings to Mars you
know in time scales are not measured in
years but get human beings there and get
people back if that's the optimistic
future if we can do all of that stuff
you'll see a different future than the
pessimistic
one so I you could probably tell I
sincerely hope this is where we're going
but there are there's there also
indications of you know the the
pessimistic future being there and so
you know I think we're not so much a
Tipping Point this very moment but over
the next several years uh you know we're
going to move in either one direction or
another so with that my key takeaways
are um first of all this is why I showed
you the the demographic data we need a
diversity of people in the Aerospace
business Empower to implement change uh
uh and an atmosphere to make it a
reality the Aerospace business has to be
open to all the capable men and women
who want to be in it we need to do that
this is something that's important for
us as a department and it's important I
I'm going to argue for the Aerospace
business that there needs to be the
development of a balance of government
governance and policy so this is some
combination both what the US government
does other governments do the UN does um
what the commercial companies agree to
uh I'm talking about the spacex's and
the blue origins of the world uh there
needs to be a balance of governs polic
but also the in Freedom uh in space is
is essential because we need to have
Innovation there uh and all that must be
evolved by both education and actions I
mean it's important that everybody
understand what needs to be done
there uh space domain and space
technology has changed you know some of
the Technologies I showed you at least
in words will will lead to dramatic
changes in the space Enterprise I mean
think of all that you can actually do
with serious nuclear propulsion I think
all you can do with serious uh inspace
servicing and repairing and
repositioning and assembly and
Manufacturing uh think of all you can
actually do with with uh laser
Communications up there so things are
changing rapidly uh and our governance
and policy has to actually keep up with
that actually I would say right now
they're changing faster than governance
and policy keeping up with that uh which
is why you see people just putting stuff
up there and seeing what actually
happens and and you know space research
which is one of the things we do here uh
within Academia with industry and
government entities remain is vital in
informing the space policy uh that
that's why I showed you initially you
know what these students here are are
concerned about when they look at all
that's happening in space they're
concerned about issues of of both the
the rapid spread of Technology but also
sustainability so uh it's it's important
that we look seriously at those issues
um so that we have an optimistic
future I think that's my last slide yeah
okay so with that let me
[Applause]
stop and's see where we got any
questions uh we we will take a few
questions from the audience we don't
have a Kion Hall in this track so
if you have any question please raise
your hand I will pass along the
mic oh there's a question over
there thanks Dan Ron Spangler from
corporate relations we know that Artemis
3 relies on the Starship human Landing
system to land people on the moon 2026
whenever all of the things it has to do
have been more or less demonstrated
except the large scale transfer very
quickly of massive amounts of cryogenic
liquid on orbit what's your view on that
is it realistic oh that's a good
question I have a whole set of views
about
timus
um so I'm not entirely sanguin that
everything's going to happen by 2026
first of all right okay uh secondly you
know you're right the so what's the
experience with transferring propellants
in
space uh that's been propelled and
transferred on the station I believe
there was there was a experiment called
orbital Express that took two robotic
vehicles and transfer propellants right
but but the answer is it's not very
much and we're talking about a lot of
propellant that has to be TR it's
actually worse than that uh because one
of the issues with that is cryogenic
boil off so if you know there's a whole
they have to do a whole set of these
missions and if they get delayed then
what will happen is they'll be losing
the cryogens faster than they're putting
stuff on there and then they will not
have enough fuel to get there so uh it
what can you say it's a high-risk
Venture right but of course SpaceX is
demonstrated highrisk Ventures as well
right so
um but that's the reason why I'm less
sanguine that we're going to do
something by
2026 you know to get actually back to
the Moon I mean now there are other
issues with timus right the NASA uh
Inspector General has pointed out the
basically if you want to run an
efficient rocket service and launching
once a year is not the way you do it you
you do it by launching a lot you do it
about the do way the space ex so that
that's another issue with space loan uh
LS you know don't get me
started
yeah follow what you just said um in the
commercial space particularly for
communications um starling's cleaning
up uh there's the real possibility that
from a commercial perspective the GEOS
have no Market left over the medium term
just as a hypothetic
what do you expect the mix to look like
long run do the Leos just come to
completely dominate because their launch
cost costs per gigabit per second
ability to reposition orbits gives them
a multifaceted commercial
Advantage uh actually I I do think
that's quite possible
um yeah I mean once you have a a
robust um internet um connection ction
you know
Leo uh I mean you can pass lots of
things through it you can replace Direct
TV for example right uh you can replace
the geom so the answer is sure no
actually I do I think that's quite
possible now now having said that I I
myself if if you actually look at how
many companies have said they're going
to do you know internet in the sky right
certainly SpaceX has right now got the
um
you know put most of the satellites out
but you know Kyper is starting to launch
those satellites W Weare satellites
there's actually another set of
companies that say they're going to do
that um I I personally don't I'm not
sure I believe that that I think the
total is actually six that six companies
are going to survive doing that I mean
some of them are going to not survive
right um I mean what of course SpaceX
and Kyo have the advantage of being
backed by billionaires right
right so so the answer is I I actually
agree with you that I think geoc coms
um will be hard to compete with those
but I just don't think that you're going
to see all of the Leo based systems
survive in
the yes that's my m just be clear it's
my personal opinion right
okay uh we will take one more uh
question from the audience any
question okay thank you Professor okay