okay let's uh let's get started right on
time both to set a good precedent and
there's quite a bit uh to do today um I
will put that back down for one second
so that those who just got in can see
the agenda for today
um uh first first two things will just
be a minute or two and then we'll spend
the rest of the time on um you know what
everybody thinks is the coolest thing uh
in the world these days in computation
artificial intelligence and machine
learning um but this is not a class in
that uh we'll spend most of our time on
uh feature extraction the necessary evil
before uh doing great things with
artificial intelligence and machine
learning when you're dealing with data
that's not already uh numbers uh I want
to do a really quick uh discussion on um
something on problem set 78 uh I'm still
listening to the composition some of
them are really really cool uh just
they're all they're all a great that
I've heard so far but uh some really
went into it um but there was one um
thing that um among people who attempted
every problem um ended up being a
consistent eror what actually two things
uh one that a lot lot of people um
missed here was in um let's say you were
in C major because that'll make life
sort of easier I gave some chords that
were like
this and uh what do we call this in C
major what's the SC if Roman numeral
we're doing the Roman numeral exercise
for a second what's uh what's scale
degree two good and what is the the
quality of the chord di diminish great
um so you don't have your problem Set uh
back for two reasons one the a couple
more songs I'm listening to and also so
how would we write two
diminished Circle yeah and then I
noticed that my thing said or if it's um
or if it's seven
diminished write this and I did not say
um in general if it's diminished write
this so I think that some people seem to
write specific code for um making sure
that only happened on seven but two
diminished happens quite often um how
does it happen in C major you're
borrowing from C minor for a little
bit so these borrowed
chords either flat and natural and then
you end up with that
DF a flat chord so that's where that
comes in but I want to make sure I'm
going to go back because there was an
ambiguity in the instructions I want to
make sure that everybody gets um the
little point back who made that who
didn't put that in okay so that was one
of the two systematic uh issues and that
came from an ambiguity for me here is
the other one that came up a lot that um
I want to sort of address um oh yeah so
so we just went from C major
and we
played that two diminished
sound then what about this
[Music]
sound anyone identify that chord by
ear just the what's that augmented
great good I was
in doing that borrowing from minor thing
and I left my blue pen which probably
shows up better um I was borrowing from
minor and I started on the third scale
degree and so this was not part of your
Roman numeral thing but it came on the
roots
question what is the root of that
chord no it could not ah we'll get to
that that's where where something
happens yep exactly it's great great
idea John E flat E flat now we'll get
we'll get to it in just a second what is
the
root of that
chord g
g and let's see if I can make one um
we'll go back to our E flat
what is the root of that
one C flat C flat now why is it and so
just just so we all have it in our ears
again
um three chords three exact same sound
but Roots the concept of root is
something that comes from a a triotic um
sort of a spelling enabled thing so
where do we find the root we talked
about the algorithm last time what do we
want to find a bunch of
stacked thirds good I heard it so
stacked thirds so here we have a third
followed by a third or a third and a
fifth depending on how you're counting
but here what's this
interval diminished diminished fourth
yeah a fourth of some sort so we have to
move it up the
octave in order to get our stacked
thir and here um we can move them both
up an
octave in order to get our stack thirds
so the diminished uh the augmented Triad
is the one of the places where the um
the concept of root has everything to do
with spelling there's one other very
common chord where the concept of root
has everything to do with
Spelling saw a big smile uh it's a
Triad diminish seven diminish seventh
chord yeah um here I'll just keep it in
the light assuming that's good so yeah
diminish seventh chord let's say we're
in c minor we're going
to start one
B what somebody shout out the next note
d
d f and
then a flat yeah so seven do with a root
on B but we can change this to move it
up an octave and flip the
enharmonic and suddenly we have third
third
third and our root
becomes D we got a lot more to get
through today so I will leave it to um
attest to prove to yourself that we can
keep doing this somehow and get all uh
every one of the four notes as a um as a
a diminished uh as having its own that
note as a root so each of the chord
factors depending on how you spell and
that's one of the reasons by the way
this gets away from the computational
side but maybe a cool computational
compositional tool one of the reasons
why a diminished seventh chord is often
a very useful way to modulate to remote
keys because you just sort of start
emphasizing a different note as your
root
okay any questions on this or on other
things well eager to get to feature
extraction on this there should be um
there should be a a notebook that says
um under today um 2023 AI template
lank that one is it it's there good good
good so feel free to download that and
put that where you are and um
and run it it will install uh if your
hard drive is almost completely full it
will install um a a learning tool kit
called orange which also in installs
another machine learning tool kit called
s kit learn and I think they might be a
little bit big might be whatever so uh
make sure to run all um first and that
will uh get you in a pretty decent uh
shape I'm going to get started on what
we're talking about today is um
something called feature extraction and
so feature extraction is a conversion of
elements in this case musical elements
into single numbers or lists arrays
vectors tensors whatever you want to
call them of
numbers it is the most boring thing I
will teach in the class and please don't
correct me if you're like you there's
plenty of other boring things you've
done but no it's it's really one of the
most boring things in the world and um
here's a reason to hate it um it really
sucks the lifeblood out of Music
everything that you love about music is
going to be converted into a few numbers
uh it is Tes the life off it is the
zombie of Music World Adam's very
excited yes Zombie Invasion uh but
there's a lot of amazing things we know
happening in artificial intelligence
machine learning deep learning
algorithms all these things and as as
far as I know they all have one thing in
common and that is they work on
collection big collections of
numbers um you know there's there's some
ways that you can work with um you know
images that effectively are kind of like
two or multi-dimensional arrays of
numbers but basically they're all going
to be numbers so you know when I when I
put some music notation on the
board we're not going to be able to work
with that even an image of it even a
JPEG unless we convert it to pixels and
convert it to numbers when you hear a
sound something like that you're going
to have to convert that into numbers in
some
ways so we're going to be just working
on converting things to numbers so uh
it's pretty simple and um
but how to do it and what to extract and
how to make your extractions is sort of
the the Deep art that takes a while now
um I I'll get to a little bit later um
some of the things that people are doing
today where feature extraction is less
or careful feature extraction is less
important and I'll tell you what those
things tend to have in common and that
is their um they work on much bigger
data sets than um than what we have so
we're g to get started on um this yep
that's my template here and we're going
to start with uh why not we always start
with our favorite Bach caral what's the
number 66.6
66.6 conjure up the bwv
66.6 I'm going to show it get it back
okay great oh feel um so we're going to
do some manual feature extraction first
we're going to convert this into numbers
I'm going to extract two things from
this number of parts and initial number
of beats per measure so let's just do
our super you don't have to type this if
you want num Parts equals 4 time
signature numerator equals 4 there I
have done manual feature extraction and
describing the piece as two numbers um
they seem to look like four four but I
didn't ever extract the denominator that
just happens to be coincidence they're
both four so I don't know if we'd even
call this feature extraction but you can
see it's it's pretty you know we were
not talking about very very much here so
I'm going to um Define uh a an automatic
feature extractor so we call it extract
meter and extract meter you can save
time by not putting these annotations it
takes in some sort of a stream I'm
calling it score even though um it's not
and returns two integers what do you
think the two inte are going to
be if you're extracting the
meter numerator and denominator great
super so we can say all the meters in
the piece equals the score meter time
signature re
curse and um the first one we'll just
get the first one first meter all
meters
zero and we'll return first
numerator and first meters denominator I
know I don't need the parenthesis but I
just kind of got used to that
it's all let
people get caught up um now by the way
uh how many time signatures does this
little Corral have are we going Overkill
by getting the first
one want to take a guess you all know it
by now
one actually has four the way music 21
counts 1 2 3 they're all the same but
this is an error I make quite a bit
often that each of the parts has its own
time signature so this is uh something
to be careful on and now we'll get to
the first sort of ethical dilemma of um
of feature extraction and machine
learning of which there will be many um
and quite a number today uh what happens
if a score doesn't have any time
signatures do we want this will this
crash first off
and if you think it will crash tell me
what the error that's probably going to
be
returned out list index out of range or
index error yep that we're trying to get
zero so we can say um something
like if not all meters now so here's the
ethical dilemma I'm going to return 0
comma 0 as a special value that's also
in integer uh to of two integers that
says I have no time signature because
you know I'm I'm raised as a medieval
musicologist so I have Gregorian chant
lying around and other meterless time um
pieces but um the other reason is that
we sometimes in case of an error or an
outof bound value we return some sort of
we call of Sentinel some kind of special
meaning number that says you know some
sort of an error happened
why because you're going to someday have
a gigantic data set maybe you're going
to be doing this up in the cloud
somewhere or something and you're going
to have
um uh you're going to be letting it run
overnight consuming a huge amount of
processor money and eventually there's
going to be some bad data in there
that's going to crash your
system and you want to be like okay I
just let this run for 47 hours and uh
now I have to start all over again
because of course I didn't save
intermediary values because you know I'm
a theoretical person not a practical
programmer but um always say write write
to dis every once in a while um
but so so this type of thing helps to
save you from a little bit of bad data
what it also does though is it can
swallow up systematic errors in your
thought you know what I'm saying that
that you didn't realize that um the one
that I always get is I'm looking at the
pitch of everything in the piece I pitch
of everything in there and then I forget
that these structures called chords
exist which don't just have a pitch they
have multiple and so I could end up
silently throwing out all of my data
about chords rather than realizing I
have a mental model problem in there and
this is some of the things that um that
can lead to uh AI that doesn't include
all of us that programmers forget that
women exist or that nonwhite people
exist and therefore oh that's data
that's out of bounds so you know we'll
we'll go with a default response rather
than learning um you know how to deal
with uh facial recognition on things
like that so here it's not such a big I
don't think that we're um you know that
we're going to have a problem with um
systematically discriminating against
Gregorian chant but um but it's these
kinds of issues that lead to so many of
the other uh ethical issues um in in
artificial
intelligence okay with that aside we've
all caught up let's see did I somebody
and everybody just save me time when I
type something wrong um check it but
let's see if that
works extract meter Bo we have our
first um our first uh automatic feature
extractor is this topic so far as boring
as I
promised no okay somebody likes it yeah
I I it's it's pretty good but let's
let's go with something else and we're
going to start with another ethical
dilemma we're going to be working with
Ryan's Mammoth collection and I think um
if you type blooming you should get
something that's not an error do you
because you've already if you've run
everything you've already run Corpus
parse blooming
Meadows
jig and let's see
that so apologies we didn't get to The
Jig um composition yet I do plan to pick
that up next week but I figure that
there's some other things that people
need for their final projects more
importantly than uh working with that um
so you all see something like
this but we're going to be back on jigs
again today for a bit now Ryan's Mammoth
collection is a little bit of an ethical
dilemma and I'm trying to replace it it
is a collection of a think something
like uh 1, 79 fiddle Tunes from the 19th
century um that has a bunch of jigs horn
pipes uh things that if you take uh Joe
Mor's um C shanties and um English folk
music class and all those things you you
can learn more about them um it also is
a large collection of musical
experiences of 19th century
African-Americans that has been um sort
of parody
and or um appropriated into white
minstral shows so I've tried to remove
um things that are um
offensive on First Sight from The
Collection titles and things like that
but um but the deeper history a lot of
these songs has to do with a lot of
appropriation so um I'm hoping to be
able to get a collection to replace it
at some point because um you know it's
not exactly everything I want to do with
it but anyhow so we have for um for
going through we have the one jig
blooming Meadows jig and um I gave you
just a contrast um uh a real
reel um and you should already have the
Reel I think uh already loaded so you
don't need to type this it's called the
seventh regiment
reel and hopefully I got
that and it looks a little a little bit
different so what we're going to do
today is try to build a system that can
tell the difference between a jig and a
reel or jig and uh we'll defit it into
the remaining 52 minutes between a jig
and a not jig the whole all of music is
divided into Jigs and not jigs it's
great um okay so we um we'll be looking
how would you how would you define the
difference you can look down at your own
so I don't have to keep scrolling back
and forth um just if if you're somebody
who didn't know hadn't encountered a
real or a jig before what is the um what
would you say is an obvious
difference Matthew you uh 24 versus 68
24 versus 68 good another
obvious one I think what's that is the S
one the time signature the same same one
time signature good
yeah seems more syn which one seems more
synr The Jig The Jig a little bit more
syncopated especially um things there's
always things like this that are not
technically rhythmically syncopated but
kind of feel a little bit
um good anything else
yeah what's that 16 16th versus 8th
notes thank you I'm going to put that in
I'm also going to disable my uh my what
do you call it my
notifications supposed to
happen automatically okay yeah 16th
versus e8th notes we're actually going
to uh possibly use that as as something
so we're going to try to um have a
system that can do the difference you
should have if you type Ryan uh you
should be you should be getting
something I'm going to really quickly um
just cut and paste what I did to get to
Ryan and explain it I first created a
sign called Ryan M where I find
everything in Ryan's Mammoth collection
and then what I've
done is here's another cut and paste
1059 I think yep is that I've gone
through everything in there and said
first off I only want to look at the
first 500 of them and then I'm looking
without parsing if the name name of the
file has jig in
it um if it doesn't have jig in it and
if you're over file 100 continue so I've
why did I do all this stuff just so that
I can get something that is
approximately 50/50 jig not Jake um so
we end up with about 200 U here I
can we end up with 212 pieces and I
happen to know that 59% of them are jigs
so uh that's pretty good these are all
what we call uh metadata entries so they
haven't been parsed
yet okay great everybody with me there
great I'm going to Define um a helper
function that is how many ethical
dilemas are we doing today uh this one's
not ethical but this one's sort of a
research thing called is jig which um
which determines if something is a jig
by looking at the file name and um lower
casing it and seeing if the word jig is
in that um I've done this with uh Rags
before uh rag time a really great um
piano genre most Scott Joplin the most
famous person and a lot of Rags have um
rag in the title Maple Leaf Rag and so
on but then there's like the entertain
you know that which doesn't have the
word rag in the title so we're
possibly having what we call a bad
ground truth the ground truth is the
definition that is correct beforehand
and so is this song a jig is this not a
jig this is probably not the greatest
ground truth there the other thing that
will come up a lot is that there is a
some pieces that will be very hard to
tell if they are and two different
intelligent people could disagree on
something that's a jig this comes up a
lot in genre classification where people
can't really decide is this country or
is this rock is this uh Funk is this hip
hop is this romantic is this classical
um so you know somebody once told me um
when they realized I came from a music
history training musicology that they
said the worst part about musicologists
getting into this field is that they
give us really crappy ground truths you
know you all won't say what the right
answer is and that's I hope an ambiguity
we like as humans but anyhow so we'll
we'll have our is jig let's um we'll
actually see um is jig blooming I think
that was the one that is jig and what
was the other one uh
real okay
so so with our garbage in garbage out
terrible ground truth um we seems to be
working okay and I happen to know 127 of
the things in there jig so let's get our
second feature extractor this one's
going to be pretty easy we'll just get
the number of sharps in the piece uh we
started working on jigs in G so we
happen to know that there are a whole
bunch of them so maybe we'll do this and
here we can just do again a try return
the
scores key key
signature the number of
Sharps uh if it's two Flats what's it
going to
return negative -2 yep great so and if
there's no key signature um this one's
actually not a terrible assumption right
something without a key signature
probably has a key signature of no
sharps or flat
I no maybe maybe we should in this case
analyze the key and uh do something like
that but good enough for a little bit so
let's see um the
blooming hopefully this will return one
oops oh I know what I did this is why
you should never do something like this
uh except index error we
said and we didn't get an index error
what did we get we got a attribute error
yep there is no Sharps cuz I forgot to
say that we want the first key
signatures Sharps you can also do the do
zero or bracket zero however you'd like
that and so let me try the get Sharps
again getting one and what's the answer
for
Bach three good you can either do that
by hand or make sure thing work great
and let's we'll Define one more feature
extractor so that we can um
oops we're actually making good time
this uh we'll do eighth fraction uh
based on based on the observation that
there's uh more eighth notes in some in
one piece than the other so we'll take
in a stream. score and this time we'll
return a float so usually you can um
return an INT which we call a continuous
a a discrete VAR answer or a float which
is continuous variable so let's just do
this get the number of notes in the
piece actually you do this you give me
go ahead and try try coding this for a
little bit because we are a couple
minutes ahead of time how do we get
the returns the fra you I need to put
this Returns the fraction of notes in a
score that are eighth
notes okay you can keep doing yours if
you're stuck I'm going to give what I to
sign
like not the most efficient use of
iterators I've done two
I'm uh where am I missing it it's
somewhere in eths right
where eight yep eight thank you
appreciate that
and go ahead and run your num a on
blooming on real and unb and use your
spidey sense to figure out if the if
your numbers are um pretty meaningful if
there's anything I can I can get from
this class to just use in all of your
programming things is always um use your
intuition to see if something like that
something
is uh working right woo wow look at
that the real is incredibly low
oops uh now I have too many eighth
fraction I should have done it eth's
fraction but whatever
I'm that actually feels too low for that
reel only 8% but I guess there's a lot
of 16th
okay give me a snap if you're ready to
move on okay hearing some snaps not all
we'll give another 10 seconds or
so so so far we have we have the first
one that seems you know really to give
at least in this one piece a big
distinction among the three um
types oops
okay now I'm going to we uh wade into
something that people don't um always
say is this a feature extractor because
it returns a number or something or is
when you put them all together is that
the feature extractor I'm not sure but
I'll use this term so the feature
extractor is going to run all of our
different little feature extractors and
in this case I'm going to say it's going
to return a tuple of I'll tell you what
these are in a bit but here I'll write
this out here a string two inss a float
and int and an
INT what are these going to
be they're going to be the file name
which is pure metadata just so we can
look at things later they're going to be
the numerator and the
denominator of the um of the piece using
our function we wrote extract me met
they going to be what's the only thing
we've written that has a returns a float
as the answer what's that eth yeah eth
fraction eth proportion whatever we're
going to call it um the number of
Sharps and then that last one we'll get
to that's going to be the ground truth
um and doing too much Json I stopped
doing trailing commas okay so the file
name um you get this from a scores
metadata object which we haven't really
talked about it's file
path split I'm just going to get the
last bit so I'm not showing my entire um
directory R Tree to everything so I'll
just get the last thing after the slash
those of you who know Python's path
Library you can probably do better
um the numerator and the
denominator will
extract meter from the
score the eths we'll say is the
eighth fraction of the
score Sharp's feature is get Sharps you
can call them whatever you'd like
and then the ground
truth is it a jig or is it
not but it has to be a number so we'll
say integer of is
jig you could also say um if you like
this python one if if jig else zero
that's sometimes uh sometimes explicits
a little bit nicer to see what that's
going to be and then we want to return
all that file name numerator
denominator eth I should do quarters I
can spell quarter feature and ground
truth I'll let everybody get caught up
while I debug my own system whoa some
fast typists in this class feature
extractor on Bach let me just see
feature extractor on uh
blooming
okay ABC file extension yep yeah a lot
of these are all written as ABC files do
we we didn't really cover no we didn't
cover ABC files because they're um
they're tiny bit more complex than the
easiest to encode handwritten things but
not um not complex enough for uh as like
music XML or
something okay so blooming Metals jig
it's in 68 77% of its uh notes are
eighth notes it's in one sharp and that
last one indicates what
again yep so the one indicates jig right
great Okay so
um what I'm going to do right now is I'm
just going to run this for a second uh
so how would I get everything so we can
do
metadata I'm just doing this so we can
kind of see how we do this in the Ryan
thing piece equals metadata entry. parse
and then we'll print the feature
extractor on the
piece and you can kind of see
yep uh because of the way I did it uh
you'll see that at first there's not too
many Jigs and then later on there's
jigs okay
um now if you um scroll back up to the
top of yours sorry I'm going to have to
get my blank template for a second oops
that's way smaller um there should be uh
on the top of your template if you
downloaded it something called WR
Ryan and um you just need to change your
path to someplace that you're going to
be able to remember it so change that
unless you have a unless you've created
a cprit user because it makes it easier
for you to cut and paste my code um
probably want to change that and then
you can run run this while I explain a
little bit what it
is um okay is Right Ryan working for
people when you get that
okay
great so I'm going
to have my own version
here the right in command
W you don't have to do any of this it'll
be kind of fun because then you'll have
right
underscore
Ryan and
sorry okay I've seen more people waiting
than typing for a little bit so I'll
just s of explain what we do U some of
these things if you work with files you
probably know them pretty well uh this
is really not necessarily the best way
to do this but I'm going to open two
files one of them is the file that we're
going to use to train um our classifier
the thing that is going to try to learn
if something is a jig or not the other
one is the file we're going to do to try
to test whether it can do it um no or
not we're going to hope that um that we
don't put the same data into both so
we're going to try to put some data in
the testing somay in the training
there's a number of different ways you
can do this type of work um you put 90%
in the testing in the training and 10%
in the testing SI you put 50/50 which is
what we're going to do uh some of it has
to do with how much data you have
um so what I'm going to do it maybe
it'll be easier to see I'm just going to
separate. tab means everything's going
to be separated by tabs so I'm going to
first put a header line that says the
name of the columns these are just for
us to read so we have a file name
numerator denominator a sharp and is jig
and so we're going to write that to the
top of it because a lot of the um
classifiers that work on Tab data expect
this to be the first line now we're
going to hope that when running this
system that uh it doesn't Peak at the
file name and we'll see because that
since obviously file name would give it
away um and then so the descriptions
what kind of data is this the file names
a string then we have discret as we said
for an integer discret continuous
discret discret so we'll write that out
again to each of the different um things
the the two files and then we have most
a third line which is mostly blank for
all these things and the first one just
says metadata um that is to say don't
Peak at the file name do not use the
file name to try to classify this then
normal information and then the class
the thing that we're trying to figure
out and we really really hope that um
the artificial intelligence uh thing
does not uh Peak at the class when it's
trying to look you can really really
quickly create an incredible AI thing if
you would allow it to peek and so we'll
put that out so that's just all headers
and that's why I didn't want to spend
too much time writing it then what are
we going to do same thing they were
saying before we're just going to get
each piece into there and I've done
enumerate for a reason so I can keep
track of what the piece number is um and
then we can extract the piece uh all the
features from it and then we'll just
write them out um in this case we're
going to write them as a string because
we can only write strings out to a text
file um write each of the features out
tab separated actually we'll get get
ready to write it we'll just put it into
a string and then um every other one
we're going to write to training and
test training and test probably another
way to do it would be to flip a coin
each time and use a random number so you
can see uh if things are going there I'm
not an expert on on this type of work
but um that's how that works I don't
think
I yeah I don't think I'm going to run it
now because I should have been running
it during this time uh you know what I'm
just going to put train
data X and Test data X so that while
it's running I have access to um
to our baked one so I can actually we
can look at it uh you know magic feature
so we switch out of python and immediate
and um look at the Shell for a
second train data wherever you put your
thing and I can
see that I've written out it's kind of
weird that the tabs don't show up you
would love to have something that would
automatically put it out but we have the
file name all our headers description of
the data the metadata here and then um
yeah we have our um all of our
information written out so that's pretty
good does this finish oh that did finish
great um
okay so now we've done our feature
extraction the feature extraction part
of the lecture is done for a little bit
um this is a small number of
features but I think that they're going
to end up being halfway decent features
um because we thought about them a bit
and when the data is small you want to
think more about your features so uh you
installed something called Orange 3 but
it's a little bit weird uh it comes as
capital orange I just I don't know why I
don't like things Capital so I always
import orange as lowercase
orange great um we're going to load our
training data and our test data so first
training data
orange.
dat. you can a lot of these things are
they're going to be very similar in a in
a super modern um uh artificial
intelligence uh sort of framework like
uh P torch or um or tensor flow or
something like this similar idea you
want to load data in as a table um if
it's too big to load on your all at once
then you know there's special techniques
and stuff like that but we'll load the
training data in and now when we look at
it it just looks a little bit
nicer um actually if I do where's our
first I
know 45 to 50 does that work yeah okay
so that might be a little bit better
because we can see we have our um our
features here 2 4 12%
and three Sharps and this one happens to
be a jig so there um and so the
afterward is what the what the class is
great and we'll do the exact same thing
with the test data and we'll call it
variable test data so I'm just going to
copy and paste and hopefully the test
data looks a lot like the training
data oh yeah yeah it looks a lot like
the the training data if you don't
change the file path see how well it is
okay um so now we're going to create
some uh we call Learners classifiers
things that can um classify the data
here's the the first one and I think in
some ways the most important classifier
that you'll ever use and that is when
did I switch into camel case okay I
guess I'm in camel case now something
called called orange.
classification. majority
learner and um what a majority learner
is is it's kind of the control or the
placebo of your system to make sure that
you don't get too excited by how good
your system is working uh what it does
is it looks at the training data which
has 100 what maybe the training data uh
has I don't know let's say it has 51
Jigs and 49 non Jigs and it
says I will always say that any piece
that's ever shown to me is a jig because
then I will get over 50% right or I will
get the highest answer of doing anything
so if you are not beating your majority
learner you um then you're not doing any
classifications so the majority
classifier hope y'all who have taken a
machine learning class do you you get
taught this or no yeah okay good good
some people this will be totally um old
story and not so we're going to the
majority learner is just a sort of a
generic thing and now we have a
classifier which is one trained on our
data so we're going to say that this the
majority classifier will now know how to
work with this particular
data um and then we'll use another one
called K nearest neighbors this is this
was um I don't know maybe 20 years ago
the state-of-the-art of of of um machine
learning it's a little bit out of date
now but it does work pretty well on
small data sets and few classifiers so
not not nothing that is going to get you
uh super excited at a top um Tech firm
but um you know it still has still has
its uses so we're going to do the same
exact same thing I just put everything
that I put for majority learner and then
put it as KN andn neighbors look at the
K which might be four might be three
might be five the nearest Neighbors in a
multi-dimensional vector space to your
one piece and try to learn where um
where in the space it
goes snap if you're caught
snap if you're not now if you need a sec
okay
good great so I'm just going to keep
track of how many correct the majority
gets in a variable called M correct and
how many correct the um K nearest
neighbor gets in a variable called K
andn correct and then total equals the
length of the test data not the training
data so now we're going to be working on
this
and should have something like this by
the way um I actually I lost like half
an hour in in rep preparing this lecture
on like wait why do I keep getting over
100% always make sure uh to recar out
your number correct as you recode or
something or make sure to do it within
your Loop okay
so good so we have 106 uh things that
we're going to be able to do now now is
for our Loop
um so we'll just do an enumeration of
each row in the test data so for I comma
test Row in enumerate test
data okay and then the majority learner
is going to take a guess for each one so
majority's guest is going to be the
majority classifier of the test
row which it's always going to guess the
same thing I guess in this case it's
always going to guess jig because
there's like four more jigs than there
are non- Jigs and then our classifier
our K nearest neighbor classifier will
also take a guess can
classifier I know some somebody's
probably saying guess is not the right
word but um you know it kind of works
and then we'll get the
real is the test rows get class so as
you said the class is either one or zero
something like that
and we can do print out something but um
print how about this we'll just say m
guess Cann
guess and uh
real so I'll I'll start this running for
for a second but we notice we haven't
put in anything on whether they got it
right or not but we can just look at
that oh one of them guesses
um so you can see that the majority one
for every single piece just puts
out yep it's always a jig always a jig
always a
jig Ker's
neighbor says I don't think this is jig
and here's the correct answer not a jig
not a jig not a jig and here K nearest
neighbor is learning that o this one
looks like a jig
so we'll I'll just modify this a tiny
bit and say if majority guests equals
real then K then majority correct add
one if KNN guess equals
real KNN
correct equals one you'll probably um
when you're trying to figure out how to
do things you'll use more classifiers
there's a lot more and so probably want
to do this you know in some sort of a
loop but
great
good so now we'll we'll see how we did
how did majority do
um here I'll do this
majority M correct I always like making
things look nice for humans
why am I anal enough to start already
putting in um some sort of a rounding
thing to look because I I do feel like
when you see all those significant all
those digits it's really really hard to
figure out um how important the
difference is so the majority uh this is
what I happen to know that there's 59%
of them are Jigs and so the majority
learner got 59% of them right and then
we'll do the same thing for
KNN here I can I can cut and paste right
we all know how to do that what are we
looking
up
great
um and we want to make sure that that's
K&N
correct so our classifiers get getting
about
87% correct at this just with these few
little things now this is always EXC the
exciting moment and then the hard part
is almost always getting it from 87 to
95 and the next harder part is getting
from 95 to 97 and then going up and up
and up from
there um so that's sort of the
theoretical part aside I'm going to um
really quickly just um go through some
things that music 21 has so this is you
know
uh uh
um that that just make some of this a
little bit
easier um so there's I know it's already
imported since I imported star but
there's something called
features and what we can do is set
equals a features data set class label
equals is jig
and then we'll do the same thing with
the test
set so far it's basically the same type
of
thing and then I believe you have if you
type FES you should have something there
I think I put pasted this this is
features these are built-in feature
extractor and each one of them has an ID
and no I don't have these memorized but
something about um
I can't remember what these are M2 you
know what I'm just going to cut and
paste because you already have this and
put it
here fears fears yes that my my hidden
uh thank you very much appreciating that
and think that should
work and so these are some features that
have already been put in um so one of
them I don't know what's the range of
the piece how far is it from the lowest
note to the highest note a lot of these
come uh they're adapted from a really
really cool toolkit called J symbolic
part of jmir by uh Corey McKay uh up in
Canada and um just ported them over
because they're they're kind of neat
then some of them are ones that um that
I've written because I kind of think
that they're a little valuable or
somebody and the music 21 team has
written so here we have a lot more
features here and what we can do is we
have our two data sets so we'll say the
training set add feature
extractors and add all those features
extractors and then same thing for the
test
set and this as I said you don't need to
be typing too much because I'm just
going to go pretty fast and what we'll
do is um I'm just going
to cut and paste this because all we're
doing is dividing things up into either
the test or the training set depending
on if it's even or odd and so we'll just
add the data on
here with some nice little features that
and this will just generate all the
headers for you oops what did I
do testing set is what I called it
before sorry training and testing that
makes
sense no did I do something wrong oh I
have to change it up here there we go
starting all over hopefully I don't have
any numb cracks great and that's just
doing all the um feature extraction kind
of getting them in that's going to take
a little bit of time so we're going to
switch like they do in the cooking shows
to the already baked version where it's
all
done okay um
oops here we
go where do we where' we
go is it yep so the next couple things
that you do you want to process all your
dating set training set and write it out
just like before process it and write it
out why is it taking so much longer
because we gave it a whole bunch of
features and some of them take a long
time to do like ones that have to do
with um variability between parts and um
parallel fifths finding if it's a
multi-part thing and so
on but then the next row ends up being
the exact same type of thing we have a
majority learner we're going to still
use the KNN learner and um then try to
see how well it did
and we keep looking and again the
majority learner is still 59% you hope
that that doesn't change and now using
all of these extra features we've gotten
our number from 87% all the way up to
61% so um sometimes just throwing more
feature extractors at the problem is
just going to have you wait longer at
the computer um sometimes sometimes
thinking really carefully about what you
already think the data might look like
is a pretty good thing and especially if
you're working with a small data set
where it's not going to be able to do
the kinds of deep um neural network
learning have to keep going through
enough to really build a model of the
the set as um some people say you know
that uh look the computers the neural
networks are getting getting better and
better and um we just need to throw more
data at it but imagine if you wanted to
have a program that was uh automatically
you know reading handwriting and you
gave the program um all these papers of
handwriting and you just gave them an
audio file of how it drops how it sounds
when it drops and try to do it you're
giving it kind of the wrong data to
learn on and so a lot of the extractors
now unless you're giv writing your own
unless you're using really musically
sensitive ones you're you can save the
computer a lot of time by trying to
trying to already say you know hey let's
process this as a symbols ahead of time
or something like that um a lot of the
by the way state-ofthe-art of symbolic
um music machine learning things are uh
you all remember the piano
rooll you know where we put things like
this to show length and stuff like that
yeah well it's converting the entire
musical score to a piano roll saving
that as an image and then using image
classifiers and image uh generators to
generate pieces that look like the piano
rolls and then translating them back so
I think I'm hoping that over the next
decade or so we we can do better and do
some things that uh help help these
neural Nets and classifiers uh work with
data that's a little bit closer to uh
the original
numbers okay um I have time for just a
little little fun thing with my favorite
uh low um feature uh extraction thing so
let me just show a couple little things
okay um
yeah the importance of first off the
importance of thinking about data sets
and ground truths um this is you know I
think one of the first pieces that
showed uh deep learning the the kind of
uh for people in the no moment uh like
chat GPT has been in the last year uh
happened I think it was about 10 years
ago when um Alpha zero and Alpha go
suddenly became the world's greatest go
and chess players um and so a lot of
people think you this was with
generalized knowledge no rules being
taught except for legal move or not um
but one of the things to think about um
the difference between a lot of the the
things that they were being trained on
and what you have is that Alpha zero the
chess plane computer you know played
what was it 700,000 games or million
games or something like that and at the
end of every single game it played it
got perfect feedback on how how it did
you won you lost you tied you won you
lost you tied a lot of the things that
we're interested in doing with music
like music recommendation or you know uh
things like this you predicting what's
the next great hit first off we can't we
don't have that correct data Maybe you
know what's the Billboard Chart or
something like that but for how good was
this piece because it's going to be
different every time it's going to take
us 3 minutes to listen to if it's
computer generating song and then we're
going to give it feedack back that we
might feel differently about that piece
tomorrow so we don't give perfect
feedback and it takes a long time so
this is why one of the reasons I like um
working with uh some of the older things
okay we'll go back great um I don't
think I've I presented this no I
presented another place so this is what
we'll end for the last 10 minutes and
talking about um some of the interesting
things that come out with features um so
how would you distinguish Coral music
from Bach from
monver so just we we're doing a lot of
Bach in this class but we'll get a
little bit more into ear here is sign
Bach so this is
[Music]
Bach and so then we'll switch to one of
the other other great composers about
100 and 100 years before Bach claudo Mon
and so some of you this might be the
first time you'll hear him
one second to the bo again so we can get
back
great what's something you you heard
different between the two of
them Som with more of minor Keys okay
somber more minor Keys we can do a key
detection
Jonathan I mean b had sounded like there
were like more people see but it's hard
uhuh yeah but it could be it could be
more people Fuller than good
yeah is more together where like lot
of do BU more together homophonic maybe
mon Verity doing their own thing good
one last one else
want okay that's a pretty good place to
start so
I threw um everything in all the kitchen
sink of classifier of feature extractors
and got to see what a particular um
algorithm did that um that uh that
seemed to work pretty pretty well and
the first um here's a little quiz it's
one of the few quizzes that uh
Elementary School students do better
than adults at so let's see if we can
figure this out 7802 is three
1065 is two okay if you've seen it
before then don't answer it 998 is
four and one 1773 is
zero if you're new to
this one two three three circles
one Circle two circles one two 3 four
circles and no circles so I put that up
to say that some days the computer is
going to be looking at things that are
really really far um out um in trying to
figure out things so there's all these
things that we could be looking at um
I'll bet that the proportion of
instruments that are electronic um isn't
going to help with Bach versus Mon
Verity but one of the things I like
about a particular uh class Pacifier
that is not close to the
state-of-the-art it is not or to the
getting the best results but this uh
tree learner can ex unlike being a black
box it can actually show what the path
so it's of a decision tree branching
tree uh it took to get there so here's
how it can say to begin if the note F
below Middle Sea is used more than 14%
of the time the pieces by Bach
otherwise if the top number in the time
signature is three or less It Is by
Bach
otherwise I love this one if the
distance between the highest note in the
soprano and the lowest note of the base
is less than two octaves and a minor 6th
then it's by boach and then there's
three more things we get to the final
one uh count the number of times each
note is used find the note that used the
most often and the note they used the
second most often if the second most
often used note is used less than 90 7%
as often as the most commonly used note
the piece is by
Bach otherwise it's by Mon and this
worked with 99%
accuracy what I loved about this is I
that this was the first decision to
distinguish and I was just baffled by it
until I realized well okay Bach has more
pieces in uh sharp Keys than Mont ver is
so okay that would make sense Mont ver
was most ly hovering around um you know
no sharps or flats or one flat assign
but then you know it's minor and there's
raised leaning tones and stuff like that
so why not well um the leading tone
tends to get raised in the melody which
tends to be in a higher
voice the middle area tenor will only
appear as FP if the key signature is
already F so it's a way of learning some
things like this and um this particular
one ended up being garbage in Gage out
that monity uh doesn't using modern time
signatures and so when we the people who
encoded this chose never to use two4
always put it into 44 two bar because
because there also weren't bar lines so
you could decide how long so this ended
up being that the computer learned not
the difference between Bach and monver
but the difference between box editor
modern editor and Mon's modern editor I
have lost the reference but I've been
told about an audio um an audio
classifier that tried to classify VI
genre and it was doing very very well
until it turns out that different genres
of music use different microphones on in
general and it was picking up the
difference between the microphone so if
you sing country music on a hip-hop
microphone it would classify as hip hop
so all these things we need to be really
careful about um what's going on with
potential for classification and so this
is where I kind of like this old school
um imagine this is s of a tree diagram
of things going left and right I guess
if you turn it sideways these kind of
old school feature um classifiers a
little bit just to check what's what
might be happening in the latest
blackbox
so you guys did a remarkable stamina you
got through the zombie of of music
eating feature extraction and um I hope
that some people will choose to um find
if you find this to be helpful in doing
something in your final project you now
have some of the tools to do it on uh
Friday we'll continue with searching and
similarity and we will be giving um the
first 15 minutes explaining what he's
doing at MIT he's a professor of
computer science and um what he's been
doing with music on his uh work so um
that'll be a start and then I'll
continue with some other things great
thanks