Good afternoon.
I'm Ernest Fraenkel, a Professor
in the Department of Biological
Engineering and Co-Director of
the interdisciplinary program
in Computational
and Systems Biology.
Any of you who've walked
around Kendall Square
over the last few
years will have
noticed that the landscape
is being transformed
by an influx of companies in the
life sciences and health care.
And that's no coincidence
because MIT is an engine
of innovation in those areas.
At MIT, the Life Sciences
and Health Sciences
span many departments--
obviously, biology, chemistry,
physics, and many of the
engineering departments--
my own, biological engineering,
chemical, civil, mechanical,
materials, and of
course, computer science.
And we live in an
amazing ecosystem
where we also have the Broad
Institute, the Whitehead,
the many hospitals around us,
and of course, many venture
capitalists.
And that's led to,
really, a profusion
of companies emerging from MIT.
You can see some of them
that have biological themes
on the slide above us.
And you've seen similar
slides earlier today.
And I think what strikes
me about these companies
is their diversity.
Everything from bionics, bionic
limbs, better diagnostics,
the platforms that accelerate
the delivery and discovery
of therapeutics.
So today, we have
the opportunity
to hear from two
leaders in developing
entrepreneurial companies
that are, really, while early,
still already having
an amazing impact.
And I'll ask them each to
introduce themselves and tell us
a little bit about
their company.
So let's start with you, Cullen.
All right.
Happy to be here.
Cullen Buie, I'm on the faculty
in Mechanical Engineering
and Biological Engineering.
The company that's spun out
of my lab is called Kytopen.
It's a company which is
developing a technology that
allows you to do
scalable gene delivery
into human cells for things
like CAR-T therapy and gene
therapies, ex-vivo gene therapy,
so therapies where they want
to take your cells, engineer
them, and then give them
back to you to serve as
a living therapeutic.
The beauty of the technology is
that it scales from the bench
to the clinic.
So a challenge in a
lot of these fields
is that the technologies
that you use for discovery
don't always scale
up to manufacturing,
but we have a technology
where the same thing that you
use at the bench can quickly
and easily scale up to what
you can use at the clinic.
So to put some
numbers to it, it can
do enough for a human
patient in about one minute.
So you could imagine easily
doing this for a large patient
population.
Fantastic.
Tasuku.
Hi, my name is Tasuku Kitada,
and I'm Co-Founder Head
of R&D at Strand Therapeutics.
Strand is a next-generation
messenger RNA therapeutics
company focused on
developing cancer drugs.
Our drugs are based
on messenger RNA.
We actually programmed the
mRNA using molecular sensors
and switches so that
we can express protein
in a cell-type specific manner.
And what that does
is that now you
can take really potent
proteins like cytokines
that might be very good
for counteracting cancers
but might be very systemically
toxic to the patient.
So now we can take that, express
it specifically in the tumor
so that you can take a
difficult-to-develop mechanism
and make it developable.
So I developed this technology
while I was a postdoc at MIT
at the Synthetic
Biology Center, together
with my business co-founder
Jake Becraft, who
was a student at MIT,
biological engineering,
and our scientific co-founders,
Ron Weiss at the Synthetic
Biology Center and
Darrell Irvine,
who was at the Koch
Institute at the time.
Fantastic.
So I'd like to hear
from each of you.
What inspired you
to start companies?
Was there a eureka
moment, or was it
more like Edison, one part
inspiration and 99 parts
perspiration?
Let's start with you, Tasuku.
Yeah.
Entrepreneurship for me
was very serendipitous.
So I didn't come to MIT
necessarily thinking
that I wanted to
become an entrepreneur.
But I feel like maybe I
came at the right place
at the right time.
A few years before I started
my postdoc, Katalin Karikó,
Drew Weissman at Penn had
developed this technology
that showed that you
can take messenger RNA
and express protein in
a very efficient manner.
And then Moderna
also had just became
a company, a startup company.
And they were working
on the first generation
of messenger RNA therapeutics.
And so we were in academia.
And while we thought
that most people were
skeptical about messenger
RNA therapeutics at the time,
maybe it was only
like a 1% chance
that it would become
useful for society.
But as academic researchers,
we can think boldly.
And we thought, let's imagine
a world in which this messenger
RNA became useful for society.
And in that world,
what would be missing?
And what we realized
was that the ability
to control protein
expression precisely
was missing for the
first-generation technologies
that companies like Moderna,
BioNTech were developing.
And so that's why
we decided to apply
the principles of synthetic
biology and program
the messenger RNA so that we can
express protein in cancer cells
specifically or immune
cells specifically.
And this was more
than 10 years ago,
way before anyone
believed in messenger RNA.
And so when we
presented this work,
most people thought it
was kind of like sci-fi.
And so I think the world
wasn't really ready yet
for this kind of technology.
So we didn't immediately
think we were going
to spin it off as a company.
It wasn't until
several years later,
when we saw that companies
like Moderna, BioNTech,
they were gaining financial
traction, at least,
thinking about IPOing.
And that's when we
thought that maybe,
maybe with these resources
behind these technologies, maybe
now there's a 10% chance of
success that mRNA could achieve.
And that's when we
spun out the company,
and we started in early 2019.
Thank you.
Cullen.
Yeah, I wish I could say
that I was two years old
and I wanted to start a company
on gene delivery technology.
And this is the fulfillment
of a lifelong dream.
That's not the way it happened.
It started for us, really,
with the grant from DARPA.
So I was actually excited
to hear about the new grant
opportunities.
DARPA kind of took a risk on
some technologies from my lab,
and this was 2013.
I hadn't worked in the space
of gene delivery at all.
I just had a crazy
idea, and they
were willing to put
some money towards it.
And I had a great post-doc
at the time, Paulo Garcia,
who became my co-founder.
And we developed this
technology for gene delivery.
And around 2016, he would
present at conferences,
and people would come up
to him after the talk,
say, this was awesome.
That was amazing.
Where do I buy it?
Where can I buy this thing?
And we're like,
oh, I don't know.
We weren't selling it.
It was very much we
started the company
to satisfy a market need.
We didn't get into
the space thinking
we were going to
start a company,
and then we're going
to be rich and famous.
That still hasn't happened yet.
[LAUGHTER]
We got into it because
there was a market need,
and we felt it was really clear
that for some research at MIT
and for some research, the
end of your progression
is publishing a paper
or a student's thesis.
It was really clear that in this
case, the end of this research
was in the marketplace.
It had to get out there where it
could potentially help patients.
And I would say
there was another--
there was a lot of
serendipity also in our story.
We founded the company
right around the same time
as the engine was being founded.
And so we submitted
an interest statement
saying we were interested in
learning more about the engine.
And they reached out to us.
I'll never forget
meeting with Katie Rae.
They didn't even have
offices at the time.
We met in a random
conference room at MIT
to talk about our technology.
And she said, I really want
to put gasoline on this
and accelerate it forward.
And they took a risk on us,
and we started the company
based on that kind
of market pool
and the interest
from the engine.
A fantastic story.
Tasuku, what
challenges did you face
taking your academic project
and turning it into a startup?
Yeah.
So the objective
of a company is so
different from
academic research.
As a company, we need
to be really laser
focused on value creation.
And so to me, it comes down to
company culture and the team.
And company culture, it seems
like such a nebulous concept,
but it goes hand in hand
with company strategy.
So what is it that
you choose to do?
What is it that you choose not
to do and how do you do it?
And so that goes hand in hand
with the company's mission.
And our mission
is to cure cancer.
And so every day, we
ask our employees,
what is it that you're
doing specifically
that creates value towards
that goal and mission of curing
cancer?
And if it doesn't really
contribute to that,
let's drop it.
And then really focus
on the activities
that lead to value creation.
And then on just setting
the company culture,
and the strategy isn't enough.
The team needs to
execute on that.
And so from a team
perspective, of course,
you need the really talented
people, the intelligent people.
But that's not enough.
You really need grit.
So as a startup, you're facing
crises all the time, right?
And it's so easy to give up.
So you need not just
intelligence but that grit
to hang in there and figure out
how to solve these problems when
they come.
But that isn't enough either.
You need to be a real team
player because drug development
is a team sport.
And so in the early
days, we brought
in a lot of talented
research scientists,
a lot coming from MIT as well.
And once we were successful
with the drug discovery
phase of the
company, then it was
time to really bring in a lot of
industry experience folks, that
can work on the development.
Our SVP has decades of
experience in industry
developing gene therapies.
Prashant Nambiar.
And then we also brought in
some folks that can really
manufacture the drug.
That's super important,
or else your drug
isn't going to be successful.
So Joe Barberio is
our vice president
of technical operations
that is really
experienced with lipid
nanoparticles, messenger RNA
drug development.
So yeah, with that, now we're
a clinical stage company.
And I think we're
proving out our concept
of taking these really
potent mechanisms
and curing cancer patients.
Cullen, as a professor,
as an academic,
do you encourage your students
to do entrepreneurship.
And if so what message
do you give them?
Yeah, that's a great question.
These days, you almost don't
need to encourage them.
Probably half the
students that come to you
are already interested in it.
So I actually spent a lot of
time discouraging students.
[LAUGHTER]
I think there are
two poor reasons
to want to start a company.
Then I'll give a good one.
The two bad ones that
you see, unfortunately,
being an entrepreneur has
become a bit glamorized,
and you can tell
that there are some
that are interested in
being an entrepreneur
because it's going
to sound really
cool to tell their friends
they're raising money.
That's a terrible reason
to be an entrepreneur.
There's a second one,
and you see this a lot.
And it's a hard one.
But people get really excited
about their technology.
They love their science.
They love their
technology. so much.
They just think everyone else in
the world is going to love it.
And the truth is that
the world doesn't
care about your technology.
They care about what it can do.
They care about the solution.
And so that gets me to the good
reason is, you need a good, why.
You need a good, who
are you going to help,
whose life is going to change by
the success of your technology
or of your company.
If you have a
compelling why, that's
a good reason to be an
entrepreneur because that's
the thing that's going
to keep you going
those late nights, those long
days, when you're raising money,
which you'll always
be raising money.
That's the thing that's
going to keep you going.
So I usually tell students
like, find a good why,
find a good problem.
That's the thing that you
want to be motivated by, not
by the technology.
The technology is nice.
The technology is
nice to get a degree,
but not nice for
starting a company.
That's a wonderful lesson
for our students here.
Tasuku, I understand
that you took
a bit of a detour between your
time at MIT and starting Strand.
Can you tell us a
little bit about it
and how it may have
influenced your path?
Yeah, and a lot of this was
really serendipitous, right?
It wasn't like this was
my grand plan in life.
So I met my wife while
I was here at MIT,
and she was a visiting
student from Belgium.
And so after I
finished my postdoc
so that I can be with
her, I moved to Europe.
And when I moved to
Europe, I decided
that getting outside of the
MIT environment, it's so hard.
You get spoiled with the
resources that you have here.
And I thought, maybe
I'll try something else.
And I joined an asset management
company, a biotech investment
fund, in Brussels.
And so I was a so-called
buy-side analyst.
And so we had
billions of dollars
of investor money invested
in public biotech and pharma
companies.
We had more than 100
companies in our portfolio.
And my job as an analyst was
to follow obsessively every
single move that these
public biotech and pharma
companies make.
And so I analyzed the platform
technologies, the pipeline
drugs, and all the
diseases that are
being pursued by the biotech
and pharma companies.
And so I didn't necessarily
really love that job, per se.
But it was so educational in
learning about what people are
doing in the biopharma space.
And as Cullen
mentioned, that helped
us think about what are
the unmet medical needs
that this next-generation
messenger RNA
technology can address?
And that led us to
focusing on cancer
and immuno-oncology using
Strand's messenger RNA
technology.
Wonderful.
Well, maybe this is
the last question,
given how much time we have.
Are there any lessons
that you learned,
advice that you'd give
to your former self
when you were just starting out?
Yeah, I'd probably
give myself the advice
I just gave all of you, which
is like, don't forget your why.
I think as you get
into it, you can
start getting distracted by
all kinds of things which
seem like success or seem like
milestones along the way--
hiring people,
finding new space,
raising money,
finding customers.
Those things are all great.
But don't forget
the core thing that
motivated you to get
into it in the beginning.
Think of the faces
of the people that
are going to be saved and
helped by what you're doing.
And maybe try to keep a
good connection with them.
In the technology that
we are working on,
it's a gene delivery technology.
And so we interact more
with customers who then
will interact with patients.
And so you can feel
a little bit removed.
And early on, I
think it might have
been helpful to just continue
to remember why you're doing it
and who you're doing it for.
Oh, that's a great message.
And so I want to thank
you both for, really,
a fascinating conversation.
I think what came out to
me in these conversations
with you is really that that
exemplifies what's really
best about MIT, people working
across disciplines, really
focused on addressing some of
the really challenging problems
for society, especially
in health care.
Let's give them a big
round of applause.
[APPLAUSE]