hello I'm L hessie Fisher and you're
listening to today I learned climate
from the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology imagine for a moment that
you're standing on a massive sheet of
ice that spans from the high Arctic all
the way into the northern United States
at its thickest point you could drill
down through almost 2 miles s of solid
ice before reaching
land today on our episode we are going
back in time to visit past versions of
our Earth that are wildly different from
today's and why well because the earth's
climate has changed before many times
before and folks like you have written
in and asked us about it what caused the
earth's climate to change in the past
and what can it tell us about the
climate change that we're experiencing
today fortunately we know someone at MIT
who knows a lot about the history of the
earth's climate my name is David McGee
and I'm a professor in the department of
Earth atmospheric and planetary Sciences
at MIT and I study paleoclimate which is
the study of the natural history of
Earth's
climate it turns out that our planet has
changed a lot before we humans came onto
the scene there was a time for instance
when the the whole center of North
America was engulfed by an inland sea a
time when alligators crawled in the
Arctic and forests flourished near the
South Pole and that's because the Earth
has gone through some wild changes in
temperature even in the last 1% of Earth
history so the last like 45 million
years we've seen changes in the earth's
mean
temperature of roughly 30 to 40° F so
huge changes in the mean Global
temperature but how do we know about
these big changes in temperature well
that really is the story of paleo
climate and it begins in Earnest in the
1700s with some peculiar
rocks people had noticed Boulders that
didn't match the local bedrock in places
where it didn't really make sense that
there should be Boulders in Scotland and
Ireland around eastern North America
they noticed striations or grooves in
the Bedrock and they realized that these
striations were things that were
observed near modern glaciers and so
people started to piece together this
story that there had been very large ice
sheets in places where there weren't
currently ice
sheets in 1824 a geologist named yenes
Mark first proposed that these ice
sheets were not just local but a single
vast mass of ice that once covered much
of the northern hemisphere in other
words that the world had undergone an
Ice
Age over the next Century scientists
would find more and more evidence
proving his theory eventually learning
that 20,000 years ago a quarter of the
earth's land surface was covered in ice
year round and that raised a new
question just how cold was the earth
during this ice age to answer that
scientists needed some extraordinary new
tools paleo climate is the art of the
possible you know there's only so many
things that you have that are left over
from thousands of years ago there's even
fewer that are left over from millions
of years ago and even fewer from
hundreds of millions of years ago so we
have to rely upon natural archives
things that grow or are deposited and
somehow record information about the
climate around them as they form and
these archives need to be preserved for
a very long time scientists have only
found a few of these relics of the deep
past often buried in unchanging
environments like Antarctic ice or
sediments in the deep sea and at both of
these
archives you have deposits building up
year after year after year and if you're
able to drill or core down into them you
essentially have a time machine I'll
just give you an example there is a
certain type of Plankton that lives in
the surface ocean these are called forif
and they're about the size of a grain of
sand really small they happen to form
small calcium carbonate shells so just
like a clam might but they're so small
that they're able to float around in the
surface ocean and when the for manifer
die their shells fall to the ocean floor
and are preserved in layers of sediment
so what does that have to do with the
temperature well it turns out that for
manifer that grow in warmer Waters build
their shells a little differently as the
temperature gets hotter the forams
become more sloppy chemists and they
allow more magnesium into their calcium
carbonate shell and so you can measure
the Magnesium to calcium ratio
and that's a very strong function of
temperature and there are other time
traveling thermometers found in tree
rings ice cores and stalagmites deep in
caves when you combine these separate
lines of evidence we can build a window
into climates from long ago what's more
when scientists tracked these
temperature records further and further
back in time a surprising new picture
appeared they were able to see see oh
wow it hasn't just been one Ice Age
there's been this cycle going back and
forth between ice ages and warmer
periods so the Earth has been going in
and out of ice ages over the last
million years at a rate of roughly one
cycle per 100,000 years so you'll have a
period like the peak of the last ice age
about 20,000 years ago and then
temperatures will rise into warm
climates like we've enjoyed for the last
10,000
years how and why well the answer
amazingly lies not here on Earth but out
in the solar
system so you might know that the Earth
orbits the Sun in an ellipsis not a
perfect circle and the Earth is also
tilted at anytime one pole faces the sun
that's the half of the earth that
experiences Summer and the other half
faces away that's the Earth that
experiences winter but over thousands of
years that orbit and that tilt well it
shifts the Earth's orbit gradually
changes as we get pulled by the other
planets and the solar system and so the
Earth's orbit becomes more elliptical or
more circular through time the Earth
tilt changes a little bit through time
in a cyclical Manner and Gra gradually
our North and South Poles might find
that during the summer they're no longer
tilted so strongly toward the Sun that
decreases how much sunlight comes into
the Arctic during local summer and makes
it harder to melt away the previous
Winter's snow and ice and it builds up
and builds up and builds up and
eventually forms an ice
sheet so then the question is okay
you're building some ice sheets in
Northern Canada and Scandinavia why does
that make the whole world cold the real
reason that ice ages are a global
phenomenon is because as you grow an ice
sheet the ice sheet changes ocean
circulation and such a way that more
carbon dioxide gets stored in the deep
ocean rather than sticking around in the
atmosphere you probably remember that
CO2 is the most important of the heat
trapping gases in our atmosphere that
are causing today's climate change and
throughout Earth's history there's been
a close relationship between the average
temperature of our planet and the amount
of CO2 in our atmosphere the scientists
use the tools of paleo climate to look
at how much CO2 was in the air during
the ice ages in fact we can actually
measure directly the air of the ancient
past because some of it is still
around in Antarctica in particular as
the snow builds up and then gets
compressed beneath other layers of snow
above it and gradually turns into ice it
traps little bubbles of air and that air
is pristine samples of the ancient
atmosphere and so scientists will
collect these ice cores bring them back
to the lab and then measure directly how
much carb dioxide is in the air from
times in the
past that's really cool all right so
let's recap so the Earth shifts slightly
in Space over thousands of years making
the Arctic summer darker and colder and
ice sheets form and spread and the
ocean's circulation changes this traps
CO2 deep in the ocean and because there
is less heat trapping CO2 in the
atmosphere the entire planet begins to
cool and so it's quite a chain of events
that leads from the changes in Earth's
orbit to the ice ages themselves so how
much do these changes add up well in the
last ice age which was 20,000 years ago
CO2 in the atmosphere fell by about a
third so do you want to guess how much
the Earth cooled as a
result we now know that in the peak of
the last a age it was about 10° f colder
than it was during pre-industrial
times did you guess correctly or were
you way off maybe you're asking yourself
now wait what just
10° isn't that the difference between a
chilly fall day in a crisp spring
afternoon yeah it's really striking to
me how different the world was given
only 10° Fahrenheit difference in mean
temperatures so where I'm sitting around
Boston Massachusetts would have had
about a mile of ice on top of me right
now from just 10° of cooling which is
about 5 1/ 12° of Celsius by the way but
this is the crucial difference between
weather and climate if the weather
changes by 10° well you put on a jacket
but if the average climate changes by
10° well you've got the planet where
woolly mammoths roamed as far south as
Illinois and Spain
and then slow changes in Earth's orbit
gradually increase how much summer
sunlight there is in the Arctic and
start to melt back those ice sheets and
the changes go in reverse so the ocean
circulation responds and allows carbon
dioxide that has been stored in the deep
ocean to come back into the atmosphere
and those Rising CO2 levels warm the
entire world like they are
today except not quite like today we
really really are living through
something that's different now so for
one thing today's climate change is
timed all wrong the Earth's position in
space is not setting us up for more
warming the variations in Earth's orbit
are fairly subtle right now and then
they'll get larger over the next few
tens of thousands of years so if there
weren't human caused climate change we
would eventually go back into another
Ice
Age and a huge difference between the
end of the last ice age and today's
warming is how fast it's happening
now so if you look at the warming coming
out of the last ice age temperatures
were low until about 177,000 years ago
and then CO2 started to rise and Global
temperatur started to rise and they rose
that 10° fahr in about 7,000
years modern temperature change is about
10 times
faster which means that today we're
facing climate change at a speed that
even our distant nomadic ancestors in
the Ice Age never confronted let alone
the more recent humans who laid the
foundations of civilization as we know
it the last 10,000 years have been a
period of stability in global
temperatures and that period of of
stability has coincided with the growth
of complex human societies and dramatic
expansions in human population and I
think it's more than a
coincidence it is true that the Earth
has gone through immense climate change
before many times over in fact but human
civilization has not and especially not
this fast today we are the ones changing
the balance of our atmosphere and we're
the ones who get to decide do we want to
rapidly Shake our planet loose from the
stability that we've always known or
will we be happier and safer if we act
to preserve the climate in which
Humanity has flourished for the last
10,000
[Music]
years that is our show for today thank
you to everyone who sent us in questions
about the ice ages you can send us your
own question by leaving us a voicemail
message at
3566 or visiting climate. mit.edu SL
ask today I learned climate is the
climate change podcast of the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology
Aaron croll is our writer and executive
producer David lensy is our sound editor
and producer Michelle Harris is our fact
Checker the music is by Blue Dot
sessions and I'm your host and Senior
editor La hessie Fisher thank you to
Professor David McGee for speaking with
us and to all of you for listening keep
up your climate curiosity
[Music]