There was essentially three types of
cereal in World War II. Cheerios,
cornflakes, and Quaker oats. That was
it. Okay. Uh but by 1970,
there was more than 150 breakfast
cereals to choose from. Uh including
ones that are very similar like apple
cinnamon Cheerios.
Okay. By 1970s, so ba but basically I'm
sorry, let me back up. I said this
wrong. 1953 type cereals. By 1970, there
150 cereals. But it wasn't
differentiation. It was that stores had
realized they could make generic
versions. So they made odeos which were
Cheerios a different name but they were
Cheerios and then they could just sell
them. They could sell them at epsilon
above marginal cost and make money. So
essentially the cereal companies were
not making profits anymore because
generic products have been introduced to
essentially mimic what they were making.
So they product differentiated. In 1989
General Mills introduced Apple Cinnamon
Cheerios. It's less old than you think.
Okay, it's before you guys, but well
after me. Apple cinnamon Cheerios. Now,
when apple cinnamon and Cheerios came
in, they were delicious objectively.
Okay, and there was no good substitute.
So, they suddenly face fairly inelastic
demand. So, they could raise prices
above marginal costs. So, General Mills,
while getting competed to death on
regular Cheerios, could suddenly have a
highly profitable apple cinnamon Cheerio
line. and they patented the apple
cinnamon formula. So for a while there
wasn't competition. Now there's generic
apple cinnamon materials but they
weren't for the first few years.
Okay. So by product differentiating
they ended this death cycle of betron
competition.
Is that good or bad?
Let's come back to welfare. Yeah. Oh
just checking your nails question answer
rather. Uh is that good or bad? Yeah.
Well, is it good or bad? Depends very
much on your model. We think it's
probably good because of the principle
I've talked about reveal preference,
which is if people didn't want apple
cinnamon cereals, they wouldn't buy
them. So, you've created a new in
product differentiating, you've created
a new product
that consumers want. Indeed, my
colleague, very famous economist name
Jerry Hman, actually estimated that the
introduction of Apple Cinnamon Cheerios
raised consumer surplus by more than $75
million a year
because they had this new thing they
wanted.
Now, on the other hand,
they were paying a monopoly price for
it. So, we are better off in a world
with apple cinnamon Cheerios than
without it. But we're still not as good
off, not not as well off if they weren't
if there wasn't more competition
providing apple cinnamon Cheerios. So it
doesn't mean in other words in
economists we talk about the we talked
about the first fundamental welfare
theorem, the best we can do. We also
talk about the second best which is well
the best we can do given constraints we
live under.
So having apple cinnamon chur the best
we could do. It's the second best. We
are better off having apple cinnamon
than not. But the first best will be
apple cinnamon materials with a
regulated price at the perfectly
competitive price or at least above it
enough to invent new products. So indeed
today only five firms make most cereals.
Five firms. There are 5,000 types of
cereal. 5,000.
So that raises
another interesting issue. So overall
economistic product differentiation is
good. We think essentially it's driving
variety. People like variety. If they
didn't, they wouldn't buy it. That's
good.
But there's starting to be an
interesting question in industrial
organization of the problem of choice
overload,
which is in some sense, are we actually
do we have too many choices? In
economics, we assume more choice is
good. That's our fundamental assumption.
But what if now you just get to the you
get to the supermarket, you look at
that, you're like, it I'm going to have
toast. Okay? Because you're like, I just
can't decide. There's so much. Well, you
could get to the point we're actually
worse off from that much product
differentiation.