So today we're continue once again the
road map we talked about consumer Theory
then we talk about producer Theory and
we got to the point we realize the one
place producer theory is harder than
consumer theory is you're not given a
budget constraint you're not told how
much you have you get to choose how much
you have you get to choose how much to
produce and we know for any quantity the
way you'll produce it we know the
efficient combination of inputs to
produce any quantity we developed that
last time what we don't know is how do
you choose what quantity to produce and
to get that we're going to add a third
instead of having two equations and two
unknowns we're going to add a third
element to the model and the element
we're going to add is Market structure
we're going to add an element of how
firms compete in the market okay and
essentially that is where we're going to
go for the next several
lectures is to think about the structure
of the market itself and how that feeds
back into firm's decisions on how much
to
produce okay and so that's kind of where
we're going today is to ask how do we
take the market impose it on the firm's
decisions from last time on that long
run expansion path we have last time to
determine how much they actually produce
we're going to start with a particular
assumption we're going to start by
talking about short run profit
maximization and we're going to start in
the particular example of a market that
features perfect
competition I'll Define this more
technically in a minute but basically
stepping back it's going to turn out the
firm's decisions on how much to produce
is going to depend on the kind of Market
they face and there's different types of
markets one extreme that we'll focus on
for much of this class is the extreme of
perfect competition basically many firms
competing to produce identical
Goods The Other Extreme would be
Monopoly one firm that produces the
good okay and then there's a h host of
examples in between indeed in between is
my favorite word in economics oligopoly
just a great sounding word okay
oligopoly is really the way markets
almost all look which is a number of
firms competing but not too many so say
we have one extreme where there's a huge
numbers of firms competing that's
perfect competition The Other Extreme
there's just one firm in the market
that's Monopoly and in between we have
oligopoly which is most Industries think
of the Auto industry there's more than
one car company but there aren't a
thousand car companies okay think about
most of the industries that we feature
uh in a modern developed economy are
oligopolistic okay and that's that'll be
the third place we turn so we're going
to start by thinking about perfect
competition then we'll turn to Monopoly
as always it's easiest to trace out the
extremes start with one extreme which is
perfect competition we'll then shift to
The Other Extreme which is Monopoly
you'll then take your midterm and then
we'll talk about the middle case which
is oligopoly okay so let's talk about
what are the assumptions of perfect
competition what are the assumptions
that underline perfect competition
okay
basically the key the technical
definition of a perfectly competitive
market is one where all
firms are price
takers price
takers what do I mean by that what I
mean by that is that no action
that any given firm does can affect the
price in the
market any given firm is sufficiently
small Rel to the market that no action
any individual firm takes affects the
market
price well when would this be
true this would be true in the case
where when
demand for a firm's output is perfectly
elastic
okay demand for a firm's output not the
market demand but demand for a given
firm is perfectly elastic and we show
that in figure
71 in figure
71 here is a case and notice the xaxis
is little Q not big Q little Q is a firm
big Q is the market this is a firm level
diagram of uh the firm's production
decision how much produce at what price
in a perfectly competitive market The
Firm faces a perfectly elastic demand at
some Price p we'll talk about where P
comes from okay but just well by the end
of the lecture you know where P comes
from but now just say there's some Price
p and at that price demand is perfectly
elastic as a
result Supply shifts in Supply have no
impact on the price charged you always
charge the same
price okay so when does it make sense
that demand be perfectly elastic what
are the assumptions is a perfect
competition when does it make sense that
firms are price takers well we make
three key assumptions the first is
identical
products the first assumption is that
firms are selling identical
products the second assumption is that
there's
full transparent full knowledge
of
prices that is every consumer knows
every firm's
price identical products every consumer
knows every firm's price and finally no
transaction costs the third assumption
no transaction
costs meaning you can easily shop at any
firm you
want the products are identical
you know every firm's price and you can
easily shop at as many firms as you want
okay now this is obviously untrue for
any Market in the world but once again
the extremes provide a useful example a
close example would be
eBay think about eBay for a very common
good buying a certain type of of silicon
chip on eBay or a certain type of kind
of food or a certain type of you know a
shirt of a certain size and style okay
the the products are identical the
prices are all listed there and it's
easy to shop there's no you just look at
the list there's no transaction costs so
in
theory okay eBay fits these conditions
in practice it doesn't and why is
that how does eBay violate how does
shoping eBay violate all these
conditions what are some some reasons
why shoing eBay isn't perfectly
competitive
yeah yeah basically you don't really
know the price indeed for many years
eBay would would not would rank firms by
the price excluding shipping we call
that a shrouded attribute in technical
terms they would sort of hide the cost
of shipping so really you weren't really
competing on prices what
else well it's hard to find truly
identical products on eBay every
product's a little bit different okay so
there's a lot and if you if products are
different you have to look into it
suddenly that takes time that's a
transaction cost so even eBay which is
sort of the canonical example perfectly
competitive market isn't probably my
favorite example is if you go to a
tourist site particularly developing in
sort of in in many countries there'll be
lots of people selling the same
around the tourist site so think of the
Eiffel Tower there are literally
hundreds of guys who have spread out
blankets saying the Sal on the same damn
little Eiffel Tower
keychain okay now there I can easily see
what people are charging they're right
next to each other little transaction
costs I can see it's the same damn
keychain and it's not that hard just ask
what the price is so that is an example
in fact I taught that example in my
online class and a student actually I
got a package in the mail once and I
opened it it was a bunch of little
Eiffel Tower keychains fell out and
someone said they'd gone and done the
exploration and it turns out all the
sellers right near the Eiffel Tower did
charge identical price once you got
further away it was a different price
why because that wasn't identical
anymore you know a different spot but
everyone right around the Tower card is
exactly the same price for the little
Eiffel Tower for the little EI Eiffel
Tower statue at which is pretty cool
okay so that's the kind of Market we
have in
mind okay now let me highlight one thing
once again this is little Q not big
Q this does not say the market demand is
perfectly elastic the demand for any
given firm is perfect elastic I'm not
saying the demand for Eiffel ties for
statuettes in general is perfectly
elastic I'm saying that a cross seller
uh The Firm specific demand is perfectly
elastic okay armed with these
assumptions and what a competitive
market is we can now talk about how do
firms maximize
profits okay how do firms maximize
profits well basically firms want to
choose the optimal quantity to maximize
profits as a function of Q which equals
Revenue as a function of Q Minus cost
the function of
Q okay all firms are choosing is Q
they're not price makers they're price
takers they don't choose the price they
just the price is whatever when they set
up their blank in front of the Eiffel
Tower they find whatever else is
charging okay there's no there's
basically no uh no scope to set the
price all they can decide is how much
quantity they want to sell and how they
want to make it they have control over
their costs so basically if we set take
the set equal to zero this says that
if we set if we take the derivative and
set equals zero to optimize this this
says that Dr DQ equals
dcdq and this is the fun this is it this
is profit maximization in one
equation okay basically you want to set
the marginal revenue equal to the
marginal
cost well in a competitive market we
know what the marginal revenue is what
do you get from selling the next unit
well you get the market price P it's
given to you the margin revenue is
always p whenever you sell the next unit
you get P we'll talk later about markets
where that's not true where the price
you get depends on how much you sell but
in a competitive market that's not true
no matter what you sell you get P it's a
flat
line okay and we know what dcdq is it's
marginal cost so profit maximization in
a perfectly competitive market means
setting price equal to marginal
cost this is the rule for profit
maximization in a perfectly competitive
market this is the general for any
Market any Market's going to set
marginal equal to Marginal costs that's
going to translate a perfectly
competitive market into price equals
marginal
cost okay so for example let's go back
to a cost curve we're using last time
let's imagine cost = 10 + 5 q^2 and we
know how to derive that we did that last
time so let's go to figure
72 okay and let's assume P equals 30
just to make life easy we'll assume P
equals 30 assume and I'll tell you later
where that comes from but for now just
take it as given okay the left panel
shows uh the left panel of this graph
shows how costs and revenues evolve as
cost
increase okay so basically when you for
every the revenue line is a line with a
slope of 30 why because every unit you
sell you get 30 that's the price the
cost line is the graph we saw last time
of the cost function t 10 plus 5
q^2 okay so basically what you see and
so you can translate that to the right
hand graph which is what is the
profit you earn on every unit
sold okay so basically what that says
the first if if you're selling zero
units you're losing money because what
what's the
revenue zero what's the cost
10 10 plus 5 squ at Z is 10 so your
profit is
-1 but as you sell units your profits
rise okay until you get to the third
unit okay where each each of the first
second and third units each of those
first three units the money you make by
selling the next unit is higher than the
cost of producing the next
unit the money you make from selling the
the next unit is higher than the cost of
producing in the next unit but once
you've reached three
units okay that's no longer true when
you go to producing the fourth unit the
money you make on the fourth unit is
less than the cost of the fourth
unit the money you make on the fourth
unit is less than the cost of the fourth
unit that's why profit maximization much
like utility maximization is a hill
climbing exercise remember I said in
economics we can do marginal decision
making here is sort of an
example okay of marginal decision making
the idea of marginal decision making is
you think of yourself as climbing a
mountain that's in the clouds and you're
trying to to the top of the mountain but
you can't see more than one step in
front of you if you take a step forward
and you go up you know you're heading up
the mountain take a step forward and you
go down you know you're heading down the
mountain you don't need to know where
the top of the mountain is just need to
know where you're heading up or down and
when you've reached the point where the
next step takes you down then you're at
the top that's what we're doing here
we're not saying we don't look at what
the problem maximizing quantity is we
solve for it we ask does the next unit
make money does the revenue made off the
next unit exceed the cost of produce to
the next unit is that next step taking
you up the hill or down the hill and
that's how we do profit
maximization you could see this in
figure
73 here we are actually taking our cost
curves
and adding a adding Revenue so the
curves on figure 73 are the same as the
ones we developed last time same as the
first figure in the last lecture all
I've done here is I've added a line at P
equals
30 okay I've added a line at P equals 30
that dash line by the way uh should go
all the way to the y- AIS we're missing
a little connection there um but there's
a line at P equals
so what how do we solve for a firm's
decision well what's through approximate
profit maximization you set price equal
to marginal cost where does price equal
marginal cost well it happens when
marginal cost equals 30 so the first
step is you find the point at which
marginal cost equals price that is
producing three
units that is the point at which price
equals marginal cost that is the profit
maximizing
point the second question is what are
the profits at that
point what are the profits at that point
well what is the average cost cost at
that point the average cost when you're
producing three units is 10 over three
plus uh plus 10 over 3 + 5 *
3 uh 10 over 3 + 5times uh 5 time 9
sorry because q^ squ okay the average
cost is 10 over3 plus 5 * 9 let me see
what I got wrong
here uh uh oh I'm sorry no you divide by
Q sorry you divide by average cost is 5
time 3 because average cost is 10 over 3
+ 5 q average cost is 10 over is is
dividing this by three by by Q so it's
10 over three plus 5 q is the average
cost the total costs are 10 + 5 * 9 the
the average costs are 10 over 3 + 5 * 3
which equals 18.33%
[Music]
on average each unit you sell cost you
18.33%
times the number of units sold you're
making 11.67 per unit you're selling
three units so your total profit is 40
which is the area of that box let's go
over it again you set price equal the
marginal cost that determines that
determines the top of the hill that is
true producing three
units at three units your profits are
your revenues minus your costs we can
divide both by Q Sayes Revenue per unit
Minus cost per unit unit times Q so
profits okay is revenue Minus cost we
can also write that as Revenue over Q
Minus cost over Q time Q right just
pulling out multiplying dividing by Q
well Revenue per Q at
three is 30 that's flat number it's a
flat line cost per Q at
30 are are 18.33%
okay questions about
that so that's how we determine the
firm's
profits okay so let me stress test you
on this someone tell me what happens to
the cost function if a firm has to pay a
tax of $10 per unit at
Sals we start with this cost
function now I want to add a tax of $10
per unit what is the new cost function
yeah exactly the new cost function is 10
+ 5 q^2 plus 10 Q many people often say
20 plus 5 q^2 usually that's the typical
first answer I get that's wrong that' be
true if the firm only had to pay an
extra $10 flat but they pay $10 per unit
so it's 10 plus 5 q ^2 + 10 Q what does
that
do to our cas
well what that means is now marginal
cost if we differentiate this with
respect to Q is 10 q+ 10 marginal cost
used to be 10 Q now it's 10 Q + 10 so
the marginal cost curve is shifted up
all the cost curves are shifted up so
now marginal cost equals
price equals price at 2 units 10 Q + 10
equal 30 which is the price at
qar equals
2 I set marginal cost equal the price
this is the new marginal cost 10 Q Plus
10 I set that equal to 30 which is the
price I get the new qars too so
quantity's fallen from three to
two the price hasn't
changed why is quantity Fallen because
it's more expensive to produce and
you're always trading off the benefit of
producing the next unit against the cost
of producing the next unit the benefit
hasn't changed the cost has gone up so
you produce fewer
units what does that mean for profits
well look what's happened of profits
they've shrunken from the larger
rectangle to the smaller rectangle two
things have changed first of all you're
selling fewer
units so the width of the rectangles
changed I see triangle rectangles the
width of rectangles
changed second of all you're making less
money per unit why are you making less
money per unit because average costs are
up
two marginal costs are up but average
costs are up two so in this case you you
make less profits per
unit okay so you make less profits per
unit and you're selling fewer units so
the profit rectangle is shrunk from the
larger one to the smaller one that's an
example of how changes in cost structure
I didn't have to make the tax I can make
any change in cost structure how changes
in cost structure can
impact uh firms
profits okay questions about
that all
right now there's one additional feature
to make this even
harder in the short run which is we need
to decide whether the firm will shut
down I've just told you how to maximize
profits set peal the marginal cost but
we're not quite
done and that's because in the short run
losing money is not necessarily a reason
to shut
down you can lose money and want to stay
in
business and the reason is because
staying in the business allows you to
reoptimize in the long run so for
example imagine the price for this good
suddenly dropped to
$10 let's go let's not have the tax
let's go back to marginal cost equals 10
Q okay and imagine the um uh the um the
margin the price is just falling to $10
the price is $10 equals 10 so that says
a qar equals one right margin cost
equals a price margin that says qar
equals one what is your profits
producing one well profits are fixed Co
are 10 plus 5 q^2 which is five are the
costs I'm sorry that's the cost you get
a revenue of 10 and you have cost cost
of 10 plus 5 so your profits are neg
five your profits are negative five
you're losing money because you sell for
10 and the cost remember our cost
formula it's 10 plus 5 q^2 so your costs
are
15 so you lose
money should you stop
production and the answer is no and why
not why should you keep going even
though you're losing
money and remember the key is
opportunity cost yeah is they covering
the cost of a variable yep well you're
one step ahead what would happen if you
produce zero what would your profits be
then no what would your profits be if
you produce
zero minus 10 because you got to pay the
fixed cost no matter what just plug zero
into this formula if you produce zero
your profits are minus 10 so you're
better off producing one than zero
you've already given the answer answer
why but you're better off producing one
even though you're losing money the
opportunity cost of shutting down is you
actually lose 10 so you're better off
losing
five and why is that why would you want
to produce losing money it's because in
the long run you could change your fixed
costs so you can come back the next
period and make it up so when you want
to shut down is not about whether you
lose
money it's about whether you lose so
much money that over comes your fixed
costs when will that be true well this
gentleman gave the answer that will be
true when ignoring fixed costs you still
lose money that'll be true when your
variable costs are below Revenue it will
be true when
PQ okay is less than your variable cost
fixed costs are in the short run sunk
they're relevant you already paid them
you're just want to ask for the next
unit will I make any money
okay or in other words you will keep
producing as long as p is is as long as
P isn't less than DC over Q the variable
cost over Q as long as the price which
we call average variable
costs so as long as the price is above
average variable costs you will keep
producing only once price drops below
average variable costs we stop producing
we call this the shutdown
Rule now it turns out in our case that's
never true because if you look at our
formula variable costs so our cost
function is Cal 10 + 5 q
^2 so variable costs are 5
q^2 average variable costs are 5
q okay average variable costs are 5
q I'm sorry five five uh average R cost
are 5 q now remember for our case
for this case the general formula for
optimization is margin cost equals price
so that's 10 Q equals P that's our
optimization condition 10 Q equals P
margin cost equals price well if you
plug so if you plug that in you get that
average variable cost terms of price is
0.5 time
P so what I did here I created the
variable cost I divide to make average
variable cost which is 5 q i then
substituted in from the optim ation
condition to get average varable cost
0.5 time P well 0.5 time P can never be
greater than
P average this number 0.5 times P can
never be greater than price this
condition can never
hold as a result with this cost function
you'll never shut
down it doesn't matter what profits are
you will not shut down okay this is a
confusing concept that you need to work
on but but it's important to remember
that when we develop Supply curves we
have to consider both what the supply
curve looks like and the short run
whether you want to shut down okay this
is something you have to practice it's
always a confusing concept but we'll
give you some practice on
that now armed with all this we can come
back to actually creating what you
wanted you demand and you said John
where does that supply curve come from I
need to know and I'm going to tell you
now where Supply curves comes from now
we get to wrap it all up where supply
curve come from well that's in figure
75 figure
75 shows
you how much the firm wants to produce
at different levels of
prices well when the price is 30 we know
it wants to produce three
units when the price is 40 it says
margin cost equal the price that turns
out to be four units it turns out the
firm's production decision is firm's
production curve is the marginal cost
curve the supply curve is the marginal
cost
curve that so we already two lectures
ago told you or maybe was last lecture
told you what Supply is supply curve is
the marginal cost curve and think about
the intuition the demand curve one
second the demand curve was the marginal
willingness to pay for a good the demand
curve was how much you're willing to pay
for the next good the supply curve is
the marginal cost of producing the next
good the supply curve is what does it
cost you produce the next good so so
demand and Supply meat where and I'll
get to that in a couple lectures where
marginal willingness to pay for the good
how much you willing to pay for the next
good equals the marginal cost of
producing that next good that's we get
equilibrium yeah it's question
here like the right side is the average
average average variable
cost no because I divided it's let me do
I did P * Q is than variable cost I then
divided both sides by Q so price should
be less than variable than than average
variable
cost no let back this is a general
formula you'll shut down when price is
less than variable costs that's the
general formula okay then I said in our
case what is average variable cost it's
5 q okay now in equilibrium we know what
Q is
we know Q is p over 10 so I can just
plug that
in and then I show for our case this
formula never
hold giv Q
what Q at no not equilibrium at profit
maximization given Q if a firm is profit
maximizing they'll use this rule Mar to
cost equals price if they use that rule
they'll never shut
down okay does that make sense okay good
question good clarification other
questions about
this uh that's a great point we are we
we we're dealing in integer worlds you
can but you can do the whole thing
fractionally the the mathematics still
holds the mathematics still holds you
just want really we're always doing sort
of it's a derivative ultimately the
question is for the next Epsilon unit of
production
is the variable cost greater than the
price you can sell it
for okay
yeah yes I because it implies ABC equals
5 Q and 10 Q equals P so I plugged
in
yep okay so now so the point is the
short run supply curve is simply the
marginal cost curve but above the
shutdown
Point S supply curve has two things it's
a marginal cost curve but only above the
shutdown point in our case there is no
shutdown point so it's irrelevant but in
general the rule is the short run supply
curve is the marginal cost curve above
the shutdown point is the technical
definition of the short run supply curve
so it's above minimum average variable
cost so technically the short run supply
curve is the marginal cost curve above
minimum average variable
costs and that's for the supply curve
comes
from now that is the firm supply curve
but we started this course with markets
so let's go to markets what does the
market supply curve look like okay so I
showed you the firm Supply 76 what does
the market supply curve look like well
let's go to figure
77 imagine initially we have one firm
that's
S1 we know what that firm supply curve
looks like we just developed it at a
price of 10 they produce one at a price
of 30 they produce three and so on
that's
S1 now let's add a second identical
firm well now at a price of 10 you get
one produced by each firm that's two and
at a price of 30 you get three produced
by each firm that's
six now let's add a third identical firm
and so on as you add identical firms the
market supply curve is a flatter version
of The Firm supply curve in other words
market supply is a more elastic version
of firm
Supply market supply is a more elastic
version of firm Supply so as more
identical firms produce the
good as more identical firms produce the
good the more elastic is the supply
curve
okay now this will give you a hint to
where ahead next time just want to ask
question about next time if I said
competitive markets have an infinite
number of firms and I said The more
firms are the more elastic is supply
curve think about what that implies to
the supply curve and we'll talk about
where next time about how that
works but for now let's talk about one
one more thing and I want to go back and
redo it all to make it clear the last
thing I want to talk about is the long
run supply curve so far I've been
talking about the short run
only what about the long run supply
curve well it turns out the long run
supply curve is just the marginal cost
curve but without the shutdown rule
because in the long run if profits are
negative you do shut down because in the
long run fixed costs aren't fixed right
so in the long run the supply curve is
just the marginal cost curve full
stop okay as long as profits are greater
than zero there's no shutdown rule as
long as you're making money you pick a
point where price equals marginal cost
the only difference in the short run the
long long run here is in the long run
you don't have this extra knowing
shutdown rule it's just basically the
long supply curve is marginal costs as
long as marginal as long as price is
above as long as profits are greater
than
zero okay so that is uh the long the the
long run so the idea is in the short run
you're willing to lose money because you
can always reoptimize your Capital you
can always go back and change your fix
costs but in the long run you've already
optimized and if you've done all your
optimizing you're still losing money
you're just out of luck you just
you you should get out of the business
okay because there's no more
optimization you can
do all right questions about
that all right so let's now put this all
together to derive the short run
equilibrium I'm going to mathematically
get you back
to where we started in the first lecture
okay I'm going to start with The
Primitives okay how do you find short e
the first is Step a is you get the
supply
curve how do you get the supply curve
well we know all the steps you start
with the production function step one
start with a production function in our
case the production function was Q
equals square root of L *
K that's step one
step two is you get input prices which
once again are still given at this point
we haven't endogenized them they're
still given and we had wal 5 R equals
okay step three I'm sorry you have your
assumptions and then the third thing is
you have a fixed amount of capital K Bar
equals 1 so you start with production
function you have your three assumptions
once again we know where K Bar equals 1
comes from that comes from long run
optimization where W and R come from you
haven't learned yet okay but in the
short run K fix so you start production
fun you have those three things we know
based on that how to develop a cost
function okay we know how to develop a
cost function we know that with these
three we devel we developed in a
previous lecture that with this
production function and these three
assumptions you get that the cost as a
function of quantity is 10 + 5 q^2 we
developed that in the previous lecture
Okay so I said if I give you a
production
function I give you an amount of capital
and I give you input prices you can
solve for the firm's cost function you
know how to do that now okay now if you
know the firm's cost function you know
marginal cost well marginal cost is just
the derivative of cost Spector quantity
which in our case is 10
Q okay we also know
know that in the firms maximize profits
when marginal cost equals
price in other words the supply curve
is Q equals 10 equals p over
10 qal p over 10 is our supply curve
we've just developed the supply curve
all I had to tell you to get the supply
curve was was a production function and
those three key input assumptions based
on that you have all you need to develop
a supply
curve you then have to check the
shutdown condition which we know in this
case is irrelevant but you have to check
it so it's Q go p over 10
where average variable cost is greater
than price which we know is always W
which we know is always
true I'm sorry where price is great is
less everywh cost less than price I'm
sorry which we know is always true in
this case so that's a supply
curve okay we've just developed it and I
only had to give you I only had to give
you two things the production function
and those and those three assumptions
questions about that
yeah 5q squ so basically um just quick
quick math on this okay let's go back
and do the math on this real quickly
just to review okay take this production
function okay Q equals uh square of k l
break out L that's q^2 over K
Bar L is Q2 over K Bar okay then then
reexpress then write a cost equation as
a function of just Q you can H you can
write that as cost K and Q I'm sorry
write cost equals 10
K plus 5 q ^2 over K
bar I just because that's the amount
that's the right that's the amount of
Labor you want to use so that's your
cost function you plug in K Bar equal 1
and you get Cal 10 plus 5 q 5
q^2 okay does that make sense yep you
bet okay so now we have the firm supply
curve The Firm supply
curve leads us to step
B which is we got to make a market
supply
curve well to make the market supply
curve we need to know how many firms are
in the
market now I'm gonna have to throw
another assumption at you next time I'll
tell you where to get this from okay all
the assumptions I making you're
eventually going to know where they come
from you know where W comes from and R
comes from and K comes from another
subject I'm going to throw at you is
little n the number of firms in the
market and let's just assume for now
little n equals
6 and I'll tell you next lecture how you
get that but for now it's useful to
start with an assumption assume there's
six firms in the market so what is the
total quantity in the market well the
total quantity is just six little
q's and we know little Q equals p over
10 we know little Q equals P we know
little Q equals p over 10 so the supply
curve is qals 35ths time P that's the
market supply curve which is just the
firm supply curve applied to six firms
that's the market supply
curve that's step
two step three is you have a demand
curve now I'm not going to go back
through all the math of that we spent a
couple lectures on this but you know how
to dve a demand curve as long as I give
you prices and income and utility you
know how to drive a demand curve you've
done that you do it on the problem set
you'll do it a bunch of times let's say
in this case just to make life easy
theand curve I get if I do that is 48
qal 48 minus
the market demand
curve okay I'm not going to go back
through all those steps because that's
that' be too much but hopefully you can
go back and review your consumer Theory
to get that okay and I'm just I mean
just making this up for this example but
you know how to derive a demand curve so
now we get
equilibrium is
where demand equals Supply where 48
minus
P equals 35ths p two
equations okay we had two we we had we
we set we set these equal to each other
to get
equilibrium so we get that
qar equals
18 the market the equilibrium quantity
in the market is
18 why because I know the market supply
curve I know the market demand curve
which I just made up for this case but
you know where it could you know how to
get one I set them equal to each other
and I get qar equals
18 okay but that's the market supply
what about each firm you want to know
what each firm's going to
produce well we
know that there's six firms in this
market and they're
identical so that
means that in this market each firm for
qar to be 18 little
qar must be three
well how do we know if that's the case
well we
know we know
that if qar equals 18 what's the price
well we know Q equals 35ths
P so if qar equals 18 P star equals what
30 right it's two equations and two
unknowns one equation was Q = 48 minus P
one equation was q = 35ths p I solved
them for qar but I I'll solve for p star
P star is 30 okay you can get it from
the man curve too 48 minus 18 is
30 okay so P star is
30 well we know each firm sets price
equal to marginal cost so now we can go
back to get the firm
Supply firm supplies where price equals
Mar marginal cost price is 30 marginal
cost is 10 Q so optimal firm production
is three which is what it has to
be the magic of this Market is that each
firm is prodes exactly what the
aggregate Market says they should
produce okay so basically we Sol we took
a firm we took
firms we built them up to the firms that
were taking a given price remember we
went to the firm we didn't specify price
price is they're price takers that's
just given from God from their
perspective okay you just when you set
up your blanket outside the F Tower just
look what everybody else is
charging okay we then so we left P to be
solved for we then use demand we then
take that firm decision make it a market
decision okay we then said we'll set
that market decision equal to market
demand and that gives you
an optimal market supply and market
price okay and you that market supply
implies that each firm must be producing
three well it turns out at that price
each firm is producing three so you're
at an equilibrium where everybody's
satisfied consumers are satisfied
because the demands being met consumers
margin willingness to pay is 48 minus P
well the price is
18 I'm so the price is 30 so they want
18 that's what they get firms are
satisfied because aggre get supply is
35ths p and each individual firm is
satisfied because price equals marginal
cost we're done that's the magic of the
market okay and this is the beauty of
being at MIT and teaching you what is
usually taught intermediate
microeconomics at most universities
you'll never find instruct economics
course that does this okay which is this
is the magic of bringing mathematics to
economics before Paul Samuelson taught
this class people would teach the graph
and be done with it okay okay and what
we've done is we' said you guys want the
math I've giving you the math I have
never ever gotten a complaint in this
course that I do too much math I only
get complaints I do two little math
which is unbeli unique I can't imagine
any other university in the world where
the major complaint you get is you do
two little math okay so I want to
explicitly write out here the math
because I think this is a helpful way to
understand it but you should have the
intuition the graphics and the math okay
questions about that
yeah the three- fifth p is the aggregate
quantity I assume there's six identical
firms each firm I said was producing 10
over P so six time 10 over p is 35th
P good clarifying question
yeah qar equals 18 well I solved here I
had two equations and two unknown one is
the demand curve Q = 48 minus P the
other supply curve Q equals 35ths P so
set 48- P equal to 35ths p and I get qar
equ 18 and P star equals
30 other questions these are great
clarifying questions remember if you're
confused most of the class is confused
you're you're you're representative of
the class so please ask those questions
other questions
yeah well you sol it's two equations two
unknown you're solving for both right so
it's a two equation we have two
equations Q equals 3 fths p and = 48
minus P You're solving for two unknowns
two equations and two
unknowns okay okay
yeah the supply curve all you need is
the firm's production
function input prices and the initial
level of capital and the rest is math
you've done and should keep doing if
you're not sure about
it great questions okay let's stop there
and um uh I hope you guys this is a once
again it's a great month for concerts I
hope you guys are getting out to at
least one this month and I'll see you uh
next week