Um I'm Ellie Nadivi. I'm a professor of
brain and cognitive sciences and I have
an appointment in biology too. And um
what I'm interested in is the brain's
ability to constantly adapt um what we
term as plasticity.
And it's a fundamental feature of the
brain to be able to
uh constantly change
um as need arises.
And uh even though we study it because
it's such a important aspect of brain
function, uh it turns out that uh when
things go wrong many
um of the things related to plasticity
um are the culprits.
And uh the other thing is that if we are
thinking about damage or any sort of uh
uh degenerative processes
or even um um disorders that are
genetic, uh if we know more about how
the brain itself can um adapt, we know
what the points are where we can
intervene to help.
Um
so I think that even though we work on
questions that are really basic science
uh it turns out that there's a lot of
interface with uh potential therapeutics
um even uh sort of predictive
um assays. I actually am excited about
all the projects in the lab. Uh so there
are kind of two directions that we have
in terms of even though our overarching
question is related to brain plasticity.
One is um using imaging as a tool to
look at how connections are made in the
brain in real time where we can label uh
neurons or brain cells and the
connections between them which are
synapses and we can monitor them coming
and going over time and things that
influence that. So that's an incredibly
powerful tool to um to look at
plasticity in the living mouse brain
which uh we're doing. And so
um
um and many
very basic features of how that happens
have sort of revealed themselves to us
through just being able to visualize the
connectivity and how it and track it
over time.
Um so because of that all the projects
using the imaging as a tool um I think
are super exciting and uh um and kind of
discovery projects um which is why I
love them because we keep finding new
things some of which we weren't really
looking for or weren't expecting
um and have been um
have allowed allowed us to really gain
mechanistic insight even though what
we're doing is just observing.
Um so that's kind of one direction that
I think is super interesting.
So um there are different types of
neurons in the brain and there are
different types of connections between
cells that are of different types and um
what we're seeing is that not all
connections are created equal. There are
some connections uh that are very rigid
and nonflexible
um sort of hardwired you might say. And
on the other hand, there are some
connections that are very plastic and
dynamic.
And so it seems that not all parts of
the circuit are equally amendable to
plasticity. And um and this is something
that we're seeing for the first time
because we can actually track um
dynamics over time and look at the
connectivity and see how it's changing
and who it's changing and uh kind of the
specific specificity of those types of
changes. So that's kind of in general
one thing that we've been able to see
that um there's a lot more heterogeneity
and obviously if you're interested in
plasticity
uh your ability to intervene depends on
your knowing
um what parts of the circuit are
amenable to change and that's where
you're more likely to be able to make a
difference.