So um I would like to uh take the work
the ideas that Rob just described and
look at the fundamental atomic um
processes that underpin these and other
types of reactions that allow us to
develop new kinds of materials. So we
we've we've seen extensively in Rob's
talk how structure dictates properties
and I took this text actually from his
abstract. Um it's very clear that the
way the atoms are arranged in a material
determine all of the important
properties the mechanical properties the
electronic and magnetic properties um
the properties in functional uh
situations like catalysis. And so um
every important characteristic really
fundamentally goes back to how the atoms
are arranged within the material. Now if
you want to see how the atoms are
arranged truly rather than showing
PowerPoint drawings with colored shapes
on them, then you're going to use
electron microscopy because this is the
only technique that has a combination of
spatial resolution and chemical ability
to determine which which blob is which
kind of atom. And um this is an example
of a high resolution electron microraph
of a layered material. So you all know
about graphine and its relatives where
the atoms are arranged in layers. Um
this is a view looking along the layers
of a 2D antifromagnet
um where we can identify exactly which
atom is where in the structure. So
obviously we look in three different
directions we'll see exactly where all
the atoms are. So these kinds of images
are really amazing in showing us where
the atoms are and therefore helping us
get some kind of intuition into how the
material will behave. However, um
structure of materials is constantly
changing. Imagine that we are uh we have
designed a material uh with a specific
structure and then we ask it to do a job
like perform a catalysis uh reaction um
be an electrode in a battery as we
charge and discharge it. Um as these
materials do their jobs the structure is
going to change. As materials are
exposed to the environment they oxidize,
they corrode. Um they may absorb carbon
dioxide. They may be exposed to a really
uh unfriendly environment such as the uh
they could be the wall of a nuclear
reactor or they could be a pipeline for
oil and gas. So these are these are very
unfriendly reaction uh environments that
will change the uh structure and hence
the properties of the material. And
finally as we actually process materials
to make them into the structures we want
clearly the structure is going to
change. So it's more likely that things
change than that they stay the same. So
the idea of taking static pictures in
the electron microscope is somewhat
limited. What we truly need to do is
record movies during reaction conditions
where we can see what the atoms are
actually doing. So these two um are
series of stills um of uh some some
different materials reactions. The first
one growth of germanmanium on silicon.
Uh the second one is a battery electrode
effectively during uh cycling uh where
you can see the initiation of dendritic
structures. You know how bad those are
for battery performance. So these are
stills this is a real-time movie of a
catalyst under its reaction conditions.
So we don't just want to take pictures.
We want to record movies and we want to
expose our sample to the correct um
conditions that will allow us to
replicate real life and understand
what's going on. So uh how do we do
this? The technique is called
environmental transmission electron
microscopy. So environmental simply
means that we put the sample into an
environment that we control rather than
the environment that the microscope
manufacturer chose for us which is a
vacuum so that when the electrons pass
through the microscope they don't
scatter off any gas molecules during
their passage. So an environmental
transmission electron microscope can
take many forms depending on the type of
experiment you want to do. And I'm
showing you our original environmental
transmission electron microscope, which
is really a case where the microscope is
a tiny part of a huge system that allows
us to do complex experiments. So the
microscope is just this little piece
here, right? So that that's where the
the electrons come out of a gun up here.
They get accelerated to 300,000 volts.
That gives them very short wavelengths
that allows them to resolve where the
atoms are in the material. They pass
through some lenses. Uh there's a
viewing screen. This is an old
microscope. You could look at it with
your sit at it and look down onto the
screen and see what's going on. The
signal gets sent to a computer hidden
away behind here. But this microscope is
really part of a huge materials
preparation, cleaning, synthesis,
calibration uh setup where we can insert
a sample which is mounted on a cartridge
like this. The sample is a tiny little
chip. Uh typically has to be thin. So
the electrons will go through it. Um and
it's placed on the cartridge. The
cartridge is loaded into the load lock.
Uh the load lock is connected to a load
of other places all under controlled
vacuum so that you can um process your
sample without it getting uh random
contamination from the air. and then
when you're ready, put it in the
microscope and then record a movie as
you flow a gas or deposit a material or
heat it up or flow a current through
your sample. So, a very flexible tool
for doing a whole lot of different
experiments. Um, I show I I wanted to
show you that older microscope because
the modern microscopes look a lot less
interesting, right? They're hidden in a
box. All the good stuff is inside the
box. This one's open so you can see the
microscope but um here you can see the
little bit of extra stuff that we added
um so that we can do preparation. So
these are based on modernday uh static
electron microscopes but with this
addition of capabilities that you can do
to modify your sample while you watch
it. Um and I have to say that electron
microscopy is a joy to work in because
the field is advancing uh in all
respects. Uh the imaging performance
gets better, the way we can handle the
data, the types of processing, the
detectors are improving, the stability,
a lot of um of uh use of of of um AI
type tools to improve what we can do so
that you're no longer limited, for
example, by how good the operator is.
you can have the microscope kind of run
itself. Right? So that's the kind of
preamble to what we wanted to do. And
now I'd like to show you some examples
uh from the real world that hopefully
give you a sense of what sorts of things
we problems we can address using this
techniques. And I want to start with
catalysis because this is really one of
those fun things where it's very clear
that what you think about catalysts
doesn't reflect what they're actually
doing while they are working uh at their
job. So this is platinum on carbon. The
platinum shows up as the little white
dots, the carbon as the kind of fuzzy
gray background. And as you uh probably
uh know, this is very this is kind of a
model catalyst system. The um the
catalytic converter in your car will
fundamentally have the same structure.
There'll be some little metal nano
particles just consisting of a few maybe
thousand of metal atoms. they'll be
supported on some kind of a a support
and as the gas flows over those
particles, they will um change the the
um energy balance of reactions that take
that you'd like to take place uh and
thereby for example uh take the CO out
of your exhaust stream. So um here's an
example of one of these prototypical
catalysts and what you can see in the
movie. Well firstly there's there's
three pictures there's two pictures
recorded simultaneously. So the
microscope is able to show us the image
that the movie that's recorded by
electrons that pass right through the
sample. So in that case you can imagine
platinum's very heavy carbon's pretty
light. um the electrons when they hit a
platinum particle, they're going to get
scattered a lot more than if they merely
hit some carbon. So the platinum in
these images shows up as the bright
spots and the carbon as the dark. You
can hardly see it in fact against the
background. This image though, the last
image is a surface sensitive image that
is recorded by looking at the electrons
that come off the surface of the sample,
low energy electrons. So effectively
scanning electron microscopy. So it's
sensitive to the surface rather than
what goes on inside. And you can see the
complimementaryary information that
comes out of this stuff. So looking
inside, we see the particles move around
during catalysis. They move. They're
energetic. There's a lot of temperature.
There's there's energy going around. The
particles simply move around. When two
of them collide, they make a larger
particle. The surface area decreases.
The catalyst loses its power because it
depends on surface energy. And that's
why you get the annoying light in the
car that says replace the catalytic
converter. And that's a a lot of money
to do that. And that's this is why you
have to do that, right? But what you can
see from this movie is that not it's not
just the surface is not merely a passive
place for those particles to sit. You
can see, especially in this one, I love
it. Um the particles actually digging
itself a little channel. the platinum's
reacting with the carbon support under
the reaction conditions and is actually
uh degrading catalyzing the degradation
of the support. So what can we learn
from this kind of thing? You can't tell
how something's going to behave if you
simply look at it before and after. You
have to really see what's going on
during the reaction in order to fully
understand the important uh phenomena
that are at play in in the process you
want to optimize.
Let me show you a more complex catalytic
particle because after all if you had to
use pure platinum things would be
extremely expensive. So it's a very
common strategy to um to cut the
platinum with some other lowerc cost
material. And so here's an example uh of
such a a bi metallic catalyst. This one
happens to be a mixture of ruinium and
iron. So we have a kind of lowcost iron
that works with a higher cost runium in
order to catalyze um reverse water gas
shift reaction and you can see
conventional microscopy of these
particles can tell us which atom is
where and how they arranged
crystalraphically within the particles.
But let's do some environmental electron
microscopy. When we first form these
particles, they're formed in a solution
phase. They they form as these beautiful
core shell particles and this is just
because of the kinetics of how they
form. The runium precipitates first in
the solution then the iron around the
outside. So the first thing you do with
these particles after you've made them
is you oxidize them and then you start
to use them for catalysis. Um this is
the first oxidation step and you can see
the dramatic change in the morphology
and the composition of the particles.
They start with the ruthenium core and
these are the transmitted images. You
see the core is becoming kind of
confused and eventually there's no
apparent core left. The ruthenium is
scattered throughout the oxidized iron
and you can see from the surface
sensitive images how the particles
they've actually centered together and
we've got faceting on the surface. So
this is like step one of making these
catalytic particles. And let's see what
happens now when we use them as
catalysts. Um we're effectively
oxidizing and reducing them under the
catalytic conditions. And what you can
see is a dramatic change in the uh
structure and the chemical like
distribution of the elements. So after
you oxidize sorry after you reduce them
expose them to hydrogen in the
microscope we see the formation of
little particles. Um our surface
sensitive imaging tells us those are
actually on the top surface not inside.
Uh compositional mapping tells them that
tells us that they're made of ruthenium.
Um so reduction creates this this type
of morphology. Oxidation turns it back
into the more uniform thing that I
showed you before. And we can correlate
these structural changes with the
composite with the performance of these
particles when in their catalytic job.
So we can truly relate the atomic
positions and configurations
w to the um to the properties of the
material and we can we can thereby gain
information about what does it take for
example to regenerate the catalysts.
Given time they um lose their catalytic
ability. a reduction oxidation cycle
will regenerate the performance of the
catalyst which is due to the uh presence
of these little particles on the
surface. So catalysis is one of those
fields where you really need to know
where the atoms are in order to
understand what's going on and not just
where they are but where they are during
the catalytic reaction. Now I want to
switch gears to micro electronics
because this is another area where I
feel that there's a lot to contribute
from understanding how atoms move around
during both processing and operation of
micro electronic devices. So as you know
uh a lot of energy in modern micro
electronics design is to do with
integrating new materials that maybe
have better performance than the
conventional silicon and silicon dioxide
as the semiconductor and the dialectric
material. Um and so you could replace
the dialectric with more useful oxides
like halfneium oxide. Um you could
replace the semiconductor silicon with
some of the new 2D layered
semiconductors like for example
malibdinum dulfide a perfectly good
semiconductor that forms as layers and
thereby naturally is kind of suited for
making very thin sheets of
semiconducting material. So you still
need now you know the whole momentum of
the micro electronics industry over many
decades has been how do we optimize
siliconbased micro electronics. So we're
not simply going to say oh this material
performs better in this little respect.
Let's just switch everything over. You
have to uh work out manufacturable ways
to do all of the processing steps that
would be required if we were to use that
one material. So as an example in the
case of malibdinum dulfide it's a
semiconductor we need to make a good
junction between it and an insulating
layer to use it in electronic devices
and one way to do that is to try and
oxidize it. This is how we make the
silicon oxide uh dialectric layer that's
used in in in micro electronics. Um and
so we can use the uh insitue microscope
to examine things like the oxidation of
these layered materials and work out the
conditions where you get useful or uh or
useless types of oxide. And this this I
put it in because it's beautiful. But
this is the worst possible uh
configuration because you can see the
oxide is these little lines, right? you
want a uniform layer of oxide but
instead we get these little needles and
we can understand why they form by
seeing the atomic motions that create
them. We can also operate our electronic
devices. Uh you can pass a current
through a neuromorphic material and you
can look at the way that the
conductivity of that material changes to
give it its uh specific types of
properties. um and those changes in
conductivity are associated with atomic
configuration changes such as
crystallization. So I don't want to talk
about those two things in any depth. Um
I because I' I'd like to give a more of
a sense of the breadth of um this this
concept of relating structure to
properties using environmental
microscopy. Um this slide shows some
contact materials for future micro
electronics. you got to get the current
in and out of the device. Um, in
conventional micro electronics, we use
gold as the conductor. Um, and we maybe
use a titanium layer to glue the gold
onto whatever material it's supposed to
be sending the electrons uh into. Um,
this is an example of a gold and
titanium uh billayer grown on graphine.
Uh, we need to make these electrical
connections with 2D materials like
graphine. uh we can explore how titanium
and gold deposit on graphine in this
case in a beautiful epitaxial
arrangement where each of the three
layers the graphine the titanium and the
gold is perfectly crystalline and all
those crystals are aligned with each
other that's how um the microscopist
look at that and say oh yeah I see that
contrast that means all the atoms are
aligned I do a diffraction pattern I see
the same thing um you can explore how
this depends on the deposition
conditions And you can explore things
like the thermal stability. We obviously
need our contacts to stay unchanged even
if the device gets a little bit hot. Um
this is a contact material for one of
these 2D semiconductors. U and you can
see the beautiful atomic structure of
bismouth on MOS2. uh in in the in the
images
we can um also look at ways to create
the actual structures that are used
within the microeleronic devices. So I'm
showing you here a video of a nanowire
being grown using a catalytic particle.
So this is one of my favorite reactions
to do in the microscope. Um we would
like to create nanoructures. We
understand that conventional lithography
has limitations. As we try and scale
down and down and down, it gets
increasingly difficult to control the um
the the the dimensions, the sidewall
smoothness, the crystallinity, the
perfection of the of the objects that
you're trying to create. So, can we
instead use a self assembly process
where the material spontaneously forms
in the structure that you would like?
And this is exactly the strategy that
Rob showed in his talk to assemble
larger objects uh in this case little
spherical particles into these large
arrays that would have photonic uh
optical properties. So in this case I'm
I'm asking can we assemble silicon atoms
into a little post that we might use for
example for a gate allaround um
transistor. So how would we do that? We
would supply silicon.
We would use a catalyst, this big
droplet of liquid, and the catalyst
would um would cat would increase the
growth rate of the silicon just at this
place um while not really enhancing the
growth rate on the sides. So everything
that happens happens at the end. Um I'm
going to have to start it off again.
Come on, let's do it. Okay, look really
closely. You see the little jumps,
right? Little jumps on this video. Um,
each one of these jumps is one layer of
silicon atoms being added from the vapor
phase through the liquid onto the
surface. And to show it more, I'm going
to show the middle of that movie, the
middle section strip. And look at it.
Nothing happens for a long time. Each
one of those lines is a layer of atoms.
Then suddenly whole layer, right? Forms
all at once. Um and we can look at this
kind of kinetics and we can model the
physics of the process that goes on. The
silicon atoms come down from the gas
phase. They land on the surface of the
liquid drop which is very accommodating
because it's an amorphous liquid. So
they stick very effectively. They
diffuse through the droplet. They get
super saturated. There's too many
silicon atoms dissolved in the liquid.
They got to precipitate somewhere. And
once a few of them precipitate, the rest
of them follow along rapidly within one
movie frame. The whole layer is
complete. And then you have to wait and
refill the droplets. So you get this
kind of kind of uh interrupted growth.
Really interesting. So we can use this
type of knowledge of the physics of this
self assembly process to optimize it. As
an example, we turn off the silicon gas.
We want to turn on some germananium and
then we can make a hetroructure like
this. silicon germanmanium layers in a
sequence with appropriate electronic
properties. So only by watching this
thing happen can you figure out how it
works. Once you finish growth, cool it
down, take it out of the microscope, it
it gets some oxygen, it oxidizes.
There's no chance then of understanding
what truly happens at the interface
during growth. So, we have the real
power of looking into the materials as
they um as they actually grow. Right?
Here's another example of that. Look at
this little jumpy movie. See the little
lines forming? Ignore the big fuzzy
stuff, but see the little lines that
that look like that? If we mag if we
took a tiny bit of that and blew it up,
it would look like this. So, we're
forming hydrides in titanium here, which
is of course a really important um
process in for example um oil and gas
industry. you want to worry about where
does the hydrogen go into in those
pipelines. This is a little bit of a
model of how hydrogen uh goes into uh
titanium and rearranges its crystal
structure. And you can see from the from
the um like the kinetics of these
reactions how it something about how it
actually happens. Right?
So, um, I talked a lot about exposing
our samples to gases, heating them up,
passing a current through them, forcing
them to change in some way, but I want
to, um, show you a couple of other ways
that we can, uh, create useful, uh,
information using these types of
experiments. And the first example I
want to show you is to do with defect
engineering to create uh, quantum
materials. So this um so the electron
beam is very can be very small. It has
very powerful it's high energy a few
hundred um kilo electron volts are used
to accelerate our electrons and can be
directed to specific locations on the
sample. Now there's very few materials
that are not affected by the electron
beam. Uh indeed the environment in terms
of radiation for a te for a sample in a
microscope is worse than being at the
wall of a nuclear reactor. So it's
actually pretty unfriendly and that's
why we often don't do organic things
like what Rob showed you because they
would just get fried completely in a
moment. They would they would just get
destroyed by the electron beam. However,
this can be useful in some context and
this is a an example where we're
creating specific kinds of defects by
placing the electron beam on one column
of atoms in a very well-aligned crystal.
So, the crystal is a another one of
these layered materials. They're so
useful in in many uh respects. Um the
layers are made up of chromium, sulfur,
and bromine. And then in between them is
a little gap, Vanderval's gap. If you
hit the chromium atoms with the electron
beam, they will move. They don't get
thrown out of the crystal. They just
move a little bit sideways, a little bit
down, and they end up in the gap between
the layers. And so this drawing is an
attempt to show that. Here's all the
layers in the crystal. Um, here's where
the electron beam came down. And you can
see these atoms, chromium, got moved to
the space in between the layers. I hope
that makes sense. This is a view, a
perspective view. This is the view from
the top after we've done that in all
these locations. So, in each case, we
hit that black I can't even do it. My
hand's not steady enough here. Right,
that black spot is where we hit it with
the electron beam. It's black because
the atoms moved away from that place.
And the adjacent regions are bright
because that's where the atoms went. So
what we've created is a perfectly
engineered defect within this crystal.
These particular defects
have properties very much like the
nitrogen vacancy defect in diamond which
um as you may know is one of the
fundamental building blocks proposed for
quantum devices. Those uh are they exist
in um in materials where the electronic
properties are such that if you make a
defect, you've created some additional
energy levels that were not there
before. And you can have uh energy, you
can have electrons jumping between these
energy levels and as they change energy
giving out or absorbing photons and use
that photon to communicate with another
defect. But in with with
spontaneous defects like the nitrogen
vacancy defect, you have no control over
where they are. You can't put them
specifically close to each other. You
can't make a beautiful array. Using the
electron microscope, you can create
arbitrary arrays rather quickly of
quantum active defects within materials.
And I think the possibilities of this
kind of um of uh material engineering
are really impressive. Um I'm showing a
couple. Do you see the difference?
Right, this one's got like up and down
defects and this one's got left and
right defects just by changing the how
the beam patterns the material and they
have different electronic properties.
You can mix them. You can do do it how
you like. Okay. So, no, I haven't
finished yet. Okay, there's more.
There's more. All right. So, so we've
moved from quantum materials to to
batteries. And this is the last example
I'm going to show uh of one of these
types of experiments. This is charge
discharge of an electrode and it's not a
real battery. It's illustrating the
point because it's my favorite movie. Uh
the electrode is here. Electro is made
of graphine. Um the liquid electrolyte
is above the um the the um sample and uh
we're looking through the whole thing.
So we can do this liquid by uh we can do
we can do experiments in liquids by
trapping the liquid between two very
thin windows and we can then shine the
electrons through the whole thing and do
this type of of um of uh electrochemical
stimulus that will um that will
replicate what happens in a battery. So
I want to conclude with just a couple of
quick uh comments. Um materials uh you
know when I started doing microscopy I
thought silicon was my favorite element.
Everything should be just silicon
experiments. What I've learned is that
there are so many different problems out
in the world. Microscopy is developing
into a really high performance technique
that can study important reactions. Uh
and just for a little flavor of what I
think will happen in the future, we can
address things like uh the reactions
that take place during cement
processing, hydration and carbonation.
Uh trying to understand how to optimize
the CO2 like footprint of of uh of
cement reactions. This is an example of
calcium oxide, one of the relevant
materials in the lime cycle created
within the microscope by uh by um
heating carbon calcium carbonate um in
in in situ. Um those are the atoms by
the way. Those are the calcium atoms
arranged in their little little cubicle
structure. Beautiful. Um uh oxidation
and reduction of iron. This is
geological hydrogen uh production where
you uh you pass water over ironbearing
minerals and the reduction of the iron
is responsible for creating hydrogen. We
can look at these reactions in situ. And
finally um I didn't really say but it's
obvious these are difficult things to
do. There's a lot of work required for
each experiment. throughput is a
challenge and so uh new techniques for
carrying out a lot of little experiments
not in parallel but sequentially can
give us the kind of information we need
to really understand reactions. So I've
shown the work of many colleagues at MIT
and elsewhere. I'd like to acknowledge
what they've all done and thank our
funding agencies. And uh just to
conclude by saying that um we get a
really good insight into what happens
during materials reactions. Uh we can
study a huge range of materials and
processes and we continue to develop um
the instrumental capabilities that will
allow us to make this even more relevant
in the future to a wider range of
materials problems. All right, thanks
for your attention.
Thank you, Francis. Uh, fascinating
pictures of these reaction mechanisms.
Really,
>> any questions? We probably have time for
one or two.
>> Yeah, go ahead.
>> Uh, I wonder if you can say more about,
you know, cement production and property
changes or improvement. Um I can't say
too much because this is something that
we've started fairly recently. But one
thing we can do is we can um we can do
we can um do some of the fundamental
reactions on single component materials.
So let's say um calcium carbonate,
calcium oxide, calcium hydroxide. these
three materials related by um for
example heating in water vapor or CO2 or
oxygen. Um you can observe the atomic
level reaction that takes place and some
of the important things here are does
the volume change? Does the reaction get
limited by distance as it progresses
into the crystals? This will tell us how
what the mechanisms are and how we can
optimize them. Now real cement of course
has has many components and they tend to
work synergistically together. So the
key thing will be to start with um a
specific component of cement like a and
then understand how it reacts with water
or carbon dioxide and then look at if we
combine them how what's the synergy
between the different components. So I I
put this up as a like you know this is
something that I think would be very
important in understanding how the final
microructure is a result of the
processing as all these little crystals
form and interlock together to generate
the strain the the the mechanical
properties and then functionalizing
cement for example by putting uh
conductive elements in it and using it
for energy storage. That's a new um
that's a new concept that I think could
benefit from understanding. You know,
you can you can build something and it
works, but if you want to improve it,
you want to see how how the atomic level
um reactions contribute to it. So,
thanks. Great question.
>> Excellent. Let's thank Francis again.
Thank you.