the organs and tissues of organisms
large and small are made of cells cells
are like building blocks stacking and
connecting in three dimensions to build
up the structures that make a heart a
heart a muscle a muscle a liver a liver
and so on for almost 400 years
scientists have used microscopes to
learn how cells fit together within
tissues in the last two decades
Technologies like DNA and RNA sequencing
have also taught scientists a lot about
how cells work and thanks to a
technology called single cell RNA
sequencing scientists are even learning
what makes individual cells within the
same organ unique and see how cells that
look similar under a microscope can be
vastly different at the molecular and
genetic level the thing is for something
like single cell RNA sequencing to work
scientists have to break a tissue up
into its individual cells that means
that they lose any sense of where a
given cell was and who it was sitting
next to in a tissue all that spatial
information is lost which is a huge
problem because a cell's location in a
tissue or organ is really important it
influences what the cell does what state
it's in which cells it interacts with
and the signals it picks up from its
surroundings this is where a new family
of Technologies called spatial omix
comes in an area of research for
exploring the molecular composition of
cells within their native tissue some
spatial omix methods use unique bits of
DNA to pinpoint cell's locations within
a sample before breaking it up others
can even individually sequence every
cell in a tissue without breaking it up
at all either way spatial omix goes
beyond traditional microscopy and
sequencing Technologies which help
scientists better understand how organs
and tissues work map complex organs like
the brain in Greater detail learn what
goes on in Cancers and other diseases
and see how small changes in single
cells can have a big impact on biology
health and disease