All right. It is the last session. You
have survived the first day almost.
And
I'm really excited about this session uh
because we started the day we started
the day looking at the planetary scale
and
honestly from a little bit of a a
slightly grim perspective. I don't think
anyone left that session feeling really
light and excited about the state of the
world.
Um so now we proceeded to talk about
people because no change happens without
people and then about what people can do
in set rules policy and now we are going
to go ahead and go back to the scale
question but from the perspective
of with people with technology with
ideas with rules
what can we accomplish?
Um, so I hope we're going to end the day
with a lot of excitement. Um, and we
also have two um relatively new friends
of mine who I deeply admire and I'm
excited to have joining us. Both not
present. So we have two videos
sandwiching our our session today. Um,
and I am going to start with one uh the
growth of gens in Europe. Sanjie Kumar
is joining us I believe. Are you in
Brussels Sanjie? Yes, I am. Lovely.
Lovely evening in Brussels. You're
>> you lovely to see you up there.
>> Uh and I am going to ask you to
introduce yourself to everyone and then
go ahead and proceed with your
presentation.
>> Brilliant. Thank you. Thank you so much
Z. Firstly for the kind introduction and
for the the opportunity to come and uh
talk to everybody in the room. Um my
name is Sanjikuma.
I'm the head of policy at the European
Geothermal Energy Council, which means
that my role is to really grow markets
for geothermal across Europe. Um, that's
the European Union, but also countries
outside such as, um, uh, Iceland,
Norway, uh, down to Turkey, the Western
Balkans, and Ukraine. So, I look at what
are the regulatory frameworks, what are
the financial structures that we need to
grow geothermal. And what I'm going to
do is kind of share some of the
experiences that we've had in Europe.
Um, let me start off with some pretty uh
basic uh things about uh the kind of the
content of Europe. Um, and then I'm
going to kind of give you some ideas
about how you can perhaps build upon the
session that you've had before the
discussions you've had uh this morning
and then the discussions you're going to
have um uh tomorrow. So let's start off
with some basics. uh there about Europe
is uh generally um our um heat gradient
is quite low. We have lower temperatures
so we don't have a lot of power
generation. Uh what we do have is a lot
of heating. Um our market is geared
towards heating and that heat market is
transitioning. As it stands at the
moment there are about 10 million people
across Europe who benefit from different
types of geothermal heat pumps. These
are small uh closed loop systems to uh
large openloop systems. uh we have
district heating uh direct use um and
that's really for uh cities. We also in
a few countries have a lot of district
heating systems just for the agriculture
community. So when it comes to thinking
about your your doing new kind of
customer base I know a lot of the
conversation is going to be around
residential consumers. There is a whole
world outside the residential space. Um
and people like farmers we found in
Europe are very very vocal and generally
tend to get their own way. So and they
have a desire to have a permanent supply
of heating and cooling. So it's a
fantastic customer base. Factories.
There's some of the big car makers in
Europe have just uh uh installed
geothermal heating and cooling systems
um uh for their uh for their factories,
for their head offices. It's it's really
big. And of course, we've got 11 million
consumers tapped into geothermal power.
Um, but what I want to do is just to
deep dive a little bit into what the
situation in Europe is, why it's perhaps
different to the US, but the challenges
that we face are the same challenges
that you're going to face as you start
to scale up uh geothermal in particular,
especially network geothermal. So, let's
start off with some basics. Um like
everywhere else in the world, the bulk
of our heating and cooling supply is
fossilbased. Um where we have
non-fossilbased heating cooling, it's
largely coming from combustible biomass.
Um and over the last five or six years,
there's been a quite a ugly discussion
around toning down the amount of biomass
uh to just focusing on that can be that
which can be sustainably sourced. And
what that's effectively done is put a
ceiling on the amount of biomass we're
going to use uh in heating. So the
growth market that they've had in the
past is going to start to diminish. And
what that's really doing is it's kind of
paving the way for um heat pumps um and
for kind of direct use geothermal. And
when we talk about heat pumps in a
European context, almost everybody
thinks of airsource heat pumps. So the
language that we use to describe uh
electric heating with uh ground source
heat pumps, geothermal heat pumps is
something we're going to come back to
later on. We also have a legacy system
of district heating. So, a lot of these
are in former Soviet countries, but you
also have them in Baltic places, sorry,
in the Scandinavian countries such as
Denmark um and Finland um uh where you
have effectively heat networks that were
built on the back of a a coal plant, a
gas plant or a waste incineration plant,
and you take the excess heat and you
pump it at high temperatures at vast
quantities through um a network. Um
these are extremely inefficient. They're
very very polluting. And what's been
happening over the last 20 years is that
people have just been jumping using uh
things like airsource heat pumps,
geothermal heat pumps to get themselves
off of these district heating systems.
So this industry has a tarnished
reputation. But if we're serious about
decarbonization, we're going to have to
rethink uh district heating and cooling
systems. And this becomes really
important to you. So it's within that
context of a multitude of supplies. um
renewable energies incumbent fossils
that network geothermal has to operate
in. So that's our competition base. Um
the other thing which is quite important
to us and will become an issue for you
later on um is the fact that we have a
largely densely populated uh
geographical spaces. So we don't have
vast lands in which we can do drilling
and great uh um uh big uh uh uh
networks. we have to operate in tightly
confined spaces. Um, and environmental
protection is absolutely key. And what
we found is is that as the geothermal
sector grows, the regulators,
particularly those that are looking at
protecting water,
drinking water, surface water, those
that are very very nervous about uh kind
of geothermal activities around them,
but also are very concerned and are
driven by the perception of negative
impacts. This has in some cases slowed
down a lot of growth that we've seen in
in some of the the really advancing
countries such as the Netherlands where
now it's much harder to for us to get a
permit. So permitting becomes an issue
once you start to see a a reasonable
size of growth um within uh your
geothermal systems. The other two things
from this one um is that when we often
talk about geothermal in a European
context, you can see from the three uh
different types of uh geothermal heat
pumps that we tend to focus on the first
two. Um so vertical ball holds or uh two
vertical ball holds linked to a
hydrothermal source. The the the example
that you have at the end with a loop
that's quite shallow, there's just not
enough space for that to really operate
in a European context. So that means
that we are looking at deeper pipes of
drilling much more sophisticated
uh and access to land that becomes more
important as well as being able to get
drilling rigs into uh people's gardens
or whole uh down streets. One of the
other things that's happened is in a few
countries where the market has started
to grow and it hasn't been regulated. Um
we've had the issue of thermal
interference where people have been kind
of installing geothermal heat pumps in
their back gardens but they're too close
to somebody else's back garden and what
you do then is they install a heat pump
a geothermal heat pump and you're
effectively diminishing the the overall
thermal efficiency of that one. there's
le lawsuits in Ireland uh for example it
kind of again dampened down uh the
growth in that market. So these are the
kind of things that you're going to have
to start to think through and for us the
the the most important issue becomes
permitting. Um you can see from the the
map at the bottom that's a map of France
at a 100 meter depth. um all the areas
where if you're going to install a
geothermal heat pump, the zones in
green, you just have to do a simple
email to your local government just to
say, "Hey, this is where I'm installing
my uh ball hole. Uh this is how this is
the kind of depth it's going to be. Um
and this is the kind of the geoloccation
as possibly
get it. Um and then that can be noted
somewhere in a registry so that later on
in maybe 1015 years time if somebody
else wants to plot something they can
very quickly check and see if there's
going to be any kind of uh negative
impact on any additional systems coming
on. Then you have orange areas. Orange
areas are sensitive subsurface activity
and you need to get some form of an
external recognition. Again this is for
like a 100 m 200 m depth. there needs to
be some form of third party assessment.
And then the red areas are really where
you need to have a full environmental
impact assessment. They're very
sensitive areas. Um and you can see that
the what the kind of the the
congregation of red dots um uh on the um
on the eastern part of France is the
Alsas region and the Alsas region is a
volcanic uh region. There have been
examples where people have drilled uh uh
geothermal heat pumps and in one case
actually uh damaged eight or nine
properties within a village and that led
to a variety of lawsuits um and really
did give a negative impression to
geothermal even though France is one of
those countries that's really gung-ho um
in our SAS the mayor of ours all of them
don't like geothermal and they lump all
geothermal into this uh basket so we
need to be very very sensitive around
the environmental impacts as your market
starts to grow. Um, just a kind of quick
thing, I I noticed you might not be able
to see this graphic clearly, but you can
blow up the screen when you get the the
slides. Uh, Sweden is the largest
country in terms of installed capacity.
Germany second, uh, France is third. But
really, the countries to look at if
you're going to look at them are
Belgium, the Netherlands, and Poland.
These these really have grown uh roughly
over the last decade. is a new entrance
and that that's where all the innovation
is happening and part of the innovation
story in a country like Belgium is
around network geos. I'm going to come
on to that later on as to why that's the
case. Um and then what you can see here
is is on the figure 14 is the kind of
the density of heat pumps uh per
thousand households. So again Sweden is
the most populous country. In Sweden,
home buyers generally tend to look at
five criteria uh when they're purchasing
a new property, and a geothermal heat
pump is normally the fourth orif fifth
thing that they look at. Um before the
construction industry collapsed in
around 2000 2020, um geothermal houses
with geothermal heat pumps sold for 12
to 15,000 euros more than houses that
didn't. Um, so there was a clear
recognition in a mature market that this
really does add value to your property.
Um, we haven't quite seen that in other
countries, but as they start to grow and
they become much more populous, we
expect this to be the Estonia to be the
next big country. Um, where you've got a
lot of geothermal heat pumps in there.
Um now what's happened is is that you've
had kind of conventional story around
district heating and uh um uh geothermal
heat pumps and then out of nowhere
network GFL came onto the scene and they
were young and sexy and fresh and
everyone's like oh my god I need to have
this. Um but this has come uh really
from three uh angles. So the first angle
is is that district heating, you had a
lot of people leaving district heating
systems and what you started to find is
that they were in communities and once
you start to take a community off a
district heating system, the overall
cost profile and the efficiency of that
district heating system become a
problem. Um so it's it's caused negative
tension with the district heating
community. On the other hand, you've had
lots of uh people who were looking at
doing their own individual installation
and then they suddenly realized well
actually we can band together and create
a community energy scheme. And in a
country like Belgium, community energy
is really the thing that's driving uh
this push towards network geothermal.
It's not just communities. It's, you
know, property developers. It's rural
communities. It's a variety of people
just saying, "Look, it makes sense for
us to work together to build a common
infrastructure because then it's so much
cheaper." And just for full disclosure,
I'm trying to set one up in my street. I
live opposite the school. I want the
school to to have all the bore holes and
for us to pay a small fee to connect to
their system. I've got um of uh of the
72 uh houses in my uh uh in my my two
blocks, we've got 30. so far who were
keen. We need to get everyone else on
board and then we need to lobby the
school to agree to do this one and get
some way in which we can finance it. But
you know individual installations are
not the default option anymore. People
want to be part of a um a collective
system. It's part of the normalization
of the technology as well. And then the
third element and I'm going to spend a
bit of time on this later on is the
planning aspect because Europe has been
heavily dependent upon imported gas and
the crisis that happened after Ukraine
was invaded. Uh the kind of response was
saying okay well we need to make someone
responsible for planning a transition.
Um and you know whilst you'll have all
the kind of campaigners saying look the
revolution is going to be exciting.
We're going to be manning the
barricades. It's not true. The energy
revolution is all about logistics and
planning and finance. That's all it is.
Um I can see Hela smiling K
on this point, but it really is that
pedantic. You need to know, you need to
get out maps of streets and start
working out well actually what parts can
we convert quickly who goes first, who
goes second, who goes third. But more
importantly, who makes those decisions?
So let me give you some examples to kind
of illustrate this transition. and and
Sanjie, I'm gonna I'm gonna briefly say
because you're on the screen that um a
couple minutes for the examples would be
wonderful. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, no, I I'm gonna race
through these ones. In fact, I'll just
give you one example here. Enfield
Council, this is a local authority. They
converted to geothermal not because they
loved their network geothermal, but
because their uh the people who were
living in the four tower blocks, you can
see two of them behind you. they were
massively massively indebted in terms of
their energy costs. So they had a social
political crisis. Um they looked at all
sorts of options and opted for network
geothermal. Instead of refurbishing one
building and one building block by by
block, what they decided to do was all
four of them in one go. And then you got
the real system efficiencies kicking
through. And you can see the savings,
you know, between 450 to 700 pounds per
year uh depending on the residents. to
the energy consumption within those
buildings. This is my favorite project
simply because this is in the heart of
Brussels and it proves that where you
have listed buildings, you can actually
do geothermal projects and that's part
of the sexy thing about it and that's
really where network geothermal has
kicked off in Brussels. Our SPA hospital
is a 16th century uh site. You cannot
touch this building place at all.
There's a huge complex of uh uh schools.
It's a UNUSCO heritage site. geothermal
was the only option and rather than
doing individual ground source heat
pumps creating the heat network was
really where you got the system
efficiencies coming through the biggest
project in Spain this is really what I
want to talk to you about couple of
things policy matters now um what's
absolutely essential is that even if
geothermal isn't mentioned in the first
round of policy once you start to get
people thinking about what zero looks
like what a fully renewable system uh uh
uh uh could be they'll almost always
come and discover geothermal and then
they'll start complaining by saying why
didn't you tell us this existed before
and what happened in Wunia which is a
small part of Belgium um is they
invested just put 35 million euros up
front for some very basic grants they
did a lot of iconic projects but more
importantly you had Carlo the energy
company all of a sudden become a
national champion in network geothermal
and Resiolia who were the engineering
design company are now winning contracts
all across Europe so there's an
industrial policy story more than just
the energy savings but what I said
earlier the planning bit is absolutely
essential and the two key things in the
planning bit is to make sure that
whenever you're conducting a plan it has
to be based on local renewable energy
supplies if you take those two words out
of it you will end up with you know
biomass you'll end up with a variety of
you know Frankenstein solutions if you
want to keep it towards geothermal
you've got to focus on the locality and
the renewable aspect around it But
really what's super pertinent around
this is the the fact that words matter.
So when we describe uh network
geothermal, the reason why we'd say
network geothermal and not fifth
generation district heating or network
uh uh uh sorry heat pump networks is
that they don't have the word geothermal
in. And if you don't have the word
geothermal, you're going to miss all of
the things that you need to go through
to get to the network geothermal system.
Always focus on who makes the
investment. So in the some of the
examples I've showed you, it's the local
government, it's a community, it's a
property developer, their needs are
completely different, but the way in
which they access finance is also
completely different. So it changes the
gambit. Um business models are the most
important thing. It's not about can you
do the project, it's about how do you
make it profitable for everybody and
that's where the innovation around you
know whether you have an onbalance or
offbalance sheet. um what's the size and
the length of the project? How do you
build in the modules? How do you kind of
seg uh disagregate the different prices
that people pay? This is the most
important thing when it comes to
designing a system at scale.
Uh super important drilling is sexy. So
whilst everyone talks about the energy
savings, the greenhouse gas emission
reductions, that's great, but in the
geothermal world, once you've done an
installation, you will not see
geothermal ever again. apart from two
black pipes coming out into a into your
heat pump.
>> So, the drilling bit is where you get
people attracted.
>> Two more things, super important. You've
got to have more and more people
providing the service of uh designing
and install installation. The more you
do that, the more competitive the price
becomes, the more you start to get
suppliers chasing markets. And this is
really the space we want to get to. And
then the final thing is is that whilst
we talk about the energy service
delivery, the real political win is an
industrial policy. Can you set up
manufacturing uh uh any part of the
component features? Can you create
companies with design experts or
training experts or drilling experts?
That's where you get the real value for
money. That's where the competitions
really start to wake up. So on that
note, think global,
think global, go.
[Laughter]
>> Thank you. Thank you, Sanjief. And I I I
see that you uh your previous slide you
apparently agree with our
administration's drill baby drill. Um
so thank you for covering so much.