in this video we'll look at an
application of the probabilistic method
to graph
Theory an independent set in a graph is
a subset of vertices with no two
adjacent for example if the graph is
this cycle on four vertices
an example of an independent set would
be two vertices like this and these two
vertices do not uh none these two
vertices are not adjacent to each
other whereas had I chosen two vertices
on the same Edge that would not be an
independent
set so important question in many in
graph theory is given the graph what can
you say about the size of its
independent sets
the following theorem due to Kon way
says that every graph G contains a large
independent set in the following sense
contains an independent set of size at
least the following quantity summing
over o v among vertices in
G one over the degree of V +
one
okay so this let let us prove this
theorem first and then we'll see an
application and some ways to interpret
this
result the proof of this theorem applies
the probabilistic
method okay so we are given this graph
G and the first thing we'll do is
order the vertices of
g uniformly at random
so consider a random permutation of the
vertices of
G and
let's consider the set I of
vertices def find as
follows these are the vertices in G such
that V
appears before
all its
neighbors
in the random
ordering okay for example from the graph
earlier had we ordered the
vertices in this order so that's say
some random ordering so let's order the
vertices is 1 2 3 and four okay so the
edges are 1 to 2 2 to
4 3 to 4 and 1 to
three what I would pick out is a set of
vertices such
that okay okay so let's see if each
vertex would belong to I the first
vertex appears before all of its
neighbors so we put the first vertex in
I the second ver vertex does not appear
before one of its neighbors one so we do
not put it in I and the third vertex
here also does not appear before its
neighbor and we don't put it in I and
the fourth vertex likewise does not
appear before all of its neighbors and
we do not put it in is well so in this
case this set picks up only the first
vertex but in more complicated graphs it
can pick up additional vertices
I claim
that I is
always an independent
set indeed it will be impossible to have
two vertices in I that are adjacent to
each other because one of them would
appear before the other in the order and
that would violate the condition on how
we chose
I next let's think about how large I is
for
every vertex V in
G the
probability that
V is in I well this is the probability
that b appears
first
among V and its
neighbors well V has D subv the degree
of V neighbors and all the ordering are
chosen uniformly at random so this
probability is 1 / the degree of v+
1 and thus by theine ity of expectations
the expected size
of this set I is equal to the sum
over vertices V in
G of the probability that this V Lies in
I and we just computed this
probability as
such this is the expectation that's what
happens on average
therefore there must be some
ordering that
induces an I so there is some
I with the size of I at
least the quantity that we
just
produced okay so that finishes the proof
of
the Carol way
theorem again it says the one the way
they think about this theorem is that if
you are given a graph G such that
typically one does not have large
degrees then it must contain a lot of
inde a large independent
set by considering the complement of
this graph G
by
considering the graph complement the
graph complement means that
we switch flip the edge and non edges
right so so this is a graph G and then
this will be the complement of G so flip
the edges and non-edges in
G independent sets
in G become
Clicks in the complement the clicks are
complete graphs with all the edges
present okay and vice
versa so we can read carway theorem for
the complement of G to deduce the
following
corollary says that every
and
vertex graph G
contains a
click of
on at
least this many vertices
okay so the expression inside the
summation is the click of uh is the
complement the degree in the
complement
okay let us derive a interesting
corollary of uh of the scary and this
turns out to be a pretty foundational
result in graph Theory known as teron
theorem ton themm says the
following
if an nver
graph
has more than the following number 1
minus 1/ r n^ 2 / 2 so it has more than
this many
edges
then the
graph
contains a
click
on more than R
vertices so tons theorem gives us some
bound on
the maximum number of edges that a graph
can have if it doesn't have a large
click and furthermore this bound here is
best is best possible in the following
sense and here let us restrict to the
case when n is divisible by R when n's
not divisible by R you need to do uh a
similar construction turns out to be
best possible and this bound is uh can
be improved slightly but not by too
much so here's the here's the example
let us take the N vertices and split
them
into equal
parts and there R parts so here in this
illustration r equal to
three and let's putting all the edges
between
Parts but no Edge within the part so
this is called the
complete R partite
graph so you see that this graph here
one can do a quick calculation to see
that it has exactly this number 1 - 1 /
R * n^ s over two
edges on the other hand it does not
contain a click on more than R vertices
the biggest click you have comes from
taking one vertex in each
part so this is an example showing that
the statement of Turon theorem is best
possible let us prove Ton's theorem as a
quick corollary of the earlier
result so by the earlier
corollary
G has a
click of size at least the sum over the
vertices in
G one over n minus the degree of v and
here let us use the
convexity so in this step let us use the
convexity of the function sending X to 1
/ n minus X so this is a convex function
which allows us to lower bound the sum
by n Over N minus the average
degree of
G on the other hand if the graph has
more than this many edges then the
average degree is bigger than some
corresponding quantity and putting this
into the expression we can strict have a
final expression is strictly bigger than
n Over N - 1 - 1 / R * n and this
quantity here equals to
R okay so there's a strict equality sign
here in particular G has a click of size
strictly greater than R and that
finishes the proof of Ton's
theorem tons theorem is a important
foundational result in graph Theory and
it's a start of a subject that we now
call extremal graph Theory
concerning what can you say about a
graph that has certain properties like
not having a large click and this Pro
that we just saw is a beautiful
illustration of the probabilistic method
two graph theory that allows us to prove
this wonderful result tons theorem along
with many other results that I hope that
you'll learn in the future