the MIT energy initiative presents
building consensus on concessions
written by Calvin
henck on the entire continent of Africa
there's only one financially solvent
utility company says Robert Stoner
deputy director for Science and
Technology at the MIT energy initiative
or Mighty the utility omma a private
company operates in Uganda under a
concession granted by the government in
utility concession agreements private
operators typically manage Key
activities such as investing in new
infrastructure operating and maintaining
existing assets to improve quality of
service and establishing more robust
billing and collection systems for a
prescribed period of time in exchange
for an attractive remuneration from the
beneficiaries of the service via
regulated tariffs although utility
concessions have been attempted with
mixed levels of success in developing
countries around the world Stoner and
other Mighty leaders see them as a
promising tool to help end energy
poverty you're bringing money and sound
management from investors improving the
quality of the system Stoner says um has
been a success overall but the
remuneration is now perceived as
excessive and it was not meant to
increase rural electrification in a
country with a low access rate despite
the moderate cost impact um has turned
into a political problem and the
government may not renew that concession
Stoner co-leads the MIT camillis
Universal energy access lab a
collaborative research group on Power
Systems in developing countries the
other co-leader of the group is ignasio
Perez araga a visiting Professor MIT and
professor at the univers ponica cames in
Madrid Spain both Stoner and Perez araga
also have leadership roles on the global
commission to end energy poverty in
March Perez araga took the lead in
organizing the online International
Conference on concessions in the power
sector the event hosted by the
government of Ghana brought together
more than 50 speakers and more than 300
participants from the African School of
Regulation the World Bank and the
Rockefeller Foundation along with Mighty
and the global commission to end energy
poverty subsaharan Africa has more than
600 million people without electricity
Perez araka notes energy poverty is a
huge problem so at the conference we are
trying to draw attention to the
instrument of concessions as an approach
that combines business Regulatory and
financial aspects in a way that can
improve the performance of utilities and
attract private investment concessions
have frequently been ignored in the
current policy debate and we wanted to
reverse that
Trend confronting
challenges in most countries with
significant levels of energy poverty
Stoner says the major problems lie not
in generation or transmission of
electricity but rather in distribution
often distribution utilities fail to
provide reliable service which
discourages customers from connecting to
the grid many who do connect do so
illegally drawing power without paying
for it which drives up costs for paying
customers also Distributing electricity
to rural areas is typically a losing
proposition from a financial perspective
making it difficult for governments or
private operators to build viable
systems that provide universal
access the distribution system is where
the rubber meets the road stonor says
it's where all the hardware of the
electrical system comes into contact
with the customers to solve these
problems Stoner says governments would
benefit from designing concessions in
new ways for instance concessions can be
designed with viable business models for
off-grid Solutions like minig grids and
Standalone systems based on affordable
tariffs along with subsidies to
developers sub franchises can be created
that carve out territories within
presently unviable distribution
companies where suitable combinations of
diverse customers can make possible
viable business models Santos Jose Diaz
Pastor a member of the universal energy
access lab helped to organize the
conference
while the ideas behind utility
concessions are sound he says it is
challenging to apply those ideas to
dozens of different countries that all
have their own specific features there's
no framework that works everywhere he
says when you analyze concessions there
are so many things you can adapt to each
country the major problem is getting the
capital to make all the Investments that
are needed but implementation is where
the plans usually fail you have to
design business models with financing
schemes that are sustainable over the
long term
learning from the
past Perez araga says that governments
and private operators are already
applying lessons learned from previous
concession agreements for instance he
points to a concession in a flood prone
area of India after the area was hit by
a cyclone the government held the
private operator responsible for
repairing the damage only to see the
company go broke and abandon the area
but in a more recent concession
agreement in the same region Perez araga
says the government stepped in to
provide funding after a natural disaster
allowing the private operator to restore
service to most areas within 24 or 48
Hours the company has the confidence
that they are supported by the
government and so they will do
everything that is needed to provide
good service he says another important
lesson governments and private operators
must collaborate and ensure that their
agreements will be financially viable
for all parties in one concession
agreement in Sagal Perez araga says the
government maintained control of more
economically viable Urban Distribution
Systems while giving over control of
unprofitable rural Distribution Systems
to a private operator with
unsatisfactory results the regulated
tariffs were unable to cover the cost of
the service and there were no subsidies
Perez araga says you have to create a
concession business model that is viable
and sustainable and that typically
requires cross subsidization among urban
and rural areas also people have to
learn to write sound contracts for
instance with clear termination Clauses
there are silly mistakes that people
have made because they were not thinking
of the many things that could go
wrong looking
ahead greguar jako who was a mighty
research fellow while helping organize
the conference says organizers had three
main goals for the event first they
wanted to create a platform for in-depth
discussions about how utility
concessions should be structured and
financed second they wanted to build a
network of senior practitioners who
could advise one another on the topic
and finally they wanted to pave the way
for a larger in-person conference later
in the year the experts were eager to
share jeo says I could feel the
enthusiasm for the first time they had
an opportunity to talk in a structured
way about their experiences we don't
want to only talk about concessions and
energy poverty once a crisis appears or
when a Development Bank has money for a
project Jacko ads our vision is to use
concessions at a large scale and back
these concessions with strong Quantified
plans to reform the power sector Perez
Ariaga calls the event an appetizer for
the work to come on concessions in the
energy sector what we are trying to do
is mobilize the governments the
development Partners the big
institutions to address the problem of
access to electricity he says we are
trying to mobilize billions of dollars
this is a marathon