all right welcome everyone my name is
Terrell Williams and I serve as the
associate director for diversity equity
and inclusion within the office of
admission I'm really excited about the
opportunity to host tonight's panel uh
which is going to be uh focused on women
with ET Sloan U we have a dynamic group
of panelists as well as a a a moderator
that's going to have um you all you know
giv some insight on our particular
processes but also the experience that's
know for um uh those who identify as
women so now I want to transition it
over to our student moderator for the
evening uh Sarah who will share a brief
introduction about herself and introduce
our panelists for the evening Sarah the
floor is yours thank you for the
fabulous introduction very excited to
have you all here um for this webinar um
as charl mentioned my name is Sarah I am
for a little bit of background I'm a
seconde MBA and I'm currently the SVP of
admissions for the flown women in
management club also known as swim on
campus and just for a bit of ground uh
what we try to do at swim is really
Foster Community um we facilitate
professional advancement and promote
gender and racial equity for women and
all underrepresented gender identities
at
Sloan um prior to Sloan I was in tech
sales at a digital marketing software
company and this summer I interned at
Google in a strategy and operations role
within their Google ads business unit
back in New York City um yeah and I
would love to transition over to the
fabulous panelists that we have today we
have Britany Lauren Paula and Elizabeth
with
us um I believe we have another slide
with all of them on it is that correct
yes okay perfect um Lauren if you could
kind of kick us off just introduce
yourself I'll have all the panelists
introduce themselves as well just to um
brief background on what program you
were in your year and uh you know what
you were doing before and also after sun
take it away
thank you guys so yeah my name is Lauren
and I graduated from the lgo program
which is the Dual MBA and masters of
engineering program um in 2023 so just
last year really it was kind was flying
by already and within the lgo program um
you can choose your Masters my masters
was in computer science or we call it
course six here at MIT um prior to
coming to Sloan I was working in both
manufacturing and data science um I
worked at Boeing and I also got a MERS
in data science previously so I had some
data science experience um and then
since coming to Sloan I decided to go
for more of a newer startup route I'm
actually working at a company called
rebuild manufacturing which was started
by a bunch of sonies that also came from
my operations program so a focus on
manufacturing and operations but what
I'm working on are some of our digital
Tech products in the
space thanks and moving over to
Britney yeah thanks Sarah hi everyone
I'm Britney um I'm an alumna of the
Sloan master of business analytics also
known as mban program and I just
graduated uh in 2023 uh before coming to
Sloan I was actually finishing up my
undergraduate degree at the University
of Virginia so I was studying statistics
and minoring in data science and I knew
Sloan would be a perfect next step into
industry and since graduating I've been
working as a data scientist for Visa in
Washington DC so I see a few of you have
put uh Washington DC in the chat so
happy to see that and I'll pass it off
to
Paula thank you so much Britany hi
everyone I am paa I am I graduated from
the MBA um program last year I cannot
believe that also one year has already
passed by and it's like right now
hitting me and amazing two years um and
before
doing the MBA program I was working at a
social startup back in Latin America I
am from Lima Peru and and I was doing
business development and but then I
decided to come to MIT because I wanted
to kind of do a career shift towards
working in technology and I was actually
able to do that so today I actually work
as program manager for machine learning
um model
um or for programs that include machine
learning model for the global team at
Uber which include different it includes
different products um across the
platforms that we have all over the
globe and so really excited to be here
with you today and and hoping to to
contribute to your journey towards an
MBA or any other of the programs that
MIT loan
has and I will pass it to
El hello everyone my name is lisabeth P
I graduated from the master in finance
in 2023 it was an 18month program and
before going to MIT I was working as a
fixed income and foreign exchange
strategies that Bank of America um I am
originally from Mexico Mexico City so I
was working there um and now after
graduating from the master in finance
I'm working at B asne Asset Management
which is a hedge fund I work mainly
doing quantitative research and on the
macro area so I mostly focused on again
on fixed income and rates products and
I'm very excited to be here today and
happy to answer any questions you have
thank you all so much um and as Dal
mentioned we do have a couple
pre-planned questions and then we'll
open it up at the end and have plenty of
time for questions that the audience may
have uh I'm sure something that is on a
lot of people's minds is career
progression career growth um so one
question that I have for you all is how
has MIT Sloan helped you navigate your
career options post uh program whether
it's MBA mban lgo or
mfin um and anyone can kind of jump in
and take this I guess I can just start
off a little bit um in my experience as
part of the master of business analytics
obviously I think all sonon we can say
that you know there's a really big
culture of sonon helping slon so that
manifests in many ways whether that's
Career Fairs or speaker series um I know
Sarah swim does a lot of those as well
um those are all really good ways that
the Alumni network and the network at
Sloan um really helps in career
development there's also the career
development office um one program
specific resource that I found super
helpful was the um Capstone and also the
uh analytics lab that we had in our
program and so both of those were
opportunities to actually work with
sponsor companies we had a range of
companies from biotech to finance
fintech Consulting and it was
opportunities for students in small
groups or in pairs to essentially work
uh like an internship with these
companies uh a lot of them actually did
have Sloan alumni running the projects
and mentoring us and those were some of
the connections that I found most
valuable um personally I was able to
work with Macy's and also visa and um
obviously um I really enjoyed working
with Visa I liked the data that they
were doing I liked their techniques and
uh that definitely helped to influence
where I am now a lot of my classmates
also found their current roles through
these analytics lab and Capstone
opportunities uh so I'd say slone really
does a good job of setting you up um and
putting you in good
position thank you I love this really
specific examples of how you know
classroom translate into real life thank
you Britney anyone else want to add
anything on that question I can go next
yeah oh Lauren and then I saw
you gon go after um well in my case and
actually kind of related to one of the
questions that have that has just been
asked through the Q&A I actually come
from a non-traditional NBA background
because I I studied Clinical
Psychology like very very different from
the business world and I was already
transitioning um before um joining Sloan
and the MBA and kind of why I wanted to
do the MBA it's because I felt that I
had already some experience working in
business development but again I wanted
to go to the tech world and I felt that
you know MIT loan was just that perfect
um compliment that I needed on my resume
especially because of why MIT is known
for um and so for me I was able to I was
able to see this career change and
career progression as well and kind of
similar to what BR said um for me I did
my summer internship at U in the MBA
program as you probably know we have two
years and there's a summer internship
ship um between the first and the second
year and it was hard to do all of the
recruiting and a lot of work but I think
it allowed me like the whole ecosystem
the alumni the career development office
they really helped me in trying like in
understanding what I wanted to do next
and what could be some possible options
for me and after a lot of effort during
recruiting I was able to secure this um
summer internship in something related
with machine learning which is what I
wanted to do and then I got the
full-time offer and you know the good
part of that is that I didn't have to
the recruitment process all over again
um for the second year or before
graduation so definitely that is
something that I would say for career
progression do take advantage of
everything that there is for everyone to
um leverage and and also especially the
summer internship which you know not in
every case you will have the returning
offer but if that if there's that
possibility then like it really helps
for the second
year really great advice paa thank you
and Lauren you had something to
add yeah I think it's quick um with the
lgo program it works like just a little
bit differently um where we have set
companies that we can intern with that
are like partner companies the sponsor
companies for our program um but similar
to The Experience they talked about like
the fact that they we already have these
relationships within lgo and set up
within Sloan um it's really helpful for
well for us we get matched to an
internship we have set companies that we
get to you know try out potentially
something totally different like for me
I tried out a private Equity internship
very different from my like more heavy
quantitative background so it was really
great to have this very like safe
lowrisk opportunity to try out something
new um and then obviously I ended up
going to a company well not obviously
but this is actually a company that is
one of the lgo sponsor companies so
again that's just an area where you know
there's a lot of these set up
established MIT relationships which was
really helpful in the recing
process cool thank you um and then
shifting gears a little bit um we all on
this panel identify as women uh we were
in some way related to swim slown women
and management during our time on campus
um so so I'd love to hear from you guys
kind of how you would describe the sense
of community among women at Sloan and
how it kind of impacted your experience
within Sloan during your time at Sloan
and also maybe Beyond um if at all um
Elizabeth we haven't heard from you in a
while so I'll I'll pass this over to you
thank you sure um so well first of all I
would say that MIT and MIT loone in
particular are very special for and
really
valuing diversity so at all times you
can see that and it is a community of
very smart people but also like people
from very different backgrounds and uh
when you're part of this community you
can see that and it's it's it there's
really a lot of opportunities to connect
with people from different backgrounds
and there is a whole setup for you to to
engage in interest groups so for example
in my case I I am Latina and new women
so I ended up being part of the Latino
and graduate student Association and
also I was involved in
The Graduate woman at MIT community so
in in general I would say that it was
very valuable to have access to these
interest groups and uh to be able to
participate in those so I would say that
it's it's just a a a great experience to
be part of of these groups and if you're
interested in in being part of the
leadership there's always opportunities
for people to join those um so really
the the the opportunities are are
unlimited great thank you um anyone else
want to add anything on this
topic um I can so something that'll
happen probably the first day that you
come to Sloan is you'll be added to one
of many WhatsApp chats and they'll just
keep expanding and multiplying over time
um so there's tons of WhatsApp tracks
that get created I feel like everyone
creates one for almost every Infinity
group and also every Niche interest you
might have like literally anything um
and one that we have that was actually
particularly active was just our like
the sloy like women chat and it was
really nice to just have this chat that
where people could you know drop in
surveys for a class they were working on
or ask where they should get their nail
zone or say hey we have friends in town
what are some you know really good
restaurant recommendations so I think
that there's just so many different like
formal channels but also lots of
informal channels to bolster community
and I would say Sal is very active in
those especially over chat
love it and happy to report that that is
a continuing tradition on campus so um
and Britney I think you also wanted to
add something or was it Paula
sorry yeah sure I can add I I have to
agree 100% with what Lauren and
Elizabeth already said um at Sloan and
especially an M program I never once
felt like underrepresented as a woman I
always felt like there was this network
and no shortage of mentors and people
you know you could be friends or just
take a lot of advice from um of course
there was that SLO women and management
chat a lot of free food there as well I
will add as with all the Salo programs
but I also remember some great events
like push for parody and um even in the
M program itself it's a pretty small
cohort 78 students but 37% of us were
women and so you know I do feel like
that number is growing over time as well
and it's really inspiring to see that
and definitely we are strong here at
Sloan and it's really nice to see it's a
great community
love it thank you um and I guess
carrying these themes over a little bit
more into the classroom I wonder if any
of you have sort of specific examples
that illustrate maybe like how receptive
faculty and you know professors might be
to adjusting their curriculum or their
teaching methods to kind of include more
diverse perspectives and voices and
opinions does anyone have some sort of
um maybe anecdote on that topic
I don't know if it's exactly I mean
first of all I would say that of course
um I think that at least in my
experience I did feel that in almost
every class the professors would try to
actually bring that diverse perspective
either through choosing business cases
from different types of Industries um or
from inviting um guest to speak ERS from
different kind of backgrounds and and
representing diverse groups so I do feel
that overall I felt that that was
represented um even um since the very
beginning during the course semester I
was really lucky to have half of my
professors and being women and half of
my professors being men which was like a
really I would say a bit of a surprise
but of course like a positive surprise
and that being said that being said I
think um at least in the MBA we have a
very um a strong um like a lot of
options that are especially dedicated to
courses or classes that will deal as
their main subject with diverse issues
there's one that I took um which was
about like um managing difficult
conversations across differences and um
with a diverse with with the diversity
mindset and and it was one of my
favorite classes with Professor car
blackborn so if you even want to go
deeper into those topics you can and
then one thing that happened that I
remind as anecdote that I that I recall
as an anecdote that um was truly
enlightened I would say is that we had
one of these classes where we would have
guest speakers every week and by the
fifth week we realized that we had three
guest the speakers that were men and two
that were women and we ended up asking
only to the women um how was their work
life balance and so we reflected upon
that because we said like oh you know we
are actually falling into this
stereotype of only asking the women how
they are dealing with their work life
balance instead of bringing this
question to everyone and I think that
the atmosphere the environment the
community that we have allows us to
bring those questions to the table and
actually make a change and you know we
did like kind of a class agreement that
from there on we would always try to
think um about our questions with a um
diverse perspective in mind as well so
that was something that that I really
that I still you know recall and use as
an example because it is again like the
environment the culture that allows you
to bring these questions to the table
and make a change from that and I feel
that in every class love it I I really
love the the kind of idea of collective
accountability and you know having
everyone in the class sort of agree to
this um new contract I love it um any
anyone else or any other thoughts on
this topic um before we move on to a
couple other
questions cool okay um and
another question that I have is you know
this is obviously about gender identity
but you know these questions don't
necessarily have to be or your responses
don't necessarily have to be um but what
was the most unexpected challenge that
you faced at Sloan and maybe how did you
overcome it um what resources did you
use where who did you lean on um where
did you
go and you can take a second to think
about
us I would say for me um I guess
somewhat of a challenge for sure is the
mam program is one of the smaller
cohorts in all of SLO um and so we tend
to kind of be in our own little bubble a
little bit separated off from the rest
of the slones and I think when it comes
to having a greater identity at Sloan
being involved that's something that you
know doesn't obviously come naturally
for a lot of the students and so I think
that was something that I really you
know knew I wanted to do is just get
involved in this amazing Community
whether that's women or um clubs career
oriented clubs um and so most of my
involvement was um with the Council of
mban as vice president but also I was
fortunate to be on the Sloan Senate and
I thought Sloan Senate was it's
essentially just like the student
government um and a liaison between the
Sloan students and then the
administration and we did a lot of fun
planning of EV EV uh there are several
subcommittees so health and wellness
committee that always planned you know
these little petting animal uh petting
zoo fairs and then there's also Dei
committee um there's the academics
committee so there there's also a bit of
curriculum reform whether that's for you
know greater equality in the education
or just changing certain lessons or
cases that we're studying um but I think
just taking those steps um to broaden
your horizon while at Sloan is really
important and it's actually not very
hard at all all the slones are extremely
welcoming um whether that's swim or at
Career Fairs so you know once you're at
Sloan just really make sure to take
those steps to interact with people in
the MBA lgo um mfin I've met so many
great classmates who are really
inspiring um great to hear about their
career progression and their goals for
the future um and so yeah it's once
you're at slone just make sure that you
take those steps and uh really broaden
your network because you'll meet so many
amazing inspiring
individuals love it thanks Britney um
anyone else have something to share yeah
uh so in my case I think the biggest
challenge was the recruiting process and
the recruiting process in my case I was
going to recruit for an internship
program during the summer after the
first year and it was the first time I
was recruiting in the US for a job in
the US um so
the process was challenging not only
because it's like a completely different
like setting and and in the US for
example like networking is very
important uh in my case like in Mexico
is not not as relevant so that was
something I had to learn and second like
I was trying to enter a more
quantitative field than my what I made
at my undergrad uh in which like most
people have like math or computer
science backgrounds so I think that I'm
having access to connecting to lumni and
also connecting to my fellow classmates
really helped me in this process because
they could give me a lot of advice on
what were the things that I had to learn
which were the courses that I had to
attend which people I had to talk to and
then at the end of the day I could fill
the knowledge gaps that that I needed to
get to the job where I am right now
cool thank you and then finally very
last question before we open it up to um
audience questions is uh you know sort
of looking back on your experience I
know it doesn't feel like it was that
long ago but looking back you know when
maybe you were applying or when you were
starting your programs at Sloan um what
do you wish you had known before
starting your program what piece of
advice do you have for uh the people on
this um webinar who are looking to
attend
SL and maybe we can start with Lauren
because I think we haven't heard from
you in a
while yeah sure um I think what I wish I
would have known probably found contrary
to what you hear is there's not actually
that much pressure to be like quote
unquote like networking all the time I
feel like I always went in I was like
okay mbas you're here to build a network
I need to Network all the time I need to
be friends with everybody
um and meet all these people which you
definitely should do but it's also can
be really stressful and really
exhausting and you can wear yourself
down really fast and I wish I had known
that the the slow Network that you get
is people in your class it's the people
outside of your class um it's really
nothing to stress about just like be a
great person and help people out when
you can and like this network will be
here for you and what I really got out
of the network honestly was a lot of
just like cultural experiences and
international travel opportunities I
didn't expect to have so many
opportunities to go on tracks to
different countries sometimes led by my
classmates that were from that country
and that was such a unique experience
and I was really glad that I got to do
so many of those
tracks I really appreciate that take
Lauren I feel like uh yeah it can be
hard to kind of bring yourself down to
reality um and I also feel like you know
echoing what everyone has said the
community here at Sloan we are a smaller
um school so I feel like the people that
you're bound to meet you will meet them
eventually so there's no rush you know
networking like crazy in the first few
weeks of school um and maybe let's move
on to Paula any kind of advice or
anything you wish you had known
before Oh my God I feel like this is a
really hard question because there's so
much that I could talk about and
I guess that of course you'll always
come with an idea an expectations about
how is it going to be and but I guess my
advice would be just like try to be as
open as you can during those two years
to truly enjoy everything that might
come that you didn't plan for um and and
and also because I think like I mean I
don't know anyone who had the experience
that the NBA didn't leave up to the
expectations I think like that's like a
really good thing that happens like
everyone is just Overjoyed with how the
experience is going I cannot say how
that goes in other schools but it was
definitely um the experience for my
class um and I know that it sounds
overly positive but like it's true and I
think a key part of that was that we all
um came with not low expectations but
with a really open mind to go ahead and
do those things that might surprise us
right like what laen you said in terms
of like going into tracks or like I
don't know experiencing something new in
my case um I knew that I wanted to go
into deep like classes that could take
me deeper into technology and machine
learning and AI but I was also very
nervous because of course a lot of
people had a background um that which
which do they had already acquired
knowledge regarding those topics and I
guess um one advice that I would give is
that even if you feel that you're not as
prepared as your as your classmates go
to the classes and enroll in the classes
that you want because it is true that
the community it is a learning community
where you can where it's actually a good
thing that other people know more than
you because that means that you can
learn from them and the the I think like
the humbleness and just like the the
openness to share knowledge is really
inspiring and again like if I wouldn't
if I hadn't done that I wouldn't be
where I am today so that would be like I
I guess that those would be my two sents
like go with an open mind and also H
just try to learn as much as you can
without without any like um preconceived
ideas on what you can do or cannot do
because of what other people already
know totally agree thank you for that I
love it um I I always say that slon are
are the best cheerleaders so even if you
feel like you're um you know not
adequate there will always be people who
are saying you're crazy and you should
just go for it so just do it and
Elizabeth any kind of advice uh from
your
end yeah uh well my advice is similar to
what Paula just mentioned so I think
that in my case at the start of the
program I was really nervous like I knew
that I wanted to do um slight career
shift into more quantive field and I
knew that like so many of my classmates
already had that background and I was
afraid of taking like harder classes H
at the end I ended up make doing it and
it didn't it it wasn't that hard at the
end of the day because and I think a big
part of that was just having the
community so like whenever things get
very challenging you can always H rely
on your classmates or on all of the
resources that you have at MIT um like
like additional time with professors or
with teacher assistants so at the end of
the day there there's always like the
resources there for you to learn and you
just have to be uh open and you just
have to like want to achieve a bigger
bigger goal and then the the resources
will be there so so I would say that you
just you just need to H know what you
want and then just go for
it great and then finally Britney any
kind of concluding advice for all of our
listeners here or Watchers sure yeah I I
would say um one thing as well and one
of the reasons I chose Sloan is because
of the such vibrant diversity within all
of the programs um even um M had 20 uh
students from 24 different countries and
you know within the MBA all the other
programs I noticed the same and that's
one of the things that I really stood
out to me about the school itself and
that I really got to love and really
Embrace and I think coming in with an
open mind and really getting to
experience all these cultures was really
so much fun so definitely com in with an
open mind and touching on the whole
point about fun definitely tons of
opportunities for that too sponsored by
Sloan uh one of my favorites was the C
functions um with with the letter c but
also u c as an sea at the beginning I
remember there was one uh yacht function
hosted by Sloan where all students from
different programs were able to go onto
the Boston Harbor kind of like a very
big nice classy party ship and that was
kind of the kickoff event to the
semester um throughout there's also
other events like Sloan Gala um where a
lot of students were able to go to this
very fancy um dance essentially event
and then host it at a mansion as well
and of course along the way there's a
Sloan Foles which is a student run
comedy show so just so many ways to
really get involved and meet people from
around the world and I think coming with
an open mind and just be ready to
embrace those new
experience cool thanks so much and with
that I guess I'll pass it back to Terell
is that correct um for the questions
from the chat
thanks s we have some questions that we
flag from the chat that I can ask the
moderator and the panelist to answer so
we have flagged a few um so the first
question we have is um what does
mentorship mean to you and how have you
found mentorship at
Sloan it's a pretty loaded question s
yeah I can take this because I feel like
the the panelists have been doing a lot
of talking so um I can talk very con
concretely about the mentorship program
that we actually have through swim uh
which is basically a program where a
secondy year um MBA is partnered with a
incoming um first year MBA uh and it
kicks off over the summer so it's just a
very you know friendly face friendly
name to kind of introduce you to the
Sloan Community um it's really to the
mentors and the mentees how they want to
structure this relationship but um I've
remained really close friends with my
mentor from last year who has now
graduated um and I hope to kind of
foster that same relationship with my
two mentees that I have this year who
are First Years um and in terms of
mentorship what I really gain from it is
just having some sort of sounding board
that is removed from you know your
day-to-day classes removed from your
day-to-day worries and just having
someone else that's outside of um what's
currently occupying your mind to uh sort
of talk to you about whatever it is that
you need help with um and having sort of
that third-party um voice to help you
through anything that that you'd like um
and then it also is great that you know
you have this sort of mentor that you
can look up to and ask for advice um and
then vice versa in terms of being a
mentor to other people um it's really
rewarding really gratifying I think it's
one of my favorite programs that we do
through
swim thanks sah another question we have
is for those who are coming from
non-traditional backgrounds uh so can
you speak to the academic workload at
Sloan and how you've navigated uh that
process whether it was the core semester
or all the elective that you have the
opportunity to
take I can take that um as I shared
before I did call psychology for
undergrad so when I arrived to the MBA I
knew that the C semester was going to be
challenging for me because I've never
taken um any accounting class or econ
class or data models and
decisions class which is one specific
class that MIT loan has at least for the
MBA and program which is part of the
course semester um I think that you know
first of all everyone who I know that
came from a diverse background we all
survived so I think that you know if you
put the effort of course um you'll be
able to navigate through the classes in
my case I actually loved it and that was
one of the reason why I decided to come
to MIT because I wanted to have a course
semester where I could have these data
models and decisions class and and of
course it came from an interest um from
a personal interest of course because I
wanted to go to Tech but I would say
that this was the best way for me to
confirm if I actually wanted to go
deeper into that world at least that was
the reality for me for DMD and for data
models and decisions and then I liked it
so much even though it was really really
challenging um that I decided to do the
business analytics certificate as part
of the MBA for which we decided to which
I decided to take um a lot of classes
that were heavy on again like um machine
learning um generative AI whatever those
things um
so if you only want to use the course
semester to go through those classes
you'll be able to um there are also
tutour that you can reach out to there's
a lot of resources study groups the
office hours like honestly I think
everyone will be able to do it and I
wouldn't I wouldn't be that much
concerned about it because it also
depends on how much you know like how
how good you want to do it if maybe like
it's a class that doesn't matter that
much to you or like it like it does it
depends but everyone will survive and
we'll learn from those but again if you
want to actually get a lot of Knowledge
from it you can no matter what your
background is you'll probably have to
put a little bit more effort but it's
doable and and for me again it was one
of the reasons why I wanted to come to
MIT thank you for sharing uh so the next
question we have is kind of a a great
segue from that previous question so um
what was something at Sloan that lived
up to your expectations and something
that went beyond or surprised you while
you were
here I can take that one and I think uh
I would also recommend this for anyone
with a non-traditional business
background but something that really
exceeded my expectations at slone this
sounds nerdy but it was Corporate
Finance I think it was like the best
cause of think get loan would recommend
anyone especially if you're not coming
from a business background to take it I
wasn't expecting to really like any of
the finance courses that I took um in
corporate finance but it's really
awesome so I highly recommend
that yeah similarly for me it's also
course related um in mban we were able
to take machine learning optimization
courses um also Hands-On deep learning
um as well as some other technical
courses like reinforcement learning and
really you know obviously because it's
MIT a lot of these Technologies are the
state-of-the-art um a lot of the
methodologies we were using were
actually formulated by one of our
programs professors he's the one who
wrote The Textbook so you know when you
come to SLO and MIT this is the
experience you're getting is really the
Forefront of the industry um at least on
the data science side and then as well
as the management side on the management
side I really enjoyed um some of the
courses with some mbas as well like
power and negotiation or consumer
behavior and a lot of the research
coming out of those classes is also uh
industry leading so it's really
inspiring every case study is really at
the top and uh it was a great
experience thank you both for sharing so
the next question we have is um about
pursuing the degree so given that
pursuing a specialization or joint
degree program ENT entails additional
coursework how does it impact the time
available to participate in other
activities and how does one balance all
the activity together um at
SL um I can answer that one so in my
case um I really want to make the most
of my time at MIT academically so I
enrolled in a very U hard courses um in
different parts of MIT and also Harvard
H but I think that you can always find
the time to um comply with your academic
and like obligations and also be part of
the community and even if you want like
H be part of a sports team so in my case
like I I could do this these hard
courses but and also I have the time or
I made the time ER to um
be the social chair of the Latin
graduate student Association and I was
also part of the gymnastics team so I
think that it's really up to yourself
you you have to think about what are
your priorities for your time at M and
and then you can always make time for
what matters to you so I think that um
you can you can get the most out of
different worlds
awesome awesome uh a few more questions
that I've identified that I think this
is really good for our panel um so one
of them it says uh did any of you
participate in any prep programs such as
MBA launch through Forte and also the
second part of that question is now that
you have concluded your time at Sloan
and can reflect on your time as a
student what Rec what programs would you
recommend um to support throughout the
application process whether it's
internal at slan or any external
programs you all may have participated
in no prep programs that anybody
participated in or anything that SL this
swim uh Club did prior to your
enrollment that you found that was very
useful
well I'm gonna toot swims horn for a
second um I did not participate uh in I
actually did participate in 4te um for a
little bit and then I actually stopped
because I thought I was going to apply a
year later but that's a separate story
um I found it very helpful for the three
months that I was in it um so if you are
interested in it I would say go for it
um but I can't really speak to it much
more than that um in terms of swim and
admissions what we do obviously I'm one
of the um VPS of admissions for swim a
lot of what we're doing is interview
prep sessions we're doing a lot of
Outreach sessions um specifically for
women and underrepresented um gender
identities um for applicants who are
interested in coming to Sloan so last
year we started actually um you know
fleshing out a more robust program for
interview prep session so if you are
invited to an interview you will be
reached out to by either me or someone
else on swim um with an invitation uh to
kind of practice and have sort of like
an ask me anything style um session with
one of the swim members to really help
you get comfortable with you know number
one seeing yourself at Sloan and also
getting you prepped specifically for the
um interview process that's just one
thing um that we do in admissions along
with other events you know obviously
helping out Terell and the rest of the
admissions team for on-site visits um
lots of happenings and we're also always
open to answer any questions if you guys
have
them thanks Sarah another follow-up
question this was mentioned earlier uh
the push for parody event um so someone
asked could you all speak more to that
event and the impact or reaches has
amongst women and allies at schan um and
they say they Googled it and it sounds
awesome but they want to know more
information about it if they
can yeah so I um was actually not on the
organizing committee so I don't want to
m speak but it is a really really
awesome um event it's evolved a lot over
the years but it has existed for a long
time in some sort of version this year I
believe it spent three weeks of non-stop
events which then culminated in a um big
swim hosted party that rang in at
midnight of international women's day I
think which was just really nice and
symbolic um events rang from everything
uh from
you know events around like uh fertility
conversations um double income
households uh how to kind of break
gender stereotypes in various different
Industries we had a session on women in
sports and sports analytics um and then
we also had you know evening events with
that were like dinner um dinner groups
with women faculty which was also really
special so small group dinners with um
some of our amazing Rockstar faculty
um who are also women um so really cool
range of events they change every year
we have a couple events that um do
really well every year so we want to try
and keep them um but I do think it's
going to be a similar format this year
in February another sort of three- week
twoe event um with lots of different
programming and um programming that's
also open to and approachable for
everyone not just
women thanks here looking forward to it
uh so the last question have before we
transition to our wrap up um is um did
you all take any classes outside of
Sloan um if so why and how was your
experience with the registration process
whether it was at the Institute or the
class that you can take uh within the
graduate schools within the Boston
area um I can answer that one so I ended
up taking many classes outside Sloan um
I took a couple classes that in Harvard
in the PHD G
Department um and in like Harvard
Kennedy School and the registration
process wasn't hard at all and uh to get
there it was really easy I had a bike so
I would just bike there it took me about
20 minutes to back there so so yeah it
was pretty easy and like even inside MIT
I took courses outside SL as well in the
course six in computer science and also
in the PHD in economics again I I would
say that sometimes it was it was even
easier to register for these courses
than to register for courses at slan
just because there is so much demand for
courses at loan that you have to
sometimes B for the courses and it's
hard to get in whereas like these other
courses um they were like just bigger
classes in the case of the computer
science department or in the PHD Eon
classes it was just very small classes
so and like very meant for for people to
join those classes so really there is a
anle opportunity for students to to H go
and uh study in in other parts and uh it
was a great experience as well