hello everybody I'm excited to be
presenting a video by the renowned
professor and uh artist George Lewis on
computers and improvisation I just want
to give a quick introduction to how much
his work had an impact on me I remember
hearing various projects on teaching
computers to do things like uh
automatically accompany a jazz
improvisor so that it would do exactly
what he or she you know wanted and put
the right chords at the right place and
then hearing a comment from George Lewis
on how that's exactly wrong in the
spirit of jazz in the African-American
tradition that when we
have improvisor
and they work in a group the other
people aren't pure uh accompanists
they're collaborators and one of the
things that a collaborator should do is
respond to you and one of the responses
is well if you get into a rut and you
keep doing the same things it shouldn't
be letting you stay in that rut if you
keep playing the same chord progressions
well a good jazz group will start
playing different chords for you or or
mix up the Rhythm to try to make you
have to think and stay in the spirit and
um there were comments about you know
with uh with the early history of jazz
coming out of a tradition of uh people
who had been through the Injustice of of
enslavement that why would we want a
computer system that replicates Jazz to
be the slaver servant of a master
performer so that there's an ethical
dilemma in ethical component of how we
teach computers to improvise and that's
why I think this video is very important
for you to see