So I'm Steve Whitaker, one of the
program directors at the industrial
lesson program, but prior to joining uh
MIT, I was with BT for about 40 years,
most of that working with MIT. So it's
fantastic to be back uh at one Brham. Um
and just want to say it's also fantastic
back in London because we've just spent
the week here meeting with various
companies and um it was really nice
during the weeks this full moon and
those sort of thing but really reminded
what a kind of fantastic city is uh what
a you a vibrant kind of global
crossroads it is uh representative of a
kind of a UK that again is a a vibrant
global crossroads with a kind of you
know hopefully a vital role in uh both
glo in global affairs and global trade.
Um this was just as out walking down the
um down the bank last couple of evenings
ago. Um I just wanted to give a bit of
bit of framing for the afternoon and
talk a little bit about why why the
events kind of structured the way it is.
Um and to ground some of the things in
where we are and you know discuss later
on where we're going. So um as my
colleagues know I'm a I'm a technologist
not a historian but we're one of those
points in time where technology seems to
be driving history. uh and in some ways
with things like social media and
disinformation history has become a
technology. So those two have become
kind of very very blurred together. One
of the things that struck me was walking
as you walk through the city you have
this these juxositions of the kind of
the uh the on the almost like the
ancient and the modern. So we were
walking down the the embankment and we
went to visit GSMA which is the trade
body for the mobile industry and you're
looking across the river and you see the
Golden Hind. You think, well, that's
this, you know, why the Golden Hind?
Well, the Golden Hind was the ship that
did the first circumnavigation of the
globe and really laid the foundations
for what then became the first wave of
globalization, globalization kind of
1.0. And from that laid the, you know,
the age of empires, the age of uh global
trade, those sorts of things. Um, and
you talk about the, you know, with the
mobile industry being very much the
infrastructure for almost that
globalization 3, you know, 3.0, So you
know as we start to kind of you know um
you know previously under you less
engaged parts of the global economy
become more engaged with this digital
digital infrastructure. So you really
see this kind of role of of London as as
part of that connective tissue in kind
of global change and global
connectivity. Um I put this up because
these are just ones we you know popping
round. Um, and if it was a quiz show,
you go, "Okay, which one is these is the
odd one out?" And you go, you know,
well, obviously odd one out is St.
Paul's, but the the reason it's
different and slightly different is that
I hadn't realized, but these and these
are just two local churches just around
the corner. They're both St. Bs. So, one
of them is St. B without Oldgate. So,
the other one is St. Both without
uh Bishop's Gate. And these are churches
that are on the Roman wall and they were
outside the Roman wall. And turns out S
Both is an East Anglian saint who is the
patron saint of boundaries. Is a bit of
a strange thing to be a patron saint. So
it's like patron of corners and stuff
like that. Um but that also means he's
like the the patron trains of travel and
trade. And so there are actually four uh
some bottes within easy walking distance
to these two. There's one that's
actually close to St. Paul's I believe
and there's one at Billingsgate which
was burnt by during the great fire not
rebuilt. But it was just kind of
interesting and it says something also
to the fact that yeah we're right by the
London wall. Oldgate was where the Roman
road to Colchester went out. Uh
Colchester was the uh the Roman capital
of Britain. Um this area then became the
kind of the um you know the point of
entry of all the trade from the east of
England coming into London. So you
imagine droing routes bringing cattle
into London uh all around this kind of
area. uh and it became very much an area
where communities you know fleeing
religious persecution fleeing other wars
would settle. So in the 1600s it was the
huge uh escaping some of the conflicts
in Europe um which made this a center of
kind of textiles and clothing which led
to petticoat market uh which is
obviously just up the road. um in the
1890s
uh early 1900s it was the Jewish
population from Russia and the Baltics
escaping the pograms um and those waves
have come through and you go through now
we went there's been a Caribbean wave
you go through some sort of south south
Asian um just a very very vibrant
community that's really connected with
the world um and always has been now
sometimes that brings tensions with it
um so um in the early 1900s you had a
with some of these waves this sort of
wave of radical politics that were
sweeping through Europe in the age of
revolutions. So you had the siege of
Sydney Street uh with kind of radicals
you know running robberies to fund
various things and then you Winston
Churchill outside the store for all
those famous photographs. Uh round the
corner uh in fact literally round the
corner uh on White Chapel High Street
was the scene of the Battle of Cable
Street uh which was a running street
battle between several thousand uh
mostly black shirts in their 30s and
about a 100,000 East Enders and
effectively that was the end of the uh
you know British fascist movement in the
30s. it was the banning of political
uniforms um crystallized the UK's
position ahead of the second world war
all these sorts of things so it's a very
different history than you get over with
that um Tower of London Buckingham
Palace which is the kind of the history
of great people this place is deep in
the history of kind of ordinary people
orary communities from around the world
coming and that really fits into a lot
of what we're uh what we're talking
about so this is kind of the view from
Wentworth Street which which is just up
the road. And you really get this
juiposition of the kind of the you know
the old and the new and in some sense of
the new being potentially depending from
your perspective you know like some of
us live in this end and some of us feel
like we're in the shadow of this new
that's that's changing so uh you can see
some of these things so about so this is
the sec so this is the this is the fifth
conference that we've run MIT and BT
have run together this is really the
second in a series and I think the last
one we ran two years ago was really
about this question about how do we when
we're building these new technologies,
new platforms that are going to affect
everybody. It became particularly clear
after things like the Snowden papers
that when we build a technology, we're
also embedding some values into how we
design the technology, how we govern it
and those sorts of things. So the
conference we ran two years ago was
about this idea of value. So how do
technology create value? How's that
value get spread? values, how do we
bring our uh shared objectives, shared
norms and shared kind of constraints
into those platforms and then platforms
for the future where we were going. So
this was very much a sense in which we
were beginning to the early ones we
started off with kind of blind optimism
about about innovation. Then it became a
bit more modulated by some of the things
that were happening in terms of things
like snow and those sorts of things. um
going forward I think we we've now found
ourselves two years over two years on in
a you know a different global context
and that's really part of what we're
here today and just to kind of give a
little kind of you know some thoughts on
that global context um the at the end of
the second world war there was this
point at which we moved from this kind
of globalization 1.0 that we mentioned
which was really a world that was
anchored in in empire and the end of
empire. Um we moved to the end of the
second world war effectly you know
modulo not being a historian there was a
sense we need a different way of
organizing things and we went for the
things that effectively helped the uh
the allies to win the second world war.
So focused on technology a sense that
open markets were a way of spreading
wealth and getting diversity in and
globalization and then also talking
democratic processes. We kicked that off
and that's been moving forward and
that's been our philosophical view of
where global integration plays out. In
parallel, we kicked off the digital
revolution very much started with
co-breaking during the second world war.
As those two went forward, they turned
into be extremely mutually um kind of
reinforcing. So um as we began to wire
the world, it made globalization easier.
You couldn't imagine global supply
chains without the internet. Um doing
that brought you know new skill bases in
from around the world. You you brought
things like China came online. Hundreds
of million people move from rural
poverty to the middle classes becoming
engaged in the IT you know Huawei etc.
So these have kind of gone together and
they've really raised hundreds of
millions of people's quality of living
but they've also built tensions into the
system and those tensions have been both
domestic and they've been international.
And I think it's one of the reasons why
we're beginning to see this kind of
fragmentation
of the global system and we got used to
the idea at the end of the second world
war we were going to do science
together. For example, the way to move
forward was that everybody do science
together and then we compete on the
applications and the economies. That
assumption is now being pulled apart by
things like the unwind between the US uh
Europe and China. So all those
expectations we had about this
trajectory we're on towards greater
globalization and the ways in which kind
of wealth and prosperity was spread
through that are coming under some kind
of threat. So now there's a lot more
talk about sovereign capacity. How do we
make sure that uh every nation has
access to the minerals and strategic
materials it needs? How does the US make
ensure that if it's going to succeed in
AI, it has access to computing
resources, the silicon foundaries, hence
$50 billion investment in the chips end
of the chips and science act. Um very
very different context. So the the idea
today was really to kind of explore some
of the ways we think about innovation,
some of the ways we think about
technology, some of the ways we think
about ecosystems, and some of the ways
we think about people in this more
contested
um slightly more volatile perhaps
fragile kind of um kind of global
system. So we're going to do two things
this afternoon. So one of them is we're
going to look at one of the the the kind
of you know one of the big drivers of
the change that's you know could
potentially really accelerate this
process. you know, AI has the potential
to really create winners and losers
unless we think about it in ways that
kind of raise the overall economy, raise
everybody up. Um, and then after that,
we're going to look at, you know, how
this plays out in both in toughte and
deep tech. How do we, you know, do some
of these hard things that, you know,
someone Mash had talked about earlier
on. How do we develop things like um,
uh, fusion reactors at a point in time
when global collaboration is perhaps,
you know, lower than it should be? And
then we'll match that with Alex from
Chattam House who will look at the
digital side of that as well. So
hopefully this afternoon will be kind of
a a kind of journey through some of
those kind of kind of discussions, some
of those questions. But I wanted to
start on the kind of promise side of