Hi, my name is Alexis Marcus. I'm part
of the admissions team here at MIT
Sloan.
So, is there a certain type of candidate
that Sloan's looking for within the MBA
program? Short answer is no. One of the
greatest things about the MIT Sloan MBA
program is the diversity of thought and
perspectives amongst our students.
There's no cookie cutter Sloan student.
And the great thing is that people are
coming from all sorts of undergraduate
majors as well as prembba industries.
Our program is designed for anyone who's
looking to advance in their field or
pivot in their careers.
Well, our application's open and we're
really excited to meet you. So, please
start your application today and submit
it to MIT Sloan in one of our three
rounds.