okay so um our last speaker for today's
Symposium is Professor Jen tan uh he's a
associate professor at Mila and at um uh
Montreal um he has done a lot of
exciting work on drug Discovery and
proin design um due to he couldn't come
in person today due to Visa difficulty
so he will present on Zoom uh so without
further Ado um J please take it
away okay uh so thank you thanks very
much uh W for the invitation and also
the introduction uh it's great pleasure
to be here uh unfortunately I cannot
come in person due to Visa issues
hopefully we can meet in person next
time um so in today's talk I'm going to
talk about geometric deep learning for
protein design uh I'm going to quickly
introduce the background of proteins so
as we know proteins are the work hes in
living cells so in our living cells most
of the functions actually carry out by
proteins right and that's why understand
the functions or proteins also designing
proteins of new functions is going to be
important in many different areas for
example Therapeutics anible design and
also enzy design in synthetic biology
okay and then so nowaday we actually see
a huge opportunities uh for machine
learning uh for protein design because a
huge amount of data set is generated in
btic domain like like for example we
have like tens of billions put in
sequence available we also have like U
uh uh hundreds of thousands protein
structure available in the pdb database
okay so a lot of different machine
learning techniques have been uh
developed for uh for party modeling so
these approaches are mainly uh divided
into two Tech two categories so the
first category is basically sequence
based approach so we we just represent
proteins as am sequence and then we can
use models like language models
Transformers to to model Ament acid
sequence so this one type approach so
another type approach is okay we can
represent proteins as 3D structures
right and then we can use approaches
like geometric de approach to model 3D
structures okay so in our approach in
our group so we have been take um we
have been taking the structure Centric
approach to model uh uh 3D structures
with geomet de learning okay so in
particular so we mainly trying to
address three research questions the
first research question is okay so once
we are we are given a 3D planting
structure how do we represent this 3D uh
this uh 3D protein structures right how
can we learn features out of these 3D
prot structures so this the first
research question the second one is okay
how can we as we know for most of the
proteins we don't know we don't know
there 3D uh protein structures right how
can we predict the 3D protein structures
uh from the am acid sequence this the
first the second research question of
course at end our end go is always we
want to generate we want to design new
proteins with gener models so I'm going
to focus mainly focus on the first
research question okay so in this in
this work so what we do is we actually
develop new um uh new uh 3D protein uh
geometry encoder to encode proteins into
continuous rep repetitions so our input
is a 3D protein structure and then given
this uh uh 3D uh protein structure we
first construct a graph out of this 3D
putting structure so what kind of graph
we are constructing here so this is
actually um a reso graph
so every node here is a resio okay and
then how do we Define the edges between
the resos so we we mainly make use of
two kinds of information so first is
structure information and and the second
is sequence information so for structure
information so essentially what we do
here we just construct The KES nebor
graph uh from the spatial uh information
of of of the protein structure to define
the the spatial relationship between the
residual so this is from the structur
information and then we also make use of
the sequential orders between the regos
in the protein sequence to Define
another type of like edges between the
between the uh between the regos okay
but anyway so here we will end up with a
resio graph and this graph is directed
and then the problem of learning protein
structure uh translate to learning the
repetition of the entire resue graph
okay so here we actually propose two
type of graph new networks to learn this
repetition the first uh approach is is
quite straightforward so we just do
massive passing between the reses okay
of course when we do massive passing
between the reses since there are
different type of edges between the
residues so we will also uh uh take the
edge type into consideration when we do
the mass passing okay so once we do the
mass passing so we can have a repetition
for all the different reses and then we
Su up all the res reputations to get the
repetition of the entire graph or the
entire protein structures so this are
first type of like architecture we
propose and and for the second type
approach okay we actually not not doing
massive passing between the Ros so
instead so what we do here is we
actually doing massive passing between
the edges okay for example we can do
massive passing between neighboring
edges uh two and two uh two 4 and 47
okay and then when we do Massy passing
between the edges 2 4 and 47 so we also
make use of the angle information
between the edges into into
consideration so by making use of the
angle information so we actually Bas
basically we we are basically better
able to make use of the 3D geomet
geometric structure of the proteins
right and then once we do the edge
massive passing so every Edge can have
repetition and then we can aggregate all
the edge repetition to get the
repetition of the whole proteins okay so
that's another type of like a which we
call gonet Edge okay and for both type
of approaches we actually train the
model in a superv fashion which means
we're going to train the new network
right from some label data uh
inding task so this is like superon okay
and then so we also prend the 3D
geometry encoder from some un labored
proteins so here the idea is very
similar to what we do um in um in uh in
uh image representation learning uh with
uh with like self learning so the basic
assump assumption here is okay we use
contrast learning we basically assume
that okay for two structure motives if
they are from the same proteins so then
their repetitions should similar
otherwise their repetition should be uh
dissimilar so that's the high level idea
okay and then so we evalu the mods on
some Downstream uh task like for example
enzyme commission number predictions for
the ction these are some classical um
protein understanding task and then in
terms of pring dat so we actually try
different the pring uh um protein
structure database one is the pdb uh
experimental uh um uh um uh structures
and another one the predicted structures
by Alpha 42 okay so here we can quickly
look at the results of the super
learning um uh uh uh performance so we
compare our approaches with some like
sequence base and also graph base so our
approaches is able to outperform both
the sequence and graph base approach
which is not surprising because we make
use of the 3D structures right and then
in particular if you compare the gear
net and also the gear net Edge so gear
net only makes use of the no the the
which do mass pass between the resid but
for gear net and Ed we actually make use
of we do Mass passing between the
between the edges which is B basically
better uh able to better make use of the
edge uh the the 3D geometric code so you
can see the performance is actually
significantly improved uh compared to
the gonet and then so after doing PR
training you can see the performance is
further improved compared to the super
wi like training so you see PR train is
is is indeed able to improve the
performance okay and then so we also
like do some aeration study on the
preing so we actually try different
pre-training database is the pdb
database which are experimental
structures and also the other four to uh
predict the protein structures so we
actually see that our prity model is
actually quite robust is a trend on the
experimental structures and also maybe
also the predictive prot structures by
Al too okay so this so so this is the
the first work and then we apply this
kind of like a structure pring and the
fine tuning idea to a real world problem
which is antibody optimization so as we
know in practice sometimes the
antibodies like like for example the
antibodies of turn through anyal
immunizations so we usually sometimes we
we need to do lead optimization right so
we need we need to do some mutations to
improve the Bing Affinity so in
particular for for this problem so what
we what we have is okay we have antibody
uh binding to a specific antigen right
and then we want to make some mutations
in the interface to improve the B
Infinity so m mathmatically what we want
to do is we actually want to build a
binding Affinity change predicted models
so we want to we want to predict okay if
we make some mut mutations on the
interface so what's going to be the by
Infinity change right so we want to
build this this Delta Del G uh predict
model so which is the difference between
the Bing free energy of the mutant and
also and and the Bing free the Bing free
energ of the the Y type okay and so so
this is the goal okay so you know Bing
affinities essentially most the the The
Binding Infinity most of the time we
mainly actually look at the interface
between the two uh protein structure to
two proteins right so you see for this
model Al also we also trying to model
the protein structures but for this for
this problem so we want to model the
interactions between two proteins
instead of like a single protein okay so
here we also uh so this a new work we
publish in this is like natural
Communications so this a new uh Al
so this for this uh work we also uh
adopt the pring and also fine tuning
framework so we first prend the model on
a huge number of like unlabeled protein
protein complex structure so that the
model is able to understand how
different proteins interact okay and
then we fine tune the model based on
some experimental data to build this
like by the infinity um uh change
predict model and then we can apply this
model to to real what the uh scenarios
we can can do in cical um screening and
identify some mutants which could lead
to higher Bing Infinity okay so this is
the main idea so we can start from the
pre turnning stage as as I just said so
for pre turnning so we're going to we're
going to pre return the model on protein
protein complex structure because our
goal is trying to understand how
different proteins interact okay so so
that's why we prend the model on protein
protein comp structure and then so uh we
also use like um uh contrast learning
idea okay so what we do here is okay we
take a natural protein protein complex
structure we mainly take the interface
so these are so this a posit pair right
so this a natural interface and then
what we do is we also make some
mutations on the interface and this this
is basically netive pair right so we we
we we do some mutations on the interface
okay we mutate the residues we change
one residue to another reg but then for
the mutated reg we also quickly um
update the structure with some efficient
siton structure predict model for
example we can sample from R Library we
can also optimize with some physic based
approaches right but then now we have
this like two two different structures
and now now we want to distinguish
whether this is a natural structure a
natural complex natural interface or a
mutated ones right so we use the graph
new networks or geomet planing to encode
the two different 3D structures right
and then we build the classify to to to
to to distinguish the two right so this
is the preing stage okay and then in the
F tuning stage as we just said we
essentially we just want to predict uh
build the predict model to predict the
Bing Infinity change so here we actually
find to the model with some experimental
data so in the experiment data like a
scan pie so we have a protein protein
comp structure and then we are given
some mutations and people already have
test the B Infinity changed for
different mutations right so that's the
the the data we use to to find the model
so we here we do do a similar things
right so we have the Y type protein
protein structures or antigen antibody
structures right and then we have some
mutations we take the two structure as
input and then you can get the
reputations of the two two comple
structures but at end here we are not
trying to do binary cation because here
we are actually trying to predict the B
Infinity change which is d d g okay and
so this model is is uh we're going to
find tun this model based on the uh
experimental Del theology data okay by
doing this so we are able to build a
predict model to by Infinity change
given any mutations on the interface
okay so once we have this model okay
we're going we're going to do some like
evaluations in cations so here we do
cross validations on the scampa data set
so we compare with some traditional
physic based methods like f x f CDG and
also some recent deep running Bas based
methods so you can see our G gyte can
aeve better performance compared to
transition approaches and then after
doing pre-training so our model actually
achieve the best performance among all
these methods so this is some in cical
evation okay and then you may Wonder
okay can this model be applied to real
world problems yes so we actually
collaborate with some biologist uh for
like antibody optimization so here's a
case like we have so our like
collaborator has a um sasco 2 antibody
actually this is not sasco 2 this is a
antibody um collected actually Harvest
from sasc one patient and then they want
to optimize this antibod so that it can
Target uh against the uh the Omicron
variant so they already have this like
um antibody and also sasco 2 um um uh uh
antigen uh complex and then we use our
models to do some in cical screening so
in the first round so we identify some
single mutations we pretty much identify
like I think s or eight uh single
mutations and also the best uh double
mutations and then we test them in the
we laap okay and and then once we finish
the first round we experiments okay we
can identify a few good single mutations
and then in the second round we just do
comori mutations we we mainly test like
uh double mutations and also triple
mutations so as end we are able to
identify a good mutant with three
mutations and this these mutants
actually by Infinity has improved at 77
F and actually this problem is quite
challenging because for the or antibody
uh the Bing Affinity is is already like
one Nal and now we able to improve to
like 0.06 Nal so so this actually the
problem is quite quite challenged so
this is the
first case study we we did with our a
okay and then we actually also
collaborate with another group which has
a similar problem so they also have like
sasco 2 antibody and then they want to
optimize this antibody to uh to to
neutralize against the new variant gm1
so we did a similar SC so in the first
mutation in the first round we we we we
we do uh inal screening so we
identify some good single mutations and
in the second round we combine them to
do double or triple mutations eventually
so we actually identify a good mutant U
which the the B Infinity has uh improved
over 300 FS compared to the the white
type okay and this paper now is actually
um in Revision in pen so so this a
second case study okay
and then so I probably do not have time
to to cover the uh the details of the
other uh work we have done so for for 3D
putting structures and also denov design
I'm going to quickly uh uh summarize
some work we have done in in in in these
two directions okay so for the first
work div pack uh so we mainly work on S
and structure predictions so you guys
probably all know like U uh uh models
like Ava fold to esm fold right but
remember that for Ava fold to esm fold
so they they main need work on
uh uh predicting the backbone backbone
structures of proteins right uh so
actually the cyons predicted by a v to
and and yes yes V so they're not
accurate so that's why in this
particular work so what we did is we
actually proposed diffusion models um to
accurately uh predict the cyon structure
as a protein so you know cyon structure
prediction is very important like uh for
drug design because you know for for for
either for small molecule or or protein
right so so so interactions between two
molecules is actually mainly happened
through through through the Cain
interaction so that's why citon
structure prediction is is very very
important problem so what we did in this
work we actually proposed a defusion
model to to to to generate or or predict
the the the S structures of the of the C
so essentially just generate the 3D
coordinates of the of the
atom uh as you because for uh siton um
uh so uh so their degree of freedom is
not the 3D coordinates of the Aton so
actually made controlled by the uh
different the four toal angles and
that's why in this new work uh in this
work U we actually didn't uh do
diffusion in the cardan space so instead
of what we do is we actually did a
diffusion we propos a diffusion model in
the torsion space so that's the main
idea of this work so I'm not going into
the details okay and then for the second
work this is also Rel to protein
structure prediction as we know like for
Alpha 42 and also yes F they only
predict a single structure for each uh
protein sequence but but we know like
each protein can take multiple
confirmations right and that's why here
we actually try to predict multiple
confirmations for given
the amino acid sequence right so the the
high idea is we got some inspiration
from traditional like a mole Dynamic
approaches especially the the approach
collect simulated okay and then we CH
joint models essential of diffusion
models uh to to to generate multiple
confirmations given the uh given given a
single M&S sequence so I'm not going to
details so this paper is accept in dcsi
clear okay and so this is the second one
and then finally for the diffusion
models and this is very latest work we
did like U just we just put uh put it on
I on
on arive so for this problem we want to
given a small molecule we want to design
a a protein Bing into this small
molecule okay so here we actually
propose a model to uh based on the flow
matching framework to model The Joint
distribution of the protein nen complex
and then given uh the the the chemical
graph so we can uh we can use flow
magion to S
simultaneously uh generate the protein
lant 3D comp structure okay so that we
can eventually we can go like proteins
binding to the 3D molecule B binding to
the the the the given Lian okay so I
will WRA WRA here so essentially
so in our group so we have been taking a
structure Centric approach to model 3D
uh structures of proteins so we mainly
make use techniques like geomet deep
learning and also diffusion models for
Manion to to model different kinds of
props in proteins in particular how to
represent 3D protein structures how to
how to better predict um uh protein
structures like citr the Dynamics and
also protein protein comp structure
prediction of course at end we care
about how can we design new proteins
with diffusion models with FR with
models like frion so that's all I want
to show thank you very much
okay great thank you d for your
wonderful talk uh any questions
um uh I actually have questions about um
your uh uh design part which you
couldn't really um go into too much
detail but uh how are you are you
generating both the Li and protein
simultaneously or your the given the
Lian confirmation is actually
given oh that's a good question so I
think so for many of a recent work the
the 3D lean structure is given so so um
in all this latest work we actually only
um give the the the 2D chemical graph as
input so the 3D confirmation of the Lian
is not given
okay and do you know the binding pocket
location or you are just gener okay we
we don't we don't assume the Bing pocket
is is given just the input is just
arbitary so just a like Lian so only the
sequence or the chemic graph is given
and then we want to generate a protein
which is able to bind to the the the the
LI but but but you're right so so we
also now doing some testing
or proposing some new varant so okay
maybe we know that we are The Binding
positions of the lean okay so in that
case we can also do some more
controllable uh protein design okay you
want to design proteins bind into
specific regions of the of the the small
molecule yeah
great uh so since we are already over
time so let's give our speaker one more
round of
applause thank you very much