All
right, our next speaker is Stephen
Barnes from uh MIT's Misty UK and
Netherlands, I believe. Stephen, um not
to forget our friends over there. Um
where we Melissa had already mentioned
Misty UK, but without further ado,
Stephen, thanks.
>> Thank you.
>> Hi everyone. Um, my name is Steven
Barnes. I am the managing director of
the MIT UK program uh, first of all and
the and the Netherlands program. Thanks
to the uh, ILP and to to BT for hosting
us here today. I'm going to talk a
little bit about the Misti program that
Melissa mentioned at the end of her
remarks um, and how we engage MIT
students in the UK and all around the
world through experiential education. So
um MISTI stands for MIT International
Science and Technology Initiatives. We
sit within a unit at MIT which is called
the Center for International Studies. Um
and we're focused on we're definitely
interested in sustainable aviation
solutions because we send about 1,200
students abroad every year. Um we work
in all of these different countries
around the world and we also have
faculty collaborations um in many of the
countries that we work in. Um these are
the areas that we work in. Um
my focus is UK and Netherlands as I
mentioned. Um and why do we exist? Why
is Misti a thing? Why you know students
are at MIT. It's this incredible
institution for science, technology,
engineering. um why would they want to
leave? Um well, it's embedded in MIT's
mission um that we are working with
others to bring the knowledge to bear on
the world's greatest challenges. So,
it's a fundamental part of MIT. We've
heard about it today about the the
stakeholders and the ecosystem. Um it's
not just in labs in Cambridge,
Massachusetts. It's also out in the
world. Um so the programs that we run um
there are four different kinds of
programs that I'm going to or three
really that I'll focus on today. Um
internships so these are hands-on
projects uh all around the world
typically for three months. Teaching
programs where we send students to um
teach in schools um and um further
education colleges. um study abroad, the
the more traditional kind of going to
either enroll in institutions around the
world or to travel with MIT faculty
members where they participate in more
hands-on workshops and then seed funds
seeding early uh collaboration early
stage uh research collaborations for MIT
faculty and researchers um with um peers
around the world. Um so just a uh a
quick overview mo we work with students
from all across the institute about 75%
of our students are undergraduates about
25% of our students are are graduate
students um and what makes MIT unique?
Why is it different? There aren't many
other universities in fact I don't think
there's any other university that I know
of that really is focused on um
providing these handson
um projectbased opportunities for
students. It's very common for there to
be a study abroad office in the UK. We
used to have Arasmus, but you know, we
have um exchange programs where students
will go and enroll in other
universities. But being MIT, we're
really focused on embedding students in
industry, embedding students in research
um as early as we can. Um
we have a pretty intensive preparation
process for the students. Thankfully for
me, the preparation to send a student to
the UK is less intense than my
colleagues who send students to Japan.
Um, I have to teach them how to make a
cup of tea without putting the tea bag
in the microwave. Um,
you joke about it, but it's true. Um, I
have to teach them that when you come
into work and people say, "You're
right." That's just a greeting. They're
not actually worried about your mental
state. Um, but so we prepare the
students before they go so they can hit
the ground running when they're here.
Um, and then crucially for students,
it's a costneutral program. So, we're
not charging students. We're not an
internship provider that ask students to
pay for the experience. We want this to
be available to all students regardless
of their background. So, we actively
fund raise. We ask companies to cover
the full cost so that students can have
these international experiences
regardless of um where they're coming
from. Um, why do companies do it? Why do
companies want to bring students from
MIT? Um first of all that you know
there's access to worldclass talent and
the students can make a real tangible
impact right from the beginning. Um when
I talk with companies here in the UK
they say well it's great we have
students we can get a student from
Imperial we can get a student from UCL
we can get a student from Oxford
Cambridge and those are all brilliant
students as well. Um I think one of the
things that sets MIT students apart is
again goes back to what Melissa was
talking about earlier. the students are
used to working incredibly hard and they
want to be challenged. So most of our
students because of the visa they come
on, there's a special internship visa
and you're not really supposed to work
more than 40 hours a week. For our
students, 40 hours a week, that's like a
summer vacation that when they're at
MIT, they're doing 40 hours a week of
classroom work and then they're probably
doing another 40 hours a week of their
their clubs, their activities, all that
kind of stuff. So, um, they can come in
over a 3-month period and really bring
immediate value and look at, um,
problems from a different perspective.
Another thing that makes it valuable for
companies is that they're building
relationships with these students, these
very impressive students at a really
critical point in their career
trajectory. So, the mentorship, the
relationships that are built with the
internship supervisors at a young age
can go on to, you know, 5 years, 10
years, 15 years down the line. those
relationships that students build with
the with their um hosts can rebound back
to them. Um and then finally, exposure
to new ideas and and latest thinking
coming out of MIT. So many MIT students,
I'm not sure exactly what the statistic
is. It might be close to 90% of MIT
students who do Europs. I'm not sure
>> over 90 so over 90% of MIT undergraduate
students will participate in
undergraduate research when they're at
MIT. So what that means is that they're
doing 10, 15, 20 hours a week of
research in a lab. So these aren't just
students who are sitting in lectures
ingesting information. They're actually
doing the hands-on research work at MIT.
And that they bring that knowledge, they
bring that expertise, they bring that
perspective to the companies that
they're working in. So that's a a kind
of general overview of the program as a
whole, the UK program specifically. Um
so it began as a pilot in 2015 with
thanks to Phil uh and Fiona who are our
faculty directors. Um so it's been
around for about 10 years. Um but it's
grown hugely in the last few years.
Obviously we had COVID where we couldn't
send anybody for a couple of years. And
to some of the the the the previous
questions about you know remote
collaboration and what what Masha was
saying about being in person you know
having the whiteboard being able to
collaborate in person the remote
internships were not a huge success.
I'll just put it that way. Especially
for students at the the beginning of
their career, the in-person in-off
interactions um with peers is really
where a huge amount of learning happens,
not just by the project that they run,
but also by osmosis being in the same
physical space. Um so the UK program
started about 10 years ago as a pilot.
Um now we send about 60 students or last
couple of summers we sent about 60
students to the UK every summer. The UK
for obvious reasons is um a popular
destination among MIT students. We speak
the same language mostly um and we um
that the the focus on innovation,
science, technology, engineering, there
are companies here that students want to
work at and crucially also place it's a
place where students might consider
moving after they graduate. Um the
students that we work with, so I
mentioned this before, we work with
students from all across the institute.
So everything from first year
undergraduates all the way to PhD
students and recent graduates. We
actually have a recently graduated PhD
student here. Where's Venit? I'm going
to call you out. Yeah, a recently
graduated PhD student who's interning at
Shell um for a few months. So we work
with students from all across the board
um and from all majors as well, all
departments. But typically what we see,
I don't know if you can see this in the
back, but there's a heavy focus on um
you know things that you would expect
there to be in the UK. There's a lot of
computer science, machine learning, AI
projects, a lot in life sciences and
health, energy, sustainability, uh
climate um but really these key sectors
that align with um the UK government's
industrial strategy uh quite well as
well. Um
some of the companies that we work with,
we really work with um everything from
large corporates. Some of these names
will be very familiar to you. Some of
these are you know startups with 15 20
people. Um and then we work with a lot
of universities as well where students
are embedded in labs and research
institutes as well. Um so um it's really
quite a a wide mix. Um
a few examples. So this is Christina. Um
she was at the welcome Sangra Institute.
So she graduated, spent six months at
the Sanger Institute doing research in
women's reproductive health. She liked
it so much that actually she she after
she graduated she decided to apply for a
visa. There are all kinds of visa routes
now to attract, you know, very high
potential international talent to the UK
so they can stay for longer. Um so she
actually converted her visa to stay and
become a full-time um lab researcher at
the Sanger and then um from there
applied for uh the Gates scholarship
where she's now studying at at at the
University of Cambridge. We have Sonia.
She was uh she's an economics major. She
was here this past summer working at
Barclays on sustainable finance um and
is actually coming back to London. They
made her a return offer and she decided
that she wanted to give London a try.
She came in the summer, so we won't tell
her about the rest of the year. Um, and
then um, a couple of others. It's not
just London, it's not just the
Southeast, we have students in Scotland.
We had Emma this summer who was at
Scottish Power working on
sustainability. And as I was talking
about, the hosts really talk about how
it's not just um, the technical
expertise, it's also the the fresh
perspective, a new way of looking at at
problems that makes a difference. Um and
then finally in in Manchester we had the
last two summers we've had uh four
students every summer at at a tech
company called Matilian working on AI
projects related to their cloud data
platform something that is more beyond
my knowledge. Um
so that those are just a few examples of
the of the kinds of uh companies and and
placements that we might do. That's the
internship program. The other program
that we run um we also have some
partners in the room today um from our
global teaching labs program. This is a
program that we run over January. Um and
again I think this speaks a little bit
to what makes MIT students unique. So at
MIT there's a the January period is
called international activities period.
It's a month where um there's lots of
things going on on campus. There are
workshops, hackathons, some classes but
students don't have to be there. They
could be on the beach in Hawaii. They
could be skiing in Colorado. Um, lots of
them want to come to wet, rainy England
or Wales or Scotland. Um, and teach STEM
classes, workshops, um, and hands-on
kind of educational programming. So, we
send students to the UK every January.
We have about 20 who come to uh
different schools up and down the
country um spreading their enthusiasm
for STEM and hopefully inspiring UK
students to um maybe follow in their
footsteps or certainly get involved in
STEM. Um and again what they're doing is
they're bringing this kind of
interdisciplinary
project-based learning. None of them are
trainy teachers. So they're they're not
in a a kind of teacher track. They're
very much scientists, engineers, but
they've had experience and exposure of
MIT's curriculum, MIT's teaching
methods, and they come in and they
infuse the uh or infuse the the
classrooms that they're working with
with that same energy and and mindset.
Um and then finally uh before I close
the the other program that I wanted to
mention is our global seeds fund global
seed funds program which um offers small
travel grants to support MIT faculty to
collaborate with peers around the world.
So um there's a a general fund where
applicants from universities anywhere in
the world can apply to to come to MIT,
bring their students to MIT and and for
MIT faculty and and their students to
travel to other countries. Um we do
prioritize um um proposals that include
students. We want students to be part
again coming back to this piece about
undergraduate research getting the
students involved at an early stage. um
we really prioritize that. Um this has
been running since about 2008. Um about
$26 million have been awarded during
that period. Some of that is central
funding that comes from MIT. Again
coming back to MIT's mission, we want to
support uh these international
collaborations and then some of it are
um funds that are sponsored by a third
party or by a local um or national uh
institution that wants to increase
collaboration with um MIT faculty in
that area. So those are just a few of
the programs that we run at uh MIT at
the Center for International Studies. Um
I'll leave it there. Uh my contact
information is here. If you're
interested in bringing an MIT student to
your company, to your school, to your
university, uh please come and chat with
me or connect with me on LinkedIn. Thank
you.