And now I'm very much looking forward to
introducing the next speaker of today
who will be talking about new lean, the
new production system paradigm for the
automotive industry. And he's going to
highlight the necessary characteristics
for production systems of the future
while going into detail on the
corresponding building blocks from
digital transformation and artificial
intelligence including practical
examples from industry. So ladies and
gentlemen, please give a big warm
welcome to the executive director of
Franhova Institute for Manufacturing
Engineering and Automation. Here's
Thomas Bowen Hansel.
[Music]
Good
morning. Good morning everybody and
thanks for having me and giving me the
opportunity to talk about um yeah a new
paradigm a new manufacturing paradigm
and um we developed that paradigm or we
started to develop it just one and a
half years ago together with the
automotive industry in um in Germany. So
I'm located in Stoutkat um and and we
are in the middle of a transformation in
the automotive industry especially in
Stoutkat a lot of suppliers you can
imagine which are under pressure because
of the um transformation to more
electrified cars
um the the digital transformation is as
well an important topic. So there the
pressure is high on the on the actual uh
suppliers especially the suppliers in
the automotive sector and we asked um
Mercedes and BMW and Porsche and
Seammens and uh and the company Dur some
of you maybe know them they are uh um
yeah very famous for their surface uh uh
painting technologies which are mainly
used in the in the automotive sector and
together with the COOs and their teams
we started to work on on that topic. Uh
how should the production system of the
future in the mot automotive sector look
like? Uh that was the question and um it
was more or less driven by the topic
productivity. Ben already talked about
that and about the importance of
productivity and when you look at the um
situation especially on the situation of
value adding automotive value adding in
Germany there's a high pressure on
productivity in the moment because of
the high costs we have for our uh
skilled people for energy uh and uh
bureaucracy costs and so on maybe it's
similar to Austria uh but it's I think
it's even worse in in Germany um out of
my point of view. And when you look at
the productivity development of
economies and here you see uh an
analysis of Gordon who analyze the
productivity growth rate over many many
years um uh based on the figures of the
United Kingdom and the United States.
You see that the um increase of
productivity per year was dramatic up to
the 1970s, 1980s and then it goes down
and or it went down and and Gordon
expect that it will go down on the same
level we had maybe 200 300 years ago and
uh some other institutions like the IG
seta they say okay we think there will
be there must be a push yeah of the
productivity
increase because of the conveance of the
beautiful new technologies we will hear
about today and you all know we
mentioned already artificial
intelligence um digital tools but as
well biotechnology and other things.
This should help us to really push the
development and um why is productivity
so important when um this is as well um
an a study of of the IG seta uh they
said okay productivity is important or
let's check what is the influence of
productivity on the wealth status of uh
Germany we have here the GDP per capita
in 2022 and if you do nothing this will
go down till 2070
by
€6,000 um per per inhabitant in in
Germany. And then the question was okay
will immigration help us? Will uh value
adding participation help us? So the
people should work more not maybe 32
hours maybe 40 hours and in average I
think women in Germany work 28 hours per
week. So we increase that as well. So
what effect will that have on our wealth
status? And the last question was okay
we increase productivity by 0.8 1.2 or
1.5% per year and you see the biggest
effect not surprisingly is um the
productivity increase. So we should
focus um on that topic. Unfortunately,
Ben already mentioned that there is no
productivity increase over the last 10
years. In Germany 2011, we started with
industry industry 4.0 digital
transformation of industry, the
expectations were extremely high. And
when we look back now uh and when we
check or analyze the the last 14 years,
there is no productivity increase. In
some areas, uh, productivity, uh, went
down in some industry sectors and Ben as
well mentioned the driver for
productivity in industrial production
was in the last years the Toyota uh,
production system and maybe all of you
working in in industry sectors have
something similar. There is a Mercedes
production system. There is a Seammen's
production system in Germany. They all
have their own production system. So
they copied more or less the Toyota
production systems the principles and
this occurred in the by the in the end
of the 1980s driven by MIT professors uh
warm and Jones some of you know the
famous book uh the machine that changed
the world and uh now the idea was hm
maybe we need as well a moment like that
now in manufacturing and um we should
analyze what do we have to change u in
in order to achieve that productivity
increase, in order to maintain our
manufacturing in Germany, especially in
the automotive sector and maybe even
increase the amount of value adding uh
industrial value adding in in the German
economy. And um first of all we analyzed
okay where do we exec expect the the
main changes and the uh the result of
the study was okay in the field of goals
maybe a little bit because we have to
integrate sustainability topics u then
uh big changes on the on the process
level and as well most changes in on the
on the tools level. So we have new tools
which we can integrate and which we can
use to increase productivity. And
um uh one uh uh finding was as well that
we need more a systemic approach because
when you look at at the actual digital
transformation in manufacturing
companies, it's often use case driven,
right? So the the boss is coming home
from a conference like that and then he
goes directly to the shop floor and said
hey artificial intelligence yeah it
seems to be a gamecher in the future uh
what are we doing in that area and then
some teams some projects maybe a student
yeah he starts then with a uh artificial
intelligence use case and whenever the
bus boss come back yeah you switch on
the light and then you show him that use
case and when he uh leaves leave the
factory, you switch out the light and
you work like you ever did. Yeah, that's
in many
areas in many in many sectors that's uh
the actual situation. So it's very use
case driven. Maybe some use cases are
beautiful use cases they work but they
have no systemic influence on the
performance of the company of the
manufacturing system. So and as well
digitization is under represented as
well in the philosophy and in the
culture. So we we said we need more
radical changes and the question was
yeah in which direction do we have to
think and how can we achieve this
systemic change in production especially
in the automotive sector.
Yeah, I already talked about the
challenges. I don't I I don't uh think
that I have um to repeat it.
Um but but we have as beside the
challenges and the the competitive
pressure coming out of China um I heard
now that in China they have in the
meantime
350 automotive
OEMs. 350. Yeah.
uh and uh yeah no I think none of of
these companies do really earn money or
are profitable in the profitable in the
moment. Yeah. So the pressure there is
as well very high and we see now based
on the actual political situation the
the competitive pressure will uh
dramatically increase out of our point
of view. So these are not uh these are
very difficult challenges but we already
heard uh Ben mentioned that that in
South Carolina there was um a real
change in productivity and in in the
manufacturing potential because of a
more
um um yeah systemic approach ecosystem
approach and in Germany and as well in
Austria we have already these ecosystems
in place. We have excellent technology
providers. We have research
institutions. We have politicians who
know that manufacturing is essential and
they have to invest. um you have
universities, we have uh all these
market leaders in their niches and we
have excellent ecosystems and we have to
use that potential right and when we
talk about future production um
sustainability on one hand but mainly
productivity u is key and that was the
reason uh why we focused on that um uh
together with uh that team of companies
uh which I have um already mentioned. So
we what what have we done? We did uh a
lot of interviews. 108 experts were were
interviewed. We analyzed more than 68
uh technologies and approaches with uh
disruptive potential. And we um focused
that down on 27 specific profiles. And
we did as well a survey and we asked in
which areas do we expect um um the um
the highest potential concerning
innovation. So we divided the
innovations, manufacturing innovations
in these uh seven groups. Digital
innovations, automation, process
innovation but as well production
structures, the whole value creation
model. So the shift of value adding
maybe to suppliers uh everything as a
service approaches, things like that.
organizational innovations and
infrastructure. Infrastructure more
focused on electrification on
um new new networks which we have to
implement. And you see uh the
expectation is that in the digital and
in the automotion in uh innovation space
we see uh the biggest potential uh which
is for all of us for all of you uh I
think not very um surprising and um uh
in a nutshell we defined as well a
vision together with uh the companies
and we said uh till
2035 we want to produce environmentally
neutral and we want to achieve a 100%
higher productivity compared to 2023. So
a real um huge ambition. Um and the the
the focus was now to find out is it
possible to achieve these goals with
specific systemic approaches and u we
showed that based on on scenarios we we
u uh we built together with the with the
OEMs and uh uh we
built a kind of systemic
uh model with different um areas digital
the digital ization area, uh the
automation area, the ecosystem area and
the human and organizational area. We
put that all together and then um we uh
analyzed three different scenarios. Uh
the first scenario was the base
scenario. So we do nothing. We do it
like we did it in the past. Uh a clear
brownfield approach. The second one was
a more evolutionary scenario as well a
brownfield approach. So we include uh
the technologies in our approach as soon
as they are mature and uh the more
radical scenario. So with real more yeah
with more investments uh large
brownfield
approach in some areas as well a green
field approach u and as well we include
organizational uh innovations and and
more radical uh concept for automation
and uh
digitalization. Uh here's in a nutshell
the comparison of the main drivers. So
in the base scenario it's only
continuous improvement. The evolutional
scenario is focusing on emerging
technologies, standardization of data as
well on collaboration
um and uh intensive work together with
the technology suppliers and the more
radical scenario is focusing on a
massive improvement of the databases. So
data is everything and it's the core of
the production system of the future. Um
the complete harmonization of the system
landscape. So a completely new IT
architecture more driven by a so-called
factory operating uh system um uh a
continuous and efficient integration of
AI in all automation technologies
um uh high um yeah um um a targeted
increase in the automated automation
oriented product design which is
extremely relevant especially for the
automotive industry. So when we do not
change or if we don't if we do not use
the possibilities we have based on the
change from the classical uh car to the
electrified um car we cannot fulfill the
requirements of a highly productive uh
manufacturing. So we we have to really
design components and systems for
automation. that is also a key
finding and as well a very strong
improvement in
cooperation. Um the whole thing is uh
technologydriven finally. So u
technology is is key to achieve these
goals and uh we as well develop then a
kind of yeah structure for us in order
to really find out what are now the the
next steps to achieve these radical
changes and to see the effects in our in
our target system. And as I mentioned
for the time being um companies often
work on that uh enabling technologies
level very use case driven as I
mentioned a you see an AI solution and
then you use it you see a a new
augmented reality solution and you start
to use it in maintenance for example um
or you have some uh some digital twin
approaches or you try to integrate um
your uh your suppliers with the help of
a data base, but it's often uh driven by
by single uh technologies or single
solution uh modules. And in the
discussion with our u with our partners,
we said okay um is there something more
than a single uh technology and we call
that then systemic technology platform.
So the convance of different solutions
into one platform technology which which
really has the potential to be the
enabler for radical change in
manufacturing. And you see here some of
of these um systemic technology
platforms which we have defined um one
we call machine competence with which is
the embodiment of AI physical AI
approach. Agentic AI is a very important
topic. Um a factory operating system as
well to use the industrial metaverse. Um
some things like dexterity I will
explain later. And then you see you can
use different enabling technologies here
in light blue to create the systemic
platform. And this systemic platform is
then the main enabler for radical change
in that sector. The automation of
automation and that will then have
really an effect on your manufacturing
system. So you need this systemic chain
thinking uh in order to uh uh to really
have then the right decisions in place
and you should start on the right side.
You should ask yourself what is the
effect I want to achieve? What kind of
radical change do I need? Yeah. And what
what kind of systemic platform is then
the enabler for that? And then you can
ask the question okay and what are then
the the core technologies in that
platform and who is the supplier? Do I
have to develop it by myself or do I buy
it somewhere and um which corporations
do I need to fulfill all the
requirements finally to achieve the
effect in my target
system? Yeah. And maybe some ideas
behind that topic uh systemic uh uh
innovative or technology platforms. Um
we see in the moment um that we move
more and more into the field of AI um
agents and the difference is compared
now to Gen AI that I do not only ask a
question and get an answer when I have
an AI agent he's doing something for me.
Yeah. So I I want to buy a material for
example and I have an a supplier AI
agent and I just ask that AI agent to
buy it for me and I need it for in a
specific quality in with a specific
price and then the II agent is doing
that for me or I have a customer order
and I have to blend this customer order
and then I ask the AI agent to do that
for me. So he executes something and
there's an action behind. So and that is
really a gamecher because these agents
they have memory functions they have the
ability to react
um they have predefined objectives they
can they are able to optimize themselves
and we see in the moment a lot of
developments going into that direction
especially on the softwaredefined
process um side. So when you talk about
business processes, order to cache
processes, you can use ex in a extremely
efficient way these new
possibilities. And um what we are
focusing on, we use this agent and AI um
approach to automize step-by-step
engineering processes. So we call that
the automation of automation. uh there
is a lack of engineers and when you
create a new automation line you have to
invest a lot of money uh into the
engineering uh into the software
programming and so on and we are already
uh um or we we we developed um a lot of
solutions in the in the last years uh to
automate engineering processes like the
automation of the uh planning of the
assembly sequence um we've created here
a startup uh offering that in the
market. The completely design of a
system, the layout optimization, the
risk assessment, the uh configuration
and and programming of the machines,
those the whole software and as well
some other uh features like uh
autonomous navigation and that will
dramatically u uh speed up your
engineering processes. For example, when
when we talk about the automated
assembly sequence, uh this reduces the
time you need for planning by more than
90%. So you're definitely faster and you
need um less experienced people to do
that. So this is a productivity driver
to think about automation of automation
or another example, this this example is
already in place. We we um developed
that together with Porsche.
Um so we we uh um developed an AI tool
to anticipate
uh customer orders and then we use this
uh virtual customer orders to um um uh
to already order uh the the longunning
components in the supply chain. And then
when the real customer order is coming,
we can just reconfigure the whole order
and we can use these components and we
can offer uh uh shorter delivery times.
Yeah. And this is the whole thing is
completely AI driven and Porsche is now
implementing uh that topic and that
helps to reduce the stock level and to
increase um uh the delivery
performance. Oh, the wrong button sorry.
Um, next topic I would like to stress
are humanoid uh robots. I think you all
heard about this development already and
uh you need a lot of enabling
technologies. Um when you go into that
uh direction of radical change with the
help of humanized robots, BMW is working
on that very intensively. yesterday or
um in in Shutgat already there is or in
Shukat is in the moment the European
robotic forum yesterday
uh Yakutza the COO of Mercedes presented
their humanoid robots approach and uh
Mercedes now in in invested around 4050
million euros intronic
uh they have a system it's called Apollo
I don't know if some of them of you
maybe know this system so they invest
own money into that uh startup uh in
order then to create their own humanoid
robots with this uh Mercedes star on on
the chest. Yeah. Uh looks very nice. Uh
and he showed some videos what what they
are doing as well. Milan Nelkovich is
has shown me some videos. They work
together with another startup in the
United States. So all the automotive uh
OEMs in Germany, they work very
intensively on that topic and I I'm
going to explain why. Um and the the the
core technology or the one or the the
very important technology enablers
behind that is to is to focus on
dexterity. So to rebuild uh the hand of
a of a human being for a robot. You see
some examples and u uh the big challenge
is then to reorient parts in a
mechanical hand. So you take some
something and you can reorient it and
then you can assemble it. Um Nvidia is
working on that. We are working on that
and we see uh there are real huge
increases in capability in the last
especially in the last six months and
most of these uh approaches are based on
virtual twins. Um so you have you create
synthetic data and with a synthetic data
you train then the artificial
intelligence uh methods you need in
order to realize these systems.
Just a
second. Yeah. And
um um and the the idea of of that
humanoid robot is that you copy a human
being and the and the humanoid robot is
able to do everything what a human being
can do. Finally, u most of the experts
say we don't know if we really will see
that in the future, but the different uh
building blocks of a humanoid robot,
these building blocks are very interest
uh interesting for for other machine
designs and uh we call that uh in the in
the meantime machine competence. So we
enable machines to be competent
competent like u human beings. So the
the tip of the mountain maybe is the the
humanite robot. But below that
development, our expectation is that all
machine systems, all production assets
in
manufacturing will become more and more
competent like human beings with the
help of the embodiment of artificial
intelligence. And so the idea behind
that um humanoid robot can be
transferred to all other machines as
well. And you can as well use then
technologies which are maybe developed
for a humanoid robot and you can
integrate that in your machine tools.
Yeah. And we some maybe some building
blocks like simple control, the uh
flexibility which is by design
integrated, the autonomous action that
you maybe have some handling systems
which are able to handle things like
human beings and as well that you can
easily train a system like that with the
help of imitation learning. And
companies like to for example um they
work in in sheet metal processing. They
already started to make their machines
competent. they worked as well with us
on on that topic. So we integrate um
human capabilities, competence
capabilities in machines so they can
make their own decisions, they can
optimize uh the process by by themselves
and and
end. And last but not least, I would uh
u like to focus as well on uh a
structural change in in manufacturing.
We call that the matrix uh production.
So when you look at the classical uh
automotive um
uh fac when you look into a classical
automotive factory you see the assembly
line like Ford has designed 100 years or
even 120 years ago and um what we do is
we uh we break now the assembly lines in
specific process modules and we connect
these specific process modules then with
the help of a fully automated
interlogistic system. So the all the
material and the product moves around by
itself on HVs to specific processes to
get processed and to get finally
finished uh and sold to the customer. So
we don't have these tacted hardly
interlink lines anymore. We have the
possibility that every uh product can
take another way through the factory
through this matrix of different uh
production modules. And the idea behind
that uh that is that we combine the
productivity of an assembly line with
the flexibility of a single workstation.
Yeah. So and that is what everybody
wants. We want to have more flexibility.
you want to produce a lot of variants,
different products but as well with a
high productivity and the combination of
both is then um the matrix production um
system and there are already um
companies like SEW in in Germany um they
have completely um implemented the idea
of a matrix production system and SEW um
they produce electric drives and gears.
We have a a high amount of different uh
variants and and products as well
custommade uh products and u um starting
in the 90s they implemented a lean
management system on a very very high
level. So a lot of u German
manufacturies manufacturers went in the
last years to sew in order to see how to
implement a lean system. But um um in
the last uh seven to to eight years they
uh they've seen that the productivity
increase per year went down and they
were not able anymore really to achieve
their productivity goals and then they
decided to radically change everything
into the direction of a full digitized
automated matrix production system. They
invested a lot of money into that. Um,
and they increased based on a very high
lean level their productivity between 30
and
50%. By decreasing um the delivery time.
So
within years ago when you want to if you
if you ordered u um uh a product at SEW
you have to wait maybe three or four
weeks. Now you get in you get the same
product within a week or less by 30 to
50% higher productivity based on that um
approach. So what I would like to show
is that there are many possibilities to
increase productivity that you have to
think somehow in a systemic way and to
connect the possibilities of the
different technologies. And maybe uh uh
two last statements. Uh one was we asked
uh during our survey uh the production
people um if their actual production
system provides the basis for radical
innovation and only 3% said yes uh our
production system is the basis for
radical innovation. only 28 said that uh
environmental or or sustainability KPIs
play a role in uh the production system.
Nevertheless, 57 said that they have an
up-to-date production system. Yeah. So I
it's funny, isn't
it? So my production system is up to
date, but it's not a basis for radical
innovation. So how will you survive in
the future? Yeah. Uh so that is that is
an issue and when you ask then
concerning the different barriers you
can you can read these barriers by by
your by yourself. Willingness to change
is always uh a very important uh topic.
So uh the attitude to really change
something um is often yeah on a on a low
level. So what is for us now the next
step? Um we try now to integrate these
ideas we have created into this house of
of uh production. We have a lot of
questions which we still not have
answered. You can read some of them.
Yeah. So for example, which systemic
platform is now really application ready
and should be integrated in the system.
Uh what what are the new design
principles for a production system? So
there are many questions open. So I our
idea was not to really answer all these
question with that project but to start
a journey together with the companies
now and maybe in 10 or 15 years I will
come back. Yeah. Uh or not I hope so I
will come back and maybe then I can show
you the complete new house of
production. Uh and then maybe like uh
WCK and Jones did then I can write uh
that nice book the machine that changed
the world maybe a second time. Yeah we
will see. I already spoke to Mr. Wik. he
will visit me in two in two weeks uh
about that. Um but that it's still a
long way to go. That's clear. Um but um
keep in
mind there will be a change. Um the
Toyota production system looks like
that. Yeah. We we have a discussion with
Seammens. They said we think about
something like that. Yeah. In the
future. So a fleet of spaceships uh self
similar real time connected and and end.
So that's uh their picture of the future
for their production system just as an
inspiration. But uh maybe as an advice,
Albert Einstein said, "Life is like
riding a bicycle. You have to keep
moving not to lose your balance." So my
recommendation is yeah, keep moving,
start moving. Yeah. And be successful in
the future. Thank you very much for your
attention.
And may I kindly ask you to stay with me
here on stage for just a couple of
minutes because we apparently do have a
little bit of time left for questions
from the audience. So checking the
screen, we just have the first question
coming up. Why will humanoid robots not
play a much stronger role in this new
paradigm?
Excellent question.
Um, we see a very fast development of
the capabilities in the moment. And when
you compare what these humanoid robots
were able to do maybe one and or two
years ago and and when you see them now,
it's
really an amazing improvement. Um, but
uh they are still not on a level uh of a
human being. And when you look at into a
classical assembly line in the
automotive sector, we are far far away
from the capabilities a robot would have
or should offer in order to fulfill
these tasks. Um so in the moment they
can handle a metal sheet and move it
like that to that and they uh recognize
yeah the the situation but they are not
able to do really complex tasks. One
thing and the other thing is safety.
Yeah. all these uh startups in in the
United States in that field they work on
the capabilities but they have no idea
what it really means when it comes to
safety topics in production. Yeah, I I I
um had that during the uh human robot
collaboration topic and we developed a
lot of solution and finally after risk
assessment usually the the closer the
cooperation was between human being and
and um robot the slower the process was
and then we had an often very we had an
economic problem really to to calculate
it and to to to u judge uh about an
investment. We'll have to wait and see
and maybe ask the same question again in
about a year or so. Thank you very much
for sending in so many questions. We'll
do our best to at least answer two or
three of them. Uh what impact would
comprehensive process digitalization
have on production error rate and
employee satisfaction?
Uh an high impact on on production error
rate for sure. We see that uh in the
companies who have already implemented
these kind of of possibilities.
um um the the more data you have the
more stable is your process. Um on the
other hand employee satisfaction um out
of my point of view when we are able to
really um inspire the employees to work
with the tools and when we help them to
develop own tools. Uh there are many
companies in the moment in Germany who
start to develop apps by themselves with
low code uh uh approaches. Then the
satisfaction rate really increases
because they the employees often are not
uh in a bad mood because of the of the
high functionality. It's often the other
way around. Yeah. they have tools we
then they do not really work and they do
not really offer uh um the support they
want to have and when they are able to
develop something by themselves or
they're integrated in the development
and they get a customized solution which
really fits to their needs then usually
they are highly satisfied and motivated
to go on and to drive that digital
digitalization process right we'll try
to answer at least two more two quick
questions so in the radical scenario
there is no HR and leadership comp uh
compliment when one would expect a
change of 100% productivity in 10 years
requiring requiring more than technology
why is it if no priority uh it is
priority but I didn't uh uh talked about
that because my colleague was involved
who is uh focusing on on on that topic
he's an expert professor
u and I don't wanted to talk about
things which are not in my specific
research area. Yeah. But the these
topics are involved and and and it's
very very relevant to have human
resource and especially um the
leadership uh and entrepreneurship on
the table. So we definitely don't want
to forget about it. We do not forget. Um
I think that's uh basically a wrap for
this Q&A because there's no more
question coming up on the screen. Please
give another big round of applause for
Thomas. Thank you very much. Thank you.