Today I have the privilege of
introducing our next speaker. Uh so this
is uh Garam Kim. She is a postdoc
post-dctoral fellow in Evan McCosco's
lab at the Broad Institute and a Leler
fellow at the Leler Center for the Study
of Neurodeenerative Diseases at Harvard.
She previously completed her PhD in
neurosciences in Aaron Guilter's lab at
Stanford University. Her research
focuses on developing technologies that
combine highresolution imaging and high
throughput genomics tools in a spatially
resolved manner. She hopes to utilize
these spatial tools to interrogate the
biological underpinnings of
neurodeenerative diseases and to enable
people from diverse fields to study
their own research questions using these
tools as well. Today she's going to give
us a primer on spatial transcrytoics
technologies. Thank you.
Oh, she'll take questions anytime. And
um thank
you. Can everyone hear me? Okay. Okay.
Perfect. Um thank you all for being here
at this early and rainy hour and thank
you uh both to the organizers for um
inviting me to to uh share this primer
on spatial transcrytoics technologies.
Um, and as she just said, please feel
free to stop me at any point. I will do
my best to answer uh any questions that
you may
have.
So, okay. So, to give you an overview of
this primer, I'll first give you a brief
introduction on spatial transcrytoics,
what it is, key concepts, and why we
want to use these technologies. Then I'm
going to walk you through some examples
and how we can broadly classify these
technologies. And then we'll discuss
each method's strengths and challenges
associated with um these types of
technologies as well as some practical
considerations for what to look for when
you're choosing uh which tool you may
want to use for your particular study.
And lastly, we'll touch on some
immediate and medium-term future
directions um in the field of spatial
transcrytoics. Okay. So what is spatial
transcrytoics? Um I think that to
understand fully spatial transcrytoics
we first want to understand its most
famous predecessors in particular bulk
RNA sequencing and single cell RNA
sequencing.
Um, so this is a cross-section of a
human brain. And as you can see, there
are many Lego pieces that define
different uh distinct brain regions and
perhaps even um distinct structures at
the micro level. And where what what
bulk RNA sequencing looks like is like
this. So, um, when we sample any piece
of tissue from this human brain, uh,
basically we grind up all the RNAs in a
way that's kind of indistinct and
disorganized because now it's kind of in
a in a soup of Lego blocks. And um, this
is advantageous in a way because it's
very high sensitivity. You're just
grinding up the RNAs and sequencing all
the transcripts that are there. However,
you're losing a lot of information
because you're averaging um all the gene
expression across a sample. So, you you
can't tell with a RNA transcript came
from this Lego block versus a different
Lego block. Okay. Then, uh the next I
guess big
um uh technological advancement was the
development of single cell RNA
sequencing. And so what this enabled was
that now we could look at individual
cell types and cell states. Um but uh so
yeah so now you can see that the Lego
blocks are kind of uh you know separated
out in space. It can be grouped and you
can kind of see what structures they
came from. Um but one thing that you
still lose is actually its context and
where it was in space. And this is
because in order to get these single
cell or single nuclear suspensions you
have to dissociate the
tissue. Um so then finally this brings
us to the advent of spatial
transcrytoics which preserves tissue
structures and it allows you to kind of
see okay uh what what did all of my
neighbors look like and what are the
kind of cell interactions and micro
environment that surrounds that
particular
cell. Okay. So why would we want to why
do we care about studying gene
expression in space? Well, first, ooh,
this is very small, but this is an
example of a very earlier um plot from
one of the earlier spatial technologies.
And what this is is it's um a um plot is
a top type of plot that you get in
single cell RNA sequencing where every
dot represents a unique cell or nucleus.
This dimensionality reduction allows us
to see that cells that are closer to
each other in their transcripttoic
profile will tend to be also closer
together in space. And so based on this
unbiased hierarchical clustering, we see
that there are distinct cell types that
are per perhaps associated with um
distinct regions. Now, um the moment you
put this into space, what you can see
and begin to appreciate is that across
these different tissue types, um you now
start to see rather than just random
dots in space that kind of cluster
together. Now, um they are you can now
start to see where they lie in space and
what its neighbors look like. And you
can even see the these uh appendimal
cell layer for instance it's a single
cell layer um right near the hippocampus
in the mouse
hippocampus. So basically studying gene
expression in space allows us to see
what cells is it interacting with? What
does the tissue architecture look like?
Um if there's a disease micro
environment uh is there any kind of
inflammatory niche? Is there some kind
of cell population that's going to um I
guess aggregate together? And we can
start to see the spatial patterning that
tells us a lot more about what's
happening
biologically. Okay. Um so in addition to
these sequencing based technologies, I
thought it would be nice to uh look at
how we came to the state of the spatial
genomics field as we know it to today.
And you know there are many historic
milestones and um so many technologies
that have been developed over decades.
But um the way that I have tried to kind
of condense it is uh I guess to the
particular experiments or developments
that really paved the way for modern uh
the the modern technologies that we know
today. So starting in 1969 is actually
when we saw the first ever INC2
hybridization.
So this was the first technique in C2,
so in place in the tissue without having
to isolate anything um that they were
able to use radioactive probes that uh
would label a very specific DNA sequence
and so you can see it labeling in little
dots um inside the nucleus and this
established the principle that you can
actually detect nucleic acids in a
native context. Um, another year and I
guess technology that I chose was 1996,
the invention of laser capture micro
dissection. And the idea was that you
could use a laser to basically cut very
focal fields of view inside a tissue and
transfer it onto this film and then you
would be able to do whatever downstream
analysis you wanted to do. So at this
point what what this shows is that
you're able to kind of preserve some
level of spatial information and this is
a big step towards um spatial precision.
And in this case this isn't a specific
cell this is actually beta amaloid
plaques um that's associated with
Alzheimer
disease. Then uh in oh okay so actually
I I flipped the order of those so please
forgive me. Um so the other I guess
major development was not just incitu
hybridization using radioactive probes
but now using fluoresence in situ
hybridization which introduced this idea
that now you can have multiplex spatial
uh transcrytoics. So you can now
visualize more than one type of
transcript at one at a given time. Um
and finally this brings us to modern day
spatial transcrytoics that we know
today. So higher throughput um
technologies that now allow us to
visualize many many transcripts inside
of cells uh using very clever strategies
or uh I guess in this context this is a
single cell with many transcripts
labeled inside uh in the case of the
right image this is one of those plots
that I described earlier but now plotted
out in space and we can see that from a
single experiment uh that that all these
different cell types are able to be
resolved.
Okay. So, what are the types of spatial
technologies if we're going to broadly
classify it? So, this is not going to be
a comprehensive list because there are
way too many technologies, but I'm going
to highlight a few especially um a few
that are commercially available or uh
perhaps were invented at the the broad.
Okay. So, uh again, there could be many
ways you could classify it. Um I think
one way that I decided to classify it is
into two broad ca categories of um
spatial technologies. So one of them is
imaging based uh spatial technologies
and the other is sequencing
based. So in imaging based methods um
the RNA is always detected through u
repeated cycles of fluorescent imaging.
So you would have some kind of targeted
probes that target a sequence that
you're interested in. um you would
fluorescently label it and you know
there's a limited number of channels
that you can image from at one time on a
microscope. So people have figured out
pretty clever ways to to really scale
this up so that you can um target you
know around 10,000 species at a time
even though most people choose not to
but that is definitely possible. Um and
one really nice thing about having this
imagebased readout is that you have
really high resolution. you see every
molecule. So it's very very uh uh like
you can see subcellular structures, you
can see the cell morphology uh and
things like that. Sequencing based
methods are different in that uh you
never actually look at the image of
um your tissue. I mean you could you
could acquire that but the actual
readout of the RNA itself is that the
RNA is captured basically off the tissue
or or through tissue dissociation and
then sequenced. And um in this case you
don't require um designing specific
probes to target transcripts of
interest. So you have a non-targeted
capture method and this actually enables
whole transcriptto wide profiling. Um in
terms of the resolution that is
dependent on technology and we'll get
into the different types of technologies
that are available. Okay. So by oh thank
you. Okay. So in terms of subasses
uh so you know these are two very broad
categories but I thought I would divide
them further into a couple subasses. So
for imaging based technologies there's a
fluoresence in C2 hybridization that I
mentioned earlier as well as in C2
sequencing and I'm going to go into what
what those both mean uh in greater
detail. And in terms of sequencing
based, perhaps we could divide it into
things that uh technologies that use a
spot-based. So some kind of barcoded
array that already has um defined
spatial positions with spatial barcodes.
Uh and then that captures the RNA from
the tissue or a cell base where you are
actually tagging the cells with the
spatial information and then um using
that to put it back into space. Okay. So
let's now go into examples of uh imaging
based spatial technologies. Um these are
just a few that I'm going to
mention.
Um but first I guess for any imaging
based spatial technology if you look at
the key principles
um there's basically three major steps.
So the first step is that you're
generating some kind of optical barcode.
So some kind of barcode that you can use
to identify the particular RNA trans
transcript of interest and that barcode
um is different across the technologies
and I'm about to get into that um but
generally you'll have some kind of probe
that's binding to a target of interest
and then um I guess you're generating
fluorescent signal in different ways
across different technologies and then
you read out this signal via single or
multiolor fluoresence.
And then uh once you have that
fluorescent signal then you would image
and then get rid of that signal and then
do another round of imaging. So you have
this constant um cycle of sequential
imaging followed by signal removal. And
you do this as many times as necessary
for your particular set of transcripts
that you're probing for. Um, and
finally, once you have acquired those
series of images, then you're going to
have to um use the actual images
themselves to figure out which
fluorescent spots um you know uh
correlated with which transcripts over
over the rounds of imaging. And so this
is how you're going to then identify
what was the actual identity of that RNA
transcript. Okay. So uh two of the I
guess um two of two very commonly used
fluorescent and sichu hybridization
methods fish methods are called murfish
and seekfish. So murfish stands for
multipplexed error resistant fish rolls
right off the tongue. Um and seekfish is
sequential fish. So I think that kind of
um is self-explanatory.
So uh I mentioned that for each of these
um technologies that they have a
different way of generating the optical
barcode. In the case of Murfish it's a
binary code. So which means every
transcript is actually just given a
random um and unique series of zeros and
ones. So so you will never have two
overlapping series of zeros and ones.
Um, so let's assume like transcript one
has like the sequence 11 one zero and
RNA 2 a different transcript has the
sequence one 01. Um that would mean that
for the first round of imaging you would
have probes that target these two
transcripts and in the next round of
imaging you would be missing um a a a
fluorescent readout for the a molecule
that's binding that particular
transcript. Sequential fish is actually
a very similar idea except that instead
of a binary code now you have a color
code.
Um so how does this look? So, uh, this
is a cell if you couldn't tell. And here
are five different transcripts that are
being, um, imaged in this round. And so,
this is just at the first base position.
Now, we're going to image and figure out
which uh, fluorescent spots had a one,
so there was signal. And in the next
round, perhaps um, this transcript now
had a zero in that spot. And so you're
imaging the same spot over all of these
rounds of imaging until finally uh once
you acquire all of the images, you
figure out what was this string of ones
and zeros at that particular um place.
And then you can decode it to basically
figure out what was the identity of that
transcript. And then again sequential
fish is kind of similar in idea except
that this time um they were given
different colors instead of a binary
ones and
zeros. Okay. And then what about the
other kind of subcl broader subclass
under imaging based um spatial
transcrytoics methods is uh it's called
INC2 sequencing. So uh two of these
methods are one's called INC2 sequencing
and the other one uh and you might know
that one uh better as Zenium uh from 10X
and uh the other one this was developed
by a faculty member also at the abroad
uh Shaw Wong is called star map another
one that rolls right off the tongue
called spatially resolved transcript
amplon readout
mapping. So uh so I mentioned that
merfish had a binary code and sequential
fish had a color code. In the case of
these instit in C2 sequencing based
methods they have a actual just a unique
nucleotide barcode. So a series of AC's,
T's and G's and
um what these this class of technologies
relies on is a uh is a technology called
I guess or type of circularizing of DNA
called padlock probe hybridization. So
you have a padlock probe is basically a
single strand of DNA and you have these
um these sequences at the ends that are
complmentary and completely next to each
other on uh that's targeting a
particular strand of interest and then
once it binds and it'll circularize then
you have a loation step to basically get
rid of that gap and now it's fully
circularized instead of just bound like
that. And then there's the other main
concept here is called rolling circle
amplification. And what that means is
that DNA polymerase will bind at a
priming site. Um and then it'll just
basically circle around and around and
around until it's just like super
amplifying itself. Um so in C2
sequencing and star map both use this
padlock probe plus uh rolling circle
amplification technology.
Um and so I guess you know yeah so
there's going to be some some reverse
transcription at some point and the way
that that is done differs um there are
different nuance uh I guess approaches
between the two technologies but the
basic idea of padlock probes and RCA um
is is there and then finally how do you
actually read out the unique sequences
that those probes bound to so there's
going to be some uh sequencing by
loation. So basically if these barcodes
are four to seven nucleotides long then
there's going to be some kind of
sequencing primer then a liation of a
fluoresence uh based nucleotide that's
going to read out what was that
nucleotide at that position. So it is
truly like you're actually sequencing
out um the actual sequence unlike
murfish and uh seekfish.
Okay. Okay. Finally, I guess the last
NC2 sequencing method that I thought I
would talk about is called expansion
sequencing. And for those of you who are
not familiar, um expansion microscopy is
a very cool technology. So, you know,
not everything, you know, is uh
resolvable in space with high
definition. So if you have something
very small and you have a microscope
that that doesn't reach that resolution,
how do you fix that problem without just
making a fancier microscope? Is that
actually instead of making the
microscope zoom in more, you can
actually just make the sample expand so
it's artificially bigger. And the way
that they do this is by embedding the
tissue inside of a hydro and then adding
water and it'll literally expand. So, so
what you're seeing here is that there
are some cells and now um they've
embedded it inside this gel and now it's
expanded and then now you can do NC2
sequencing as you would have done
otherwise. Um the other thing that was
uh in this um expansion sequencing paper
is that uh you could also do XC2
sequencing. So basically after you've
sequenced it in C2 if you wanted to have
an additional quality control you could
um basically isolate out um the rollies
that you created it uh in C2 and then
sequence it out you know
externally. Okay. Yeah. So basically the
three key steps are expansion in C2
sequencing and then optionally XC2
sequencing. That brings us to sequencing
based spatial technologies. So um there
are also a lot of them. I won't uh talk
about every single one but uh that's
just some listed. Um and again the key
principles that are shared across all
capture and sequencing based
technologies. Um, in terms of
capturebased technologies, the idea is
that you have some kind of capture array
that has some kind of spots that could
be like literal spots, it could be
beats, it could be some kind of cluster.
Um, but each spot has a unique set of
spatially barcoded DNAs. And these um,
barcodes have a unique spatial barcode
per one of those spots. It has a unique
molecular identifier. So if you have
multiple molecules that share the same
spatial barcode that can be captured and
then it has a polyDT at the end. So
that'll allow us to capture all
polyadenolated mRNAs in a very unbiased
manner uh or unargeted manner. Um, and
then yeah, so and then I guess so the
key principles in addition to the use of
a capture array is that you you're going
to place a piece of tissue. Uh, it could
be fixed or frozen and then you place it
directly on top of the barcoded capture
array. Um, then you would actually
capture the RNA. So perhaps the RNA will
diffuse onto the array and bind to the
spatial barcodes or the other way
around. Then you're going to prepare
remove the tissue and prepare um I guess
you know you'll have some kind of
reverse transcription to get cDNA then
you'll prepare the libraries for
sequencing and then you'll actually
sequence it out. Um so that's the basic
principles. So now going into examples
of major capture and sequencing based
methods is uh I guess I put these three
on the same slide cuz I guess uh you can
kind of see side by side how they're
quite similar but the ways in which they
differ. So 10x Genomics has a product
called Bizium. Um the difference so
basically the original version has a a
glass slide that has this kind of uh
barcodes at at uh a resolution where you
know the beads are about 100 microns
apart center to center. And so you can
imagine that's actually on the lower
side of resolution now in retrospect uh
because it's not single cell resolution.
Single cells are much smaller than that.
Um however since then there's been
Vizium 2 which has been um adaptable for
uh fixed tissues and Vizm HD is the
latest version that now gets actually
down to two micron resolution and they
use um squares that don't have any
spacing in between. So it's supposed to
be a lot higher resolution
um and it's compatible with formal infix
paraffin embedded or FFP tissues. So
actually tissue fixation is another
topic that we'll come back to in a
little bit. Um then there's this
highdefinition spatial transcrytoics so
called high definition ST. So ST which
was the version before this is actually
I think the first spatial tech like high
throughput spatial technology. Um but
the idea here is that you have um these
wells and each of these wells has a
single bead and each of the beads has a
unique spatial barcode and so this bead
is about two microns in size. So that's
that's where the high definition came
from. And then slideseek is a technology
that was developed in in uh my lab which
is uh Evan McCosco's lab in
collaboration with fa hen's lab also at
the broad and the way that uh these
capture arrays are created is that uh we
have a bunch of 10 micron beads that are
uh that we can basically spin down onto
glass slides and or a glass surface and
it'll just be randomly situated and we
will uh sequence those so that we have a
ground truth of where the spatial
barcodes are at each of those locations.
Then we place a tissue on there allow
the RNAs from the tissue to diffuse and
bind onto um the the these uh bead
capture uh the polyDTS here and then uh
and then we'll do the downstream
processing to to get the libraries
prepared and
sequenced. Okay. And then um this
another technology that also rolls off
the tongue is called dit dbit seek. So
this is a little bit different from the
capture based arrays that we just spoke
talked about. So DBS seek stands for
deterministic barcoding and tissue for
spatial omix sequencing. Um and uh and
instead of bead or wells this actually
uh or having this kind of array this is
actually a micrflu
micrluidics based method. So basically
you have micrfluidics chips that have uh
parallel lanes throughout and you clamp
this microffluidic chip directly onto
the tissue and then into the
micrfluidics wells you're going to
introduce uh
polydagged DNA barcodes um inside those
channels and let it just flow over the
tissue. Then you're going to uh add a
second I guess perpendicular um
micrfluidic chip on top. And then and
then uh what you put into that is a
biotinilated second barcode that's going
to have your unique molecule uh
molecular identifier information.
Um and it's biasilated so that
downstream you it can bind to strep
tavitin beads and um be used during uh
library preparation and generation. Can
I ask you a quick question about that?
Are they are there plans to make this
three-dimensional so that you get the
xyz position of these barcodes? So I
think that is a common goal across all
the technologies. Um, star map is the
only one from the among the technologies
I've discussed where in their initial
study they they kind of presented it as
a 3D method. One thing I didn't mention
is that star map um has hydrogel
embedding as well and they do very mild
expansion and also tissue clearing to to
kind of help with the imaging. Um in the
case of debt seek I don't believe that
is uh it's there yet but I think all
technology at the end of the day are
striving to get there at some point.
Yeah thank you for that
question. Okay. Um so now getting to
higher resolution this is called
stereosseek so spatial enhanced
resolution omix sequencing. And um what
this type of array uh uses is called DNA
nanobballs um which is DNB. So basically
what you do is you have single stranded
DNAs and you also use rolling circle
amplification to just make like a bunch
of copies of itself and and then because
DNA is very negatively charged it'll
just kind of like spontaneously like go
into like this ball which is why they
have um all of these balls and then they
have a pattern chip and basically they
they'll flow over these this DNA nanob
balls across all of the uh uh the the
flow cell. And because these nanobballs
are about 200 nanometers um in size,
it'll naturally kind of only occupy one
per uh patterned spot. Um and then uh
and then that's actually used to capture
the RNA. And then um again, similar
principle downstream, but that that's
primarily the difference um with other
technologies. And I believe this is the
last capture based method that I'm going
to mention. It's called open ST. It's
open because like everything their
scripts and uh their methods and
everything is very open. They want
everyone to use it as open- source
technology. But they had a very clever
idea of taking the aluminum flow cells
which have very very high resolution uh
and it's very tightly packed and they
took advantage of their sequencing by
synthesis method to basically within the
flow cell um generate unique spatial
barcodes there and then and then they
would do um some kind of post-processing
to to make it
um amendable to RNA capture and you can
basically break up They have like a you
can cut these flow cells. They have a
cutting
like you know like some technology that
they say you can also do. Um and then
basically in terms of the size that
you're able to spatially profile is
going to be limited to the size of these
flow cells. So you can see actually in
length it's actually quite good. I think
it's I forget exactly how many
centimeters maybe like nine or 10
centimeters or something like that but
in width it's you know small small so um
but I think this a really exciting idea
and again you're going to have the RNAs
bind to that flow cell and
um yeah and and you're able to then get
very high resolution information. So
that was all spot-based. But the second
subclass I mentioned and I'm actually
only going to give one example and um
this is the technology that is most dear
to my heart because my postto project uh
is built off of this technology. So if
you have any specific questions, let me
know. Um uh so what I mean by cellbased
is that instead of capturing RNAs onto
an array, we're actually now um tagging
the cells with the spatial
information. And this method is called
slide tags. And so slide tags actually
still uses a beat array as well. And
they also have spatial barcodes. The
difference is that um now it has a photo
cleavable linker so that when you shine
UV light on it um the spatial barcodes
will cleave off of the p uh the of the
bead array and tag the tissue. And so
you just have an intact piece of tissue
and once the nuclei attacks then you can
actually isolate the nuclei and then you
can use any established single cell
profiling technology beyond even um just
the transcripttoone to profile these
nuclei in a very high throughput
fashion. So it it it basically um I
guess will I what's the word tag tag
tail tail anyway? it it'll it'll um
blend in to existing workloads very
easily because all you're doing is just
adding a tag of DNA barcodes and then
you just remove the the array. Um so
then I guess the advantage of this is
that now you have the very high
throughput capture um unargeted capture
of RNAs. So you can still get this high
resolution um um and then um and then at
this point using the spatial barcodes
that was uh that each nucleus is tagged
with you can now map it back into space
um uh depending on what what were the
spatial barcodes and in what quantities
it was tagged
with. So now when we're um actually
comparing all of these spatial methods,
you can see that the resolution uh the
spatial resolution across these
technologies differs. This is this
figure is taken from a review in um that
was published in 2022. So it's
definitely missing some of the very big
technologies, but you can see that even
at that time um we were you know seeing
0.25 25 micron resolutions.
Um yeah and but you know
uh one thing I wanted to mention is that
so far we have talked about spatial
resolution and like you know how small
are these spots that we can actually tag
tag the cells with but actually um at
the end of the
day that's a spatial resolution but what
we haven't really discussed is the RNA
resolution And
um and at least on the RNA end at the
end of the day, single cell sequencing
remains kind of the gold standard for
unbiased transcripttoics. It's very
reproducible. It's commercially
available. There's a massive
computational toolbox. Um it it covers
genomewide
uh transcripts and there's also
established multi modality in terms of
um what other information you can
capture. Especially I think one of the
most common ones is the RNA and the taxi
multiome and and uh one way to really
drive this home is a direct comparison
of the RNA profiles and UMAPs across uh
four different technologies. Three of
them capture based and one of them um
cellbased. And so you can see that uh
again I mentioned at the beginning that
in when you have this dimensionality
reduction um cells that are closer to
each other in uh in in their gene
expression profile will also be closer
to each other in um space. Uh and the
more clearly that they isolate from each
other um I guess the more distinct they
are. And when you also look at you know
various um cell types and gene
expression you can see for instance in
the senium data set that uh when you
look at a excitatory neuron marker
across all the clusters that perhaps
it's it's looking like like it's
expressed in a lot of clusters. Um, and
part of that is that actually the spot,
no matter how big or small, you can have
nanocale resolution in a spot, but you
still have to actually map it back to
the cells. So, it's actually a very
tricky computational problem to try to
deconvolute um what the signal from each
of those spots and which cell it came
from. Um, so that that's just another
thing to keep in mind um as as we
consider these technologies.
So now we'll briefly touch on the
strengths and challenges of each of
these methods and hopefully have a a
practical how to really choose the
platform that's that's for you. So the
strength and challenges of imaging based
methods
um as as you saw you can really directly
visualize every single fluoresence
molecule and so that subscellular
resolution is really nice like it's I
think there's something very beautiful
about being able to see the morphology
and the cell structure and and
everything around it. Um, so you get the
morphological context. You can also
co-detect it with protein. Um, and you
don't have any kind of tissue
dissociation artifacts because you're
looking at the tissue as
is. However, um, in terms of, uh,
potential challenges is that that
requires very specialized microscopy
equipment. Um, you will be limited to
targeted gene panels because you have to
always design the probe. um you do have
a kind of molecular crowding situation
where you you know if you have too many
molecules together in space and you have
florores that are bleeding into each
other um that that might pose a small
challenge
um with expansion I think it's a little
bit more resolvable but nonetheless that
can be a challenge um imaging based
methods also will pick up all
fluorescent signals and that's not
limited to specific fluorescent signals
It will also pick up background
fluoresence and particularly in human
tissues there's gross amounts of
autofllororesence that come from
lipopusin buildup over time. So that is
also another challenge to keep in mind
given that um there's this uh probe
hybridization stripping u and rounds of
imaging uh these protocols can be very
complex and uh require very long imaging
times and that can also sometimes lead
to photobleaching and light toxicity. So
that's also, you know, dependent on how
many rounds of imaging, what does your
panel look like, how many transcripts
are you trying to probe, but that is a
uh potential challenge. And uh with each
of these probe designs, you need it you
need it to actually be all at the same
time. You need to be very highly
specific. You don't want it to cross
react because they are kind of short um
oligo sequences that are, you know,
binding to your transcripts of interest.
So you want to make sure that it's not
going to have offtarget effects and bind
to other similar transcripts. Um so
that's what we mean by minimal cross
reactivity. And then you want to make
sure that the hybridization efficacy is
pretty uniform across all the
transcripts. You don't want one um probe
that's going to bind much strongly much
stronger than another transcript. And
finally, you know, to follow every
single one of those dots and and um
figure out keep track of their identity,
it can be very computationally
intensive. I may have missed this. Uh
did you are all the methods um poly t
RNAs or can you capture non um
polytarnas? Uh you can.
So, so one of the uh technologies that I
use is actually
um well, so 10X has this flex kit that
has probe based capture, but it captures
a whole transcripttome and depending you
can just basically change out the handle
so that um it's binding to whatever
transcript of interest. I think poly
RNAs are easy cuz they're all regardless
of transcript identity, they all have
A's. Um, but I think there are ways to
enrich or deplete for specific uh types
of RNAs or sequences that you might be
interested in. But, um, I think most of
the technologies start from the poly
RNAs because it's kind of low hanging
fruit. Um you know if you use random
primers you can capture other RNAs.
Um you can also you know add a poly
adenolation step which is uh something
that a later version of debit seek
called pathodit does and um other
technologies have done that not
necessarily just in the spatial context
but just in single cell context. Um so
there there are ways to to capture other
RNAs as
well. Okay. And then in terms of the
sequencing based methods well I just
mentioned oh so so even the probe based
method it's still covers the whole
transcriptto. So the throughput is the
same but I guess uh yeah so in that
particular uh case it's using probes but
it's whole transcriptto. Yeah. And it
doesn't add more time to have whole
transcription. Okay. And then the
strengths and weak uh not weaknesses
challenges of these capture and
sequencing based methods is again um
when it's sequenced it can be unargeted
and cover the whole transcriptto in a
very high throughput manner. Uh it's
compatible with existing next generation
sequencing workflows uh and a lot of
more standardized workflows that maybe
people are more broad like widely
familiar with. So it requires less
specialized equipment. But the
challenges can be that well you don't
have imaging so you're definitely going
to have lower spatial resolution even
when the spot sizes are very high in
resolution. Um so in in many tissue
types you often find in the current
state of technology that you can't
necessarily resolve individual cells
with super high confidence. um as as you
have RNAs that are binding to your
capture surface you might have some
potential RNA loss during that tissue
removal. Um alternatively when you have
cellbased actually it's not listed here
but you know once you tag the tissue you
have your whole tissue but during the
dissociation you might actually lose um
have some dropout of cells as well. um
when the RNA is actually diffusing into
onto the array the diffusion might not
just be you know clear one to one but
actually like sideways diffusion as well
so that could also blur some spatial
boundaries but um one thing I I
mentioned is that you know the spot size
isn't everything so we might think that
looks very very high resolution so for
instance stereo seek which
um has you know I think 200ish ish
nanomar resolution. They actually find
that when they're trying to assign cells
to uh or spots to cells, it it'll be
like 400 spots that are are encompassing
the cell, but they because they have so
many spots, then they actually have to
bin it to include be more inclusive of
its neighbors. So, so I guess the spot
size isn't everything in terms of
resolution. And also um I guess this can
be higher cost per sample um depending
on the fabrication of the capture
arrays. So if you're choosing a method I
think uh uh yeah a nice way to approach
this is by you know first defining your
biological hypothesis and what is your
actual question of interest. Is this
more for you know discovery? Are you
looking for something new that maybe you
weren't looking for or are you
validating something or do you need to
do take a more targeted approach and
what are your gene coverage coverage
needs? So maybe you don't need to target
the entire transcripttome but maybe you
do. What are your resolution
requirements? Do you need to be looking
at the subcellular level or is it more
you're uh interested in like you know
general broad structures in which case
perhaps the tiny resolution differences
actually really don't matter to you. Um
uh and then I guess scale goes uh
handinhand with that. Another thing to
consider is the sample type. So, you
know, a lot of these technologies
actually require fresh frozen tissues,
especially because RNAs degrade very
quickly and need to be um uh preserved
correctly and the moment you fix it,
you're introducing a lot of these cross
links that can be damaging. Um, however,
like FFP tissues for instance, again,
it's formal and fixed paraffin embedded.
So they're these wax cassettes of all
these archival human specimens across
basically every pathology department in
every hospital. It's so widely
available. Um and is is is the
preservation method like you don't have
a choice in the type of fixation or can
you actually um choose the fixation type
because you are planning the experiment
and collecting the tissues yourself. So
um I think the technology you choose
might not have a FFP compatibility. So
that is something to
consider and uh section thickness of
what you want to capture as well as u
the tissue quality of what's available.
Um I think a couple other things to
consider is you know the actual
technical expertise that that are that
is around you and all of these
technologies often um require very heavy
computational support or skills. Um I
think some commercialized technologies
try to streamline that for you but uh
that is definitely something that's uh
not to be overlooked. And finally uh
there are you know very practical
considerations in terms of available
infrastructure. So is the equipment
available? Um what are your budget
restraints like and uh and do you want
flexibility in in what the technology
does? So if it's commercially supported
it's going to be very expensive and um
probably a lot less flexible than if
you're working with an open platform or
something that a collaborator might
have. Um so perhaps that is much cheaper
and also but and also provides greater
flexibility. Okay. Okay. So in terms of
future directions so what's still hard
is I just mentioned that FFP sample
compatibility can remain challenging for
actually like most of these tech uh
applications. Um and you know if you can
proactively actually fix the tissues
yourself that's that's very nice because
you can control it but often it's
hyperfix. So that's that's very
difficult to get around and um you know
in our lab as well as in many other labs
we're trying to figure out how to
actually extract more RNA information
even if there are these archival
specimens that that we can't choose how
they're fixed. The cost barriers still
can remain high and the computational
demands like I mentioned um can require
a lot of work and and the other thing is
across all of these technologies there's
actually very little standardization. So
you know in terms of common benchmarks
uh I think it's it's it can be a little
bit difficult to really um standardize
across all the technologies in terms of
what is coming up in the inter uh the
immediate to intermediate term
um is you know technological
advancements we're going to you know
technologies are going to continue to
become higher resolution and uh one
thing we didn't I kind of mentioned but
we didn't really elaborate on is
actually the capture area. So, you know,
a lot of these might be, you know,
millimeters
uh big in terms of the surface area
you're looking at. Um up to 13 cm is I
think what I have seen published. Um but
I think scaling up the capture area
consistently so that people people can
you know not have to subsample their
tissue in to a very tiny area. the
compatibility with FFP tissues. Um you
know that most of these protocols are
incredibly timeconuming. So how do we
streamline that to a faster workflows
and increasing multiomix capabilities so
that um we can really combine all the
OMIX together to really scale this up
and get more uh rich
information. One thing uh that I'm
personally interested in is pathology
integration. So a lot of you know
neurodeenerative diseases or all
neurodeenerative diseases have these
protein pathologies that may not be
inside well one it's protein and two um
it may not be inside the nucleus
especially when you're using a
dissociation based technology. So um uh
so in really integrating that and being
able to capture you know
multi-dimensional information uh would
be useful and finally uh I think there's
a lot of computational advances that
will be very exciting. So you me you
asked about 3D reconstruction. So that's
definitely in the works. Um really you
know really studying on a like higher
throughput level uh the cellular
communication networks and their
proximity. And finally, you know, if you
can use machine learning models to
actually do feature extraction um from
images uh or just pattern recognition
and spatial data, perhaps there will
come a day when we have outputed enough
really high quality data sets that we
will be able to actually just image a
cell and potentially uh be able to infer
its transcrytoic state. So I think that
is probably a slightly longer term
perhaps not so long because AI is crazy.
Um but uh that that is uh yeah what I
think are exciting future directions.
And finally, this is the last slide is
that I just wanted to uh say you know
there are all these technologies but uh
you know from the history of you know
the foundations before spatial the
current era of spatial transcrytoics to
now you know spatial transcrytoics has
come a really long way across all of
these species and using all these
various technologies you see all of
these beautiful spatially resolved uh
figures and I just think that's really
exciting and I hope that you are excited
about it
Um this is just for further reading
reading if you're interested. This is
not a comprehensive list at all but it
will be in the slide deck so that you
can refer to it if you want to read more
about any technologies and thank you for
your attention and I will be happy to
take any questions.
Thank you so much. I think because of
time we'll end here but if you have
questions just please stick around. Uh
no seminar today and we'll see you next
week. Thanks everybody.