My my time at Sloan was before Chat GPT
existed, but I think of my classmates as
the early version of that where, you
know, I was interviewing for during the
course semester for my summer internship
at various pharma companies and I didn't
even know what some of the acronyms and
ways that they solve problems were
versus I had colleagues who had been
working in life sciences consulting who
had come from these companies and you
know I could just put in the chat, hey
what does market access actually mean or
how would you think about this problem
or does anyone know of any other drugs
that had to launch in the last five
years in a, you know, accelerated
approval framework and I could just get
really quick answers from my classmates
and everyone was not only willing to
just give the data but also sit down,
talk to me, walk me through it, help me
prepare for these interviews in a way
that, you know, got me upskilled really
fast.
Welcome everyone. My name is Terrell
Williams and I serve as one of the
associate directors here at MIT Sloan
and I want to welcome you to Thursdays
with Terrell. Today's session is going
to focus on the power of alumni
engagement. So without further ado, I'll
go ahead and uh pass it over to my first
guest for the evening, Greg. And I'll
have Greg introduce himself, a little
bit about his role and how long he's
been here at MIT Sloan.
>> Great. Thank you so much, Terrell. My
name is Greg Bachelor. I'm the interim
director of strategic alumni engagement
here at MIT Sloan in the office of
external relations. So, I've been at
Sloan since 2018, though I started my
career at MIT in the Central MIT Alumni
Association started in 2011. So, the
time flies, but I'm thrilled to be here
and to have my home here at Sloan. So,
happy to be with everyone today.
So, MIT Salon I was working in um the
biotech space um specifically in the
regulatory affairs that's the group that
interacts between pharmaceutical
companies and the global regulators um I
had spent about 10 to 15 years doing
that um and prior to that I was I'm a
pharmacist by training um and I decided
to come to Sloan because I wanted to get
a better understanding of strategy and
finance around biotech and and early
startups within the life sciences space.
Um I graduated in 2024 from the Sloan
Fellows MBA program. Transformative
experience spending the year at Sloan.
Picked up skills that I didn't think I I
um that that I didn't think was going to
be offered such as skills around
leadership and it was uh it was a a
thing that I I I highly recommend and
completely transformed my life.
>> Thank you, Lawrence. Then I will pass it
over to Marissa.
>> Thank you. Um, welcome everyone. My name
is Marissa Constat. Prior to Sloan, I
worked in academic um, medical health
and in research programs and clinical
research and global health. And I came
to Sloan to pivot into industry. And
since I graduated in 2021 from the
full-time MBA program, I've been at
Vert.Ex Pharmaceuticals in the global
pricing and market access strategy
function. And for everyone's awareness,
I live here in Boston and I'm also a
board member on the Sloan Boston Alumni
Association in charge of um organizing
recent alumni events and alumni
engagement. So excited to talk to you
all today.
>> And DK, I'll pass it to you to wrap us
up.
>> Hey there, my name's uh Dave.
Uh can everyone hear me well?
Okay. Um, so prior to Sloan, I uh went
to undergrad at UCSB where I got a
degree in electrical engineering. I was
there went to the military for four
years. as an engineering officer, left
out, served as a project manager with
Motorola Solutions. Um where at that
point I decided to get my MBA for
product management and what's afterwards
um ended up going to currently at um
Microsoft where I work as an AI product
manager.
>> Thank you all for sharing. So Greg, I
want to pass it back over to you for our
first question for a moderated session.
Um, can you share an overview of the
office of external relations? This may
be the first time that our audience is
hearing this term. So, can you share its
role in supporting the MIT Stone's
mission and kind of your roles and
responsibilities within that office?
>> Yeah, thank you. Um, so first, the
office of external relations kind of
mission statement is to engage students,
alumni, and friends with one another and
MIT Sloan to really inspire the
investment of time, expertise, and
financial support. So I like to boil it
down as it's about community and
building the network and it's also about
philanthropy. So I work on the strategic
alumni engagement team. So we're really
focusing on the network and
volunteerism. So we work with alumni all
over the world who want to support the
school and stay engaged. So we do that
through events, through volunteerism.
Some of our big events are marquee
annual events like reunion where we're
bringing alumni back to campus and
reconnecting with their classmates. Um,
and we really put a big focus on
intellectual programming and faculty
events. We also support regional club
volunteers. So, I'm thrilled Marissa's
here to talk about the Sloan Boston
alumni association. We also work with
other volunteer groups around the world.
And then, of course, Terrell, you're
with admissions, but we support the
admissions team. We support other
departments at Sloan like the career
development office and our action
learning team. So really keeping alumni
connected to all of the other
departments across the school as well
and fueling the ecosystem here. So I
mentioned to philanthropy we are a
fundraising organization. MIT Sloan
wouldn't exist without the generosity of
our alumni who give back not only their
time but also their financial support.
So that's for things like fellowship,
the Sloan annual fund and also for
faculty research. So it's engagement,
it's volunteerism, it's philanthropy,
it's all connected. So, it's really the
whole whole ecosystem there.
>> Thank you for sharing, Greg. I I'll stay
with you for a moment. So, could you
share um some additional trends that
you're noticing in how alumni prefer to
stay connected to the school?
>> Sure. Sure. Um this may not be a trend
necessarily, but I think one of the
things that's a true differentiator for
MIT Sloan, our alumni love to be
together. We have really smart people
who want to do big things, and when you
bring them together, uh the magic
happens. So, um, you know, I think
prioritizing that intellectual content,
you'll see that in all of our events,
you'll see it at reunion, that feeling
of being back in the classroom and
always learning together. I think our
alumni really want to be on the cutting
edge of new research. So, um, you know,
not a trend, but definitely something
that's, uh, you know, a differentiator
for our Sloan alumni community. The
learning doesn't stop. [laughter]
>> Awesome. Thank you for sharing, Greg.
So, now I want to pass over to our
alumni guests here as well. So just I
know we touched on this during your
introductions, but can you all kind of
share some additional insight on you
know what led you to ultimately enroll
at MIT Sloan?
>> I can kick us off. Um for me I I found
that there were a lot of different
reasons people were going to business
school and and for me I was pivoting
into industry for the first time. I'd
never worked for a public corporation.
Um, and I really wanted the intellectual
chops to to really stand up to to what
I'd done. I'd studied communication in
undergrad, but I didn't have the
technical uh background that a lot of
folks have coming into Sloan. And so, I
really wanted to double down on the the
quantitative skills, and I felt like
Sloan was a unique way to both do that
in school and to leverage the reputation
of MIT um further uh for my employers in
the future.
Thank you.
>> Yeah, I think for me it's a two-part. I
think the first part is for the MIT and
the second part is for the people.
Initially when I knew I wanted to get an
NBA and as I started to look at
different programs I was like hey I
really want a quantitative program that
can dive down really get into the weeds
with the technical aspects of
everything. And so as I went through the
list MIT definitely stuck out as one of
those who had like great tech
placements. Um but what really
solidified it for me is the more I
interacted with these different schools
um the mantra like Sloan's helping Sloan
it's really true um there are so many
kind nice nice people I met uh who had
amazing background that network like
this is definitely spot for me
>> yeah um I think the main reason that I
chose MIT Sloan was
twofolded. I think the first thing was
that coming from a true technical
background as a pharmacist by training.
I really value the technical approach to
management that um MIT Sloan um had
within the course and how they wanted to
approach um just teaching management in
general. Um I wanted to be um at MIT
because of the the the connection that
they had to the biotech space in
general. So I think you know the overall
MIT ecosystem um there's a lot of great
labs and a lot of vape professors who
helped launch a number of pharmaceutical
companies and then I think the the thing
that stood out to me really stood out to
me a lot was the principal leadership
aspect the values associated with being
um a Sloan I think that you know I think
the intention associated with how we
interact with the overall business
community I valued a lot and I wanted to
continue to kind of live that in my in
my next role.
>> Thank you all for sharing. D, can you
touched on something that I was going to
ask anyway, but I'm happy you shared the
Sloan helping Sloan ethos that we have
here. So, uh, could you all share some
examples of what that looks like before
someone's time at Sloan, during someone
time at Sloan, or even after they
graduate from Sloan?
>> Nico, you can go ahead and kick us off.
>> Yeah, I can definitely start with that.
So um I'll start with the uh before
Sloan. So before Sloan one thing like I
said the network community really drove
me to apply and accept here but there
were a handful of people who as I
reached out like hey I'm applying to
this school can you help me out? Um
there's this program um it's called plug
now plug g um it's a small club but
essentially um there are current
students who go through actually help
and assist before getting into the
school. Hey, let me look at your
applications help you out was primarily
for um marginalized communities. And so
for me being a Latino, I really love
that I felt um a sense of community
there even before heading to Sloan and
after Sloan um was actually funny. The
reason I'm actually at Microsoft is
because of another Sloan. Um she was
also for a grant and I think when I was
applying for work I was like hey where's
the best place I can apply to? Um, so
many Sloanies gave me referrals. They
like connected me with their hiring
managers. They really set me up and so
honestly wouldn't today without other
Sloan. Uh, which is once again one of
the biggest reasons I chose the school.
>> Yeah. I mean I I want to add also like I
I came to Sloan without any business
acronym or background. Um so when I
stepped into the classroom I think you
know there's this finance there was um
um courses that I hadn't um DMD there's
courses that I hadn't um had a lot of
experience with that um we informally
rallied together to kind of dive into
those courses from strategy courses to
finance courses to kind of you know help
each other get through the classwork and
I think that's really one of the strong
um uh um facets about the people that
end up coming to Sloan, right? Is that
they truly believe in this Sloan helping
Sloan and um I realized earlier I didn't
mention that I I I launched a a venture
fund and that's what I I'm doing after
Sloan we invest in the biotech space but
one of the ways I was able to launch
that fund was because I partnered with
one of my um Sloan classmates to launch
the venture fund and we kind of came
together and he provided a lot of
assistance. he's done venture work
before um or VC work before and he kind
of we partnered together and really was
able to drive the the launch of the
venture fund. So, um yeah, it just
speaks to like the type of people that
um that Sloan accepts and the desire to
kind of support each other through these
endeavors.
Maybe one thing I'll add is um how much
I learned from my fellow Sloan both in
school and and since then. Um, you know,
there's this was before my my time at
Sloan was before Chat GPT existed, but I
think of my classmates as the early
version of that where, you know, I was
interviewing for during the course
semester for my summer internship at
various pharma companies and I didn't
even know what some of the acronyms and
ways that they solve problems were
versus I had colleagues who had been
working in life sciences consulting who
had come from these companies and you
know I could just put in the chat, hey,
what does market access actually mean or
how would you think about this problem
or does anyone know of any other drugs
that have had to launch in the last five
years in a you know accelerated approval
framework and I could just get really
quick answers from my classmates and
everyone was not only willing to just
give the data but also sit down talk to
me walk me through it help me prepare
for these interviews in a way that you
know got me upskilled really fast and I
continued to to leverage my peers you
know before um before graduating through
through classes through taking an econ
class or a data class that you know was
brand new material to me. But also, you
know, in my first couple of years of the
job when I had colleagues who had spent
a decade working in life sciences
consulting and had this whole breadth of
knowledge that they could point me in
the right direction really quickly so
that I could be better and more
effective in my job as well.
>> Thank you all for sharing. Greg, I want
to start with you on this next question.
Um, you touched on this earlier about
your collaboration with the admissions
office. So, could you share how alumni
interacts with newly admitted students
before the program begins and how Sloan
encourages those early connections to
shape those student outcomes?
>> Yeah, thanks Terrell and a big kudos to
your team for helping facilitate those
connections. Um, but I think
specifically about our Sloan alumni
board. So, a key um volunteer group for
us who are active and willing to do
admit calling. So, you know, again, your
team provides the structure uh and the
outreach opportunity, but really to have
alumni who are willing to call admitted
students and share their experience and
kind of put their minds at ease, right?
To be hearing from folks who have walked
through the doors of MIT Sloan before
you and get those firsthand experiences,
I think is incredibly invaluable. And
our alumni are always willing to make
those calls um and make those
connections. So, that of course comes to
mind first for me uh and appreciate the
partnership with admissions on that.
Awesome. I know we have some uh newly
admitted students on our call, so I'm
pretty sure they, you know, had those co
contacts from our alumni and and as well
as some current students as well to kind
of talk about the experience here, kind
of help them with their transition. Um,
passing about to the alumni panel along
those same lines from the alumni
perspective. Um, how can incoming
students best take advantage of the
Sloan experience inside and outside of
the classroom?
Yeah, I would say I would say one of the
things that um was recommended um to do
um while I was at Sloan is to have these
informational interviews, right? And I
think um a lot of the Sloan alumni is is
is always open to having these
conversations with um current Sloan
students and you can leverage LinkedIn
or you can leverage the professors to
connect you with the alumni and I would
say it's I would say to start with
exploration conversations with with the
alumni um space. So these informational
interviews you go in trying to learn and
understand exactly what people are doing
right now. What was their experience?
How did they go from Sloan to their
current role and from the majority of
you know my experience and also my other
classmates MIT Sloan alumni is they
really take that Sloan's helping Sloan's
not just at Sloan but they take it post
Sloan into the alumni um um space. Also,
>> I think another underutilized resource
at Sloan is the faculty. Um, one of the
reasons that I ended up choosing um,
Sloan was one of the faculty members was
doing research on um, how to apply
financial models of diversification and
investing and and hedge fund management
to cancer research and how some of those
similar concepts could, you know, not
only create sustainable biotechnology
companies but have better results in the
from the scientific standpoint. And it
was so fascinating to me and obviously I
immediately wanted to take this
professor's class but on top of that you
know I was intimidated to to ask for his
one-on-one time but he was willing to
give it with you know open arms you know
for office hours for for having lunch
occasionally talking about my career
choices content in his class I was
interested in and a few of us actually
ended up becoming fairly close with
these similar interests and I know one
of my friends ended up writing a paper
with him that year. you know, these
aren't things that you typically do as
an MBA student, but if it's something
that you're interested in and there's a
faculty member studying it, they're so
willing to give you their time. And that
has gone on as alumni as well. I still
meet with um that small group of
students and we have like quarterly or
so once or twice a year maybe um through
the years we we have dinner together. Um
I I work with some of these faculty
members as an alumni member to do alumni
lectures and yeah they're they're so
willing to give their time if if you're
interested in coming to them with kind
of real career questions and and ideas
like Hey, what year is my graduate? What
industry graduate?
Uh when I was recruiting this huge help
like hey where can I best like be
connected
create resource that I feel like is
underutilized.
>> Awesome. Thank you all for sharing. We
had a little bit of trouble hearing you
at the last part but I'll let you start
this next question. um as it pertains to
your um connection to the community
postgraduation. So, I know you're a part
of the um the Sloan Affinity Group
alumni serving as one of the
co-presidents. So, could you share um
what strategies have helped you build
lasting relationships within the alumni
community?
So some things that I do uh one from a
social aspect is there's a groups one of
five groups where every last five years
depending on your area you're in SF
you're in LA you can definitely get
tapped into that group and they have
events all the time going on where you
can connect with others. Um also like by
class we have a group chat where like
hey everyone from Boston class of 2024
get to hang out get together and do
different aspects. Um so I think those
are some really good ways I stay
connected but from the I guess more of a
develop side. So I joined u uh it's a
small affinity alumni group from
affinity clubs. So, if you're part of a
ABC, the African Business Club, uh BBSA,
the Black Business Student Association,
or HBC, Hispanic Business Club, um
you're able to join this and be
connected with those from similar
backgrounds. And we do a lot of effort
help with current students, making sure
they feel like they have their resources
necessary. We engage with alumni,
sharing like their specific graduation
events, they're aware of it. So, those
are some ways that I stay.
Thanks. And Marissa, I'll pass it over
to you as well. You talked about your
engagement with the Sloan Boston Alumni
Association. So, you can talk about ways
that you've been able to stay connected
um postgraduation and some of the maybe
initiatives that you have led.
>> Yeah, absolutely. So, I've worked really
closely with Greg and his team with the
OEER. Um they have a group called Sloan
5 uh which is really focused on the most
five recent years of alumni and they
provide us with with resources, swag,
funding, everything we need as long as
you know we can put on an activity and
invite everyone to join us. And what I
found um over the last 5 years since
I've graduated is that Sloan really want
to get together as Greg touched on. um
they just often, you know, people are
willing to raise their hand and help or
show up for an event, but they might not
have the bandwidth to kind of own it and
and put it on to begin with or it's a
little intimidating to think, you know,
what if I put in all this effort and
people don't show up. And so that's
something I've been able to do both from
the the board perspective and also just
as an alumni member. Um, so I've
organized, you know, maybe 10 or so
events, um, since I graduated, ranging
from happy hours in the Boston area and
just trying to keep things both on the
week nights right after work or some
things people preer prefer the weekends
where they can bring their families. Um
and then also giving people something to
to rally around whether we have a
faculty lecture or um you know a new
book being published and faculty will
come in to sign their book and talk
about it or um a holiday party all the
different themes. And I think one thing
that's really helped me do that is by
keeping up with these these WhatsApp
groups and the chats and really finding
out what do people want. Do they just
want a place to meet and get together
and get their own drinks or do they want
something a little more formal to dress
up and go dancing and, you know, have a
holiday party? And so we can provide a
little bit of everything and constantly,
as you'll learn in course semester,
seeking feedback and acting on that
feedback. Um, is has been a really has
been a really great way to stay engaged
and and to give the community kind of
different reasons to get together. And
it helps us meet other alumni who are
choosing to stay in our same region.
Thank you both for sharing. Greg, I want
to come back to you because I know we're
getting towards the end of the uh the
year, but in the month of January, we do
have a lot of upcoming initiatives. So,
you know, what are some initiatives that
you're most excited about as we're going
into this next year?
>> Yeah, thanks. Um the spring of course is
a super busy time at MIT Sloan, but I
think for our office and our team, we
get really excited about thinking about
our graduating students who are about to
enter the alumni community. And so we
put a lot of effort into that transition
and how we talk to students about the
opportunities to stay connected and
engaged. So we do a big alumni
opportunities fair uh to you know make
those opportunities visible for students
and you know recruiting for volunteer
roles. Um but we also do a Sloan helping
Sloan's spring event every year that is
really around enabling career
conversations. So, I want to emphasize
this isn't transactional like how to get
a job, but it's really bringing students
and alumni together to talk about their
career journeys um and to build that
network and that supportive community
where folks can share best practices and
you know tips and you know how how
they've navigated um their lives and
their careers post MIT Sloan. So, that
happens every spring in partnership with
a number of groups and offices here on
campus. So, we're excited for that as
well. Awesome.
So, I'll have one final question before
we transition to the open Q&A. This
question is for all panelists here. Um,
so this is actually a question that we
got on the registration form that I
wanted to make sure I asked. So,
engaging with alumni is always scary as
a prospective student. So, you know,
what are some of the ways to ease that
introduction or connection process for
people trying to reach out to alumni as
they're trying to figure out if Son is
going to be a good place for them for
the next two or maybe even three years
depending on what programs they're going
into.
I I would I would recommend always to
start with um alumni that is in either
in a space that you're currently in or
in a space that you're looking to get
into. Um I think alumni is always ready
to have the conversation around uh the
work that they're doing. Um and I think
it's a great way to initiate that first
initial conversation. Um, and I think
and I also think that like and I think
as you looking as you're looking to um
potentially um apply to MIT Sloan, you
should also look at the different types
of um activities and programs that that
are offered at Sloan and find out if an
alumni has participated in those
activities previously and those things
will help you connect with those
individuals also on the thing that is
that is most interesting to you. I think
Salone has the healthcare conference,
the African business student conference,
they have the um the sports um the
sports conference. Uh um and there's
there's just a number of conferences
that you can that you can attend and a
lot of alumni have either supported
those conferences or go to those
conferences. Those are other ways to
kind of make those connections with the
alumni.
I think one other simple thing is just
to to be really flexible.
Excuse me. Um is to be really flexible
on your timing. And now we have the
option. People are really used to, you
know, a phone call, a Zoom, um offer to
get them coffee at the office, you know,
meet them somewhere that's convenient
for them. Um, I think, you know, people
are always happy to talk about
themselves and their journey as long as
you have really specific questions and
asks as to like what you're trying to
dig into. Um, so, so keeping that in
mind and and being as flexible as you
can on that to be respectful of their
time is also really helpful.
>> Yeah, I have nothing more to add to
that. I think that was pretty spot on
overall.
Awesome.
So now I'll leave the remaining time for
our open Q&A. There are almost a dozen
plus questions in here. So I want to
make sure that we get to most if not all
of the questions here. So I'll start off
one. This is one looks like it's
targeted towards Greg. So for
international students planning to build
ventures or return to emerging markets,
how does the alumni networks continue to
play a role postgraduation?
Yeah, I mean I think one thing I want to
emphasize, so we are based here at MIT
Sloan and we have MIT Sloan alumni clubs
regionally in some of our major markets
like New York, San Francisco, but once
you graduate, you're also part of the
wider MIT and institutewide network of
alumni. So we have 31,000 Sloan out in
the world, 141,000 MIT alumni all over
the world. And so you have access to
those networks and internationally where
we don't have too many MIT Sloan
specific clubs we have almost 100 MIT
institutewide clubs and often Sloan are
the ones who are rising to leadership
position of those volunteer networks. So
I think you know definitely tapping into
the alumni clubs across MIT wherever you
are in the world. We like to say
wherever you are in the world there's an
MIT network there for you. So that's
what I would add.
Thank you for sharing, Greg. Marissa,
>> I was just gonna Can I just build on I
just want to like give give Craig's team
credit where credit's due. like my class
graduated in um 2021 in the midst of the
pandemic and we had a lot of really
creative ideas for how we could get
together and you know now that you know
after the pandemic when it was okay and
safe to get together again and every
time we had an idea we had at least two
or three folks from OEER like happy to
hop on a call with us figure out if
there was resources if there were people
available and you know it was really
driven by by our students and completely
supported by the school and it just was
really nice to have that network ability
to kind of if you can dream it we'll
help build it kind of a scenario and
that included virtual things that you
know we involved students from clubs all
over the country but it also included
having events in New York having events
in London you know it was it was just a
lot of um it was a lot of support for
for the creative thinking that the
alumni came up with and I think it was
nice to know that that happened even
after graduation.
>> Awesome. Thank you for sharing that
perspective Marissa. I know sometimes
students are often curious about how
that that that co year went and how
students were able to engage within the
community. Um and happy to see that
you're still engaging postgraduation as
well. I'll stay with you for this next
question because it does have to do with
healthcare and I know you did I want to
say complete the healthcare certificate
while you're at Sloan. So for students
that who know what they want to do
postNBA and want to use Sloan as a
testing ground particularly in
healthcare. What are some intentional
ways you've seen them design their
experience beyond traditional coursework
and student activities? So that could be
more personal, but if you have any
classmates you want to highlight and
what they did to kind of build their
their classwork.
>> Yeah, absolutely. I think this is a
great opportunity to highlight our
action learning approach at Sloan um
where many of our classes have kind of a
a projectbased component where you're
working either with specific cases, with
companies, with other alumni. There's a
lot of different ways to do it and some
of those classes are healthcare focused.
You know, the healthcare certificate has
a healthcare action learning class,
healthcare lab, but many of the other
lab classes have healthcare type
projects. And so that one that was like
actually really formative for me was
every time I looked at, you know, a
global lab or, you know, an
entrepreneurship lab or some other type
of lab, I was like, well, this is
Boston. There are a lot of companies
that are doing life sciences that are
doing these things. So what are the
individual projects within those kind of
courses that I can tailor to to my
interests and to my level? Is it working
with you know thermoffisher on an
operations to deliver their some of
their products to their life sciences
companies? Is it um helping kind of the
biotech decisionmaking process and
really understanding what it goes into a
life science venture um activity and and
what those risks assessments are. And so
not just thinking like what are the
healthcare focused classes but what is
the content that can be applied and um
maybe I can speak to one specific
project. One of my favorite classes I
took in my second year was the
innovation ecosystems class and I wasn't
particularly interested in starting my
own venture or forming kind of an
entrepreneurship type um resume but that
class was taught by um some faculty that
they were they were really focusing on
how do you build a system around
innovation and we had the opportunity to
kind of dig into a certain case and so I
took you know I told the professors that
I had one specific case it was a final
group project and I didn't care if
anyone else was going to be in my group.
I really wanted to do this case and my
case study was vaccine development for
COVID. Um I was really interested in how
you know um Biontech this tiny company
out of Germany came up with a solution
and then but had to you know partner
with Fizer because they didn't have the
innovative um ability there in Germany
and within their company and similarly
Merna was in the US and they were able
to fund raise and triple their size and
work with the US government and do
everything in house and those were two
completely different models for
innovation and so I was applying the
class concepts and I ended up convincing
one other student to join my project
because she was, you know, just excited
that I was excited. But the faculty were
okay being flexible. You know, typically
it's a four or five person project, but
I talked to them at the beginning and
was like, look, this is something I'm
really interested in, and I know that
there's a group component here, but is
it okay if I really like run with this?
And and they were totally comfortable
with that as long as we had that
conversation to tailor the class to to
my interests and the research I wanted
to do.
>> Thank you for sharing, Lawrence. I'll
pass it over to you for this next
question. It has to do with specifically
the Sloan Fellows program, but also your
your venture that you were able to
launch. So, looking back at your
transition after the 2024 Stone Fellows
program, what specific resources from
the career development office or alumni
um prove most pivotal in landing your
next venture/shop?
>> Yeah. Um I think there was a couple of
so the co office um career development
office provided one of the things that
they did is for the stone fellows and I
think they do it for the two-year
programs is they offer these set of
courses on on interacting with um either
alumni or people within the industry and
how to set up like I mentioned earlier
informational interviews but just how to
better interact with individuals so that
you are getting the best responses when
you need to reach out to to people
within the space that you want to get
into after after business school and um
so there's there's the course that they
that they offered and a couple of
classes that they offered that you can
take um and then there's like the actual
working with a a um an adviser in the co
office that introduced me to alumni that
had launched either launched their own
venture fund or were in the venture fund
uh were working for other venture um um
venture funds in the Boston area. And
those in introductions really help to
shape kind of like my thinking and my
approach in in possibly launching the in
in in launching the venture fund. So
they do it in in in many different ways.
um thinking about a specifically how to
interact with people that will help you
understand how to launch the fund and
then be connecting you with the right
individuals one-on-one meaning the the
co office individual will send an email
introduce me and then I will connect
with them connect with the the alumni
through through that way. So yeah they
they really played a major role in kind
of just shaping my understanding of of
who to who's best to interact with and
then also developing my my investment
thesis for the fund.
Thank you for sharing. The ne the next
question I have is open to the entire
panel. So um from your experience, what
are some of the unwritten norms around
engaging with Sloan alumni that new
students often miss?
>> Oh, can I I have something?
>> Yeah, go ahead.
>> Um so essentially so the first day of
Sloan, one of the one of the things that
you learn very quickly is that everyone
is super accomplished and everyone has
done something. Um, and everyone is
pretty humble about the things that
they've done. Um, and I think you don't
necessarily need to um, sell yourself
um, in regards to who you are to have a
conversation with somebody from Sloan. I
think people from Sloan value the the
opportunity to just either learn from
somebody or to share something that
helps someone else. So I would highly
always recommend that you know as you
interact with alumni or Sloan or or or
alumni or Sloan, you don't need to sell
your who you are to them. They're
they're open to having these
conversations.
I would add I mean we're often talking
to students as they're approaching
graduation and so you know they're often
in career and job mindset and I
mentioned this earlier but um you know
getting out of the transactional mode
just remember when you join the MIT
Sloan community this is a community for
a lifetime and so it's not just about
getting a job like truly emphasize like
trying to build relationships with the
other people who have come before you in
this community as well. So just keeping
that again, it's a lifelong community
here.
>> Yeah. I think one one really important
way to do that is to to make sure to to
continue your alumni or community
engagement goals regardless of where you
are in your job search. Um just kind of
remember consistently like what what do
you want from a network? What do you
want to you know what level of
engagement do you want with the
community? not just when you need
something, but when you know for for the
long term and and thinking about how how
that means showing what that means for
you and how showing up looks like um you
know on a day-to-day basis sometimes it
can be really hard to to
show up and for an event or some
activity because and you're thinking,
well, what am I going to get out of
this? But I feel like you're always
happy to to do it in the end. And so
just giving yourself some grace to to do
that.
Yeah, I think doubling down on that, I
think the actual community aspect, not
treating treat uh treating everything as
like a transactional relationship like
hey, I'm g reach out to this person XYZ,
but I want to develop a relationship. I
think relationships are the big thing
around alumni, community, and
networking. Um, and not just like, hey,
what can I get out of this? Um, finding
ways to like understand that person,
what they're going through like their
career journey is really important.
Awesome.
Thank you all for sharing. Uh I know
we're getting close to time, but I want
to kind of save time for a few more
questions if possible. Um so this is
open to everyone. So um how does the
Sloan Alumni Network retain alumni
engagement and that stay relevant to
alumni's needs as they progress through
their career journey?
Think that may be a specific question
for you, Greg. I'm not sure, but anybody
can feel free to answer. Yeah, I mean
there are the nitty-gritty technical
things. We send surveys. We get
feedback. We constantly are meeting with
alumni on the road and working with our
volunteers to hear feedback from alumni
on the programming they would like to
see. Um whether that's career or faculty
engagement or intellectual programming.
Um and then down to how do we change
some of our traditions like what do we
do at reunions? Bringing C functions in,
you know, all of those different ways um
that we can, you know, keep alumni
connected. So those are just some
thoughts off the bat.
>> And the next question I have will be for
those that are looking to pivot careers.
So you know what is the most effective
way to reach out to alumni working in
the a sector that they're interested in?
I think one effective way is actually
having a reach out on LinkedIn, having a
really clear and concise message. Um,
I've seen some messages where there
essays, hey, I'm a I have a lot going on
in my personal life, in my uh job life,
career. um and seeing like something
four or five like paragraphs like oh man
this is like entire I think just keeping
like short simple friendly ask um is one
a great way um just for like the sake of
time and u simplicity