And it is now my pleasure to introduce
the next speaker who will be talking
about XR in manufacturing building the
factories of tomorrow. So XR is
reshaping manufacturing by
revolutionizing how we design produce
and maintain. The upcoming keynote will
explore promising XR applications, their
role in creating efficient, sustainable
manufacturing systems and the road map
for overcoming barriers to unlock their
full potential. So ladies and gentlemen,
please join me in welcoming the postto
scientist at Technicia Universate Vin
which is the Vienna University of
Technology, Sara Sheffa.
[Music]
[Applause]
So, thank you very much all for coming.
I feel very honored to be here today.
Um, and I hope I represent Austria in a
proper way because I am Dutch. So, let's
see if I can do it in a proper way. Um,
so today I will be talking about
extended reality and manufacturing. I
always say um sometimes I feel like I
live in Sara's reality. It's a bit the
domain in which I work. So, it's uh
yeah, I will discuss later what extended
reality means. Um, and let's let's get
started.
Hey. So let's augment the future
together. Um a short introduction about
myself. As you probably know from my
accent, I am Dutch. My name is Saraser.
I'm a postto at Tuin. Um I have an
expertise in extended reality
troubleshooting, predictive maintenance
in in the domains of manufacturing,
production, logistics, and management.
And a fun fact is that I'm third
generation of ship builders. So my
father and my grandfathers were all ship
building. In the ship building, I mean
we are Dutch. All we have is water. So
what else can I become? And um so when I
was uh I told my father I would like to
become an engineer. And then he said
Sara before you enter that office of
becoming an engineer you have to go to
the to the workshop and you have to work
with your hands with the with the boys
and and girls who who work in the shop
floor because you don't have any
experience. You need to weld. You need
to get your hands dirty and you need to
get working. So I said okay let's try.
So um I went for almost a year at the
shipyard and I was working in my one
year my overall walking with the mis
like a welding equipment and why am I
telling this because it's very important
to get get to know the workers that you
work with um to identify yourself with
them and if you have new technologies
such as extended reality you need to
incorporate it in such a way that they
can relate to it. So you cannot just
come up with the technology, bring for
example the holo lens to the technicians
and say here's the technology solution
let's get to work. You really need to
embed such a solution into the
workforce. So therefore the human in the
loop operation but also the human
machine interaction is very important um
to consider. So apart from the naval
architecture, I also because I thought
naval
archite architecture is very specific.
Um maybe I should extend my my field. So
I then worked in aviation and um then I
went to the railway sector and then I I
basically almost covered all the
logistics uh field. Um then I also
worked for a project with semiconductor
industry. So I think I covered some some
application
areas. I cannot work all by myself of
course. Um I have a very good team
behind me and the research unit that I
work in is the production maintenance
management team of um professor Vasil
Anzari. So he is leading our team on
datadriven production and maintenance
management. And we are a group that's
really data driven. So we have a lot of
projects about AI, AR um and then we
incorporate also the sustainability
asset aspect in this um environment. And
another thing that's very interesting is
that we have a pilot factory and a pilot
factory is basically um a condensed
setting of a real world industrial
scenario. So what we can do is we can
mimic um yeah scenario in a logistic or
in a
production field and then have it in in
our own consent setting. So we have a
bit more control. So there we can
conduct um experiments for
example and then um because I feel like
I always have two fathers. One of them
is C, one of them is is Fasil. So the
other professor that I collaborate with
is um professor Gord Matias and together
we are building up a new research group
and this is a technology enhanced
logistic and maintenance management
group and of course here we also
incorporate a lot of human in the loop
oper operations the supply chain
management. So not only do we look at
into one specific asset but into the
entire supply chain and another thing
that is very important for us is
education and teaching. So we cannot
uh so we are responsible for teaching
our future engineers and maybe
technicians our future the workforce and
therefore it's also very important to
incorporate them into our vision.
When we go to the state-of-the-art of
manufacturing, we see that in recent
years a lot of um data
um came up with the manufacturer,
maintenance and project production and
logistics systems. So we see that coming
from all these assets a lot of big uh
yeah a lot of information is coming and
this information we need to perform
maintenance for example on the rolling
stock and what we see in this area is
that a lot of information technology and
operational technology intertwine and
then it becomes difficult to solve
issues in when you have system failures
in for example a train
um not only in trains but also in the
other transport uh sectors. So therefore
we need to get an understanding of what
does this data mean that that that
exists because we have to deal with
real-time monitoring data but also with
historical data and all different kind
of data. So how can we structure this
information in such a way that we know
what has failed or how we can support
for example technicians.
So if we go and for a deep dive into the
state of manufacturing and the problems
that occur then we see for example that
there is the IT and OT convergence. So
the information technology and the
operational technology systems from for
example a rolling stock or an aircraft
whatever um they come intertwined and
when a failure in that system occurs
then it becomes very difficult to
understand what has failed and how you
can resolve this system failure. um
there at the same time there's also a
lot of fragmented data and it mean it
means that there's a lot of data and
different data sources. So for example
if I'm a technician and I have to
troubleshoot something then I have to
use different information sources to
access and then to identify what is the
problem. So therefore my decision-
making not only for the managers but
also for the the the work floor and for
the operators becomes more difficult
because they yeah really need support in
this and the operator requirements
basically means is how can we support
the operators so the future technicians
in resolving this uh yeah issues and
another thing is that we face is the the
loss of not only tested but knowledge in
general. So for example, a lot of people
they they get older or some people they
stay only for a few years in a in a
certain job and then they leave the
company and then the knowledge is lost.
So how can we deal with these kind of
issues and at the same time we also have
to um be mindful about the
sustainability pressures. So we have to
support sustainable operations,
sustainable manufacturing systems. Um so
these are also things that we have to
keep in mind.
If we um look into extended reality, I I
didn't know how many people know about
the concept of extended reality, but
extended reality is basically um all the
different realities in the continuum. So
it goes from augmented reality to
virtual reality in in which augmented
reality you have an overlay on the real
environment in like two or 3D. Mixed
reality is a combination with AR, VR and
virtual reality. then you are completely
immersed into the virtual reality and in
the next video um I will focus I will
give an example of virtual reality I
collaborated a lot with the Dutch
railway companies Dutch railway company
it's only one and um here we have two
different scenarios so the first one is
about uh the system failure of a door
because in the rolling stock we see a
lot of system failures in the door
system so that basically the mechanism
of the door doesn't close properly
And here we made a simulation to train
the technicians on how to uh step by
step resolve the issue. And the other
one is about um the conductors because
conductors have to deal with a lot of
different people when they work on the
platform. So some of them are disabled
so they need some support. Sometimes
people are aggressive so you need to
deal with them as well. Um so those are
the two um examples that we will see.
Yeah, that is
so uh
nasty. Yeah, fine.
Okay.
So, the subtitles of the the last part
kind of disappeared, but it was a way of
are you okay? And then the woman could
roll into the into the train. Um, and
the second uh video that I would like to
introduce augmented reality is also in
the context of the railways. Um and here
we conducted different yeah research
already and we given a short overview of
the IT and OT convergence and then we
move towards the troubleshooting. So
troubleshooting is basically a way to
automatically detect failures of a train
and how to step by step solve that
issue. The railway industry experienced
a digital transformation in recent years
the impact of which is complex. Also,
traditional operation technology systems
become more and more connected and
intertwined with information technology
systems. This is called
convergence. Digitization and
convergence of IT and OT systems becomes
increasingly important for railway
operations to achieve less maintenance
cost, efficient and reliable operations.
However, the convergence of IT and OT
requires new maintenance strategies and
thus paves the way towards the use of
new technologies such as augmented
reality. We examine the use of AR as a
tool for IT and OT failure analysis. AR
can support the operator by
troubleshooting IT and OT failures and
give step-by-step guidance to resolve
the issue. We already explored future AR
applications in NS which are automatic
fault detection, translation of work
descriptions, inspection of complex
components, having access to remote
assistance and assistance for
specialized work. Operators work in a
dynamic working environment requiring
both high adaptive capabilities and
expert knowledge. We proposed an
adaptive architectural framework aimed
at shaping and structuring the process
that provides operators with tailored
support when using an AR tool. Ongoing
research focuses on combining artificial
intelligence and AR to create a
troubleshooting tool for IToT converge
systems. So this um is about the
operator 4.0. I think it has some
alignment with with John's presentation.
Um so the operator 4.0 0 who is the
operator 4.0 So it's the future
technician. So it's a person who works
with new technologies such as augmented
reality, virtual reality, all these kind
of um end tools. Um and this person has
to work with yeah these new has to find
new ways to work with the technology.
The technology has to be embedded within
his working method. And um this is Tai
and Ta was performing some experiments
on the train and Tai has different
expertise. So TA has diff. So if I
compare my own expertise with TIC then I
can say that I am less experienced. So
for example Tai would need less support
than I would need. And at the same time
his ergonomics are also different. Um
and also his interest. So for example
Tai could be color blind and therefore
he needs different support than for
example I would have and at the same
time he has more knowledge than I and
how can we capture that knowledge that
is in his mind. Um at the same time we
have different maintenance operations.
So they are more dynamic. There are
different task requirements, different
planning and methods needed, different
ways of performing the maintenance. And
we have on the other hand also the
technology itself. So we have hardware
and software constraints. Um cont the
system needs to contextualize and
customize the information. So
basically um one of the constraints
could be that if it's summer it's very
warm to wear such a such a device and
therefore there is a need to have a
dynamic tool that is tailored to dice
and also to me. So you need to have yeah
a dynamic tool that changes its
information
supply. And if we look into the data
collection and data platforms, we see
that as we discussed before, there's a
lot of data segment fragmentation. So a
lot of different information is stored
in different places. So the real-time
monitoring information is here. Um the
operational data is stored in a
different place and the work
instructions are located somewhere else
and how can you then perform decision
making, make the right decisions in the
troubleshooting procedure. So what we
did here is we collaborated with the
Tokyo Institute of Technology as well
and
um there they were more focused and
specialized in in database research. So
we created the database and we filtered
all the information coming from the
railway company. We could filter all the
relevant information that was useful and
we could filter the information that is
useful for the technician. Um and what
we incorporated here is for example
machine learning and um natural language
processing to detect what kind of
information was stored in the system. So
for example we saw that operators would
fill in that the toilet because we had
to focus on the sanitary system then the
operator would mention the toilet looks
like a Coca-Cola can and a Coca-Cola can
I mean we don't know what it means but
yeah in their minds a Coca-Cola can
means that the toilet was clogged. So
all these kind of things makes it more
difficult to use natural language
processing. And in the video we um
applied the decision- making supports.
What we did is we collected some systems
of the sanitary system and from all the
systems in the train the sanitary system
has very high priority because if there
are no um toilets functioning properly
in the train you cannot um operate the
train for passengers because we all need
to use the bathroom if you need. So what
we did here is we collected the systems,
we um combined it with object
recognition so you can really see what
kind of button you have to press um and
you could uh then see what for what kind
of step-by-step information you need to
solve the issue. So this is a very
condensed laboratory setting and this
system could also um save and store the
information that you put. So for
example, if today I clean the the
sensors of the toilet, then it remembers
and then it predicts when I have to
clean the sensors
again. Other research is focusing on
combining AI and AR. At the moment we
have a project going on with Carion. Um
and here we want to reduce the human
error by implementing
um AI powered aircraft inspections
um to enhance safety and improve
maintenance accuracy. So this project is
u at the moment conducted by a PhD
student in our research group. Um and
then we also have a topic about the
knowledge management. Uh here we
conducted research with the Dutch
defense and then we had an a product. I
cannot mention or specify what specific
product. Um and then the the military
military guy had to disassemble and
assemble
um the the product together. Um and that
was a very nice way in how we could
capture his knowledge because um at some
point he was deviating from the
maintenance manual and in that way you
can kind of capture a little bit of the
the knowledge and then you can um save
that information and then put it back
into the system for in this specific
case it was in the
AR. Um then we go to the
troubleshooting. Troubleshooting is a
way to automatically generate the
failure mechanism of a system and this
is also a way of understanding complex
problem problems and supporting operator
4.0. Um in this example we were um
putting in a standardized procedure for
the door system failure. As I mentioned
before the the door system failure is
also a reoccurring problem. Um what we
see here is that troubleshooting is most
useful if you use it in cases in which
it is highly complex and also um not
commonly used. So if you put such um um
problem into the AR system and a
technician knows how to resolve it then
the next time he it becomes easier to uh
resolve the issue. So you really need to
incorporate the more complex uh problems
because once it's standardized then
people know how to solve certain
issues. Then we had another um example
of combining AI and AR. Um we had a
collaboration with Albelli and Albelli
they print the photo books um to store
all of our beautiful memories. And um
what we noticed here is that Albellyi
when they so this is the printing
machine to print the photo books and
when Alelli was printing the books then
sometimes the the cover of the book had
a round shape of or it was um tilted. So
you need to have a straight book spine
and based on the shape of the book spine
you you would know where to solve the
system failure in the machine itself. So
here we combined AR knowledgebased
systems and artificial intelligence. So
you could really detect with the holo
lens uh the object and then the
step-by-step instructions would follow
related to the machine on how to solve
uh the system failure.
The
last more
technical
[Music]
part.
No, wait.
So the last um part um is about the
functionality.
Um so what we have here in this video
below is we um had a real
troubleshooting scenario of the train.
So first we had a condensed setting in a
laboratory setting in which we were
troubleshooting but then the technicians
they gave us the feedback. They said
tada cut the crap we need to have the
real the real deal. we don't want to
perform experiments in a in a lab uh
setting. We want to solve it in a real
case scenario. So then we transformed
from the lab to the real train. And what
they could do was really nice because
they could put the system error exactly
as we tested in the lab but then in real
case um we had um we used the point
clouds to create the 3D image and then
you can have the object recognition. And
at some point it was quite funny because
one of the technicians he said um s do I
really have to pull these plugs and I
said yeah I think so but I don't know I
mean we never did maintenance on a real
train but in the end they were able to
to solve the issues. I think that was
quite nice experiment. Uh and at the
same time we have the multi- aent
collaboration.
So the multi- aent collaboration means
that if I collaborate with someone on
the same asset let's say a car um then I
can see what my colleague is seeing and
I can help him or her in certain ways.
So um here you can see the different
views um and also I think the ergonomics
here are captured. What is important
here is to have the data collection anal
analysis in a proper way. So you need to
have your real-time monitoring data in
order and the the fragmented data in one
centralized place and you need to push
the right information to the technician
that is relevant for him or her to solve
the system failure.
[Music]
So going uh forward to the next topic uh
we also look into the organizational
impact as I mentioned before we cannot
just go with the technology put it
somewhere and then make sure that
organization can manage themselves. Um
one more specific technical um detail is
that the user interface design needs to
be in such a way that everyone can
comprehend the information intuitively.
So for example I would need different
user interface than than my colleague.
Um so you need to design it in such a
way that I can perceive it properly so
it becomes easy
understandable and at the same time um
it's also important uh to develop an
extended reality road map for
organizations. So what we did um with
another company is we created uh we
could compute the maturity level
readiness of this specific technology
for the organization and what we saw is
that it is really necessary for for
organizations to develop a road map have
dedicated extended reality teams with
centralized documentation. So your data
infrastructure need to be in order in
order to use such a technology. You need
to make sure that someone has ownership.
So has the leadership within a project.
The data accessibility is of course
important because if you don't have
access to the data then it becomes very
difficult to proceed.
Um and then uh another important part is
besides a case study you should
incorporate a pilot program and a pilot
program is kind of um maybe a year or
something to incorporate the technology
and see how you can improve. So this is
also something that we have been working
on with the Dutch
railways and um the funny thing is that
the other day I was invited by Austrian
company and then they asked me s you
have very interesting technology and
knowledge. Can you also give us some
direction? So I came up with my um with
the presentation and my vision on how
they could incorporate the technology as
well.
And then one of the guys said, "Yeah, I
think paperbased manuals are just better
than this." And then I thought, "Okay, I
think I wasted an hour here." But okay,
I think it's important for people to uh
step on this um track of digitization
and implementation of new technologies
um not only for organizations but also
for teaching. So what we did at TUV so
far is we did incorporate and have some
projects running for extended reality in
teaching for
example and um one of the examples that
I had is I had a company an aviation
company and they came to me and they
said we would like to have helicopter
blade inspections and we would like to
incorporate thermal
um heat detection so heat mapping and
that you could really see as an
inspector how to um incorporate or how
to see or control the the quality of the
helicopter blade. And as a researcher,
sometimes we're also a bit lazy. So I
went to my students that I teach a
course for and I told my students,
"Guys, this is a case study from a
company. Can you solve this?" Um and
they were able to solve the case and
then they indirectly helped the company
also um contributing So what I think is
very nice is that not only do we support
companies, we can also implement case
studies for students, the future
engineers to learn how to incorporate
these new technologies and how to work
with organizations. So then they are
really embedded um in the teaching as
well and therefore
um we created a road map for
uh the teaching as well. So uh first
it's very important to identify what
kind of cont content you can give for
lectures um what kind of domains are
relevant and then you specify the
specific technology you want to work
with. Um at the same time you also need
to have 3D models the scenes the
scenarios that you want to teach. You
need to train your your teachers um and
staff on using these technologies. You
need some to have some support some
motivation of students and then in the
end you need to have some kind of an
environment to support um yeah the
creation of such a study program.
um not only do we focus on the students
but also for organizations. So if you
are an organization and you want to
start with AR of new extended reality
technologies then it's very important to
have a plan of approach um and of course
a goal um that you want to achieve
within a few years and at the same time
it's also very important to create a
community of practice to have dedicated
AR teams and to also have a backlog so a
centralized data platform.
Um, of course you cannot just wing it.
You need to comply to rules and
regulations um from the AU EU but also
from your yeah local government and then
you can create a solution outline in
which you evaluate whether or not the
project is um
sustainable. This is also a road map
that we developed. So what we saw in the
um back in the in time that um they
started with remote support uh trials
and remote support basically means that
if I work here and I collaborate with my
colleague in the Netherlands then I can
look and support him from a distance.
The documented assistant is the next
step in which you put all the documents
like the work description in one folder
and give step-by-step um directions. the
sequence assistance. Then you you add
the 3D models, you add the object
recognition. So it already becomes a bit
more smart and intelligent and um the
next step would be intelligence
assistance in which you combine
augmented reality and artificial
intelligence and who knows maybe in the
end we will end up with robots.
So I would like to end this uh keynote
with um saying that I think it's very
good that we are all here today and it's
good to connect not only with the
technology but also with each other uh
worldwide because I think it's important
that we can all augment the future
together. So thank you very
much for a little bit. Yes. May I ask
you to stay with me on stage just a
little bit because I can already see we
received questions and here's the first
one. How long do you think it will take
for XR to be common place in industries?
How can industry, academia, government
help speed up adoption? I think it's a
very nice uh question. What I do think
is um it's very difficult to say when is
the technology ready to implement. So
what we see for example if you look into
the holo lens if if it's a end tool
already then we can already understand
that technicians cannot work with it
because um the feedback that I received
is for example it's too heavy I get
sweaty it's um so or if it's too dark
then I might fall in a manhole and these
kind of things um and I do think that if
you incorporate industry academia and
government all together um and start
projects together it will definitely
speed up the the adoption because then
it becomes a more known phenomena and
then people will understand that it's
important to incorporate.
Pick another question. So what are the
biggest barriers to ARMR VR adoption in
manufacturing and how can we increase
adoption rates? Yeah, I think um in I
think some of it was already covered
before. So I think at the moment the the
hardware itself is still a bit
limitating. So um there are some
limitations with sometimes accuracy but
also um with the connection with the
Wi-Fi for example. So that has more
hardware restrictions that it becomes
difficult to to adopt and at the same
time sometimes it's also difficult for
technicians to um accept that they have
to work with new technologies because
sometimes they are a bit worried that
they might be replaced in the end by
robots. So I think it's also important
to emphasize that it is um an addition
to the work and not a way to replace the
workforce. All right. So let's maybe
have one
more question. So could XR be part of a
business model for outsourced
maintenance operated by external
companies or is just cost cutting in
internal operation and maintenance?
Um I think at the moment it could be
part of the business model. Um what I
see right now is that a lot of companies
they try to really set up the new teams
and they really want to do the
maintenance themselves. But I can also
understand that it's better sometimes to
outsource because um sometimes you don't
have the capabilities to to um code for
example or put all the maintenance
information in it. So then it becomes
better to outsource some kind of things.
All right. Thank you very much. Thanks
for sharing your expertise. Please give
a big round of applause for Sara Sha.
Thank you so much.