Good morning everybody. Welcome to the
MPG primer. Today I have the absolute
pleasure of introducing Sarah Urbett.
She is a cardiology fellow at MGH and a
post-doal associate at the Broad in the
lab of Purit Natarajin. She previously
comp completed her MD PhD at the
University of Chicago in statistical
genetics. Her research focuses on
developing statistical methods to handle
genomic and clinical data. In her free
time, she enjoys bicycling and Chicago
pizza. In today's primer, she's going to
present a practical primer on um Beijian
statistics. So,
thank you. All right. I don't know.
Okay. I don't really need a microphone.
I'm pretty loud. Um all right. So, hi.
Good morning everybody. Um so, this is a
hefty title. Beijian statistics is a
very large is a very large uh field. And
as appropriately I have 84 slides just
for the morning which we are not going
to get through. So it's kind of a choose
your own adventure a little bit. Um and
we'll start with the things that I was
asked to talk actually everybody when
they hear about Beijian statistics they
say well what do you have against P
values? I have a lot of things against P
values but I'm convince all of you to
have things against P values also. Not
really but um so that's one of the
topics that we can discuss. Then
conjugate models which are a really neat
way of entering into Beijian statistics
because they combine sort of the
uncomfortable part of Beijian statistics
is a lot of the sampling that we know
about MCMC and you probably have heard
of. It's a sort of painful but useful
technique. Um and so we can avoid that
with a lot of these conjugate models
that are useful in mixer models. It's a
later topic and then of course if we
have a little time which we won't we can
talk a little bit about um Beijing
clinical trials anyway. All right. So
the p value paradox. So uh what is a p
value is the question for the
audience. Does anyone want to answer?
Okay, we don't have to. That's okay.
It's early. Um right. So it's a
probability of seeing a statistic as or
more extreme given that the null is
true. It doesn't say anything about the
alternative. And also quite often we're
not actually interested in we we we
don't want to know the probability of
seeing statistic as or more extreme
given that the null is true. We want to
know that the probability that the null
is true or the probability the
alternative is true. And so to
illustrate this, I kind of came up with
this neat diagram. This is um Dennis
Lindley talks about how a p value really
isn't evidence for the alternative at
all. And so this is two different
distributions. So the distribution on
the red is the null. The distribution on
the blue is the alternative. Also, just
to note all these slides, um I had a lot
of fun and pain. Um this is a this is a
software. It's called CTO. You probably
heard of. So CTO has a way of making
presentations. And the nice thing about
this is afterwards you can log on and go
through all the code if you want to try
to figure out how to make these
simulations yourself which I highly
recommend not but I just think it's a
great way to learn statistics to go
through the code. So anyway all right so
in this diagram we have uh statistics
that arose from a null distribution and
we have statistics that arose from an
alternative distribution right these are
the two truth situations and you can see
that if I observe a value which yielded
a p value of 0.05 5 this 2.5 under the
null distribution the posterior
probability which is the probability or
the yeah the yeah the sorry the
likelihood the probability of seeing
that statistic given that the null is
true is actually higher than the
probability of seeing that statistic
given that the alternative is true. So
we always need to consider the evidence
for the alternative when we're
evaluating the the the
null, right? And this is what I was
describing before is that the statistic
that a p value gives us which is the
probability of seeing statistic as a or
more extreme given that the null is true
is not really what we're all trying to
get at as scientists which is the
probability of a hypothesis given the
data. So um and this is not actually
restricted this sort of philosophy the
idea of this prior that a lot of people
think about with Beijians that's it's
not completely um you can have sort of
an ambivalent prior what we call a fra
prior and you can come up with the same
sort of drawing that a frequentist would
but it gives you an entirely different
interpretation interpretation about the
probability of hypothesis given the data
and I'm going to show you this so these
are some pearls uh in the Beijian
framework work that parameters are
random variables. We can actually get
uncertainty because we get this
distribution over what we think the
hypothesis is the null hypothesis or the
alternative hypothesis. We can integrate
evidence from outside sources using our
prior distributions and also we get this
natural quantification of uncertainty
through either sampling or through the
conjugate distribution because we get a
distribution on the hypothesis. Okay, so
here this is so here's a a classic a
classic this is what our posterior
distribution of a hypothesis is. So our
probability of the hypothesis given the
data and we observe this point estimate.
This is how we draw this. So a credible
interval and a confidence interval. What
I want you to see is that they're
actually quite similar, right? They
overlap because I used a very flat
prior. But the interpretation of them is
really different. So what is a credible
interval and what is a confidence
interval? Probably start with the
confidence interval. What is a
confidence interval? Does
everybody? Okay. So it's the long Yeah.
Okay. Who's running? All right. So it's
the long run frequency of observing a
statistic within this window. So that
would say if I ran and I say who's
running because it's kind like who's
running who's doing this many
experiments, right? Time is short. We
got to move. Okay. So if I did if I if I
did a thousand
experiments, 95% of them would contain
the true parameter of interest because a
parameter is considered as fixed in the
frequentist analysis 95% of the time.
That's kind of a long winded way of
describing it, right? What what does
that mean? If I ran this experiment a
thousand times, if I created a thousand
times that I would actually have the
ability to run the experiment, the true
parameter of interest would be in this
interval 95% of the time. I don't know.
That's a lot of words. So, a credible
interval, which as you can see considers
sort of the same area, is the is the
very intuitive explanation. It's just
saying I have a there's a 95% certainty
that the that the random variable lies
within this interval that it actually
lies within this interval and that's
because the basically the probability
mass under this distribution lies in
that area. So you construct this new
distribution based on the posterior
distribution. It has a mean and a
standard error in this case or mean and
a variance in this case and you say what
is the interval that would contain 90
95% of the the mass there.
much more interpretable. Okay, so now
we're getting to B theorem, which is u I
think a lot of us have seen this in you
know introductory math statistics. It's
the probability of the hypothesis given
the data times the probability of the
data given the hypothesis times the
probability of the hypothesis. So you
can forget the constant in the bottom
and the probability of the data given
the hypothesis is called the likelihood
and that's what a frequentist deals with
and the probability of the hypothesis is
called the prior and that's what people
think of Beijian statistics is limited
to but it's really not. It's this
compilation of these three elements
actually this normalizing constant is
kind of annoying but it's there um that
really summarize an entire body of
statistics from the Reverend Thomas Baze
um and it's quite useful. Okay. Uh, and
so this is this is an example. You can
go through the code actually, but um, as
I'll talk about these con, you'll see
that things sort of repeat themselves or
also foreshadow themselves. That's kind
of intentional. It's good to repeat
these things. But um, this is a nice
example of a Beijian how how the Beijian
framework works, right? So we have some
prior belief about what we think the
alil frequency is. This distribution is
called a beta distribution. That's not
important. That's just a word. But
basically it's a distribution of how
confident we are in the value of the
alle frequency. Right? It's a random
variable. It's fluctuating somewhere
around there. It's not now it's not
totally random. Somewhere there's a true
universe that suggests what the actual
frequency is. But it serves as a as a
random variable in this in this sense.
So there's um so there's this prior
distribution. Then we meet our new
observed alo frequencies that has this
distribution. Uh that's the green,
right? And then so it's some sort of
amalgamation of the prior and the
likelihood gives us our posterior. And
as I'm going to talk about in the
conjugate section, there's some really
nice properties that I actually don't
have to do any sort of sophisticated
sampling. The way that when you work out
the the algebra, effectively, I'm just
taking each of these new observed units,
combining them with the prior, and then
I get this really nice convenient result
that gives me a posterior without having
to do any sort of fancy
calculus. Not that fancy calculus is
wrong, but um okay. So now so let's go
back to our p- value friends. So our p-
value as we said was more in the
likelihood camp. It's not the
probability of the hypothesis given the
data. It's the probability of the data
given the hypothesis. And basian have an
answer for this as well. But remember we
wanted to talk about the alternative.
That's really important. So we can we
come up with this idea of a baze factor.
And there's to be confusing two kinds of
baze factors. One evaluates the
probability of the data under the
alternative hypothesis divided by the
probability of the data under the null.
And that's called the beta 1 0 because
one is in the nu numerator and zero is
in the basement. Or there's the
alternative the base factor 01 which is
the probability of the data under the
null hypothesis divided by the the data
under the alternative. Equivalent
statements just inverses of one another
but they do it to you know keep you like
a bar for entering. So you got to have a
license to become a patient. Um okay so
why is this important? Well I'm going to
show you that it's important. So I wear
several hats, none well, but um in one
of them, you know, I spent some time in
in the hospital, right? And uh and and
it's very useful because you can quickly
take some feeling about your prior
belief combined with this nice
convenient way of parameterizing our
evidence uh under two different
hypotheses and generate a posterior
distribution really quickly. I'm going
to show you that magic so you can use
that. Okay, but first um right, so what
does it actually mean when we observe
these very low p values? So, I made this
nice app actually. See if we can
actually access this. I'm a little
scared because if I access this, we may
never get back. I don't know. Do I do
it? Do it. Okay, we're going to do
it or not. We may not do it. Okay,
that's not working. Oh, do I have
to?
Huh? Great. Well, that worked well.
Share. Oh, because I'm only sharing one.
Okay, great. All right, sorry guys.
Interlude.
Okay, so this is really nice. Okay, so
this is a shiny app. So we have this we
have this prior belief on what we
believe about uh the truth of the
association, right? So that that falls
into our prior that's about the
hypothesis being associated or not being
associated with the hypothesis. So we
have that belief. Now we observe this p
value which translates as I was
describing this b factor. The p- value
is in the likelihood camp. So the p-
value itself is not directly a
likelihood but it's in that camp. It's
the probability of seeing a statistic as
a or more extreme given that the null is
true. And say that p value suggests that
there's a
99% probability of seeing the data given
that well it's a probability of 90 a
0.01% of seeing the data given that the
null is true. Uh but it doesn't mean a
99% chance of true association. That's
the key point in this plot. So but if we
combine that so if we convert that p
value to a baze factor and combine it
with the prior we actually get only an
18% probability of the al uh probability
of the alternative hypothesis given the
data and we can try this with different
assumptions right so in this so we can
try actually a larger observed p value
and of course that's going to make our
posterior even lower and we could also
try uh the prior probability of
association could increase this actually
right so that's going to increase our
posterior so there's there's definitely
fluctuations here. But the key point I
want to make here and if you walk away
with nothing is a p value of
0.01%. Does not mean that there's a
99.99 probability percent probability
that the alternative is true. It
actually tells you nothing about the
alternative. It just says that that's
quite unlikely under the
null. But it depends. I mean I could say
uh I see three tusks, so it's probably
not an an elephant. That's probably
true, but that doesn't mean it's a
person, right? Like it's Yeah. So
anyway,
um, go
back. Okay, now it's all going to fall
apart. Whoops. That's now we stopped
sharing. Sorry about that,
guys.
Okay, look at that. Okay. All right. So
we have this convenient way of
converting P values to B factors as I
was describing to translate this
frequentist quantity and something
that's useful as Beijing or useful just
period and full stop. Um okay and so
there's these three uh brilliant guys
who came up with this paper um in the
70s actually that translated these p
values to a base factor and this
remember I said I was going to be very
confusing and throw around base factor
01 to base factor 1 0. So now we're
talking about the 01 just to make it
interesting, right? And so what is the
base factor minimum is? Well, it
basically says this is the minimum
amount of evidence for the null
hypothesis we would get making the most
sort of um uh optimistic assumptions
about the alternative hypothesis.
Because if this is this base factor is
weighing the probability of the data
under the null hypothesis over the
probability of the data under the
alternative hypothesis then if we had
really big basement or a really small
you know attic then we're effectively
going to get a very low base factor
minimum and so that's saying a p value
of 0.05 5 translates to this minimum
base factor. P value of 0.001 translates
to that. Well, what does that mean? That
basically means roughly that there's 37
as much evidence for the null as there
is for the alternative, which is
actually only 2.7 times as much evidence
for the alternative versus the null.
That's really not convincing at all.
Like I'm not making any decisions with
that. And yet we build a lot of our
decisions in certainly in medicine or in
science based on this p value. So you
have to be really thoughtful. Now, there
are situations in which observing that p
value depending on the the the
population of other tests or on our
prior belief going in here like I just
showed in the app might actually be very
convincing and so it's useful to think
about and often I would argue you know
we actually are all Beijians as
scientists or as clinicians because we
probably wouldn't run an an experiment
unless we had some prior belief that we
you know we thought there might be a
reasonable chance of it being workable
or true. Um but that just denovo without
any information with using effectively a
flat prior ignoring the prior
information and just evaluating the
evidence for the alter the null versus
the alternative. That's that's the
translation. That's pretty powerful
actually if you think about it. Like how
does that how does that make us all
feel? Should we do a checkin? No. Okay.
All right. We're moving on. Jokes are
not hitting this morning. Okay. All
right.
Um, so now we can flip that around and
take the the denominator over the
numerator, right? And the evidence for
the alternative versus the evidence for
the the null. And effectively, this is a
table also from that um sulky a
follow-up Selki paper. And they actually
said a base factor of 1 to three is
barely worth mentioning. So that 005
taken in and of itself is between one
and three. It's a a base factor of 2.7.
We're not even going to talk about it. I
mean, that's kind of sad actually. I I
don't know. Okay. So,
um all right. So, how do we turn this
base factor into something that can give
us those posterior probabilities that
we're interested in? Well, remember that
uh the example that the the sort of
cardinal um important rule that we
learned in uh from the beginning slides
that the probability the the posterior
probability the probability of the
hypothesis given the data can be written
in this way. And you can actually
rearrange the algebra and take that
likelihood the probability of the data
given the hypothesis times the
probability of the hypothesis is
basically a ratio of the B factor uh
times the prior odds. Show you this
right. So we can take the B factor 10
times the prior odds. Now this is in the
reverse way. the probability of the data
given the alternative over the
probability of the uh data given the
null and then times the prior
probability of the alternative over the
prior probability of the null. And you
can quickly translate this wherever you
are. You just in sort of the back of
your mind if you think that denovo the
alternative hypothesis is three times as
likely as the null and you observe this
base factor that perhaps corroborates or
goes against that feeling and you can
convert that actually into a posterior
odds which can be converted into a
posterior probability.
And so these are the important uh
takeaways from this, right? So p values
are answering very different questions
that I think that we're most thinking
about um and that we we maybe denovo
think that that they should be
answering. Um we a base factor allows us
to compare these competing hypothesis in
the likelihood space which is still in
the Bayian space. And even these
significant p values provide weaker
evidence than typically assumed. And
actually what's nice is um and it's one
of the slides I've commented out because
I didn't know if I'd have time, but if
you um so if you actually draw the log
10 p value versus the log 10 base
factor, the evidence the the translation
is it's actually upshifted effectively
meaning that uh the minimum b factor is
always actually less evidence uh against
the al well it's less evidence against
the altern less evidence against the
null than the p value would suggest. Um
and so right these base vectors have a a
natural interpretation and you can
conveniently convert uh when you have
the base vector when you have the prior
probability into posterior probability.
All right. So, multiple testing. So,
we're moving on. We're making good
progress. So, now we've developed these
p values and we have not just one or two
p values, but we have many p- values.
Many people in this building have many
p- values, right? That's kind of our
idea. Um, and so there are some sort of
cardinal feelings about how we deal with
all of these hypothesis tests because if
we're running a lot of hypothesis tests,
even in a frequentist sense, we realize
that we need to control the probability
of seeing the data uh given that the
null is true is very small. the
probability of you know the complement
of that taken to a large number actually
gives you a value that's that's not so
small um and so what do we do with this
information right uh and so this is
where I was going to draw some sort of
uh the way that we typically think about
this in a frequent setting and this is
actually how I sort of started out when
I was in undergrad um I was introduced
the idea of false discovery rates and I
said that's pretty cool it's important
to think about but how do you calculate
some of the important quantities there
so all right so this is our null
And this is our
alternative. Now you guys may have seen
this, but suppose that we observe a
statistic that's right here. Okay, this
is
our and we observe not just that
statistic, but we observe a whole list
of statistics. We have a whole list of
findings that we're calling significant.
That often happens in um you know
genomic discovery, right? So we have
this list that we're calling significant
and we want to know instead of the
probability of the data given that the
null is true what we said the p value
was we want to know the probability that
the null is true given that we're seeing
a statistic as or more extreme we want
to invert that and that's called a false
discovery rate which is typically
thought of as a as a frequent quantity
but I'm going to dispel that notion
today oh no oh no what did I do
okay oh my goodness okay all
All right. So this is called
FDR. All right. So we observe this
statistic and essentially we're say
we're looking at the ratio and we're
saying that this is the portion of the
statistics as or more extreme given that
the null is true because this was the
null distribution, right? And this is
the whole list of
discoveries. So the fraction of this
we'll call this a over this area b. So a
over well we could say that perhaps this
is this is b this is the portion that's
coming from the uh alternative
distribution. So a over a plus b equals
fdr. But the interesting thing about
this is we actually don't know how close
these distributions are and we don't
know uh the enrichment of our set of
tests in alternative distributions or
alternatively enriched in in null
distributions. So that's where we have
this nice result and if you essentially
plotted a histogram of p values that
were all generated from a null
distribution they would be completely
uniform. So you look at where that
distribution forms a uniform height
divided by one basically normalized when
it's density and so in this sense we see
the p the pi is 7. So the proportion of
null tests is 7. That means it forms it
forms it begins to form the null
distribution. Uh it 70% of the tests
effectively are are are forming that
null distribution. And so that value is
equivalent to our prior. So now if we're
turning this into a basian quantity, the
probability of the null hypothesis given
the data is proportional to the
probability of the data given the null
hypothesis times the probability of the
null hypothesis. And I can write this as
pi 0. And then this probability of the
data given the null hypothesis we know
is our likelihood, right? So we can
calculate
that. Okay. So the challenge though is
how do we calculate pi zero? And also
perhaps we're not interested in entire
list of tests because we're only
observing one test at a time. And so
that's where I'm going to introduce you
to this local false discovery rate that
was pioneered by well Ma Matthew
Stevens, my my my PhD adviser. um and
but is uh I mean it's been it probably
has been around been around before but
um it's it's very useful to think about
in this sense and inherently it can be
inherently a Beijing quantity. Okay, so
this is what I was just describing. So
the probability of the null hypothesis
given a particular Zstistic is the
probability of the Zstistic given that
the null is true times the probability
of the null is the probability that the
null hypothesis right which is just one
minus the alternative hypothesis there.
Okay. And so in this
parameterization we have the density
function which is the probability of the
zstistic or the data given that the null
is true and this is for null statistics
right is a normal function. So it's it's
a normal density zero sigma squar. Now
what if it's from the alternative
distribution? What if we meet a zstistic
from the alternative distribution? Well,
in that sense, we're actually going to
have this is where Yeah. So, okay. So,
we have an overall distribution that I'd
probably put this order in funny, but
basically, we have let me let me draw
this out a different way. I think
I Okay, we're going to have a bit of a
tree.
And so in our first TR
tree in our first tree before we meet
any data we just have the probability of
the Z statistic where where it lives
right and so that's going to be normal
zero sigma square this is called or
prior mean prior mean prior variance and
this is of the true effect. So these are
the true effects are centered around
some distribution where perhaps the
prior mean is zero but some of them are
true and so they're out here. These are
this is the true effect. Now we observe
a new one that's noisy. And that's going
to be centered around that true prior
effect plus some
noise. And then our posterior, which is
going to be the probability of the Z
given the Z hat, is now going to be have
its new posterior mean and this new
posterior variance.
And that's calculated by effectively
integrating over the prior mean and the
likelihood the observed data. And now
you get this marginal likelihood which
is the probability of seeing which yeah
so the marginal likelihood is now going
to have when you integrate this observed
Z over the prior mean it's going to have
this noisy mean and the prior variance.
Okay. So what did I show here? Right?
Yeah, this was the prior likelihood.
Okay. So and the overall distribution
then when we observe it's a mixture,
right? It's a mixture of these null
statistics and these alternative
statistics. Um and this was sort of the
the formula. So the the posterior um on
on the the distribution of statistics is
basically um uh or the well the the
prior is a mixture over these each of
the component distributions and this is
the um the conditional likelihood. Yeah.
So the point I wanted to make here was
sorry this too much for this. Oh my
gosh. Sorry about this. Okay. So the
point I wanted to make here though was
that figuring out this balance the
distribution the pi one or the pi zero
figuring out the balance that sort of
optimizes this the likelihood the
observed data is is tricky and it
requires uh these empirical bays
techniques that really um uh determine
what sort of optimizes you can in
empirical bays you're optimizing the
likelihood. So finding the balance of
pies that really optimizes seeing u
seeing the set of statistics you have.
So perhaps you have a lot of really
large effects that aren't noisy. So then
your pi 0 is very small, your pi 1 is is
quite big. Or perhaps you have a lot of
small noisy effects and then your pi 0
is going to be um very large and your pi
1 is going to be very small. And
similarly the balance of sigas tells you
exactly how large the effects are. And
so you can fix one and try to estimate
the others or you can try to fix them
and estimate them jointly in a in a
beijian sense. Um okay so right so this
is the population. So what we observe is
we observe these effect sizes. We of
course don't know which ones are null
and which ones are true. Right? So um
but uh the the the goal is to try to to
try to estimate that and let's see I
have this nice right. So after you've
done that um you can see that when you
apply this this this technique that's
effectively shrinking um effects with
noisy standard errors that are quite
small towards zero you get a a plot like
this. And how does it learn how does it
learn that nicely? So effectively it's a
mixture remember as I was describing
it's a mixture over these um these prior
variances. And so for each statistic
that you observe, you say, well, is it
more likely to observe it with a large
prior variance, which is a true effect
variance, or is it more likely to
observe it with a small prior variance
because it's so noisy. And so the larger
prior variance that you get that really
makes sense with the data that you're
observing tends to shrink the data less
and um sort of shrink the basically the
prior, which is a spike prior. It's fit
at zero um will matter will matter less
and the data data matters more. And so
then in that plot that we just
had you'll tend to see that that large
effects are are are boosted and small
effects are
shrunk. Um so you can see that yeah okay
so so what is mash? So mash is really an
extension of this but now instead of
looking at only the population within
within a univariate population. So in
one trait in in one trait we think about
uh the abundance of large and small
effects. So that's the proportion that's
the pi and then we think about the scale
of the effects. Now we have multiple
effects in multiple traits and we might
say that the effects in other traits
tend to boost the effects in one trait.
And so that u matrix is now actually
capturing the shape or the relationship
among traits but it's also got the
scaling parameter that's just
like this uh sorry right just like the
prior variance that we observe there. So
the take-home point is the prior
variance actually helps you helps you
boost the data that you're observing.
And if we have a large observed effect
with a small noisy uh with a small
noise, then we're actually going to to
to boost the posterior and recognize
that um uh recognize that a large prior
variance would sort of best best fit
that situation. And if we also observe
that there are large effects in other
conditions, we'll boost it even more. Um
right okay so so this is kind of a neat
so the way to wrap your head around
this. So as I said this sigma 1 and
sigma 2 are the prior variances. What
are the terms on the off diagonal? So
those are the covariance scale by some
some correlation and so the correlation
really controls so if we have two traits
I think I have this plot here somewhere.
Um right. Okay. Well, if we have if we
have two
traits, so trait
one, two,
um, and they're quite they're they're
correlated, but they're it's quite
noisy, right? So, we'll see a big cloud
of
points. But if one increases in the same
scale that the other increases, then
it'll be this straight
line. And so the question is, well, how
would you get something that's on the
off diagonal, right? So that you would
just change the relationship between the
prior variance for two and the prior
variance for one. So suppose that two is
always constituently higher than one to
get something like this. And if one is
always larger than two, you get
something like this. And the row
controls how cloudy those are around
each other. And that prior assumption if
it's if it's uh congruent with what
we're observing, right? Then we'll tend
to sort of boost that component of the
mixture model and the ultimate posterior
will be heavily informed by that
component of the mixture
model. Okay. So how would I get a one-1
line? So that's sort of an exercise to
go through yourself. But that
effectively is saying that the
correlation coefficient is one. They're
perfectly correlated. And this is not a
one-1 because I was trying to show a
situation in which the effect in two is
greater than one. So that prior variance
for two is greater than one. But if you
wanted a one- one line, it would just be
this whole matrix would be would be once
effectively. Okay. So bringing it home,
bringing it all together. Um so uh
different different different shrinkage
approaches that we have. So if we have
these observed effects, they're quite
noisy. In a univariat shrinkage
approach, we treat each group
separately. We don't consider how the
effect tends to behave in other
conditions. And if we have, you know,
large effects, they're tend to be
captured by components of the mixture
that have a large prior effect variance.
So we'll shrink the prior shrink the
shrink the shrinkage if you will and
recognize the data. And if we have a
small noisy effect, we'll tend to sort
of augment this prior which has a spike
at zero uh and exclude the data. And if
we have multivaried shrinkage the
relationship isn't one to one because we
might observe two small effects but in
one small effect case the effect in
other conditions was quite large and in
the other small effect case the effect
in other conditions was small. So in the
first example we tend to boost it
because we recognized it had friends and
the friends were all going to the party
and so it wanted to sort of increase as
well and in the first in the second case
you know we'd recognize it seemed to be
sort of noisy across the board so we'd
shut that down.
All right. So, observed effects are
noisy. Only considering information in
ones. Yes. And sharing is caring. So,
I'd like to I can't believe how quickly
we're going. Um,
so ask questions,
please. No question. Okay. All right.
Well, yes, please.
Yeah.
alternative hypothesis.
Um how do you do multiple alternative
hypothesis? You just compare them,
right? Yeah. So you would do I mean so
in the first step, good question. So in
the first step you would have multiple
base factors, right? Because you would
be weighing the evidence of the null
versus the alternative in multiple
situations and then you would develop a
posterior probability for each one. But
presumably um so you could think about
having this is a cool situation. So you
could have a matrix basically that
quantified the prior effect the prior uh
the prior variance how strongly you
believed or didn't believe each one of
those prior hypotheses. So that would be
incorporated in your prior and then your
likelihood instead of being a univariate
likelihood. So a univariat base factor
because a base factor is really this
ratio of normal densities right so in a
one one situation one hypothesis testing
situation you have the probability of
the data suppose it's normal under the
null hypothesis over the probability of
the data under alternative one. Now if
you have that in multiple conditions you
have a vector which has a multivariant
normal distribution. Presumably there's
some correlation or coariance between
the two. Perhaps there isn't. I don't
know. Um so if you had that then you
could actually use a mash type situation
for that question because now you have
your observed likelihood as in across
multiple features as well as the
coariance matrix for that. Yeah. Yeah.
That's a really good question Roman.
Yep. Wait, can I so the people online
could agree.
This is great Sarah. uh question for you
around um c does do Beijian statistics
ever hold back novel discoveries in that
if we are too attached to a prior it's
difficult to violate our expectations
for instance like what I'm thinking
about is like really unexpected
discoveries like you know recently
there's been implications that MS are
maybe due to you know vicella zostustra
virus and like we had no idea about that
so how do you how do you deal with
something like Yeah. So, great question.
Okay. So, carefully is the first is the
first answer, right? So, um Okay. So,
there's I have this plot actually I I
quite like because Baze actually has
this built-in safety valve. A built-in
sort of uh uh what you call steering
wheel bag. What am I thinking of? Yeah.
Airbag. That's the word I'm looking for.
I ride a bike, not a car, as you can
see. Um yeah, carefully also. But, okay.
So in this situation, I'm giving an I'm
cutting to the chase a little bit, but
there's um there's these conjugate
priors, which are these convenient
parameterizations, right? But this is a
neat a neat example. So okay, so there's
three different prior here. So I have
this flat prior, which is completely
indifferent. I have no idea. I'm going
in and I'm saying I have no idea if it's
big or small. I have an informative
prior, which is helpful because it's
bringing me towards a truth. And I have
not only an uninformative prior, but
it's actually incorrect. So
uninformative would be totally flat.
incorrect would be wrong, right? We all
know the meaning of that. And what's
what's the
um Okay. And what the neat thing about
this is you're straying from the truth,
but you're not straying that far from
the truth because we are combining
evidence from I mean, we are combining
the likelihood. Um but I mean you you
you are moving it a little bit away from
the truth. That's for sure. But I think
my answer to that would
be in the long run. So I'm being a
frequentist now I guess isn't in the
long run we're running um isn't
imparting imparting no truth all of the
time so having a flat like a flat a flat
prior effectively and not incorporating
anything that motivated our very
expensive
experiment isn't that more of a danger
than some of the time moving yourself
towards the truth and some of the time
moving yourselves away that's like a
philosophical question we need like a
different discussion for that but so
there is there there There is a danger
certainly of uh if you have too punitive
of a prior certainly sobering your
expectations too much and there's also a
danger in the other way of if you have
uh too informative of a prior that moves
you towards an optimistic direction or
the wrong direction that's also that's
also a concern I think in practice um
because people there's like you know a
concern there's an inherent sort of
animosity towards overzealous prior I
think in general we we tend to use flat
flat prior at least in the literature
I've seen certainly in medicine. Um, but
the other and maybe this is kind of from
the clinical trial standpoint is as I
showed in the beginning the beauty of
basian statistics is that even with a
flat prior you get the same shape
distribution as the frequentist analysis
the confidence intervals and the
credible intervals have the same numeric
values but the conclusions that you make
the philosophical conclusion that you
make which is I have a 95% certainty
about the value of the parameter is very
different than this sort of long- winded
handwavy in the long run frequency the
constructed interval will contain the
true parameter of interest 95% % of the
time like what does that mean? How is
that helping me make decisions in the
clinic for 15 minutes? You know, I can't
even say that sentence in well I can't
because I talk too fast but often people
can't you know so um yeah so that's my
soap
box. Okay. All right. We're moving on.
So what do I want to talk about? So I
want to talk about condu prior. I think
that there's a lot of I thought about
I've been thinking about this talk a lot
and you know science is tough right now.
It's it's kind of makes us may ask a lot
of questions but I think at its basis
science math these things are beautiful
and we got into this because they are
beautiful and uh so I think it's
important to recognize that sometimes
kic and prior are beautiful and they're
beautiful because they save you a lot of
work frankly um so all the calculus that
I was showing here basically this
integrating you can imagine that you
know that nice integral that we remember
which is integrating the likelihood over
all the possible values of the prior can
be saved
because we have these convenient
parameterizations. So a very very simple
that we use in genetics a lot is the
beta distribution. So it's a probability
over probabilities. Basically it's a
distribution over we could say alo
frequencies for instance. So we have
some prior belief of what that is and
the relationship here is these are
called hyperparameters or pri parameters
of the prior. So alpha and beta roughly
capture something about you'll learn in
statistics that everything sort of has a
shape and a scale roughly basically. So
the relationship of a over a plus b
gives you the mean basically. And a plus
b the sum tells you how concentrated
that is. It's like the precision or the
inverse variance. So if you have a
really high a plus b, it's going to be
really confident about your mean. And if
you have sort of a a very flat one, it's
like in the in the mash example, you're
really uncertain about that spike. Okay.
All right. So then we observe so many
successes and so many failures. Perhaps
that's a counts. Perhaps it's coin
tosses, etc. And what's beautiful is
instead of having to do that complicated
calculus, we just add the successes to
alpha and we add the failures to beta or
however you want to
perate. Okay. And so this is what I was
uh this is what I was I was trying to
show um earlier is basically under the
flat the informative or the
uninformative wrong prior you actually
approximate a posterior that's kind of
robust to these poor assumptions because
the more data that you observe the less
the prior matters. And that's actually
really evident. I love the beta. I love
the beta distribution for this example
because every time you can see actually
that you update this posterior
distribution, yesterday's posterior
become or yeah, yesterday's posterior
becomes today's prior. You update your
distribution and that alpha which has or
the beta distribution of 28 which is
alpha 2 and beta 08 matters less and
less after we observe the third group.
We've kind of totally moved around. So
that sort of answers your question. I
think that we have this robust safety
valve or airbag that helps us respond to
new data that we
observe. Okay. Anyway, so that's that's
a nice result. Um, okay. And so this is
showing sort of after one observation.
So our prior distribution is all the way
over in the red and after 10
observations, we've essentially moved
away quite a bit. So there's that nice
convenient. All right. So then there's
another example. If we have multiple
alals and a dish is important. I'm only
it's kind of a natural extension. The
beta is like a simple case of dishes. Um
but I'm I'm throwing that out there
because if we get to the mixture models
uh we can discuss that there. Um but
effectively so now I have a vector
instead of uh instead of just having one
probability I have a vector of
probabilities and they have this prior
distribution called a dishlay. I'll show
you the nice plot here. Okay. So
basically uh suppose that I have it
lives in this space right? So um so
suppose there's uh you know the
probability of three groups and they
live somewhere in the space where they
sort of all add to one and what's nice
is as I was describing with the beta if
the value is large the probability mass
is concentrated more in the center even
if it's one one or even if it's even if
they're equivalent even if this triangle
looks more like this if if it's a
triangle it's concentrated in the center
and if we're really uncertain it's quite
a big cloud of points. All right so
let's go back. So now we have this prior
of 222 which means it's it's basically
the triangle. Everything is evenly
distributed but it's a little bit more
concentrated than a 111. And we observe
these 10 A's, these five Bs and these
three C's. So we simply our our our
likelihood is a multinnomial likelihood.
The probability of observing 10 given a
particular value of the the prior the um
parameters and then we just add those
values the likelihood values effectively
the new counts to the prior
distribution and we get this beautiful
plot which is quite simple. there was no
calculus required, no pain, just get new
clouds. Um so um anyway, so that's
that's that's the dish there. Okay. And
then one final the conjugate normal and
this is important because that is
actually we take a lot of advantage of
that in ash and mash. And so we have
this prior distribution. So the prior
true effect mu or beta, right? If you
look at the ash or mash literature, it's
centered around some prior mean and some
prior variance. And I like to think
about this because this is a true effect
variance. This is where the true mu or
the true beta live. There's some
distribution of zero truly zero and some
distribution that's not truly zero.
Right? It lives on that line. Now we
observe a new statistic, a new beta hat.
We will it's noisy and it's centered
around that previous truth plus some
some variance, some noise. And you could
write it out basically as a linear
combination. You could
say that Z hat is equal to Z plus Well,
I shouldn't use that. Okay, let's do it
this way. Sorry, guys. All right. So we
could say that B hat is equal to B plus
Z where Z is normal 01. And this is
considered sort of an error. So in a Z
in a in the exchangeables. Oh my
goodness. What did I do here? Okay. Keep
doing that, don't I? Yeah. All right.
Okay. So we're we we assume it's new. We
assume that the noise is known. So now
the question is what do we get the
posterior? And so we're going to do some
fancy math, some fancy rearrangements of
terms. It's not that complicated, but
there's there's there's symmetry here.
So, if you notice, this is the
likelihood one on I guess on the right,
right? Is x minus mu. You know, the
normal the normal density. And then on
the left, it's the expression for the
prior, which is the prior minus the
observed prior that we're evaluating at
a particular time minus its prior mean.
So, when you rearrange those terms, you
actually
get this beautiful expression for the
posterior, which looks just like the
first one, right? It's a posterior mean.
So, it's got it's a it's a normal
distribution. So it's got instead of
being centered around the prior mean now
that it's seen the data it's centered
around the posterior mean and the
posterior variance. And a neat thing
about this is so this is going to be the
posterior mean and this is going to be
the posterior precision if you
will. So you can actually think of that
this is again phase is beautiful. We can
think of the posterior mean as a
weighted average basically of the prior
mean how how much we believe the prior
distribution and the likelihood. And how
do we get those weights? Well, it's
effectively proportional to the data
precision and the total precision,
right? So, if we actually have strong
confidence in the data and we're very
flat prior like we were talking about in
the ash example where we had a very flat
prior because we had these large sigas,
right? And the data is strong, then we
would actually move more towards the
data. And if we had a very large data
variance, it was very noisy or a very
imprecise data, precision and variance
are inversely proportional, then we
would actually move more towards the
prior. And so smaller values of the
prior variance would support it. And
that's pretty cool. So our posterior
mean is a direct combination of how
strongly we believe the data likelihood
and how strongly we have a prior belief.
And so the more the more evidence we
have from our from our observed data and
perhaps the flatter the prior uh we will
get closer our posterior mean will look
more like our data. And see do I have
any plots there?
Yeah, I guess I don't have any plots,
but that effectively would give you uh a
distribution like like I showed for the
beta plot where you know you'd have your
prior mean centered
around
zero. You observe your data looks
something like this with a very it's
very narrow so it's very precise and
it's large and then your posterior mean
would probably be somewhere around
here. Okay, great. Okay. And then so
this is just showing and this is the we
take advantage of this in these summary
statistics. So instead of having to deal
with uh all of the observed values we
actually in a G-W was we get a summary
statistic right that's often what we
work with we get a summary statistic. So
you have this beta hat in its standard
air and the convenient it turns out you
can conveniently use the the conjugate
formulations for that same
um okay great yeah so see I just want to
make sure there wasn't anything I wanted
to say here
that
see okay I don't think so
yeah four minutes I have four minutes
okay well that's a good yeah so Um right
so uh when we don't have okay this
empirical base so one of the questions
is you know um how do we uh estimate
these right how do we estimate the sigma
and the pi for instance um from from
from the data um and so actually we can
use uh techniques so in the next section
I have this thing called uh the em
algorithm so you sort of fix one and
then estimate some of the other priors
um the pi hat for instance or you can um
sort choose sigma values the scales for
the um that we were using in the variety
of the the grid for ash or mash um from
the data. So a set of a set of sigas
that we think are very small or very
large it would sort of fit it
appropriately or sometimes these
hyperparameters like I was talking about
in the beta distribution we might have
some belief from the data some empirical
data that suggests that we should use
this and actually saves us a lot of time
because when we can't use a conjugate
parameterization and we have to do MCMC
sampling um that you know takes a lot
more time so if we have if we have a a
empirical estimate of what we think the
alpha and beta are from the overall data
we can plug those in and and make our
life a lot easier. that's often done for
the hyperparameters. Um, okay. So,
right. So, the next part of the talk was
on mixture models and I I have some
really nice didactics and things um
inside. So, so I don't want to like rush
through it. Um, so either I can come
back or you guys can go through it on
the slides online or email me. I would
like to I'm happy to set up a time and
all these things. I like I'm really
passionate about this stuff. So, thank
you guys so much for listening for your
great questions. Thanks everybody.
Remember, we have two weeks off. And uh
yeah, have a good day.