Good morning everyone and welcome to MIT
data center day one here. I'm Jim Flynn.
I'm a program director here at MIT
corporate relations
and I want to say on behalf of MIT that
we're delighted to have you all here.
First, I want to do a quick
acknowledgement to our two audiences. We
have a a pretty good crowd here in
Cambridge this morning, but we have an
even larger audience online joining us
from all over the world, making this a
truly global event. And I want to thank
everyone again for joining us. This
event is organized and run by the MIT
Industrial Lazison Program or ILP. And
if you're with us today, you are
probably either already an ILP member or
you're at least ILP curious. So, I hope
you don't mind if I take a a minute or
two to just discuss the program for
those of us that may not be as familiar
with it.
The ILP
has been m the front door to MIT for
industry for over 75 years. We've been
connecting companies across the
institute to faculty, labs, centers,
consortia, students and startups. Those
connections have been finding real world
solutions to your challenges.
So why do companies join the ILP? It's
largely because the ILP is the only
program at MIT that cuts across the
entire institute and the startup
ecosystem surrounding it. Every employee
of an ILP member company has
complimentary access to this event and
dozens events of events that we run each
year.
These events
are not the only thing that the ILP
provides.
At its core, the most important part of
the ILP are the connections that we make
to MIT.
Those connections spark collaborations
and the collaborations drive progress.
MIT data center day stands as an example
of the kind of the kind of unique value
that the ILP brings to the table.
No other program at MIT is designed to
bring together the diverse expertise
that we have assembled here today.
We originally planned for this to be
just a half a day forum, but we quickly
realized that if you're going to tackle
the key issues around data centers that
you not only have to talk about things
like AIdriven demand, but you also have
to consider things like data center
design, cooling systems, power grids,
orchestration, security, and much more.
And this being MIT, it's not surprising
that we'll also cover areas like quantum
computing and other emerging tech
technologies that could make data
centers of the future look very much
different than they are today.
So today you'll hear from computer
scientists, civil and mechanical
engineers, cyber security experts,
material scientists, and more. We'll
talk about software, hardware, cooling
systems, and even sustainable cement.
MIT's motto, men's at Manus, is deeply
ingrained in our culture here. It
signifies that we are not only focused
on advancing knowledge, but also its
application.
Nowhere is this more evident than in the
vast and I would say almost unique
startup ecosystem around MIT. That's why
we created a program called the MIT
Startup Exchange. It's so ILP members
could go beyond just learning about
things that could matter in a few years,
but to work today with over 800 MIT
connected startups that are taking MIT
inventions and innovations and creating
real products and services that you can
use now. So this form reflects what
makes MIT unique. Where else would you
find a physicist, an architect, and a
computer scientist all debating the same
building and all of them being right? At
MIT, it's not a joke. It's just a normal
Tuesday.
So to summarize our aims here today, we
want to leave you want you to leave here
with three important things. First,
insights from the researchers and the
entrepreneurs working at the forefront
of compute and infrastructure ideas.
These ideas that spark new approaches to
challenges that you're facing today such
as
balancing AI demand with energy
resilience and sustainability.
And third, connections. Because we know
that innovation and breakthroughs happen
when industry, academia, and
entrepreneurs all work together across
organizational boundaries and across
disciplines.
So, buckle up. We'll be covering
everything from atoms to algorithms to
air conditioning. And in true MIT style,
we'll wrap up with pizza and beer
networking and of course a lot more
brainstorming.