So today uh we we set aside that part
and look at what is uh often the hardest
thing to actually make it real uh to put
in the around design, build, learn,
research. So we get to work in a sense.
Um and just like yesterday, uh there are
many people, experts, ideas that we
couldn't ram into this two-day session
in 10-minute segments. And so we are so
aware of that. There is still a
whiteboard
um with at the break you can add the
names of people and experts and ideas
that you really think need to be in
here. We may have attempted to get them
here. Um but we really want to hear that
from you as well as feedback. Um we're
trying to capture and share kind of a
pulse of information, the state of
knowledge. As you saw yesterday, there's
all kinds of views, all kinds of
perspectives, all kinds of voices and
language. and we just welcome them all.
We're not saying that we shouldn't have
some healthy debates. Um, so I really
hope it goes as well today. And I want
to pass it over to uh Juliet who will be
moderating our very first session.
[Applause]
Hello everyone. Um we're excited to
start our day off with some talks about
design principles for geothermal energy
networks. We have three great speakers.
Um two of them in person and then one
online. So we'll start our day with
Connor Dwe uh who is a licensed engineer
at Geoys and who teaches an IGBA um
ground source heat pump course. Um,
Connor,
>> okay, good morning everyone. Um,
so I I spoke with Zena before this this
meeting. I I just wanted to, you know,
thank all of HEAT for putting on the
session. and I left yesterday quite
optimistic on the geothermal district
space in the United States which is you
know it's it's very um relieving I'll
say with the with the times. So thank
you all for putting this on. So my my
background is in engineering uh I have a
doctor in what's called uh earth energy
resource engineering. I'm a licensed
engineer in the state of New York and
also uh the province of Ontario and
Canada. Um I also help teach the
certified geo exchange designer course
which is run by international ground
source heat seat pump association and
this specific slide deck today just goes
through that introductory level uh CGD
type type course. So we thought we'd
start with the fundamentals of heat
transfer uh to get into you know the
ground source heat pumps and and how
they work. So we have conduction,
convection and radiation. By definition,
conduction is when heat is directly
transmitted through a substance when
there is a difference in temperature. So
if you're holding a metal rod and that
metal rod heats up on one end, you feel
that heat through your hand through
conduction of that metal rod. We have
convection, which is the rising motion
of warmer areas of a liquid or gas and
the sinking motion of cooler areas of
liquid or gas. So if you're holding your
hand over a fire, you know that heat.
You're not physically touching anything,
but you feel that heat and that's that's
convection.
Lastly, we have radiation. The process
where heat energy is transferred from
one object to another through the
emission of electromagnetic waves. I
promise the rest of the rest the rest of
this presentation won't be this dry. Um
just getting through the fundamentals,
but when you're suntanning, you know,
you feel that heat, that's radiation.
Okay, so geothermal. What is geothermal?
While geo means relating to the earth
and thermal means relating to heat. So
the earth temperature is relatively
constant throughout the year, right?
It's around 50 here. I think it's 55
degrees Fahrenheit. Whereas in the
winter time it's 10° outside and then in
the summertime around 90° outside, but
the ground stays that same 50 55° F. And
to harness that energy, you can install
a ground heat exchanger, which is
plastic pipe that's buried in the ground
and it transfers heat to a volume of
earth around that around that pipe um
through various ways. You know, shallow
ground heat exchangers take advantage of
radiation, mainly conduction. Um but
there's also conve convective heat
transfer with that groundwater. You have
heat exchange fluid that's pumped
through the pipe. I'm getting used to
this laser here. heat exchange fluid
that's pumped through this pipe and then
connected to that heat pump. And the
reason why these systems are more
efficient is because of this sign graph
here. So the source temperatures going
to that heat pump from the ground heat
exchanger range between around 40 to 90
degrees Fahrenheit, sometimes as low as
30. But this specific graph is collected
from four years worth of data in a very
cold climate in in Winnipeg, Manitoba.
So during this same time period, the
outdoor air temperature ranged from -20
to + 100° F. So you can imagine that
getting your source temperatures from
the that more extreme uh you know air
compared to your ground heat exchanger
temperatures makes the heat pump work
harder. It has to work harder to deliver
that same amount of heat. Um so heat
pumps like to receive more moderate
temperatures so they don't need to work
as hard. And how a heat pump works is
just like a fridge, right? It's it's the
vapor compression cycle is what it's
called. It's no different than a fridge
other than a reversing valve. But the
the process is you have an evaporator
that transfers heat with your external
environment, right? So your air, your
ground or your water. You have a
compressor which compresses the
refrigerant and increasing the pressure
and temperature. Chemistry 101. If you
increase pressure, you increase the
temperature. You have your condenser
which condenses the refrigerant vapor
into liquid and that phase change
transfers large amount of heat and then
your expansion valve to rinse and repeat
reduce the pressure and temperature to
prepare for the next cycle. So our our
ground source heat pump in heating again
we have this reversing valve which
differentiates our fridge from our our
heat pump. So we can also do heating be
strange if a fridge did heating. Um but
we extract heat from our ground loop
where we have three units of heat coming
from the ground. We have our compressor
which uses electricity to compress and
heat the refrigerant. That electrically
powered equipment generates heat as
well. Right? That's your power input.
That that compressor. There's also the
circulation pump and fans. And then you
give those four units of heat to the
building. Right? So that hot refrigerant
is pushed through the condenser and then
rejects that heat to the air in the
building. And this is how you get your
coefficient of performance. So you may
have heard the word coop or or
coefficient of performance. And this is
how it works. You you transfer those
four units of of energy which is
combined thermal and electrical energy
to the space by only using one by only
paying for one unit of electrical energy
to power that compressor circulation
pump and fans.
In cooling mode, we have our heat that's
extracted from the air in the building
vaporizing the refrigerant. So, those
three units of heat from the building,
we have our compressor again that
compresses the heat uh compresses and
heats the refrigerant. Our reversing
valve is on, right? So, we flip that
flow of refrigerant. So, it's going in
reverse now. And then that hot
refrigerant is pushed through the
condenser and rejects heat to that
ground heat exchanger. We need to get
rid of that electrical energy. an
electrical heat and the heat from the
building and we put that in the ground
loop. So what's the difference between
earth energy resource engineering or or
geothermal engineering and conventional
HVAC systems? Well, the the main
difference is that for ground source
heat pump systems, you should be
considering the total demand, right? the
total demand of a building, not just a
peak of the coldest day of the year or
the warmest day of the year, but your
total heating and cooling on an annual
basis to determine your total supply
because you're designing your source,
right? And so in a conventional system,
you have a pipeline that's large enough
to meet the peak heating day, the
coldest day of the year, right? You have
your natural gas pipeline that's feeding
that equipment. You have your water
utility line that's feeding your cooling
tower to dissipate heat on the warmest
day of the year. And as long as you pay
your energy bill, you should be okay.
But for a ground source heat pumps
scenario, we are also considered with
our our total loads, right? Again,
because we're designing our source. So
this example illustrates this. So we
have a church, a retail store, and an
apartment building. They may have the
exact same peak and and peak heating and
cooling loads, 40 tons of cooling and
385 MBH of heating, but due to the
difference in occupancy of those three
different buildings, the total heating
and cooling loads are going to change
quite dramatically, right? You think
about that church probably highly
occupied once or twice a week, right?
You have a lot of people in the room
like this space, you have a lot of
lights on. those internal heat gains
help uh heat the space and that's only
available maybe once or twice a week. So
your heating load over an annual um set
of of data is probably going to be
higher than than your cooling load.
Whereas your retail store, you know, you
could think of maybe an IKEA, you have a
lot of internal heat gains, a lot of
people, a lot of lights, a lot of um
internal heat gains that you need to get
rid of. So you put those in the ground,
right? you need to reject that heat and
the apartment building probably
relatively balanced between heating and
cooling. So the heating and cooling load
ratio can change even if the peak
heating and cooling loads are the exact
same. And how this affects the ground
loop and why it's important is because
and this is especially true for a
vertical ground heat exchanger scenario
with a lot of conduction, right? you
have a fixed volume of earth that you're
exchanging heat with and so it it's more
similar to a battery in in that case
compared to a conventional system there
there are nuances right and there are
you know each project is unique um but
even in openloop systems for example
where you're tapping into an aquifer and
pulling heat and rejecting heat to an
aquifer we've seen we've been measuring
a system in Winnipeg over the past uh 5
years or so and they've increased the
temperature of that aquifer by 5 to 8° F
um just because they're rejecting so
much heat into that aquifer. So what can
happen is this curve here, this
temperature drift where you may fall
outside of those efficient operating
parameters. When we talked about that
ground source heat pump, it likes to be
fed 30 to 90° Fahrenheit water, right?
But what can happen is you can fall
outside of those efficient operating
ranges if you're not considering your
total loads. if you're only looking at
your peak loads. So, it's important to
not only design again off of your your
peak loads, which are certainly
important, but your total loads are are
also important to determine your your
total demand to design your supply.
So, when you have a customer or anyone
frankly who's interested in a geothermal
system, where do you start? If they say,
"Hey, you know, Connor, I want I've
heard of this geothermal technology.
I've heard is pretty cool. Um, what do I
do? Well, you'd probably want to start
with the building, right? Again,
determine your total demand to determine
your supply. And then you can start
looking at your mechanical system, your
geothermal mechanical system, and your
site and geology. The site and geology
is going to dictate what type of ground
heat exchanger you go with. There's many
different ways to exchange heat with
your external environment. Again, all
you're doing is obtaining moderate
temperatures so that your heat pump
doesn't need to work as hard. So that
could come from the air. You know, in
Seattle, it's pretty moderate there. So
air source works fine. Um, but in
Winnipeg, in a cold climate like that,
not so much. So you could have a
vertical ground heat exchanger,
horizontal surface water, aquafer. I'm
staying at Susan Murkott's house right
now, and she's a professor here at MIT,
and she is a standing column, and that
was pretty interesting to see. So there
there's many different ways to give your
heat pump source temperatures that are
moderate. Um, but at the end of the day,
what matters? Well, what matters is
we're trying to save on energy, right?
That's why we install these systems. But
if it's going to cost you an arm and a
leg to do that, it's probably not going
to make a whole lot of sense. So, to
balance the energy cost with the
construction cost is the most important
thing to make sure that it's practical,
right? Because if if it's too expensive,
nobody's going to buy it um at the end
of the day. Um, and there are
intangibles. You know, a lot of people
value carbon in different ways. In
Canada, we have a carbon tax. Um, so
that's that's quantified. Um, but the
main thing to consider when you're when
you're looking at a geothermal system,
in my opinion, is to balance these two
things, construction cost, and then the
energy savings that you're getting from
that investment because you're buying an
asset, which is that that ground heat
exchanger.
So, before I pass it to my colleague
Nick, I thought I'd throw in a little
segue slide here. I believe one person
had a similar slide yesterday where it
looks at the temperature in the
distribution piping of district systems
and over time we used to use really high
temperature right I mean we still do
today pressurized steam but that leads
to low efficiency and so over time we've
been able to reduce our temperature in
our distribution piping which has led to
an increase in efficiency so now we're
dealing with ambient temperatures which
has increased our efficiency in these
district energy systems quite
dramatically. So, thank you folks for
listening and I'll now pass it to Nick.