Now, let me be clear for a second. I
want to distinguish comparative
advantage from just the term advantage
or what we call absolute advantage. I
want to distinguish those. The best way
to distinguish those is of course think
about LeBron James mowing his lawn.
Okay, let's think about LeBron James
mowing his lawn. Now, LeBron James does
two things. Play basketball and mow his
lawn. Okay, and let's assert LeBron
James better than anyone in the world at
both playing basketball and mowing his
lawn. LeBron James awesome. I mean, the
guy's built, right? He just crank on
that lawn. Okay, so let's assert LeBron
James is the best person at both mowing
his lawn and playing basketball. He has
an absolute advantage in both
activities,
but he has a comparative advantage in
playing basketball. In other words, he's
way better. Let's take LeBron James
versus me. Now, there's two goods
playing basketball, mowing lawns in two
countries, LeBron James and Gruber.
Okay, LeBron James has a massive
comparative advantage in playing
basketball. I suck at basketball. Okay,
he's a un a billion to one comparative
advantage in playing basketball. Mowing
lawns, he's maybe five to one. He's
certainly better than me at mowing a
lawn, but is he more than five times?
Could he do it five times faster than
me? Probably not.
So, LeBron James is an absolute
advantage over me in basketball and lawn
mowing. But his comparative advantage is
basketball. LeBron James should, and
this will be the hint of where we're
going, LeBron James should specialize in
basketball. Let me mow the lawn.
Now, in fact, I shouldn't mow the lawn
either
because let's take me versus a a uh
landscape contractor and let's do
economics and lawnmowing.
I am certainly better than the land the
average landscape contractor at
economics.
I'm probably worse at lawnmowing. So, I
should then hire the landscape
contractor. It's all about comparative
advantage.