All right, good
morning, everyone.
My name is Robin
Wolfe Scheffler.
I'm from the MIT program
on Science, Technology,
and Society.
And it's my pleasure
to introduce this panel
on revolutions.
As you've seen this
morning, people commonly
talk about the life
sciences in the modern era
as one of revolutions--
the revolution of DNA,
the revolution of informatics,
the revolution of gene editing.
As a historian of
the life sciences,
however, I'm not
quite sure if this
is the metaphor we want for
talking about the work we
do here at MIT.
A revolution, if
you'll remember,
implies a violent turning
over of the world.
Indeed, philosophers of science
who have looked at revolutions
have gone so far as to suggest
that the worlds of science
before and after
a revolution are
incommensurable with each other.
There can't be any dialogue,
only misunderstanding.
Speaking in revolutionary
terms, therefore,
risks obscuring the rich history
of work at a place like MIT
and dismissing its importance
to the present day.
And I think this gives us
a shallow understanding
of the types of
innovation and cooperation
that make our Institute unique.
A better metaphor than
revolutions, if all be forgiven,
is that of waves.
If you think about a stream
of drops landing on a pond,
the force of each
wave might dissipate.
The discovery of DNA
becomes ubiquitous as a tool
for research over time.
However, it's still there.
It still shapes every
subsequent type of work.
New drops on the
pond add and interact
with others that came
before it, creating
new and unexpected patterns.
And I think this
sounds much more
like the work that's
happened at MIT,
as we've heard from
Professor Sharp
and we will hear from the
speakers in this panel.
Ideas and institutions
build upon each other,
rather than violently replacing
or superseding one another.
New people and new ideas
find new uses for old tools,
and they combine them
with their new knowledge.
The story is not
one of displacement
but of constructive interference
and intermingling of science
and engineering to produce
unexpected and new ways
of knowing life that
could only happen here.
MIT is so special precisely
because our pond, if you will,
has seen so many
drops land upon it.
So, without further
ado, it's my pleasure
to introduce three
speakers who have both
made their share of
waves at MIT and have
seen many wash upon its shores.
First, Tyler Jacks, who
is the David H. Koch
professor of biology,
a Daniel K. Ludwig
scholar, the co-director of
the Ludwig Center at MIT.
And he's going to speak to
the long history of assembling
genetics, informatics, and
technology to study cancer.
Second, Douglas
Lauffenburger, who's
the Ford Professor
of Engineering
and a founding professor
of the modern Department
of Biological Engineering.
He's going to speak to the
entry of engineering approaches
into the study of life as a
novel way of studying and doing
science.
And finally, Ruth
Lehmann is the director
of the Whitehead Institute
and a professor of biology.
She is going to highlight the
long work of the Institute
in combining
approaches, old and new,
to understand the complicated
and rewarding question of life's
complexity itself.
So, without further
ado, I'd like
to bring Tyler
Jacks to the stage.
[APPLAUSE]
Well, thanks, Robin.
And welcome, everybody.
Thanks for joining us.
I'm personally extremely
excited that we're here today,
celebrating the
launch of MIT HEALS.
As you heard, I was
involved with Kris Prather
in leading a faculty
committee that
led to a series
of recommendations
that arguably brought
us to this point.
And I'm just so excited about
what this collaborative will
do for our community, for our
region, and really for the world
as it relates to
advances in life science
and, importantly, in health.
I've been asked to talk a little
bit about cancer research at MIT
and tell the MIT cancer
research story, which
I'm very happy to do.
It's a long story.
It goes back, as you heard
from Phil Sharp, 50 years now.
In fact, we're celebrating
the 50th anniversary of cancer
research on the MIT
campus this year.
It began modestly in this
converted candy factory
on Ames Street,
where MIT decided
to invest in molecular biology
and recombinant DNA technology
to understand the
mysteries of cancer.
And that effort, as
you heard from Phil,
was massively successful and
really laid the foundations
for modern-day
molecular oncology.
Over the years, many,
many MIT faculty
got interested in
cancer research.
It really touches every
corner of our University.
And in response to that, we've
created the Koch Institute,
which embodies this
spirit of collaboration,
as Phil called it,
convergence, bringing together
multiple disciplines to
address and hopefully overcome
the challenges of cancer.
The Koch Institute
is a physical entity.
But it also connects many
aspects of the MIT community
around these most
important problems.
And I'll touch on
some of the activities
that the Koch Institute faculty
are working on today and project
on into the future.
But I want to begin looking
backwards again to the Cancer
Center.
This is a picture similar
to one that Phil showed you
of a group of investigators who
were recruited to the Cancer
Center, including Bob
Weinberg, Nancy Hopkins, who
was showed in the previous
image, David Baltimore, Salvador
Luria, and Phil Sharp
himself, thinking about,
how do cancer cells
arise from normal cells?
What are the changes
at the molecular level
that drive that process?
And Bob Weinberg,
who's circled here,
was interested in the question
of whether normal genes are
altered through mutation in
the development of cancer cells
from normal cells.
And he set about to find
the first cancer gene.
And after some years of
effort, he and his lab group
published three really
landmark papers in 1982
describing the first
human cancer gene.
It was called HRAS, which is
mutated in bladder cancer.
That was where it was found.
But it and its
cousins are now known
to be mutated in many different
very important human cancers,
including lung cancer and
colon cancer and pancreas
cancer, and more.
It really is an important
driver of the cancer process.
It becomes an oncogene
through a very subtle change
in the DNA, a single
nucleotide change, which leads
to a single amino acid change.
And that converts the
protein to an oncogenic form.
And the hope of
that research was
that, if we could understand
cancer at this level,
we could actually address it
molecularly and maybe find
new drugs that
target this altered
protein and similar
altered proteins
and bring about more effective
treatments for the disease.
That has happened.
And I'll touch on that briefly.
It happened here too,
but it took a long time.
RAS turned out to be a
very difficult problem.
And it actually took
nearly 40 years,
investigators from
academia and then industry,
to target altered RAS.
But in 2001, first Amgen and
then Mirati, now owned by BMS,
successfully developed
KRAS-targeting drugs,
which have been approved
by the FDA in lung cancer
and more recently
in colon cancer.
And this represents
a major shift
in our ability to control
those cancers that I
mentioned that have
KRAS and other RAS gene
mutations as drivers.
So that was then, a
single cancer gene, 1982.
This is now, where, with the
advent of high-throughput
DNA-sequencing technologies, the
sequencing of the human genome,
as you heard from Phil--
major contributions by the Broad
Institute and others at MIT--
we now have collectively
sequenced probably close
to a million cancer
genomes by now
and discovered not just one
human cancer gene but probably
500 cancer genes,
genes that are altered
by mutation in human cancers.
And there's more than a hundred
molecularly targeted drugs
like these that I'm
showing you here
that have been
approved by the FDA
for the treatment of cancers
with those alterations.
So the promise from 1982
has actually borne true
in spectacular fashion.
These genes are
mutated sometimes
rarely in a given
cancer but sometimes
commonly across many cancers.
This is an analysis
done by investigators
in a large international
collaboration,
including the Broad
Institute investigators,
looking at 26 commonly mutated
cancer genes across here,
26 different cancer types.
And again, this allows
for molecular diagnostics
to identify particular cancers
with particular alterations that
allows them to be treated with
targeted, more precise cancer
medicines that are having
significant benefit.
Now, at MIT, we're
approaching the complexity
of cancer, this myriad of
mutations in cancer genes,
in lots of different ways.
We have expertise in
my lab and elsewhere
at the Institute in modeling the
molecular alterations in cancer
in genetically
engineered mouse models.
And we can do this using
a variety of techniques
to very accurately model what
happens in human cancer cells
but in a tractable experimental
model system, the mouse.
And these tools
are useful not just
to understand the molecular
development of the disease
but also what one
can do about it.
How can you use these models to
detect cancer at earlier stages
or treat it more effectively
or maybe intercept
its progression from its early
stages to its later stages?
And this is very active and
fertile ground here at MIT.
The technologies for making
genetically engineered mouse
models have improved
dramatically over the years.
I started this work myself
here at MIT in 1988.
And it was very difficult
to do back then.
Now, with tools like CRISPR, we
can do this very, very easily.
And the most recent
version of CRISPR tools
that we use in this
process is called
prime editing, a method
developed by David Liu
at the Broad Institute,
which takes the Cas9 enzyme,
modifies it so that it no longer
makes a double-stranded DNA,
but rather a single-strand
nick, and then fuse that nickase
to a piece of reverse
transcriptase,
an enzyme that will
take an RNA template
and convert it into a DNA form.
This was actually
a discovery made
by David Baltimore, which
was the thing that won him
the Nobel Prize in 1975.
And you can therefore feed this
enzyme a long extended guide
RNA that will bring it
to a place in the genome
but also have an extension on
it that has a mutation, shown
in red here.
And the reverse
transcriptase activity
will then convert that
mutation in RNA form into DNA.
And that DNA will then be
transferred into the genome
at that specific position.
This is an incredibly
powerful technology.
We've used it in
collaboration with David's lab
to make mice that
carry the prime editor.
And now, in a
simple system where
one designs a guide RNA
carrying a mutation of interest,
one can introduce that into
animals and mutate genes
at any position in vivo.
And we've done that
in one example,
again bringing us back
to the RAS oncogene,
to look at different
alleles of KRAS
and how they affect tumor
development here in the lung.
And I won't belabor
this point, but suffice
it to say that different
mutations cause
different phenotypes.
They all cause cancer, yes.
But some of them, G12R
here, causes a much more
profound cancer phenotype than
the other three for reasons
that we don't understand.
But in all likelihood,
this is teaching
us something very important
about the biology of RAS
and how, ultimately, we
will want to target it.
We can do this in a gene-by-gene
and allele-by-allele fashion
today.
But we are also able to use
massively parallel methods using
CRISPR-based libraries to
mutate many genes simultaneously
or create many alleles
of genes simultaneously.
This is the work of
Francisco Sánchez-Rivera,
assistant professor
in the Koch Institute,
who has developed methods to
introduce, via prime editing,
whole libraries of guide RNAs to
mutate a given gene of interest
at every position, to create a
massive number of alleles across
that gene, ones that are
known to be mutated in cancer
and others that perhaps are
not yet known but might be
discovered in the future.
And by this method,
by introducing
a range of mutations in
a pool of cancer cells,
one can then subject them to
a variety of functional tests
to determine the consequences
of these individual alterations
and, again, help
predict what will
happen when we find
these mutations
in the clinic in the future.
Now, I've spent most
of my time this morning
talking about biology
and molecular biology
and genetic engineering.
But as I mentioned,
the Koch Institute
is also about the convergence
of engineering and science.
And so I want to give a few
examples of technologies
from the engineering domain
that are actively being pursued
and are impacting how
cancer patients are treated
and also how we discover
cancer in the future.
Phil mentioned that one of
the focuses of our research
is to find new ways to deliver
medicines to cells, including
cancer cells.
And we have great
expertise in nanotechnology
in Dan Anderson's lab, Paul
Hammond's lab, Bob Langer's lab.
They're leaders in this space.
But we're also
interested in using
new engineering-based
methods to deliver
more conventional
drugs, including
conventional chemotherapy.
You might be surprised to learn
that chemotherapy is used today,
and the dose of
chemotherapy is used today,
based on formulas
that were developed
more than a hundred years ago
that simply asked the body
size of the individual
who's being treated based
on their height
and their weight.
And by this very simple
formula, regardless
of the particular
individual, whether they
be very tall, short,
and heavy, they
might get the exact
same dose of drug.
And the distribution of the drug
in those two different people
is likely to be
very, very different.
And their genetics is
likely to be very different.
And their metabolism is
But the formula doesn't pay
attention to any of that.
And so Louis DeRidder,
a graduate student
in Bob Langer's lab
and Gio Traverso's lab,
working with collaborators
at the Dana-Farber,
decided to try to
bring technology
to solve this problem in
a very simple fashion,
to develop a closed-loop
system that would actively
measure the concentration of a
drug, like a chemotherapeutic,
while the patient
is being treated
to test the concentration
of that drug in real time
and then adjust the dose as
a function of the measurement
of the drug in the bloodstream.
They call this system CLAUDIA.
And it's not just an idea.
They've actually built it.
Again, the concept
with CLAUDIA dosing
is that one can actively measure
and therefore monitor and adjust
dosing so that the dose of the
drug in that individual patient
will be at the desired amount.
Whereas with the body surface
area dosing shown on the lower
left, one would
overshoot in some cases,
undershoot in others, depending
on the various factors
that I mentioned previously.
They've built this device.
They've tested it in
an animal model so far.
And what you can
see from these data
is that, compared to the
standard approach, which
overshoots in this
particular example,
leading potentially
to overdosing,
with the CLAUDIA system, they
can get very, very consistent
dosing across long
periods of time.
So it's my prediction
that, before very long,
this technology will
be used in the clinic
to improve efficacy and avoid
toxicity in cancer patients.
So for today, we need to be
able to treat cancer patients.
We need to develop new
precision medicines.
But as we look to
the future, I think
we can imagine a better time
when we can avoid cancer
altogether, when we can
predict more accurately who's
going to develop
cancer and intercept it
at a very early stage.
And here I want to
close with an example
from Regina Barzilay,
which does exactly
that, using the power of
artificial intelligence
to predict the future of cancer.
And this is a personal
story for Regina
because she herself developed
breast cancer in 2014.
And she, during that
journey, asked her doctors,
why couldn't you have
known this was coming?
You take an image of
my breast every year.
Surely there was something
there at an earlier stage
that would have told you that
I was going to get cancer.
And they put their hands up and
said, we do the best we can.
But Regina wasn't
satisfied with that answer.
And so she wanted to
know, perhaps there
are latent signals in
mammographic images
that would tell you that
there's a cancer coming
at some future time.
And so she then collaborated
with colleagues from the Mass
General Hospital and
elsewhere to use AI technology
and deep learning algorithms
to ask the question,
if you train computers
with thousands of images
from women who didn't get breast
cancer in the future, ones who
did in three years
or in five years,
can you actually
develop an algorithm
that can accurately, or at
least more accurately, assess
the risk of an individual?
And I'm happy to say
that this has worked.
In a paper published
a few years ago,
they demonstrated
that they can develop
a neural network which is quite
predictive in assessing risk.
It dramatically
outperforms the standard
used in the field
today, which are
based on things like family
history of disease or age
but nothing about the
particulars of the individual.
The AI-driven
model, called MIRAI,
greatly outperforms
that technology.
And because it was
developed initially
with a data set from a
limited number of hospitals,
they've now moved beyond and
tested these systems with data
from seven different
hospitals across three
different continents.
And the algorithm
works equally well,
if not a little bit better, with
those diverse data sets, which
is very, very encouraging.
And this has now been
implemented across the world.
This slide says there's
1.7 million mammograms that
have been screened by MIRAI.
I checked this morning.
We're up to 1.9 million.
So this is being
dramatically rolled out
to improve the doctor's ability
to accurately predict and then
monitor patients who are at
the highest risk of developing
breast cancer in the future.
So I'll close there
and remind you
that we're celebrating 50 years
of cancer research at MIT.
It's been a long and
remarkably successful journey.
But I think the best
is still yet to come.
We at MIT have
tremendous strengths
across our great University
to bring technologies
from far and wide to apply
to these difficult problems.
And I think with the
MIT HEALS initiative,
we have potential to
do that much more.
So I'll stop there and thank
you for your attention.
And I'll now introduce my
colleague, Doug Lauffenburger,
who will take it from here.
[APPLAUSE]
Morning.
I'm very appreciative to be able
to participate here and provide
a complementary partnership
perspective from engineering,
celebrating alongside the
remarkable past of Life Sciences
at MIT and anticipating
the surely even
more remarkable future ahead.
So I need to start from this
engineering perspective of what
engineering contributes.
Engineers create
technologies to be
useful to solve problems and
address challenges in society.
They do this by
bringing together
manipulation of components
and making new components
to construct these technologies.
But they do it in
a manner that's
going to be predictive rather
than trial and error, which
involves quantitative
measurement and modeling, so
synthesis and analysis.
And as was pointed out
by our Dean of Science,
you can't translate
anything from nothing.
And so the engineering
technologies
are grounded in particular
branches of science.
And that's really what defines
the discipline of engineering,
is what is its
foundational science
that it's going to
measure and model
and then it's going to
manipulate and make from?
So examples include mechanical
engineering and electrical
engineering, firmly grounded
in the realms of physics,
and chemical engineering,
materials engineering,
firmly grounded in the
science of chemistry.
Those are very well
established examples.
And, of course,
what happens then
is these engineering
disciplines are
aimed at a spectrum
of application realms.
Could be manufacturing, energy,
transportation, environment,
including medicine and health.
And so engineers
will bring together
their analysis and synthesis
of their branches of science
to address these problems.
And in fact, in the engineering
world, ever since the 1950s,
these classical engineering
disciplines have been applied
very effectively to
medicine and health,
with outcomes such as
prosthetics, kidney dialysis,
heart pumps, imaging,
drug delivery.
And these all came
from the physics-
and chemistry-based
engineering disciplines that
existed at that point in time.
And so if you look
back, you could
call this-- this really was mid-
to late-20th-century convergence
of engineering disciplines
with medicine and health,
just that minimal
biology was involved.
And so when people talked
about biomedical engineering,
it was a big M for medical and
a very, very tiny b for bio
because it really was not
involved in a substantial way.
Nonetheless, it was
the right convergence
for that time pre
the revolutions
that Phil talked about.
So since that time, since
the '50s, '60s, '70s types
of convergence, there have been
indeed these two major life
science revolutions or waves.
I like the notion of waves.
Molecular biology,
being the first,
permits biological science
to be fused with engineering.
Engineers can use molecular
and cellular components
to make new biological
technologies.
So that enables the
biological engineering.
The second one being the
genomic biology revolution.
And that, in fact,
requires bioscience to be
fused with engineering on the
highly quantitative measurement
scale modeling to
understand and model
in a predictive way
these very complex
molecular cellular systems
so that the new biological
technologies synthesized from
molecular biology revolution
can now be analyzed in
a predictive way based
on the genomic
biology revolution.
So you see, those
two revolutions
laid the foundation for a
brand new kind of engineering
that was not
possible before them.
Not surprisingly,
MIT is the place
at which this new
biological engineering
discipline was created.
In 1998, it was established,
became a full-fledged department
in 2005, and became course 20.
And what you see is
that it now stands
alongside the physics-based and
the chemistry-based engineering
disciplines.
But now its science foundation
is molecular biology
and genomic biology.
And from that foundation,
it can make technologies
in a predictively
designed way to apply
to manufacturing, energy,
environment, defense,
and medicine and health.
So it's alongside those
in being able to address
the challenges across the
entire spectrum of society.
Now, I want to make sure I
say something about education
because you really can't
make long-standing waves
or have a sustained
revolution without educating
the next generation of people
who now think in the new ways
and have capabilities
in the new ways.
So a very profoundly
important thing
about biological
engineering here
is it became course
20, the first new MIT
undergraduate
major in 39 years--
entirely new curriculum.
Students were rooted in classes
from the biology department
and genetics and biochemistry
and molecular biology.
But all the engineering,
analysis, synthesis,
measurement, and modeling
is brought to bear purely
and solely on the molecular
and genomic biology
in an entirely new way that has
never existed at any institution
worldwide.
And now these
students are going on
to become the next
generation who
are addressing these
problems in ways
that the physics-based
engineering
and chemistry-based
engineering just don't
have the capabilities to do.
And so now we can add to the
armament that the world needs.
I will note, at MIT,
education is a huge priority.
And in fact, I need to spend
happily, unfortunately,
most of my day in
my office having
office hours for my
undergraduate students
who have an exam
tomorrow morning,
and they want to discuss the
questions and the problems
and the topics.
And to me, that's
a huge priority,
as it is for faculty
across the Institute.
So what are the
products of this,
along with new types of
ideas and technologies?
Of course, not surprisingly,
companies have been spun out.
And I loved Phil's
list and could
put biological
engineering-spawned companies
alongside.
I'm just going to
note a few that
are widely recognized
as preeminent
in their particular fields.
So Adimab out of Dane Wittrup's
lab in biologics discovery
and engineering.
Synbio out of Linda
Griffith's lab in Oregon
on chip technologies.
Pivot Bio from Chris Voigt's lab
in agricultural biotechnologies.
Applied BioMath, now part
of Certara in systems
pharmacology, from myself
and a number of colleagues.
Also note Strand
Therapeutics at the bottom
now bringing synthetic biology
into the realm of engineering
immune cells to
be more effective,
again, in a
predictively defined way
by Ron Weiss and Darrell Irvine.
To end in the last few minutes
in a forward-looking way--
but, of course, to look forward,
you say, where are we going?
And, of course,
where you're going
depends on where
you're already rooted.
And so one of the
major things that's
coming out of this
discipline is addressing
what I think is one of the
long-standing challenges that
has not been addressed
effectively yet.
President Kornbluth talked
about the hard, hard, hardest
problems.
That's what this is.
You all are very well aware
of the attrition in the drug
discovery and
development pipeline,
that a very, very small
fraction of therapeutics
that enter the clinic succeed.
And the biggest
problem of that is
that the major costs
of the pipeline
are in the clinical trials.
So you're wasting the
vast majority of the money
that you're investing.
So this is a critical problem
that's been around for decades.
And again, people say, well,
we're doing the best we can.
We need to do better.
Society needs it.
So what is at the
root of this problem?
There's multiple
issues, of course.
But from our point of view, it's
the very poor translatability
from animal models
to human patients,
that one can do very, very,
very effective things in animals
that just don't work in humans.
That's what's got
to be improved.
And why is that?
Well, traditional
animal-to-human translation
focuses on using
genomics largely
and other quantitative
measurements,
identifying pathways and
processes involved in a disease
or lack of response
to a therapeutic that
are observed from very well
controlled animal experiments
and presume that,
if those are what's
most important in the
animals, then if we can find
some hint of them in the
humans, they're also going
to be important in the humans.
But this is incorrect.
In the vast majority
of cases, the things
that are most important
in the animals
are not what's most
important in the humans.
Therefore, things that
work very well in animals
are not effective in humans.
And this is the
long-standing lament.
Again, you're all familiar
with of curing disease
after disease in mice with no
consequent benefit in humans.
I call this the
"tip of the iceberg"
problem because what you're
looking at is what's most
important in the animal
with very little guarantee,
and, in fact, very minor chance,
that it's actually what's also
most important for
the human patients.
How do you address that?
Well, this is where
the combination
of biology and engineering
inherent in this new discipline
really holds a lot of promise,
that if you understand,
on the one hand, what
these biological pathways
and processes are, what
the data represent,
and, on the other
hand, you're capable
of the sophisticated
computational analysis
and modeling-- one
can bring together,
for instance in the
example I'm showing here,
using a semi-supervised AI
machine-learning approach
in which the secret sauce
is not the sophistication
of the computation, but it's
the understanding of how
the data map and what the data
mean biologically-- then you
can find pathways and
processes that are, in fact,
most important for
humans even when
they seem to be of negligible
importance in the animals.
So I call this, instead of
being focused on the tip,
you can actually find the
iceberg underneath that's
most important for the human
by this combination of omics
data, understanding biological
pathways and processes,
and the computational
machine learning.
These are projects we've
been pursuing not only
with a number of the biopharma
companies in this area
and elsewhere, but the
Department of Defense, the Gates
Foundation for vaccines, and,
not surprisingly, the FDA,
which wants to improve this
and the methodology for this
strongly.
Some examples have to do
with Humira resistance
in Crohn's and colitis with
a very well known biopharma
company, with the Army--
protection against
neurocognitive trauma--
and I can name others.
And most importantly,
this approach
is now being adopted into
industry therapeutics pipelines.
And so I believe that we will
see, over the coming decade
or so, significantly
improved translatability
from the preclinical
studies to clinical.
So that's just an
example of rooter
where we are now in
biological engineering,
looking at the kind
of challenge that
has been too hard to do before
but is no longer too hard.
With that, I thank you
for your attention.
I thank you for being here
at this momentous event.
And it's a great pleasure to
introduce our next speaker, Ruth
Lehmann, who's a professor
in biology and director
of the Whitehead Institute.
[APPLAUSE]
Hello, good morning.
It's a real pleasure
for me to be here today
and to celebrate HEALS.
Like Sally, I am also
a recent recruit.
And I also have to say that
it is just invigorating
and empowering to
be in an environment
where the University is without
limits and the environment,
the ecosystem of Kendall
Square could not be better,
and the hospitals
across the river
give us really an
opportunity to think big.
What I want to tell you
about is a little bit
about the Whitehead Institute.
And I'm calling it a
radical experiment.
This is actually
a title of a book
about the history of
the Whitehead Institute
that Gerry Fink just completed.
And at the beginning, when the
Whitehead Institute was founded,
it was clearly a
radical experiment,
and it wasn't always taken with
total positivity, let's say,
because it was a bold approach
having an Institute which
was independent in its
research, government,
and finance, solely associated
with an institution,
with MIT, where all the
faculty are teaching at MIT
and are in departments at MIT.
The founding vision
was very bold, as
bold as MIT is, to assemble
the best scientific talent,
to catalyze their
work with support,
and to encourage them
to go their own ways.
There were many
early breakthroughs.
And actually, you heard
about quite a few.
You heard several times
about the breakthrough work
of Bob Weinberg.
And that was at the
Whitehead Institute
in the field of cancer,
work in STEM cell biology,
transcription, and other fields.
In particular-- and again,
you heard this already--
one third of the
human genome was
sequenced at the Whitehead
Institute in collaboration
with the NIH and MIT.
And that led then,
by Eric Lander,
starting the Broad
Institute as a spin-out.
What's also really important is
shaping a new generation, not
just as teachers, but also
the Whitehead Institute
established the Fellows
Program for newly minted PhDs.
And the first notable Fellows
are David Page and Eric Lander,
and others are George Daley,
Angelika Amon, and Peter Kim,
and also David Bartel,
who was mentioned earlier.
So what are we about today?
Today, we are 18 members--
14 of them are tenured.
And we have six Fellows.
And we have a large number
of graduate students
and undergraduates and postdocs
working in our laboratories.
And probably, one would say
from just the recognition,
the experiment was a success.
But it's still an
experiment as I see it.
So what are we looking for?
And when I speak here
about the Whitehead,
I think I speak about biology.
I speak about basic sciences.
We really, today, want to
understand how organisms
perform their tasks in life.
And that is to encapture
the complexity.
We believe that that
has to be achieved
by a mechanistic
understanding-- as we heard
Phil Sharp saying, measuring.
We want to understand
it mechanistically.
But then we do want to
deconstruct and reconstruct
to really understand
complexity of life.
And that can be done only
by collaborative work.
And that is to draw from
biology, physics, chemistry,
engineering, and
increasingly computer
science, AI, and machine
learning to develop new tools
and designs.
In general, we don't want to be
afraid of asking any questions.
We don't want to be afraid
to change directions
if that is important.
And I think HEALS
will empower that
through the collaborations
that will spark new ideas
and new points of inflection.
So two points, when we
think about history,
we can jump at today.
We can analyze cells now
at a level of resolution,
and we can ask and model
cells in a way, that
was unforeseen before, leading
to a project spearheaded
by Jonathan Weissman, and also
with the work of Ian Cheeseman,
to describe actually
a virtual cell,
to know every component,
every aspect of what
is happening in a cell.
But going one step
further, how can we
understand a whole organism?
How do we understand the parts?
How do we bring neurobiology
and immunology together
to understand how an
organism actually functions,
how it feels an infection?
So these projects are
supported by some initiatives.
And these initiatives, they're
trying to be very bold.
And they're trying to really
address some of the pressing
issues of today's challenges.
So the Whitehead Initiative of
Biology, Health, and Climate
Change addresses
questions directly
of agricultural
questions in terms
of drought-resistant
seeds, but also,
how does temperature
affect the cell?
How does a cell work at
different temperatures?
And you will hear later
in the next session
from Sinisa Hrvatin
about hibernation.
The Women's Health Initiative
brings fundamental science
together with
really understanding
why is there a health bias.
And I'll talk to you a
little bit later about this.
And all of this could
not be possible,
grasping this
complexity, without using
AI approaches to lead the way
but also to be led by the data
that we are accumulating.
We are not alone.
I always see the Whitehead
a little bit as a hub.
We have lots and lots of spokes.
Many of those spokes go
across the street to MIT.
But also, we have lots of
interactions with hospitals
and other universities.
We seek out collaborations,
and collaborators seek us out.
So today what I
want to talk to you
is actually give you five quick
vignettes about some science.
And they're pretty much
all going on right now.
These vignettes are also
highlighting how we're perhaps
addressing, somehow, Doug's
criticism to basic science
that we're doing this all in
model organisms because, as you
can see, much of what
we're learning here
is directly either applied
to humans, in humans, or not
in humans but in plants.
And so I will be talking about
these five challenges in biology
and actually for human
health and the planet.
And so let's jump into it.
First, I'm going to talk to
you about the Lourido lab.
The Lourido lab
works on Toxoplasma.
And many of you know how
dangerous Toxoplasma can be,
as it infects a large
percentage of the population
and can have really
serious consequences
for pregnant women, infants,
and immunocompromised people.
So what Sebastian and his group
have done is they took all
the 8,000 genes of Toxoplasma
and made gRNAs against them
so that he can interfere with
those RNAs and then infect
the organism where normally
the infection occurs.
And then they're able
to use different tissues
and different-- and look
at what of these cells
are now surviving.
Those cells which are
surviving are obviously
not the ones whose genes are
required for the function.
And so he can directly
select with this whole genome
mutagenesis for genes which
affect fitness and has
identified a number
of genes which affect
the fitness of the infection.
And this is clear
how it's directly
applicable in the future.
The next, we go to another
challenging problem.
And that is, how do we make
better drought-resistant plants?
How can we deal with the
issue of food supply?
And so what most of you know
is that many seeds are actually
produced by crossing
different parent plants.
And then the seed itself is much
better than the parents were.
The problem is that
those seeds can not
be propagated continuously.
And so if they're
just grown, then there
will be a large variety.
So what Mary Gehring
is addressing
is to ask the
question of, could we
actually make seeds which
can be asexually propagated?
And that actually happens
sometimes naturally.
And so she is using these
kinds of seeds which sometimes
make that mistake of not needing
fertilization to find out
what factors are required.
And then can we up the
opportunity for seeds
to develop asexually and
then produce populations
of seeds that can actually
be used without having
the hybrid-vigor problem?
The next question is going
directly to human biology.
And that is addressed
by David Page.
His lab really is puzzled by
this striking and still very
unexplained sex bias in the
prevalence, the severity
of diseases between
males and females,
also, certainly,
drug sensitivity.
And so what they found is really
surprising and very interesting.
So when we just look at
all the cells in our soma,
in our body, not the cells
in our reproductive organs,
there are two types of
chromosomes, sex chromosomes,
the X and the Y.
And when we look
at the expression of the
active X chromosome in males
or females, so XX
versus XY people,
the active X is
expressed the same way.
So all the genes are--
there's no sex difference.
But the sex differences
come from the genes which
are expressed on the so-called
inactive X, which is actually
not inactive but expresses 38%
of the genes on the active X.
And also, there are genes
expressed on the Y chromosome.
And these could really influence
the expression of these genes
are making a cell different,
any cell in the body different,
whether it is in an XX
organism or an XY organism.
And so the idea is that this
can have an influence on disease
prevalence and sex bias.
The next issue is
another big question.
And that's the big question
of neurodegeneration.
And there is so little
that we know at this point
where we can really do something
about neurodegeneration.
A particular type
of neurodegeneration
is neurodegeneration
caused by prion disease.
Prion disease is usually a
very swift neurodegeneration.
And the death is due
to the accumulation
of misshapen proteins.
And so Jonathan
Weissman designed
CHARM, which is where a
fusion protein recruits
a methyltransferase specifically
through a DNA-binding domain
to a specific gene.
And by that, it methylates that
gene and silences that gene.
And so this can be
delivered into the brain.
And in mice, this reduces 80%
of the prion-gene expression.
And mice, which are
affected by prion disease,
live longer after
this injection.
And so my final
vignette is perhaps
the most biggest
challenge in human health,
and that is chronic disease.
There are many types
of chronic diseases.
And the problem with
chronic diseases
is they're not due
to a single gene.
So we cannot start
with a single gene.
But they have
multifactorial causes.
And we don't even exactly
know what the causes are.
So what Rick Young
and his colleagues
found is that often through
elevated oxidative environment,
through the pathogenic factors,
proteins are less mobile.
They are less mobile because
their cysteines are altered
so that they are now
interacting with other proteins
more through
cysteine-cysteine bridges.
And he phrases this
as proteolethargy.
And this proteolethargy
may, first of all,
lead to reduced
function and output.
And they showed this very
clearly with insulin receptor
mobility being reduced.
And it is also a target
which can actually be
more globally and widely used.
So I hope that with these
vignettes that I just presented,
you got an idea of where
basic science meets
translational science.
And that couldn't be
more better illustrated
than the many companies
which have sprung out
of these initiatives that
have started at the Whitehead
Institute.
I'm really looking
forward for HEALS
to further enlarge the
interactions that we have.
And I think the
possibilities for science,
both at the mechanistic
level and understanding
the complexity for
health and the planet,
is really, really great.
And I look forward to that.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]