U thank you everyone. My name is Narin
Talbergata. I'm the CEO and co-founder
of Tessle Biosciences. I'm an MIT
undergrad alum. Uh course 6 class of
2013. Uh went on to get a PhD in biology
uh from Harvard working on organoid
cultures which is a big part of our uh
of our approach at at TESL and actually
co-ounded it with a fellow MIT alum as
well. So what we work on at Tesla is
virtual tissues, basically models to
simulate how human organs behave in
health and disease um by way of labin
the loop experimentation in order to
identify better drug targets and design
real drugs for largely chronic
inflammatory and fibroic conditions.
These are the settings where there's
just massive unmet need. Uh where
despite all of the advances we've seen
in uh biioarma, these diseases remain
largely refractory to many existing
therapies or people ultimately fail on
next-gen therapies and new ones are
needed. And the best models of human
biology to enable discovery for these
conditions are actually the ones that
tend to be the hardest to scale. Uh
putting aside the issue of a human in a
clinical trial which is just you know
the ultimate in in an unscalable disease
model um the best proxies you can find
for things like lung disease which we
work on very actively at Tesla uh also
bowel disease Crohn's etc are actually
cells drawn from patients taken from
patients that are grown in these
organotypic settings in which they uh
behave quite a bit like the uh tissue of
interest or the tissue of origin and in
those settings it's not just that you're
able to grow the tissue in the right
structure. They actually carry out and
exhibit behaviors that are quite
reminiscent of uh what actually happens
in people and can be measured in a
doctor's office. What you might call
clinical end points in a dish and this
is things like mucus production by lung
cells from patients with COPD. This is
things like stiffness of tissue uh in
fibrodic models of what happens in the
intestine of a patient with severe
Crohn's. So we should be using these
sorts of models for discovery and
validation of targets and drugs and in
fact optimization as well of those
drugs. But it's the complexity of these
systems and their cost which limits
their use in discovery where they could
really be most impactful. So where these
systems are used today is largely um
sort of after the main uh heavy lifting
of discovery is done more or less to
generate supplemental data for uh a
pre-clinical or clinical development
package rather than as the machine from
which a novel therapeutic hypothesis
emerged and in which it was validated.
So really that's what we're focused on
at Tessle is making it possible to scale
up these models through a combination of
a lot of work on the wet lab side to
make these systems more scalable but
also primarily our active learning
powered uh AI powered engine on the dry
lab side which allows us to simulate the
functional behaviors of tissues in
silico so that we can iteratively pick
and focus on the subset of perturbations
to test in vitro the subset of targets
to perturb using methods like crisper in
order to find novel targets that can
actually modify uh the disease behaviors
uh that we wish to reverse in a person.
And in fact, using this approach, we've
uh developed our own drugs. We've
identified and nominated and even um
secured chemical matter for uh a target
that would reverse goblet cell
hyperplasia and lung disease. So in
patients with diseases from COPD and
asthma to bronchiactis
um which are characterized by overp
production of mucus which makes it very
hard to breathe even if the underlying
disease is theoretically under control.
We have a therapy which can actually uh
reverse that problematic disease state.
But the underlying approach here allows
us to use and harness the power of
patient derived cells which model those
kinds of complex organ dysfunction in
settings where brute force screening is
just not possible or intractable. And in
fact in many different ways we've been
able to show that our approach is up to
30x more efficient than you know just
doing a uh unbiased brute force screen
using a large library of compounds or
perturbations.
And so our traction to date, we've been
able to use this approach uh in order to
as I said identify and nominate our own
drug candidates and expect uh to
nominate a development candidate at some
point next year. But we've also been
able to extend and apply this platform
beyond our focus area in the lung. Uh
currently working with two of the top 10
pharma companies. We've got a research
collaboration going uh focused on
identifying and screening target
combinations which are relevant for
example for multisspecific antibbody
design. We've got a pilot with another
top 10 pharma company to deploy some of
these organoid models for uh
inflammatory bowel disease. And we've
also recently secured uh some support
from ARPA to expand our work on tissues
to the setting of admetox prediction as
well. So of course there are many
diseases of things like the intestine uh
where modeling human intestine in a dish
is useful but the intestine is also the
front door for most medicines that we
take today and therefore therapies for
any disease in any organ ultimately have
something to do with the availability of
a molecule and its ability to transport
across the intestinal barrier. So these
are all settings in which we have a
growing portfolio of capabilities in
which we're already working with
commercial partners and we're actively
looking for additional research
collaborations including beyond this
core focus of immunology that I've
already discussed uh as well as
potentially co-development opportunities
for our lead molecule which is advancing
towards the clinic. Thanks.
>> Thanks Nan. Um first question um what
about the model for lungs for babies?
Uh, sorry. Lungs for babies, you said.
>> Yes. The model that you're working on,
but for babies.
>> For babies. Yeah. In fact, I I think a
lot of the potential for approaches like
ours is to essentially expand into
settings where um there are unserved or
underserved patient populations and we
can take advantage of the fact that we
can get or use tissue from specific
patient types including let's say
pediatric patients, right? So um I mean
I think the unfortunate truth of drug
development is that pediatric drug
development is complicated hard uh not
necessarily incentivized the right way
but it's also a setting in which I think
what's missing is the ability to
extrapolate right and to say here are
the treatments and dosing regimes that
have been approved for adults. um can we
use a system like what we've developed
at TESSL in order to essentially develop
the cipher or or figure out what is the
way to translate the uh the therapies
and the targets and the dosing amounts
to this new uh patient population which
could include for example uh younger
children and in fact we've thought about
this a little bit more in the context of
IBD in the context of the gut where for
example uh even standard of care
therapies like anti-TNF are not um
widely used in children in in quite the
same way they are in adults. Um but it's
certainly applicable in the context uh
of the lung as well like asthma is a
very big unmet need. Uh viral neutrfilic
asthma is a very big unmet need and
problem in in young children as you I'm
sure many of us are aware uh especially
if we have our own.
>> Yes. No, that's good to know. Um and on
your platform how did you determine that
it's the efficiency is like tenfold?
Yeah. So there's two ways of doing it
basically. Retrospective and
prospective. So a retrospective approach
is to say hey look we've got our
algorithms here. It's what's you know
illustrated partially here by this
active learning loop of um you know
taking data feeding it into our model
making a prediction and then updating
the model based off of the results.
Right? That approach you can essentially
pretend you had done that on uh many
many existing data sets. Right? There
are people out there who have screened
the effect of perturbing every single
gene in many different cell types and
they've measured the the phenotypes, the
outcomes. Uh and so in that setting, uh
that was brute force, right? Somebody
tested 20,000 different conditions at
least uh to generate data. uh and if we
essentially say hey had we taken our
approach and you know uh generated
batches of predictions and used that to
converge on the top answers and stop
when we declared ourselves to be done.
Uh we frequently find that you need you
know as few as a thousand or 2,000
perturbations to identify all of the
same top targets. And so that's where
you get you know this 10x 20x speed up
is saying a,000 versus 20,000 or 2,000
versus 20,000. But we can actually show
also perspectively that that reads
through to our own uh work. So we have
ongoing target discovery efforts in lung
disease where we have some of these
benchmarks and we say hey look you know
if to date we've perturbed 200 genes in
the setting of our lung screens and
we've identified already uh you know 40
uh 40 hits active hits um how much
higher is that hit rate than what we
naively expected by chance from uh the
sort of brute force screens or those
random benchmarks and in that setting
we're doing at least 5x better. So
that's that's the sort of way that we
keep ourselves honest. Um it's a it's a
fun and complex detail I think of AI and
biology that benchmarks are uh uh hard
to define but extremely valuable to know
how you're doing. And so if anyone wants
to talk about that I'm happy to as well.
>> Thank you. Good to know. Thank you.
Thanks again.