AI is not just a technology problem.
It's also a human design problem.
believe it or not and uh if you our next
speaker, Professor Patty May will
discuss about this and also explore how
optimizing the human AI interface can
drive better outcome. Now, Professor
Patty May is uh germs Hawome professor
of media art and science. Let's welcome
welcome professor May.
[Applause]
Good afternoon.
So, one of the fun things about being a
faculty member at MIT is that every year
you get this new crop of young students
that are very eager to sort of adopt the
latest technologies, whether they're
commercial things or more often even
things that they've developed themselves
that they think will improve their lives
and uh make it possible to accomplish
more and so on. And so it really um
offers us faculty an opportunity to see
what our future um way of living with
technology may look like. And so these
days um that actually future that I see
um my students uh adopting is one not
unlike the one in the movie her which is
a great movie by Spike Jones by the way.
um what is depicted in that movie
basically the students spend many hours
a day conversing with AI AI really
mediates and helps them with every
aspect of their lives not just coding or
workrelated things looking up research
etc getting new ideas for research
projects but also deciding uh what
present they may want to uh buy for
their uh boyfriend or girlfriend or
dealing with medical issues that they
may have. It acts as their coach. It
acts as their friend. Um it acts as u uh
everything sort of hopefully not lover
uh like in the movie but um who knows.
Um so of course that future is very
exciting once we have AI with us all the
time sort of helping us with all these
aspects of our lives. Uh we can augment
our performance and productivity
um for in the area of learning. Um it
enables this like personalized situated
learning in the area of health.
Increasingly, we're seeing uh that
companies are integrating these um chat
bots uh with smart watches and other
sensors that we wear all the time. So,
they'll be able to help us with our uh
interpreting what is going on with our
health, with our sleep and all of that
in intelligent ways. Um, for the
elderly, I think there's enormous
potential for these uh AI assistants,
especially wearable AI assistants to
help people live in their own lives uh
live in their own homes for longer
independently. Um, of course, in media,
it's going to change media and
entertainment completely and uh towards
sort of more personalized, much more
interactive u media and entertainment
and more. But of course there are still
a lot of challenges and I'm sure you've
heard about them today. Um often uh
there's a lot of technical challenges
things like hallucinations and uh
inaccuracies and the weak reasoning
skills of AI. AI is biased. There are
safety issues, privacy concerns, um cost
issues, environmental cost issues and
more. But these are not the only
challenges that we have to solve uh for
AI to ultimately be successful and
really help us with uh all of the and
improve our lives and work. AI is not
just an engineering challenge. It's also
a human design challenge. In the work
that we do in my lab, we show that there
are a lot of risks um and human
challenges that we have to overcome when
we inter uh integrate um AI into
people's uh daily work and lives. Things
like over reliance and misplaced trust.
uh one of my students had AI write a a
related work section of a paper before
we submitted it and uh only uh just
before we submitted it we realized that
most of the citations
uh were non-existing ex uh apart from
the fact that the citations were all
very believable so it really required a
lot of work it wasn't nonsense it looked
very believable and very real Um there's
loss of
understanding increasingly if if you
rely on AI sort of to um help you with
interpreting information, working
through things and so on, we risk
understanding things ourselves less. I
think there's a very dangerous uh
phenomenon that people in AI are talking
about the AI developers are uh talking
about called vibe coding where instead
of understanding your code you actually
just sort of tell an AI in natural
language yeah yeah build me this app and
it should do this that and that and then
you see how it behaves but you never
actually look at the actual code to make
sure that that vote is um doing the
right thing. I think it's extremely
dangerous to um rely so much and um on
AI to do these things that ultimately uh
we have to understand and be able to
control ourselves. So there's a risk for
a loss of agency that we lost uh the
control of the systems that govern our
lives and that run our companies and so
on. Uh
deskkilling is another risk. Uh we're
showing uh in some of the experiments
that we do uh in my lab that the more
you rely on AI to help you with a skill,
of course, the less you develop that
skill yourself or the worse you get
yourself at that skill. So we're not
thinking long term about the
consequences of adopting these
technologies. Misinformation and
manipulation. We've done work in my lab
together with Elizabeth Loftus to show
how easy it is for an AI, especially one
that you get to trust over time as it
knows you and helps you for a longer
period of time, has a user model and
memory of everything you've talked
about. People start trusting these
systems so much that then that trust can
be abused to slip misinformation
um uh into people's uh minds and and
really uh persuade uh them to have
certain beliefs or adopt certain
behaviors and so on. unhealthy
attachment. I'll talk about that in a
little bit, but it does exist of people
to AI and people literally replacing
human relationships with AI
relationships. Uh dehumanization that
that leads to. The more you talk to AI
that is always um aiming to please you
and telling you that you are right,
etc., of course, the less good you
become at talking to real people who may
not always agree with you. and weakening
of social ties. Um, those same students
that spend two hours talking to AI.
Well, they spend two hours talking to
other students and family members and
friends before that that they may not
talk to as much right now because a lot
of their problems are solved by AI. So,
I think it will result in weaker social
networks.
So the central question of my research
is as AI advances and and it is a very
exciting advancement. How do we ensure
that people and humanity will advance as
well? And we do a lot of experiments to
show that this is a real problem. But we
also try to come up with solutions
actually that um companies and everybody
can adopt. For example, in the area of
decision making, um, increasingly our
information processing is mediated by
AI, right? Um, whether not just when
you're a doctor, say, making medical
decisions as we just heard, but also um
your access to information increasingly
you see AI summaries instead of doing
searches and looking at source materials
and so on. So what happens when people
always have AI available at their
fingertips when making decisions? We did
a study that shows u or that looked at
uh a thousand newspaper headlines um
that u were either true or false and um
we had a number of human subjects that
um could actually be advised by AI. They
had a AI right there telling them I
think this newspaper headline is true or
false and giving an explanation uh for
why it uh thought so as well. And what
we learned is of course um in gray you
see um how well people do without AI
assistance. So we had three um groups of
people. Some people used uh no AI in
gray. Some people used an accurate AI
that gives you the ground truth for
those thousand headlines. And some
people had a deceptive AI that tries to
convince you of the opposite of the
truth. And so in gray you see how well
people do without AI for true and false
headlines. Um in blue you see how well
they do when they have a an accurate uh
truthful AI at their fingertips and
their performance does improve. But in
red, you see how poorly they do when
they have an AI at their fingertips that
gives them inaccurate information.
People really believe in these systems
too much and um adopt their
recommendations and their feedback too
readily without thinking for themselves.
We showed in a follow-up paper that the
solution to this is to have a little bit
of friction and not make it too easy for
someone to get the AI's uh decision on a
particular problem but instead you have
to make you have to force the person to
engage in thinking about the problem a
little bit themselves so that you can
really benefit from both the human
intelligence and critical thinking as as
well as the AI uh intelligence in
quotes. Um so AI that actually first
asks you a question about the decision
that you're making results in even
better performance than an AI that uh is
accurate and in much better for
performance than uh the uh malicious
AI. So for AI to deployments to be
successful in a real context um it's not
sufficient for models to be accurate and
fair and ethical and explainable. But we
really need to test how people respond
to these having these uh systems at uh
their fingertips and working with these
systems and we have to optimize
objectives that are really of a human
nature as well as an AI nature. Some
other examples um you heard today about
AI being used in learning and of course
there is uh a lot of worry on behalf of
teachers and parents uh because kids can
too readily just ask AI to do their
homework for them. So um but we did a
study to show what the effects are on
learning if you use AI and this doesn't
just apply to students but really to the
workplace as well.
So we did a study where we had um two
tasks that our uh human subjects had to
perform writing an essay and then a
computer um uh programming problem
basically. And we had three groups of
subjects. People that could use chat
GPT, people that could use just search
uh so Google without the AI summary and
uh people who could only use their own
brain, no tools. And we actually had um
uh EEG cap um and we also looked at eye
gaze etc to analyze what happened in the
brains of people uh these different
groups as they were solving these
problems. The essay by the way was an
SAT prompt uh for those of you that have
like 17 or 18 year olds you know what
I'm talking about.
Um so the differences that we saw in
average brain activity were striking.
Actually the group that used Chachi PT
showed the least brain activity uh
especially in the prefrontal cortex uh
sort of where a lot of the uh uh
reasoning goes
on. The Google group did a lot of visual
activity that's happening in the back of
the head. uh they had to look at a lot
of stuff and decide what to adopt etc.
But they also had um critical thinking
that was uh being shown. And then the
group that just used their brains uh
basically showed uh the most um sort of
uh um uh activity in uh sort of the
frontal uh cortex. But another
interesting result, we also analyzed the
essays that people wrote, the
programming people did and so on. it.
This is you don't have to try to
interpret this, but we looked at the
topics people wrote about in their
essays, and it turned out that the group
that used CHACH PT, they all came up
with similar essays to the same uh uh
SAT prompt, uh they didn't show much um
sort of uh divergence or um of uh
different points of view, etc., which is
typically what is looked for in these
SAT essays. They were all delivering a
good but the same types of essays about
the same topics. Now, you risk that in
your company as well. If you have all of
your employees using uh these systems to
assist them, yes, they may perform well,
but they're not ex they're not getting
better. They're not exploring new ways
of doing things or more original
innovative methods to approach a
problem. We asked the group that used
ChachiPT to write the same essay. All of
them actually all three groups we asked
to write the same essay they had written
before. They had to write again three
weeks later. Some people in the chatbt
group didn't even recognize the prompt.
They're like, "Oh, really? I I wrote an
essay about that." they couldn't repeat
anything. They hadn't learned anything.
So yes, they delivered a good essay, but
they hadn't grown uh in their skill
level themselves. So keep that in mind.
Um we are building solutions again. Um
like one system that we're building at
the media lab is um a system that helps
you with essay writing but instead of
doing the writing for you it actually
looks at sorry what you have and it
analyzes the argument you're making the
logic of your argument etc. And it
provides feedback pointing out
weaknesses and suggestions like maybe
you can give an example here. Maybe you
should have a couple other reasons why
uh that justify this claim that you're
making or present some data over here
just like a good teacher would, a good
tutor would. And we hope that that will
result in uh systems where ultimately
the student uh benefits uh and and
develops their skills but still can
benefit from the intelligence of AI, the
the fact that it's accessible, etc. and
that maybe not all of them have access
to a real uh a good human
teacher. We're doing things in the area
of memory. Um for example, um this is a
system that many business people tell me
that uh they want. It's sort of like a
personal uh u LLM or a personal system
that um monitors uh your conversations
and we can talk about privacy. It it
recognizes who talks to you if you've
named those people based on their voice
and it also asks uh you to ask for
permission to record uh um conversations
with a new person etc. You can delete
them.
Can you guys hear that? It runs on
unobtrusive maybe not. So let me talk
about it.
So, this system, an audio headset,
continuously records all of your
conversations. So, he can ask later,
what was his name again? Um, because he
can look at the the conversation. A week
later, you need access to information
from that conversation.
And the system constantly predicts what
words from your past experiences and
conversations you need um in a
particular context. But it does that in
a very minimal way where the disruption
is minimal unlike that of smartphones.
You may look up some notes you took in a
smartphone but that takes a lot of input
efforts and effort to interpret uh the
out the output. So we build a system
that is minimally uh disruptive that
just gives you a minimum number of words
that can trigger your memory for some
information that you need. We've also uh
looked a lot recently at the um how we
may want to design human AI interaction
uh in the area of socialization. I
mentioned earlier that I'm concerned
about people getting less good at
talking to other people as they talk
more to AI or just being less interested
in talking to um people and uh I think
these uh worries are justified. Um
there's a growing and widespread use of
uh chat bots for inter for personal and
interpersonal types of uh relationships.
um many people using these uh chat bots
as a psychologist um um asking for
relationship advice etc. There's even a
lot of services like replica and and
character.ai that are explicitly
designed for mimicking human
relationships. Um, and there's sometimes
awful outcomes like this sad suicide of
a teen who um had a an a chat system
that was he believed his uh lover and um
that one of the interactions he
interpreted as the system telling him to
commit suicide and he did a 14year-old
um very um sad. Now luckily there those
are still pretty rare but um just uh in
the last six months we've been doing um
a study funded by open AAI the open AI
safety team actually and in
collaboration with them where we wanted
to understand how common this type of um
close um relationships uh with uh chat
bots is and what the effects are on
people's uh well-being. So we did a
study where we looked at their different
models, the engaging voice one, the
neutral voice, uh the text model. We had
different tasks and we um uh enlisted a
thousand people to talk to
chat for at least five minutes per day.
And some of them had to talk about
personal things, others had to talk
about only practical things. and a third
group could choose what they talked
about. So in total we actually had nine
conditions and we looked at outcomes
like loneliness
um how lonely are people before and
after how much do they socialize with
real people before and after emotional
dependence on AI and problematic use of
the AI. What we learned is that uh the
people people were told you have to do
at least five minutes a day. Many did a
lot more time than that. Extended daily
use was correlated with worse well-being
with worse uh psychosocial outcome. So
you see on the bottom axis the daily
duration how much people spent time with
these chatbots and no matter what
condition they were in this is the
average for all the groups. Um you see
increased loneliness for people that use
AI a lot each day.
um decreased socialization with real
people and more dependence and
problematic uh use as well. Um we also
looked at the uh details the differences
between the different models etc. But
you can read all of that uh online. Um
the solution really and which we have
been working on again with uh OpenAI as
well is for one to um to basically uh
understand how prevalent his behavior is
and trying to track it with automated
classifiers of conversations while
preserving privacy. But then second also
build models that um have pro-social
behaviors that demonstrate pro-social
behaviors and encourage the person to
interact with real people. uh an AI can
be incredibly useful to support people
in um how to understand uh the
difficulties of their human
relationships, encouraging them to
interact more uh with other people and
so on. So we're developing a benchmark
now to um understand for all of the
different models out there how
pro-social they are. um so that that can
be sort of one of the benchmarks that
can be used for AI models. So I'll
summarize by saying yes AI is definitely
here to stay but let's design it to
augment people to preserve human agency,
meaning and well-being and that is um
not a trivial task and is not
necessarily the case for today's um
models. Um, if you're interested in
this, we are starting or have started a
big uh multiffaculty research program at
the media lab, advancing humans with AI
or
AHA. Um, and you can get more
information there.
aha.mmedia.mmit.edu. And we also have a
openly streamed for free uh conference
uh happening next week um on Thursday.
Uh so you can look up the link the
streaming link at that same website and
we have amazing speakers like Jiren
Laneir um uh Ariana Huffington Douglas
Rushkov Tristan Harris experts from uh
Microsoft Open AI um uh academics from
Stanford, Cornell, Harvard and more all
reflecting on can we design AI to
support human flourishing. So please uh
join us for that online if you want to
hear more. Thank you.
Thank you. And uh we probably have do we
have one qu maybe one question if you
can. Yeah. So the question is what are
suggested approaches to overcome the
influences of LLMs on diversity, equity
and inclusion? Yes. A very interesting
uh question. uh there is already a lot
of effort um uh by at least some of the
foundation model makers in uh improving
uh diver diversity, equity and
inclusion. Um one of the solutions I
think is just being open about data sets
for example because ultimately these
models are just um basically statistics
and math. they're not inherently say uh
biased and so on but they reflect the
biases that happen that exist in the
training data. Uh so it's important that
um and and unfortunately a lot of the
makers of these models are not very open
right now about what data they train on
etc. so that we can do audits of all
that data and make sure that the data is
as unbiased as uh
possible. Just one y or okay one more um
what kind of new and bettermental skills
do you expect people to develop after
using genai tools for a while? Yeah, so
there's very interesting work that just
came out uh this week actually from
Dartmouth. uh they have been doing work
there uh for the last four or five years
on developing AI based uh chat bots for
mental health and um you may have seen
it in the news it's in MIT technology
review last week and so on or this week
even um showing that uh they have uh
with a special purpose model that they
created it uses um something I think
similar to a rag uh approach where they
give it a lot of special training data
that they had uh carefully curated and
it u reached the same level of uh
effectiveness as a human therapist in uh
reducing uh depression uh anxiety uh and
other uh conditions. So I think it's uh
there's a huge potential for AI to help
with um mental health. Uh but their
studies and their repeated efforts um at
getting this right show that it is again
a tricky problem not one where we just
build something and don't do much
testing and release it uh but uh one
that has to be carefully curated and
where the data has to be carefully uh
curated and so on. Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you very much.