next we'll hear about evolo H and how
they are decarbonizing the chemical
industry with a lowcost electrochemical
platform um due to an unforeseen event
Jimmy roas is not able to be with us
today but I am happy to introduce you to
Art Charley Chief commercial officer at
Evol art please take it away thank you
certainly and let me extend apologies
from Jimmy he had a family e Mery uh
earlier in the week and so was unable to
do this uh but very keen on the ties
with MIT and so he uh wanted some one of
us to be here to uh be able to produce
that let me uh try to move through this
quickly so we don't fall too far behind
uh iolo was founded for the purpose of
large scale manufacturing of
electrolyzer stacks and the sour story
behind it is uh Jimmy did his couple
degrees at MIT went to Stanford did a
PhD with a focus on entrepreneurship he
ended up at breakthrough energy
Ventures vetting hydrogen projects there
were all sorts of interesting technology
new Catalyst membranes Etc but no one
focused on the manufacturing and the
manufacturing is important because if
you can hit the actual targets for
hydrogen I I'll move my cursor over here
on the left it would require gigawatts
and gigawatts of Supply to manufacture
the hydrogen in demand probably through
uh 2050 you're talking about thousands
of gigawatts of installed capacity those
Stacks only last for so long 10 years 15
years maybe consequently you have to
replace them and we did an estimate it
would require up to
150 factories each one making 15 GW per
year that's a lot of capacity it doesn't
exist today and so what we find is in
the industry as people develop green
hydrogen projects um only about one out
of 10 is actually reaching a final
investment decision and that's because
the costs are high and the availability
is limited the cost are high because
existing uh Technologies use very
expensive materials precious metals uh
toxic membranes uh very complex
Logistics you see for the alkaline
electrolyzer the picture in the middle
on the left uh that one's about 6 and a
half megawatts weighs 80 tons so uh it
can't be moved over public roads or by
any kind of public conveyance you need
special transport uh transport for it
the Pim electrolyzers are smaller more
compact but because the use of precious
metals particularly idium which is a
critical limitation and the complex
Supply chains that go behind it they
tend to be very expensive uh and then
the Opex is hot uh they often can't load
follow so they can't be tied directly to
Renewables I know Mr giner mentioned
something about uh battery uh interfaces
and how expensive those are it really
becomes a limitation to tie together
lowcost renewal energy with high volume
electrolysis capacity and then the
second part is is that the scaling these
up to the gigawatts and gigawatts that
are needed um is uh is not really
possible with existing methods the
supply chains are broken they tend to be
made laboratory style uh and and very
inefficient that way the manufacturing
processes likewise are not very scalable
and I'll show you some data on that and
then the last part which I think is
critical especially for anyone who's
worked in the the chemical process
industry uh they tend to have very
limited warranties one or two years of
defects and workmanship and no
performance guarantees so over the
lifetime of the stack the performance
will degrade efficiency will go down
more electricity will be uh used and the
manufacturer has no responsibility
behind that so trying to fix these
problems becomes the real challenge in
the green hydrogen space so iolo went
after this uh in a number of ways number
one is we went for economies of scale in
manufacturing by using roll to- roll
processing think newsprint something
very highspeed where the parts are all
uh made on a roll and then cut from that
in a SYM and in our process all of the
repeating component on in the cells are
made via roll to roll processing uh it
is very highpe speed which means more
can be produced in the same space it's
also a more compact way to make it the
second part is we use a technology
called anion exchange membrane
electrolyzers similar to the pen
electrolyzers I showed the great thing
about an exchange membranes is it's
possible to use only lowcost materials
and our focus on that was to be able to
use domestic Supply chains so stainless
steel uh nickel foam uh nickel Catalyst
uh hydrocarbon membranes all things that
you can Source literally anywhere around
the globe uh but because of the low cost
it makes it possible to scale the
manufacturing and then we want to
convert that into the lowest cost stack
in the industry because we start with
lowcost materials and a high-speed
manufacturing process we estimate that
our cost to manufacturer be one tenth of
the cost that we're seeing in forecast
for
20130 uh firms like Bloomberg NF and the
like have made estimates we believe we
can manufacture for a fraction of that
and as I said because it's only
commodity materials your uh limitations
to scale are greatly removed because now
these are available in in large amounts
and then we believe that will deliver
the lowest levelized cost of hydrogen
what you see here are a couple of uh our
one megawatt Stacks uh that we've
manufactured we don't have the full roll
roll process but we're getting there um
it uh is load follows uh and load sheds
instantaneously so you can tie it
directly to the
Renewables uh and likewise you've got
lower engineering costs because it's so
compact that uh you don't have a lot of
installation cost or cost in the balance
balance a plant that's required to uh
required to make these one thing I'll
point out is it's a very unique design
if you've seen many electrolyzers they
typically have big end plates bolt
circles retention rods and the like uh
our stack doesn't have any of that it's
compressed uniformly by the wrap that
goes over the top and consequently it
doesn't have any issu issues with torque
amongst the cells or having to retension
the rods over time because of
relaxation that means it's much easier
to maintain in the field and what the
what's the outcome from that well the
graph on the left shows you that uh as
you drop the cost okay so on the bottom
axis uh from above two to below two you
begin to open up a number of markets
which really can't be addressed by green
hydrogen as it exists today and that
means the scale of the market uh
increases dramatically and as you see it
uh scaled here we go from a few
gigawatts all the way up to uh 800 gws
and that's in a 2030 sort of time frame
because now you're able to compete with
hydrocarbon sources of hydrogen and also
produce at the scale that those
hydrocarbon sources can produce up and
then that opens up all sorts of
industrial hydrogen markets as mentioned
before uh the ammonia space uh in steel
making Etc all of these now have the
opportunity to be converted likewise you
uh by making ammonia or by making
methanol you can get into any number of
large range of uh energy transfer or
energy uh export sorts of projects the
scale of the projects now become bigger
because that can be done likewise you're
able to uh focus on uh making energy in
one part of the world and moving it to
another part and so in particular when
you look at places like uh the Middle
East North Africa south Asia
particularly India South America where
they have huge potential for uh for
example solar idance but they're so far
from the main markets for electricity
that they'll never be able to uh
commoditize that and turn it into a a
export uh uh product but now by being
able to make hydrogen with that
electricity and then make these
exportable products you're able to uh
recognize that one of the uh project
developers that we're working with has a
project in marania for 35
GW of um electrolysis capacity which is
more than all the electrolics capacity
installed to date so we're very excited
to see these kind of big projects become
uh possible realizable through this
technology in fact we recently closed
our first sale it's 500 megawatts uh for
a very large renewable energy producer
who makes uh ammonia will make ammonia
with it and that's a binding sale
contract it's not a letter of intent but
certainly there's money behind
it uh a few last thoughts here uh our
factories because they're high speed
they have a smaller footprint which
reduces building costs they have a lower
equipment cost as well what you see in
the graph on the left is the factory
cost per gigawatt per year of
manufacturing you see a Volo down below
20 uh dollars uh $20 million pardon me
per gigawatt whereas you see some of the
participants in the space uh cin and
plug power and the like who are much
more expensive typically it's around a
hundred million doar per gigawatt we'll
bring it in at a fifth of that cost
because it's very Compact and that
allows you to do that kind of vertical
integration where uh material comes in
one door and out the other door uh as
product very quickly a high uh
inventory turnover becomes an important
measurement of production cost and that
would allow us to be able to do negative
cash conversion Cycles in the long run
other words you get paid before you pay
for the raw materials uh and our
thirdparty assessments of this
manufacturing cost you see in the graph
here uh some of the uh markers are uh
hidden but anywhere from a 100 units so
100 electrolyzer Stacks per year to
10,000 electrolyzer Stacks per year you
see a very gradual drop off in that
manufacturing cost it cost you about two
and a half times here what it does cost
you here to make stacks and that means
you don't have to fully load the factory
before you're able to produce at a low
cost uh we have a single product this
one megawatt stack which we can build
into larger units uh in shipping
containers uh We've proven those stacked
material costs exceptionally low levels
and the third party uh some of you may
be familiar with strategic analysis who
did this for us and so what that means
when you break down the cost of the
stack uh we believe we can go to market
uh $200 a kilowatt and you see the cost
of materials and Manufacturing and
warranty in there which means there's
plenty of room to be able to to uh move
that and manage lower cost even going
forward uh just want to say something
quickly about our partners uh of course
our our lead investor the engine
Ventures they from the IM Community
breakthrough energy and Sapphire
Partners uh our development Partners
some of whom are also investors next AA
energy the largest renewable energy
developer in the americ perhaps one of
the largest in the world uh and we have
some exciting projects going on with
them uh 3M uh the guys who practically
wrote the book on Roll to- roll
processing so very exciting to be doing
some development with them and then
SoCal Gas who is very much focused on
using their gas grid for hydrogen uh
moving hydrogen hydrogen projects and
the like some of the things we're doing
now uh working on large scale commercial
uh Pilots multi megawatt scale Pilots
we're doing working with a number of
epcs on the engineering and balance of
plant design and then of course uh
talking to developers around the globe
to be able to bring these projects
forward and I think I brought it in
under time so kaarina I'll let you take
over thank you thank you very much art
for the presentation um we have few
questions for you as well um the first
one is a membran part of the innovation
of eolo or am is purchased off the shelf
from supplier okay that's that's a great
question uh we do not make the membrane
and we do not Source membranes from
other startups who make AMS and part of
the reason behind that is because their
startups they're developing a product
they typically don't have the quality
procedures in place that typically don't
have the scale to manufacture that would
allow us to do gigawatts per year I
think at the last the last count I heard
of is we're working with four different
multinational membrane manufacturers
lots of people have seen interest in
this place particularly with the issues
around the posos materials which are
used in the proton exchange membrane
electrolyzers and so consequently lots
of large membrane manufacturers are
wanting to get into this space we
evaluate those materials uh Our
intention is to go to market as a
membrane agnostic manufacturer which
means we can Source from a number of
parties and still deliver the same
performance and lifetime that um we uh
will warrant for our product okay thank
you um what are developers or epcs
demanding from oems like eolo and are
those demands being met
um so another great question one of the
things I touched on before was that
typically for electrolyzer manufacturer
they have a very limited warranty one or
two years defects and workmanship no
performance guarantee overtime or even
initially and so consequently when an
EPC builds a plant he has to wrap a
warranty around the entire plant that
promises the uh the project developer
the owner that it will use this much
electricity to make this much hydrogen
it will have a certain amount of uptime
the maintenance will uh be at a certain
cost and the The Limited warranties that
are typically issued in this field
become very challenging our focus is to
issue uh we're still working on the
details with an insur but we believe
we'll be able to go to market with a
lifetime warranty think like the
warranty you get on your automobile
tires of five to eight years when we put
our product in the market thank you um a
final question for you uh can you
clarify why several new sites say that
Supply is much higher than
demand uh yeah so uh that's a question
of uh paper capacity versus real
capacity so in the after 2020 2021 lots
of uh companies incumbents startups Etc
announced factories that they intended
to build but frankly because they're so
expensive most of those have not come to
fruition no one's even put a shovel in
the ground and so consequently that
capacity on paper looks quite
large but the reality is the actual
manufacturing capacity is quite limited
and I'll say this even in Volo we
announced a 3.75 gwatt per year Factory
in LEL Massachusetts which we intend to
start up in
2026 uh it appears in a lot of list of
factories even though uh we occupy the
site we have our development equipment
there I showed you a picture before with
the stacks that were at that site but it
does not manufacture at
3.75 kwatts per year today so we have to
be very careful and kind of put a jaist
eye on some of these estimates
because they take press releases and
tabulate from that and the vast majority
of those plants do not
exist thank you very much har and thank
you again prau for being with us today