I'm Mark Galer from Lincoln laboratory
uh and as I'll describe in a moment that
Lincoln laboratory is uh up in Lexington
of course we've had a long association
with campus as I'll describe um and
we're going to change gears here a
little bit uh and talk about next
Generation Computing uh but before I
begin uh want to thank Vladimir for
inviting us to to participate in the
Nano Summit where we're very honored to
do so uh of course we've collaborated
for decades uh with researchers on
campus uh but that has gotten more
engagement as Nano has been constructed
and we're looking forward to that uh so
I do have a couple of colleagues that
will dive into some details uh as we get
into the session uh so Ryan ke will come
up after I'm done and he'll talk about
our work on ferroelectric fets um so
Ryan has joined the laboratory about
four years ago he came to us from Intel
where he was working working on the 20a
uh process um he did his education at
Yukon and Penn State University and then
after that Alex WN we'll talk about our
work in superconducting electronics um
so Alex has been at the laboratory about
10 years and focused on superc conduct
electronics at whole time and he did his
education at Boston University in
vanderbelt so with that um I'll jump
into um Next Generation Computing and so
since this is the first time that
somebody's uh from lincol Laboratory has
talked at the summit I thought I'd begin
with just uh in my setup piece a little
overview of who we are at Lincoln where
we came from um and then how we
collaborate and connect with Nano uh
before we get into our more detailed
technical talk so the laboratory
actually has its origin in the radiation
laboratory that was on MIT campus during
World War II uh those you might not
realize that uh microwave Radars were
invented in World War II with the the
the British um about half I think 100 or
so Radars were developed uh at the rad
lab um they deployed about half of The
Radars that went into theater there um
at the end of the war they shut down the
radiation laboratory they wrote a series
of books that really defined the
foundation for microwave engineering um
and and that was it but then in the late
40s early 50s uh the Soviets had
developed a nuclear weapon and we were
concerned about them flying a longrange
bomber over the North Pole and so the
government came back to MIT and said hey
you did a great job for us in World War
II can you build a radar system for us
to protect the US and so we did um ended
up being the sage system it took about
seven years to develop um it was
operational from 1962 to 1983 uh
developed way or there was deployed well
over 100 radar installations with
communication networks Etc um so today
our mission has grown quite a bit in
where technology and support of National
Security and we have a number of mission
areas uh that are shown on the bottom of
the screen there uh so as I mentioned
we're out in Lexington Mass on hansam
Air Force Base uh we have about 2
million square fet of lab and office
space um we're about 4,500 employees and
we did $1.4 billion worth of research
last year um in our key roles are really
system architecture engineering so this
is like designing constellations of
satellites and how they would get used
um long-term technology development
sometimes we engage for decades with
some of our sponsors uh to develop
technology um but we're really
passionate about is system prototyping
and demonstrations and this is a great
example of of that so we developed or
matured a 3D liar uh system so this
image was collected over Boston uh so
from an aircraft that flew at 13,000 ft
and collected in under two minutes um
and so what makes this image different
from a typical image is that the imager
that we use um behind every pixel it has
a timing circuit so we can send out a
pulse of of photons from a laser um and
knowing the position of the aircraft and
the direction that the imager was
pointed we can collect the data back
because we have the time of flight
information and we create this 3D Point
Cloud U that we can then Traverse
through this and so this was actually
deployed for uh the Department of
Defense in Afghanistan and South America
but it's also been used by FEMA for
disaster relief after earthquakes and
hurricanes and the like um so a lot of
the Prototype systems that we build
actually rely on microelectronics and so
through the years we've developed very
capable microelectronics fabrication
capability and we sort of intentionally
position ourselves in this no man's land
as I'm showing here so you can kind of
plot research flexibility uh versus
process maturity and of course the
factories that make seos are highly
capable yet they're very adverse to any
kind of change in their process um the
universities on the other end of the
scale their job is to create new devices
and so they Embrace materials diversity
and and and Fabrication flexibility
however they typically don't have the
scale to create circuits that are going
to go into prototype systems so we
choose to be in this middle land uh so
that we allow a lot of materials
flexibility yet we have Quality
Management Services or systems in place
so that we can yield larger circuits um
so our facility we operate at 245 uh
there's about 60 people that are
dedicated to this um and we have uh
proper certifications for that
um and so how we connect with Nano uh is
is shown here that uh you know of course
Nano isn't a normal university uh clean
room it's uh much beyond that and part
of what's happening is that we're
installing 200 mimer tools um but all
the same that Nano is probably going to
be a little more focused on device
Discovery and and you know materials
research um on that 200 mm platform and
we're working out the process where we
can transfer Wafers back and forth where
we can take advantage of some of the
capability that we have at Lincoln
Laboratory um to do more routine
processing U mature those devices so
that we can get them into uh these
prototype systems that that we really
enjoy
building um so we uh work on a variety
of materials so we're definitely a high
mix low volume Fab um but we will work
at all stages of materials maturity uh
from component Explorations with
emerging fet technology uh to component
capability uh both opto Electronics as
well as Electronics devices and some
some prototype systems uh so we have
full flow processes with pdks and all of
that and you can get to us through Nano
we're sort of tied at the hip uh from
that respect and and we welcome
collaborations going forward okay so
with that as a little bit of
introduction let me set up uh the talks
that you'll hear next and so one of the
things that we like to do as we work on
Research is really try to understand
where it fits into the big picture and
so we've created this hierarchical model
for computation and of course our
computation systems are extremely
complex machines uh even though they're
micro scale um and but if we look at
what goes into one of these
computational systems uh that we see
that sort of at the foundation we decide
how we're going to encode the
information into a state variable what
kind of device we're going to use the
materials Etc um and then as we go up
into the stack we have different levels
of optimization what kind of um circuit
architecture are we going to use
computer architecture Etc and in the
Golden Era of scaling the dinard scaling
um that and it's sort of the 2000 time
frame that you know life was great all
the focus was at the lower part of that
stack U making significant progress
every couple of years with faster
processors more more transistors Etc and
so there really wasn't a lot of need to
optimize the higher end of the stack um
what we've seen in the last couple of
decades is that as that dard scaling has
slowed down or stopped um that we have
optimized our computer architectures uh
in terms of started with gpus and then
tpus and now we have uh AI processing
units and the like um but even so with
those optim we're starting to run out of
steam that we're having to create
nuclear power plants to power our data
centers for that um so it's our belief
that we can you know maybe now is the
time to start looking at the lower end
of that stack a little bit more and see
is there new technology or different
technology uh that we can use um to to
relook at that and reduce the energy
consumption of these computational
systems and so what we'll see in Ryan's
talk is a different type of seos
transistor that's based on ferroelectric
layer um in the gate stack uh for for
benefit um and then with Alex's talk on
the superconducting electronics we're
actually going to go all the way to the
bottom um and look at a different state
variable in terms of how we encode the
information um into the circuit and then
the material system will be different um
so with that I'll turn it over to
[Applause]
Ryan all right well good afternoon
really appreciate this opportunity to be
with you all and want and want to thank
all the organizers for the invitation I
think it's been a great Summit so far
and happy to be part of this um Next
Generation compute session um so I'll be
sharing some of thech technology that
we're working on at Lincoln laboratory
to help develop computer chips that will
function more akin to how our brain
functions and before I get into that
neuromorphic Computing and the
ferroelectric transistors that we think
will enable that I want to put up this
slide is just kind of a broad landscape
overview of the computer chip
Technologies so this is this technology
has continuous innovation at its core
right this is the technology of Mo's law
better performance every year um to to
improve our lives in a myriad of ways
and those Innovations they cut across
all the system hierarchy of these chips
so starting at the very building block
of our integrated circuits at the
transistor level we see the adoption of
new materials and new device geometries
in order to further the number of
transistors that we can fit onto a given
siiz
chip we look at interconnects today
we're seeing the separation of the the
power routing from the signal lines in
order to improve efficiency of the way
these chip operate like Mark said we're
seeing the introduction of new chip
architectures Al together so the
graphics processing unit that we see has
been been very popularized from Nvidia
um taking over giving more computational
throughput compared to what we used to
rely on just the standard CPU years ago
we're also seeing innovation in
packaging so adoption of chiplets 3D
heterogeneously integrated materials to
Advance the functionality of the chips
chips that we put into
field and um all of these Innovations at
the Leading Edge these are all going to
be leveraged and used to enable the most
computationally intensive technology
applications that face us today so from
the machine learning algorithms and
large language models that go toward
personalized AI patterned and image
recognition that would be required to
support autonomous vehicles for example
the drug in material Discovery what
proteins should we be synthesizing all
the way to our Edge devices our
distributed sensors that need to
transmit data to the cloud for
computation to be done and then get some
signal back on on next instructions to
to comprise the internet of things and
of course the chips that we that we
design for all of these
applications we want them to work as the
highest performance possible and the way
that we get more performance from the
chips that we design for those
applications is typically Al bought with
power usage and I think that can be
appreciated by just looking at this two
AIS plot the y- AIS is computational
throughput that these various chips that
are populating the graph kind of are
capable of delivering and you see that
if you want more performance you
typically get that with more power and
it's a tricky tradeoff especially as we
consider that today somewhere between 5
to 15% of the global energy production
is used for computation and this is
forecasted to rise very deeply as we see
more data centers come online and the
internet of things grow faster
still so we need we need a new paradigm
here we need a better way of getting
more performance for a given power
because the alternative is as Mark
alluded to you see some companies saying
oh we'll just make our own nuclear
reactors to power our data center and
that might work for some of the
centralized Technologies but until we're
all ready to sign up to have our own
personal nuclear reactor um we need to
come up with something more creative on
the on the device side and so to do that
I think it's instructive to consider you
know this line that defines the
performance you get for a given power
usage and this line is defined by the
Von noyman bottleneck this Von noyman
bottleneck gets its name from the Von
noyman architecture this is the
architecture that leading chips today
still use so if you were to delid the
latest Intel chip that's coming out this
month you'll find that you know there
are multiple tiles here there's a Wi-Fi
tile we have a graphics processing tile
up top some IO here but the biggest tile
on the chip is the
CPU and what we have here is an8 core
CPU you see the big cores around the
periphery of the CPU and all around
those cores are these different levels
of cash memory and the cash memory is
there to give the the logic cell that's
doing the computation easier access to
the data that's stored and there's level
one cache that's relatively fairly
accessible but as these technological
needs require more and more data to to
perform their
functions the logic cell needs to reach
further and further away physically
because the logic and the memory are
physically distinct components into
maybe the third level of cach memory or
the main memory that might be off chip
entirely costing 100 or 1,00 times more
an energy penalty to go get that data to
do an operation on this also accounts
for about 80% of the time latency in the
way modern chips operate and so what can
we do about this well if the issue is
that we have distinct uh functionalities
of our chips located in distinct areas
well let's just put them closer together
let's um improve the memory capacity in
those cache cells and indeed this is
what's done on those gpus so this is why
I have the GPU and the supercomputer
slightly above my Von noyman bottleneck
line because they're already doing this
they're getting the memory cell closer
and closer to logic they're developing
ways to make those level one caches
larger but there's that we can do better
yet if we take a queue from nature and
think about how our brains operate well
our brains actually do computation in
memory and so if we could not just put
the the computation um near the the
memory but actually enable the memory
cell to do computation itself well now
we're talking about a way to access um
highly High throughput highly efficient
chip architectures and if you want to
design this type of
in-memory uh logic cell there are a few
main things you're going to be looking
for one is low read and write energies
second would be fast read and write
times and the third is nonvolatility in
the architecture we don't want to have
to always apply power to this circuit in
order for it to keep its memory so we
really want the nonvolatility as well
and as you consider the spider chart
against um these very these variables
that would be attractive for embedded
non-volatile memory architecture this
ferroelectric Field Effect transistor
scores quite well across the board and
so what I'd like to do is you know we
understand the Leading Edge today but
what's coming tomorrow I think a very
attractive device is the next Generation
transistor of a ferroelectric transistor
and how this could enable Beyond Von
noyman architectures in memory
computation and potentially neuromorphic
compute chips so I'd really like to
introduce this F electric chip for
anyone who hasn't um heard of it yet uh
a ferroelectric material let me start
there is a material that exhibits a
spontaneous and reorient internal
polarization so a standard dialectric or
a standard insulator the center of
positive and negative charge on a
atomistic unit cell level are collocated
so there's no dipole that exists in a
insulator but a ferroelectric the center
the spatial Center of positive and
negative charge are physically separate
um and so there exist this spontaneous
dipole in the unit cell and the
interesting thing about fer electrics is
not only does a dipole exist but you can
indeed apply an external electric field
and switch the orientation and then that
unit cell will stay in that polarization
orientation until acted upon and you can
cycle these many many millions or
trillions of times they're very stable
materials they've been known for over a
hundred years however they've all it's
been only observed in material systems
that are not seos compatible or not very
seos compatible either in their
composition or their scalability that
was the case until around 2011 where
stable Fair electricity was identified
in doped hnea material systems so while
hafnia is a normal dialectric if you add
some dopen elements you can actually
stabilize Fair
electricity and so what I'm showing here
is haia being doped with zirconia where
both end members hafnia and zirconia are
normal dielectrics we see multiple
stable ferroelectric phases in the
intermediary and this is very enticing
now as you start to think about ways to
um include this spontaneous polarization
into computer chips because well by the
time this was discovered in 2011 hafnia
was already the gate oxide for
state-of-the-art devices and so you're
already halfway there if we could just
add some zirconia into that
compositional mix we could start playing
with this new mechanism at the heart of
the transistor right next to the channel
operation and indeed these different
phases of ferroelectricity are useful
I'm going to talk mostly about the
in-memory compute um capability with the
ferroelectric phase but if you start
pairing these together you can build
some very interesting gate Stacks where
I won't have the time today to get into
the details but I encourage you to look
at this paper that we worked on with
Professor Chima who's now MIT faculty
where we were able to take our 90 nanm
seos node it's a pretty mature node but
by integrating these halfa zerconia
super latus gate Stacks we were able to
demonstrate a two node advancement in
the transistor performance competing
with a 40 or even a 30 nmet transistor
node so yeah please do check out the
paper but I'm going to continue on now
with our in-memory compute theme um
thinking about how a ferroelectric
transistor could be built with this
material
first take a step back I'm sure a lot of
us are familiar with the transistor but
for those who aren't we're talking about
a device that it's a three- terminal
device so if we apply a bias from uh
whoops back if we apply a bias from
source to
drain um we would be providing a driving
force for current to flow through the
Silicon Channel but because silicon is a
semiconductor and kind of ground state
it's not a very good conductor of those
electrons that want to flow
so we would register a very low current
think nanoamps but by by applying a very
small signal to the gate terminal that's
what I'm plotting on this xaxis you'll
see many ordered magnitude increase in
the amount of current that's reaching
the drain um as the channel is inverted
and the Silicon becomes strongly
conducting so this is the general basis
of a transistor we can use these two
distinct states to store data perform
logic
operations and a like so what happen if
we put a ferroelectric right there at
the heart of the device as the gate
oxide well when a ferroelectric material
is uh initially grown it will typically
organize itself into domains that you'd
have offsetting polarization directions
so if you look closely here I have some
domains where the polarization is
pointed up and some where they're down
and they kind of go back and forth to
kind of find a nice equilibrium without
too much charge free energy to pay for
but like I said if you apply a voltage
across a
capacitor like the gate oxide for
example you can align all of these
dipoles such that all of the positive
charges would be facing maybe the bottom
of this capacitor as the gate oxide that
means you're putting positive charges
right near the channel interface that
attracts negative charges up in from the
silicon and effectively what this does
is it reduces the voltage required to be
applied to the gate in order to turn the
device on you can remove this voltage
and it will stay in this state and
function as a normal transistor with
this lower threshold
voltage alternatively you can switch the
polarity of the applied voltage reorient
all of the domains end up with a
positive charge at the bottom attracting
um attracting that kind of holes into
the channel and you'll see the turn on
voltage shift to a higher value and so
what we have is this reprogrammable
switch where we can put the device in a
low VT or a high VT State and Define
this memory window such that based on
however it's programmed we can later go
back and ping this gate with a given
read voltage and see if the bit is read
at low current or if it's at high
current and this is how this transistor
nonvolatile memory
works and and and because of this
functionality you know it's again very
attractive for inmemory
computation this is some data from
Global foundaries they have arguably the
most mature ferroelectric fet technology
this is not just a concept even though
I've only really shown schematics so far
um these devices are being built they're
being built at scale Global foundaries
has pretty high yield and repeatability
on these devices they're using a gate
first integration scheme and instead of
doping the haia with zirconia they're
doping with silicon nonetheless they
have a nice impressive memory window and
um through this gate first integration
scheme have shown some promising
circuits in University collaborations
using this device they've also been
ahead of the pack and identifying what
are the real challenges to really put
this device into high volume
manufacturing they're working on charge
trapping and endurance problems that
they've already been able to
identify we're also working on this
device at Lincoln Labratory and we're
taking a slightly different approach
we're using a replacement gate scheme so
this means we fabricate the device
nearly till it's about done you really
could call it done and make contact to
the device and use it as a transistor
but rather than calling it done we go
back and we open up and remove the gate
that was present the polysilicon that
was there that was serving as the dummy
gate terminal and the silicon dioxide
gate oxide that was there we clean it
all out and now we have an opportunity
to redeposit a special gate oxide a half
Neo zerconia gate oxide or any other
ferroelectric material that's of
interest and once we do this we can move
it right to the end of line make
contacts there's no more High thermal
process steps that might um disrupt the
functionality of those special layers
that were
deposited so with this technology we're
working on developing a full process
design kit that has all of the
parameters and design rules that would
be needed for a circuit designer to come
up with the ideas of how to actually use
this new device we haven't before had a
transistor that could have its threshold
voltage changed like this in a
non-volatile way how do you even use
that we're hoping to be able to set up a
mechanism where we can work toward um
finding the best Gat stack possible for
this type of
technology and kind of some early looks
at what can you even do with this um it
have already been published in
literature so Professor K who's a who's
a collaborator of ours is showing here
um on on on your left some very
efficient highly parallelized memory
cells where you could do this highly
paralyzed memory um using a standard SRM
circuit but it has a very large
footprint and it requires a whole lot of
power but nonetheless this is the
architecture that's used on server chips
and alike but by moving to a
ferroelectric Fed architecture you'll
see about a six order magnitude
Improvement in the energy and time
latency with a smaller footprint due to
the non-volatile nature of the
device another example here Professor
Bowen at Stanford is showing thinking
about neuromorphic Computing and
recognizing the spatial temporal
electrical patterns that our brain uses
in order to encode complex
information and um well there's a little
bit of Animation there but um you know
could we use the same type of spatial
temporal
signature and apply it across a varied
uh gate electrode and because we can we
have control over how much of the
polarization rotates with an applied
electric field with the fer
we can encode a very specific
um uh very specific conductance through
the channel based on the localized
dipoles that are in the ferroelectric so
we have this like secondary axis to
start encoding information and um
mimicking neural
networks so just to summarize you know
we think about these very
computationally intensive applications
and want to continue to find ways to
enable high performance at lower power
improve efficiency and we think that the
in-memory computation with ferroelectric
fets is is a great candidate we're
working on this in the microelectronics
laboratory just up the street MIT
Lincoln Laboratory um to support further
labto faab
transitions you know talked about the
Leading Edge and how ferroelectric
transistors could play into neuromorphic
architectures in the future but the
exciting thing is that there are a whole
host of um potential solutions to
advance the technology of computer chips
and um my my colleague Alex is going to
come up here shortly and and speak about
superconducting
Electronics as one of them um with that
I'll just thank you for your attention
and leave this here for a second just
thanking the collaborators from MIT UC
Berkeley Notre Dame and the whole entire
microelectronics team so thank you very
much
[Applause]
uh I'm Alex W I also work at Lincoln
laboratory I work on an even more exotic
technology than ferel electric uh
transistors although it's actually been
around a little bit longer and so in
some ways it's more mature and we're
building bigger circuits out of it um so
I'd like to tell you a little bit about
that so uh a little bit of the
background why bother with such an
exotic technology we're going to replace
semiconductors with
superconductors uh people have thought
this might be a good idea for for quite
a while you have as a quick refresher
semiconductors are terrible at
conducting electricity you can make them
a little bit better or a little bit
worse normal metals are pretty good
conductors but they still burn a bunch
of power and you have dual heating
superc conductors at DC don't burn any
power so you could set a little
circulating current in the super
conductor and it will sit there until
the end of the universe um so that that
might be a low power way to build
Electronics but how are you going to
practically do
that so there's a bunch of potential
applications I'm going to focus on
digital electronics which is sort of the
same theme uh as my colleague there's
also applications for things like RF
Electronics particle detectors and
Quantum information science um super
conducting cubits are sort of the
leading Quantum uh modality particle
detectors can be made all sorts of ways
superc conductors uh have uh this this
quick turn on that depends on
temperature so when a a particle hits it
you can get good energy resolution by
seeing how good of a superconductor it
is right at the transition temperature
and uh similarly in the RF domain
there's very low losses at high
frequencies okay so you know a little
bit about this uh energy of computation
is becoming enormous people are building
uh multiple nuclear power plants to deal
with it mois law is over dinard scaling
is over and so we might try to do
something different um so I'm going to
propose we jump to something as
different as possible let's just pick
the device that has the lowest
fundamental switching energy that we can
come up with uh so it turns out there's
this adiabatic limit uh known as the
land hour limit that says if you change
the amount of entropy in the universe by
sending two bits into a gate and
deleting one of them only one comes out
that costs KBT ln2 energy basically so T
is the temperature you're up you're at
KBT is uh related to the thermodynamic
system and okay these funny superc
conducting objects here we can build
parametric amplifiers that are
superconducting all the time and we just
use a nonlinear inductance in the
superconductor instead of even using
resistance we never even switch it
normal and we can get you know down to
KBT if we want to and we can build
things like adders that actually do
relevant
math um the second reason you might want
to go to superconductor Electronics
which is historically why it was
investigated for a long time although it
turns out there's it's it's a little bit
harder to find applications that benefit
purely from speed um
is that you can set you can set records
in the fastest switching technology so
if you want a digital frequency divider
you can make one it runs at close to a
terahertz if you want to make things
like G bet adders you can you can build
those that run at 100 gahz plus in
practice most of the world is limited
not by
single-threaded uh speed it's limited by
power and so I'm going to focus on
power all right so there's a lot of
recent progress over the last 10 years
or so that means that it's now possible
to build relatively large circuits um
whereas 10 years ago it was not and
that's why I'm here
now so if you look at say a 909m seos
Fab both of these Fabs exist within
Lincoln laboratory Lincoln has the
state-of-the-art in superc conducting uh
fabrication where we're building these
circuits you can compare to 90 nmet seos
Fab it's a similar stack uh similar line
width similar Edge tools similar depth
tools the main difference is that you
know number one we replace our metal
wiring layers with niobium which is a
super conductor transition temperature
is 9 Kelvin we operate typically at 4
Kelvin about the boiling point of liquid
helium uh and we replace our transistors
with something else called a Jose's
injunction which is essentially a weak
link that you can either switch just
long enough to uh emit one magnetic flux
Quant to to change out of the superc
conducting State just for a short time
um or my preference is to not switch it
at all and just use it as a nonlinear
inductor that depends on the amount of
current flowing G it uh so the the moral
of the story is that we get to repurpose
these older 90 NM seos Fabs and uh
dinard scaling would never existed for
superc conductors it's been long dead so
regardless of the size of the device the
power dissipated is the same so we don't
have to push to three nanometers or half
a nanometer uh to get attracted power
numbers which is another
benefit so
historically Dudley Buck invented the
catron at MIT in the 50s uh which is
basically an super conducting equivalent
of a transistor you wrap a wire around
the super conductor put enough current
through it and it kills it so you switch
between super and normal um for a long
time there was work on switching
superconductors between the normal State
and the super conducting domain you
still burn power when you're just a
normal metal and so there's you know
it's inherently never going to be quite
as efficient as being purely in the
superc conducting domain and you know
over the past number of years people
have moved to things like uh you know
Cupid Focus processes uh for simulated
in meing like d-wave um and we've moved
to never switching things out of the
superc conducting domain as well even
for classical Electronics to get the
lowest possible
power we've also pushed in scale so this
is to give you an idea that we can
actually build relatively large circuits
so this is a a shift register memory
people use these to kind of just
Benchmark processes and show that
there's no dead bits Etc um this W you
know held the record for quite a while
although I think DW's recent processor
is a little bit bigger at this point
it's near a million Junctions uh it's a
1 centimeter by 1 centimeter chip uh if
you can see the in the blowup picture
there's uh a couple of bit cells there
each one is Four J
injunctions and you know it's a 200
kilobit memory cell so we can we can
build things of of large and relevant
complexity and we've been scaling since
then so that was a few years ago and we
continue to scale on a quasi mors law
path although we don't get the benefit
of reduced energy you still want to get
to a scale that's large enough that you
can fit important things like multi-bit
parallel multipliers and adders Max we
want to build a processor that can do
something useful uh it has to be big
enough to have enough throughput to do
something useful and so over the past
several years we've scaled to you know
megabits per ceter densities which
starts to look relevant uh to folks who
design in
cosos and you can plot Wikipedia has a
JJ count page that compares us to the
mors law scaling transistor count page
we started a little bit behind we're
still a little bit behind uh but we're
trying to jump up the curve as fast as
we
can okay so now now that you know this
thing exists we can build megabit you
know per centimeter squared uh type
circuits we can build big parallel
multipliers Etc uh if you're somebody
who wants to design of this process how
do you do that in
practice so I'm going to Advocate that
you use this funny object here known as
a Quantum flux perimetron
uh it looks pretty similar to uh Cubit
design there's a couple of Jose's
injunctions so those little X's are
essentially nonlinear
inductors and it operates if you've ever
seen these old famous papers on
adiabatic computation and the there's
this beautiful adiabetic model that says
here's the lowest energy way to possibly
do math uh you take an energy level and
you don't uh just drop from one energy
State down to another one instead you
slowly move your system to a state where
two energy levels exist to one where
only one energy level exists and back
again and that's literally what we do so
we have this nonlinear inductance which
changes the energy state of the system
and effectively all you have to know uh
in designing this is that if you put in
positive current flowing from top to
bottom you can call that current level
one when your clock comes if it's a
small positive current it'll amplitude
it up to data level one so one micro
micr might come in 50 microamps will
come out if it's a small negative
current minus one microamp minus two
minus5 it's going to get Amplified to
minus 50 microamps out and it does that
because of this either change in the
energy landscape you can think of it as
or this kind of saturating nonlinear
inductance of the just
injunctions um and if you want to start
building math out of this you can build
majority Gates uh which just says if you
wire a few currents together maybe it's
plus one plus one and minus one two
cancel out plus one wins out gets in
simplified back to the data level and
this majority gate is a three three
input gate um and that plus inverter
gets you uh gets you any logical
function you
want so here's a couple of these uh bit
cells and some of our recent work on
this library and so we've designed these
Gates you can see uh at your left the
layout which is a you know zoomed in GDs
file which is the same same technology
used to fabricate C circuits you can see
the schematic
um and at my right your left you can see
uh memories that are built out of this
Quantum Flex parron based circuit done
with collaborators here uh at CBA on MIT
campus and we stored a bunch of data uh
and the impressive thing about these is
that they may not be as large as the
earlier
memories but the bit level energy is
about 10 - 21 jewles you know per bit
which is so this is s 24 KBT level
energies to store this
information and we started building
bigger things so that was a a little
three bit uh energy cell or three bit
memory cell uh and we've recently built
up to larger register files which looks
like the level one caches that you might
see in the stack of a of a computer core
as well as things like parallel
multipliers adders Etc built out of the
same cells uh and we have a pdk we have
a cell Library we have a lot of things
that we can share to make this easier
for uh digital designers and analog
designers in the real world to use them
as if they're sea
settlements so this is uh not from us
but from some of our friends one of whom
uh is just down the street at Atlantic
Quantum now who's historically at
Yokohama National University uh showing
that yes in fact you can build full
processors out of this that have uh
useful instruction sets and still
operate with this few KBT level energy
all
right so the the P section is what I
would argue is the most relevant
application building low energy
processors scaling these up tackling
this large scale energy problem using a
totally different technology um if you
wanted to do something different so
occasionally for things like DSP for
example you want to know uh you just
want the answer as fast as you can
possibly get it so you might want to
figure out how do I design a circuit
that operates digitally at 100 GHz uh in
that case what you can do is you can
actually switch the superconductor
there's a limit to how short of a time
you can switch it it has to be at least
one magnetic flux Quantum because
magnetic flux is quantized in superc
conductors and so you can put a little
shunt resistor that lets it switch just
for that long and then it ret trps um
and then you can take the little pulse
you've
generated looks like a current voltage
pulse it's about uh 2 molts times a PC
maybe 2 molts high PC wide and now you
can start do doing processing at NE
Herz um in order to do this because we
only have a two- terminal device uh what
you do is you store some information in
a local Loop and then you basically
sample and check with a clock whether or
not there's a one or a zero stored in
that
Loop and we can work all you know I can
give the examples for end Gates or Gates
Etc if you care later uh but the moral
of the story this is again this lets you
build everything you want and it
operates at a few hundred
gahz so here's an example
uh 8 bit serial letter uh one reason I
say in specific this is relevant to
things like DSP and less relevant to
things like CPUs is because if you want
to operate at about 100 gigahertz you
start to run into this problem that uh
if you have your memory over here and
you have your CPU over here the speed of
light unfortunately is only so fast and
it's it's not getting any faster and so
uh unless you know you think of a a
smart way to collocate these objects um
you know it takes SE some number of nanc
just to get back and forth between the
CPU and memory and so it's it's
essentially impossible in the typical
Von noyman sense to operate a CPU at
these speeds uh people try to do things
like pipelining um but that only works
even in theory to you know some number
of logical pipeline stages and it gets
slower and slower so there's but you can
still build things like adders
multipliers uh lots of DSP
related problems including things like
Matrix math that people care quite a bit
about all right what
next so my hope with this is to
introduce all you folks who might be
smart electrical engineers computer
scientists Etc to this uh unusual
technology it's relatively mature in the
fabrication space but there is an
enormous amount of innovation in the
computer architecture space how to
encode information how to process
information what to do with extremely
low energy computer
processors um and there's you know
significant active work um in the design
of all of these elements and it's
scaling quickly so over the past uh five
seven years or so we've brought up this
process uh we call it sfq 5e single flux
Quantum uh e for energy efficient and
we've had collaborators at many many
places uh over 300
Publications uh co-authored using this
process uh and I hope that perhaps uh we
could encourage some of you to to submit
as well and help solve this some of the
interesting problems in this
field okay thank you Alex so why don't
we take a few questions
okay so before we get to some of the
questions from the audience um why don't
I start with sort of a question from
each of you uh or for each of you on
what do you see as the top one or two
things that are really holding back to
mature the technology that you're
working on start with Brian and where's
it going what is the goal that you see
next and what are the the top one or two
things to prevent you from getting yeah
it's it's
there are a number of so for ferel
electric fets um there are a number of
of challenges and things that we'll need
to continue to do in the development so
this is a new uh device that's kind of
been prototyped there's still a lot of
issues to work out in terms of endurance
reproducibility and avoiding like kind
of killer defects that have all been
sorted out on Advanced Coss nodes but
now introducing this new material you
have to kind of go back and understand
you know what are causing some of these
new defect modes and and circuit
failures and how do we engineer around
those I think there's still questions
you know what is the actual correct and
best gate stack to use um um but I I
think there's a path forward on on most
of these questions for f electric fets
okay so some question you ask yeah I
think for superc conductor Electronics I
I so there's a lot of work still in the
computer architecture space and then you
know what's the smartest way to encode
information what's the smartest way to
you know at the viice level and then at
intermed intermediate levels of the
hierarchy you know one uh long-standing
problem in this field was how to make
dense enough uh memories such that uh
the Fab area isn't totally dominated
just by memory area your logic's very
efficient um I personally think we have
probably solved these problems uh or or
a couple of things in the pipeline will
solve this problem and I the secondary
problem is is just that Hardware
development in general takes some time
right you know you design a chip that
takes you maybe a month or two to figure
out how to do that and get it to the
state that it's uh clean enough you can
go into Fab and you're pretty sure that
it's going to work if it's a large scale
chip and then you know fabrication takes
a few months and testing takes a month
or something like that and so you know
at this point we're at the scale of
multi-bit parallel multiplies and things
like that and I think you know one or
two iterations from them is is large
scale processor so I I think we're not
too far behind but that time constant is
relevant okay thanks um yes so let's
take one from the audience do Legacy
architecture such as seos limit the
potential of new materials such as
ferroelectrics in microelectronics is
there a balance between Progressive and
disruptive design
here right so I mean the way I kind of
see this playing out I think I think the
right approach is to be as disruptive as
possible in University settings and in
laboratory settings and the industry
will kind of
um pick out and and define the
Progressive way to integrate them at
scale um the good thing about seos is
especially at this phase it is a mature
technology we understand the physics
quite well we understand the
architectures quite well there are many
modalities of architectures now where
maybe integrating new materials on a
nanowire device at 18 angstroms is
really hard but oh if we put this in at
45 nmet or a 90 nmet node we can unlock
new capabilities that even those very
highly Advanced chips don't have that's
one of the approaches you know with this
ferroelectric fet it's it's going to
enable new capabilities this
non-volatile memory element doesn't
exist in in the same way in current seos
architectures so it is a new device to
be considered in addition to transistors
capacitors and resistors that we can now
build into circuits and and think about
how you know that in my opinion
Progressive change of just adding
another element to the gate stack how
that Progressive change can actually
deliver some disruptive outcomes yeah so
just to dig into that a little bit more
are there examples now of um inmemory
compute architectures maybe with
volatile device as opposed to a
nonvolatile device that at least the
architecture is proven and are there the
expected decrease in energy consumption
yes yes so um the way that kind of in
memory comp compute circuits are built
today is with static random access
memory and it is possible but it's uh
very power inefficient there's a huge
power draw because you're having to um
in parallel power at least you know
16 transistors in order to just do one
bit of operation in that cell so if you
start multiplying that out and you need
to power all of these uh circuits in
parallel it's something that you can do
on a on a data center scale something we
can't do on any Edge device right so in
some sense the architecture is proven
it's just that the device technology
hasn't caught up to the potential for
that architecture yeah I I think that's
right that you're Marrying an
application and a demand to kind of a
new way of doing it that's more energy
efficient okay and so now if we pose the
same question to Alex so here of course
you're you know wiping the SL clean so
to speak starting with the new state
variable and all the way up um but you
know the computational Paradigm that has
been matured with the seos underpinnings
is very powerful and so yet we don't
want to abandon that so how do we marry
this disruption with the goodness of the
M the mature seos ecosystem yeah I think
superc conductors are exotic enough that
um it's important to keep the highle
system architecture you know somewhat
similar to seos so that people can still
you know so that
the uh machine code that your C compiler
sends to still things like do a multiply
do an add go you know retrieve something
for memory just to limit the barrier to
entry you know that being said the
lowlevel circuits uh you know in many
cases are are implemented totally
differently even in this in this case of
a a memory I think a great example is um
superconductors because they are quite
low loss in data transmission so if if
you you know switch something just long
enough to create one uh one single flux
Quantum pulse it could go around in
circles uh with quite little loss in a
superc conducting wire and so it turns
out that delay line memories in superc
conductors are extremely dense and
efficient uh whereas you know they
historically actually existed in some of
the earliest computers back in the 50s
60s uh using acoustic delay line
memories with Mercury tubes and things
like this um but in superc conductors
again there you know some of these
unusual architecture choices that
existed back when we had other materials
make sense again um to the to the folks
that eventually have to write P torch
code and and you know run models on
these things that should be abstracted
away but I think there's a lot of room
for architectural innovation in superc
conductors okay thanks
so how much would the helium Supply
limit the expansion of superconducting
computing is there a more readily
available high temperature alternative
uh
so we do have some systems that rely on
a awful lot of helium some of the
accelerators large particle accelerators
rely on superconducting magnets and
there's an awful lot of liquid helium
that goes into those systems uh to cool
them down um so I don't know the details
on this but helium is limited resource
um and I imagine if we wanted to get to
a paradigm where all of our data centers
relied on liquid helium because the most
efficient way to cool these systems is
actually to embed all of the circuitry
in a bath of helium and then as it boils
off you reliquify it and that's the most
efficient way to cool these down however
there are some
closed circuit systems uh that that
don't require that liquid helium uh and
and they're a little more efficient yeah
at at data center scale the helium
reification plants that are used for
particle accelerators is they're like
essentially the same thing same same
power draw um those could be used that's
convenient because somebody already
built all this infrastructure and
there's infrastructure for Clos cycle
helium C coolers all the way down to uh
you know a couple hundred mows of
cooling at 4
Kelvin which you know is like a rack
mount box you can buy from M yeah so so
they're so yeah so so right now there
are solutions to it and we're not helium
limited I think even at the scale of a
couple of enormous data centers we would
not be limited this sort of comparable
to particle accelerators that you know
that said there is uh additionally a
path which looks maybe a little bit more
like the more law scaling path so we we
don't have Denard scaling smaller
devices don't get more efficient uh but
if we go up in temperature devices do
get more efficient because cryocoolers
do worse and worse relative to Carno or
perfect efficiency the colder they get
um and so we're working on materials
like nium nitride folks are working on
nium Ty nitride and there's paths you
know potentially to things like some
demos have been done even ybco at 77
Kelvin um so there's a path to continue
to go to higher and higher temperature
superc conductors
uh which also improves our Energy
Efficiency and reduces Reliance on
things like liquid
helium
right okay so I don't know that I
understand this top question how can the
comp human computer be applied to Next
Generation Computing to prevent excess
energy consumption is
it I'm not as good at Matrix multipli as
in my head as
a as an Nvidia h100
unfortunately so so maybe you know but
that's an interesting architectural
question what what am I what am I doing
that the h100 is not maybe we can
reframe all the problems and I can just
uh un chat gbt for you yeah it is
interesting you you look at the image
recognition speech recognition that
we're all capable of it's pretty
impressive if you compare that to the
power that's required compared to the
h100 from Nvidia and we're doing it on
like 20 watts and so I think it is
instructive to look to biology and sort
out you know what's going on here what's
the piece that we're missing in the way
that we currently design
architectures um and circuits and I
think it's it's very exciting research
of nor morphic Computing um dendritic
learning all of these are very
interesting Pathways and um I think we
have we need creativity
um it's attractive to stay in the same
line of thinking with seas because
there's so much industry behind it but I
think the more creative we can be to
come up with new ideas on how actually
fabricate novel circuits that may mimic
um the way our brains work you know we
might be able to make these energy
efficient advances yeah my this so this
is like a little bit out there uh but
I'll just throw it out for fun my
understanding more or less of of of why
things like biological systems are very
efficient is because you know all right
in a normal digital system you have some
Channel and you know Shannon's Channel
capacity theorem says we want if we want
to put as much information on that
channel as possible we should encode
digital information just ones and zeros
um but if you want to send the same
amount of information with less energy
cost then you can send you can use more
symbols and so you could use like a
unary code where you only send a bit
once in a while and you know it's sort
of time bin coded so that that sparse uh
information codes lots of bits at once
and so in big 3D networks you actually
have lots more Channel capacity than you
need and so you can very sparsely encode
your information and you know people I
think even from the sort of neural
network perspective sort of believe that
sparsely connected 3D networks are much
more efficient than uh than densely
coded networks or 2D networks so I I
think that's sort of where it comes from
it's hard to replicate that in
microelectronics so uh but maybe we can
think of ways to sure well so sort of on
that theme um question these two
technologies are still rooted in digital
Computing do we think that analog
Computing will play a role in the future
for example materials that
perform Matrix Vector
multiplications so uh yeah I can I can I
can note that talk to that a little bit
uh thing number one is that the most
expensive part of this Computing is
still things like memory access uh and
it's important to get dense memory as
close to your processing uh to minimize
overall you know energy cost to talk
between these two objects um so it turns
out actually in this in this qfp case
that thing I showed you this majority
gate uh we think of it as a three input
digital majority gate but if you
actually send uh amplitude coded data uh
you can get like a 4- bit multiply
accumulate out of that same object for
for free the downside of that is okay
now you have an extremely cheap multiply
accumulate but it's still just as
expensive to get data from the memory
and that already costs you 10 times more
than doing that bit level uh single bit
majority gate and so the in contrast I
would say where analog uh coding could
potentially be used uh would be things
in like for example L line memories like
un coding is very easy to use in that
case where we decide where are we going
to store the pulse uh and and time code
that right now we're again still limited
by density and so uh that's not the the
most efficient way to use it but if we
end up you know where we have more
channels than we need that would that
would be another way to push energy for
sure yeah yes so I think just going back
to that hierarchical model for
computation that sure analog Computing
is interesting I think it is useful for
some classes of operations um or or
computations and you know there is you
know as we look higher into that that
stack uh more know the so-called domain
specific accelerators where if you're
willing to limit the types of problems
you want to solve with your computation
system you can tailor that stack to be
very efficient for those and so there is
a lot that we can trade and doing analog
computation is certainly one of those
trades doing Quantum computation is
another but what you're giving up is the
generality of what that machine can work
on um and the reason the Von Norman has
been so successful is that it is so
versatile uh but but as we learn you
know we need to get beyond that for some
of these harder problems that we want to
solve yeah I I might add one thing it's
interesting to think as when I showed
that dted Intel chip and they're already
doing
multi-tile um chips and this is getting
toward that 2.5d
integration this is interesting to Think
Through you as we think about the
architectures that are married together
through chiplet integration you could
think about having a Leading Edge chip
in the digital form factor have
integrating analog compute RF compute
all in the same um platform and so I
think that these various approaches will
start integ together and it won't be
this or that but we might have many
capabilities on on one chip on one
package
okay so there was a question um so maybe
I'll just pick up from the do we think
the Next Generation Computing is startup
friendly sector um maybe it is tough
Tech right uh I think that
there's certainly some possibilities um
it probably needs a few more years of
maturation uh some kind of a Foundry
process into what you could design but
there's certainly lots of opportunity uh
in this space especially the
superconducting uh electronic space
that you know it has received so little
attention compared to what the seos
architecture or a paradigm has that
there is lots of room for Discovery and
innovation
that I think could revolutionize the
field there's anything Yeah Yeah from
the from the Fab side super Condor
Electronics is probably a little bit
lower barrier to entry than than Coss
because we're dealing with sort of 99
meter Fab nodes at this point and we
don't have um an energy requirement to
push to you know dense subnanometer Fab
nodes um on the seos side I think there
are plenty of people who work um you
know an architecture level innovations
that tape out to tsmc Etc and and that's
you know maybe within the seos domain
but in some cases people have uh used
seos processes and and somewhat new ways
so yeah yes so maybe with that we'll
conclude the session by saying first
we're very pleased to be part of the the
Nano Community um not a lot of people
know about us up in in Lexington but um
you know we're very accessible uh very
much want to collaborate with startups
with you know researchers with companies
um so uh we have lots of different
mechanisms that we can use to do those
collaborations uh so um please you know
let's let's engage if you have some
ideas um in in any ways that you can
imagine so thank
[Applause]
you for