So, I'd like to say um I mentioned I'm
leaving. Uh 10 years ago, I was
fortunate enough to work with Kim on
what was uh the US government announced
17 innovation in manufacturing
institutes. Uh and Lionel spearheaded
the one on photonix and as a result MIT
won and it's uh currently one of the
most successful AIM. Photonix is one of
the innovation manufacturing institutes.
So, thank you. That's a good answer to
that question.
>> Exactly.
All right. Our next speaker
have my notes here. Uh is Professor
Donna Freriedman. She is the FG Keys
Professor of Chemistry at MIT and the
inaugural director of quantum at MIT.
The university's hub for advancing
quantum science and technology.
Professor Freriedman is internationally
recognized for her pioneering work in
molecular quantum materials and for
driving collaboration across
disciplines, another theme of ours
today, to accelerate quantum discovery
and innovation. Today she'll share an
overview of the MIT Quantum Initiative,
highlighting how it's shaping the future
of quantum research, education, and real
world impact. Um, I'd like to say we
have a network break after this, but
I've canceled it for a pop quiz on all
things quantum, so pay attention.
>> [applause]
>> Is someone gonna wire me up?
Um, okay. So, why don't I get this set?
Um, we will not be cancelling the
networking break. Just to be clear about
that.
Uh, you know, I used to teach general
chemistry. Um, and for nine years I
taught general chemistry. Honestly, it's
the most rewarding teaching that I've
ever had. But the one piece of negative
feedback I got that was consistent was
that I wasn't loud enough. And so I
dealt with this in a way I felt was
appropriate, which is I had the TAs use
caution tape to tape off the entire back
of the classroom so everyone had to come
closer to me. Um, I felt that was a
great way to use feedback from teaching
evaluations in a constructive way. Okay,
so now that I'm miked up and we have
slides, thank you. Uh, what I'm going to
do is give you a broad overview of our
new initiative. um formerly called
quantum at MIT renamed cumit by the
amazing MIT branding team. Um and so
this is the MIT quantum initiative. I'll
tell you how I'm thinking about this
initiative and a few things that we're
going after and ideally I'll leave
significant time for questions. This
overall will not be a technical talk but
I would be delighted to talk about the
technical aspects of this. What I'd
really like to use my time to do is to
frame out this initiative and talk about
how it's different than other quantum
initiatives that are uh rising up around
the world. So,
oh this is I guess not okay. We're just
going to do this. Um okay, so let me
begin by talking about how I see quantum
and how we're framing this current
quantum revolution. So the way that I
would frame it broadly speaking is the
first quantum revolution a 100red years
ago was about observing the quantum
nature of the universe and over a
hundred years we've moved from
observation to control. Now
how are we controlling it in a wide
selection of manifestations? So here we
have um four idealized areas and of
course networking is the subject of um
this session. But we can think about
quantum computers and how quantum
computers can solve certain classes of
problems quantum sensors, quantum
networks, quantum metrology, etc. And
the thing that we're focused on in the
MIT quantum initiative is the problems
that those things relate to. So MIT has
been superlative at tool building. On a
later slide, I'll show you the MIT
quantum network that connects from MIT
to Lincoln Lab that is built on the
fiber [clears throat] optic cable and
many of the things that we're familiar
with. But what I would argue is that MIT
solves hard problems and in the quantum
space the tool development is
accelerating rapidly. But the hard
problem is functionally identifying why
do we care and bringing together the
people who have problems that can be
solved by quantum and the quantum tool
developers in a co-design approach. And
so this is what we're focused on. We're
focused on developing quantum
interconnects. were focused on thinking
about what are the new algorithmic
problems beyond Shor's algorithm that
quantum computers will be useful for and
what is the user space beyond this and
so we're building our core tool set but
we're also very focused on creating this
additional layer around our core quantum
technologies.
So this is a um graphic in progress
illustrating some of how important this
is when we think about every aspect of
quantum. And so this is where we're
going in the future. Let me spend one
slide on the past. Um MIT's excellence
in quantum is beyond reproach. This is a
photograph from Endicott House. And one
could argue that this is the start of
and indeed the Endicott House website
does that this is the start of the
second quantum revolution. And so we've
all seen the photo with all of the men
from the first quantum revolution. And
this is potentially the analog. If
you're interested in the people in the
photo, the QR code will give you all of
their names, but it will not give you
the name of the dog. Um and so what does
it mean that this is where we started
the second quantum revolution? Well, the
idea that we could use quantum to move
from tools to function is something that
was scattered.
You can argue a revolution is what
happens when the scattered ideas
coalesce into a single constructive
movement. And so this is probably the
historic moment over 40 years ago when
this happened.
And today MIT has continued in its
excellence. We have quantum computing
and algorithms. I probably don't need to
tell you all about um how MIT is leading
in neutral atoms and in superconducting
cubits which are two of the best
candidates for quantum computers. Um we
have also led the way in applying
quantum tools towards challenges. One
could argue that LIGO is the best
example of success for quantum sensors.
quantum sensors detected gravitational
waves and that's a great example of the
type of problem that we want to solve
identify we want to know something in
the universe what are the tools that we
need to build that we need them to be
very delicate and then this elaborate
construction process between scientists
and engineers across many forms of uh
intellectual spaces led to the detection
of gravitational waves with a quantum
tool more relevant to networking I would
say that the development in clocks um by
folks like uh Vladon pictured somewhere
there is um a really important area.
Where is Vladen? He must be in
simulation. There he is next to Wolf
Gang. Um so
these are areas that are rapidly
emerging. MIT has also been great at
translation. Cuera and Atlantic Quantum
are two quantum companies that have come
out of MIT. Among many, Atlantic Quantum
was just bought by Google. Um, and Cuer
is making the news every day uh with uh
their neutral atom quantum computers.
One of the largest efforts right now in
our quantum initiative is this new
building project. And so, let me just
tell you a little bit about it.
Everything I've talked about in terms of
co-design and bringing people together
relates to how we also structurally
co-design the elements. Um, and this is
something very similar to a lot of the
networking infrastructure that we talked
about. And so if we talk about quantum
networks, there are a lot of
applications that are frequently
discussed. But let me talk about my
favorite application. My favorite
application for quantum networks is
networking different components of a
quantum system together so that we don't
need a quantum classical interface.
Interfaces are always the problem. And
so if we want to I'm a chemist so I
think interfaces are always the problem
but I think that they're a large
challenge in quantum. If we want to
process our quantum information and then
for example get a sensor to extract data
from the real world and signal process
that if we have to go through multiple
classical interfaces will effectively
lose the power of these quantum systems.
So what we're thinking about with this
system is creating an allquantum
ecosystem. And if we could create an
allquantum ecosystem, this would be a
first um type of system. And so this is
how we're thinking about building it
out. Now, of course, to mirror the
previous talk, the key ingredient here
are interconnects. We need to keep
everything in a single quantum space. If
you ask some companies, interconnects
are most useful for networking dilution
fridges to make larger quantum
computers. I think that's very important
too and I think that but I also think
that that's a clear path forward that we
will invest in regardless right quantum
interconnects are important everybody's
working on quantum interconnects to
integrate different quantum computers
together considering all quantum
ecosystems where we add in sensors and
other components and our quantum system
isn't a quantum computer it's a quantum
computer a quantum network a quantum
sensor that enables us to have new
knowledge about the world around us,
whether that's a biological solution
where we're looking at an enzyme or a
material where we're looking for subtle
differences. Uh, for example, you could
say hotspots in a battery. So, in all of
these applications, keeping the
information quantum is very important.
Okay, perfect. I'm just going to end
with our leadership structure. Jon
Yotter from uh Lincoln is missing from
this. This morning uh we got official
confirmation that we can add her. You
know what Lincoln is like. Um so that
took a little bit of time. Um and I also
want to advertise our launch event. We
have a bunch of amazing speakers
including the director of IBM research,
a couple of Nobel laureates, um my dean
in the school of science, um
Eric Lander, uh who will talk about
early adoption of quantum techn of
technologies globally, not quantum. And
so I think I left some time for
questions, which is most of what I'd
like to do here. So it thank