so welcome everybody and may I start
with using the word wow I did not expect
for this event we would have about 500
people show up so thank you for spending
your afternoon or evening depending on
how you define it for us uh in the
inaugural fireside chat um with the CTO
of open AI Mira morati and this is the
opening Fireside chart for Circ which is
an important pillar of the College of
computing uh that is about social and
ethical responsibility in
Computing and uh we have here the
inaugural Dean Dan Hatten Locker who
will say more about the college but this
is one of the three important pillars of
the college which has a truly
interdisciplinary goal to bring faculty
and students across all five schools
together and think about these issues
both in research but also our goal is to
have these issues addressed in every
single classroom at
MIT the long-term goal is hopefully as
MIT we will be able to influence policy
in this space both in the US and
hopefully
worldwide before moving on and
introducing Dan I think I want to
mention a few Logistics
first the first part Dan is going to
have a conversation with
mea and for the first about 45 minutes
and then we invite you to go to
slido.com and scan the QR code that you
just uh saw on your screen use firesight
uh- chat f23 to submit your questions
and done live would actually be
discussing your questions with me
on that note it is a real pleasure for
me to introduce Dan Hatten loer who is
the inaugural dean of the Schwartzman
College of
computing we actually brought him back I
should say here from Cordell Tech where
he basically was uh was helped found
Cordell Tech which was about digital
technology and oriented to graduate
school in New York City he was the first
Dean and the Vice Pro most and actually
he came back because he received both
his Masters and his PhD from MIT so it's
wonderful to be able to work with him
and his Deputy Dean ASAS daglar and
before actually uh leaving the floor to
him I also want to introduce my partner
in crime Casper hair from the philosophy
Department who is the other associate de
[Applause]
forer and I also want to extend a big
thank you to Corey Harris who's been
running around helping us with this and
Terry Park Yumi and all the people that
are making this possible on that note I
think we want to listen to Dan and ver
thank you
Dan so I'm I'm really delighted to have
this opportunity for us to speak today
with mea Mara thank you so much for
joining us Mira um I put together a few
questions for our discussion at the
beginning that were informed already by
things that people in the audience had
sent at the time that they registered uh
but let me just quickly give a a little
bit of a quick bio here for people
although I think you don't really need
much of an
introduction um so Mir is the chief
technology officer of open AI uh the
company behind chat GPT and Del she
leads the company's research product and
safety teams which work together to
create safe and Powerful AI that
benefits humanity and has a positive
impact on the world mea and her team are
pushing the frontiers of AI of what the
of what AI can do aiming to make it
safer and aligning with human intentions
and values uh I wanted to say a little
piece about meera's career path and I'll
come back to that at the end of my
questions because uh I think for all of
the students in the room here that's uh
that's uh it's it's quite interesting so
she managed the product and Engineering
teams at Leap Motion led the design
development and launch of vehicle
products at Tesla including the model X
and uh also was involved in Innovative
programs in Aerospace and she earned her
bachelor's degree in engineering from
the dart myth School of
Engineering uh so with that uh I thought
I'd you know start with a few questions
here and the first thing M I just wanted
to give you a chance to comment on a
little bit maybe to sort of level set
the audience was just uh you had quite a
number of announcements this week uh and
um you know so maybe maybe we'll focus
on on on the on the GPT Builder
interface and sort of uh really sort of
a platform for creating your own chat
GPT including for people with no coding
knowledge although that shouldn't be a
problem in this room uh and and sort of
how you're thinking about that with
respect also uh to pray paying creators
uh for their work since that seemed to
also be a a piece of what you were
talking about with the with the GPT
Builder hi everyone can you hear me okay
yep that's great thanks well thanks so
much for having me very excited to be
here um so yeah as you know we have
first day event on Monday
and announced a lot of new things on
thep but also a new prodct like you
mentioned were calling TOs and it's
really you know a step in this direction
of building um agents that that um help
help us collaborate um and basically
teach us really how to collaborate with
AI system and they're going to be
everywhere you know in our uh creative
spaces in our U um you know Works spaces
and really I think something that we
won't be able to leave without um but
imagining future where you know the
systems are everywhere and operate
autonomous ly is both really amazing but
comes also with a lot of um risks and
trepidations and so we need to move
carefully towards that world and try to
understand um iteratively what it looks
like and build a more robust reliable um
and thoughtful path as it's going to
have a lot of implications for society
and so we want to make sure that this
journey towards a world where agents are
you know everywhere um AI agents are
everywhere is
one that is allows for continuous
adaptation to this technology um and so
in our strategy of iterative deployment
we decided to roll out the first
iteration and learned from how people
are using um the gpts and what they're
doing with them and just in the first
couple of days um we have seen a lot lot
of fun and creative uses of it um a lot
of attention On Tools like browsing and
Del so it's just all really fun to
see so I'm gonna I'm gonna already go
off the script of the questions I had
prepared just because when you were
mentioning uh you know sort of
collaboration of humans and and
gpts uh this is this is something that
uh some of us at MIT have been spending
quite a bit of time thinking about out I
think often today's AI is framed sort of
as AI replacing people and if you go
back all the way to
1960 uh uh you know long before pretty
much everyone in this room except me
probably was
born and including on the zoom I'll
include you in the room era uh um jcr
lick lighter at MIT actually was already
postulating that the real value from
machine intelligence was going to be
that the collaboration of humans and
machines would produce results that are
better than either one alone and so uh
and so I think uh just be great to hear
your your thought you know since you're
now really sort of starting to focus on
collaborations and and tools for people
really collaboratively creating these
interactive things just is that changing
your framing from you know sort of AI as
a simulation of people to you know sort
of replace them to something as a really
collaborative tool where we're trying to
get better outcomes than from AI by
itself or people by
themselves yeah I think you
know for a significant period of time
we're talking about
collaboration with AI this hybrid
interactions and um really using AI
systems as tools to elevate us and uh
you know in our day-to-day job but also
in our creativity and you know maybe not
everyone wants to work 40 hours a week
maybe some people want to work 5 hours a
week and so like making things like that
possible that maybe before we not um but
I really believe that we can have this
future where for quite some time AI
systems are tools that we collaborate
with and then at some point you know
they will get Advanced enough and um
there is a question of you know how
exactly we interact with these AI
systems and what do we want them to do
and what do humans focus on um but I
think for quite some time the goal is to
give people access to these tools and
make it very easy to use them and it's
great if you can program but if you
cannot program then you should just be
able to program in natural language and
that's what people can do with gpts so
we showed demo on Monday where a few
demos actually where just in a couple of
minutes you can program gbts and natural
language to assist you with various
tasks and that's what we want to be able
to do to bring the powers of
um U this these superpowers to to humans
um and anyone can just you know build
these tools and use their creativity
they can prototype stuff very quickly
communicates with um team members like
you know designers or product managers
can communicate their ideas very easily
to the engineering team they can iterate
very quickly um so that's sort of how I
imagine the DAT to interactions to be
and you know in a way we're already
there in the way that we use CH GPT or
um you know code interpreter or uh
co-pilot that we launched a couple of
years ago in CL collaboration with
GitHub um so I think these are some good
examples that give you a sense of how
we're already collaborating and working
with the systems and then there is a
question of you know over time how much
do we
delegate and um the nature of the tasks
possibly becomes more and more abstract
um but for now I think we're really
automating the part of that's kind of
repetitive of our tasks and and also
helping using this these tools to help
with
brainstorming um or usually I Define it
as like the first step of any particular
thing that you're doing whether you're
an accountant or analyst or a consultant
or a designer it's really that like
first step um that the AI systems can be
quite helpful with today
great thanks so I'm going to go to some
of the uh things that came in uh
beforehand from people in the audience
and I had a chance to review and try to
kind of group together in some quasy
coherent way so uh so we seem to be in a
world of you know sort of AI optimists
on one extreme and AI pessimists on the
other uh where do you place yourself in
that and how does that affect your
leadership at open
AI um I'm definitely optimistic in
general and I think it's very important
to see to have a sense of
possibility and optimism because you
know things have a sense of being
self-fulfilling as well um and it's
important to have belief and faith that
things are going to go well but not I'm
not saying that one should be optimistic
uh
blindly
and with that optimism comes also you
know a large degree of preparation and
being quite I'd say cleared eyed and
open eyed about all the challenges ahead
and there's you know a set of immediate
urgent challenges that we're facing as
we're releasing these Technologies and
trying to make them as accessible um as
possible but also you know
predicting the capabilities and risks um
as we're
preparing to train more and more capable
models
and I think the the foundational thing
uh kind of in the medium term is really
building the science of prediction and
we did this with with with gbd4 and
we're betting more and more on this
understanding how to predict the cap
abilities of the models that we are
building and with that also preparing
for red teaming preparing for the risks
ahead and how to mitigate um the risks
that are brought along with more
powerful capabilities and it's sort of
like you know I would call that like
kind of medium-term risk or as as we go
from urgent things to more more
long-term uh capabilities and then in
the far end of course we're facing
questions around um catastrophic risk
and you know the systems that are
self-improving and extremely capable and
so how do we get ahead of that what do
we need to understand what kind of
research do we need to be doing today to
be prepared for this um
unknowns and we've you know at open and
I we've invested quite a bit in what we
call Super alignment and so it's this
idea of doing a lot of research to
understand how we align this very
capable increasingly capable models that
eventually become you know AGI or ASI uh
eventually and this is a extremely hard
technical Challenge and we're investing
quite a bit from compute perspective but
also uh in terms of just hiring great
team of research Searchers and giving
them space to focus on some of these
very
uncertain um and difficult research
agendas so in terms of uh given the
importance of
prediction uh of uh given the importance
of prediction being able to predict
risks that you were talking about do you
have uh you know to share with people
who are sort of not involved in you know
what you're doing inside the company
sort of examples of things where uh you
know either you were you know surprised
one way or the other in terms of your
either ability or inability to predict
risks and sort of how how should the
World At Large think about uh risk
prediction and how well that
works yeah
so you know if you think about gbt 4 it
was a brand new frontier uh Model A year
ago and we did very precise capability
predictions ahead of time um we put in
six months of work into safety before
releasing doing a lot of red teaming um
doing a ton of evaluations and uh then
we proceeded to do this very controlled
deployment where we rolled out to a set
of trusted users understood what they
were able to do and what some of the
risks of that were and then over time as
we build more confidence about being
able to handle the risks and mitigating
them we broadened up access to more and
more users um but yeah I think in terms
of our core safety decision has been
really building the science of uh
prediction and following the strategy of
iterative
deployment um before we even
released big models um so let's say gbt
3 for example we had been studying
misinformation for a really long time
and um but we didn't have you know first
experience with it because we had never
deployed such models and so before we
released gbd3 we were extremely worried
about um the effects that it could have
on elections and just misinformation at
large on the internet and not that
that's so important that's extremely
important but what we saw from actual
deployment was that a bigger much bigger
risk was um you know spamming content
which is you know still bad but perhaps
uh not as bad and not exactly what we
expected so we kind of reoriented our
work then to be a to to focus on on
those
mitigations um but I would say you know
a lot of the things that we're dealing
with right now
uh in terms of risks to some degree we
had thought about and had predicted them
many many years ago like let's say even
four or five years ago but you don't
know exactly the degree to which the
problem will be pervasive important
critical and um how precisely it will
impact things like for example education
is um something that you know we knew
bt4 and Char gbt would have some effect
but we didn't know exactly how so we
started studying Provence um of uh of
content and being able to detect what's
sayi generated what's not I generated um
but we don't understand you know the
impact that these Technologies are
having on the education system and how
things will evolve over time and so we
know there is some some sort of impact
but we don't know exactly what how and
so it's very important to actually
continuously study this and be able to
um react and be able to kind of uh
iterate on on the strategy on the
technology um work with different parts
of society that are uh affected by it
and figure out some ways to gather input
not just from people that use the
technology but also people that are
affected by it and are not necessarily
using it so it is quite complex in that
sense because you know you need to
coordinate so many aspects it's a
technology that affects everything it's
such a
fundamental uh unit of things and
changes the fabric of society so it's
you know it's like Global coordination
task it's just a really huge
task and so maybe this is to the
education space I'd thought about it as
a broader question before based on what
people said but um like what role do you
see it's a lot to take on in addition to
developing these models and testing
these models and predicting things to
really think through impact in various
different domains to what degree do you
see you know collaborating with Academia
or with other kinds of
organizations uh who might be able to do
things like help study how these things
are being used and can be used in K12
education or in other places um are
those things that you're looking to do
to sort of build uh you know either with
other companies sort of non-competitive
consortia or with Academia to to study
some of these broader kinds of questions
to give you sort of a a broader platform
for thinking about
risk yes for sure I mean you know we of
course have a lot of responsibility as
developers of the technology but it's
not uh really possible for a small group
of people in an organization to um to
figure out how technology will be
absorbed by society and the entire
infrastructure that needs to be built to
make this you know just really
beneficial to everyone and so I think
one of the big benefits of chbt was
really bringing AI the effects of AI and
the experience of AI in the collective
consciousness because before then I
think people obviously had a sense um
but not everyone could just experience
the power of these very Advanced AI
systems and know what it feels like and
I think that had an incredible effect
because people weren't just reading
about it um or yeah hearing about it
they could just feel it experience it
for themselves and um I think this
really pushed
governments all over the world into
action to think about how to coordinate
organize govern AI systems and we've
seen actually a ton of moment in the
past year um I mean last week the UK uh
uh AI Summit was held where we the all
all the major AI developers were there
and um thinking about you know voluntary
commitments that organizations can make
and
so I think this is a really inflection
point for AI governance um and that's
because it has it has sort of penetrated
the the collective Consciousness and
there was an important moment now you
know when it comes to our role and how
we work with various organizations Civil
Society Academia and so on we try to do
as much as possible and we collaborate
with organizations like code.org or KH
Academy and uh try to empower them to
build with our technology get their
feedback um and they were actually they
were helping us understand some the very
early use cases around AI tutors um and
and how to make them effective and we
got the the uh feedback from Educators
but now we're also working with a few
universities just to understand how we
fects things in the classroom especially
with ch GPT um and so there is quite a
bit of work that we're doing with
various organizations and I think
there's obviously always more uh that we
can do but our priority is really to
just make it accessible easy to use and
to really just Empower everyone to um be
able to use the technology and start
thinking about how it impacts their
specific domain um as we don't
necessarily have expertise say in the
domain of education but we want to give
people the tools to experience and
understand it for themselves and you
know be able to gather that feedback um
and make the technology more robust or
more helpful so with the race to develop
and release larger models
um how do we stop this from sort of
becoming a race to the bottom on safety
concerns uh you know you sort of
mentioned things like uh you know uh the
recent Bletchley Park people getting
together and talking about this but you
know when when realities of competition
come to Bear often uh these things can
be good intention you know uh somebody
I've learned a lot from in my life likes
to say Good Intentions without
mechanisms don't actually get anything
done uh so how how how do you think
about mechanisms there for
that yeah there are a few things well
one I'd
say this is why we spend a lot of time
thinking about the structure of open AI
sort of anticipating a future where
things would get quite competitive and
AI would be um would just have a very
important place in the economy and so we
uh we we kind of change the structure of
open AI into this limited partner ship
which is still governed by the nonprofit
but it allowed us to then you know raise
money so we could buy the supercomputers
to be able to do our research and our
work um but it's still governed by the
nonprofit and it has a limited cup what
we call limited profit cup and uh and so
that that ensures that you know the
primary uh objective is really achieving
the mission uh which is building AI that
that really benefits all of humanity and
the structure the mechanisms the
incentives are important they're not
everything but they're really important
and so I I'll start with that but then I
think you know as
we're deploying things uh it's also yeah
it's also very important to make sure
that um we get the things around
governance right and so right now
there're a lot of there's a lot of
debate around regulation and we've been
pushing for regulation of Frontier
systems that don't necessarily affect
you know the startups or innovation of
small companies and so on but put some
sort of degree of checks and balances
and Regulatory framework around models
that are really at the
frontier and um encouraging the
government to think
about uh yeah regulating this model
models that have incredible
capabilities in the near term I would
say you know with opening I would just
have a whole set of things uh that help
us think and uh think about how to
deploy safely and responsibly and it's
not really a One Stop uh you know it's
not just something that you add at the
very end it's it's something it it's
it's integrated from the data
uh from point point of view of the data
to into the algorithms into um you know
building the product into actual
deployment and looking at uh how people
are using the AI and then feeding it
back into the technology and having this
full loop um that we continuously
iterate on and that's that's really
important and also providing some
accountability by you know when we
whenever we release some new technology
we have Safety Systems card we do a lot
of red teaming uh often we we publish
the outcomes of of the red teaming um
and so I think you know it's important
for for the industry to have some sort
of Standards around deployment and uh
what we have seen I would say in the
past year past couple of years is that
there is a lot of voluntary standard
setting from the big companies we saw
this a bit with the White House
commitments as well um but yeah it's
important to avoid kind of this race to
the bottom um and I would say yeah
that's that's very important and if we
just focus on sort of the worst outcomes
um I would focus on if if we have to
focus on one thing and like the worst
outcomes I would focus on the frontier
systems and being able to work with
governments and other um a developers to
regulate the frontier
models so um so it's
uh the uh executive order that the Biden
Administration put out uh a couple weeks
ago um certainly I mean it has a lot of
breadth to it uh but part of it is
definitely looking at Foundation models
and what they term dual use Foundation
models that can have uh sort of
potential defense uh kinds of uh uses
you know um and uh how are you thinking
about that executive order and how it's
affecting what you're doing because it
has reporting requirements and other
things how are you thinking about and
preparing for
those yeah it's pretty fresh so we're
studying and looking at it and seeing
you know what it actually means in
practice and what the effect of it would
be um but generally I'm very supportive
of figuring out the appropriate
um regulation around Frontier models I
think it's valuable to think of it in
terms of
capabilities and uh you know building
building the science of predicting these
capabilities and and determining any
thresholds or regulation based on that
uh but this is just all very fresh and
you know internally we're looking at
this and and we're figuring out what it
means and
how uh how how to make sure that it's
something that's practical um you know
you don't want regulation and the actual
science of doing things or uh the
Practical actions to be detached so
um i' say the short answer is that you
know we're still reviewing it but on
principle yeah we definitely are have
been encouraging having some sort of
regulatory framework around Frontier
models so there's another piece of that
uh reg of that executive order that I'll
sort of summarize in the following I
mean it's long but I'll summarize it as
you know uh using AI is not an excuse
for you know breaking existing
regulations and laws so that you know if
you make your Frontier Model available
and somebody else uses it in a way or
either uses or misuses it in a way uh
that's you know counter to other
existing laws or
regulations uh it's sort of not an
excuse um do you see that as something
that exposes you all to risk in terms of
how people use things do you think that
you know that's a part of the
responsibility of these very general
models is to have guard rails in there
that actually help guard against misuse
you know like uh somebody pretending to
be a lawyer or pretending to be a doctor
by sort of you know kind of Consulting a
a generative model or those things that
you think fall within scope how do you
how do you see sort of teasing apart in
some sense uh the amazing capabilities
of these General models and then the
ways that they may be used for very good
purposes but also misused in a lot of
different domains and how the
responsibility there kind of uh shakes
out yeah so I I think it's very sort of
domain specific use case specific like
of course there's some uh Common Sense
guidelines and guard reals around uh you
know what's legal and what's not legal
but a lot of it like a lot of the hard
decisions and the nuan decisions are um
quite details like for example you have
to think you know how how let's say how
is a lawyer using an AI system and you
go through the use cases the various use
cases and you try to understand and like
right now for example there is human
oversight so it's not like you're
delegating all the decision making to an
AI system and there is yeah there is
human oversight what we call human in
the loop and uh you know that we came up
with sort of that uh usage guideline by
understanding how people were actually
using the system and where the gaps were
where the concerns were for us um and we
go through this entire process where we
work very closely especially when it
comes to opening up a new domain um or a
new capability um then we will work very
closely with trusted Partners to
understand precisely how they're using
it where the risks are and generally
especially you know with Enterprise
customers they do have an incentive for
the technology to be robust reliable
useful um otherwise you know even from a
business perspective it's not very
useful if it cannot really follow the
intent if it's not reliable if it's not
robust and so there is this very good
incentive alignment um and and you know
we learn a lot we share the tools the
safety tools monitoring tools any
systems that we build to be able to
empower other people um to you know
establish their own guardrails on top of
the model guard rails or the product
guard rails that we put in place um we
also share those with our developers and
with uh our customers at large so I
think it's quite specific um it's it it
really depends like these questions are
going to get harder and harder over time
obviously but uh yeah I I'd say it
really depends on the use case it
depends on the domain it's it depends on
the capabilities of the models where you
sort of draw the
line thanks um so uh so another area of
question um that you know I know you're
very familiar with is there are a number
of creative professionals who are
concerned about chat GPT and their
intellectual property rights but at the
same time there are also creatives who
are very excited about using generative
models like chat GPT and Delhi um so how
are you thinking more generally about
respecting rights of creators and
authors and it certainly seems like at
least a piece of the recent chat GPT
Builder announcement was sort of maybe
one step in that direction of starting
to think about how you might share
Revenue with people who you know put
their creative Talent into into building
customized gpts but what about all of
that other creative material that's out
there that's that's that's being used by
these
models yeah so in building the Del
modules most recently Del 3 um we're
working with a lot of licensed data um
or and uh we've worked very closely with
creators to actually get their feedback
on um how to develop the product and how
to make it most useful and um also just
think about and iterates on you know
data sharing data contributions there is
a this this whole area of you know how
do you
attribute um value to specific data
that's that's sort of contributed into
model training that's a difficult
technical question and then you know as
we address that or while we're
addressing that we also want to think
about the economics of um you know
sharing the benefits of these models
with the creators so we're doing quite a
bit of work there with you know
Publishers with um creators um and then
with the gbts that we just announced we
we're we're going to have a Marketplace
soon where people can um publish their
gpts and be compensated uh we're we're
figuring out the details of this but
this is this is quite nent and we're
basically just getting very involved
with creators and getting a lot of
feedback from people on what would make
sense what would be valuable um and you
know there is the aspect of getting
input and figuring out economic models
but there is also this aspect of
um of of understanding data attribution
this a bit of a challenging technical
problem that we've been working on so I
think there's a lot to do here but this
is I expect this to evolve and to change
a lot um our goal is definitely to
figure out ways to compensate creators
or at least people put people in the
driver's seat to choose if they don't
want their data to be used for uh
training models and so we've done a lot
of work in data privacy and and user
controls to to try to give people you
know as much um as much control and as
much stay as possible
to figure out you know if they don't
want their data to be used for
training great so I'm going to switch
gears now to uh some of the audience
questions that have come in uh and um uh
so one one question is uh open ai's
mission is to create AGI that benefits
all of humanity how can young people
like us and obviously I'm quoting the
audience not myself how can young how
can Young People Like Us build this
future uh what engineering challenge es
and problems stand in our
way there's so many engineering
challenges and even bigger challenges
that are sort of at the intersection of
many domains a lot of the interesting
problems that I see right now is sort of
like they're they're Frontier problems
uh when it comes to building the
Technologies and also a lot of problems
that sit at the intersection of many
things like Society societal impact
technology safety you know the legal
Frameworks you know we're changing
everything
and and we need people to really think
about how to evolve and change
essentially all these different domains
as and build the the infrastructure for
society to be able to adopt and use this
technology in a way that's very
beneficial so in a way I think I don't
know perhaps it's the most exciting
moment um in history to to to do really
important and impactful work that's
really going to shape the way that we
live um and the quality of our life in
the
future great thank you um so open AI is
clearly leading in the domain of natural
language
processing uh and and and also the image
I'll add I'll make an editorial comment
because I think also image synthesis uh
but uh does open AI have any plans to
lead in other domains of AI and then you
know in particular in the question was
applications uh video generation use in
biology uh there's certainly a lot of
interest around MIT and some other
educational institutions in uh
generative AI for scientific discovery
uh with you know biology as one example
uh are those places that you know where
you're Al looking at applications and
other domains or you sort of focused on
the frontier models in in in natural
language and en
Vision so the way that we think about it
is you know
um what what's most likely path to safe
and beneficial AGI and so we kind of
build our research agenda around that
and of course a big bet that we made a
few years ago was on scale or large
language models and scaling those mod
models this was a very significant um
paradigm shift at the time and now we're
looking at basically bringing together a
lot of modalities into these large
models and so we want um a lot of data
and we want different modalities and we
want to continue to be able to scale um
the systems over time and so when you're
thinking about modalities I'm sure
you've seen our uh text to speeech model
but you know we're we're looking at
everything whether it's images um or uh
Voice or video so we're kind of working
on all these different modalities and
then in terms of applications there is
certainly the work that we've been doing
with ch GPT and our first party product
and we're also we really want to bring
these Technologies into the platform so
other people can build with them as well
that's extremely valuable um
and you know I'd say we're not
necessarily investing in a specific
domain like biology unless there is some
very good strategic reason to do so
we're not experts in biology and so
typically we would work with um a
company that has expertise or
institution that has expertise in
another domain and we bring our own um
to to figure out what's possible at the
frontier of some new domain that's how
we normally do it
um
and and in terms of scientific
advancements I think that's very
interesting and it's one area that I'm
personally very excited about seeing how
these AI systems will help us um
basically just you know figure out new
things and discover new things and
um internally of course we've been using
co-pilot like systems and weave systems
to help us um uh with say you know
safety monitoring and these are based on
gp4 so we're already using
gp4 like systems to help us um U to help
us with various aspects of our work um
like a notable example is definitely in
building safety infrastructure and
monitoring uh but I think over time this
will evolve more and more and maybe you
know you can imagine having a AI um
scientist um that runs on gpus and helps
us Advance research and helps us do
alignment research in fact it's one of
our uh core research agendas for
alignment building sort of this AI uh
alignment researcher so I think yeah
this is this in particular is something
that we're very excited about and you
could extend that to other scientific
domains of
course great um so these are just like I
tried to organize the other questions so
these ones have not been organized but
they're they're all quite interesting
not surprising given the audience uh so
um do you have uh thoughts or comments
on human out of the loop systems like
fully autonomous multi-agent generative
AI systems that don't involve any sort
of human oversight or
collaboration yeah obviously these kind
of systems would be very powerful and
you can imagine them being extremely
useful um I mean even in just the in the
use case that we just discussed if
you're doing scientific research um or
any engineering work you go to sleep and
you have got your AI collaborators
continuing to do that work imagine how
quickly things could advance but of
course the uh challenge there is making
sure that these systems are aligned and
they're following intent and not just
you know explicit intent but um implicit
um and sort of high level ambiguous
intent and making sure that they're
really aligned with what you want them
to do that that is a challenge and uh
that's something that we've been working
on for a while we started with
rhf and um we built we built um um
instruction following models uh with
ilhf and there was kind of probably yeah
the first step that we the first time
that we saw safety into production into
um this this Real World products and we
brought Safety Research into Real World
products and then after that um
obviously we continued this work work
with ch GPT and extended it further we
did um a lot of alignment work with gb4
and gbd4 was the most aligned and most
powerful model at the time so I think if
we just kind of proceed in this path
where we continue to do a lot of um
alignment research
and capability prediction work build
build up the science of prediction
um and and develop uh continue to
develop and deploy employe iteratively
learning from every step while the
stakes are still low I think there is a
path to getting to a place where these
autonomous agents um can be robust and
safe but there are a lot of research
questions ahead of us that we need to
figure out and
answer when you when you mentioned R lhf
there um uh I guess I had a follow-up
question which is um uh have you been
used
[Music]
reinforcement learning with AI feedback
like just in terms of the challenges of
scaling human feedback and if so are you
finding that useful like sort of how do
you look at the scale problems of
alignment um and and sort of humans in
that feedback
loop yeah that's you know um the hiring
a lot of contractors and giving them
Direction initially after gbd3 that was
very important and Building Things
instruction following models but of
course with um CH GPT then our Our
intention was to have this as a research
preview and get a lot of feedback from
the research community and um use that
feedback to for RF or generally to just
make the the model better and more
robust and more reliable but of course
in four days we saw a million users and
so this opened up a new opportunity
which was you know now all of sudden
then if um users um were willing to we
could um use that input for for
rhf and so that's that's very valuable
data fly will and um of course you know
we had to make sure that um users were
willing to provide such input and give
them the controls to decide for
themselves but in terms of scalability
that that is one path where you know you
have access to a large user base but
more importantly perhaps is also the
quality of the data and making sure that
um you know the quality of the data is
high so that generally requires um very
specific data collection
campaigns and there is a lot of work
that us and
also I I think a lot of other AI
developers are doing on high quality
data
collection great um so on the Education
topic uh there's been a and and you
mentioned uh you know code.org there's
been a big push for students to learn to
code in recent years uh if if we're
really able to code in natural language
you know how do you see that change in
K12 education do you see you know like
what how do you see sort of
the human coder with a co-pilot the
non-human coder like what should we be
thinking about in terms of uh at least K
through 12 education and and trying to
get kids to
code there is you know a lot of code to
be written in the world and so I think
for um people that want to learn it's
just a great opportunity I don't think
it's going away anytime soon and I think
it's great to be able to learn and build
things yourself now the Technologies
we're building make it much easier both
to actually learn how to code and make
sure that it's you know catered to the
way that you think and you can just ask
so many questions you know the system is
just running on GPU so it's quite
patient and it will uh you know you can
the the learning can be quite
personalized and cater to you which can
be very effective um but you know uh at
the the same time it's also quite these
systems are far more accessible than
ever and so if one just wants to um code
in natural language they can also do
that where they provide sort of high
level guidance uh
to GPT or other systems like it and can
build uh prototypes or actual products
with um very little coding language so I
think it's become both much easier to
learn uh probably easier than ever and
much easier to build all the tools all
these tools are accessible available and
so people just need to explore and if
they're curious all the tools are are at
your
hands uh so one of the questions that's
been rising in popularity here somebody
asked it is uh our open Ai and MIT
thinking about a partnership that could
benefit the MIT
community so obviously there are a lot
of students here who are interested
in in your in in in your tools and your
engagement with places like
MIT I am open to your
proposals good we we we'll we'll uh
we'll we'll be back uh I mean I know
there have been some discussions going
on that that I'm aware of but I'm I'm
not sure that any of them that any of
them are that far along at this point so
uh and um and there's certainly a lot of
sort of pointwise interactions between
various faculty and research groups at
MIT and Folks at at at openai but I
think it just shows the level of you
know broad student interest in what
you're doing and how they can really
become expert in it um amazing uh so
um you know when it was lower down on
the list I would have ignored it but it
went all the way up to the
top uh uh um so there's a set of
questions here sort of around you know
mechanisms uh to help ensure you know
sort of
fairness uh um you know combating bias
uh um uh you know sort of ethical
development of Technology you know you
you've spoken quite a bit to some of
those kinds of questions more broadly
but are there are there specific things
maybe that you're the fact that there's
still questions coming up my guess is
people are hoping there might be
something that's a little bit you know
uh a concrete example uh or something
there in terms of mechanisms that you
see that are that are working in in the
work that you're doing
um yeah there's certainly uh I mean
we're doing so much work in this whether
it's in text or images um combination of
all these things um so I'm thinking
through the work that we did with Del
recently um Del is definitely the most
advanced image system out there and uh
we had to do quite a bit of work in
making sure that you know we'd mitigate
some of the harmful biases um within the
system but
also you know you you have to get the
balance right uh with mitigating biases
with figuring out how um you know let's
say you don't want to necessarily
optimize too much for engagement because
you end up with other issues and so once
you optimize one metric you can see a
lot of other things uh uh degrading and
so one thing that we've learned is that
whenever you're optimizing for one thing
you have to be super careful because
probably bunch of other things that you
didn't expect would be degrading and
so um you have to take a very holistic
View especially with very complex issues
like harmful bias and constantly be
auditing the system end to end when you
tweak something and so we we've seen
this a lot you know there was uh I think
Del to we tweaked something when it came
to uh the ratio of um gendered images
and then we ended up with some uh result
that we didn't expect that a lot of the
images of women were sort of
hypersexualized because that was the
content in the data so then we had to go
in and intervene again and uh make sure
that you know it was more balanced and
we were not ending up with these
unintended consequences so these issues
are very complex and they require having
quite diverse talent in the team to be
able to handle them and doing a lot of
red seaming with people from um you know
with different expertise because we
learn a ton from that early red teaming
initially with trusted users and then um
with a broader set of people and be
constantly intervening and tweaking but
at almost like all stages from data to
the algorithm itself to the way that we
deploy the technology in the product and
the way we design the product the access
around it as well as um you know the
post deployment so if figuring out uh
stuff around like you know classifiers
monitoring uh usage policies and things
like that
um so yeah it's a d is probably great
example of this a lot of examples around
our um base model on chbt so we you know
we have our usage policies and then we
build systems that help us Monitor and
like automatically monitor according to
our usage policies um and sometimes you
know we have over refusals because we're
being too conservative and that's kind
of annoying for the user it's not so
much fun and the system Hedges a lot so
we have to optimize for that perhaps
collect more data higher quality data
better data and uh intervene again uh so
we have to do tweaks like that and in
some cases you know there is kind of
this tradeoff between um truthfulness
and
factuality is and and like creativity or
the the personality of the model like it
being fun and
creative um and so this is actually
quite a hard balance to strike between
creativity and factuality perhaps even
in humans um and so this is something
that we've learned a lot about in the
past year and have iterated a lot on and
also people have different expectations
or preferences and so we introduce
custom that puts people more in charge
of kind of the personality of uh the
model and how the model behaves within
certain bounds and guard rails of course
but yeah I would say these are probably
some of the things we've learned some of
the things we've done over the past year
in these different models now that's
that that that's great I think that's
some of the kind of next level down
things that that help people understand
understand a little more um so another
question that's been voted way up and
I'm going to read the question but I'm
going to presume it's been voted way up
for part of the question the question is
as a member of the MIT Albanian
Association I'd love to hear a little
bit about how you ended up where you are
today and any advice you may have I
presume that some of the people voting
that up just want to hear about your
career and aren't all members of the MIT
Albanian associ but may may maybe we
have a big contingent who came to hear
you today but but but probably not
hundreds of them so uh but anyways I I
think people would love to hear a little
bit and this will kind of get to one of
the questions I had also just um you
know how you got to where you are what
your thoughts about you know careers are
um you know on the one hand you're
you're way past being an undergraduate
but on the other hand you know you've
had a you you you know you've you've had
a sort of you know very rapid rise in
the kind of responsibilities for things
that you're doing so be really great to
to hear your thoughts on Career
advice um so yeah I I grew up in Albania
and uh I I then studied I I did my high
school in Canada or half of my High
School uh at United World College uh in
Canada and then I came to the US for
college but I've always been interested
in math uh and Science and I was always
interested in and kind of just building
stuff and I studied mechanical engineer
I studed math mechanical engineering and
eventually right after school um ended
up working in Aerospace and then in
automotive where I learned a lot about
how to build complex things you know
you're talking about uh you know very
complex systems with thousands and
thousands of Parts um and um you know
everything comes together software
Hardware um electrical engineering
regulation all everything comes together
there and in terms of you
know the career path I never really had
a very specific plan in terms of I
didn't have a specific plan of where I
wanted to end up but I always kind of
followed my curiosity and always wanted
to just build things and uh I wasn't
afraid to jump domains so after building
a lot of
expertise um and knowledge in a specific
domain I wasn't afraid to just kind of
start from scratch and I've done that a
few times in my career so you know in
Aerospace and and then going to
automotive and then going into virtual
reality and augmented reality and more
computer vision and AI work and then
obviously as in the past five years into
working in Ai and really being dedicated
to AGI so there is something there but I
also think that's quite specific to how
I learn and uh you know the things that
I'm interested in and uh usually I I'm
interested that in the intersection of
many things technology that that sort of
affects many things and working at the
intersection of many domains um but
generally you know that would be my
advice to just do really the thing that
you're most curious about and most
excited about I think it's kind of
maybe uh people hear this a lot but it's
really true and because when things get
hard then it doesn't feel like work um
and things will inevitably get hard and
so I would say especially earlier in
your career like but perhaps always just
focus on learning and maximizing your
learning and the things you're curious
and excited about no I think I I
actually think it's great advice you
were saying it's it's maybe just how you
are but I would say I think often people
focus a little too much on sort of a
linear career path and trying to plan it
out and I think you know when you said
you didn't really think about a a goal
you thought about the moment and really
learning what you could learn and doing
what you could do in that moment uh I
just I think you can strain your
opportunities by trying to think about
the linear path so I I really I think
your your career career and your
attitude is something that that that
everybody should hear that's and I could
sort of see it from your the set of
things you'd worked on so i' sort of
already written a question about this
but but I'm I'm glad it came up um so
this is related but maybe different
enough that um so just general advice
you have for aspiring entrepreneurs and
innovators about what to do in their
early 20s so it's getting a little more
specific uh and then may maybe
especially for people who are from a
minority
background
um I mean I would say for everyone just
uh especially right out of school it's
so much easier to take risks um and just
try things it's like the best thing to
learn about what you want what you will
enjoy what you'll be good at is to
really try and build stuff uh make
things like really make things and
try as many things as possible and I
think that really gives you a sense of
taste about what you want to do and what
you're good at um and it also helps
evolve your taste you know whether it's
in research or you know any domain it
doesn't really matter but yeah I'd say
it sounds generic but I I really think
it's the best advice to really just go
do stuff and not really overthink it
especially like that early in your care
career where you know you don't have a
ton of built up expertise and so the
opportunity cost may not be as high I
think best thing to do is to just go
make things and try things and build
things so this is another question
that's related to something I'd written
before so it's good on my questions said
overlap uh what what what actions are
being taken uh at open AI to address the
environmental impact of the AI systems
uh the extremely large amount of uh GPU
Compu resources being used in the
training uh and and then of course as
they're integrated in society in the
long term also a lot of aggregate
inference uh you know like right now
maybe the training is using most of the
but as you most of the compute power but
as you start to integrate these into
society broadly it becomes certainly
becomes
both the specific action that we're
taking is making the systems more
efficient um but yeah I say yeah General
we work with Microsoft that's really
thinking about how to offset some of uh
the impact of this but longer term what
I'm really excited about is um getting
these Advanced systems to help us figure
out maybe either new scientific um
solutions to dealing with climate change
um or perhaps just you know figuring out
the infrastructure of more sustainable
energy and making that just really um
the the default way of consuming energy
generating consuming energy um and this
is something that I'm particularly
excited about figuring out how to use
Advanced AI systems to help us deal with
these extreme challenges that you know
just left to our own devices we haven't
really figured out and they're not
exactly on track I would say to solve on
our own um so I'm hoping that you know
medium medium to longterm AI can help us
with that but in in in the in the near
term
um we're we're working on things like
yeah figuring out how to optimize data
centers and the design of data centers
and also working with Microsoft s on
that and also just making the systems
more and more
efficient so here here's a different
form of question thank thanks for the
that one do you agree with the
prediction that having a job will be
optional in the
future um it depends how far in the
future but yeah if you
look far enough into future possibly yes
yes but not in not you don't see it as a
short to medium term thing maybe in the
next 10 years let's say yeah yeah well
and I'm sure you're doing the work of at
least several people right now in your
job so it's probably it's probably hard
to think
about jobs being optional where you're
sitting right
now um so uh so a 100 years from now how
do you think people will look back on
open AI what do you want open ai's
impact on the future and Humanity to be
in that sort of time
scale is a really long time the you can
pick a shorter one I'm just reading the
question know it was hard to predict
what was going to happen this year we
didn't predict the chbd moment but you
know looking far enough into the future
I I would hope
that at the very least open
AI um has
had a crucial
impact in helping Society build AI
systems in a way that's um safe and we
figure out how
to distribute the benefits of AI systems
to everyone and so whether it's open AI
that has figured that out or led the
work or
inspired um people to do that I think
that that's great but the end impact
like really figuring out how
the path to to safe and aligned Advanced
AI systems um and in addition to that I
would say
also inspiring
or helping
Drive um Innovative and practical ways
to good Global governance of AI systems
I think that's a huge huge challenge um
and a lot of governments and Nations
have sort of um become very aware about
this Challenge and are trying to
coordinate in different ways you know
through the UN or uh various Global
Summits and I hope that I think this is
incredibly important and I hope that
opening ey helps to get this
right thank you
um so uh how do you think about the role
of open academic research with respect
to sort of
um leading generative AI models so in
the early days of open AI you were
fairly active in publishing in the more
open academic literature uh and and more
recently that's less the case and not
just for open AI for you know is the as
this has become a more competitive space
companies that were sort of part of an
open research Community for very
understandable reasons have been
starting to do that less but how do we
how should we think about the the role
of open academic research uh and the
importance of that in the advancement of
things in this
area yeah so um first of all you know we
still try to do um open research in
areas where we can or you know when we
have systems that we can open source and
the larger Community can benefit from
them and do so in a way that we consider
to be safe we do that so we've open
sourced um elements of Del 3 and we've
open sourced our whisper system
um
and when yeah when when we look at what
we can open source um I know this a heed
debate currently open source say versus
not but I think the question is
really how do you think about alignment
safety second third degree consequen
of um releasing the systems and what
happens once they're released because
once they're uh open source you know we
don't have a lot of we can really
enforce guard rails and for with gbd4
for example you know we spent a really
long time figuring out the guard rails
and um around the system and how to make
it safe and how to deploy safely um and
we' have continued to build and invest
in the infrastructure
and so I think these are very important
questions not to be taken lightly but uh
in terms of like open academic research
it doesn't have to be all centered
around building large models um we want
to make them easily accessible and when
it comes to these large models and uh
for specific purposes like for example
figuring out um risks or understanding
capabilities we do a lot of Clos work
with um experts like for example in
misinformation or bio or whatever things
we're worried about when we're
developing a new model and we give them
more access than we give you know uh
General user or Customer because uh we
want them to really
understand the the capabilities and and
risks of the model so I think this is a
really important way to contribute um
with understanding the capabilities of
the risks of the models especially when
it comes to certain domains like you
know when we're thinking about cyber
security risk or um bio risk um or
misinformation um when we're developing
new models I think these are important
areas to collaborate or um or you know
figuring out even just new research
directions like for example we have
funded did a lot of um Safety Research
recently and both through open Ai and
also in a few
collaborations um through the AI safety
Summit so I think there are a ton of
opportunities for actually advancing
open academic research just about doing
so in ways that are not uh sort of
undermining the uh colossal amount of
safety work that we're doing when it
comes to developing and deploying large
language
models great so there are two two
threads there that I'd like to pick up
on um uh the first was you mentioned
about open source um and one of the
questions here had been are are there
any steps that can be taken uh you know
whether by companies like open AI or uh
you know governments or others consumers
even uh so that technology that is open
sourced in the generative AI realm isn't
uh modified for malicious
purposes um we're actually doing some
research on this right now but I I don't
have anything Noble to share but I think
I mean the bottom line is that it's
really hard once you're uh open sourcing
this models you don't really have
control
um over them anymore but we are doing
some research on it because clearly
there is also a lot of appetite to have
uh access to these Technologies and it's
completely understandable so we we've
been doing some research for a few
months now to figure out this question
and it's pretty challenging we'll
probably have something to share next
year I
think it's great to know you're you're
thinking about that I know I know others
are as well but as you said it's a
really really really tough uh tough
problem um so uh let me see I knew I had
a second question from that I forgot
should have uh it wasn't one of the ones
that was in the list um so another one
from the list say do you see open AI
branching out into more embodied
AI so that um you know robotics other
things where
uh
um I mean not in the next
year but is but know future but uh no we
you know I I don't think in the
immediate term we're not thinking about
robotics we are thinking about I'm sure
you've seen sort of yeah speculation in
the news and um thinking about device
integration and so so on like thinking
about uh what this future with AI
systems could look like and what future
devices could look like but that's just
really you know very early thinking and
nothing really concrete to share and
then on there's a lot of interest in
sort of explainability of these
models and sometimes some of us like to
say interpretability because
explainability sometimes suggests the
model can explain itself uh which which
is maybe a higher bar even than being
interpretable by people uh are those um
you know what are you doing looking at
those kinds of problems
does actually you know Alexander MRE
from MIT joined us recently to help us
think about these problems and actually
uh yeah supercharge the research around
interpretability and uh General
generally the science of predicting
capabilities as well
um obviously some work that uh we've
done is actually started ended up in
chbt but it it started as is uh
understanding um uh improving the
truthfulness and the factuality of this
models and understanding what was
happening so having some sort of
interface dialogue interface to get a
sense of what was happening with the
models um and it it ended up after a few
iterations of research and you know how
research evolves it ended up um in in
GPT but initially it started with this
question of how do we understand what is
happening with these models and Socratic
dialogue is a good way to even uh you
know understand what students are
thinking about or how well they
understand the subject or your colleague
or someone this is how we kind of
communicate and get a sense of you know
even in interviews how uh much expertise
someone has in a given subject and so uh
then there is a question of how much you
can trust that and hallucination and
other problems but it does give you some
insight when the model when you can when
you have this ability to interact with
the model in a way that we interact with
each other um so and and so I think that
is interesting and and the work that uh
We've started with our super alignment
team doing on interpretability and uh
new research that we are seeding um in
this direction but it's still really
quite
early great thank you so there are way
too many questions here so I'm going to
stop for a second and just say uh in
this in this whole long list of question
I I feel like you know we we're giving
you an oral exam or something one
question after another uh so uh what
have we not
asked that we should
have is there
anything no all right so uh that's good
so so do do you have any question you
would like to ask us because otherwise
with that I think I'll there's no way
I'm going to get through this list so
we're going to run out of time but uh
but I thought I'd see if there's a you
know any question you think we should
have asked or uh or any question you'd
like to hear uh from the collective uh
audience
here I think we covered quite a broad
range I hope it was
helpful yeah yeah so but we really
appreciate your your time mirror and
your thoughtful answers to uh all of our
questions as you can see there's a huge
amount of Interest here at MIT and what
you all are doing and an engagement uh
with open Ai and we look forward to uh
continuing to work with you all thank
thank you very much we really appreciate
your time so much thank
you