let's get started uh welcome back 21m
383 computational music theory and
Analysis went through probably one of
the most slide heavy one of the fastest
classes ever on Wednesday that I'll be
doing uh this semester today we're going
to switch gears we're going to do one of
the least Tech uh heavy classes in this
semester and then we'll probably keep
going back and forth this is the only
one that in my particular notes it for
my lecture it says mike Don't Panic
there actually is no power point because
I was panicking the other day when I was
preparing this I was like wait wait wait
wait I did I delete it no there is
nothing because I want us to step back
for a little bit and think about some of
the things and do some work on um some
of the things to do with what we mean by
music because various musical points
because there's a lot of things that we
can know that are um you know just sort
of um uh just just sort of intuitively
we all know what that is but then um we
might not um you know we might not be
able to explain it to a computer because
computers are smart or computers are
dumb what do you think shout it out dumb
neither no neither dumb neither no no
smart okay I think computers are really
really dumb until we make them smart so
or something like that great there's
some people in the back that whose names
I don't know could you take a sheet of
paper you can also use your outline to
put your name on it because uh the
outlines for reading later and it's kind
of nice that this way you have it for
later and this way you won't um sort of
get me if I go out of order right um
okay
so I'm seeing who your names are can you
take a second and at least the person
you're sharing a table or sharing the
invisible table with um and introduce
yourself if you don't know that
where okay now add into your
conversation add into your conversation
what you think a note is you can also
keep getting to know each other the same
time but what you think a note
is okay I'm going to be asking you for
for some definitions in a second but
before we get to that um all I want you
to do is take your definitions you've
kind of got them first thing and you
just got to count notes okay so I'm
going to sing some things and you tell
me how many notes I sing so write them
down and then I'll ask them later
um first
set pretty easy right
second
one third
[Music]
one fourth one
and fifth
one great talk with your talk with your
neighbor and see how many if you got
answers that line up with each
other okay let's let's come back
together
um let's come back together we have um
uh I believe that the normal
distribution of names in this class is
kind of like the uh letters in the
alphabet so we we'll start with J's I'll
call who's the alphabetically first J is
it
Jason Jason um something something like
and if I change the things I'm doing it
accidentally because I don't remember
what I saying but um the first
one three notes three notes how many
agree how many disagree
agrees
disagrees okay good that was the right
answer I saying three notes good who's
alphabetically next after Jason we have
we have some Jonathan Jordans we have
Jake oh okay you we went out sorry about
that Jake um no even if we do Jacob or
something it's still I'm still wrong
okay
Jake this is what I
saying one note agree or disagree who
agrees who
disagrees good everybody is wrong I
Sayang four
um okay next note well next one I did I
I went I went up
[Music]
right uh next up alphabetically would be
uh Jonathan comes before John and comes
before Jordan so
Jonathan okay uh my was two notes two
notes good uh who
agrees okay we got some agrees um who
dis
agrees okay good we'll we'll continue
with the J's on that John you disagreed
what's the number you came up with uh I
thought because you sing a lot I think
you Sayang at least one note oh okay
okay
well greater than one note no greater
than or equal to one note right okay so
that that takes a little that's that's a
pretty pretty broad spectrum I like that
it's always good um who who agrees with
greater than or equal to one note or or
wants more disagree if you want more
specificity than that who agrees with
greater than or equal to one note good
Jordan's on your side and you just got
some some people good so who disagrees
with that with everything beforehand up
till now great so um I think we have um
no Jason we've already gone through who
who raise your hands again if you
disagree I want to keep going
alphabetically next among the disagreer
and that would that might be uh Kara
Karima yeah yeah uh I I wrote na na okay
well well na a or we we'll we'll make it
so it parses in Python not a number is
that okay okay good good and any um
anybody still still have your number not
said Adam yeah I said 14 or 15 14 or 15
okay very very specific um what did you
base that on so you went from a c to
either a c or a d so it's like if you go
all the chromatic notes and slur them
all that's what you get okay okay good
so we have we have a range extension um
good uh anybody else have a number that
doesn't hasn't been done
yet okay um so that's that's
particularly good um this one I went
with INF oh sorry I wasn't telling you
what what my numbers were yet okay well
that one that's what I went with um and
then uh next one D
um we have
some you want we have a a listener but
you want to be a participant or also
yeah go ahead so with that one I wrote
six
six anybody agree yep anybody
disagree good
okay and
um yep and now oh no I was giving I was
giving the right numbers yep so I'm
going to say I did that I did that uh
nobody disagreed the correct answer
there was
two and don't worry don't worry this is
frustrating be frustrating and
then uh who's also around K or do I hear
l
zero anybody
disagree great uh uh person who's
disagreed who has to speak um I just
said one one good good who agrees with
one good how many people have heard
neither zero nor
one y so when I was not writing a lot of
these I put two answers to a lot of them
depending on okay but you can only give
one right now well I was how I not how
i' like pitch wise and I was I was
taking I I was taking perception
spectrograms and a clap has like all of
the
so so so give me a number so that one
would also be INF INF okay
good this one I'm going to go with
zero and I will tell you um there isn't
a single answer on here that I couldn't
that you couldn't argue for and be
correct so um why three notes I think we
all agreed because I think I saying bom
bom bom I count each of those as one
note right second one was four
cuz was a half a whole note tied to a
quarter note tied to uh a 60th note tied
to a 64th
note and I do believe that is the
closest shortest representation I can do
notationally so I was thinking in a
notational sphere
here this time with the gando I was
thinking of it as an infinite number of
notes because if it's continuous it
could be but on the other hand it any of
these other ones could be correct now
let's see if anyone can come up with how
from
D I came up with
two the two different pitches that's one
good way to do it um I'm glad I I hit
the same pitch each time maybe I'm close
um that's not the reason why I was
thinking yeah it's like the trol trevolo
yeah it was something like I know well
don't know what thing we're in but yeah
I was thinking it has something like
that or actually would be measured
tremolo wouldn't it be
like anyone know this sign where you
have a beamed or no just one beam right
two beamed dotted half notes you see it
everywhere every once a while when
you're playing like POF off or or uh or
shert and stuff and I always like oh I
have to remember what that is but that
means fill in the space of one dotted
half note with as many eighth notes as
it takes to fill it in alternating
between the top one and the bottom
one and
clap I thought a note to me had to have
some sort of specifiable
pitch so I count zero
now everything that somebody said uh one
for for this or infinite are all valid
definitions of what we're going to be
talking
about and here's the thing 99% of the
time when I'm not trying to set up an
example for um you know for kind having
fun in the first week of class with you
all uh there's no way I would call that
second one four notes right I mean if I
hear it I'm going to be one
so one of the things that's going to
come up quite often is that depending on
what purpose you want to do with
something you're not going to be able to
um necessarily even know how many notes
or how many of something there is let
alone what's the correct spelling of
something or not
um so I think we're just going to be
playing around with something like this
now go back to your definitions of notes
that you had before and let's grab into
groups of four so your two groups that
are the same joining with a group behind
you so that's we're going to get good
spinning over here we'll create a group
of three here and three here and we'll
we'll break up uh this this group and
talk about what your definitions of the
notes were with the other group and then
try to figure out a if you had correct
definitions or if you had compatible not
a correct definition compatible
definitions of notes before that with
each other's group and then also if you
want to change definition based on all
the weird numbers that we came up with
here so go ahead and let's take a couple
minutes to do that great let's let's all
come back together
and
um there was one word that I just kept
hearing as I was going around and it
begins like this I want any any group
use a word that begins with this in
their
definition yeah John go ahead
representation representation
yeah so we can kind of start with
a is
uh of
is any anybody's definition um
completely incompatible with this
opening like couldn't be put in is no
smile of thing okay so what are some of
the ways that your groups could have um
could have uh done this I didn't think I
heard um because it's physically
difficult what uh Jonathan Kara Jordan
and Misha's group um came up with what
do you How would how would somebody in
this group uh continue that uh everybody
has oh you guys are all normally
distributed names so I've heard from
everybody so um would you like
to is a representation of
anything with a
pitch and
duration I groups disagree with that
yeah so I'm coming at this from the
percussion perspective where a note
doesn't necessarily need a pitch and it
doesn't necessarily need a duration okay
so so we have um not necessarily on that
so do you have a positive did your group
come up with a positive
um uh definition from that I don't think
our group came into agreement good let's
hear something is a note as a
representation of an instance of stri in
something an instance of striking
something okay anybody
um so it's Matthew anybody um want
to want to um go
forward with that like sorry I can't
talk and write something else at the
same
time
anybody's that's um perfect to for out
things while you're speaking uh anything
with a pitch and a duration I think an
airplane on a airline flight has its
pitch and duration right so we I'll
start calling them Notes too no I'm just
just having fun just trying to just
trying to get us to think so we can
start making things how we're going to
make this happen for a computer I I like
both of these an instance of striking
something so yeah I feel like that
doesn't really apply to certain
instruments like violence for example
you don't have to anything to issue next
not
good so it's somebody who hasn't spoken
want to defend an instance of striking
something as applying to the
violin yeah go ahead Vanessa so I mean
if you want to be annoying you can use
like a version of striking in a much
more General sense necessarily be like
hitting anything just be when you're
moving a bow across strings you can say
that that counts as like a form of
striking even if it's not like the most
straightforward definition okay about a
wind
instrument
okay who's you y all most of you are are
Juniors and seniors and things so y all
most of you all have gotten through your
um physics mechanics uh General
Institute requirement anybody want to
say how do what's how's sound
produced or perceived maybe moving
vibrations of air vibrations of air good
and and so there's a lot of air
vibrating way way down the street why
why do I not hear
it the inverse Square law yes that might
that might be but what what is not
happening with the movement of air it's
not reaching our ears it's not reaching
our ears it's
not what what what is the what is one of
the first thing it reaches in our ears e
drum ear drum oh so maybe there is a way
so we could say an instance of something
striking something um such as air
striking a
drum
before half an hour of you ago how many
of you would have said that that's a
note
what's it
striking it doesn't need a strike you
said it's a representation of oh it's a
representation of something striking
good good okay any other things that we
want to do with confusing confusing
definitions before we get to the one of
the points of this
class any other really um great
beautiful things that wasn't covered
here
by the way I I forgot to do this part on
there
um how many
notes okay so if there's something when
you play that the three different sounds
being done could be considered three
different notes so is a chord a note or
is a chord a bunch of notes not or is a
chord something
else I'd say this because we're going to
spend the a lot of the first problem set
in the next week is going to be on how
to represent music for the computers for
the computers as as
1960s for a computer so how do we um how
do what kinds of choices will lead us
into bad places fastest and which Ones
Will Keep Us in good and useful places
for the longest amount of time notice I
didn't say which ones will never lead
you astray because you're always every
definition that you're going to encode
into a computer at some point is going
to completely screw up something for
instance
um we might say one
note add a little ornament to
it still one note in some certain senses
but y that kind of turn can really
change everything so those are going to
be coming up over and over and over
again how to represent for a computer
and whether or not any one
representation is going to work um
somebody said a note is a representation
of anything with a pitch and a
duration um there are some people who
use the term note and the term pitch
absolutely interchangeably
and I do it sometimes also you what
pitch was that what note what note did
you play um things and other people use
a note to mean the pitch and the
duration as two different
entities now
obviously that also leads to certain
contradictions I would hope that we
think that an eighth note is a
note right I mean it has the word note
in its name we're not we're not talking
about uh Quavers in in Britain I mean at
least here in good old us OFA we put the
word note in our eighth notes but by
this definition pitch and duration and
eighth note itself is not a
note because it doesn't have a pitch so
we're going to be finding that we're
going to going back and forth quite
often now let's um your problem set is
going to be dealing with certain
representations of pitch at least the
non duration part of something I I will
say uh I some will pop ahead when when
the um when the lecture is getting too
cerebral and things like that um in
music 21 the software we're going to be
using quite often this is probably the
best closest definition to how music 21
Associates um things it's something with
a conceived of single pitch and it
conceived of single
duration and that might mean that
something like this is conceived of as
having a single pitch
or this is conceived of as having a
single pitch that's a Trill sign um but
there are other times when we don't
conceive of something as a single pitch
um and duration so let's talk about
representations of duration so we've
gone from the trick questions and now um
now I hope I haven't like uh ended your
faith in humanity in the class now I
want to go to some a little bit um more
thinking about standard situations and
not weird tremolos and gandos and all
that stuff um want to think about how
are some ways you might represent pitch
uh duration for a
computer and we'll
say um
I'm going to put the term here
musical as if somehow there's a
different world of time in music than
there is in everywhere else it's sort of
there's three kinds of time in the world
there's one on your clock there's one on
music and there's the one they teach you
about in relativity class that you hope
you never hear again right um so
thinking about this what are some ways
that you might do I think we've we've
grouped enough I think people want to be
able to shout and some people whose
names are toward the beginning and end
of the alphabet might want to be able to
say so what are some of the things that
a musical duration representation might
include okay I think that's that's good
enough I I I think it's it's sort of
like doing jumping jacks you just you
know sort of get get the thinking
calisthenics going so um what what's
some of the things that you might do for
representing duration Jordan said saying
yeah yeah like seconds or seconds good
now let's think about it um
we we'll make our default assumption for
this class that we're thinking in Python
of course obviously any halfway decent
programming language can go for another
so how are we going to represent seconds
for a note yeah go ahead oh was that I
guess like typically don't we use like
TI and that kind of like well we'll get
to that keep that word there for a
second great but what kind of um what
kind of is string a good
one array how are we going to represent
seconds yeah go ahead like a float float
okay
good why not
int yeah just shout out yep go ahead
because we can have in between like good
good we can have in between great super
um other other things I'm going to uh
other things you might want ways you
might want to represent
duration yeah go ahead Matthew fraction
fraction good that fractions seconds as
a fraction or or so thinking both uh
represent section seconds as a fraction
instead of a float so you don't have the
Precision issues of a float uh um I also
think it might make sense to represent
it as a beat and fr okay okay well okay
we go that's that's two things we have
beat there good good we'll keep keep
going what are some other things CU um
that we might do yeah I was also
thinking fraction but like fraction of
whatever measure you're looking at
fraction of measure so if you have like
a three four
measure and you had a half note that
would be 2/3 of the yep okay so good 2/3
that's a particular place where the
difference between float accuracy and
fraction uh came can can be very very
important good our beat and fraction of
measure um basically saying the same
thing uh with a reciprocal relationship
can somebody come up with a reason not
to yess I mean not necessarily because
like something could be on the second
beat and have like a duration of one or
it could be a second beat and have a
duration of Two And if it was a fraction
of a measure their values would be okay
good so we have beat as in what beat is
it on and and that would be very
different um if we thinking about how
many beats does it last though because
so thank you Vanessa fantastic um is
that basically the same as what fraction
of the measure is
it thank I see Matthew but I want to
want to get I think I'm going this way
cuz I'm camera shy uh so let me let me
lean in over here see if there's things
are anyone want to who who says it's
basically the same
thing and we can go all the whole room
who says it's it's it's could be quite
different okay go ahead I guess it was
like depends on what you define the beat
as so it's like 58 time or something oh
okay so five eight we'll say we'll do it
as this I don't know if people know that
symbol um
so how many beats does this
get two in some ways and how many this
one three good and now give me another
number that we could use instead of that
for a lot of five8 yeah 106 106 yeah we
could we could do any other good good we
have an infinite number of non-reduced
fractions we can do great I love that
that um how about
this no I won't write that yet
um how many beats does this
get three three is a good answer and
there's another good answer one one from
one one two right so how many beats does
this get
so there's some ways of doing it when I
put this symbol I'm saying I'm going to
go one one two one two and they're
they're not so a beat can actually
change its length during a measure in
some representation so this this is one
of the ways I was thinking not exactly
the same same thing but pretty pretty
close good let's see what are some other
ways we might represent duration for a
computer
I'm going to go back to the uh in just a
little bit the um the names the some of
the things I've heard otherwise I heard
I heard something over here that um I
think I think Adam or say one of you
Derek like an attribute like a DOT is
like an attribute great so we might keep
cheack of attributes like how many dots
does it
have good anything else like that thank
you
super yeah yeah you take a number for
the nth note it is so if it's an eighth
note you say eight okay dots would be an
eight dot eight okay so we can represent
it as now
um eight dot works pretty well as a
float but is there another way we might
consider that if we're talking it works
well as a string it works better as a
string right because eight dot dot
suddenly you're you're kind of getting a
crash error right so that's one way you
can do it um other
ways and then so we would say 16 dot or
something like that good good what are
other attributes we might want to
represent to talk about the duration of
a
note are all notes um yeah you could you
could also have things in the triplet
you could have things in the
triplet yeah
good you can also have things in a
quintuplet right see if I can squeeze
this
in and you can also have
things in a triplet within a
quintuplet this is called nested tuplets
um
so I will guarantee you I have seen at
least 20 representations of notated
durations where the tuplet was
originally created as an attribute and
then it needed to be represented as a
list array uh tupple something like that
of a tupple of tuplets try to say that
10 times fast um for a indeterminate
number of tuplets that might be applied
to a certain notes so these might be
certain things good uh anything else
that we might use to represent duration
yeah go ahead certain markings like
Stato or like good so we might have um
modifying Ying uh I don't know
articulations and expressions or
markings well it's called markings
because who knows what they are
markings I'll make a formada on my eye
good so um yeah we have our dots
maybe more defin
good so we can think of tudos that those
affect the duration great now I don't
want to um go too much further on this
um now our music is on uh I was going to
use obsolete formats a CD or streaming
what are the most um useful
representations of
duration of notes let's
say or other things which ones of these
are most
useful yeah I've heard you a couple
times from you so great super Ms got it
who else got
one is this a great duration that you a
representation that you're hearing of
the duration of a note when you're
listening to streaming
music maybe not but but boy that could
be useful for other things what about
seconds that's going to depend
on let's say you're listening just for
fun seconds very good no maybe not I
don't I don't usually hear seconds but
who's somebody who involved in the
streaming music process who might really
care about seconds of
notes I guess like computers the
computers why yep and and but what kind
of human might might be really
interested yeah some editor person the
editor yeah the um the person who's
doing the recording editing they're
always going to be thinking about uh
okay let's clip from 22.4 6 to 22.0 48
when somebody coughed and will will'll
come up with something right so those
types of things come up quite a bit in
in that type of World um now what if
we're um you've written your Great Piece
it's already been recorded performed and
things and now youve send it off to your
sheet music publisher what are the ones
they're going to Care the most
about's some what's a representation
yeah John PCH dur duration the pitch and
the duration good and how are they going
to be thinking about duration how's the
engraver um that's the person who who
makes musical scores the term for that
um what's what's the engraver what's she
going to be um thinking about in terms
of
duration what do you think about when
you when you're looking at musical score
yeah um the beat and the modifying the
beats the modifi good good the um what
do what are we going to call something
uh the difference between an eighth note
a quarter note a half note St all that
stuff what do what do we want to call
that do we we all have been doing music
for a very long time we all must know
the term for that
right there is no generalized term for
it so what do we want to call it in this
class somebody shout out something or
we'll call it the the the note animal
what what animal is this note or what
flavor is this note that's a good one
actually I wish I had gone with that um
16th notes are really really tasty
today anybody have a suggestion of a
term Essence the essence what essence of
note is good good I will tell you that
Essence is better than animal probably
as a term it's probably better than
flavor and it's better than what all the
rest of us didn't say because the first
thing you have to do when you're
representing for a computer is come up
with a name for everything yeah Vanessa
oh no okay but come up with a name for
it what duration the duration okay so we
might have the duration of a duration is
a quarter and the number of dots is two
a lot of representations do that the um
I think Mei calls that part A duration
so that's a very good term for it other
other
terms get good at naming things come up
with names fast in this class so let's
let's just pepper pepper some pepper
some bad names for it Jonathan what's
what's that almond the Almond what
Almond is it I
think I mean I the length what length
good what length does that not it's a
quarter note what length does that know
it's an eth note there might be a better
term but that's a pretty good one that's
good yeah I feel like span isn't what
span I like that what span I it might
not be so so perfect but you know it's
it gets us when you think think about
things what's something that expands um
things that people uh spend a lot of
time especially what course three uh
thinking
about bridges good and when you start
thinking about bridges what's something
that we haven't even thought of that
looks like a bridge when we think about
durations and notes slurs slurs ties
good slurs ties I was also thinking of
beams any of those good so start when we
start thinking of terms like this we
start thinking of cases who had thought
about ties and slurs in your
definition who had thought about
Beams I I hadn't thought of TI and so
when we do these types of things
suddenly why something is a good name or
might not be a good name can help us
think about what other things we're
going to have to represent I'm looking
at the time we're not going to be able
to get through all the different types
of representations here but but good now
what would it
take let's say you have
this what's it going to take that's a
dotted quarter note that's not a not a
trick question what's it going to take
for you to figure out how many seconds
that is who has performed music from
sheet music in this class in your life
okay it's basically
everybody so when you do that you have
to decide how long you're going to play
that right you might not even be
thinking it in your head I've never been
like okay I'm going to play that for3 3
six5
seconds um how do we how do we go from
this to a number of
seconds yeah good oh sorry there was two
in a row going behind first U well it's
based off the tempo based off the tempo
good has Tempo been included I suppose
it's almost implicitly included in beat
but Tempo is this particular term so we
have Tempo how do we measure tempos
Tempe Tempe
what's that be beat per minute
good beat per
minute so what do we need to know also
in addition to Tempo in order to figure
out how many beats something
is we all think of 44 right so yeah Jake
you intentionally say 365 because it's
38 of
the7 375 but yeah whatever I I don't
know it was something something like
that yeah I I I I very rarely do
anything intentionally so so maybe it's
karma um uh what do we need to do to get
beats per minute how many beats is
this depends depends good depends on the
everybody shout it out time signature
good so suddenly moving from this
representation of notes to seconds we
need Tempo in beats per minute and a
time
signature
good let me give you another one what if
I said the tempo here
was
Alro ma non
tropo okay the other thing if it gets
too much longer than that the other
thing we need is an Italian dictionary
right U algro but not too Allegro not
too much um so what do we need also in
order to convert this to seconds
let's take a take a stab at it you guys
have all been speaking pretty well
Hannah I don't think I've heard from you
in a little bit what would you say you
need in order to convert this to I say
knowledge of
what knowledge of like what it means in
terms of the temp knowledge of good
knowledge of a conversion do can you
give me a conversion maybe what it means
what it a conversion to let's say
BPM what would be uh what's somebody uh
Hannah if you want to or pass it along
to somebody else take stab what are you
going to name
that algro
approximately seven no okay two million
no okay good we we're we're narrowing it
down uhbe around like 110 110
good anybody want to go higher than 110
what do you want to go with 126
126 very specific number um any anyone
want to go
lower I'm going to go a little bit lower
and say
90 because the other thing that you need
to know is the cultural
context and
because each of these
things changes so much handle has a
Tempo marking of Allegro
Adagio what does that mean those are
like contradictions that's like you know
how how do you like your cereal I like a
hot cold um yeah but at a particular
time that is so sometimes we ignore
quite a lot of these right uh I know I
use uh and by the way Han I pretty close
I think I use 118 in a lookup table when
I have no idea what I want to do from
Allegro um or sometimes I've used 126
I've used other things 110 110 I usually
use as the the it depends on whether or
not I have a conception of the term Alig
gretto in which case I need to make room
for that but yeah 11's also very good uh
good by the way every guess that people
are doing has been really really really
good in this class so just just keep
taking the guess and I'll when we start
talking too much then I'll you know then
I'll I'll slow it down but good so these
are all the various things that we might
do to convert from one to another um
there was one other Tempo um uh one
other way that we could measure duration
that I think uh Marlin said um that I
was like sh not yet not yet not yet but
comes very important do you remember
what we said tick ticks good so you can
measure on the number of bugs that get
into your hair when you go hiking right
no what do we what do we mean by a tick
this has a different meaning than from
my understanding is how like the
computers process like whatever program
or application and that me kind of like
tis and so that kind of dictates how
what a second is based on great yeah so
what we can do is we can think of time
as somehow
discreet that time moves forward and by
the way there's some there's some uh
theoretical physicists who've been uh
trying to study whether time actually is
discrete and moves forward in know 10 to
the Nega
58 seconds or not um but but that we can
think of musical time as a screet number
of something in a purely computer world
like
tix which is both brilliant and a way of
just um shuffling later to some other
later part of the program the actual
conversion of this to seconds or to
quarter notes or to eighth notes or
anything like that
um but it's very very useful the one um
thing that you term that you may have
heard of before midi the midi file
format the midi things midi tends to
measure everything in ticks um there's
there's some some things are not and
it's a little bit of a simplification so
ticks end up being sort of ticks per
second or ticks per tick per second is a
pretty good one for Tempo and the other
one ticks per
per per quarter note comes up quite a
lot
um
intriguingly because of the problem of
68 and 5'8 and these weird things um
measure fundamental measurements in
terms of Beats have not primarily been
taken on by um by comp by people who do
um musical representation it's generally
seen as a slightly higher representation
which is ironic because it's one of our
fundamental ones for as musicians right
me you think of that oh that lasts half
note it lasts two beats right and then
somebody reminds you oh what about cut
timeing like uh you ruin everything
right you know because we generally do
some things like this
um I will share now what um I ended up
in my program in music 21 deciding
that for some reason the quarter
note is the fundamental measure of
everything else so that um everything
send to get measured in quarter
lengths which is a terrible term boy I
wish I had come up with something better
uh Essence that's almonds I wish I had
measured in Almond because quarter
length takes a very long time to type
with the camel case in the middle um and
and we didn't have uh what is it get
GitHub autopilot and things like that um
um yeah by the way I didn't mean to put
um no chat GPT on the syllabus I put it
on uh the thing later today you have fun
with it but not when we're doing any
sort of um writing your essay or
anything like that but we maybe we'll
come up with a music a chat music or
something later on the semester and try
to see how we can um do things like that
but yeah uh I wish I had come up with a
better thing but almost everything
measured in quarter lengths what's nice
about that is how many quarter lengths
is a quarter
note one one good good good we're all
we're all still awake I know it's Friday
late and things but yeah so I don't um
what how many quarter lengths is a
quarter note in
68 one one how many quarter lengths is a
quarter note in algro one so so these
things but then how many seconds is
something that's 1.5 quarter lengths ah
now you have to keep up with everything
so you can kind of think about when
you're thinking about now let's get to
the first word in this class it's not
representational music theory it's
computational when you're starting to
think
about I'll abbreviate it quite often as
Q L um
to
SEC and maybe we'll say sex are floats
in this case
case uh I've use a lot of typed python
by the way where if you haven't ever
seen this um you'll put put this in to
say what I expect to do so it's sort of
you know the uh you know all the all the
um all the joys of having to type more
things without type safety um it's not
so good but what do we want to put in as
our attribute or attributes here we're
going to return a
float what's the first thing that we
that we need ql to
seconds many how many qls yeah so maybe
it'll be ql some people like to do ql in
and that's going to be measured in what
do we want to make
that
float good could be a float in probably
not good enough name something not
representational um as an INT in in
quarter lengths eighth note good good um
the issue I tend to sometimes use the
fraction class if you haven't ever done
that because uh the first time they had
three uh triplets add up actually
triplets work fine five quintuplets adds
up to
1.1 uh quarter notes that's um why I
started moving that but floats pretty
good good what so that's attribute one
is that anybody want another attribute
in there
qu length seconds yes the Tempo Tempo
good so we can define a Tempo object and
now we're going to see um or struct or
some some kind of a thing well Temple
could be a a basic thing it could be a
float right what else could it
be what do we if we're not thinking
about algro monopo as used by handle as
opposed to uh mlon or something like
that what do we
yeah beats per minute beats per minute
okay so we have beats per minute that's
the most common one right so that's
going to be what do how do you measure
beats per
minute oh sorry sorry what what how do
we want to represent it float
good
so we passed in first thing a quarter
length second thing a Tempo um is that
enough
why not time signature time signature in
order to Define what what are we
defining by the time signature how many
beats in quarter length is great beats
per quarter
length so TS will measure in beats per
quarter
length and what do we want to make that
also float
good let's let's do this you don't need
any sort of go ahead grab laptops let's
Implement quarter length to
Second let's do it as paired programming
so we learn from each other so um the
person on the left is the who who's done
paired programming person on the left is
the driver unless unless the person on
the left doesn't have the thing and
that's your your left not my left um and
everybody else will that it's 4:34 will
take about 10
minutes okay just just just before we we
continue and start going on things how
many people wrote five test cases before
you started how many people wrote 10
test cases how many people wrote one
test case one test case how many people
wrote zero test cases okay this is
you're going to hear this a couple times
the next class and stuff and this is
very different guys just one second you
get back into it very different from a
lot of the especially intro level CS
class at MIT but because this isn't a
really big established field I I I told
all yall that you're really you this one
of the very few classes like this right
one of the really important things is
writing test cases and especially
looking at corner cases so get in the
habit of this you're going to if I'm
feeling nice I might give one or to test
cases with correct answers on things but
a lot of it is sit down and think at 60
beats per minute at um 44 how many how
long what's the answer for a quarter
note for
one one good least make sure your code
does that before we go on so keep going
try try some running and try
some okay let's let's all come back
together for a bit because this this
isn't the problem set and I want to want
to kind of move on and things
what one of the terms I heard a lot um
for uh was this one let's do a
dimensional analysis or things like that
for somebody who didn't use that term or
who doesn't we're all coming from
different backgrounds and things what's
a dimensional analysis sto geometry
story geometry well thank you for
obviously skating for
there uh we'll get you other the called
what's that called stochiometry
stochiometry I i' I have I I must have
failed trigonometry so I didn't get to
that one what what is
what okay what what what what what what
that mean I honestly I just learned a
new word thank you that's just
dimensional analysis for chemistry
that's just dimensional analysis for
chemistry okay good I I we remember I I
was up the river so we didn't we didn't
learn these things um uh what's the um
what what do we mean when we're talking
about dimensional analysis yeah it's
like a conversion between equivalent
units conversion between equivalent
units good what are some of dimensional
analysis things you uh you've done
before this
class other things Yeahs physics so so
what's what's a dimension what's kind
try convert like um where Str is like
meters per second like miles per hour
great meters per second to miles per
hour and absolutely thank thank you so
we have the particular conversion there
so we have meters seconds miles hours
what what were some dimensionality
things uh uh Dimensions that that you
use now that you might not have used in
your past
before yeah beats quarter lengths beats
per quarter length it beats quarter L
quarter length per beat good beats
quarter lengths absolutely um you've
probably done heard beats per minute not
everybody has thought of it as okay then
I have to convert to um beats
per beats per second which is not
something we think about we're very very
good at think about beats per minute as
musicians we're very very bad at think
about beats per second or seconds per
beat and then beats per what was the
other thing beats per quarter
length awesome so that came up quite a
bit on on things going on what were some
other things that seemed to um stump or
be be fun or interesting or that you
learned from programming this I heard a
lot of we don't need the time signature
I think I think I heard that aloud at
least three or four times so but what do
you do if you have the time signature
and the problem let's say we're leaving
out that 5'8 where the beat changes
stuff how do we convert from um time
signature let's let's think of time
signature first as a struct as a as a
two Tuple of numerator and
denominator how do you convert a
numerator to denominator into um beats
per quarter
length what is 44 how many beats per
quarter
length good what is uh
22 how many
beats oh good I I did I did hear it but
I heard a lot of I love it this is this
is why I'm hoping to get to his class I
heard a lot of very loud wrong answers
and then very very trickling right at
the end of little whispered right answer
uh how many how many beats per quarter
length for cut time for two
two two two and I also heard
whispered somebody had
1 12 how many beats does it take to play
a quarter note in 2
two how long does each of these is that
correct am I wrong this
time half a beat this is half a beat and
it gets a quarter note this is half a
beat and it gets a quarter note okay
what about in
32 half 1 half so what do what part do
we not need
need
numerator so for this particular thing
we don't need the numerator we would if
we yeah go ahead Matthew don't we need
the numerator in 68 do we need the
numerator in 68 yes so what do we need
the numerator
four we only need the numerator to do a
modulo
operation to see compare if it equal Z
but is that good enough because because
68 98 128 these all generally default in
most conceptions not all but in most
conceptions as the the number of Beats
is divided by three on that so is that
good enough does everyone know modulo
notation like the remainder when divided
by three equals zero so does that work
68 great uh 88 nope that's a normal one
98 great
so 64 great that six how many beats does
have in in treated in this in this
way two two one two one dot dot two dot
dot yeah I say it has two in I one two
three four but I I'm giving you the big
one great so six 64 How many does 916
have three three great so this this
works right we've we we have all our
good test cases
there yeah you're smiling big anyone
else smiling big you're smiling big what
what's the test case we've missed 34
34 so 34 has one
beat right because you divide by three
so what what do we have to
do this if the numerator modu 3 equals
0 and
num not equals
right that's assuming we've already done
our assertion that n numerator is
positive and all the other things right
so these are the algorithms that you
already know in your head for music by
being musicians but they are not the
algorithms that you have been
programming before here's a particular
one that's that I always like to do and
I don't think we're going to have time
to go through it today because you guys
have been such great participants in my
um in my terrible uh employees and
things um given a a note given a quarter
note let's say we we'll keep it really
simple because we're already in we'll
call the quarter note one one quarter L
one beat or
something given a DOT how many
beats 1.5 given two
dots three
dots oh somebody had is Trail off good
end
dots what is the
formula yeah so so working this out and
if you want I'll put a link online uh
once I originally had to write out this
formula because I kind of needed it it
becomes kind of fun so um yeah so it and
end up being uh what do you call them
these are meren numbers which are not
the same as meren primes they end up
being um sort of n minus one uh what is
it 2 to the N - one over 2 to the N so
you end up one and one half slightly
under one and 3/4 1 and 78 so 2 to the N
whatever so you can to figure out okay
and hopefully that works um two to the
zero sorry that that goes down below
that's not part of the exponent I should
make that nicer 2 to the N minus one
over 2 to the N sorry I haven't been
writing on whiteboards in a year so My
technique is a little low so does that
does that work or one plus right yeah so
uh does that work for zero dots what's
two to the
zeroth what's two to the Zer one one
minus one is zero so that cancels that
out as long as that's not zero there
good so we get one what happens if you
have a negative one
dot 2 to the
1 12 minus
one2 over two to the um over 2 to
thetive
1 over2 and what's that end up2 over2 1
+ 1 equal zero zero so every time you
don't hear any music no you're hearing
the grand Symphony of negative one
dots I think that's a good place to wrap
up