yes so we are delineate uh we are
transforming information overload into
insights for
biofarma um and uh I am the co-founder
and CEO and I was also an MIT PhD
candidate in biological
engineering oh my slides are
stuck okay there we go um so I also have
about 7even years experience Building
Systems pharmacology models uh for
companies like fiser and AST zica so
help them design their clinical trials
um optimize doses things like that I'm
joined in this endeavor with my
co-founder Jo ibal who is an expert in
digital transformation software
Solutions primarily in the Aerospace
industry um and delinia is a growing
team of about 20 engineers and
researchers focused on applying AI to
accelerate analysis workflows uh
primarily in biopharma and currently
we're going through the Y combinator uh
ACC program we're coming up to the end
of the batch so we're in San Francisco
right
now so you know the computational
analysis workflow is still really
scattered um depending on the industry
it can require a lot of manual effort to
digitize and structure information into
data sets that align with internal
processes specialty software or
guarantee the kind of high accuracy you
need in a domain like bio PHA so even
with large language models things like
deep research still PhD scientists are
doing this type of work manually um so
for example uh some of the customers we
work with in large Pharma they have
teams of scientists um spending months
to create a single data set um so we
want to accelerate that take away that
manual effort so they can focus on the
science so our platform processes really
any source and structures it to create
quality controlled data sets um as well
as performing some an automated analysis
on top of that data um so we can process
things like research papers we also
pretty uniquely get out the numerical
data from plots and graphs so a lot of
the scientific information that exists
out in the world is kind of Trapped
Behind These plots and graphs and we
have a custom model to get that data out
um so we use custom computer vision but
also all the state-of-the-art large
language models to extract this data we
also have a human QC team they're all
trained um in the biof fora domain to
ensure that everything is 100% accurate
um and then we have some co-pilot
assisted analysis um to help the
scientists in getting that data in the
right format or making a decision using
that
data um as a case study we helped a top
Pharma company create a small molecules
database this database was used to train
an AI model that ultimately helped them
reduce animal testing pretty
significantly um so we helped them
extract data from about 900 research
papers um we used our computer vision
methods to get out that precise
numerical data from graphs like this um
some of them were even more confusing to
look at because they were from papers
from even the' 70s and stuff when they
were just
scans um but then we combin that with a
contextual understanding of really how
that data was collected so what was the
experiment done um what was the compound
that was used um a lot of detail and
constructed a 23,000 data point data set
for them to um Plug and Play into their
AI
model and so there's a couple of things
that make us really unique um one is
that were fit for purpose so just from a
semantic description of your goal um you
can find the papers that um align with
that and then extract that very specific
numerical information out um so plots
and figures is another one of our unique
uh advantages and then we structure the
data and clean it across all of these
different sources so that it meets um
certain requirements and then the
structuring is aligned with internal
processes or specialty software um so
it's really um you know easy for them to
continue their workflow and they don't
have to change the software that they
use to do the analysis they don't have
to change um their processes it's all
aligned um so we've made a lot of
progress uh up to this point so we have
data service contracts with uh two large
Pharma companies um we're going to be
acknowledging some of their Publications
um we are a preferred vendor of data
sets for one top Fara company um and as
I mentioned we uh were lucky to receive
the early acceptance to y combinators
winter 2025 batch um which we're uh
finishing up right now and we're really
looking to partner with biofarma
companies especially those that have
needs related to Data Mining and
structuring of complex information
especially when the workflow around it
and the software is also uh kind of
complicated so please reach out
thanks Emily great thank you so much um
so you're obviously first focused on
biofarma but um can you tell us if this
can be applied also to maybe a few other
areas yes absolutely um we definitely
believe it's flexible um we are also
working with people in the process
engineering space um they have similar
problems um and uh yeah definitely this
is flexible to this great and also um
for companies that have developed
internal large Lang language models
Solutions um is there flexibility to
integrate um this as well yeah that's a
that's a great question so definitely
especially the module that gets out the
numerical data from plots and graphs um
I suspect that is a problem that other
um Industries face but currently there's
no AI solution to do that and that could
be a standalone module so um definitely
uh we could explore that than thank you
so much emilys