Okay. So my plan for today is to start
off by showing you how to derive the
generating function for Catalan numbers
and then I will show you how to find the
formula for Catalan numbers using the
generating function and finally I will
um you know answer questions for you
know
because we're having a Thursday And
this Catalan number generating function
is not going to take the entire hour and
a half. I will um throw the floor open
to questions about what to um no about
material for the test. And so the test
covers everything we've done so far. I
don't think there are going to be any
Catalan number generating functions on
the test. So, but you know seeing the
material for today is not going to hurt
you on the test because it's more about
generating functions.
Okay.
So recall that the Catalan numbers
counted a whole bunch of different
things and
Catalan
numbers
count
binary trees
or maybe I should say rooted binary
trees.
So
here are the five rooted binary trees on
se seven nodes.
There we go.
So C sub3 equals 5. And they count dick
paths.
So dick walks were walks that never went
below zero and go from zero to 2n. So
for
for C3 there should be five of them. And
there are
um wait I want to go up twice down and
then over
and down here. Let's do up down up down
down and up down down down down.
Okay. So how would you get a generating
function for Catalan numbers?
Well,
you want some kind of recurrence.
And
so,
well, first let's start out by looking
at binary trees.
So a binary tree
well unless it's a binary tree on one
node it starts with a vertex and there
are two
um
you know there's a two branches because
in our definition of binary tree every
vertex has two branches coming out of it
and now on this branch we have t
Let's call it A and this branch we have
TB
and suppose
we want to say count C subn
um
let's say C subn which is the number of
binary trees on
um
2n minus3 nodes I Yes. No. 2 n + one
nodes
is going to be equal to sum j = 0
through n minus one
c subj c n minus j minus one. Why?
Well,
number of possibilities
for this tree is C subj because it's
just a smaller Catalan number. And if
this side
has 2 J minus one nodes, this side must
have two N minus J minus one nodes.
And so this is
number of possibilities
is
two sorry is
c sub n minus j minus one.
And when you combine these two trees and
add a node you get
uh Catalan number C subn.
So C subn equals summation J= 0 N minus
one CJ C N minus J.
And we can check that if you want with
the Catalan number three
I'm sorry five
um
14. Sorry, I cannot remember my Catalan
numbers. So here 14 should equal 5 * 1 +
2 * 1 + 1 * 2 + 1 * 5 and it does. So
this recurrence checks out.
So now you know this recurrence.
How would you
write down a formula or an equation with
C of X?
I = 0 to infinity
X
to the
N
C subn.
So what's a
equation for C of X?
Anybody?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, exactly.
um C of X is equal to C of X
squared. Actually, this isn't quite
right because if this is J and this is N
minus J minus one, this is N. So, we
need to add another X here to make the
degrees, right? And um
this isn't quite right either because
c of x starts 1 + x + 2x^2 etc. And this
side is divisible by x. So this side has
one in it. So we need to add one for the
initial condition.
And now we have an equation. It's a
quadratic equation. We know how to solve
quadratic equations. So let's do it.
Um
c of x
is equal to
um
well let's put this quadratic equation
in the standard order. C of X^2
- C of X + 1
= Z.
And we have
1 that's minus B plus or minus of 1
- 4 A C that's 4x
over
2 a that's 2x.
Okay, so there's two possibilities for
this. How would you figure out which one
is the correct one?
Any suggestions?
Okay. So what is
C of
what do you get when you substitute
x = 0 and c? Well, you get 1 + x + 2 x^2
+ dot dot dot, you get one. So if you
substitute x= 0 in here and you have
the plus thing you get 2 / 0 which is
infinity. So that's not right. If you
substitute the minus term you get 1 - 1
/ 0
which might be right.
And you can easily check with calculus
that limit as x goes to 0 1 - 1 -
4x over 2x
um
is equal to 1.
So the right
value is minus
Okay.
So, how do you evaluate this?
Well,
to get the tailor expansion of this, you
use the binomial theorem. Binomial
theorem
use binomial theorem.
Um so what the binomial theorem says is
that
um I guess 1 + a to the k is equal to
+ k choose 1.
A + k choose 2 a 2 + k choose 3 a cub
plus dot dot dot
And it's also true for fractional values
of k. So 1 + a to the 12
is equal to
um I guess 1
+ 1/2 choose 1 a
+ 12 choose 2 a 2
+ dot dot dot
Okay.
And of course you have to take this and
subtract
it from one and divide by 2x.
So
um
so I'm going to do 1 -
1 - 4x over 2x. So that's the generating
function for Catalan numbers
is equal to 1 / 2x
and there's a one here as the first term
but it gets canceled by this one. So we
don't have a constant term which is good
because we don't want a 1 over 2x in our
expansion. So the next term is
um
12 * - 4x
+
12. So
12 choose 1 = 12.
12 choose 2 = 12 * - 1/2
/ 2 factorial
12 choose 3 is 12 * -2 * -3ves
/ 3 factorial etc.
>> [clears throat]
>> So this is
12 * - 12 / 2 factorial - 4x^ 2ar.
Okay, I have forgotten the minus sign
here because of the minus there.
Plus
12 - 12 - 3
over three factorial
and there's a 4x cubed.
So let's put that here
and a minus sign.
>> [clears throat]
>> So the first thing you can check is that
all of these terms are minus are
positive because this minus cancels this
minus this minus
this minus is squared. So this minus
cancels this minus
this minus is cubed but there are two
minuses here so that one cancels this
minus etc. So we can ignore the minus
signs.
Okay. So I would like to take the term
for
x= 3.
Well, I want to claim that that is
7 halves * 5 halves * three halves.
um
times
12 * 12
actually this is a minus one/2 divided
by
okay
so I guess that is five factorial
um
there's a four to the 4th Here
there's a two here and a two
to the
two to the 4th here. Well, no.
Um,
well,
I hope I haven't forgotten any terms.
So,
okay. So, what is this?
Top is 7 * 5 * 3 /
2 5th * 2 * 5 * 4 * 3 * 2 and there's a
4 to the 4th up here.
[clears throat]
So
there are five, six, seven twos on the
bottom and eight twos on the top. So
that's 2 to the 8th over 2 to the 7th
and the 3 and the five cancel out and
you get 7
equals 14.
So we did this right
and I want to claim just by
well just by generalization
that this is um going to be
um 2 n -1
c subn = 2 n -1 double factorial. So
double factorial means 2 n -1 2 n - 3 2
n - 5 all the way down to 1. So this is
7 double factorial 7 * 5 * 3 * 1
4 to the n + 1
/ 2 * 2 n + 1 times
um
should be n + one factorial.
And wait, this is x= 4, not x= 3.
And this is so this is
Yeah. 4 4th
* x cubed
over 2 * 5 factorial. So this is indeed
n +1 factorial
and this is
two well there's 2 to the n + one twos
here and another two and we have
n + one factorial. [clears throat]
Okay.
So now we need to manipulate this into
some kind of
oh I should say x to the n here
we need to manipulate this into a better
form and the way we do that is we say 2
k - 1 factorial is equal to 2
k factorial over
2k * 2k - 2 all the way down to 2k - 4.
So this is just the odd.
So this is this is the odd terms between
1 and 2k minus one. So this is all the
terms between 1 and 2k and we divide by
the even terms and we get the odd terms.
But this is just 2k factorial over k
factorial * 2 the k.
So that says that c subn is equal to
2 n factorial
divided by n factorial.
And over here we have an n + one
factorial.
Okay,
there's a 4 to the n + one on top
and
there are
* 2 n + 1 * 2 to the n on the bottom.
This 2 the n comes from this one. This 2
the n + one comes from that guy and the
two comes from
this 2x
and everything cancels out except all
the factors of two cancel out and we're
left with 2 n factorial over n factorial
n + 1 factorial which is 1 / n + 1
2 n choose n
which you should recognize as the
formula for Catalan numbers. Yes.
>> How do you get?
Oh
well
the catalog numbers are 1 one two 514
and this is just
summation
c subn x to the n is a generating
function
and that's 1 + x + 2x^2
+ 5 x 4th 5 x cubed
+ 14 x 4th
dot.
So the expansion
here are the first few terms of the
expansion. The first term you have a
minus 4x and a minus1 over 2x because
the minus1 over 2x sign minus one over
2x term here comes from this minus sign.
The second term you have 12 * - 12
/ 2 factorial * -4x^2.
So this is positive. This is minus and
this is minus. The third term you have
this minus this minus and this minus and
multiplying them all together you get a
minus sign and it cancels out this minus
sign. So it's positive. So all the terms
are positive
and
really um
[clears throat]
yeah. So um
so now that we know all the terms are
positive, we can ignore the minus sign
on this. although
you're multiplying by.
Yeah.
Okay.
So this is
another way of getting the formula for
C subn.
And I want to say that there's a
completely different way of deriving the
this
formula for the Catalan number. we
derive this equation in a completely
different way. And I figured I might as
well show it because
well because it illustrates uh you know
it illustrates a neat technique of um
generating functions that I had some
questions about in my office hours
yesterday. So generating function
Catalina numbers also correspond to dick
paths.
Okay.
So a dick path can be broken
into a sequence of
paths
with
plus or minus one steps.
And
which touch zero only at their end
points.
So
let's do it for this
dick path.
The first dick path is the sky. The
second one is the sky.
One, two. The third one is the sky. And
the fourth one will be the sky.
So it's pretty clear that every dick
path can be broken into a sequence of
this kind of paths.
So
if d of x is the generating function
for paths
that
well for paths that only touch zero at
their own points
Well,
we can use the theorem about sequences
generating functions from sequences.
this to get the generating function for
cataline numbers or generating function
for dick paths. So
C of X is equal to
1 / 1 - D of X, right?
but
d of x.
Well, um,
you have
everything in D of X looks like
this
where this is a dick tap
and you have an up step on the left and
a right step down step on the right.
So every
one of this kind of paths it just comes
from a dick path where you add two steps
to it.
So this says that
d of x is equal to x * c of x
because x
to the k was twi in this
um generating function x to the k was k
was twice the number of steps in a dick
path. And to get the
raised dick paths, you add two steps to
a dick path. So you get x * c of x. So
we have c of x
= 1 / 1 - x c of x.
[cough]
[clears throat]
And you should be able to multiply this
equation
on
both sides
to get um
so we have c of x
- x c of x^2
- 1 = 0 which is the same equation we
had earlier.
>> [clears throat]
>> and you get the same quadratic equation
and you can do everything exactly the
same way as we did earlier.
Yeah.
>> Right. Okay. So,
[clears throat] so D of X are paths that
start with an upstep, end with a down
step, and never go below one.
Okay. Um,
this equals some n= 0 to infinity
d subn x to the n.
DN paths
of length
2N
which start
start
up
end with a down step and never
go below
one.
[clears throat]
So here we have
let's call this zero call this one
and we have a path up here that never
goes below one
until the last step
in which case it goes down to zero.
Now if you take off the last step and
the first step here
you get
this thing is a dick
path.
So d subn is equal to the number of dick
p of these raised dicks paths is equal
to c subn minus one because we have
subtracted
two edges from
d subn to get
a thick path.
So, d of x
equals sum
d subn
x to the n
is equal to sum
c subn.
x I'm sorry c n minus one x to the n
is equal to some
oh gosh
is equal to sum
I'm going to claim this is c sub nus1
x to the nus1
times x
And maybe we should
well
there's no no
d paths of length
zero. The shortest one is of length two.
So this summation starts at n equals 1.
And we can just say n = 1 to infinity.
And this is
n = 1 to infinity.
And you can recognize this as just equal
the generating function for catal
numbers which is x c of x.
Okay. So I said I would hold a question
and answer session in the last um I
guess 30 minutes of this
um question. So is there anything that
people want to um you have a question?
>> Oh okay.
Well, I mean that just comes from
plugging this equation into this
equation.
How did we get?
>> We got the top equation because of this
theorem about sequences for generic
functions
which
um
maybe you
maybe you used on your homework
yesterday. Although um
so let's go over this theorem about
sequences.
Okay. So suppose a generating function
suppose
a generating function
functions
counts
let's call them objects
there are a n object objects
of
size
and or size might be the length of a
dick path or or I guess size might be
half the length of a dick path but it
could be anything else anyway
can think of this as an abstract
quantity.
So we ask how many
sequences are there
are there
of
let's call these objects alpha of
objects
alpha 1 alpha 2 alpha 3 through alpha
Okay.
And these sequences can be of any
length.
And the size of a sequence
is equal to sum i = 1 through k alpha
subi
I'm sorry is equal to the size of the
sum of the sizes of these objects.
Then
the generating function for the
sequences
is 1 / 1 minus the generic function for
the objects.
And I should write down the generating
functions for the objects.
A of x=
some n=
I guess 1 to infinity alpha subn x to
the n
because you're really not allowed to
have objects of size zero
in this theorem because then there would
be an infinite number of sequences
of size k which doesn't make sense
because if you could add ar ar ar ar ar
ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar
ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar arbitrarily
many objects of size zero.
You can get arbitrary many objects of
any finite size or any arbitrary many
sequences of any finite size and that
you know that gives you infinities.
Okay. So how does this work for dick
paths?
Well,
any dick path
is just a sequence of rays dick paths.
So you have a ray. So here
actually here the dick path is the empty
path. So the rays dick path has length
two and size one. Here the dick path is
up down up up down which has size two
and the raised dick path has size one
more up down up down down.
And here the dick path is up down the
raised dick path has size two. And here
you know we have dick path of length of
size three. So the raised dick path has
size four.
And now
what we do is we use the formula for the
number of
you know we say a dick path was
just a sequence of raised dick paths. So
that means c of x = 1 over 1 - d of x.
But raised dick paths
are just
dick paths with two extra edges. So d of
x = x * c of x
and you get c of x = 1 over 1 - x c ofx.
Um there I believe there was a
generating function problem on the
homework with tiling things of length
three with
2x one tiles and you can use the theorem
about generating functions for sequences
to solve that one too.
Okay. Well, I have I have prepared
another problem which is very similar to
that problem. So why don't I present the
similar problem?
Okay.
Oh, and okay. And I actually think that
I will
um
How many
tilings
of a 2x n
strip
with two shapes of tiles which you can
rotate
and reflect if you want.
So these are the two shapes.
Use the sequence theorem for generating
functions.
And um
let
a of
let a
let's use a lowercase a a sub
n be Number
of Kylings
of 2 by N strip
with no which cannot be separated and
two
cannot
be separated.
into
a 2 by k and 2 by n minus k strip.
So in some sense this is the number of I
don't know fundamental tilings of a 2x
strip which cannot be cannot be
assembled out of other tilings.
Okay, let's let's think let's try to um
figure out what these numbers are.
So the smallest tiling
is clearly this
and this is
um
so this is a sub3 because there are
three
you know this has length three and there
are two of these tilings because you can
reflect it along a horizontal line. So a
sub3 = 2.
a sub4 equals zero. I want to say there
are no ways to tile a 2x4 strip with
those tiles.
A sub5 equals 2
because
A sub6 equals zero.
So let's call the number of tilings.
Let B subn be number of tilings.
So B subn
is going to be 2 0 2. But I'm going to
claim that there is a tiling
of B subn, but it's not a elementary
tiling because it's made up of two um
subtitles.
Um
I'm doing a bad job of drawing it.
I want to claim that there are four of
these
because you could reflect the first half
or you could reflect the second half.
And that's just this squared because you
take two A3s
and put them next to each other. And if
there are two tilings of length three,
this gives you four tilings of length
six.
A7 = 2
and um
B subn is a number of tilings where you
don't require that they're fundamental
tiling. So B subn can be made up of the
B's can be made up of two tilings
which are just stuck next to each other.
Whereas the A's we want to require that
there are no vertical you cannot find a
vertical line that splits this tiling
into two.
>> So the vertical line is defined by the
separated into K nus K.
>> That's right.
So um
and I want to claim that
a sub8
= a5 * a3 + a3 * a5 is equal to
because you can take this tile and put
it next to this tile
or you take take this tile and put it
before this tile. Or you can take this
tile and put it before that tile.
[clears throat]
So thinking about this, if you don't
want any vertical lines, the only way to
get an A
tile is
to start
with um
an L and put all these Z tiles next to
it.
and then end it with an L.
So,
a
sub 2 K + 1 is equal to two. So, the odd
the odd A's are
there are two ways of
giving a fundamental tile for odd
numbers and zero for even numbers. So
that means a of x
is equal to
um
summation
k = 1 0
k = 1 through infinity
x to the 2k + 1 * 2
= x cub 1 / 1 - x^2.
Okay.
So now let's compute this generating
function.
B of X is equal to
1 / X cub
1 / 1 - x^2.
Okay.
1 -
Oh, wait. I forgot. There's a two here.
So 1 - twice that
is equal to
okay we can multiply 1 - x^2 on the top
and bottom and we get 1 - x^2 over 1 -
x^2 - 2x cubed.
Okay,
so we have a generating function for=
sum b subn x to the n.
Okay, so we have a generating function
for b.
Now
I want to say that you can read off a
recurrence from a generating function.
Sorry, it's kind of a minor thing. Is
that B
of the top right corner of this?
>> Oh, yeah. Right.
B
um 8 equals 8.
Thank you.
>> So the it's not A8.
>> A8 equals zero.
Okay. Yeah. So, this is B8= A5 * A3 plus
A3 * A5.
I'm sorry about that. Yeah.
Okay. So, we have um
>> a question. What did you do to get to
simplify for the ax
thing before you do the um sequence
theorem?
>> Okay. Well, it's just the sum twice
times the sum of x to all odd numbers.
And
[clears throat]
um
okay, maybe I should do this more
slowly. This is x cubed
time sum 2 x
to the 2n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n
n n n n n = 0 through infinity
because the smallest one of these is x
cubed. So you can multiply by that and
then you have all the even ones after
that. And now this
you should know the formula for a
geometric series
is equal to 2x cubed over 1 - x^2
because sum n= 0 to infinity of x to the
2n is 1 - x^2.
And actually that's very easy to see. Um
because
1 + x2 + x4 + x6 plus dot dot dot * 1 -
x^2
is equal to 1. And now we have a - x^2 +
x^2 - x 4 + x 4 - x 6 plus x 6. So all
the other terms cancel out.
So this is a formula for a geometric
series.
Okay. So
what did we have? We have yeah
I want to say that you can read off a
recurrence
from a generating function.
So suppose you have P of X over
>> [clears throat]
>> um 1 - x^2 - x 2x cubed
p of x gives
initial conditions
and 1 - x^2 - x 2x cub gives recurrence.
So
this recurrence says b subn is equal to
b subn minus 2
+ 2 b sub nus 3.
So
um I guess we can
explain this.
So
summation b sub i x to the i is equal to
p of x
over 1 - x^2 - x cubed.
So what this means is that
um
I want to multiply both sides here. So
we're going to get b subn x to the n
minus
B n - 2 x nus 2
* x^2.
Oh, wait. This had a two
minus
b nus 3
x to the nus 3 and um
and there's a two here
equals
x to the n term
of p of x.
So multiplying just this by both sides
and pulling out the
x to the n term
oh * x cubed
gives you
that.
So this says that bn - bn minus 2 - bn
minus 3 equals zero unless
there's an x to the n term and p of x
and p of x is a
polomial with only a finite number of
terms. So after this finite number of
terms you have this recurrence.
So bn is
bn
Okay,
let's go back
here.
So we have b subn = b n - 2 + 2 b nus 3
b 0 = 1 b3 =
b5 = 2
b6 = 4
B7
= 2
B8
= 8 etc.
So let's see if this works.
So
B2 should be equal to B 0 +
2 B minus one. But B2 is zero and not B
not one. But that is because
we had
the um
v of x = 1 - x^2 over 1 -
x^2 - 2x cubed.
That's because this term was minus one
which says that
B2
B2 equals
B 0 minus one when you work it all out.
But after after the second term that
recurrence works great. B3 is equal to
2 B 0.
B4 equals
2 B2 + I mean B2 + 3 B1. B5
is
B3.
B6 is 2 B3.
B7 is
B5. B5.
B8 is
2 B6
plus B8 is
yeah B8 is B6 plus 2 B3 which is 8
etc.
So you can just read off
the recurrence from the bottom of the
generating function and the top
numerator tells you
um what the initial conditions
are.
Okay, any other questions?
Okay, I I also could say that you could
have figured this out this recurrence
out
without using generating functions
because
basically if you have a
Oh, wait.
uh tiling that looks like this.
There are two ways to extend it. You can
um
extend it. Use the same tiling in the
first part
and add one of these Z tiles
and add that
or you can extend it.
Okay. So this is
you know you've extended this by two. So
that gives you the formula BN minus 2.
Here you've extended this by three. But
there were two ways to do it because you
could have added this block or you could
have added this block reflected around
its ver its uh horizontal axis. So that
gives you two bn minus 3.
And you cannot extend the
empty tile
in the second way which explains why B2
is zero and not two
which explains why B2 is zero and not
one.
So you could have gotten this recurrence
without using generating functions.
Okay.
So
any other questions?
>> Yeah.
>> So like this problem intuitively is that
a n is like counting the components. So
bn is like a sequence of individual
components.
>> Exactly. BN is a sequence of these a n
components. So you get
um b of x = 1 over 1 - a of x.
>> Yes.
>> You go over how you got the bn
recurrence.
>> How I got the bn recurrence.
>> Oh
well.
So it's something I mean if you go
through our proof about how to construct
generating functions from recurrences
you know
if a genering function
has I guess summation
f subn x to the n equals Equals
P of X over
um
-
A1X - A2X^2
- A3 X cubed.
Actually this is more general than that.
P of X
gives
initial
conditions
and
we have
F subn =
A1 F nus1
+ A2 F NUS 2 plus A3 F sub NUS
EG. If
p of x = 1 + x 2x^2
then
I want to say f sub0
= 1
f sub1 = 0 and f sub2 =
>> [clears throat]
>> or well actually that's not quite true
because um
I should probably use this as the
example. We have b of x = 1 - x^2 over 1
- x^2 - x cubed.
[snorts]
So
1 / 1 - x^2 - 2x cubed
would give you f0 = 1 and
fn = f n - 2 + 2 fnus 3.
So that would give you one zero one
two
and this is
okay f4 would be f_sub_2 one again f5
would be 2 + 2 which is 4.
So this is 1 over 1 - x^2 - 2 x cubed.
But we also have - x^2 over 1 - x^2 - 2x
cubed. And this gives you basically this
except you have to you know this will
give you a minus one here and then zero
minus one.
Um the next one was min -2
and
-1 -4 and then when you add them up you
actually get the sequence of f subi. So
that gives you 1 0 0 2 0
two
um etc.
And
yeah, we have one 0 02 02
etc.