hello everybody congratulations on
getting problem set one
in now the reward is your first
unlocking video so a topic Part D this
is topic one D and you get to have
certain tools that you can use to build
future problems and solve future
problems and build future problem sets
uh using music 21 so I'm in Jupiter you
probably want to be doing this well you
can do it in Jupiter or you can do it in
your own favorite editor by the way pie
charm will really save you problems on
in this class okay so we're going to uh
introduce music 21 you can import music
21 but n not really we're going to do
from music 21 import pitch because
you've unlocked your first pitch object
and Pitch module pitch is lowercase here
so it represents a module in music 21
and uh we'll be calling things in it now
in the problem set you were probably
representing pitches as something like
this or you know and harmonically
equivalent whatever um in music 21
you'll probably want to use our pitch
object so the pitch object is found in
the pitch module it's the pitch module
is lowercase p and the pitch object is
capital P and we can do the same thing a
Shar 4 and in Jupiter we can just hit p
and get that you can also if you're on
the terminal print p and you can see the
representation is slightly different
okay so let's figure out what we know
about this pitch object so
during the problem site you were
creating functions that worked on string
or other list inputs but now we're going
to that we have an object we're going to
be calling methods and attributes
directly on it so one of the attributes
of the pitch is its name and the name
you can see is a string that's why it
has the quotes around it a sharp great
and um well where's its octave take a
guess you. octave
okay so this is nothing too surprising
here um let's grab ourselves uh a
slightly different pitch we'll say um b
equals pitch. pitch
b0 say B here is that b 0 and we can get
the pit B's name which is B also get B's
step which is also B so those two things
look like they do the exact same thing
but go back to our P object and figure
out for a second what the difference
between name and step
is okay did you figure out that P's name
has the sharp in it the P's step does
not so this says what diet onic step
what letter name is in the pitch
itself
and are these things mutable I actually
made a mistake in the four to five class
on the first day and said that these 21
objects were not mutable they actually
are and
um what uh but most of the methods that
are called on them try to not mutate by
default so but if you want you can
change it so now p is a gsh
4 P's octave stays app 4 um how do we
get that GAR 4 you could do print p.
name plus string of p.
octave you get that or there's something
called name with octave which is pretty
nice now let's create a B flat in octave
6 so we'll call it B flat equals pitch.
pitch take a second on what goes
here okay we're back and then we can get
be flat and octave six there notice by
the way again that we don't uh ever name
variables with hyphens in them because
uh it's trying to say well B minus flat
wait yeah that doesn't make any sense so
B flat is B minus
6 and uh sorry B yeah B flat 6 take a
second and try to figure out what if you
wanted a B natural in Optive -6 how
would you do
this great did you get really low B
equals pitch. pitch b i before and now
really
low. octave equals
-6 notice that the name with octave for
this is the same
as oops where was it as B
Flats name with
octave so probably you're going to want
most commonly to when you're actually
working with your with your objects to
do the two
parts separately so that you can see the
difference between that
and
that okay so now we have a pitch and
it's kind of like big whoopy dooo you
could have done this yourself and uh you
know why why do we need to do anything
with this well let's
create uh another pitch and we'll make
it a pitch that's pretty
common we call that middle C right great
so here's middle C and we can get its
midi number and so it knows things like
this if we say p. octave equals 5 now
it's middle of CL and we figure out what
its mini number is that's that's pretty
fantastic
um we can also do kind of fun
interesting things what's its name in
Spanish what's it name let's say
um see double
flop name in Spanish now I think that
that's pretty right what's his name in
German okay it's actually actually a
little bit more fun if you worked with
German names
like this
and right that's not part of the lure in
this class but kind of a fun thing to do
um we worked on the distinction between
uh midi and PS in your um in your
problem set so let's recall what does PS
stand for
get pitch space so the pitch space is
the same in this case as the midi number
they're exactly the same U some things
we can do though is well let's say we
set it to 70.5 does that have a name uh
yep that's kind of weird thing um you
can get its full
name be half flat okay so we're learning
certain things that we can do with this
but P's PS is 70.5 but midi must be a
round number so it's I guess be just be
natural the other thing is if we go to
really low B was it really low B flat no
really
low it was just be natural really low B
and get its it's oct6 get its
name and get its
PS wow that's extremely low that's what
is that 10 109 notes below middle C but
its midy number is constrained to be
between 0 and 127 okay these are just
kind of fun things to play around with
you can um do a directory on any pitch
object and see some of them the are in
here ignore the ones with underscores
for now we can see that um Oh there's uh
the frequency so let's let's
create what's the only one that most of
us know the frequency of on the top of
our
head great A4 is 440 so we're well an
American made this so it's not 442 or
anything like that
so you'll see that not everything we'll
be um working with here there's certain
things of fundamentals and um and
harmonics and and stuff like that that
we'll get to but let's um let's see what
some of these are
um are uh methods and not um and not uh
attributes so let's do P.G lower and
harmonic
and that gives us a g double flat maybe
we'll make p an A flat now we can play
around 415 yep that's lower n harmonic
is G Shar
and let's the higher n harmonic of a
flat think about it in your
head right B triple
flat okay by the way P doesn't change
that's what I said about the um this
being mostly non-mutable so we have to
assign that bple flat to something else
triple flat
flat yeah so much um great and now we
can do the bple
flat. name and let's give it full
name right
okay going back to P which is this a
flat 4 one of the other things we can do
if we want to have mutable um objects
will go lower and harmonic to get the G
sharp but let's we have we can do this
particular attribute where we can see um
in place equals
true and now it doesn't return anything
but P has switch from a flat to TSH so
you can do things however you would
like take a minute now to explore the
system and here are some questions that
I'd like you to work on while you're
exploring number one what happens if you
create a
pitch without any
arguments what happens if you create a
pitch with uh number as an argument
too big
and what happens if you create a pitch
and leave off its
octave okay those are the pretty fast
ones now some a little bit more fun ones
um how are accidentals stored on a pitch
object in music
21 do all notes have
accidentals take a few minutes and work
through that on your
own great are you back let's see what
our answers are what happens in Crea a
pitch without any other arguments
we get that it's a c and if we get what
that notes midi number
is 60 so it's a C4 okay something a
little bit strange what if you create a
pitch with a number as its
argument uh let's say
61 okay now we get a c for how does it
know it's our d flat does doesn't really
know that great
um now let's see what happens if um you
create a pitch and leave off its octave
I think we might have already seen this
but C sh we'll call
this
sharp and notice the difference here
there's no octave number shown when we
when we do this that's but when we look
at its MIDI it's still 61 well what does
this mean well it means that certain
things were going to end up um getting
uh treating octave as something that's
implicit so here if we just say pitch is
a
c and
60 let's get its lower and harmonic that
should be a B Sharp we'll call it BS
B
SHP B's AR of BS um and now let's look
at its midi
number oh it's jumped all the way up
because what it tries to do in this case
is if you give it no octave it tries to
create everything in the octave around
middle C so that's kind of neat um okay
next question is a little bit harder how
are accidentals stored on a pitch object
in reason 21 well let's look at B's
accidental
back so I didn't totally spelled that
right um and it has these little carrots
around it which probably means it's some
sort of a object thing so we'll call it
act for
accidental and see that here and we
can get the type of it oh okay it is uh
its own object and we can endure The
Accidental to see certain things that it
knows its alteration what is
that 1.0 that's the number of semitones
above the uh accidentalist object there
great um and well that's basically the
one I mean you can do um I think it has
a name
also right well that's a sharp um that
name equals flat okay we're going to be
able to change oops plat as a
string does this change hey it does now
ACC was a attribute on this bar object
so now let's see did we change anything
about
bsharp hey now it's a B flat um same
great we can see that uh we can also do
Unicode name and get okay great so we
get to see the nice if you ever want to
print something out you have all of
that the last question was do all sorry
oake do all pitches have
accidentals so let's try working on that
um acal obviously it does great but what
about C equals pitch. pitch let's make a
low C here C2 great c c do
accidental oh do I forgot to print
something well let's get the alter on it
oh we get an error
so certain
notes do not have accidental if
accidental set to
none but we can assign it explicitly an
accidental so we can call pitch.
accidental natural
and now we can see that it has an
accidental with an alteration of
zero I think this is a good enough place
to stop for a little bit with pitches
take a little break and I'll be right
back with you with durations