I'm Caroline ooler a professor in the
department of electrical engineering and
computer science and the institute for
data systems and Society at MIT and also
a core faculty member at the broad
Institute one of the world's leading
biomedical research centers at the broad
I direct the Eric and Wendy Schmid
Center which seeks to create a two-way
street between machine learning and
biology and hi I'm or ashenberg
associate director of computation
biology of the claran cell Observatory
and the B Institute the claran cell
Observatory is led by Dr romx Xavier and
for over a decade we have led pioneering
efforts to understand how cells work
together to create healthy tissues and
how that process unravels during
diseases like autoimmunity and cancer
and today we want to share with you an
exciting challenge taking place this
October so the Eric and Wendy Schmid
Center and the clareman cell Observatory
are holding the autoimmune disease
machine learning challenge we're
collaborating also with Crunch and
Foundry as well as Harvard's laboratory
for Innovation science mit's department
of electrical engineering and computer
science and the institute for data
systems and society and the Mass General
Hospital Center for the study of
inflammatory bowel disease today we're
here to talk about why we're doing this
Challenge and also to discuss the
problems at hand we'll talk about
autoimmune diseases where our immune
system mistakenly attacks our own
healthy tissues exciting new biological
data sets that could open novel avenues
for treating Pat patients with these
diseases and why we think machine
learning is the key to unlocking the
power of these data we'll also get into
the challenge itself can you design
algorithms that identify genes driving
an autoimmune disease and increasing our
risk of developing cancer now for some
of our viewers it may have been a while
since biology class in high school or
college so or let's talk about our
immune system and autoimmune diseases so
normally when we get sick say with a
virus our immune system mounts a
response resp immune cells travel
through our body to the site of
infection recognize cells infected by
the virus and destroy those cells this
response protects us against viruses
bacteria and even cancer right our
immune system has a remarkable mix of
capabilities both a built-in ability to
recognize features shared across
thousands of different pathogens and a
learned ability to recognize pathogens
it has never seen before which is what
happened during the covid-19 pandemic
however this power comes at a cost the
immune system can mistake our own
healthy cells and tissues for a pathogen
and attack and kill them this is the
basis of autoimmune disease yeah and
many of us have family and friends with
autoimmune diseases such as diabetes or
multiple sclerosis one of the most
common autoimmune diseases is
inflammatory bowel disease or IBD IBD is
caused when the barrier between our gut
and the microbes living there breaks
down and as this barrier falls apart our
immune system attacks both our gut and
the resident microbes there resulting in
chronic inflammation IBD symptoms are
painful and affect quality of life and
treatments range from steroids all the
way to surgery to remove the disease gut
tissue to make things worse IBD also
increases the risk of coloral
cancer over the past 50 years we've made
great progress in treating IBD patients
but we're really not there yet we still
don't fully understand the steps behind
behind the progression of IBD and
without this we cannot develop new
therapies or detect and treat coloral
cancer earlier so how can we reach these
critical goals so first let's talk with
a pathologist about how IBD is
diagnosed I'm Dr Angela shei an
assistant in pathology at Mass General
Hospital and an assistant professor in
pathology at Harvard Medical School as a
pathologist who specializes in
gastrointestin illnesses my role is to
accurately diagnose whether a patient
has IBD how severe their disease may be
and whether or not they have developed
secondary complications this information
guides the therapeutic approaches
doctors choose to manage their patients
disease and so how do you make the
correct diagnosis it all starts with
examining very small pieces of tissue or
biopsies that are taken throughout the
grro intestinal tract from a patient
during an endoscopy procedure this
tissue undergos process processing in
the laboratory that allows us to cut a
very thin five Micron tissue section
that is stained with two routine
chemicals hematoxilin which stains
nuclear material blue and eosin which
stains the cells cytoplasm pink this
processing allows us to visually
evaluate the composition and
architecture of the cells that are
making up the
gut here we are looking at a hematoxilin
and ESN stained image or h& image for
short of the healthy adult colon the
staining reveals four distinct layers of
the gut each with a specific function
the inner layer is the mucosa which is
the layer that comes into contact with
digested food passing through our gut
and is very important for absorbing
nutrients and water this layer is
supported by a subjacent sub mucosa
third is a thick smooth muscle layer
called the muscularis propria which
helps with peristalsis and pushing food
through the gut lastly there is the
outer advant tial layer with a sosal
surface right but how does each layer
work well each layer is highly organized
and does a lot for example the mucose is
divided into the epithelial compartment
the lamin apropriate compartment which
contains inflammatory cells and the
muscularis mucosa beneath it the
epithelium forms beautiful cryp
structures that have stem cells at their
base all of which continually
differentiate into cells that absorb
nutrients or cells that secrete
important signal
now as a pathologist I have looked at
thousands of these h& images during my
training and clinical practice and so my
eyes are quickly drawn to the pathologic
features in these tissues here we are
looking at a colon tissue from a patient
with ulcerative kitis the most common
form of IBD and what you will work on in
this challenge you can immediately see
how much the gut tissue changes during
ulcerative colitis we see dramatic
differences in the tissue layers their
anatomical structure structures and the
individual cells when I diagnose ulcer
of colitis I look for several features
for example here I see distortions in
the cry morphology and here I see an
infiltration of immune cells including
neutrophils remember inflammatory bowel
disease is an autoimmune disease so the
arrival of these immune cells makes a
lot of sense I don't just use these
images of the gut to diagnose IBD I also
use them to look for warning sides of
cancer as the risk for coloral cancer
can be up to two fold higher in I
patients here we see low-grade dysplasia
which are abnormal epithelial cells in
the gut that may develop into cancer
depending on the severity of the
dysplasia we may try to remove the
tissue through an endoscopy procedure or
even remove larger portions of the colon
to prevent cancer improved understanding
of dysplasia could lead to earlier
detection and more informed patient
management
decisions so routine h& images have been
analyzed by Pathologists for hundreds of
years
but I think it's important to recognize
that there are limitations to what we do
so for example all we can really tell
you is the activity of a disease at a
certain point in time what we cannot
inform clinicians and patients is how
they might respond to specific
treatments or how they might actually go
on to develop secondary complications I
think that this is a new future Horizon
for pathology and integrating what we
see on histologic findings with
additional molecular biology and
computational methods to really have an
impact on the treatment of patient
diseases so to summarize Dr sheor
Pathologists guide the care of IBD
patients by analyzing tissue from the
inflamed gut they stain this tissue with
special dyes which reveal the spatial
organization and anatomical features of
cells in the gut during IBD these
changed dramatically in Telltale
patterns allowing a diagnosis to be made
such h& images of the gut are rely
collected in hospitals around the world
resulting in a data set of potentially
millions of images while such images
have guided patient care for decades we
are ultimately using known patterns in
the tissue to label the diseases in
these images right but how can we
identify more powerful markers of early
cancer so that we can detect cancer
earlier than Pathologists can currently
do or how can we better understand who
will respond to which therapy or even
ultimately develop new Therapies
for this we need to be able to translate
from the morphology of a cell which we
can observe in an h& image to the
internal functional state of a cell
given by the activity of our
genes so we each have 20,000 genes in
each of our cells and distinct groups of
these genes are activated together to
carry out the programs within a cell now
during disease hundreds of these genes
change their activity and drive
dysfunctional changes in the tissue
therefore identifying the alter Gene
programs can highlight new targets for
therapeutic intervention and allow us to
pinpoint earlier any transition to
cancer so given how important they are
how can we measure these Gene
programs unfortunately this is not a
measurement typically made by
Pathologists and even when they do they
measure at most two or three genes but
ideally we'd like to measure thousands
and this is really where large- scale
data sets and machine learning come in
the life sciences are in the midst of a
data Revolution where it is now possible
to accurately and in very inexpensive
ways do large-scale DNA sequencing where
we have advanced molecular Imaging and
single cell Technologies allow measuring
the activity of all 20,000 genes
simultaneously in single cells for 1
million cells per experiment in addition
over the last 10 years there has been a
really exciting development new
technologies many of which have been
developed here at the broad have made
spatial genomics a reality right so
while single cell Technologies require
isolating single cells from the tissue
context spatial genomics Technologies
allow us to measure the activity of
genes directly within the tissue context
giving rise to a very high content and
high resolution view of a tissue these
Innovations in the massive data sets
they produce have really brought us to a
new era in biom medicine our ability to
generate data is rapidly outpacing our
ability to analyze and interpret it to
give you a better idea a single lab can
generate a data set that Rivals and size
the entire movie library of Netflix here
at the broad just the genomics platform
alone generated 100 pedabytes of data
last year which is 100 million gigabytes
put simply we have reached the limits of
uned human
comprehension but fortunately the last
two decades have witnessed not only a
transformation of the life sciences but
also the data Sciences as we all know
we're living in the Golden Age of AI and
machine learning but unlike in the more
traditional applications of machine
learning and AI like recommender systems
or online advertising in the biomedical
Sciences the ultimate goal is often to
understand the underlying mechanisms for
example in our autoimmune disease
machine learning challenge we want to
comprehensively identify Gene programs
in IBD by connecting tissue images
collected by Pathologists to this high
resolution view of genes active in the
tissue afforded by spatial genomics and
we want to identify genes that Mark
potential cancerous regions in the G so
the mechanistic aspect is really
important for this application the
tissue images processed by Pathologists
are cheap to collect and number in the
millions worldwide in contrast spatial
genomics data sets where we measure
genes directly in the tissue are
difficult to collect very expensive and
number less than 100 for IBD linking
these different data modalities would
give us the best of both worlds the
intricate spatial organization of the
gut tissue provided by pathology with
the detailed Gene programs provided by
genomics but how can we translate
between these two modalities this is
exactly where you and your algorithms
come into our machine learning challenge
to identify Gene programs from IBD
tissue images and discover genes that
Mark the progression of IBD to
cancer to make this happen we've
collected eight spatial genomics data
sets from the gut tissue of patients
with and without IBD and we measur the
activity of 480 genes across hundreds of
thousands of cells in these tissues from
these very same tissue regions Dr shei
performed pathology analysis and
prepared h& images so that means for
these a tissue regions we can see how
the twocc color h& image translates to
the 480 color image that measures the
activity of 480 GS but of course you
remember we said that each of our cells
has 20,000 genes so what about the
missing
19,500 genes that we never measured
unfortunately current spatial gen ICS
technology still aren't able to measure
the activity of all our genes at single
cell resolution together with h& images
in the same tissue region but we will
provide you with single cell data
collected from IBD patients where we
measure the activity of all 20,000 genes
but at the cost of losing the location
of the individual cells in the
tissue now given these training data the
challenge is to design the algorithms
that can predict the activity of all
20,000 genes given the tissue images
from Pathologists or in other words
translate from a two color h& image
taken from an IBD patient to a 20,000
color image of that same tissue region
which predicts the activity of each gene
in each cell in the tissue region this
will allow us to identify distinct
groups of genes that are altered in IBD
as well as in the transition to cancer
most importantly this will provide new
candidate Gene markers for the early
detection of dysplasia and thus early
cancer detection as well as new
potential targets for therapeutic
[Music]
interventions so here is the exact
breakdown of the challenge in part one
you will predict the activity of genes
from pathologist tissue images and we
will evaluate you on the held out sets
of tissue regions and genes to help you
develop your algorithms we will provide
you with your algorithms performance on
a validation set of tissue regions in
part two you will propose new genes that
based on your algorithms would boost our
ability to distinguish gut tissue
regions with dysplasia from those
without finally in part three you will
come up with a new metric for ranking
how well a set of genes identifies
displasia and we're really excited to
announce something unique to this
challenge which is that the top scores
from part one will have the G means they
identify as marking dysplasia
experimentally validated in the lab so
you can get to see how well your
algorithms actually perform in
identifying regions of IBD tissue that
could develop into cancer now note that
a biology background isn't needed to
participate the Eric and Wendy Schmid
Center will provide all challenge
participants with a short online crash
course the broad Institute is a global
leader in biomedical research
particularly in genetic sequencing so
this this is really a unique opportunity
to learn from leading life science and
computational biology experts the crash
course will take you through the biology
of our immune systems and IBD and how
Pathologists diagnose IBD in patients
you'll also learn more about the
technology that we use to generate the
spatial and single cell genomics data
sets from the gut that you'll be working
with the crash course will give you an
introduction to the biases of these
types of data and how to work with the
data you'll be well prepared for the
challenge at hand now the challenge will
run from October 2024 to January 2025
you can sign up as individual or a team
and we'll be giving out monetary prizes
to the winners of each part of the
challenge totaling
$50,000 the top algorithms will be
presented in the resulting
Publications now another great product
of this challenge is that the resulting
data algorithms and code from The
Challenge will be made open source for
the community to use we will also be
adding to these spatial data sets as new
experiments and data become available
and we would love for you to remain
engaged in this problem even after the
completion of this particular
challenge to achieve the goals of this
challenge we're going to need new ideas
new ideas that break through the bounds
of the traditional approaches that
address the most pressing questions and
ultimately help us intersect machine
learning with Biology so so not only
will you get to do something you love
but your algorithms could change the
course of how we diagnose and treat
IBD if you haven't already register now
we're very excited to be working with
you