Right. Good morning everybody. Uh,
welcome to a very special MPG primer
doing something different today where we
have a career panel and I'm going to
hand it off to Pam to get things kicked
off. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Michelle. Okay, great. So,
um, thank you all for coming in person
and online and it's really my pleasure
to um, introduce this panel of um,
esteemed scientists. Um I know each of
them through different channels and um I
will let them introduce themselves but I
just wanted to thank them for coming and
sharing your journeys. Um I think what
the first thing we wanted to do is have
each of you spend a few minutes just
introduce yourself tell us a little bit
about your journey and um where you
started and where you are now and then
we can take it from there. Thanks. Go
ahead Joanne.
Yeah. All right. Great. Yeah. Such a
pleasure to be back here. Uh I think for
many of us who spend time at the Broad
and it's always fun to walk back in the
doors again and uh uh so great to get a
chance to to meet all of you and talk.
For me, I started out uh probably like
many of you with a PhD in science. I
studied uh biochemistry at Berkeley and
then did a posttock actually two postocs
one in a children's hospital in Paris
and then one at Janentech. Uh after that
I was uh stepping back uh as many of you
may do and thinking about what to do
with the research background that I had.
I knew that I really loved science and I
really loved research but I didn't
necessarily really like doing research
myself. Uh and so with that I was
looking for ways to be involved in uh
you know kind of the forefront of
science and especially my interest has
always been in uh drug discovery uh and
looking for different ways to do that.
And so I went first uh to Nature
Publishing Group where I got the chance
to work with Pam and with Kyle um uh to
start up a journal called uh that was
new at the time called Nature Chemical
Biology. And so I spent a bunch of time
there getting to know the chemical
biology community, early stage drug
discovery, uh, and from there uh, met,
uh, people at the Broad and got the
chance to move here and and work here on
a bunch of different projects that were
all connected to either discovering and
validating targets uh, for drug
discovery or early stage drug discovery
uh, with small molecule tool compounds
uh, small molecule discovery.
I found from working here that I really
loved the science. I really loved the
early stages of drug discovery, but I
wanted to really be a part of then
taking that drug discovery forward and
and into the clinic and wanted to do
that on the business side rather than on
the science side. And so I went from
there to F-Prime Capital where I worked
within a early stage venture investor
uh and got to see how they thought about
science that was investable uh and how
to progress uh companies and from there
got the chance to co-found with two uh
two faculty from the broad Stuart
Shriber and Robnik Savior uh about eight
years ago or so now a company called
Janana uh where we had a small molecule
discovery platform uh took that company
through to into the clinic and proof
concept. Uh it got bought uh by a
Japanese pharmaceutical company last
year and now have jumped into a another
startup company uh with technology out
of UMass Medical uh team working on RNAI
approaches for neurological diseases.
And so uh with that I'll I'll pass over
but just to give you a sense of all the
many different kinds of places I was
able to to go and work uh with a with a
PhD in science.
>> Hi everyone. Uh my name is Laura Stppel.
I'm a partner at a healthcare based or a
healthc care specific investment firm
based in Boston called RI Capital
Management. Um I started out my career
also doing a PhD at MIT actually. I was
over at the pick pickower institute
across the street actually not at Brody
but collaborated with um Ed Skolnick was
was at the Broad at the time. Um
collaborated with his group and and the
medicinal chemistry unit doing some drug
validation and pre-clinical mouse
models. um kind of always knew that I
didn't want to be in academia, but
didn't exactly know where I would go.
Kind of assumed I would go into biotech,
more in a a research role. Towards the
end of my PhD, developed a pretty
debilitating mouse allergy. Um and mouse
was my model system. So, kind of a oh no
moment um of what am I going to do with
my life? So the the BCS U brain and
cognitive brain and cognitive science
graduate program is actually really
supportive and entrepreneurial and um
gave the grad students a ton of money to
organize a career fair. Um turns out
it's really hard to organize a career
fair. I thought like companies would be
piling in to come meet with us grad
students. Not the case. Um, so it was
definitely a heavy lift and at the time
I was just chatting with a friend and
and colleague from material science or
former grad student at the time who
worked at RA Capital and he was like,
"Well, why why doesn't RA Capital come?
How about finance?" And I was like, "I
don't think anyone's going to be
interested in finance, but thank you."
Um, but desperation got the best of me
and and invited them in and actually
learned a lot more about this world of
healthcare investing through that
process. um ended up, you know, really
resonating with um kind of this idea
that I could use my scientific training
to look at companies developing really
cool different types of of science and
drugs and modalities. Ended up joining
as an associate on what's called the the
Tech Atlas team. So, it's kind of our
internal think tank uh research engine
made up of largely PhDs and MDs that
work alongside the investment team to
diligence all the investable
opportunities that come our way. um and
ended up really loving investing um and
stepping onto the investment team a
number of years later. Um so RE Capital
is a multi-stage investment firm. What
that means is we do everything from
venture capital, new company formation,
similar to what you would think of like
the flagships and and arches and third
rocks of the world. Um and we do
everything from that to public market
investing including now as some of our
portfolio companies have matured
commercial stage uh companies. So it
kind of spans the entire gamut of of
company life cycle. Um and uh yeah as a
part of that I have an opportunity to um
not only you know look at and invest in
really cool companies but also join the
board of companies and really help shape
you know the the direction of the
company. Actually R Capital was an
investor of Janana um Joann's company
and we were really excited um you know
to support that company through through
to the end. Um, so yeah, that's the how
I got to where I am.
>> Um, hi everyone. I'm Serena Silver. Um,
I um actually know Pam from our time at
NYU in the same uh fly lab and uh
applying to PhD programs basically
around the same time. Um I did my PhD
right next door at the Whitehead. um and
uh then I did a posttock uh at Harvard
Medical School both in uh Drosophila
labs which is not your typical path to
industry. So um you know but I think
that the basis of genetics was really
key uh in my transitions while I was a
posttock I realized that you know I had
kind of been on that academic uh career
path and realized that wasn't the path
for me um and so started to look around
and understand how I could make that
transition. Um I was this was a long
time ago. So um it was the dawn of RNAI
and actually the dawn just just before
we started to be able to do RNAI and
mamalian cells at scale. And so I came
to the broad in 2006 um to lead the
first screening projects, RNAI screening
projects. Crisper didn't exist. I know
that might be hard for some of you to
believe, but um there were zinc fingers
which were really tedious and then uh
RNAI which was super exciting at the
time. And so took the experience I had
with RNAI screens in Drosophila cells
and brought them over to work in human
and mouse projects uh in what was then
the RNI platform now the GPP and uh
spent five years um building screens uh
collaborating with folks all over MIT
and Harvard and beyond um and then um
made a transition to industry. So I was
recruited to Santa Fe um so big pharma
experience uh there I was in the target
discovery uh group um ultimately led
that group and then uh moved over to
Noardis um to lead the molecular
pharmarmacology group which is another
way of saying cellular assays that
enable drug discovery. Um so both of
those were actually in oncology space.
Um my career has kind of gone from that
early discovery all the way now into
clinical. So you know at Santa Fe it was
really all about target discovery,
target validation. At Novartis it was
around actually now that we have found
the target and there's still some target
discovery there and actually some big of
the big crisper screening efforts but
now that we found the target how do we
develop the best cell assays to actually
find drugs small molecules or biologics
that act that meaningfully biologically
move the the biology the way we we want
it to to actually address disease.
Um after Novartis I I loved what we
could do there. I mean the amazing
capabilities at a place like that. Um
but you know there's also a lot of
process in a big in a big organization.
And so I was excited by the idea of
going to a smaller company where I could
have more day-to-day impact on strategy
and really be part of driving uh the
company forward. And I joined a biotech
called Fulcrum Therapeutics which is a
rare disease company. It was in some
ways kind of going back to my Drosophila
genetics days and developmental biology
days of how could we actually address uh
these genetic uh diseases especially uh
cickle cell disease um and uh
musculardrophies like FSHD.
Um while I was there uh we uh brought um
a small molecule to the clinic for cle
cell disease which is actually just had
a a really exciting readout at Ash this
week. Um a few years ago I really wanted
to go back uh to oncology um just driven
by you know I think many of us have a
lot of personal connections to oncology
um and really wanted to move back to
that space and so I joined Accent
therapeutics um first as vice president
of biology and now uh at this beginning
of of this year uh became the chief
scientific officer. So, Axen is a small
molecule oncology company looking for
precision oncology uh targets uh that
can really address uh very selected
populations based on genetics or cell
state uh in oncology and we have two
programs uh in the clinic became a
clinical company about a year ago. So,
it's been really exciting to kind of go
from those early target discovery
efforts uh now to actually you know
working with investigators and
clinicians to to bring these molecules
to patients. Um,
and uh, yeah. So, and I I was at the
Broad from 2006 to 2011. So, before this
whole like extra building was was
happening, I've actually parked like I
my parking spot used to be on so many
places that there's now a gigantic
building. It's really disconcerting to
drive through Cambridge.
>> So, I'm Kyle Vogen. I'm an editor with
Nature Genetics here based here in
Boston. Um my path uh into science
started in Montreal where I uh grew up
and went to McGill University and in the
course of my undergrad there got
interested in you know academic research
um especially in my senior year in the
honors project. So I was enjoying
enjoying what I was doing. I ended up
staying at McGill for my PhD in the same
lab that I had done my um undergrad
honors project in and um really loved
you know the process of doing science.
certainly was on a traditional academic
uh track. Um about halfway through my
PhD, I remember seeing a a job ad for an
editorial position at Cell and thought
to myself, hm, that looks interesting.
But of course, at that moment, I was
busy doing my, you know, PhD and and
fully committed to sort of the academic
uh career uh path. And um I
it was in a biochemistry department, but
doing mouse genetics and ironically, I
also developed a mouse allergy. Um, I
don't know if that would have stopped me
from working in a mouse lab, but as it
happened, I I was very interested in
developmental biology. And the lab that
ended up being drawn to is a lab that
worked primarily using uh the chick
model. Um, so at Harvard Medical School,
medical school with uh Cliff Davin. So I
came down um to Boston for my postoc and
uh was enjoying you know that process
and again thought I was on a traditional
you know academic path but um discovered
as I as I went through it that there
were certain things that came naturally
to me other things that came less
naturally to me and I noticed one thing
that other people seem to have which
which I lacked was this determination to
work through problems at the bench. Um,
and so I could, you know, uh, I could
always find energy to to read, write,
talk about science, and I enjoyed doing
experiments and loved when they worked,
but they didn't work. I didn't
necessarily have the same whatever grit
that I saw other people had. So, at some
point, I had to decide, okay, am I going
to make this academic career work? Um, I
thought I could if I really wanted it,
but I wasn't sure anymore that I did.
And I wondered what what else could I
do? and and that editing had always been
in the back of my mind because it was
something that came naturally to me in
terms of, you know, I had a lot of
opportunities to um to write, you know,
review type things. I always was kind of
the person that people would go to when
they had their manuscript and they
wanted some feedback on on it. So, um
so, but short short of it was I finally
decided, okay, I'm ready to make that um
you know, jump in that direction and
Naturics happened to be um a journal
that was hiring. So, I applied,
interviewed, got the job, and that was
in 2003, and I've stayed with the
journal um through since then, initially
working in New York City, but I
relocated back to Boston. Um, and that I
will add that that's a little bit um not
typical. Um, most editors who go into
it, some some like me do stay in it for
the long haul, other people do it for a
season, move on to something else like
Joan or or Pam. Um, so um so it
definitely can be a full career. or it
can also be a step along a career
towards something else.
>> So much. Um I think we'll ask one
question and then we'll open it up to
everybody. Um we're wondering what
skills do you use most often in your
role that you didn't expect to rely on?
Thoughts?
Uh I guess for me the
the part of my role that I like the best
is the part that's science as a
foundation but it's really connecting
with people and team and finding the
right set of people that have the right
um you know technical and scientific
capabilities but the right passion for
solving the same problem. And so it's
the
uh really the the people in team part of
it that in my mind makes the difference
between uh things really really tough
problems being able to succeed but also
it being fun along the way whether you
succeed or not. Sometimes the science
doesn't work. Uh and so I would say the
the people part of it is the part that
um the science is the foundation but
that's what I really love to be able to
to build on to do.
I don't know that this isn't surprising.
Um data analytics for sure. I mean you
know certainly analyzing my own data as
a PhD student like you're the
expectation is that you'll do that but
just developing the skill set to analyze
literally any data set that comes your
way. Um, and you know, I was very
focused on pre-clinical data when I was
doing my PhD, but now I spend so much
time analyzing clinical data and, you
know, it's a lot of the same, you know,
kind of what you need to pay attention
to, you know, picking up on small
nuances and differences and um, so
certainly like a strong foundation in
data analytics. And the other thing is
just having, you know, the kind of
executive presence to go into a room
meeting with management teams of
companies. Um, you know, and and
certainly that was very intimidating for
me initially coming straight out of my
PhD and they're putting me in, you know,
the room with the CEO and the the CMO of
this company and and I'm leading that
meeting. Um, but certainly like lab
meeting presentations and just the back
and forth and dialogue that happens
there, the ability to ask critical
questions in, you know, a productive
way. Um, those are definitely like soft
skills that I picked up during my PhD
that I use a lot of at RA.
Yeah, I would I would definitely echo,
you know, the team social emotional
dynamics uh and the the data analytics.
I would actually also say, you know,
first principles, you know, that sort of
foundation of like being able to
understand why something isn't working
or pick up on things to ask those
questions. Um, it's really, you know,
you you being be because I'm not in the
lab, I'm also like removed enough that I
can sort of sometimes kind of pick up on
those and I'm always pleasantly
surprised where I feel like I've
actually still added value even though
I'm not in the lab anymore with a qu,
you know, with a a question around
experimental design or troubleshooting.
Um, I think the other thing I I just
want to echo from what Laura said is
that the presentation skills are so
hugely important. And in my PhD, my PhD
adviser, like she was so amazing about
making us all do practice talks. You you
you'd give a practice talk and the you'd
go through it all and then the lab would
give you feedback and nitpick on every
single slide. And that was the best
training for everything I do today. Like
communicating your science clearly and
the message and the storytelling the
more you practice that you know even in
my postto there were some posttos when
they were going their job interviews
like they just went on their own. They
were like I I know what I'm I can give
my job talk. I know my sites and I'm
sure and many of them got great jobs but
there were others who actively sought
feedback along the way and just practice
that because it's going to be the most
valuable thing that you can do and just
you know having no ego about your slides
about what you put together and just
saying like help me make this better
like I had a office mate at Novartis who
actually remember in my interview like
she was actually the most intimidating
person who interviewed me right and I
was like oh I have to turn off this
person Right? And we became obviously we
became great friends but she was also
the person like if I was going to
present something if I showed her that
slide like she would be like what's that
point there right? So she was actually
like the best person to go to because
she would actually pay attention. So
both developing that skill set to pay
attention to those details in your own
data for your for your peers and when
you find that those people who actually
can give you that constructive um
criticism and feedback like cultivate
that relationship, keep asking for that
feedback, get really used to that um
because it actually will make all your
science better and all your
communication better.
Um for me the thing that stands out is
the need to be a lifetime learner and um
especially
obviously science is always you know
moving forward and even in you know a
particular subject area there's always
new things to be learning but um I'm
amazed at how much I have to draw on all
of the different things I've learned
over the years even you know at a
genetics journal sure we're publishing
genetics but we need to know
biochemistry or molecular biology or
cell biology or physiology or anatomy,
um, developmental biology. And so,
again, just having that ability to,
you know, absorb and then draw on all
that that broad knowledge base to be
able to kind of appreciate, you know,
manuscripts that are spanning across a
really broad spectrum of, um, science.
So, yeah.
Um, I thought we'd open it up for
questions. Anyone have anything? Go for
it. If not, I can keep asking, but
>> um, yeah, thank you so much for coming.
It's so cool to have like such a large
variety of the non-academia,
uh, represented here. Um, but it's still
sounds like you all had a academic
background and you all did a PhD. Um and
I know that multiple people in this room
including myself don't have a PhD but
work as staff scientists definitely on a
posttock level and have the experience.
Um now you hear often that oh it's
getting less and less important in
industry but often times when you see
job postings it's always still like a
hard requirement. Um do you have any
advice for people like me um when you
are approached or get applications by
people who don't have that formal
requirement? Um yeah any advice or how
you see that how you would approach
that?
>> Sorry. um you know so we don't require a
PhD or or MD um to join kind of our our
I guess research group the tech atlas
group that would kind of lead up into
the investment team um most of the
people do have a PhD or MD but there are
certainly some folks and some folks who
have actually stepped onto the
investment team actually one of our
managing partner founders you know
doesn't have a PhD it's really about
demonstrating the ability to you know
kind of analyze data at that level. Um,
and at RA we do have kind of a in the
application process, there's an
assignment as part of it. It's um, not
not really a case study like you would
do with consulting, but sort of similar.
Um, so there's an opportunity to prove
that out. So, you know, I think
developing a strong network and, you
know, kind of getting your foot in the
door to then be able to prove that like,
hey, you know, I actually have the same
skill set that everyone who um, you
know, was was silly enough to sit
through five plus years of of a PhD and
and posttock. Um, but yeah, I I would
say don't let it hold you back. You
know, certainly it just probably takes a
little bit more of kind of that initial
step to to get, you know, the folks
attention to to give you the
opportunity. But certainly there have
been a lot of really really impressive
colleagues that I've worked with who do
not have PhDs.
>> Yeah, I would say um a couple things on
on that like certainly um I've had
people in my teams at Novartis uh in
folkram at Accent who you know have had
and at Santa B across the gamut who've
had what we would consider like PhD
level roles, lab head type of roles
without a PhD. they generally had more
time in you know sort of equivalent
amounts of time in terms of experience
and building up that experience and and
knowledge. What I would say in terms of
critical things to be able to make that
jump. If you think about what someone's
being asked for in a job application or
in you know if they're coming from a PhD
or postoc they have a story a scientific
story to tell in terms of what they've
done as an independent strategy thinking
through the next steps planning those
next steps 100% many people without P
you know that's not does not require a
PhD to do that right but I think what
you want to pay a lot of attention to is
how are you telling that story of your
contributions of your skill set and and
sort of demonstrating that for you know
the person on the other side of the page
and you know ideally as as Laura said
you're doing some networking so people
know you as more than just that you know
sheet of paper um but I think those
opportunities to give a talk at at at
you know forums at the broad to um be
part of you know you don't have to be
the first author on the paper but you
know there should be figures that you
could point to like that this was you
know and you know for most um industry
kind of lab based jobs. You will be
asked to give a a scientific
presentation for example, right? So, and
you've seen if you're at the you're
here, you've seen lots of beautiful
presentations. Think about what yours
looks like. Start to build that um that
that storyline. And again, it can come
from different parts and and you we all
present data that is is done as a team,
but being able to sort of say these were
my ideas. This is, you know, what we
what the next step was. a lot of, you
know, a question I ask a lot of people
when interviewing people for like entry
level industry jobs is like what is
coming from academia, right? It doesn't
have to be that what they did is exactly
on target for what we what we want. But
I'm asking for like how are they
thinking, right? So how do what how does
what you did what are the next steps?
What's that enabling in the lab? what's
that getting people excited about and
sort of demonstrating that you're
thinking like people who you know who
who are asked to think that way as a PhD
not because others don't have cap that
capability but just hopefully that helps
>> I think and the only thing I would add
is all of us here and so many people you
end up working on things that are not
anywhere near the science you did your
PhD in and so um
and it can be that with a PhD you learn
how to think very deeply about exactly
what you're doing, the details, the
nuance, the uh you know, the next
question. But when you go beyond that,
it's it's really more the ability to
step back and see the big picture and
know how to ask the right questions and
know how to put what you hear in context
of a bigger landscape, whether it's a
bigger science landscape or a business
landscape. and and so I think there's
although a lot of people do have PhDs
and MDs in the end it's when you have
conversations with people there's
equally um
you know no requirement at all and lots
of people who succeed because of the way
that they think about the context of the
science and the bigger picture and the
impact and I think in a conversation
it's really easy for that to come
through and so to me in the places I've
been as well I don't see uh it's how you
think about and approach how you spend
your time in the questions you ask that
makes the most difference.
>> Thank you all.
>> So
>> hello. Thank you very much for um this
organization.
I um I would like to ask like
considering these repeat evolvement of
technology and science like you example
the there wasn't crisper but there was
at least zinc finger so uh in academia
we are pretty much like subject to adapt
these new developments all time I wonder
how it feels in the other career paths
like uh this uh like I don't know now we
are speaking of AI and then there was
another stuff so I just wonder how it
feels and how you uh would what kind of
suggestions you would give us and uh who
uh try to grow in this uh ecosystem.
>> Yeah, I mean I'll I'll say that on the
publishing side of things that we're in
I guess it's the same situation for us
as we're watching the field and trying
to anticipate you know where the field
is going. So again I've been at the
journal for more than 20 years. So when
I started you know microwaves were just
coming out you know and suddenly there
was wow exo sequencing and whole genome
sequencing and it really I think and
then all the omix technologies that
the technology has really driven the
directions that the fields have gone. So
from our point of view it's recognizing
where the field is heading and getting
getting trying to get ahead of that you
know to to be able to prioritize the
right the right areas. Yeah.
Yeah, when you when you initially asked
your question, right, what immediately
came to my mind was AI. Um, and you
know, it's something that it's such a
broad term and it could apply to so many
different things. It could apply to drug
development. Um, or it could just apply
to like, you know, productivity and and
the kind of AI tools that you use in
your everyday. I think for for me, you
know, that's really what I've had to
adapt to. I think I was labeled a
dinosaur by my um by my boss. Um you
know, and and I've seen some of the
younger colleagues that I have that come
in and have really like leaned into it
and just the productivity that they've
been able to gain by embracing it. Um
and it's hard to carve out that time to
actually do it. But I definitely think
it's worthwhile to, you know, stay up to
date on all of the emerging, you know,
assays, modalities, AI that you can
because there are other people doing it
and that's giving some folks an edge. So
I I think it's worth the investment for
sure.
>> I'll give maybe a little counter to that
which is I think it's it can be so
exciting all the new technologies. I
think the more you can ground it in the
key questions, the more you'll be able
to differentiate. Um, so it's not I, you
know, I think it you get some exposure.
Obviously, you know, if if you're good
at it, if it's exciting to you, lean
into what you're excited about. But, you
know, it can be tempting to sort of feel
like, oh, everyone's doing AI image
analysis or whatever it is, but does
your project need AI image analysis, or
would it really be better served by, you
know, a a different technique, right?
scanning EM or whatever. I'm making
things up, right? But I think just
really coming back to like the clear
scientific questions and goals and how
the technology can serve those
and not being too worried about like I
have to be doing the latest thing.
>> That's funny. It's at actually at RA
Capital that they have this question
that we got asked when I was at my last
company all the time which is like oh
sure you have a really cool technology
but like what's the killer actual drug
discovery clinical development app for
that and and finding that like where
does a new technology connect with
clinical impact and and company value.
And so it's a uh kind of a
multiffactorial uh uh challenge to come
to the right answer to that. But that's
part of what makes uh makes you know uh
biotech and fun actually is trying to
find that intersection.
>> I guess I'll add one more thing too like
this is also an area where flexing those
collaboration and teamwork muscles can
be fantastic right so at my company
we're not an AI company we're like
really you know hardcore biochemist
biologists but I think but we have a
great partnership now with an AI company
that we're working with. We just had a
poster uh at the recent triple meeting
where we had a you know co-authored um
some work where basically you know some
of our biological findings and how could
we translate that and could we use their
AI model to sort of get some do some
digital pathology type of of
interpretation. So you know I think
these are all different avenues too to
think about well you know here's my
scientific problem is there a really
cool technology lab that you know would
make sense to to collaborate with so I
can learn more from like the people who
are truly in this space and also advance
the project. So
>> guys, um I have a question. So as people
that are considering to go into industry
and not wanting to continue the academic
path, I'm wondering like if we want to
get into industry, I know you guys
mostly went did posttos before going
into industry and I guess you had gone
from grad school to industry. So I'm
wondering now there's a lot of like
fellowships to go into like you know
biotech like posttock positions in
biotech or VC fellowships. So do you
think people wanting to break into
industry need to get these like
fellowships or maybe internships to get
experience in these mark fields or do
you think it's still possible to come in
with like none of this experience
because now it seems like you kind of
have to get experience to get in this
field and kind of seems impossible to
break out you know once you've only been
in academia.
>> I I can definitely speak from the you
know the venture side of things. Um, we
we've certainly hired people that have
been at some of these fellowships, but
the vast majority of hires that we make
did not. Um, you know, I don't think
it's a bad idea to do a fellowship. Um,
you know, especially if the bandwidth uh
to to take that on with everything else
that I'm sure you have going on. Um, but
it's certainly not a requirement. And,
you know, at RA, I think we maybe have a
different mentality than a lot of our
peers and we love to train people
internally. we think kind of a little
bit different sometimes especially being
a multi-stage investment firm like Jan
said we're we're not just looking at
like is that you know modality that
platform is it awesome is it going to be
a game changer but like what are you
applying it to like are you actually
going to develop in a meaningful enough
market opportunity or a met need in
order to attract later stage investors.
Um, so you know, we we typically like to
kind of train people internally. Um, and
and while we've had very successful um,
folks join our team from doing those
fellowships, it is absolutely not
required.
>> Yeah, I was laughing when I was on my
way over thinking that uh, mo so many
people that I worked with at the Broad
now are in industry whether it's venture
or pharma or biotech in all different
kinds of roles. And so many of the
people that I worked with that were in
venture biotech and industry are now,
you know, in academics and at the broad.
And so, uh, at least for me from when I
started, everything feels so much more
flexible now where there's there's many
different paths you can go on, you know,
in and out of all these different types
of organizations. And so I to me I
wouldn't be so um uh fixed on the path
but really like at each step you only
have so many opportunities you know that
present at any moment in time when
you're thinking about your next step and
just choosing the one that that seems
most exciting where you learn the most.
>> Yes, I would echo the learn the most
part. Right. So I think a few years ago
there was a lot of movement right from
grad school to industry. If you go five
years before that you definitely needed
a posttock. I think we're back in an era
where the job market's a lot tighter.
So, you know, having more experience can
differentiate you, especially, you know,
even if it's more academic experience.
So, just, you know, I think a lot of it
also obviously depends on, you know, how
you fit the roles that that they're
looking for. Is there a special skill
set? Is there, you know, a secret sauce
that you are you coming from a lab that
is super relevant to the company that
that you're applying to? I think um you
know there's you know what is it you're
going to learn in your posttock what is
it that you're going to be establishing
one of the things back when we really
required posttos one of the things we
were looking for there was typically
grad students are less independent in
terms of their project planning project
selection um than than grad students
right um that's not necessarily the case
and it really depends on whose lab
you're in you know and the structure of
that um so think about the ways you know
your your skills have developed. The
other thing I'll just say is that you
know grad school you don't ever know
when it's going to end right you've got
this sort of long time horizon posttocks
are different right I did a two-year
posttock a lot of people I know did
shorter posttocks you know especially if
you do an industry posttock you know
those tend to be two or three years
right so it is you know think about what
you'll learn in in that situation if
it's worth it if it makes sense um I
will say you know at nois we had a ton
of this is a really really robust and
and wellrespected postto program. Every
posttock I know from Novartis has gone
on to fantastic industry jobs. There is
probably no better way to build an
industry network because between the
people at Novartis and the people who
leave Noardis while you're there, you
will know somebody in like, you know,
100 companies in the Boston area and
beyond. So, um, but again, it really
will depend on your situation, but there
are so many things you would learn in in
some of those, you know, environments as
well.
Um, so I'm wondering how you see
opportunities for scientists evolving
outside of academia in the next 5 to 10
years and if we should be keeping our
eye on specific sectors as we look.
That's a tough question. Um
uh def definitely as uh as we were just
hearing the you know the job market is
changing a lot and industry is changing
a lot. Uh definitely I'm not the person
who's the you know best at uh you know
having the broad view of where we're
headed. Um but the at least from sitting
from the biotech pharma investing side
everything is getting feels like it's
getting so much more global
and so the ability to
to to interact and find the right people
with the right technologies or the right
capital or the right uh clinical sites
on a global basis gets more and more
important. And so
a network in Boston is always a
fantastic thing to have, but I I feel
more and more that the um
there's a lot more balance in terms of
where innovation and where science is
happening and where money is found. And
so having the the broader global view of
of biotech, pharma, drug discovery
industry uh feels more and more
important to me.
I can answer this from the lens of a a
VCM where I see a lot of innovation and
my expectations over the next couple
years. You know, I think it's a a funny
coincidence at RA that many of us on the
investment team actually did PhDs in
neuroscience.
And it's like what, you know, why is
that? And you know one of the reasons
could be that you know 10 years ago um
you know when I when I finished my PhD
it was really hard to develop companies
um or or start companies or or develop
drugs in CNS. There are just a lot of
barriers in terms of accessing the
brain, getting enough drug across the
bloodb brain barrier. Um, you know,
having adequate targets, heterogeneity
of disease, like lack of understanding
of the genetic u makeup of of some of
these more broad buckets of disease like
autism spectrum disorder. Um and I think
that there's been a lot of progress
there over the last couple of years
especially in in unlocking some of these
um you know getting drug across the
brain for example and and better
understanding of the genetics of some of
these diseases. So I expect to see some
more innovation hopefully. I think it's
a huge unmet need. You know, I kind of
heard that, you know, there's been so
much innovation in cancer biology and
drugs for cancer because we understand
the genetics and have the ability to do,
you know, very specific and targeted uh
drug development approaches and we're
getting there with neuroscience. So, I I
think that that is definitely an area
that I really hope that we'll see more
innovation over the next 5 to 10 years.
Hello.
Um, I'm wondering if you could go back,
is there anything you would have done
differently to prepare for your career?
There is nothing I would have done
differently. I feel like the fact that I
I did nothing to prepare for my career
um actually made me kind of the best
employee at RA Capital and probably one
of the reasons why I was so successful.
like I I came in with a completely blank
slate and I just wanted to absorb and
learn and ask questions and you know I
was able to kind of learn on the job
which is really cool to have the
opportunity to do it. Um and so you know
I can't say that I would have changed a
single thing.
>> I would probably just tell myself to be
more patient. Um
he's laughing. That's my husband over
there. Uh because I think there were
times where I was super frustrated that
things weren't going as fast as I wanted
or I wasn't getting a promotion as fast
and like I think you know there's so
many things I learned along the way. so
many there were times when I took a more
lateral move which gave me actually so
much more breadth of experience and I I
don't think I even understood at the
time how valuable that breadth of
experience would be in addition to kind
of the depth you get in a PhD and so you
know just having a bit more patience
because you know then things all kind of
clicked into place
>> yeah and I would say for my current role
you know I don't think there's anything
that I could have or should have done
differently that would have put me in a
better place to do what I'm doing now.
For me, it's more the question of what
if I had done something completely
different and how would my life be
different? But that's, you know, that
that's sort of more of a life question,
you know, like gee, what if I had gone
to med school instead of, you know, or
what if I had X or Y or Z. But as far as
being prepared to do the job of an
editor, I feel like, you know, the
things that, you know, I did along the
way equip me well to do to do the job
that I'm doing.
No, I mean I the same. Yeah, I wouldn't
do anything differently, but also no
step was predictable along the way. And
you have to stay true to your own
personalities and interests. And there's
people that I know that I admire so much
where they knew exactly where they
wanted to head and they, you know,
charted the path to get to to where they
wanted to be in an amazing way. I know
other people like me too that you know
you had no idea where you wanted to head
and you just kind of took it as it came
and and that worked out and um but it's
it's what you know it's what makes you
excited every morning to get up and do
what you're doing that makes the most
difference.
I have a kind of a related question but
you all kind of change path a little
bit. Did you learn it on the job? like
you said, yeah, but did you get also
some extra formal training like I don't
know in business or whatever to help you
be successful in the new job or
>> Yeah, I have to say um both Santa Fe and
Novartis had really fantastic um
programs around management and around
business. I did like a mini MBA I
wouldn't really I don't think anyone
with an MBA would call really call that
but you know program at at Santa Fe. Um
that was super helpful to sort of learn
more about the business uh side of
things. when I was at um Noardis, they
had really fantastic management
training. Um and not just the training
itself, but because you did those as a
cohort with people, it was also like a
really fantastic bonding experience with
a smaller group of your colleagues from
across the organization actually, which
is also really important in a big place
like that. Um the other training that
I've sought out over the years is also
mentoring programs through things like
AWIS or HBA um which have all been
fantastic and um are things that really
also can grow with you. Um I was also
part of a group at at Google Ventures.
So I think really seeking out these
things both inside your organization and
external um can be super super powerful.
>> Yeah, I definitely echo that. So, so I
did like all the training in and what I
actually do in my role. I received um
you know in in my capacity at AR Capital
like I'm so lucky and grateful to have
such incredible mentors there who really
took the time to take me on and and
develop me as an investor. You know,
I've I've paid that forward and and
taken on a number of of colleagues that
I work with very closely and and helped
develop them as well. uh to echo you
know a for example I was a mentee there
back in the day and actually it was
coincidental is at the time that I was
interviewing for my job at Ari Capital
so they helped me talk through like how
to negotiate a salary like that's
terrifying especially coming out of your
PhD where I'm like I make $30,000 a year
like I will literally work for you know
for that um so you know it's a starting
point um but yeah and you know then I
became a mentor uh down the So certainly
seek out opportunities like that. Um
there's there's a lot that you can do if
you're interested in biotech investing.
This is going to sound really silly. Um
but probably the best thing you can do
is follow what we call like bio Twitter.
Um go on Twitter and follow a bunch of
personalities who like follow these
stocks really closely, follow the data
coming out. It's kind of good exposure
into what it would be like to actually
be in that world. Um, but yeah, I I
can't say that, you know, like reading a
textbook on how to make a financial
model is going to be very helpful.
>> Yeah, I would actually just also there's
a lot there's a couple podcasts out
there. Um, there's Biotech Hangout which
covers a lot of those Twitter folks. Um,
and actually I'll make a plug for the RA
Capital website because there's a lot of
learning stuff on there. Um, it's
actually really and it's all freely
available. There's a lot of just like
how does companies like how does this
work this investing thing like at a at a
high level but that's really I think a
good place to start as a as a scientist.
>> Yeah. And I think what everybody has
said there's there's formal and there's
informal ways to learn what you need to
learn same as PhD or not doing a PhD but
the one is learn you know learning the
things you need to know but the other
part that's so important is meeting the
people that help open up the
opportunities to take a new job to be a
mentor. And so wherever are the places
where you both learn but also broaden
the people whose uh you know you build
relationships with who can mentor you
who you can uh you know you can mentor
over time as well. Uh and there's lots
of ways to do that but it's it helps a
lot to continue to learn but also
continue to to meet new people and and
hear their thoughts as you go.
Um, so we're running at the end of time
and I thought we would end with just
everyone giving their last piece of
advice. Maybe keep it to a sentence or
two um of uh for the trainee in the room
seeking non-academic career paths.
I I would say um try to know yourself
and pursue the thing that you think
lines up best with your skills,
interests, and heart.
Yeah, keep coming to things like this.
Look for organizations like AIS, like
HBA, like um you know, various
scientific organizations. Uh look for
ways to share your science and yeah,
>> I'd say keep an open mind and and stay
curious. You know, if I had actually had
the opportunity to dismiss finance as I,
you know, my gut was to do, I would have
never ended up where I am. And I
absolutely love what I do. Um, so just
keep an open mind.
>> Yeah, there's just so many opportunities
and they're they're as exciting science
as what you do in academics, but just
from different aspects. And so so don't
be afraid. Uh there's just so many
different opportunities that are all
terrific uh to be able to pursue.
I think we can end for folks here, we
all meet over there at 9:30 for the
talk.