[Music]
The floor is all yours. Thanks. Thank
you.
Well, welcome back. Um, our next uh
presenter is Bruce Lawler. He's managing
director of MIT's machine intelligence
for manufacturing operations. Today he
will explore with us practical and
successful applications of analytics and
AI and manufacturing across small,
medium and large enterprises in the US.
He will show us where to invest to start
and sustain a digital transformation
journey drawing on research and best
practices from MIT and McKenzie. He'll
also give us insight into impactful uses
of generative AI currently shaping the
future that will drive future
investment. Please welcome Bruce Lawler.
[Applause]
[Music]
Good morning
everyone. Thank you. So I'm going to
show you the MIT fire hose. So when you
come to MIT they tell you it's like
learning uh learning there is like
drinking from a fire hose. So I'm going
to go through a bunch of slides pretty
quickly. feel free to take pictures, but
I just want to let you know that each
slide's only going to be up there for a
very short amount of time if there's one
that you
like. So, uh, first of all, MIT MIMO or
machine intelligence and manufacturing
operations. We started this in in 2018
before AI was cool. Um and our focus is
really how do we bring AI into
manufacturing and operations and we have
three major uh pillars research,
education and collaboration. Uh so today
I'll share some of our research.
Obviously this is uh this seminar is
about education and obviously
collaboration. So I'm happy to talk with
all of you uh at at our breaks.
So today first I'm going to give you a
brief history and a current status of of
AI and and more in the consumer uh space
uh because it's moving so fast and and
what I'm trying to show you there is how
quickly uh capabilities are increasing
and cost is decreasing as kind of a
forcing function for for what's going to
then move as a wave into manufacturing
in the next five years. Um we recently
published in Harvard Business Review a a
article called what companies succeeding
in AI do different Differently. So we'll
talk a little bit about uh those results
and uh which of those things you can
implement
um and specifically where they invest.
So for those of you who thought I was
going to tell you the next Nvidia to
invest in, no, I'm telling you how to
invest in your own businesses uh to uh
to make them more productive. and then
we'll we'll go through a bunch of uh use
cases primarily and a few case studies
uh that we can uh that you can learn
from.
So first of all uh history of AI it it's
had a long history
um started back in the the late 50s
early 60s there's been a couple of
winters here uh this is kind of a
symbolic phase uh this is more of an
expert system kind of phase and so I put
some kind of uh some milestones in there
so the neural network the thing that
really powers the technically the
perceptron
uh was invented uh in 1944. So the
concept's actually pretty old. It really
took until now to have the compute power
uh data and uh more advanced algorithms
to to power it.
Um many of you remember Deep Blue. Uh
and obviously this was a moment that I
think most of you probably didn't
realize uh transformers were invented by
at Google. Uh but then the introduction
of chat GPT is kind of what's kicked off
this current phase and things have moved
pretty quickly since then. Um we've got
a lot of capabilities. I'll show you a
couple examples. These multimodalm
models are some that I think are
extremely powerful.
Um especially in manufacturing and
operations. Uh what we see is we're
getting a lot of choices in 2024. Um we
also saw openweight models. they existed
previously from meta uh deepseek many of
you have heard of uh so that is really
driving down price and increasing
capability but also openness open weight
models uh the sharing and this is unlike
any most other technologies that have
been created is the amount of sharing
and availability uh globally for these
tools and then in 2025 we've seen some
really interesting things uh with
reasoning models uh we've already talked
a little bit about agentic AI AI. Uh,
and then for those of you who have seen
some of the computer use capabilities,
uh, certainly from Enthropic and others,
you can now install it on your machine.
It can read files, it can execute
commands on your computer. So,
literally, uh, can take over the screen
on your computer. So, um, you know,
these capabilities are all coming very
very quickly in in in the ability to
automate work. And it it's very
different from robotic process
automation that's come before it. So
just a couple of examples. Um I don't
how many people have played with chat
GPT Dolly. Right. So uh I I'm going to
give this a prompt. I'm say change the
flowers to an orange color. What do you
think's going to
happen? It's going to make those orange,
right? No, it actually puts orange
flowers in. So these are the kinds of
real world training things that these
models are capable of. And this is
really for those of you who've been kind
of sleeping under a rock. Uh this one um
you know I think is is just a a couple
of examples of how these models are
learning physics. So you normally see
you think that was a generated image.
Now these images also we can train them
with uh physics and Nvidia's done a ton
of work there where uh we don't have to
do finite element analysis anymore. We
can actually just train a neural network
with physics uh and it can do these kind
of things and obviously a little ad
there
um from from Amazon to give you an
example of of how pervasive these things
have been. Um for those of you who don't
know that these models can code um they
can. So Andrew Carpath uh was famous two
years ago for saying English is now the
most powerful computing language. Uh so
what this is and I apologize for the bad
grammar here. I didn't write that. Uh so
it's essentially asking a prompt to
build an app. Um it's now writing
JavaScript.
Uh and uh the nice thing about the way
uh Enthropic has interviewed their or
developed their product is it can now
actually run in the same browser. So
it's kicked off um that JavaScript and
it's a simple app. It just paste your um
your text in there and uh depending on
the speed at which you want to talk um
you know it will tell you how long your
talk is going to take.
Nothing earthshattering about that app
other than it wrote the code itself. It
it didn't have to compile it, but it's
running it here in the browser and uh it
picked those four levels. I didn't tell
it four pick four levels. I didn't tell
it what uh speed and words per minute.
It figured all of that out for me. And
so you start to think about the
implications of that coming into
manufacturing.
uh and and essentially we'll talk a lot
about the front office today the types
of tasks people do
um how many have heard with re heard of
reasoning
models how many have used them right
okay good so here's an example of um a
reasoning model once again this is just
using um sonnet 3.7 here um so this is
the text that's given to the model and
and what reasoning models are is they
take large language models and they call
them repeatedly
um to ask it different questions and
essentially reason through things and it
takes the output of one answer and uses
it to drive
another. Um many of you also probably
heard that um large language models
can't do math and they cannot but they
can generate the code that does math. So
now it's going to go through it's going
to run the calculations that I asked it
to run. Um, it's going to do the
analysis that I asked it to do and
essentially in 24 seconds it's going to
do what probably would have taken a
human and a half a day or a day to do.
Now, you need to think of it as an
intern. It's not necessarily going to be
right. You should check it. Um, but the
point is these things are happening
faster and faster. So, as you're looking
at developing uh production schedules,
quality manuals, uh routing sheets, um
things like that that you use every day
in manufacturing, think about these kind
of tools, not necessarily today, but
very, very soon being able to help with
those kinds of of tasks.
The other big thing that's important
because cost is super important is
really the decline in cost. So, um, for
equivalent LLM performance, we're seeing
about a 10x decline per year in cost. By
comparison, Morris law is about 2x. So,
that's a huge difference when you
compound that year over year over year.
And so, this was done by Andre and
Horowitz. that, you know, in 2022 GPT uh
cost uh $60
um for hitting a benchmark of
MMLU42. It's just a human performance
benchmark, but they set that as the
constant. Um you know, by 2024,
essentially that cost was zero in many
ways driven by these openweight models.
So uh if you look at we've uh
uh you know we've had a thousandx
decrease in three years for comparable
performance. Now what people are asking
it to do has gone up and up and up. Uh
like these reasoning models you know
that model ran for 24 seconds that I
just showed you. So it's
um the you know is everything the
requirements keep going up but the cost
is going down. And to put that in human
terms, if I were to stand up here and
talk for 10 hours a day for a year, you
could summarize everything that I said
for $2, which probably everyone would
say that's really worth it rather than
listening to you for a year, 10 hours a
day.
So now, if I'm Corona, I want to make
ads for all over the world. I could
obviously send people to all these
different beaches. That would be nice, a
nice job to have, but pretty
expensive. And I could do all those beer
ads. And this is not surprising in in
today's age. What do you think it costs
to generate all those different
images?
Anyone, a US cent, euro cent, whatever,
roughly the same these days. So I think
it's it's that price performance that
people don't fully grasp and the change
of that and how you could bring that
into your
operations.
So all right I'm going to talk a little
bit now about the research that that we
do.
Um so the the problem that that I think
exists I don't worry about worker
displacement. What I worry about is not
having enough workers. So in the US our
uh manufacturing unemployment rates very
low. We have about as of last year June
we had about uh you know 600,000
unfilled jobs. We think in the next uh
four years five years you know there'll
be 2 million jobs uh that are unfilled
and other people have mentioned that you
know we're losing about 11,000 Americans
a day to retirement. I'm guessing you
have kind of a similar problem and it's
uh whether we call it a skills gap or an
expertise gap as Ben alluded to
um you know there's uh a lot of people
that are retiring out of the workforce
that know how things are done and so
I'll talk about some use cases later
about how we can uh capture that
knowledge from those people before they
leave but also take the instit the
knowledge that's embedded in the these
systems today and apply that uh to our
problems. And obviously rising wages, we
want to pay people more. We want to be
more productive so we can pay people
more. Um but obviously that drives up
the cost of our products. So uh in
partnership with McKenzie, we run a
study every two years and it's
specifically to look at the adoption of
AI in manufacturing and operations.
And I'm not going to uh go into great
detail because today because in the
workshop tomorrow we will go into more
detail. How many people will be
attending tomorrow's
workshop? Okay. So um I'll I may I don't
have all the slides in there but I may
voice over a few things since there
aren't going to be that many people
tomorrow. So uh we look at about a
hundred companies across all these
different segments. Um it does skew to
larger corporations as you can see over
here and you don't really see that on
here. So you know the much larger
corporations do tend to do more with
with AI and machine learning. Uh these
are the types of of companies
uh that we talk with and we we try to
look um we look at different K per KPIs
key performance indicators. We look
across multiple use cases, multiple
business outcomes. Uh and then we look
at nine different enabler categories. Uh
we've upped the number of KPIs to our
2025 study. Um so we've increased uh the
size of the study a little bit because
we needed to add Gen AI. Um we have
published several times in Harvard
Business Review. Uh, I'll talk today
about that rightmost article, what
companies succeeding in AI do
differently. Uh, we do have another
article coming out next month on
mckenzie.com that will uh be more
detailed. So, um, feel free to look
those up. Uh, you can find the links at
mimo.mmit.edu.
Um so let's talk first about about what
uh we did uh in in the study as as we
look at it. And it's the only study that
I've seen that
links the enablers which is essentially
the money you
spend to the outcomes. So the results.
So if you do X, what's the correlation
uh to the outcomes? Uh so and what we're
trying to do is give people a road map.
How do I how do I know when I invest in
certain things that there might be a
certain outcome from them? And then we
uh we clustered them in uh to leaders
uh leaders, planners, uh executors and
emerging companies over here. And
certainly in
2021, uh, the everything tended to skew
a little higher, which means you're
spending more money. And the enablers,
I'm sorry, are things like training, the
people you hire, the data you collect,
the things that you you spend money on
that make you more capable. Um, so
people spend a little bit more money. Uh
what we saw then in 2023 and this was
after chat GPT came out um and it helped
raise awareness it didn't really move
these particular numbers that much is
things shifted over to the right so
better results so shorter payback
periods better KPI performance
um and we also saw
um the emergence of people down in this
space. So, I'll go back one. You see
there's not a lot of people here. Oops,
back too many. Um, and then you see
people emerging here. And they're able
to get results by spending less. And
we'll talk in a minute about why that
is. So, you say, well, why why do I need
to spend? You notice leaders in the
upper right, they spend the most. Why do
I even care? Why do I want to be a
leader? uh the reason to be a leader is
because they get better performance. So
in 2021 they had about three times the
KPI performance. So KPIs are things like
efficiency over here uh cost
um revenue, customer responsiveness,
um and so cost is you know things like
scrap rate etc. And so they get better
performance by 2023. Uh we saw a 4x
increase of the leaders over everyone
else. So uh the best are getting better
and pulling ahead.
Um so that's in some sense you could say
I'm not a leader. That's the bad news.
We'll get to the good news in a second.
But there is a reason to invest that you
do get the kind of efficiency gains you
were hoping to
get.
Um, and how do Now I'm going to go into
like how do leaders get there? Um, one
of the big changes was what this chart
is showing you is leaders in light blue
and the bottom 50% in in black. But who
owned AI? So in
2021, it was, you know, kind of down at
a VP or sometimes director level. So it
was primarily held here um is where a
lot of the energy was in these two
levels but then by
2023 it had moved up to a board level or
CEO level priority. So I think that that
that was a big move that we
saw and you know the implications are
are really kind of large and so I'll
talk a little bit about why a CEO
matters right so um two uh pretty famous
CEOs I I know General Electric isn't
doing very well right now but back in
Thomas's Edison's day it was quite a
successful company um how did how did he
get there right he was meticulous does
it with his lab notebooks. Um they
documented and measured everything and
he was able to invent things like the
electric light bulb, the phongraph and
moving pictures. So uh pretty successful
with datadriven uh technology. Henry
Ford is famous for his time motion
studies. Most people think it's the
assembly line which is obviously part of
it. But he also then totally optimized
that process through a lot of data
collection and was able to reduce uh
production times and costs and they
really had a culture of datadriven
decision-m making. We talk about
digitization
uh as being important and and it is for
the efficiency of collecting data, but
you still need a mentality and a culture
of datadriven decision-making and these
gentlemen had it even though everything
was done by hand and with paper. I'll
throw out two other CEOs that uh you've
heard of. You probably recognize Jeff
Bezos from his picture. Um they really
measure everything. I've had the
pleasure of working very closely with
Amazon executives and
um everything gets measured and you you
try to predict as much as you possibly
can and he's been able to do that uh and
optimize logistics and supply chain but
then also customer preference right you
for those of you who use Amazon you know
you get lots of
recommendations uh the other person on
the the right you may love or hate uh
Starbucks. Um, and uh, Howard Schultz
really has used data to mine consumer
preference and determine on which corner
we're going to put a Starbucks. Um,
so and uh, the one thing that they did
is um, uh, Bezos and Schultz, they now
have automated AI, automated analytics.
So that's the big difference, but you
still need that datadriven culture. And
so we've seen that in the data from the
McKenzie study. And I just wanted to
give you some examples. And now when you
bring that back um what you
see is uh the the impact of some of
those changes uh specifically uh in kind
of culture
um because uh you know what happens
obviously is CEOs help to drive culture
but what what this chart shows is where
leaders were thinking about problems in
2021 here and here and then where they
move to by
2023. So what we saw is people didn't
think they had the skills in 2021. They
think they do now have them or it's at
least less of an issue and culture is
less of an issue because remember by now
people have chat GPT that they can use
and they're realizing oh I really don't
have the data that I need. Um I now need
to do these ROI calculations. I'm I I'm
not really prepared to do them and now I
don't really have all the time and
resources. So, it isn't so much about
the the lack of expertise on AI. Um it's
really more about did I collect the data
and can I uh calculate the returns? And
that's this unclear ROI is where having
CEO level support is super important
because if you've ever been caught down
inside an organization trying to do an
ROI calculation and convince finance and
the rest of the organization
uh that you should be able to do
something uh you realize that
um having a a CEO level mandate is is
very important.
So um we talked a little bit about data.
I wanted to quantify what that means.
So in our leader category over 90% of
them recorded data on 10% of or more of
their equipment. So they do record data.
They do store data. And Thomas talked a
little bit about the u the effect of
that because what happens is you end up
storing data on more than one device
uh and more devices in a row. And when
you store things on more than one device
in a row, you can actually automate
chains of things together very much like
you would automate a factory uh with
multiple um
uh robots if you were doing that. So you
can do the same thing with data. You get
better at collecting data. You get
better at storing data. You get better
at processing data. So we do find that
there are economies of scale and
certainly storing them in the cloud uh
is is super
valuable. Uh there's some other
attributes of data. I know this chart's
a little uh hard to read. Uh
but what we do find is that the leaders
uh share data with their
suppliers. Uh they acquire data from
their suppliers and they share uh data
uh with their customers. Uh they give
their employees access to data. We see
um you know almost 100% of leaders or
actually 100% do give frontline access
to data.
um whereas uh you know the the bottom
50% really don't do that as nearly as
much and I you know I talked about the
the one of the investments in data
collection but uh leaders have a program
for determining which data matters and
deciding to collect it and to store it
and they typically uh store it on the
cloud and they store it on the cloud so
they can get more access to tools and
very importantly combin combine
different data sets because it's uh very
important to have what's called a label
data set. I know whether a part is good
or bad and then I can compare it to all
the process variables
uh that were existed that made good
parts or bad parts and now I can start
to determine what will make good or bad
parts.
Um partnering is very important. I'll
give some use cases on that.
Um what we've seen is uh the the types
of partners here are academia startups
consulting vendor and industry partners
uh and the industry the vendors would be
like SAP or Zemens the people you're
already using and so what we've seen is
uh because these vendors are uh you know
having better solutions uh they're re
companies are have now using startups in
academia less. So that they're still
using them at a kind of a 50% rate, but
they don't need to rely on them as much
because there's more sources. In 2021,
there just weren't other sources
of of people to partner with. And and
that's really a key recommendation is
don't try to do this yourself. Uh it's
if if it was complicated in 2021, it's
only gotten more so. Uh but the good
news is there's a lot more uh solution
choices available to
you. Uh training. So we that's going to
be a pretty continual theme training on
not AI but making decisions with data.
You don't need to train your whole
workforce on AI. What you need to train
them to is is make decisions with data.
And what we're looking here is uh the
really a big disparity in training
between leaders in the bottom uh 50%.
And you know obviously they train their
engineers but they train everyone from
line workers
um up to division
leaders. Okay. Um, I will give you now
some uh a few case studies that uh
relate um excuse me that cover some of
these examples
and I'll I probably have more than I
have time uh to go through.
So, how much time do I have and I want
to kind of gauge this.
Okay. So, we can kind of go through um
as many or as as few as you want. Uh
some of these uh case studies come um
there's a program at MIT that I'm a part
of called the leaders for global
operations. And um a lot of these case
studies are drawn from these sixmonth
research projects that uh the students
do. So they go on site at these member
companies and um they do theirh thesis
uh work there, their thesis research and
um these students are getting both a
masters in engineering and MBA. So they
combine the business aspects uh with the
technical aspects.
So uh one example here um is is not from
that particular data set but it's a
company called North American Stainless.
Uh they sit uh in Kentucky uh which is
no one here's from Kentucky but it's not
known as a one of the more
forwardthinking uh states much like
South Carolina was
um you know before BMW came there. Uh
but this particular factory is pretty
advanced. They make uh 2 billion pounds
of stainless steel a year. So very high
volume. They have 1,400 employees. How
many sensors to do you think exist in
this
factory? It's stainless
steel. You know, it can't be that
complex,
right? Guess anyone? How many data
sensors do they have? Okay. 30,000 is
the answer since no one will guess which
is probably way more than what other
people thought. What percentage of
people here do you think can write a SQL
query? So do basic have frontline access
and then can actually manipulate it with
you know relatively old tool
SQL. Turns out 5% so 70 of their people
can actually get in write queries on
their data. So for a factory that you
think is not that advanced, they're
actually quite advanced.
um you know they have a problem here um
with these 30,000 sensors. How do they
determine uh what's they know when they
start to get bad steel but that's
usually too late because the you know
the temperatures take a long time to
ramp etc. So what they've done is
they've uh in this case partnered with
Falconry to look at two years of
historical data on these 30,000 sensors
and learn what is normal behavior, not
normal behavior. And it automatically is
able to tell them the yellow bars are
things that are anomalous behavior. And
so they're it doesn't try necessarily to
solve the problem or say for sure
there's a problem. It just tells them
when things are bad. And uh you know, I
love the VP quote, which is um when I
have a problem, I want you to blow away
all the hay and just leave me with a
stack of needles. I want to know where
to look. Which of the five sensors out
of the
30,000 are different that I should spend
time on? So, it's a great use of this
technically would be machine learning.
Um here's another example of of
partnering. Uh this is one that we
worked on at MIMO. So, Analog Devices
makes
semiconductors uh in the US. They're
actually one of the the largest in in
Massachusetts. They have 24,000
employees. Um and the problem in
semiconductor manufacturing, especially
high mix, low volume, is it can take
months to create all the different
layers because they make so many
different products.
And in this particular case, um, you
know, after three months, they were able
to electrically test this product to see
if it was correct. Well, they ended up
with millions of dollars in scrap. Um,
and the so they came to us and said,
"Can you can you help us with this?" And
and we did. Um, the problem they have is
they have almost no bad parts. Their
yields are so high. um and their
processes are so well controlled that it
very rarely happens. So uh we had a
problem it's called class imbalance. We
have no failures basically and we have
to tell them when things are going
wrong. And so that was a really
interesting uh project. uh the first two
years were uh spent largely
understanding the problem and proving
that we could solve it on one recipe in
one uh one machine and then it was
extended further to another two years to
say now do this on more machines with
more recipes so more types of chips
uh we talked about training so this is
another case study Merna Academy not all
of you obviously can afford what Merna
uh does very popular um vaccine company.
That's what they're known for as a
vaccine company. They're really an mRNA
company, but they're an AI first
biioarma company. And because they said
we're AI first, we're going to create
our own academy. The important thing
here is they trained everyone in the
same vocabulary and the same level so
that when they talked about analytical
problems, they all were coming at it uh
with the same uh kind of baseline
knowledge and the same approach. Um so
that's
um and you don't have to form your own
academy to do that. you can work with
your local universities to just make
sure everyone's has a tiered kind of uh
education. We have a program called
yellow belt in the US which I'm not sure
how many how popular it is over here or
black belt, yellow belt, green belt um
that's
u that you can also take advantage of.
So let me
um talk about a couple of uh other case
studies or excuse me use cases. So one
of the most popular
um uh case stud or uh use cases is
forecasting. So forecasting can be used
to increase sales. It can be used to
reduce inventory or it can be used to
inform investments. Um I'll give you an
example here of of Zara. Uh
Zara needs to predict sizes small,
mediums, and largest when I make a
product. And they actually were able to
uh look at the text descriptions of
products and then relate that to
historical uh sales for those text
descriptions and uh predict future um uh
mixes so that they don't lose sales and
they don't have a lot of things that go
to the discount
rack. We I'm just kind of I'm mindful of
time. I can keep going for hours. Um
Okay. So, I'll um I'll just This is a
visual inspection. We talked a little
bit about that. Uh this one
is and they're just doing visual
inspection on uh on semiconductor or uh
printed circuit boards. Uh this is a
change over time in a mill. I wanted to
give someone a really a heavy industrial
uh
problem. And uh the this is a stainless
steel mill and in a stainless steel mill
uh it's very important that it be um
super smooth. These are the the finishes
that go on your sinks and on your u
refrigerators. And so this mill uh
actually has to be super flat. And so
they have to get it perfectly
calibrated. Uh and they're actually
using a visual inspection to see what
the people are doing and also um to see
if this door is open or closed because
it turns out there's so much vibration
in the middle they can't get a sensor to
accurately predict it.
Um I do want to talk about this one here
uh because this is probably the most
prevalent uh use case. Um, so Panasonic
make batteries for Tesla. They make 5.5
million cylindrical cells a day. Um,
they got hundreds of uh cell winding
machines. They have 350
technicians and they trained a mo they
have a historical database of a million
trouble tickets.
Um, so what they did here is they
trained an LLM on those million trouble
tickets to help those 350 maintenance
technicians uh do a better job of
keeping these machines up. I'm running a
symposium on May the 6th. It's
interesting. I've got Nissan, Toyota,
Kamasu, and Panasonic all coming to talk
about similar applications of LLMs,
whether it's to keep an assembly line
running to help you in Kamasu's case
assemble these big complex uh earth
movers. Um, and so Toyota and Nissan are
both keeping the assembly line running
and they're keeping battery machines
running. So, this is probably one of the
most prevalent use cases I'm starting to
see right now.
Um and
I'll this is another really uh
interesting gen AI uh visual inspection
uh some uh drug discovery uh kinds of
problems. Okay. So where to invest the
the summary slide train your workforce
in datadriven decision making
um drive it through the organization use
lean use a worker centric approach. I'm
a big fan of digital lean. Um, choose
impactful projects that have ROI. If
they don't have ROI, they're going to
fizzle out. Uh, typically things that
generate revenue are more impactful than
things that save cost. So, if you can uh
find a revenue uh generating product and
collect
data, partner, as I mentioned, I've
given you some examples. And I think
there's a huge opportunity in
unstructured data. um which is what LLMs
are. Historically, we've done machine
learning on structured data. Uh I showed
you one example of starting to combine
structured and unstructured data, but I
think that's another big
area. Um
so, hit that QR code. Love to have you
travel to Cambridge May the 6th. Uh but
also our 2025 study is out. So, um you
can find that on our web page here. Um
or you can uh ask to uh be sent the
study. It's frankly just easier to go to
the web page and click on the link and
start to fill it out. Uh and then for
those of you in the workshop, uh hit
that QR code and you can download uh the
the materials for tomorrow.
Okay, I think we have an opportunity for
a few
questions. Let's
see. How do you see AI impacting front
of house tasks versus back of house
task? Right. So if you if you go back to
to World War II,
um 40% of product cost was direct labor,
people in the factory doing things. As
Ben will show you, that cost has come
down to roughly 15%. If you looked in
the same time period, the front of
office tasks like engineering, design,
planning, scheduling, procurement, all
the things the people that sit at desks
do has remained relatively flat at uh 12
to 15%. And when you look at what LLMs
are capable of doing and generative AI
is capable of doing, that's the area
where we see the most opportunity for
impact are those how do I get more
efficient in all those mental tasks, not
the physical task. I'm not saying don't
do the physical tasks. uh but I think
there's a huge opportunity in this this
knowledge work and unfortunately if you
look within a factory you see a lot of
that sits on someone's PC or uh you know
my biggest friend and worst enemy is
Microsoft Excel because that's where
everything sits but at least there's
data there uh sits in email servers how
do we get all of that into one
integrated data set where we can start
to do things so uh we think there's a
lot of a lot of opportunity there
Okay, maybe just one more uh question.
How do you balance short-term ROI
expectations with long-term digital
transformation goals when implementing
AI solutions?
Um, so the, you know, the challenge is
if you're trying to implement an AI
solution and you don't have Wi-Fi in
your factory and you don't have sensors
on your
machines, it's going to be really hard
to make that full business case. there's
too much risk. Um, and I don't even
really talk about digital transformation
as much as datadriven decision-m if
you're going to make decisions with
data. You will have put the sensors in
to collect the data. The transformation
will come over time. But I think it's
it's the ROI of looking at a line and
saying geez if we could track uh you
know the performance. If we could
automate statistical process control on
this line um then that would be worth it
to us. So you got to work your work your
way up not try to say I want to do AI.
You you've got to go through all the
steps. Well thank you very much Bruce.
Thank you.