(graphic whooshes)
(gentle music)
- Hi, my name is Hari Balakrishnan.
I'm a professor in the Computer Science
and Artificial Intelligence Lab
and the department of EECS at MIT.
About 20 years ago,
together with my colleague,
Professor Sam Madden,
I led a project in the
area of mobile sensing
called the CarTel Project.
With mobile sensing,
the idea is to take data from
sensors on mobile devices
and internet of things
devices attached to vehicles
to understand transportation issues
such as efficiency and safety.
In 2010, based on the academic success
of the CarTel Project,
I co-founded a company called
Cambridge Mobile Telematics,
or CMT,
whose mission is to make driving safe
and sustainable around the world.
The rise in distracted
driving has directly led
to an increase in road
crashes and fatalities.
At CMT, one of the observations
we made many, many years ago
is that the same smartphones
that are causing a lot of these problems
could be used as a force for good
because they contain a
large number of sensors
that could be used to
automatically measure
how people drive,
and that's what we built at
CMT over the past decade.
But not only that,
we've also developed an
innovative internet of things,
or IOT technology, called the driver tag.
These driver tag devices are small,
two-inch by two-inch devices
that attach to the
windshield of the vehicle
that come with their own sensors,
communicate with a phone,
allowing us to process data
to measure how people drive.
We built and shipped over 30 million
of these devices worldwide
over the past several years.
In 1998, there was a lot of
excitement in the community
with the possibilities of
bringing together computing,
wireless communication, and
sensing into small-form factor.
I got interested in how to
take this idea of sensing
and apply it to assets that were moving,
namely cars and vehicle.
- When I got to MIT,
Hari had been working
on the Cricket system,
which is an indoor positioning system,
and it had a lot in common
with the kinds of things
that we were building at Berkeley.
It was a wirelessly
networked sensor system,
and so he and I started thinking
and talking about how
we could collaborate,
and we both got very excited
about this idea of mobile sensing.
- In 2004, this was the
advent of the CarTel Project,
one of the first projects in
the world on mobile sensing,
which is combination of
sensors on mobile devices
and being able to draw
inferences of what was happening.
So we did a number of different things
within the CarTel Project.
Jacob Eriksson, one of our postdocs,
had this idea that, "Hey,
we built all this stuff.
How do we get a lot of data,
and how do we do
something useful with it?"
He said, "Let's partner with
local Boston taxi companies
and put this stuff on their vehicles
and go about driving and measuring
road surface conditions."
- We sort of doubled down
on this idea of safety
and measuring whether, you know,
drivers are safe and roads are safe.
We identified a number of
different commercial markets
with some of the big insurance companies
who were also coming to realize
that you could use sensing
as a way to really directly measure
whether drivers are safe.
- I started reading
about insurance companies
putting expensive hardware in vehicles
to measure people's driving quality
to price insurance correctly
and maybe give people
discounts for better driving.
If we built all this technology
with mobile sensing from phones
as well as inexpensive
internet of things devices,
we could absolutely beat these
expensive hardware devices
that people are going after.
And in 2009, started
the company on the backs
of a NSF Small Business grant, an SBIR,
that really allowed us
to take the technology,
license it out of MIT,
some software out of MIT into the company,
and that really led us to create CMT.
One of the challenges
to measuring road safety
is collecting large amounts of data,
and that comes from
sensors on mobile devices.
They come from the tags,
they come from phones,
and increasingly from connected vehicles,
and we also process
data from video sources.
But how do you calibrate this?
This is a piece of equipment in our lab
where we can take these
devices attached with sensors,
put them here, and then
rotate these devices,
so have them accelerate in
different configurations
and see what the quality is,
and then decide how to take that data
and put them in a form
that's equivalent across
different data sources
before we put them out in the field.
Advanced computing and AI technologies
are fundamentally important
to draw inferences from sensor data
to understand and improve road safety.
For example, when a phone is
in a vehicle being driven,
how do you know if it belongs
to the driver or a passenger?
Obviously, as a driver,
you shouldn't be using
your phone while driving,
but a passenger can use
the phone all they want,
so you need to differentiate
between these two.
So how do you know if you're in a car
or some other mode of transport,
like a bus or a bicycle or a train,
and that involves
machine learning as well.
The driver that's in a crash,
how can you tell the
difference in real-time
using noisy sense of data
between a genuine crash
for which roadside
assistance has to be sent
versus somebody hitting the brakes hard
and the phone flying off?
These are the types of problems
that we at CMT have been tackling
for the better part of a
decade to make our roads
and drivers safer around the world.
Over the last 10 years,
CMT has grown
to become the world's largest
telematics service providers
with over 450 employees.
What I've found is that
the two biggest attributes
that determine success in our field
are intellectual curiosity
and collaboration.
(gentle music continues)
This is a really exciting time
to be working in the
field of transportation
and automotive and road technologies.
One example of it is
understanding driver risk.
Another example
is in understanding the
inherent risk of vehicles,
and making vehicles safer,
and understanding road risk.
The combination of sensor technologies
and artificial intelligence
is fundamentally changing
these fields here.
So I couldn't be more
excited for the future
of how AI impacts road safety.
Don't drive distracted, folks.
(gentle music)
(car whirs)