Hi everybody. Sorry about the um delay.
I'm Lily Thai. I'm a professor in the
political science department and
director of the MIT governance lab which
is a group of behavioral and social
scientists who work with policy makers
and practitioners to research and
develop innovations um bridging the gap
between citizens and government um
particularly in challenging environments
and by that we mean anything ranging
from Appalachia to you know rural
subsaharan Africa.
So, our research aims to address how
people increasingly want to be able to
have a say in the organizations and
communities they belong to. Even though
they usually don't want to have some
they don't want to say something about
every single issue, they just want to be
able to say something when they have
something. Um, people might want to have
a say in policy decisions in their
communities or what we call big D
democracy such as a town hall in
Wisconsin or participatory budgeting
here in Cambridge. They may also want to
say in everyday decisions um in their um
uh uh communities um such as schools,
workplaces and companies or what we call
small d
democracy. Technology now makes it
possible for everyone to have a say. But
we know this can be very overwhelming in
two ways. Um number one, it can be too
much information. Um so how do we how
can we possibly comprehend everything
and summarize it and digest it? And
second, people are of course learning to
behave very badly on social media.
Discourse has become really univil and
there's an urgent need for online
platforms that are what we call more
pro-democratic. We want to use
technology to help understand all of
this overwhelming information and to
restore civility. And more civility,
thankfully, is something that people
across the board agree about. So we see
former VP Mike Pence in a talk at
Dartmouth highlighting that partisanship
does not need to be vicious and that
quote democracy depends on a heavy dose
of civility. He says, "I honestly think
we would do well as a nation to return
to that principle of freedom and mutual
respect." Similarly, we see former
President Biden asking Americans to cool
down the rhetoric after the
assassination attempt on President
Trump. And ordinary Americans want more
civil discourse, too. Each year, the
American Bar Association polls the
public on civic literacy and current
events. And surveys from previous years
show Americans believe society has
become less civil and therefore want
more compromise from their politicians
and um blame social media and public
officials for the decline in
civility. So one method to use
technology to increase mutual
understanding and civility is through
deliberation. Deliberative democracy is
a form of democracy where people come
together with mutual respect and as
political equals to discuss political
issues, listen to each other and make
decisions about matters of common
interest. Deliberation is thought to
have benefits for individual
participants to improve the quality of
the decision and to have system level
benefits legitimizing the political
system as a whole.
Online deliberative platforms have been
growing in use in both the public sector
and the private sector and there are
applications in the private sector that
could strengthen the small D democracy
and build our skills of engaging um
democratically with one another in our
everyday lives. These include things
like employee town halls or even just
doing quick temperature checks among
working groups to see what people are
thinking without going the through the
you know the sort of tiring rigmarroll
of calendaring and scheduling a meeting.
Um it could help with coping with coping
with the move towards shareholder
democracy and it can even just improve
how consumers deliberate over online
reviews.
Our focus though is on how we can build
on existing technologies and improve
them with rigorous interdisciplinary
research and how we can innovate by
integrating generative AI to enhance the
benefits of online spaces for
deliberation. So first we wanted to
approach this issue by identifying a set
of guiding values and principles for
what we felt were socially and ethically
important. So the first thing we did was
to write an MIT AI impact paper laying
out these principles and values from
political philosophy. We wanted to
preserve um agency. So preserving agency
ensures that participants make the
choices not the AI. Encouraging mutual
respect was another important principle.
And we also wanted to promote equality
and inclusiveness. We want people to
feel protected. So we think that the
identity of participants on platforms
should be anonymous but authenticated
and participants should be
representative of the population as a
whole. Augmenting citizenship ensures
that AI helps participants understand
other perspectives or the issue more
fully but doesn't substitute or take
away from the actions that citizens
themselves should have control over.
With those principles, we've developed
our own AI integrated platform for
deliberative democracy, which we call
deliberation.io. And we've designed this
platform to be modular so we can include
or take out modules as our research
uncovers what is most
effective. Right now, there are four
modules that we are working on. And each
of these circles is a module we have.
Under each of the circles is the goal
that the module is aiming
for. And for each of the modules, we
have particular outcomes that we're
interested in studying. Things like, are
people able to justify their reasoning
for a particular position? Um, do they
have empathy for other positions? What
is the area of agreement? And do they
find the decision legitimate and are
they willing to cooperate with the
decision voluntarily? All of these are
outcomes related to what we want
deliberation to do in order to support
democracy. Importantly, we are testing
each of these modules in what we call
evaluation guided system development.
That is to say, we're using randomized
control trials or AB testing to make
sure that we're not just getting user
engagement or more users using the
platform, but that the positive system
level and decision level democratic
outcomes we care about, the downstream
effects are also um something that um
are we're seeing when people use this
platform. If you take nothing else from
this presentation, I hope that you'll
take away this that we should all be
demanding that the technologies um that
are being developed are tested and
assessed to see if they have these
positive downstream outcomes rather than
just always focusing on maximizing the
number of
users. So, I'll give a brief overview of
each of these modules and say a little
bit about what we're learning in more
detail. So, here's an example of how a
user joins a conversation on
deliberation.io. IO the user starts by
expressing oh let me see if this is play
is this
playing actually this is the screenshot
okay so the user starts by expressing um
how much they agree or disagree with an
issue in this case should the US have
for example an automatic voter
registration policy then the user makes
a comment which will be seen by others
on the
platform after the user enters their
comment they then enter what we call
what we've nicknamed our socratic
dialogue module. So, this video shows a
sample interaction and let me just see
is
this
moving. Okay. Well, um statically, this
is actually supposed to be run as a
little bit of an interactive video, but
um but in any case, um the user here is
concerned about possible biases in such
a policy. And the chatbot then responds
by reasonably probing this concern and
asking the user why would an automatic
policy might have biases. um an AI
chatbot um asks in in other words the
user to reflect and reason through their
comment and then the user has the option
to update their comment if they would
like. So our results from a study of
1500 research participants show that
users who engage in reason giving with
our Socratic dialogue LLM actually
moderated their positions and moved to
more centrist positions after the
exercise. So amazingly, in other words,
an AI chatbot that supports a user
through a little bit of reflection just
between the user and the chatbot
actually helped to depolarize the
discussion. Engaging in reason giving
with an LLM also led users to report um
higher quality of conversation, higher
perceptions of feeling respected, um a
more pleasant experience, and more
willingness to engage in civic
participation after the deliberation. in
this case, signing up to receive a
newsletter. These are all extremely
encouraging results for bringing more
civility back into the discussions and
decisions that we have to make
together. A second module that we're
testing is something that we've
nicknamed face of the crowd. And the
idea behind this module is that people
tend to believe that they are farther
apart on a question than they actually
are.
So visualizations from this module
quickly summarize the conversation for
participants. Um in one of our studies
we asked research participants if they
support the use of the military against
civilians during peaceful
protests. It turns out both Democrats
and Republicans tended to oppose
military use in this case. But people in
both parties had misconceptions about
their fellow citizens. So, Democrats
started off the deliberation believing
that Republicans are more supportive of
military use than they were, than they
actually were. Um, interestingly,
Republicans also thought that other
Republicans were more supportive of
military use than they actually
are. We then showed visualizations of
where people actually stand on the
issue. And those who saw these
visualizations and realized there was a
large common area of agreement between
Democrats and Republicans tended to
increase their support for not using
military force against peaceful protest.
So therefore increasing the number of
people who are in the common area of
overlap. Our third module is something
called dynamic deliberation which is an
AI moderated conversation on our
platform. The AI generates uh an
agreement statement based on the
existing comments that have been made in
the deliberation or conversation and
then poses a subsequent um question to
the group in this case about how to
define peaceful
protest. So what we saw in the
conversation about the use of military
um on peaceful protest was that people
were like they you know people tended to
agree yes we or no we don't think that
the military should be used against
civilians um in peaceful protest. But
then people started to get stuck on what
the definition of peaceful protest was.
And so here the chatbot says okay people
seem to agree on this but um let's now
talk about what we mean by peaceful
protest. So they have a second round of
discussion to try and um come to an
agreement on the definition of peaceful
protest.
This slide shows sort of the process um
through going through the first round of
um discussions, an AI statement of
agreement that summarizes what we agree
on and then an AI question prompt that
then leads to a second round of
deliberation and then a second round of
agreement. And what we found that was
really interesting was that in all cases
the AI moderated conversation led to
more support for rights to peaceful
protest. In other words, um people again
moved towards the area of common
agreement and we saw this change with
all groups with Democrats, with
independents and with
Republicans. Other results that aren't
shown here also include increased
understanding of what was being
discussed and increased perceptions that
the platform was
legitimate. Using NLP, we also saw that
AI moderated conversations encouraged a
greater diversity of comments. um a
greater diversity of words and a greater
diversity of
topics. So it does seem like AI
generated statements can be another way
of summarizing a lot of information
quickly for participants. And we're now
doing research to understand whether
participants feel that in some ways an
AI moderator is seen as more impartial
and that's why they see AI moderated
deliberations as more legitimate.
Although we say all of this of course
while noting we should continue to be
careful about understanding exactly how
the AI
works. The last module I'll discuss is a
comment ordering module and um this
shows um comment voting on our platform
and actually it's supposed to show a a
series of comments. Um after each
comment the user selects a button agree,
disagree or pass and the next comment
shows up. So, comment routing or comment
ordering are important parts of a
participant's experience with online
deliberation platforms. Um, when users
take part in a conversation online on
online deliberative platforms, they're
exposed to a set of comments, usually
displayed sequentially.
So computer scientists generally design
the order in which these comments are
displayed to help the algorithm work
most efficiently and not necessarily by
these kinds of downstream social
considerations such as making the user
feel um more heard or making them feel
like the process is legitimate. So we
were interested in examining this and we
did some research where participants
first indicated their position about
automatic voter registration and then
they were randomized into one of three
conditions. similar comments, comments
that were similar to their own opinion,
moving gradually to different um those
who started off with viewing comments
that were very different from their own
opinions and then slowly moving to ones
that were more similar and then random,
which is actually I think the default
case typically in these
platforms. Um so interestingly we found
that participants in the similar to
different condition were more likely to
find the process more legitimate and to
feel more represented when compared to
the random order condition. People find
it more comfortable to first see
opinions that are closer to themselves
and then move to more different ones.
They're they seem to be more likely to
accept different views when they're
moving from similar to different.
So again we see participants feel that
they feel more respected
um among yeah when they when they are in
um the similar to different comment
ordering. So to summarize through our
Socratic dialogue module we're learning
that AI assisted reasoning can move
opinions to more centrist positions and
depolarize the discussion. Showing
people the face of the crowd
visualizations can help us find clear
areas of agreement, correct
misperceptions about polarization when
it doesn't actually exist, and realize
how much we actually agree with one
another. AI moderated conversations with
AI generated agreement statements and
questions can lead to more nuanced
discussion, more understanding, and more
legitimacy of deliberation and decision.
and similar to different comment routing
helps people feel more respected and
more
represented. All of our studies have
been done in the lab so far with
research participants, but we're now
also working on a set of field studies.
Our first one will be with the
Washington DC government with the office
of the chief technology officer. So
using deliberation.io, we'll discuss two
policy issues with citizens in DC. uh
one the use of AI in government and two
AI in the future of the DC
economy. We've already won one f we've
already run one focus group in DC. Um
here are some of the photos from that.
And um the actual town hall discussions
for the DC city government go live in
July and October.
We also have some plans to design a
preference aggregation module and we're
also running full studies of our pilots
where we're exploring topics with
different levels of polarization to see
if the results um replicate and hold for
these different kinds of topics.
Finally, we're working with potential
partners on other locations for field
studies including Michigan, Texas, and
Utah. And we hope that this work will
help participants and policy makers make
sense of the information they receive
from online town hall meetings and most
of all restore civility to our political
discourse. So a big thanks to CIRC and
Schwarzman for enabling this work. It's
relatively rare for those of us who
study political philosophy and political
theory to be working together with
computer scientists. So we're very
grateful to CIRC for making this
possible. And I should also say that I'm
gonna flip hopefully um to the beginning
because I failed to talk about the
research team. Um this is Copiad with
Sandy Pentland, my colleague in computer
science. And we're joined by a very
talented research team of grad students,
postocs, and research scientists,
including Lula Chen, um GVLab's research
director who's here with us today. So I
look forward to the questions from all
of you. And I'm going to ask Lula
actually to join for the Q&A. Thank you.
Thank you very much. Lily questions.
Uh so you you use the the the phrase
like this is the AI uh supporting that.
Can you say more about which AI is that
your your like customized AI or from a
company and and uh would this AI be able
to get the different uh opinions come to
like more close to the central? Would
that also be able to shift this central
point toward this way or toward that
way? Yeah, we do use I mean we do see
them shifting opinions and moving people
more to the middle. But um if I'm not
mistaken, this is based on GPT40, right
Minnie? Yeah. Um do you want to say
anything more about how it was um the
prompt engineering that we used? Sure.
Actually, oh you might have to just
raise I'll just speak loudly. Um so u
maybe I can address the shifting
opinions part. Um so in our um in the
design of this we really want people to
think through their opinions but we
don't necessarily try to shift opinions.
So, for example, with Socratic dialogue,
uh the the way that the AI prompt works
and what we're asking people to do is to
reason through why they think what it is
that they think, but we don't
necessarily say, well, then you should,
you know, the AI then says you should
think XYZ, something like that. So,
we're not trying to shift opinions in
that way. Um, and then for for the
system prompting, we've been doing uh
it's mainly just prompt engineering that
we're working on here. uh in terms of uh
some of the specific cases like with DC
we are thinking there are some values
and rules that DC wants to have for the
for uh making sure that that interaction
with the AI goes well for citizens so we
do have some training that will happen
with with that but in this first in
these iterations we're just doing system
prompting uh prompt engineering that way
thank you for your talk that felt
actually very uplifting uh we've talked
a little bit about introducing bias when
we use an LM, how do you make sure your
moderator moderated chatbot doesn't
introduce bias? Uh, pretty much Yeah, I
mean, I think this goes back to what
Lulu was saying that the the chatbot is
supporting reflection. So, it's actually
taking what the person themselves says
and just asking what's your reason for
that? Um, or what do you mean by X? Um
so there's no um there's no the chatbot
is not engineered to nudge them in any
particular direction which is why it's
so amazing that once you support a
little bit of reflection like what are
my reasons for that or why do I think
that that you actually do see people
moving towards the
middle. Is that fair to say? Yeah.
Uh hi Lily this is Katherine from urban
planning. Uh thank you so much for a
great presentation. I want to ask you
all about the Overton window, like this
idea that there's like a kind of sphere
of reasonable discourse under which we
can um debate and then certain things
fall outside of that. And I think one of
the things that's so maybe challenging
and polarizing about the current moment
is that both like the statements and the
actions um of both the current
administration and and others as well um
h are are shifting the Overton window.
And so so it makes me think about like
the questions that you're posing here
and like who would be uh engineering the
questions that would be the subject of
deliberation and debate because it seems
like what's um really happening uh at
least in this current administration is
really pushing on that Overton window
such that now we're going to be debating
you know should we be kidnapping
students off the street for writing
opeds? You know what I mean? um which
which feels like an entirely
unreasonable thing to be debating about
and like I don't want to like sort of
move my position on that in any way
whatsoever but but so I guess can you
comment on that and sort of like how do
we how do we think about what is even a
reasonable question to come together
around when we are living this moment of
kind of like extreme actions and
complete norm busting that is going on
right now. Yeah. Yeah. Um, I mean, I'll
turn to you, Lula, because I'd be
interested to know what your question
your answer is, too. But, but Katherine,
I think, you
know, if I could answer if I could, if I
had a good answer to that question, you
know, we'd be all set, I think, in a
way. But I think what I would say is
that my hope would be technologies like
this that are designed to be to uphold
pro-democratic values and principles,
make it easy for anybody to ask a
question. That's number one. And number
two, because they're designed and tested
to be pro-democratic and pro-social,
that um norms that promote respect and
inclusiveness
um and open-ended curiosity and
open-ended um um consideration are
easier to uphold in this kind in this
kind of online environment. um that um
part of the problem of course is that
the social norms that exist in quote
social media which is really antisocial
actually promote don't enable that and
so therefore um perhaps overly narrow
the Overton window beyond what it can be
but I don't know if Lula you want to add
to that. I I agree with Lily there. I
guess the other I hope it's not a cheap
answer, but um at least when we're
testing this in the field, we are really
working with governments and we're
trying to find questions that are very
practical that people are actually care
about, you know, where should we put
bike lanes, those types of things. Um so
we're trying to keep that topic uh
narrow at least in these field tests
that we're doing. So that's where we're
constraining it. But once it's open, I I
agree with Lily. You know, it we'll
we'll we'll hope to see more uh of these
good norms coming about.
Okay, let's thank uh Lily and Lula
again.