together with Alexandro we will present
now diffusion for molecule
generation. So now what is going to
happen? First I will have a introduction
with uh why and how molecule generation
is done and then I will go through
kerality and isometric groups very
important concepts and then I will have
a brief diffusion
basics and then uh diffusion on point
clouds and then last of my part will be
problems with E3 invariance.
And then Alexandro will take the latter
part uh and talk talk
about how to actually use fields and new
representation for molecules and then
talk about the challenges and solutions,
how to handle these and then empirically
confirm these results that uh that uh
the theory I will present here
first. Okay. So why molecule generation?
So we want to make some molecules for
medicine and historically those have
been found from
nature. But now we can use generative
models to generate an initial set that
we can then in silico filter and then
further filter in the wet
lab and then we can furthermore do
conditional modeling. So taking some
condition like a binding pocket and have
a better initial set and using this kind
of automated pipeline could give uh a
lot of savings because because drug
discovery is extremely
expensive. But first the models need to
actually generate some sensible
molecules.
So they need to adhere to basic
chemistry rules like the octed rule and
then they need to be stereochemically
feasible. So the 3D confirmation has to
be something that can actually exist and
the models need to scale to larger
compounds both computationally but also
when larger compounds they are more
complex. So the models need to also know
how to model these more complex
molecules.
So for this the as Martin tell told that
these molecules has to be represented in
some good ways. So so that the model
model can actually use uh important
features. So uh a little bit like just
Martin said that this miles which is
this string representation it kind of
doesn't make sense because there is no
natural start and end or ordering of
molecules and also in the smiles
representation one molecule can have
many different very different smiles. So
the model would have a hard time adding
both of those representations to the
same molecule.
Then also graphs are kind of good but
these do not consider the 3D
confirmation. So there is also a
deficiency there. And then we have point
clouds. So these are quite good. So
these are just points living in the 3D
space. So these can handle the 3D
confirmations and then the the bonds can
be either modeled directly or then
inferred from the distances of the
points that can be
atoms. Then lastly we will have fields
and this is
uh amazing and Alexander will present
more of the fields
approach. So then you can actually for
the generation of these molecules you
can given a graph generate the atoms for
the graph and get a molecule or you can
generate fractions instead of atoms or
then you can just create the
connectivity graph connect different
atoms but the thing we will consider
most here is to generate molecular graph
and the 3D structure. So the the full
molecule
And now one important thing is parality.
So this is handedness and this is a
special property that the mirror image
of a molecule cannot be superposed on
the original
one. So so it's exactly like your right
and left hand. You cannot rotate your
right hand or translate right translate
and rotate your right hand to get your
left hand. You actually have to have a
reflection and kality is quite important
in biology.
uh for example like the metabolization
is dependent on on the on the kyal
nantomer and also here the ibuprofen is
only effective in one of the
nantiomers. So kality is is an important
feature and kind of related are the
mathematical isometric groups where we
have the ukidian group which is
rotations translations and reflections.
So if some function is invariant to to
E3 then it cannot distinguish between
the two
enant. So kind of a better way is the
have se pre-invariant methods so that
rotations and
translations do not make a different but
then reflections
do. So this this would be like really
nice for all these molecular
generation methods. We will I will come
back to back to this
later. So first I will show some
diffusion basics. So diffusion is well
quite a good generative uh approach used
quite a lot. So uh we want to model some
data distribution of interest
and and uh more specifically we want to
sample more from it. So how do we do
this? We we take a noise distribution
here a Gaussian and then we want to
couple these
distributions. So going from the uh
interest distribution of interest or the
data to the easy distribution is quite
easy. We can just gradually add Gaussian
noise. This is called the forward
process. So here we can we can choose
that do we add a lot of noise in the
beginning or middle or end and then uh
to what sort of gaussian we come. So
this is kind of the noising schedule
that we can
choose and then eventually we want to
learn the reverse process. So to take
noise and then make this back into the
distribution of
interest and yeah for example
images this is uh quite uh quite uh
basic application and uh we we are using
the the DDPM
formulation and and here we have X0
which is the clean data point and x1 is
the is the total noise data point and
here q denotes the forward process. So
the noising process this is defined by
our noising schedule. So we know this
this is as gaussian and the the the p uh
is the the reverse and this is something
we want to
learn. So at any time point now between
between the zero and one we would like
to have the same distribution if we go
from the forward and go for backward. So
one could simply take now the the
forward here and the backward and then
match them. But this would be kind of
computationally unfeasible because you
would need to have a two v random
variables and make a montal estimate of
that.
So instead you can match it to the
posterior of the forward and you using a
clean clean data point and this this
will then also be tractable the
posterior and now we can
actually match this which in a
computationally feasible
way and the the reverse process can then
be parameterized by taking the the
posterior and instead of a actual clean
image we take a neural network and
predict a clean image based on the noisy
image. And now we can have a variational
lower bound and make a loss. And now the
the main part of this loss would be the
matching of the the posterior and the
reverse. And these would be then
Gaussians with the same standard
deviation. Uh so we can further simplify
this this loss to just a squared error.
And then also in practice it is easier
to learn just
noise data point. So this is kind of
mathematically equivalent but it's in
practice a lot
better. Yeah. I think I'll skip this but
this there is a neat way of doing uh
conditioning for
diffusion and this that was classifier
free
guidance but yeah okay so diffusion on
point clouds so there is this EDM which
is like a seminal work for this E3
equariant molecule generations so these
are then using point clouds so points in
in in in 3D space and This is then
parameterized by a graph neural network
that takes distances as
input and then then yes this 3D
coordinates are are then then diffused
and modeled and based on on the on the
clean uh positions of the atoms then you
can determine the bonds. So here it's uh
it's important to note that both the the
positions and those also the the bonds
and also the types of the of the atoms
can be changed basically at every time.
So you can never know that this is for
sure a
carbon. Yeah. Here is a illustration of
of the den noising process.
Okay.
Now, now the the those
are those are this is actually
like kind of nice this uh point clouds
having the
E3 invariance because of the rotations
and translations. But uh there is this
problem that if we have a a E3 invariant
distribution then the enant will appear
at the same
probability. So this is quite bad. For
example, if you want to model a data set
of highly metabolizable molecules and
this is very dependent on on the kyal
configuration. This is actually not good
if we have a E3 invariant method because
then it was just randomly 50/50 choose
which Nantium will come
out and actually so this GNN in EDM and
many other point clouds is E3
invariant. So this also makes the
conditional
equivariant and furthermore this will
make given that the prior is invariant
this will also make the the probability
distribution that you generate invariant
and and this means that
yeah it cannot consider the
kality the the current uh point cloud
methods
Okay. So now can we fix this and make it
SC3
invariant? So now we can take a function
that is SE3
invariant. And if we actually have a
function that takes an object of m
uh n dimensional vectors but m is less
or equal to n then actually the function
output will be e3
invariant and yeah just to remind that
yeah we can do any rotation and the
function will be
same but now actually because the
dimensionality
uh any reflection can also be formulated
as this rotation and we can look at this
example in in 3D space where we have
these three points
uh and we we can reflect them but we're
reflecting on this this yellow plane but
the reflection is actually exactly the
same thing as the rotation around now
the line L
here. So, so now if the function is is
SE three
invariant, it will all also be E3
invariant for these three
points. So, so this means that that if
we have just three points, you cannot
get an SE3 invariant feature.
Okay, but we still want this. So if we
have now E3 invariant features and a
function that eats those
features, then it cannot be anything
else than E3
invariant. But okay, so how how can we
get something that is SE3 invariant but
not E3 invariant? So we have one
suggestion uh which is the determinant.
So we have four points and we subtract
one of the points from rest of the three
ones and then we take the determinant.
So the terminant will will have the
value and the sign of the the volume and
the sign of the volume of of this
tetraedron and and the sign will
actually tell the the the kyal
nant. And then actually if we have two
of these function outputs if we do not
have the same four
points they will actually be independent
of each other.
And then now we we say that okay if we
want to have one of those point clouds
that for any time point we actually
cannot know what the atom type is and
also the exact connectivity then we need
to have O to the N to the power of four
of these features and this is kind of
bad meaning that it's kind of hard to
actually create this uh point client
point cloud method
uh that would actually be SE3 but not E3
in
variant and that's that's what I wanted
to say. So now Alexandra will will
present uh a
solution. Um hello. Yep. I am Alexander
Ditresco and I will continue by
presenting one of our recent works uh
published this year at Icleair entitled
E3 equivariant models cannot learnity
field based molecular
generation. So I will briefly recap what
Danny said.
We want to uh present uh generative drug
like molecules uh generative models for
drug like molecules uh because uh this
can be a means of more efficiently
exploring the vast space of molecules
and this might help us in the near
future to accelerate drug
discovery. And then we know that the
efficiency of drugs is highly dependent
on their three-dimensional
confirmations. And therefore much of the
prior work has focused on these point
clouds that uh model directly the atom
coordinates and atom
types and that they are predominantly
free invariant. So invariant to any
global translations, rotations or uh
reflections of the
molecules and there is this problem that
kyal molecules are not reflection
invariant and that reflections of
molecules that contain chyal centers
will create an antim pairs which have
distinguishing properties and that if
invariant methods cannot capture or
distinguish. And so furthermore, we also
argue how parallel adaptations are quite
challenging to develop uh while keeping
rotational invariance. And then here is
the uh same image with ibuba that is
only efficient in its s
form. So we propose diffusion models on
fields and concretely we define scalar
fields in the threedimensional space for
each atom and coalent bond type
uh which have the following form. So
they are sort of uh unnormalized gausian
balls with specific uh field parameters
uh gamma and standard deviations and
they of course depend on the atom
positions m and kind of a depiction of
these continuous uh fields uh is on the
right hand side where we present this
benzene which is a planner molecule and
therefore we can only show a z equals
zero section. of the field. So the field
is 3D but now we only look at the
section of
it. Uh we form our inputs by evaluating
these fields at specific locations G and
uh we do this for both the atoms and
bond
fields and we select equally spaced
locations G. uh therefore uh creating
fields like this image.
Uh and then yes so the final input
representation is the concatenated
uh evaluated fields for every atom
channel and every coalent bond channel.
Alexandro how are atoms and bond fields
coupled? Obviously one is heavily
dependent one on another.
uh right so I'm not exactly sure what
you mean by coupled but uh I guess they
are separate fields but they of course
uh influence the neural network
activation. So the neural network I will
describe later how the neural network
works but the neural network sees both
fields and atoms at the same time and
should hopefully learn to create
reasonable molecules and as we will see
later to a good degree they are
so the neural network in other words
learns you cannot have a bond if you
don't have two atoms right on the right
positions. Yeah. So it is considered to
have been better than at least that. So
it's it's never generating bonds at
where where there aren't atoms.
Yep. Okay. So now we will go through the
architecture and the invariances of our
architecture. So since we have equally
spaced grid locations G uh we can use
the three-dimensional adaptation of a
unit and just briefly describing what
this does. Uh so we have multiple
downscale and upscale layers for various
resolution levels and then we have sort
of similar to a skip connection uh
layers that concatenate the downscale
hidden representations to the upscale
hidden representations. And the
intuition on this is that the
architecture can capture both the the
global features of the molecule as well
as the local features for the low and
then high resolution levels
respectively. In terms of the ify
invariances, we have good translational
invariance inductive biases because this
uh this
architecture has most of its parameters
in convolutional neural networks.
then we have no reflection invariance
which is of course a good thing as we
can distinguish an antiimer but we do
not have rotational
invariance. So what we propose to
mitigate this issue is that uh we
define reference rotations as rotations
about their principal components and
again again the same benzene molecule is
depicted here.
uh now going through the diffusion
noising process. So we use a variance
preserving noising process defined by
some alpha parameter that gradually
removes the signal you not which is the
clean uh input field and then the noise
added at each time step is directly
defined by the alpha t schedule which
defines how fast the signal is removed.
For alpha t we use an generalization of
the cosine noising schedule uh with with
this new
parameter and setting new equal to 1 and
u equal to
1.5 will result in generating bonds
faster or equivalently destroying atoms
faster. And this is an example of a
generated uh generated molecule. So here
we show 200 highest values across all
the bonds and atom type uh atom type
channels respectively. And you can see
probably also related to the question
earlier that they are sort
of even though we don't restrict the
model to generate specifically bonds at
locations where there are atoms or vice
versa then of course these are
still reasonably well coupled in in a
sense. Then uh after we have generated
the fields themselves, of course we just
have some values in the field
dimensional space, we we would like to
actually retrieve the molecular graphs
from those
fields. And first uh to do this we look
at the atom
fields and we detect field locations
that have high enough peaks and assign
the number of atoms and rough locations
m for each atom
type based on threshold based algorithm
which is a very efficient relatively
simple
algorithm. After this our rough initial
atom positions of course are not good
enough. We want to actually optimize
them. So what we do is essentially we we
fit the functional form of the atom
fields to the generated values. So the
bolded UAX here is the or represent the
generated generated field values at
locations X and G. And we would want to
minimize the square error loss to the
functional form of UA M of X for all the
locations for all the atom locations M.
So we optimize the atom locations
here. Then uh to initially extract bonds
this is quite a bit easier. We simply
can look at only the mid positions
between any two atoms. So, MI plus MJ by
2 and determine whether or not a high
enough value is within that region. And
for each MI plus MJ by two value which
is high enough we assign assign some
component gamma J. And then this time we
optimize for the gamma values.
So you can see a very similar uh
optimization function here. So the arc
mean over the gamma this time.
which u which also minimizes the square
direct loss between the functional form
of the bond fields and the generated
bolded
UBX. And on the right hand side image we
have an example of a QM9 molecule with
noised out fields. So the procedure is
generally robust enough that if you
don't actually add noise to the fields
of a data molecule, the extraction will
just be correct. So here we also added
on top of the original field some noise.
And then we we can see that the wand
marked with X should not be there. It
should not be there because there are no
actual Gaussian picss at the at that
specific location. And correspondingly
after optimizing for the gamma values we
see that one gamma has a much lower
value than the rest meaning that that
specific location does not contain uh a
gshian uh
u for for the bone
fields and uh yes
so here is roughly how how the bones
look they are depicted here with some
sticks of different colors for different
coalent bond types and the field values
at their
centers and this is finally the the
complete molecular graph which has been
extracted by this
procedure. So yeah the the full pipeline
is sort of you generate these field
values at specific locations that you
predefine and uh after the values have
been generated then you need to extract
the molecular graph in this kind of
complicated way but not not really that
complicated. So there are two sort of
deterministic optim extraction phases
and then subsequent optimization phases
that happen here to extract the the
molecular graph. Um could you explain
how you like initialize the whole
process like with the atoms and the
bonds in this field like let's say you
want I don't know a molecule with like
six carbons and 12 hydrogens like how do
you
actually initialize the bond in the atom
feel to get something that sort of looks
yeah so are you now talking about uh the
generation phase where I'm actually
generating the fields or are you talking
about the graph extraction phase
first. Okay. So the first starts as any
other diffusion model you just simply
have random noise. So each location in
the three dimensional space is
considered to be isotropic normal
gshion. So the initialization is simply
throwing a sample from a randomizotropic
gion putting that into the neural
network that does many time steps of
dnoising and then you arrive at a clean
field or hopefully clean enough field
and based on that you extract a
molecular graph here. So you cannot also
enforce the model to generate six atoms.
It will generate some number of atoms.
So there there's no way to like
condition it to sort of yeah so you can
use classifier free guidance which Danny
has very briefly mentioned.
Uh so yeah I mean you can do conditional
generation. It's a conditional
generative modeling
problem. You can also condition on the
atom types with atom counts which we do
but it's not necessary I guess.
um is another way to condition it just
like how you train the model. So if you
I don't know choose a certain class of
molecules to train on then it's going to
spit out things in in that class I would
assume. Yes, of course. Yeah. So it
should model the distribution that
you're training on. Yes.
Okay. Uh sorry. Yeah. So right here I'm
at exactly I guess that point which is
classifier free guidance which is one
method to actually define
um conditional generation for diffusion
models in general not necessarily for
this but in general it has been
defined.
So since many evaluated metrics are
highly correlated with atom counts we
also consider actually conditioning the
the generated fields on specific atom
counts. So now we actually try to
enforce to a degree a continuous degree
by some parameter beta that the fields
will generate specifically some number
of
atoms. Um and yes as as we have seen uh
point cloud methods are restricted to
have a
prespecified number of atoms n which
they can move in space and den noiseise
to some atom types and to kind of
um to kind of determine how how much the
atom counts conditioning is or how how
important this conditioning is to
various metrics. We also consider this
classifier free guidance. atom counts
and we define specifically some variable
Z which are bean atom counts where each
bean contains roughly the same number of
molecules in the data set and these
beans somehow resemble the the number
rough number of atoms that should be
generated and the beta controls the the
uh the guidance amount that we require.
So how much do we want the generated
fields to adhere to the correct number
of atoms that we condition on can be
specified by the parameter
beta. Okay. So briefly for the
benchmarking data that have been used.
First the smaller data set QM9 which
contains molecules of nine heavy atoms
or at most 27 atoms including hydrogen
and there are four five atom types and
about 130,000 molecules and one example
of a molecule is depicted
here then uh GM drugs it's a
considerably larger data set this data
set contains many confirmations of
various energies for each molecular
graph. And therefore this number of
confirmation is a lot larger than the
number of 300,000 unique about 300,000
unique molecular
graphs and
uh yeah up to 181 atoms I think if you
include hydrogen and probably the
average is about 40 atoms and about 27%
of those molecules are actually also
chyro so containing some chyro
Briefly uh we go now through some
experiments. First of all, the atom and
molecule neutrality defined as the
percentage of generated molecules that
are neutral and the percentage of
generated atoms that are neutral. So the
the molecule neutrality is defined
slightly differently in that it
considers a molecule to be neutral if
only all of its atoms are neutral. And
then validity checks only that the
molecules can be parsed by artic which
generally checks for valency and whether
the molecule can be
calculized. Okay. So on the on the
lowest row we have the data kind of
showing that on the QM9 the easier data
set roughly 100% of the molecules are
neutral and valid. So meaning that
larger numbers are just better on this
data set and uh yeah we obtain very good
performance. So uh
outperforming pretty much I guess all of
the other
methods and then for the GM drugs uh
here there are many many caveats that
need to be explained. I guess any one
method in this table cannot be compared
strictly or reliably to any other method
almost
um on on this specific data set because
there are very many settings that have
been used. So some models generate
explicitly the uh the aromatic bond
types. Some other models use only five
lowest confirmation energies. We used 30
lowest as some of the first works on on
on this and some even used the lowest
kind of creating hugely different
numbers of training molecules
um which of course makes the the
comparison not
super not super
reliable. Then we look at a few molecule
uh quality properties. So for this we
define the total variation between the
count distributions of various atom
types and convolent B types. So the
total variation is just some distance
metrics metric between distributions
between uh probability
distributions and then um we also have
the MSD defined as the maximum
similarity test. So we take the tanimo
tanimoto similarity between the morgon
fingerprints between the generated
molecules and the test data molecules.
So there is a subset of the data that is
considered that's the test and then
uh based on uh based on the most similar
fingerprint
we which is yeah between zero and one we
we measure the average maximum
similarity to test of the generated
molecules. Could you briefly elaborate
what you mean with similarity here again
and how you would measure this or score
this? What's the metric? Yes. So um so I
guess it's the tanimoto similarity
between Morgan fingerprints where the
tanimoto if I remember correctly it's
the just the intersection over union
uh of the exact same uh fingerprints
that are
some more yeah some some representation
of molecules. a very a very very
simplistic representation of molecules
and then we take all of the generated
molecules and compare them across all of
the test data molecules and then kind of
match to the best
match. So in a perfect scenario I guess
you would assume that this number should
go to one or very close to one.
Does uh some of these metrics also cover
how well you cover the landscape of all
the molecules points? Yes.
So especially TVA and TVB and then there
are a couple of other metrics I guess in
the data set that consider uh mode
coverage but the idea is that they also
consider as Martin said um not only how
high quality the molecules are but
whether you cover the whole distribution
that you are training
on. So that was a good
point. Okay. So here we obtained roughly
competitive performance except with a
big exception on the total variation of
atoms. Uh and then we yeah we we
reiterate how essentially point clouds
are are constrained to generate a
specific number of atom atoms for each
molecule. Uh so because of this you can
of course trivially match the atom
counts of the data and then of course
the various atom type atom counts will
probably have like a much better EVA.
But this is yeah kind
of just some some property of point
clouds and then similarly on GM but yes
again with all the caveats that have
been mentioned with different data
settings
different bond representations and so
on.
So yeah, the conclusion would be that
the method
is having quite high performance and
then as we will see later can also
nicely capture viral molecules or
distinguish an antimic pairs which is
quite
nice. Okay. Now before that I will
briefly go through confirmations. So
before the parality part I will briefly
go through the confirmation metrics. So
the first one is quite easy. It's the
distribution of the generated bone
lengths and this we measure in pometers
because the models are generally so good
in generating confirmations that yeah
you you actually need to measure them in
pometers and notstrom which is the the
scale that you usually use for bond
distances and then yeah we we just
achieve surprisingly good performance
even though we don't directly model the
coordinates we are still able to to
achieve really really
Verstein distance which is well another
um another metric
for or distances between two probability
distributions and the same for bond
angles now measured in degrees. So on
QM9 about one vasstein distance measured
in degrees it's looking quite good and
similarly for GM it doesn't it doesn't
become that much worse with with the
bond length and bond angles. So those
were the simpler metrics and then we
also look at energies confirmational
energies and the first one is molec
molecular field force field energies
which directly or explicitly consider
coalent bond types and since many of the
methods explicitly consider coalent bond
types we we
we also include this this
metric for field uh for confirmational
energies. And then finally XTB
vaserstein distance. Uh so energy is
computed with the same tool that has
been used to optimize or the same yeah
same tool that has been used to optimize
the the confirmations of the data that
we are actually using for the training.
So again roughly very good confirmations
given that uh no explicit
um no explicit there is no explicitly
modeling the atom
coordinates. Yep. So this was the point.
Okay. So now the kality
experiment we look at a very simple uh
small 48 molecule data set where all of
the molecules are kyal. So that they
have a K center and we specifically have
a carbon connected to another carbon,
nitrogen, oxygen and
hydrogen. And
then the the way the hyality can be
determined as Danny presented earlier is
with some function f uh which is the
determinant of the kind of well it's the
signed volume of a of a of a
tetrahedrin. So the tetrahedrin if you
look at the signed volume you can
actually strictly determine the kyal
configuration well that coupled with the
atom types and the residue types
essentially can tell you directly what
the kality is but what this experiment
shows is that on a skewed data so the
data is shown in blue the data
distribution is shown in blue it's
skewed towards one of the anantimer
configurations and we try to find which
med methods can capture
this uh and first in orange we we simply
have an empirical confirmation that
essentially the a molecule and its
reflected counterpart would be will have
an equal probability. So you can say the
the equal uh equal probability on the
two
modes and yeah this essentially just
confirms that the anantimer are
non-distinguishable for if invariant
neuronet network
parameterizations. Then we actually
surprisingly look at GDM which is a non
EA invariant point cloud method and it
seems that point cloud methods still
seem to suffer uh on uh on on a kyal
data set. So even though now clearly the
model distinguishes the two anantimer
there's some difference in the generated
distribution for one of the anantimer.
So the left one has fewer which is
correct and the right one has more
generated molecules. Still the middle uh
there is a middle zero volume
tetrahedrron that are generated which
are of course are unnatural
confirmations and they seem to have this
this sort of problem when when directly
modeling specifically I data set and
then we finally have fields which seem
to be quite appropriate for for this
task where FMG in red captures this
distribution quite well.
Okay,
so I will now briefly go through
conditional generation where we consider
two different properties and the setting
is that we have 50% of the Q9 data as
the training data and 50% as a training
data for a discriminative models for
discriminative model for the same
property that we train the generative
model and uh these are the two models
for alpha polarizability and delta
epsilon the homolumo gap for the orbital
energies and then we correspondingly
have two
classifiers determining what
polarizability and homol gap the
molecule a molecule
has and then we measure how well the
molecules adhere to the property y that
we use uh to condition using the fi y is
either alpha or delta epsilon
And what we find is generally a
reasonable adherence to the conditioning
property. Uh but mentioning here that
the model seems to trade kind of this
rough measure of stability on the QMline
data set which is neutrality for
adherence to the conditioning property.
But in general uh quite reasonable and
then it's also quite nice here to
mention that since we do not need to
explicitly generate a specific number of
atoms this would probably be quite
useful in general for conditional
generating conditional generation uh of
of molecules with with some specific
properties. So if we want to have many
properties to condition on a uh so to
generate gen gener conditionally
generate molecules on a vector of
multiple properties that vector of
multiple properties in point point
clouds would have previously needed this
joint distribution of the properties and
the atom counts which of course cannot
necessarily be so easy to determine
based on a b based on some data set but
here yeah you don't need this and then
we show this so beta equals z fg beta
equals Z is a model that is not
conditioned on atom counts and can still
uh conditionally generate
some some molecules.
Could you briefly say again which data
has been used here and in terms of
absolute abundance or absolute number of
inputs roughly estimate how big was your
training and test data set? Yeah. So
it's GM9 and I believe it's the training
subset which is 100,000 split into equal
parts. So 50,000 for training the
generative model and 50,000 for training
the discriminative models. So the test
here is the discriminative model telling
whether the generated molecule is
correctly generating according to the
conditional distribution power.
Yeah. Okay. Now
we okay we briefly show some
uh ablations um so some of the design
choices that make our performance
competitive. So we first look at
removing the reference rotations which
have been presented as a as a way of
mitigating the rotational invariance
problems and then or the lack of
rotational invariance problems and then
uh FMG is a model that receives randomly
rotated molecules as training input. So
before we create the field we randomly
rotate the molecule and then this for
instance has a molecule neutrality at
82.6
Whereas adding the adding the reference
rotation so fng beta equals 0 the number
becomes 92.2. This is by far the most
important design choice. And then we
also have the atom count conditioning
which is quite important for TVA but
roughly doesn't change that much any
other metrics. So other than atom count
metrics of course conditioning on atom
counts doesn't doesn't change uh the the
quality of the molecules as much. And
then finally this is sort of an
empirical confirmation of how nice our
confirmations are. So even when
detecting bonds based solely on the atom
distances we are able to achieve a
nutality of 91%. So the the bonds here
are detected based on some some
um intervals uh some reasonable
intervals where equivalent type b one
type one for instance between carbon and
nitrogen uh should be and uh
yeah so I was going to go a bit through
scaling but I don't think there is that
much time I
The bottom line bottom line here is that
uh it is probably about three to four
times slower during training compared to
the one of the simpler point load
methods EDM. Um but then
u but then still manageable especially
in terms of memory and then the
generation speed is on par if not even
better for very large molecules. So
molecules of 180 atoms or so. And then
yeah to summarize uh yeah fields provide
a pretty promising molecular
representation. And then we have seen
how point clouds are unable to
distinguish between an anti-mer variant.
And furthermore adaptations that are
paralleware are arguably pro
prohibitive. And then surprisingly point
clouds in general might have problems
with Cality. And then that uh their
flexibility
allows allows conditional generation
without restricting or requiring the
atom
counts. Reference rotations keep our
performance highly competitive. So this
is a very important design choice. And
for future directions uh the main point
is the size of U which we consider to
further optimize through various
u there are various options here. So the
first idea we we have is to perhaps have
sparse or uneven set of points G uh
where we evaluate our fields and of
course it was this would probably
require a different parameterization.
For instance, attention parameterization
is quite well suited in this case. a
more coarse
resolution. The latest kind of results
or experiments showcase that it's
probably possible to create an even more
coarse resolution and have the fields
become smaller, thus allowing deeper
neural network architectures and
probably better performance in fitting
our data sets or latent diffusion.
representing the fields as uh as some
latent representation that is of much
lower dimensionality and then creating
the diffusion model in that
space. Uh and then conditioning on
multiple variables is probably a very
nice experiment and probably quite
difficult to do in point clouds since
they require the atom counts. And
finally pocket conditioning which
is which is probably possible uh as
opposed to for instance protein
conditioning. So full protein
conditioning in fields is probably
prohibitive but pocket conditioning
given that if we want to generate bind
binders for a specific pockets pocket
that would be quite quite interesting
especially given the kyal sensitivity of
the model.
My talk focuses on on latent variable
models and and the goal is to give a
kind of an overview that how structured
variance of of those latent variable
models can be used for quite many
different prediction and optimization
tasks. So Disan Alexander's uh
presentation focused on on generation
using diff diffusion models. I have a
little bit more on sort of a modeling
focus in in in my talk not just
generation. Before I start I just very
briefly listed what our research group
really does. So o overall the work is
divided into sort of a probabilistic
machine learning computational biology
and and then applications and the talk
that I have prepared for today sort of
covers many of of these
topics and and we are really focusing on
nonlinear or deep latent variable models
which are generative models of of this
type. So we have a latent variable
generated from some base distribution
typically a goian in standard uh models
and and then the actual data item
conditional or the latent from some
other distribution which is typically
from the exponential family. The
specific feature of of these models is
is that the parameters of the
exponential family are obtained by a
nonlinear mapping D which takes the
latent as the
in standard uh deep latent variable
model. Once we observe data why we we
become interested in in the posterior of
the unknowns which are the latent
variables or if we don't know the model
yet we would like to use maybe the
evidence or the marginal likelihood for
training the model. Unfortunately both
of these quantities are are
interactable. So in in machine learning
uh field a common approach is to use the
autoenccoding variational bas which
means using variational amortized
variational inference. So we estimate
the the true posterior distribution of
the unknowns with some parametric uh
distribution Q and an amortization means
that we have a another mapping called
encoder function that maps the data item
into the parameters of the various
approximation and and if these
mappings FMC are neural networks then we
are talking about the
VAE all right and then to make these
models a little bit more useful in
practice. We are primarily focusing on
conditional gener models. So we always
condition the generation with some
coariates x both the generation of the
latent and and then the generation of
the actual
data and and then the amortized
inference also sort of have access to
these conditioning var sort of the sort
of same same setup but now we at the
conditioning terms as
well and then there are different uh
parameterizations for the conditional uh
modeling. So we can define the model
such such that the both the prior and
and the decoding likelihood see the
coariates or or such that only the
likelihood or only the prior is the
coaras and we are primarily focusing on
on the last
parameterization. All right. So I I'll
try to cover three topics which sort of
address the limitations or in in some
case also possibilities of these VAEs
and conditional VAS. The first focus is
on on uh on on the fact that the data
samples are completely independent in
the standard
models and why correlations are
important and I I thought about maybe
highlighting the longitudinal or
temporal data as an example case because
that's sort of the most obvious reason
why bother modeling correlations. So
longitudinal designs are are specific
type of time series data sets that
consist of multiple subjects and each
subject is then measured repeatedly over
time as as sort of illustrated here. And
then this experimental design sort of
implies that there are correlations both
within a subject over time as well as uh
correlations across multiple subjects.
And then if we want to use these kind of
a latent variable models for for this
type of data, we would like to be able
to model these correlations because
otherwise yeah it's a kind of a
nonsense. There are many ways to
implement the correlations in in these
models.
uh on the probabilistic modeling side I
think the gossian process approach is
probably the most commonly used and and
what it means is that the we simply
assign the L- dimensional latent
variable Z to have a multi output coium
process prior sort of a kind of a
technically we can say that Z is now
defined as a function of X coverates
inputs and and then we assign this F
function a Gaussian process
prior and this cosian process prior
typically has a zero mean and then it
has in this multi- output case a cross
coariance function which measures the
smoothness of the correlations and
dependencies in the latent
arrive and and then what this means in
practice is is that now if we take any
finite collection of inputs let's say n
data points or n prediction variables
then the corresponding latents have a
joint cosian uh distribution correlated
cosian distribution so The latent across
these n inputs then have a joint coian
in this case a zero mean and and then a
full coariance matrix defined by the
cross coariance of the cosian process
prior and then the s of the intuition is
that the uh crossarian function sort of
defines that how strongly the different
data points are coupled. So for those
data points where the inputs are close
by then the correlation is high. For
those inputs where the for those data
points where the inputs are far away the
correlation and then of course that
strength of the correlation also learned
from the
data. So this has been proposed already
a while ago. What we have been primarily
using is is is this kind of a additive
variant of of the model. So that the
latent variable is is defined to be sort
of a sum of of GP briers as as denoted
by here. Uh such that each of these
functions as a separate cosian process
drive and kind of the benefit of this
kind of approach is that it it sort of
allows us to have some sort of
interpretability of the latent variables
because we can now automatically factor
them in into additive terms much like in
in linear mixed modeling approach.
And then then the the conditional
generative model becomes the following.
So now the latent variable it doesn't
have the standard IID cosian instead it
has the Gaussian process prior which
implies correlations but again remember
that this is in in in real life this is
a normal distribution correlated and
then the the uh distribution for the
data items remains the same uh decoder
based exponential family distribution.
Are the multiple uh kernel functions
here operating on different dimensions
of the coariantss? Yes. Yes. Yeah.
Thanks Martin. So indeed the way we
typically implement these models is is
such that each function depends only on
on a subset of the coariates and and
then that provides the
interpretation and then I use again the
longitudinal data as an example. So
because now much of the sort of the
magic of these techniques builds on on
the choice of the coariance functions
and for example in in in the case of
modeling long material data we can use
for for example the exponentiated
quadratic kernel to model uh shared
effects shared across all the subsets.
uh category effects we can model maybe
using a product kernel of the zero sum
and and then uh the EQ kernel and and
then we can also have non-stationary uh
effects uh such as one may expect in the
case of rapidly happening kind of
happening uh events like disease onset
and and then we can have uh ID specific
random variation using
uh the the product of the ID and and
then the EQ kernel again and then we we
sum them up. So again this is just a one
dimension of the latent space. Of course
the latent space has many dimensions for
visualization purposes. I'm only saw one
and when we add the kernels or the
latent corresponding latent variables
this is then the the final latent
variable that we have but now we can
automatically decompose it into these
interpretable terms via the additive
feature. Okay. And then a couple of more
details before I I'll show how how these
things work. So let's say that we have
data set XY size N. So we have n many
data points. the the coariates or the
inputs, the corresponding data items and
and then the latent variables which we
never
observe and and then we are primarily
first interested in the in the marginal
likelihood because we we want to have
some sort of object
uh or objective to train the model. So
we can choose the parameters and
hyperparameters so that the marginal
likelihood is is maximized and and
exactly the same way as for the standard
models we we just integrate out the
latent variables to get the marginal
likelihood. And the only difference here
is that now the the while while while
the likelihood term factorizes then the
prior does not because we have
constructed it in a way that it catches
the correlations that we want to model.
Okay. And and then again these models
are are really not tractable. We don't
have analytical solutions. So we need to
rely on on autoenccodoring variational
base. So we have a we we approximate the
true posterior of the latent variables
with the variational family. uh in in
most of the work we are using mean field
approximation where we have a encoder
that maps each data item into the
corresponding parameters of the mean and
variance of the latent variables and
then then these functions muan and sigma
the typical neural network encoder
models and then we can use for example
the elbow objective to to to have a
lower bound for the uh margin
likelihood and and then Again, it has
the same form as as the elbow typically
has. I have written it here in in a
typical two-part uh way. So that the
first part shows the reconstruction loss
and then the second part shows the
regularization scale divergence term.
The first part is easy to compute
because these uh elements factoriize
according to the data points. The second
part does not because we have
constructed it in a way that it contains
the correlations that we want to model.
This has a closed form solution because
everything is gaussian. If you just have
million data points, then it's million
times million matrix. So this can be
slow to compute. So we have some
theoretical results from earlier work
where we proposed a provably tighter
evidence lower bound for the uh evidence
for a longit longitudinal or additive CP
models and then that provides us an
upper bound for the KL term here. so
that we have a objective against which
we can train these models and then we
also have a kind of a no mini patch
compatible scale h upper bound.
Okay, I'll show first one simulated data
set and then the point is to sort of
demonstrate that what these models can
do and we we took the emnest images
thousand different digits those now
represent our patients and then 20
different time points are obtained by
rotating and shifting the image
according to the coar associated to each
subject or bas and then we have a
additional 100 test subjects such that
we are given the initial data points and
and then the goal is to predict the
remaining time points that we have not
seen for the test
subset and and this is an illustration
what for example our model can
do and and we have compared our model
against many competing techniques some
of which use also gossian process based
techniques some use RNNs some use GANs
and and in in many cases it seems that
the our additives CB based VA model is
is is a good choice and how highly
performed. I'll show you a couple of
examples for real data sets a bit later
uh for for real electronic health record
data sets. But then I I thought that
maybe I saw this sort of a um
preliminary results uh from time series
single cell RNA sequencing data set that
we have been working on. So as you all
know sorry can I ask a question just on
the previous slide? So when you did the
simulation like how did you decide what
correlation structure to use
uh across I guess the time points and
these patients who are just spitting out
I guess numbers and then does the
complexity or simplicity of the
correlation structure change how much
data you need to train a model. Uh so so
the first part of the question was that
how how we choose the correlation
structure. So uh I I think in this this
case we we can't really interpret the
model as a as a just black box but we
need to make some modeling choices and
and then I I think a natural way to do
this modeling choices is is based on the
coariates that one has available. So we
are modeling the effects of the
coariates in the latent space and in in
this case I don't remember exactly but I
I suppose we had six or maybe a bit more
effects in the latent
space. Okay. Okay. So I guess that
answers my other question which is just
like you have more coariants you just
need more data I guess to uh yes
maybe also related to that but um in the
modeling how is that affected by
multiolinearity so for example if you
have age and blood pressure or something
like this you would already assume that
those um correlate with each other and
so how how would you deal with that?
Yeah. Well, I I I don't really have a
good answer, but I I I agree that it
would complicate things and then
obviously one can do some sort of a
coverage selection that which are really
important, but we haven't really gone to
that direction. That's a good good
question
though. So another application is
modeling time series uh single cell RNA
sequencing data. And so what this kind
of experiment gives is a large number of
highdimensional observations YT of
individual cells C at different time
points T and then the the kind of the
key feature of this modeling technology
is that you can measure one cell only
once and then then what we see is is
only the sort of a marginal
distributions at different time. But
nonetheless, we we thought that we we
want to try this uh our models on on
this type of data as well. We we can't
really apply the models directly as we
as I explained a couple of slides ago.
But what what is typically done in the
field is is to use some sort of earth
moving distance or style distance to
match the predictions model based
predictions with the data. So we we have
the uh data points in many cells at at
certain time points corresponding
predictions and and then we can use the
uh squared
ukidian uh loss to to get the vaserstein
two type of a distance measure between
the predictions and the the data points.
So what we what we can then do is to
train the kind of model that I explained
earlier but replace the reconstruction
loss in the evidence lower bound with
the corresponding waserstein such that
we we still get the predictions from the
uh kind of estimated latent variables
but we match the predictions with the
data only via the baserstein matching
between the individual
cells and this is something which is
finished but I I thought that it's kind
of interesting. I I wanted to present
that anyway and we we we have tested
this on on a couple of different data
sets. Uh so here are are some data sets
used in in other computational works
earlier from SR Josephine and then
mouse this many cells this many time
points and and then we we can try to
evaluate that how well these kind of
latent variable models are able to
interpolate between the time points. So
we kind of intentionally leave one of
the time points out and and then see how
well we can reconstruct the missing time
points use using our models and seems to
perform relatively well at least against
the previously proposed models which are
mostly using neural OD type of
techniques for the modeling and then
here are the corresponding
uh prediction. So this is the the data
colorcoded uh according to time points
and and then these are the uh
predictions from from our model in again
2D embedding
space. Okay, before going into this
electronic health record type of
analysis I I just want to mention that
many real world data sets contain
missing values. So any any subset of the
features or the coverates may be missing
completely at random. it's sort of
trivial to handle the uh uh completely
random missingness from the from the
features but less so from the from the
coariates and and then the goal is to
learn conditional va
uh from partially observed data sets
that contain missingness also in these
predictor variables
x and we we we do that by by augmenting
the the general model with the prior for
the coariates as well. such that the
joint distribution for the data latent
and and coariates factorizes
according and and then I I just note
that in in this case the coariates
contain both discrete and and continuous
variables. So it's not quite exactly the
same as as typical VA setting where
everything is continuous in
latency and I I will not go into details
but but the concept is sort of quite
quite simple. So we we extend the
amortized variational approximation also
for the unobserved co variates x and and
then we maximize the evidence lower
bound such that we simultaneously
marginalize out any uncertainty in this
unobserved
cover and in in in terms of elboy it
leads into this kind of objective where
we have
the typical reconstruction loss and and
then the k diver divergence the scale
divergence just happens to have now is a
two-part expression one for the missing
coariates and and then one for the
latent variables which involves analysis
expectation and and here is one example
how this kind of a model works so we
took the some observational longitudinal
data uh focusing on on Parkinson's
disease follow up about five years 500
patients uh about 3,000 samples
relatively low dimensionally in this
case 42 features observed seven covers
available but now it's a real world data
set so missing missingness in the
coverage is something between two and
and 32 so quite quite high missing and
then we apply these uh techniques that
try to handle the missingness in the
predict prediction variables as as well
and then evaluate
using future prediction task. So we are
given a data set and then additional
test subjects such that we have the
initial trajectories of the test
subjects and then we would like to
predict the future uh y values given the
the partially observed coariates x0 star
and I I don't have a comparison ac
across many different techniques and I'm
just showing that how this kind of a
technique that handles the missingness
in the coariates performs. So the red
bar is is something where we just don't
care. We press enter and and hope for
the best. Uh the the orange bar shows
the performance using the commonly used
mean imputation for the coverage. This
is KN&N imputation. And then this is our
approach that handles the the missing
coariates variationally as
well. Okay. and and then so now our
models can handle completely at random
missingness in the features and the
coariates. So we have the partially
observed coverates correlated latent
variables and then partially observed
observations. We can easily extend them
to handle structured missingness which
is missing at random or missing not at
random.
quite a realistic uh assumption in in uh
in medical data sets for example and
then that happens by adding an
additional latent variable that models
the missingness pattern as such and then
connect that to the missingness mask
which then implies that which uh data
values are are
used. We can also extend the models such
that they they uh model the marked point
process. So also the measurement time
points are random variables and then we
can do that using uh this
uh nonhomogeneous point processes or or
self exciting box processes or whatever
we want to choose use and then that
happens before the the actual modeling
of of the of the of the high dimensional
data. the play diagrams looks a little
bit more complicated but still sort of a
straightforward. I will not go into into
details of how how these are
implemented. I just want to illustrate
that what these models can do. So this
is again a simulated data set for for
simplicity. This is a kind of a real
data set. Again, the emnest type of
longitudinal data. And then this black
box now denotes the missingness mask
which we we can model separately. And
then some of the missingness patterns
also depends on the strength of the
underlying signal. So the stronger the
signal in in the digit tree, the higher
probability that the the pixel values
are also missing.
Um now I skip the the empirical
evaluation but it it performs really
well. Okay so that's the part one. So I
I tried to illustrate uh how these
structured meaning correlated latent
variables can be useful for longitudinal
modeling and and illustrated that using
uh electronic health records type of
data and then uh also something for the
time series uh single cell RNA
sequencing. We have also used this for
survival modeling in in in a
longitudinal setting. We have also
changed the CP prior with the linear mix
model prior to get a sort of a similar
performance. And then we have a some
work which sort of tries to improve the
underlying methodology so that the the
the um the the performance improves
across all these methods. But it's still
sort of unpublished.
Maybe one question about the intuition
here. So it used to be so that in the
old days we use this simple imputation
methods just to be able to use more data
in our models. But it seems here uh that
also modeling these intermediate
relations between the coariantss has
some sort of benefit on uh your
downstream tasks of of interest. Is that
the correct way to think about exactly
correct? Yes. So I I would claim that uh
in in most real data sets there is some
correlation between the missingness and
and the the the statistical properties
of the model. That's the way it's done.
Okay, the second part will be a little
bit shorter but focuses on on on using
these latent variable models for basian
optimization and you may be familiar
with the concept of latent space uh
basian optimization. So it's a kind of a
way to do blackbox
optimization of highdimensional or
structural structured objects. Why? by
combining latent variable modeling
typically variational
autoenccoder as well as basian
optimization for some specific feature C
using GP srogate in the latencies and
this is a figure from one of these early
studies where they used exactly this
technique for for optimizing molecules.
So you can sort of think about the the
molecule being encoded into latent base
representation and then do you do that
for for many molecules and implement
then the uh CB based surrogate basian
optimization in the latent space. use
some acquisition function to choose
which molecule to to quantify next and
then do the experiment and feed the data
back in and
continue and then obviously the the the
actual molecule that you want to
generate next is is then obtained via
the decoder from the
latency and our hypothesis is that u
maybe these conditional latent variable
models go process prior VAS in
particular can provide provide a better
structured latent space for basian
optimization.
So our approach is is something where we
uh do latent variable modeling using a
conditional CP prior
VAE where we have let's say the
molecules Y generated from the latent
variable Z but now the latent variable
would not be independent but depend on
on exactly the uh feature that we would
like to optimize as well as possible
additional features that we know of
these molecules as an example.
and and then apply the standard basian
optimization in the latence space that
we obtained from this kind of a
model. And one one needs to keep in mind
that in in this kind of a setting the
the coverates are then only partially
observed in a in a typical basian
optimization setting. You have only a
handful of data items for which you know
you know the quantity that you you would
like to maximize or minimize. So this is
only available for a typically a small
number of data points that that that you
want to do the modeling. And another
special feature is that
uh we we may have additional properties
known of these data
items called X in in in real world
applications. This is typically a kind
of an approach which is not really
commonly used in in basian optimization
but I I I think one should because
there's possibly information in these x
values that tells something about the c
as
well. So this is sort of the approach
that we have we have proposed. So now
illustrated in the context of molecule
optimization. So the sort of the middle
part is is similar with the existing
techniques except that uh when when we
represent the the molecules in the
latent space we do that by assigning a
latent variable this correlated prior.
This correlated prior is the same
additive CP that I I used earlier such
that now it depends on on the features
that we may have partially available
from from different molecules and and
the hope is that now the latent space is
automatically saved according to these
predictor variables C and X and and then
hopefully it makes it easier to to
predict the X or optimize sorry optimize
the C once the patent landscape
is shaped in an hopefully optimal
way. Okay. So the pod algorithm is is
something that we we train a GP prior
VAE with partially observed coariates. C
and X may or may not be partially
observed. Y values are are fully
observed. We obtain the latent
embeddings Z for these data items. We we
carry out the basian optimization in the
latent space. We have been using the the
expected improvement acquisition
function. One can use also other
acquisition functions. Then we we decode
the chosen data point Z prime to an
actual data item Y prime. Evaluate the
blackbox function to get the C C prime
and maybe also X prime if if that is
available. feed that again back to the
basin optimization loop and
continue and here are a couple of
examples how how this works. So uh the
first focus is on generating molecules
using the jungry VAE. This is probably
not the
state-of-the-art technique for for
molecules anymore but it doesn't really
matter. We we are giving the all models
the same VA architecture and then only
changing the changing the way we we
treat the latent variables. Uh the data
is from this zinc 250K and we assume
that only 1% of those have been
observed. So we have uh the and and the
goal is to optimize the uh soal
penalized lock b quantity of these
molecules and then uh only 1% of the
molecules has this feature known we are
using the this lo penalized lo p as one
hour of cover rates as well as
additional five features which we can
easily compute from the molecules that
we are we are modeling and then this is
sort of the party which is now
hopefully giving us a benefit in in this
basian
optimization and and here is a
comparison of of different techniques
uh over the number of basian
optimization steps that we we we take
and and then the penalized lo score on
on the y-axis and the purple line is is
the performance of of our model. So um
may maybe not u outperforming but I
would say that the competitive
performance relative to the other
techniques. Another example using
generating single variable mathematical
expressions using grammar VA. So
something kind of a maybe complicated if
you think think about optimization in
continuous domain but again the the VA
architecture gives us the latent
variables and and then the the basin
optimization is implemented in latence
base. So the target is is to find this
kind of expression and then the
objective is the MSC of this function in
in a certain range of inputs X. And then
sort of the the key innovation of our
technique is is to use this C value as
one of our partially observed coariates
as well as other coariates that we can
easily sort of obtain from these
expressions that we are we are
modeling. And again uh uh uh many
different techniques compared the the
purple one being here our model that
again performs quite
competitive. All right. So that was the
part two. That's the only sort of
uh finalized work that we have been able
to uh put together for the high high
dimensional basin optimization but
there's a sort of more in in sort of a
planning at the moment will be also
presented after a couple of weeks
together with Alexanders and done his
work the
same and then then the final
part I think I still have time for that
uh focuses on on on the fact that these
latent variable models cannot really
model temporal or dynamical
systems. Although it it turns out that
they are of course easy to extend the
direction as
well. And and the problem setting is is
something that uh we have high
dimensional observations why
uh of of dynamical systems of of a
dynamical system at arbitrary time
points and across many many
trajectories. So time points arbitrary
and and then the corresponding
measurements and then the measurements
in this case could be for example images
or or or single cell data as an
example and and the goal is to model the
data using a continuous time dynamics in
a in a low dimensional space. Now the
the latent spaces here is denoted by by
X and and the the um the the latent
space dynamics are now illustrated by
this uh line in in in two dimensional
space and and these are the high
dimension observations. This is
something that we would like to achieve.
Of course there are many different
techniques available already which can
do that. We are we are using the latent
neural OD as our sort of starting point
where the initial state in the latent
space is sampled from some prior
distribution. We sample the
parameters of the dynamics model
assuming that they also modeled uh
probabilistically and and then we solve
the intermediate or uh later time points
by solving the initial value problem of
the of
the dynamical system. essentially
numerically solving the the OD system in
the latence space starting from the
initial state all the way to the later
time points DI for each of the
measurement time points we then decode
the data using the decoder function uh
with samples from the exponential family
distribution. So the concept is shown
here on the right. Initial state sample
from from some base distribution. Then
we solve the initial value
problem or numerically integrate the OD
system decode the the latent days into
the uh
data. Okay. So that has that was
actually proposed already at the time of
the neural OD paper 2018 and and then
follow-up papers focusing on this latent
neural
ODS. Uh but what is challenging with
with these techniques is that the
training on on long trajectories can be
really slow and and unfortunately
unstable. So there's theoretical work
for the discrete time systems saying
that the the the sort of
the objective uh function in terms of
the liic constant can kind of grow
exponentially in in terms of the length
of the trajectory uh and and that's sort
of demonstrated here in in this uh
empirical evaluation. So the the plot at
the top shows the train loss uh over the
iterations of the training procedure
where we double the length of the
trajectory every 3,000 iterations. So we
optimize first double the length of the
tra trajectory and optimize and then
suddenly after certain time point the
optimization doesn't really work anymore
at all. Demonstrating that the the the
uh optimization simply becomes unstable.
mo most likely due to to unstable
gradients of this model. The bottom
figures illustrate
the what the loss landscape looks like
at these optimized positions. And then
this is obviously just a onedimensional
projection of really high dimensional
optimization landscape but sort of a
nicely uh agreeing with the intuition
that uh with longer trajectories the
optimization landscape becomes highly
highly multimodal.
So we have been proposing these kind of
a multiple suiting based approaches
where we split the lat and trajectories
into into short segments and that's not
a novel idea either. We would like to do
that probabilistically though so that we
can still sort of train these
probabilistic genative models and and
for that purpose we we have been
proposing this auxiliary suiting
variables s variables which are these uh
suiting points here in the in the latent
space and and then a reasonable prior
for these suiting variables which has
this kind of a first order marovian
structure such that
the next suiting point is always close
to the end point of the OD solution that
we obtained from the previous
time and and then the generality model
becomes something as as shown here. So
again we sample the dynamics parameters
the decoder parameters from from the
corresponding distributions. We we
sample the suiting states from this
continuity prior from the previous slide
and then always solve the intermediate
points using the initial value
uh solution of the corresponding OD
system such that we start from the
suiting variable and then integrate
forward in the lat and then decode the
the latent uh sorry the the data items
from the corresponding latent variables
that's sort of demonstrated here on the
on the
again difficult to handle anything
analytically. So we are relying on on
amortized variational inference. So the
target is is this uh joint distribution
of the dynamics and decoder parameters
as well as the shooting states given the
observations of the trajectory and and
then that is now approximated by a
variational
distribution which uh is factorizes into
uh components corresponding to the model
parameters and and then amortized part
for the suiting states.
Um and then if you think about it sort
of in terms of a VAE uh language here is
our generality model and and then now
the the uh in variational inference of
the suiting variables then gives you the
kind of encoder structure for for your
model. Okay.
Um so then the second important aspect
is is the specific type of attention
model uh attention based encoder model
to to be able to uh implement this both
efficiently and accurately. And we have
been proposing the the uh encoder which
is
u flexible and and efficient such that
it uh handles irregular time grids. So
the time points can be arbitrary in in
your measurements such that the encoder
generalizes to new time grids at test
time. It can handle long
trajectories. It allows us to do
parallelization as I'll show a bit later
and then handle noisy and partially
observed
data. and and the the encoder has this
kind of a three-step uh structure where
the first part compresses the high
dimensional data into some lower
dimensional representation. The
aggregation part is implemented by a
stack of attention layers using a
specific type of attention technique and
then then the the last part simply sort
of reads the parameters of the of the
varian
approximation. And if I have time I I'll
just try to quickly illustrate that how
this specific type of attention encoder
works. So the what is shown on the left
is the standard dot product attention
technique where we take the dot product
of the uh curies and
keys and then the corresponding softmax
to to get the weights for the values. We
we have been proposing a a time where
attention such that we are only looking
at a kind of a reasonable window around
the current time point that we are we
are modeling using a a time where
attention mechanism defined by by uh
this this formula which is illustrated
here. So that allows us to uh such that
the the attention model doesn't grow
arbitrarily large while the the length
of the trajectory uh increases.
We have also replaced the uh standard
positional encodings with continuous
relative positional encodings so that
the encoding of the position is now
positioned at the time point that we are
interested in in
modeling and and then again uh evidence
lower bound based uh training of the
model. You don't need to care about the
complicated expression. The point that I
wanted to make is that again it has the
same structure. The first two parts
correspond to the reconstruction of the
data from the latence and then the four
remaining parts uh implement the
regularization. The parts which are uh
highlighted in in red involve the
dynamics in the latent
space and and uh together with the
multiple suiting and the factorized
approximation for the for the uh suiting
variables we can solve all these or
these two terms in parallel which sort
of increases the efficiency quite a lot.
If you have a long trajectory, you you
just chunk it in into small parts and
and then the optimization of the entire
trajectory can be run in in
parallel and couple of simple toy cases
first to illustrate that how this works.
So pendulum is the first
example bouncing balls in a box. So the
the dynamics are defined by real physics
and then the observations are these
highdimensional image based observations
and then then the rotating am as a as a
a second additional
benchmark.
Uh and then this is just a quick note
that how well this our model can can
make the future predictions compared to
some existing neural OD processes or OD
to VA models. And then the blue one
seems to perform quite well across these
uh synthetic
benchmarks. And then this is sort of
effectively what the what model tries to
do. So this is the data high dimensional
trajectories. These are the
corresponding
predictions and and then we we can also
use these uh to to somehow quantify the
uncert kind of the amount of uncertainty
in the latent variables.
So, so this is now the the uh mockup
data from the Kaki Melon University
where where a person is wearing about
100 sensors at the joints and then then
it measures the 3D position of the
sensors and then the goal is then to
model the dynamics and obviously that's
difficult to do using parametric models.
So, but it can be easily done in in
latent space dynamics models. In this
case, the visualization is is done for
by using a 3D uh latent space where we
implement the the kind of a latent
neural OD system that I I I I proposed
and and then starting from the initial
state, we we sample the parameters and
initial states multiple times and and
then you can interpret these uh lines as
a samples from the posterior. sort of
demonstrating how the amount of
uncertainty increases while the person
walks further to the future and then
this is the corresponding then
reconstruction in in the actual data
space. Okay. And then
then now moving back to molecular
biology examples. So the the same kind
of a setting that I already explained.
So modeling now transcription dynamics
using single cell RNA sequencing the
setup is exactly the same that that you
are very well familiar with. So high
dimensional observations YTC of the
individual cells at individual time
points and each cell is measured only
once. And so we can't really use the
models directly as I explained but again
the kind of earth moving distance based
measures to to to
to kind of connect the predictions with
the data are are really
useful
and motivated by by actually many of the
existing techniques. We we just wanted
to test that how how how well our models
would would perform in in these kind of
tests by by
training the the our latent neural OD
using the signal cell uh data and and
now changing the loss to be completely
based on the process based loss in in
the data space as well as in in the
latent space. So this is also something
that is not finished yet but I'll just
show you the kind of pre preliminary
results and this is visually what what
is happening. This is not exactly
correct but uh the the predictions are
now the individual cells at different
time points which we connect to the
actual observations using thestein to
measure. We implement the same
waserstein loss also in the latent space
but I was not able to put that in in
this figure.
Sorry, sorry for that.
And and then we took a couple of uh data
sets from mouse and and and zebra fish
and and then simply compared our
modeling tool with one of
the I think state-of-the-art
uh um models called SC node and then
these are the uh the the time distances
for later time points in this time
series given the initial part of the
data and then how well we can predict
the population at at later times and and
measure the the performance via the time
distance. What
um trade off to these multiple shooting
points bring because let's say we want
to
model the dynamics all the way to X5
starting to starting from X1 but do we
need this as intermediate measurements
that we need to take? Yeah, that that's
a really good question and and then I I
think that in this particular uh example
case maybe the multiple shooting is is
not the key determinant of the
performance but we have been also trying
a kind of a different variance where we
we where we model both the sort of
indirectly the splicing as as well which
seems to further improve the the
performance a bit using the inronic
uh reads as
well. Yes, depending on the length of
the trajectory, the the importance of
the multiple shooting becomes more or
less significant. And and here is the
kind of the
illustration for what the uh true data
looks like when the data points are
colorcoded by the time points and then
the predictions and and then for the
mouse data it's seems to be performing
visually better whereas for the zro is
less. So but again this is not yet
finalized. So something that we are
still working. I want to conclude with a
really quick note that we have been also
extending these techniques to to spatial
temporal processes. So the dynamical
systems do not need to depend only on
time but maybe also on space and and
then we are talking about partial
differential
equations and uh we have been extending
these latent variable models to to sort
of a learn space-time continuous neural
PDS again from partially observed states
and here are some sort of a
illustrations of the physics systems
that that we have been considering. We
have also tested these techniques on on
some uh uh spatial trans transcrytoics
data
sets but maybe I can't really report
anything on those yet.
uh and then then kind of the last uh
model variant is is that we have been
also extending these to kind of really
extreme cases where the where the we are
we are interested in modeling
spatiotemporal dynamics as well as point
poser point process observations. So in
a typical setting when one talks about
the spia temporal modeling the
measurements come from a some sort of a
fixed grid but we we have been
considering a case where where the
measurement time points as well as the
locations are also random variables and
they depend on the underlying uh
dynamics and then this is something that
Valerie will also present after two
weeks in the same context.
So that was the part three. So we have
been working quite a long time on on
these latent variable neural or cosian
process difference equation
models and and then lately being also
focusing on on modeling transcription
and dynamics using these kind of
techniques both using dynamics model as
well as the correlation models that I
explained earlier and we would be happy
to discuss more about those if you are
interested in and then extended these
techniques to go to partial differential
equation type of systems. Would be
really cool to to try this on on spatial
transtomics if you have a temporal data
on from those kind of
systems and and then ultimately we would
be interested in in controlling these
systems. But this is something that we
haven't really had time or success so
far. But this is the the only
publication that we have been able to
put together so far.