Hello everyone and welcome to MIT
Startup Exchange demo day. Thank you for
being with us wherever you may be today.
I'm Marata Rodenstein, program manager
with MIT Startup Exchange and shortly
you will hear from eight exciting
startups. They're among those that have
more recently joined our program and so
you can meet them all here right here
right now.
Next,
um I will give a brief overview of our
program and then you will hear from the
startups. So as you might know MIT
startup exchange was created to support
MIT connected startups as they grow
expand and help solve some of the
world's greatest challenges and we do
this by fostering partnerships and
collaborations between the startups and
industry primarily members on the
industrial leazison program or ILP and
also the MIT innovation ecosystem and
beyond.
The startups in our program have a
strong connection to the institute. They
may be based on MIT licensed technology
or founded by MIT faculty, staff or
alumni. And they also may be vetted by
some of our MIT peers including the
engine, start nano or CEL startup
connect plus.
We have around 800 startups in the
program and they usually join at pilot
stage or beyond and they may represent
any sector and any geography. Here you
can see the breath of solutions of the
MIT startups and I've noted in bold
those that represent the startups here
with us today. Of course, we start with
AI and ML, big data and analytics,
sustainability and renewable energy and
life science and healthcare among
others.
So when it comes to value, everything
that we do is for the exposure of the
startups and for opportunities for
connection with industry. And we do this
in a variety of ways listed here and
also in a customized approach. For
example, we launch calls for startups.
We call these opportunities and they're
based on a corporate's priorities and
internal challenges. and startups can
apply on our website and if selected
they could work with you as an ILP
member to help you solve a problem that
you may be facing in your industry.
We also host one-on-one meetings, demo
days like today, other webinars and
conferences that have a um component of
a startup lightning talk segment and and
an exhibit. And we also host workshops
and trainings sometimes in conjunction
with our MIT peers.
And so what is demo day? So it's a
virtual forum to facilitate corporate
interactions with the industry ready
startups in our program with the goal to
explore potential collaborations and
partnerships and that this can happen
sooner rather than later. It's a short
and sweet approach. And so the format
today will consist of eight startups for
four minutes um presenting followed by a
couple of minutes of Q&A and then we'll
jump right into breakout rooms. So
please join us for that where you can
engage further with the startups. For
the Q&A part, I ask that you please post
your questions to the Q&A button at the
bottom of your screen indicating which
startup the question is for. And
throughout we want to keep this dynamic
and interactive. Please use the chat to
connect with the startups as well. So,
and as always, of course, um connect
with us if you need help uh reaching out
to the startups. My email is right there
and also it could be via your ILP
program director. We have several of
them joining today. So, thank you as
well for being here. And a couple of
final reminders before we start. The uh
presentations of the startups are being
recorded. And also at the end of the
event, you'll see a brief pop-up survey.
So, please help us with your feedback.