good morning I'm Josh Adler I'm the
founding CEO of wellsite
Navigator uh and a Sloan fellow graduate
class of
2013 what we do is provide a platform
for safe and efficient off-road
fieldwork
navigation imagine that you're driving a
4,000g fuel truck in West Texas to
deliver that fuel to a work site on a
50,000 an acre private Ranch you drive
off of the blacktop County Road through
a gate onto a maze of dirt and gravel
roads those dirt and gravel roads are
eroded they're uneven they're very
narrow for a giant fuel truck they're
pitted with mud puddles and the only
directions that you have are handwritten
notes from your dispatcher in the office
you've never been there before these
roads are not in Google Maps they're not
on any map there's no street signs
you're pretty much making a guesstimate
of which way you need to go you pick one
of these narrow dirt roads drive for a
few miles and you get stuck in a ditch
you climb out of the truck to figure out
why you're stuck you're inspecting the
truck your leg gets caught the truck
rolls over on you and you're
dead that really happened two years ago
for a contractor working for for a super
major in Texas in fact some version of
that happens every 3 days in the United
States just in Upstream oil fieldwork
not to mention all the other natural
resource Industries out there and other
kinds of field workor according to the
CDC vehicle incidents are the leading
cause the majority cause of Workforce
fatalities in energy work in the United
States over 100 per year that's a just
in oil field that is just in the United
States and what's the reason for most of
that it's because the workers in the
field don't have accurate realtime
driving directions for where they can go
safely and efficiently on authorized
routes also fieldwork Logistics are one
of the biggest wastes of money for
companies that do field work in
particular we found that the average
field worker spends about 30 minutes per
day lost on dirt roads it's pretty easy
math to find that that cost their
employers over $10,000 per worker per
year just in wasted labor Fuel and
maintenance cost and that's not to
mention the cost to the organization for
the loss of productivity for needless
emissions and for the risk and liability
costs associated with people getting
injured or doing damage to
property what if you could solve all
that by having a system that allows your
company to create the most efficient
safe and authorized routes from the
office or the field as realtime
navigational directions for that entire
Workforce including the
contractors that's what we do wellsite
Navigator ensures that your field
Workforce is always safe and never
lost in fact we are already the most
widely installed and used software in
the US oil and gas industry with over
500,000 individual installations at more
than 2,000 companies since we started
doing this in
2012 so what we do is we enable that
safe and efficient fieldwork Direction
by allowing companies to create and
optimize custom routes locations work
sites and the individual jobs people are
supposed to do convey them as real-time
nav a and also at the same time gather
realtime information from the field and
share that throughout the workforce as a
central geospatial knowledge database
this is a bit what that's looks like
this is a real product being used by
thousands of companies
today and then you can also generate
analytics and understand who is actually
following the directions who isn't who
is performing effectively in their job
and who should be reconsidered as I
mentioned we're already in a very large
portion of the US oil field industry
today and upstream and really what we're
hoping to do working with I mitp
partners and what we're here today for
is um we see an opportunity to expand
Beyond oil and gas to other natural
resource Industries Renewables power
infrastructure and maintenance uh even
construction and we also are eager to
start meeting companies that have uh
operations in other countries as today
were entirely US and Canada and so
please come and talk to us out uh in the
hallway after the presentation today
I'll be here all day and I look forward
to meeting you thank you very
much thank you Josh