So we have to move on to our last
speaker in this session and that is way
who is assistant professor at the center
for genomic mechanisms of Massachusetts.
Oh sorry genomic medicine of
Massachusetts general hospital and
Harvard medical school and associate
member of the Stanley Center for
Psychiatric Research Broad Institute of
Mid and Howard. Thank you very much for
the introduction and uh sorry I can't
can't be there due to co and um I'm
really grateful for the opportunity uh
to talk about our recent work that we
try to tackle some challenges when we
map genetic effects for highdimensional
molecular phenotypes at a single cell
resolution. So in this talk I'm going to
talk about uh EQL in the context of
single cell RNA sick and our work has um
can can be easily extended to other
molecular phenotypes. Um so uh
population scale single cell RNA
sequencing technology uh has helped us
uh to improve the EQL mapping by
connecting the uh genotypes to gene
expression at cell resolution. As you
can see, we can combine different cell
context to understand the genetic
regulation on gene expression at a
higher resolution. And then in the past
several years, there are more and more
single cell EQL studies have been
published. So as we can tell from this
plot, the y-axis axis shows the number
of individuals in each study and the uh
size of each dot uh reflects the average
number of cells per individual in those
studies. And the dot up here is the 1K1K
study published in 2022 and in which on
average 1,00 immune cells uh from each
of the 10,000 individuals have been sequ
RNA sequenced for the gene expression
and these cells um can be grouped to uh
14 different uh immune cell groups cell
types. Uh so as we see that the data
sizes are rapidly increasing and this
year we can see fingen has uh sequenced
uh one 10 million single nuclei from
more than 1100 uh blood donors and which
increases the uh number of cells per
donor by 10 times more and the um the
10k 10k study which is the next step of
1k1k and in their first phase
um published uh this year and they
sequenced 5 million PBMC's from uh close
to 2,000 donors which uh further
improves the number of donors by twice.
So as we can see that although this
large amount of single cell RNA
sequencing data are becoming available
and typically and we still need to
harmonize um and aggregate those cell
level read counts to donor level uh as
some metrics such as some mean or medium
across all cells per each donor. So we
can use existing EQL mapping tools uh
for the genetic mapping uh which leads
to several limitations and I'm listing
two of them here. The first one we uh
actually ignores the whole spectrum of
readouts from cells. Uh instead we just
use the single value and ignore the
share structure and uh variations across
cells. Uh this can lead to reduced the
power. And then second one we uh treat
all the cells um as identical repeats
and then we um just to simply ignore the
cell context and different cell
annotations and then lose the
opportunity to uh detect those genetic
regulations which can be heterogeneous
and we call dynamic EQL effects. So in
today's talk and I'm going to go through
two uh recent methods we have developed
to tackle those different uh limitations
and then I'm going to go uh also
introduce this really uh exciting study
conducted by Molina's group uh which
generates uh human ado edocide village
with different stimulation applied uh to
provide really fantastic opportunities
for us to uh ask which disease risk
relevant variants are linked to cell
state and stimulation or donor level uh
context EQL map EQL.
Um so there are several challenges when
we try to map EQTLs at single cell
resolution and the first one is we need
to uh directly model those read counts
from uh cell level. So we need to model
repeat and complex data structure and
then we cannot simply assume um they uh
follow normal distribution as we can uh
see that most of the genes their read
counts actually are quite scaled and
they are uh discrete read counts
and then as the data size are
continuously growing and we need a
really fast and scalable tools to be
able to analyze those uh single cell RNA
sick data and And the last one is um as
the number of donors have been increased
in these studies uh which allow us to
detect those rare and less frequent
genetic variations uh for EQL mapping
which have been largely underststudied
in previous studies and the uh single
variant test is underpowered for those
genetic variations. So we need to have
efficient approach to analyze them and
uh there are some pioneer work uh try to
detect eqls and also context dependent
eqls at a single cell on a sick data and
uh as we can see they have successfully
identify uh eqls u by directly modeling
read counts and while suffering from
different limitations and the shared
limitation they have is they are not
efficient enough. So usually um they
need some hierarchical approach to
conduct the analysis
and um so as we given those different
challenges I've described and there's no
scalable and efficient computational
tools uh exist to handle all of those
challenges simultaneously for us to
conduct EQTL mapping using single cell
RNA sick uh which motivates uh our work.
So if we take a another look at those
challenges, we realize that they
actually uh they're actually quite
similar to those we observed in in GIW
was for human disease and traits when we
analyze large scale bio banks and for
example in GW was we need to model uh
population substructure sample
relatedness between individuals and uh
we uh when we when the traits are not
continuous traits and we need to model
those binary phenotypes
uh countbased phenotypes and then as the
uh bio bank size keep growing and the
scalability and efficiency is also a
challenge for the G-W was tools and uh
for rare variations actually GW was
field has has grows really uh maturely
and we have investigated those uh rare
var r v r v r v r v r v r v r v r v r v
r v raration associations with human
disease and trace uh substantially. So
uh based on these similarities and uh
given that our previous work uh to
develop a suit of tools for tackling
similar challenges and testing common
and rare variations for human disease
and traits in large bio banks and we
decide to leverage this uh efficient and
scalable tool infrastructure and to uh
apply them to uh EQL mapping. So and
then we uh our first tool is called Sage
QTL and which is leveraging the Sage
GWAS tool uh to efficiently mapping EQLS
at a single cell resolution and as we
we're listing here it's a collaborating
work with Anna Kumer who is part of the
1K1K team and we're trying to use
efficient poismics model to model the uh
complex data structure uh and then we uh
leverage some uh approximation and
computation approaches to make it
scalable and then we uh try to use the
setbased test which has been commonly
used for uh human disease and traits and
to uh group rare variations based on
functional units and testing them uh
together. So for the sake of time I'm
not going to go to those math details of
our tool and we have used um three
representative cell types in 1k1k across
different uh cell type abundance levels
to show that sageql has well calibrated
false discovery rates. And then these
are the benchmark we have when we try to
analyze uh 1K1K data. As we can see to
analyze all 14 cell types and uh if we
we want analyze all 20,000 genes in each
cell type and you can uh you can use 200
CPUs and finish the work in one day. And
then um due to the reduce of the uh
overhead in reading genotypes and if you
want to uh do the trans eql mapping for
all genes and which means you uh conduct
a genome wise scan for 8 million genetic
markers for each of the 20,000 genes and
uh an extra hundreds of CPU hours is
needed and I think the computation cost
uh here uh is not a bottleneck and the
bottleneck here is how do we efficiently
store uh those um 20,000 time 14 uh G-W
was summary statistics
and then as expected we have observed by
directly modeling single cell read
counts and our tool can identify uh
about 48% more ees than the pseudo bulk
approach using tensor QTL so the
improvement is uh across all cell types
and we can also observe that number of E
genes increases as number of cells
increases with both methods.
And uh based on these vin diagrams of
the E genes identified by two methods
and we can see uh SQTR has successfully
identify those uh E genes that identify
by pseudobul approach with additional
ees identified. Um so uh for example in
the monocytes and this is a locus um
from the G-W was for IBD and uh as we
can see when the top the locosis plot on
the top shows the results from sage QTL
and then the uh top the plot on the
bottom is from the tensor QTL. So we can
see uh by um conducting EQL at a single
cell resolution we can successfully
identify this uh this EQTL uh which has
been missed by the pseudo bug which
didn't really pass the significant
cutoff and then uh this EQL is actually
monocy specific and which is not
observed in other cell types
and uh so if we take a look at all the E
genes uh identified across 14 cell types
and we see that about uh 44% from the
unique E genes are specific to a single
cell type but note that this type of
analysis had this limitation it is it
can be confounded by power unbalance in
different cell types due to uh cell type
abundance
and uh further we have uh uh this
analysis was done by Anglicia from the
1K1K group And we try to uh
collocicalized our EQL with GWAS summary
statistics and show that uh sage QTL
identify additional immune disease
associated lowi that are immediated by
gene expression
and then uh this heat map pl heat map
and shows the trans eqrl regions that we
identified in the naive CD4 plus T-
cells and the uh vertical ical line
shows the location of the EQTL signals
and the horizontal line shows the genes
that we're we're testing and uh as an
example we can see that uh by uh based
on the genome Y scan for uh EQ for the
gene expression and we see that for
these two genes the gene MRPL32
not only has a cis EQL identified but
also a trans EQL uh on chromosome 16
which is a cisql of another gene spns1.
So it seems these two genes are both
involved in mitochondrial pathways.
And then for rare variations uh we're
trying to group rare variants uh within
each genes and of course we can annotate
them at in different uh in different
ways based on functional units such as
epigenetic features uh pathways and then
we use different setbased tests to
account for uh different scenarios of uh
effect directions and the signal sparity
uh to improve our test power. And then
we identified uh over 5,500 E genes uh
with rare or less frequent variant
signals. And then after conditioning on
the nearby common EQLs, 21% of them
remain significant. So that means um
they can uh contain know independent EQL
signals u that are uh different from the
common EQLs.
And then uh Lingong Hu who is a very
talented uh associate computational
biologist abroad and conducted the more
uh analysis uh try to comb apply uh sql
in different data sets and one is
another PBMC uh data set and then the
other one is the retino data sets and
both of them have relatively smaller
sample size u which with around 100
donors but uh we have successfully seen
the um better performance of Sage QTL
over the pseudo bulk approach. And then
uh more recently uh we have successfully
applied sqdl to 10k 10k and finen which
are the two of the largest data sets
from the single cell RNA sick. So we
have made this uh tool an open-source R
package and people can apply and then
given the this this work that we show um
the better performance uh to detect
EQTLs when we model single uh single
cells um directly instead of pseudob
them and um we still see those
challenges because uh you know limited
overlap has been observed between GW was
loi and eqls There have uh different
there there have been different
hypothesis to explain this limited
overlap and one possibility is the um
context dependent EQL which means
probably uh the EQLs that are more
relevant to GW was or human disease uh
can only be observed in certain context.
uh for example uh the the cell level
context can include uh cell types and
cell uh transition differentiation and
different cell states
and uh again the pioneer work has uh
tried to uh identify those context
dependent EQLs and for example the
Nathan at all uh study has successfully
identified the dynamic T- cell state
dependence um uh EQLS uh that
the collocicalized with the disease
lossi and um and then again these
methods uh still suffer the efficiency
issue. So uh they usually require to uh
first scan the main effects eqls and
then uh only conduct try to conduct
context dependent eqls for those uh
significant main uh genotype eqls which
can make some signals that we can see
from the uh later slides. And so and
then given this this uh challenge and we
decide to extend our sage QTL framework
to uh detect those uh context
dependent eqls. We called it sageql
dynamic which is uh led by uh the
another talent um associate
computational biologist uh Cristiana
Louu and then uh together with Anna
Kumer. So um I'm going to uh go through
really quickly about the details.
Basically we try to model the uh context
dependent eqls at the interaction term
of genotype with the context while uh
accounting for the different gene
expression levels due to context uh
values uh through the fixed effects and
also random effects in our posom mix
model. And then we also try to combine
different uh uh context dependent
signals using a variance component based
test scat test to so uh some users if
they require and then then they can
reduce the testing burden. And then in
1K 1K B cells experiment and we uh try
to analyze two different B cell subtypes
and we include the donor level context
age and gender and cell level context
pseudo time which measure the cell
transition from B naive cells to B
memory cells and then uh the cell cycle
score which measure uh the cell cycle
stage of of of each cell and these are
uh different QQ plots from different
tests uh for uh G by different context
and then also the main G effects and
also the scat test which combined all
the effects together. So uh if we take a
look at the main effects and of course
as expected and we can see uh when we
analyze all uh the two different B cell
types together we're able to identify
more uh EQLS simply based on the main
effects
and uh if we take a look at the G by
cell cycle score and this is the E genes
we identified uh with uh that shows the
significant
uh cell cycle dependent EQLs and then on
the left we can see uh the alilic
effects actually changes um across
different sores and then as a checkup
and we uh plot the total read counts of
that gene to show that uh this
observation is not uh this this uh
context dependent eql is not uh
confounded by different gene expression
levels uh across s scores and appar
Apparently this gene is uh its function
has uh is really tightly related to uh
the S phase of the cell cycle u to
ensure accurate uh DNA replication. And
another check is the G by s pseudo time
uh which measures the transition from
naive B cells to memory B cells. And we
have seen that there are 25 uh E genes
when we test uh this context. And then
uh as you can see some of them are not
uh detect by uh if you by the main uh
genotype effects and uh as one example
the need one gene uh which is uh has a
really close function relationship with
the immunereated disease. As you can see
the p value for the main G effects is
not significant all but we see the uh
significant p values for the pseudo time
by G. And then if you take a closer look
and you can see that actually the EQL
effects has different uh uh effect
directions in two B cell subtypes. And
then when we combine them together and
only test the genotype effects and they
can be cancelled each other and only be
uh seen when we can when we uh test the
G by pseudo time dynamic EQL.
And then uh those E genes that
identified by both uh genotype and the G
by pseudo time tends to have the similar
uh consistent effect direction but a
different magnitude. So um and then I
want to emphasize that uh the you know
the 1K1K data set probably is not the
most ideal data set for us to look at
the dynamic EQLs and fortunately
Molina's group has conducted this study
that uh actually perfectly um matched
our goal which is uh uh let's check the
disease relevant relev risk relevant uh
variants that are linked to different
cell state and different uh context uh
uh specific um equity mapping. So um
this work has been done by uh E and uh
Hin uh from uh Molina's group. If you
want to know more details, please check
uh E's poster uh number 40 uh this
afternoon. And uh so basically our goal
is to uh discover genetic mechanism re
relevant to uh metabolic disease
development in the context of
environmental cues. So as we can see
there can be um different glucose levels
and then uh hypoxia and free fatty acid.
So uh it has uh selected 118 donors from
this cell gem bank and uh then uh apply
four different stimulations to uh the
adipose tissue derived messencho stem
cells and then after differentiation and
these cells can be uh differentiated to
two four different cell types and um I
would mention like to mention that this
edible side village um is approach is
really costefficient for us to study uh
stimulence dependent EQLs
uh because they can be uh sequenced
together and then uh demultiplex plexed
by some uh computational algorithm. So
in the end we have uh single nucleotide
uh RNA sequencing coupled with single
nucleotide at tech sequencing from over
uh 300,000
total nuclei
and uh then uh we can see that the four
in the four different cell types and we
can uh have different cell states and
then leverage different stimulations to
apply sageql dynamic and to check uh the
EQTLs from the main genotype and EQTLs
under different stimulations. And these
are our U preliminary results from the
adolesite population. And um this plot
shows the number of E genes we identify
from the main genotypes and also from
the uh different context dependent um
EQLs. And uh our main observation is
that uh compared to the sex and age
which are donor level context and our
stimulation dependent uh context
actually identify way more uh eqtls than
uh simply uh check the sex and age uh
status
and then uh after collocicalized with
the relevant chiwas and we uh have
successfully observed that the single
cell context EQTLs identified by Sage
QTL dynamic uh has uh is more uh way way
more enriched in in the G-W was losi uh
than the pseudo approach which we try to
uh aggregate cells from each different
simulation and different contexts
together and then test them at at a
donor level.
And uh also we want to mention that
chromatin accessibility QTLs actually
collocicalized with more uh GWA signals
than EQTLs and which is as expected
because there are way more uh genome
region has been checked in the uh CAQTL
mapping than the EQL mapping. And here's
an examp interesting example that shows
us the value of uh stimulus dependent
EQLs. So as we can see um when we this
is the GW was locus from the insulin
sensitivity index adjusted BMI and then
uh we if we only check the genotype only
in edible site and we didn't really
observed any EQL signals and then uh the
EQL signal is only observed when we
leverage the low glucose context. So
this EQL collocicalized with G-W was
locus and is low glucose uh dependent
and this gene apparently um has a close
relationship with the uh insulin
sensitivity and advocite
differentiation.
So uh in summary uh we are uh developing
tools and applying the tools and
collaborating with Molina's group to uh
uh further exam the context or
stimulation specific EQLs and hopefully
we can identify disease risk variants
that are regulate gene expression under
different uh uh environmental
stimulation and context that can be that
can be uh help further explain uh the
G-W was signals that we observed for
different disease end points
and uh I would like to thank all the
collaborators from the government
institute of medical research from
Australia and the 1K1K 10k 10k 10k team
and then uh our collaborators and my
senior mentors from broad m and uh fam
in the finen study and also uh Molina's
group and other folks in the nova Bordic
Foundation Center
and of course the uh fantastic postocs
and ACBs uh for their hard work.
Thank you very much um for a very
interesting presentation. I think we
have time just for one question maybe
two
tunas from the University of Copenhagen.
Um yeah thank you for really really for
a super inspiring presentation. I was
wondering in terms of um power
calculations can you just give me some
intuition about the number of samples
needed to um do those particular
analyses in the tissues you were
discussing here?
>> Yes. So our lowest sample size we have
tried is the 80 uh is 90 uh sample 90
donors and then uh we uh I think we've
try tried tried our approach in uh 50
donors and we still see some improvement
uh but note that uh if we take a look at
a single cell read counts and um many
genes have really spar really high
sparity level and we have lots of zeros
in the in the in those vectors. So uh we
have have to apply a cutoff that we
require uh genes that are expressed in
at least 10% of the donors to conduct
EQR mapping. So I think that that that
standard has been commonly used uh in
our uh days uh single cell analysis uh
studies. Um so uh we need to keep in
keep in mind that uh when we decrease
the sample size and we might we might be
able to uh test fewer genes.
>> One last question.
No more questions. I just have one quick
question. So you also look at the the
direction of expression uh with respect
to the rare EQ tails. Can you say
something more general about that? Did
you mostly observe an increased or
decreased expression or how did they
affected the expression in the cell
types?
>> Yeah. Uh that's a great very interesting
question. So uh in our uh main study we
haven't really take a closer look at the
effects of the uh rare single rare
variance effects on uh gene expression.
And then uh we so there are different
types of tests we have conducted. Burden
test is simply combine uh the genotypes
of the rare variations and scat test
actually uh is more robust to different
uh variance uh directions in the testing
set and then later we have um checked
the single variance effect sizes and we
see uh if I remember it correctly most
of them have the decreased uh effect
size uh effects um so they're they tend
to decrease the gene expression
But we need to uh as as we know that
statistically uh the effect the effect
size estimation for rare variance is
quite challenging. So uh to be able to
have a you know solid conclusion we have
to uh make sure our single variant
effect size estimation uh is uh further
uh validated.
>> Okay. Thank you. Okay. So I think we
should end by giving applause to all the
three speakers in this session. Thank
you very much.