They often say it doesn't take a rocket
scientist, but what if it does? What
does it take to make a career in
launching vehicles into outer space?
>> Arrow Astro Professor Carrie Cowboy of
MIT tells her story about how she got
started and what she finds most
exciting.
So I was working in college and um I was
there on um federal work study. So I I
you know had to get funding to go to
college and didn't didn't have another
way to do it. Um and so I'd been working
in the libraries and I saw this
advertisement um for somebody needed an
undergraduate researcher to help with a
Mars rover program and that turned out
to be professor Steve Squires at Cornell
who ended up launching the the Mars
rover. So I started interning with him
and um was working on Mars rovers with
Steve Squires for a while and then um I
was in electrical engineering and got
into satellites. Went to grad school in
that. So that's kind of how I got
involved. It was it seemed like a cooler
job. I love being in the library, don't
get me wrong. Definitely a book word. My
first my I'm a bookworm and my first
word was book, but like
but the rovers were were a lot of fun.
>> But but you love this. You love
satellites. Why?
>> It is challenging. Um, it is one of the
most mentally challenging, toughest
fields I've ever been in because when it
breaks, it is gone. And it is really
hard um to
obtain funding, get funding to do it,
get the hardware built, have it working,
get it to the rocket, have it to survive
the rocket launch, get up to orbit, and
then you're able to do things and get
perspectives that really there's no
other way to do it. And you're also able
to answer science questions um like for
astronomers and astrophysicists or
people who are doing remote sensing on
Earth that you can't get that data any
other way. Um so that and that part's
really rewarding. Watching a rocket
launch is worth a good five years of
working your butt off. I would say like
if I had to give the trade like just
having a rocket launch, feeling the
blast and watching knowing that you know
your spacecraft is on there and then you
have to run back and make sure it works
but like that it's on there and it's
going up is like one of the coolest
feelings ever. So there's a lot of joy
and pride and um skill building and
challenge in in in the field. So that
that's one of the reasons why why I why
I love it even though it's really
frustrating a lot of the time.
>> As you do your work here at MIT, can you
see what the next big thing is likely to
be?
>> Um it's it's exciting. You never know
what the next big thing is, but some of
the things that I think are exciting are
um the ability of satellites to
communicate directly to cell phones.
Now, I know um Aridium and the Aridium
phones have been a thing for a while,
but directing connecting directly to
existing consumer electronics without
modification, your iPhone um is
happening. And so they're essentially
showing um there are multiple companies
now who are starting to show that you
can actually take the technology that
are normal cell towers on the ground and
put them in lower Earth orbit and they
will work with your phone. And so we
have some search and rescue signals and
partnerships between um companies um
like Apple Global Star and there are a
few other companies that are working in
this space to do direct to cell phone.
Um I think that's going to be really
interesting um as as as time evolves um
especially as we have more autonomous
vehicles and people are you know needing
entertainment and data in in different
places because they they have more time
to use it. Um I think also on orbit uh
getting to the point where we have more
compute on orbit. Right now satellites
mostly are run by um not very
sophisticated computers. Um they're
they're getting better um and they're
starting to use more commercial
technology, more of the um Nvidia chips
and AMD chips on orbit. Um but when
we're developing it's really hard to
only just take pictures and then send
them all down to the ground. So you have
a lot of data that in the normal mode of
operations you take a lot of data and
you communicate it by radio usually
because of weather all down to the
ground and then you process it on the
ground and then you tell your satellites
what to do next. So there's a cycle of
getting data down to the ground and it's
hard to get data down to the ground. Um
getting frequency licenses is difficult.
It's expensive. Requires a lot of
management. Um requires a lot of power
on board. Um, so putting computers on
board that can survive on board and
running now some of the new AI models so
you can take the picture on board. You
have a model that can decide whether or
not what you wanted in the picture is in
the picture. If it's in the picture, it
prioritizes it. If it's not in the
picture, it throws it out. If it's a
cloudy picture, it throws it out and
saves only the things you really wanted
and then sends it back down. Um, also
getting the satellites to communicate
between each other so that they can tell
each other, hey, I finished this task,
here's the next in the task list, passed
back to you, kind of like playing tag
instead of waiting for that satellite to
tell the ground and the ground to tell
everybody what the new plan is. So being
able to replan, retask, um, and to be
able to make decisions about what is
good and bad data dynamically will be
new and exciting.
One of the things Professor Cowoy and
her team of grad students is working on
is a sort of robot that can be launched
into orbit and then assemble satellites
in space to avoid the rough and tumble
of the launch itself.
>> All right. So, um, so this is a project
that's called orbital locker. Um, one of
the challenges about space is that you
have to get everything to orbit. And to
get to orbit has to go in a rocket and
rockets are very vibrating, dynamic,
loud, they shake everything a lot. So
>> during the launch
>> during the launch, yeah, it's for those
first couple, it's only a couple
minutes, but they're very important
minutes. And so everything we do about
satellites, we pack them in tight. We
glue everything down. Everything's tied
down, latched down, you know, locked in.
so that nothing breaks um and most of
the time um when it's going up in the
rocket um and then when we get to orbit
the you know fairing opens we get to
orbit the satellites deploy it it's in
orbit the solar panels will unfurl um
but you basically have the thing you
built on the ground um what we were
thinking is wouldn't it be great if you
could put
a platform in orbit that
was packed with things that don't break
when they're on a rocket. So, very
simple components that you can just stow
away and you had these kind of robust
robots that can unpack it themselves,
but then they can build whatever they
want. Once they get up on orbit, there's
no shaking once you're on orbit. It's
very quiet.
>> So, it's a kit.
>> Yeah, it's like a kit. It's a kit where
the only thing that has to survive the
rocket launch are these um XYZ, so three
axis robots that move around and an arm
that snaps everything together. And um
as long as these elements are robust
enough to not get destroyed or damaged
in the launch um you can go up to orbit
and build something as big as you want.
>> But you have to program in advance what
the robot has to do assemble in what
order and things, right?
>> Yes. So there's a lot of algorithm work
and software work and that. But the nice
part about this is the platform on orbit
you can still talk to. You can reprogram
things on orbit. You can give it
different directions if you want to. You
just need to make sure you kind of know
what's in your warehouse. So it's kind
of like almost a a warehouse of hardware
that you could use on orbit to assemble
things and deploy them and make them as
big and as complicated as you want
without having to fit in the, you know,
the couple meters. Um, I think you know
if we get Starship up to six meters um
of space that you have in a rocket, you
could go well well beyond that and not
have to pre-plan everything to unfurl
and deploy. You could just build it the
way you wanted it as big as you wanted
um once you get up there.
>> Is this a prototype? Has this actually
been used?
>> This is a prototype. So this this has
been used um so this recently in May was
on a zero gravity launch. So the
graduate students, James and Laya, who
are working on it to get on one of those
um planes that do the parabolic flights.
And so you have microgravity for, you
know, a few seconds, 30 seconds at a
time. And so they had the robot working
there. And they they actually um learned
a lot about cord management. So wires
don't behave this. They don't lay down
like like this when they're in gravity.
Like they're kind of held down, but when
they're on orbit, they move around a lot
more. And so we had to um update our
wire management systems. Um and then
we'd like to get this to be a prototype
on orbit um on the space station so it
could be inside the station and we could
start to demonstrate it or on a free
flyer on its own satellite um later. So
that's that's kind of what we're hoping.
>> That does it for us here at Wall Street
Week. I'm David Weston. See you next
week for more stories of capitalism.
[Music]