we've learned some amazing things about
woodpeckers when they Peck they hit the
tree going at about 15 M an hour and
they endure decelerations of up to 1500
G all to eat to court to make nests and
to store food for their families but the
answer to how they withstand these
decelerations when they Peck is really
quite simple the deceleration that the
brain can withstand without injury
depends on its size this is an example
of a scaling law the smaller the brain
the larger the deceleration that it can
withstand scaling laws govern many
phenomena in nature for instance there's
a scaling relationship between the speed
of flight and the weight of a flying
object and this scaling log governs
everything from the tiniest little gnat
to large birds like swans and even up to
the largest Plains like Boeing 747s
scaling laws are Universal and they
describe many many processes in life for
more MIT moments from MIT open learning
like subscribe or follow