Good morning everybody. It's great to be
here with you. Uh I'm Michael Carney.
I'm uh general partner at the Engine
Ventures. I'm gonna I'm gonna pivot the
conversation away from the application
layer of AI that Paul just talked about,
I think, very eloquently and excitingly
into how AI is a real forcing function
for basically everything happening in
the broader economy around the
translation of breakthrough science and
engineering that I think about. Um, I'll
start and it's great to see many
familiar faces and I've talked through
the story of the engine with many of you
in the past. Um but I'm just take you
back uh to remind you all 15 10 years
ago in 2015 um the the venture landscape
for translation of breakthrough science
was very different. um and things,
ideas, inventions were sitting on the
shelves in labs, not translating from
the academic realm into the commercial
realm. And Raphael Rafe, the president
of MIT at the time, wanted to do
something about that because MIT's
mission is ultimately one of global
impact. Uh and so he set out uh to solve
that problem. That problem was well
articulated in a in a paper out of the
MIT energy initiative around venture
capital and clean techch but it had
broader implications across deep tech
altogether making the case that venture
capital was not the right instrument for
for bringing these technologies out of
the lab. Um I think interestingly and
I'm friends with Ben and Verun uh and
Libby who were on that paper and Frank
um all of whom now work in venture
capital or incle techch startups uh who
have been venture venture funded. So the
the world has truly changed from that
moment. Um Raphael set up the engine as
an institution to solve some of the
frictions in that translation story. Um
the engine came was born out of the
president's office at at MIT as an
institution with multiple parts. The
first part was a venture capital fund
with the mandate to fund breakthrough
science and engineering but with the
understanding that things that would
change the world and ultimately be um
pillars of of the economy would take a
little bit longer than some of the
softwarebacked startups um that have had
emerged in in the ecosystem. uh and that
patient capital was necessary early on
to help those companies get to scale.
The second element of it was an infra in
infrastructure. So uh and we have the
engine ventures and we have the engine
accelerator down the road 750 Main
Street. We have a home for startups that
are working on deep tech. uh 300,000
square feet of space uh for for
companies that are doing life science,
chemistry, clean tech, robotics uh and
and AI underlying all of that uh to go
and live in the early days of company
formation with the goal of accelerating
the pace of experimentation. And then
across those two implementations, the
venture fund and the infrastructure,
there's a set of programming to help
early entrepreneurs
get into market. And then there's
network building around all of the
stakeholders that are necessary for
those companies to be successful. That
was the experiment that Raphael set up
back in 2017 when he launched the engine
out of MIT. We are now eight years in
and I'll tell you a little bit about
where we've come and I think where we're
going. Uh on the venture side, we have
funded about 65 companies across three
broad categories. The first is energy.
The second is human health. The third is
advanced systems and infrastructure. And
if I'm being candid, the third bucket is
a catchall for breakthrough science and
engineering that applies to everything
that isn't in human health or in energy.
Um, but I think primarily you we have
seen a lot of concentration in some of
the AI hardware um the chips, robotics,
etc. that that are prominent today. Um
so we've invested across three these
three broad sectors. Um
and our portfolio has grown quite
significantly over that time. Um raising
over seven billion dollars. We're now
investing out of our third core fund. Uh
we have about a billion just north of a
billion under management uh to support
these companies as they are scaling. Um
so we're we're eight years or eight
years really into this experiment that
MIT set up. uh and I think the the the
the returns on that experiment we'll
we'll know but we won't know till 2035
20 240 um whether or not it has been
successful but I think we have early
proof points of that success um we have
proof points on the capital side and the
company growth side and and a lot of
these companies are thriving and and
expanding into global markets but I
think equally important is we have proof
points on the human capital side. So
over the last 20 years and some of you
know this very well, this ecosystem has
developed a very robust pipeline for
life science startups uh capital for
those startups and a very close
connection between those startups in the
corporate world. All of the many of the
life science corporates majors are are
located based have have a facility here
in Cambridge probably within 500 ft of
this building. um we are beginning to
and and I think importantly
because of that we see a lot of fluid
labor mobility between the large
corporate world and the startup world
that is a real important s symbol of
health of the ecosystem itself. Um when
you have companies that can recruit
executive talent out of large companies
there's a signal about the the
reliability and the the health of that
ecosystem that people are willing to
make the jump into startups. as I see it
when we see that fluidity I have a lot
more confidence and I think the
individuals have a lot more confidence
making the jump into startups it's a
signal that if one startup fails there
is another one to go to and another one
after that and you can build a career
doing that in a way that you can't when
there's not a really robust ecosystem
around you we are beginning to see that
outside of life sciences so in energy in
robotics uh in in AI hardware chips
fetonics etc this area has become I
think a really important place for
people to build careers in these sectors
and that in itself is a signal of the
success of of the of the experiment
Raphael launched uh eight years ago. So
alongside that, venture capital dollars
have begun to flow into the sector in a
fairly robust way, climbing through the
co years uh and being relatively
uh I think reliably resilient uh in
recent years when venture markets have
pulled back uh from a lot of these
sectors and I think that is because the
the opportunities that these sectors
provide remain large uh and and um
exciting for investors as as people are
going forward. Now there's a lot of
variance here and we'll get into that
and what I think the next five years
look like will be telling uh for for
many of these sectors. We'll get into
that in a little bit. Um there is a new
landscape emerging uh and four key
themes that we track uh that are
affecting these companies and these
sectors. Um, you heard from Paul a lot
about AI. Uh, and that you can't escape
a board meeting, a newspaper, uh, any
headline that doesn't include AI today.
And that should raise some red flags.
Um, but it is also something we all have
to kind of co be cognizant of. Um,
beyond the application layer, I think
where Paul was focusing a lot of his
presentation, AI as a general purpose
technology is being you being used
across industrial sectors. um to improve
productivity, to improve efficiency, to
reduce costs. Um correspondingly, energy
demand to power the inference and the
training for AI has has is is escalating
in a way that we have not seen on the
energy side in over 25 years. So demand
going up is a massive driver of economic
activity and it allows startups to
compete in a way particularly on the
energy side that they have not been able
to before uh in in the last 30 years or
so. Um so that's super exciting. Second
and we'll get into more details there.
Second is uh you may acknowledge that
there's a new administration in
Washington and the game is changing in
many different ways and finding signal
from the noise coming out of the uh the
news every day is difficult. Uh so we've
had to spend some time there but I think
there is there is uh some clear insight
now that you can drive and and take a
look across portfolios to be productive.
Um and we'll see where that goes. Um the
third is that mature deep technologies
have now been established, have been
successful and provide a very clear
roadmap for how a startup doing deep
tech can reduce cost, scale and increase
returns for their shareholders. Um we've
seen it in in energy and solar and
batteries. Uh we've seen it in in um
life sciences with AlphaFold and we've
certainly seen it on the chip side uh
with some of the largest companies in
the world. Um but despite that there is
a growing disconnect in the macro
realities of the economy that we that I
see and the reality of venture markets
and we'll get into that as as we go
here. So starting with the top um uh
Paul took you back 250 years. I'm only
going to take you back 250 years. um
innovate and and then and candidly I
think actually this would be a pretty
linear chart from two 2500 years ago to
1700 AD. Um but innovation really
started with the industrial revolution.
It has had epoes of growth and
acceleration in that time and we are now
at the very beginning of the next scurve
that is going to launch productivity
forward and that uh will impact the
economy at large in every sector within
it just as all of these other ones did
over the last 250 years. Um,
AI is driving the largest construction
boom, the largest economic mobilization
that we have seen in the United States
since World War II. This isn't just in
software, it is across the board. And it
is massively shifting the contours of
the economy uh and the landscape for
companies that are going in. So just as
an example, uh some of our companies on
the energy side used to be selling power
or working with utilities who um you
know are not the fastest movers and now
they're selling to Microsoft and Google
and Meta and Nvidia who move at the rate
of software innovation.
So being able to keep up with that is a
is a new challenge for these companies
as they're going forward. Um Paul
mentioned this a little bit so I'm not
going to harp on it but innovation is
unfolding faster than ever. It took Jack
Chat GPT just uh two months to hit 100
million users. Uh and you can see the
comparison across some of the prior uh
software startups but that is
accelerating the speed at which
companies need to need to operate. Um,
and the Magnificent 7's cash flow,
orders of magnitude larger than it was
previously, is being reinvested into a
lot of the foundational pieces of AI,
the energy demand that that comes along
with it, the hardware for the chips for
that they are necessary for training our
modules, etc. Um
Jensen Hang suggested that over the next
five years he expects that there will be
three to four trillion dollars invested
in the AI infrastructure opportunity and
as I look at different projections for
what that looks like I'm not sure
anybody has a real clear sense it is
growing rapidly uh and we'll we'll see
it's g but it is it is certainly going
to continue to grow.
Um
however as I mentioned the hardware
innovation cycle is two to three years
the software innovation cycle and and
it's very hard to move that needle right
that that is mostly has physical
constraints the software innovation
cycle is rapid it is it is months it's
maybe a year but I think that's getting
ever shorter as Paul mentioned um there
is a ton of a ton of things happening at
the application layer and the
architecture layer and the foundational
model layer. Um where we look for it on
the deep tech side, we look for
interesting things in compute and
connectivity, the infrastructure to
underly those and then the power to
serve it. And there's real opportunity
that I think is sustained long term uh
to serve those markets uh from a from
the physical instantiation of AI which
is super interesting. We've I've put
some of our companies here um that are
working in that space and we'll talk
about a few of them in greater detail uh
going forward. I mentioned that global
energy demand is accelerating for the
first time in 25 years. Um on the right
you can see the projections around
global data center uh electricity
demand. Basically base case 2% growth
over over the next 10 years, high case
4% growth. Um, but just a month ago, Sam
Alman said, "Actually, I think we're
going to need 250 gigawatts just for
open AI. 250 gawatts for reference in
the United States would be about 30% of
electricity demand." Um, so that's these
numbers are really stabs in the dark.
And the IEA last week came out with
their projections um, which are really
interesting. They they have noted the IA
is the International Energy Agency.
noted a little bit of this, but the
numbers just don't add up. And and it's
not their fault. Projections are hard.
Um and but the uncertainty around this
is is pretty impressive. The upside uh
being quite massive for energy
development. Um
the next question you should ask is
well, what energy is going to be
deployed to meet that? Uh and and that
is that is I think the question on a lot
of our minds
for sure. Some of that is going to be
met with existing resources, fossil
fuels, gas in the United States. Some
coal plants are coming out of retirement
um to be able to meet the demand here in
the next three to five years. And that
has really serious implications for the
climate. Um but on the on the market
side, that demand is also pulling new
technologies into market. We are seeing
um utility scale projects in nuclear, in
geothermal, in energy storage, in fusion
all being announced all for with the
effort of getting shovels in the ground
over the next five to six years for new
technology at large scale, which is
really exciting. So, it's a really great
time to be in that in that space. Here
I've got um three MIT spin-offs to
highlight. Form Energy is doing long
duration energy storage. They are they
just actually commissioned their first
project in Minnesota with Great River
Energy. Um Blue Energy is developing a
small modular nuclear reactor
development platform with their first
project down in Texas. Um MIT the CEO is
out of nuclear science and engineering
form energies technology out of lab of
Yetme. Uh and Quaz is doing enhanced
geothermal. um they are they are out of
the plasma science infusion center um
with a project that they're developing
uh in the ring of fire in Nevada um
concurrent to all of this and and all
three of these companies now are working
with the kind of AI hyperscalers um
because that is where the demand is
pulling them into market.
Shifting gears just a little bit. Um
it's it's quite clear that the new
administration in DC is shifting uh
efforts. Um this was that pulling back a
whole bunch of Biden era grant programs.
Uh and now you repurposing that capital
uh into new projects. Uh the geopolitics
and national priorities are shaping
technology choices uh and company
choices. Um in the in the United States
uh supply chain resilience has always
been something that we have prioritized.
I think right now the administration is
act is funding um a putting a lot of
money into expanding our ability to do
rare earth uh processing uh novel novel
recycling technologies of of um critical
minerals and um the opportunity to
onshore manufacturing for rare earth
magnets. There was a few announcements
recently. Um all of that is providing a
signal of a fairly robust industrial
policy uh that I don't think we had
anticipated. Um but it is certainly
coming on the energy side. Finding
signal from the noise has been
difficult. Uh and you all have tracked
the headlines. Um it has been this
I would say um pros and cons across the
board of of what is happening. And
certainly uh the notion of climate
change is not one that is embraced. Um
but I think we are beginning to see some
policies that look quite favorable for
technologies that could ultimately in
the fullness of time serve uh to to
reduce massive amounts of emissions and
I think innovation is a key lever uh to
do that in the absence of of robust
federal policy. Um across our portfolio
we have five broad areas uh in the on
the energy side we have we invest into
base load energy transmission and
distribution and storage we invest into
electrification of end uses and
industrial processes alternative fuels
resource efficiency and industrial
processes
um there's a handful of our companies
there but I think what's really
interesting is um when I look at the
effect of existing policy, US and Europe
policy on our portfolio.
It's actually a lot of green. Um there's
a significant amount of uh subsidy even
through the the tax reform package that
passed the this summer um for base load
energy, transmission, distribution, and
storage. If I was to highlight one area
where I think it is challenging is it is
in electrification and it's because cost
of electric power will go up without
subsidies for solar and wind. Um
that was already happening though
because the demand for power from data
centers is driving up electric power
everywhere and so the challenges for
electrifying end uses and uh we're we're
already meeting some headwinds.
Certainly those are more aggressive now
um without the support for wind and
solar here at the United States. Um and
I worth noting this is a energy specific
set of policies. This is not a climate
specific set of policies. So certainly
our ability to meet climate goals under
this framework is not uh not possible.
Um we are going to be building and
already have started building a whole
lot more natural gas. I mentioned the
coal restarts that are happening in the
United States. This is not about that.
This is about how does how does the
setup policies impact our portfolio.
It's a different conversation. Um and if
I were investing as a project developer
in wind and solar, this would be a
different presentation.
Um
the third topic is these mature
playbooks for new technologies showing
how you can return shareholder value,
reduce costs and scale into these
markets. Um I'm going to talk through a
couple examples. The first is on solar
and lithium ion batteries. Um
on the on the left hand side of this
chart you can see the cost reductions as
a function of production scale for solar
and for lithium ion. That learning rate
shows the opportunity of innovation to
change markets. you've got in I actually
I was in the energy storage world
gridscale energy storage world before um
being in my current role and I watched
as a competitor the cost of lithium ion
drop from about $1,000 a kil a kilowatt
hour to less than a hundred uh and that
was frankly terrifying um and but but
that is what what's happening and has
the potential to happen across
technology trajectories it is also why
in the fullness of time innovation gives
us the best chance to combat climate
With new technologies coming into market
and using this new demand to scale them
up, we can change markets. It is
actually the only thing in energy that
ever has is innovation. And the three of
them over the last 30 years, the first
is natural gas hydraulic fracturing dro
completely changed the energy landscape
here in the United States and globally.
The second is solar and the third is
lithium ion. we have new trajectories in
in fision and fusion and geothermal that
pro that present that same opportunity
and it's immensely hopeful
in um oh a couple uh energy companies in
the portfolio also MIT startups all of
them um mantle is developing carbon
capture solutions they're their first
project is is in construction and almost
commissioned in uh at a pulp and paper
facility in Quebec form energy I
mentioned before longduration energy
storage atmazero
uh deployed their first air the world's
first airsource heat pump steam boiler
uh to a food and beverage customer in
Lovelin Colorado and Vier is uh
deploying and they just commissioned
their first unit of high temperature
superconducting cables uh for inside the
data center power modules to the rack
and transmission lines um all of these
are now in manufacturing and in scale
scale up and so those cost those cost
projections and the the ability to drive
down and compete um they're on the cusp
of realizing that reality. Um AI has
also given us a whole bunch of um
productive um I think acceleration of
innovation and potential in the life
science space. Um Alphafold is the data
point there. The ability to create a
protein bank that accelerates our
understanding of how uh how to treat
disease is is transformative and has
been is a massive leap in the field.
That's super exciting. We now have the
opportunity to take a look at where else
can we see that type of innovation come
to market quickly. um
in life sciences the access to data is
going to drive the speed of AI of of
adoption of AI and the usefulness of AI.
A lot of that is happening at that top
layer. Um the real challenge and the
real opportunity that we see is the
ability to both shorten the pre-clinical
phase with robust data sources and and
technologies that are able to accelerate
the data production. And then
alternatively if you can take your
clinical trial success rate which is now
less than 10% and you can increase that
you have you you can create a whole ton
of value in the economy and also also
produce many more uh life-changing
therapies uh which is which is really
exciting. So that's where we're looking
for those the next set of AI um AI
augmented success stories in the life
science.
All right. So um the
current dislocation between the
macroeconomic realities of what's
happening in the realities of VC
markets. So um I showed you the chart of
where we invest. 70% of venture dollars
are going into the application layer of
uh AI. So some of the many of the things
that Paul Paul talked about the
infrastructure layer of AI is where we
see a whole lot of resilient value. Um
and right now the venture landscape is
not fully a funding that in the way that
it probably needs to. Um I think what's
really interesting and this is
particularly true on the energy side uh
where you have um the demand signal
long-term demand signal uh very high and
yet the venture communities pulling back
right as we have proof points that they
can be successful and so it means that
from an investor perspective you've got
to build coalitions and groups of
investors that can work together to
bring these things to scale. I think one
of the things that makes me most excited
when I look at this moment in time is we
have a whole about
30 40% of deals involve corporates and
they are all engaged partners in this uh
in this opportunity um over the long
term that's really important that it
continues. So, I'm going to leave you
with um one last thought and uh this is
the key question that everybody should
be asking. Is this a boom cycle or is
this a bubble, right? Um and there are
reasons to believe that both are true
and that is probably unsatisfying. Um
but the story of capitalism is money
will flow where there is large
opportunity. The.com bubble burst
paved the way for the magnificent 7
today. Out of that moment in time came
the largest companies in the world. The
same is probably true today. Out of this
moment in time in 20 years, we will have
the most the largest companies in the
world. Um, and that's super exciting.
The next thing, and I I I felt this way
listening to Paul's talk. The next thing
you've got to think about is how does
this affect people, right? And what is
what is the productivity enhancement?
How are people going to be affected? How
are jobs going to be affected? And how
do you build culture around the use of
AI so that is sustainable prosperity for
everybody? Uh that is the challenge I
think of our time going forward. And
with that, Katarina, I'm I'm all set.
I'll open it up for a couple questions.
We have time.
>> Yes. Thank you, Michael. Super
insightful. Thank [applause] you. Um any
questions for Michael? We have time to
maybe a couple.
>> It looks like
>> one in the back.
>> Okay.
>> Um I really like what you said about
data availability funding or enabling
AI. How do you get um over the
disconnect with investors and VCs um to
fund things hard tech that's actually
going to provide that data?
>> Yeah. So I think um there's
there [clears throat] the sectors are a
little different. Um but when we look
and we invest at the very early stages
of these companies um even at those
early stages finding the investor
syndicates that are going to be
productive partners for the long term is
ever more critical particularly as the
venture markets are pulling back. Um so
that is the core body of work that takes
place in those early days is who are the
partners that you're going in with? How
do you work together? What are the
different roles everybody's going to
play and how much capital do you have to
get them? You got to take these
companies further down field than maybe
a traditional seed investor might
originally think about it.
>> Thank you, Michael. I'm curious of your
exit strategy. Um, for instance, like
Mantel, it requires huge capex for the
company to grow. Um I know uh Mantel is
also has been working really hard to uh
find the project financing. So what is
your um strategy not only for the exit
also for about you know ramp up their
really like business scale.
>> Yeah. So I think on the project
financing side scale up this is where
we're in a different moment in time
because we are actually getting
customers to pay for that and those
customers will pay for it. the first
one. These are the hyperscalers and and
other similar similar parties are
willing to pay for the first one. Um or
have a PPA to cover the cost of the
first one that you can then get project
finance into which wouldn't have
happened before. Um and then uh but
you're giving up you're giving up some
rights to the next set of projects,
right? So they're doing it because
they're they are buying capacity into
the 2030s, well into the 2030s. Um and
so there's there's novel formations of
of coalitions of of players that are
enabling that in a way that didn't
happen three four years ago. Um on the
exit side, so I think one um the these
different sectors behave differently uh
as it relates to exit markets. However,
the what what I'm seeing and I think
what the markets are seeing is if you're
selling into into th those customers
like they believe in the long-term
upside there and you are being traded at
or or valued at revenue multiples that
hard tech companies never saw before. So
there was an announcement last last
week. It was a liquid cooling company
acquired by Eaton uh for $9 billion and
that company had something somewhere
between 200 and 500 million in revenue.
It's private so I'm not exactly sure but
but that that's the multiple that we're
talking about um because of that upside
the topline growth potential. Um if you
are if you are a company selling um a a
piece of infrastructure to a utility
you're you're tra you get traded at like
a two 2x 3x versus 20. That's how the
the markets are just valuing the valuing
these companies differently. Um and it's
interesting to see I think the
durability of that is a good is like
core question going forward.
>> Thank you. Final question for Michael.
anyone.
>> Okay.
>> Seems great. Thanks everybody.
>> Thank you, Michael. [applause]