okay hi everybody um welcome to the
broad MIT Series in chemical biology and
the first seminar of the spring Series
so I'm delighted to introduce Professor
Wilfred vanderdonk he's here from
University of Illinois Urbana champagne
um to tell us about his terrific science
this hour just as a little introduction
um Wilford began his education in the
Netherlands and came to the US where he
did his PhD Rice University and then
came to MIT for a postto with Joanne
stubby so welcome back yet again um and
then began his career at University of
Illinois where he um Rose through the
ranks and is currently the Richard E
Hecker endowed sharing chemistry and
also an investigator of the Howard
Hughes Medical Institute um since 2008
so Wilford has received many awards um
I'll just mention two of the most recent
um in 2021 he was elected into The
National academ of Sciences and is the
2024 recipient of the Bader award from
the American Chemical Society this is an
award for excellence in either
bioorganic or bioinorganic
chemistry um his research program really
is at the intersection of chemistry and
biology focused on Discovery and
fundamental understanding of
biosynthetic Pathways enzymology um and
new natural products so Wilfred welcome
back delighted for your talk right
thanks Liz can you hear me okay yeah
working out uh thanks for the kind
introduction and I also like to thank
the faculty of the broad and the MIT
chemistry department for the invitation
uh I was really looking forward to this
uh ahed invited me about two years ago I
think but I couldn't at the time make it
for various reasons and so I've really
been looking forward to my visit and it
has been as in operational as I
anticipated so it's been really great um
the title that I gave uh again a long
time ago uh was genom mining for new
natural products as well as new
chemistry um um I will mostly focus on
the latter part so genom mining for new
chemistry and so uh why would we genom
mine for new chemistry well of course
there's the inherent interest in the
chemistry that takes place in nature but
also over the last 10 15 years I been
another very good reason to look for new
enzimatic reactions and that is uh the
uh real uh Embrace that the industry has
shown to using biocatalysis in the
biosynthesis and chemoenzymatic
synthesis of um Pharmaceuticals and so I
think a real watershed moment was this
2010 paper from U scientists at Merc and
codexes where they showed they could
take an enzyme and through directed
Evolution use that enzyme to set that
stereo Center here in this then clinical
candidate Genovia and so that trend has
continued and so uh in process chemistry
uh using enzymes has become a very
popular way to reduce waste and increase
uh the efficiency of making
pharmaceutical so a few more examples
are shown here these are molecules that
were discovered by Medicinal Chemistry
using purely synthetic chemistry uh but
once they went into clinical development
and uh of kilograms were needed
chemoenzymatic routes turned out to be
really the most efficient um and so uh
if you're a process chemist in industry
and you are given a molecule that is
already set the molecule has gone
through the development and now it needs
to be made in large scale for the
clinical trials uh if you want to make
it chemically you have a 100 Years of
methodology development to probably come
up with with a dozen or more routes to
make the molecule but if you want to use
enzymes that is not the case actually
the number of enzymes that are available
that allow you to use enzymatic steps in
a chemoenzymatic pathway uh is very very
limited and indeed all of these examples
use enzymes that did known chemistry
that had been studied previously the
directed Evolution essentially allowed
them to take uh uh substrates that they
naturally do not take and so if you read
these papers there's often statement
like this this is taken I forget from
which one it's a quote that for this to
continue we really need to discover new
enzymatic transformation such that
hopefully at some point for the
biocatalysis you also have
multiple retrosynthetic routes by which
you could try and make a molecule very
efficiently and so that made uh that
started making us think as to how do you
discover fundamentally new enzimatic
reactions and so there's a number of
ways I think you can do it you can do it
the way
Francis Arnold and people coming out of
the Arnold lab have done where you
essentially have enzymes do reactions
for which there is no natural
counterpart and that has been very
successful uh another way to do it is to
say okay there's still thousands upon
thousands of unknown proteins genes that
are annotated in the databases as
hypothetical proteins or domain of
unknown function and some of those might
also be doing interesting chemistry and
especially in the realm of natur
products there's there's amazing
structures and of course these need to
be biosynthesized and there might be a
really interesting chemistry that is
hiding there and so we started then a
program where we wanted to intentionally
look for enzymes that we didn't know
what they might be doing now that's
easier said than done my colleague John
ger for about 10 years uh ran this
enzyme function initiative and the whole
goal there was to assign functions to
proteins of unknown function and he
would tell you and his colleagues would
tell you that the hardest thing is to
figure out what the substrate is going
to be of the enzyme if you don't know
what the substrate is you cannot really
know what the enzyme is doing and that's
where we thought we had a really unique
angle because we had been working on the
biosynthesis of a class of natural
products that are called rips these are
ribosomally synthesized peptides they're
Gene encoded and then because these
structures are limited to the natural
amino acids what nature does is a large
number of post transation modifications
on part of that peptide that we call the
cor peptide I'll show you a few
structures these are often
macrocyclizations but also all kinds of
other chemical
Transformations a leop peptide that is
important to guide these enzymes is then
cut off and then you have the natural
product class that I now referred to as
ribs and so um rips were long believed
to be a very small group of natural
products but with all of these genomes
that have come out we now know that it's
one of the largest class classes of
natural products on Earth and that is
because they're made by all domains of
life in all domains of life so ukaria
ARA bacteria and among the bacteria
almost all Fila make ribs so it's not um
limited to say tinam my seeds or or C
bacteria and so if we think about this
pathway it's really perfectly set up for
a number of different things one is to
do genom mining for new natural products
I'm not really going to talk about that
today uh because everything here is Gene
encoded and hence you can turn on the
computer look for biosynthetic Gene
clusters that are making molecules that
you've never seen and you can then
transport these Pathways into hyicus
host like eoli yeast and so on but for
this stock it also is a great way to
discover new chemistry suppose that this
is a hypothetical Gene cluster and that
the computer says about the yellow and
the green enzymes that those are domains
of unknown functions or uh enzymes that
are hypothetical proteins because the
little Gene there en codes for the
precursor peptide we have a direct route
into assigning the function of these
enzymes we know that one of the genes in
that cluster is making an enzyme that
does the first reaction on that peptide
the product of that is going to be taken
by the next enzyme and so by
coexpressing different combinations of
enzymes we can walk towards the
functions of these hypothetical proteins
so in our lab we love biosynthetic Gene
clusters that have a lot of domains of
unknown functions or hypothetical
proteins because that allows us to find
new chemistry
potentially and so um let me first show
you a few structures to have an idea as
to what are these post transation
modifications that are introduced um and
so here are just five of what are now
more than 50 classes of natural products
in the thiopeptides you see that there's
Pines and thool and one thing that we
see often is that the amides that of
course are a vulnerability for peptides
with respect to proteolytic degradation
that often these are converted into
other structures such as these thool and
oxazoles or tho amides or meated amides
or n2c cyclization side chain
cyclization as I mentioned many of these
have macrocyclic structures to uh uh uh
impose a confirmational constraint that
makes these molecules
active and so uh the first example where
we were able to to use this approach to
assign function to proteins of um
unknown function is a little dated now
but it sets the rest of the story my two
posto ching and Michael F decided to
work on this biosynthetic Gene cluster
from pseudomona syring that's a plant
pathogen and we had a number of
questions we didn't know what the enzyme
encoded by this dark blue Gene might be
doing and we didn't know what this
protein encoded by the gray Gene H was
doing but we knew it was a member of the
domain of unknown function 692 and we
also knew that there was a really large
protein family of for which no functions
had been determined previously so using
this combinatorial co-expression in Ni
coli Chi and Michael were able to show
that the first step is actually
catalyzed by that blue the enzyme
encoded by the blue Gene and it does a
reaction that they hadn't really
anticipated so the enzyme adds 16 from
cine TRNA to the end of the little
peptide that is encoded there so
essentially the same chemistry that the
ribosome would do but without a template
no mRNA is present there so we didn't
really know what to make of that but it
became clear that it must be on pathway
because after the cine is added now
these Dove 692 enzyme and it needs this
uh partner Protein that's why we also
have color that in Gray and it does a
reaction that we have really never seen
before so the enzyme excises the beta
carbon as form8 we can show that using
carbon 13 and then reattaches the sulfur
to the alpha carbon with retention of
configuration that the steps after that
are a little bit more traditional so the
two yellow proteins also collaborate the
E enzyme takes Sam and turns it into
carboxy Stam here and then the F enzyme
then transfers that carboxy methyl group
to that sulfur to make now an analog of
glutamate we call it thog glutamate and
then there's a protease in the gene
cluster that then cuts off what we have
just made we regenerate the precursor
peptide it can now go around and around
and around so we have catalytic use of
the precursor peptide it's a scaffold on
which a natural product is being bound
so when we had discovered this we
wondered okay how often do we find these
type of Pathways so I'm going to tell
you about other examples of these
enzymes which we now call Pearls for
peptide Amino TRNA ligases I'm going to
start out by telling you more about this
Dove 692 enzyme family of which there's
about 16,000 in the current genomes and
so uh if we make a so-called sequence
similarity network uh using the the
tools that have been developed at the
enzyme function Institute uh something
that was started with py babit uh these
types of uh Renditions of sequence
similarity networks and then John girl
really has popularized them so every dot
that you're looking at is an enzyme if
the dots are close together then there's
high enzyme similarity to thoughts are
further away from one another the
sequence similarity is lower and then
you can set certain cut offs uh by which
the enzyme families are uh put into
different groups so in this particular
at this particular cut off the
assumption is that these blue enzymes
are all isofunctional they're going to
do the same reaction but a reaction that
is different from say the red ones or
the pink ones or the orange ones so I
just showed you what the green ones are
doing here and actually as we were
working on this another paper came out
from Amy Rosen frikes lab that worked on
the pink ones and she showed that that
enzyme family does again a remarkable
chemical transformation I challenge you
to draw a mechanism to turn ayine into
an oxazalone tho Ami there so now we had
two enzymes two really unusual reactions
but 16,000 others and so we wanted to
see what else was in this enzyme family
um and so before I show you some of uh
other examples um uh uh of groups uh on
this sequence similarity Network let me
first show you a crystal structure of
one of the pink ones that was solved in
China in changu by way Chang and his
co-workers and so in blue you see the
protein this is the dove 692 in pink is
its partner protein that binds the
substrate and in yellow you see the
substrate and so when we zoom into the
active side we see that this is an
unusual enzyme family because it's a try
nuclear iron dependent enzyme uh and so
if you look at all 16,000 of these
proteins the ligans for three irons are
are almost entirely
conserved and so that was U very
interesting the 16 of the substrate you
can see makes a a a bonding contact to
one of those irons and So based on the
structure and the the the reaction that
our enzyme catalyzes we can then propose
a mechanism M and so that is shown here
so I'll first go over the mechanism and
then I'll tell you what our support is
for this mechanism and so we know that
we have three irons in our enzyme also
we have also Crystal structures with we
Chang in a collaboration that also
contain three irons we know that at
least one of them needs to be reduced we
don't know if they all need to be
reduced but if they're all oxidized we
have no activity um we know we need
oxygen uh the reaction doesn't go
without oxygen and so we believe that we
first make a feric superoxo species and
we think that that does a hydrogen atom
abstraction of this activated position
here at the beta carbon that would
generate this radical and you can
actually draw a number of different
mechanisms to go from this radical to
this U tho Hemi
ml um and so this is just one way by
which you can draw this this also can go
by by other uh steps if that happens
then we make an iron for oxide species
uh next to this alcohol and we believe
that that might do an oh
oxidation of course an O bond is very
strong but we're also making a new o
Bond so thermodynamically it should be
okay and in another enzyme system that
is a mononuclear iron dependent enzyme
in collaboration with Marty Bolinger and
carsen creps I think we have very strong
evidence that a FAL can oxidize an O
bond to make an oxygen centered radical
um what probably pulls the whole system
forward is that if you do generate that
radical very rapidly you will do a
bision to make a much more stabilized
radical and a glycal type radical that
could potentially then do a rebound to
make the observed carbon sulfur Bond and
it could then also uh lead to hydrolysis
of this thioester to give the two
products so the support that we have for
for this is that if we put dudum on the
alpha carbon we see no change the derium
is retained so we don't believe that
there's any chemistry that happens on
the alpha carbon if we put the tyum on
the beta carbons one ends up in the
product the other is lost into solvent
as we would expect perhaps the most uh
telling is that if we do the reaction
with O8 labeled oxygen only one O8 ends
up in the product suggesting that the
second oxygen comes from solvent comes
from water and so of course that doesn't
prove this mechanism and we would love
to try and trap some of these
intermediates as we did do in for that
other enzyme in this paper thus far that
hasn't really been successful and so
we're still working uh with Marty in Kon
to see if we can get more direct
spectroscopic evidence for this
particular mechanism now a few points uh
the first thing I I want you to remember
that here we have a carbon that is at
the Tho alahh oxidation state and that's
because later on I will show it again
but I will not show these first steps
leading to that uh that
intermediate okay so back to the
sequence similarity with network then uh
can we discover other reactions in this
enzyme family and so I'm first going to
tell you about the orange family here it
seems like I'm starting to run out of
battery I'll change it in a second um
and so Richard aeku he's a he was a
postdoc in the lab started working on
that he picked one gene cluster from
chisso bacterium it contains a precursor
peptide that you can see the sequence of
all orange proteins from the previous
slide they have sequences of precursor
peptides that always end in the last
seven amino acids that are identical
that are bolded here and so what Richard
was able to show that if you then put
this into uh eoli you do
coexpressions if you coexpress the
substrate with the dove 692 enzyme in
red and this partner protein in Pur
purple you get an addition of 10 dotons
and so the question is what is 10 doton
we can treat the peptide with an prodas
that Cleaves right here at this lysine
and from that we know that the the 10
Daltons are added at C Terminus of the
peptide and so um um um uh at that
moment then uh we decided we need to do
NMR that's really the only way by which
we were able to determine what exactly
the uh the change in mass is due to and
it turns out that the change of of 10
Delton is a very complicated change
because it's removal of four hydrogens
and then addition of a meth group so
it's minus four and then plus 14 and
that gives you the net change of + 10 I
must have put them in the wrong way I
had 50% chance
that and so the um
let me let me change them
around guess I can do it the
oldfashioned way so that's the reaction
that the enzyme catalyzes as you can see
a lot of different things are happening
here and so the um the enzyme uh makes
two rings so that's loss of two
hydrogens to make this ring a loss of
two hydrogens to make that r ring so
that's a loss of four hydrogens and then
that is the addition of the methyl group
so to orient you this sulfur makes a new
Bond to this carbon this sulfur migrates
to that carbon instead of breaking this
bond that I showed you previously in
this case we're going to break this Bond
and this nitrogen picks up that carbonal
to make this hento in structure and then
the sulfur that migrates to the alpha
carbon is then methylated and we have
shown that that comes from Acid anol
methionine we don't know the absolute
stereochemistry yet here at these two
positions and so we have a lot of NMR
data that supports the structure and
we've done quite a bit of labeling data
so we know that these Alpha carbons end
up at these positions more tellingly if
we label the carbonal of the cines we
can show that this carbonal ends up here
at the hentain so certainly a very uh
unusual reaction not sure that this is
going to be a useful reaction but
certainly new chemistry um and so we
have renamed the duve 692 family then as
the mon as the multinuclear iron
dependent oxidation enzymes why not
truclear well because there are some uh
uh this uh disagreement in the
literature between two groups on not our
enzymes but another enzyme whether the
active enzyme is truclear or dinuclear
and so for now we just want to make sure
that we don't bias that argument um and
so then going back uh to the the
potential mechanism we don't have any
evidence for this mechanism but as you
will see there will be similarities and
commonalities between the previous
mechanism and I start out with that
first intermediate that I I reminded you
to remember a tho alide and then a feric
superoxide so in the previous mechanism
we had this hydroxy attack it to do a
hydration in this case we use the
nitrogen of the next amide X amino acid
to attack the Tho alide that would give
us this intermediate beta lactam then we
believe that this nitrogen which we
remember need to pick up this carbonal
could attack the
betam and then we would generate an
alcohol that is now set up for the same
type of chemistry which is
oxidation bet decision generation of a
radical that now can form an episulfide
and then the second cinee can open that
up and we can meate at sulfur and that's
why we really want to know the
stereochemistry and are working hard
towards understanding the
stereochemistry because there's clear
predictions here about what the stereo
chemistry ought to be uh based on this
mechanism so whether this is correct we
don't know uh but we do know that it at
least uses similar type of chemistry as
the previous mechanism and Amy in her
mechanisms for the sand aaum
biosynthetic enzymes also has very
similar mechanisms with respect to what
might be
happening so I've shown you now three
reactions all on cyes and all
unprecedented and and not predictable I
don't want to leave you with the idea
that these enzymes only act on cyes
because we have several examples where
that's not the case and so one example
is shown here this was the work of den
noen who is now here at MIT in Michael
L's lab he was a joint student with my
colleague Doug Mitchell and he worked on
this cluster from bural area tylon
densers and again this this combination
of enzymes we have never seen before we
like that and he was able to show that
there's a B12 radical Sam enzyme that
first methylates on the beta carbon of
this thyrosine with the shown
stereochemistry and then a p450 takes
the two tyrosines and it crosslinks them
but it does so with with the
stereochemistry that I'm showing you
there so you get only one atropisomer
and we know that because we have a
microed structure of the of the product
and then the M Neo ax as I already
mentioned not on ayine in this case it
acts on a c terminal aspartate and turns
that into a beta keto amino acid a
structure that medicinal chemist have
used for a long time to make Inhibitors
of proteases and then the last step this
methyl transferase here Mephiles at this
position and then was able to show that
this is indeed a syis proteas inhibit we
do not know why the bural area is making
this molecule but again uh uh
unprecedented chemistry uh and the final
example that I want to show you is
actually from unpublished work for my
current postdoc shakar party so he
picked yet another Gene cluster in this
case again a combination of biosynthetic
enzymes that we have not seen before
there about a few hundred examples of
those and uh this uh this sequence
similarity logo shows that this part of
the substrate that is bolded here is
fully conserved in all of these several
100 precursor peptides and so what Sher
was able to show is that in this case
the mnio enzyme acts first so all of
these pathways are strictly ordered uh
in this case nothing happens until the M
Neo has done a reaction and as you can
see the chemistry is again very
different in this case it takes two
phenol alanines and makes two or
tyrosines and then after that this
arginase acts and it takes this fully
conserved Arginine and turns it into an
ornithine and then another radical sem
enzyme does again
macrocyclization to now make a different
ring pattern uh and again we do not know
why these organisms are making that at
the moment we're mostly focus on
discovering new enzymatic chemistry as I
said in the title of course we're very
interested also why these organisms are
making all of these macrocyclic ites but
for now we have put that on the side and
we will go back to that later um and so
I've shown you now five different
reactions all unprecedented and other
labs have also contributed to these and
so Mo sayos who actually was a a student
here with Joanne uh he showed yet
another reaction where this carbon
nitrogen bond in the backbone of a
peptide is broken to make an amidated
peptide and the group of Jacob du brisan
in France showed yet another reaction on
cysteine where cysteine is converted to
this tho
oxisol so I don't know if any of these
reactions will ever be useful for a
directed Evolution campaign to make
structures I do know that they make a
lot of heterocycles and of course
heterocycles are quite frequently found
in natural products and whether so
whether it's an oxazalone or henin or
thio oxisol these are all structures
that we have haven't really seen uh in
in natural
products so let me return then to these
Pearl enzymes these enzymes that add an
amino acid at the end of a
peptide at first glance a silly reaction
because you could have encoded the cine
on the DNA and the ribosome could have
made this but after we figured out this
catalytic cycle it makes a lot of sense
because you now have a catalytic peptide
you don't have to make 50 amino acid
peptide every single time you want to
make a natural product and so uh we have
then started looking for other enzymes
like these uh and at last count we have
now eight of them uh that all add
different amino acids and all in an
amino ail TRNA dependent fashion and I
think when we're all going to be done
with this we're going to
find cases of all 20 amino acids uh I'm
pretty sure that there's going to be
enzymes out there that add or any of the
20 natural amino acids uh to the end of
of peptides they all make different
natural products the biosynthetic
pathways diverge after the addition of
the the amino acid but we think that
this is quite interesting given the the
the real interest there is currently in
the pharmaceutical industry in peptidic
uh
Therapeutics um because those can be
made by solid phas peptide synthesis but
maybe some steps also can be done using
biocatalysis and so then these enzymes
might actually be quite useful um and so
we have started to try to understand how
they work and so first some isotopic
labeling studies that were done by Zang
gang Zang uh he first put an O8 at the
end of the peptide was able to that that
O8 is actually U liberated as phosphate
the reaction requires ATP and so we
believe that we first get a
phosphorilation to make an asil
phosphate activated carboxilate that the
nitrogen then of the amino ail TRNA
attacks that to make the Amite Bond and
then doing the reaction in O8 labeled
water showed that actually the activated
Esther that the ribosome uses to make
proteins or enzyme just just hydes it so
it seems very wasteful uh it seems a
prime example of the opportunistic
manner of evolution presumably all these
organisms that use these type of enzymes
they benefit from the natural product
that making uh but they're certainly not
making it in the energetically most most
efficient manner um and so um um we
don't have Crystal structures of these
enzymes H so we don't really know how
this all fits together but then when
Alpha 3 came out last year my current
post Joseline Ramos fuera put it all
together so protein peptide substrate
ATP and
TRNA and the the the the prediction is
rather stunning I think U knowing that
there are no examples of structural
information on these so Alpha fold
places the three prime end of the TRNA
where the amino acid would be attached
right in the same vicinity where it
places the C terminal of the precursor
peptide and that c terminal carboxilate
is right next to the gamma phosphates of
ATP so it's exactly set up for the
chemistry that we know the enzyme does
but that Alpha fold of course doesn't
know
and so uh the the phosphorilation and
then here is where the amino acid would
be attached ready to attack that
carboxilate there and so uh uh in three
dimensions is a little bit better to see
and the other thing I want to point out
up here it looks like there is a contact
with the anti-codon loop of the TRNA and
so it seems like there's two-o
interaction in order to make sure that
the right amino acid gets put on both
based on the anticodon as well as based
on the uh on the the amino acids so
we're trying to investigate this right
now again uh my student Den W and he's
working together with hero zuga who has
this Flex asme technology that allows
you to change the TRNA and the amino
acid and put different amino acids on
different trnas and vice versa to see
whether that recognition is indeed real
of the anti-codon loop um jeline has
already made the mutations of all the
conserved residues that Alpha fold
predicts are important for recognition
of ATP and of the amino ail TRNA and
indeed if we mutate that tyrosine or
that Arginine or that Arginine that are
fully conserved and that are making
contact to this the the three prime CCA
arm that of course every TRNA has we
lose all of the activity so we believe
that these predictions are actually uh
potentially quite quite uh
correct so um if we assign functions to
enzymes that only are involved in pearls
then I think it would be useful but it
would still be sorry involved in rip
biosynthesis that would be useful but
still somewhat limited but fortunately
quite often the enzymes that we study
are also found in other context sequence
context other Gene clusters and so I
want to show you that in the context of
these pearls because we also find those
in polyketide synthes gene clusters and
also in non-ribosomal peptide synthetase
Gene clusters and so then the question
is what do they do in that context
sometimes they are attached to thio raay
domains sometimes they are part of a
complete module and sometimes they are
Standalone pearls and so uh we have
started to investigate these as well
then and this is the work of uauu a
current student in the in the lab so he
picked a gene cluster from stab brania
nenus it contains an nrps PKS a
thioesterase a dehydrogenase and then
the Pearl that we want to know what is
it doing in this
context and so he first took the enops
and the PKS uh expressed it in the holus
host streptomyces elbus and by doing
unbiased U metabolomics was able to show
that two new molecules are being made
compound two and compound one it turns
out that compound two turns into
compound one as you are doing the purif
if ation and the structural elucidation
and so compound two turns out to be a DI
orginal compound that has a Ura in the
middle and then an ethil Ketone at the
end and compound one is where this
nitrogen reacts with that Ketone to
cyclize it and turn it into this
structure so um then uh when we put in
the pearl also so coexpress the Pearl
together with the nrps and the PKS we we
again get two compounds and the
difference between what I just showed
you is that now two uh three Anin have
been added to the structure suggesting
that the Pearl is adding a three anine
and at first glance you might say well
you have an nrps this is already making
a peptide why would you need another uh
enzyme to make another Amite Bond and
the the the enel lies in the fact that
you have made a Ura so if you have made
a Ura you have essentially inverted the
directionality of the peptide uh and as
was already pointed out by Chris wallish
in in this publication when he studied
Ura formation in non- ribosomal peptide
synthesis uh this is his proposed
mechanism where the nitrogen can react
with bicarbonate and he shows that that
is the the source of the carbonal in the
Ura then you can draw a number of
different mechanisms I will just
describe one if this oxygen attacks that
carbonal there you would make an
anhydrite like structure and then you
could have an o2n uh uh carbonal shift
in order to give you the Ura structure
now if you think about this structure
this is uh this is activated to do more
chemistry at this
thioester but at this other
carboxilate with assembly line chemistry
you cannot really do anything with it
and that explains that when we look at
the dictionary of natural products and
we look at all Ura containing molecules
they all always have only a single amino
acid on one side of the Ura and then on
the other side in black is where further
elaboration by PKS or non-ribosomal
peptide synthesis has taken place and
that shows that you the the system
cannot do chemistry here apparently that
if a natural product can be made that is
beneficial to the organism by doing
further chemistry here a pearl is
attracted into the biosynthetic uh
pathway because now you can phosphorate
here we have shown that the 3nine comes
from 3L TRNA and so now you can also
extend in the other direction and so
very curious there's a few thousand
examples of this in the databases uh
what other structures are being made to
finish the biosynthesis of this
particular structure the polyte synthes
then adds a methyl melan unit to this
thioester here then the thioester cleave
this off the culation domain and then
the dehydrogenase domain that I haven't
really talked to you about thus far uh
it actually uh de desaturates this E
Group to this Alpha Beta unsaturated
Ketone and that's why we left it out of
our experiments initially we had put it
in but this is so reactive that it that
you constantly find other things that
have added here and that really made the
study much more difficult so we left
that out in the studies that I just just
showed
you so so far I hopefully have convinced
you that we can do genome mining for
rips and that I can also assign function
then to these hypothetical proteins that
these pearls add amino acids to both
ribosomal and non-ribosomal peptides and
that these M NEOS really are incredible
Catalyst that catalyze all kinds of
different oxidative reactions in the
last few minutes I would like to very
briefly touch upon some other things
that I normally talk about when I don't
talk about G mining for chemistry uh and
that is that this these biosynthetic
pathways are really versatile to do
bioengineering uh that you can do genome
mining uh in an automated fashion we've
done this together with my colleague qu
inzo who has these robots that drive up
and down do all of the the molecular
biology to refractor biosynthetic Gene
clusters into plasmas and we then put
into eoli to then produce the rips and I
want to start out with uh pointing out
that these enzymes are really great to
make libraries of polycyclic peptides
another popular new drug modality that
is being studied a lot in the
pharmaceutical companies so this is just
a summary slide showing all of the
different rips that to date uh have been
turned into libraries like 10 to the 6
to 10 to the8 variants of um of
polycyclic peptides because these
enzymes are very forgiving with respect
to the sequence of the core peptide so
we have done this for lenti peptides uh
we've done Fage display of these
compounds ye display we've done reverse
to hybrid experiments we've done epitope
graphing hero zugo and Yuki goo have
done mRNA display of these thop peptides
here at MIT Chris void has made
libraries of these reny peptides and
then selected them for binding to
certain Target proteins uh David Craig
in Australia has done a lot of epot
grafting on these plant cyclotides uh
and Doug Mitchell and Constantine sein
of have made libraries of lasso peptides
and then selected those for binding to
other proteins to disrupt protein
protein interactions so I think this is
a really tremendous space to make
libraries of cyclic peptides by using
enzymatic means which means you can
access very large
libraries um with respect to
bioengineering I wanted to point out
that if you if you do mRNA display or
Yeast display or Fage display typically
you then look for binding with a
purified protein that is maybe labeled
or maybe um fluorescently labeled and
you can find binders to all kinds of
different proteins but it would be
really nice if you could do this in the
context of human cells where there might
be protein protein complexes there might
be glycosilation happening and so can we
do this in in mamalian cells can we make
these bacterial and fungal proteins
sorry products
in mamalian cells and I've already
pointed out that these These syntheses
are incredibly portable because all you
need is a ribosome and 20 amino acids
and so indeed we have recently shown
that we can make these molecules in HEC
293 cells this is one example where this
compound here was made and you can see
from the fragmentation and also from the
stereo chemistry and the bioactivity we
are making the same molecule that in
this case an anus kers make um in its
own setting and in this case it's a
compound from a basilla strain and again
we get the exact same outcome uh but the
nice thing is because these are peptidic
you can send the products to where you
want to make it go for instance if we
want the cyclic peptide to go to the
nucleus we can add the nuclear
localization sequence um and in this uh
let's focus just on this here you can
see if we don't have the nuclear the
the nuclear localization sequence the
product is in the cytoplasm and if we
add the nuclear localization sequence
now the product goes to the nucleus
these were transient infe transections
and hence uh only two out of maybe 10
cells um are are transfected in this
case um we can of course increase the
transection efficiency or do selections
which we didn't do in this particular
case we can also send these products to
the cytoplasm sorry to the cytoplasmic
membrane by again adding a cytoplasmic
localization sequence we can send them
to the ER and when we then take them out
and see are they still fully processed
in all cases uh for this particular
example the ad dehydration and the three
cyclisation had still taken place so I
think there's uh there's potential here
to start looking for disrupting protein
protein interaction and doing it in the
native mamalian context rather than uh
doing it by mRNA display or Yeast
display or some other uh initro
method U and then to end since I
mentioned I had originally in my title
uh that I was going to tell you about
genome mining for new natural products
and I haven't really told you anything
about that uh let me just uh point out
two rips that come from our own
microbiome and that are medically
important um neither of these were
discovered by us but both of them were
made in Eola by and we have been
collaborating with the people that have
been working on it uh so this is a
molecule that is called blon that was uh
discovered by Eric Palmer and his
co-workers now at the University of
Chicago uh and he shows in this paper
that if you have in your microbiome this
organism blo a productor that makes this
blaison that you are protected uh from
um establishments of vomisin resistant
and coxy infection so the these can no
longer establish in the the gut um area
uh and so we're working with Eric's lab
to see if we can improve the activity of
this molecule either as a therapeutic or
as a
prophylactic um now not all ribs that
are made in our gut are good uh and one
that is particularly bad is cyen this is
made by pathogenic and Terra coccus
falis it was reported first in the 1930s
uh that this was leading to death uh and
in
2014 I think it was we determined the
structure by making it in eoli and then
determining the structure of the of the
compound when we published that we were
contacted by a lot of different Labs
that ask can you send us some uh and one
of those lab is uh burn Schnabel an MD
at UCSD uh he sees infectious disease uh
patient and when he asked for the
material he said you know all the
patients that I see um they they are
going to die so these are patient
numbers that are infected by anaus falis
that can make
cyto I should point out that this is a
specific form of liver disease this is
alcoholic uh hepatitis um and so there
is no cure uh the people that come into
his office will die and so after we send
him the cyto lion he was able to show
and that's all his work that it is
indeed a cyon that is directly
responsible for the destruction of the
liver of these patients that uh
eventually leads to their death so we're
now working on inhibition of the
biosynthesis of cyto lion to see if that
can lead to a potential treatment so
with that let me thank the people that
have done the work you've seen their P
their their their pictures uh let me
tell you where they are now um Richard
is at Merk Ching is down the road at
brandise Michael is at Science magazine
uh jeline and Shaker are still in my lab
zengar is now at shangdong University
Den as I mentioned is here at MIT in M
Michael L's lab Sarah is at just evotech
UA is still in my lab and we've had
great collaborations with Doug
Mitchell's lab I want to thank our
funders I want to again thank ahed and
and Liz for the invitation and you for
your attention thank
[Applause]
you great thank you so the floor's open
for questions and we're in a really big
room so there's one mic over there um if
people on that side want to get up and
go and I can run it here or put
it and I guess in the spirit of this
series we'll ask for trainy questions
first
question in the
Middle where are
you do you guys ever look at induction
of these biosynthetic Gene
clusters yeah we do and it's that's a
bit of a sore point so we often buy the
organism that we get the cluster for
most of the genes I didn't really say
that but all of the genes were ecoli
optimized they were synthetic they came
from twist biosciences uh but then uh
quite often when we have made it uh uh
we don't know what the activity is of
the molecule and we buy the organism uh
and see if we can uh tweak it for um um
uh production because maybe we didn't
make what the natural organism make and
in I would say 90% of the time we cannot
find conditions where the the natural
biosynthetic Gene cluster is turned on
and we try all kinds of different things
you know stressing adding antibiotics uh
there's a lot of things that people have
developed uh and this seems to be a
general thing in the rip space so um
I've heard urine peel at the ATR
complain to me that these rips never
actually are made and so it is indeed
something that is uh a problem because
we cannot always test clearly the the
reactions that the these enzymes carry
out are the reactions they carry out uh
but what the the function is of the
natural products we would like to know
too uh and then uh if we have made the
wrong compound or perhaps we're missing
a step or perhaps not all of the
reactions were uh performed the right
way we would like to get the natural
product and most of the times we don't
see
it go to the microphone over there yeah
hi uh thank you for the great talk and
about the mechanistic studies of the uh
multiiron enzyme so like you said you're
going to do some spectroscopic studies
so are the intermediates like are the
time scale are uh is it allowed to do
like some frequence studies or yeah
that's exactly how so in the study on
the non-he monuclear iron dependent
enzyme that I alluded to uh we did both
flow studies in my lab and then also
free scrench studies in mossow and epr
in Marty and Carston's lab to uh stitch
together uh seeing the the F real
species and seeing that the decay of the
fal species was both had both an isotope
effect on the solvent and a substrate
isotope effect uh and U I haven't showed
you that enzyme but that can really only
be explained if it is the O Bond uh that
is being activated
uh and so that's what we have been
trying to do unfortunately not all
enzymes are equally well suited for
these type of experiments you need high
concentrations some enzymes you cannot
get high concentrations you need a
certain window of the kinetics in order
to be able to to to to trap them uh and
so uh we are very hopeful in the first
enzyme I showed you that breaks the
alpha beta carbon Bond uh the second
enzyme is not well behaved that I showed
you thanks for the talk um how do you
plan to inhibit the biosynthesis of the
cycin is there one enzyme that is
particularly easy to destroy uh all ribs
need to have the leader peptide removed
and without the leader peptide being
removed they are
inactive so that's one uh the enzyme
that makes the Rings I didn't show you
this at all but uh
the uh it has an
mamalian lipid kyese fold so my
colleague sa n was able to get a crystal
structure of these enzymes closest
structural homologue is actually
mtor and clearly lots and lots of
compounds out there already that inhibit
Emptor that we are seeing if we can
repurpose them to inhibit this bacterial
kise but these bacteria kise first
phosphates and then eliminates the
phosphate to put the double bond in to
make a dehydro amino acid so it will be
quite different we already know because
we've published the the crystal
structure the active site is different
from say mtor so we we're not worried
about you know treating uh patients to
trying that cyon is no longer make and
then at the same time inhibiting mtor
and getting all kinds of other effects
that we don't want but at the moment I
don't have anything that that looks
particularly exciting uh but that's what
we're doing
hey Wilfred um this is very interesting
the Pearl enzymes so do you do you see
any evidence for code on bias or do you
think they accept all the different
cognate trnas for yeah it's a great
question so we have one that adds lucon
and so in bacteria there's six different
ISO except the trnas all of them work um
and so uh we don't yeah we we clearly
need to do more so if there is an
anti-codon Loop recognition that tells
you that it can only be to some of the
nucleotides uh but yes we have not seen
any when we first discovered them we
thought that maybe this is related to
secondary metabolism certain trnas are
induced late uh in the in the life cycle
of bacteria so far at least in vitro we
don't see any preference for one or the
other
but they have to accept the TRNA for
that amino acid if you give them a
different TRNA they won't work correct
yeah but with with hero with Huga we can
put sure the wrong amino acid on the
right TRNA and as does it still work and
what if you put the right amino acid on
the wrong TRNA but those those studies
are ongoing so I can't really tell you
yet I like your orange t-shirts yeah
they do double duty it's the color of
illino and it's the color of the
Netherlands and so we
from Total Football to Total science
right there you go I just want a follow
to that like maybe you already answer
this but I was curious if there's a TRNA
abundance issue like are they using
pretty abundant tras in the particular
organism or that kind of gets to how
important and how specific are these
natural products yeah yeah it's it's a
it's a great question the first one that
we discovered is actually one that used
glutamil TRNA I didn't talk about that
and that comes from a lactic acid
bacterium lactic coccus uh and if you uh
uh look at what are the most prevalent
uh um small molecules in eoli it is
glutamate so we thought like yay and
then we talked to someone who studies
lactococcus lactus and it's not
glutamate so not yay and so it it
doesn't seem to be correlated with the
the the the amount of uh Amino ail TRNA
there is of course for for the great
majority of the organisms where these
clusters come from we actually don't
know there's no metabolomics that has
been done that we know what the relative
amounts are of the different metabolites
but for the one that we do know it
didn't
correlate so we don't know we don't know
why um um yeah and how this evolved and
we can also not predict we had hoped
that the the alphafold structure would
allow us to predict before we do the
experiment because that would make it
much easier to find the other 12 that I
want to find uh and so far that has not
worked out so Alpha fold is good but not
not perfect and it cannot predict at the
moment the substrate selectivity for the
amino
T also some one up there
thank you for the great talk uh I had
another question about the Pearl enzymes
uh is there something um about the
structure that limits the enzyme from uh
acting on proteins with long CA terminal
Tails or does it have to be just rips
and uh you know other smaller peptides
and I'm curious if uh there have been
proteins with that modification of
observed yeah it's a great question so
uh as far as we uh know currently and we
haven't studied all of the eight that we
uh the one that we have studied most
puts on a tryptophan uh it is uh quite
forgiving with respect to the sequence
of the peptide uh which surprised us to
be honest uh so we don't understand why
it's not adding tryptophan to a lot of
different things there are certain amino
acids that needs to be spaced a certain
distance from the C terminus and you
need to have those otherwise it doesn't
work but we've taken the last I think I
think it was 12 amino acids uh and put
it on a protein put it on MVP put it on
egfp uh and then the enzyme does add
tryptophan to the protein so it is a tag
that allows you but then you add an
amino acid that of course you could have
also encoded on the on the uh TRNA uh
sorry on the on the DNA but we are very
interested in looking at unnatural TR
Amino isolated trnas that have been used
for the codone suppression type of
technology and see if we can tease our
enzymes starting to put non-natural
amino acids onto proteins but we haven't
yet done
that if I can add to that um I think at
least in UK carots the the identity of
the C Terminus sometimes determines the
stability of the protein so this could
could be a really neat tool to tune the
stability of prot that's a great idea
yeah I hadn't thought of that but yes
you're
right
Laura um I was gonna just ask another
mechanistic question so in the I know
they're
not I'm call
mever so those enzymes um you propos for
one of them this interesting mechanism
where you make that kind of radical
later as opposed to just abstracting
that position which you show doesn't
happen and I just wondered if you had
any calculations or anything like that
that might provide insight into why
those other steps Happ yeah radal yeah
we we have we have not um to be honest
we we we we made that Alpha dutter uh
position because we thought that's where
the abstraction
yes also because then I could draw
making an EP sulfide and opening it up
move the sulfur to the alpha carbon so
that was our preferred mechanism Bas
your other mechanism that's kind of what
I thought you yeah so we have so so uh
we have a crystal structure but we don't
have a co- crystal structure of that
enzyme so the co- crystal structure I
showed you was for Amy and way Chang's
enzyme uh and so we don't uh we haven't
done any calculations um but yes we
should yeah probably because um we
actually I cannot even tell you what the
calculated activation energies are of
any of these steps and maybe some of
them are ridiculously high so it it's
something that yeah a lot of work we
still need to
do okay with that let's thank Wolford
for terrific seminar