I remember spending several weeks in the
summer at my grandparents farm.
My father came from a small farm.
It's a farm that's been in the family for
a little over a hundred years.
And going and seeing how a working farm
works was really fun.
He's very supportive, Saskatchewan, and
part of it's because of the weather.
It is incredibly cold in the winter.
We have a joke where I grew
up that there are four seasons.
Almost winter, winter, still
winter, and road construction.
I always had a real interest in
understanding the
fundamentals of science.
And so physics is a great part of that.
And I love math problems.
I love solving a problem
that I hadn't seen before.
I first heard about MIT, actually from an
MIT alumnus who was living in Regina.
At the science fair, people come by to
see what you're doing.
And this is somebody who stopped by and
we spent some time chatting.
He liked my project.
And he told me about the Institute and
how much it mattered to him.
And that led me to then think about, oh,
okay, I should think about,
is this a place I might
want to go in the future?
Showing up in Boston for the first time
was a little bit of a culture shock.
Drivers are different here
than they are in Saskatchewan.
I would really say it was
the institution that drew me.
It was that challenge to go to a place
that was really world ranked
and see if I could survive in that place.
Well, it's an intense place.
It's a friendly place.
It's not highly competitive.
It's a place where people work together.
It's a place where you find colleagues
who help you think through a problem.
Talent comes from everywhere.
And MIT is great at leveraging that
talent and attracting that talent.
My role as Chancellor
for Academic Advancement,
I usually describe it as
being MIT's ambassador.
MIT has such an incredible
history of changing the world.
And if I can make a connection between
somebody from the
outside and a faculty member,
if I can create a little more support so
that some student can come here
that otherwise couldn't afford it, that's
a different way to make an impact.
So many of the challenges that we're
facing today are global challenges.
If we fix climate in the United States,
you don't really do it
because it's part of a global system.
Having this global perspective means that
we can work with
partners around the world.
What is exciting to me about MIT is this
communal perspective
on collaboratively tackling hard
problems, making the
world a better place.