good morning and thank you all for being
here um just uh since I'm I think I'm a
last minute addition to the program just
by way of introduction I'm a professor
of nuclear science and engineering here
and for the last nine years I've been
over seeing mit's activities around the
world as the international Vice
Provost uh but as was said uh for the
last year or so I've also been leading
the development of mit's new climate
project and this project um was
introduced I don't know whether we can
move the slides forward yeah well maybe
um the project was
introduced
uh or launched by our president Sally
cornbluth shortly after her arrival at
MIT last year and her challenge to the
community was we really need to do much
more on this issue
and she's continued to make clear that
this is one of her highest
priorities she found a receptive
audience about a third of our faculty
were already working on different
aspects of the problem and if you
include students and postdocs and
research staff that probably meant
somewhere between 1 and 2,000 MIT people
already engaged in this uh uh process
problem and they're contributing in many
different ways one of the ways is to
start new companies uh typically seven
or eight of these are uh spinning out
each year based on uh MIT Pi so uh pivot
bio for example is using synthetic
biology to produce more resilient crops
able to absorb nitrogen with much lower
emissions than uh through conventional
fertiliz Iz es Boston metal is seeking
to eliminate carbon emissions from steel
production Sublime systems is
commercializing an electrochemical
process to eliminate carbon emissions
from cement production thoen is
developing a new zero emissions chemical
process to produce hydrogen form energy
is manufacturing ion air batteries to
provide long duration electricity
storage for the grid electrified normal
Solutions is converting electricity into
the high temperature heat above 1600° C
needed for many industrial
processes commwell Fusion systems is
commercializing its compact High field
Fusion reactor technology tokomak
technology and quaz energy is developing
a deep geothermal power system using its
high power microwave drilling technology
so a lot was already happening when
president corn Bluth issued her
challenge what she asked was that we
bridge the gap between what we've been
achieving as a collection of energetic
and ambitious individuals and the even
greater contributions we're capable of
if we act together and the new MIT
climate project is our
response the path we've chosen is a ho
of Institute
mobilization that's essentially designed
to help us do bigger things more quickly
the goal is for MIT to become within the
next 10 years one of the world's most
prolific and
collaborative sources of
technological behavioral and policy
solutions for the global climate
Challenge and we know that we'll have
succeeded if after 10 years years our
work has changed the expected trajectory
of global climate outcomes for the
better that's the Benchmark against
which we want our efforts here to be
judged the core of the climate project
is the six missions
university-wide problemsolving
communities each focused on a clear and
Broad objective each Reaching Across the
in Institute and also outside for its
membership and each charged with Road
mapping and assessing progress towards
its Mission identifying critical gaps
and bottlenecks constraining that
mission and launching and supporting
projects to overcome those bottlenecks
where our community the MIT community
and our partners are well positioned to
achieve impactful results the the six
missions are not surprisingly
decarbonizing energy and Industry
restoring the atmosphere while
protecting land and the oceans
empowering Frontline communities
building healthy and resilient cities
inventing new policy
approaches and wild
cards several of our very talented
Mission directors are here they're going
to roduce themselves in the panel
session that's coming up but just here
to highlight uh a couple of the
distinctive things about this
effort one is that this climate project
will not create a new school or a new
college at MIT that's the direction that
several of our peer schools are going in
we considered this too but concluded
that it isn't the right approach for us
partly because there isn't time for it
second while excellent scholarship will
be a necessary part of what we do the
primary objective is to contribute real
world impacts at the scale that the
climate problem demands and this means
working with scaling Partners from the
very start
organizations
individuals many of you in this room who
understand much more than we do about
the Practical challenges of building new
Solutions and bringing new solutions to
scale
and third rather than approaching this
peace meal one solution at a time what
we're looking to build here is a system
for continually generating new climate
Solutions A system that is lay it on top
of our schools and departments and labs
and centers that many of you already
interact with and that spans the whole
Institute if you look at our history it
suggests that this in institution is
never better than when we come together
to solve big problems and this problem
may be the biggest one of all so we hope
that some of you here will choose to
work with us on finding and scaling the
solutions thank you very
[Applause]
much now I'd like to welcome to Stage um
a Amy nordrum who's who'll be moderating
the panel um from mit's technology
review and um a selection of the mission
directors and I'll let her introduce
everyone thank you for joining us and
we're looking forward to hearing the
discussion come on up
[Music]
everyone Jo
me hello everyone good to be here with
all of you today thank you Rebecca for
the introduction and Richard for the
remarks I may nordrum at MIT technology
review and we have a rare opportunity
here to have a number of the mission
directors from the new MIT climate
project together speaking publicly about
this important work I think they've been
mostly heads down since the announcement
uh of their roles earlier this year so
looking forward to catching up with them
and hearing what they've been focused on
and also hopefully getting to some of
your questions throughout the discussion
so please do get those in uh through the
app to kick us off I would just love to
ask each of you to introduce yourselves
uh tell us your name and what project or
Mission you are in charge of and if you
could name one climate problem within
that area of focus that you think
deserves more attention and
resources okay so my name is benedetto
marelli I'm an ass professor in civil
enironmental engineering and I'm
directing the wild cards Mission and so
the wild cards by definition has no real
Focus everything is a focus and what we
try to do is to scout technologies that
have a very high potential to really
drastically change the trajectory of
climate but of course that will be also
High
risky thank you so I'm Chris canido
professor of Applied economics in the
Sloan school and I'm the mission
director for inventing new policies I
think so it's it's it might sound weird
for a professor at the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology to say this but
technology alone is not going to solve
this problem almost by definition so uh
climate change is a classic example of
an extern ity and in the presence of a
negative externality you need policy to
come in and intervene into the market to
make things better and the question is
how do they intervene into the market so
one of the big folky of of this will be
to think about new ways to intervene
into the market to bring along the
technologies that should be adopted but
aren't being adopted by their themselves
and also change consumer
firm uh Behavior if in ways that are
more uh
proclimate uh hi my name is Mio maero
I'm a faculty member in architecture and
urbanism and I'm leading the Frontline
communities um empowering Frontline
communities Mission and I think in many
ways my mission um infuses all of the
different missions that we have here and
um there's two sides to it one in the
mitigation side we want to make sure
that the clean energy economy that
there's equal and diverse participation
in that and also that the technology
invented reaches everyone and not just
the people that can afford it um so
working with Co mit's collab and other
groups within MIT we hope to work on
that on one side and then on the other
side the impacts we've seen of the
climate having changed already uh
modeling work working with the
scientists at MIT and down scaling with
engineers at MIT and really working with
industry Partners to have that
technology for modeling and scenario
building so that places can prepare uh
is a really big Focus that we need to
consider thanks M good morning my name
is Christoff Reinhard I'm a colleague of
Miu in the School of Architecture and
planning I the director of the building
techn ex director of the building
technology program and now I direct uh
the resilient cities uh Mission um why
are we focusing on cities you all know
probably the statistics uh over half of
the population worldwide is living in
cities uh over 75% of the carbon
emissions are generated in uh cities and
um sorry um
and sorry that hasn't happened to me in
in a long time and uh and a lot of our
um resources are also located within uh
cities and when we look at what MIT is
currently doing overall then we are very
good at engagement we're working with
the private sector with the public
sector and we are um engaging with
Frontline communities at the same time
we are extremely good at Urban analytics
and we are coming up with new Solutions
be it more uh innovative ways of air
conditioning buildings and what we are
hoping to do within this mission is
basically to vertically integrate
because this is something which I which
I think is really missing that we are
bringing these three different groups
within MIT closer together and within
there we are probably going be going to
focus on building first because they
have such a big part of um form such a
big part of the carbon emissions
worldwide wonderful thank you all there
is much work to be done in all of these
areas of course but I want to begin with
a few areas that we have spoken about uh
as having Common Ground between your
missions and where you might overlap
your efforts so let's start with
electrifying heating we have seen a lot
more heat pumps being sold in the United
States in recent years in fact they've
outpaced the sale of gas furnaces for a
few years now so there's progress but is
that transition happening fast enough
and what more needs to be done here and
Christof I'd love to start with you sure
I mean electrifying heating is somebody
that everybody is talking about uh as
Chris said the technology is there and
we are promoting it very heavily but of
course the tricky thing is for lot of
households should we actually Implement
heating because right now if you're
having a natural gas furnace it's
actually a bad economic decision to do
this so it's for the better of society
but it's necessarily better for the
individual so we have to really figure
out how to create policies that make
this tenable for everybody on a
technological side Elsa olivetti isn't
here but it's not necessarily even a
good thing to just uh put a heat pump in
place because we are shifting the peak
loads from the SU air conditioning for
electricity to the winter and we are
actually not really clear where that
electricity is going to come from so I
think more integrated ways of thinking
about this nobody should get uh a heat
pump without having photovoltaics on the
roof weather Rising the buildings as
well so that it makes an overall good
contribution uh to the system as a whole
yeah Miho do you want to speak to that
as well in terms of making it work for
the
individual yeah so that's been a
challenge to exactly because of what
Kristoff has been saying that um there
is this trend going towards but whether
it makes economic sense for a family to
do it depends on how old their current
furnace is and making these decisions
along the way including weatherizing the
building and Mass Save does a lot of
that there are so many resources on the
table to do it but then if you imagine
different families who don't have
necessarily the time to go through that
process where working three different
jobs and and um and so I think trying to
make sure that these Technologies when
they're available how that information
about the resources available get
communicated to different communities um
is really a big part of what we'd like
to work
on and Chris there's been as Miho
mentioned a lot of government incentives
State programs uh encouraging people to
install heat pumps so how well has that
worked and is that the best Str will it
get us all the way there what else do we
need yeah so this is a classic example
of how policy can make things worse um
and I'm going to I'm going to resist the
urge to jump on my soap box I'll I'll
I'll point you to a a Boston Globe opet
I wrote last spring on on this very
topic but the way we price electricity
is absolutely terrible for two reasons
one is we don't the cost of electricity
to generate electricity moves a lot
within a day across seasons and so on in
the typical location in the US you face
the same price regardless of what the
actual cost of generating that
electricity is the second and and most
relevant for heat pumps is we have if
you think about the cost of running an
electricity system you have all these
wires that are in place this
infrastructure that's in place and then
you're also generating electricity wires
are to an economist called a fixed cost
right they don't vary depending on how
many electrons are flowing through wires
yet we turn that to the consumer into a
volumetric charge so if you look at your
bill right now over half of your per
kilowatt hour charge is paying for those
wires so what what that means is if you
give me a heat pump today give it to me
for free I won't want to use it because
the price of electricity on the margin
is is more than twice what it should be
so it's cheaper for me to run my furnace
than it is for that heat pump so that's
a
problem um I think it also points to the
fact that and we have data on heat pump
adoption in in Massachusetts the
majority of heat pumps are being adopted
during the summer but really most of the
heat pumps my my impression is although
we can study this most of those heat
pumps are going to replace window unit
air conditioners rather than actual
furnaces so so is that a good thing I
guess on the margin that might be a good
thing since they're more efficient than
those window units but but they're not
going to lead to the deep
decarbonization that we think they're
going to lead to so this is where policy
needs to be aligned with with the
technology yeah that's a great
perspective I want to turn now to the
topic of data centers and energy and
water demand which I'm sure is top of
mind for many of you out there in the
audience and there's been a lot of news
about this recently uh there's Rising
demand uh for energy for data centers
and water to cool them of course we've
seen Microsoft recently uh strike a deal
to restart Three Mile Island for nuclear
energy Google is working with an
enhanced geothermal company called fvo
to provide electricity to its data
centers these are all really great
corporate efforts but ultimately kind of
peac meal so I'm curious and maybe I'll
start with you again Kristoff what do
you see as the most sustainable path
forward for all of society on this
issue I mean data sets are obviously
very uh critical right now for our
economy and our Innovation we need them
they're also very hard to handle because
we cannot ramp them up and down really
easily so they're really like a Sitting
Duck in a way that uses a lot of
electricity uh so from a city
perspective they're interesting because
wherever a lot of electricity is being
used a lot of heat is being generated so
thinking of innovative ways of cooling
the system and using the rejected heat
in the building sector I think that is
really an attractive notion that has a
lot to do with where we are actually
placing uh the data center so if we do
that in the upper United States where
it's cooler that's probably a better
idea than if we are uh creating extra
heat in Silicon Valley or somewhere in
the desert so there are the synergies
that we should probably think about more
as a society where where we want to
place
them and Chris I believe you had some
thoughts on this topic as well yeah and
and and it piggybacks off of what
Kristoff just said I I think we're we're
kind of being defe a lot a lot of times
when talking about data centers we don't
have to take the location as given um
and in fact they might be an asset to
the grid if we could optimize where we
place them um and that could be placing
them in low carbon regions it could be
potentially changing the contracts that
data centers sign with their customers
so right now they are very
inflexible uh but that's because when a
when when I go to buy data center time
with AWS
they don't offer me a contract that pays
me to be flexible right in in theory at
least to an academic I don't care if it
takes a millisecond longer to do my
calculations if you're a DAT if you're a
stock Trader maybe it does but a lot of
demand through the data center could be
flexible more flexible and then it could
follow load from intermittent uh
renewable generation or or move
depending on what the season is and so
on so I think there's a lot lot of space
here to think about how we can use data
centers as an asset and not just a shift
out in the in in the load for for
electricity benedetto it feels like an
area where we could use a wild card or
two what do you
think many
options some of the options would also
to completely reinvent how data is
processed and where data is coming from
and the Silicon based Technologies
eventually can also be replaced with
other Technologies so there are of
course many opportunities I think what
the wild cards will have to do is to
evaluate how quickly they can be scaled
and how quickly they can have an impact
because there are so many ideas that are
coming with uh new technologies that
have a lot of promise but we are on a
Time clock and so when it comes to the
wild cards really is understanding and
evaluating what can be scaled in a 10 to
25 years time period to have a real
impact and a tangible impact on the
climate of course also generate wealth
and be sure that everybody can benefit
from it yeah that's a tough
job okay well I want to now change over
to a topic that we all have in common
which is food and Agriculture and
producing all the food that we all eat
every day this is a really tough area in
which to reduce emissions particularly
as the global population grows and
people become more wealthier and begin
to eat more and more meat it's also a
deeply cultural topic and shaped by the
geography and the weather uh wherever
you live and the ability to produce your
own food is a very you know powerful
thing and important to uh many people so
mial I'll begin with you does knowing
all of that affect how you approach this
challenge compared with other uh other
areas I think this challenge is
exceptionally difficult because beyond
all the things that you included there's
also the cultural aspects of where where
and how farming has been done in a lot
of places I'm thinking more globally
rather than just within the United
States and so I do think that it takes a
significant amount of time from whatever
is invented in the lab to actually then
reach a global scale um and so it's a
big
Challenge and Mi I'll stick with you
because you spoke in a previous panel
about how hard it is to scale up the
kind of community engagement efforts
that you typically have done in your
work which are by their very nature very
time intensive require relationships
built over many years how are you
thinking about that now
I'm still thinking about it still
struggling um but I've had the
opportunity in the last month or so to
meet so many new faculty members that I
hadn't met before across MIT and
understanding they also all have their
networks and so then already
exponentially this has grown and I plan
in the spring to host several workshops
also with my other um Mission leaders to
really reach much more of a global
um global leaders in communities and
have having a much wider Network um
where we will find ways to still have
that kind of quality connection but um
be able to share what we're doing here
and also learn from all of the issues
that they are
facing yeah that's encouraging to hear
uh benedetto food and agriculture what
Solutions are on your mind what have you
seen out there that looks interesting
another area where I think we need some
radical new thinking well I'm very
biased because this is my area of
expertise and research but I I think
that food it could be an agriculture
would be a very very good test beds for
the whole climate project because it
brings together all the missions like uh
food and agricultural systems are
producing 30% to 35% of the whole
greenhouse gas emissions plus we have a
big big societal problem which is the
fact that we are producing too much food
effectively believe it or not but we're
wasting it too much food right so the
food that we are wasting can feed 1.6
billion people while we have almost a
billion people that suffer from food
insecurity and at the same time 25% of
the water that we're consuming goes in
food that is never eaten I just gave a
talk last week at the an anticipatory
talk for policy maker actually and it
was about what agriculture will look
like and it's going to change it's going
to change completely it's going to be an
additive agriculture right so we're
going to add two billion people and
there's not enough land so we need to
find new way to make food and we need to
convince people that there are new ways
to make food and they need to eat
different food and as cities are growing
um the amount of processed food will
increase so the impact will increase so
overall I think um the opportunity here
is to and this is why the climate
project is so important because you need
a the whole Institute to work together
toward this big thematic that go from
education to research to policy to
knowing directly from the stakeholders
what they want but also educating the
stakeholders to what they can get out of
innovation and and so I think this is
very exciting for food and the and the
wild cards would be extremely well
poised to innovating food and
agriculture particularly having in mind
uh communities that don't have access to
food but also the world South which is
going to be in their need of food as the
hot topic for uh climate change and for
population growth are there yeah lots
more to come lots to follow there it
sounds like well I do want to take an
audience question I see a couple of good
ones coming in and we'll try to get to
some of these as we go I'll begin with
the top one there giving the most votes
and I'll open it up to anybody who would
like to speak to this which MIT Clean
Energy Research domain is most right for
commercialization and Partnerships with
industry you would like to take that
one I mean I'm biased but I think Urban
analytics is something especially if we
look beyond the United States uh where
we have made a lot of progress I always
say part of the city's Mission I want to
model every building in the world
meaning that we are able to predict
energy use potential for overheating
potential for various energy saving
measures and there's this is already a
really busy place in the startup
industry and I think a lot of startups
are trying to develop good use cases but
I think usually the quality of the
energy model in the background isn't
very good so I think this is something
where MIT can really make uh in
collaboration with partners and
countries across the world World a real
fast uh effort where we provide
simulated data for free to everybody for
usage be it cities or be it um
individual startups or companies to
basically understand where in the
building sector is the carbon used where
are the opportunities to reduce the
carbon and I think this is something
that U we can start right away first off
I've heard you say this a few times that
you want to build a model of every
building in the world so just say a
little bit more about that like how do
you do that what what can we learn from
that have you started like what I don't
know what that look like I'm it's a good
tline uh I noticed um we have Model 25
cities in the world so I'm not just a
guy talking um uh and so there we've
engaged with cities the the use case has
been that a lot of cities says that by
2050 they want to be carbon neutral
because it sounds good and then most
cities have no ideas of what to do to
their building sector to realize this so
we are basically harvesting this a big
Urban data set combining them with
detailed knowledge of the building stock
and then saying this is current energy
use these are related carbon emissions
and once we have that we can also say
How likely is that a building is going
to get hotter than another building so
doing heat waves what can we do about
that and of course it just provides like
a step by step uh technologically driven
pathway what you can do and so um I
think we actually just built a model as
a prototype of 2 and a half million
buildings in Massachusetts so uh if you
sent me an email we are not making it
public but I can show the URL where you
basically see you can zoom on every
building here and we are now working
with the state together to understand
what kind of value can you gauge from
that that's so interesting uh well Chris
I'm going to come to you next with a
question about the grid uh there has
been a lot of progress uh especially in
California installing batteries that
have lowered the risk of rolling
blackouts there during heat waves but
there's still many interconnections that
need built there's a Transformer
shortage uh many renewable projects are
running into permitting delays what do
you think are the most important new
policies or reforms that we need to help
us move to a grid or to a grid fuel
primarily by
Renewables yeah I would say it it really
is about the infrastructure so right now
if you build a solar farm in some parts
of the country it will take six years to
interconnect that solar farm to the grid
like that just can't be uh it's hard to
have 2030 goals when it takes six years
uh to to interconnect uh zeroc carbon
Technologies and even data centers on
the load side it can take multiple years
before you can connect so on the policy
side we need to fix that queue uh how do
how how do we allocate costs one of the
problems with interconnection in in many
locations is the first one the
interconnect Bears the burden of the
cost so that means you everyone wants to
wait for everyone else to be first in
line and and then that just creates this
que and reordering of the queue and and
so on and then transmission more
generally so uh my we have a research
center here called the Center for Energy
and environmental policy research where
over the past year we've we've modeled
uh specific bills that are on the floor
of Congress right now to build more
transmission and look to see what that
does to cost what it does to reliability
resiliency and in carbon emissions and
our grid is not set up for a zeroc
carbon world so in the past we've been
able to move power plants to where the
people are but right now the good
renewable resources are where the people
aren't so we're going to need to move
those electrons much further distances
than we have in the past um and you have
this you know kind of cool I I don't
know why I I think I might be the only
one that finds this super cool but if
you build a bunch of transmission east
to west you actually take advantage of
the sunrise and the sunet um so that
allows your Renewables to go further
when the sun is down on the east east
coast we could be importing electricity
from the west coast and vice versa you
wouldn't import it that that far but you
get the the drift so we need to beef up
what that that grid looks like in order
to take advantage of uh all these
renewable resources that's such a cool
idea and there was an audience question
related to that on transmission and
whether some of those transmission
projects how they would impact the
wiring cost that you spoke about earlier
yeah and I think Brian Brian De brought
this up um you know again um from a
policy standpoint we we rate lines very
crudely uh when thinking when an
independent system operator who's
running a grid is thinking about how
much electricity it can move from point
A to point B the amount of capacity on a
transmission line varies depending on
weather conditions um but we don't take
that into account at all um so there are
a lot of ways that we could expand what
the the transmission capabilities of the
grid without actually building anything
and there's also technologies that can
uh better handle where the electrons are
flowing in the in the grid and so on so
that's a a I don't know the answer to
this but you could imagine um a
regulatory framework where a utility
wants to build new transmission lines
but not use their transmission lines as
uh efficiently as possible and I'm not
pointing fingers I'm just saying one
could imagine a regulatory framework
like that so that's where thinking about
how policy can can actually better align
the phys physical capabilities of the
grid uh with with what um it's allowing
the power plants and load to
do excellent thank you all for the great
questions keep those coming we're going
to jump around a bit because I do want
to get to a couple more of these Miho
why don't you take uh that last one how
do we engage this is a hard one how do
we engage public and Community Solutions
in a highly individualistic Society such
as America how do you get people
thinking differently about some of these
solutions that we
need um I mean it is starting to happen
we're seeing micro grids we're seeing
different Community neighborhoods coming
together um I think that it is it's a
difficult very very difficult question
um likely we will have to make quite a
few changes in ordinances and permitting
in order for these kinds of
neighborhoods that want to work on
something like this to come together
um and figure out how to explain really
what the economical benefit and the
societal benefit is of uh Community
Solutions and then the public sector can
play a big much bigger role because I
think a lot of issues that we're looking
at too is just like so many of these
Technologies focus on home ownership and
then a lot of the communities that we do
work with don't own their homes and so
how do we then within public housing and
other places like that also um leverage
what it is that we're working on here
it's a great Point Kristoff just maybe
to build on that I think this is where
through the missions are also learned so
many activities that go on at MIT and
last Wednesday there was a great event
hosted by Mariana aaya a professor and
dust we were in aate and worked with
various communities and in order to talk
to lowincome folks there what they can
do actually to better their buildings we
had like a three-step Approach at the
beginning we did a game all together
everybody got a budget on $9 million in
the computer and we modeled how do you
best basically uh picking from various
Technologies reduce the energy use of
this apartment buildings within a budget
and then Mariana basically took it over
and asked about what is actually
important to you as individuals and
finally a came in and said as it happens
we have here all the coupons you can do
this right away so I think our
colleagues are been doing really fun and
Innovative works and I think through the
missions we we can scale that yeah those
are examples are so useful in thinking
about these issues um all right benetto
let's talk wild cards this concept cep
is so intriguing I think a lot of
companies out there would love to have
more of this kind of innovative Blue Sky
Thinking but it's so rarely happens how
do you go about encouraging this what
are some of the conditions that help it
to take hold that you hope to Foster as
Mission director so we're still trying
to understand how we can hack the Wild
Card uh wild cards is difficult to give
you a recipe that is going to work
everywhere I would say the most
important aspect is uh uh first of all
having a very peripheral vision so to be
sure that we not um avoid um considering
some technologies that's just because
they it seems like they don't have much
sense at the beginning so it requires a
lot of understanding of the new
opportunities and but also be requires
being bold and try new things I would
say one of the major effort that we're
going to have is really engaging the
stakeholders that know about the
problems very quickly like the details
of the problems that the wild cards are
going to solve very quickly and these
are industry first of all because you
are the one that actually solve the
problems uh and the second of all is
also the communities that will be using
the wild cards uh we will have a
completely different approach whether
the wild cards have will have an impact
in the global south or what is called
the global North uh because that would
require a completely different um
landscape of scale up at deployment uh
but also it will will require to operate
with different type of margins so we
would like to focus on wild cards that
maybe have lower margin but go big when
it comes to the impact of society and
this would be mostly so Society for
their well-being right and this is
really for the global South for the
global North we're going to look mostly
at solutions that could help um mitigate
uh climate change and but a little bit
less on adaptation probably um I think
the one of the
biggest determinant for a wild card C is
that it has to happen in a very short
amount of time the inovation right so if
I think of the of the two wild cards
that we that occurred globally in the
past years are covid first of all covid
is a it was a real wild card and and the
deployment of the covid technology so
the the rapid testing and the vaccines
was our reaction to a wild card and so
those are good ways to think about how
we Scout Technologies so thinking at
technologies that are
already have a very um advanced
technology Readiness level which was for
example the MRNA vaccines which we knew
could happen but then it required really
a lot of investment
policym and also convincing people
adoption right so which was the biggest
problem in reality uh and so that would
be an example and the other example is
the revolutions that we had with the AI
uh in the past uh year or so where
really AI came I mean AI is a is a old
story but the application of AI to the
to the common people and the fact that
it became uh an opportunity that
everybody now can use to enhance their
lives so that's another case study they
were having to evaluate how we can use
wild card and how we can uh successfully
select them yeah that makes a lot of
sense and then coming back to climate
change there's an audience question here
for you about which area do you think
has the highest potential for wild cards
at the moment is there an industry or
sector that you have your eye on so
believe or not this is the question I'm
asking myself every day when I go to
work work so I don't have the answer yet
I would say
um tying in with what was said before uh
having an idea
of understanding how to build a climate
conscious Behavior Uh from PE from the
people perspective that could be a wild
card like really having people
understanding that they need to change a
little bit
um what they're doing and the need to so
far the world has really been anthrop
entric so we really thought about that
the human head was the only important
thing because we always fight we always
fought against nature right and now we
shape nature too much and at at the
expense of everybody um eventually so it
came back to us and so we need to change
also how we perceive climate and what we
need to change in our daily Behavior
without consuming less because I think
one of the biggest issue with the uh
climate conscious behavior is that
everybody perceive it oh we need to
consume less and I think that's not the
answer because that will decrease the
economy in reality right so we simply
need to find the balance between uh what
we consume and the impact that it has on
our world so that would be one of the
focus for for sure the White cards yeah
I want to take one more audience
question here it's getting uh the most
votes the topic of water and land use
keeps being avoided how do you all
balance these resource demands with our
enthusiasm for energy as you say we're
all consuming well it's avoided because
the directors are not here that is true
it's we don't care about it it is also a
mission yeah but each of you obviously
there's a lot of intersection with your
areas so who wants to speak to that well
I can start I mean one of my research
Focus F fi sorry is U food and
agriculture so land is part of it and uh
and also water so I think we will focus
extensively on be sure that we are
becoming good Steward of the water and
land and that the new technologies will
will will have a good impact on on those
two aspects yeah and look climate change
I talked about negative externalities
climate change isn't the only negative
externality out there so um when we
think about policy impacts we're not
just looking at one benefit we're
looking at the full Suite of benefits
and uh so you know sometimes the you
could have co- benefits sometimes you
could have costs that are incurred
because you're trying to fix a problem
over here
and making exacerbating another problem
so that's certainly within the realm of
of how we think about policy policy
impacts winners and losers that's going
to be front and center on in the policy
mission for sure and and land use and
water is just one of those local
pollution is another right um you know
as we decarbonize can we decarbonize in
a way that actually benefits on the
local pollution side as
well you're each early in your process
here and you're as benedetto said you're
kind of setting out your priorities and
proposals and thinking a lot about which
issues to tackle first uh and you're
charged with accelerating you know
scalable Solutions in each of your areas
so I'm curious how are you looking to
evaluate all the projects and proposals
and phone calls that I'm sure are coming
your way these days what are some of the
criteria you have in mind to make sure
the things that you do back or put your
resources behind are scalable and
practical and can have real impact in a
short amount of
time anyone who' like to take that talk
about that all the time uh and it's very
hard be in this to evaluate what we are
doing because even if we say for example
we want to focus on retrofitting
building it's not us who are going to
retrofit every building in our free time
so in a way we have to try to understand
what of our recommendations that are
being put out are being adopted in the
world and uh based on that hope
um see that we have an impact I think
it's also very practical if we are
creating uh certain resources and we see
that um millions of people hopefully are
using this um then I think that
constitutes
success it's very difficult yeah and
everybody claims every carbon I think
every uh CO2 ton of CO2 that's being
saved there are four or five people that
say it was me the homeowner the
installer the maker of the heat pump
everybody gets a
ton complicated I think for me is really
evaluating whether the solution is
scalable because I think one of the big
problem with climate Tech is to be sure
that it can be scalable has economically
sense at at scale and can be scal in a
short amount of time and that's where I
really eventually like to engage with
the industry because that's where we
need to see whether there's already an
infrastructure present or if some of the
industry leaders are ready to maybe
change some of their um efforts and some
of their fori to focus on these new
scale up opportunities that they have so
that they can make money but also having
a positive impact on climate me I'd love
to end with you can you tell us about a
community that you've come across that
demonstrates the kind of climate
resilience or preparedness that you're
hoping to Foster in more places as you
look across all these missions and areas
that need a lot of work how much time do
we have there's we have one one and a
half minute there's so there's so many
of them around the world that are and
and and some of IT addresses the
previous question of land use too is
like there are some communities that are
moving
um from the coastline and really
understanding land use wise where should
we be building and Kristoff has a
statistic of how many more uh locations
we'll be building and how much more
housing we need to build glob globally
and so where are the decision- making
points for that and then also being
courageous to make decisions to move
when necessary um and then there are a
lot of other places that have um started
building in things even to their Parks
right so how do you then design your
Park so that it then prevents uh
flooding for the rest of the
neighborhoods around it and there are
many different ways and many different
places that um the people are starting
to work on on this and I think
one series of win-wins would be finding
ways where we can for example for
schools for
shelters you need the shelter where then
there is a hurricane and you need people
to evacuate to it so then it's great if
it's off- grid and it's able to still be
sustained in those extreme conditions
whereas at the same time making a
school into a system that is able to
operate like that you are reducing
energy loads and then also teaching
students about how all of this is a
win-win situation alog together and so I
think there're multiple places that are
doing that too and I've gone over time
and so I'll stop here well I think
that's a perfect note to end on uh thank
you all for your excellent questions I
wish you all best the best in your work
we all need you to succeed no pressure
and uh thanks for your time today thank
you very much
[Applause]