Let's get right into it. I have there's
a bunch that I want I want to try to
catch up from yesterday. Um, you've just
turned in paper number one, but I'm a
big fan of trying to have people do work
um like do the daily work in the class
thinking towards what the major
assignments are. So, now I have to tell
you about paper number two. Um, for
paper number two, you're going to
identify a specific learning
environment. You're going to identify
uh like the physics department at MIT,
your middle school, your elementary
school, your high school for world
languages department, um an afterchool
program you work with a library, but
something like very specific where you
know not not not not you know like
schools in general, a place um and
you're going to um reflect upon a
particular education technology and you
either going to recommend or not
recommend that they adopt this
particular technology. Um so part of the
argument that you'll read about in the
in hopefully through the first half of
failure to disrupt um is that while we
can get a general sense of the efficacy
of different technologies, we could we
could say, you know, this class of
technologies seems to have better
research evidence behind it than this
class of technologies. There's really
nothing that anyone has ever invented
which is like really every school or
every department ought to be using X. um
all those decisions have to do with um
particular times, particular places,
particular people. Um so what you'll
have to do is um identify some
technology, kind of classify it like
what genre is it from or what is it
like? Um what are its potential
benefits? What are its affordances? What
are its limitations? And then what is
the characteristic of the place that
you're recommending it to? And do the
sort of benefits and needs and
characteristics of a place all line up
such that you recommend adoption? Um or
do they not line up such that you don't
recommend adoption? Um it's a it should
be a memo sort of directed to a
particular stakeholder, a department
head, an assistant superintendent for
curriculum instruction, the library
director, the president of the Boys and
Girls Club, whatever it is. I think uh I
had one student who was building a
program for Ukrainian refugees last year
and he basically wrote a memo to himself
um which was fine. on pages 74 through
76 in failure to disrupt which at least
in the hard cover I think it's the same
in the in the paperback um there's a
section called what a department head
should do which is not exactly this
assignment but like a pretty close
worked example um it's sort of me like
working through um so whatever I I think
that ex that specific example is about
using intelligent tutors so you in math
class so you should pick something other
than that specific example um for you to
use um but uh um you know you you should
think about doing things like, you know,
um assessing the claims that the
developers of this technology make,
seeing what kind of research evidence
there is around that. Um seeing under
what sort of context this seems to work
or not, what kind of enabling conditions
are required, whether or not those
enabling conditions exist. Um we'll talk
about all these kinds of things over the
next few weeks. Um so that uh um so you
don't have to understand what you're
going to do right now, but I want you to
have a sense of this assignment. Um it
for some of you, you will pick a a
context that you can work with that you
actually know a ton about. Um that or
like even if you didn't know something
about it, you would be able to like like
oh the you know the head of Aereroastro
is a good colleague of mine. I'm going
to just go ask him what he thinks about
this or like whether what capacity are
and things like that. There may be other
things that you sort of need to
fabricate um which you would be allowed
to fabricate. You just have to like
somewhere stipulate along the way that
you're fabricating them. So I know you I
have to be like um you know the
characteristics of the world language
teachers in my high school are this and
you might not actually know who the new
staff are and things like that but um uh
but but that would be okay. Um
uh there's pages written about what
you're supposed to do in the syllabus,
but that does that give you like a
general sense of the target that you
should be thinking about over the um I
don't remember I don't even remember the
exact day it's due, but it's like
roughly a month from now. Each
assignment takes about a third of the
class. So um that all seem good. Great.
Um,
uh, anybody have any questions that they
want to ask about that
assignment? Okay. Um, let's wrap up
MOOs. So, last time we were talking
about MOOs sort of made these three big
bets. Um, that they could provide new
pathways into higher education for
people with limited access. Um, that
they could reorganize, disrupt, unbundle
higher education. They could create like
new structures across higher education.
And then the one that I was most
involved in is that they create a new
datadriven science of learning. Um I
maybe part of the second one but maybe
sort of um you know maybe was clearly a
bet for some actors less so for
nonprofits more so for for profofits was
that you could make a whole bunch of
money doing this. Um that has not panned
out as well as some people had hoped. Um
so here's an announcement today um that
Accenture is purchasing Udacity. Um, so
Udacity was the company that was founded
by Sebastian Thrun. Sebastian Thrun is
one of the people who taught this intro
to AI class that like made the whole MOO
phenomenon start. Um, people are not
exact. Um, uh, Accenture is like a
consulting firm and they're going to use
it to do sort of AI training. So, so
this is so this is not like transforming
all of education. This is doing like
pretty wellestablished executive
education. Um, and there may be ways
that you could do executive education
better with the MOO platform than you
could with other pre-existing
technologies or strategies or things
like this, but like this is not going to
profoundly change the way executive
education unfolds. This is just like,
you know, somebody who sells executive
education buying a potential provider of
it. Um, in the notes here, it says that
uh their best guess is well, they is
that they they uh um a deal fell through
with an asking price of about $80
million. And so they nobody knows for
sure, but they think that this deal was
probably about that size. Um but uh um
Udacity took in $300 million um of
investment. So I I don't go to the Sloan
School of Management like some of you
do, but I'm pretty sure that if you take
$300 million and sell a thing for $80
million, you didn't do it right. Um or
or at least your investors don't think
so. Um, but I think that's some, you
know, to me it's a great indication of
where these partic where this like class
of technologies have settled out. Um,
which is like $80 million is a lot of
money. If any of you if any of you were
offered $80 million for a business,
you'd probably be like, "Yeah, that's
pretty I'll take $8 million. That seems
great." Um, uh, but what what it's
accomplishing is like a very um a very
wellestablished existing thing in the
education system. You might say that um
or a way that I've phrased it in the
book is which I which a colleague of
mine Mim Emo really came up with um is
that uh these technologies did not
disrupt education systems. They were
domesticated by education systems.
Education systems said like you fit
there like you little company you would
be pretty good at doing executive
education. Why don't you do that? Um
that is not at all what Sebastian Thrun
was envisioning when he said that there
might be only 50 educational
institutions in higher education in the
world. Um um but to me this is like this
is like very representative of how I
think education technology often works.
Um we very rarely build things that are
totally transformative and we can often
build things that are like useful in
pretty specific contexts. Um
uh I had I and lots of other people had
really hoped that there would be very
new kinds of science that would be
possible. Um, so we had never really in
higher education had a system where you
just had all of a sudden millions and
millions of people doing online
learning. Um, and all of that was being
recorded. Um, so when I got hired to
help sort of build the research
infrastructure for Harvard X and MITx
and edex, uh, you know, one of the most
exciting things was like all of these
people are signing up and they're all
clicking and we're recording everything.
Um, what you know, you might think of
like when you went to think think of all
of the things that you did in school.
Probably even better as an example, like
think about all the things that I did in
school. Um, so I filled out zillions of
worksheets. I typed all kinds of papers.
Like all that stuff just ended up in my
mom's attic and was eventually thrown
away. Like the whole records of my
learning were lost. Um, but young people
today have their records of learning
stored in all of these online platforms.
If you saw what millions of learners
were doing um in really granular,
detailed ways over days or months or
years, shouldn't you be able to figure
out all kinds of exciting things about
the science of learning about like what
are the most effective teaching
techniques? How do people learn best?
All all kinds of things that might be
helpless. Um and it proved to be much
much harder um than people expected. I
would say the core reason why it proved
to be really hard um is that you can
have terabytes of data about what people
click and still not really know what's
going on in their heads. Um what what
what people click on on a screen or what
they add as an answer to a problem
doesn't necessarily tell you all that
much about the cognition that they went
through to get there. Um it doesn't tell
you a whole lot about which parts of the
instruction that they received to that
point helped them do that. There was a
whole for years there was a whole class
of papers that just sort of correlated
everything to everything else like how
many times did you click, how many times
did you log in, um how many units did
you do, how far apart they were, how all
these kinds of things and basically like
there was a whole a whole series of
papers that were all published that were
all along the lines of people who do
more stuff do better than people who do
less stuff. Um like if like people who
clicked more often in the systems,
people who like watched all the videos
did better on the problems, people who
did all the problems were more likely to
pass the course, people who logged in
more time, people who spent more hours
were more likely to pass the course.
Like none of that is interesting. Like
you didn't need a $60 million research
enterprise to figure out that doing more
stuff helps people learn. Um there are a
few things that we did um that uh and
I'll talk about them more as the
semester goes on that tried to go beyond
that. Um there were a bunch of us who
are really interested in this idea that
like um uh a bunch of people have done
research that suggests that the
attitudes that you bring to a learning
experience really matter for your
success in that learning experience. Um
how many of you ever heard of stereotype
threat? Um so stereotype threat is this
idea that if we tr if we trigger
stereotypes that people have um as they
enter a learning environment or as
they're in a learning environment um
those stereotypes can negatively impact
them. Um so if you ask people to
describe their gender before a math test
then people who identify as girls are
more likely to do less well. Um you
could do the same thing in different
racial configurations and other kinds of
things like that. Um, and the way that
you can inoculate people in theory
against some of these kinds of things is
by emphasizing how they belong. Um, is
by saying like you belong in here, like
you have a space, you deserve to be
here. And so, um, you could you could
imagine that if people go into a
learning environment and they're like,
I'm not sure if this is for me. Then
like you're sort of like you're paying
attention to not feeling like this is
for me and you're not paying attention
to the learning and then a test comes
along and you don't do as well on that
test and then that makes you feel like
you belong even less and then you're
feeling kind of more unbelonging and
then you don't do as well and you get a
negative cycle. You can imagine the
opposite where you feel like oh I
definitely belong in this learning
environment like this is going to be a
good growth experience for me and then
you like are focused on learning and
then you do better and that makes you
feel like you belong and on and on. Um,
so the we were really interested in
these entry points. Um, and um, almost
every MOO that basically every class at
Harvard MIT offered had a little
precourse survey at the Have any of you
ever taken a class that has like a
little survey at the beginning of it for
your mukes? If you did it for Harvard
MIT, I probably wrote it. Um, and uh,
especially if you did it a few years
ago.
Um, and uh, so we started randomly
assigning people these little
interventions. Um, we would like you'd
answer a bunch of questions about what
you know about the topic and then we'd
say things like, um, write a letter to a
future student. Oh, I hear one was a
values affirmation. Um, pick from this
list which of these values are really
important to you. Um, and they I don't
know, they could be like loyalty,
personal growth, family, all kinds of
things. Um, write a short letter to
yourself about why taking this class
aligns with those values. Um, so asking
people to just like write for a few
minutes about why we do other things
about belonging, write a short, write a
short letter to a future student in this
class about why they should feel like
they belong, things like that. Um, and
our hope was is it would have this kind
of like, you know, trigger this positive
cascade at the beginning of the class.
You feel like you belong more, you feel
like you value it more, you do better,
you pay attention more, you do better,
you learn more, all those kinds of
things. Um we started by trying these in
just a couple of classes. Um and the
even if we were picking a couple of
classes, we were still doing like some
of the largest experiments that had ever
been conducted in higher education. Um
you know, we could pick like a couple of
classes that might have 10,000 people
that were actively participating in it
and doing our our things and things like
that. Kind of a lot of folks. Um so here
are four things that we tried. Um one
was plan making. um having people write
down exactly how they planned to
complete the class, like when they were
going to do it, um who was going to help
them, how what they were going to do
when they get stuck, those kinds of
things. Um this value relevance things
that you just described. Um and then
mental contrasting with implementation
intentions is basically like what are
the kinds of things that might make you
stuck um and how would you get unstuck
when you encounter these things? um when
we did them in one or two classes at a
time, they worked pretty well. Um so I
don't know how familiar you are with
statistics, but the beta parameters are
the one you look at. So this plan making
things, people were were four percentage
points more likely to finish the class
if they got the intervention that they
didn't. Um that's huge. That's that's
you know, if you ask you ask people to
do something for five minutes at the
beginning of the class and they're 4%
more likely to finish it. Um just like
the cost benefit of that is off the
charts. That's fabulous. Um, uh, this
one was getting people to do more
activities, getting people to persist
longer, getting people to complete
better. Um, all these kinds of things.
And some, you know, some of these
studies were huge, you know, 5,000
people, 3,000 people, 2,000 people. Um,
that's pretty good. Um, we then were
like, we were we were pretty excited
about ourselves. We're like like we've
come up with some stuff that like
doesn't cost anything and really helps
learners. Um, let's go ahead and take
these things and use them in all of the
classes. Let's let's let Harvard and MIT
let us test things in every class. Um
and it is not uncommon in um educational
research that if something works in a
little space that when you try it at
much bigger scales it doesn't work. Um
that is a very frustrating finding but
also very common finding and that is
exactly what happened to us. Um so we
took these things that would which you
know again would have been considered
like huge studies in education you know
randomly assigning 4,000 people to to a
treatment or not is is enormous. Um and
we did it with a quarter of a million
people. Um which like a lot of learners.
Um and basic and basically everything
that we had tried and wrote a bunch of
papers that said hey these are pretty
good ideas we had to be like actually
they don't really work that well. Um,
and
uh, I part of the problem was they would
uh, they would they appeared to work in
some classes but not others and we
couldn't make any sense of why. Um, part
of that is that it's hard for us to know
a whole lot if you're we did it in about
250 classes and it's hard to know the
difference between those those different
kinds of things. Um but we like you know
we we listed characteristics of a lot of
classes and we put them into big AI
models to try to figure out why and all
these other I mean you can read the
paper. Um but uh it was sort of an
enormous effort and at the end of it you
know a thing that we we we had lots of
people in there but we weren't able to
identify things that worked particularly
well. Um and this was pretty consistent
across this enterprise. Um in fact to my
knowledge there's virtually no one who's
doing research on Harvard or MITx
Arvidex or MITx classes anymore. Um and
uh um and so this was the sort of third
of these big bets. um you know the the
hypothesis was that vast new you know
there are people like Peter Norvig and
uh um who's a woman um Daffhne Coller
who formed Corsera who thought that um
datadriven education would be very
similar to datadriven uh medicine like
just like the human genome project sort
of revolutionized a datadriven form of
medicine that you know Corsera edex
could revolutionize a data driven form
of the science of learning um and we we
knew a lot about what people clicked but
we never really got much more data about
what was going on inside people's heads.
Um the other sort of huge issue is that
if you really want to do educational
research that studies like how to help
people learn better, you re you need
variation in the course that's deeper
than what we were attempting. Like you
need to be able to do more than just
change a little thing at the beginning
of the course. You have to be like,
well, here's one good way of teaching a
class. Here's another good way of
teaching the class. Let's, you know,
let's try both of them. Well, it turns
out that like it was very difficult to
go to faculty and be like, will you make
two versions of this course um so that
we can test some of these different
ideas in them? Um because people had
barely enough time and resources to make
one version of the course and so forth.
Um so like the other two big bets mukes
um they for the most part uh didn't pan
out. Um, and I think if you if you if
you go back 10 years from now and read
the um, you know, the op-eds that David
Brooks and Thomas Freriedman were
writing in the New York Times about the
totally transformative impact of online
education, um, people would be pretty
surprised 10 years later to find out
that like, you know, it's good for
things like executive education um, or
helping people earn a second master's
degree, which are not bad things to do,
but again, there's sort of smaller
components of it.
Um, I've thought a lot over the last
couple years about like, okay, so if
we're not going to totally reform the
educational system with independent
self-paced online learning, um, what
else might we do? Um, well, you know, so
for instance, I've told you that, um,
already affluent, already educated
people are reasonably likely to persist
in online courses. Um, well, there are
all kinds of already affluent, already
educated people who work in the public
interest. There are people who are
teachers. There are people who work in
public health. There are people who work
in nurses. Um lots of them work in
contexts where they don't have a lot of
learning um after their college degree
um or their advanced degree. So what if
we created online courses um that you
know a good fraction of people would be
able to persist in and finish um that
would be able to help them. Um there was
one course that we built um called uh
launching innovation in schools which
relates to uh um uh uh um the stuff in
iterate that you read a couple classes
ago. Um, and in our course we make them,
we make all of our, not everybody did
this, we make all of our courses openly
licensed. Um, so we we we make it so
that it's creative common. Anybody can
take our things and do anything they
want with them. Um, there were some
folks in Ukraine before the war who had
translated our courses into Ukrainian
and put them on a Ukrainian platform.
Um, and for a while at the beginning of
the war, I don't know if this is still
true, teachers still had to like get
reertified, do training and things like
that. Um, so some some enormous fraction
of the Ukrainian teaching force had at
least, you know, signed up and plausibly
taken one of these courses and things
like that. Um, so there sort of, you
know, for us it was kind of a proof of
concept that people, uh, um, can benefit
from some of these kinds of things. Um,
with Mariana's adviser, uh, Jose, we got
really interested in, um, what if the
thing you want is not really big MOO
providers, but very small local MOO
providers. Um, so there's an
organization called Edrock in Georgia in
Jord um, Jordan run by the Queen Rana
Foundation that makes mukes in Arabic
for people in the Arabic world. Um,
there are like lots of providers that
offer courses in the local language of
their environment that are tailored to
the particular environments that they're
in. Um, and
um, these tables are unreadable but
except if you go in them and look at
them. Um, but you know, there's evidence
that you could actually do a better job
getting people from more diverse
educational backgrounds if you offer
them in local languages, with local
providers, um, with the with the topic
area and content areas that would be
interesting to people in those local
places. Um, so what we needed was not
sort of like, you know, giant global
elite driven online learning. Um, but
maybe maybe another pathway be with like
lots of distributed local online
learning that was particularly par, you
know, tailored to people's cultural
interests and labor markets and civic
spheres and needs and things like that.
Um, and there might be, you know, um, I
mean, I always try to sort of remain
open to the idea that that any of these
technologies could have new people that
come along and refresh the ideas around
them. Um, but we should we should
probably think of those claims with like
a pretty high bar. You know, if someone
comes along and says they have like a
new AI powered MOO platform or something
like that, you you know, now you could
be like, well, let me tell you what the
research suggests about the original MOO
platform. Um, what some of the
limitations were, what it accomplished,
why it tackled some big problems that
turned out to be really hard. Um and uh
uh why you know and then and then you
know what what is it that what is it
that a new effort would be able to build
on top of that? Um those are some of the
things I want to tell you about MOOs.
What other things struck you about them
or what questions did you have or um
what what have we discussed in the last
few classes that fit or don't fit with
your experiences?
I mean, I guess just a general question
is like what is the real motivation for
like higher educational institutions to
want mukes to exist considering that
their entire business is based off of
them? Not it was it was it's weird,
right? Yeah, like like people got super
enthusiastic for a long time about
digitizing faculty labor. Um I I would
you know so what were some of the things
people would have said at the time? Um
in 2013 people would have said something
along the lines of for particularly for
the last 40 or 50 years but maybe for
100 plus years um there's a class of
universities that brags every year about
how many students they don't serve. um
you know around around around this time
every year you know um Stanford and MIT
and Harvard will publish statistics
about how many applicants they rejected.
Um but one of the things that they could
do with MOOs is start bragging about how
many people they served. Um for the for
the faculty who especially early on who
got who got millions of people to sign
up for their courses, it was
exhilarating. Um it was incredibly
exciting to be able to say like you know
I mean a nan argawal used to say you
know if I said if I taught uh 61 at at
MIT for the next 40 years um you know I
I still couldn't have as many students
who showed up in the first round of this
class that I offered and things like
that. So that was exciting. Um I do I
have a hunch that um that when people
were afraid that this might profoundly
change the education landscape that
elite universities wanted to be in front
of it rather than behind it. Um like as
soon as there were some commercial
offerings that were available. There
were folks who said like man um we
really ought to have um we ra have a
nonprofit alternative. We ought to have
universities are involved in this. Um I
mean another really important structural
factor is that
um university revenue sources are
constantly under threat and they're
constantly going up. Um so health care
costs are constantly going up,
technology costs are constantly going
up. Um and if you're a state university
like across the United States, we've
been dramatically reducing the amount
that like the taxpaying public support
schools and asking students to pay more
tuition and so forth or a higher
percentage of their tuition. Um, and so
a bunch of folks thought they could make
money doing that. You know, not like
make money in the sense of putting in
their pocket, but um, make make money
uh, doing that. So those were those are
some of the kinds of reasons um, that
people got really excited about it. Um,
but uh, but yeah, in in retrospect, in
some ways, you're like like what, you
know, why why do I mean at the time
there were definitely plenty of people
who are like, you want to take this
thing that we sell to people for $80,000
a year and give them to them for free?
like what kind of plan is that? Um or
you know for 35 bucks or other kinds of
things like that.
Um, one thing that I was thinking about
uh with like respect to like presenting
books as like helping underserved
communities and stuff is like the issue
of like space cuz to me I feel like um
like having been in like a pretty
underserved like high school and stuff I
was like okay well but even like in a
position of higher education space is a
very big issue for a lot of these spaces
where it's like you simply can't just
sit at home and even if you have access
to a laptop or something to do that and
it was like I I just wanted to know if I
mean this bike kind of also like just
connect to the larger social aspect of
it but I was wondering if they had if
this even came up when they were talking
about like the accessibility of these
systems there I mean there I used to
joke to something like anyone even the
poorest peasant in the most remote
African village who has highspeed
internet and a basic understanding of
matrix algebra can take the introduction
aeronautics class. Um I was like yeah
there actually are not that many
peasants who have who meet both of those
criteria. Um but um u it it was always
the case there was a very famous case of
there was the article in the New York
Times about him was called the boy
genius of Ulan Bar. Um so there was a
student who was in Mongolia um who got a
perfect score on the first MITx class
and was admitted to MIT. Um and and this
was sort of taken as proof that like
anybody anywhere in the world can get
access to our courses and we're going to
be able to find the you know the best
high school students and bring them to
MIT. Well, there are some more details
to the story. One is the principal of
that school in Mongolia is as I
understood at the time the only person
from Mongolia to have graduated from
MIT. Um so there was kind of a
connection there. Second, um there was
like a an advanced physics class that
was offered that used the material, but
there was a posttock who I think was at
Stanford or Cal some elite school in
California who went and like studied
with these kids um for a bunch of
months. Um so one thing you could say is
like oh we just need to get muks into
every school and then we'll help people
find their way to MIT. The other thing
you say is like we just need MIT grads
being the principal of every school um
and then we can get people coming to
MIT. But this kid, his name was Batouch.
Any he did a bunch of education classes
in MIT. He was a remarkable kid. Um, he
used to watch two videos at the same
time when he was doing these classes.
Um, it doesn't make any sense, but
there's a great news article that shows
his little setup of him watching two
videos at the same time. I He's clearly
a smart guy. Um, but it was really
important to the narrative of MOOs. Um,
that uh look look at look at how far
into the periphery that we've reached to
sort of bring people into the core. um
you know and so folks like me who are
writing papers are like I'm not like
that is that is neat that is a true
story is an awesome kid that is not
representative of the of the broader
system that we've built here um and uh
yeah you know people really want it was
interesting people really wanted these
things to be democratizing
education but then when it was pretty
obvious they weren't they were still
like yeah well okay we'll just use them
anyway um I I I know I helped support uh
um I did an evaluation of the supply
chain management program which was one
of the first programs that said um do
half the program online. So you have to
take and pass sort of proctored tests in
four or five online classes and then
we'll give you half a degree credit and
you come to campus and finish the other
half of the degree. Um and uh it was
kind of you know um there are a lot of
good things about it actually. So, one
is supply chain management is a
relatively new field and so there aren't
a lot of universities around the world
that offer it and MIT is pretty good at
it. So, this was a good way of like
having more people be able to do it. Um,
it's a relatively small program. They
don't have a ton of faculty. So, you get
twice as in theory you could have twice
as many people come through campus if
they do half the stuff online and half
the stuff here. And there were actually
some really cool findings where the
folks who the f the way they did it is
they kept an an in-person cohort and
added a a uh an online cohort that
showed up with the inperson cohort in
January. Um, and we did some surveys
about how both groups felt in terms of
their connection to MIT. And they both
felt really strongly connected to MIT.
Actually, in sort of funny ways, like
the on-ampus people were like, we've
been here all year, like this is our
place. And the online people were like,
we've been taking these classes together
for three years. Like, this is our
place. So, they both felt really
connected in interesting kind of ways.
Um, the grades of the online folks were
actually slightly better um at the end
of the first cohort, although who knows
if that would have persisted um into
time. Um but the uh the only people who
persisted through the online courses
were people who already had jobs in
logistics industries were getting their
second degree were already affluent.
They're disproportionately guys. Um
there's a whole line of research that
really focuses on um people's ability to
conduct self-regulated learning,
people's ability to sort of like persist
through difficulty and and things like
that. And so you talk to learners and
they would talk about how they, you
know, took their lunch breaks and they
studied, how they took weekends and
studied, how they stayed up late at
night and they studied and p, you know,
and in especially if you think about it
through like an individual sort of
psychological perspective, you're like,
"Yeah, those are all great qualities."
Um, another thing we realize though is
like like if you're studying like in the
evenings, you're probably sherking
family responsibilities. Um, and in lots
of cultures across the world, it is way
easier for guys to sherk family
responsibilities than it is for women to
sherk family responsibilities. So, in
some in some ways, like self-regulated
learning was the same thing as sherking
family responsibility. Like the thing
that you'd study from a psychological
perspective as self-regulated learning
would be sherking family
responsibilities from a sociological
point of view. Um, and so again, just
giving us more ways to think about as we
create learning environments, who will
benefit from them, what are the enabling
conditions to help lots of people from
lots of different kinds of backgrounds
and places in society be able to benefit
from them, things like that. Um,
uh, I think something that stood out to
me was their business model of the mix.
I think I don't like really understand
it because I think for me as someone who
went to international school in Africa
and I would say it's what maybe like top
five like in my country or something and
pretty big like in Africa like I've
never heard of any like MIT or Harvard
course like in my life. I'd probably say
none of my teachers have heard about it.
And I think it made me wonder like who
exactly like they're targeting because I
don't think it's necessarily like young
high schoolers like trying to like get
into college because what I did realize
when I MIT and when I Googled like how
to do linear algebra or like all these
things is then I would see like MIT
courses and MIT open courseware and all
these things pop up on YouTube. But then
back in high school when I didn't know
what like linear algebra if you don't
know what linear algebra was, how are
you going to search for a linear algebra
course? Yeah. Yeah. No, that's a that's
a terrific example. I mean, the business
model, I mean, Daffhne Coller and I
think in one of her first talks refers
to it as a blue ocean business model,
which is basically, you know, the the
potential addressable market is like six
billion people in the world or
something. You know, anybody who has got
an internet connection, if you, you
know, if you can sell $35 certificates a
couple of times, you know, to six
billion people over and over again, you
can make a lot of money doing that. um
the um and there were efforts to try to
you like create institutional
connections. So like CS50, who's
Harvard's computer science class, has a
whole program to help high schools adopt
CS50, like to adopt the online CS50
materials in their in-person
instruction. Um so there's some fraction
that you, you know, hanging out in
Africa would have encountered this
course and just decided to take it. Um
there's some sense that your school
might have like made you know connected
with one of these sort of formalist.
There was another great story of uh the
guy who founded Stripe was from St.
Louis um and uh was like I want to live
in St. Louis and he's like I can't hire
any developers in St. Louis. There
aren't enough developer. I'm pretty sure
it was St. Louis. I might have the town
wrong. Um so so when Mukes came out he
was like oh let's just offer let's offer
CS50 in St. Louis and we'll start like
building infrastructure for this. and
like they started some pilot program and
it like completely filled the library.
Um you know there just hundreds of
people who like with a little additional
support. So they ended they ended up
like creating a community space for it.
So you use the online materials that
that was I think there were models like
that to try to bridge the gap that
you're describing um that it's not
realistic to just you know like have
kids encountered these classes and
decided to get excited about them and
things like that. still um almost all of
those intermediate bridging layers
require human capital and humans are
super expensive and then you sort of
erase the kind of financial advantages
of uh um that the muks were sort of
promoting in the beginning. Lots of
online programs have found this like
it's pretty cheap to offer online
classes um but a lot of times people
just drop out of them. if you want them
to not drop out of them, you have to
hire coaches and adviserss and, you
know, assistant instructors and things
like that. And then you've just ra, you
know, you sort of brought back all the
costs that you got rid of from teaching.
Um, is there like a statistic on how
often state universities create mukes
versus like
these IVS schools? Because the thought
occurs to me that maybe the reason why
it doesn't matter if like Harvard or MIT
or Stanford puts out a MOO is because
you're not coming to Harvard or MIT or
Stanford just for the information. Yeah.
Because obviously what's associated with
that is kind of like this title and this
class ratification thing that isn't
accessible through a MOO. So it doesn't
matter if like the entire world has
access to a course that's meant for
learning because part of what you pay
for and part of the real target audience
of these universities is people who want
the the title associated well there
there's a economist at Stanford who
wrote kind of a cool paper that says the
way you have to understand elite
education funding models is that they
like roughly offer their education for
free in the hopes of having a very small
percentage of people pay very large
amounts of money for their education
later. Um, like basically we we
subsidize people's tuition in all kinds
of ways. So we at least we subs even if
your tuition feels really high, your
tuition is subsidized far beyond what it
actually costs to educate you. And then
hopefully 1% of you will give tens of
millions of dollars back to MIT later.
And so this person was trying to sort of
think about like what you know how like
given that's actually how elite
universities are funded um why do you
know like what effect will muks have on
those kinds of relationships? But there
were plenty of public institutions. Um,
uh, one re, you know, one reason that
public institutions got really excited
about it is their job is to serve as
many people in the state as possible.
Um, and if you're in a big, you know,
you're in a geographically large state
like Virginia and you're the University
of Virginia in the middle of it, like
it's pretty hard to help people in the
Tidewater, um, and in the southwest area
and in the DC area and other things like
that. Um, so, you know, Michigan made
big investments, Texas made big
investments. Um there there were lots of
flagship public schools um that uh um
probably the most distinctive one maybe
not in MOUS but just in online learning
generally is Arizona State University um
which has really transformed itself
through online learning into a global
institution which they really see as
like as missiondriven like how how do we
just have as many people as possible in
Arizona beyond Arizona get access to the
learning opportunities we create. Um and
there there's something very noble that
I that I find about that. Um, I wanted
to follow up on your first question um
about the business model. How have
for-profit universities sort of reacted
to MOUS um since their entire model is
trying to serve as many underserved
people as possible and just like
charging them a lot and the fact is that
a lot of them are also online. Yeah.
Like the University of Phoenix, I think.
Yeah. University of Phoenix, Kaplan, um,
uh, uh, Southern New Hampshire
University, Western Governor's
University. I mean, I think there were
some like Southern New Hampshire
University would have really
welcomed in in some of their reactions
were like, "Hey team, this is not new."
Like this is exactly what we've been
doing for decades. So, so a weird thing
was that there was a status flip in
online learning. In 2010, online
learning was a very low status activity.
um it would have been primarily
conducted community colleges, for-profit
colleges, state colleges and overnight
instantly Stanford, MIT and Harvard made
it an elite activity. Um they instantly
radic there's actually all kinds of
sociological theory about this where um
the the middle class people have to sort
of like avoid the activities of lowerass
people and pursue the activities of
upper class people and lower class
people pursue the activity of people but
upper class people can actually pursue
the activities of lowerass people
because their status is safe. Like every
once in a while though trends come along
of people who like dress like trash or
you know sort of like um you know other
kinds of kinds of you know adopting
adopting sort of lower class activity.
So there's some sociological theory that
sort of is behind some of that. Um but
it was a hu it was it was one of the
things that was sort of striking about
that moment. So a bunch of these
universities were like give me a break.
We've been doing this forever. I I gave
a talk at Oakland University, which is
kind of a community college in Michigan,
and they and they were like, you know,
they'd be like, why are you using video
like like text is so much better? Like
we've been doing this for years. Like we
would like lots of people can't download
the video. Like bandwidth is not that
good. And there's not really a benefit
to watching someone say something versus
reading what they would say. Like what
are you all doing? And be like, you
might have a point there. Um because cuz
uh because they were doing something.
But on the other hand, um if you're
really fired up about online learning,
um and Harvard and MIT and Stanford and
John Hopkins in Michigan are like, "No,
online learning is cool now." Um there's
ways that you can use that to raise your
status to legitimize your activities and
other things like that. So, so existing
players um there, you know, but and they
weren't they weren't really
pursuing similar kinds of markets for
the most part. I mean, there's there
were a handful of MOO efforts that tried
to um help people earn bachelor's
degrees, and they were mostly totally
unsuccessful. Um, and there weren't even
really that many of them were that were
tried, which is that is kind of like the
sweet spot of most, uh, for-profit
colleges. Um, uh, which are, you know,
which in which in many respects there's
a lot of evidence that they're just a
disaster for lots lots of people don't
finish. People finish with a lot of
debt. Um, Trese McMillan Cotm wrote a
book called Lower Ed where she described
them as a negative social insurance
program. Um, where on average people are
worse after finding their ways into them
than they were beforehand. Her book
Lower Ed is pretty fabulous. Um, all
right, let's make sure that we get a
chance to talk a little bit about part
two. Um, which is algorithm guided
learning at scale. So it sounds like a
bunch of you this this we're heading
into new territory for me which is like
well how raise your hand if in your K12
experience you did something that you
think was algorithm guided learning at
scale like you sat in front of thing
okay this like this is by far the
highest percentage that I've had in this
class thus far so it's not so we're so
so I think um it you know I don't know
five years ago people like a handful of
people would have done it or would done
a little bit as a curiosity but like
clearly if you all know what is and
things like that like this is becoming a
sort of much more mainstream activity um
in uh in people's classes. What what did
you what was your sense of them? Um so
so Dana's sense was that they were like
kind of pointless and she could just
have her mom do them for her. Um what
were what were other
people's sentiments about them? Emily?
Oh, I thought well for me like in high
school we used this thing called me bean
where it was like you take an assessment
and it would kind of like rank you like
where your reading and your vocap skills
are at and then like you kind of log in
every week to do it and like learn and
progress I guess. And I thought it was
like it was useful for us because like
even though we had like regular classes
or honors classes for English like
within that class like everybody's vocab
like was different varied a lot and it
was like it was very hard for like the
teachers to to figure out like what kind
of vocabs to teach like what materials
to provide for us cuz like everybody had
different things and like a lot of times
we were just in class like I know this
word and like you just stop paying
attention but then other kids are like
well I have never heard this word. I
hate to like learn it. For us, it was
like it was cool, but then like one of
my friend, she like assessed it and then
she she was she started off in like
highest like level ranking and then like
after she finished they just bumped her
back down to level one. So then like she
just like went back to like learning
like blue green in like high school and
sophomore year. That sounds like a
flawed system. Yeah. I will tell you
that when I was in the fourth grade, we
had a similar version of that. Um, they
were called SRRI reading cards. It was a
like a file box. Um, and it was a bunch
of like short stories or non-fiction
passages that were arranged in order of
difficulty and you would just like go
and read one and answer a bunch of
questions about it and if you got them
all right, you'd go on to the next one
or a couple later and if you got them
less well, then you like went back to
earlier ones or your teacher helped you
or something like that. Um, so there
were so this this I mean it's something
that will come up, but this notion that
like oh what would it look like to like
figure out what kinds of learning
experiences people need in that moment
and try to meet that need instead of
teaching everybody the same thing at the
same time um has been compelling for a
long time. It sounds like it was
compelling for you at least until the
system sort of freaked out and made you
learn kindergarten words again. Yeah, we
had something with like reading as well,
but I think one of the issues was we it
was not nearly as consistent because
like I mean it was meant to be done like
once a week or twice a week like a lot
of the examples we saw in class but like
it'd be like oh like whenever the
teacher like didn't want to deal with
kind of like bring in the car and like
okay do this. So, it was so inconsistent
that I was like, "Okay, well, like I
don't exactly know if I'm improving or
I'm staying stagnant because like I
haven't seen this program for two weeks
now." Good. You said two things there
that I really want you to hang up hang
on to. Um, one is you said something
which Larry Cuban would have said about
television things or things like that,
which is that the designers of this
program have a vision, but the teachers
have a different set of needs. So, the
teachers are like, "I need to do some
grading today or I don't feel well.
We're going to do this thing." which
which would have been the exact same
thing as like rolling into television
and putting on a a movie for people to
watch. Um and also um that these systems
have some kind of pedagogical model
behind them and their effectiveness may
have to do with how well that
pedagogical model is implemented. Um, so
if people so if a if a system is
designed to be used with some
consistency, you know, twice a week in
six week chunks or something like that
and you don't use it with it with with
that that program design in mind, it
might not accomplish what you wanted to
do. So it's not just a matter of like
downloading the software onto kids
computers. Um, it's a matter of getting
whole systems to implement them. We're
going to look at some research I'll show
you on uh on Monday. I don't know if
I'll make you read it, but I think I'll
just summarize it for you. Um about some
of these intelligent tutors that are
really focused on um letting people work
on problems that are challenging for
them, even if it's from material that is
from earlier in the year, previous
years. Um and that system only works if
teachers actually let their students do
that. Um if teachers force their
students along sort of against the will
of the system, then the system doesn't
do what it's supposed to do.
I think like I guess like elaborate a
little bit why on like my experience was
the way it was was like not only were
teachers like your experience just like
doing it randomly like they weren't
incorporating it into like their
curriculum like they were just like
slapping it on top of it and like when
students already overwhelmed with like
after school activities and things like
that it then like and it was like more
of a math based thing than an English
where like you kind of see some of like
the benefits early on. Um, so it was
like just kind of thrown in there but
not incorporated in the curriculum and
then it's just like essentially became
low priority and like for a lot of
people. So if a so if a system so if a
system it like depends on some hybridity
if it depends on some things that are
happening in class and some things are
happening online like if those two
pieces are not fitting together it's not
going to accomplish what the system
wants to accomplish. Um, all right. I'll
give you a funny little piece a little
personal piece that is behind some of
the technology. I explained some of this
a little bit. Um, but my father has more
or less done one cool thing in his life.
Um, which was to which was to get a fake
person into Princeton. Um, he he uh he
and his frat buddies um invented a
person named uh uh J. David Osnot. Um or
Joe Dnot or Joe does not um and uh they
like found a friend of theirs to take
the SAT for him. They found some friends
at a frat house in Michigan to make up a
fake transcript. They got one of them to
go and do an interview and things like
that. And they got this fake guy into
Princeton. Um, and they eventually had
to admit it. Um, and it's and uh at some
point somebody was taking one of them to
uh um to the admissions office to go
explain to the admissions officer that
they had gotten a fake person into
Princeton. And this guy started asking
them a whole bunch of questions about
how they took the SAT. Um, and it turned
out this guy worked for Educational
Testing Services, which was also um in
Princeton, New Jersey, and was trying to
figure out some of the sort of test
security things that were going on
there. Um, so as I mentioned last time,
one of the things about one of the ways
that you can make tests more secure, um,
is that you can make it so that tests
are of equal difficulty, but they use
different questions. Um, so, uh, you
know, the the students in Boston are not
taking the exact same test that students
in Hawaii will take six hours later or
students in other parts of the world or
things like that. In order to be able to
do that, you have to be able to um
create a mathematical representation for
any given item of how difficult that
item is. Um, what people basically
decided to do to um to solve that is to
model the difficulty of items as
logistic functions. Um so on the x- axis
you have this thing which is sort of a
proficiency score like roughly kind of
how hard in any domain this would be. Um
and then the probability of a correct
answer. So these are sort of three
different possible distributions of
items. Um so for instance um which of
these items would be more difficult
would be the most difficult for
individuals with proficiency score of
one.
So people on the blue have almost 100%
probability of getting this one correct.
So it'll be the green one. Um so this is
the probability answer get. So for um
for this particular item um people with
a proficiency of one are about 50%
likely to get it right. These are the
people who are about um you know 90% to
get it right almost exactly likely to
get it right. Um so that seems like a
useful thing to know about an item,
right? Um now you can figure out like oh
let's give them the the blue item first
and then the red item and then the green
item or something like that. Um um not
only that, but if you model it this way,
you can also figure out how
discriminating an item is. um which is
how likely is it that people around a
given proficiency are are likely to get
it wrong or not get it wrong like sort
of how um how how tightly clustered are
the answers versus be or how spread out
are the answers going to be. Um uh so
you know wherever you see you know a a
around one um you would imagine for this
one um that like a whole bunch of people
with scores sort of slightly less than
one um would do would be would be less
likely to get right and then more likely
to get it right. Where sort of around
here because the lines are are um more
horizontal there um just about everybody
who gets those items are going to be
right. So it's not going to give you
that much information um about uh about
how well people do. Another way that you
could do this is like draw a
distribution of where you think a group
of learners would be. Um, you know, so
this is like the various skill levels in
a class and the sort of distribution of
probabilities of people getting it
right. Um, and you can see that like the
item that sort of like traverses through
the heart of that group is going to be
the one that's best at like efficiently
measuring the proficiency of that group.
Um, you don't have to totally understand
all the math or all the ideas about
this. probably like the intuition that
you need to develop is in the 1980s a
bunch of people came up with like a
pretty good statistical toolkit for
figuring out how difficult an item was.
Um the first thing that they did with it
was make different kinds of tests um for
sort of test security purposes. But
almost the next thing they did with it
was start developing systems that use
computers to evaluate people's
performance on an item and then figure
out like what is the next good item to
give them in a sequence and all the
things that you're describing Khan
Academy all other things like that. Um
they may not use this exact statistical
toolkit but they all use something
that's sort of similar um to
that. The reason um you know and one one
piece I mean part of the reason why in
the book that I take a couple of pages
to describe item response theory to
people is again to try to give the sense
like it's not magic um it's not like
some impossibly difficult thing um that
that computers and scientists like on
the very cutting edge of mathematics
have figured out like this is like a
pretty wellestablished set of tools that
we've studied for a long time um if
people come up with new AI powered
intelligent tutors we should absolely
absolutely be able to ask the question
like, well, how are they really
different from the intelligent tutors
that we've had um for decades in various
formats? How how different are they from
the box of SRR(I) reading cards um that
I had when I was in the fourth grade?"
And there may be some ways that that
they're different, in which case we
would expect much better outcomes. There
may be some ways that they're quite
similar um in which case we might not
expect that many differences. Um but the
the heart of the reason why people
wanted these kinds of tools to exist was
personalization. Um that that there was
that that that a goal that you can get a
lot of people around is the idea that
wouldn't it be great if every learner
could have an experience that's tailored
um to their to their own personal needs
and interests and experiences and things
like that. Um I noticed I don't know
around 2008 2009 2010 that lots of
people in education got interested in
personalization. A thing that was weird
to me is that there were people who are
interested in personalization who
disagreed about everything else. Um so
there would be people who are like
really into um school choice and
traditional instruction and sort of like
conservative curriculum values who are
you know um who like typically were more
associated with people on the political
right though not always in America um
who got really interested in
personalization. There were also people
who were who were educational
progressives who were really interested
in alternate projectbased school kinds
of models. They also were talking about
personalization. Um, and I thought to
myself, okay, um, if these groups who
don't agree about anything, um, are all
using the word personalization, they
can't possibly mean the same thing. Um,
because they have really different
values and so they probably don't agree
about this either. Um, oh, this was a
slide that my colleague, uh, Dan Meyer
put together of this is some technology
from the 1970s. Um, you know, right at
the dawn of personal computers where we
were trying to like give kids math
problems, evaluate them, give them
harder problems. This is a slide from
2012. But the thing that you can see is
like there's 40 years between these
pictures um and they are strikingly
similar um in their setup and their
outfit. Like this is a this is one of
the longest you know trying to
personalize education with computers is
one of the oldest enterprises in
educational computing. It is one of the
main things that we've been trying to do
for 40 or 50 years.
Um if there is any single paper that got
people extremely excited about this um
it was called the two sigma problem the
search for methods of group instruction
as effective as onetoone tutoring um
where this guy Benjamin any of you ever
heard of Bloom's taxonomy
um it's this uh little pyramid that has
sort of different kinds of uh um
learning activities instructional
activities you could do. Turns out that
Benjamin Bloom did more than one thing
in his life. He didn't just make this
taxonomy, but he did other kind of
studies. He didn't actually do these
studies. He was reporting on some
doctoral students of his um that um were
studying tutoring. And in these tutoring
studies that they did, you just get like
astronomically good results. Um they,
you know, they said that they could get
results two standard deviations better
um than what uh what you typically find.
That's the two sigma problem. um a two
standard deviation improvement in
education is is impossibly good. Um most
of the things that we do um get a tenth
of a standard deviation or a hundredth
of a standard deviation improvement or
something like that. We usually get
really small gains, but tutoring works
really well. I mean to some extent you
could be like I'm pretty sure like
medieval lords knew that tutoring works
pretty well. Um the reason why we don't
do it is it's enormously expensive. But
what if instead of medieval lords hiring
governnesses to tutor their students um
like what if computers could do that? um
what if what if what if you know
computers which are relatively
inexpensive um could do this kind of
tutoring. So this has been a dream. This
was you know Daffhne College dream,
Scon's dream, lots of other people's
dream as they're imagining um sort of
what's possible here. Um there were
around 2010 there were probably two
different groups of people who describe
person who who made personalized
learning sort of central to their ideas
and their philosophies. Um, one group of
people were really interested in what
they call blended learning. A formal
educational program in which a student
learns at least in part through online
delivery with some element of student
control over time, play, place, path or
pace. Um, some of it may be supervised
uh and then and then some of it at home.
Um, the alternative view was called
connected learning. Socially embedded,
interest driven, oriented towards
educational, economic, political
opportunity. Connected learning is
realized when a person is able to pursue
a personal interest or passion with the
support of friends and caring adults.
Um, so what what do these what else do
these two ideas sound like?
Yeah. Yeah. Good. So, so you could have
said cognitive load theory and situated
learning. You could have said Dian
Thordike. You could have said
instructionism and constructionism. Um,
this is like the reoccurrence of these
two themes over there. like there's
always two ideas um and they're and
they're always being reformatted and
they're always getting connect with each
other. So this is like the the Dewey and
Thike version of how we're going to make
personalization come to life in the
world. Um we'll talk more about
connected learning in a week. Um but
mostly what we'll talk about today is
what this blended learning um might look
like. So one Khan Academy doesn't have
this anymore. Um but they used to
represent um their mathematics content
in K through2 as a knowledge map as kind
of a galaxy. Um one of the things that
this blended learning version of
personalization requires is you have to
know all of the stuff that you want
people to learn in advance. So if you
want to create an algorithmically
optimized pathway for people through a
set of learning materials, you have to
know what that what those learning
materials are so that you can write the
algorithms that drive them through it.
Um that's very different from this
connected learning view which says we
should figure out what kids are really
interested in and help them create
personal pathways through whatever it is
they want. Um you know so you could
imagine that the goal of Khan Academy is
to take some individual kid and figure
out the fastest most efficient way for
them to traverse pathways um through
this kind of thing. People were were
very compelled by that model. Um
partially you know it's interesting they
were sort of contrasting it. Um, a lot
of time people will will sort of
critique what they call the factory
model of schooling. Um, which is that
like students come in in cohorts,
they're sort of stamped at the same
time, they're move through the same
materials despite all their individual
differences. It's not really true. Um,
but there are a lot of folks who will
say that schools were sort of organized
around factories in order to generate
factory laborers and things like that.
And there are certainly ideas um about
how we use time and other kinds of
things like that um that go across
institutions and society. This is this
is a representation from a keynote um oh
sir Ken I'm forgetting he has he's the
most popular keynote on uh uh on TED um
the most po I still think it's true the
most popular TED talk um that was ever
written somebody will have to look up
Ken and figure out who I mean by this um
but uh I don't know if this is actually
from that or sort of a follow-up
representation of slide um so then the
question is like um does the does per
does this sort of blended learning model
have a kind of like truly individualized
thing or are you just kind of like
stamping each child with the same stuff
in their own rate? Um like they all you
know they all still are going to get
kind of stamped with these materials but
maybe they'll get stamped through the
factory um at their own individual path.
Um Ken Robinson Ken Robbins um Robinson
Sir Ken Robinson the uh people make all
kinds of crazy claims about these
systems and sometimes I like to share
these crazy claims 10 years later um
because they sound sort of silly
afterwards. So in 2009 um Klay
Christensen who was one of the people
who who defined blended learning wrote
this book called disrupting class. Do
you in the business school do you does
do you study still the theory of
disruptive innovation? like is that a
thing that was like crazy popular a
while ago and I think it has sort of
faded but um they applied this idea
called the theory of disruptive
innovation and they said in 2009 they
made the prediction um that by 2019 50%
of all grade 6 through 12 courses would
be online that they would cost a third
as much to deliver um that your school
system would cost like about as third as
much to operate as it does right now and
they would have better learning
outcomes. Um, how many of you were in a
school where 50% of all of your classes
in secondary school were online or
predominantly online? Yeah, zero. Pretty
much didn't work out that way. Um,
Sebastian Thrun, the the quote that Dana
saw was up there. Um, Salan had an
extremely popular TED talk called Let's
Use Video to Reinvent Education where he
sort of described this vision um where
kids would sit down in front of
individual terminals. They would learn
at an algorithmically optimized rate
through mathematics content. They still
might do things together like a teacher
might come and collect students who are
stuck in the same thing and remediate
them together or take advanced students
and do projects with them or things like
that but the heart of their mathematical
learning would be individual. Um there's
one guy who's actually I think probably
the most wrong of them um who won the
2013 TED prize. He got a million dollars
um for this idea that uh you don't even
need schools or educational systems. If
you just give kids laptops they can
teach anything by themselves. Um and uh
he had this whole program called the
hole-in-the-wall program where they put
computers in public spaces in in
Southeast Asia. Um anyway, there like
there are millions of parents who live
through the pandemic that can confirm
that kids with laptops cannot teach
anything to themselves.
Um South is interesting to me because
there are millions of people who have
watched his um 2011 TED talk about this
model. there are many many fewer people
who read an interview that he did in
2019 with District Administration
magazine. Um so District Administration
is like a little trade magazine for
superintendent. Um in between um
starting Khan Academy in 2019, he built
his own school called the the Khan Lab
School. Um it's a private school. It's
in the Bay Area, California. It costs 20
or $30,000 or something like that to go
there for a year. But it's basically his
laboratory. Like he can sort of
implement any model he wanted. He can
pick his own faculty. He can pick his
own curriculum. He can recruit whatever
students he wants. Um, and he does this
for a few years. And he says, "Now that
I run a school, I see that some of this
stuff is not as easy to accomplish
compared to how it sounds theoretically.
It's taken me and the Khan Academy
longer to realize this, but not everyone
can easily move to a mastery based
self-paced learning model overnight.
That's hard to do. There a bunch of
efficacy studies for that type of model,
and they're robust, but change is hard.
More recently, we're seeing that if
students put 30 to minutes to an hour
per week or one class period per week
towards softwarebased self-paced
learning, schools will see a 20 to 30%
greater than expected gain on state
assessments. That's exciting because
that's a dosage that's very doable in
mainstream classrooms. We tell schools
to give students 30 to 60 minutes of
Khan Academy per week with teachers
doing traditional curriculum four days a
week and you're going to get dramatic
improvement. You'll get the best of both
worlds. Um, so this is like a pretty big
step away from let's reinvent video with
education. It's it's saying like instead
of reinventing education with video,
let's do practice problems one day a
week. Um and uh you know again you can
think about like is this disrupting
education or is education domesticating
the system. But there's something which
struck me about this argument which is
like I think I've heard this before. Um
and one of the earliest places you can
find it is in 1994. Um so there are a
group of folks at uh Carnegie Melon um
who took a bunch of computers um that
had online pract digital they wouldn't
have been online network they would have
been digital practice problems brought
them into in the Pittsburgh public
schools um and said to the teachers hey
teach regularly three days a week and do
this two days a week and apparently for
most part the teachers were like eh
we'll do it one day a week um and uh
they got you know um the experimental
classes outperformed students in
comparison classes by 15% on
standardized tests and 100% on test
targeting these objectives. So like
roughly the same order of magnitude kind
of gains at Khan Academy slot. So
anyway, one of the ways that you could
frame that um is that with like 10 years
and $150 million of philanthropic
investment, Salon learned what you could
have learned with a trip to the library.
Um uh which is that like they're already
existing models for how you can
incorporate intelligent tutors and
practice problems into what you're doing
and they work pretty well. I'm curious
to know so we discussed that like this
individualized
has many benefits. Um, but I'm curious
to know if there's any studies that
show particular subjects they might be
more effective or not. That's great.
Yeah. Yeah. Um, many um it you it really
mostly works in math. Um uh the the
evidence for the current EV the current
evidence for for base for reading is
very weak. Um and we'll talk we'll show
more examples of that and read some more
papers about that for next class. Um but
when when we try to so here's the trick.
When we try to evaluate these tools um
you don't want to look at any individual
study. A because any individual study
can be wrong. Um and be well maybe
that's the main reason. Any individual
study can be wrong. Um so what you do is
you do what's called a meta analysis.
You look at groups of studies. You say
like what are all the studies that have
been done with intelligent tutors in
math? What are all the studies that have
reading? And generally speaking, the
only places that we
find consistently more positive things
which are not hugely positive is in
math. Um what complicates that a little
bit um is that some of the some of the
strongest studies and evidence for
mathematics have been more recently. Um
now one possibility is that that's a
fluke. Another possibility is that we're
figuring stuff out. So you sort of have
to decide to yourself like do you want
to average over the whole length of
studies or do you want to sort of
reinforce your ideas based on more
recent things? I'll make an argument
next class that actually like some of
the recent studies in math seem to be
pretty robust. Um people try this stuff
in early language acquisition. Um
Dualingo I think has some evidence that
they can teach you about as much in
Dualingo as you learn in a first year
college class. Um although you should
probably note that like you really don't
learn that much in a first year college
class in the language. Um computer
science uses tons of things like this.
Probably many of you who've done
computer programming with cat soup and
things like that. They probably have
sort of hinting and other sorts of
things that are that are baked into
that. um doesn't doesn't seem to be very
involved in later language acquisition.
People don't use it that much in science
or in social studies. Little, you know,
a little bit in like chemistry, physics.
Some places have some practice problems,
things like that, but not about like the
conceptual um understanding, more about
the sort of procedural fluency kinds of
things. Um, and so they they definitely
seem to, you know, they they what they
require in addition to these like item
response theory models which figure out
how difficult an item is, is it has to
be able to be autograded and there's
only certain kinds because it has to be
able to instantly it has to be able to
instantly assign you what the next item
is. Um, and so the only way we can do
that is we choose items um where we can
be pretty confident that a machine can
can ascertain whether or not you've done
it correctly. You can do that in any
field with multiple choice, but multiple
choice is kind of it's good for some
things. It's kind of boring. Oh, I was
just going to ask like when you said
that it's good with working with math,
like I guess you sort of answered it
later in your speech just now, but um
what do you mean by it's good with math?
Because there's a difference, a really
strong one between procedural fluency
and like conceptual understanding. And
when I was thinking about writing this
thing, I actually loved Yeah. And the
reason was because like my math teachers
were trying really hard, but it was like
boring. And Il was like something I
could use where you like don't have to
do the same grade. You can like go past
your grade and then you learn a bunch of
procedural stuff and you feel like
you're so smart or whatever. But that's
not true because procedural fluency is
not it's not mathematics. It's definit
Yeah, it's not really math. I mean a
riff that I'll give you a little bit
later in the semester. So in the the
common core state standards for
mathematics um describe mathematical
modeling as five steps. There are five
things mathematicians do. Um they find a
problem in the real world. They arrange
that problem in some kind of structure
like an equation or a table or
schematic. They resolve the computation
in that structure. They make a claim
about how the answer relates to the real
world. So it's like 47 board feet or 47
kittens or 47 acres. Um and then they
explain their reasoning. Um, our
autograders can only assess one of those
five things. Um, our autograders
basically can only assess whether or not
you like address the computational part
of things. They basically don't work for
the other four. Um, if you use
mathematics
professionally, the like the only value
you have as a human being are in the
four things the autograders can't
evaluate. Like if you use mathematics
professionally, you probably have
machines compute all the answers of the
things that you're doing. um the value
that you as a human bring is in like
figuring out what problems are
interesting and setting them up and
explaining them to other people and
putting the answer into some kind of
context. So I think you're absolutely
right. Now what do we mean? What do we
when we say it improves math? Um almost
always what we mean is that in a
randomized control trial um people in
the control condition get one um set get
get some average score usually on an
annual state test and people in the
experimental condition get a higher
average score um again on the same state
test. That's what we usually be mean by
math that works by by having a thing
work in math or any other subject or
things like that. We might not use a
state test. We might use some other
particular evaluation or things like
that. But that's almost always the way
these things are evaluated. And if those
tests those tests are called math tests,
but they don't test you on everything
that's important in math. Um, and we'll
get into that more as we go along, too.
So, you've identified a sort of crucial
issue. Let me try to give you a few
other things to send you on your on your
way with. Um, there is a wonderful book
by Morgan Ames called The Charisma
Machine. um which studies uh the one
laptop per child program. It show it
studies a particular implementation in
Paraguay which was kind of a cool
country to study um because like you
could you you basically can like know
everything that's happening in Paraguay.
It's kind of a small place. Um and and
Morgan was embedded there. Um she argues
that there are sort of two kinds of
stances that people can take towards
technology. One is the charismatic
stance. The idea that like these
technologies are going to be new and
different and transformative and that
the future will be brand new and
different because of these things. And
that's what Salo Khan sounds like in his
TED talk. Um an an alternative stance is
the tinkering stance, which is what
Salan sounds like, you know, sounds like
um in his district administrative uh
interview. Um that existing systems
domesticate new technologies, that a
pretty good guide for the future of
schooling and education technology is
the past. Um and it's not that we can't
make things better, but that making
things better is hard and it takes a lot
of time and involves sort of building
capacity as community. You could think
of um failure to disrupt is basically a
celebration of the tinkering stance um
which you don't have to agree with but
the but the one of the hearts of the
argument is that charismatics don't
really help education systems. Um making
huge promises that we can't deliver on
is not helpful. It diverts resources
away for whether they could be most
useful. A much more useful thing to do
is to be real realistic with school
systems about what's possible. to accept
the fact that usually the things we
improve are are only in some subjects
but not others and not even in the
entirety of those subjects but only in
part of those subjects and only for
certain kinds of students in certain
kinds of contexts. And it's still worth
pursuing those things because the way
you make education systems better is you
just like relentlessly try to improve
little bits of them by a little amount
over and over and over again. If you do
that long enough they get better. Um but
uh if you want you know the the
underlying argument behind the whole
book um is like stop trying to disrupt
things and instead take you know accept
the limits of what can be accomplished
with education technology but also
recognize that even if the improvements
we can make are small small improvements
compounded over lots of students over a
long period of time really matters.
Um I want to say briefly and maybe I
won't finish this but um personalization
was a pedagogical idea but it's also
connected to sort of broader political
economies. I think I sort of first
brought this up when we talked about
instructionism and constructionism too.
Um that these these pedagogies can be
aligned with values. The instructionists
say learning is hard. The
constructionists say learning is natural
and easy. um that therefore schools
should be disciplined, rigorous,
controlled, schools should be free,
democracyinducing. Like there are values
that get associated with these things
and there were values that got
associated with personalization. In
particular, the emphasis on the
individual as like the main unit of
analysis when thinking about how to
improve schools. Um to me, it's not at
all clear that that's right. So, one
thing that people thought about a lot
and this related to muks and intelligent
tutors and things like that is folks
have said like it's crazy how many
different things we ask teachers to do.
They need to design assessments, design
lessons, grade assessments, give
instruction, coach people, provide what
the British call pastoral care, which is
like taking care of people and making
them feel good and helping them when
they cry and put on band-aids and things
like that. Why on earth would we expect
an adult to be good at all those things?
Um, like what if some people are just
really good instructors? Like what if we
just have these rockstar teachers like
Sal Khan and Sebastian Thun who are just
better at doing direct instruction. Why
are we asking every teacher in the
country to be able to explain math when
Sao Khan is really good at explaining
math? Um and then you know we could
unbundle that part of their work out um
and instead just have them focus on the
things that can't do which is putting
band-aids on kids and grading their
feedback and talking to their parents
and those kinds of things. So not not
crazy at the start of it. Um people have
taken this idea even further which is
something like what if we just unbundled
schools entirely like why do we pack all
these different functions in schools? Um
why don't we have schools do things that
they're um partic you know why why don't
why don't we let people gain learning
experiences where they want to. Um there
is a great leftist thinker named Ivan
Illich. We're going to read some of his
book, Deschooling Society later, which
was written at the dawn of personal
computing as an incredible prediction
about the future of learning online.
Totally extraordinary. Um, but he was
very taken by the ideas of this guy
named Milton Friedman um who's a very
famous economist um who believed really
strongly in the power of markets. Um
that governments weren't really good at
solving problems, that markets were
really good at solving problems. Like
what if we got rid of schools and just
had people engage in a kind of
marketplace of learning activities? Like
what if we sort of unbundled the
different functions of schools? Like why
do you have to take math and English um
and physical education and sex education
from the same institution? Like why
don't you just let people buy those
learning experiences from wherever they
want to? Um this is the horseshoe is
here because this is like part of the
arguments where sort of people on the
left people on the right suddenly found
themselves in this sort of strange
convergence um around personalization.
Um maybe maybe I'll pass this just to um
so the idea like the pedagogical ideas
of personalization got connected to a
broader political uh project which is
enormously successful in the United
States particularly in conservative
states right now of trying to um
refashion school systems with less of a
focus on schools and much more of a
focus on individual students. Um
uh a very popular idea um among people
who advocate for this sort of thing is
to say like why do we give monies to
schools to educate people? What if we
took those that money and gave it
directly to students? Um uh sometimes
these systems were called vouchers. Um
like don't don't send people to public
school, give them a voucher to buy any
school they want. Um it turned out the
word voucher was extremely unpopular. um
and like evoked a a voucher that you
would get uh like in an airport when
your flight is canceled that doesn't pay
for your hotel and things like that. Um
for a while they experimented with this
idea of like student backpacks um like
the money would go into a student
backpack but that evoked this idea of
like backpacks full of cash which was
kind of unsemly. Um so the so the term
that that students right that folks use
right now um is uh to fund students
instead of systems. Um give money to
individual students. These are all the
states in 2023 um that passed or were
considering legislation that would say
we're going to take your property taxes.
We're not going to give them to schools.
We're going to give them to individual
kids. Um and the individual kids can
then use those dollars to buy whatever
public school they want or to buy a
parochial school or to buy pay more
money and buy a private school or any
kind of things like that. Um were those
funds given to all students? Uh or was
there a criteria? The idea the ideal
model is that everyone would get them.
um like if like if you believe in this
sort of free market system um the only
way public schools should exist is if
they compete against the market compete
in the market for other kinds of
schools. You can also imagine you don't
even need schools like what if you
bought your math from Khan Academy and
your health class from CVS and your
language class from Rosetta Stone and
your sexed class from the Big Valley
Creation Science Museum and your English
class from the National Writing Project
and things like that. Um and you know
this is like a broader political vision
of what schooling could be in the future
that online learning um enabled and to
some extent um parts of it are
enormously successful. I would say the
pandemic because people basically hated
online learning as a whole sort of threw
cold water on a whole bunch of these
things. Um but um a thing I want us to
keep coming back to as we talk about
things like personalized learning um is
that they are they can they can be
construed as pedagogies but these
pedagogies are almost always connected
to like broader political movements um
about how we organize schools. Um the
most political question you could
possibly ask is how should we raise our
children? Um in some ways it seems like
an extremely technical question um but
it is a deeply moral value laden
question as well. Okay. Um, we will
continue this uh little bit and say some
more things about it and uh look at some
more well we'll probably get pretty deep
into the evidence in the paper that you
read um trying to get at some of the
questions that Mari asked before of like
like what is the evidence base for how
well these things work some of Alvo's
questions like what does it mean to work
we'll do a bunch of that with
intelligent tutors um on uh Monday um
have a wonderful weekend I look forward
to getting and reading all your papers
and if I can help you with anything let
me know thanks everybody