okay uh this is a talk about one Topic
in the linear alge book that that people
have
appreciated uh and that's the four
fundamental
subspaces so in doing it we'll
understand better what a Subspace is and
these four are associated with a matrix
so we start with a matrix and I want to
describe its colum space and its row
space those may be not new to you the
null spaces of the Matrix and it's
transposed that superscript t means that
the transpose exchanges the rows makes
them the columns and the columns become
the rows so that's a trans space so have
two matrices they each have a column
space and a row space so four
fundamental subspaces and then this
great first fact about linear algebra
about the row rank equaling the column
rank so a matrix just has one rank well
let's go just just to say where this
these topics apply the most in a for for
square Square matrices where you have
maybe 12 equations in 12
unknowns M and N the the the row count
and the column count are the same those
are normal in physics and Engineering
you're trying to find the stress on a
structure or there there you have a
square Matrix that's usually invertible
well the four fundamental subspaces are
still there but two of them are empty
the null spaces I'm thinking this Matrix
is invertible so the null space is only
the zero vector and same for the
transpose
so that that solving ax equal B is a
separate and and fundamental problem
here are the more
statistics like regression like leas
squares and data science now so many
applications so I thought data science
is so big that it would be worth
focusing again on this case where a is a
rectangular Matrix the rectangular
Matrix couldn't have an inverse on both
sides because because on one side you
put m byn m by m and on the other side n
byn it can't be the
same and but there is something called
the pseudo inverse that that's a little
Advanced but you'll see what it's about
so we're we're in the data science world
oh and I thought I'd show a picture the
big picture of linear
algebra before and then you'll see it
again when you know more about it but
this is the picture that we're aiming to
understand the the column space is up on
the top right and the row spaces on the
top
left and again for an invertible Matrix
those that's the whole space that's the
whole space but for for data science
matrices we have null spaces and those
are the
two with a capital N for null
space uh and you'll see what those are
so that they complete the picture this a
just a lovely picture of the the
subspaces associated with the Matrix a
okay so I'll you'll see this again when
we know when we've gone into each of the
four so here's the first the column
space of a matrix so I have to take an
example so there's a matrix that has two
rows and three
columns and we'll find the four
subspaces for that
Matrix okay so the first one is the
column space so what does the column
space mean if it's all so the columns
are column vectors 14 that's a vector in
two-dimensional space 25 is a different
Vector 36 is another Vector all in
two-dimensional space and we take their
combinations all
combinations of V1 time the First Column
V2 * the second V3 * the 3 that's a
fundamental operation of linear algebra
multiplying a matrix by a vector and
notice that
I don't do it the dot product the
standard way I do it the linear
combination way writing this keeping
keeping vectors in the
picture combination of of that and we
want to find if I allow V1 and V2 and V3
to be any numbers all numbers for all V1
V2
V3 each each choice gives us a point and
the each which is in in two-dimensional
space here because these are vectors or
have two
components and if we take all
combinations all the v's possible that
will fill up a plane and in this
case there's only the XY all the vectors
are in the XY plane and those
combinations will just fill the plane
because 14 is in a independent direction
from 25 actually just the combinations
of 1 14 and
25 will fill the plane you've got to see
that you got to picture that in your
mind the vector 14 points somewhere the
vector 25 points somewhere else and the
combinations of those two give all the
vectors in between and all the negative
vectors because the v's could be
negative numbers so the first two
already fill the whole XY plane and so
that's the column space for this Matrix
is the whole plane so that's kind of you
know an extreme case we we got the whole
XY plane and and as it says at the
bottom the first two columns are already
in different directions they would have
their combinations would produce a whole
plane just with the first two and the
third is a little
extra okay
good for the column space so next space
for this same Matrix is the row space
but I like that letter C and I don't
want to introduce a brand new letter if
I don't have to so what I do is
transpose The Matrix transpose means the
Matrix gets turned on its side and the
14 was the first column and now it's the
first
row and so now I have a a different
shape Matrix it has three rows and two
columns and now I'm taking combinations
of
those and what do I get that here here's
a good example I have two columns two
vectors A1 and A2 and they are in
threedimensional
space so one vector in three-dimensional
space is just along a line and if I took
all the mul If I multiply by anything
I'd get the whole line but it would be
just a line but now I throw in the
second column that by itself would give
me a line in another Direction but when
I take all points on one line plus all
points on the other line I fill a I fill
a plane a two-dimensional
plane I nearly said the whole space but
that's
wrong so the the row space here is a
two-dimensional space a plane inside
3D these these all these columns have
three components so they're vectors in
threedimensional space so we're in the
the space we live in 3D but the the uh
A1 and
A2 and their combinations fill a plane
in that
space that that so the this is the
second of our four
subspaces and and you you can read below
when I'm taking negative combinations
that gives me the vectors in the
opposite direction they can V1 and V2
can be any
numbers decimals fractions whatever so
here's a picture of this space I like
this picture I think it's got just about
the right number of vectors to show you
the
combinations this is only whatever it is
25 combinations or something uh no just
20 so we have 20 points but there that's
enough I think to visualize the whole
plane is if if our a if we take a
fraction of those we fill in that inside
but also we take three times them and
four any number times these particular
vectors and that'll they'll go outside
the
the part I've drawn so I've drawn a part
of the row space of the Matrix
combinations of the rows and I've drawn
drawn in marked out 25 20
combinations uh or maybe only
16 uh yeah but you know it's enough for
us to imagine what the whole filled in
plane would look like okay so that's the
other
key space the row space now only two
more spaces to go in this example the
null space what does that
mean again it's a space of vectors and
in this the null space of the Matrix has
all the vectors X that give ax equals z
that's if you know all those then that
that's a natural bunch of vectors so
here we have to solve ax equals
0 so there's you see the a matrix the 1
2 3 4 5 six and you see the X vector and
you see the com the multiple so I did
multiplication and I've got uh dot
product there and now I'm setting to
zero do you see any X1 and X2 and X3
that work that get the I have two equ
equ both with zero on the right hand
side and they have a solution because I
have three unknown two equations so
there should be some Freedom here and uh
there the bottom line of this slide
gives the gives the answer uh if I take
one of the First
Column - 2 of the 2 + 1 of the 3 I get
zero
and that means uh I found something in
the null space do you see that going
back to the Matrix if I add 14 and 36
that gives me 410 and that's just twice
25 so that line of vectors through 1 - 2
1 is the null
space if you've got the null space and
that's what elimination and linear
algebra finds this
solution uh one more space to go and it
is a little special
because the only contains the zero
Vector so again I'm TR this is the null
space of a transpose so I flipped those
rows and made them columns again in a
transpose now I have three equations and
only two unknowns and there could be
solution if I had three equations and
two unknowns there could there's always
the zero solution and in this case
that's all there is that's all there is
those two columns are in one two three
is a that column is a vector in 3D 456
points another
way and and any combination is just
going to have some part of 1 two 3 some
part of 4 five6 the only way to get to
the zero Vector is to have zero of each
so the only solution to these three
equations with two unknowns is zero and
zero so the null space of a transpose in
this
example was
uh pretty small it's got one vector in
it though the zero Vector but that's all
so now we've done the four spaces may I
bring back the picture and you'll see
how they fit again so this is the column
space let's review the column space had
two columns in it it didn't need all
three columns of a it just had two two
columns and and their combinations which
picked up the third
column so it was Dimension
two this space this Matrix
has R is the letter R stands for the
rank of the Matrix and that's the number
of independent
columns and in this case you remember
there were two the third one wasn't
important and it also this is a
beautiful fact that same R is the number
of independent
rows and you remember this Matrix had
just two rows and they were independent
so rank is two we can find the rank from
the column space or we can find the rank
from the row space and the Beautiful bit
of mathematics is that they the the
number of vectors you need is the same
and then the null space of a we I think
we
found one vector perpendicular the
rows and uh
the no space of a transpose might have
been zero in that case or vice versa
anyway we have
found all the the pictures all the
numbers that go with the example but
here you're seeing not an example but
the big picture this is the fundamental
picture of linear algebra in I've
learned that in that in reading that
section of my textbook students really
bring things
together
okay so let's see what do I want to say
next about these four
subspaces apart from recommending that
you take some Matrix yourself and figure
out the four
subspaces so here's the fact that I've
been talking about the column rank
equaling the row Rank and that that's a
beautiful but not obvious fact if if you
had a 50 by 70 M Matrix well just
finding how many independent colums and
how many independent rows would be a
challenge but the numbers would be the
same the number of independent columns
equals the number of independent rows
that's just linear algebra magic and
that number we call R so that sort of
measures the real size of the Matrix and
uh I every uh textbook has to prove that
and I like to build it out of this uh
factorization for me factorizations are
fundamental to linear algebra for for
everybody really and uh so I can I I'll
come back in a on another day maybe to
talk about that factorization but the
rank is two here your here our friendly
Matrix a and it we divided it into we
took the independent columns 14 and 25
as the C Matrix and then the r Matrix we
just filled in to get the right
answer
and the two was the number of
independent columns and two is the
number of independent rows so this this
AAL CR gives a beautiful proof of
that Dimension theorem dimension of row
space equal dimension of column space so
that's just a nice part of the
theory okay
now now
[Music]
we going to use the what we just the
four
subspaces it's everybody now knows the
row space and the column space have the
same Dimension r and if I take something
in the row space multiply by a it's in
the column space of course everything
when I multiply by a is in the column
fills the column space
and the for that part of the problem
from row space to column space from uh
space of of Dimension R to a space of
Dimension
R The Matrix is in in verble every and
and I give a proof that you don't need
but but that's a sign of an invertible
Matrix when every every uh Vector goes
all vectors go to all different vectors
here go to different vectors
here and that's from row space to column
space that's that's a key that's that's
the heart of the Matrix is the part that
that goes that actually does something
nonzero that takes the row space to the
column space and
then you can think about the Matrix that
brings it back just undoes this and
that's called the pseudo
inverse and its symbol is a with a plus
sign or a
dagger so that's a kind of new
newish le less less familiar idea
that because the Matrix a between row
space and column space the null space is
not in the picture for this slide just
between rows row space and column
space that that's a perfect match those
two spaces so there's
a m Matrix that brings me backwards an
inverse Matrix but it's called the
pseudo inverse because
I'm ignoring any null
spaces so it doesn't it's not a true
inverse because
you're a true inverse shouldn't have a
null space
there okay now application so I've
discussed the four subspaces and I
suggest you figure out what they might
be for some other Matrix but now I want
to use that idea in a the most
important type of
application for statistics it even has
two names statistics people call it
regression and linear algebra people
call it leas squares and uh that's the
problem there make find the vector X
that makes axus b as short as possible
minimizes the length if there's a
solution to ax equal B then we take that
X and we get ax - B would be
zero but when we have null spaces and
things around uh we may not be able to
get ax equal B but what we can get and
do get is
that equation a transpose time a * x = a
transpose time B in other words you
could see actually by Calculus if you
took the derivative of ax minus b^ 2
because you always take derivatives if
you're minimizing something and set them
to zero it would lead to that
equation that square makes it brings in
an a transpose and and that's the
equation you get so that's the equation
that LE squares problems have to solve
yeah yeah that and that
it's it's uh one of the fundamental
equations of linear
algebra okay and and uh so what what I'm
saying down here is there's one X hat
now I'm calling the solution here x hat
uh because it uh I'm not solving ax
equal B I'm solving this easier I made
more solutions or created some solutions
when I multiply both sides by a
transpose so the solutions Solutions now
are called X hat and there's one
solution in the null space there's one
solution X hat in the row
space because the row space and column
we have th this is R equations in our
unknowns and it's got a got a unique
solution X hat that that X hat is the
goal that's the answer to the regression
problem the least squares problem X
hat
solves makes ax minus b as small as we
can make
it that's that's the least squares
problem least squares small
square and uh so that's the one we're
after okay uh just to finish up on the
pseudo inverse which is a cool idea let
me come back to the main slide of the
whole talk the four subspaces and ask
what the the pseudo inverse does you
remember what the Matrix a does it takes
a vector in the row space multiply by a
you get something in the column space
something in the null space you multiply
by a and you get zero now we want to go
backwards so the beauty is that this
part which is what we want to just
reverse is uh uh those have the same
Dimension so we're fundamentally looking
at a square Matrix which has an inverse
when we're up top so that's what the
pseudo in
is it takes the the Y back to
X and what does it do to these sends
them to zero just the way a transpose
does so you the pseudo inverse gives the
correct inverse up here where the real
action is and down here where matri
where vectors are sent to zero can't
bring them back from zero they're de but
so every Vector here goes goes to zero
so that's the pseudo inverse it has the
has all the the four sub spaces are just
reversed right to left and uh it's a
useful idea not the most basic idea it
doesn't show up in all courses but when
we had the four subspaces here it was so
easy to tell you what the sudo inverse
is so it just takes just so neat with
this figure ites takes each Vector in
the column space back to the vector in
the row space where it came from so
that's a plus the pseudo
inverse okay thank you that's the four
subspaces of any Matrix and you'll
remember that if the Matrix is
invertible uh square and invertible
these two spaces are gone and we simply
have uh the row space and the column
space are both the full space and we
have a perfect onetoone exchange then
luckily a lot of matrices are invertible
but this covers the case of matrices
invertible or not square or not every
Matrix has got those four fundamental
subspaces thank you