when I got my first smartphone and I
landed on YouTube I went looking for
answers to some of the questions I had
and then I found this entire world of
people who actually had answers and all
this other knowledge that was out there
for
free I'm Sarah Hansen for this episode
of chalk radio I sat down with two very
special guests hi I'm Emanuel igazi I'm
a data scientist a creative a learner
and AI SP I'm from campala Uganda East
Africa hi I'm Michael Jordan Pilgreen
I'm from Memphis Tennessee I'm a learner
an educator an engineer and a bridge
builder and it's a pleasure to be here
today Michael and Emanuel are two of the
millions of people who have used MIT
open courseware in their Journeys as
lifelong Learners after connecting with
ocw they connected with each other and
are now good friends despite living on
two different
continents in this conversation they
explain how they've both used ocw to
transform their lives and later they
tell us about the open Learners podcast
an exciting new season of chalk radio
that they're hosting that will bring
stories like Theirs to listeners and
Learners around the world so what
exactly is an open
learner so an open learner can be a lot
of things I think Emanuel and I within
the context of open courseware and MIT
specifically think it's anybody that is
engaging with material and hopes of
learning
anything and we specifically call it
open Learners because going back to when
we first met being from Memphis
Tennessee and Emanuel from Calo
Uganda it was so fascinating that we
both had experienced a certain level of
anti-intellectualism growing
up and I think as adults we're both at
the point now where we can be open about
learning and I know that's a weird
concept to wrap your brain around but it
finally feels good and like
accepted it is something to be proud
about being proud of being a learner
everybody comes out of a fouryear degree
nowadays especially in the United States
and they think they need to be an expert
and they try to put on this Persona that
they do know everything and it's okay to
admit I don't you know and and I'm
willing and open about the fact that I'm
still
learning I was curious to know how
Michael and emanuel's learning Journeys
eventually LED them to MIT open
courseware I've always been interested
in finding out
how things work and more so how we work
as human beings uh I know this is going
to sound cliche but I was that kid who
used to look up at the stars and wonder
what all of this is what are we what is
consciousness what is life how comes I
can talk and that tree can't you know
and the further I grew up the more I
went looking for these answers to these
questions that father led me to the path
of psychology philosophy and trying to
answer the great questions of the world
how I got to ocw was that through my
hobbies what I like I came through
psychology I was trying to just you know
at any point in life at any stage in my
life I always have a
psychological kind of thing that I'm
watching or studying you know just for
my own interest just to try and
understand I'm still on this journey
trying to understand who we are what the
world is and you know the wise the house
the great questions of the world I'm
still on that
journey I was led to been learning an
MIT open course where doing a very
stressful and desperate part of my
life I am trained as a poet from my
undergrad degree during the covid-19
pandemic all
the artwork jobs out there both public
and private facing sort of evaporated
overnight and I had to figure out what
was next and I found an introduction to
finance course by Andrew low and I fell
in love with his Charisma and his
ability to Captivate an audience and
that led me to discovering Gary guinsler
you know the SEC
commissioner and I was just shocked that
he had multiple courses online for free
where he's articulating and dialoguing
with students in a masterful way about
Capital markets even for people that may
not be interested in capital Marcus he
was able to digest these very complex
interconnected Concepts and simplify
them in a way that everyday Learners
could interact with and that fascinated
me and it encouraged me to continue down
the financial technology
path so how exactly did these two open
Learners connect and end up co-hosting a
special season of chalk
radio so after watching the psychology
lessons because this was one of the most
profound like I said I'd been doing
courses on this but not from like the
top top institutions so when I found the
top instiution was honestly different so
I was like this is amazing does this
professor know what he's doing for the
world and I remember sitting one day and
I'm like you know what I want to thank
this person I'm done with this coures
cuz this is something groundbreaking so
when I saw the psychology profess Prof I
wrote out to him like thank you for this
amazing course you're doing amazing work
I just wanted to thank the professor and
then CT wrote me
back for those of you who are new to the
podcast the Kurt he's referring to here
is Kurt Newton the director of MIT open
courseware and he asked if they could
share my story I didn't understand what
that meant at the time but I was like
okay cool and then in that email they
sent me a link to Michael's story we're
going to write a story about you and
it's a story like this one so one day
I'm playing around my LinkedIn and I see
an invitation from Michael I'm like wait
I know this gentleman so I accept the
invitation then I write him back I'm
like thank you for inspiring us I saw
your story it was a great piece uh thank
you and Michael wrote back like do you
want to get on a call I was like why not
so we get on a call I remember that day
my power even went out
yeah so I had this laptop that had like
20% battery left I was like either way
I'm taking this call if we talk for only
like five minutes it's okay so we talk
Michael was it blew my mind that this
was this person across the continent but
then as we kept talking we found that we
have similar interests we both have a
background in arts we both L philosophy
and psychology we are both on this
journey to kind of transition our
careers were both and it was just
mind-blowing to me and that this what
brought all this together was this
platform this ocw platform and since
then we've been talking almost every
week here at ocw we love how open
learning and open education can forge
the kinds of relationships that Michael
and Emanuel have it inspired an idea how
could we amplify this community-building
effect of open learning to even more
people and so a new podcast was
born we are just trying to do or give
people what me and Michael
experienced like these were two people
from two separate continents other side
of the world ours apart but then you get
to talking and then you find you kind of
have similar interests and now you get
to know this person and then you get to
start this commune with this person they
become your friend they become your
mentor they become your colleague
building that community and that
connection between Learners across the
world despite everything despite
differentiated
context and different you know
Lifestyles all these things that people
are still fundamentally the same and
going through the same struggles going
through the same self-doubts When
approaching learning really giv giving a
platform for people to continue to share
their stories and
hopefully that will serve as
inspiration along the way for other
Learners right just
another support system to know that
you're not alone in this journey when
you're going to learn it's about the
people that you can go along with
because in schools that's easy you're
all in one Community you're in one space
you know
but online learning and open learning as
a whole it's kind of vague and it's not
so clear written but in school you know
I'm in class with 70 people you know so
that's what we're trying to give people
with this open learning platform also
maybe learning in your culture is an act
of defiance right you know
especially given the global context not
everybody can just openly learn whatever
they want and I think an inspiration for
change we are looking at talking to
people from every continent every
background every culture whichever
tradition is constrained those who can
learn those who can't learn just to make
them know that whatever it is you're
going through it's scary yes but you're
not alone he's another person from the
other side of the continent who went
through the same thing and they made it
and it was okay and we just want you to
know that and that's the purpose of open
learning
if you're interested in sharing your
open learning story with Michael and
Emanuel and maybe being featured on
their upcoming podcast please send them
an email at open Learners corod mit.edu
we are so excited to launch this special
season and to share more stories like
Michael and emanuels with the world so
stay tuned to this podcast feed for
updates thank you so much for listening
until next time siging off from
Cambridge Massachusetts I'm your host
Sarah Hansen from MIT open courseware
MIT Chuck radio's producers include
myself Brett POI and Dave Lansky show
notes for this episode were written by
Peter Chipman Jason player made our
episode cassette animation on YouTube
We're funded by MIT open learning and
supporters like you
[Music]