Good morning everyone. Um, great to be
here and uh, thanks again to ILP for
inviting me. I'm here to talk a little
bit about um, some of the exciting
things we see going on in networking and
space and uh, edge computing. So, we'll
get get to it. So, this is what I like
to call the cloud above the clouds. Um,
and we'll we'll get to why, but lower
launch costs and now we've got some
competing rellanding vehicles, reusable
launch vehicles with um, new Glenn um
improved manufacturing in the north
orbit where we can really get to
flatpacked commodities of scale in terms
of satellite fabrication and um, you
know, just
commercial line production of many
satellites.
Um, and now that we are getting to the
point where we can directly connect to
our consumer devices and we have the
3GPP making modifications to the
standards to allow for the latency and
power management um that is necessary to
enable this. We're really enabling
global connectivity. So what's next?
Um,
so today we have on orbit we have
sensors, we have communications, and we
have radio down links or radio frequency
RF down links. Um, and we have all of
our compute on the ground for the most
part. We take data, we send it down for
analysis. We send up commands, we take
more data, we send it down to the
ground. Um what we're going to see
happening increasingly um as these
backbones of communication get
established in space is more on orbit
decision- making inference making
dynamic tasking um where the sensors are
gathering the insights on orbit making
decisions on orbit retasking on orbit
and sending information down and a much
lower volume just the insights that you
wanted and needed for the most part to
to the ground. Um we're enabled to do
this by some of the technologies that I
just opened with. And um what we're
going to see, I think, is this motion of
um decision- making and autonomy um edge
compute and inference on orbit. So I'm
calling that cloud above the clouds um
because we're we're really getting to
that point, which is exciting. But why
now? So what's why is this all happening
now? People have been talking about
dynamic tasking and autonomy and orbit
for a long time. So what is falling into
place right now and what are the
opportunities that we have um that
enable us to make you know some pretty
great advances which I'll get to at the
end. Things that I'm really excited to
be working on. Um so we have these low
earth orbit LEO mega communications
constellations. they're there. Um, with
the lower latency and the global
coverage and the remote access over
ocean, over land, um, they still want to
optimize for where the most customers
are, but still the capability is there.
Um, we have enormous data volumes that
are being generated from high resolution
earth imagery, hyperspectral imagery,
synthetic aperture radar which can see
through clouds day, night. Um we have an
really significant advances in
onorbiting compute and running AI
machine learning models on board
satellites on really capable commercial
processors um on orbit right now. Um, we
can do this in low earth orbit, perhaps
a little bit more challenging at higher
altitude orbits like um, medium earth
orbit where the GPS satellites are or
geostationary orbit where a lot of our
communications transponders are um, just
because of the radiation environment
further out. But in low Earth orbit, we
can do this. Um, we don't really need,
we're getting to the point where we
won't really need to down link
everything. will be able to run things
on board and make decisions and see, oh,
you know, I was tracking the shipping
container with this ID number with this
tracking number and I saw where it went
and I got the update on its latest
status. So, now I'm going to go on to
the next task or I didn't get that
measurement, but you know, two
satellites down, going to fly over in
about 15 minutes, I'm going to pass that
task backwards and we're going to try to
get it with that one and see if they
have clear cloud coverage. I didn't get
it. So um deciding and delivering on
orbit is going to become more of a
thing. Um we have laser inter satellite
links between the satellites right now
um to augment the radio frequency cross
links. Radio frequency has a bunch of
challenges that I'll get to. Um and I'll
talk more about laser communications
work that is being done at MIT and MIT
Lincoln. Um and we have come to the
point where we're really getting to
programmable space where we can have
really targeted satellite services, not
just sensor data dumps down to the
ground anymore. we can start to really
configure things dynamically.
So the challenges that we need to
overcome that we'll we'll talk through
but we're we're getting there is limited
power. So being able to operate really
efficiently thermal constraints in space
there's no convection. You know all
these images of your workstations or
with fans to cool the chips doesn't work
like that in space. You either have
pipes to move fluids around or you have
radiating panels to cool your chips. Um
so thermal constraints are an issue.
Precision pointing. So, um, anybody
who's ever given a presentation with a
laser pointer knows that like trying to
keep the dot on the on the screen can be
a little bit of a challenge. And just
imagine that at thousands of kilometers
to hundreds of kilometers distance,
right? And trying to do that with free
floating satellites that have other
things going on. Um, they're moving. So,
you have Doppler shifts and um,
handoffs. Um, you have some latency that
you have to deal with, gaps and timing.
You can't have everything on a regular
um, periodic time schedule. Um
regulatory is a huge issue for both
spectrum and imaging as I think we're
all aware. Um really bandwidth challenge
for spectrum and imaging is um often
very inconvenient and requires a lot of
paperwork and tracking. Um we have
weather that we need to deal with for
the ground down links. Um and we want
the autonomy to be reliable and cost
effective. It doesn't do us any good to
have autonomy if we have to have a
standing army to make sure that the
software works all the time and the
hardware gets replaced and isn't broken
or the procurement pipeline is you know
stable and we don't have to redesign our
boards every six months. Um so and then
we also want to deal with
interoperability and I have some ideas
on that across fleets and platforms that
I'll get to later with federated um edge
compute and of course security. So these
are these are the challenges that you
know are MIT level challenges that we
can help work on.
Um, so I'm going to go over some of
these building blocks, just a few of
them, not all of them. That's a big
list. I'm just going to focus on a few.
Um, so Lasercom, um, the
non-aterrestrial networks, um,
protocols, um, on onboard and edge
compute, and submission apps, and then
then we'll go through, um, some others,
and I'm happy to talk about some of the
others, too. So, the challenges that,
um, some of these address are really
regulatory, security, and jamming. Those
are those are some of the big challenges
that we're overcoming to make this
happen. One of the ways that we're doing
this is with these inter satellite laser
cross links in low Earth orbit. So, um,
the way I like to think about this is
laser communications on orbit from
satellite to satellite where you don't
have to worry about weather because
you're not down linking it. You're just
going satellite to satellite. It's not
really replacing radio. I don't want to
think about it that way. Radio is
extremely valuable. Um, but it's more of
like imagining the Ethernet fiber that
happened when the internet started to
really take off here on the ground
happening up there. So that that's what
we're seeing. We're seeing this
high-capacity spine in a space internet
come into being that's making these
modern satellite networks behave like
cloud backbones, fast, secure, scalable,
and RF is going to keep us or fan out,
our last hop um universally available
even with weather. We can use optical
for some of that as well and I'm I have
I have ideas on how to do that too but
um and and have been working on that but
um RF for the laptop is is good. So um
we have these laser interatellite links
um again space equivalent of optical
fiber and then we have the changes to
that 3GPP has been putting together for
the 5G and then future 6G um pro
releases. So the non-aterrestrial
network. So um this is having a base
station on satellites on aerial mobile
platforms your user equipment or your
cell phones. And they have um reduced
capability internet of things and
directto device connectivity all built
into the new releases for this um user
equipment and um base station hardware
which will make it easier to connect to
more platforms more effectively than
we've we've been able to do before. Um
and then there's been a huge
proliferation um although the
availability and pricing is sometimes
not exactly what we want for the onboard
AI and edge compute um chipsets um
there's some great chipsets that are out
there that we can fly and have flown and
have been flying and demonstrating
onboard satellites um from GPUs to
FPGAAS to AS6 that can do tasks like
feature recognition classification
um you know lots of different models
that they can run um that we have run
even on demonstration platforms
So, um, with the laser angel satellite
links, there's really, like I said, no
clouds to get away get in the way of
space-to-pace links. You can get over,
um, well over a 100 gigabits per second
per cross link. Sometimes they do this
with multiple colors of light at the
same time to you can't get all the all
the bits in one color. But, um, the
beams are very narrow, which means that
they're secure. You're not going to
bother other people. The coordination
that you need to do is minimal. Um
there's very low regulatory burden right
now. Um unless you happen to be, you
know, a government program in which case
you need to coordinate with your
government friends, but other than that
there's very little regulatory burden.
Um but you have to be able to precision
point your um your terminals online and
they're pointto-point and there are some
great technologies that we use here on
campus to do that. Um steering mirrors.
Um there are micro electromechanical
MEMS steering mirrors that we've been
using on some of the terminals. Um, and
these are these are things that we we've
been working hard to do that enable uh
more cross links to overcome some of
these data problems. What I'm what I'm
showing on the top here is a you know
finding the other guy is hard. So the
green beam is a wider beam to do the
search with and then you can switch to
your narrower data beam once you found
your other link. Um there are um you
know some of the links on orbit links
are being made and unmade at the level
of hundreds of thousands of links being
made and not made and unlin orbit. um in
lower lith orbit today. So the the laser
comm cross links that are out there are
linking and unlinking like crazy.
They're doing a good job of it. It's
very reliable. This is a problem that
people have um been working on and have
solutions to. Um this is just a quick
example of a little um program that we
have at MIT for NASA doing a instead of
a larger satellite crossing doing them
very small on little nano satellites. So
this is a program called click b and c.
We already did click A with a down link
to a very small telescope in in a shed
in Westward. The students um didn't like
that in the winter. It was kind of cold.
But um the cross links, we won't have to
worry about the shed quite so much. And
so this is some hardware that that we're
building just as an example of some of
the hardware that you can build to do
this on on campus or working with
campus. Um so for the 5G
non-aterrestrial networks, I mentioned
that 3GPP is been modifying their
releases to include this um
non-aterrestrial capability. It it
handles things like Doppler shifts from
relative motion of your platforms. You
don't want the user end to have to deal
with this. You don't want to have to
modify your mobile phones. You want the
base stations to have to deal with that.
Um there are modes without um hybrid
automatic repeat request, which you'd
think you'd need for these platforms,
but it can be really um difficult to
implement and maintain when you're power
and resource constrained. And so it's
that this reduces latency and conserves
the resources on um on your devices. And
then there's this idea of grant free
which allows you to send packets without
having to preschedu them. Um so there's
a lot of these capabilities that are are
being incorporated into the new releases
um for 5G and then future for 60G that
will enable um our user devices to be
more connected to um satellite and
aerial platforms. So these are things
when we're planning for our new
capabilities that we want to build into
our systems. We want to plan for this
hybrid capability both the optical cross
links and the user devices connecting.
Um so in in the past we used to have
just uh transparent or bent pipe
capability where basically bent pipe is
like the idea of the pipe is you send
the data up that goes right through the
pipe and comes back down somewhere else.
Right? It's just kind of like going
through a pipe. Nothing changes in the
middle. Um, right now we're looking
towards in the newer releases in release
19, we're looking at um, this new
capability where you send data up and
you can do something with it. You can
modify the frequency it's at. You can
change some of its properties. You can
change where it's going. Um, and you may
be able to like amplify, retransmit,
change the data, multipplex things in
and out. Um, so these are things that
you'll be able to do in some of the new
releases which will allow some of this
onboard decision-m retasking um
reorganizing of things as well as doing
that up there and and also incorporating
connecting it with the users down on the
ground. So these are things to again to
keep an eye on um that that I think will
be really enabling um that we want to
make sure we're we're incorporating into
our future planning. Um this is a real
eye chart, but I'm just going to talk
through it really quickly. There's a
longer paper on this that I have linked
if you guys want to um see it. But these
are just like going through ways that
you can use AI on a satellite, right? So
AI as the parent category, subcategory,
machine learning. There are different
types of AI. These are the yellow boxes.
Constraint satisfaction, supervised
learning, unsupervised learning,
reinforcement learning, evolutionary
algorithms. We went through all the
reasons, you know, methods that you
might use, the tasks from assignment to
classification, clustering, anomaly
detection, optimization, the different
algorithms that you could use for each
of these different tasks. And then the
easy part to understand really is the
example applications from planning and
navigation, scientific prediction, cloud
filtering, feature extraction,
spacecraft health management, navigation
and tracking, um configuration
optimization. These are all the things
that you know at a high level survey we
could think of to do with AI on board
and that we can start implementing now.
Um this is just a one example when we're
implementing an multimodal. So we're
taking satellite images. Multimodal
means not just color images but also
thermal images um maybe SAR or radar
images and we're fusing them together um
as they're coming into the model and
we're using them to do a classification
task to find something um to locate a
topic and decide like you know did this
task get completed or not did I see a
flood is the flood increasing to a
certain level that I'm worried about do
I see wildfire boundaries changing do I
see crop growth vegetation being
affected by weather by a certain level
that I'm concerned about that I want to
report back. Um so these are things that
um you can do on board. So you would
take the data in and you would um use uh
in this case you know different types of
um machine learning models from um
neural networks to um genetic algorithms
different ways to to use the different
models and get out on the output your
your inference the information that you
cared about. So you you've trained it
you train it on the ground for the most
part although I have a later example
that I'm going to talk about that that
we move a little bit of the training on
orbit but just weights changing but for
the most part you do a lot of the heavy
compute on the ground and running the
models on orbit isn't as compute heavy
and it's capable your your processors
are capable of doing this you're just
running them. All right so um a little
bit more about the autonomy and resource
scheduling. So this is a fun little
animation that um one of our our loud
students made um where I like I was
saying you can cover unpredictable
phenomena, cloud cover, wildfires,
weather events um and you can tackle you
know where you're taking the image and
when. So this um method um is actually
avoiding clouds. I have a different
student who wants to cover clouds for
understanding um earth's climate but um
but this is just going through an
example um where we have um on this
slide we have all the black dots are
unobserved activities um the red is it's
using data cloud masks that it's getting
from some of the go weather satellites
that are available every 15 minutes
globally or for you can patch that are
global for the most part um and you can
decide okay of my activities, which ones
are cloudy, which ones are clear, and
then you can task the satellite as it's
flying along. It compares its path and
its tasks against the cloud map. It
makes decisions of what's the most um
useful thing to do, and it goes for the
green dots um which are the the tasks
that it's um trying to track. So, this
is the actual model of the algorithm
working um could be run on board. And
you can see it, you know, doing the best
it can, kind of almost like a video game
trying to win all the green dots. not
quite Mario Kart, but um the satellite
version of it. And you can you can have
um multiple ways of implementing this um
with um gathering your your queueing
data or your masking data depending on
what you care about. In this case, it's
clouds. Um this is the student who
wanted to track clouds on purpose. So,
I'm just showing hers as well. Um so
that you can see that if you did want to
track clouds for some reason, if you're
a scientist or you you cared about where
was going to be overcast, maybe you have
a reason for for using the clouds. um
then um then you can do that. Um this is
uh work that we've done to use machine
learning models to look at the telemetry
streams. So on board the satellite just
like on board your computer it has logs
and data that it's coming out from your
hardware at all times kind of its status
and it's just reporting. The satellite
does that too. It's called its telemetry
streams. It's housekeeping telemetry.
You can actually have a machine learning
model running on your housekeeping
telemetry and instead of thresholding,
which is what we do now, alarms go off
if we go above or below this level. Um,
you can actually have it look for things
that are unusual, behaviors that you're
taking that aren't typical for your
normal behavior. And it can send alerts.
It can infer what went wrong. And um,
we're getting to the point where it can
even make decisions to self-correct. So
instead of just powering down and
calling home for help, it could do
something more intelligent to reduce
downtime and improve uptime and improve
um um customer service. So um here we're
using ensemble learning and decision
trees um XG Boost in particular to
implement something like this on board.
Um the there's also this idea of
federated learning in low Earth orbit.
So, um, you have this, we're getting to
the point where we're going to have this
connected network. Um, and they want to
coordinate with each other, but they
don't want to tell each other
everything, right? You might have some
proprietary information that you don't
want to share. Um, but you want to
contribute to an overall good and you
want to, you know, get something from
the other team's data. Um, but you don't
want to share everything with them. So
what you could do is have a small global
model that you could pass with your
cross links between your different
vehicles and you could train it on the
data that you have locally that you
think is valuable or the insights that
you have locally that is valuable. You
could adjust the weights and then pass
it on to the next guy. So the model gets
updated. Your actual data doesn't
actually go into that update but
everybody benefits from the improved
performance. So this is an idea of
federated learning in orbit where we can
have our satellite constellations
coordinate with each other and work with
each other without necessarily giving
all the information away. We can do this
on the ground too. Um but the idea of
doing in space is pretty cool. Um and so
instead of moving data around to a
central server, you send the smaller
models across the other spacecraft. you
you run training on it with the data
that you're willing to share and um the
model gets updated and sent back around
to the folks who are part of the club.
Um we're also very interested in using
um autonomy on board to make bigger
things in space that are more useful,
bigger antennas, bigger imaging systems.
Volume in a rocket is really costly and
constrained. Um, so we we can, you know,
start to think about, okay, well, what
if instead of putting the big thing in a
rocket, having it be a one-time
deployable like the James Web Space
Telescope, what if we just built it up
there? Um, and so we're looking at some
ideas now of using um less humanoid
robotics. You could use arms, robotic
arms and things like that, but the six
degrees of freedom, they can be a little
costly and complex. You can do this much
more simply like we do in factories now
with automated assembly. these XYZ
cartisian robots that we see in um you
know manufacturing companies, car
companies assembling things and putting
them together. You can send up a
satellite with one of that those systems
on it um with full of parts. Basically,
this is one that's full of tile parts
that it's packed together to form a
large flat surface. Um and you can put
those in this in the um rocket instead.
And you can use um and train models to
build lots of different things with
these um tiles or with these um systems
that you can you can assemble together
on orbit.
>> We're we're prototyping it. It's at the
um kind of sandbox toy level in lab
right now, but yeah, we're it's
something that that our our group's been
working on.
>> Um we don't have a launch yet. We're
This is like very early stages, but
happy to talk if people are interested.
Um, James Dingley is wonderful. He also
is a really well-known YouTube
communicator. If you haven't seen any of
his videos, they're fantastic. So,
definitely check out some of his work.
He's one of our students here at MIT.
We've got some great students and he's
very dynamic and very very got got some
great work out there that's not the
robotic assembly as well. Um so future
roadmap we're doing optical cross links
now and we're getting to the point where
we have basic AI and autonomy on board.
Um we're looking to develop more
multi-satellite ground station routing
and advancing the autonomy making the
tasking more complex more useful um and
doing more for resource management power
um thermal as well as network management
and the ability to quickly recover on
orbit. Um, I would love to get to the
point where we enable federated learning
on orbit. Maybe this like more secure,
less open, but still valuable sharing of
models and updating them among multiple
parties. Um, you can imagine different
types of groups of companies that might
be interested in doing something like
that. Um we should be working on um
radio interoperability with the new
non-aterrestrial network um protocols
that are coming out um so that we can
have um interoperability both between
the platforms and the user devices as
well as interoperability between the
operators. Um I think we'll we'll really
be at a point where we can start moving
forward when we're not so constrained
about who's working on whose network. Um
and then this new idea of um
self-healing capability and self-aware
connectivity. So in addition to
monitoring your telemetry for um
anomalies, wouldn't it be great if you
never had to write another software
device driver in your life because the
packets come in, your model can look at
the packets, figure out what packets
they are and write the code it needs to
interpret them on the fly instead of
having some software engineer only write
the interface to one thing and then it
doesn't work and you don't know what's
going on. And um so yeah, I one too many
issues with USB on my side. I'm a little
I'm a little bitter. Um, okay. So, I'm
just wrapping up ways to work with MIT
on this. My group or any of the others.
I know Ali Dwax's group who spoke
earlier is working on this as well as
several other faculty member here on
members here on campus. The ILP program
is a great way to do this. Um, you can
sponsor graduate research on campus. So,
some companies work my group directly.
You can sponsor undergraduates to work
with us on campus. And there's also a a
high school and undergraduate training
program called the Beaverworks program
that you can get involved with for the
younger students depending on when you
want to start grooming your workforce
pipeline. Um
you can um collaborate on calls for
proposals with us um with uh the faculty
members as PIs. Um we're more than happy
to connect you with our students to hire
as interns over the summer. And then we
actually have students available for the
entire month of January every year. So
not not all schools have that but
January every year the MIT students are
available for internships. Um you can do
non-resident graduate student
sponsorship where the students have
completed all their classes and then
they basically just go work at your
company while working on their PhD
degrees as as advised by their adviser.
The adviser has to go along with it but
it's possible to do that. Um we're happy
to invite you here to give seminars.
We're happy to invite you to give
lectures to our grads and undergrads. Um
we're happy to go talk to you. Um, ILOP
is great about trying to get us to do
that and um, I you know,
getting through fighting through our
email streams. Um, I know these guys
work really hard at that to get in touch
with us, make sure we we spend some time
and then we can also spend sbaticals at
at your institutions as well. So, um,
with that said, I I just wanted to close
with I you know, I think there's a lot
of a future in cloud computing and a lot
of things we can do uh on orbit above
the clouds and I'd be happy to keep
working on that. So, thank you.
Question time. Any questions over here?
>> Carrick,
good see. Um, uh, unman submersible
have, you know, flooded versions and
then ones that are fully pressurized to
protect everything inside of them. You
compute at higher altitudes. Could you
just, you know, if you didn't want to
have to rag hard everything, could you
build a box? Um
the question briefly.
>> Yeah. So the question was um at altitude
does everything really need to be
radiation tolerant or can you um put it
in a box with either pressurized gas or
put it in um some type of um metal
container to help protect it. Um the
answer is it that can sometimes help. Um
sometimes not. A lot of the radiation um
is very high energy meaning it goes
through just about anything. If you try
to put metal around it, it will just
make secondary radiation. So it'll hit
the metal and then there'll be a cascade
of more radiation coming off the metal
on the other side. Um so so sometimes it
helps, sometimes it doesn't. Um it kind
of depends and how much mass you're
willing to put on there. Um and um so
how thick and um the pressurized vessels
also um make everything more expensive.
My problem with pressurized things
because of the safety concerns. Um so
when you go up on a rocket they really
don't there's this rapid change from you
know um surface air pressure to vacuum
and that that's over the course of like
90 seconds and they're very concerned
about leaks and damage to um things on
board. So so sometimes sometimes you can
um and some sometimes you you may not be
willing to take the mass or cost hit for
doing that.
This may be too broad a question, but if
you think about like you mentioned the
confluence of factors that lead to the
why now and there's like the pointing
there's the laser that exists in the
academic world and like the FFRDC world
and there's like a normal pipeline to
tech transfer for like the radons and
bees of the world which then like begs
the question where do you see I guess
the economic opportunity for like the
startup ecosystem to take advantage of
this like new economy versus uh the
incumbent so to speak.
>> Yeah. So, so the question is like with
the the things that are happening now,
the new capabilities um and outside of
the institutional pipeline to um FFRDC's
to research, how do you know licensing
through universities or big
organizations? How do you get more
startups involved, more commercial space
involved? Um MIT does have a technology
licensing office and um most of the
students here are open to the idea of
supporting startups or doing their own
startups. I know several that that are
um as well as the faculty, myself
included. Um so I think I think there's
a there's a lot of opportunity um to
have the people here be interested in
working on it. The other half of that is
making the case for return on investment
and commercialization and product to the
investors that we need to support the
work. um that that is finding the happy
medium in between where there's a
product and a customer and a number of
units and a you know return on
investment that they're expecting um
compared with the technology that you're
promoting is takes a little bit of
working out. Um so I think I think one
of the things that could speed that up
is having more conversations and more
clarity among the young people who are
working on this and really want to do
it. Not all of us are young, some of us
are older, so I won't be agist, but um
but having a little bit more clarity
about like exactly what's expected, what
bars they have to hit in terms of um
being investable. Um that that that is
almost as clear as the tenure process
rules here for most people. Like not
very clear. Nobody's really sure where
to hit. It kind of depends who you talk
to and what you're working on. So I
think more clarity there would really
help speed things up. But you know,
human human engineering is another
another challenge. Um yeah. Could
the learning systems talking about one
day be used like if you had the
automated robots to build satellites,
could it be used to kind of train them
to make fixes inside the system of
robots working together? Yeah, I think I
think it's really valuable like you're
saying exactly for um information and
knowledge sharing that might not be
fully transparent but mostly transparent
and sharing skills. Um imagine if you
had a bunch of mechanics who you know
had a central knowledge base that they
passed among each other. They don't want
to give all their trade secrets secrets
away but they might give some right to
try to encourage people to use their
business. Um so yeah you can you can
think of it like that. Um, and I can
definitely see that applying to onorbit
assembly as well, where, you know, you
have one system that's putting this
together. It's had this level of
success. It knows what its issues are.
It knows what its challenges are. And
that has been um put into a machine
learning model. And then those
parameters passed and shared between
three or four, maybe more different
groups that are doing the same thing,
and they're all able to build on it. So,
I think I think that would be really
valuable.
>> Yeah. Uh I remember you mentioned that
the training will be done on the ground
before
it is launching on on the orbit. I I
guess once it is on the orbit, can we
retrain or retrain the model so that it
can do something different from what it
was originally trained for?
>> Yeah, I mean if you have enough compute
capability, you certainly can. Um, I
think sometimes that can be one of the
most comput intensive parts of using
machine learning, um, is is the
training. Um, and so if you're planning
for that andor you have the time, um,
it's possible to do that. So I'm not
saying you can't, I'm just saying, you
know, the efficiency is is a different
hit than just running the model.
>> Yeah. So the the question was, um, can
you retrain on orbit? Um, yes, thank you
for the reminder.
Anybody else?
I guess we're good then.
>> All right. Thank you very much.