inside of the incandescent light bulb
there's a filament and they've used
tungsten because tungsten has the
highest melting point of all the metals
inside of that light bulb there is an
inert atmosphere there's argon and
nitrogen gases to protect that filament
so take one of these filaments outside
of the light bulb and I'm going to turn
on the
electricity in the oxygen atmosphere the
electrons are flowing through there and
the tungsten atoms are boiling off with
the electrons I want to do one more
experiment we're going to take one of
these filaments and we're going to stick
it down into the liquid
nitrogen there it is in the liquid
nitrogen take it out
Amanda so even the liquid nitrogen is
surrounding that that filament and
protecting it and uh you've got the
situation where you don't have the
oxidation that's going on for more MIT
moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow