Episode
two. All great ideas start out bad.
All great ideas start out bad. Most look
horrible at the start. And yet, this
should come as a relief. That idea you
had or heard this morning that everyone
laughed at could be the start of
something. That's right. The idea does
not need to look disruptive or scalable
or exponential or like a business yet.
You can start with what you have.
This is often difficult for people to
accept. Most innovation stories are told
in hindsight, which creates a cognitive
bias. If you have read a lot of
innovation stories, it may be hard to
accept that the start of those great
stories is a poor fit for the
innovations they became. But success
isn't hiding in the idea. It follows
from what you do next. Here are some
examples of bad ideas that graduated
into becoming great innovation stories
to tell. In 1878, Sir William Priest,
who at the time was chief engineer of
the British post office, mentioned that
the lack of voice was causing Americans
to adopt an idea that had no future. He
was talking about the telephone.
Around 1914, the Ford Motor Company
increased worker wages manyifold above
the minimum wage. Critics thought Henry
Ford had gone insane. But the Ford Motor
Company did not go bankrupt like critics
expected. Instead, they initiated a
trend in the auto industry that caused
cars to become affordable. In the late
1960s, in an interview to the New York
Times, Dr. May, the inventor of the
laser, spoke of it as a solution still
seeking for a problem. Today, lasers are
everywhere.
At the turn of the 21st century, one of
the companies from famed investor Vinad
Kosla had a chance to acquire Google for
about $750,000.
They passed. They felt it was too
expensive. After exiting PayPal, a young
Elan Musk founded an out for profit
called Mars Oasis to take a small
greenhouse to Mars. He and his team
tried to buy rockets from a group of
Russians, but the Russians laughed at
them. So instead, they set out to build
rockets themselves and ended up founding
SpaceX.
In 2021, a new company called Colossal
announced plans to bring back the woolly
mammoth in an attempt to stop climate
change. You can read about it in the New
York Times. These examples cover about
150 years worth of unlikely innovation
stories across many domains. investment,
industrial factories, new technologies,
entrepreneurship, not for profits. Even
in every case, an idea that seemed
preposterous at the time it got started
has ended up leading to something we now
think of as an obvious innovation. Well,
to be fair, as of the recording of this
video, the jury was still out on whether
the idea to bring back the woolly
mammoth will end someplace worth
inclusion in the list. But that only
strengthens the point I have been making
all along. At the start, preposterous
ideas and good ideas look the exact
same. After hearing all these, many
people still find this notion really
difficult to accept. You see, most
entrepreneurship and innovation
frameworks create the illusion that you
just have to find the idea that will
work and then execute. It's as if the
idea had to have it all before you even
start. And so the list of requirements
for the idea grows. It has to be
scalable, disruptive, singular,
exponential. It is easy to see why
people have a hard time letting go of
that illusion. If ideas came pre-labeled
as good, bad, slam dunk, etc., then all
you'd have to do is talk to a few people
or users, do a minimum prototype, and
pitch it, and you'd be mostly done. In
our experience, reality works another
way. To be clear, there is no guarantee
that your idea will ever graduate from
being bad.
But all that matters is whether the idea
can supply you with the spunk you need
to get you started on the real job.
And the job is to fix the idea. And it
amounts to being wrong a lot and
surviving it all. That is what I call
being productively wrong. When I say
this, people often ask, "Oh, you mean
like fail fast?" No, fail fast and being
productively wrong are not the same.
This is a key distinction of this new
mindset.
The fail fast phrase has been used so
much that it now looks like failing is a
cause for celebration.
All you have to do to join the cool kids
club and claim yourself an innovator is
to fail. It isn't. It is still better
when things work. I cannot fathom Steve
Jobs celebrating failure that way. And
yet a lot of famous people speak often
of failing. Failing fast and failing
often, but we really listen to them
because of their success. So it is hard
to know what they mean by failing and
what you should get from it. This can
help. Ditch the fail fast mantra. What
matters is to realize that the idea you
start with is a poor fit for what you
think you want to accomplish. And the
only way you can discover that is by
making your ideas real and tangible. You
may wonder what I mean by making an idea
tangible. Nowadays, very often we talk
about ideas, we create powerpoints, we
describe them to others, we fall
increasingly in love with the idea we
had. But that idea only lives on paper.
By making it tangible, what I'm asking
you to do is find a way to make a
physical something that you could point
to so that other people can actually see
your idea somehow in action. Making your
idea tangible is how you realize you had
not thought it all through and you start
to learn how you were wrong.
I will tell you more about this in
another video. Finding something wrong
about your idea isn't failing. Only
people afraid to be wrong confuse that
for failing. Finding something wrong
about your idea is how you start fixing
it. You can take forever to do this or
you can find ways to find out how your
idea was wrong sooner. But it isn't
failing. It is the precise opposite. It
is a pursuit of excellence.
Innovation rarely emerges from planned
sloppiness. You have to care about
excellence. You need to hate failing,
but you cannot be stigmatized by it.
There is no merit in failing. There is
no stigma either. But you're in this to
succeed. So fail only in ways you could
not have predicted. As you will see in a
few videos, this mindset, the pursuit of
excellence, and the absolute
determination to not fail is how
astronauts go to space and back.
[Music]