[Music]
I'm Carara Miller.
>> And I'm Rob Stoner.
>> And from the MIT Energy Initiative, this
is What If It Works, a podcast looking
at the energy solutions for climate
change.
Today, we're going to take in the big
picture view of how energy systems are
shaped and which technologies might win
out. But first, just consider how
indispensable reliable energy is for us.
We rely on our energy systems to allow
us to do work, physical work, process
information, support all economic
activity
and we're always trying to, you know,
improve that energy system. I mean, it's
never been static. That's Jessica
Transic, a professor in MIT's Institute
for Data Systems and Society. If we look
back to the beginning of
industrialization in the late 1800s, we
started to adopt coal fired electricity
and then over time used more natural
gas, nuclear power, increasingly solar
and wind energy and you know we also
have the fuels for transportation for
industry. So things are always changing
and the economy the country that can
have the best functioning energy system
is going to have an advantage. That
advantage, she says, can play out in a
number of ways. It can be an advantage
in cost. It can be an advantage in
maintaining human health by, let's say,
creating cleaner air. It can be an
advantage in producing fewer greenhouse
gas emissions and helping to reduce
climate change.
>> It's really difficult to isolate oneself
from the evolution of technology that's
happening and really changing this
energy system, which is such an, you
know, fundamental part of our economy.
But of course, as policy changes, so
does our support for different
technologies. Transit says it's likely
that the technologies with the most
momentum are just going to keep moving
forward in our global marketplace almost
no matter what. Solar energy is growing
rapidly. Wind energy, electric vehicles,
batteries, and heat pumps. to step back
from those markets and not invest and
not try to be part of that transition is
risky. Part of that risk is missing out
on the sorts of jobs that these
technologies generate. And those aren't
just jobs for scientists, nor are they
just jobs for factory workers. More and
more, they're a whole different kind of
job. A job that brings technology to the
customer and optimizes it for them. And
in the US where far more people provide
services than actually make goods that
is an area for real potential growth.
installing. Let's say if we take rooftop
solar, installing the hardware and you
know acquiring customers and everything
that's not hardware represents about,
you know, up to 50% of the total cost of
these installation projects of the
actual delivered service, the solar on
your roof. And so there's a lot of room
to improve that. There's a lot of room
to find new creative ways to bring in
energy storage or to, you know, at the
utility scale to combine solar and wind
energy, you know, or at the commercial
scale looking at commercial solar
installations. I think there's so much
room to innovate in that space. But how
did a technology like solar get to where
it is? How did it become cheaper,
better, increasingly ubiquitous?
Transics research looks forward but it
also looks back. In the 70s and 80s,
Japan was a really major player in terms
of creating incentives for the growth in
markets for solar energy. They
subsidized the adoption of solar energy
and that grew markets for solar energy
in Japan. And then Germany took over as
the leader through their feedin tariffs
which essentially guaranteed a price for
solar electricity that incentivized the
growth in solar energy markets. And
there were other countries contributing
at this time as well with their
policies. But I'm just talking about
those that were leading in terms of the
size of their solar markets through
these policy instruments that they were
adopting. And then more recently, China
took over. And what you saw was that as
these different countries were growing
their market share through the use of
these policies,
private companies competed for market
share. They invested in this technology
trying to gain the advantage through
innovation over other companies. The US
also played a very significant role in
terms of government policy and investing
in research and development funding from
government that contributed a
significant amount to where we are now
with solar energy costs. So overall
we've seen that costs have come down by
more than 99%. It's a really rapid cost
reduction trend. Costs have been falling
by about 10% per year. Lithium ion
batteries are the one other energy
technology we've studied that have seen
such a rapid cost reduction. But solar
energy, it's so much cheaper than it was
a couple of decades ago. And when we
model this process, we can actually see
what's actually driving the improvement
at different levels. So we can see at
the level of engineering design how much
of the cost reduction came from
improving efficiency how much came from
improving different kinds of materials
that are used. When we look at all of
this at the global level what we
estimate is that about 60% of that 99%
cost decline came from market expansion
policies that then kickstarted a lot of
private sector innovation. So it was
really yeah it was really the private
sector that was innovating but it was
incentivized by these government nudges.
So there are many different types of
policies within that category. That's
one way to do it. And then about 30% of
the cost decline came from
research and development funding. And so
the bottom line is we can use these
kinds of insights from the past
to be more strategic going forward about
what we're investing in. So these kinds
of analyses can also be applied then
prospectively looking forward in time.
As listeners may know, the US didn't
sustain its lead in solar panel
manufacturing.
It wasn't able to sustain that lead. But
maybe with these kinds of insights, the
US or other countries or companies could
really find those mechanisms to invest
in, you know, at the high level in terms
of the policies, but also at the
engineering level. What are the key
mechanisms at the right time for
different kinds of technologies?
So, so let's talk about some of those
technologies because you know we there's
still a tremendous amount of innovation
going on in the United States not
necessarily in solar and wind although
there's still quite a lot going on both
of those as well but in other areas like
fusion magnetic fusion non inertial
fusion
nuclear fision the development of small
modular reactors and advanced reactors
is it is it possible that in a funny
kind of way that if we make solar and
wind too expensive and batteries too
expensive things that we tend to import.
Does it tilt the field in favor of those
other advanced technologies and maybe
give us a whole new kind of advantage?
Am I just being a mindless optimist or
is that even slightly credible to you?
>> Some of the technologies that you
mentioned are at very different places
in terms of their development
>> years years and years before we have
fusion reactors.
>> Yeah. And I mean I think there's still a
lot of opportunity to innovate in terms
of manufacturing but also the
installation, the deployment,
the business models in some of these
technologies that are already growing
rapidly at the global scale. solar
energy,
storage, solar coupled with storage,
solar and wind, uh, heat pumps,
electric vehicles, electric vehicle
batteries. You know, the charging
infrastructure for that could be
improved. There's a lot of room for
innovation in home energy systems. Uh,
demand side management is an area that
I'm interested in and that's been around
for a long time, but there's many new
ways to do it. I think that the US and
other countries that are not currently
dominating in these industries can still
do a lot within these industries that
are growing that are becoming rather
established. They can still participate.
I also understand Rob the reason for
mentioning some of the examples that you
did. So for example, there's a lot of
work happening on nuclear fision related
innovation in the US and
>> you know I just think though that it's
risky to step away entirely from the
technologies that are already expanding
and to not make an effort to take part
in that transition. You don't
necessarily want to try to do what other
companies if you're a company or what
other countries if you're a country
trying to incentivize innovation. don't
necessarily want to do what others are
already doing really well, but you can
take a part of that transition and you
can try to innovate there.
And I think you have to do more than
simply prevent those products from being
affordable in the US because at the end
of the day to be competitive in this
space, you don't want to just think
about what is within your national
borders. You need to be able to sell to
other countries. So the strategy of
saying okay let's step away from these
technologies that are produced by others
let's step away from those industries
and try to only support other ones that
are less mature and then sort of hope we
can catch up overnight and grow these
new industries you know simply adopting
policy in the US and focusing on the US
I think it's not really a winning
strategy it's certainly very risky I
think we have to take that global
perspective you mentioned and fusion for
example which is earlier in its
development and certainly that can be
part of the portfolio. So the goal you
have as a country versus a company is
quite different but both want to be
thinking about technology portfolios how
you're investing in technologies. You
can't invest in all of the above equally
because it's usually not a good
strategy. You want to see which ones are
maybe a little bit more likely to
succeed or a lot more likely to succeed.
But then you also want to invest in some
technologies where the future's very
uncertain, but they could be wildly
successful if things go, you know, the
way you want, if things go well. So you
want to have that balanced portfolio
and if you have the resources, you can
include riskier technologies, earlier
stage technologies. You could include
nuclear fusion in that portfolio.
But my point is that you also want to
continue to keep those markets that are
already growing the technology serving
those markets. You want to keep those in
your portfolio as well. You can try to
offer a better service. You know, for
example, a more robust home energy
system, a faster way to complete
construction projects, that sort of
thing.
So I mean I wonder if there's a
technology or two that if you are
looking forward now this could be
looking at the US it could be thinking
about globally but that you find
particularly exciting and that you feel
like is a game changer.
>> So I think what I'm excited about is
actually the fact that we have more
tools that we can use to provide this
high quality energy service.
you know, one that's cleaner that causes
less negative health impacts, one that's
more convenient, one that hopefully will
provide more affordable energy,
including to people around the world
that don't have access to modern energy
services, but even within countries like
the US, people don't always have access
to highquality energy services, reliable
energy. So, there's just more tools that
we can work with. So, what are some of
these additional tools? I've already
mentioned a number of times solar and
wind energy, but just to come back to
that for a moment, one of the nice
things about solar and wind, other than
the fact that their costs have been
coming down, is that they're available
in many parts of the world. So, you have
this resource if you combine the right
amount of solar, right amount of wind
for a particular place, you know, if
you're strategic about those
percentages, you can get a pretty
reliable resource. So if we take
Scandinavia for example, this is a
region and actually let's talk about the
Nordic countries which includes a couple
more countries. This is a region that
has nearly reached complete
decarbonization. So almost entirely
removed CO2 emissions from its electric
power system. And so what are they using
for generating electricity? They're
using nuclear energy. They're using
hydro power. They're using some biomass.
They're using solar. They're using
increasingly wind energy. So, they've
created this lowcarbon electricity
system. Not every country has those same
resources. But my point is that
depending on where you are, you can sort
of mix and match these different
resources. So with these additional
tools, with these large energy resources
and then also with the ability to use
electricity
for more services, you know, you can use
electricity now for much of your
transportation if you want. You can use
it for your heating through heat pumps.
These give you more options as well for
getting rid of carbon emissions, for
developing that reliable energy system.
So I think it's really that combination
that I'm excited about. But there's also
other aspects I think are encouraging
and sort of interesting to see where
things go. Demand side management is one
technology that we need to look at. It's
been around for a while, but there's
potentially the need for much more
demand side management. There is
potentially more economic value in
demand side management going forward
because you have these fluctuating
energy resources like solar and wind.
You have potentially new demands for
electricity coming on board. So you want
to manage those fluctuations on the
demand and supply side. So what is
demand side management? It's basically
saying that you're shifting demand
around in time and space. So you are
maybe charging your vehicles and with
demand side management you could be
incentivized to charge your vehicles
during certain times. And we published a
paper a couple years ago looking at
simply installing
workplace charging. What we see is that
simply by installing those electric
vehicle chargers at the workplace, the
effect can be very significant in terms
of smoothing out the peak and
electricity demand in the evening, kind
of flattening what would otherwise be an
evening peak. That's great because you
can save on building power plants. You
know, by putting your chargers in the
right place, you may not have to build
as many power plants. And you could also
use what will otherwise be solar energy
that may be wasted on the grid. So
that's an example of demand side
management. And in that case, you know,
you don't even necessarily have to ask
people to change their behavior or
charge at certain times. It's really
just about putting the physical
infrastructure in the right place.
You're putting it where people are
naturally parking during the days. And
so that's one example. And there's other
examples of demand side management, too.
you could incentivize using
a bit less energy at certain times.
That's not very popular. But what we're
seeing now is that some companies are
saying, "Oh, yeah, you know, if you're
willing to pay us that much, because
actually the savings to the system can
be very significant, they're saying,
okay, if you're willing to pay us that
much, we're more than willing to make
our demand, some portion of our demand
flexible." I mentioned heat pumps
before. You can use what are called air
source heat pumps where you're drawing
from the air so that the air is sort of
providing your temperature differential.
But you can also do water source heat
pumps. You can do ground source heat
pumps. And these water source ground
source heat pumps can be advantageous in
certain climates where you have very
cold temperatures. So this is another
exciting area of innovation. Geothermal
overall is an interesting area. There's
so many different areas and so I think
there's definitely a need to diversify
the portfolio, but still I think it
really does make sense to stay involved
in those industries that are currently
rapidly growing and find ways to
innovate within those. instead of a
specific thing like wind, you're kind of
excited that there's a new way of maybe
looking at grids and making them work
with like all the tools in the toolbox.
>> Yeah, exactly. grids and just using
electricity for more energy services.
You know, that's something that we
talked a little bit ago about these
trends. And that's a trend that I think
is also difficult to stop because
there's there's just an inherent
advantage to being able to plug in and
power something. You know, not like if
we were char if we were charging the
batteries here on our um devices using
like a generator and we had to think
about going and you know refueling or or
you know getting fuel for that. That's
just it's just inherently less
convenient than if you can just plug
into a grid an an electric power grid.
It's cleaner. It's easier. So I think
those, you know, that is a change that
I'm excited about and I think it's going
to continue. It's one that's difficult
to stop that transition.
>> So where does the where does the um
momentum or inertia come from in these
trends and a lot of what you do in your
research relates to trends and how
things are going to be in the long term.
A lot of that comes from cost, but how
much of it comes from
trying to capture foreign markets,
trying to head off climate change,
trying to create new industries, trying
to employ people. I mean, you know,
there there are many other things that
ultimately bring innovation to the
market besides the brilliance of the
initial invention. I think you call
those elements of the structure of
practice and some of the things you've
written. So the question is where does
the the momentum come from? What
incentivizes people and what do you
think is preserved
as as we go through this maybe short
period of change, maybe a longer period
of change where we're trying to
repatriate manufacturing.
>> At the end of the day, it's about
people working and you know getting paid
to innovate in these areas, right? Like
that's where it starts. It starts with
people. And if we look back over the
last 40 years, there's been a lot of
innovation in batteries and solar
energy, wind energy. Before that, as I
mentioned at the outset, we've had a lot
of improvements. The first coal fired
power plant started out at 3% efficient.
In 1882, I think in the US, and that
efficiency has increased substantially
to above 30% efficient on average, I
believe in the US right now. and it can
be higher than that. Um, so you know
it's like where did these changes come
from though, right? what what actually
has worked and I think we'd be
hardressed actually to find a historical
example of where
tariffs or sort of preventing
the flow of knowledge embodied in
technology has actually worked in terms
of benefiting new industries, new job
creation, technological innovation. I
mean there may be an example but one
isn't coming to my mind based on the
work I've done and so what what has
worked is to invest in
these changing industries these changing
technologies right you had Denmark that
adopted a lot of wind and there are kind
of homegrown industries benefited and
innovated and took a lead in terms of
both wind turbine manufacturing as well
as wind installations s and China of
course has also since then grown and and
really dominates in that area as well.
But you know Denmark's a tiny country
and they're still playing a major role.
So the examples that come to mind of
these strategies in terms of growing
industries, innovating, growing jobs
have really been about investing in in
in change and seeing what innovation
comes out. You know, there are
signatures in the data of where things
are going. The future is never perfectly
predictable, but I think ignoring the
signals in the data and sort of trying
to step back, trying to reverse these
processes of technological change is
more likely to result in actually not
staying at the forefront.
So, you know, this isn't exactly what
you were saying, Rob, but I think it it
relates to it. Um and I and I do agree,
you know, we want to diversify our
investment portfolios
and invest in a range of technologies,
but we also want to place bets based on
the information we can get in data and
actually technology change is not as
unpredictable as some people think. You
have created data models that sort of
look ahead at you know what the rate of
adoption might be, how fast we can go,
that sort of thing. give me an example
of what you're seeing and how you think
about like what those models may be
telling you.
>> There's a couple things we learned. I
mean one is that you know when we
started looking at a range of
technologies including energy
technologies what we saw was that
actually Moors law is not just for
computers. So we found and you know
published a paper in 2013 showing that
many technologies follow exponential
improvement trends and that simple
models like Moore's law and something
called Wright's law actually have some
predictive power in terms of giving us
some information about how technologies
are going to change in the future. Those
predictions are never perfect and you
always want to estimate the uncertainty
associated with those predictions, but
it's a good starting point. So that's
one thing is that you can use these
these data trends to get a sense of how
things are changing. The other thing
that we've looked at is ways in which
you can identify specific you know
aspects of technologies what we call
mechanisms of innovation to invest in
that may bring about the effect that
you're looking for. So you can actually
model a technology look at how all of
its different interconnected parts might
be able to change and then use that
information to inform what bets you're
placing. You know, should you invest in
greater efficiency or using less
materials? Or even at a higher level, is
it more about research and development
investment or is it more about scaling
up manufacturing? Or at the policy
level, should we invest in research, you
know, should governments invest in
research for this particular technology
or is it more about stimulating markets
and competition in the private sector,
you among companies that are going to
improve these technologies. So it really
doesn't have to be entirely guesswork.
And that's also where I come back to,
you know, regardless of your politics.
It's like let's take this information
that we have about how technologies
change, which ones are changing, you
know, trying to pull back from electric
vehicles, trying to pull back from
solar, wind, from energy storage, you
know, it's it's again it's it's not it's
just risky if you look at where the you
know what the data is telling us. I'm
not saying you can't slow it down or
make things more noisy, more volatile,
but I just don't think it's going to be
successful strategy in the medium to
long term.
[Music]
I wonder how you're feeling about the
future and uh we've talked about a lot
of things. You think you your work has
this sort of predictive element to it.
What do you think when you think about
the present but but also think about
what's ahead and and I I wonder what
your sort of level of optimism is?
>> Yeah, I mean I think I focus less on am
I optimistic or pessimistic but more on
like what is it that we want to try to
achieve with the future of technology.
You know sometimes it's it's about
understanding what is it that people
need. We touched briefly on electric
vehicles which is something that I've
worked a lot on. So maybe I can give an
example from that. You know there one of
the questions was okay well given how
people are driving how they're moving
around in their vehicles what would they
want their batteries to do for them? How
good do batteries need to be? Where
would they want the chargers to be? And
actually what we found was that you know
despite the fact that everybody's
driving differently
some people drive much more some people
drive much less and if you want to cut
your carbon emissions best thing to do
is to walk and next best is bike and you
know then public transit and so forth.
But you know if you look at how people
are are driving and despite the fact
that people have very different patterns
and how they go about their day, what we
find is that there are ways in which you
can really shape the technology toward
meeting all of these people's needs.
There are key locations where you want
to put chargers and if you invest in
chargers in those locations, you're
going to meet the needs of maybe 80% of
people. If you randomly put chargers in
shopping malls and other, you know,
public locations, you might meet the
needs of about 5% of the population,
right? So, and that's just one example.
That's just electric vehicles. You know,
we we saw that, okay, if you improve
batteries by this much, that helps, but
there's what's called a heavy tail.
Everybody has these high energy days. So
there you need to put chargers, fast
chargers in certain locations along
highways and along rural roads to make
sure people can charge when they need
to. So that's just one example, but my
point here is that we can also study how
it is that people are using technology,
what it is that they need, and then
another way to shape innovation is to
direct development toward those goals.
So Jessica, how do you think about, you
know, going from
early stage inventions to deployed
inventions at scale and and and what
that process looks like and and you know
what do we lose with tariffs? Do we lose
any of that? Is that does it change?
Yeah, I mean I will say that with the
innovations successes that we've seen,
you know, solar energy costs coming down
by more than 99%, wind energy costs
falling exponentially as well, battery
costs uh improving. You know what you
see is that part of what drove these
technologies forward was competition at
the global scale and companies competing
with one another to gain market share
globally. That's a larger market that's
going to drive faster progress. So I
think that's really important.
The other thing is that you know if we
think about what does it take for a new
technology to get invented to you know
see innovation which then involves the
adoption or the use of that technology.
It normally takes as especially in this
space of of energy what we've seen is
that it takes some early government
policy interventions and some investment
in research but also some incentives for
companies to grow markets and you know
for consumers to to purchase these
technologies and then you kick off this
process of competition and like I said
that we've seen that happening at the
global scale And the interesting thing
that we see from our research is that
you can actually be pretty strategic I
think in what mechanisms
you invest in in this process. So what
do I mean by that? But what I mean is
that you can take a technology like say
solar cells and say okay if I improve
these materials and this you know
improve the efficiency by this amount
how much might the costs come down and
then from there you can say okay are we
at a point now with this technology
where we should invest more in research
or more in scaling up manufacturing to
get economies of scale and then from
there you can actually go all the way up
to a policy level and say, "Okay, how
much do we want to balance our
investments in in growing markets and
stimulating private sector competition
versus investing in government funded
research?" So, this can be a pretty
deliberate process. There's always
uncertainty, but I do think that there's
ways to actually,
you know, be strategic, be deliberate in
how these investment decisions are being
made, even, you know, more so and much
more so than we've done in the past.
These are really interesting points. You
know, with globalization comes global
scale. And so, yeah, much more intense
competition, comparative advantage for
some who wouldn't otherwise be able to
provide these things within their own
markets, but also the scale of market
and the opportunity to achieve economies
of scale. And those those things we lose
if if we delobalize or or withdraw. And
it would be very hard for us to bring
new technologies to market solely within
the domestic market of the United
States. They'd be inferior technologies.
They'd be more expensive for a number of
reasons.
>> That's um a potential outcome and a very
scary one. You have done research
looking at how we take sort of highlevel
very broad targets and goals for the
climate and then translate them into
performance targets for specific
technologies. What did you find out in
doing that work?
Well, so two examples I think were some
of the early examples of this work and
then we've extended it to other cases.
But uh one was the case of stationary
energy storage because there was a
widespread recognition that we wanted to
bring we meaning people working on
energy storage wanted to bring the cost
down of energy storage. You know like
batteries for example that are
stationary so they don't have to be
lightweight. they can have higher
volume.
There was a widespread recognition that
cost should come down. Everybody knew
that. But the question was, you know, by
how much should the cost come down in
order for this technology to really make
a difference? And so that was one
question that we that we posed. And you
know, we started looking at an
application of storage where you're
using storage to do what's called price
arbitrage. So you're selling electricity
when the price is high and then you're
storing, you know, you're you're storing
that solar and wind energy when the
price is lower.
But we were able to arrive at a cost
target for storage. And then we
ultimately looked at, okay, if you want
to be able to meet all demand with solar
and wind or just 95% or 90%, what should
the cost of that energy storage be? And
there's always uncertainty of course,
but we were able to zero in on a
quantitative target that then has been
helpful in you know comparing different
technologies coming out of startups for
example or more mature companies that
are trying to bring their costs down.
though at the time we found that you
want to see a further, you know, if you
really want to get to really cheap
energy storage that can support very
large uh amounts of solar and wind and
even getting close to a completely solar
and wind dominated power grid, you want
to bring battery costs down an
additional maybe 80 to 90% relative to
where they are now, which could be
doable. I mean, it remains to be seen.
So, that was one example. And then the
other one was looking at electric
vehicles and saying where would you put
well first of all how much do you want
to improve the energy density of
electric vehicles and then where would
you put chargers electric vehicle
chargers what power should they have and
that involved looking at how people are
driving around in their cars where
they're stopping for how long. We were
able to identify some locations that
were, you know, predictably really high
payoff in in terms of supporting
people's need for charging without
causing delays, you know, without
causing them any inconvenience. really
understanding who your consumer is and
what they need because if you don't meet
those needs then
>> and I think with the with the stationary
storage it came down to patterns in the
uh solar and wind resources you know
like what were the fluctuations in those
resources what were the characteristics
the characteristic patterns there that's
what ultimately defines that storage
cost target
>> sounds obvious when you say it but you
know people really don't do these
analyses
It's and very often we're we're aiming
for a target which is you know merely
cheaper than it is now but it it maybe
taking in a direction that's still
completely untenable.
I won't name technologies but I mean
some that are near and dear to my heart
have that tendency.
>> Yeah.
>> Jessica, thanks so much. This is great.
>> Thanks Jessica.
>> Yeah, thanks so much. This was great.
[Music]
What if it works is a production of the
MIT Energy Initiative. If you like the
show, please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen. And remember to
subscribe on Apple Podcast, Spotify, or
wherever you get your podcasts.
You can find an archive of every
episode, all of our show notes, and a
lot more at energy.mmit.edu/mpodcasts.
And you can learn more about the work of
the energy initiative and the energy
transition at energy.mmit.edu.
Our original podcast artwork is by
Zitler Design. Special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible. I'm Cara Miller.
>> And I'm Rob Stoner.
>> Thanks for listening.