Open education here means open resources
in and outside of the classroom for our
students.
We're inventing a more open future for
all curious minds by sharing a treasure
of knowledge for you to discover
anywhere, anytime.
We're rethinking open by recognizing
voices and expertise from people of
diverse backgrounds are absolutely
necessary for expanding and growing open
educational resources.
>> 20% of our faculty have adapted, adopted
and/or created OEER. We are inventing a
more open future for all consumers and
producers of knowledge by leading in the
development of sustainable open
publishing models and open-source
publishing technologies. We are
relentless in our pursuit of a more open
and equitable scholarly landscape.
>> Open is democratizing learning and
knowledge to the world.
[Music]
here. Open is in our DNA.
>> It captures Arab commitment to sharing
our best educational contributions in a
way that everyone can build on them and
make them even better.
>> Here, openness is a core value. We share
information, innovations and ideas with
enthusiasm. We champion open courseware,
open access, and open science. All
crucial to our mission. Our doors are
open, too. So, come join us.
>> Come join us.
>> Come invent with us.
>> We can't wait to welcome you.
>> I think you would enjoy seeing Cambridge
and I certainly look forward to meeting
you. So, let's do it.
[Music]