Up next, please welcome Bevel Software.
Bevel Software, which is uses NAI
enhanced step-by-step reverse
engineering approach to help companies
quickly adapt to change with minimal
risk.
>> Okay. Hello everyone. Um, let me try the
pager here.
Oh.
Spoilers.
[laughter]
All right. Hello everyone. So I'm the
founder of Bevel. I was a previous
researcher at CCI under Thomas Malone
where I started to see a little bit of
the challenges of deploying agents in
industrial settings. I'll talk to you
today about UTCP and how to integrate
LLMs and agents securely in your
organization. So before we get too much
in the crux of it um why is this
important especially at coms the next
phase of the engine is being defined and
it's going to be agentic in some way and
it's going to be a lot of connecting
capabilities and APIs to agents. The
question is what are agents? What is
tool calling? Well, LM agents are
autonomous LMS that make decisions under
complex environments and tool calling is
giving them these superpowers, these
capabilities, connecting them to the web
browser, connecting them to Gmail,
letting them be able to take decisions
and kind of act in those environments.
Now, what is the problem? Well, actually
deploying this, I don't know if anyone
has ever tried, but deploying the
deploying this securely in industry is
actually very very challenging. The
reason is because you have three
options. The first one is to do nothing
and wait for the technology to get
better, which happens. But if you don't
want to be left behind, what you can do
is also build custom API integrations to
every agent. And once you're dealing
with tens or dozens or hundreds of
agents and dealing with hundreds of
APIs, this becomes a very technic like a
very large engineering effort. The other
option is to use existing protocols such
as MCP that um Dr. Clark talked about
earlier um to connect your internal APIs
and your internal capabilities to your
LM agents. But the problem with that is
actually it's not secure. You're adding
a new calling layer that is not battle
tested, that is not used before and
increasing the attack surface. So kind
of to summarize this, you could rebuild
all the tool integrations to your
agents. You could use existing protocols
and and improve the increase the attack
surfaces and and the security risk. But
what if there was a fourth option? What
if you could use UTCP that is both
scalable and secure?
What is UTCP? Well, UTCP is a protocol
that actually uses your battle tested
infrastructure to connect it to the API.
It's secure, it's scalable, and it's
neutral by definition. It's secure
because it connects it makes the
connection directly without having to
add a new layer. Um, that could be a
security challenge. It's scalable
because it's lightweight and very easy
to implement for the agents and it's
completely open source and neutral.
We're actually even talking to the Linux
Foundation so to make sure that UTCP is
as vendor neutral as possible.
Now what is the secret sauce? Why does
this work? Well, let me compare a very
quick comparison to MCP maybe to get a
hands-on who knows about MCP in this
room.
All right. Um, so MCP, what MCP does is
it adds a new server between your API
and your agent. That creates a huge
security risk because it could either be
an MCP server that you don't know or
even if you build it yourself, it could
be a new attack surface for people to
jam. However, with UTCP, what we do is
we actually do these instruction set,
these descriptions, what we call
templates that just describe to the
agent how to call the API, what par
parameters are used, and what data does
it need, etc., etc., etc. But that way
keeps the security in check and the
scalability also
implemented.
So we have already been working with
companies to actually implement this and
we see the engineering effort is so much
less. You don't need a new MCP server
for every API. You don't need to buy to
build custom integrations for every
agent. Um the workload is much much more
lightweight meaning faster innovation
for you, less engineers and stronger
capabilities faster. For example, we're
working with senior architects at AWS
that have a lot of independent server
providers. And these ISPs have just a
lot a lot a lot of internal APIs. And
what Luca Prosi said, for example, a
senior architect at AWS was that they
could reimplement everything
theoretically for their clients, but it
was just too much work to do with MCP.
And with UTCP, they get the security
they need, the scalability at a fraction
of the engineering effort. So if you
want to deploy LLM agents and you want
to do it faster and securely, we'd love
to talk to you. We'll be at the exhibit
right there. Um I would love to speak
about how you can make autonomous
agentic first organizations. Thank you
very much and it was a pleasure talking
to you.
[applause]
>> Thanks Juan. Any questions from the
audience?
>> Well, can you tell me why do other
protocols fall short fall short in the
security? Yeah. So actually the only
other protocol is MCP. Um the other
protocols I don't know how this works.
The other protocols are usually agent to
agent or even agent commerce but MCP
specifically just improves the attack
surface whenever you're building it
yourself. And what happens a lot is
there are existing MCP servers you
connect can connect your agents to but
they are unverified and they could be
they could inject malware or inject a
lot of bad context to your LM agents. So
UTCP kind of uses existing
infrastructure instead.
>> Any more audience?
>> Okay, one more question. Why does UTCP
require less engineering effort?
>> Yeah, so once you have like hundreds or
more of potential APIs or data sources,
it just requires a lot of effort to
rebuild your infrastructure.
Essentially, the internet is being
rebuilt for the AI agents, right? We're
talking about all of the internet being
accessible and you can rebuild all of it
and have to rebuild all the security for
AI agents or you can leverage it and
connected directly to LLMs even as they
get more capable. So that way it's just
much more straightforward.
>> Thank you so much Juan. All right,
any other questions? All right. Okay.
Thank you.
>> Thank you very much.