And so now uh for the final part of the
third lecture uh where we'll talk about
the uh three crunches that you'll be uh
doing. So in the first two crunches um
we'll ask you to predict the effect of
uh held out genetic perturbations uh on
the adiposite uh gene expression
profile. So on the gene expression
profiles of uh the individual uh cells
and um the difference between crunch one
and two uh is that uh in crunch one
you'll be using this single gene uh
knockout uh data set that we spoke about
experiment one uh while in crunch two
you'll be working with this uh double
gene knockout experiment um what we
introduced earlier as experiment two
and um what we'll be evaluating on um is
first of all how you perform uh on whole
transcriptto uh predictions. So
predicting the expression level and uh
in parallel we'll also evaluate on um
the uh ability of your models to predict
the proportion of uh cells expressing
each of the programs that we've spoken
about and are interested in. So the uh
differentiation programs and uh some
metabolic programs and so we'll announce
winners uh separately for each of these
tasks um and uh separately for each of
these two uh crunches.
So for crunch three we'll instead uh be
asking you to propose new double
pertubations. So two gene knockouts uh
that skew the proportions of uh specific
adiposite states. So for example uh
we'll be asking you what the the top 2G
knockouts are that your model predict
will most push towards this uh
differentiated adiposite state and
initially there won't be uh new data
that uh will be generated for this
crunch but uh the winners of crunch one
and the winners of crunch 2 will have
their uh top predictions uh their top uh
double perturbation predictions
experimentally validated and this will
be the set that everyone um is
evaluating. ated against
um so everyone should participate. Okay,
so that's it for the introductory uh
lecture series. Thank you for following
along and we can't wait to see uh what
you create.