I now have a very hard task I need to
pronounce names properly which I will
I'm sure not do but let me introduce
each of our panelists ask them to join
me up here and I'll start with paramar
from uh scg if you could please join
me and then a Tom from leader fold
[Music]
group JJ Jang from CP
group and finally cherum porn from
Bangkok Bank please join us
[Music]
so for me this is going to be fun it's
like an oral exam um but I won't treat
it that way but the goal is to talk
about integration of AI into businesses
and we've got four leading Executives
from from a range of of disciplines um
here in Thailand to give us that sense
um I'm going to moderate this I'm going
to ask panelists um we won't get to all
10 questions I gave you we'll get to
most of them them um I'd encourage you
to keep your answers succinct but to the
point we want to hear what you have to
think but we each spend 10 minutes on a
question we're going to do one and a
half questions uh and I'm going to jump
around on the questions but I I know
you've all thought about these and I
want to start with the integration
question um AI continues to evolve um
what are the most impactful ways in
which your company either has or plans
to integrate AI into your operations and
if you can share an explicit example uh
of how AI has driven a business outcome
that would be great um and I don't know
if somebody wants to start if not I just
pick volunteers but
uh per okay I think I'm next to you
so uh it's very clearly that SD has uh
looked at AI as uh something that
provide huge
opportunities and also threats okay uh
we are you know looking for to get
benefit from AI in in four level uh the
very basic one is the for each of our
individ uh individual employees to have
their know productivity gain okay uh uh
roughly we have just done a survey and
uh they said that they are gaining
around 10% of productivity which was to
our surprise okay maybe because the the
the base is very low I think the next
level of benefits that we we are trying
to get is to have uh and of uh big
impact on productivity gains and better
customer experience and we are seeing
some of the benefits already I give you
some example maybe later in in the in
the session and finally uh we are not
there yet but I think we are aiming uh
to achieve that that is to to have ai to
help us come up with either new business
model or a business reprocess okay we
can even with the same uh business we
can totally overhaul the uh the process
how we how we do business and uh we have
so far you know structure ourself and uh
uh employ resources accordingly okay for
example on the second level of getting
big impact we have uh know uh example uh
group groups of people in four main
areas
operations R&D
uh sales and marketing and then the
admin administrative uh uh activities so
we have champion on each of the uh you
know uh of the discipline and quite
fortunate that you know uh as a congrate
we have various kind of knowledge and
expertise and with this kind of
structure we are seeing some of the
cross pollination some cross Lage of all
the you know AI activities and and
benefits I guess I would stop here first
so that other yeah thank you if I can
add to it really quickly really
interesting to hear the range and I'm
fascinated by the fact that early on
things like productivity Improvement are
things you can do but you ultimately
want to get to business processes and
business plans and that's I think really
valuable but thank you that's great H
yep okay um I have a good pleasure from
him so let me try uh so for M groups so
we operate uh our biobased business from
Shuka of course and along the w chains
so uh we focus on um Farm to Table value
Shain Transformations which uh it evolve
from the digital Transformations into AI
transformation strategies so we focus
around four dimension of transformation
balance scard so the first area is
around to improve business performance
uh both the Top Line uh and the bottom
line uh among our 30 project of AIML
that we are running uh we have around
six projects that already reached
technology liness level seven and above
which have start to uh generate the
business impact like uh over 5 million
some of models for examples so that is
one category of the intention that we
aim to use AI to drive business
performance second uh Dimension is
around to improve stakeholder experience
in our case uh it's not just customer
but it's a Upstream meaning Farmers
supplier communities to the customer so
in our case uh we uh provide provide the
tools like AI to improve stakeholder
experience like to the farmers we
provide the um tools like ekyc to
onboard them so in the past it took a
few weeks for them to on board to engage
with midon and now with the AI and ekyc
and Technologies we reduce the time to
just 5 minutes uh for uh 25 Farmers
across uh the factory that we operat so
that improve the experience of our
stakeholders uh in term of productivity
we also um Drive adoption of AI uh at
the current stage we um develop mgpt the
internal version of the the GPT uh 40 uh
and already used by um 2.5 th000
employees uh with the Run rate of
consumption um close to 1 billion token
annually so um that also improve the
productivity of our employee as well uh
and finally we focus on the digital
capability of employee so we aim to
drive like 5,000 uh digital uh AI
literacy of employee which we work with
uh h a lot to develop the capability
development programs yeah so already a
lot in place which is really great thank
you
JJ yeah so CP group is a lot
conglomerate in many vertical so I just
mention a few
examples so we use the food for traffic
of our Telecom to help open 7-Eleven
store choosing the right location right
that helps with 14% increase of revenue
for the new Star open so I think that's
good and then the we use AI technology
you our fintech solution have zero zero
account being taken over by scammers or
so so I think that's a another another
thing right and we use uh customer
support AI technology in customer
interface that improve uh NPA score to
over 95% right so I just mention a few
example that past we have been doing
right and then we also use AI for
network uh Telecom Network Energy
Management that helps reduce energy cost
by 10% over so I think that's a that's a
few example but we Haven the there are
many AI from the large language motor
side we are getting in but that's that's
we'll talk later yeah okay and and again
I think interesting that there are lots
of productivity things that are easier
to deal with but thinking about
improving the customer experience is
part of this as well and all of you are
thinking about that at some level of of
how do you change it CH
por U at the bank there at least uh
three specific areas and one General the
first specific area is on the fraud
fraud detection yes and uh has been in
the past three years the number of fraud
case increased dramatically especially
on the retail like Mobile Banking uh so
we have a lot of rules now that popping
up and it's getting better and better um
the second one will be the uh uh for
most of the time to transfer fund to the
other person now you you require a if
it's above 50,000 B you require the face
recognition the live uh test that type
of thing so and and this has to um I
think every few months you notice a uh a
new a new a better performance uh coming
up uh faster and more accurate Etc
uh the third one is is about the um the
credit card the the delinquency
prediction uh using the uh more data
than what we the bank used before but
for us this is just a beginning but I
think this is an area of a of a
tremendous opportunity to improve uh the
last one is on
operational uh this is spand across most
of the bank area because we are in
almost every area we have all like
paperwork or operational and so these
now we focus on the input uh because a
lot of input now we just automated using
uh character recognition uh uh uh using
image Etc so that that improved uh on
the cost side a great deal so these are
great and I'm going to follow up for
those of you who want to to respond to
it and chairo part of it was driven by
what you said there are things that are
operational that improve the performance
of the company that's valuable it
reduces costs but your example of of um
you know a transfer of funds above a
certain level that now it needs to do
face recognition before it will accept
it makes me wonder about and again for
any of you that want to respond to it
what's your customer EXP acceptance of
these Technologies I mean do people
resist a change in how they deal with
things or do they see this as a plus of
you know it's safer or it's better it's
more more efficient and again invite any
of you that would want to to ask but CH
point if you don't mind since you raised
it you know customer acceptance do they
find it invasive to do it or they find
it reassuring I heard both uh uh uh some
who really scared about the uh the the
fraud case Etc they they accept it quite
well but they complain that why sometime
you ask them to Blink three times and
smile and then and then uh uh you have
to take off your glasses and then we
couldn't understand the instruction that
type of thing okay yeah U so yeah that
there's both both ways others experience
with with customer
acceptance uh it's not an issue in our
case because uh know since we have tried
to enhance the capability of our shb we
never ask the customer to do anything
more so it's uh they don't feel anything
except that they get better faster
response more accurate response and uh
better information okay so basically we
we hide everything behind uh the engine
so that they they don't feel anything
yeah yeah yeah uh in our case um it's
it's more about when we do the
technology adoption for the the farmers
uh especially um many of them are older
Generations so it's um it's not like we
to them the tools the AI and whatsoever
and and um expect them to use it uh we
still mix it with a human touch so we
still need the people um to be with them
uh explain the Technologies uh uh
explain why it iserve to use when we
scan the phas if they have question we
answer when we scan the I ID card we
answer all that uh so yeah human tou is
what we we use to uh achieve the change
management part with the farmer
especially those who who don't familiar
with the Technologies uh yeah and and we
still that is the the key point that we
need to keep uh when we roll out
technology with the the farmer groups
yeah
great JJ do you want to add to this you
don't have to but I'd love to hear I I
think it's very good I you the Bankok
thing with face recognition right is
quite simply so we we do the uh the uh
EC right the the the kyc for the for the
our true money wet we make the biometric
process is simil right so to improve
customer experience and and customer
care after all we use AI to improve
customer experience and enhance NPS
score right so so so I think indan is
generally helpful right as long as you
simplify the step all the time right and
make it secure so so I think it's is
well accepted yeah that's great so I'm
going to switch to a a second topic
um as preface I think there are a lot of
workers that feel threatened um AI is
changing jobs uh it it's making some
jobs
much less useful if you like it's
certainly changing jobs I
I shouldn't say it's my favorite example
but when people ask me about jobs that
are are going to go away I would not
want to be a paralal today um at least
in the US because an AI system can do
the search it can do the uh writing of
motions it can do a lot of the things
although as you heard uh a lawyer in New
Jersey who had it actually write a
motion and didn't check it got into deep
trouble when it invented cases but you
know there are jobs that are going to
change with that as background
my question for you is how are your
companies thinking about this both the
talent gap of of hiring new employees
that have experience in this but also
just internal training or other ways of
trying to help student sorry help
workers upscale and related to that is
this a place where you think
universities should help um but I guess
let me phrase it better the question is
how are you dealing with um the Gap and
how are you dealing with trying to help
employees adjust to the fact that their
job may change
um par Mar I'm going to start with you
again eventually I'm going to go to the
other end and start down there so you're
not always trapped first but please okay
uh I think I I will start with the
mindset uh I know you start with the
question of do people feel threat of you
know having AI replacing them I think
our mindset is not doing the same with
less resources our mindset is doing more
with the same res
resources okay so our employee feel save
that they're not going to be replaced
but we want them to be more productive
so we can grow business with the same
amount of resources so obviously we have
been uh you know uh Paving a road map on
how to develop our uh talents I think we
use both not both all know buy borrow
and Bill uh on on the bill side we have
uh come up with uh you know very
activities and training programs to make
sure that I know our people firstly well
aware of the benefit of AI and they know
how to upskill themselves yeah yeah no
that's a really good point it's a really
good
point uh as for M group some what see uh
they separate between two part the the
uh collaboration with universities and
the talent souring part and also the
second part is around the talent
development uh but before that um I
think m is quite lucky that uh people
don't fear about placing jobs because uh
we aim for a lot of business expansion
and people feel like with that Target we
we never have enough people to to reach
the goal um so uh obviously AI will be
part of the the the the tools that help
uh people reach the goal um and we we
don't uh people don't don't have the
culture to fear the Technologies uh back
to the thaan sings uh we we do a lot of
mou with universities to to Source the
AI uh Talent uh with the professor um
like with the professor in the satellite
image processing that process um
satellite image that uh land scan
through the cloud for example uh
Professor that work on the specific
industry in the architect for example
and and so on or like logistic
optimization no uh in in that case and
we also do a lot of uh program with uh
student uh because now uh we cannot uh
recruit them after they graduate but we
need to uh make the student have
exposure with the project that we work
with them since year one even year one
in the bachelor degree um so uh like for
example recently we have the yes Heaton
event that we invite uh student from our
University in Thailand uh and then we
got around 60 people invited uh screen
and then compete in the the business
case of M group in four different
business unit and then that is one
example of how we develop the pipeline
of the salent that we bring to the the
company uh in term of the skill
development um this one thank to HR they
have like digital capability road map
for uh executive level and employee
level how we going to develop uh AI
understanding for both executive level
uh and for employee and then we try and
we also try to promote employee to uh
competitive in the the even internally
as well um like uh live last year uh we
have around 10 buus that compete in the
internal competition to build some um
local application some of them use AI uh
and and that is kind of the culture and
capab development programs that we have
in organization to promote them right
JJ our primary responsibility is to
protect our existing invest investment
so we will upscale the uh employee right
through many AI training program we we
done a lot of training and our CEO and
many executive here plead some of the
program to build Innovation ecosystem so
we have we are building a center of
Excellency for technology partnership uh
with International partner startup at
University we're doing a executive
training program with MIT in the
planning as well so so this is our our
group CEOs which
right we have two digital academy which
help train we have CP University and we
have this Center of exellency being set
up here and to facilitate that uh
process right of course we're open to
talk top expert in Ai and uh and we keep
a constant uh discussion with startup
and uh and big and small technology
company and China us Japan Singapore
Israel England right so we build all
this ecosystem so we don't we stay on
top of the curve that's great Turn Point
uh uh to drive uh ahead fast uh uh we
focus on the driving from the mid level
up the top of per perid first so try to
get the leader to pull their
organization forward so we use Partners
we have uh three group of Partners first
is definitely
universities uh uh both local and
International International definitely
is a m uh at the bank of bank we use
many program with MIT you know action
learning Etc you have students coming in
uh and that helps a lot um the second
one would be
the uh the software vendors yes because
they are real expert in some of the area
so so we use them
um and the last one would be the the
Consultants that has some specific
knowledge um and uh this way if we can
change the mindset and get the um get
the top management and middle management
get their feet wet uh uh and we relying
on them to drive the rest
yeah what I heard here was a a lot of
examples of ways in which you can
partner with universities uh I like your
example of also looking to the vendors
as an example you know grow with Google
is an interesting approach to trying to
deal with it part of my question is MIT
has certainly thought about using our
online learning platform not just to
offer MIT courses but to think about
could we create more specialized courses
smaller courses many employees don't
have 6 months to do something but and
I'm I'm inferring that this would be
something that you would see valuable in
in terms of doing let me put one other
piece on
this what's the role of the government
and I'll give you the example with the
as I'm sure you may know with the chips
act in in the US which passed last year
on
semiconductors part of that Act created
funding from the federal government to
encourage universities to create
specifically upskilling programs for
people in that IND whose job was going
to go away I don't mean to put the Thai
government on the spot here but but you
know is there a role for the government
to provide funding or do you think that
the companies just need to take care of
that themselves and just anybody who
wants to comment on that I'm curious
your
thoughts JJ looks like you're ready to
go I think I think government role is to
provide a sovereignty AI infrastructure
right I think they're in the plan
indirectly building s
infrastructure right it's very difficult
I think for TI private company to jump
in that space because this is a big boys
game in some require billions of
billions of dollar so we have to
essentially play our game smartly based
on uh leveraging the Giants sit on the
shoulder of the Giants right and the
leverage of domain knowledge and do a
way that don't get obsolete right but
riding on the evolution of the
foundation model and and both over the
world right so I think the agentic
framework as well as the the the the
application side which will try to shine
right and government of course should
support that effort with some some some
infrastructure support right but if they
have the money right and and that's a
thing that I
feel chort please the government has a
very important role as especially on the
education side and I think we have too
little number of uh too small number of
graduates in the science and technology
area and uh when I had a chance uh that
was way back about 10 years ago when it
was a stock exchange you went to Mexico
and you heard the president saying about
that country and they produce 100,000
engineer per year and I'm looking back
it what are we doing here and and and
that was 10 years ago but
nowadays the science technology is much
more important than 10 years ago yes and
that's a I think a great point that
universities can help with which is to
think about how can we influence earlier
education how can we influence K12
education an elementary school student
today uh and this came up in an earlier
discussion the jobs by the time they
graduate are going to be very different
than what they are today and so so
certainly government can encourage that
but I think it's also an opportunity for
universities to think about how do we
how do we help with this I'm going to
switch gears and again I'm going to pick
up um on on something that a number of
you have raised
um there are lots of users of AI who
worry about ethical issues and ethics
can be around privacy and and chair po
I'm going to use your example again I
don't mean to pick on it but I think it
was a great example of um you know you
do face recognition in order to do a
bank transfer I imagine you have some
customers who are uncomfortable about
what happens to that face image after
it's done I know in the US there are
people who object when they go through
security at an airport that that it's
face recognition so there there are
privacy issues there are also worries
about accountability in in terms of
using this um and and there's just
worries in terms of of legal liability
you know if a autonomous vehicle hits
somebody who's responsible um you know
the owner of the car the programmer who
created it um you know there's a whole
range of of issues around there how are
you and your company thinking about
essentially responsible AI us while
still maximizing what matters to you
which is how well you run the business
how do you think about basically these
ethical issues and I'm going to start in
the middle just to spare people so JJ
we'll go to you first on this one if you
could please just how do you think about
ethical issues
oh first of all transparent explain what
we do right because explainability is a
difficult thing but we explain through
transparency explained how we got there
right you know the whole neuron Network
large language model sometime you don't
really know how it inside work but we
talk about explainability in terms what
data source and why what is the purpose
and and and being transparent and and
make sure we don't do any bu right and
we have governance process also in each
project to to oversee this these things
right to avoid this uh ethical issue
yeah and so so that's it okay no that's
great CH horn okay
um
accountability is the responsibility of
of the the organization that like our
organization we
cannot uh Outsource accountability so
regardless of what if if you use it is
your your
accountability now the the problem is um
there are other layers such as
transparency Etc so as long as you um do
it with care to have the as transparent
as possible uh that would help
um uh but uh for the for the
AI a simple one that that I
experienced an easy
one um was that uh how do you know that
whatever you
say it has your organization name on it
now if if anything that is wrong because
of whatever AI told you to and you don't
understand where it came from yeah then
at the end of the days your um doing the
Christmas I I asked chat gbt to draw a
Christmas picture for me they said okay
U draw a golden eagle standing on a snow
and and the background is MIT Dome yeah
okay it came out very
nice but
unfortunately the Dome has a Capital
Hill Dome on it not an MIT though but
but the bottom is MIT and it has a US
flag on on it said I'm in Thailand I'm
I'm Tha you know so I asked them again
to please remove the flag they came back
with slightly different picture but the
flag flag is still there so chat gbt
does not know us Flags yeah okay so yeah
whatever you do or what do you say to
others and you use the information that
the chat GPT know well bear in mind that
uh it's
not that's not not it's smart but
sometime it he has his own problem it's
a it's a great example and I I
appreciate you're raising the um
ultimately the responsibility rests with
the company it is your name that's on
that and I think that goes back to this
question of how do you help your
employees your staff ask the hard
questions about is this the answer I
want is this something I'm that I'm I'm
I'm willing to deal with
and we'll come to that I think in the
next question but it's a good example
paramat yeah uh you know at the very
beginning of uh our AI Journey uh
responsible AI was one of the very first
topic that we discussed okay uh but
fortunately I think philosophically it's
something similar to the
pdpa okay so when we imp pdpa it's about
you know uh privacy it's about transpar
currency and by protecting others
identity and and information so uh it
was not that difficult for us to you
know uh uh adopt this and uh communicate
to employees but I must accept that you
know you need to take the right balance
because you
want certain level of freedom for our
employees to employ AI but you know at
the same time you want to make sure that
they are using it responsibly so uh we
have uh a body know at the corporate
level that have the governance policy on
that but again I know it's still about
the we call it a self governance okay
because we still want the ball to to
continue rolling yeah that's good call
Yeah in our case um quite similar to um
scg so uh we also treat them uh AI
governance um similar to data governance
uh and personal data protection
governance so all of them are quite of
many in under the GRC government Lis and
compliance uh at the corporate level so
uh we do have the corporate policy
endorsed by chairman level so meaning
all employee need to uh understand the
policy how serious that that we take the
the governance of this kind of thing uh
in place and then uh with all the policy
uh we continue to drive the
understanding of the employee what they
should do or not or should not do under
a different situation and employee we we
also appreciate that uh company has a
clear uh Direction about how what to do
and not to do under different situation
that's great I'm going to follow up on
this um
quickly with an odd question you may
think all my questions are odd but
that's okay um as you think about
ethical use of AI are there cultural
differences and I'll give you an example
which I'll do
quickly for the last several years I
I've given a series of three lectures at
the schwarzman college at Chena which is
a a great program of very International
of of Future Leaders on ethical use of
AI and we were talking about face
recognition and the use of face
recognition and in the US as I'm sure
some of you know there are cities that
have basically banned it there's real
concern about it and one of the students
totally surprised me it's a young woman
from France who was part of the program
who said you know last night at 1:00 in
the morning I was really tired of
working I needed some fresh air so I
just went out and I was walking on the
streets outside of chingua and I felt
completely safe because I knew that
there were security cameras everywhere
that there was face recognition going on
I felt very safe and it made me realize
there may be a cultural difference you
know you wouldn't you wouldn't succeed
with that in San Francisco or Boston but
there she had a very different view so
with that is a weird background
are there cultural differences and and
what you may Implement here will it be
different than something that gets
implemented elsewhere and how do you
deal with that and again if somebody
wants to respond to it I would love just
a reaction but are there cultural
differences to the ethical use of of of
AI
systems JJ you shouldn't nod your head
because I'll take that as a chance to
jump in but please I'm a long time
speaking here so I may speaking out of
steps right so we I I my experience that
we generally follow Europe uh standard
very well like pdpv gdpr right first of
all an AI act right but in terms of
trusting government certainly the China
side privacy is important actually in
China despite whatever the America says
right but they try the government right
because they equally apply to everyone
right even you the in the tally you get
a camera they will make sure that no
body Ste that toilet Ro right so so the
TR of the government I think may be a
little bit different from uh the US side
right it's all about experience right in
China used to be 7 million children get
stolen every year but now with camera
everywhere people are scared right so so
but I think Thailand somewhere in
between so I would say
yeah I have a a case of
Thailand um for information about your
credit
worthiness Tai they don't like anyone to
have it at all uh our our credit
bureau compared to us and China is very
poor in other
words information there is almost
useless to to to to anyone
um uh so so they don't want any of their
information to be public however on your
face your picture we post everything on
online you know Facebook everything you
you you see who you are everywhere I
don't think that's how I care about the
the the the your face is going to be
somewhere else you know no it's it's a
good examp recognize it's a good example
it's a good
example I'm going to link this to
another question that I know we
discussed earlier and that's um the
regulatory landscape because certainly
with ethical use regulations can be part
of that um and as we said earlier today
this is an area that's still very much
evolving um and and again as I said
earlier I give credit to the EU I think
they've taken a good run at this it's a
good start to it my question for each of
you is um how are you as a company
trying to engage with policy makers to
um to ensure that the the things that
you come up with using AI um are aligned
with regulatory requirements how are you
trying to help influence those and what
do you see is the the biggest risks in
in in this space of of um you know
either a lack of Regulation or an
overregulation actually getting in the
way of of of of using AI but the general
question is how are you thinking about
working with policy makers um to to try
and think about the right way to come up
with rails for this and uh I'm trying to
bounce around where I start with so aom
I'm going to start with you but um if
you don't mind and then we'll go down
the road but please thank you uh I think
for Thailand um and in asan regions uh I
think regulatory uh are not really
strict firstly uh as in European
countries um they are quite uh more
favorable to the business so uh for
example um the recent regulation around
data and Cloud uh they are kind of
consult with the business a little bit
whether how leate uh still possible to
allow business to operate in Thailand so
it it kind of um uh B directional uh
consultation between regulation and
private sector side um so I think the
the regulation will not be very strict
but in a way it will not uh really lose
uh as for Thailand so I think uh as for
uh private sect sector we yes definitely
we need to uh continue to monitors uh
the regulation uh as for M group we have
the uh the compliance team to always
monitor the regulation and also uh work
closely with uh uh government sector on
that part so uh once the there are
regulation especially lead to cloud data
or AIS then we translate into the the
GRC operations yeah that's great JJ
regulatory isues how are you thinking
about it my feeling is Tai is quite
conservative in regulation right they're
they're weak lose flexible execution but
they are quite strict in the government
side this is the feedback many startup
coming here they don't fa the the tire
is quite strict right in FDA Food side
of regulation in gen editing right in
data privacy the ACT is quite strong
because they follow the European side
quite strongly right but there is cing
more or less a little bit flexible right
as well right so so I think uh there
there's always Loop loophole gray area
like exom being used by many cosmetic
clinics even though is regulated
completely
forbidden their stem cell they're very s
right being and similarly I expect this
uh some of these areas right that could
be coming in right they just don't know
how to regulate this it right so they
look at the Europeans for the leadership
right which is on the conservative side
and then
adapted execution wise right this is
just my perspective observing here but I
find it in I find it interesting that
again that European model it's not
perfect it may not totally apply but it
is a model that that that placees used
to think about this right CH Point okay
I observed that uh the re reason why the
regulator came up with whatever rules is
because they they uh see the risk has
raised to the level where uh it has some
certain impact on social or or whatever
the day they regulate so what I'm
thinking is that uh we have to be able
to spot the risk
first of of what what are the Rison
using for example if
you um uh want to use
geni um uh the bank will not allow the
uh employees to use a public gen it has
to be an Enterprise wide yeah because
all of the information in public you
assume that it's going to be everywhere
anyway so we have to spot where where
are the risk and if it happen to be uh
something of concern we should find a
way to mitigate it first uh because we
know and if we
write that one will become the
regulation for sure and and therefore
we'll be ready uh rather than be
surprised by by uh the the regulator so
the last thing we want is we want we
don't want to be the last who who be
prepared and so I suggest that stick
closer to the regulator would be also
the best because if if U if you hear
something first uh you better move
quickly yeah it's a great Point perar Ju
Just to add on a little bit I think I
quite agree with that my observation is
that uh latory bodies are still quite
flexible uh uh in this in this
context uh but the other side of the
coin is that you know the risk is now
they are
I think figuring out what to do with it
my my my fear is that because
historically when Ty Regulators want to
come up with something they will go to
you know Europe and Japan and the US and
combine the toughest measure of all the
tree and put into one you know
regulatory paper and if that is the case
I think we're going to be in a very
different environment so I think I agree
with bishon that uh know even though
they are quiet now but once they you
know start to give up some signal we
need to be very proactively work with
them otherwise we're going to be facing
with something that we don't want to see
which is the toughest regulations in the
world and that last point I want to
dwell on just very
briefly there was a study done a few
years ago a survey done by one of the
business Consulting groups I I don't
remember which one it was Bane or kmg or
one of them but um where in different
countries they ask people who do you
most
trust to to come up with regulations and
um it was an interesting study if you're
interested send me a note I'll send it
to you but one of the things that came
up in that study and it goes back to one
of the earlier things said in China they
trust the government to to come up with
that regulation in the US they
absolutely don't trust the government in
Israel it's even lower than the US so go
figure where that is but the one that
consistently was high on on the list to
my surprise was
universities and I think the reasoning
was a nervousness and I think Parma it
relates to what you were saying right no
disrespect but if a government
bureaucrat is setting a regulation on an
advanced piece of technology do they
really understand it well enough to set
it um whereas one hopes that a
university researcher who doesn't have a
vested interest in in it might do a a
better job so I'm curious again any of
you that want to react should
universities play a role working with
companies like yours to help The
Regulators decide on this or should they
stay clear from
it I I actually see a lot of Regulation
recently that uh University uh sector
help to lead the public healing activity
with the private sectors so yeah I think
that that really um good point that that
you mentioned is really um easier for
private sector to to discuss uh openly
uh what are the concerns and and
whatsoever uh yeah so so I think uh yes
uh university did help so you just gave
us more work to do so thank you very
much but it's okay um JJ please go ahead
I my experience the tech government do
does work with University like as TDA
for example for many regulation right so
the private company can provide input
from a business perspective right but
they do work with University and
Research Institute in the way government
Affiliates yeah one last question on
this and then we're going to switch uh
and we'll leave a little time at the end
for questions from all of
you one of the things in the European
standards that I found intriguing was
again they had a set of levels of of of
AI that you
needed um the the the guard rails were a
little little different but one of the
things in many of them was that they
tried to Define standards of
performance that a product needed to
meet before the government would
authorize the use of that product in
your experience is that doable um you
know can you um can you say you need a
false positive rate of of this or a
false negative rate of that can you um
and I'm sure it depends on the area but
again for any of you that want to
respond can is it reasonable to think
about actually setting standards that a
new product has to meet before the
government would authorize its
use chort please one case is on the
performance of the the service that the
bank provide like the bank of Thailand
has a fairly strict
U but not regulated but but uh
supervision or whatever you call they
can find us uh if our Mobile Banking is
down more than 8 hours a
year that is really serious and it's is
published to uh everyone every month you
know so uh yes uh from the bank point of
view the standard can be set you can set
it that's that's really encouraging to
to hear JJ
please just pdpa is the example right we
follow the government directive to have
governance framework like having a data
officer with the process at least the
governance framework and we have to
State claims that obey the government
deadlines for certain degree but in
reality I'm not aware of anybody get
fund like the European uh I could be
wrong but you guys can tell me yeah so
I'm not aware in CP we got there right
so so like I said they generally
conservative on the regulation and
following the guideline but flexible in
allowance tolerance in execution so so
to so sometime we clean up in the back
hand to make sure we catch up but we are
may not be at the day one there but we
make sure the framework is there yeah
yeah I'm going to do oh sorry P Mar do
you want to say something oh please just
quickly I think uh generally
conceptually if can put standards on
thing it's good but whether you can
implement it you know but uh effectively
is is another story so I think on AI
something that is still moving very fast
I hope that they will not come up with
standards that will know inhibit the
progress of using
AI all right I'm going to do one last
question and then we'll we'll open it up
to the audience I can see we've already
got questions showing up
um it's probably an unfair question so
you don't have to answer it but um I'd
love to hear your
responses if you put
yourself we're what 2025 put yourself in
2030 5 years from
now what would you like to see as a
trend or capability from AI that would
have a dramatic effect not only on your
business but on your clients on your
customers what you know what would you
love to see so it's Crystal Ball we
won't hold you to it I don't know maybe
Todd when he runs this conference 5
years from now which you won't do we'll
ask you so what happened here but you
get the idea what what would you like to
see JJ go one thing humanoid robot
because we will have Labor issue tent
issue and efficiency issue to humanoid
robot right and of course today we're
already doing code writing and customer
care but in the food factory in the in
the retail store to do many of the I
would say more than human intelligence
right because they can recognize
misplace item with misplay price tag
right they can see something lying
around in the store right that could
trip customer so they can deal with it
as well so
so I I I love it and I'm going to do a a
blatant piece of advertising here
there's a company called Boston Dynamics
that makes a humanoid robot if you
haven't seen their video from two years
ago of their dancing robot go check it
it out it's better than most humans it's
not what you're looking for but human ey
robots other things what would you like
to see Chum porn what what please what
would you like to
see I would think
healthcare like ear early detection like
the the the the lecture this morning um
you can detect like breast cancer much
earlier the have thing uh that would
help because uh
um if not we all going to be bankrupt by
the yeah
um the cost the cost because now the
combination of insurance plus the high
cost in the hospital are uh eating up
your
budget so hopefully if we are not sick
or sick less uh that would help I agree
it's a great
example paramat um
well I might sound a little bit
different but um to to me I think in
this world the biggest problem or the
the most Waring trend is the increase in
inequality so I hope that AI uh in many
angles would be able to reduce that Gap
okay we talk about education how can you
know but people who doesn't have
anything can learn very freely uh know
the early detection of uh diseases of
the new drugs that are accessible to
more people so I think in in short to
reduce inequality yeah it's a great
example an uh as for me I think uh what
I wish is that uh in the next like five
years uh AI will um make sustainability
more accessible for more organization so
meaning now when we do the scope one two
three it take a lot of effort to early
collect all the information and
Implement all the actions even for large
organization along the whole value
chains uh not to mention nowme how they
going to do that so uh with the AI
Automation and everything uh I I hope a
I will make all the activity around this
entire scope 123 will become more
accessible and down to the level yeah so
I love the examples I think healthc care
is a great one I think inequality is a
great one I I I think uh you know
flexible use of AI is a great one I will
add my own person I shouldn't say
personal favorite but but one of the
examples for me is I really hope that
the technology for autonomous vehicles
gets to the level where it can really be
used because the cost to nations of not
just fatalities but just injuries is
massive and just the human loss around
that if you can drive automobile
fatalities close to zero it's a huge
impact on a country with that we have a
few minutes left um and I'm going to ask
the staff I know we've got a bunch of
things on the the list why don't we just
go to the the one that's at the top of
the list if you could post it up we'll
um
let somebody can do that for me please I
think it says uh something like we can't
read all of it because the clock's in
the way so in your opinion what would
be I don't see it up can you there we go
all right so the top one if you could
just highlight it
anybody that wants to take this in your
opinion what would be a good start first
starting point for a business to start
integrating AI so what's your advice to
your colleagues about how do you get
going and integrating AI into your
business customer care sorry Customer
Care customer caring that's a good
example other
thoughts chair I I just say just just
get the the leader of that bu unit to to
you have to educate them an awareness on
the benefit or the risk of not having AI
uh use as as a tool uh and uh yeah yeah
good AI is not free so you need to use
it effectively so I think the first like
like in many cases you have to get the
problem statement right first don't
start with AI but start with your
business cas T and then try to figure
out how AI can help you do that more
effectively and cheaply and faster yeah
yeah good example I think the first
thing is I think start with the ideation
among the leadership teams and get the
commitment and Alignment together what
the organization should do with with
thei yeah so increase the trust um you
know that that you're going to be able
to use it we got time for one more
question and so I'm got to try and read
that
um I'll do it this way talk about the
risk of data leakage privacy which is
believed to be difficult to avoid or
control is it worth to compare the
benefit uh of the AI new technology so
concerns about privacy and data leakage
thoughts go
ahead aamc go ahead okay I mean in our
case it's quite lucky because most of
the AI are not relate to personal data
yet so uh we are more around the
agricultures data around manufacturing
data for example so uh it's um sensitive
yes we don't want to have it leak but uh
at the same time it's not about personal
data when we we do it with AI so at
least uh we are quite um sever in this
case but uh anyway um the company will
need to do a lot of data protection
cyber security and everything
uh but uh I have to admit that at the
currently M we do the the traditional
cyber security practice but we are still
exploring the AI security uh so we still
exploring with a lot of partner how how
do we really protect the AI security
yeah that's great JJ go ahead so I've
been talking to people about
architecturing this properly right A lot
of people doing fine tuning right making
API Cod that that actually share some of
the Privacy data right with third party
so in that respect you also lose out
when the foundation model evolve become
more powerful so you have to retain
again so cost more lot of money or
alternatively you can take a different
architecture that using your internal
data applying traditional AI tools that
get some database knowledge some graph
right but let the foundation model
Loosely Couer so as Foundation model
evolve increase you don't get affected
and you save your money and data privacy
as well risk right of course you have
all the internal uh governance but I'm
just talking about from architecture
perspective that you protect about your
future because Foundation model evolve
often supp the specialized model so you
want to make sure the foundation model
continue to improve and your specialized
knowledge remain being applicable to
that new Foundation model so using
agentic framework using Loosely AR cered
architecture this will help as well it's
a great
example I'm going to ask the audience a
favor and I know I've had my back turned
to this side of the audience much please
join me in thanking our four panelists
for what I hope you found a really
interesting discussion thank you
gentlemen
[Music]