All right, I think we are ready for this
first session. My name is Dontis. I'm
from Mos University and I'm also a part
of the NF NF um center and uh I'm
chairing this session and I have been
really looking forward to uh to hearing
uh these three speakers and the session
is on scaling variant interpretation and
the first speaker is Ruth Lo and Ruth is
um professor at the Novonics Foundation
Center for Metabolic uh re research at
the University of Copenhagen and the No
Foundation Center for Genomic Mechanisms
of Disease at Broad Institute. So,
welcome Ruth.
>> Uh good morning. Thank you so much for
having me and thank you for the
introduction Dita. My talk is on the
genetics of obesity and more
specifically and how we actually
shouldn't curate uh our phenotype in
this case obesity to to get to the next
level of uh of uh variant to function
translation.
So very briefly, my disclosures have no
effect on anything I tell you. So no no
secrets here. Obesity is a traditional
common disease just like type 2
diabetes, cardiovascular disease. The
environment has an important impact over
the past 30 40 years. Uh the prevalence
of obesity has doubled, tripled. Uh and
that's definitely driven by a changing
environment. We eat more, we move less.
Um but it's in particular people who are
genetically susceptible who will respond
to this environment and who will gain me
more more than people who are not so
much uh uh uh susceptible. So the
heritability has been estimated to be 40
to 70%. Which is considered and again
very similar to other complex diseases.
Maybe different from other complex
diseases is that obesity is a very
visible public disease but I'm not going
to talk about that today. But it's also
a very early onset disease unlike type
two diabetes and cardiovascular disease.
So that's when we think about um
prevention. That's something we need to
take into account. Furthermore, it's
also a disease that involves a lot of
organs uh or tissues, not just the
brain, not just the fat cell, but when
it comes to like connecting obesity with
coorbidities, many other tissues and
organs are involved.
Um when it comes to gene discovery, it's
been actually um a very successful um uh
pathway I would say is that we started
in 2007 with a discovery of FTO with
only a sample size of 5,000 individuals
and then over time we've identified more
and more variance mostly because we
increase the sample size more and more
and many of these efforts have been uh
like uh driven by the giant consortium
like headed by Joel Joel Hershorn
And uh by now we have more than 1,700
variants that have been identified
mostly associated with body mass index
or first identified for body mass index.
A few have been identified uh for other
adepositi related phenotypes.
And what we've learned in the context of
the biology is that uh the brain is a
central is a central organ probably
affecting um uh like our um hunger,
satiety, reward systems uh in the brain.
The hypocampus lyic systems like are are
driving this whole process. You see here
this is a uh a nice figure from from
2015 but it is still the case. Not much
has changed uh since then. Um but the
variant to function translation has been
very slow.
FDO was the first discovered uh
phenotype almost 20 years or 18 years
now. You see very nice signal disease
again from an older paper where the p
value is 10 to the minus 60. Now we're
at like 10 to the minus 200. And
initially we thought that FDO was the
causal gene and there was quite a few
papers in cell in nature nature genetics
that showed very credible results for
FDO as a causal gene within uh within
the context of obesity but soon after uh
the discovery others researchers started
to venture out like some thought it was
RPG group 1L uh that was the causal gene
because it's encodes the the basil body
of the primary celia which we know from
the barbeetle syndrome because of
obesity but like others including
Molina's team thought it was more IRX3
or even further down IRX 5 that was the
causal gene so there was a little bit of
um discussion in the field but then over
time things got clearer and maybe uh
this story got concluded with the paper
in science by uh uh the Marcela nogo and
Molina's team where they in indeed
concluded that the signal here in FDO
within neurons and preadiposytes seem to
reach to IRX3 and IRX5 and that may be
sort of the causal genes within these
locus and this is just an example to
tell you it's like it took them quite a
few like took them about 14 years to
come to that conclusion and there's,700
variants actually that are waiting to be
translated. Maybe there's like a dozen
of variants that have been translated
from variant to function within the
context of obesity but that's about it.
within my team we've tried to approach
the variant of function in a more uh
it's like bionirmatic ways like a
statistical way because I don't do
actually lab work uh so Diane um used I
think about eight approaches that were
were at the time that she was doing
these analyses to to do the gene
prioritization and then uh she counted
how much the same gene was prioritized
by the by the different approaches
Uh so here summarized in this upset
plot. For example, here you see that
here are the different approaches that
she considered for the gene
prioritization and you see that uh 86
genes were were prioritized by four
approaches and could be any combination.
Um 34 genes by five and uh six gene by
uh six. So that's not all approaches but
uh these are these six genes and I won't
go into the detail but some of them are
indeed like confirmed uh or not
necessarily confirmed but also supported
by animal studies that they may play a
role in in obesity context and not
always uh they do not always point to
the brain but often also like a deep
side biology and then another project
that is in process and this also is like
a collaboration with Molina's team like
is Virginia. She's doing using a more
multi-omics approach where we go from
snip to BMI uh through uh maybe gene
expression and proteomics data. So what
she did is she combined uh all the uh
publicly available EQL data uh across
multiple tissues. Sometimes she did a
meta meta analysis. She did the same for
the proteomics data and used that in her
analysis to um basically uh align all
the variants that we have and I should
have emphasized these are the the 500
variants that have been reported in the
Yangoidal paper which is the latest
giant paper. uh she prioritized 413
genes in 189 lowi. Again an upset plot
but the main message here is that again
the brain remains the most uh the tissue
in which the most genes are being
prioritized or seem to be playing a role
but other tissues are now also popping
up.
She then overlated so here are her
results uh based on the
collocicalization with EQL and PQL QTL
data. She overlaid that with the data
from from Diane right here and then
overlay that also with the results from
CS2G and you see there's 37 genes that
are prioritized by all three methods and
now she focuses on these 37. Uh here are
some of them to to really summarize the
data in a paper that will be coming out
soon. So this is a plot that we use
where we have a variant the genes that
are prioritized in which tissue. So it's
just a lot of data to really summarize
into uh one uh nice uh story but that's
coming up because what's next is
actually is like the giant consortium
has been working so I haven't updated
this plot uh since 2021 and that's not
because I've been lazy but it's mostly
because there haven't been that many new
discovery uh studies. The giant
consortium has been working on a meta
analysis. uh giant itself combined the
data of 2.1 million individuals and then
collaborate with 23 ME. So now we have a
meta analysis 5.6 million people and
this is um so now we have uh really
9,000 LOSA actually that we have
identified and the Manhattan plot looks
like this.
It's funny. Um
so the the the the significance
threshold is right here and you ask like
uh sometimes is it's like uh too much
data not not necessarily helpful. So
what can we do with this kind of data?
We we thought like let's start with the
easy things instead of varant to
function let's just do make a new
genetic score and we published that like
uh in the in the summer it's a rule of
let this effort. So now we made a
polygenic score um uh that that works
actually really well like better than
than the previously reported genetic
scores. You see here the results in the
European ancestry like let's focus on
the blue dot here like the explained
variance is now 17.5%
and we see actually it does pretty well
in other um ancestries
in central south Asian east Asian middle
eastern at mixed American but not still
not uh in in populations of African
ancestry. So that's definitely needs
more work and maybe starting point of of
predominantly European data is is not
the way to go. uh the prediction of
obesity has gotten better. So here are
the results in biomeds bio bank veterans
program UK bio bank for obesity class
one which is BMI over 30 then class 2
over 35 and class 3 is over 40 and um
focus on these results here then you see
that the the area under the receiver
operating curve is is getting pretty
good so it's like 7 for just your
regular obesity and you have to keep in
mind like that obesity is still 50% %
heritable, 50% or 50% genetic, 50%
environment. So we'll we'll never be
perfect in predicting uh regular or
common obesity. So 72 is is pretty good.
And as we go to more extreme obesity, we
get better. And maybe that is because
more extreme obesity is maybe even more
genetic than just your common forms of
obesity. And we see this already at a
very young age. You see, it's like from
this is data from the Alps study from
zero to 25 years. And we have three
curves with the the people who are in
the lower desile of the uh the polygenic
score in red, the people in the top
desile in blue and then the average in
yellow. And you see already at age five
that genetic predisposition is coming
through. Um and it puts you on the track
throughout life uh to be heavier or
leaner than than the average depending
on where you are. Another thing we're
doing right now is is led by Victor
who's also here um is just building on
on the uh the the idea that genetics can
support uh drug development. We using
the giant data to to look in how how
many of the lossi indeed provide support
for uh gene uh for drug discovery. So
this is very preliminary preliminary
data. Um so out of the 9,000 LOSI we
prioritize 7,000 genes and 700 of these
genes actually are already the target of
either approved drugs or drugs that are
close to get on to the market but not
for weight loss. Um so the question is
here that how many of these drugs that
are approved or in in in the in the
process of of approval could be used to
for repurposing in the context of uh
weight loss. And then among the uh new
targets that are not currently um or
among the the new genes that are
currently not target for uh uh current
drugs, how many could be new targets?
And there we use the data from the uh
illuminating drugable genome initiative.
And here we see that again about 800
genes are predicted to be druggable with
high confidence. So maybe among those
there's maybe new anti-obesity targets.
Uh of those 700 so most of them are
anti- antibbody druggable and 100 of
those are small molecule drugable. Again
very preliminary data. uh but this these
are projects basically to avoid the real
task which is the variant to function
right so because uh remember I told this
maybe a dozen of variants associated
with body mass index that have been
translated into function but now we have
9,000 uh it's a little overwhelming it's
been taken a long time for us to really
write up the story into a a concise and
meaningful paper
um and maybe the real problem is is is
is
not just um the amount of data but is
also the phenotype. Some people have
tried to um shortcut the the variant to
function by uh focusing on rare
variants. Uh here you see a few
initiatives. Uh the giant consortium
here used the exone chip quite a while
ago. It was a cheap way to get to the
rare variants. We had 700,000
individuals find actually three variants
that are truly rare uh below the 1%
level including the two variants in the
JIP receptor. These are coding variants.
um a paper by Regeneron that combined
data of 600,000 people identified 16
genes mostly focusing their paper on
GPR75.
We don't know yet whether that's a real
drug target but they are definitely
working on that and then there's a
recent paper by the Cambridge group
combining data of 400,000 individuals
and their paper mostly focused on
bassoon. This is just to say that this
seems an an efficient way to to go from
varant to function within the obesity
field. Um but you still need a lot of
data uh for a few targets. Um so maybe
the problem is not so much uh with with
the amount of data. It seems that we
have a lot of data but maybe it's the
problem is really with the phenotype
body mass index. Everyone agrees that
it's actually not a very good uh
phenotype.
um because it's pretty crude and it's
far from the real biology. So in my
group we've really been focusing on
curating the phenotypes uh focusing on
more refined adiposity traits. Um, one
study is is focused on um, body
composition really and and tomorrow
Victor will uh, talk about this this I
think it's like an exciting study where
we look at variance associated with
muscle mass and fat mass in the same
direction or in the opposite direction.
He'll tell you more about that. I'll
tell you a little more about the
uncoupling of obesity from its
coorbidities and that that's coming
next. But we're also focusing on using
PETCT scan data from medical records of
Copenhagen Hospital um to to quantify
brown adapost tissue activity but also
other uh other depositive phenotypes and
that's uh very much in in development as
well. So we use AI to do the
quantification
and um we also focusing on fat
distribution. So obesity is is it's not
only about too much um adiposity but
also where exactly you will store it and
uh we also increasingly focusing on
biomarkers particularly with the
proteomics uh becoming increasingly
available. This this promises to be an
exciting field as well. So today I want
to focus on on this story and actually
just got published last week in nature
medicine and is led by Natalie Shami
who's here as well today and uh by JJ
Wang. So what we did is we did not do a
case control analysis of healthy obese
individuals versus unhealthy obese
individuals because there's a lot of
discussion about that but we we looked
at uh these phenotypes body mass index
body fat percentage and waist hip ratio
on one hand and uh these cardabolic risk
factors on the other hand. So lipids
blood pressure and glucose and insulin
and what we did is uh so this story
actually builds on a previous story
where where we use summary statistics.
So here we use individual level data of
mostly of the UK bio bank. So what we
did is we take a distribution of body
mass indexes. It's it's right skewed but
we made a standard normal a normal dist
a normal distribution with a mean of
zero standard deviation of one. And we
did the same for all the traits um and
also for the card metabolic trait. So
each phenotype is now on the same
distribution and um we made a new
phenotype by subtracting one from the
other. Say my body mass index is plus
three on the BMI side but minus3 on the
LDL side. So the if you subtract one
from the other depending on which one
you extract. Now I'm all of a sudden
plus six. So that becomes a whole new
distribution and now we did the G was on
that new distribution. So if I'm plus
six, it means that I'm a healthy obese.
I'm a person with healthy obesity
because I have a high BMI and low LDL.
If you're minus 6, you're the opposite.
You have may have a low poly index, but
you have a high LDL. And we did that for
BMI and LDL, but we did that for all
these possible combinations. So we did
uh created 24 new phenotypes. We did a G
G was across these 24 um new phenotypes.
We made sure that the signals we
observed are collocicalized and we ended
up with 205 new lossi in 206 with 206
independent association signals.
So just to confirm uh we then made uh a
score of these 206 uh loi or 266 loi. So
we have the uncoupling score because we
really look at how adiposity is
uncoupled from these cardabolic risk
factors and we compare it with your
typical um unhealthy obesity score you
could say it. So red is is the healthy
score. Uh blue is the unhealthy score.
And you indeed see like if you do the
association within the UK bio bank
there's no effect on height but you
quickly see that um the um the
difference is particularly visible in
the VAT SAT ratio where if you have an
unhealthy score there's not so much an
effect and I should here's the null line
but if you have a healthy score you
actually have a favorable fat
distribution and you see the same for um
waist to hip ratio uh where the
unhealthy score is a source with a
higher waist ratio where the healthy
score does not have too much an effect
on fat distribution. Um it's more
visible if you look at the uh risk
factors where here is the null line and
you see that the healthy score lies
mostly on the inside uh on the negative
side. So the protective side of this uh
radar plot meaning is it's associated
with lower blood pressure, lower glucose
levels um lower HBO and C triglycerate
and of course higher HCL as expected
whereas the unhealthy score is also as
expected uh lies on the the outside. So
this is just for confirming that what we
find is indeed healthy obesity versus
unhealthy obesity.
uh we do a FI was we did a FI was within
UK bio bank and indeed we see like a
nice confirmation that both scores are
associated with increased obesity but
the unhealthy score is indeed associated
with higher risk of um type 2 diabetes
hypertension and the uh healthy score is
has a protective effect of interest is
of course that the or the association
with other diseases um not the non-card
metabolic diseases that seem to be
associated with um weightbearing
diseases such as cellulitis um uh
varicose veins and so much. So it's of
course a bit tricky to call it healthy
and unhealthy because in the end uh the
risks of the people with a high healthy
obesity score uh they're still
associated with these these diseases in
the same way as unhealthy score. uh we
also confirm these results in uh
children uh focus on the cardioidabolic
risk factors. If children with a healthy
score and they're at around the age of
11 and 12 they already at that age you
see that they have a protective profile
compared to children with a high score
on the unhealthy score. If you look at
the card metabolic uh of if you look at
tissue enrichment analyses with the
healthy uh variance the it's
particularly the peripheral tissues that
show up adipos tissue abdominal fat and
so on but also cartilage adrenal stomach
uh whereas the unhealthy score uh in in
similar to the BMI score is associated
with um uh the central nervous systems
because clearly different biology that
is being observed. We also look at the
proteins. We know from the UK bio bank
data that high body mass index is
associated with high protein levels
probably because this the bigger you are
the higher the levels. That makes sense
and that's shown in this data from from
Sunidal. So when we looked at at the
scores and their association with um the
the the UK bio bank proteins um the
unhealthy score which has some more
power is associated with more proteins.
The unhealthy score is also associated
with 337 proteins. 28 are associated in
in uh are overlapping.
Um of the overlapping proteins 85% are
in the same direction and this what you
see here. This is somewhat like there's
three dimensions to this plot. Um on the
right hand side means higher adiposity,
higher cardabolic disease for the red
dots. Uh but for the yellow dots it
means like a higher adiposity lower card
metabolic risk and on the left hand side
lower adiposity lower card metabolic
risk for the for the red dots again and
for uh the yellow dots lower adiposity
higher card metabolic risk. Um so these
176 proteins are they're actually
consistent your the traditional
adiposity proteins leptin fatty acid
binding proteins uh you see them pop up
uh in both uh at both plots on the same
time and the same like with with some
others on on this side. So these we call
these proteins are adipositely driven.
What about the 15% others? There's about
32 proteins that are actually going in
the opposite direction. So they will
show up here in the red dots but here on
the on the yellow dots and on this side
on the red dots and here on the yellow
dots. So for example um growth hormone
receptor LDL receptor apo um F uh FGF-21
um like too much data to really go into
the detail right now. Um but for us it
it suggests that they're they're not
driven by adiposity as such because then
they would lie on the same side but now
they lie on the other side and what
could explain here is that they're
driven by uh the health status the card
metabolic health status and then there's
another and then go a little faster.
There's 129 proteins that only show up
for the uncoupling even though this
uncoupling score has less power than the
uh unhealthy score. uh we see adipoq as
expected to show up uh lipoprotein
lipase myostatin so there's a lot of
interesting proteins that are showing up
to be associated with uh either score
telling us more about the biology
going a little faster um I showed you
like that we have one uh set of 206 uh
prote um genes that are associated or
variants that are associated with this
unh this healthy profile but actually
they also cluster within uh multiple um
subclusters. For example, here these are
the it's a heat plot. These are the 266
variants associate body fat percentage
and body mass index and by definition
because that's how we discovered them
with a protective profile with any of
these cardabolic risk factors. But you
see they clusters this cluster three is
a source with lower body fat uh lower
blood pressure. Cluster five with lower
glycemic traits. Cluster six uh with a
healthier lipid profile. Cluster one is
pretty complicated because it has a
healthy profile for triglycerides but
unhealthy for glycemic traits. And then
four, seven, and eight, they're actually
more globally associated with a
healthier profile. So combining u oh
yeah and then we did a variant to
function prioritization binatically
overlay with GTEx data and then in
collaboration with Molina also using
CS2G
and uh combining all that data and
knowing the the clusters in which these
variants fall and sort of having that
more refined phenotype for each of these
variants we were able to prioritize some
of these genes um better than we we
could without that information. So here
I'm just going through it highlighting
some of these genes. If any of these
genes are familiar like please let me
know because we're now working on like
the v the real variant of function. So
even though this study was published the
study is not complete and we're working
with Molina's team uh and one posted in
my group Molina um um uh uh Elonor
Manita is is here uh doing this real
variant of function in the lab with with
Molina's team.
Um this is just to say and maybe to
conclude that it's like uh gene
discovery is maybe complete but we
really need to work more on curating the
phenotype to get the phenotypes closer
to the biology to to facilitate and make
it make it much easier to do the variant
to function translation. So it's
important to just not forget about the
phenotype.
So uh just to point out that the biology
that we implicated with uh the the the
genes that we have identified are the
ones that we've identified before. Uh
but actually now with the with the more
data we we've we strengthened these
observations and we actually identified
a few new pathways that seem important
in the variant to function translation.
Just to say like identifying uh variance
is not hard but genetics may help
elucidate the the heterogeneity within
obesity or any complex trait. Uh we see
multiple loi that couple uncouple
adiposity from its coorbidities. uh
multiple mechanisms seem to be
underlying and by combining this like
better description of the phenotype with
uh the the variant to function
translation I think we may like expedite
uh the actual uh variant to biology uh
observations
very grateful to my team at CBMR at the
icon institute as well uh working with
Molina has been a a blessing like really
has pushed me to the next level of the
variant to function translation and
going beyond the bionformatics uh and of
course also the oops the giant
consortium
um with Joel uh hers leading it and of
course uh the funding for this work I'll
finish here
thank you Ruth for a very very
interesting presentation so are there
any questions from the audience
So, so a couple questions R. So, one, if
if you were to filter genes um by just
the number of genes that definitively
have multiple variants uh that can can
be linked to um the phenotypes of
interest. Does that help um narrow the
list? So, I'll ask three quick
questions. That that's question number
one.
>> Question number two is I never saw GLP1
come up on any of your gene lists. So if
you were to do a retrospective on GLP1,
where would it have fallen out kind of
in in this list? And then the the final
question is on on FGF-21,
it looks like it goes in one direction
and then the other direction. So
increases risk of atyposity and and then
decreases risk of cardioabolic disease
or or cardiovascular disease. So if you
were to you perturb that, would you
expect uh differential effects across
those two phenotypes? Right. Actually, I
did uh the first question about
filtering genes. What was exactly what
you mean?
>> Multiple alals at a locus to help
whittle those down for
>> That's a good question. Actually, we
haven't looked into that. Um but indeed,
we are working on the variant of
function in the lab with Molina. Um
don't know what the process the stage is
at the moment but uh
[Laughter]
>> uh yeah.
Yeah, waiting for the data. Um, for GLP1
receptor varants, um, it's very
interesting with the 9 million uh, with
the 5 million meta analysis. It's it's
it's starting to show up. It's a very
nice peak on GLP-1 receptors. uh but
this is the first time we see it uh in a
meta analysis show up in adults is very
intriguing but uh a small well small
28,000 um individuals meta analyses in
children but but um in children before
the age of three GLP-1 receptor variants
are showing up there and that's actually
a phenotype BMI before the age of three
is not correlated with your adult
phenotype so it's very intriguing we
don't quite know what's happening so but
then we need 5 million people to find it
in adults. Um and then your third
question I already forgot.
>> Yeah, it's true. It's like and I didn't
mention it here, but these are plasma
proteins and um these are still very
correlated phenotypes or correlated
observations. We haven't looked really
at the causality. Is FGF-21 up uh as a
causal uh or as a consequence or as a
compensatory? Like there's a few other
of these proteins like LPL um and
myostatin that are in the direction that
we didn't really hypothesize would be
but that maybe have to do with with the
fact that these plasma proteins