okay so good
morning but we finally got to the heat
interaction so we're almost uh
comfortable with the old ideas of uh
thermodynamics being the the theory of
uh heat and
work we did
temperature um usually there is also
another thing that maybe I didn't stress
enough
uh
usually you taught that thermodynamics
deals with large amounts of uh
substances many particle systems
but you see that um if you went to the
seminar yesterday suggested if you're
going to the seminar by Professor Howard
Stone uh who is a very important name in
in fluid mechanics and uh you'll see
today that uh much of current interest
is in small devices
microfluidics uh
bacteria floating on uh
um Solutions trying to find food or
other
things few
particles in some extremes like in the
quantum thermodynamics only very few
particles maybe
one whereas in the fluid mechanics of of
small systems it's it's few but not so
few nevertheless it's not many so these
are not macroscopic systems so you would
Wonder well H does thermodynamics
apply okay this is precisely the reason
why I'm postponing the part that deals
with many particles in other words all
that we have done so far if you noticed
didn't require require any assumption
about the number of particles so all the
things that we do also today until uh
maybe the next or the next uh
other uh lecture does
apply to microscopic and mesoscopic
systems right so this is important
because if you do if you if you work
downstairs in the atopos microfluidics
lab or if you do research in
biology at some point you're going to
have to uh even if you are an
experimentalist you're going to have to
make a model of your experiments if you
are a theorist you start from the model
if you're an experiment theist you want
to uh correlate your data and you need a
model usually to do
that and therefore what we are doing
which is of course a lot of theory a lot
of
equations
but is exactly what you need to do this
modeling so that's the motivation for
this course
it's it's timely also because uh
it's it's one of the few ways of
presenting thermodynamics in such a way
that in it starts from generalities that
hold not only for macroscopic
systems okay me just uh review quickly
what we did last time we defined heat
interactions
so a heat
interaction was defined as one in which
a
system two systems A and B initially at
uh stable equilibrium
States exchange energy and
entropy but they do so in such a way
that even if you
put uh in between them some Machinery
that tries to separate the the energy
transferred into
uh into two streams one of which is pure
is work so it's just pure energy and no
entropy that machine will not succeed so
no no fraction of the energy exchanged
can be recognized as
work so
heat
is the extreme the the farthest non-w
work interaction hardest from work most
distinguishable from work and that
definition uh leads to the condition
that the two systems to have a heat
interaction must be at almost the same
temperature if not the same
temperature because only in that limit
the carau ratio between the two
temperatures which represents the
fraction of the energy that could be uh
uh identified as
work goes to
zero okay we also mentioned
that in spite of the usual understanding
that uh heat is uh the energy transfer
between bodies at different
temperature uh and therefore seems to
contradict what our
definition we notice that if uh the
standard model that we adopt in a heat
transfer is a local uh equilibrium or
quas equilibrium
model whereby the
system is divided in in smaller
systems that are modeled as being near
equilibrium not at equilibrium
like highlighted
here uh near near equilibrium and
therefore in that way
first of all you could assign the
temperature of the of the equilibrium
state that they these elements would
reach if you isolate them from the rest
and just let them relax to
equilibrium and uh and second um
the on the eever Suess
diagram we notice also this is important
and we'll return to this uh the heat
interaction
on one
side um pulls the pulls the system in a
in a direction that uh so on the eers
sucess
diagram if I'm here and I'm going to
inject uh both energy and
entropy that's the direction in which my
state will
move and if another interaction
injects uh the same energy
uh but takes away I'm sorry takes away
energy same energy but takes away more
entropy then it goes that way and the
two are not aligned so in order to align
them to to keep the state at steady
state so so that the state doesn't move
you need also something and that
something is
uh is another Vector which which is uh
representing the entropy produced by
irreversibility so you need a
irreversibility to
keep fluid element or a solid element in
a uh steady state when subjected to a
gradient in temperature so that means a
temperature difference between one side
and the other
side
okay so let's do something new
now not very new but it's another
another it's
similar um to what we have done when we
proved the conditions for Mutual
equilibrium between
systems this time
though we are not applying the maximum
entropy principle but we apply are
applying the principle of entropy non
decrease in weight processes
and let me say it again the principle of
entropy non
decrease is for weight processes or for
systems that are isolated in other words
it's impossible to decrease the entropy
of an is of an isolated system or a
system that under goes only a weight
process otherwise it is possible to
decrease the entropy like we do here
like heat interaction is precisely the
kind of interaction that allows to
extract entropy from a system
right all
right so here the idea is that we start
from a composite system of two systems A
and
B at different
temperatures this time they're different
and we uh ask ourselves is it possible
when is it
possible for them to exchange energy and
volume so through
a movable
partition so here is the initial State
and on the E sucess diagram for the
composite system I denoted by this point
here
and here's the final State same energy
and same volume so it's on on the same
energy line for the composite system but
internally some energy has gone from a
from A to B so for example if de is
greater than
zero uh the energy of a is increased so
the energy has flown from uh B to
a or if DV is greater than zero
uh the volume has increased so that
again system B has Lo lost volume for
the gain of volume of system
a what we apply here is a condition that
since this is a system is isolated so a
particular case of a weight process with
no external effects
uh the the entropy can only
or remain zero if the if the process is
reversing
so the final
entropy of the composite must be greater
than the initial and so we have this
inequality here S2 greater than S1 which
we write this way which we write this
way then the tools are the same that we
already used we use
additivity we use
the
fundamental
relation remember now here your system
system a starts from a stable
equilibrium State we want to extract or
to uh let's
say change with a negative
de the the
energy and so at the new level of energy
there are many states that can be
obtained so I'm trying to explain the
reason for this less than or equal to
the change in entropy for system a
is either this one but it can also be
less I mean I'm sorry
more
okay and the same for B
so we end up with this relation
here and so these things must be greater
than
zero because these are all
connected so now we can still uh choose
some special
cases for
example uh suppose we don't change the
volume so the Piston is uh
it's it's blocked by a
stop uh or there is no Pistons this is
just a
wall then DV is equal to zero so this
contribution isn't
there and suppose we want to transfer
energy from B to a so that de is greater
than zero here it
is so if this is greater than zero then
this term in parenthesis must be greater
than
Zer and that hopefully will say that t1b
must be greater than T1 a
if in a process without external effects
some energy is transferred in the
direction from B to
a we we we we say this in words by
saying
that uh the
temperature or
better somehow or equivalently the minus
the in the negative of the inverse of
the
temperature can be understood as an
escaping tendency for
energy so if you have two systems that
have the different escaping energies the
one who manages to give energy to the
other is the hotter one the one that has
a higher escaping
tendency all or we could
choose suppose we choose that the two
systems A and B are initially at the
same
temperature so this term in parenthesis
isn't
there and we want system a to acquire
volume at the expense of system B all
right so T the denominators here are
equal uh and so we find that P1 a must
be greater than P1 2 B me sorry this
should be also one
one this should be ones I have to
correct
that so
that's so you can interpret
pressure as we all have the typical idea
as a capturing tendency for volume
okay now we can do the
same when instead of exchanging energy
and volume these two systems exchange
energy and
particles and let's say
particles of one type I see here again
another two that slipped fine I to
remember to correct that
so it's the same story only that instead
of energy and volume it's now energy and
amount of constituent
I still the system is isolated the
entropy can only increase and we end up
with these uh
inequalities the first one still
confirms that uh uh the minus one /t is
escaping tendency for
energy regarding chemical potentials
again suppose
that you choose the initial temperatures
T1 and ta and TB to be
equal so the denominators here become
equal and this is going to be zero so
the only term is is this must be greater
than zero so if I want and also this DV
sorry for the uh the slide is was a cut
and
paste this should be at D
end and also this
one I want to see if you
are uh if you're
attentive well
anyway the result is that
U if dni must be greater than zero if
you want want therefore that system a
acquires uh particles of type I through
this semi perable membrane that allows
it to get it from system
B you need the chemical
potential of uh a to be greater than the
chemical potential of
B is that
correct I'm not so sure anymore because
of all these
mistakes and in fact it
shouldn't it should be uh because
there's a minor sign here and so I
either put a minus sign there or I
invert the and the positions of andb
okay
because in order for constituent I to
flow from D to to a I need that the
chemical
potential of constituent I in system B
be higher than that in a because
chemical potential at least the title I
got wrong right and it's an escaping
tendency for
constituents so this gets a feel of what
the chemical potentials are if you have
a feel of what the temperature is you
also have a feel of what chemical
potentials are temperature works for
energy chemical potentials work works
for uh molecules and atoms and so
on and in
fact again if you visit the talk today
by Professor Stone you'll see a lot of
uh chemical potentials
they the chemical gradients they call
them they don't to for short instead of
saying chemical potential gradient or
gradient in chemical potential I simply
say chemical gradient and since the
chemical
potential goes with the logarithm of the
concentration we'll
see so a gradient in the chemical
potential goes with the gradient of the
log of C
and that's 1 / C gradient of
C
usually people don't talk a lot about
this one / C in
front uh and they simply say well for
example diffusion processes
uh depend on the gradient in
concentrations
true they also also depend on on the
gradi in concentration but there is this
C at the
denominator and when you have a number
at denominator and it is small this
enhances things so the gradient in
chemical
potential uh is has two contributions
one is also this C at the
denominator so for dilute systems the uh
this gets
Amplified and uh it's very nice to see
how many
experiments uh they are able to do in
which this is the driving
force but it's also very nice to see
how the modeling
part is still a bit uh I would say
primordial uh and uh
uh very few people really care about uh
checking uh if some of the non-
equilibrium phenomena that we will talk
in particular on Sager reciprocity cross
coupling effects that we will discuss in
the third part of the course whether
they do play a role or not whether they
are small or not
usually they are neglected but just
neglected because you want a simple
model not because you know that the
effect isn't
there so that's why there is a still a
lot of research and you find lots of uh
very interesting papers on these
subjects okay so talking about
experiments uh last time we also talked
about we made a quick uh survey of
the
methods that we have in order to measure
properties of substances or properties
of
systems so one is the measuring the
temperature with the thermometer
measuring the pressure with the
monometer measuring the chemical Pro
potentials through a measurement of the
partial pressure of a
constituent when this constituent is in
mutual equilibrium with the system of
Interest through a semi-permeable
membrane permeable only to that
constituent When You Reach chemical
equilibrium that defines the partial
pressure of the constituent in the
mixture and that's how you measure that
and I skip uh the other slides but just
uh uh remind you that we we we said that
eventually if you are an experimentalist
and you like to characterize properties
of substances or maybe you discover a
new substance and you want to
characterize it what you have to measure
in the
lab and what you have to publish and
eventually gets listed in a um like the
handbook of a chemical
physics or the nist uh website where you
can find properties of substances as in
the old times you you would buy the book
The CRC Handbook of chemical physics now
uh books are like uh
in
disappearing uh so you're all virtual
and so you go to the uh websites and
look for these properties or you buy
softwares
uh
I you probably use some software uh that
has
builtin uh correlations for many
substances and these
correlations give you
values for these quantities the specific
I'm sorry the yeah the heat capacities
of your
substance um
the
compressibility
Kappa
isothermal or sometimes also another
kind
of the isentropic
compressibility which is equivalent or
connected to this one and also here it's
either the heat capacity at constant
pressure or the heat capacity at
constant volume because through the
Mayer relation they are
related and the coefficient of expansion
of your
substance for
example the
compressibility uh if you are in solid
mechanics you remember the young modulus
of uh some
elasticity well uh this is a sort of
young modulus in the bulk so in
elasticity you do the stretching in one
direction if you do it in all three
directions you get uh the
compressibility
coefficient
no that's because uh uh that's because V
you for a specimen of
like parallel
ID uh is given by that and uh if you
have one
over V
times the partial of V with respect to
um P at constant T time minus that's
Capa
T that's the isothermal
compressibility so you could you could
write that as
minus the partial of the log of V with
respect to
p and because of the additivity of
logarithm this is uh you could write it
as the partial of
L1 respect to P
so times partial of
L2 is that
correct yeah no uh plus not minus
not minus okay minus uh
L3 okay so
this and that's also sorry uh oh
boy that's more than a senior uh moment
let's do it
again log L1
partial PT minus log
L2 and so
on and each one of
these is the young module it's one over
LDL over P so it's the the percentage
stretching changing in in
distance uh for an increase in uh in in
pressure uh
uh and that's the thing that you measure
with the compression compression machine
it's the young mod modulus in that
direction all right once what we
proved is that once you have U
this functions
here you don't just need the one point
you need the entire function so how they
vary in temperature and pressure at
given
composition then using these formulas
you can integrate these
formulas and obtain the values for
energy and entropy and therefore you can
reconstruct the fundamental relation so
that's how you measure the fundamental
relation somewhat indirectly through its
derivatives temperature pressure and
derivatives of derivatives like the
specific heat or the heat
capacities Okay so that introduces to
the subject that I started uh I just
barely started last
time which is a
again uh a bit boring because it's like
a mathematical game played on the
fundamental
relation but it is part of the
traditional um topics that we do in
thermodynamics I certainly think that
are needed when you do measurements and
you want to correlate the data you want
to make sure that this relations are are
are
satisfied so let's just let's do it I'll
do it as quickly as
possible
um so the idea of Leandra
transform is to describe a a curve this
curve instead as the the the the direct
description f equals F of Y so this is f
and
Y in a more indirect
description in terms of the
family of it the tangent lines to the
curve so that the curve becomes the
envelope of this family of
lines and this family of lines is
described by uh in such a way that you
choose a value
for the slope of the line and then you
shift the line until you make you find
the point in which your curve is tangent
to that line with that slope and then
you mark the value of the intercept at y
equal 0 here we call it l of L of Lambda
so this L of
Lambda is the legender transform of your
original
function when I have more time but I
don't uh
hear I like to play this game this is a
game in which you can this is
the the Lan Transformer has applications
also
in mechanics for example it allows you
to
design uh in a bridge you know those
bridges with lots of wires you want to
have the wires be distributed in such a
way that they make this envelope and you
want to decide which shape of envelope
you want okay for example so here's my
bridge and suppose I want my
uh the the envelope of these uh things
that sustain the
bridge from a distant distance you want
it to have a certain shape maybe a
circle or maybe an ellipse or whatever
so you fix that shape and then by doing
the Leandra transform you find the um uh
the the points where you have to U Pull
or or attach your
wires
okay so by construction
here essentially L you see if you look
at this triangle you realize that L is
simply
F minus y times the tangent of this Ang
angle which is
Lambda so L is f minus Lambda
y f f minus Lambda
y so that's how you construct
it h you can play these are some
examples for example e to the
Y the Lan transform is Lambda minus
Lambda log
Lambda or thean form of of half of Y 2
like
Parabola uh is
exactly uh the same
function and so for quadratic
forms if you put the half the half is
important what is also interesting is if
you like this game I'm not going to to
the details but here is the proof that
uh when you do this kind of
transformation and this is why Leander
does it you don't lose information about
the original
function uh and so if you do
again the lender transform of the of the
lender transform you get back your
original
function this is similar to what we've
done
here because we describe
uh
uh this function
here
in in a smart way which was devised by
Gibbs uh in the late 19 uh 18
1800s
um by descri by tangents by you you
describe this function by its partial
derivatives the temperature is is the
slope in One Direction and pressure is
the slope in the other direction so this
is why this transformation
matters and uh here in fact is that
transformation
done starting for example on the
fundamental relation based on energy in
energy
form for for which you
remember this is the form of the
differential so D is TDS minus
pdv plus chemical
potentials times the
end and this line reminds you of what we
just saw so it's the definition of the
generic definition of Lan transform for
for a function f of
Y so L IS F Lambda
Y and here is the application so if I
take that
function now it is a function of many
variables so I have to choose one at a
time and do a lan transform of one for
example I want to substitute
s with
T so I want to find an equivalent a
function that contains the same
information
of the fundamental
relation but in which the independent I
change the independent variable s to the
uh to its
slope
T all
right so it's f f the new function the
Lan transform is the original function
minus the product of Lambda time y so
Lambda in this case is T and Y is s
this function is called the hel mol free
energy and you can uh uh also write very
easily uh
the
uh let's do it um
only forget about the amounts so
okay so we have this one up
there now we have defined the function
fals e minus
TS we want to compute
DF all right so this is like
D minus D of
TS and then we can use the I think it's
called lightness Rule that this is equal
to uh so D for de we have it up there
it's t d s minus P
DV and here this is minus t d s minus s
DT so one of these will cancel
that and we are left with minus sdt
minus P DV which I hope is what is
written there
yeah
okay okay now so in a sense from the
Practical point of view what have we
done here we gained the fact that we we
we we have a new function that contains
the same information and it is in terms
of properties easily measurable
temperature volume
I could have done it
also with respect to the second variable
so change the volume with pressure it's
the conjugate variable so the the temp
the the doope in that direction is the
conjugate value uh to the volume is the
pressure is minus the
pressure all right then the L transform
is u e the original function minus the
slope which is minus P * V so that's e
plus
PV that's called the
enthalpy and you have used it for bulk
flow interactions we'll review that
extremely quickly uh probably next
time no later because it needs uh uh to
it needs the the microscopic the simple
system
model all right so you take
uh you take this one it still as the
uh see this is now a fun becomes a
function of spnn you can compute as we
did the
differential and uh it's it still has
entropy so now we can take the Lan trans
form of this
one with respect to entropy so
substitute s with its conjugate which is
T not it's not at always entropy that t
is the conjugate of s because previously
here you prove by looking at the
differential that t is also the partial
of H with respect to
S so by doing that differential we we
have found that
t which is from the fundamental relation
up there is the partial of e with
respect to S when the other variable is
V I forget the N for the
moment now we also
proved well we didn't prove it but that
lines that form of differential says
that this is the partial of
H what is it partial of H with respect
to
S when the other variable
is
p
okay so I do the Lan transform of this
one so H minus the slope which is T
times the the the original variable
independent variable so that's H minus
TS that's e minus TS plus PV that's the
Gibs free energy very
important and you
to compute this uh uh
differential yeah because you see by
looking at
U by looking at the form of the
differential like this
one I look at the
coefficients uh it is clear
that this that I circled is the partial
derivative of x with respect to T when V
is the other
variable so from this one I immediately
can see that minus s is the partial of f
with respect to
T when V is the other
variable and the other it says that
minus p is the partial of f with respect
to
V when T is the other variable
okay we could also go
on usually Nobody Does this
because uh you're not interested in
small
systems but we do it because we
are so if I take the Gibs free energy
and transform with respect to one uh of
the amount ounts so I want to substitute
now amounts ni I with its conjugate
which is the chemical
potential the
slope because the chemical potential is
the partial of G with respect to Mu at
constant
10 or
when all right so I have G minus uh n *
mu and I
mui
okay
um I was short of letters for this uh
game
so since eventually the last one I want
to call Oiler free
energy and this
one maybe could be called osmotic free
energy because it plays a role and but
because uh
some colleagues uh who are working on
Nano
thermodynamics uh are using introd are
introduc beginning to introduce these
names uh so I just call it EU
Sabi and if I do this not just for one
but for all so I keep going until I
exhausted all uh the um the constituents
I have this function that I call the
oiler
relation Oiler free energy it's G the
Gibs free energy minus mu *
n okay
if you remember
yeah
Sor the f
ah yeah this is also probably a cut and
paste problem I guess oh no no
no no no this is still okay because if
you if you start from um
the Elmos free
energy and you
transform you get rid of the volume to
get
pressure then you you also get the G
three energy because the G three for the
GB you get G Gib three energy when you
transform with respect to S and V and
you can do it you can do it doing first
the S and then the V or first the V and
then the S and you get the same result
sorry I think I was so f is comp energy
f is the letter for the El free
energy ah ah the F up there you're right
yeah yeah yeah it's it's difficult to
find
letters uh even if you use the Greek
alphabet and so on there's still not
enough okay um I wanted to emphasize
that this one will will go back to this
one and I call it Oiler
because some of you might object well
but this is
zero and and the answer is yes this will
be zero for the macroscopic
systems but for microscopic systems it
is
not and that's why I I want to uh uh
give it a name and uh and uh let it play
some role until we introduced the idea
of many
particles because um because you this so
in a sense you we could write we will
see that in the limit of many
particles which means uh
negligible wall raction
effects because the key will be the the
this will tend to
zero
yeah that this one is not
zero and therefore it's something that
you can measure it will depend on the on
on how many particles you have um I just
like for
GBS
do is in this realm it it starts from
the oiler relation the oil requires uh
the condition that EU equals
zero and so you get all those like the
phase rule that comes out of the GS do
relation that
applies in this domain of microscopic
systems but
here uh let's say that it's
still a bit open no there is there is a
book which by
Terell maybe one are teral
teral
kill thod
dynamics of uh small
systems long ago forget now the exact
date
uh who did care about uh this
thing but I'm not sure that he
went uh far enough to talk about phase
uh phase transitions in in that
domain so this is still pretty
pretty
open subject but it's becoming important
because of the enormous advances in the
in in
in I would say experimental technologies
that allow you with microfluidics or uh
um Quantum dots and all that stuff to
deal with very small uh systems a few
particles okay
well math and math and math all
right I told you when we have a function
we can play as as as much math as we
want forever and
ever there are so I'm I'm concerned here
to tell you only about the useful
math and apparently also the second
derivatives are useful
at least if our project is that of uh
measuring
properties because again we don't have
the entropy meter and we don't have the
energy
meter so you have to rely on these
tangents to measure
properties so each one of the functions
that we have defined through the Leandra
transform
has first uh order derivatives but also
second order derivatives for which we
have the Schwarz theorem of
uh symmetry that says that the order of
derivation doesn't
matter so for example if I take the
second derivative of the just the
fundamental relation in energy
form with respect to snv
that's
equal if I do first s and after V and
and vice versa okay so since the partial
of e with respect to V is minus the
pressure this one can also be viewed as
minus the derivative of minus the
pressure with respect to the entropy
when the other variables are V and
N the right hand side can be viewed as
the partial of e with respect to S
that's T the temperature
so it's a partial of the temperature we
expect to be at constant I mean at when
when s and n are the other variables so
we get a relation
here is the relation is still
not fully practical because yes it does
have measurable properties almost all
all the all places except entropy here
and entropy there
let's do the the same game these are
called Maxwell relations by the way
uh and there are many anything that
derives from this Force theorem becomes
a Max
relation if you play that with on the
elol free
energy here is what we
get this is a bit more practical because
you see we have just the entropy here
and the rest is easy easy measurable
stuff pressure volume
temperature so that means that if you
take your
substance and want to know how much the
entropy varies with volume at a constant
temperature you could measure it
indirectly using this relation by
measuring how
much by taking the substance increasing
the temperature a little bit seeing how
the pressure increases at constant
volume and and once you've measured that
you've measured that indirectly so this
is one way to it's like an entropy
meter it's an indirect measurement of
entropy you could build an entropy meter
based on this
relation if you do the same with the
enthalpy you get this one not very
useful because it has s on both sides
it's not easy to keep s constant because
keep s
constant
uh yes you could
do a a weight
process and uh you could make sure that
it is
reversible but usually reversible
processes are not easy to do and often
you have to
extrapolate to some zero velocities or
some very high velocities so not easy to
make a to make sure that the to be sure
in the lab that your process is
reversible the last one if you play the
Maxwell relations game on the G free
energy is also useful it could also be a
basis for an entropy meter because it
has entropy only on one
side so you can see how the entropy
changes the function of
pressure at constant temperature by
measuring how the volume
changes if you change the temperature at
constant
pressure
okay you can also have Max will
relations when you take some derivatives
second order I mean second yeah second
order
derivatives with
respect
to pair of variables of which one is the
the uh the amount of one
constituent okay so if I do
that temperature and one constituent
here's the
relation the derivative of G with
respect to
n is the chemical
potential so this is the derivative is
minus the chemical potential
uh no
sorry no it's is the chemical potential
then I I I I move the minus sign on the
other
side so the so this one is the
derivative of mu with respect to
T whereas the derivative of G with
respect to T is minus
s and so this is the derivative of s
with respect to
n when the other variables are TP and
the other amounts of
constituents this is important because
as we do um mixtures uh
starting
soon the second part of the course uh we
will call this the
partial entropy of
constituent uh constituent I in the
mixture
in the limit of large amounts the
partial entropy contributes to the
properties of the mixture in proportion
to the amount so you multiply the
amount times the partial entropy sum up
and you get the entropy for your mixture
that's why it's called partial
entropy this is true only in the limit
of Oiler going to
zero you do this same instead of T you
do for the pressure and you get this
other derivative of the chemical
potential with respect to
p and this is what we will call the
partial volume of the constituent in the
mixture again if you take this one
multiply by the amount sum over all
constituents that gives you the volume
with in
general as long as Oiler is equal to
zero you could also take the the the
double derivative with respect to two
different amounts of
constituents and you have this sort of
reciprocal uh relation says that uh the
derivative
of potential of constituent one
with respect to the amounts of
constituent two is equal to the
derivative of potential of two with
respect to the amount of constituent
one we will uh use
this in one of the proofs related to the
DM
margules
relation yeah you could
also play the same
game starting with
the
relation
uh I don't have well starting not with
the fundamental relation in energy form
but in entropy
form and here is the result of the game
let me skip the details
one of the functions is called the mure
free
energy It's s minus E over
T is
entropy or say entropic
formulation uh becomes more and more
important and so you will
find in the literature
often uh if you go
um yeah people that
[Music]
do small systems or Quantum
thermodynamics uh s minus U over T you
find it a
lot some of them recognize that this is
due to M some just call it free
something or free
entropy so this
um following them I'll call it massure
free entropy although the
I I think the term may be a bit
confusing because um um I'm not sure I'm
not sure what free entropy
means sometimes the words the wrong
words are are confusing and cause uh a
lot of damage so if I do that I'm sorry
about
this but I needed a
name this is also because instead of um
the G giving it this kind of name for
example in the book with u uh Professor
giftos we were very careful not to use
names that were sort of misleading and
so we used we call them characteristic
functions characteristic stable
equilibrium State functions it's a more
a septic uh uh way of
U defining the same thing plank also has
its own
and uh
again if I do the transform with respect
to all the variables includ
uh should I includ yeah including also
the yeah including also the all the
amounts I end
up with the equivalent of the oil
uh relation
here uh I'm call uh how did I call it
Su which is equal to minus EU over
T notice that also the
others are very for example
plank is minus G over T so it's like a
GS free energy divided by the
temperature
and M is L M over t so they are
related and of course you can play also
the game of uh double derivatives
here
well by the same token these derivatives
are useful if you want to construct an
energy
meter okay the the first one not so much
because you have energy on both sides
but this one
yes I can measure as how the energy
varies with ECT to volume at constant
temperature by measuring pressure
temperature and how the pressure varies
is a function of temperature constant
volume so you could build an energy
meter based on this
equation this one no because it has uh
both sides but the last one
yes although it's not so
simple you have to realize that uh
you have to here change the
temperature of your
system and see how the volume will
change while you
keep p/ T constant so if you double the
temperature you also have to double the
pressure in order to keep that ratio
constant and then you measure the energy
how the energy varies with the function
of
P all right so we have ways to measure
stuff and
uh and therefore to characterize the
stable equilibrium St states
of
substances all right so now we go
back
to one of the
uh characteristic questions of
that we for which thermodynamics was
born how much useful things or how much
work now that we've defined it can we
do by uh exploiting a
change of some system from one state to
another for example by cooling a hot
object or also what is the minimum
amount of work that is necessary in
order to obtain a certain change in
state of some my system for example in
material processing uh I
transform uh I got bunch of raw
materials coming in and I want to
produce my uh product like steel no
steel is product you have put you have
to put in uh iron ore and carbon and
lots of other stuff energy so what's the
minimum
requirement to uh produce a unit of your
product that is
also
um the typical
question we have already seen the
answer for or uh the case of a
system that varies in uh you want to you
fix now select your system you want to
have a change from A1 to
A2 which could be heating or
cooling if it is cooling it means that
you are extracting energy out of your
system and then maybe you want to know
how much of that energy can be used in
order to lift a weight so how much is it
useful or it could be
instead a an increase in energy you want
to heat up your
system and then maybe you want to
know uh how much do I need to lower my
weight so what's the minimum lowering so
what's the minimum work I need to spend
in order to heat up
something and here we do it with a
reservoir if we have a reservoir
available we can do a lot of stuff that
we cannot do in an adiabatic or a weight
process without the reservoir so the
reservoir plays a
role as we
know so all these questions about
maximum minimum work that can be done or
useful stuff that can be
done get solved and this is the basis of
all the homework problems that you have
in our book but also uh any course in
thermodynamics you solve this Problems
by one defining the
system uh choosing a system for which to
make an energy balance and an entropy
balance and the choice of your system
depends on the question of the
problem the energy balance
here is easy and uh so
it's the difference between the final
and initial energy on the left hand side
must be equal to the net energy
input of your system so here since I'm
interested in uh uh the the
work done in order to lift the weight or
maybe the work re received if the weight
goes instead
down um the system I I'm doing the
energy for is the composite system a
andr so the entropy
balance
says the final entropy which is the sum
of the uh entropies of the two systems
minus the initial
entropy must be equal to the entropy
exchanged plus the entropy generated
within the system but since this is a
work interaction only there is no
entropy exchange so there is zero here
and then there is uh entropy
generation and then I also have to
remember that at least for the reservoir
I know uh
it's I know an easy I mean the the the
fundamental relation is easy enough that
I can write it it's the equation of a
straight line so a linear relation
between change in energy and change in
entropy the slope being the temperature
of the
reservoir
okay all
right so now you solve that so we have
three equations you can use them to
eliminate two variables so let's
eliminate the change in energy for the
reservoir and the change in entropy for
the um for the
res you combine and this is what you
obtain you you're left with one
equation E1 initial energy of a minus
final energy of a minus the temperature
of the res times initial entropy of a
minus entropy of final entropy of a
minus s generated multiplied by
TR so you could write this as uh W
rev minus TRS generated
because when s generator is equal to
zero the work is is corresponds to the
reversible
process you could also write this in
terms of what we already defined as
available
energy so the work done in the
reversible case so
this uh first part of the right hand
side is equal to the
difference of the available energy of
system a in the initial
State and that in the final
State and this is the formula for the
available energy that we have seen when
we just after the definition of entropy
if you go back you can find that okay
there is still another interesting way
of writing
this by defining
a um we can call it an availability
function another
function uh um I'll call it canonical
availability
function just because
later uh we need to Define other similar
things and we need the names but soon we
will get short of of letters and names
also in this business here in any case
we call gamma e minus
TRS and notice therefore that the
available
energy is equal to gamma minus gamma
R gamma
R is the
evaluation of this function at the state
a r where the system a is in neutral
stable equilibrium with the
res
okay so the available energy is the
difference
between the availability function at the
generic state of your system and and the
value of that availability function at
the mutual equili state with the
reservoir notice
that when I am at in equilibrium with
the reservoir the temperature of um by
by the conditions for Mutual equilibrium
the temperature of my system a is equal
to the temperature of the
reservoir and so this t R in that state
is also the temperature of your
system so in that stable M Mutual stable
equilibrium State gamma
R takes up the value of one of those
Leander transform that we called the
helal free energy we called it
f e minus
TS but this function is not e us Ts for
other states it's e minus TR r s so it's
different we can do the representation
on the E sucess
diagram so
gamma is e minus TR
RS okay so let's see uh
e is this
much from here to here
to
yeah no sorry let's say that we set this
equal e is equal to zero is here the
origin so E1 is this
length Okay and then I need to to
subtract TR * S1 so TR is the slope of
this line so I take it as a line with a
slope equal to tr starting from the
origin so TR * S1 is this segment
dashed so gamma is represented by
this distance between this and that
because it's this L length minus this
length
Okay this is for the generic State a A1
for the state in which the system is in
mutual equilibrium with the reservoir
its temperature
TR we are
here and that same construction so the
distance from the line with lope TR
originating at the origin
uh is this
much so so this is gamma
R and now you may you may see that this
gamma
R is the minimum value that that
characteristic function can
take I'm sorry that availability
function can
take any other state whether it is
stable equilibrium so if you go along
this curve
either side of AR or if you go inside
the region of non
equilibrium of course here we are
talking about fixed values of N and
V the function the the the values of
gamma are greater than gamma R so gamma
R is
minimum so that means that if I start
from here and go any where
else I must decrease gamma I'm sorry I
must increase
gamma all
right so I start from State a r go to
any other
state then the Delta so the change in
gamma is
positive that condition
gives
uh rules
about
um it it's the
generating uh
inequality for inequalities regarding
the second order derivatives and
therefore they have to go do with
stability and the uh the concavity or
convexity of Curves
in particular this is in a sense a
review because we already encountered
these particular
ones but this is just to give the idea
so I'm I I apply this principle that is
I move away from this state no matter
where I go I Al I always increase
gamma
uh so let me apply it to one particular
change so I decide to go
to just a small change so with a small
amount of u entropy change DS D for
infinitesimal and also I choose to
move along the stable equilibrium State
curve so I'm going this side but the S
could also be negative so I can go the
other side but along the stable
equilibrium State curve
okay so if I change the entropy and I
move along the uh stable equilibrium
State curve the energy changes according
to the fundamental
relation so I
move from
ER to another energy which is given by
the foundamental relation it's given by
this
one and I can use a tailor series
expansion around uh the original
point and
uh there yeah okay so the taor series
expansion has a value which is equal to
a which cancels with that and I have
first order term which is the derivative
of e with respect to s which is the
temperature which at the
uh point where I stting uh is the
temperature TR time the S Plus the
second order terms in the tailor
expansion and remember that here V and N
are fixed so this we could call it the
second differential of a at fixed n andv
okay so that's Delta
e now I substitute into Delta
gamma to compute so Delta gamma is going
to be uh since gamma is e minus TRS
Delta gamma is Delta e minus TR Delta s
so I
substitute and this TR Delta
s cancels with that one so I'm left with
the second order differential only
and since these plus the dots dots dots
must be strictly greater than
zero it
requires that this term must be greater
than or equal to zero so that gives
us one
condition I could also have chosen to
move to a state
in which instead I change I decide how
much uh I change energy I still move
along a stable equilibrium State curve
but now I decide the value of the
E well then the Taylor series expansion
gives me this and the Delta gamma
becomes
minus the
second lots of things cancel as before
and so I'm left with Delta gamma is
minus uh the second differential of
s and for this to be greater than zero
it
requires that to be uh whoops this is
wrong this should be I have to correct
that too this should be less than or
equal to
zero okay I'll correct it in the slides
okay so remember when we talked about
concavity we had quickly passed this U
uh slide where we took the fundamental
relation and took in full Glory the uh
Matrix of second order
derivatives uh which is the asan of
Matrix of the relation
if some of
these if you for if you keep fixed some
of these variables it becomes a function
of fewer variables so the the as becomes
smaller and if I keep if I keep n and v
as we did in the previous thing uh uh
fixed this becomes just the as becomes
just the second order
derivative all right so let's we may
call it the partial
s and
uh what we
proved is that d s
d2s should be and here it is correct
less than or equal to zero
okay so d2s is equal to uh the second
derivative
times D
Squared because here the 2s in general
is the asan Matrix that you gets
Multiplied on left and also on the right
by the de so you get the de squared and
all the combinations this is in general
in the particular case this is just de
squared and since it is squared that
simply
requires that this
derivative uh be negative and therefore
we get the
uh
concavity of the S versus e relation
which justifies
uh our drawing the eers
Suess diagram that
way but for
example recalling that the partial of s
with respect to e is one over the
temperature this
derivative can be written this
way because it's derivative with respect
to e
of one/ the temperature so it's minus 1
/ t t s * derivative of t with respect
to e and if you go back to what we
defined we called heat capacity at
constant volume this is just the
inverse of
CD so this second derivative is equal to
-1 / T ^2 over
CV and that requires therefore that CV
since it has to be negative it requires
that CV is greater than equal to
zero so for your models if you have a
substance with a negative CV you are in
trouble you have no substance you made a
mistake
um also from the other um equation that
we have oops condition that we have here
d2e greater than equal to zero we
can uh remember that the partial of e
with respect to S is the temperature see
this is also written is also equal to
the partial of t with respect to
S
okay which is greater than
zero and this
also uh is related to to the one above
gives the same practical
result these
inequalities
um give a an interesting uh give rise or
are manifestations of a a general
principle that it's chatelier or
chatelier brown theorem or
principle that uh if we combine it with
the idea that we have seen today uh that
temperature is an escaping tendency for
energy you see what this
says if uh at fixed N andv I give some
energy to my system
it increases its
temperature well we all know that did we
need so many lectures to get to this
result all right this also says that if
you give some
entropy the temperature will
increase but the
temperature is the escaping tendency for
energy so that means that if I give
energy to my system
in a sense it
reacts by
hiring its willingness to give away
energy so it it is as if it counteracts
it wants to counteract what you're doing
so if you externally uh heat up the
system uh you give energy and then it
reacts
by uh shaping things so it as as soon as
it can it gives that energy away
so for example if you start with your
system in mutual equilibrium with your
thermal Reservoir and externally give
some energy to your system it will get
off equilibrium off Mutual
equilibrium higher temperature than the
reservoir that higher temperature will
so that will make will make up a
difference in temperature that will
drive an energy exchange back to the res
thereby your system will try to
reestablish
equilibrium so you can see this natural
tendency
of uh reestablishing equilibrium here as
a
uh as a theorem
that also emerges from the uh stability
condition
and the concavity of the fundamental
relation chatelier Brown theorem of
course is more General and we'll we'll
see a little more the next time about
this it's not just when you do this with
respect to these variables but also when
you do it with respect to many other
variables and also it has an additional
little um other twist that uh um we we
will see when we do two
variables okay but for today I think
that yeah we are
done and we are just in time okay so
I'll see you next time