welcome everyone thank you for joining
us today from all around the world for
what will be a terrific conversation
with our special guest June odongo on
how opening up learning can close
knowledge gaps my name is Chris cazola
and here at MIT I'm our senior associate
Dean at open learning and this is the
first in a new open conversation series
that focuses on the experiences and
impact of open learning for empowering
people to improve their lives
communities and the world and as we set
out to craft this new open conversation
series one person we really wanted to
talk to is June odongo Jun is an
Innovative entrepreneur a founder and
now the CEO of SGA Technologies a
logistic software and services company
in Kenya catering to businesses that
ship in Africa today she'll share her
insights on learning entrepreneurship
and the role of open education in
upskilling and changing our world so
June thank you so much for speaking with
me and our audience today your
experience is truly
inspiring thank you so much I didn't
know I was your first thank you it's an
honor yes yes no uh it's been great to
sort of hear and and learn about the
work that you've been doing over the
last few years and I wanted to just kick
it off by asking you to tell us tell us
about your personal Learning
Journey um well let me tell you a little
bit about my background uh which
actually connects somehow with um ocw um
so um in terms of my education I have a
computer science degree from UMAS Lo
which is about 40 minutes or so from MIT
uh many of my University professors were
actually MIT computer science graduates
um and I also have an MBA from the
Harvard Business School um in terms of
how summarize my Learning Journey um I
mean a combination
of uh formal education as I've just
described and then just you know
complimenting my education here and
there uh I think because of these
lectures that I had who had been at MIT
um and we were a lot of our CK was
actually mimicking MIT classes right so
when it came to studying I and I by the
way I went to if I can date myself I was
in undergrad I graduated in 2005 so a
long time quite a long time ago um and
that's actually how I Came Upon um open
learning um effectively to complement
what I knew the MIT students were
studying um to help me perform better
you've you started by taking some
courses on uh MIT open courseware but
you you certainly didn't stop right and
so you know you've you've definitely
been engaged in sort of online learning
continuous learning uh upskilling
throughout your career even after sort
of two really significant degrees so
what what motivates you to keep learning
right um you're a busy professional how
do you you know how do you make the time
why why is it important to
you oh I almost feel like there's no
choice right I mean like in our company
for example I mean we're trying to apply
technology to some very complex um you
know you know comp Computing problems
that would say or mathematics problems
in um in logistics right um so I also by
the way I should say this I happen to be
one of those people who um I apply so
much of what I learned in uni both in
undergrad and graduate school like often
times people say oh whatever I learned
you know I'm not using I am the exact
opposite of that right so building on
that is you know context right you know
the way we think about I think the way I
fundamentally think about solving uh
problem solving is the same but the
context is constantly changing right
there's new ways of solving some of the
same problems or if you're if you're
getting to if you're encountering a new
problem you need a new way to think
about it right and the solution can
either come from you it can you can
borrow from other people right and if
you're borrowing from other people it
could be traditional it could be new
right and the the way to get that
information is to insert yourself you
know into materials talking about what
you know how other people are thinking
about these things or even enhancing
your own knowledge if you're trying to
come up with your own solution so for me
I you know I just think I have
absolutely no choice but to continue
learning and in our company we have our
team members are quite young um you know
often times they recent University
graduates
um I do not write software anymore I
used
to I I just don't one of the things for
example I'm trying to do is you know
we're using languages that I didn't use
you know when I was a student like I
think we used C or something in computer
science by using Ruby I need to learn
how to use Ruby on Rails but more
importantly we're also trying to apply
um technologies that have advanced
significantly in the two decades since
our I've been outside of school right
whether it's things around machine
learning artificial intelligence and so
on so some of the work I have to do in
terms of learning is relearning what I
learned in school so I'm actually I
actually go through some of my old
curricula and then introducing new
Concepts you know on top of that so it's
I I I it's just embedded in I think
learning has to be embedded in what
we're trying to do and what I'm trying
to accomplish
yeah that's a that's a fantastic story I
think it reminds us that um that the
education that we get with our degrees
for those of us who have had the
opportunity to study right um is
sometimes very a set of concrete skills
but it's really just an investment in
our future right but if you don't keep H
it's if you don't keep investing right
if you don't sort of keep watering the
plant right it it won't continue to grow
um
that's that's really that's really neat
so you've talked a little bit about some
of the work that your company does right
uh SGA Technologies um and um and the
ways that technology and software um and
software solutions to Logistics problems
um are part of the work that everyone in
your company does but um uh you've also
in in other discussions that that we've
had um sort of reflected that it's been
difficult to come
by software developers right to to hire
recruit train retain them um so tell us
a little bit more um about how you've
managed not only to sort of continue
your own education um but to kind of
build this up um for your all the all
the people who are part of your
team so it's less an issue of finding
software developers because there are
actually plenty of them here but more
about finding software developers we can
afford
in you know in an era where software
Engineers are such a hot commodity right
and you know you bring them up and you
know Google Microsoft or whatever comes
and snaps them um so for us it was
actually more the issue was more
resource constraint right um not be you
know when I started this company
initially I was bootstrapping it using
my savings and then when we got got
initial
funding um it wasn't a super substantial
amount so we've had to run a really
really lean company right and that meant
we couldn't afford senior developers and
and so on and then even if we could you
know there's um because of how hot the
market was for engineers they wouldn't
they likely wouldn't have lasted because
you know there's always somebody who pay
them more so the approach I took was to
hire um very high potential um younger
people right so fresh um computer
science graduates you know folks who'
been who were just grad uating been out
of school for no more than three years
um yeah so so that's that was the
fundamental problem um and then the way
ocw actually came into the SAA story it
it was not intentional um at all so what
happened was there was a candidate um
who had been recommended by one of our
Engineers um she was an electrical
engineer and she was very very green and
we initially rejected her application
right so um her name is Cynthia and um
the person who had recommended Cynthia
is called Warren um so I got back to I
did so I reject her and she doesn't say
anything um much like how I used to be
when I was a candidate I I don't take
rejection very
well maybe I don't maybe she was lunch
lunch who knows but um in any case I I
get back to Warren and I'm like hey so
this is the feedback on your friend you
know um she's just too green and you
know he says she's really high potential
like you need to just think about that
again so we go back and I you know I I
talk to Cynthia and and she was working
she was designing some kind of Hardware
uh board somewhere and I was like okay
that's pretty cool for someone who's
barely out of school um and I just you
know and I thought okay she was very
very bright what she didn't have was a
computer science um degree which for us
is very very critical in our company
because we are applying algorithms
complicated Al algorithms and
complicated
math um and I just thought well you know
when I was a student there was this
resource mod ocw that I used um where
you could learn some of these things
right they were complimentary to these
textbooks you know so I just suggested
to her hey
um you could join s if you're willing to
quit your job and do this for six months
and I created a curriculum for her which
actually mimicked the last two years of
um the computer science program and she
said yes and some and then we ended up F
finding this path of um bringing on
board you know otherwise talented um
individuals who for one reason or
another do not have the education we
need right so as of today we've done so
Cynthia she did that program in
202 was it last year maybe a little bit
I think she started um end of 2022
true no no no end of 2023 because this
is our first full year actually as an
engineer at Sanger um and then we've
since put two other individuals through
that program right um one the second
person we put through is actually not a
full University graduate is someone who
comes from an other resource
background um but had the desire to be
an engineer had gone to a coding boot
camp coding boot camps for us to not
give uh folks what they need uh at least
for what works in our company uh we put
him through that and then we've since
put in someone else who has a similar
has sort of like a similar skill set so
we've been able to complement you know
so we've been able to complement our
team so half our team um is from this
program wow yeah yeah so that's really
interesting um and that's exactly the
kind of story that makes us excited at
open learning um it's the kind of thing
that motivates the staff who work here
and certainly the faculty at MIT who
share these materials they don't have to
do that they don't uh they don't get
paid to do that um they sort of sharing
these materials in order for other
people to use them now it sounds like
the special sauce right that comes from
from s Technologies from June odongo is
that is your work in identifying from
this big curriculum of materials exactly
what's valuable for you and your firm
and your team um so that's some some
really amazing work uh it does raise for
me another question um you know i' I've
I've taken courses watched videos and
lectures from from open courseware um
and some of them are really
hard um and some of those problem sets
that we that we share with the world are
are really difficult um so I'm curious
you know uh your the staff who who
you've kind of shared this curriculum
with do they do they think it's too hard
do they think it's hard and fun what's
what's been their reaction
it's
hard I mean they're very complex courses
I mean you know you know networking
Theory you know algorithms you know I
don't know if they consider it
fun um no one's told me they find it fun
uh but one thing that's Universal
amongst them is that
um the amount of learning they get is so
so so significant you know just in a in
a span of six months right um so I think
they feel better about themselves you
know in terms of what they're capable
even from a learning
perspective there must be at a moment um
in in their work or or even in your own
um where that light bulb goes off right
where you're just dealing with some
really tricky work problem right um and
then suddenly you know you realize you
have the tools right um because of
because of a course that you took
through open courseware or something
else
right you reminded me of
something um so the team member who
recommended Cynthia um was also
mentoring her um during that process and
one of the courses is um you know is
something called automata I forgot the
full name of the course um and whatever
problem he was working on at the time he
was like oh goodness like you know there
was something in the automata class that
he was helping Cynthia with that he
recognized could help him solve a
problem that he was working
on yeah so it's almost like yeah it's
almost like this extended hook in the
learning right it's not just for the
person who's going through it because
what we also do is we want them to
present to us something um at the end of
the coursework right on some topic so in
Cynthia's case for example it was graph
Theory right like could you tell us what
you learned on on you know on in graph
Theory right so what happens is there's
a relearning also for someone like me
and then um I remember there some
algorith I forget which
algorithm she presented and I was like
oh my God this is an Insight I had in
terms of you know these kinds of like
nodes I was thinking about in in sort of
the network design for the logistics and
I couldn't remember that you know I had
been taught this I don't even know if I
was taught it but I was like you know it
was very validating for me because I'm
like oh wow I recognized something by
myself that is in that is in a textbook
yeah you know yeah yeah no it feels
pretty
great I I love it I love it it's um and
that's a part of the joy of teaching and
learning right and some of that happens
in the classroom but it but it happens
our whole lives right um so let me turn
now and ask um sort of the the bigger
question you know we've I've shared a
little bit about why MIT does this you
know the big so what question right and
I want to hear from you a little bit
about about the kind of impact that that
you try to have I mean you have not just
developed a company you've also uh
you've been involved in and starting
nonprofits um you know you've been
trying to make an impact um in the world
and I wonder what advice you would give
to to other people right um to the
younger version of yourself right um or
someone who's out there today um for how
they could you know how they can make a
difference I think the impact question
is Big um I don't know what I would tell
my younger self but I think I I can
think of what to tell other folks which
is um for
me there are certain kinds of oh the
ideas or
problems that latch onto me so
viscerally that I feel I have no choice
but to get involved in solving the
problem or addressing the problem and
when I have that
emotion
um I just pursue the emotion you know I
think that's sort of behind the
nonprofit the nonprofit We have is
called Zoom Memorial found foundation
and what we do is we equip
um community centers and schools in in
very rural underserved places with
computers and Computing
education and that is linked to my dad
so my dad was an electrical engineer um
unfortunately he died when I was quite
young like uh more than 20 years ago but
I would hear stories of folks saying oh
he showed me my first computer or you
know the first time I touched with a
computer was with your dad or he taught
me this or whatever
and um and I wanted to do something you
know to
continue you know let's call it his work
and that's how and you know a little
tiny story um I worked for this company
called EMC in hopkington a data storage
company that's now um acquired by Dell
and it was Earth day and they were
recycling computers like there was some
email where computers were being
recycled and can I just say I was crying
at my desk had broken up with some
person and I see this email I'm like
wait I sto crying and I'm like I know
what we could do with those computers
and those computers end up um long story
short we end up kicking off the
nonprofit that way by refurbishing these
things uh with the company in terms of
how I got interested in logistics it's I
just was so frustrated I was moving
quite a bit in a short period and just
moving was so awful and I was like
people have been moving since time in
Memorial like why does moving suck so
much and I just got sucked into
Logistics not that I had necessarily a
passion for Logistics but it was a a
nagging problem and then I'm also very
big on not regretting things I'm very
big on the regret Min minimization thing
um so I tend to just ask myself at any
given point like if life ended today
like would this would I feel okay about
where my life has reached and sometimes
the answer is yes and sometimes the
answer is no and I find it's yes when I
feel I've done something that was
meaning meaningful to me and seen it
through completion or a good outcome or
something that could continue and I find
that it's new and I'm in the middle of
something I'm like oh wait I have this
thing to do um yeah so for me yeah I
just I just move with um what grips me I
think or I would say man no that's a
fantastic story that I I appreciate that
you know those kind of personal
connections that whether it's with you
know with a family with a just a moment
that hits you um that uh that that you
know we feel things and and then we re
you know we reach out right and and act
on them um and build you know either as
individuals or or with others um is
there a role for open education um in
that in moving from that that visceral
feeling to the
doing I mean for sure but I would just
add just one point to my earlier one is
to also just go for it even if you don't
know how it's going to end up so in the
story of the nonprofit what I did was I
just wrote the company back and I said
could you give me those computers and
then before I knew it they were
interested in the idea then the me and
my colleagues were refurbishing the
computers and then they were donating
money like I just never foresaw that I
was just like give me the computer so
folks should just
start um and then in terms of
um with open learning you know so after
I um at some point I think earlier in
the year late last year maybe a year ago
I posted I did a LinkedIn post about the
coursework um and the response was
pretty good in that folks said you
know we didn't know we could learn this
way or you know can you show me um where
I could complement
this where I could mine courses um for
my company so a friend of mine for
example runs a um a rose Farm in Kenya
and she's in agriculture so her problems
are different um and you know and she
asked if I could help figure out how
they could also use um open learning
right in her come in her case it's a
company of 800 800 people many of them
are firm workers right so how one would
think about um what kinds of lessons one
could glean from something such as open
Lear learning it's you know very
different it's a very very wide scope um
so for me I think it's it's pretty
applicable in just about every scenario
right their classes on how to think
making decisions for example like for me
I I have this deep interest in
behavioral um economics just how one
thinks about you know when you're
Building Technology but the behavior of
folks you know which is always not how
we think about things rationally like
how do you like how do you think about
this so for me um in almost every
setting I think somebody can find
something in open learning that's going
to um complement that thinking you know
whether it's something pretty basic or
something pretty
Advanced right okay no that's that's
inspiring and I'll I'll borrow that line
just start um know we'll sort of I think
a lot of people will take that away from
our conversation and and speaking of all
those other people um it's time now I
think to to to Pivot and now I think it
would be a great chance for us to take
some questions from the
audience all right so June I wanted to
just uh start with one question that
came in from the audience um from one of
our online from Mary um who was
listening in and hearing about the ways
in which you've talked about how you've
upskilled your workers um and yourself
uh on the technical front um but one
thing that Mary's asking is um how how
or what recommendations you would have
for helping people develop their their
social skills in communication in
leadership um in networking um have you
found resources to do that and have you
done that in your own work and have you
helped people in s Technologies do that
as
well okay so I think um hi Mary first
thank you for your
question um so for communication
I think many of my colleagues used to do
Toast Masters and that worked for them
so if Toast Masters is around you
somewhere I I would recommend that
because I think many people can write
well or communicate um through writing
um and it's sort of you know
communicating verbally or in public uh
spaces or in meetings um that tends to
be difficult maybe because of confidence
or that kind of a thing so I would
recommend something as simple as Toast
Masters um something that was useful to
me was um learning tips on something
called executive presence I remember um
looking at executive presence tips uh
very early in my career things like you
know sit up you know when you're
talking um you know how you should stand
and and things like that for me um I
found those to be super super super
valuable um especially in the early days
when trying to establish my career um
for my team um I think the current
generation is facing I think a different
set of communication problems I think
that that we used to face you know for
us it used to be a lot about public
speaking but I I think because of a lot
of social media and so on I you know
what I see commonly is um writing
writing challenge
Alles right um or being very Curt in
writing you know very very brief um so
for our team the thing that I'm usually
pushing on is just written
communication right um no you know I
don't like to see slides or that sort of
a thing I want someone to express their
idea in writing and I with the correct
spelling and things like that and I will
send it back um if it is not if it
doesn't meet that standard yeah so so I
I think it just depends on you know
where someone is in the career what
their background is and so on um and and
just also observing if the someone who
one admires who speak well speaks well I
think there's nothing wrong in emulating
that yeah yeah no I think that um among
other things one of our most popular
videos on MIT open courseware is from
the late professor Patrick Winston um
entitled how to speak um and um and it's
been picked up you know millions of
times millions of views and I think it's
just an indication of the importance not
only of mastering technical content um
or business content or other things but
actually being able to express it and to
share it right I I'll look for it
now but you had you had mentioned
actually um you know the importance of
emulating a public speaker um uh as As
One path toward developing someone's
personal public speaking skill skills
and that brings me to another question
this came in uh from Rodrigo um who has
also joined us uh and online and sent
this via email um who asked who who was
your most influential Professor right um
so who you know who most influenced you
as you were learning and whether that
was in the classroom or
outside H hi Rodrigo oh that that is a
difficult
question I I got along so well with my
professors
and and even professors in my school who
were not teaching me directly like one
of the people I think who was most
impactful to me was this guy called
Professor
Maloney uh who worked at EMC which I end
I ended up joining he was not my
professor but we got along and then I
you know I got an internship at EMC that
I ended up um not taking and then I got
a full-time position and you know I
don't think I would have gotten that
without him because I had not imagined
working for a company like that or an
industry like that
um yeah I think Fred Martin is someone
who stands out to me he oh my goodness
he was an MIT grad actually I think now
he is a he might be dean of the Cs
Department of University of Texas at
Austin yeah so I I I didn't really enjoy
very much my Hardware
courses but he was my professor and he
made it fun and I and I did well and I I
think I purely really did well because
he was great um you know uh yeah so yeah
I don't know I love I love Academia I I
love many people so I really cannot pick
just one person I cannot no that's a
great point in many ways part of the joy
of learning is learning from different
people in different ways right and so
sometimes there is one individual
teacher or Professor who makes that huge
difference but sometimes it's that it's
the the range of them that makes all the
difference in the world world and why we
need to kind of keep learning and keep
finding new new voices new mentors as we
move in different parts in our
lives nice um so one thing um another
question that that has come in and I
think this is really important for uh a
valuable sort of insight that might be
valuable to other people who are looking
to use sort of mit's open resources in
training employees and their
organization um which is the question of
of assessing the impact right and and
the learning right so a lot of our
course offerings particularly on MIT
open course whereare they're you know
they're open they're self-paced um
there's no sort of necessarily metrics
of whether you've passed or failed right
our mitx courses do have assessments
they do have uh you know certificates
for people who complete them but for you
um as manager and as the CEO um how did
you how did you know um you know how did
you measure or or did you um that your
employees when they were using mit's
open resources were were mastering the
material that they were learning to
apply it and they actually really were
making a difference in their
work well in our case you know I would
say the
measure there were three kinds of
measures though I I think one well one
is
not you know I don't know how useful it
was which was you know do the exercises
in the course you know don't just listen
to the classes do the exercises and then
report it was self-reporting which is
why you know I don't know how you know I
don't know what we can say about that
but self-report on how you performed you
know you know because at some point you
know answers are given and you can see
whether you got something correct right
so that was one um and then the second
measure um was actually the pace of
learning right um one can tell
how one is doing you know based on
whether somebody is like taking too long
or something like that you know like
just like what's going on and then also
ask asking questions because we are
familiar with the material you know
because we are technologists and then
also asking the the um team member who's
going through it to present on a key
Topic at the end of
it right um so to present well you need
to at least Master at a theoretical
level what it is you're going to present
oh right because we you know all of us
gather together and you need to make a
case and we're learning and answering
asking questions that we you know we
want answers from um so those are those
were some of the ways to measure and
then the last one I would say is
just you know application because our um
ultimate intention is that the way of
thinking about a problem is
reshaped um so then the proof of the
learning is in the pudding right which
is your actual output once you start um
solving problems within the team yeah no
I think and I just just want to I just
want to add something on this so one of
my very close friends is a um I was
about to say he's a CTO but he's now a
CEO at this financial technology firm
here that's doing really well and he has
helped recruit just about every engineer
in our company and we've been talking
about recruitment a lot uh
because of um you know these uh
gpts that help people um you know answer
questions you know like once upon a time
you could give a coding exam and you
know you know and and you know you watch
somebody do it and now you know somebody
can do it online and you know and then
credentials like you know I've mentioned
before I think even earlier in this chat
that you know having a computer science
degree is very important to us like he
challenged me on that actually quite a
bit and he is someone who also holds
like a masters and you know bachelor and
Masters in computer science um we're
changing the way we hire to test problem
solving right and yeah so it's actually
a long about credentials because we have
had experience and I think many
employers have had this where folks can
have the most amazing credentials they
still can't do the work MH right and
what I'm finding also is folks who are
self-directed and have um a lot of deep
interest and I think this was true too
when I was an engineer myself the best
Engineers ended up being folks who just
for whatever reason they chose that
career and they didn't actually
necessarily go through a machine like me
for you know learning right they for
whatever reason they just had this like
deep passion and they opted in right and
you know I I think that's where some
such as open learning uh becomes very
powerful and actually someone added me
on LinkedIn um and when I looked at his
profile he had switched his career into
Finance or something just from open
learning like I literally just looked up
his profile yesterday right complete
switch of a career right
so
um I people people see good work you
know people see good work work um the
world is changing it's hard to argue
with uh folks who work hard yeah yeah no
I think those are great points and I
think it U the the proof is in the
pudding as you say right um and and I
would also pull out the importance of of
pres knowing that someone has learned it
by having them present on it right I
always say right the best way to to
learn something is to teach it right and
to be able to teach it to others um and
also um that
sort of self-pacing self- ownership
right um so it's so the you know in some
ways you're opening learning
opportunities to people in your firm um
but it's really up to them right to to
to track their progress to to apply it
and and that that's the best way for
them to learn it but I think the number
one thing I'll take from what you just
said is that phrase opt in you know sort
of just opting in to to learning to
curiosity um is is really key to what it
means to be an agile work worker in in
the 21st century right these
Technologies are are changing so rapidly
um and that any even the best degrees um
won't last anyone for a lifetime anymore
if if they ever did
right and okay so let's um I want to
switch now to a little bit um uh some of
the questions that have been coming in
are really about you um and and and your
work and and your your journey so so I'm
going to sort of turn turn some of those
to you right now um and so one of the
things that that comes from from Mark um
along the way is a question about um
what's the most valuable lesson that
you've learned as as an entrepreneur um
you've reflected a little bit um in our
conversation about um you know sort of
be being an entrepreneur um what's a
what's you know what's one that you
would share with
Mark oh Mark hi that is a tough tough
tough
question um
most valuable so first I I think
entrepreneurship is
more for me it's like a it's a career of
the
heart uh because it's just so difficult
to be an entrepreneur like you know
everyone's read about you know the
roller coaster emotions and you you know
the you know difficulty in maybe getting
financing and you know product Market
fit and all these things the I mean the
reality
is is much much much tougher um than one
we'll ever read anywhere or even if you
have friends who are entrepreneurs and
you are observing them there it's just
one of those things where you you can't
actually explain what it's like to be an
entrepreneur you just have to experience
said and and that's why I think like my
mom my mom is a businesswoman and
there's a time she had told me you know
like the way the things she's pursued
it's when she can't sleep over something
right and it's persistent and she just
cannot run away from you know an
idea and you know I think
entrepreneurship you know is or should
be should be um driven by that kind of
thing a kind of
obsession uh because it's there's so
many things that are happening to make
you want to quit right and just to give
you an idea like I
know I know very many entrepreneurs I
know entrepreneurs who do not have
resources who have a lot of resources uh
but all of them sort of suffer the same
the kinds of emotions they suffer are
Universal right so I think if it's not
driven by something inter colel um it
can be very challenging I mean of course
there people who are just super rational
about it and they have a Time plan and
you know in three years they're out and
you know they've sold the company and
whatever they know how to do it like an
assembly
line um but yeah i' would say yeah I
think the heart piece is probably the
for me it's the thing that's kept me
going and therefore I would say you know
that's the
lesson well that's fantastic that that
sticking to it right is is really
important and that um so that's also a
question that comes in from uh from
YouTube from Christopher who asks um how
do you stick to your learning goals
right um so in some ways it's it's that
related question right um is the answer
is the answer they the the
same um hi Chris
um I I think let me talk a little bit
about my Primary Learning right now
which is um reading a lot of biographies
from
Founders okay and found a podcast like I
love love love this podcast called um
Founders you know which is and and and
in the definition founder is um not just
someone who started an Enterprise but
you know historical people who've just
done enormous things so it's anyone from
a Rockefeller to
Oprah um just stand outs and
um so I'm I'm a bit obsessed with that
um and you know so basically this guy
called David SRA just summarizes this
book so I end up buying some of those
books and then subscribing to something
called Founders notes which is a summary
of the books you know and I literally
have like five of those like up on my
screen um all the time just refer to um
I'm not measuring my learning right now
as something around breath right so it's
not I don't need to have like a a wide
scope for me it's like the depth of
something and sometimes it's just a
singular concept that I'm sticking on um
and that and then that concept is
changing because sometimes it's
something about like you know what makes
a great team but sometimes it's how you
know how do you apply technology like
you know like in our case even
internally not just externally for our
customers um and then you know I've
mentioned you know for example I like
something like behavioral economics so I
have Richard T book right and then there
just a set of books that I just keep in
front of me even if I haven't read them
sometimes I'll just pick and try to go
and see if it's referring to something
um so I don't have a specific goal I I
would say for me it's a moving Target um
and then I just find that at any time
when I'm struggling with a particular
concept for whatever reason something
you know if something pulls me to it
like we we're building some kind of a
document reader um using something
called Clover AI I think I saw someone
post on LinkedIn like this paper by
these students you know and I was like
oh let me just read this you know and
then it ends up being this thing that's
now very a very very key part of what
we're offering as a company so yeah so
sometimes like it's just clicking now
now I don't have a calendar I don't have
a list of things I have to learn yeah um
that's good to know that's good to know
because I think for someone um who's
hearing your story story right um
imagines that um you know that it's all
very all very disciplined all very by
the book so it's proba so it's very
heartening um to know that sometimes you
just fall down a rabbit hole right um
and just uh and just Discover
right and that's good because that's
actually one of the questions that came
in um on YouTube um from a um was asking
about whether it's better to be more
more uh you know more systematic or to
uh or to go down these new nous rabbit
holes um and I think you know I'll take
a stab at answering that question that
um I think it's important to to do a
little bit of both right that sometimes
um there is a a need if there's a if you
know that there's a particular skill
right that you need to master right to
try to find a path to doing that right
and here in open learning we're sort of
developing and we'll be rolling out sort
of new tools for people who come to our
website to actually find guided pathways
through our learning you know through
their own learning Journeys right so if
they say I want to you know understand
um you know this corner of data science
where I really need for my work to be
able to understand you know how vacines
work right and that'll be coming over
the course of the next year so I
encourage people to come back you know
early and often over the next few months
as we roll those things out um but
there's also you know I think what um
you know in our our YouTube viewer
described as a a rabbit hole another
term for that is Serendipity right is
you never quite know and you gave an
example of that you know you stumbled
across a post on LinkedIn you followed
you followed the links and it and it led
you in a new direction right and so um I
wish you know for my answer to that
question to um to our friend on YouTube
is I I wish I knew um you know which
things were um were serendipitous door
opening transformative experiences which
are just rabbit holes um and I'm not
sure you know it until you see it is
that your
experience saradipity is my favorite
word oh great yeah yeah yeah it's my
it's it's I feel that that's what gu
that's what guides me
personally and so when do you turn from
Serendipity to structure that's probably
what you know what people who are you
know the difference between between uh a
creative person with entrepreneurial
Ambitions and an entrepreneur like
yourself so how do you turn from
Serendipity to
structure I I don't even know how to
answer that question because I I feel
like these things go hand in hand okay
you know you've heard those saying
around you know like opportunity comes
when you're ready and you know um and
and things like that so I I I see it I
see it very much like that I mean day to
day as a company for example we have a
plan you know that needs to be
structured right um but I also typically
say that we have you know an emergent
strategy right which is yes we have this
plan and we're supposed to we what we
think we should do is go down this path
but at the same time we're taking in
information you know to see if there's
new data that says maybe there's
something we can change right um
sometimes the thing that makes you
change that strategy is what we can call
certainity because you you know
something catches you and then it you
know brings together this other thing
that you had learned but it allows you
to see it in a new way or it opens up a
path for you to go further that you
wouldn't even have foreseen yourself so
I I don't think it's about you know
turning from structure to Serendipity I
mean I think these things coexist
right oh fantastic that's great
advice so another this is related in
some ways to a question that came in
from Neema um and so Nema is asking um
in today's sort of World um sort of fast
moving high-tech world right um how how
can someone best learn quickly right um
and then maybe I'd also ask you to
reflect on what are the things that you
think people need need to be learning
right
now that's a good question Sima yeah and
I think they're kind of related so how
do you learn
quickly
um I think you learn quickly by training
yourself to learn in the first place
yeah
yeah um like I just noticed something
this this week like I was in a I was in
a board meeting and I hadn't read the
board pack on time and I felt very very
guilty because that's a very bad thing
and I open up it was like 46 pages and I
was able
to go through all the pages in a
relatively short time and I ended up
asking the most questions um in that
particular meeting and I I was actually
surprised by myself and I realized oh
once upon a time when I was in grad
school I was reading you know 100 Pages
a
night right and because I used to read
100 Pages a night now I can go through
you know half of that in a very quick
period um so I think learning fastest
just training yourself training yourself
to learn and you know
creating maybe environments of focus
while you're learning so that you can
absorb what you're learning because then
you're going to feel better and you're
going to notice that you're learning and
then it's just going to get easier and
easier I think it's learning is just a
muscle like you know like anything else
that's what that's what I would say
absolutely um yeah and you also need of
course like things like a clear mind and
that sort of a thing you know so
understanding the kinds of environments
that allow you to learn better because
for example if you if you if you've
slept well you're going to learn quicker
you know things like that or maybe if
you had coffee I don't know um and then
and then I drink a lot of coffee um and
then um so the other question was uh
what should people learn
now um I have sort of two reactions to
that and I think even something on the
on the previous question so I'm not one
of these people who is a fan of like
learning fads like I just I am anti them
you know like in this last decade when
when folks that were just like everyone
should learn how to code you know the
last 10 to 15 years I'm like come on you
know we need people who are creative we
need people who can Market we need
people who understand philosophy and
psychology and and and so on like
they're very very important um even in
in very very technical areas um so I
it's so so when I say that I think it's
difficult for me to pick what someone
should learn because I you know I think
people should learn the things that that
they enjoy um otherwise you know it's
not I mean you can know a lot and do
nothing with it right um and but then if
I had to um pick something to learn
right now it's you know I really really
dislike this Buzz of
AI especially as a as a CS person um the
term is misused and that sort of a thing
but we cannot deny the super fast pace
of things like we just cannot deny it
right so if there's anything I I would
say somebody needs to learn now is about
the technologies that are completely
reshaping our landscape because there
are affecting us and will affect us
whether we like it or not um and we just
have to get on board with them and and
it's it's it's a simple as that yeah no
I think I think you're right and I think
those those are going to transform every
workplace right at the same time I
couldn't agree more right the importance
um that you've identified of of you know
people learning in all different
directions right and following their
passions and you know whether they're uh
in Psychology and economics and
marketing all those fields that you
mentioned
so this brings us I think to the final
question um which is directed at at you
U what will you be looking to learn um
the next time you visit MIT open
courseware well outside of the um how to
speak that's the immediate thing I'm
going to look for great that's fantastic
um yeah yeah yeah uh so that's the
immediate thing I'm going to look for
but outside of that um still very
interested in the sort of like
Behavior the behavior of things and then
um I need to use statistics and I did
not like
statistics once upon a time I need to
brush up so just brushing up on you know
on on on previous previous knowledge uh
still just because of my day-to-day work
right okay well that's fantastic um and
I hope you um have some good experiences
the next time you visit I might open
course whereare
always always so um uh this was a
wonderful conversation with you June and
I just want to um thank all of you um
who've joined uh online or elsewhere um
for for joining at this conversation
sharing your experiences either now um
or or in in other formats um and I think
you know we all share uh the enthusiasm
that that June brings to to learning um
to uh her creativity that she brings to
her work and and I'm really glad that
that we've been able to share this um
with with the world
um and I welcome you uh on behalf of all
of open learning to to stay in touch and
to keep learning with MIT open
courseware um and all of our open
learning offerings um and we and
encourage you to consider supporting our
work um by sharing uh the resources that
you encounter with your friends and
family and colleagues um by sharing your
own experiences and your story um
directly with us um the the ways that
mit's open learning resources have
transformed your personal Journey um to
learning and into career transformation
and finally um for those of you who are
in a position to do so we encourage and
invite you um to consider making a
donation uh that would that would
support our efforts um and help us bring
these uh to the rest of the world as
effectively as we possibly can um so for
now um I'm going to just say a final
thank you to June adongo and to everyone
who joined us online um until our next
conversation keep learning thanks very
much
but