from the MIT energy initiative this is
what if it works a podcast looking at
the energy solutions for climate change
I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob Stoner and
this is what if it
[Music]
works we're going to talk in a few
minutes about some cuttingedge ways to
take carbon out of our world well why
would you want to do that carbon dioxide
of course is a powerful greenhouse gas
that contributes to climate change in
fact its levels in the atmosphere have
been increased nearly 50% just since the
1950s the Earth does have biological
systems that can remove carbon but they
cannot keep up with the sheer scale of
the stuff that is being dumped into the
atmosphere from Industrial Systems from
our various modes of transportation and
on it goes so what ideas do scientists
and Engineers have for removing it we
will get to that but first to get a
sense of where this whole line of
thinking got started you got to go back
at least to the mid
1980s in 1985 an incredibly well-known
scientist a star in the general public
named Carl Sean testified before
Congress we're very pleased that you
would take the time out of
your schedule to come to a place like
Washington where everything seems to be
living in today and not in tomorrow to
share with us your particular view of
how our past and our present uh May well
affect our future Carl thank you thank
you very much Sean was an astronomer at
Cornell who had narrated a big series on
TV called Cosmos and he showed up in DC
in 1985 to testify about climate change
which was just starting to get on more
and more people's
Radars the uh Power of uh human beings
to affect and uh control and change the
environment is growing as our technology
grows and uh at present time we clearly
have reached the stage where we are
capable both uh intentionally and
inadvertently to make significant
changes in the global climate and in the
global ecosystem a few years later in
1988 NASA scientist James Hansen would
also warn Congress about the fact that
the climate was changing and that was
right about the time that our guest
today Howard Herzog arrived at MIT the
first summer I was here back in 1989 I I
came here to work on a variety of uh
energy projects but the first Sumer I
was here uh there was a researcher here
from Japan actually doing nuclear
research but some of his colleagues back
in Japan asked him a question can you
capture carbon dioxide emissions coming
out of a power plant Howard is an
engineer a senior research engineer here
at MIT he has now written a book called
carbon capture he's the co-author of an
upcoming book on carbon removal and this
struck him as a very interesting
question can you capture CO2 emissions
coming out of a power plant three of us
formed a team and issued a report and
said yes it is feasible cost a little
money but uh you can do it and we
published and we were one of the first
people to publish in this area there
were a few other groups publishing and
that field eventually became known as
carbon dioxide capture and storage or
CCS for short but that first project led
to another project at had a big research
needs assessment for the Department of
energy in 1992 with some co-authors here
at the uh back then it was called the
energy lab and that just kept going
after about 10 years it was the major
part of my uh research portfolio and has
remained that way for the past 25 years
or so during that time hoe has seen the
interest in climate change grow we
organized a big Symposium called Energy
and environment in the 21st century so
was back in 1990 and our big keynote
speaker was El Gore and he was a Senator
and all I remember him talking about was
this trip underneath the arctic ice in a
submarine but he has also seen interest
in climate change Splinter back then it
was a bipartisan issue it was the first
George Bush that was president when the
framer convention was to be ratified
that came out the Rio back in 1994 he
signed it I forget it was overwhelm prly
approved by the Senate so it wasn't a
political issue back then it became that
over the
years I can't pinpoint anything but I
think all of our politics has become
more polarized and uh this was just part
of the polarization uh which is uh too
bad because you know it affects
everybody you know red States blue
States uh it's not something that's easy
to solve unless you have everybody on
board to really have good climate policy
it really has to be bipartisan and
bought in by a majority of the people
and
unfortunately that's not where we're at
today we're going to talk about pulling
carbon out of the atmosphere but to know
whether that makes any sense you really
have to think about how much it costs to
both put carbon into the atmosphere and
to pull it out fossil fuels how he says
are a pretty great energy source and if
you don't acknowledge the fact that
they've got a downside by putting a
price on them people will turn to them
which is logical Europe has put a price
on carbon which can go up to $100 per
ton of CO2 how he says but of course
people are resistant to pay that kind of
tax it's going to cost more to reduce
our carbon emissions but the real
question is if we don't reduce our
carbon emissions what's the cost there
and that cost can be high high but still
there's a lot of interest in removing
carbon dioxide from the atmosphere so
what do the range of options look like
once the carbon's already out there
howwi we laid it out for us there's two
ways to get Co2 out of the air okay one
is biological and that's through
photosynthesis plants do this all the
time they record the CO2 level in the
atmosphere at the monolo observatory if
you look at that it's not a straight
line a squid goes going up and down in
the uh spring all of a sudden the plants
come to life and they suck up a lot of
the carbon dioxide and when they die in
the fall it goes back up and you can
actually see it in the measurements in
the atmosphere plants I saw a
visualization of this I have to say at
the MIT media lab Rachel Connelly who
works on NASA stuff it was amazing
during the Spring and the summer there's
so much less carbon dioxide in the air
right than in the winter when there just
so many few leaves to suck it up yeah
and for people who think well there's a
southern hemisphere too but most of the
lands in the northern hemisphere that's
what really controls that and the
measurements are being made in the
northern hemisphere so you have
photosynthesis and the other is
chemically and the way you do a
chemically is you do it with what I call
Alkali and Alkali just means it's a
chemical that's basic and CO2 is an acid
so think of when you're a kid and you
did the volcanoes with the baking soda
and vinegar vinegar is an acid baking
soda is a base and they react together
same with Alkali and carbon dioxide in
the atmosphere the problem is we don't
have Alkali rying around why don't we
have Alkali rying around because if it
was the CO2 in the atmosphere would
react with it and neutralize it so we
have to create and that costs money and
there's several ways to create this
Alkali and so what you have are things
like direct air capture which uses
absorbent talk about things like enhanc
weathering people talk about liming the
ocean lime is a alkaline material I've
heard of weather forecasting what Isa
sorry in enhanced Rock weathering so the
way that nature takes seal to out of the
atmosphere is by reacting with alkaline
rocks and these a lot of these alkaline
rocks are silicate type rocks and the
problem is the time scale for this is
100 thousands of years so that's slow so
there's always been a slow removal of Co
to into rocks over time but they want to
enhance that they want to get this thing
from taking 100,000 years to taking days
pressing fast forward on nature if I
could take this rock and really crush it
up so it's fine so a lot more sees the
air it will speed up the reaction but
the problem is to crush it up that fine
it takes a lot of uh energy whatever we
look at those ways take energy so so
those are are are the um things now now
when we go back to photosynthesis
there's two ways to to think about it
one is let's just plant a tree and leave
it there and so there's a concept called
stocks and flows stocks means how much
you have in a given Place flows is the
flow going between so what we're doing
with climate change is we have flows of
CO2 in the atmosphere primarily from our
our fossil fuel use and that increases
the stock of CO2 in the atmosphere some
of that will get also absorbed in in the
trees and vegetation and the ocean but
about half of it stays up in the
atmosphere so if we stop emitting CO2
today we stop the flow but the stock is
still up there you know that's the issue
that's why it lasts a long time and it's
the stock that's in the atmosphere that
determines how severe climate change is
going to be how how the temperature rise
and the other impacts so one thing we
can do is we can just plant more trees
we can figure out how to get more trees
or more stocks of carbon on a certain
area actually the soils contain about
twice as much carbon as the trees and
vegetation so if we want to get into
there Wetlands for instance contain a
real lot of uh carbon and you know a lot
of wetlands have been degraded over the
years restoring those Wetlands could
really absorb carbon so that puts it all
in the atmosphere but we can also
Harvest the carbon from the trees in the
vegetation and do other things with it
one thing people talk about doing is
making biochar which is like a soil
supplement and uh putting that in the
soil but basically where we are today
that's it and it in general it's a lot
cheaper to reduce emissions don't let it
get up in the atmosphere in the first
place but there are some removals that
are fairly inexpensive and if they are
and and like planting trees is one of
them
but there there are other issues with
that we can come back to specifically
the permanence issue that's a fine role
today but most of these other ones are
very um expensive so you really want to
reduce first but once we reduce 70 80
90% it starts getting very expensive to
reduce the last 10 or 20% and these are
what people sometimes call residual
emissions so it may be cheaper instead
of um trying to minate these residual
emissions to offset them or
counterbalance them with carbon removals
so to get fil fuels off an airplane is
not going to be easy if they Electrify
airplanes only be for small planes all
these airplanes are made for jet fuel
you know there's a lot of issues of
safety and everything so it may cost
$1,000 doll to try to get it off a plane
but we can remove it from the atmosphere
for a few hundred dollar that's a real
benefit so the ipcc which is the
International Panel of scientists to
which you belong or have belonged at
times chartered by the UN
fccc the United Nations framework
convention on climate change has become
very clear in their last couple of
reports about just what that removal
rate has to be by the middle of the
century and they're talking about
something like 10 billion tons a year
net are going to have to be removed by
us and put somewhere where it can't get
back into the atmosphere are you saying
that that's overstated because they're
underestimating how fast I'm saying
there's a lot of uncertainty in that
number and it's a debate to have in
mid-century when we're going to be a lot
smarter on on the cost and benefits of
all this because we can't start lowering
the stock of CO2 in the atmosphere until
we get to that zero so I think our full
focus should be getting on Net Zero and
you know we haven't been producing
emissions fast enough and I don't think
it's good to say oh that's okay because
if we overshoot we'll be able to remove
it and then they try to prove it I think
we should focus on reducing our
emissions as quickly as feasibly
possible there's technical feasibility
but there's also political feasibility
here that should be our focus and you
know we're developing these things to
remove it from the atmosphere right now
and we should continue doing that
modeling out to 2100 you know has a lot
of uh so so we we create the
Technologies and I know that you've gone
around the world visiting some of the
startup companies that are trying to
perfect technologies that can work what
have you learned and what what are your
feelings about what they're doing and
and the odds that will really have the
capacity well I mean I I think you're T
I mean what I focused on a bit recently
is the direct air capture yeah and I
don't know how many compies are out
there but I think it's probably over 30
DC they call it direct and um I've have
visited a couple of the leading
companies and there's one company clim
marks that's actually doing it so what
air are we talking about here are we
talking about air that comes out of like
power plants are we talking about just
like the regular air around us it's just
that regular air around us these are big
machines and they push the air through
the machines with big fans to move it
but basically the air is pretty much the
same everywhere it's uh has about 420
430 parts per million CO2 it goes
through the machines and it comes out
the other side they take out maybe 60 to
75% of the uh CO2 in the air that goes
through the machines wow so then if that
works for getting the carbon dioxide out
of the air why are we not running this
machines 247 every country is this the
solution
well that's what some people would like
and that's why this technology has sort
of become a darling with billions of
dollars being invested okay in it but
the bottom line is very costly so we
talked about uh like the uh European
trading system having a carbon price of
about $100 per ton if you go online
today to kimar's website you can buy
offsets and the cost there is $1,500 a
ton of carbon so so that's a lot of
money is that cuz they're gouging
consumers when they buy no car uh
actually they may be charging less than
the real cost so is the deal then that
okay yes they can run these machines 247
but it's going to cost them so much to
do it we can't afford it and it's not
just money it also costs a lot of energy
so you have to use clean energy if you
hooked up one of these machines to
coldfire power plant you would actually
put more CO2 in the atmosphere from the
coldfire power plant than you would
capture from these machines so you
really need seems like a bad decision
and the question is if we have that
carbon free energy is it better today to
use that to take CO2 out of the air or
is it better to uh supplant fossil fuels
we're using today with that clean energy
and it's almost the latter that's the
case so as I say carbon removal becomes
important as we start uh approaching Net
Zero get the last 20% or so of residual
emissions compensated for but today
there's a lot cheaper ways to reduce
emissions that's where our focus should
be and some people call uh things like
direct air capture you know a dangerous
distraction because of that because
we're not focused on reducing the
emissions today so okay so if you're a
government or you're a wealthy investor
you know investing fund and you're
thinking how to deploy money
you work in thinking about carbon
capture would you say like this is not
where to spend your money go spend it
somewhere else well I mean carbon
capture is different from carbon removal
I'm saying that I think there's good
reason to invest in carbon removal today
to develop the technology but to deploy
it at a large scale I don't think the
time is right yet but on the other hand
it could take 10 20 years to really get
these Technologies commercially ready
there's a lot of carbon removal
Technologies we don't know what are the
best and so working on them we're not
really spending a lot of money today in
the development of it now of course if
you have a company and trying to develop
this you want to deploy it as much as
possible you better have some patient
investors yeah but you either got to get
the cost way down which I think on some
of the things are going to be hard
because um to do it chemically it costs
a lot of money to uh develop this Alkali
the you need to process a tremendous
amount of air to get out um a good
amount of se2 because it's so dilute in
the air so if you want to capture a
million tons a year we put out in the
United States five billion tons of CO2 a
year so just to capture put out five
billion if you want to capture a million
a million tons which is okay but not so
great all right yeah yeah you need a
structure so so just think of the air
going in with a fan the cross-sectional
area is sort of the the thing
perpendicular so let think of it like a
building you need like a three story
building that's uh 3 miles long all
covered with fans that's to capture 1
million which is one 1,000th of a
billion of course and we got to get to
something like so you so if you want to
capture all the CO2 we're putting out it
it would take we don't we don't produce
enough electricity to Drive these things
to to even get our in the United States
to get our 5 billion but but as I'm
hearing you talk I mean your message is
sort of on different time frames let's
right now today yeah reduce our
emissions of CO2 where we can but in the
future when we need to start doing
removals use the lowcost options
available to us like growing biomass
making biochar sticking on the ground
and then and then look to the Future
when we might have the electrical
capacity and the efficiency in these
machines to start doing it actively
correct so this this tiered system and
we're buying time right and of course as
analysis we can say that but the real
world's messy yeah so when you have 30
companies out there developing direct
air capture Technologies they don't want
to
[Music]
wait so this there's direct capture but
I mean a lot of our colleagues here
lately have been talking about the idea
of direct ocean CER Dak and dock yeah
what's the idea there in a given volume
there's you know maybe a hundred times
or a little over a 100 times more carbon
in that volume of water than in the air
wow why why because water is a thousand
times denser than uh air ah okay so but
so you got to move you got to move the
same amount of mass that's what drives
it but
that doesn't guarantee you anything uh
actually the mass fraction in air uh of
of carbon is higher than it is in the
ocean also in the ocean it's not in the
form of CO2 it's uh dissolved carbon is
carbonates and bicarbonates primarily
and so therefore the technology to get
it out is different and once again from
things that I've read this is very early
stage of this but what I've read on this
subject so far is it takes a lot lot of
energy and maybe even more energy than
uh direct air capture right but but from
what you were saying earlier because the
the carbon is more concentrated in the
water the volume of water you have to
move through is much smaller and
therefore the machine is much smaller
not necessarily
oh why well it depends on how it comes
out and the main thing that they're
using that have come out now is
electrochemistry so yeah so your
cross-sectional area is smaller but
that's it takes energy to move air but
it also when you're putting these
through electrochemical devices those
devices take a lot of energy too not
necessarily move the air but to get that
carbon out of there then there's a whole
problem once you get the carbon out of a
certain amount of seawater you got to
put the sea water back in the ocean what
does that do because well would that
affect the ocean flux with the
atmosphere would that uh give you
environmental impacts when you're taking
out of seawater you're changing the
chemistry of that bit and when you put
it back in that's going to have some
impact so we got to really understand
that plus you know it's tough enough
getting uh a permit for a wind turban uh
when you're going to try to do things in
the ocean like that it's going to take
some time getting a permit I see you
think fisherman and so on might be
pushing back a little bit if you're
going to start I mean that's why it's
worth research now to understand these
things to answer these questions so when
you do go for a permit you have the
answers do you think I mean I know this
is projecting forward and I know we
don't have the answers but do you think
when we eventually figure out in
mid-century how we're going to address
climate change that the idea of actually
taking carbon out of the atmosphere Out
of Water whatever is going to be a big
player here and it won't just be let's
switch to wind let's switch to solar
let's switch the kind of cars we drive
ET it's because of the physics of the
problem it's hard for me saying it's
ever going to be cheap but what are the
impacts you know so we talk today you
know they talk about the social cost of
carbon which is really people give
numbers to it we don't know but what the
concept is is every time we emit some
carbon dioxide to the atmosphere there's
a cost of that and impacts from climate
change so if we want to remove it in the
future there'll be benefits how much are
those benefits yeah compared to the cost
of removing it that's the decision
people will make at that time and say is
it worth doing that I I keep an open
mind about it but I don't feel strongly
one way or another I just hope we
decrease emissions fast enough so it's
not going to be necessary for us to
remove that we don't get to your
research yet like you're the just in
case research well no I mean I started
on carbon capture and I think carbon
capture is a way to reduce emissions to
the atmosphere we're using more coal
today I mean Coal Keeps increasing the
US were you know closing coal plants but
China India are still building it you
know people are always going to want
energy and you know the question is you
know for them to do their missions doing
capturing a power plant uh can be cost
effective and that's a lot less money I
think once you build up carbon capture
and get the supply chains right you can
do it for under $100 a ton at at a at a
power plant from and maybe May you know
maybe even get closer to $50 a ton so
you know that's different than we're
talking numbers up now in the hundreds
of dollars or so so we haven't really
talked about where you put the CO2 once
you captured we talked about biochar a
little bit but so so basically where can
you put it so you know as I say there's
three reservoirs that they call
atmosphere Ocean and the terrestrial
biosphere so the more we put in the
ocean or the terrestrial
biosphere the Les is in the atmosphere
planting trees is one way to keep in the
terrestrial biosphere biochar is another
way to do that once again those are
issues of permanence will you really
keep it there for the length of time you
need or will things like uh pestilence
and fires you know uh disrupt some of it
or or even changes in land use but you
know you keep up there at least that has
the effect the other places are like I
mentioned enhanced Rock weathering you
turn it into rocks or you can put it
back into geologic formations so these
geologic formations are where we take
out oil and gas uh we can put them into
those same reservoirs or there's a lot
of geologic formations and and a lot
more of these than oil and gas
reservoirs uh that are uh basically deep
and they're filled with brine you want
to go over 800 M deep that way the CO2
stays in a dense phase a liquidlike
phase you can put them in those um
geologic formations and uh hopefully you
know we've had the oil and gas stay on
the ground for literally millions of
years so hopefully that's a permanent
solution so those are what you can do uh
is there enough space down there I mean
you have reservations about the the
limits of's a lot there's a lot of space
down there the theoretical space is very
large there's there's two issues one you
know how much that theoretical space can
we use and secondly it's not everywhere
you know it's in all parts of the world
but it's not in every place so for
instance um you know here in New England
we don't really have a lot of that
formation a lot of those formations are
where you see oil and gas production
today we do have we do potentially have
some capacity here in New England uh
offshore but it hasn't really been
explored because the places people have
explored Underground or where they're
trying to get out fossil fuels I guess
that's another big application of of CO2
once it's captured to use it to pump
into active oil and gas reserves to
produce more efficiently CO2 is good at
um you pump CO2 into an active oil
reservoir what they call mobilize the
oil it changes the oil viscosity so it
flows better so there so there's an
irony there but but is that also
potentially a pathway to almost have a
circular flow of carbon from the
reservoir out to where we use it back in
agains you know you can maybe produce
carbon neutral oil that way but that
that's not a negative emission or or or
or in the long run it's you know you
really got to cut back but what that's
been useful for it's been a stepping
stone to help some of these initial
projects you know which are financially
challenged uh to begin with uh it helps
finances those projects because they can
actually sell the CO2 and get a little
money for it in fact accidental
petroleum but but uh what was it carbon
engineering carbon engineering correct
to to do precisely that inject carbon
into their Wells to more oil atmosphere
to produce oil with the idea that it's a
stepping stone I guess well we'll just
say oxy's a little more bullish on all
this than I am uh you know they they
want to have a half a million ton of
year plant operating by the the end of
next year um I saw VI talking about this
recently she's she's quite convincing
when when you hear her but yeah I'm I'm
going FR path I'm going to go back to
the old British proverb the proof is in
the pudding so well Warren Buffett's
bullish I he's been he's so sold on the
story that oxy's putting out that he's
acquired most of the company wow well
doin
right I uh I take a wait and see
attitude um I know we wanted to I think
finally talk about some of
the maybe more Fringe ideas of like how
to like really geoengineer if we think
wow things are getting too hot there's
too much carbon out there what can we do
and I feel like these efforts to change
like clouds change the weather these
kinds of things like they get a lot of
media attention I don't know if they
deserve the media attention but they
seem I think so interesting and exciting
that people can't resist talking about
them so just first of all talk about
like what kinds of things do people talk
about that you might be able to do and
then tell us if like you can really do
that yeah it's the most common one
people talk about our solar Radiance
management putting up a sun sheet and
the the the most common there is putting
aerosol particles up in the stratosphere
and so it reflect sunlight so this
doesn't do anything to the carbon
dioxide but it it cools the Earth so
wait so the idea is you've got Sun the
sun's Rays coming down and you're like
no let's reflect them back right we
don't want them here okay and there's a
whole series of of things to do it that
so this goes back a long time there was
a uh National Academy study sometime
around 1990 I can't remember the exact
date and it was really thick it might
have been a th pages
and they had like a uh 15 or so page
appendix they had a lot of appendixes
and one was on geoengineering so there's
a really thick report this one appendix
there was an art and I still have the
article in my drawer an article in
Newsweek called the wings of Icarus a
two-page spread and all they talked
about from that report were the
geoengineering ones you know talked
about shooting um Navy shells up in the
atmosphere to do sades and putting a sun
shade you know actually putting things
in space at some of these lran points
still talking about I know they're still
talking about it and it's something
people like to talk about I actually
have a section in the new book saying is
carbon removal
geoengineering and I think the answer it
there's an array and it depends how you
define geoengineering people don't know
so people say when we're Ming CO2 up our
chimneys or our tail pipes is a
geoengineering experiment cuz we're
changing the Earth is causing climate
change in that case anytime we remove it
would be two but probably the most
benign uh in terms of that is direct air
capture because you're really not
affecting anything except taking the CO2
out of the air and I think and that's
another reason people like it a lot and
the Other Extreme is uh this ocean
alkalinity uh enhancement where you're
putting uh alkaline subjects in the
ocean so so you can get more carbon stor
accelerated sort of dissolution of Co 2
into the ocean yeah when you put more
Alkali in the ocean it it it will absorb
more CO2 from the um atmosphere and also
it will neutralize a little of the ocean
acidification that's being caused by the
extra CO2 going in the ocean right now
so it looks pretty interesting but
there's a lot of uh questions on what
the uh impacts so it'll be something
that go slow but that's that really is
geoengineering um even though there once
again you are affecting the CO2 in the
atmosphere as opposed to trying to you
know when you're trying to manage the
solar radiation there's no guarantee
it's going to be an exact match so some
places it make make climate change
impacts worse while make it better in
other places and then of course I would
suggest you become a lawyer so you can
take all the law cases suing the people
that that the solar Radiance it sounds
like you're like you're skeptical and
it's also so I I would think impossible
to test many of these things out like
until you just do it you decide we're
going to pull the trigger and do this
yeah down the street or maybe I should
say up the river at Harvard um they were
going to do an experiment on this in
Sweden and uh it ran into opposition and
they they they never ran the experiment
because of the the local opposition I
think it's hard to run an experiment on
that there's there's research you can do
to better understand it the best
experiments are natural experiments so
when a volcano erupts that's basically
what they're trying to do so we have
data from that but it's what I said in
my first book geoengineering is a hail
Mar pass in football and you ask any
football coach you want to avoid the
Hail Mary yeah so I guess that that same
it doesn't work most of the time but
that same caution applies to direct
ocean capture as well from what you were
saying earlier we're going to be
affecting the alkalinity of the ocean
and its biology very locally and that
could have real impacts unlike Capt it
from the atmosphere the D dilute nature
of what's in the atmosphere is actually
advantageous so so you know I think when
you work in the ocean you are much more
on the geoengineering Fringe than say
planting trees or restoring Wetlands so
can we do it I mean can
we use these techniques to
address this increase we have in our in
our missions and and head off climate
change or is that even the right way to
think about it there there's a there's a
person uh that I worked with in the past
from Oak Ridge named Greg Marland and
once again this is back 25 years ago he
ran a little Symposium and in the
morning it said can we
geoengineer the climate and then the
afternoon session was should we
geoengineer the climate what could
possibly go wrong
so I I think the most important thing we
can do now is reduce emissions as
quickly as possible and so maybe I I can
end where the uh last statement of the
new book we wrote and the best way to
remove CO2 from the atmosphere is not to
put CO2 in the atmosphere in the first
place great
advice Howard Herzog is a senior
research engineer at the MIT energy
initiative he's the of the book carbon
capture and of an upcoming book on
carbon removal Howard thanks so much for
being here thank
[Music]
you what if it works is a production of
the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend to listen and remember
to subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu
podcasts and you can learn more about
the work of the energy initiative and
the energy transition at energy. mit.edu
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob Stoner thanks for listening
[Music]