hi everybody I'm back uh great to be
back here and um a lot of what I'm going
to say sort of uh I think parallels what
Andy just said which is that you know
we've got to get better at understanding
what's going on and we need better data
and so we've come up with a way of doing
that
for uh uninstrumented parts of an
operation so yes you can right now do a
lot of stuff if you have great data
analysis with machines but what about
people and so that's what we approached
in our uh when we started this company
we are a Google Cloud partner but we
also work with other clouds but Google
uh we've been working them first and so
they are also promoting our system to
all their uh all their customers as well
so let's go to the next slide here if I
can okay there we go um
so the big problem that we noticed when
we started out talking to manufacturers
is that a lot of parts of an operation
are very much people Centric there are
machines that they use but people are
using the machines the fully automated
part parts are are are actually pretty
much minority and so you can get this
kind of data like oh the lathe stopped
and so we have this overall equipment
effectiveness of 34% this cncc machine
is running um that's great but then
there's all these other parts of the
operation that are just not really
giving good data if they do they may
have people uh scanning things with a
barcode scanner saying I'm just going to
start a build and they scan something
and then an hour later you get another
scan saying I just finished a build now
sometimes they forget to scan out and
then you have bad data so this data
quality when you're relying on people
whose job it is not really to enter data
to be in charge of that data quality is
not so great who's who's had a problem
where they got a reason code from a
manual data entry that was not very
helpful who's ever had an unhelpful
reason code anyone yeah okay admit that
um so what we built was a way to use
off-the-shelf cameras to uh have our
Machine Vision system recognize people
and tools and parts and equipment and
all sorts of other parts of the process
and track them all the time and the hard
part was when we started out you know
the kind of um technology that was
available you could track things but it
couldn't tell us what the relationships
were so being MIT people we said I guess
we're have to invent our own engine to
understand relationships and so we went
to the drawing board and for two years
we we had to invent a new kind of AI
system that could actually understand
all the relationships all the time
between all these things it's not easy
especially if you want to do it in real
time and we had to also do it in real
time because our customers want to know
now they don't want to know next week
what happened today they want to know
now what's going on right now because
our customers are plant managers uh line
supervisors operational leadership
continuous Improvement leaders quality
leaders safety leaders all these people
are our stakeholders and so we had to
have something that was fast so we use
Google Cloud for the cloud operations
right now we can use other clouds too
but um we also have an on Prem solution
and this has been very attractive to
some of our customers because they have
a place where there are a lot of people
working that doesn't have a gigabit
connection who has a place without a
gigabit connection where you got a lot
of people working anybody out there yeah
and uh so without a gigabit connection
sending 100 streams of video to the
cloud is not possible but we can send it
to a server here that processes the
video locally and does a lot of the
Insight generation right there on a
server on the local area network and
then can also communicate with the cloud
and so again you know having many ways
to plug into this has been valuable we
had to build our own dashboard because a
lot of our customers aren't using
Tableau or Microsoft powerbi they can't
really build dashboards themselves so we
built a a very nice dashboard that a lot
of our customers are very happy with if
they don't like that they can use apis
to pull our data and visualize it any
way they want uh we also have our own
alerting system so we send out uh text
messages and emails and other kinds of
alert systems when our agents uh Det
something that needs really rapid
response so that's the other thing that
you know there's a lot of who's heard
the word agent lately in in this AI
stuff right A lot of people talking
about agents and so what we think of
these are is visual agents and that's
sort of I think an upand cominging uh
Frontier you want an agent that not just
can read through all the texts and all
the emails and all the and and and and
and pull out something for you you want
an agent that can be your eyes uh so you
can see when there's a safety issue
coming up or you can see when um you
know there there's there's there's these
places where people should be working
and no one's there maybe they got told
to go somewhere else but they shouldn't
be doing something else they should be
back here right so that kind of when
that stuff happens our system can tell
the right people hey check this out
there's something going on here that you
need to look at and that's been the aha
moment for our customers like wow this
agent is actually helping me out a lot I
really appreciate that so that's sort of
what we offer to our customers and we've
seen really clear Roi from this um you
know these are the sort of very clear
ones that are quantifiable like we have
a customer where they actually measured
their capacity month to month after six
months because they were able to
identify a lot of the unexpected
downtime this is manual downtime this is
time when people are just waiting around
for parts people are waiting around for
uh a part to be moved into their area
where they can start working on it
because the pre previous team finished
what they were doing that kind of stuff
added up and that is continuing to
increase their productivity so this is
without buying any new Capital Equipment
no new machines not hiring any new
people this is just everything as it was
but pulling out the wasted time using
our agents um we have customer also same
same some some customers use both so
this one A different customer but they
also do productivity stuff they also do
safety stuff and this is a big cultural
shift we talked about cultural changes
cultures of safety um are important and
uh so to get that kind of change in
culture if you have an Guardian Angel
which is an AI watching for near misses
and uh accidents that are about to
happen and then everybody knows that
these near misses have been adding up
this week they they start changing the
way they behave because they now it's
not just uh I'm just doing whatever I
want no one's seeing what I'm doing now
I could die and this thing is actually
making me be better so that's that's
that's important this is the kind of uh
data view that we have in our dashboard
you can sort of see if anyone's ever
analyzed like uh performance of a
machine I I'm not treating people like
machines I don't want to do that but on
the other hand there's some really great
science of manufacturing and science of
operations that comes from thinking
about things like you know uh what is
this time loss what is the par on the
breakdown of time loss we can do that
now for a fully manual uh location so if
you're building big things big expensive
things and one day of is a giant problem
for your manufacturing operations team
getting this kind of report daily about
what our time loss was every day it's a
big deal and so that's how we've been
able to do all this kind of stuff and
you can see cycles and all that kind of
stuff here I'll do more demos of my
booth over there so come by afterwards
if You' like to see more about what this
does um we are highly secure and uh so
that's gotten us into a lot of places
where they're worried about data
security especially you know on Prem and
the cloud that helps with security and
um why Houston uh I think Texas is a
great state because it's got this
incredible ranking compared to
California it's the second one here in
terms of patent filings and also um in
terms of the Metros you know we got
Dallas right there so um we've got a lot
of great Texas power in in high-tech in
Ai and I think this is a great place for
Leela AI to get uh going we don't have
any customers yet in Texas we'd love to
have
so um thanks for your time today there's
my email you can always email me but
please come and check us out especially
if you're involved in operations
efficiency uh highx is great we love
people who make one-of a kind things uh
big things that that's who our most of
our customers are in high mix low volume
so if that's what you do uh please come
on over happy to talk to you thank you
very much
[Applause]