Well, welcome back everyone. Um, like
Nikki, I am a program director at the
MIT office of corporate relations in the
industrial liaison program. My name is
Cheryl Greenberg. Um, I work with a
number of the company people have that
have attended today. Um, I'd like to
introduce our next presenter, Professor
Manolus Kellis. And if I were to ask you
what you thought the primary research
interest area of a professor like
himself in the department of electrical
engineering and computer science, you
might guess
wrong. So I will tell you professor
Manolus Kellis his primary interest is
in computational biology. So remember
department of electrical engineering and
computer science. In addition, he also
develops new algorithms and machine
learning techniques for the
interpretation of complete genomes, the
understanding of gene regulation and
embryo
development. This is along with research
projects in machine learning, robotics,
computational geometry, and much more.
You can always check out his web page if
you want to get a better sense of him.
and today he will be speaking to you
about AI foundation models for
chemistry, protein structure and
function and personalized therapeutics.
Please join me in welcoming Professor
Manolas Kellis. Thank you. Wonderful to
be here.
It's so nice to see so many familiar
faces. So nice to see so many folks that
we've interacted and collaborated with
through the years. Um, what I'm going to
tell you about today is how we use AI
for understanding human health, for
understanding biology and the
foundations of biology, of chemistry, of
protein structure, of protein function,
and how we use that to guide both the
what and where and how to target for
whom, which is the genomic medicine
part, and also how to develop new
therapeutics, which is the therapeutic
development part. So uh I'm a member of
the uh computer science artificial
intelligence lab but also a member of
the broad institute and the first
vertical that I'm going to be showing
you is how to go from genomics to
circuitry to targets to drug design and
eventually animals and uh patients. And
then the second one is how do we
understand the diversity of patients?
How do we understand patient
trajectories? How do we understand in a
multimodal way how to combine clinical
notes and quantitative data and all of
this information cutting across all of
these different data streams to uh
really deliver personalized precision
medicine and the last part will be can
we step back and see how is AI going how
is it doing and how can we leverage AI
as a partner ner not as a replacement.
So a lot of people are freaked out about
AI and that's because we've kind of
developed an ecosystem where the humans
are left out. So what I what I will show
you is a new approach of visual AI that
lifts humans up instead of replacing
them. that basically puts you on the
driver's seat by showing you directly
how the AI is thinking of your data,
making all that available and giving you
access to sort of poke around the
neurons and the latent representations
which we're using for drug discovery,
protein function and patient states.
Medicine has really come a long way. So
uh from treating the patients from the
outside and you can see here an image of
a god or maybe a temple physician. Um
today things are very very different. No
one will confuse a physician with god
although you know reports might vary. Um
and you basically have this peerreview
committee these nurses. Actually not
much has changed I have to say but what
has changed is that we're treating
patients not from the outside anymore.
We're not simply making guesses anymore.
It's not just about correlations
anymore. It's not just about
epidemiology. It's really about
mechanism. And that changed, of course,
with technology. What allowed us to
change this is number one, the
microscope, being able to actually peak
inside the human body, look at
individual cells, and even look inside
those cells to recognize more than a 100
years ago with the first diagnosis of
Alzheimer's disease, the first
Alzheimer's patient of Dr. Alzheimer,
the recognition of amalloid plaques and
tangles. And here I'm showing you at the
bottom left two phenotypes in four
cells. The phenotypes are amaloid
plaques and neuropibrillary tangles. How
far we've come. On the bottom right of
the slide, I'm showing you 2.4 million
cells. And every cell instead of having
two measurements now has 20,000
measurements. The expression of every
single gene in the human genome. And I'm
not showing you one or two patients. I'm
showing you 430 patients in this
particular slide. So every dot is a
20,000dimensional vector which is
projected into a two-dimensional space,
an embedding space if you wish. And
we're going to be using embeddings in
the third part of the talk. So brace
yourselves. Now, an embedding space is a
space that preserves the pair-wise
distances between elements in the 2D
version, just like in the 20,000D
version. Humans are not that great about
visualizing 20,000 dimensional points.
So, just for the benefit of the
audience, we went down to 2D. Everybody
with me here? So, what does that mean?
It basically tells us the
transcriptional position of every cell,
i.e. where is that transcriptional state
of that cell? And we can now study
phenotypes. We can project phenotypes
onto those cells and basically see how
our Alzheimer's patients changing not
just in one or two variables, not just
in one or two genes, but in hundreds of
genes, in all of these different
pathways and hallmarks of the disease at
a time. Everybody with me here? Who's
excited? Come on. Who's excited? Yay.
There you go. All right. So, how are we
going to do this? We're going to do this
using AI. And that's what I'm going to
be telling you about. How AI can really
help us transform both the understanding
of disease, the understanding of
biology, and the delivery of
therapeutics and even the design of
therapeutics. So, the tools are of
course phenotypes, of course,
transcriptional state, but also an ace
up our sleeve is
causality. And the quickest way to
causality is genetics. In other words,
if you have a genetic variant that
correlates with the disease at 93 years
of age and you inherited that variant
before birth, it's unlikely to be that
you have this variant because you ate
more or you exercise less or you name
it. Okay, that's the best closest
approximation to causality that we have
because we can find these correlations
between genetic variation and disease.
And because of the temporality of when I
inherited that variant, I can now see
what is the mechanism through which this
genetic variant alters transcriptional
and cellular function and then by
extrapolation how that might actually be
implicated in the disease mechanism and
therefore how that can guide us to carry
out a more mechanistic a more systematic
a more rational approach to genomic
medicine and therapeutic design. Who's
with me so far? Yeah, good. Awesome.
So, what are these new technologies?
Number one, a major shift is going from
hypothesisdriven research to datadriven
research. That basically means that
instead of just simply formulating
hypothesis, gathering a bunch of data,
doing all of the thinking before
targeting the study, which basically
gives us a highly biased with relatively
little novelty and little ability to
discover new things. We're instead
seeing the shift to gather massive
amounts of data, shoot first, ask
questions later by building systematic
data sets, building these resources, and
massively sharing them in a
comprehensive way across many different
data modalities. The second dramatic
shift that we're seeing is that we're
going from correlation to
causation. So throughout human history,
epidemiology has been all about
correlations. If you drink a $7
Starbucks coffee every morning, you have
better health outcomes. Is it because
you probably can also afford a better
health care, you know, more exercise,
you know, a more steady job and you name
it, or is it really that Starbucks is so
awesome for you? I mean, could be both.
Um, there's also a correlation. The
countries that consume the most
chocolate are also showing more Noble
prices. We can again argue about
correlation and causation. I'd rather
postulate correlation.
Um however uh with genetics we have the
ability to now switch to causality to
basically look at the correlation
between genetic variance and disease
outcomes and there's a unidirectional
arrow there. Calculate polygenic risk
scores for a diversity of latent
factors. I don't need to look at
individual variants. I can just say how
am I predicting the complete burden on
this particular pathway of genetic
variance associated with a panoply of
locations which are then converging on
higher predicted uh I don't know
neuronal activity which then we can
correlate with I don't know chocolate
and Nobel prizes and so forth. Um and
then of course perturbation experiments
are much easier in a cell than they are
in a population. With I don't know
social experiments it's very hard to say
okay great let's put all of the kids out
of school for two years and see what
happens where whereas with cells it's
much easier to sort of you know go and
confirm this postulated causality. And
then the third major shift which I will
focus the last part of my talk on is
we're going from classical data analysis
namely where there's a new methodology
for every problem where the human
scientist does all the thinking and
there's very few parameters we're trying
to minimize the parameters and have very
targeted models to a place where
generative AI and deep learning and all
of these foundation models live and
that's the place of multimodality that's
the place of representation learning
that's the place of hier hierarchical
abstractions on primary data, secondary
abstractions, tertiary, etc. where the
AI is actually truly understanding the
concepts and can give us massive new
insights. Okay, so combining all of this
together, our team has basically taken
on to understand first of all the
causality underlying the most pronounced
the strongest genetic associations with
some of the biggest plagues in our
society. The first is obesity. The
strongest genetic association with
obesity lies in the FTO locus in intron
2 of this giant super long gene that
turns out to be a complete red herring.
So the FTO gene we showed is totally not
involved in al in
obesity even though the genetic variants
that are truly causal sit in that gene.
How is that possible? That's possible
because 93% of genetic associations do
not affect the proteins directly.
Instead, they affect the non-coding
regions and those non-coding regions are
responsible for where and how and when
the genes are actually
active. Everybody with me here? So, what
we found is that this genetic locus is
in fact targeting two genes that are
sitting 1.2 million nucleotides away.
And those genes turned out to be newly
discovered master regulators of a
process known as thermogenesis. This is
where your adipocytes instead of storing
fat storing calories into these energy
lies that we call
lipids instead are depolarizing the
mitochondrial membrane leading to a loss
in the proton gradient and energy loss
as heat. So by controlling the fate of
padypiposytes into either energy burning
or energy storing
cells, this genetic locus causes people
to have one standard deviation higher
weight in adulthood. This is remarkable.
So I'm I'm a homozygous risk carrier. So
my entire family has been obese. I um
you know I I haven't eaten since
yesterday. I went to the gym this
morning. I bike in every day. I go up
the stairs. So yes, I you know, of
course, environment matters. So if you
know your genetics, you can, you know,
either take a bunch of pills and, you
know, that's fine. No, no problem with
that. Or you can actually just live a
healthier lifestyle. So anyway, I
digress. So we were able to trace the
strongest genetic association that spans
50,000 nucleotides down to a single
letter down to a T2C mutation that
basically causes the ARID 5B repressor
to no longer be able to repress the
corresponding target genes that it
normally binds and to therefore lead to
this derression of Ryx3 and RX5. this
derression of this master enhancer and
the shut off of thermogenesis. So why
are we excited about the circuitry?
Because by understanding the circuitry,
we can actually intervene. It's not just
an academic exercise. Yeah, we figured
out which is of course fun and cool. But
uh we can actually know where to
intervene. And I have to say a joke
about this this MIT professor who is
involved to uh uh to come to this
factory that had just completely broken
apart. Nothing was working. And then he
spends a lot of time thinking and then
he puts an X on the wall and then uh
they ask him to, you know, they they
check behind the X and indeed that's the
that's the part that was missing. That's
the part that was broken. They fixed it
and then the factory that was spending
millions of dollars in like a year was
now back running. So then they asked for
the itemized bill. They asked for the
bill. He sent a $10,000 bill and they
said, "Could you please itemize it?" And
he said, you know, chalk $1. Knowing
where to put the X,
$9,999. So this is the knowing where to
put the X part. Changing an equal side,
no problemmo. But knowing what to where
to put the X, that's that's where all
the money is. Okay. So what we figured
out is that by knowing where to put the
X, we could change a single letter out
of 3.2 billion letters in the genome. I
mean, that's precision medicine right
there, right? 3.2 billion letters. We
choose one and we alter it. And what do
we see? We see that we can completely
restore thermogenesis in obesity risk
patients by a factor of seven. and going
into mice and changing the downstream
target genes by deressing them. We
basically see that these mice
are unable to gain weight. You put them
on a treadmill, you you know put them on
a couch, you feed them whatever they
want, they don't gain weight. They're
unable to gain weight. All of their fat
tissues are sort of gone. They're super
healthy, super lean, red, juicy organs
instead of like the Sorry, my appetite
started. Um, all right. So, so we want
to do this systematically. We want to do
this for every gene, every disease,
every genetic association of the genome.
And of course, I have to show you more
than one example. So, here's ApoE4. So,
this was published in the New England
Journal of Medicine. This was published
in Nature. Uh, so here we have the
strongest genetic association with
Alzheimer's disease. And the ApoE4 alil
that increases your risk tfold if you're
homozygous carrier. What we found is
that for both Alzheimer's and control
individuals that were carriers of the
risk alil
apo4 we found increased cholesterol
biogenesis but surprisingly decreased
myelination. Milination is of course
where the cholesterol ends up at the end
end of oligodendrites that basically
coat your axins with myelin with this
lipid layer to basically protect them
and to make the electrical signal flow
faster. So you would expect that that
would be associated with less
cholesterol not more cholesterol because
we're clearly upregulating cholesterol
biosynthesis. So what's going on here?
What's going on is that the cholesterol
cannot be transported. instead it gets
stuck in the endopplasmic reticulum of
the oligodendrites and you see all these
bubbles here instead of this nice sort
of lean export. So what we reason is
well maybe if we facilitate transport
using
cycllodextrine we can restore
mileelination and restore cognition and
indeed that's exactly what we found both
in human cells and in an animal model
and animal cells we're able to restore
cognition by understanding the circuitry
and being able to intervene third
example cancer imotherapy and again I'm
going through the big plagues of our
society here so Alzheimer's cancer
obesity so in cancer Iapy is
magnificent. It cures 50% of the
patients. Well, it's magnificent for for
those 50%. For the other 50%, it's a
waste of time. But what we were able to
show is that the difference between
responders and non-responders to
imunotherapy was in fact a lot of genes
downstream of a small number of
regulators. So using a combination
therapy by understanding again the
circuitry, understanding the
epigenomics, we were able to get 100%
imunotherapy response.
So we can now start taking on disease.
But again, thinking about Alzheimer's as
a single disease is a little weird
because the manifestation of Alzheimer's
is dramatically different from person to
person. So what we can do now is scale
up. Instead of just looking at one
patient, we're looking at 400 patients.
In this particular case, 427
individuals, 2.4 million cells as I
showed you in the first slide. And we
can now look at the diversity of
phenotypes across pathology, cognition,
cognitive decline, amaloid plaques,
neuropibrillers, neo inflammation. We
can now start looking at the diversity
of disease at the phenotypic level and
start matching it with the diversity of
disease at the cellular level and we can
now discover these hallmarks of disease
and start associating them with distinct
combinations of phenotypes. For example,
we found that resilience is associated
with choline metabolism. And if you
consume more choline, you know, chances
are it's protective for or against
Alzheimer disease. And we're able to
understand this by building these
networks of modules of hallmarks inside
the cell and then associating with
distinct regions in this cellular
landscape. We can do the same thing with
understanding the epigenome, not just
the transcriptto. In this particular
case, we're looking at how the
epiggenome changes across again 3.5
million cells across 400 donors where we
now have matched DNA accessibility and
gene expression and we can now find this
very dramatic shift in epigenomic
information. So we basically have this
epigenome rewiring and this epigenome
erosion that happens in the Alzheimer's
individuals but then restoration in the
control individuals and we can find the
regulators the the the targets that we
should be going after to restore
homeogenesis. We can also use spatial
transcodies to understand how the
localization and the organization of
these cells inside for example the
arteries or the inima the lumen and the
media of your coronary arteries in the
context of again the fourth major killer
coronary artery disease actually number
one in developed nations where we
actually find specific subsets of immune
cells that are engulfing the lipids from
your bloodstream are in fact
disregulated in specific spatial regions
that allows us to again now know how to
intervene and going back to the concept
of we don't want to treat Alzheimer's
monolithically yes we can understand the
hallmarks of Alzheimer's
disease what are the pathways that are
recurrently perturbed at the genetic
level at the epigenomic level at the
transcription level at the cellular
level and ultimately manifesting in the
endotypes the imaging
the biomarkers and ultimately the
disease phenotypes. But we can also go
down to single cell
resolution. Let me
explain. Every cell in a differential
expression analysis currently is thought
of as 100% Alzheimer's or 100% control.
We basically say what is the difference
in expression between Alzheimer's cases
and controls.
But we have thousands of cells for each
person. Not every cell is 100%
Alzheimer's. So what we can do now is
flip this around. We can basically say,
let's look at the transcriptional
landscape of the cells, this embedding
landscape that I mentioned earlier. And
we can now color every cell according to
the color of the donor, 100% red or 100%
blue, Alzheimer's or controls. And now
we can basically say for every cellular
neighborhood, for every transcriptional
neighborhood, is there an enrichment for
Alzheimer's, for control or for neither?
And therefore, we can define
neighborhoods that are very healthy in
blue or very sick in red or
intermediate. And every cell now, we can
ignore the original phenotype that it
had because we have 400 people telling
us what those phenotypes are. And we can
now color every cell according to the
color of its
neighborhood. Why is that exciting?
Because we can now instead of finding
five differentially expressed genes, we
can find hundreds of differentially
expressed genes. Because we're not
looking at case control where every cell
is colored either 100% red or 100% blue.
We can now look at the gradients and say
those cells that are in very sick
neighborhoods have much more much
stronger disregulation of these genes
versus those genes. Who's with me so
far? Yes. Awesome. Now we can go a step
further and say well remember this red
blue coloring of the individuals are
sick or healthy. We don't have to do
that anymore. We can now look at that
person's microgal cells and say well
their micro gleal cells were clearly in
blue neighborhoods and theirodenderites
were in red
neighborhoods. So we can now start
mapping phenotypes to the cellular level
and from the cellular level map back to
the individuals and start inferring
transcriptional states for every person
and for every phenotype in every cell
type. This is completely transformative
of the way that we use single cell data
and of the way that we understand
disease in the first place. We can now
understand patient hogenity at
unprecedented resolution. That allows us
to now start looking back at the
genetics and instead of just looking at
the genetics in a completely blind way
the way that it was done in 1905 by RA
Fischer, we can now in 2025 say not
every genetic variant is born the same.
Some genetic variants are perturbing
those hallmarks that we identified in
the epigenomic regions in the genes in
the pathways in the cell types in the
cellular states that we uncovered as the
hallmarks of disease. We can now just by
looking at the genetics of a person say
well that person's risk for
neuroinflammation is much higher than
for lipid dysregulation and for whole
cholesterol homeostasis etc. So we can
now start doing genetic predictions at
extraordinary resolution and therefore
start developing therapeutics and start
targeting those therapeutics for each
person in a different way. Which of
course takes us to the last part of the
talk about specific targets. How do we
now develop these molecules? Well, we
start of course with a protein target,
but what we want to do is scan through
thousands of known drugs and use a
gradient ascent to basically understand
again this latent embedding space of
chemistry and walk up the chemical
gradient of affinity towards that
protein. And then when we find a region
in that embedding
space where those molecules are more
promising, we can start generating
outbdings. can start constructing
molecules from those coordinates in that
latent embedding space. So it's a very
new paradigm for discovery where
basically we understand the drug
landscape that's feeding the AI. The AI
is interacting with the human and we
have complete control on how we we climb
those gradients. So my student Safi
who's going to be presenting a poster
later, please go talk to him. He's the
smartest person I have ever met. He is a
freshman at MIT and he's beating the
state-of-the-art in drug discovery in
the world. He had seven publications
before even coming to MIT as a high
schooler and four patents. So this is
like this kid is extraordinary. So so if
you want to collaborate with him just
don't steal him please, but work with
him directly. You don't need me. Um so
he developed affinity net 1 2 3 4 5 6 7.
He's now at 10. At eight, he had already
surpassed the state-of-the-art and he
has continued just like blowing the
competition out of the water. So, he's
basically now building these native
embeddings and outbeddings speaking a
single language between chemistry and
language and human language. How? By
co-mbbedding the landscape of patents
and the landscape of chemistry at the
same time. So he can now look at
different regions of the chemical
landscape and say hey you know what
should I be using for cardiovascular
disease or Alzheimer's or cancer and so
on so forth and he's developed in the
last you know few days um these agents
that are able to now go through the
entire drug development process. So
these agents are you know sort of first
understanding what is the disease how
should we be targeting it like then
mining the entire literature and all of
our transcriptional states to identify
targets then validating these targets
using our multimodal information across
lipidomics transcrytoics epigenomics
then climbing up that tree of
therapeutic space and chemical space and
in the end generating these reports and
every few hours he has coded a new
agent. So if you have collaborators that
are invaluable in your company, talk to
Safi, tell him what they do and he'll
replace them very
soon. So, so um that didn't quite come
out the way that I was hoping, but but
you can now construct a virtual team
with every expertise, every data source,
every approach, every angle that you
would like to build using these um
agents. And we can now start combining
this geometric deep learning
representation of the latent embeddings
of the chemistry and the protein
landscapes and the cellular landscape
and the patient diversity landscape and
the genetic landscape and then start
optimizing jointly these molecules
across both protein and chemical space.
So that's the first part of the talk
telling you about how we are
transforming the space of biology,
chemistry, healthcare
and using this unified approach that
cuts across all of these layers of
genetics, circuitry, target genes,
epigenomics,
transcrytoics, protein targets, protein
structure, chemical structure, and then
eventually screening them in both
organoids and optimizing the chemistry.
So that's the first part. But I want to
make a small parenthesis here and talk
about that bottom right corner that
everybody's asking me about. I heard a
lot of you basically say, "Tell me about
geni. Tell me about all of these
representation learning. Tell me about
these foundation models. Tell me about
these agents." And I want to spend a
little time on that and basically tell
you how far we've come. The left part of
the the slide is the good news.
We now have deep representation learning
across all of these different data
modalities. We now have multimodel
understanding that combines these
modalities together. And we have an AI
that is able to do intuitive reasoning.
That's already really great news. The
bad news is when I ask people, hey,
what's the future? They say, oh, chat.
Chat is the new search. Chat is the new
um, you know, question answering. Chat
is the new um, uh, everything. So, so we
are effectively locking the humans in a
box where they're able to interact with
this magnificence of data only by
sliding questions on a little note in a
little hole in the box. The AI is the
genie. Imagine yourself in the cave of
wonders in Aladdin, the first one. I I
haven't seen any of the other ones. So,
uh I was 16 at the time. Just kidding.
Maybe I was actually I don't know. Um,
so anyway, so, so imagine Aladdin in the
cave of wonders and the genie is flying
around and seeing all the treasure.
Aladdin blindfolded inside the box is
able to only ask questions. The the the
genie comes back and says, "I saw these
mountains and these valleys and I saw
these beautiful treasure and I saw this
data set and that data set, etc. But
here's the answer." And if you don't
like the answer with a chat only
interface, you're stuck. There's nothing
you can do about it. You can just say,
"Well, try again." That's it. You can't
just say, "Oh, wait a minute. I have a
new insight here which is unfortunately
making humans dumber because you can't
check the AI anymore. So I want to go
and um show you this cartoon from the
80s here of
um Dilbert very um you know ahead of its
time where Zimbu the monkey has the
monkey has designed three commercial
products this week. We better find out
his secret. He's using his tail. He has
a natural advantage. I feel the jaws of
evolution on my throat. Good gravy. Did
you see him cut and paste? Your big
mistake evolution wise was inventing
computers that are easier to use if you
have a tail. In an ironic twist in the
Darwinian saga, you've guaranteed the
extinction of your own species, says the
monkey as he's continuing to to code
with his tail. Okay. So, so why am I
showing you this? Because we made that
mistake. We constructed that world. We
constructed the world where we are
blindfolded and we don't have access to
the data. And again, what I want to do
is create a cgraphy for data. a a
landscape of chemistry, a landscape of
proteins, a landscape of patients, and
be able to navigate in that landscape,
be able to understand the slopes and the
land masses and the anchor points and
the highway names and the street names
and what it means to go up this gradient
versus that gradient and so on so forth.
That's what humans are best at. We
evolved eyesight for millions of years
to be able to understand landscapes, to
understand topography, to to understand
all of these things. And language is
only like 70,000 years old. Language is
very new by comparison. So what I want
to do is transition where the AI is
providing us landscapes of information.
Imagine every patent, every memo, every
email, every person in your corporation,
every project, every love letter, every
poem sitting somewhere in this latent
landscape of all of knowledge and being
able to directly navigate on it. Imagine
you have to browse through three million
patents or three million drugs or three
million articles from the New York
Times.
instead of first putting them into
buckets and then saying, "Hey, what's in
the bucket and how many articles in
every bucket?" Imagine being able to
actually fly through the data. So, we're
basically giving a lad in a magic carpet
and you're now able to fly through three
million articles from the New York
Times. These are not buckets. This is a
ctography. It's a map. And it allows you
to now label these points according to
the enrichment of the topics that are
represented in every one of these
places. And you can now ask questions
directly. You can basically use a lasso
tool to say, "Hey, what's happening
here? Hey, if I go from here to there,
what is happening?" So, we've
constructed this tool that we call
mantis. Mantis is not the animal. Mantis
actually the animal is is named after
the it's called preying mantis, right?
And and and the reason why it's called
mantis is because in Greek the word
mantis is the seer, the one who sees
beyond, the one who can see directly
embedding landscapes. Okay? So we have
basically constructed Mantis for
navigating directly this embedding
landscapes. This is an an a landscape of
20,000 human genes and you can basically
go into it and ask questions. You have
cluster, you have the lasso tool, you
have neighborhoods, you have this
cognitive map, you have codes that that
you write. For some questions, the AI
will answer directly. For other
questions, it will say, "Well, let me
write a program for you and I'll run the
program and find out the answer." And
then you'll see the answers visually.
You have these ontologies coming from
scratch. You have the ability to search
and we've constructed these
landscapes by um through all kinds of
ways. So in this particular way, we're
basically looking at 20,000 genes from a
knowledge graph that is able to um take
care of understanding the relationship
between genes and diseases and
phenotypes and drugs and cellular
components and pathways and so on so
forth. And every one of these nodes
starts out with its own meaning. The
disease has a meaning, has a projection
in the late embedding landscape. The
gene has an initial meaning based on its
description, its language. But then the
connections between them are spreading
activation. They're message passing
information between them leading to a
revised representation where every one
of these genes and notice you might
realize the picture is exactly the same.
So I'm able to go and search for example
for uh lipids and then I'm able to find
every molecule that is associated with
lipids and you know I can uh you know
then ask to the AI um what are the major
diseases uh that these genes are
implicated
in and I'm passing it the context for
example I can just say um let's see
lipids and then the AI I is able to now
go and answer directly in that landscape
and I can of course navigate this
landscape and you know sort of go and
you know create additional
uh I mentioned the lasso tool earlier.
So here I'm creating an additional bag
and for every bag notice here it says
mitochondrial genes and metabolic
functions. Why is it saying that?
Because this is not your grandmother's
AI tool. This is like modern AI. It's
basically using, you know, talk to your
grandmother. You she'll be very excited.
Um, so, so as soon as I select
something, it tells me what it is.
So, the way that I describe data science
is imagine my three-year-old sitting on
the carpet and then sorting little
flashcards of, you know, squares
together or all of the yellow triangles
together and so on so forth. That's data
science. Data science should be that
easy. only dramatically augmented where
the kid can say okay great summarize all
of these books and you know like give me
the cross cutting concepts across all of
those books and that's what we have
constructed so we are now able to go and
directly navigate these latent embedding
landscapes and we're not able to do that
just with text we're able to do that
with images with DNA sequences with
chemistry with protein structures with
patient records with cells with
knowledge graphs with scientific papers
with with free text and with multimodel
representations. That's the major thing
that has happened in AI in the last 12
years. So if somebody says what happened
the last 12 years in AI, you tell them
latent spaces. It's the Z vector. It's
not just the data and the labels. It's
those latent representations. And what
Mantis does is that it takes these
latent representations and it makes them
accessible so that you can trust your
AI. You can say, "Hey, how are you
thinking of this gene?" And the answer
is, "Oh, well that gene sits there in
the context of those other genes." and
so on so forth. Okay, so we can do this
with cellular and transcriptional
landscapes. We can do this with
chemistry. We can basically build these
multimodal representations. We can do
this with every patent and every grant
and every paper that has been published
by MIT. So we can basically build these
multimodel
representations and start mapping
multiple cryptographies at once. If you
notice at the top left here, I have
connected the patents and the papers.
And because we want to have fun, I've
connected the cognitive landscape to the
physical landscape of where at MIT those
inventions were made. And I can do the
same thing over time and basically see
how knowledge changes over time. I can
do things with quantitative data across
100,000 loans. Or I can take every
startup in AI and medicine and then
start seeing what are the capabilities
that they have and how do they compare
to each other or take prerequisites
between every class at MIT regardless of
what department it's in and and I can
take my own people and see how is a lua
and how's Benjamin project progressing
over time in their thinking in their
code commits. So we have constructed
these tools for auto ingestion, for
summarization, for clustering, for
search, for ontologies, for
collaboration. We have these quick
sheets that allow you to look at the t
the tabular view or the embedding view
of every region in this landscape. When
you search, you see the results
organized not in a single list, but
instead organized by topic. So
basically, when I search for lipids, you
can see every single gene, but all of
the different processes that they're
involved in. We have these flash cards.
We have these agents living together. We
have u these macros that you're able to
say okay watch me to the AI and you know
it can follow you. It can learn from you
and so on so forth. So um that's what we
have and we are now able to sort of
study the latent embeddings of proteins
and of chemistry and of images and so on
so forth and that allows us to now
understand the chemical landscape at
unprecedented resolution. map it to the
protein landscape and use all of that to
basically bring humans back in the loop
to basically be able to discover
alongside the AI. This is now looking at
patients and from the mimic data set and
sort of how they relate to each other
and you can see the different types of
phenotypes. You can ingest any type of
information from your entire company.
You can basically do this crosscutting
search. You can, you know, study
categories and trajectories and
partitions and iterate over them. You
have all of these quantitative tools for
quant for for analysis across uh you
know many different uh data types and
and tools and most excitingly you have
now these multi-talented AI agents. Some
agents are able to write code and
execute it are other agents are able to
sort of reason about drug discovery and
other agents are able to sort of take
you all the way through the entire
discovery process. So we have also
integrated this with every tool you can
imagine. For example, you have this
Chrome extension that when you search in
Google, instead of just getting a list
of results, you can basically directly
see the latent representations of all of
your answers, you know, directly in a
Mantis um landscape. We're able to now
look at any article, for example, the
article in AI in Wikipedia, and now map
it into all of the concepts that are
being asked. And you can now do that
across all of the the documents in in in
your corporation. You can do that in
sales. You can do that in every single
aspect. And this is really peing inside
the brain of the machine. But it's also
peing inside of the brain of the human
because those latent embeddings that the
machine constructs are in fact the same
latent embedded that we construct
because the machines were trained
through self-supervision in the same way
that the humans were trained. So we can
now start peeking inside the brains of
the humans. So that's the road ahead. In
my view, the road ahead is being able to
construct these embeddings, these latent
representation across all of these
different data modalities and to use AI
as a Google maps that allows you to have
these extraordinarily capable agents,
but have full traceability where every
answer can be traced to individual lines
of evidence where we have these
extraordinary power and we're able to
navigate through the data landscapes.
Was excited about that? Good. Awesome.
Good. I'll stop there. Thank you so
much.
We have time for one question. By the
way, I know I know why you offer
chocolates to your guests when they come
to visit your lab. All the calories you
can get, all those Nobel prizes. The
brain spends a lot of energy, so you
should not feel bad about chocolate when
you're listening to lectures.
Quick question for anybody. I know
that's a lot. Okay, we have time for
one. How do you How do you get companies
to actually give you the data? What
you're doing is amazing. So, so but like
actually you know because that's a
fantastic question. That's a fantastic
question. Any tricks? So, so, so, so we
have constructed this in a completely
modular way. There's a front end,
there's a back end, there's a compute
farm and there's a broker where you can
register different compute farms. You
can basically project to the front and
the back end only the stuff that is
sharable. So, you can basically say
okay, I can compute in the compute farm
the later embedding representations and
then project them forward. You can also
have the entire thing living in one box
at your company. So we what we have a
partner right now in healthcare where
the data is not allowed to leave their
premises. So we have taken mantis and we
have installed it on their premises and
of course with AI you might be like oh
well what if I ask openAI something or
cloud something else will that leak? And
for this we have actually
implemented several tools locally. So
for example, DeepSeek and VLM that
allows you to now construct whatever you
would like completely locally within the
farm. So basically uh you can install
Mantis have completely private data and
nothing ever come out of the box except
for the people using it. Comput
you don't need that much compute power.
It's it's it's you know the training of
the model is very hard but once the
models are trained you can deploy them
very cheaply.
I'll take one more question while we're
switching. No, I think we're just sorry.
Thank you. Thank you so much.