so I'm currently in um I'm in Houston
Texas for a conference called drilling
for hydrogen and I'll talk a little bit
about uh why that is and what's exciting
about it um before then Paris from a CEO
actually founder Eden um I did my PhD in
the MIT hulie joint program uh course 12
just graduated last year and uh started
this company actually while also a PhD
student and what we're developing is
technology to unlock um self-surface
resources you have heat underground you
have natural deposits of page
underground people didn't actually know
that um you have minerals on the ground
you have all the gas on the ground you
have the ability potentially um and CO2
underground but all of these things
require a rock fracturing technology to
allow you to access the subsurface um
the traditional way of fracturing walks
is with a technology that a lot of
people are familiar with called
hydraulic fracturing you inject very
high pressure water into the subsurface
um this water is used to create tinell
stresses in the Rock but has
environmental issues from um induced
sity to uh contaminating your your
groundwater so now residents around
hydraulic fracturing operations you know
don't have clean drinking water um
because of this a lot of uh States and a
lot of countries have actually banned
hydraulic fracturing um so what we're
developing and our technology is a new
fracture mechanism instead of using high
pressure water we're using electric
hosis and I've been studying this
mechanism for the past four years um you
get very similar phenomena of creating
fractures in the Rock if you get high
enough voltage into the Rock um but the
benefits are you can reduce or eliminate
the generation of earthquakes that
happen due to lubricating Eves when you
inject fluids and you can mitigate the
groundwater contamination issues you
might have because you're not exchanging
water um so the way our technology works
is that we put electrodes into well bars
deep on the ground um we apply uh
voltages very high think hundreds of
thousands millions of volts into the
rock until you start to generate thermal
stresses in the Rock and The Rock begins
to fill um this technology has
applications across pretty much any Rock
and any Reservoir that you want to go to
from geothermal geologic hydren from and
carbon storage uh you need to have
fractures in the subsurface uh we've
receiv received multiple Awards by the
US Department of energy for essentially
all of these markets um because the
technology could be that powerful when
unlocking these natural
resources so where we are in our
development you know this isn't just a
theory we're not just drawing cartoons
of electricity and and and hoping that
we can have mechanisms happen we've
actually done it so last year we we took
the team you can see these are two of
our Engineers we worked with the oil and
gas company and we deploy our technology
and we put these electrodes that we
manufactured designed ourselves deep
into the well uh we turned on um the
electricity um and then we modulated how
much energy was going into the Rock uh
we did this over the course of two weeks
and we saw a significant increase in
production from this Reservoir um the
the well was initially producing 20
barrels of oil per day uh we went there
we did our stimulation job and then we
left measured uh production again and
production increased uh to over 100
barrels of oil coming out per day
um so the the the operator here uh they
paid for the pilot operation and they
made money off of this pilot um what was
really unique about the the pl of the
technology was that we did this we
increased production using uh zero
gallons of water we did not inject a
single drop of water into the subsurface
while we were stimulating this Reservoir
so we were very excited about um the
potential for the technology has been
proven in oil and gas res now we're
looking at one the technology in
different geological ours so what we
have coming up are additional projects
uh with the um sponsored by the doe you
are technology for geothermal
applications and granite in the US we
have customers in the Middle East North
Africa you are adop our technology um we
have uh we signed our company actually
signed the world's first mou uh for
geological production um and we we
signed this with the Omani government
last year and we're looking at doing
that project
with them we drill Wells we use our
technology to fracture the reservoir um
and then we show the increase of
hydrogen production coming out um
sometime later next year we also have
multiple contracts with mining companies
um who need to have their their their
mining fracture in order for them to uh
decrease the amount of energy uh
required to then grind out the the
minerals from these rocks so we have a a
lot of really unique use cases all
related to the energy transition for the
technology so what we're looking for are
people who own Wells um if if you own
Wells or you have access to um or with
networks of people within mining G hogen
geothermal Caron storage or traditional
oil and gas uh these are all markets
that our technology um can play in so
thanks thank you
Paris um let me start with a question
here um you talked a little bit about it
but where have you seen more traction if
you could expand a little on
that so the easiest thing for us to do
is deploy an oil and gas well um just
because the market is so big uh that
that's the biggest Market but we
actually received the most traction um
in the mining industry there have been a
lot of innovation and mining companies
who have these groups that are actively
looking to sponsor startups um to help
them uh increase their mineral yield
because their ores are degrading um and
they have a really key Ro of play the
anyg transition to provide critical
minerals for solar wind and other kind
of uh applications so a lot of the
traction recently has
been okay thank you and um what is the
energy requirement to create fractures
in a lateral 3
kilometer that's a great question uh in
our Pilot We consumed uh less than 100
megawatts of
energy um so know at $100 per megawatt
you know talking 10,000 record of
electricity um back
soon by thank you thanks