you should be able to answer a question
that I love to ask young students when I
go out and talk in schools and that is
how far away is space. There is an
official definition of where space
begins that's recognized by the
International Aeronautical Federation.
That's 100 kilometers the famous
funarman line about 62 miles and when
you go above this altitude you're
officially entitled to your astronaut
wings on the scale of our globe that is
about 1 and 12 cm. That's how high you
have to go to become an astronaut. I
hope you understand, however, that there
really is no abrupt boundary between the
atmosphere and outer space. The air just
gets thinner and thinner as you go
farther away from the Earth's surface.
So, when you really think about it,
space isn't very far away. It's closer
than New York City is to Boston or
London is to Paris.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.