Thank you everybody for being here. Um
we have an announcement about the MPG
retreat which is in February. Um we're
seeking volunteers to join the
scientific and social planning
committee. So please take a picture with
your phone or um get that QR code to
sign up. Um another announcement um next
week was meeting free week. So we don't
have primer but the week after that we
will have a primer from Pamela Robertson
from the broad clinical labs talking
about clinical genomic resources um but
today we have um two speakers from the
lab lab um and I'm sorry Sulki Kwan is a
research scientist one not a post-doal
associate so sorry about that um but um
let's see um I had these okay
Okay. So, Silki is a research scientist
in computational biology with a focus on
protein biioiniratics and variant
interpretation. Her research focuses on
understanding how genetic variation
alters protein structure and function
using computational models to uncover
mechanisms of disease. And then we have
Dr. Yu Chan who is a postoc. He is
research focuses on developing pipelines
to interpret structure function
relationships and base editor tiling
screen data. He integrates AI, bioysics
and structural biology to interpret
variant effects and guide protein
engineering. So um great we'll turn it
over to you guys.
>> Yeah good morning everyone. Um um it's a
pleasure to present our genomics to
portal in the MPG um session.
GTP proteins portal is a discovery
portal uh designed to help researchers
to link the genetic screening outputs to
protein sequence and structures. Our
team is in the bioinformatics and
machine learning group under the letters
to cure accelerator at the broad
institute.
Before I dive into the portal, I'd like
to acknowledge that this was a truly
team effort. Um and I'd like to thank
many our collaborators and funders who
made this uh entire project possible and
valuable and thanks to our scientific
illustrators as well to create a
beautiful um visuals for the portal and
this work is published in uh 2024. So if
anyone is interested in more please uh
check uh please feel free to check out
the papers as well.
Um you know Mr. portal started um on a
fundamental questions that how we can
connect um genetic variations all the
way to the protein structures. So let's
say a geneticist identify the genomic
variance on the genomic coordinate um it
it points out the mRNA sequence change
in a specific transcript and then it
translate into the amino acid change and
um ultimately impact the protein
structures on the 3D space. So
understanding this entire flow of the
information is uh crucial to understand
this bio uh to understand the disease
mechanism and thereby build biological
hypothesis and therapeutic strategies.
So understanding how this protein coding
varants affect protein function is
crucial uh for translating um genetic
genomics discovery into the clinical
insights as well. And here's an example
of the DXCX gene which encodes RNA
helicase and researchers have identified
five denovo variants from the patient
fiveense variants from patient and when
they mapped the variants onto the
protein 3D structure you can see that
they are um clustered on a certain
regions of the protein which turns out
to be really important functional motive
of the protein which is um the RNA
binding motive. So this immediately
suggests that um this mapping um reveals
the mechanisms and suggests the
mechanism that this disrupting this RNA
binding ability would uh drive the
pathology of the disease. And this is
not only case study. We have many more
genes where we see a disease mutations
cluster together and impact uh specific
protein functions. Your modulin kidney
disease mutations are clustered in the
end terminal part of the protein and mor
2 mutation um is and on the protein
protein binding interfaces and more
interestingly in case of the GABA
receptor you can see the mutations
clustered in different regions of the
protein actually display a a different
severity of the phenotypes as well.
So when you actually start looking at
the data um and the data landscape these
days you'll notice there's an incredible
amount of datas available. First u
genetic variation thanks to the high
throughput sequencing technologies. Now
we can identify um clinically relevant
variants and they are all deposited in
the clean bar databases and we have a
huge number of um human population data
population variation deposited on the
NOMA databases and interestingly um if
you look at the clinical significance
identified um as a function of time you
can see the number of variance of
uncertain significance um is growing
really fast compared to other variants
of of turns out u other variants um of
pathogenic or benign.
So that highlights uh the need for the
better uh variant interpretation tools.
Second structural biology. We now have
over 200 million experimentally resolved
structure in the protein data bank and
alphafold is um creating millions of
proteins data. So that suggest we now
have an unprecedented coverage of the
protein structure for the human
proteome.
And lastly, functional genomics such as
deep mutational scanning experiment is
now testing like hundreds of thousands
of variant at the same time creating a
rich set of functional datas as well. So
each of these uh field is extremely
valuable on its own but the real power
can come from when we actually integrate
this data. So our central questions was
how we can usefully integrate this data
and this is what exactly the genomics
genomics to pertise portal is aiming
for.
So this our genomics port uh proteins
portal combined multiple databases and
provide this holistic um identifier
mapping. So if you query a gene you can
see the connections uh of this ensemble
transcript and refi uh to the uniro
protein uh isopform identifiers and to
the structures as well. So if you uh and
then we map a variant on those
transcript u seamlessly all the way to
the proteins 3D structures along with
other protein features that we
integrated as well.
So currently uh the portal integrates
the genome genetic variation from clean
bargmd which are disease uh related ones
and also human population um varants
from nomads. So um altogether we
currently aggregating more than 49
million genetic variations for the human
for the entire human proteium um not
only including uh single nucleotide
variants like miss nonsense synonymous
we also have a non SMV mutations as well
and we also provide the database
specific filters to make this
interpretation
uh intuitive so you can actually see uh
varants by their um molecular phenot
types and plus you can see the nomad
variant by LIO frequency or account and
for clinical uh clean bar variant you
can filter them um by the clinical
significance so you can see like I'm
interested in pathogenic variant I want
to see the benign variant so you can
like opt in and out from the portal
interface
um one of key strengths of the portal is
that we have like the highest structural
coverage. So, um the alpha fold uh
protein structure prediction covers the
structure of more than um 12,000
proteins
where there's no experimental structures
available at all. So if you get look at
the chart we can able we are able to map
more than 70% of the nomad variant 50%
40% of the clean varnage GMD variant
where there was no structures available
then um we can retrieve them um by
incorporating the alpha databases. So
all together in total we were able to
over um we were able to map over 90% of
the variant on the entire human
canonicalizer forms um successfully on
the protein structures.
So now we have a genetic vari um covered
and what uh next step is to layer them
on the protein feature databases. So we
collect many different protein features
from different databases and we provide
um them uh as a category of six
different protein features. So I'll just
briefly introduce what's what that
means. So physical chemical properties
about like the side chain chemistry of
the amino acid like such as polarity
hydrophobicity
and we also have a full set of premputed
structural features from alpha fold and
PDB. So you can see the secondary
structure annotations um solvent
accessibility and um importing the
confidence of alpha score and also um
the precomputed um potential binding
sites on the protein surfaces as well
from the app pockets
and also from the structure we um
premputee the protein interactions
within the protein or between the
protein which is this four different
types of chemical bone that you can
identify within the structure
and we also bringing in uh the rich set
of uniro sequence annotations and they
mainly focus on like the active side
binding side with important functional
sides and domain annotations regions
motive. So you can um pull this uniro
annotations on the sequence viewer all
together with other features as well.
And we bringing in the post transl post
post translation of modifications from
the phosphocosite plus databases as
well. And lastly we um work with the
mave db which is a public repository for
data set um from this multiplex essay of
the variant effects. So if you if the
protein has um a multave data published
in the literature they catalog them and
from the G2P portal we visualize them as
a heat map and it's currently available
in about 500 proteins.
So I'll u we have a two different module
from the genomics to proteins portal.
First one is a resource module where you
can uh search your gene or protein by
their um gene symbol or uniro ID so that
you can access the entire um resources
that we uh put together in the portal.
And the second module is the interactive
module where you can actually upload
your data, your mutation, your
annotation and work with the um known
protein structures or even you can
upload your structure um to
interactively work with the data.
So I'll briefly uh I'll just walk you
through to the resource module
to the portal. So and the research
module as I described you can search by
gene. So I just search the gene and
it'll take you to the landing page. So
from the landing page you can see the
the generic information about the gene
and protein. So it has a cross reference
to external links to gene card hgnc and
panther. And if there is a known um gene
disease relationship established by JCC
you can see that and you can visit them
as well. and the uniro link is provided
and it provides the canonical protein
isopform identifier. So if you go down
we have five tabs. The first tab is uh
for the our sequence viewer. So this is
the ma one of the main feature of the
portal. So then you can bring in um and
filter in and out many different um
protein features on the track. So you
can click whatever uh protein feature
that you are interested in and you can
always zoom in and out viewer so that
you can click your um regid of interest
and this is by default provided for the
canonical protein isoform. But if your
interest, your protein of interest is
non-cononical protein isopform such as
this -2 protein, you can click it and
then we align it then for you on the
sequence viewer. And you can see there's
a gap um of this in the non-anical
protein isopform. But you can also
translate this full set of um protein
feature annotated here to the
non-cononical isoforms as well. And you
can always screenshot um click by
clicking this to download this high
resolution images of the sequence viewer
that you um customized. And you can also
download the annotation as a CSV file so
that you can make a you can bring in a
table and analyze um from your own
pipeline
and also you can just see the tables
here on the website. So click the view
table you can just see like full set of
features. um aligned by the protein
residue residue ID
and I'll visit this fourth tab which
shows the table of our um identifier
mapping from gene to transcript to the
protein isoform. So you can see what is
the canonical iso form for this gene um
annotated uh with asteric and you can
see what's the canonical ensemble
transcript here and you can see also for
the refy you can see what's the main
select transcript uh where many of the
clinical variants are annotated on and
go to the uh additional resource um you
can see the um external link to other
databases is about this gene such as US
UCSC Campbell drug bank and the disease
annotation database like om morphanet
and if when there is a mave data
available so I'm bringing in a case
study gene where the mave data is
available if you click the additional
resource tab you can see the preview of
this mave data um as a heat map and you
can always select um the data set
relevant
And it also direct you to this um
reference databases of the MA. So then
you can look at more detailed data and
download it.
And let's go to this uh let's see the
variance now on this sequence viewer
here. So I'll
go to the another case study genes which
is a tozel kynise 2. So if you click
this variant to protein sequence tab,
you can still see this um same sequence
viewer that you have looked at this
protein sequence annotation tab but in
this tab you can bring in the variant
data. So you can uh you need to select
the u transcript here for the mapping
and then now you can see there's a nomad
variance um categorized by their
molecular letter consequences and LIO
counts and LIO frequencies. So you can
click um I'll just show you the
multitune nomad missence variant here
and um sometimes you your um transcript
[clears throat] where many of where all
of this clinical variants are annotated
is not always encoded the canonical
protein iso form. So in this case this
-2 protein is corresponding to the mason
transcript and now all of this uh
clinical data is annotated on this
transcript. So in that case uh to
address this we provide the um mapping
and aligning variant from the another
transcript. So if you click this button
you can select another transcript to be
aligned. So I'll click here to the main
select transcript
and then now you can see this clean bar
variants annotated on another um protein
which has a gap in the middle now
aligned to the canonical protein
isoform. So you can see those variants
now with the full set of protein feature
annotation um annotated on another
protein sequences.
And you can also view table here to see
Nomad variants and has informations and
also the clean bar variants as well.
Yeah, there's no record because we
selected the canonical prin.
And now we can map those onto the
protein structure. So if you go to the
third tab variant to protein structure,
we um list the list of the PDB entries
and alpha fold entry. So you can always
um sort them by the method and
resolution or residue count. So if you
are not sure which structure to pick um
I suggest you to pick the most covered
uh PTB structures but we also have a
alpha structure which provide the full
length um structure of the protein as
well. So I'll um go with um the alpha
structure. You can click any any rows
that you want
and you we are now seeing the alpha
whole structures here in the structure
viewer along with the sequence viewer
and you can um see another structures um
of this protein and if you click it you
see how these are aligned on the protein
sequence space. So for example, this 7
L0
um PDB is only covering those uh regions
of the protein out of this entire um
length
and I'll just yeah drop it in and you
can if you click the nomad variant I'll
just click the misses nomad variants not
aligned one and I'll show you the
multitone and maybe many all of them is
very rare nomad variation
and Now we have an aligned misense
variant from the -ash2 protein and I'll
click the also the misense variant and
only a pathogenic um clean bar variant.
So if you click this uh track now you
can map them onto the protein structures
you can map it all together
um the clean bar variant together with
the nomad as well and you can also bring
in um other protein feature annotations
like if you click this amino acid
property color by the property um
surface area alpha hold competence
and the PPIs and active size so I'll
show you um this variance along with the
domain annotation. So from the uniro
it's annotated at the protein kynise
domain here. If you click it um you can
see there's a light blue area where this
domain annotation is located. And if you
you can make a full screen
you can see that this nomad multiden
variant is kind of spread all over the
protein structure. But this clean bar
pathogenic mutation is is uh mostly
populated in this protein kynise domain.
Um not surprisingly it's important
functional um domain of the protein.
If you disrupt this um region you'll
you'll get um a disease.
Yeah. And you can download this uh
entire visuals uh that you customize
through the pimole script. so that you
can work further um for your publication
quality figures or other analysis
available in the pimos as well.
Yeah.
So this was a resource module and we
have uh introduced another module which
is interactive module and I'll hand it
over to you John uh to present um and
walk through the interactive module.
So from here I'm going to introduce
interactive model of genomics 2 protein
or shortly G2P portal but I'm going to
want to start with like asking
questions. How many people here have
experience of mapping your experimental
data on 3D structures?
No.
Right. So I didn't expect that but if
you have any experience it's not very
easy. I mean if you have a decent script
it's quite easy to just use it to map
your screen data or experiment value
onto the 3D structure but in short it's
quite tough it it's it could be very
errorrone uh process
I'm going to highlight two things on
this interactive module the first thing
is this interactive module of genomics
to protein portal is super easy to use
literally you can just copy from access
spreadsheet and paste it and then we can
visualize it on the protein structure.
The second part is I guess this just
browsing the available resource on this
DN uh protein is important but more
important application is mapping your
data and then actually see uh alongside
with the other features that the just
key introduce. So you can actually
analyze or interpret better in the like
uh var variants or other structural
feature. So that can help you to
understand your experimental data. So
I'm going to walk you through just one
by one. So the interactive module you
can click this on the right hand side
button and then you'll see the two subm
module here. Uh the first case the most
of first subm module is when you have a
gene or protein identifier like a uni
pro ID and you have your own
experimental value like Excel
spreadsheet then we can start with the
first module. So I'm going to get I'm
going to actually have a example DNMA
which is DNA method transferase uh gene.
So if you type it, it'll show you the
canonical unro ID here. So which looks
correct. So I'm going to proceed it.
Then it will show you the all the
available protein data bankm
3a structures but only for the human not
human nonhumans are not here proteins
are here.
Um I'm going to select those uh one
specific structure because the later uh
later part I'm going to introduce the
data which is uh mutational screening uh
or functional screening data and then I
want to see that the mutational data
with a homodimer of this DNF display
protein. So I'm going to select that PTB
has homod.
So if I click this PDB,
>> you can actually see uh make it bigger.
Yeah, it looks homodimer here.
And you can also check the coverage of
uh this DNMP 3A gene and their
corresponding PDB here. So it actually
cover half of the DNP3A protein. And you
can see that two chains are here.
And you can see the color corresponding
chain A and chain C.
But if the cover is not enough, I mean
if you're more interesting to see the
full coverage from alpha structure, then
you can just move on to the upper tab
and you can select the alpha structure
to map your data.
Right? So I'm going to just keep with
the homodimer.
Then we're going to have this uh
annotation view. So here what we're
going to do is putting the experimental
data.
So
let me open the Excel. So this is a data
for this mutational function uh scanning
data. I'm going to just copy whole
spreadsheet data and then I'm going to
paste into here
and then submit here. But if you're not
very familiar with this uh the form or
formatting things, you can actually
click here see the example how the
formatting should be followed by this
kind for we defined here. So it could be
uh just comma separated or tap separated
but you can have any kind of format uh
any kind of headers like this. I'm going
to show you more uh real case scenarios.
>> So if you submit your data then the
portal automatically process it and then
it'll show you this kind of uh screen.
Then in this step what you need to do is
check whether this data is correct or
not. So for example the first column has
to be always the residue index. It's
because genomics the protein portal
needs to uh has to uh need to map your
data with this column information to the
other genomics to protein resource data.
So this uh column has to be always
rescue index. Um but you can actually
have different column not just position
but something else.
All right. And then I'm going to explain
three things. So you can see that
buttons have a different uh labels here,
mutations and scores and features.
uh each data type has a different
representation. So for example, if I set
this human residue column with this
mutation data type which requires
specific formatting. So I'm going to
just quickly show you
what formatting this mutation column
requires is this first row.
So it was actually invented for uh
showing information with spear
representation in 3D viewer. We're going
to see in the next uh page. Um here I
actually follow this the last uh
formatting. So any letter single letter
uh here. So you can see that the second
column has one letter which is Y type
rescue letter.
And the second uh the third column is
score. If you put any values in this
score column and then define as a score
then you can color your protein with the
gradient or uh continuous gradient
column. So like a red to blue, white to
blue,
anything.
And the last type is a features. So
feature column accepts either value or
string or text.
So I'm going to show you one of the
example here.
So I already marked some residue of
interest and their uh location. Oh,
these residues are co-actor binding
site. So I actually type in there
already. And this is a residue in
homodimer interface.
The last column is another way we can
show something. uh so because the
feature column will color this protein
structure but if I have it as a mutation
then I can actually change the represent
representation with the sphere. So you
can just play with your columns with a
different data type to show in different
representation in 3D structure here. And
importantly if you have any uh typers or
something you can actually modify from
here
you can change it except the f uh except
this headers here. Okay. So once you
submit your annotations
and you can see that the structure
we selected
um here and then this is color by based
on the selection of events uh the last
sequence view I'm going to color this
one based on the score of this the score
screening the data that I fit in
you can see that the darker purple color
is representing higher the value of the
screening data
and because there are so many uh color
or screening data here and then I
actually marked very high scoring region
with mutation data type rotation. So you
can actually see that with the sphere as
well. So those are having spears have
very darker purple on the protein uh
cartoon as well.
So with this information we might be
able to interpret some important
biological
uh things but I'll further go with
adding the genomics to protein resource
features. So if you click this view
additional annotation that is way we can
add features from resource module. So
first I'm going to uh map clean variance
information. You can see there's no
information available because clean
variance informations are mapped onto
the second transcript here. So if you
click the second transcript then now
you'll be see that uh clean bar map on
the second. So I'm going to select miss
sense but only pathogenic variants.
So now we can see that 60 pathogenic
variants
on top of this uh the scores of our
experimental data. Some of them align
well, some of them not. So it actually
give us like some kind of information by
m how the mutations align with the
pathogenic cleanar mutations.
But I'm going to actually add few more
features such as potential small
molecule binding site which is from F
pocket prediction.
You can color the protein structure with
this F pocket. And you can see that
those greenish part is where the small
model can bind. And another important
thing could be here because I was I said
like I'm interesting to see the
homodimer context. You can see that
there are three features available which
represent the uh protein protein
interaction side which is coming from
analyzing all the DNFT3 PDB and finding
um protein protein interaction residues.
Um okay I colored them here. So this is
this mustard color is showing protein
protein interface residues or
interacting residues in the NMP3
protein.
And if you so I want to actually see
that whether this high scoring residues
are aligning
then you can see that oh okay these two
residues could be very important
mutations in terms of DNF3 function
because this is uh actually happening on
where the protein protein interaction
happen.
Okay. So
>> all right and
those are the feature we can edit on on
and then you can also change this color
by using this edit colors and select a
corresponding features you can change
the scores a color not blue purple but
different colors here.
Okay. Um
and as Seri mentioned
>> can I ask a question? Sorry to
interrupt. Um, I'm wondering about what
to do when you're mapping your mutations
on your favorite protein of interest,
but your mutations are not like
obviously segregating to a certain area.
Um, I know that's kind of an open-ended
question, but um, you know, what kind of
statistical tests could you run? Um,
like taking it in taking into account
the 3D structure. Um I mean some of the
things that you showed like the TLK2
it's like nice when it obviously all
goes to the kynise but usually they
don't. So how do you approach those
scenarios?
>> So I'm asking like how we map the
mutations of the protein.
>> Um no um what do you how do you
interpret
>> interpret the mutations
>> interpret the mutations on the structure
when the clinical what you think are
clinically pathogenic variants aren't
mapping obviously to a domain.
Um
>> yeah, we actually have many case many
case studies where we don't have a clear
clusters of course. Um so I'll probably
I was going to preview a little bit but
we are actually designing a like scoring
system for a variant where you we bring
in all these protein features and um
like see what are those features are
actually relevant to the pathogenicity
so that we can like provide like or help
to build a hypothesis. So okay this
variance is not clustered but it has
this this is features and it has a
certain like area in the protein 3D
structure so that it may have an impact
on like proteins functional side or it
can be from okay this is a disrupting
physical chemical property. So we are
actively working on this variant
interpretation tools and is about to um
incorporate it into the portal but if
you have any interest of your gene you
always uh you can feel free to reach out
to the group so that you can yeah
collaborate we always welcome
collaborations. Yeah
>> thank you but yeah we don't actually
give any uh scores here but you can
actually compare with those pathogenic
varants on top of your mutations.
Um okay where we yeah we can actually
export this annotations and then we can
actually analyze uh in the text or table
formats. Um here I want to actually show
you another thing. So the cool thing
from here is
we can actually go back to the structure
and then we can actually interpret this
one in the different context as well. um
let's say DNT3A actually metilate the
DNA right and then we can actually check
whether these mutations are close to the
DNA as well so what I want to try to
show you here is even if you go back to
this the all your steps and then click
on new PTB structure
it actually kept all the information
what I did and then actually you can
actually keep all the annotation as it
is but you can change the structure So
you can actually have another
interpretation by changing your
structure in this interactive module.
Um the last part here I want to show you
is a sharing function. So if you want to
keep this session active for next seven
days, you have to click this share
button and then you have to put your um
Gmail account and add it. Also, you can
actually share this one with your
collaborator by their putting your their
emails and create account create a link
and then you can just copy this link and
share it. So, if I paste in here,
then I can keep this session for next
seven days.
Okay, I think that's pretty much
everything from here. Do you have any
questions so far?
Any
questions?
Um, I have a Well, there's two
questions. Well, one is how do you deal
with or can you deal with inframe
deletions? So, or or Exxon skipping? Um,
we I work on a large autism cohort and
we're finding a lot of these types of
variants. Yeah, we we um in the uh
sequence viewer tab, you'll be able to
access the inframe um delions um and
frame shifts variants of but you can map
those position on the protein structure
but interpretation is that like since
that position your protein sequence is
going to be entirely changed. So you
might um have to aware of that this
interpretation into the onto the print
3D structure might not be that accurate
but you can um pinpoint where is the
mutation but like other functional
annotations and this PPIs and structural
feature might not be um biologically
relevant and it it should be really case
by case you need to look at like where
the sequences are going to change
>> by your yeah your non SMV sequence
mutation.
>> Um, another question on the channel here
is someone's asking about clinically um,
publication ready images. If you could
just kind of show that one more time
because I think that's of interest.
>> Oh
yes.
So,
so yeah, we can export this one here as
well. Um, there are a ton of way to
export the images here. Uh, I also
personally export this uh session. Um,
if you're very familiar with this more
star viewer. So, this is what's this is
called a more star viewer which RCSV
data bank also use it. So if you
actually save this session export it you
can keep this exact same uh view for
>> can I can I add to the please question.
So if you go back you can so folks can
also download the pimal script. So all
the mapping that is performed they can
download and open locally in pole
session and that is the best way to
generate a publication ready figure.
from the portal will be this structure
viewer and then you can look at the
screenshot over there on the screen
viewer that takes the screenshot of the
entire sequence viewer.
>> Gotcha.
>> So the sequence viewer and structure
viewer side by side and if you want to
deep dive then I what I recommend is to
download the pal section open it in the
primal end.
>> Cool. All right great thanks. Yeah. And
that primer section will have all these
uh features that sit out. So actually
have almost the same features.
>> Very good. Cool question.
>> So right now you have showed about
single protein and how mapping uh you
know variance to a single protein. Is
there any plan to get into protein
protein interaction and having interface
between these two proteins and mapping
those variants to it?
>> I actually put that
Yeah, you can bring in any PTB structure
if you have a complex uh protein
structure chain A and chain B and chain
is A is your interest of protein and
chain B is another one if you go can you
pull up a um PDP structure with other
chains
>> such as yeah
sure
Yeah, if you pull um if you load this um
heterdo like complex structure with DNA
and everything, you can see actually the
chain information here. So this chain K
and P is DN MT3A and chain N and S is
other protein. So you can map protein
and where see where those mutations are
located and um from this uh PPI features
this is the premputed ones that we
calculated from all available uh PTB
structures. So if you click it here like
interchain hydrogen bonds
and you zoom out and you can see the
hoverboard text here. So it says um two
annotation. I'm not sure if it's
working.
You can see the home of a texture
annotation which says K 299 and K 343 um
is interacting um and F303. So if even
if it's an between chains we annotate
them in this tab so that you can
download it actually later for the
analys for your analysis.
>> Great.
>> Uh so uh this is a amazing resource. Uh
so I saw that you have already mapped
all the nomad and clean bar variants
into this uh all the protein residual in
this portal but is it possible to map
say any arbitrary uh genomic variants uh
for example that's uh found in a new
data set and map and to the protein
structure here.
>> Yeah that's exactly what this
interaction
>> the uh mapping module does. So he
uploaded uh this uh base set in
screening data but um as long as you
have a right format which is HVSP like
formats or um the single amino acid u
letters uh you'll be able to map any
mutations. So if you go to here
just click any case studies any
structures
in this annotation tab you can just
arbitrarily say okay this is residue ID
column and this is your mutation and
like I don't know position 34 y 34k
something like this that will just yeah
take you to this mapping
>> from the simple
>> not too much about like like this uh h
as you're talking about genet genomic
coordinates.
>> Yeah. Is it possible to become a close
to say the GRCH38
and first do this mutation? What are the
recommendations?
>> Um in that case I I recommend for to use
to use the the web ensemble web tool so
that you can upload your genomic
coordinate and will give you the protein
consequences and we only support the
protein consequences at this point.
Yeah.
So yeah, this interactive module
supports program level mapping. Yeah.
>> Uh there's a question on Zoom. Um do the
annotations you map to the structure
include pro post-transational
modifications including recognition of
gly glycosol transferases ubiquinases
ubiquinases etc.
>> Yeah we have a we we are bringing postr
modification uh from the phosphoite plus
database. they uh uh collected um
experimentally validated and predicted
the possible site plus size. So as long
as the data is there uh in the database
you can bring to the portal and see in
the 3D space.
>> Cool.
I think we are running out of time so I
hand it over to Siki for the finishing.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So um we have another module
which you can actually feed your own
protein structures as well. We are
skipping this but feel free to watch
this tutorial video that we have. We
have a full playlist of YouTube tutorial
that you can follow about various
functionality of the pre- teams of the
portal. So go back to the slide. So I
know many of you work with the
confidential data and um worry about
like uploading your data to anywhere to
to address this. We care about the
security and confidentiality. So we bu
we built our infrastructure so that your
user uploaded data never leaves on the
uh label leaves the user's local device
and circle on the front end. So it means
it never shared or stored through the
backend server of the portal and your
interaction mapping module requires you
to the Google signin authentification.
So it added another layer of security
that only verified user can um upload
and access the interactive mapping
module.
So for uh developers and anyone's
interested in um incorporating this
genomics portal to their um own
pipeline, we provide uh the swagger API
interface where you carry your gene and
then get some of the features from the
portal and we have also Python client
library. So you can see this API tab for
more information
and another thing I want to mention is
that we maintain and update the portal
in a regular basis. So some of data um
which is really timesensitive we
dynamically load them such as the list
of PDB available. So as soon as it's
deposited in the PDB or alpha you'll be
able to access the structure and of some
of the premputed data like structural
data or the PPI data uh we update have
we have a major by annual update and um
for the clean bar variant given that
it's a rapid speed of the data
submission we update the clean bar uh
variants on a monthly basis. So if you
go to the release log tab on to the
portal, you can see all of this version
information at a particular point and
all of this log that we updated so far.
Um today we have more than uh 10,000
users um and researchers around the
world and we this uh platform is
continues to grow. We are we continue to
expand our functionality to different
directions and I just want to highlight
a couple of direction that we are
actively working on. First is as um the
question that we are developing the
variant scoring system from the preins
3D structure to interpret this variant
um by their protein level features and
like which feature actually attribute
that I'll u have another slide for this
to briefly introduce it and we are also
thinking um working on this agent system
that you can curry um from this large
language models uh you know natural
language basis and We have also working
on this integration of the on demand
tool so that you can actually run a
couple of tools on the portal and
analyze your datas as well.
So just quickly introduce this scoring
system um we have a we had a question
like so which protein features are
actually um enriched within the
pathogenic varian affect the pathogen
pathogenicity.
So I it's there's no time to explain it
in detail but the main idea is that we
created a data set of the pathogenic and
proximity 9 and with the uh feature
enrichment analysis and created these
types of incilico scoring systems so
that you can u curry a mutations for
example um I search the par gamma r 194
um y w mutation it will give you a score
and it'll give you the interpretation
Based on the score, this is likely to be
pathogenic with a certain um confidence
and by the nature of the design of the
score we can actually decompose the
score into different direction of of the
protein feature. So you can actually
measure
where is the score coming from is coming
from biochemical property change or it's
coming from the structural stability um
aspect or functional side domains. So we
hope uh this score to provide and help
to build a hypothesis um and it should
be uh really gene by gene approach where
you have an expert knowledge and you
have a score then you will be able to
create a hypothesis.
So um this is all about platform. You
can visit our website and go to the
about page to read all the documents
here and please follow our uh the
twitterers and you can directly contact
our through the email and as I briefly
mentioned we have a YouTube tutorials
ready so you can always [clears throat]
visit them and we always welcome users
feedback so please use the feedback form
here from the portal um and if you have
a case study we very much welcome to
collaborate and provide a hands-on
workshop that we actually did uh
multiple times for those groups as well
and more tutorial will be coming. So
please stay tuned uh on our YouTube and
thank you all for listening and I happy
to take any questions.
>> Okay. Um any other questions from the
crowd?
Okay. Thanks so much for your talk. We
really appreciate it.
Um and then the seminars next door.
Thank you.