LHF: Hi everyone, and welcome back to Today I
Learned: Climate, the climate change podcast
from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
I'm Laur Hesse Fisher, and I can't believe that
this is going to be the last time that I ever
utter those words. Yes, I am leaving the show.
Very sad to do that. It has been a wonderful,
remarkable experience being here and creating
the show with my wonderful team. And at the same
time, I'm really excited to share what is coming
up next for TILclimate, because it certainly is
not going away. So in this episode, what we're
going to do is we're going to talk a little bit
about the secret sauce of how we make the show
and what makes it special. We're going to talk a
little bit about some new things that are going
to change with the upcoming season. But first, it
is my distinct pleasure and honor to introduce to
you Madison Goldberg. Madison is going to be the
new host of Today I Learned: Climate. Madison,
welcome to the show.
MG: Thank you. It's such an
honor to be here. I'm really excited.
LHF: So, we're going to get a huge opportunity to get to
know you and your background. You are no stranger
to science communication. You have a degree
in earth and planetary sciences from our dear
friends down the road, as well as in journalism.
And you have worked on the Scientific American
podcast and on Living on Earth, on that show. And
also you've done deep reporting on environmental
issues in Pennsylvania. So you have so much
to bring to this conversation. Let's start
off. I want to ask you, what sparked your fire
for science communication?
MG: Yeah. You know,
I had what I think is not an uncommon path into
science communication, where I started in science.
You know, I studied, in undergrad I studied
earth and planetary sciences, as you mentioned,
and I adored it. I worked with amazing people.
I did, you know, earth science research, and it
was awesome. But I realized that I think, like,
the parts of it when I was just really fired up
and in my element were were not necessarily, you
know, in the lab per se, but when I was, you know,
at a big earth science conference, in the giant
poster halls where everyone has their posters out,
and going around and learning from people,
learning about their research. I also have, like,
this very vivid memory of, before one of those
conferences, I had made my big poster and it was
spread out on the table and my grandparents were
visiting. And I distinctly remember the joy that
came from explaining to them what I was doing and,
like, them at least pretending to be interested.
And that was fantastic. And you know, from there
it was just, I was really lucky to have folks
who encouraged me to keep exploring it, both in
science and in writing and journalism.
LHF: So, I love that. And you chose audio as a way to
express and kind of do your science communication.
What do you love about the medium of audio?
MG: Yeah. You know, at the risk
of sounding obvious, you
hear people in their voices, and I think that's
really special. You know, on TILclimate, you hear
from scientists in their own voices. I think you
can really hear when someone gets animated, and
especially like, now that we have so many people
who are deploying climate solutions in the field
and their communities, getting to talk to them
I think is really, really special, and I think
it makes it tangible, hopefully, for listeners
in a special way.
LHF: That is absolutely why we
prioritized having a—this is a podcast, because
we wanted people to feel a closer connection to
the science. I mean you, read about it, you see
reports, you see statistics and graphs. It feels
very distant and kind of abstract, and so this is
a way to hear the stories and the interests and
the words specifically from scientists and kind
of, I don't know, personify them a little bit more
than you get to do in a more traditional way that
science is communicated and climate change science
is communicated these days.
MG: Yeah, absolutely.
I think that personality aspect is crucial, and
I'd love to hear a bit about how how you've gone
about that, how you thought about how to cultivate
that personality of the show.
LHF: So, thank you.
So we built the show for people who were curious
about climate change already. Maybe they were new
to climate change because of a job, or maybe they
were confused by lots of different things that
they hear about on the news, and they just wanted
someone to provide a kind of signal through
the noise of what was going on, like, simple,
clear explanations. I feel like as the host, I get
to be curious on behalf of the audience, right? We
have the scientists that are there. I get the
honor to be able to ask them all my questions,
and then I have to figure out how to distill
that down to the most basic key things that
our audience needs to know. Like, let me give you
one example.
MG: Yeah, please.
LHF: So, one of our
first episodes was with Professor Kerry Emanuel,
and we were working on a show on hurricanes.
And what I learned is that the way that hurricanes
form in an ocean is actually really complicated.
And then we were wrestling with this, like, how do
we deal with this? What do we—and then we realized
the thing that we need to communicate here, it's
not all the mechanics of how a hurricane starts,
but the fact is that a warmer air means a
warmer ocean, a warmer ocean has more energy,
that basically creates more energy inside of
a hurricane. And the hurricane, like, absorbs
more of that energy, and that's why it's more
intense. We don't need to get more complicated
than that. So what we always try to do with all of
our shows is take the topic and kind of distill it
down to something that feels memorable and simple
and crisp for people to remember.
MG: Yeah. Yeah.
That actually reminds me—you know, you mentioned
that I was fortunate to do a fellowship in
Pennsylvania reporting on environmental issues.
One of my very first assignments was something
that this reminded me of. And, you know, we made
these very short radio spots sometimes that,
you know, you just have to be snappy. They have to be
within the window of time that you have. And so I was
supposed to make an explainer about climate models.
LHF: Oh boy.
MG: Yes, and under a minute.
LHF: Oh gosh.
MG: So it was—honestly, I'm
so glad that it was my first assignment, because
it was an incredible challenge. My editor and my
other colleagues there helped me so much. I think
it was this amazing exercise in forcing yourself
to think about, there's a million different
directions that I could go here. Climate models
are obviously an immensely complicated area. But
there are certain things that I think serve
people who are hearing it as they're driving,
and other things that probably aren't that useful
to them in that moment, that they can figure out
if they want to go and learn more.
LHF: So what I loved about what you said
is that you provided that
explainer as a springboard, right? So it's like,
okay, let's give people exactly what they need
to know to understand why it's relevant for me,
or why I could care about this, or should care
about this. Maybe they're satisfied with that. But
maybe actually it's a step towards a deeper dive,
with a basic level of understanding. And I think
that's a really valuable and important role of
science communication.
MG: Yeah, totally. And on this idea of,
like, making things memorable,
I think, you know, you kind of mentioned like,
okay, so how can we get to people and how can we
sort of find these ways of putting it that help
it stick? Like, I know that's something that you
guys have thought a lot about, and you've thought
about, you know, different metaphors you can use or
things like that. Like how do you think about that?
LHF: Yeah. So, one of my favorite metaphors
that was introduced on the show was our direct
air capture episode. So, this is the idea of,
okay, there's all this carbon dioxide in the air.
Can't we just suck it out, right? And like put it
somewhere, do something with it. So Professor
Niall MacDowell was our guest speaker, and he
introduced this metaphor of, like, imagine like
the molecules of oxygen and nitrogen and CO2 and
all the other stuff that's in the air, the gases
that are in the air, are marbles. And everything
that isn't CO2 is blue, and CO2 is red. And we're
talking about, CO2 is about 420 parts per million,
right? So we're talking about—so there are, if
there are a million blue marbles in the sky,
then 400 of them, about, are red. And if you're
trying to pull, like, sort through all of those
marbles and just pull out the red ones, well,
that's actually really hard to do. And it ends
up that it's really energy intensive to do
as well. And so just that visual of, like,
oh my gosh, okay, I can kind of get a sense of why
this is, why direct air capture is so expensive,
so energy intensive, so hard. I think that
visual really helps, and I've used that in
explaining direct air capture to other people as
well, and it's been pretty effective.
MG: Yeah, it's effective for me. I mean, that's awesome.
Putting a picture in people's heads, and these
sorts of metaphors, I think are really important
in the same way that, you know, audio demands
a lot of strategies of science communication
that—maybe different ones are needed elsewhere.
So part of what this stems from is that a lot
of people, when they're listening to a podcast,
they're doing something else. Like that's what I'm
doing. Like I'm, you know, driving or doing the
dishes or doing laundry.
LHF: Folding laundry.
MG: Yep. That's the classic. And so because of that,
and because, you know, I think it's just a
different thing to expect someone to rewind,
excuse me, as opposed to like, scrolling back up
and rereading something. It goes by fast. And it
can be easy to have, and very understandable to
have, like, half your brain on it and half of
your brain on something else. So I think these
structures, and I mean something like, "this is
what we're going to talk about today," or, "wait,
let's make sure we caught that," and repeating it,
or at the end being like, "this is where we
went on our journey." I think those things are
really important, and I think that's something
that on the show you've done a great job of,
and it's been great.
LHF: Well, I can't take credit
for that. That is Dave Lishansky,
our brilliant audio producer. He is a genius.
I know you've had a chance to work with him,
and everybody who's listening to this episode has
had the privilege of being able to listen to his
talent. He's just, he has a natural sense of how
people listen and, like, when people need mental
breaks, and how to—I mean, he always has said, and
I'm looking at him because we have a video of him
right over there over Zoom. And you've always
said, Dave, that podcasting is a visual medium,
and it is, because we have these imaginations,
and as we're hearing, we're imagining what we're
thinking and what we're hearing in our minds. And
of course it forms for different people, and we
have to carry people along like what you said.
So another part of bringing listeners along on
the story is a lot about trust, because one of the
benefits, of course, is we're from MIT, so we have
an incredible cadre of researchers and people that
we can pull from for the show that brings a sense
of credibility. But then also, we don't expect our
listeners to take what we say for granted. We come
with a lot of curiosity. We also try to come with
a lot of skepticism. And what I mean by that is,
a scientist is naturally skeptical. I mean, you
know, you're a scientist, right? And journalists
are also naturally skeptical. And so they're
trying to not take things at face value. So in
addition to explaining, kind of, what folks know
about, what scientists know about climate change,
we also try to communicate how they know what they
know. So one of my favorite episodes was "TIL about
planting trees." And the whole concept is like,
well, can't we just plant a whole lot of trees,
and like, if not, why not? And all of that. And
so we took at it like, okay, let's actually get
genuinely curious about that. And as part
of that episode, we looked at—oh my gosh,
we had to, talk about science communication.
First, we had to start with like, okay, well,
we have to explain how trees take up carbon
and then emit carbon, right? Like I'm looking
at Aaron Krol, our executive producer and writer
for the show. Where we just spent a long time. I
remember you and I spent a long time figuring that
out, and redoing the calculations, and oh my gosh,
it was a whole thing. Anyway, so we had to explain
that part, and then explain how it works, like,
inside of a tree. And then we realized, well,
we're not really talking about trees. We're
talking about forests, right? Because like, that's
the scale that we're talking about here. And so
when you want to measure the carbon dioxide uptake
and release in a forest, there are like, these
radio towers that can like, use sensors and like,
you know, measure the air flow, and there all
these calculations. So we're explaining how that
works. But as we're explaining how that works,
we're also demonstrating, like, okay, we know
these things, but we don't know them perfectly. So
it's like, we hope that, by explaining how things
happen, it also elucidates some of the challenges
that exist in trying to deal with climate change.
MG: Totally. And so we're talking a lot about sort
of, these ideas of how to communicate the science,
and the nitty-gritty of that stuff. But obviously,
you know, I know a big focus for you in creating
this show is also a focus on the solutions. And
I think, and I have a lot of empathy for this
feeling—I think it's very easy to feel doomed,
and to feel scared, and to feel overwhelmed by
the prospect of of climate change, and, you know,
is it too late to do anything? What do we even
do? Like, I think that's a totally understandable
feeling. And something that I've really
appreciated about the tone that you've created on
the show is, I tend to leave the episodes feeling
more motivated, you know, more like a sense of
efficacy, a sense of possibility. And I'd love to
hear, sort of, you know, you've been working on
this show for many years, how you sort of molded
that, how you thought about that.
LHF: Man, I'm so thankful and grateful that you get that
impression from listening to the show. It's
definitely something that we prioritize. I don't
feel doomed about climate change. And I've thought
a lot about why that is. And I think a lot of it
is because I do this work, and I am connected with
so very many people, smart, committed, authentic,
hardworking people, like thousands and thousands
and thousands, and if you look at the global
climate community, millions, who are working
strategically on this issue. So I don't feel
alone. And of course I'm concerned. I'm very
concerned. We need to take action. But I think
that feeling of, you said motivation, agency, and
being a part of something, shifts the way that you
interact with a problem, and that's part of what
we want to bring to this show. Because the fact
is, we have a lot of agency. There is a toolkit,
a toolbelt of solutions that need to be employed,
and there's a lot of work that needs to be done,
and there's a lot of work that can be done. And
so in every episode, we really try to focus on,
okay, where is the sense of agency? What are
the things that are holding back progress,
but then can actually be done to move things
forward? And I'm just thankful that we've been
able to figure out a way to do that.
MG: Yeah. So on this sense
of agency and efficacy that you've
tried to cultivate, you know, how do you go about
that? What does that look like in the show? What
has it looked like thus far?
LHF: Yes. The reason why I sighed
is because it's something that we
thought a lot about, and we've really wrestled
with this topic, because we know this is not a
"what I can do about climate change" show. And
at the same time, a lot of people are wondering,
what do I do about climate change? And we tackled
this in an episode. So the point that we try to
emphasize in the show is that climate change is a
systems problem, and one individual is inside of
a system. And so we need a systems change solution
to this problem. Okay, that sounds very technical.
It's very MIT, you know, what does that even
mean? It just means that these things are big
and complicated. So in that episode, we encouraged
people, instead of asking "what can I do," to ask,
"what can I influence?" What communities are they
a part of that they can shift something there?
Are there faith groups that have buildings and
infrastructure where they can shape things? Are
there nonprofit organizations that they're a part
of that maybe could do advocacy work? You know,
what are they—are they inside of a corporate
infrastructure or a legal infrastructure where
they could shift systems? Like, that's the kind
of work that really needs to happen in order to
deal with the systemic issue. So in all of our
episodes, we try to frame it through that lens.
Like, let me give you an example. We worked
on an episode recently, you were involved in
this episode, called "The Great Indoors," where
we talked about buildings. And so we could have
just focused on, okay, what are the steps that
everybody needs to do to kind of retrofit their
homes and have better energy efficiency and save
money and blah blah blah. We did talk about that,
but we didn't just talk about that, right? We also
talked about the larger issue of like, okay, you
can retrofit your own home, but how does a city, a
state, a country, retrofit an old building stock,
like existing building stock? And then what do we
need to do—oops—what do we need to do on setting
new building codes and new kinds of standards so
that new buildings that get built abide by, like,
certain kind of energy efficiency, da da da. So
you can't—we can't just stop at the individual
level. We really want people to be thinking of the
larger picture. And part of it is, we know that
there are all different people of all different
walks of life who are listening to this show. We
know that we have city planners and former mayors
and policy staffers and people who have, you know,
set procedural guidelines in their corporate
infrastructure. Like, we know that people are
listening to the show, and everybody has something
that they can influence. So we really try to frame
it so people can find themselves as best as we can
inside of that context.
MG: Yeah. Yeah, I'm really
glad you brought that up, because a concept that
has greatly resonated with me, as I've learned
more about climate communication, is one that—you
know, there's a scientist and climate communicator
who I really, really admire, Dr. Ayanna Elizabeth
Johnson, and she talks about this concept of a
climate action Venn diagram. So thinking about,
you know, what am I good at? What are the things
that need to be done? And what brings me joy?
She talks about finding the intersection of
those things. And I think that gets to this idea
of, what are things that I can do, based on the
networks, the communities, that I'm a part of.
And as she mentions, it's important that it brings
you joy, because that's something that you can
keep doing, you know, and hopefully will derive
satisfaction and fulfillment and purpose from.
That really stuck with me. And so when I heard
that episode that you mentioned, "TIL what I can
do," which focused on this sort of framework,
I really appreciated that, and I think going
forward in the show, I hope that that's something
that we can maintain.
LHF: Well, speaking of which,
so I mean, what we talked about today are,
you know, like the principles and the elements
of the show that has made it the show that it is
today. And when you came on board, you know, I'm
really excited for you to keep championing that.
And you have such an interesting background
and like, such an interesting skill set,
and I've heard rumblings that there are
going to be some new elements to the show
to take it to the next level. Can you give us
any sneak peeks about this?
MG: Yeah. Well, I think something that I have experience
with, and that is one of my favorite parts of doing
this kind of work, is going out into the field
and talking to people. You know, field reporting,
specifically field audio reporting. Speaking of
things that bring one joy, this brings me a good
deal of joy, and it's something that I'm really
excited to hopefully incorporate a bit more of
in the show, in addition to sort of the sit-down
interviews that listeners are used to. You know,
climate solutions are being deployed now. And
I think the chance to hear from people who are
both working on those solutions, and working on
the research, you know, that underpins them and
whatnot, I think can be—hopefully can make things
tangible for listeners. And so that's one thing,
is this sort of on the ground look. And actually,
you know, I had a chance recently to go out with
some researchers from MIT who are doing some field
work down on Cape Cod in a marsh there. You know,
you spoke about how trees and other vegetation
stores carbon, and so they are doing research in
that realm. And I'm really excited to weave that
into the show going forward. And then I think just
this sense of momentum, this sense of possibility
that you've talked about, that's something that I
really will strive to maintain. I think that's
super important. And something that you hear
sometimes, and that has been very motivating to
me—I know it made an appearance, this concept,
in an episode—is that every fraction of a degree
of warming that we can prevent matters. You know,
we have these sorts of numerical thresholds that,
you know, global agreements are aiming to avoid,
but passing one doesn't mean, you know, throw in
the towel and be done. And so that sense both of
the urgency of doing something, and the fact that
we can, and there are, like you said, a toolbelt
of things. And people can leverage their networks,
people can leverage their skills. There are so
many, there are so many tools at our disposal, and
that emphasis is one that I hope and that I will
strive to continue on.
LHF: And there's also this incredible
opportunity for us to build something
better than what we have now. On the show, of
course. But also in the world, right? I mean, this
is, a lot of conversation about climate change is
escaping the worst impacts. And there's also the
opportunity of, well, what can we build for the
future that's better than what we have today? And
that's the most important thing to look forward to.
MG: Yeah. So, speaking of the future, of
the world and also of your life, can you tell us a
little bit about what's next for you? What are you
working on, and what can people look
forward to from you?
LHF: Oh, thanks for asking that. So for
the last several years, I had just been fascinated
by what's actually holding us back, right, and
actually accelerating action on climate change.
And it just became clear to me over and over again
that the polarization, the political polarization
of the issue of climate change, is I'd say one
of the top, if not the top things in the United
States. So the fact that one side of the political
spectrum sees the issue differently than the other
side of the political spectrum. And so I've been
doing a deep investigation into that over the past
couple years. One of the reasons I left MIT is to
really pursue this completely and more fully. How
can we build better bridges, better understanding,
in order for climate change not to be a polarized
issue anymore, and for us to decarbonize no matter
what president is in office or who has power in
Congress. So I could nerd out for another hours,
hours and hours and hours and days and days,
on all of that. If folks are interested in
connecting with me on that topic, you can find me
on LinkedIn. Who knows, maybe I'll do another show
focused particularly on depolarization of climate.
But that is where my heart is at right now,
and I'm really excited to pursue it. And then
speaking of, you know, my heart, I'm going to get
corny here. So it's been such a, just a privilege
and an honor that MIT entrusted me and our team
with representing MIT research and philosophy
through the show for a public audience. So that's
been a true joy to be able to explore how to do.
The podcast is one effort inside of a program,
and we have a fabulous team. Aaron, you've been
my partner in crime in making this so successful.
Obviously Dave too on the show. And if folks
don't know, check out climate.mit.edu for all
the different resources that we have. It's been
just a true joy to be able to produce something
like this and for this show. And I just want to
say to all of our listeners, you know, thank you
so much for being here for the last seven seasons.
It's been such a privilege to be able to have you
in my head as we've been writing these episodes
and producing them, and of course hearing from you
over phone calls and emails and LinkedIn posts and
everything else. I'm really looking forward to you
continuing with us and the show.
MG: All right. And to all of our
listeners—and to the folks watching
this as well, since it is in video form, too—thank
you so much for being here. We're really,
really excited that you're here, and please stay
tuned for the next season. I'm really excited.