Today I'm going to tell you about some
work that's been done in my lab over the
last couple of years or so uh where
we're interested in a new platform for
targeted theronostics that we call
antibbody bottle brush conjugates or
ABCs and I'll give you the sort of
history of this project what the goals
are and um where it stands today. All
right. So um to begin um should I stand
on this stage? Is there a reason not to?
I was going to walk around but um okay
if I cannot I'll do this. Um so to begin
I I I uh want to just sort of remind you
of one of the key principles of drug
development. That is the idea of a
therapeutic window which essentially
just defines the difference in dose
between a dose that has efficacy and a
dose that has toxicity. And um I would
say it's a safe assumption that
regardless of what medicine you are
developing, it doesn't matter what the
modality is, small molecule, big
molecule, you know, biologic, whatever,
you want the therapeutic window to be as
wide as possible. And you could argue
that the entire history of drug
development is essentially a um an
attempt to increasingly improve the
therapeutic windows of medicines for
different diseases. Um, and if you then
look at all the different ways that that
has been approached, you can break those
down into roughly two different general
areas that are shown here. One is what
I'm going to call therapeutic window
based on a mechanism of action. And one
example of those are these drugs called
molecularly targeted therapeutics. These
are the drugs that sort of came in uh
after sort of the early stage
chemotherapeutics in the context of
cancer where people started to develop
small molecules that could selectively
target biological pathways that for
example a cancer cell needs for survival
and a healthy cell does not need. So
even if the drug molecule is exposed to
both cell types, one is selectively
killed over the other one. Right? Um,
and you can contrast that with a
therapeutic window based on delivery.
Um, which is basically just biasing
where the molecule goes. And so in this
case, if you have a healthy cell in a
diseased cell, you achieve a therapeutic
window by just making the drug
preferentially go to the health to to
the disease cell and not the healthy
cell. Right? Now, um, both of these are
very powerful and have led to sort of,
you know, many many many valuable
medicines. Um but they both also face
substantial challenges particularly in
the context of cancer where for example
it's quite rare for there to be a
mechanism of action that a cancer cell
uh requires for survival but no healthy
tissue in the body also requires for
survival and hence we can have narrow
therapeutic windows because of sort of
ontarget off tissue effects. Um and
similarly you know even with say I would
I would say the gold standard of a a
delivery based therapeutic window which
would be an antibbody drug conjugate. Um
we know now that only a small fraction
of a of a dosed for example antibody
drug conjugate in any other kind of
delivery based system um ever actually
finds its way to target cells. And
oftentimes there are antigens that are
yes overexpressed in a tumor but are
also expressed in healthy tissues in the
body somewhere. And those anti-drug
conjugates conjugates will go to those
healthy cells and deliver highly
cytotoxic payloads and cause off-site
toxicity. So while both of these are
powerful that neither is perfect.
There's no sort of magic bullet yet. And
um several years ago actually about 15
years ago or so I started to think about
the question of how to combine these two
mechanistic paradigms. So utilize both
mechanism of action and delivery based
therapeutic windows to generate more
effective and safer cancer therapies. So
what do I mean by that? What I mean was
why can't we use payloads that have an
inherent mechanism of action bias for a
disease cell in the context of say an
antibbody drug conjugate where we bias
their delivery to target cells
such that in a sort of very
simple-minded way. Every molecule that
makes its way to the cancer cell brings
a drug molecule to that cell that's
really good at killing that cell. And
every molecule that doesn't bring that
molec every ADC molecule that doesn't
ever arrive at the target cell is
carrying a payload that based on its
mechanism of action is less effective at
killing a healthy cell. Right? So you
could think about sort of multiplying
these two therapeutic windows together
in principle. And it seems kind of like
an obvious thing to do. So you have to
ask yourself why isn't this why isn't
this done? And um you can survey the
literature and this really nice review
article from Daichi Sanchio that was
published a few years ago I think was
very inspiring to me at sort of pointing
at a direction for why this is the case.
So if you look at ADCs today, I mean
there are hundreds in clinical trials
and you know thousands that have been
studied academically and a few dozen in
clinically approved, but those
clinically approved ones basically
utilize three or four different fairly
fairly small number of different payload
mechanisms of action. And even though
some of the structures are different,
you know, the DNA damagers or topicase
inhibitors, they um carry have one thing
in common, which is that they're
extremely potent molecules. So this
summarizes essentially um or classifies
different payloads that have been tested
in the context of ADCs by their free
payload potency. And what was found that
you know drugs that are say subs
singledigit nanomar potency have been
successful in the clinic and drugs that
have you know are lower potency above
that singledigit nanomar potency have
not been successful in the clinic. And
um and so they the authors conclude that
the payloads of early ADCs are not
sufficiently effective and that one of
the big I mean you know holy grails of
this of the ADC field is to be able to
develop new payloads and expand the
mechanisms of action because again right
now there's only you there's less than a
than a handful of available mechanisms
of action for these constructs.
All right. So long story short we want
to enable molecularly targeted
therapeutics. Well what's the problem?
Well, it turns out that most of those
drugs fall on this side of the potency
scale. It's really hard for chemists to
make things that are, you know, subnanal
or picomar toxicity. That's very very
rare. And so when one finds one, it can
be a good ADC payload, but they tend to
not be extremely selective, right? So
they're really good at killing, but
maybe they don't have the mechanism of
actionbased uh therapeutic window that
some of the molecularly targeted drugs
have. Okay, so this leads to a question.
If we want to use a payload that's say
one or two orders of magnitude less
potent than these ones currently used
with ADCs, what could we do? Well, um
you might say, well, if I have an
antibbody here and let's say I have a
drug to antibbody ratio of eight, so I
have eight molecules of of the payload
per antibbody and you know, let's say a
given dose is effective, but I now I
want to use a payload that's 10 times
less potent. Well, I could just dose 10
times more. That's one possibility,
right? You just increase how much you
give by a factor of 10. There are
challenges to doing that, just simply
dosing 10 times more of an antibbody
drug conjugate. There's cost, there's
viscosity, and other issues. But I think
um it's also been shown and there's some
really nice recent um reviews on this
topic that uh by by doing a meta
analysis of all the clinically available
data, it's now known that all clinically
approved ADCs are dosed in a pretty
narrow range anywhere between 1 to 10
milligrams per kilogram of the ADC.
And what why is that? And certainly
certainly ADCs have tried like some of
the very very earliest ones were dosed
at 20 mix per higher doses than that. it
had some less potent payloads and they
weren't very effective. All right, so
why is this the case? Well, it's the the
thinking is that first on the low end,
we can't go much lower than 1 milligram
per kilogram. Uh because what happens is
antigens expressed in the pervascular
region sort of around the tumor right
where the antibi drug conjugate would
extravagate from the blood vessel and
enter the tumor. Now there's a high
density of antigens and all the
molecules would just bind there on the
surface and they can't go in they can't
penetrate into the tumor. Right? So it's
thought that maybe above 1 milligram per
kilogram you get into the range where
you can saturate the tumor periphery and
then have enough extra molecules to go
in. But you then can say well why not go
above 10 migs per kig. And aside from
the you know dosing challenges and cost
and things of that nature there is
evidence to suggest that at at much
higher doses you start to saturate tumor
antigens and then all the excess
molecules are just essentially like
unargeted nano particles that can
distribute around the body. And so you
don't actually gain more efficacy. you
get a little bit more toxicity by dosing
more. So this suggests that if you want
to use a 10 times less potent payload,
we can't just dose 10 times more because
we'll be in a regime where maybe we've
saturated tumors, the drug will no
longer be effective. Um, one other
interesting thing to note and this is
guides us when we think about what doses
to use in our pre-clinical studies is
when we start off with a new ADC
payload, one one that's not currently
established with ADCs, we can ask
ourselves, well, what payload dose
should we start with? And I and I when I
first started on this, I thought, well,
you know, let's say we we know a drug is
toxic at 10 migs per kick, but if I
attach it to an antibbody, I would
expect I could maybe dose more than that
because now I'm selecting where it goes,
right? Right? And so maybe I get those
20 mics per kick. But in fact, that
hasn't been borne out. And the really
nice uh review from last year has shown
that in fact ADCs don't usually display
higher maximum tolerated doses. You just
can't dose more. And that's because
ultimately the same amount of drug gets
exposed to the body. So what is
recommended is instead that you start
with if if you know the maximum
tolerable dose of your free payload, you
should use the same thing on a payload
basis in your new ADC. So you shouldn't
try to go above what's a known clinical
dose. So with all that information, what
we can say is, well, if we take payloads
where we know a maximum tolerable dose,
but we know that they're 10 to 100 times
less potent than ADC payloads, maybe we
could think of a way to incorporate that
many of these payload molecules onto a
single antibbody. Right? So, and by the
way, here here are the um titles of
these two articles that I I highly
recommend. Neither from my gra my group,
but they're uh I think really really
give a nice summary of the field. All
right. So, then back to this question,
what what can we do? I already said I I
think I showed that we can't just dose
10 times more. So, the other option is
if we want to keep the antibbody dose
the same and use a 10 times less potent
payload, we need to have 10 times more
molecules per antibbody, right? And so
we need to increase the drug to
antibbody ratio by a factor of 10 or by
a factor of 100. And I want to make that
really clear like I'm not proposing to
do that with existing antibbody
payloads. It's not necessary. They're
potent enough. In fact, you could maybe
use even less of them. But if you want
to use payloads that aren't that potent,
I you you may not have any other choice,
right? And so how could you do that? How
could we make ADCs that still function
yet have 10 or 100 times more payloads?
And of course, um, you know, you you
can't just Oh, it looks like my slide
advancer is
dying on me.
Ah, let's go back. Okay. Um, you you
can't just attach 10 times more payloads
to an antibbody because, as you might
imagine, that's going to disrupt the
antibbody function, right? Um, usually
these conjugations are done to either
cysteine residues or lysine residues.
you know, you've got 80 if you wanted to
do 10 times more than 80 lines, you
could functionalize, but if you do that,
you're going to make a big hydrophobic
blob, right? And this is not going to
function.
Uh so we started to think about how to
overcome that problem and several years
ago thought about well what if we
instead of attaching a bunch of payloads
to an antibbody um develop some kind of
rigid backbone that we could string
along several payloads and linkers onto
that backbone and only couple that onto
a single side of the antibody. thus
effectively only functionalizing the
antibody once and then having whatever
the drug to antibody ratio that we
desire tied to this this string.
This has also been tried before. Um, and
it's faced a lot of struggles. And you
can imagine one of the struggles being
that, you know, just like if we put 80
payloads on an antibbody, we start to
disrupt its function because payload
molecules tend to be a little bit
hydrophobic. Um, and you know, they can
cause aggregation. They can disrupt
antibody function. Well, if you put 80
hydrophobic payloads on a long chain
attached to an antibody, it's also
probably going to present problems,
right? Aggregation uh, and things of
that nature. And in fact the the
attempts to do this previously
the only way people could get them to
work was put maybe 10 to 20 kilodolton
of space between each drug and linker.
So this is drawn like they're very close
together but imagine like 20 kilodolton
of hydrophilic space between each drug
just to give enough hydrophilicity for
these to stay soluble. And thus the drug
to antibody ratios achieved were on the
order of say 10 to 20 not a factor of 10
not an order of magnitude. So all that
work to get maybe a doubling of the DAR
isn't going to open a completely new
payload space. So the idea that we came
up with actually about again quite some
time ago was to think well instead of
having a link one linker and one payload
for every repeat unit. What if we also
installed a branch point at each repeat
unit with a hydrophilic side chain here
shown in cartoon in blue such that for
every payload and drug and every payload
and linker you have this little blue
chain and the little blue chain would
extend just beyond the payload and
linker almost like a coaxial cable kind
of shielding the middle part with this
external
blue hydrophilic region. And if one
could do that, then in principle it
would allow you to make an arbitrarily
long
uh polymer chain, it would allow you to
use whatever payloads and linkers that
you want because their physical
properties would actually be decoupled
from the physical properties of the
overall structure because again that
would be dominated by these blue chains
and perhaps you could address this
problem. So I'm going to focus on just
this blue multicolored cartoon here. If
you if you look at this structure and
you've ever used a bottle brush, you
sort of clean out a bottle with a metal
thing with little spikes coming out of
it. A bottle brush. Well, in the field
of uh of polymer science, we call these
molecules bottle brush polymers because
they look like bottle brushes at the
nanocale. And so we coined this term
bottle brush prod
uh to describe this portion of this
molecule. Um, and we think that they
could enable novel ADC payloads and
payload combinations if they can be
made. And so when I started my lab now
again quite some time ago, the first
question was how to even make molecules
like this because molecules like this
were not known in the literature. Um but
we thought they could represent a
powerful new platform for therapeutics
that could have advantages and sort of
orthogonal functions compared to other
things like liposomaal nanoparticles and
and dendrs and other kinds of uh
conjugates or nanoparticle platforms
that are out there. So how do we make
this? I'm going to skip over lots and
lots and lots of work and graduate
student and posttock time. just
highlight our most recent which is still
old but the way we we make this platform
molecule today a former student now a
professor at Dartmouth Hong Nuen
developed this very simple three-step
synthesis to this platform molecule that
in two additional uh one pot steps can
access this molecule in blue and what
this is is uh I'll break down it's got
three major components one is a a
normine I'll talk about what that is for
in a it. But the key part is this
tertiary amide with a terminal alkine.
And here I show a 3 kilodolton
polyethylene glycol chain which is what
we use for what what we will use for all
the studies I'll show you today although
we you know we've published many papers
on changing what this is and various
other things. So what this what this
molecule effectively is is a peg chain
with a branch point and this norbborine
and the branch connects to an alkine and
what that alkine what we can do is take
essentially any uh payload molecule we
want and we've used small molecules
mediumsiz molecules like protax we've
used oligos we've used peptides there's
a number of I mean this can be almost
anything and and what we do next is we
we do some kind of medicinal chemistry
in a sense we we append onto that
molecule a linker here shown in green
I'll show some examples I mean these can
be any traditional ADC linker or any
other kind of cleavable bond that we
want and then we have an aid group and
with that aid group in the presence of
copper one we can do an aid alkine
cycllo addition reaction aka a click
chemistry reaction and very simply
conjugate that molecule to that alkine
to make this what we call the branched
macro monomer where there's a payload a
cleavl linker and a peg chain. And then
in with this molecule that contains all
the functional components that we want,
we can do a polymerization reaction
using what's called the grubs third
generation um complex, which I won't
bother going into those details right
now. But by simply controlling the ratio
of this molecule to this one, we can
polymerize through this norbborine to
grow this this purple backbone to make
these bottle brush pro drugs of whatever
length and dimensions that we want them
to be. All right. And again by
controlling the length of this we are
directly controlling what the drug to
antibbody ratio would be once we
conjugate this onto an antibbody. Right?
So uh this very simple platform we've
been studying this for quite some time
no antibodies involved just showing how
we can make things like this. This is a
short list and we've got many many more
to add that of just some of the payloads
that we've used some of the little gray
spheres. you know, started off with kind
of chemotherapeutics and have looked at
epigenetic regulators and immune uh
stimulants and protax and you know these
gray spheres can also be imaging agents.
We've made uh MRI contrast agents using
this technology. It can be almost
anything and also the green linkers can
be almost anything. For example, we've
taken some compounds like be bromine
inhibitors and we've made 10 different
linkers to compare head-to-head 10
different BPDs that are identical in
every way, size, and shape and
everything, but they just differ by the
linker, the mechanism for the drug
release. So, we can investigate its
impact uh selectively.
All right. Um, now this one of the
things I I'm really think is unique
about this system is just how
reproducibly it can be synthesized and
how its physical properties are truly
independent really of what the payload
we're using is, which is part of a
design idea, but it turns out to be
true. This is just a few examples of
some data. Size exclusion,
chromatography, and dynamic light
scattering. Two ways we can measure the
size of these objects. And um what I'm
overlaying here is six different BPDs.
Uh the top three, so black, red, and
blue have different payloads. The sin
and ant are actually BPDs that have
synergistic and antagonistic
combinations of three drugs incorporated
within them. So one thing I I didn't
mention, but you can imagine is if I can
make a drug conjugated macro monomer and
I just polymerize it. Well, if I want to
make a BPD that has two drugs, I can
make two drug-loaded macro monomers and
pyrize one and then plyize the other.
And if I want to have three, I can just
take three drug loaded macro and
pummerize them together. So, I can take
essentially any ratio of different
molecules that you might want and build
them into a BPD quite quite quickly and
know in advance that that that the
physical properties like size, shape,
solubility, and everything are not going
to be a function of what the ratio of
those drugs is or even what those drugs
are, which I think is quite unique. I'm
not sure that there's any other uh
nanoparticle type of technology that
could do that. So here you see from size
exclusion chromatography all six of
these are essentially indistinguishable
by dynamic light scattering. They're all
essentially identical size. Their
average uh hydrodnamic diameter is about
10 nanometers which is similar to um a
monoconal antibbody 10 to 15 or so. Um
and then here's a a cryeleron microscopy
image of just one of these just to show
an example but they are approximately 10
nanometer particles.
Uh so with that as the background of
BPDs
the big question is then how do you take
a BPD which is like a antibbody sized
synthetic polymer carrying however many
drugs we want and how do we attach that
to an an antibbody which is an antibbody
sized nanoparticle. uh they're both
about 10 to 15 nanometers in size and
such chemical reactions are not trivial
try to take two relatively large objects
and bring them together um and we you
can do this a number of ways potentially
but uh we recently found uh one that's
quite effective and this is work done by
Benlu a former posttock in the lab and
and what he realized is that when we
grow these polymers using olphin
metaththesis polymerization the end of
the polymer has ruthenium carbon double
bond. And what we usually do is we
quench that and we we throw away the
ruthenium and we just use the polymer.
We don't want that there. Um but uh what
you can actually do instead of just
quenching it and throwing away is you
can use this as as a useful site to
attach exactly one
click chemistry handle in this case a uh
a tetraine which is what this thing is
over here. And so by adding this
molecule one to this polymerization you
don't have to do anything else. You grow
the polymer, you add this molecule and
it clips off the rathenium and attaches
instead this tetraine onto the chain
end. And uh in case you haven't haven't
seen this before, tetrazines are really
really useful functional groups for
doing a a reaction called an inverse
electron demand deals alder reaction
which is also one of the of the family
of reactions called click reactions.
It's actually the most efficient of them
that has the highest second order rate
constants and things of that nature. And
and indeed we can take this with a
single tetraine on the end and make an
antibbody that has the corresponding
reaction partner called the transcyllo
octene. And this can be installed
through any traditional antibbody
functionalization
protocol you know lysene amidation
cysteine you know alpha beta alpha beta
saturated carbonial conjugate addition
whatever whatever we'd like. And we
simply mix these two things together and
we induce this click coupling reaction
that forms our antibbody bottle brush
conjugate. Okay, there's no clock up
here. So let me see where I Okay, I've
got some time. Uh,
all right. So now I'm going to uh
transition to showing you some of the
data from this. This paper actually just
came out um about a month or so ago. And
in this paper we describe we synthesize
and describe over 10 different ABCs
highlighting I think really the
modularity of this system. Um here are
examples of payloads that we used. Uh
doc rubicon do rubeson you know kind of
a classical chemotherapy. Um but
actually you know it's a topo isomease 2
inhibitor which is a mechanism of action
not known in ADC world. So topo one
inhibitors are really really popular. Uh
topo two inhibitors not yet established
to to to work well in at least in the
clinic. Um one reason is because Dr.
Rubson's about 10fold less potent than
the best ADC payloads out there. So we
have this in the library. We also have
SN38 which is a which is a established
payload in Troeli. Um we have a topo one
inhibitor by the way. We have we have
pletaxel. So taxel microtubial inhibitor
but unlike you know MMA which is now in
the sub singledigit nanomar potency.
This one is much less potent and not
successful in ADCs yet widely used in
the clinic for various types of cancers.
We have ARV771 a betron domain uh well
actually a BRD4 degrader. So this is a
protac molecule. Um and we also have
just SCI 5.5 as a floro near infrared
florore that we can image uh and we can
combine these mix and match them to do
simultaneous imaging and and and uh drug
delivery as we want. All right. So um
here's a a TEM image of some of these
actual ABCs. again confirming I mean if
you take a roughly 10 nanometer object
and couple it to another 10 nanometer
object you should get something that's
on the order of you know 20 nanometers
but two spheres together and if you look
really carefully and these are not
oriented in any specific way but if you
pick some of these you can actually see
two blobs connected to each other um and
they're all very uniform in their in
their size um and very small I want to
emphasize that you know people use the
word nanoparticle a lot and sort of
generically u but nanoparticles span you
know, two to three orders of magnitude
of size. And here we're on the, you
know, our nanoparticles, our our bottle
brushes are on the size scale of a
protein, right? Which is a small nano
particle um compared to say like an L&P
which is more like a 100 nanometers,
another order of magnitude up. Okay. Uh
one obvious question is if you conjugate
this big thing to an antibody, does it
disrupt the function of the antibbody?
Uh the good news is it it does not. Um
first here what I'm showing are uh gels
uh comparing so of course we use
trstusmab in the data I'm going to show
you today of course we can take almost
any antibbody that we want or peptide or
antibbody fragment but most of the data
in this paper focuses on just trstuzzmab
because of its clinical importance and
for comparison to other clinical ADCs.
So here in this lane is an ABC with a
DAR of 60 and here's a DAR of 120. So
we're getting to this you know really
increasing the DAR by a order of
magnitude or two but even there we get
by by microscale thermopheresis by um uh
by u SPR analysis and every method we
can measure for looking at antibbody
binding affinity we don't substantially
disrupt it compared to trstismab or
kadsyla or enheru which are other
trstismab based um herto binding ADCs by
flcytometry we see that the RABC shows a
couple of order orders of magnitude
greater cell binding compared to an IGG1
version. So an antibbody bottle brush
conjugate conjugated to IGG1 that
doesn't target anything or the bottle
brush polymer by itself which we good we
don't expect to have any cell
selectivity or targeting. Um, and this
series of confocal fluorescent
microscopy images shows you uh cell
binding and uptake, which you probably I
don't even know if you'll be able to see
it here, but but what this is is a an
ABC that contains SN38 as a payload and
SCI 5.5 is a die. So this the SCI 5.5 is
is coalently attached to the bottle
brush. So it tells us where the bottle
brush is. SN38 is a fluorescent small
molecule that once it's released, you
can see where it goes. And so four hours
after exposing cells her two positive
cells to an ABC targeting her two that
has these two molecules you see red
fluorescent just around the periphery of
the cells suggesting that we've bound to
the outside of the cells and if you look
a day later most of that red fluoresence
has moved inside of the cells into
punctates suggesting that we're now in
endoomes or loss and you already start
to see strong blue fluoresence in the
nuclei of some of these cells. If you
look a little bit later, even more the
blue and the red fluoresence are
starting to not collocicalize with each
other because the SN38 is being released
whereas the red part is staying on the
bottle brush, right? And so what this is
directly showing is cell binding uptake
and then release and the payload going
to the nucleus where it can do its job
as a topo isomease one inhibitor which
um you know this just highlights that we
can being able to put an imaging agent
and a payload into one ADC like
construct allows us to do this kind of
mechanistic um analysis.
Um we've done a lot of invivo studies
and preclinical murine models of uh of
cancer and I'm just going to highlight a
few of those here. This paper has lot
lots of data in it but this is one of
our first studies using a DAR 135
uh ABC and if we compare you know
animals given just saline vehicle
control um our BPD and our ABC IGG1
variant so it's a non-binding control
have some efficacy because again we are
dosing a nanoparticle-based prod drug
this some of this molecule accumulates
in the tumor and some of it shows an
effect but compared to that tumor
targeting ABC uh in this case we achieve
you know 100% survival and out to um
almost you know getting close to a year
these mice are fine with no sign of the
tumor uh recurring either you know
visually or by histologology and I want
to note that this is done at a dose of
monoconal antibbody of five migs per kig
which is within the 1 to 10 migs per kig
range and that amounts to a dose of 1.1
migs per kick of SN38 which is within
what's already given of SN38 in the
clinic right in the form of urinican or
liposomaal arenkin or even in the case
of tbelvi. So these are doses that are
very you know already acceptable for
clinical use and we're getting this sort
of efficacy.
Um [sighs and gasps]
we've done head-to-head studies with
kadila. I don't have those data here but
I've I've showing that you know the even
more the better ADC even is no offense
if you make kila but TDXD and her two
which is a really amazing heru targeted
drug. It works incredibly well in her
two positive cancers. It also works in
her two low cancers and it's maybe even
approved in her two negative cancers.
Kind of works. It's like magic. Um part
of that is because it's a nanoparticle
carrying a drug which is a discussion I
could I will try to stay on on topic
here. But um what we see is that
comparing TDXD which is an HERU
biosimilar to our SN38 heru targeted ABC
and HER2 positive BT474
uh tumor model. Uh and this in this case
in our hands we get sort of stasis or
slight regression with both of these
drugs. But what's interesting is that in
HCC70 which is a herto
ultra low herto expression where TDXD is
sort of the level of expression that
it's actually clinically approved. we do
get better efficacy um at the same
antibbody dose and and part of the
reason why or at least we hypothesize is
that in low antigen expressing cancers
having more drug molecules per antibbody
can facilitate higher efficacy because
for every binding event and a molecule
is taken into the cell you're able to
deliver more of those drugs it's a
little bit apples and oranges here
though because we're using SN38 and TDXD
uses exatkin which is actually or
actually DXD but it's a a derivative of
XTK and and it's actually a much more
potent and more stable drug. So we're
SN38 is not quite as good as it even
though we because of our higher DAR we
can outperform it. Okay. Um I'll wrap up
here very soon. I showed you doc rubeson
again. Dr. Rubeson not effective in not
potent enough to be used in clinical
ADCs but by having a DAR of 135 we can
sort of completely clear tumors. Again
uh these are xenographs in mice but
similar story at a dose of antibbody
that's very manageable and a 1.9 mix per
kick of dox rubin is already given in
the clinic uh in the form of doxil which
is a liposomaal docubit
um and results that look like this for
protax uh for other payloads and also
for different antibodies. So we don't
have to only use her too. We can use in
this case mukawan is also described in
this paper and we've used several others
in unpublished work. So I'm going to end
there uh thanking the NIH and the
American Cancer Society in Yusede for
funding um this work um as well as the
Koch Institute of which I'm a extramural
faculty member and we use a lot of the
resources there. I'll also mention that
um a few years ago along with a couple
of my students we spun out a company
called Window Therapeutics that is
working to bring these kinds of
molecules to the clinic. So with that
I'll happy to take any questions. Thank
you.
[applause]
>> Questions for Jeremiah.
>> Thank you so much for the uh great talk.
um uh if I understand it correctly um
well I'm not sure you have already
mentioned about this um you conjugated
the die with the preload and then you
monitor the die to see you know uh as a
as as a marker how the cell process like
intake and transport the payload and
eventually release. My question is um is
there any way to confirm really what you
see is not just the die?
>> Yeah, good question. So it's a not it's
not quite what what you said though and
I'm sorry I didn't make this very clear
and I went through it very quickly. Um
so maybe if I go back. So I said
in this section so we have ABC bound
die. What I mean by this is this is
attached to our our bottle brush polymer
but it's attached through a non-
cleavable linker. So the die molecule
cannot leave the bottle brush.
SN38 yes it's a potent topo isomerase
one inhibitor but it also happens to be
fluorescent. So when it releases we see
this molecule as blue fluoresence
and the red fluoresence is is is marking
the brush. Yeah. So at the starting
point they collocicalize because the
drug is attached. Once the drug is
released you get red in some regions and
blue in other regions and that's because
they've separated.
>> Does that make sense? Yeah.
>> Thank you for allowing me to clarify
that. Right.
>> No thanks.
>> Any other questions?
>> Thank you very much Jeremiah. Thank you.
[applause]