hello computational music analysts I'm
going to talk a little bit today about
some topics that are not in themselves
essentially computational although
having a computer helps but are really
about the intersection of mathematical
and quantitative thinking with music
analysis music theory and musicology the
study of music
history and these are some of the things
that I've done in my own research that I
hope will make you think about some ways
that data analysis can go beyond the
score and tell us something more about
the history of
music what I'm not doing computational
music analysis my other job is as a
medieval music researcher and one of the
certainties I was always taught um about
Medieval music is that we've
lost most of it we've lost so much of it
and I mean it's it's just incredible how
much we have in fact most people always
said that um The Sur the music that
survives is just the tip of the iceberg
it was first said by a very important
medieval his U musicologist Nino Perot
uh but this term was picked up from on
by dozens of other people and so um when
we think about what's lost it could be
number of manuscripts that's lost or it
could be things that um were lost
because they were never written down and
we've forgotten them but if we want to
think about even the things that were
once written down on songs that were
once written down the pieces that were
once written down uh how many of them do
no longer have any copy of at all um
what is the tip of the iceberg uh is it
90% that's what a lot of people say you
know the visible part of the iceberg is
is it 99% lost uh 99.9% lost or is one
person said basically everything so I'll
call that
99.9999% my friend and former teacher
Sean Gallagher once asked me hey would
there be any way you know you're a math
guy to prove this to show that it's true
and you know I immediately said no you
know there's no way we could do this
then I thought a little bit more and
realized there are people who look at um
you know how things get lost and stuff I
uh later on I found this great article
on um what happens in peer-to-peer song
sharing uh when you just start
disconnecting lots of computers from the
network as happened during the Crackdown
on napers and things like that and um
and they showed that as you go from if
you have a 100,000 computers on a
network you might have five million
songs uh but if the network gets down to
you know maybe 10,000 or 15,000
computers you only lose about half the
song so that was kind of interesting to
me that was a little bit
counterintuitive that you could really
lose a lot of nodes on a network and not
lose a lot of the content there and I
kind of thought well you know computers
might be something like medieval
manuscripts that we lose a bunch but
maybe we still have the songs so I wrote
two articles about this topic first um
is what I'm really going to be talking
about now uh it's an article called
tipping the iceberg in a journal called
mus discina and another it's a little
bit harder to find uh it's called monks
manuscripts and other peer-to-peer song
sharing networks of the Middle Ages it's
in a great uh book that the University
of Pennsylvania uh helped publish called
Kus scriptus Technologies of medieval
song like the idea of Technology
existing throughout history anyhow so
one of the ways that we could do this is
just you know look at all the records of
missing pieces and see how many of them
we have and that's kind of sarcastic but
there are things uh that exist in the
world like this um there's a
manuscript it's actually only uh I think
two or four pages survive now um that
was owned by The Duchess of troil so
it's often called the tro uh manuscript
it's in um it's in the National Library
of Paris now and if you look at this
manuscript uh what what we only have a
couple pages of it but we have the
entire index the table of contents that
tells you uh what the names of the
pieces are and what page they would have
been on in the original manuscript so we
can look at well we don't have this
manuscript but how many of these pieces
do we have we have we lost so we can see
that uh I've marked here these are all
the pieces that we're pretty sure we
don't have copies of and um here's all
the pieces that we're pretty sure we do
have
copies there's some pieces that we can't
really be sure they're um parts
of Medieval music Traditions like the
mass that have these somewhat generic
names like k or something kind of like
if we saw oh we lost Symphony well you
know who who Symphony things like that
um so when we overlay these two together
we see that actually those that survive
really outrank those that don't so so in
this particular index we have 114
compositions that um of of which 109 are
identifiable and 68% of them seem to
survive or another thing that I looked
at was this collection of um sonnets by
a kind of cool but second tier Italian
poet named pranii and one of the things
that um that makes a lot of people think
he's second tier is is he throws in a
lot of his songs just uh lists of things
lists of all the food they eat at lists
of all the dances they they danced that
day and in this particular case a list
of all the songs that were sung Begins
the top Bo kind of kind of nice for
where we're about to be in the year uh
with the violin Viola something they
made all the May songs like Ros Ki my
the rose that never changes it
colors etc etc we can basically figure
out which ones of these um things are
titles of songs and then we can see how
many of them we know so
Ros is a song that survives so is so
is but some of them like uh toward the
bottom we don't know that song so so we
can look over and again we can see how
many of them survive how many of them
don't survive and then these other four
um where we can argue about um that
there's songs with similar titles are
they just being misquoted or um are they
same or is this really a song things
like that so uh it's these are the two
proportions that it could be so
depending on what we look at there's
somewhere between 16 and 17 compositions
and three to to seven of them are lost
10 to 12 survive um so that's about 59
to 75% of the songs here
survive if we look at all of the sonnets
in this collection by protani there's 59
identifiable compositions and 40 of them
surviv so that's
71% so here's two pieces of evidence um
both from textual sources to try to see
um how how much survives or how much
doesn't but can can we do
better one of the things I thought of
was that there are people who spend a
lot of time trying to count things that
are difficult to count because you can't
sort of capture them all uh they are the
animal population
biologists they are people who go out
and um they can't capture every deer in
a forest so what do they do they um they
might go out here's one way that they do
it they may go out at a certain point
and go and um capture you know all the
deer they can capture in a couple days
um you know maybe it's let's say it's 10
10 deer and they go and they tag the
deer in some way or something somehow
somehow they you know so they can
recognize the same deer again then maybe
you know they let a month go by or
something not too long but more enough
time that animals can move around and
stuff and then they go out and they
capture deer for a day again and let's
say you know they capture 10 deer again
uh the point is the second time they do
a capture this called capture recapture
methods the second time they do it they
look to see how many of the deer that we
captured the second time did we also
capture the first time if you think
about it if you go into a forest and you
know you you walked around pretty
randomly or something and you all of the
deer or nine out of the 10 deer that you
captur the first time you see the same
ones the second time you might think wow
we've seen almost all the deer in the
forest on the other hand let's say you
captured 10 deer and none of them that
you captured the second time had the tax
you'd be like wow okay I know I've seen
20 deer here but law of averages suggest
there's a lot more than 20 deer and in
fact there's um there's formulas that
can you can uh that people do with this
type of thing
um so I tried to figure out you know
what would be the equivalent in in music
and so um I started to think you know uh
let's go and look at some equations we
might make uh if we had the number of
pieces if we knew the number of pieces
that originally existed and we
multiplied by the probability that any
given piece would be
missing we would know the total number
of missing
pieces that's
fantastic that is a very hard uh
equation it's very hard to argue against
but it's completely useless right we
don't know the number of pieces
originally we don't know the probability
that any given piece would be missing
and therefore we don't know how many
missing pieces are so one equation three
unknowns we don't know any of
them
but we can think through some of the
things here um I'm going to go through a
quicker version of this but I have
elsewhere well I have in my article um a
little bit deeper version that talks
about all the UN um the assumptions that
could be in play but let's start with um
how can we figure F out the probability
that we're missing a given piece well
here's one model and it's it's kind of a
um it's kind of a bad assumption maybe
to start with but here's one model uh
what if there's just medieval scribes
had baskets of pieces you just all the
pieces they knew them all their head
there something like that and they kind
of randomly chose ones that they were
going to write down well then the
probability that a given piece would be
in a particular manuscript is
approximately um the proportion of all
of the pieces in the manuscript there's
if R sub I is the number of pieces in
the manuscript and N is the total of
pieces originally copied then we would
know the probability that a piece would
be in a given manuscript or song book
it's not exactly that number because you
don't do duplication but but it's pretty
close um uh it's actually the people
have argued against me that you know
like well you have to correct for that
error but you only have to correct for
the probability of duplication if um if
the number piece in that manuscript is
very is close uh some major uh
percentage of the total number pieces
originally copied so um that's already
kind of getting anyhow so this is the
probability that given piece would be in
the given manuscript from here we can
work out what's the probability the
piece is not in a given manuscript and
we just subtract that from one great so
so that's that's pretty good now let's
say you have two independent manuscripts
they're being copied in different places
you know different people whatever
something like that what would be the
probability that the piece would not be
in any of these two manuscripts and so
you just multiply the probability that
it wouldn't be in one
manuscript and not in the other and so R
sub one and R sub2 they're going to
depend on how many pieces are in the
manuscript but this would be the
probability that some piece existing or
not would be in would not be in any of
two
manuscripts so there's about 85
surviving medieval manuscripts in the
period I'm most interested in um so of
Italy from 1370 to
1420 just after the black death and um
during the time of the great papal
Schism so there's about 85 of these
manuscripts so what's the probability
that any given piece would not be in any
of the 85 surviving
manuscripts and it looks something like
this
um
so this is something you know that's
it's a it's a big long um number but you
can see that right at the very end this
whatever this works out to is the equal
to the probability that a piece would be
missing because if a piece is not in any
of the surviving manuscripts then it's
missing to us today so this is kind of
great we know all these are numbers
because they're simply the number of
pieces in a manuscript today uh not in
originally say so we can take this and
we can go back to our original equation
with three
unknowns and um substitute it into for
that P of M place so we can see that now
we have one equation and two unknowns um
it's still a pretty honky equation but
uh well that's good one equation two
unknowns still two many unknowns right
we need two equations at least if we're
going to do two unknowns but we can look
at this last answer this m what are the
total number of missing pieces well the
total number of missing pieces is just
the number of pieces that originally
existed which we don't know minus the
number of pieces that survive which we
do know if we have a pretty good catalog
of everything that survives today then
we can figure that out so now we go back
and we see that we have actually just
one equation and one unknown uh it's a
pretty big equation um in fact a lot of
the literature that I was reading from
the 60s and 70s 80s was about okay you
can't possibly solve an equation you of
this dimensionality uh exactly so here's
all the sophisticated math that we can
do to
um to try to um you to try to
approximate it but in fact nowadays it's
it's pretty simple what we can do is we
can try different numbers for n the
number of original pieces starting from
you know one more than the numbers
fiving pieces or something try all these
numbers into here until the left side
and the right side approximately Balan
and we can do that with computers so uh
when I did this I mean it's uh this is
article I think like 13 14 years old uh
it's before um before python was big so
I used Pearl and I just did find U find
and find the hypothetical total number
of manuscripts given all the things that
we know and so on so on and um we're
able for each of um four
different uh genas these are different
types of music we're able to figure out
what percentage of the pieces are
probably missing these are you know I'm
uh there's error bars on this is rough
guesses um but we can see that the
percentage of missing pieces maybe in
only
one in only one of the genres is it
predicted to be more than the number of
total number pieces than you know than
the number of surviving pieces in fact
for some of these genres we predict that
hey we have almost everything
there
um so one of the things we could look at
instead of saying uh how many pieces
were once copied but no longer exist we
can take that total number and say wow
maybe we have all but 25% of
them now there were a lot of assumptions
that went into that um that scribes are
correcting things randomly and so on and
so forth and that you know that there's
not pieces that are more popular than
each other and so on and so in the
article that I wrote there's um ways
that you can compensate for this and
ways that we can test for for instance
we can hold out um 10% of the
manuscripts at random and then say not
just how many pieces would um would we
expect to um would you know would we
expect we lost but if we gained 10 more
manuscripts how many more pieces would
we expect to have that we didn't know
already and then we can look at okay now
put those 10 men get back and voila uh I
think I can't remember off the top of my
head right now I you know one of those
things I published so I don't have to
remember but uh I think that the
percentage of pieces that were lost I
think I think it was you know within 10%
of something or so so these models were
pretty pretty good so we can use this
mathematical thinking and just a little
bit of programming to answer questions
that were thought to be completely
unanswerable in
history thanks