okay um we're going to uh go through a
little bit um a topic that you've
unlocked now with the end of problem set
three uh which wasn't totally wasn't
officially locked but we didn't really
talk about it and that's stream
filtering so let me put this down and
let's do a little bit of Jupiter work so
go ahead and get get yourself um
situated in that give you second or
two I and I think I saw scores generated
in text um for everybody um there was a
great question on the list what do you
do if you're score if you're not yet on
Version 9 which none of us are
um and you want to see more the score
you can do showmusic xml. PDF and if you
have M score that will um that will open
um that'll automatically generate you a
PDF of more than just the first page you
can also just um do show. music show
musicxml sorry those should be straight
quotes I'm just used to putting them as
curly quotes you all know that right um
and that will just open it in your U
favorite notation editor
great um so let's get started let's
um let's not load our favorite bakal but
let's load our new favorite piece by um
a Boston based composer Amy
Beach and it's um a piece for you see I
even start typing Bach it makes life
oops
ah um when I'm not
teaching in the semester I have
um let's import start all right now so
we don't have to remember everything but
not every module is unlocked yet usually
when I'm not teaching class I make it so
that that's automatically imported for
me you um so I don't have to type that
so if you see me make that mistake
that's what it is
um we'll just start by looking at this
piece and it has a similar structure to
the piece that we have been doing o we
have some layout errors today on my
thing but uh it's piece called prayer of
a tired child for four-part uh chorus of
women's
voices and
um
and see that the four parts are soprano
1 soprano 2 Alto 1 Alto 2 and then
there's a fifth part the piano and the
piano part has well we'll we'll see what
it what it is in just a bit um
so how would we get this um soprano 2
part what do we want to do you all have
been gotten pretty good at at manual
filtering so beach. something actually
talk talk with your talk with your
neighbors a little bit about that we
have some odd number neighbors and try
to try to talk through what you do it's
more important that you can talk can
explain things then do it
instantly you want to get the um soprano
part so good good one way if you if you
find one way keep going for another or
two until we get it there's about five
different ways
good
here everybody give a thumbs up if you
think you know how to do
it if not keep talking with is that
almost that's almost Universal thumbs up
Jonathan was that a thumbs up yep good
okay great um let's see uh Jordan what
how would you do it dot parts and
brackets for one brackets for one good
so we've already started with one of the
things on today uh this was in one of
the users guide thing dot Parts is a
kind of filter that filters out
everything that is not a part
object and so this will let you find
things good what's another way we can do
it somebody else uh who have I've not
been calling on so much Derek
I think you can like put in
quotes as the like the index uh for the
index
to
Parts oops sometimes that autocomplete
is less than
helpful oops what do I have to
do what am I looking
for somebody help soprano two yep great
so he has to be exact does not grab the
first one that kind of makes that good
what's another way somebody
else Vanessa the first one you did the
first one great Matthew get element by
ID good get element by ID soprano 2
that's helpful if you don't know um well
for instance uh well not piano piano
let's try that um part do get element by
ID
piano you actually get nothing in that
case they'll we'll see that there's some
interesting things when it comes to
piano um let's let's do this for p in
beach.
Parts print p
and we can actually see a couple things
here one is that the piano is
represented by two of something called A
Part staff that are separate parts in
the ontology of Music 21 in a lot of
other systems they are the same part and
they're two staves within a part and
every one of these representation things
has huge drawbacks to them and when
somebody comes up with a representation
for piano music that does not have the
drawback um you can please please
publish that and you will make the world
so happy because everything is fine with
treating a piano as two parts let's say
it's in 3 four
um as two separate parts as long as I'm
try should try to make this at least
vaguely consonant um as as long as you
do something like
this it's when you start
doing that should go up shouldn't it do
proper
stemming that you have the problem right
that suddenly a musical melody that
starts in one part continues into
another part does your ontology allow
for beams to cross
Parts well you I I never you asked me to
create an ontology for something that
wasn't Western classical music I have no
ontology for yeah but this is this ends
up being uh one of the main things
whenever somebody says they've created a
new way of
representing um classical music thing I
always do because I'm a smart alec and
if you want to be a smart alec just
always go up to that person who's like
oh I have a mtip just ask them how do
you do cross staff beams in your
ontology
and they go well we haven't gotten to
that this is like the this is the first
thing that almost every ontology should
start with how do we represent cross
staff beams if you figured out how to
represent cross staff beams or or chords
that span what would be a good chord on
this uh I guess we're in first inversion
Here chords that span multiple staves
it'll figure it out the music 21
ontology on this is uh it's really not
what it should be on the other hand when
you represent everything as one staff
and you have to say Okay well this is a
note on staff one this is a note on
staff two then your sort of left to
right
parser ends up failing quite a bit
because you go left to right and then
you say okay now let's jump backwards a
bit and um when you have some sort of an
array some sort of a sequence of objects
that go all in a row but then sometimes
jump backwards and fill things in uh I
guarantee you you will be managing what
we call cursor hell for the rest of your
life trying to figure out where you are
left to right and how if you're thinking
about uh your Big O algorithmic notation
um you know how how can we simplify
things how can we make walking through a
score uh be o of n or how can we
do if if we do guess a number between
one and one 100 and I tell you higher or
lower what's the uh Big O we're talking
about log log n good good yeah some
things M does really really well with
this is great A lot of things I might as
well yeah so you all know log n well
what happens to your log 10 log n
guessing if you have an array of things
that go 0 1 2 5 11 14 8
2 suddenly what are we back to to find
any element in something o of and you
have to look at every element so you
can't know where something is yes Adam
you were reciting the Cal numbers for a
bit I think I was yes but but something
something we we will get to later in the
class the strong
law of
small
numbers you can look at this up
somewhere it is the
number numbers
numbers it is
one of the biggest mistakes with
computational work in any
non-computational
non-traditionally computational field
like musicology and that is to say you
don't have to look it up now you can
look at it later basically there aren't
enough small numbers for all the things
that you want so anytime you're giving
out small numbers there's almost always
going to be a pattern it's going to be
Catalin numbers it's going to be
Fibonacci numbers and people always find
patterns in all these um these things
okay that was degression on a degression
um
on a slight degression so we'll go back
to the main thing which is finding Parts
in here good so we have a way of going
through and finding interesting Parts
I'm going to turn this off sorry so we
can see better is that a little bit
better yeah good okay great so um we can
figure out all the parts some of the
other things you can do it for for thing
in
beach. recurse
if is instance help me I'm going start
with this if is instance be my GitHub
autop pilot I've typed this oh good good
some people have played with with this
if is instance thing thing comma what
what are we looking for stream stream.
part if um well we can say here we can
start with this part num equal 0 do we
want to do NE one we'll say negative 1
um part num equal 1 uh here we we'll say
soprano 2 equals
none part n not equals one plus equals 1
If part num
equals so we start with negative 1 so we
get to
one um soprano 2 equals thing and let's
see if that works coding on the
Fly okay good I can still do that that's
a
really really brutally awful way of
doing it right but you can can do it
that way
um so there's one other way that I'm
going to get you and why did I come back
to the recurse way of of doing this
because there is one particular shortcut
that you're going to find very useful
um and that is so we so Beach index you
know this one right index zero oh this
one uh for those of you who just assumed
that everything starts with a lot of
things we have a whole bunch of text
boxes what happens around 10 we're still
doing text boxes which appear somewhere
on oh there we go part 19 is soprano too
but here's another way that we can start
getting two parts this is exact um a
little bit different we have but instead
of putting a number in there we can put
in a
class and that lets us go through
everything so we can say for p in Beach
stream. part print
p and that will be one of your simplest
ways of going through things for um for
instance for our in stream uh Beach
sorry I should scroll down a bit Beach
note.
rest print R and now you can see quickly
get a sense of what durations are used
in every rest in the piece sorry I'm not
going to scroll down because people want
to see that give you a chance to catch
up and see what are some of your
favorite um things does the piece have
any cleft
changes actually let's just not say
cleft Chang does it have any time
signature changes so let's see if we can
how quickly you can have the computer
figure out does this piece change time
signature have any no are there any cff
changes let's try
that I'll code one behind you I'll code
doesn't have any time C
changes in case you don't have
this what do we think about CFT changes
yes
no no we got yes we got yes ready got
yes it does have some Cliff changes
so shall you do the same I'll get let
people have a little bit more and then
we'll let um we'll let a yes give me the
code for doing
this okay I talking who uh yes Jason you
were you yes or yeah so what should I be
typing uh for.
recurse
recurse if is is instant
okay let's let's go to the new new thing
instead of if is instance what do you
want to do instead of that you're you're
on the right track but now we have a new
way of doing it so this is a shortcut
for recurse and things Jonathan c. cf.
cleff yeah so it's basically the same
thing and um oh here is something that
came up in a couple things now I know
it's going to be a cleff so maybe thing
isn't the best thing best so that do you
like that no this this comes up a lot
what um Adam doesn't like it somebody
else not who not anybody else not like
this yeah Paul what do you not like
about it because
it's because C is part of the
music yeah because cleff is part of the
music 21 input um some people who uh
hate that I recommend um uh importing
all of music 21 so you could do this if
you
wanted and then clef is only referenced
with a what do you call it with a prefix
of Music 21 and some people really
insist on that uh you might have a
friend who talks about don't pollute
your name Space by things you don't know
um which is can be pretty good advice
but yeah you can do that um so so thing
is not bad I sometimes do um leave off
the vowel um some people don't like that
uh somebody in pet 3 did a lot of this
with Note putting an underscore after
afterwards that's a pretty good um thing
the other thing I will often do is just
use the first letter um even though I
usually like verbose things if I'm going
to do that so okay um and uh Jason or
Jonathan whoever was starting wants to
go next priny is that what you did or
yep right I'm going through well and we
have a CL change so cluff change anybody
object Angelica
go Adam has a but yeah Vincent um I
think I tried that at first but I didn't
really know if like the base Cut Thing
belong to like the Chanel part never
changed and so maybe like you could
probably print out the part and then the
C that it corresponds to oh okay within
the part good so what we could
do let's see how how can we get the part
name on
this for yeah good I just have another
fold before that that in the parts
repeat and Beach and now we'll um so the
diff Difference by the way dot Parts is
not recursive but we're hopefully the
parts are at the topmost level of the
score so it doesn't matter we could do
either way yep and then for print P
maybe print P actually I usually like to
do something like this when I have an
outer loop
oops then we'll do for C in Beach
C.C print
C what did I do wrong recursing I'm
recursing and Beach what should I be
doing P cl. cluff good don't um in no in
any life don't let me make a fool of
myself especially not when we're when
we're filming this class so yeah call me
out when I do something like that but
great so now we can see
ah
oh so there are there actually is a
cluff change but not in one of the
voices I was thinking none the voices
did but the piano part does change CLS
here's another way we can um we can do
this I'm going to be unlocking some nice
stream things for this we can just skip
that outer loop for C you can just keep
going and um doing things for in
Beach
C.C let's do this print C comma I'll let
everybody get caught up on
that c. get context by
Class stream. part and make sure to
close your second
parenthesis so this is a way of moving
upward in a hierarchy to try to get what
the most recent part
is same type of information but maybe a
little bit easier for your computer to
parse what what should we do if we want
to know bless you uh where that uh base
cluff change takes place let's assume
it's like vogner's loow grin we want to
switch the whole thing yeah you can get
jet context by class for stream
measuring great so I'm going to cut and
paste cuz uh we don't want to spend this
whole class watching me make um make
typos context by class stream.
measure it's a lot of things when you're
zoomed in you don't get very much maybe
I should print that in separate lines
but I want to look at the bottom
one measure 29 off set
112 uh here's a trick that
um that I explained at the beginning of
this class I'll open it up in a PDF
reader um
and hopefully this one has measure
numbers defined yep
112 no 29 29 there we go
finally there what is
that give me some ideas what what's the
piece scored
for what what are the what are the
instruments in this women's course and
Pi
piano what are you going to guess unless
uh Amy Beach likes to use 20 million
Ledger lines there's something about the
about the
peace about the piano
part that's M it's like pretty high up
yeah so it's up with the voices the
whole time
until right at the very end and so you
can probably take a guess that something
dramatically changes at the
end and it doesn't just go down because
well we're a tiny bit where where's that
note we're a tiny bit too low for
trouble cff so we're going to drop down
into Bas clo no no we get very very low
again um so you could think about it you
know immediately you could kind of ask
what are pieces that have a dramatic
change in range only at the very
end anytime you see something like like
this always be thinking of what are the
next three questions you can go from
here so this is um pretty interesting
type of research problem that becomes
faster to find with the computer um we
could also you all know how to find the
highest or the lowest note in a part
right yeah okay you're all you're all
experts at that now after problem set
three so um we can figure out this um
thing from from
here uh I by the way given the um let's
let's look at the beginning and stuff
and is there anything always take a
second when you have a new piece I
should um there isn't a good recording
of this piece if anybody sings in a
four-part women's choir um or AC capella
group that could do it it would be
really nice to get a good recording of
this
but what is where where is the interest
in this piece is in Soprano 1 soprano 2
Alto one or Alto 2 or more than one
place Adams will give other people just
a little bit
time Adam where do you think interest is
the middle two the middle
two who uh we we asked this before who
who sings Al um a middle voice an alto
me of soprano uh tener voice and some
people how often is that the most
interesting part in the piece almost
never Almost Never ever okay so either
um either Amy Beach is very very kind to
Middle voiced people or um there might
be another
reason what's the name of this
piece told you a little bit ago you have
it on your
computer see if see how much that sticks
in when we're doing these kind of Corpus
analysis I'm going to give it back to
you in a second when we given one of
these Corpus analyses try to think of
what kinds of questions you might answer
based on thing what's the prayer of a
tired child how do you think I don't
know why the layout's so bad today but
uh I think there might be any
connection of the title to this
opening just spread around I
see well first what what makes it a
prayer
yeah starting with our father starting
with our father yeah depending on your
religious tradition that that's a uh for
some Christians that can be a pretty
standard thing what makes it do you
think the um prayer of a tired
child okay good call on somebody else
let's put somebody else else on the
spot Vanessa what makes it
tired Tire okay so the Texs definitely
good good always go go with that uh yeah
you I think it's of how soft it starts
out so it's definitely soft yeah so we
want to do that good anything
else pie Jonathan I me two the part just
the samee over right so what does that
what might that have to do with
tiredness I mean you're just not moving
you're just not moving you're yeah
you're you're either not moving because
you're you're falling asleep or you're
not moving because you're you don't have
the energy to move up or down so this is
one of the things you can start thinking
about how is uh how in a text can uh how
might the text have something to do with
the amount of motion in a
piece um so you know we can look at that
and then finally finally um you measure
four they finally get to move and which
direction does the soprano 1 move when
it finally gets to
move down okay so so these are some of
the things that you guys were putting in
your questions on the bach Corrals um
that can apply to other pieces not just
by Bach by the way how long yeah then
when the lowest voice I always want to
say Bas but uh Alto 2 moves where does
it finally go down
also great so um some of the things we
can do with this now let's get back to
filtering back to the piece um let's say
we want to see this um measure here
let's grab the entire context for um for
where this happens and just show show it
so what we can do is we can do Beach do
measures let's say 28 to 30
doow hopefully I got the right one
yep so everything gets cleaned up when I
don't show the the beginning um so you
can get another one of these commonly
used filters is the measures thing now
um I don't know if this was a mistake in
ont ology or not but decided that
measures will um be based on how um how
a musician thinks of them so 28 to 30 is
28 measure number 28 to measure number
30 inclusive um so some of you guys saw
this what are some things that can cause
the number of let's say bar lines um
minus one uh to be not the same as the
number as the the meas the measure
number the highest measure what are some
some things that might look like
measures that don't get counted as
measure numbers in your experience yep
Vanessa
pickups great pickups did you have
another one that you're saying no good
anybody else think of
something ah if you have a Koda or
repeat and then you expand the repeat we
tend to call that like measure 1 2 3 4
five well we'll say six cuz you usually
repeat even numbered measures and then
you repeat it we sometimes call that
like 1 a 2 a 3 a 4 a 5 a 6 a the measure
after 6 is usually seven it is not 13 if
you repeat right we don't count that
here's another commonly encountered one
especially seems to happen in 34
uh here we'll sorry let me start that
again pick up
[Music]
measure anyone see
this
Etc where you have a incomplete measure
a repeat sign and then you begin the
pickup again
afterwards generally we'd call this
measure one 2
3 four
five but most computer representations
will represent this as a measure and
this as a measure that are both part of
the same conceptual measure um why it's
easier sometimes to to only look for
repeat signs at the ends of measures and
not have to look through between every
note to see if there's a repeat sign so
those are some of the reasons it might
uh call off so here's how we can do it
this
way um another thing that you'll find
quite often uh and it said what the
offset of that offset
112 we could say um well piano right uh
yeah left hand equals beach. Parts the
final part and then um Pian left hand
get Elements by
offset uh what do we say one time oh
let's let's grab a little bit of context
100 to
150 oops
and want to cast that into like a list
or something like
that and so that lets you get things
from um from within a smaller
area you'll find there is also because
get Elements by offset is not recursive
there is a recursive version get
Elements by offset in hierarchy and I
wish I had come up with a shorter name
for that but um so you can be able to
find anything at a particular element
within a
hierarchy so these are some standard
things some other people were putting in
using uh Lambda filters in some of the
code do that who has worked with a
Lambda filter before in their life not
everybody most people okay so you can
you can say you can write a little piece
of code to say just get me things that
aren't on here um one thing that one
reason you might want to use some of
these built-in uh features is that it's
a little bit expensive to iterate over a
stream so uh the filters do sort of a
pre- iteration um for those uh who are
in finance it's kind of like a tax uh
tax free tax exempt uh Savings Plan
you'll just you only get out the
elements and unwrap them and make them
look really nice once you have
it peek under here see if there was
anything else I wanted to do nope that's
basically it
on any other questions yeah um yeah so
uh during the pie I forgot if we cover
this um at some point in class but when
I when you flatten um it loses some of
the information when I try to then get
CL get um context by class um like for
for example I think like yeah it just
assumes everything is the last part even
though it's not is that because of like
how flat these are yeah it's because
it's um here so let's let's do this
we'll say Beach flat equals beach.
flatten and now um here we'll look at
the first like 100 things in Beach
flat and yeah so we get everything
that's here and within that um so we're
getting all of these things here almost
all the other get contexts will work
really well we'll get to slurs and
Dynamics and how they're represented
because they're fascinating uh later but
the thing is Beach flat itself oh is a
score with um in this case sorry so the
in some cases if if you flatten a part
it becomes a part if you flatten a score
it becomes a score so if you flatten a
part you won't be able to get the its
original part context but you should be
able to get it with this were you not
able to um yeah like if if you iterate
through these and then like through the
notes in the flat for example will you
be able to get the correct like all the
parts yep uh let's see I they should be
different right let's hope so
Class stream.
part sorry is that the very
end that's oh
interesting that seems to be a
bug I'll look into that see what see
what might have caused that to come in
um we have a pretty rigorous testing but
I don't remember ever testing on that
particular one um
yep that's why I have you thank you yep
um yeah that'll be interesting what you
might be able to do um I'm not going to
try to no part of this class is about uh
working around music 21 bugs um though
you will find them let's see what
happens if we do uh we get context by
class stream.
measure okay
and okay so that one does change so I
suppose you could do this you get the
streams measures context and then get
that measures uh context by
Class
part and now we have different stuff
I'll try to figure out exactly what's
happening to not make it not make that
work properly um it um but it was
happening with the B Cals also right so
it's not a piano bug the piano paring H
still has bugs um that's why you're not
going to be working too often with piano
scores only when I I've um really done
that great any other things before we
move on to the next and most fun topic
for a little
bit okay I'm going to move over to the
board for a little bit and let's um
let's just do some by hand warm-ups
we're going to be moving on to intervals
for a
bit
and these will all supposedly notes
there supposed to be lined up just write
them down here I'll give them as number
one 2 3 4 5 6
seven want you to say um and actually I
won't put them as chords I'll always put
them here so that there's a
directionality on
them
and go ahead and work through as I'm
writing that
what the interval is in terms of not
number of semitones but we'll call it
we'll call this the dionic interval
these are one of these things people
haven't completely done so like major
third perfect fourth things like that
for all these just do it as a
review second one's always
actually sorry I'm going to change
number four for a
second want to have at least
one goes the other direction I'll put
this up
for a second okay just so we're on the
same page everybody just one second
everybody shout out number one on the
count of 3 1 2
three major third okay good keep
working I just want to make sure we're
all using the same
system so let's let's get back together
even if you don't have them all we have
a ma 3D the top um and we'll we'll start
with Angelica um and we'll move uh no
we'll move this way um what what' you
get get for this one do you have that
diminish fifth diminish fifth anybody
get another answer it's good anyone any
other answers yeah diminish 12 diminish
ah any other
answers augmented fourth anybody we have
augmented fourth on the table okay so we
have a couple different contexts where
any of these things can be right oh and
uh I want on this one also I should have
been um pretty anal from the beginning
if I want to say a direction before the
major 3D what do we want to say up or
let's let's be a little bit more
elevated it is a an ascending ascending
major third
good this is usend I'm just going to do
that for a little bit so we can keep
going with that um so it's a diminished
fifth what's a context where diminish uh
fifth is as good an answer as diminish
12th and what's one that doesn't what
are we assuming which type you've been
doing some of the reading what's the
equivalence class that we're using that
allows
this o octave equivalent so the O of
OPEC if we allow the o equivalence class
then we don't care if it's diminished
fifth or diminished 12th when might who
who is a stakeholder who might care
about um can you sing this can you sing
this piece uh it has a whole bunch of um
diminished fifths in it I go yeah no
problem I'm an experienced singer great
so you're going to sing uh what what
notes that you're going to sing this
note and then you're going to sing uh
this note you said you had no problem
seeing diminished fifths right so there
are contexts where we will very much
care about not having octave equivalence
and there's other ones where we won't
um we'll I'll give you the music 21
terms for um for how these things work
but we sometimes call this a simple
versus a compound interval so sometimes
we care only about simple intervals
sometimes we care about compound uh uh
when's time that we might be okay with
calling it augmented fourth what
equivalence
class uh might be in
play spelling spelling or and harmonic
yeah so if spelling doesn't
matter what's what's an app that you
might make um that I have made I suppose
where um where when you're doing this
kind of interval ident ification you
want to be careful and turn off spelling
for a bit what's the context of interval
um identification where you don't want
to be too uptight about whether they
hear it as a whether I gave it away kind
of diminished fourth or augmented
diminished fifth or augmented fourth
yeah is it one where you're just like
train your like interval training yeah
where you're doing ear training right
can you you can't usually hear the
difference between diminished fourth and
augmented fifth at least not till you
hear the next note right when you hear
the opening of The Simpsons then you
know it's augmented fourth and non
divish fifth based on where it goes um
good okay then um next one let's keep
going don't want to spend too much time
on this want to get some programing what
uh Paul do you want to take a shot on
this one you can take a shot or pass go
but you take a shot augmented second
augmented second and just three put
identic what what direction ascending
augmented second good
great I don't think there's any way that
you could say it's an augmented ninth
you can always reduce the octave but you
cannot that's an interesting
non-equivalence class right you would
never be allowed to call that augmented
ninth but you can call this one in
diminished fifth great
uh number four uh let's continue
Jonathan uh descending augmented octave
good descending augmented uh augmented
octave great now let's uh keep going
around to Matthew um what do you want to
call number
five for lack of a better word I might
say augmented augmented augmented second
augmented augmented augmented second
everyone agree with
that well let's look at let's look at
this so
uh D2 e is what
kind what's that note what's that
interval major second so D to e sharp
is augmented so anything bigger than
major is augmented I want to make sure
that this year we don't lose any points
on the problem set from uh from us
teaching the computer wrong so good
augmented second so what's this going to
be augmented augmented second or doubly
augmented second so good so what do we
have to add this what do
we triply augmented
second quadruply augmented second you
know those um quadruply augmented
seconds
right uh let's do your tonal theory is
that consonant or
dissonant consonant consonant
all diminished or augmented intervals or
doubly diminished or doubly augmented
whatever are traditionally considered
dissonances no matter what they sound
like so if you doubly augment triply
augment quadruply augment they will
generally be regarded as dissonances be
because you're they're either a
dissonance or you have written them
wrong and the one um that comes up is
aug augmented second which sounds just
like the beautiful minor third but there
so we have quadruply augmented very very
close Matthew you shouldn't you should
feel proud on that uh quadruple
augmented second ascending or
descending ascending
good great and Misha you get this one
I'm not sure okay good pass on Jason
good uh doubly diminish second doubly
diminish second let's let's double check
that here that's a minor second right so
diminish second dou diminish Second
Great ascending or
descending spell this way ascending
spelled this way it's ascending and so
let's hear those two
notes ascending doubly diminish second
anyone want to make another
argument yes Adam you should just
consider what the final pitches are
actually what the final pitches are what
do you mean by final pitches eventually
it turns out to be an f and a e
eventually it turns out to be Adam has
an ontology that pray that um that
privileges the ear over the written
ontology that will do him very well in
most contexts except for in a sheet
music Factory right yeah so so sometimes
we'll want that sometimes uh we won't
but yeah so you could do that uh any
other argument about when so we have
ascending but sounds descending or
descending sounds ascending how um if
you wanted to say I'm on midi note what
is that
65 this is midi note 65 and this one is
midi note
64 what's the chromatic number of
semitones distance sorry for writing so
small minus one right so if we don't
care about
spelling it is a negative
interval um here is a context where you
might care about how it's written in
particular let's say for
some deranged reason you needed to write
this as a
chord oops sorry there are certain rules
about where the accidentals go from
bottom note to next note
so these are some of the things that
come up with computers these are
underdefined
parts of Music
Theory underdefined parts of music
theory that um that will come up quite
often that nobody has absolutely decided
on these things because you will see
that they do come up in real music music
but they're very very rare and they're I
mean um believe the number of doubly
diminished octaves in the music 21
Corpus of tonal music of music of the
18th 19th century out of millions of
notes there's about 28 times that it
happens it happens once in the beach p
no it happens in the climan piece um so
it does happen in pretty normal music
but when you see this what do you think
is Happening by the way when you might
have this happening at the same
time what's context Adam maybe two parts
have a crossover two parts are having a
crossover what's what's the top part
doing the one that starts off higher the
top part is going down it's the one with
the right the one with the the the F
flat yeah so sometimes when you're
writing a chromatic scale for an
instrument or something you'll use a lot
of uh flats and then the other one could
be going up um I think you'll that this
happens in John Philips Souza's March
the
thunderer is a melody in the
Baseline and that there's um I think
that's one where there's a d there's
either a diminished octave or W
diminished octave in the piano part and
in the instrumental Parts you get these
uh doubly diminished seconds and
diminished seconds that happen there
good so one of the debates is whether or
not this number tells you ascending or
descending versus the other one now last
one uh we ended with
Jason Vincent did you no go ahead uh
like diminished
Unis one diminished
one ascending or
descending n
n null poter
exception uh what do you want to call it
then let's come up with a music term
besides null like a new term uh no
anyone know a music term that's neither
ascending or descending for an
interval you don't usually use it in
intervals but you might use it for types
of
motion the stationary we use another one
sometimes um oblique has anyone heard
that term no okay so some people have
when there's some motion and some not
motion so some people say
that yeah so there's kind of a B so you
could say it's no motion is a diminished
Unison um the other thing that some
people want to do is to make everything
always be positive so you can call this
also what's another term we could also
say I'm just going to get a fresh thing
over here so we can look at that from e
natural to E flat we can call this
diminished Unison what we we also call
this augmented Unison and then
what's the
directionality uh descend descending so
some
people descending augmented Unis some
people who have done some programming um
things have thought about maybe the
diminished Unison should vanish from our
vocabulary because it's unclear whether
music works like um integer
multiplication if you have a
descending diminished Unison
descending diminished Unison does that
mean descending multiplied by diminished
Unison which is negative negative
negative means you're going up a
negative times a negative is a positive
at least the descending augmented Unison
escapes that
argument so some of the weird things
that come up great let's start um any
any questions on this before we move on
thanks let's get aead start on one of
the hardest parts of problem set 4 uh
what I'd like you to do is given two
music 21
notes first give me what the number one
2 three we call this the generic
interval some people use the term dionic
interval for this but we'll use dionic
interval for things like perfect Unison
major 2 minor 3D so on first given any
two notes what's the um what's the
generic interval between them and then
let's see if we can work up to what the
dionic interval is just as a reminder
there is a class called interval you it
is still locked on this so we'll do this
for about the last six minutes and
that's how we'll end the class today
I'll just be going around and helping
people get started thanks