The brain is a very intricate
network of neuronal cells
and glial cells.
So in order to understand how
the brain works,
we need to study
the information across
multiple spatial scales.
One of the major missions
in our lab,
we’re trying to develop
new tools that allow
researchers to do
not just the
molecular sequencing,
but also brain structure
mapping,
as well as, in the long run,
integrating brain activity
observation, connecting all
these modalities into one
measurement so that we can
have a holistic view
of how the brain works.
I was born in China
a small city named Xingtai.
From when I was very young,
I already got pretty intrigued by
mathematics.
Starting my undergraduate study,
I was a little bit bored,
by all the courses.
However, when I started to work
as an undergraduate in the lab,
it feels totally different.
I feel I can design a new molecule
that doesn't exist before,
and I can study the structure-activity relationships.
It just feels like I was able to create
something that no one else knew yet.
I think the Broad Institute provides
a very unique scientific environment
where we can have
a truly interdisciplinary lab,
and not confined in any
traditional academic department setting.
I can just identify the right question
or identify the right mission
and do whatever we can
to work as an interdisciplinary team
to tackle that question.
My central teaching philosophy is
trying to allow the students
to rediscover the scientific knowledge
rather than just asking them to memorize.
You have to give opportunities
to students and trainees
to explore by themselves,
which means they need time
and opportunities to make mistakes.
It feels like I still have
all my lessons,
and examples.
All the memories are still fresh
so it’s like a direct passing down
of things I try to avoid
or things I recommend.
In a research lab, if you encounter
a failure, it's not a failure.
You can always repeat
and restart over and over again.
So I do think sitting in the lab,
I feel the world,
it’s actually a nicer place to be
because I'm not afraid of
making mistakes
and I just need to keep trying.