the MIT energy initiative presents paper
thin solar cell can turn any surface
into a power source researchers develop
a scalable fabrication technique to
produce ultra thin lightweight solar
cells that can be seamlessly added to
any surface written by Adam zwi for the
MIT news
office M Engineers have developed ultr
light fabric solar cells that can
quickly and easily turn any surface into
a power source these durable flexible
solar cells which are much thinner than
a human hair are glued to a strong
lightweight fabric making them easy to
install on a fixed surface they can
provide energy on the go as a wearable
power Fabric or be transported and
rapidly deployed in remote locations for
assistance in emergencies they're 100
the weight of conventional solar panels
generate 18 times more power per
kilogram and are made from
semiconducting inks using printing
process that can be scaled in the future
to large area
manufacturing because they are so thin
and lightweight these solar cells can be
laminated onto many different surfaces
for instance they could be integrated
onto the sails of a boat to provide
Power while at Sea adhered onto tens and
tarps that are deployed in Disaster
Recovery operations or applied onto the
wings of drones to extend their flying
range this lightweight solar technology
can be easily integrated into built
environments with minimal installation
needs
the metrics used to evaluate a new solar
cell technology are typically limited to
their power conversion efficiency and
their cost in dollars per watt just as
important is integrability the ease with
which the new technology can be adapted
the lightweight solar Fabrics enable
integrability providing impetus for the
current work we strive to accelerate
solar adoption given the present urgent
need to deploy new carbon free sources
of energy says Vladimir bulvik the fairy
bores massu chair in emerging technology
leader of the organic and nanostructured
electronics laboratory one lab director
of MIT Nano and Senior author of a new
paper describing the work joining bvic
on the paper are co-lead authors Myan
saravana pavanam an electrical
engineering and computer science
graduate student at MIT and Jeremiah
Maura a research scientist in the MIT
research laboratory of electronics the
research is published today in small
methods slim down
solar traditional silicon solar cells
are fragile so they must be encased in
glass and packaged in heavy thick
aluminum framing which limits where and
how they can be deployed 6 years ago the
onlab team produced solar cells using an
emerging class of thin film materials
that were so lightweight they could sit
on top of a soap bubble but these ultra
thin solar cells were fabricating using
complex vacuum based processes which can
be expensive and challenging to scale up
in this work they set out to develop
thin film solar cells that are entirely
printable using ink based materials and
scalable fabrication techniques to
produce the solar cells they use
nanomaterials that are in the form of a
printable electronic ink working in the
MIT Nano clean room they coat the solar
cell structure using a slot dcoder which
deposits layers of the electronic
materials onto a prepared releasable
substrate that is only 3 microns thick
using screen printing a technique
similar to how designs are added to silk
screen t-shirts an electrode is
deposited on the structure to complete
the solar module the researchers can
then peel the printed module which is
about 15 microns in thickness off the
plastic substrate forming an ultra light
solar device but such thin freestanding
solar modules are challenging to handle
and can easily tear which would make
them difficult to deploy to solve this
challenge the MIT team search for a
lightweight flexible and high strength
substrate they could adhere the solar
cells too they identified Fabrics as the
optimal solution as they provide
mechanical resilience and flexibility
with little added weight they found an
ideal material a composite fabric that
weighs only 13 G per square met
commercially known as dyema this fabric
is made of fibers that are so strong
they were used as ropes to lift the
sunken cruise ship coasta Concordia from
the bottom of the Mediterranean Sea by
adding a layer of UV curable glue which
is only a few microns thick
they adhere the solar modules to sheets
of this fabric this forms an ultra light
and mechanically robust solar structure
while it might appear simpler to just
print the solar cells directly on the
fabric this would limit the selection of
possible Fabrics or other receiving
surfaces to the ones that are chemically
and thermally compatible with all the
processing steps needed to make the
devices our approach decouples the solar
cell manufacturing from its final
integration saravana pavanam explains
outshining conventional solar
cells when they tested the device the
MIT researchers found it could generate
730 watts of power per kgam when
freestanding and about 370 WS per kg if
deployed on the high strength dyema
fabric which is about 18 times more
power per kilogram than conventional
solar
cells a typical rooftop solar
installation in Massachusetts is about
8,000 watts to generate that same amount
of power our fabric photovoltaics would
only add about 20 kg 44 lb to the roof
of a house he says they also tested the
durability of their devices and found
that even after rolling and unrolling a
fabric solar panel more than 500 times
the cells still retain more than 90% of
their initial power generation
capabilities while their solar cells are
far lighter and much more flexible than
traditional cells they would need to be
encased in another material to protect
them from the environment the
carbon-based organic IC material used to
make the cells could be modified by
interacting with moisture and oxygen in
the air which could deteriorate their
performance encasing these solar cells
in heavy glass as is standard with the
traditional silicon solar cells would
minimize the value of the present
advancement so the team is currently
developing ultra thin packaging
solutions that would only fractionally
increase the weight of the present
ultral likee devices says maora we are
working to remove as much of the
non-solar active material as possible
while still retaining the form factor
and performance of these ultra light and
flexible solar structures for example we
know the manufacturing process can be
further streamlined by printing the
releasable substrates equivalent to the
process we use to fabricate the other
layers in our device this would
accelerate the translation of this
technology to the market he
adds This research is funded in part by
nespa through the MIT energy initiative
the US National Science Foundation and
the Natural Sciences and Engineering
research Council of Canada