OK, folks, we are
going to get started
with this breakout session,
as we continue this fantastic
day of science and engineering
here at MIT, for the HEALS
Initiative.
I am delighted to get
to introduce and share
the biosphere breakout
session today.
My name is Matt Shoulders.
I'm a professor of
chemistry, and really
happy to see all of you here
for this important topic.
You made your way
all the way over.
We really, really appreciate it.
And it's a beautiful
new space here,
so I hope you're enjoying it.
Today, I'll start with just a
few brief comments of my own
and then hand it
over to a fantastic
cast of four speakers
whose names you
can see on the prior slide.
But we'll introduce
them along the way,
to tell you about the topics.
To tell you about
really amazing research
and the future of this field.
Understanding how living
systems power life on Earth.
And I'm really excited
to hear their talks.
When the talks are done--
and this is important--
when the talks are
done, we're planning
to have about 15 minutes,
10 to 15 minutes for a panel
discussion.
That's why we have chairs here.
So think about the
questions that you
want to ask these
fantastic faculty,
because if you don't, I'll
have to ask all the questions
and your questions will
be far more interesting.
So we'll have time
for that afterwards.
OK, so why do we have
a biosphere breakout
at the MIT Health and Life
Sciences Collaborative?
I hope and think that the
answer should actually
be obvious, right?
But the interface between
life sciences and health
is critically important.
But the health of people, the
health of the environment,
the health of the globe, the
health of the planet, life
sciences are central to
solving the major problems
that health in all those
spheres depends on.
Life sciences are absolutely
central to solving
the key challenges that we face.
So these range, of
course, from rapid climate
change that we have
to adapt to, and we
have to figure out how
to also halt or slow.
Life sciences are
these challenges
that face the life sciences,
including enormous increases
in demand for food, for
resilient agriculture,
and for healthy food.
We also face the damage done
to deteriorating environments,
and the effects on well-being
caused by all of that.
And really, the
life sciences are
key to solving these challenges.
Whether you talk about
synthetic biology,
plant science, microbiology,
environmental science, ecology,
the viable solutions, the
globally deployable solutions
to these types of challenges,
to the health of our world
and the health of
humans are going
to come in a meaningful
way from the life sciences.
And we also, along the way, as
we come up with these solutions,
we have to think about
ethical and equitable means
of deployment right
from the start
as we think about
inventing these solutions.
So MIT is a leader
in this space.
You've been hearing about lots
of amazing biomedical research
and tremendous
discoveries being made.
But at this interface
between the life sciences
and the biosphere, the life
sciences and the climate,
life sciences in
agriculture, there's
also huge opportunities
for impact on health.
In fact, even sort of small
incremental improvements
in these spaces
can have the sort
of massive effect on human
health and planetary health that
would elude most types
of drugs that you
could dream of inventing.
So we think this is super
important, super relevant
to the HEALS Initiative.
And today, you're going
to hear from these four
faculty about both
challenges and solutions
to problems at this
interface between life
sciences and the environment
and sustainability.
And you're going to hear them.
You're going to hear them
talk about challenges
that are facing our globe.
And all the way down to
individual communities.
And the talks today
are going to start
at the molecular
scale, as we first
start by talking
about photosynthesis
and the basics of
photosynthesis and how
it powers the entire planet.
How we can maybe
understand it better
and improve on it to
find great solutions.
We'll go from the molecular
scale to the scale of crops,
and actually providing
food for the world.
We'll talk also today
about how the changing
climate and the interface
between the climate
and green spaces plays
huge impacts, has
huge impacts on human health,
and human health equity as well.
And then finally,
at the end, we'll
go back to the global
scale and we'll
think about how tiny
microorganisms play
a huge role on Earth.
And it's a very fascinating
area there as well.
You're in for some
great treat here
with these four
wonderful faculty,
and I should get off the stage
so you can hear from them.
Our first speaker is Professor
Gabriela Schlau-Cohen.
She's the Robert T.
Haslam and Bradley
Dewey, Professor of Chemistry.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
Well, thank you, Matt.
And thanks to all of you who
made this journey over to this--
enjoyed this view
and these talks.
So Matt introduced
us to photosynthesis,
and photosynthesis occurs in
a wide variety of organisms
and a wide variety
of environments
to collectively generate
energy on an enormous scale.
Now, behind this feat is a
series of remarkable features.
For example, if we take this
corn and this crop field
here, one question that you
may have wondered yourself,
and is actually a central
question in research
in my group, is why is it
that plants like this one
don't get sunburned?
So plants don't have to put on
SPF 50 when they go outside.
They stay in the sun all day.
But yet, except in a
few limiting cases,
they don't get sunburn.
Now, the reason for this is
they have their own built
in molecular machinery.
It serves the
function of sunscreen.
In my group, we're interested
in understanding the mechanisms
behind this molecular machinery,
both for fundamental knowledge
and because of this plot here.
Shown are yields
for four major cash
crops as a function of time.
And what we can see
over the next decades
with predicted demand
in dotted lines
and predicted supply
in dashed ones,
is that there is a
growing mismatch.
And not having enough food is
a huge issue for human health.
It turns out we need to eat.
And so that means that
one of the biggest health
challenges facing us is figuring
out how to bridge this gap,
so the supply meets the demand.
One way to do that is
to increase the supply.
Fundamentally, the food supply
comes from photosynthesis.
But photosynthesis operates
at a measly 1% to 3%
efficiency for biomass
or food generation,
with the rest of
the energy getting
lost to things like metabolic
processes, inefficiencies
or environmental responses.
For example, under certain
conditions, up to 70%
of the absorbed light gets
converted to heat and lost.
This is that sunscreen
process that I was telling you
about before.
And so in many
conditions, it's actually
that conversion to heat
that limits crop yields.
So if we want to
understand this energy
allocation and these limits, we
can go back to our crop field.
And we can zoom in.
And what we find are some of the
most sophisticated nanomachines
on Earth.
These are the photosynthetic
super complexes
that collectively
capture light and then
convert that light
into chemical fuels.
These chemical fuels are then
used for biomass generation.
Now, even in the first
steps of this process,
this energy allocation
is already occurring.
Specifically, this is where we
see the allocation of energy
into these environmental
responses converted to heat
and lost.
But the size of these
slices of pie, they
actually change
with many factors.
And there's been decades of work
in plant biology, spectroscopy,
plant science, that have
all led us to understand
that, for example, with
something like weather,
this amount can
decrease dramatically.
But if what we want
to do is understand
what it is that's
controlling this,
so we can begin to think
about manipulation,
we really want to understand the
specific proteins responsible.
So, for example, in
green algae and moss,
these are good model systems for
understanding energy allocation
in green plants in general.
The specific protein responsible
is one that looks like this.
Here's the structural model.
It's called light harvesting
complex stress related,
or LHCSR.
This is a protein that
actually takes that sunlight
and converts it into heat.
And the level of that conversion
gets controlled by that protein
by structural or
conformational changes.
So if what we need to
understand is energy allocation
in photosynthesis,
what we want to know
is what is the conformational
switch in proteins
like this one that activate the
dissipation of energy as heat.
And so if we want to understand
this dissipation of energy
as heat, a really important
reporter is fluorescence.
So fluorescence is
something that's
used to study photosynthesis
on all sorts of length scales.
This is a wide
interdisciplinary community.
So what happens is proteins
like this one absorb light.
The amount of light
that comes in then
can come back out
as fluorescence.
So the more light that
comes out, the less energy
is getting converted
into heat and vice versa.
Now based on this
inverse relationship,
this is how fluorescence is
used to study photosynthesis.
And like I said, on many
different length scales,
from the kind of individual
proteins experiments
that we do in my group, all
the way up to the global scale
where fluorescence is measured
in satellites from space.
And that really allows us to
connect these different scales
using these different approaches
to understand energy allocation.
But say we want to understand
these individual proteins
and this conformational
switch, that question.
I posed before.
Well, one challenge in a
typical biochemical experiment
is we may take proteins like
this one and measure around 10
to the fourth individual
proteins at a time.
Well, the challenge with
that kind of experiment
is that each one
of those proteins
may not be in the
same conformation
or may actually be undergoing
a conformational change.
And so experiments
had traditionally
averaged over this, making
it impossible to identify
these conformations and the
different energy allocation.
Now, it's because
of that limitation
that over the past
decades, single molecule,
or in this case, single
protein spectroscopy,
has emerged as a powerful tool.
This is one of the major tools
that we use in my research
group, where we can zoom in and
measure the fluorescence of one
protein, and then
another and then another,
to collectively understand all
of their fluorescent properties.
So here's an example of
some data from my lab
where we look at the
fluorescence distribution.
And so what we see are
two peaks, one of which,
whereas more of light harvesting
confirmation, and the other
is our dissipative confirmation,
where the energy is
being converted to heat.
So this one has less
fluorescence coming out.
And so this data was taken under
conditions that mimic low light.
But we can change how
we're doing our experiment,
understand how energy allocation
in photosynthesis changes.
And so if we do the same
thing, mimicking high light,
what we see is a change
in our distribution
and an increase in
the level of energy
going to heat by around 50%.
So more energy gets lost.
So collectively, this allowed
us to identify these two peaks
and see how this
switch gets turned.
So we now have
this understanding
of these individual protein
conformations, how they change,
and how they're
controlling energy
allocation in photosynthesis.
And so with this fundamental
understanding of the protein
level properties,
we can now begin
to think about that gives us a
blueprint for what's happening
in organisms like this one.
So we can think about
reallocating this,
redistributing the energy
potentially to increase biomass,
and maybe even one day
increase our crop yields.
And with that, I'm
going to turn it over
to our next speaker
who will talk
about continuing to think about
how to change these organisms.
Dave Des Marais from Civil
and Environmental Engineering.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks, Gabriella.
So I'm a plant biologist, and
so Gabriella has just given you
a fantastic introduction to one
of the most amazing and central
things that plants do for
the entire biosphere, which
is to take solar energy that's
abundant but transient source
of energy, and to capture that
energy through the process
of photosynthesis,
interacting with CO2,
with water to make sugars.
And as probably even most
elementary school students know,
the other thing, of course,
that comes from this
is also very important
for the biosphere, which
is oxygen, biomedical
oxygen, which we can breathe
and which allows
respiration to be
such an efficient process for
harvesting and using energy.
So what I like to teach
my introductory students
in biology, that we're taking
this transient source of energy
and we're trapping that as the
bonds in the sugar molecules,
right?
So now we have this physical
thing that a plant or an animal
can use to transport,
to move around,
to use as energy when
they would like to.
Not necessarily when
the sun is shining.
But as you probably know, sugars
play a second equally important
role, which is those
initially fixed
carbon molecules form the
backbone of everything else.
And I literally mean
everything else.
Everything that the
plant makes, everything
that an animal might eat
from that plant, everything
that a fungus might use as
it decomposes that plant, all
of those organic biomolecules
begin as carbon photosynthate.
But there's also very
important other molecules
that are part of that
fixation process.
So you know we need
to eat protein,
because protein contains
things like nitrogen and iron.
Our lipids, of course,
are often very complex,
large macromolecules.
And not only the composition
of those molecules
depends upon other nutrients,
but also the processes
to generate those molecules.
The very action of
doing photosynthesis
requires all sorts of
interesting elements
that are largely
gained from the soil.
So what is the ultimate source
of those important components?
Well, there's many, many
elements that organisms need.
Plants and us.
Nitrogen is often
was thought about,
but there's also countless
mineral molecules.
Where do those come from?
Well, ultimately, those
are weathered off of rocks.
There are abundant
sources of many
of these minerals
in the lithosphere
and as rocks weather,
those enter the soils,
those can be captured by
the biosphere, by capture,
by plants and microbes
to build their biomass.
Nitrogen is also
incredibly abundant
but is abundant
in our atmosphere
as nitrogen gas, N2 gas.
And you may know that nitrogen
gas is incredibly hard
to break apart those
two nitrogen molecules.
But breaking apart those
two nitrogen molecules
is critical to
turn that nitrogen
into usable forms of nutrients
like ammonia nitrate, which
plants can uptake,
turn into proteins,
thus providing us
with a food source.
Now in natural
communities, which
I have grown up studying as
an evolutionary biologist
and ecologist, in
natural communities where
plants and animals and microbes
are found and where they thrive
is really a function of
what's in those environments.
If there's rocks nearby
that can weather out
these important minerals, well,
then the kinds of plants that
can make use of those minerals
or that do well when they're
in excess or in deficit, and
similarly, for nitrogen, where
there's enough
nitrogen in the soil,
there's plants that will
thrive in those places.
And if they don't
thrive in those places,
in those natural
communities, well,
then they can move someplace
else, or they might go extinct.
So natural communities
have evolved
over hundreds of thousands
and millions of years
to have compositions
of plants and animals
and fungi that
form the biosphere.
Some plants die, they rot.
They create nutrients
for microbes
which produce and sort of
continue the cycle of life.
But in agricultural
systems, we don't
have that same nice
balance, unfortunately.
It's not simply a matter of
having the plants grow someplace
else, because we want to
have those plants grow
at very high yield,
in the places where
we need them to be growing.
And so that creates a real
problem when any of these things
become out of balance.
And this has led to what
has been called the nitrogen
problem.
So we know that nitrogen is a
key limiting nutrient for most
of our agricultural production.
Most of our calories
in the world
come from cereals, either that
we eat directly, corn and wheat,
or that we feed to our animals,
which we then eat the animals.
And to maintain these very
high yields from cereals,
we need to have a lot
of nitrogen fertilizer.
As I told you, those
things can become limiting.
If you imagine a common
agricultural year,
you're pulling up all that
biomass, you're shipping it off
and the nitrogen
is going with it.
So we're constantly adding more
and more nitrogen fertilizer
back to the soil.
The predominant source of the
nitrogen in the developed world
is through industrial
fixation of nitrogen
through the Haber-Bosch process.
Here's a few figures to
make the point to you
that this is an incredibly
resource intensive process
to capture that
atmospheric nitrogen
and turn it into ammonia that
we can feed to our plants.
So just huge proportions of
the total global carbon budget
come from the process of
making industrial nitrogen.
But even more
depressing is that most
of the nitrogen we
put onto our soil
doesn't end up in our plants and
doesn't end up in us as food.
It's running off, or
it's being lost back
to the atmosphere as
climate changing gases.
So this is the nitrogen problem.
Now, you're probably
aware that there
are plants out there that have,
in a sense, figured this out.
So in places where nitrogen
in the soil is very limiting,
microbes can fix that
nitrogen. Atmospheric nitrogen.
And many plants
have figured out how
to coexist with those microbes
and make use of that nitrogen.
So there's this
really nice exchange
of carbon from the plant and
nitrogen from the microbes.
And of course, legumes like
soybeans and many other beans
are the most famous
and widespread example
of this in our food system.
But cereals don't
have this trick.
They don't have-- and they
haven't figured out how to have
that symbiosis, how to get these
relationships with microbes
to provide nitrogen. So this has
really been sort of a moonshot
genetic engineering project
since at least the 1970s.
And a number of proposals
have been brought forth
about how we might try to
introduce this nitrogen capture
process into our cereal crops.
So at base, what
this issue is, is
how do we get the nitrogen
out of the atmosphere,
into a microbe, and into the
plants we want those microbes
to be associated with?
And in turn, what
is the plant then
giving back to those
microbes in exchange
for this resource, this
valuable, energetically
intensive resource capture?
So this is the central question.
And this is a
question, a challenge
that we've been tackling as
part of the MIT Climate Grand
Challenge Program, led by Chris
Voigt, a number of faculty
from across the Institute
where we're trying to address
this nutrient use in agriculture
problem in a very holistic way.
And what I want to
share with you today
is a small piece
of that project,
which is trying to optimize this
particular little interaction.
How do we get those microbes
to capture the nitrogen,
give it to the plants that
we want them to give it to,
under the conditions that we
need them to do so, and then
have the microbes in a sense
cultivated by the plants.
So Professor Chris Voight
here in MIT's bioengineering
department, is really focusing
on this first question.
How do we genetically
engineer bacteria
to fix the nitrogen when and
where we need them to do it?
My group is really interested
in the plant side of this.
My group is comprised of
plant physiologists, plant
geneticists, and we
think very deeply
about how plant performance
is driven and affected
by environmental conditions
and environmental change.
And one thing we've
been focusing on
in the last few years
is trying to understand
under what conditions
do plants provide
these cheap carbohydrates,
organic acids and sugars
to the microbes in the soil.
Is there genetic
variation in this process?
How does the
environment drive this?
And critically,
could we understand
at a mechanistic level how
to manipulate that process?
These are some really key
questions we're interested in.
What molecules are
there being produced?
Does the environment
drive this process?
And critically,
can we manipulate
the production of what
we call these accidents?
Now to do this requires
a tremendous amount
of technological know how.
So we're looking at roots,
so they're below ground.
We can't just walk
up to the plant
and measure them without
disrupting itself.
So we're collaborating
with a Professor Sixian You
here in MIT's research lab
for electronics and EECS,
who's developed non-label,
non-invasive imaging
technologies for living tissue,
where we can look at the roots
in situ, as they're growing,
and look at their metabolism,
look at their chemistry,
look, see how they're
growing at the cellular level.
And my PhD student,
Chloe Heitmeyer,
has developed a
very simple system
to grow these plants under
controlled conditions
where we can actually
then image them
in situ, and critically
sample those exudates
from living plants.
So as I introduced
the beginning,
I'm a plant biologist, right?
And when I talk to my
colleagues at the universities,
they say, well,
what on Earth are
you doing in this environmental
engineering department at MIT?
And this is what I'm doing here.
The opportunity to collaborate
with electrical engineers
and to recruit the best
PhD students in the world
to come and work in the
lab is why we're here.
It's this interdisciplinary
fearlessness
that I think so many of us
here at MIT bring to the table.
And I hope that we can use
this integrative approach
to tackle this very
simple, very complex,
mechanistic problem in a
way that we can hopefully
advance food security and
ultimately human health.
So with that, I'd like to
introduce Professor Janelle
Knox-Hayes who is a professor
of economic geography
and the planning head for MIT
architecture and planning.
All right.
Good afternoon, everyone.
And thank you so much for
joining this panel today.
I'm going to present
some research that's
looking at the interface,
taking a scale out
at the city level, the
interface of climate
impacts like extreme heat
and health dimensions.
And so this is based
out of work that
was completed a
couple of summers
ago in the height of
the COVID pandemic,
with Cynthia Rosenzweig at
Columbia University and Juan
Camilo Osorio at
Pratt University.
And we were really
interested in understanding
what was happening
with the pandemic
and how city officials could
respond to interventions
such as extreme heat in the
summer of 2020, and 2021,
when the pandemic cases
were at their highest.
But people were not able
to be brought together
into cooling centers.
A lot of public infrastructure
wasn't operational.
And so we wanted to
look at those dynamics
and see how extreme
heat is really
factor of a range of different,
not just natural conditions,
but built environmental,
socio-environmental conditions.
So our questions
for the study were,
what are the places of highest
risk in heat for COVID?
And we focused on
New York City in part
because Cynthia and Juan Camilo
are based in New York City.
We had really good access
through their network works
to a range of data, including
COVID health data and then
also this satellite imagery.
But New York City was
also the ground zero
of the pandemic for
the United States.
And what we quickly discovered
is that the pandemic
unfolded in waves.
And we could track those waves.
They were very distinct
within New York City.
So we basically mapped
three waves of the pandemic,
and that allowed us to
look at the relationship
between the environmental, the
built social infrastructure
and the sociodemographic
characteristics.
And then we also
wanted to understand
the neighborhoods that were
most impacted by COVID-19.
We were able to
show that there's
a direct correspondence with
compound risks of extreme heat.
And while it's not yet
published in this work,
we also looked at factors like
flood risk and air quality risk
and show that those
risks, they're compound.
If you're vulnerable
to one of these risks,
you tend to be vulnerable
to all of them.
And so in sum, we're looking at
a range of economic inequality,
health, built
environmental factors,
and natural environmental
factors, including
heat, extreme--
or sorry, extreme heat,
air quality and flooding,
and creating a compound
risk index for the city
that they can use to make
different planning decisions.
So there's a lot of data here.
I know I don't
have a lot of time
to try to walk
through this, but I'm
going to try to walk through
some of the key findings
from each of the
waves of the pandemic
and then look at
our index and how
that can shape different
public understandings of how
to respond to things
like the COVID pandemic.
So the unique challenge,
again, the cooling strategies
such as cooling centers, did
not meet the physical distancing
requirements of COVID.
Vulnerable communities had
less access to green space.
The other scientists
on the panel
have been talking about how
significant different factors
of plants are for generating
food, for remediating heat,
for generating energy.
And we absolutely saw that
in terms of vulnerabilities
to COVID-19.
We know a lot about
the impact of crowding
in the spread of respiratory
illnesses like COVID-19,
and that there's a
general relationship
between density, urban
density and spread.
What was really
interesting about our data,
though, is we were able
to parse urban density
and show that the most
dense areas of New York City
actually weren't
the most vulnerable.
There are different
kinds of densities.
And so I'll walk through
what those results look like.
And then we looked at the
social determinants of health,
including racial dynamics.
We created a social
vulnerability factor index
that included things like
language, isolation, access
to resources, education
level, income level,
and compared that as
well with COVID cases.
So just to take a quick
look at New York City,
we're mapping the five Boroughs.
And I don't know if I
have a pointer on here.
Maybe I do.
Yeah.
Where we can see Bronx, Queens,
Brooklyn, Staten Island.
And then we combine for to
understand vulnerability
the first two waves,
because there's
different factors that occurred
across all three waves.
And the first wave,
initially people
were being told to stay
indoors, not to mask.
Later that was reversed, and we
realized actually being outside
is much better.
If the weather is good and you
have access to green space,
get out into fresh air, don't
be crowded into indoor spaces.
And masking became essential.
In the second wave
of the pandemic
there were lockdowns
across the cities.
And you can see here
the timing where we
were able to map each of these.
Sorry, my pointer isn't quite--
first wave between January and
July of 2020 was a summer wave.
The second wave, between
August and July of 2021,
included the peak
in a winter wave.
And then between the second
and third waves, the biggest
intervention.
This is when the vaccinations
became available.
So you had a much
more extreme variant
of the virus in the third wave.
But the we'll look at how
vulnerability played out
through vaccinations.
All right.
So this study
design, really this
was taking inspiration from
an epidemiological study,
Madrigano, who created a
heat index for New York City
and creating a spatial
variation of that.
So our data are all associated.
We had more than 30 variables.
We associated them
spatially rather
than trying to think about cause
and effect of the pandemic.
We were looking at
spatial correspondence.
We created this
compound risk index
and then we evaluated
the interventions.
And the way we did this was
by combining the variables
into different factor groups.
So we looked at
vegetation density
to understand this
relationship of green space.
We looked at impervious
surface, because again, it's
not a matter of total density.
And you really in New
York City see that
with the impact of Manhattan.
Manhattan is incredibly
dense, but it
has, with Central Park in the
middle, really good access
to green space, and then other
sociodemographic conditions
that made it less
vulnerable, at least
in the first and second
waves of the pandemic that
helped us create this idea of
a mixed density variable, which
we differentiated from
rental overcrowding.
So it's not just a
matter of density.
The mixed density in some
of the places in Manhattan,
it allows for this concept
of a 10 minute city.
People who are living
in those conditions
had access to childcare,
to food resources,
to quality green space.
They might be within 10
minutes of their workplace.
And that had a severe
impact or high impact
in reducing the
severity of COVID cases.
And then also the distance,
this was kind of critical,
especially for those that didn't
have access to air conditioning,
to public cooling.
And then finally, the
social vulnerability,
we combined different factors
to look at social vulnerability.
So some of the map
on the left here
shows the top 15 most
vulnerable neighborhoods.
And a lot of these
were widely reported
in the news, Kensington
Heights on the north.
And then I'm not sure why
this isn't quite working.
Corona was one of the most
impacted neighborhoods
in Queens, and then
Sunset Park in Brooklyn
were some of the areas that
were getting a lot of attention.
And one of the first
things that you notice
is the distance of
these neighborhoods
from quality green space.
So we used a number
of different factors
to map and measure
green space and look
at where our communities
and what kind of access
do they have.
And then this is,
again, quite different
from impervious surface.
It's one of the core
vulnerabilities.
You can see how physically
dense Manhattan is,
the relative impervious surface,
but that doesn't necessarily
correspond with
quality green space
because you have good
access to green space there.
I'm going to skip
through the regressions.
I think there's interesting
results in the paper,
if you're curious
to dig through that.
And just quickly highlight
some of the key findings.
In the first wave,
temperature and COVID-19 cases
concentrated in the
same neighborhoods.
So green space is not
only for mediating heat,
it's also for mitigating
the impact of the pandemic.
It was highly significant,
especially in this summer wave
where people needed access
to quality outdoor space.
Social vulnerability was highly
significant across all three
of the waves.
And again, for those
that are curious,
you really can see
this impact here.
There were really
interesting differences
across the waves for access
to cooling infrastructure,
as you can imagine with
significant lack of air
conditioning was significant
in predicting vulnerability.
And then of course,
distance to open
space and social vulnerability.
In the switch between the
first and second waves,
we identified a really
fascinating transition.
It was known that Black
and African-American
populations were particularly
vulnerable in the first wave.
Hispanic populations were
also particularly vulnerable,
but for whatever reason didn't
get the same level of media
coverage.
And we were able to
demonstrate with our data
a shift that occurred
between waves one and two
where that vulnerability
was largely addressed
for Black and African
populations in the second wave,
and it was not addressed
for whatever reason
for Hispanic populations.
We looked into the
employment records
and there's actually, for both
African-American and Hispanic
populations, a number
a higher majority
that are working in
essential services.
For the Black population,
that was primarily in transit.
For the Hispanic population,
that was primarily
in cleaning services.
So there may be
some factor there
that that's not fully
explained in our data that
should be looked into as
to why one population was
more vulnerable.
And then the rental
overcrowding.
We saw a huge impact
there with the difference
between rental overcrowding
and mixed density.
And so this map, I just
want to quickly illustrate
the differences here.
This is the first
wave mapped over
Black and African populations.
You can see how strong
the direct correspondence
between COVID cases
and those percentages.
And then this map
is the blue hashes
are showing the second wave
of the pandemic and Hispanic
populations.
And again, you see, especially
in Brooklyn and Queens, a shift
away from predominant Black
and African populations,
but the direct impact on
the Hispanic populations.
All right.
And I'm almost out of time.
I know there's so much
data in here to cover.
Rental overcrowding,
again, a huge
overlap in prediction with COVID
vulnerability, which was, again,
very different for mixed density
in the first and second waves.
What's interesting
is in the third wave,
we really see the impact
of the vaccination rate.
This had a profound shift
in moving the vulnerability.
So you see the
areas in Queens that
were deeply impacted in
the first and second wave,
are less impacted
in the third wave.
Manhattan finally had a bigger
impact in the third wave.
And this may be as a
consequence of people's
choices around vaccination
and where that was directed.
And so just to conclude,
I know I'm out of time,
but the way that we utilize this
is we combine all of the data
and created this risk
index for the city
so that they could see where the
areas that are most vulnerable.
This part, the oceanfront
areas around Long Island,
are very well understood
for flood risk, especially.
But this Back Bay
of New York was not
well understood, how vulnerable
these populations are here.
And then we went
through and looked
at the existing
interventions for heat,
open spaces, pools,
open and cool streets,
and mapped the correspondence
of areas that are high risk
and have low access to services.
The areas that are high
risk but have good access
to services, and
then the areas that
are low risk and low
distance to cooling,
and presented these
findings to the city
so that they could look at
mapping their interventions
and understanding where were
existing vulnerabilities
and where should they
better be targeted.
All right.
So I'll leave it at that.
Thank you very much.
[INAUDIBLE] And happy to pass
it now to our next speaker
from Biology Institute,
Professor Penny Chisholm.
Thank you.
I have a couple of props here,
which I'll explain in a minute.
Well, it's sort of
obvious, but so I
am going to focus on the
big picture with this talk.
And we're going to go
back to photosynthesis.
What I'd like to do
is, first of all,
show you my favorite
slide on life on Earth.
And I'm going to describe
my passion for phytoplankton
over the last 40 years.
And I'm going to use that as an
example of how curiosity driven
research can yield really
interesting understanding
of life on Earth.
And this is just going to be
one organism I'm talking about,
and there are millions of others
that we should be studying.
So that's my pitch.
And then finally, I'll make a
big pitch for that, for MIT.
So first of all, life on Earth,
this is my abridged version.
We can't forget that
life all depends
on this process
of photosynthesis.
Well, there are some microbes
that can make biomass
from deep sea vents,
but if you track that,
they need oxygen, which
comes from the surface.
So all of life depends
on this photosynthesis,
taking solar energy, CO2 and
turning it into food and fiber,
and then all of the
organisms on Earth
that can't do that, take
that, we eat and we respire,
and use that chemical
energy to live.
And I feel so
passionate about this.
I actually collaborated
with a friend of mine.
We wrote a children's book
called Living Sunlight,
and it starts out-- it's
narrated by the sun--
and it starts out with
a child with its hand.
It said, the sun says, "Put your
hand on your heart and feel.
Feel your heart pumping.
Feel how warm you are.
That is my light inside of you."
And I showed this to a friend
of mine when we were drafting it
and she said, that's
a beautiful metaphor.
And I said, "It's
not a metaphor."
I said, "That is sunlight
energy in there."
And I just think it's so
important to think about that.
Because half of the MIT--
well, I digress.
But half of the MIT plant
scientists are in this room,
and we need more of them.
That's one of my messages.
OK.
So now on today's Earth,
these two reactions
are fairly balanced, roughly.
But if you integrate over
millions and millions of years,
there's more productivity
than there is respiration.
And we have this
fossil fuel, which
is basically ancient plants.
That's buried sunlight.
Another book over there.
And what we are doing
in this 150 years
is taking that and burning it,
same process there, respiration,
and that's the CO2 that's
increasing dramatically
in the atmosphere.
Hence climate change,
hence MIT's huge initiative
on climate.
So all of these initiatives
are in this one slide.
But today I'm going to
focus on that neglected
little green thing
up there, which
is the microscopic plants, the
phytoplankton, that do actually
roughly half of the
photosynthesis on Earth, if you
round up.
Maybe a little bit.
And you can't see
this very well,
but it's from another children's
book on the phytoplankton.
But there they are, these
little microscopic green plants.
It's in the upper 200
meters of the ocean.
This is roughly to scale.
And they feed all of the
life in the ocean ecosystem,
even the life in
the deeper waters.
And that is through the
settling of the biomass that
is not eaten in the surface.
We call this marine snow.
And so it's dead stuff
and mucus and everything
that's colonized by bacteria.
And as it settles, of course,
there's no photosynthesis down
there, so there's no
consumption of carbon dioxide,
but there's respiration.
So the bacteria are
respiring carbon dioxide.
And what that does is it sets
up this concentration gradient.
It's pumping CO2
into the deep ocean.
This is called the
biological pump.
So phytoplankton
serve this function
in the oceans of constantly
keeping the CO2 concentrated
in the deep ocean.
And just as a thought
experiment, if they didn't exist
and you mixed all
the ocean, so all
that CO2 equilibrated
with the atmosphere,
there would be 2 times as
much CO2 in the atmosphere.
We'd be really cooked.
OK, so when I came to MIT, I was
already studying phytoplankton.
And the most of the different
species, here are some pictures,
are roughly were between 10
and 100 microns in diameter.
In 1979, a colleague of
John Waterbury in Woods Hole
discovered these tiny little
1 micron phytoplankton
is called synechococcus.
They're shown here fluorescing
orange because of the pigments
they have, and they
were discovered
because a fluorescence
microscope was suddenly became
available and you could see
these tiny little things.
And I was lucky enough
to have a team of people.
To work with a team of people.
We took a flow cytometer, which
is a laser based instrument
on a ship, and Rob Olson,
brilliant young scientist,
was able to see even smaller--
whoops-- even smaller
than synechococcus.
You can't really see it.
There's two little
red dots there.
That's also chlorophyll
fluorescing.
That circle.
This little organism
called prochlorococcus.
It's the smallest and most
abundant, photosynthetic cell
on the planet, it turns out.
It's less than a
micron in diameter.
It's the size of the wavelengths
of light that it absorbs.
And I've been studying
it ever since.
It's been my muse.
And we now know that
there are three billion,
billion, billion prochlorococcus
in the global oceans.
They're everywhere in the
warm mid-latitude oceans.
Their annual photosynthesis
is equal to that
of all crops on land.
And over the years, we've
been able to isolate them
into culture.
And after the human genome
was finished being sequenced,
we were able to start.
They were one of the first
microbial genomes sequenced,
because they're so small, you
could do it in half a year.
Now, you can do
it in a half day.
It's very exciting.
So we're knee deep
in genomes now.
So genomes, transcriptomes.
We use all the
technologies that are
developed for
biomedical research,
we apply to prochlorococcus.
And now we have a
database, we can go.
These are transects in
the world oceans where
we have a database of
prochlorococcus genomes
from all over the global oceans.
And so over the
years, I just let
prochlorococcus point the way in
terms of what we should study.
And this is a beautiful
model organism
to use for what I call
cross-scale biology, which
is really ecology.
But that word is loaded.
So we call it cross-scale
system of biology.
And so my goal was just to
use this organism to study it,
not only at the molecular
level, but all the way
to the global biosphere
level, the oceans.
Which you can do with
this simple little cell.
And some of the things-- these
are just some of the stories
that we've learned
across, along the way.
The first thing we learned is
that although this cell has
about 2,000 genes, every
time he sequenced a new one,
you'd find 100 new genes
that you didn't see before.
And the projected pangenome
of the collective of all
prochlorococcus in the
oceans is about 80,000 genes.
That's four times the
size of the human genome.
So this tiny,
simple little cell,
it's really a superorganism.
And we can debate whether
it's a single species,
but by many measures
it's a single species.
So it's incredibly diverse.
And that's how it
maintains these populations
throughout the oceans.
Also one of my postdocs recently
discovered a novel gene transfer
agent, which he named
[INAUDIBLE] after a goddess
of good fortune or something.
Anyway, these serve
to move genes around
within the superorganism
to continuously create
the diversity in the system.
They also make these
novel metabolites,
secondary metabolites.
They make hundreds
of these molecules
that in most model microbes that
are studied make one or two,
and we don't know what
their function is at all.
That's-- somebody else has
got to figure that out.
But it's really exciting
because the cells are
trying to tell us something.
There are thousands of these
molecules in the ocean,
so we see them in the cultures.
You go in the ocean,
look at the sequences
and you can see that there
are thousands of variants.
Also we've studied vesicles.
They pop out little
lipid bound vesicles
that contain DNA and RNA.
So then you go to the
oceans and you say,
are there vesicles
in the oceans?
Yes, there are.
There are thousands
of different species
are making these
vesicles in the oceans
and putting them out there.
It's like dissolved information
going around in the oceans.
And also studying interactions
between prochlorococcus
and other organisms, a
new evolutionary theory
was developed.
Not in my lab, but
in a colleague's lab,
called the Black
Queen Hypothesis,
which is really interesting.
So some people say, well,
that's all very interesting.
It's basic research,
but how can we use them?
And I get this
question all the time.
And I say, well, they're
out there doing their job,
keeping the biological
pump and all of that.
But I look to the Sand County
Almanac for the answer from Aldo
Leopold and hopefully
not insulting anybody
in the audience who
wondered how to use them.
But I'm sure that in
time, they will be used.
They are the smallest
amount of information
that can do this amazing
photosynthesis reaction.
OK, so what do we
need more of at MIT?
I think we need more of
this curiosity driven
research on life on our planet.
And I'm all for human health.
And that's what this
initiative is about.
But also, I think
we need to broaden
our scope of life sciences
to embrace, most importantly,
plants.
I think we need
more of that at MIT.
So life is a complex
adaptive system.
And this-- here's my laser--
this is where we've
focused a lot of energy
here in biology at
MIT, for good reason,
and with amazing results.
I think that focus is
incredibly important.
But what I like to remind us is
that this is how things work.
But this, at this level, the
ecosystem level, the population
level, is why they work
that way, because that's
where evolution is operating.
And there's feedback
mechanisms from these.
This level of
organization feeds back
on this level of
organization and shapes it
through natural selection.
So we need to look at both
how and the why of the system.
And this movement is underway,
I'm very excited to say.
I say let's not miss out.
Molecular biologists, let's--
these are papers that just came
out recently.
"Let's Reconnect With Nature,
Integration Across Scales."
This one is actually
from a colleague at MIT.
Mick Follows.
"A Metabolism Shared
Across Scale."
So there is a movement
to go in this direction.
So with that, I
think prochlorococcus
and all the people that
contributed to this,
but most importantly
two foundations
made all of this work
possible, the Moore Foundation
and the Simons Foundation.
I never would have been able to
do this without that support.
It's extraordinarily important.
And finally, you probably
can't read this, but this.
I was playing around
with the ChatGTP
and said, what would
MIT and Kendall Square
look like in 25 years if
my fantasy world existed?
And that's what we
hope will happen.
And it came up with
plants all by itself.
So it understands.
I'm supposed to sit down.
[APPLAUSE]
OK.
Fantastic.
Let's see.
So I hope-- I really
enjoyed these talks.
I hope you did too.
I think it really captures how
life science, broadly defined,
is going to play a huge role in
many aspects of human health.
And these are leaders
in that space.
So this is your chance
to ask them questions.
And I heard there's a prize.
First question gets a free book.
But you do have to come up to
the mics to ask your question.
So if you can come up to the
mics and ask your questions,
that way the interpreter
can hear and interpret.
Thank you.
OK I have actually
three questions
for three different people.
And they're quick.
One is, given that the
nitrogen fixation requires
a combination of a
plant and a microbe,
is anybody talking
about simultaneously
engineering both of them--
both kinds at the same
time to communicate?
Second question.
The density that you
cite in New York,
do you consider per
area or per volume?
I mean, New York
is really built up,
so that might make a difference.
And the final question
is, in deep sea vents,
is it really
dependent on the sun?
I guess we can
take them in order.
Yeah, sure.
We can take them in order.
Dave and then Janelle.
Yes, so the way we're
envisioning this
is sort of a
co-optimized system.
We're not using any sort of
directed evolution process where
we're--
the process is not
so much co-optimized
as the goal to have a
co-optimized system where
we understand what the plants
want, what the microbes want,
and how they're
talking to each other.
So yes, the idea is to
have them synergistic
and sort of designed in
tandem to be together.
Yeah, and on the
density question,
it's a terrific density--
or a terrific question.
We were looking at density in
terms of the total population
density.
And then for mixed
density, it was including
building type and building use.
So mixed density included both
residential and commercial.
And when you map out what
that variable where it is,
again you see the
areas like Manhattan
have a lot of mixed density.
Rental overcrowding was also
taking total population density
and combining it
with housing type.
So type of family, is it a mixed
family, a multiple family unit
complex, and then number of
residents in that in each unit.
So, so rental
overcrowding showed
areas where you have
rental use, but then high--
more density in
each rental unit.
So kind of I think
that is both combining
the area and the volume
for that question.
The deep sea vents,
the bacteria down there
are oxidizing hydrogen
sulfide, and so they
need oxygen to do that.
To fix CO2.
Right, Dave?
Yeah.
So it's coming
from the atmosphere
up above, which is
coming from the plants,
and finding its way down
to the deep ocean and that.
So in effect, they need
oxygen from plants.
Thank you.
Hi, my name is Amy Nurnberger.
I'm from data and specialized
services and research data
management.
Thank you, each of you, for
such delightful presentations
showcasing the
variety of work that
is done around the
biosphere and plants.
Given that necessary
interdisciplinarity,
the focus on collaboration
in this initiative.
Can you each speak
briefly about what
you would like to
see from yourselves,
from your colleagues,
from others on the stage
to increase the effective
sharing, and reuse
of the data and other
associated products
that your research creates, so
that you can more fruitfully
grow from each other?
Thank you.
Well, I think one of the
themes of this session
is across scales.
So I think the key to
that understanding,
and Penny did a great job
of wrapping it up with that,
is understanding how to
get the output of one scale
to merge the input of
the other and vice versa.
And I think sometimes
fields are very
specific in the type of
data that they produce,
and how they look at it.
But I think finding
metrics, like in some ways
actually, I think
photosynthesis is
a great example for this
because of fluorescence,
like we both talked about.
That actually allows
a kind of cross scale.
Because you can
look at the process
itself in a way that you
can't with other things.
You need an exogenous reporter.
And so I think while we have
that in what we measure,
we maybe don't save it in
the same way or report it.
And I think having
catalyst type funding that
allows you to build across
fields allows that kind of thing
to happen.
Yes.
I mean, your question kind
of keeps me up at night,
to be honest.
So we've heard a lot
about omics this morning.
Penny mentioned different omics.
I do a lot of
genomics and we've had
20 some years now to think about
what to do with genomic data.
In a sense it's kind of
easy and that there's only
four letters that
make up-- five if you
want to count Uracil for RNA.
But it's something that's pretty
easily stored and manipulated
and we more or less
understand what it is.
And we've now gotten
to the point where
we can collect
all the other omic
data much more easily than we
can analyze it or even handle
it.
So I am very interested
and very concerned
with how we would standardize
metabolomic, proteomic
phenotypic data,
that kind of stuff
that Gabrielle's lab generates.
These are optical things.
Like how do you quantify and
store that and compare it?
So thinking about ways
to integrate big data
and be clever about how
we generate the big data,
I'm very bullish on.
And think we need to spend
a lot more time on doing it.
And I'm optimistic the
people at MIT can this out,
but it's something that
we're very focused on.
Yeah, so another area of my work
I wanted to talk about today
but didn't really have time is
Indigenous community planning.
And I've been building
a group in urban studies
and planning that's
really focused
on trying to weave traditional
ecological knowledge
into conventional sciences.
So for example,
the nitrogen cycle.
That's well known in
Indigenous practice
of growing three different
species together,
the corn, beans, and rice,
to help fix the nitrogen.
There's a lot of knowledge
about plant urban
and natural systems that comes
from Indigenous communities.
So the green space we
showed in the COVID study,
how significant that is.
It has a cooling factor,
but it isn't just
the physical cooling factor.
There's a lot of well
demonstrated health literature
about how being around
high quality green space
or high quality density of
trees helps human health.
And one of the things--
one of the students in my lab
has started studying is seeds.
The way in which they have
actually acoustic resonance.
So she played sounds
to seeds, and then has
demonstrated that the
seeds actually respond.
There is sound that comes back.
And she's done some really
amazing architecture
and art displays,
mapping and showing
what that sound looks like.
But we're partnering now with
Professor Nicholas Makris, who's
in aeronautic and
acoustic engineering,
to look at that sound
resonance across a broader
spectrum of trees.
And it could
revolutionize the way
we think about urban planning
in relation to plants.
So there's a whole, not
just within the seeds,
but mature plants, a whole sound
biology that exists around them.
And we're in planning, often
thinking just about sight.
Visually, what are we seeing?
Or even the light impact
is somehow a site impact.
But acoustically what is
happening both in our natural
and our urban environments
is critically important.
And so this kind of combination
of Indigenous knowledge,
what is known about the
species, what they're
speaking, what they're saying.
The urban planning and
then the life sciences
of understanding the physics
and the engineering of that
could be really critical
in unpacking and creating
new areas and ways in which
we think about planning
and development and health.
And so I think this initiative
really captures that spirit.
And that's critically
what we need more,
is to put people from
different disciplines
together, from different
ways of knowing together
and combine that knowledge
to better effect.
Be efficient.
I'll just second what Dave said.
Because we have just this
extraordinary database
of prochlorococcus
sequences from all
over the global oceans just
screaming with studies,
with things to tell us.
And it's just a huge challenge
getting it all organized
so that others can use it.
So we have time for one
more question today,
which is fantastic.
You guys didn't have to
listen to any of my questions.
So well done as an audience.
Go for it.
So my question is about
the COVID-19 research.
I'm curious.
I think it's Lydia
Bourguiba's lab
that showed a real
correspondences between humidity
in the immediate environment
and COVID transmission
and that in tropical
locations, it's
when the humidity goes
above a certain point that
COVID transmission increases.
And in climates
like ours, it's when
we start to spend a
lot of time in dry heat
in the winter that COVID
transmission increases.
I was really struck by your
mapping of flood zones and heat
zones with COVID.
And I'm curious if that is--
if there's any
collaboration there?
If that's another factor,
and if that sort of humidity
might be another
interventional lever that we
could use in public health?
Absolutely that's
a terrific point.
And thank you for highlighting
that research within MIT
as well.
It's something we haven't
published the flood risk
paper yet, the flood
risk version of this,
but something that was really
significant in type of building
was basement use.
Where are people
living in basements?
It's a huge vulnerability.
I mean, you can
understand for flood risk.
Obviously, we've seen
that in New York City
before with some of
the major storms.
But then also with COVID risk.
And so humidity might be one of
the factors where again, where
are people living
in crowded spaces,
rental spaces with
suboptimal urban conditions.
And then how is that
increasing the compound risk
or the compound vulnerability.
A great point.
Thank you.
Thank you guys very much.
Thank you for being here.
You have 20 minutes to
make your way back over.
So thank you, guys.
[APPLAUSE]