An autonomous underwater vehicle is
basically like a drone. So the operating
environment is a little complex as
compared to uh surface vehicles and
aerial drones. But over the last few
years we are using new technological
advancements like 3D printing and high
power embedded computers to build
vehicles that are at a lower cost and
micro vehicles as compared to large
AUVs. So we can eventually use them in
swarms instead of just using one vehicle
for a specific mission. There are many
advantages for that. If you want a
monitor underneath a large ice shelf,
instead of using a single vehicle where
you can get a single measurement of a
single track, now you can use a network
of AUVs where you can get the temporal
and special variation of multiple areas
at the same time. So we can get more
information using a swarm instead of
using a single vehicle.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.