What if a material could mimic the properties
of living tissue, hold vast amounts of water,
and help solve some of the planet's biggest
challenges? Meet hydrogels, soft, flexible,
water-rich materials that are quietly shaping the
future of medicine, technology, and environmental
sustainability. A hydrogel is, you can think of
it as a molecular net that likes to capture water.
And it's an interesting material because it's
not quite a solid and not quite a liquid,
but molecules interface with it as if it's
a liquid. Hydrogels are networks of polymer
chains that can absorb and retain extraordinary
amounts of water, sometimes up to 99% of their
weight. This gives them a unique blend
of softness and strength, making them
behave more like living tissue than traditional
materials. In healthcare, hydrogels are making
the leap from the lab bench to the human body.
Conventional hydrogels have been widely used
in biomedical applications such as scaffolds
for tissue engineering, organ regeneration,
and carriers for drug release. Used in wound
dressings, these materials can speed up healing
by maintaining a moist, protective environment.
Others are being designed to mimic soft tissues,
stretching and flexing with the body in ways
rigid implants never could. So we call this a new
field that we pioneered hydrogel bio electronics.
Traditional implantable materials such as metals,
ceramics always form this kind of scar tissues
on the interface. Hydrogels, especially adhesive
hydrogels, can eliminate the scar tissues. When
scar tissue forms, it can stiffen and thicken
the surrounding area, reducing flexibility and
disrupting the delicate structures of organs.
It can also interfere with the performance
of implanted devices. Because these soft
biocompatible devices mimic the mechanical and
physiological properties of biological tissues,
they can remain in place for months or even years.
Beyond medicine, hydrogels are helping to address
some of the planet's most pressing resource
challenges. In agriculture, they're being used
to improve water retention in dry soils, reducing
the need for irrigation, and helping crops survive
in increasingly unpredictable climates. Farmers
for more than a thousand years, they could tell
just from the coloration of the leaves that there
were problems during growth. Maybe that there
was insufficient watering or maybe the fertilizer
wasn't applied or there's a bacteria or a fungus.
The problem is even today that information gets
the farmers far too too late. What we're doing is
we're making a whole new generation of sensors
that can be interfaced to the plant and get
that information within minutes, sometimes even
seconds. These sensors made of hydrogels gently
penetrate plant tissues without triggering immune
responses or stress, giving farmers a new window
into crop health. And when it comes to clean
water, hydrogels are also playing an important
role. So an example application that we've been
really excited about is harvesting water from air.
Hydrogels have been particularly interesting
because when you tailor these hydrogels with
salts in particular, it can actually get a lot of
the water vapor even in these very aid climates
to be attracted to this hydrogel. These materials
can absorb water at night, then release it during
the day, requiring no electricity, just sunlight.
In this case, you can apply heat and you can use
a relatively low amount of energy to then release
the water from this hydrogel matrix and actually
get your clean drinking water. The exciting thing
about hydrogels is the ability to scale these
materials. Right now, we're working on these
prototypes in the lab. So a really important
next step is being able to take these hydrogels,
being able to develop them in a way to now make
tons of this type of material and integrate them
effectively into now more manufacturable systems.
Researchers at MIT have played a leading role in
advancing hydrogel research. Across the institute,
many groups are now exploring applications
ranging from self-repairing materials that capture
atmospheric carbon and methane systems that filter
micro pollutants from water to hydrogels that
could inspire the next generation of sustainable
heating and cooling systems for the home.