Hello everyone. I'm uh Karn Kaship. Uh
I'm a undergrad and graduate school alum
from uh computer science department at
MIT. So Posh is a vertical AI company.
We focus on the financial services uh uh
segment of the market and we've
developed a pretty comprehensive AI
platform. Uh we develop multiple
different solutions for financial
services organizations. Today I'm going
to highlight a couple of our solutions.
One is a AI powered knowledge management
system. The other is an AI powered help
center. The knowledge management system
is for employees. The help center is for
customers or potential customers. So the
uh challenges that we often see working
with a lot of our our uh bank and
financial services customers. They have
a lot of uh issues with um uh employee
retention and knowledge retention.
There's constant uh turnover whether
it's frontline staff or even uh back
office staff. Uh retaining employees,
hiring employees is a challenge. Um we
see continuing elevation of customer
experience. You know, historically, it
was okay for a bank to have, you know,
not great customer experience. Uh, today
it's no longer about the bank that
you're competing with down the street.
It's about, you know, the the next
generation fintech companies or the
experiences customers are having with
Amazon and Uber and other uh companies
as well. Um, and lastly, you know, we've
seen a lot of attempts at self-service
and financial services. Uh, those have
all been kind of the previous generation
of self-service tools. So, non AI power,
non-personalized. Uh, and we think that
self-service is still very promising,
just the way that you do it has to be
modernized. So um one of the things that
we're really targeting that's really
rampant across financial services
organizations is legacy search or
keyword search. You know whether it's
internal knowledge, customer knowledge,
there's a lot of unstructured
information, but it's not really
accessed in an intelligent way. Um so
the first one we're going to talk about
today is our uh AI powered knowledge
management system. Uh using AI to not
only uh provide better answers based on
documentation, but also using AI to
actually help uh author documentation,
analyze documentation against regulatory
compliant sources. So if regulations
change, can we quickly use an AI agent
to analyze against your policies and
procedures and flag if something is now
non-compliant within your policy or
procedure base? Right? So this is an
example of uh the the experience of the
tool. Here you can see a user can ask a
natural language question just like you
might with the chat GPT. Uh we site
source documentation. We uh actually uh
open up the source documentation and
allow you to actually see uh the chunks
or segments within the documents where
the um answer was actually pulled from.
So, you can see here automatic scrolling
and highlighting of that information.
Um, we also allow for the ability to ask
uh follow-up questions in a
conversational manner. So, if you want
to dig into a particular question, can
you um you know ask ask a more detailed
question. This is good for new hires who
don't know how to ask the right
question, you know, instead of having to
try over and over, you can just clarify
what you meant really have a
conversation with the knowledge. So a
lot of this stuff I mean it's it's
pretty obvious that tools like chagbt
can be powerful but uh we're bringing
this into an agentic application even
for the management side of knowledge uh
regulatory compliance checks document
authoring and maintenance and so forth.
So um on the customerf facing side let's
pivot there. Um you can see an example
here. This is a a virtual assistant that
we have with a bank here in New England.
Um so it's you know kind of powered by
uh more LLM and Agentic applications as
well. But I want to show you our uh
customerf facing help center solution.
So very similar to what you saw on the
employee side, but uh a lot of our
customers have search bars on their
websites, in their mobile applications,
digital banking applications. And
typically when people use search bars,
they don't get an answer. They get a
bunch of results back and the results
are usually very annoying to have to go
through and there's no guarantee that
the answer you want's even in the
results. So we see with our customers a
lot of lost revenue opportunities and a
lot of frustration because a customer
doesn't know how to navigate a very
extensive complicated website. So just
like we're doing with the employee base,
we're also bringing it in a customerf
facing lens uh with call to actions with
uh suggested actions as well. So taking
them directly to an application form for
example um or a scheduling tool if they
want. So uh we have a lot of different
products. I I just covered a couple of
them today. Some things that we're
working on right now that are not uh
public on our website, we're working on
uh AI simulation training. So actually
having AI avatars that simulate the
customer uh and letting uh call center
agents, collections officers, loan
officers actually have conversations
with uh simulated customers before they
actually deploy into the field for
example. So um we're looking for you
know design partners for new things that
we're working on. We're looking for uh
existing organizations uh domestically,
globally especially if you're in
financial services or tangential
industries who are looking for uh some
of the solutions like what I showed
today. But uh open to any questions. Uh
hopefully this was a good overview of
Posh.
Hi. Um I'm from the insurance industry.
Do you have any uh use case there? Yeah.
So um you know same stuff that I talked
about. Uh you know we're building uh
knowledge management, customer help
center, uh AI simulation for training.
Um a lot of those use cases we've
designed it for industries that have uh
uh GRC requirements. So uh governance
regulatory control uh requirements and
compliance requirements. Insurance is
definitely uh part of that financial
services umbrella for us.
One over there. You have to build a
database or Oh, I'm sorry. Do you have
to build a knowledge base or a database
for every industry you go into
presumably? So that insurance might be
different than from healthcare or
something else. Do you participate in
all those industries by the way? And
then what's the ramp up time to get into
a new industry? Yeah, exactly. So that's
why we we've gone vertical. we're we're
just focusing on financial services um
for that reason. Um so we've done a lot
of domain specific work for financial
services. So for us that's like banking,
wealth management, fintech insurance,
that's kind of what we consider
financial services. Um but from when we
onboard a customer, uh the customer's
knowledge also has to be a big part of
these conversational applications. So a
lot of what we've done is not just
making the knowledge easy to access in a
conversational tool, but also building
aic workflows on the back end to make
the knowledge management easier on the
on the on the organization as well.
Right. To adapt to each organization
you're going. Yeah. Exactly. Right.
Okay. Thanks. Thank you, Karen. Thanks
very much. Thank you.