Now, I'd like to turn it back over to my
colleague Eduardo, our our fearless
webinar host, who will close us out for
today. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Tricia. Before we close this
webinar, we like to remind you about the
upcoming conferences on Friday, November
14, 2020 MIT Madrid symposium on
November 18 and 19, the 2025 MIT
Research and Development Conferences uh
conference and also the upcoming
webinars, the MIT Startup Exchange
December 2025 demo day on December 10
and the Quantum at the turning point
webinar.
on December 11. If it works for you,
please answer the survey. Thanks for
joining this webinar today. I hope you
enjoyed it. Have a great rest of the
day. Goodbye.