[APPLAUSE]
Good morning, everyone.
And welcome to MIT Human Insight
Collaborative's annual event.
I'm Anantha Chandrakasan,
MIT's provost.
And it is great to see
all of you here today.
This is going to
be an exciting day.
MITHIC is about
inspiring our community
to think differently and
work together in new ways.
It's about embedding
human-centered thinking
throughout our research,
innovation, and education.
What you'll see today
is that one year
in, MITHIC is off
to a strong start,
advancing work across
the institute that
broadens our perspectives
on global challenges.
After the keynote address
this morning from Sloan Dean,
Rick Locke will have two morning
sessions and two afternoon
sessions.
These sessions will
highlight the remarkable work
sparked or supported by MITHIC.
MITHIC is supporting efforts
like the Compass Initiative,
which you'll hear about
in a little while.
Led by Professor Lily Tsai,
the Compass Initiative
is helping our students
grapple with questions
that don't come
with simple answers,
questions like,
what do we value?
What are our obligations
to each other?
MITHIC is already
complementing the work
of other strategic initiatives,
such as the MIT Generative
Impact Consortium.
You'll hear this afternoon
about the ethical deployment
of artificial intelligence
for healthcare applications,
and the fascinating
work at the intersection
of AI and anthropology.
Along with other
projects that will
be discussed in
today's sessions,
you'll get a clear
sense of MITHIC's impact
that cuts across
disciplines and departments.
When the program wraps up at two
o'clock, we'll have a reception.
I hope you'll stick around and
continue the conversation there.
I particularly want to thank the
MITHIC team for their hard work
to pull this day
together, the faculty
lead Keeril Makan and staff
members Jen Altan and Elena
Nosiglia.
[APPLAUSE]
I also want to thank the team
in the Office of Innovation
and Strategy, which support
all strategic initiatives.
MITHIC and other
strategic initiatives
would not be possible without
the incredible support
and leadership of
President Sally Kornbluth.
It is really her vision of
what we can accomplish when we
unite our strengths together.
And with that, it is
my distinct privilege
to welcome on stage,
President Kornbluth.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks, Anantha.
I'm actually really excited
to see everyone here.
This is fantastic.
And Anantha gave a bunch of
thank yous, which I will echo.
And of course, I have to add to
that a big thank you to Anantha
for all his work and support.
So MITHIC is actually the first
of our truly Institute-wide
initiatives or collaboratives.
And when we launched
MITHIC last fall,
I had talked a lot about
doing big things together.
And I believe that this
is even more important now
than it was earlier.
Because of a suite of
federal actions, which
I know you're all aware of,
universities across the country
are navigating a difficult and
constantly changing landscape.
And at MIT, we are
doing everything
we can to stay the course.
And I believe that
our best response
to these ongoing challenges
is to just simply keep
doing our very best work.
MITHIC and all of the
presidential initiatives
are a vital part of our
strategy to advance excellence
within and across
high-impact fields
from health care, climate,
education, AI, manufacturing,
quantum.
And over the past year,
MITHIC has opened up
an incredible range
of opportunities
for faculty and students
to ask new questions
and arrive at better,
bolder, and more nuanced
answers grounded in the
wisdom of humanities, arts,
and social sciences.
MITHIC also serves
as an inspiration
to a new generation of
philanthropists, alumni,
and friends who want to
join our efforts to drive
new and unexpected
collaborations, the ones that
spark ideas and
solutions that would not
have come about otherwise.
And clearly, this strategy
is beginning to work.
Last fall, we received 89
submissions in response
to our initial call
for MITHIC proposals.
Thanks to support from
alumni friends, all five
schools and the college, we
funded 31 projects representing
22 units across MIT.
And ingenious ideas for research
under the MITHIC umbrella
have continued to flow.
We put out a second call in
September and received nearly 80
more proposals,
which are now being
reviewed for funding in 2026.
And as we keep raising money,
we hope that funding rate
will continue to go up.
The enthusiastic response
shows that there's
an immense desire across
MIT for pioneering research
that blurs the boundaries
between disciplines
and spurs exciting
new collaborations.
So let me just
highlight one example--
and you'll be hearing
about many today--
the Living Climate Futures Lab.
As you'll hear
today, this lab works
with people and communities
from Massachusetts to Mongolia
who are grappling with
the impacts of climate
change on their daily lives,
on health and food insecurity,
and housing and on jobs.
The lab brings together
environmental scientists
and engineers with
anthropologists, urban planners,
historians, experts in
Indigenous research methods,
and artists.
This amazing array of
knowledge and experience
reflects a very MIT attitude.
If we're hot on the trail of
an important and interesting
problem, we will gladly
ignore all the fences
that typically keep
academic disciplines apart.
Like all of the projects that
are being supported by MITHIC,
the Living Climate
Futures Lab also
embodies MIT's singular brand
of excellence-- collaborative,
hands on, and deeply relevant
to the world and the people
around us.
Before I close, I want to
echo again some of the thanks.
The faculty leaders
who have envisioned
the enormous potential
of elevating the human
centered fields at MIT.
I mentioned Anantha,
but I also have
to mention our Dean
Chastain, Agustín Rao,
and the associate dean
and founding faculty
lead, Carol Macon.
And after all this time, I
think I'm finally pronouncing
your name correctly.
Maybe I can mangle
it a few more times.
But I think I got that right.
And I also want to thank
all of you who are here
to celebrate MIT excellence
across the full spectrum
of human wisdom.
So, speaking of
wisdom, I now want
to introduce you to our
keynote speaker, Rick Locke.
He's the John C Head III
Dean of the MIT Sloan
School of Management.
And actually, I would
defy any school,
anywhere to have the dean
of the School of Management
giving the keynote address at
a humanities collaborative.
I think that is
really emblematic
of the interdisciplinary nature
and the institute-wide nature
of this initiative.
Rick's wide ranging
experience and accomplishments
include serving as the
dean of Apple University,
the provost of Brown
University, and advisor
to organizations from Nike to
the US Department of Labor.
But he began his career at
MIT, earning his doctorate here
and heading up the Department
of Political Science.
Now I've come to know Rick.
And, actually, I knew
Rick for a very long time
because we were both
provosts at the same time.
And I think we met
every week during COVID
to talk about important
things like masking.
So, we've had a lot
of conversations.
He's always impressed me with
his intellectual breadth, way
beyond COVID maneuvers
and fresh ideas.
He'll speak to us today
about the human side
of the enterprise-- the
human side of enterprise.
And then he'll sit down
for a chat with Dean Rao.
So please join me in welcoming
back to MIT, Rick Locke.
[APPLAUSE]
Good morning, everyone.
And thank you, Sally, for
that nice introduction.
Thank you all for inviting
me to speak with you today.
It's a genuine honor to be here
to see some familiar faces,
but also to meet
some new people.
Today, what I'd like
to do is share with you
some early reflections on the
future of management education.
And what I'm going to do
is divide my brief remarks
into three parts.
First, what I'd like
to do is describe
how this is a pivotal moment
for the world of business,
and as a result, for
management education,
given some significant
challenges under way.
Second, as the still
relatively new Dean
of the MIT Sloan
School of Management,
I'd like to offer some thoughts
on how MIT Sloan, by becoming
even more embedded
in the MIT ecosystem,
can lead in addressing
some of these challenges
and in reinventing
management education.
And finally, I'd like to
provide an example of how
we can collectively, all of
us, do this exciting work
by discussing the challenges,
but also the opportunities posed
by generative AI,
and how bringing back
the human side of
enterprise is key to how
we manage this moment.
So let me begin with
the challenges, which
are also opportunities.
In recent years, the context
within which business
has been operating for decades
has changed in significant ways.
Now I'm going to present a
highly stylized description
of that context and
the changes underway.
The reality, of course, is
that's much, much more nuanced.
But let me just give you the
less nuanced portrait of things.
Over the last several
decades, business
has operated in a
more or less flat
world where geopolitical
and cultural differences
across countries and
regions were eroding.
A world in which innovations
and communications, logistics,
design, and the spread
of global supply chains
allowed firms to produce more or
less anything anywhere, usually
driven by low input
and labor costs,
and then sell their
products or services
across the globe in
an array of markets
with little concern for
trade restrictions, tariffs,
cultural barriers, or even
the true cost of externalities
like carbon emissions.
Again, this is a very
highly stylized description
of the context.
The world was never as flat as
Thomas Friedman once argued.
It was always much more lumpy.
But the assumption that we were
living in a globalized world
with a more or less
friction-less flow of capital,
of products, of
people, of services,
was one that was shared by many
business and political leaders.
This model of business has
been challenged in recent years
by a variety of
forces, including
the rise of geopolitical
tensions between countries.
And we can talk about
the US and China.
But of course,
it's more than just
those two countries
that have led
to the rise of trade barriers
and the reconfiguration,
or even diversification
of global supply chains.
Now that reconfiguration
of supply chains
happened before
the current moment.
It happened during the
first Trump administration.
It happened because
companies were
thinking about their
global carbon footprint.
It happened because of
the pandemic and the need
to have more resilient
supply chains.
But recent efforts have really
accelerated this process
of trying to reconfigure
and change global trade
and commerce.
The second pressure,
and this is one
that we don't talk
about as much but I
think is equally important, is
the reemergence of regulation,
not just in the EU but in
the US, in different states
and in other countries, as well.
Think about the Digital Services
Act or the Digital Markets Act
and what that has done for
especially the digital economy.
This is shaping how companies
make and sell their products
and services around the globe.
Third, there's a
growing awareness--
and I think this is a good
thing-- and concern over climate
change and its
impact on society,
and thus the need to develop
low carbon products and business
practices, business
models in the near future.
Fourth, there are these
emergences of and maturity.
Or maybe not maturity,
but evolution
of disruptive new
technologies like AI
that will impact
existing business
models, work arrangements,
and employment patterns.
And finally, there are changing
employee attitudes towards work,
towards work life
balance, and expectations
they have of their employers.
These and other
challenges threaten
to up-end existing business
models and management practices
in the US and around the world.
I believe that we are
in a pivotal moment
when individual firms and
even entire industries
need to rethink their business
models and ways of operating
in the world.
And there is no clear,
already established path
for them to follow.
In enterprises across
the world, leaders
are trying to figure
out how to operate
in a more regulated and
politicized environment.
How to reduce carbon
emissions while still making
innovative products and taking
advantage of their globally
dispersed suppliers
and customers.
How to manage a workforce
with new demands
and new expectations.
And how to integrate the promise
and potential of generative AI
into existing and future product
services and business models
in ways that will increase their
company's competitive value
and not undermine it.
And the sad truth is that
most management schools,
business schools, cannot guide
these leaders since we, too,
are stuck in the past.
To be completely frank, most
management business schools
have been teaching
the same material
in the same way for
decades, not adapting
our models, our frameworks,
and our theoretical approaches
to the dramatic changes
underway in the world.
And the students know it.
And so do their
future employers.
Now, I don't expect
this crowd to be
a regular reader of a magazine
called Poets and Quants.
This is a magazine that
talks about business schools.
But last late July, an article
came out in Poets and Quants
basically quoting all these
business school students
at Graduate School of
Business at Stanford,
where the students
were basically saying,
we're not learning anything.
We're not learning any skills.
About a month ago, a similar
article in the same magazine
came out about Wharton,
where they basically
argued the same thing.
These professors are
teaching the same things
that they've been
teaching for decades.
We're not learning
any new skills.
Now I was, as the
new Dean of Sloan,
greatly relieved that they were
writing about others and not
about us.
But the fact is, they could
have been writing about us.
This is an industry problem.
This is not a school or
particular university problem.
And this is something that
we have to take on head-on.
But I believe that these
and other broad challenges
create exciting
opportunities for MIT Sloan
to build on and expand
its unique assets,
to play a leadership role in
addressing these challenges,
and in the process, reinvigorate
management education, management
research, and practice.
Now, I know this sounds
like a sales job.
But I really, actually,
really believe it.
So why Sloan?
Why do I think this is such a
great moment for MIT and MIT
Sloan?
And I believe it's because we
possess several amazing assets.
The first is that
we have a world
class, research-oriented
faculty, many of them already
working on some of the
important issues of the day,
whether it's health or climate
or advanced manufacturing,
or the future of work or GenAI
or any of the other key issues.
We have people already
working and collaborating
across the university
on these issues.
We have amazing faculty,
incredible students,
and an incredibly dedicated
professional staff.
And our curriculum
has traditionally
blended theory and
practice, hand in mind,
which is exactly
how adults learn.
So we have these incredible
assets in our people
and in the curriculum
that we have already.
Secondly, and this is the most
important asset I think we have,
is our embeddedness in MIT
and in the MIT ecosystem.
Across this great
university, colleagues
are conducting
cutting edge research
on some of the key challenges I
described earlier, whether it's
climate change, health care,
advanced manufacturing,
generative AI, and so much more,
by becoming even more embedded
in this ecosystem.
And what does that mean?
What it means is more
collaborative research,
more collaborative teaching.
Between Sloan and the
rest of the institute,
I believe that MIT Sloan can
help translate innovations
in these and other areas
into new enterprises,
into new business models,
into new policies,
into new ways of thinking about
the world and the economy.
This is Sloan's role
in the MIT ecosystem,
is to play that translational
management role.
And let me just
elaborate on this.
As I said, MIT's Sloan
faculty already very
actively involved in many of
the presidential initiatives.
When I think about the GenAI
or climate, even MITHIC,
we have Sloan faculty who are
involved in either the steering
committees or
co-leading these things.
And this is great.
This is a way that we're
bringing people together.
But we can do so much more.
And the way that I think about
this is, how can MIT Sloan lower
the barriers so that students
from all over the institute
can take our courses,
maybe even earn a degree?
How can MIT Sloan
begin to develop
with other parts of MIT
cutting-edge certificate
programs or other
courses of study
where we're bringing together
people from engineering
and science and
humanities with Sloan
to actually address some
of these big issues?
I think there's so
much that we can do,
which is not only
good for MIT, but it's
a way of really reimagining
management education
and management research.
Now when I think
about this, I think
about increasing MIT'S Sloan's
embeddedness within MIT means
more than simply deepening the
ties between, say, the technical
and the commercial
sides of campus.
It also requires that MIT
Sloan work more closely
with colleagues in SHASS and
reinvigorate its long standing
tradition focused on the
human side of enterprise.
As many in this room
may or may not know,
MIT Sloan has a long and
distinguished history
of focusing on the human
dimensions of business.
In its early days during
the post-war boom,
the US enterprise,
as US enterprises
were growing and
trying to figure out
how best to engage and
motivate their employees,
Sloan Professor Douglas
McGregor published
an important book called The
Human Side of Enterprise.
It was published in 1959.
And in that book, McGregor
outlined Theory X and Theory Y,
opposing theories
describing why people work
and how they should be managed.
Theory X assumes that workers
are inherently unmotivated.
And this leads to a
top-down style of management
based on compliance
and a mix of carrots
and sticks to reward
or to punish employees.
Theory Y, on the
other hand, assumes
that employees are intrinsically
motivated to do their best work
and to contribute to the
organizations that employ them.
This leads to a very
different management style,
one that empowers
workers, that gives them
greater discretion
over their jobs,
and cultivates higher
levels of engagement.
McGregor was only one of a
long list of MIT Sloan faculty
who worked on this more
human-centric approach
to management.
And I think of the
work of Lotte Bailyn
or Ed Schein on organizational
culture, or of Tom Kochan,
Bob McKenzie, and Paul
Osterman on what they called
high performance work systems.
They fall clearly
in this tradition.
I see my own research on labor
standards and global supply
chains following this tradition.
And faculty and students
in what Sloan now
calls the Work in
Organizational Studies group,
continue this important
line of research,
as do our colleagues at the
MIT Leadership Center, which
is also based on Sloan.
And so for Sloan to deepen and
expand and expand this work,
we need to increase
our collaboration
with colleagues in SHASS
and across the institute.
And this is why MITHIC
is so important for MIT,
but also so important
for MIT Sloan.
I believe that tapping into all,
every part of MIT, everything
that has MIT to offer, would
help MIT Sloan chart the future
to shape how new
technologies like AI
will reconfigure
industries and careers,
how new enterprises
will be created and run,
how individuals
will work and live,
how business practices will
become more sustainable,
and how national economies
will develop and adapt.
It's an incredibly exciting
time to be at MIT--
to be back at MIT.
So let me illustrate--
And I'm almost done.
Let me illustrate how we can
together do this important work
by highlighting some important
research on GenAI that
is already taking place at
both MIT and at MIT Sloan.
Now as you all know,
Americans today
are both ambivalent
and anxious about AI
and its impact on their
jobs, on the economy,
and on society as a whole.
Many see opportunity.
62% of respondents in
a recent Gallup survey
believe that AI will
increase productivity.
53% believe that it will
lead to economic growth.
But still, 61% of respondents
in this Gallup survey
think that AI will destroy
more jobs than it will create.
And nearly half, 47%
of the respondents,
think that it will
destroy more businesses
than it will recreate.
These are real concerns
from an anxious population
voiced at a time of great
economic and political
uncertainty.
This is a critical moment,
with enormous consequences
for the workforce, for
organizations, and for humanity.
And as the latest generation
of artificial intelligence
leaves its nascent phase, we
are confronted with a choice
about which path to take.
Will we deploy AI to
eliminate millions
of jobs across the economy?
Or will we use it to
empower the workforce
and enhance our
human capabilities?
Fortunately, colleagues
at MIT and MIT Sloan
are already doing important
work to show the viability
of the second path.
For example, in their 2023
book, Power and Progress,
Daron Acemoglu and
Simon Johnson argue
for recharting the
course of this technology
so that it promotes shared
prosperity and complements
rather than substitutes
for the work of humans.
Writing later with another
MIT colleague, David Autor,
the pair argue that the
direction of AI development
is a choice, and argue
that leaders and educators
must choose a path of
machines in service of minds.
But what does this mean in the
context of today's workforce
and workplace?
How do we create
organizations and paths
that travel this human
centric, worker friendly path?
Part of the answer
lies in research
from MIT Sloan Professor
Roberto Rigobon
and postdoctoral
researcher Isabella Loaiza.
These scholars analyzed 19,000
tasks across 950 job types
and found five human
capabilities that are increasing
in value as AI advances.
These are empathy, presence,
opinion, creativity, and hope.
This Epic framework points us
on a path towards upskilling
workers, with a
focus on what they
call the fundamental
qualities of human nature.
These are simply a
few of the examples
of the exciting and important
work taking place across MIT.
There's so much more
work taking place,
but work that allows
us to see the choice
and begin to imagine how we
take that second choice that
enhances our humanity
and empowers people.
This work suggests that job
loss and de-skilling are not
inevitable outcomes
in this new era of AI.
From Theory X and
Theory Y to Rigobon
and Loaiza's important work--
I've now lost my notes--
I'll find them.
Here it is.
Insightful, epic framework to
the new educational paradigms
made possible through
initiatives like universal AI
that was recently released
by the MIT Open Learning
Initiative.
MIT and MIT Sloan have a history
of charting and paving pathways
to an exciting and
productive future of work
that not only includes
humans, but makes
the most of our humanity.
Together, we can
invent this future.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]