all right well welcome everyone um it's
nice to see you and it's uh I'm sure and
that we'll hear I hope from the people
who are joining us on Zoom this morning
um the title of my talk is an updated
perspective on gwi Association studies
um I do want to get into some
fundamentals of um the study design and
methodology behind a genomite
Association study but I'm going to um
wrap up the the primer lecture on uh
showcasing a modern genomite Association
study one that was just published a
couple months ago and and really
showcases the power of this singular
tool in um human genetics and genetic
epidemiology um and then I'll I'll I'll
I'll wrap up with a um with a a very
short vignette on how we can leverage
the results of many different genomite
associations studies to try to
understand some fundamental um aspects
of of a particular um trait or
disease so um genomite Association
studies um leverage a fundamental
Concept in genetic epidemiology called
heritability um heritability is a
statistic um on a disease or a trait um
that estimates the degree of variation
in the in this trait in a pop population
that is due to genetic variation between
individuals in that population um there
are many ways to estimate heritability
um I've listed a couple of the most
common uh techniques um we can compare
individual phenotypic variation among
related individuals in a population um
if you have a a study design um of a
nuclear family for example you know
expected uh um uh trait U Co ices
between the individuals and the families
based on the amount of uh the uh the
genetic uh the DNA that's been inherit
inherited um um through the pedigree um
you can also estimate heritability by
estim examining the association between
individual genotype and genotype data um
and by modeling summ summary level data
from genom Association studies so um you
only really perform a genom Association
study on a trait that is heritable um um
as you know the the purpose of a
genomite Association study is to um
discover particular genetic variants
that are associated with your outcome um
and if a trait has no heritability then
uh perhaps you would go looking other
epidemiological methods to find the
relationships between that trait and
other things other risk factors not
genetic risk factors
um the another fundamental principle of
um genomite Association studies is the
this idea of genetic architecture of
human diseases and complex traits now a
genetic architecture of a trait um is a
is comprised of the number of genetic
Losi that are associated with um that
trait their frequencies if being common
low frequency are rare and then their
effects and the strong strong or weak so
this this um graphic that I have up here
is is from a 2008 review um in nature
reviews genetics that showcases that
when you have a very rare variant with
high penetrants those are the type of V
variants that are studied in rare
disease genetics um whereas in um
genomewide Association studies uh We've
most of the variants that are discovered
are common frequency and uh low effect
may I ask a question about that abely
yes um in that bottom leftand corner are
there really cases where the the VAP is
very low with uh weak effects or is that
just we're filling up the entire space
with the bubble um you mean that the
hard to identify genetically section
well back in 2008 um the tech the abil
our ability to um uh find genetic
variants with ver that were so rare um
in the for the purpose of genomite
Association studies was very limited um
so I would say that um nowadays we have
a much better um ability to identify
variants that are very rare that have
low effect because we have um in many
cases whole genome sequence Association
studies that are being performed so
cohorts with with um full uh spectrum of
genetic variation du to the the fact
that the technique of whole genome
sequencing has been um um performed on
the
samples um
so I would and I'll say another bit is
statistical power which I'll talk about
a little bit I will play a role in being
able to identify genetic variants that
are very rare with low and mod moderate
effects um so extremely large sample
sizes would be necessary in that case
are there any other
questions all right so the purpose of a
genomite Association study on a
particular trait is to dis discover or
Define the genetic architecture of that
trait in the particular um with with the
data sets that you have
available the generated genotypes
Etc so we um most commonly or
traditionally the genomite association
study tests this common disease common
variant
hypothesis um so uh gas were developed
for variants that were of some level of
frequency of high enough frequency in
the human population to have been put on
this
technical um product called the
genotyping array um and simply we've got
um single nucleotide polymorphisms Snips
which now have um we have the ability to
um read out um gen IC variation that is
more than just a a a a coding change but
that might span many uh from you know to
be a deletion of an alal or a variant um
or or be a a substitution so so nowadays
we have a the ability to U see much more
sophisticated um alic variance variation
than just single nucleotide poly
polymorphisms
but uh generally we we in the situ we
have an alil A Place In The genome where
there is a change um and the leil has a
kind of a observed frequency in the
sample in the population that you're
studying and our hypothesis is asking
the question you know is the presence of
this nippol Associated or correlated
with our disease and trait so C alil
being perhaps I think the example that I
have circled here with the 25% frequency
in this certain population we want to
know if the C Al is associated with the
trait we generally want to just scan the
genome and at every alil where
there's there's a you know a variant
observed um asked this question so we're
going to be performing a statistical
test at you know millions and millions
of places along the genome but you know
us if you're going to be performing a
statistical analysis you have to um put
together a model of of the the variables
in your Association analysis and um that
requires the us as the analysts you know
studying this question to um decide how
we're going to treat the um this genetic
uh the genotypes and The alals observed
at this particular location how are we
going to code them for our numerical
analysis so that um uh where as as we
look for a
correlation um I'm putting up here the
three common genetic models um and uh
depiction of of what model what we we
are imposing in terms of what we're
looking for in in this um in this
statistical analysis the additive model
um is one where at this particular
location you're looking for a
correlation with or an effect of the C
alal for every individual you'll be
counting um how many Cals they have in
their genotype so an individual analysis
has either a zero one or two as the
variable value um that's used in our
analysis uh you could also model a
dominant or recessive um effect U
nowadays there are statistical tools
that allow you to do gws with um more uh
sophisticated models like a dominant
model or recessive
model
um this is one of the things where uh
after 1520 years of doing Goos I just
take for granted but um when when Doo M
Association first started there was a
question about what was the best coding
of an Al if you're doing a scan of you
know millions of alals across the human
genome um and there was some literature
that came out that um that uh
concluded that if you don't know what
the model is then the added model will
be the best you know generalized model
to use in the uh you know for these
millions of
variants any questions about this I did
build a bit of um time um here for for
us to have questions I think if you have
a question you should go to the
microphone or get get it be passed along
to you ah thank you y in the graph in
the bottom left left what's the Y AIS
right um so um think of a a like a
regression analysis where you're trying
to find a best fit um between in a
relationship between a covariant and
your outcome so um so if we were going
to um that this uh this line could uh
represent the uh um the expected change
in the trait value between people zero
or one or one and two as their kind of
value for the genotype for the AL yeah
so um I would say that this this is
maybe like an idealized model whereas in
real in for a real analysis you'd have a
scatter of lots of different points and
you're trying to do a best fit like just
a regression type analysis is there a
question from online uh yeah we had one
online if you could go back to the
figure with the effect size and the Leal
frequency
that bottom left corner Nicole was
asking about um ah yes yep that that
size of that bubble they're saying is
still probably a pretty big bubble but
we don't have the heterogen across
populations to be able to capture those
variants yeah so so yes the point is
that low frequency variants that have
slow effects are still going to be hard
to identify because um looking at the
right population or looking across many
populations um heterogeneity in the uh
the fact that the AL Leo may not exist
in some human populations and so there's
lots of sources of um heterogenity I
would say that would contribute to these
variants being hard to explore so that
sounded Blessed Like a question but
maybe a comment I appreciate that and
people who are on the on the zoom you
can feel free to fill in and you know
more comments because I'm going to keep
things at a pretty high level during
this this primer go ahead in which in
which case would you use a dominant or
recessive model over like an additive
model so like in what context is that
better I would say if you want to do a
genetic Discovery analysis um and you
want to explore the you just you want to
test the um the uh possibility of there
being genetic alals with a meres of
effect across the genome in the field of
type two diabetes uh we recently had a
paper published
showing the results of a gen a recessive
genetic a recessive model gwas at a very
large one and then so that was quite
interesting for us to find the genetic
alals that show a recessive effect but
not an an additive effect yeah so it's
just another technique in terms of the
discovery of um genetic variations and
and exploring the genetic architecture
of a trait thanks so I think if it's a
if you have if you have a hypothesis
that things could be um there could be
genetic variants under that have a
recessive model or dominant model or we
want to explore it's you know you would
just uh employ one of those statistical
tools that U model recessive effect in
Gs all right so implementing
implementing a statistical a GW
statistical tests here I think it's
really important that if you're about to
embark on performing a genomewide
Association study
um or or trying to understand a genomite
Association study that you find a good
textbook that um it starts with some
fundamentals and
biostatistics um and uh start
understanding the distribution of out
your outcome and covariates make correct
statistical modeling I would say any
genomite association study start apart
from the genetics looking at your
outcome covariant confounding you know
making sure that you understand the um
the outcome that you're studying uh and
um
are using the appropriate covariates to
control for confounding in your model
I'm not going to talk too much more
about this but um there's tons of
literature out there about um using
genetic principal components as a a
method to control for the problem of
population structure and this
uh the problem is generally stated as
there being differences in AAL
frequencies between groups in your
analysis sample that that track that are
correlated with the differences in the
trait or disease that you're studying so
um before you you employ a Goos study
the the um associations between your
outcomes and your co-variates and
understand the structure of your sample
so that you um are starting off with a a
a good epidemiological model before you
add in
the genetic variance from the
gws so y the basic question I'm just
repeating it here are the AL the
genotypes of the snip correlated with
the phenotype so for quantitative trait
quantitative traits here are some
examples height blood pressure
measurements gene expression levels
other physiological measures So within a
cohort you have um these variables
available to you um we set up a simple
regression framework and most all modern
Geno Association study methods or tools
and techniques just extend this model
and there are edge cases and there are
some pretty cool methods that are out
there but for the purpose of this primer
I want us all to just become familiar
with the the the the basic model model
that's that's being explored here so um
again if you're not familiar with a a
regression linear regression or multiple
linear regression and you want to become
more familiar with it I would I would
have you go back to some um basic
biostatistics textbooks and just um
start learning about trait variability
correlation and then regression and then
multiple
regression um so we're going to fit a
regression
best fit line like that between a trait
and a snip controlling for your
Compounders um and and if there is a
relationship the the regression estimate
which here I have represented by this
beta snip will be
nonzero um generally if there's you know
we would not expect the um uh the
regression estimate to be nonzero if
there is no association so under the
null hypothesis which is a statistical
term for no effect
um we we our estimate will um have
estimates of those variance under M
hypothesis would be zero um of course
when you're sampling they're not which
is what we're going to get into in a
couple minutes about false positives but
um for a uh snip that is associated with
your trait when your um regression
estimate is greater than zero then you
interpret that as saying the alil is
associated with higher values of the
trait and when the estimate is is less
than zero your Al is associated with i a
typo lower values of the
trait now if you have a case control
study design or a binary trait um the
the question becomes if there a
different in a frequencies between cases
and controls and then the um previous
regression framework is extended into a
logistic regression um where the out the
uh the effect estimate is an odds ratio
which is a measure of the increased or
decreased risk of this disease on a m
multiplicative scale and and the odds
ratio under where there's no effect
would it be expected to be one um so an
odds ratio greater than one it it means
that there's increased risk of disease
associated with the Al and odds ratio
less than one decreased risk of disease
associated with the
AL um when you perform a statistic iCal
test you're going to have a P value as a
result of the statistical test the
definition of a P value is a probability
so it's it's it's a chance of observing
as strong of an effect as the one you
have in front of you for that particular
variant if there is no
association um and so uh I'm getting
into some more statistical language so
if this is unfamiliar to you then I
would again uh invite you to go and
explore for um some of the fundamentals
of biostatistics but when we're um
setting up a statistical experiment we
also we we set prior to doing our
experiment a kind of a false positive
rate that we would expect to um well
that we're going to use and uh you'll
hear sometimes people saying a false
positive rate or an alpha level of 0.05
as being one that's an acceptable uh
false positive rate for a single
experiment and this means that if there
is no association between your trait and
your
outcome um if you were to go let's say
and Sample po um uh group uh create
samples in your population many
different samples of this particular
variant so maybe perform any gws in many
different groups of the people then
about 5% of these tests would have a P
value um less than 05 so so just due to
sampling variability and just Rand
Randomness you're going to get
some um results that have P value less
than your threshold of of determining
something is important but the problem
with genomite Association studies is
that multiple tests when multiple tests
are performed the probability of having
at least one false positive is greater
than Alpha it's just like a a numerical
fact if you work it all out so in we're
not doing a test of a single genetic
variant we're doing a test of millions
or hundreds of millions of of genetic
variants in this one sample that you
have for your genomite Association study
so to um um maintain an overall false
false positive rate of 05 you have to
adjust this threshold of that you're
going to um see uh decide is uh
sufficient for you to call something
statistically significant um and it's
based on the number of independent tests
being performed um so so in you know we
have this Bon Fon method for correcting
P values or adjusting adjusting a
familywise error rates in an experiment
where you're be looking at more than
just one single statistical test um
where you take your overall false
positive rate and divided by the number
of tests now there are um there's a lot
of early literature around on what
should this P value be in the case of
genom Association studies and um the the
field settled on this this number of 5
time 10us 8 which uh can be obtained in
a couple different ways but based on the
the array the genotyping array
technology available at that time um and
um correlation link equilibrium which is
another population genetics term um that
exists in the human in the the most
likely sample that were that that were
being studying at that time there were
about a million independent um regions
of the genome so 05 divided by a million
you get something around five time 10
minus 8 so this is one of the origin
stories of that significance threshold
for genomite Association studies which
is um commonly used these days um more
um in more
modern more recently um there have been
other methods of obtaining statistical
significance thresholds and sometimes
for a gen and white Association study
you'll see something like around 10
Theus 9 or 10us 11 10us 12 all justified
by trying to estimate the number of
independent tests being performed in at
in a large scale genomite Association
study we have a a quick question on line
um could we calculate the risk ratio
instead of the odds
ratio that's a great question um so
going back to the model for um a case
control study um I would say that we uh
sometimes a risk ratio could be a more
appropriate measure of
Association um but uh since we're using
a regression framework perhaps it's
easier to obtain an odds ratio from a
regression um uh the the uh the whole
the way that this whole formula works
out and you want to get to a a measure
of risk in the case of a binary outcome
you take that um the regression
coefficient for the snip the beta you um
and use it as a ex it's e to that beta
equals an odds ratio just
mathematically uh so I would say that in
genomite association studies we use odds
ratio because of the ease of calculating
it from the the regression a logistic
regression um it's a good point because
if you're studying common diseases in
epidemiology you learn that perhaps an
onth ratio is not going to be a good
approximation for a risk ratio so it's
it's a good point to keep in mind I have
another question you can use the
microphone yeah um from the previous
slide when you have the regression
equation set up yeah so is um is the
goal of the study to discover like these
beta values so would that be done
through a grid search or do we is it
just the beta for this snip so the the
solution to um I would say that it's a
it's a um standard solution for us
solving leg uh like linear regression
which is is not a grid search there's
actually a numerical solution okay um so
it's not a machine learning approach
this just kind of a um there's a a set
of formulas that would be used um to
obtain the estimate from the sample and
then the many many extensions that go
off from this it's it gets more
complicated but that's the gist of it
it's it's basically calculated from the
observations in your
sample um and uh it's there's a lot of
literature if you want to learn more
about how the regression estimates are
obtained in a multiple linear setting
okay and is y is it like we're finding
all of these betas or just the actually
fit the whole model for every snip and
uh sometimes if your model is really
complicated and this is why we have to
use more modern techniques it can take
several seconds to or like half a second
to actually get these numbers from from
your um you know the the data you have
and so when you're doing a million or
100 million or 500 million um Snips um
it can take a really long time so there
are now a number of techniques that
speed up these calculations your
estimations but I really not going to
get into that for the primer thank you
oh
sure all right so let's dive let's let's
get into some of these other can we move
quickly through some of these so I
talked about the genom significance
threshold traditionally being 5 time 10
minus
8 I'm going to get into describing well
here this is a depiction of a Manhattan
plot which uh um we often see for genom
white Association studies where a um
every point is a snip that's tested and
um on the Y AIS um we transform the P
value of that snip by taking a the
negative value of log 10 of that P and
you know that there's no reason why it's
this and not something else it's just
that uh we want a way to let uh variants
that have low P values be you know seen
easily so this this um transformation
has just was applied and has worked
really well for us um so you have this
early type two diabetes um um GW you
have a a region on chromosome 10 which
had where you see a number of genetic
variants with low P values these are all
in the same Locust they're correlated
with linkage distin liberium in in that
area which is I think I said earlier a
population genetics term um but you can
see how
the um the places of statistical
significance Rise Above the Rest that
they look like the skyline of
Manhattan um we use quantile quantile
plots or QQ plots to um look at the
results of a genomite Association
studies to make sure that the underlying
model is good and that confounding is
well controlled um this is because that
under the null hypothesis um there is an
uh we we expect the uh so when there are
no association between a variant and
your outcome um we expect the kind of
the points in the quantal quantal plot
to follow the x equals y line here just
the way we've constructed it um I would
say nowadays we we've have very well
powerered genomite Association studies
so this was from the early days when we
did not have well-powered and by powered
I mean um statistical power or ability
to detect associations due to having a
large enough sample size
um which I'll I might get into a little
bit um finally um The genome well not
finally this is is kind of wrapping up
some of the the primer like the really
basic Tech um terms that we use um the
genetic variants that we're studying um
we we we don't really uh know if they
are the ones that are causing the
association between um our uh the um
whatever causing whatever
um I guess biological or physiological
change that impacts the your outcome of
your
phenotype um and back in the early days
of genom Association studies we were
using genotyping arrays which were
pre-made products that read out the
genotype of a particular individual at
all these different set locations and so
um maybe it was more like this uh the
the situation where the the red places
on along this strand of DNA were what we
actually had available to us in our
genotyping array
data um but the true Association here
which is kind of this blue bar or dot
figure
thing uh was the the causal variant but
it wasn't included in our genotyping
array uh thanks to a um technique called
imputation where we can leverage
sequencing data in populations to kind
of fill in the Gap because humans share
this you know very very very high
percentage of of the their genetic
sequence um we we didn't so before we
used had this imputation techniques
available to us we just had what was
available on the geny raay which meant
that we might that most likely weren't
being we were not observing any causal
variance so or or the causal variance at
a location
um and and the the reason it worked is
because of this this equilibrium which
is the
correlation um between observed alals
that are just present due to um the the
changes of of alal frequencies in human
populations we have a quick question on
the previous slide could you touch on
inflation in uh the Lambda looking at
the QQ plot um I would so and how to
interpret well I I think that may be a
little more than I want to get into
during the primer but I would say that
if you're studying in the context of you
know my Association studies if you
um look at the you know you can study
the distribution of all the variants um
in this in this way and you can of
measure
using a metric called the genomic
control measure which uh is the median
test statistic producing that that would
be somewhere in this this this
distribution you compare the observed
median test statistic to the OBS
expected median test statistic and that
basically says you know down in this
part of the
distribution um where you find the
median um that the observed median is
larger or smaller uh than what you would
expect um and that's just a key uh uh
that's a um IND indication that there
could be some modeling issues um some
undetected confounding in your um
analysis and that you should go back and
revisit often or traditionally it's been
population structure the need for um
controlling for differ in the Leal
frequencies and subpopulations in your
sample that um could be corrected
through the use of genetic principal
components but there are other uh
reasons um that could change that that
could lead you to do it different type
of
modeling all right so um we we have have
depicted here a regional plot which is a
zoomed in version of The Manhattan plot
and for most U genomite Association
studies there'll be Loi where there's an
association the authors of the study
want to say something about those
regions so they'll use a a regional plot
that depicts um U the um linkous
equilibrium stati ICS between your more
here I'll use my mouse like the index
variant this is the variant that has the
lowest B value or that you are the most
interested in and you can kind of uh
calculate pairwise link with all the
other variants and then put them on a
plot so it's it's it's a useful type of
depiction next primer if you're going to
be studying learning about eqtls the
idea of things at the regional level
will become really
important um finally here well finally
in this whole I think yeah we're gonna
go into a couple different themes next
um I'll cont I wanted to contrast the
observed genetic architecture of common
diseases and biomedical traits um this
is from a uh review in nature review
genetics from 2018 called genetic
architecture the shape of the genetic
contribution to human traits and
diseases um H so on the leftand plot
I've showing you the the I'm sharing the
um genetic architecture of type 1
diabetes versus type two diabetes um
from known at that time and you'll see
that there are quite a number of
differences in the genetic
architecture um you'll see that there
are a number of low frequency um
variants that are associated with type
one diabetes um there's this point up
here which is a
a frequent variant U that has a very
strong effect on type 1 diabetes
contrast that with a number of low
effect variant across the alal frequency
spectrum I would say that as um the
statistical Power Of Studies have
increased we actually have been able to
fill in a lot of this the variance in
this area for type two
diabetes um on the right hand side we
have vitamin D levels and L
cholesterol um you know here showcasing
that vitamin D level maybe it's a less
heritable trait there are fewer variants
associated with vitamin D level I used
in this
particular figure um and a number and
many more associated with LDL
cholesterol so a trait that you're
studying could have any any sort of
genetic architecture um you might have a
hypothesis about what the genetic archit
architecture is but um I would say the
the purpose of further genomite
Association studies on all these
different traits and outcomes is to
really kind of Define the Gen genetic
architecture of that
trait are there any
questions all right so I'm going to dive
into some some examples um back in
2010 um the there became this this sort
of celebratory depiction of of all the
genomewide association studies that were
discovered because um it was a little
slow goinging in the beginning because
we didn't realize that such that that
statistical power could be as well we
didn't realize that the effects that we
would see out come back here were going
to be so low and that the um the the
ability to detect these in a jwi
Association study um dependent on the
the size the sample size um so back in
2010 you know great we've we celebrating
we found some genetic variants that were
associated with many different types of
traits um in 2014 even better you know
it's this is good you know we're gaining
momentum and but in 2019 you know it's
it's saturated so um so many different
groups across the world are doing
genomite Association studies on so many
different traits um meta analyses are
coming you know are happening to combine
the uh many small samples into a big
meta sample and um by this time in 2019
it was pretty well establish that gomite
Association studies were successful and
were a good tool to find the genetic
variance associated with traits and
outcomes I would say it was hay at the
beginning around 2010 de there were a
lot of there's a lot of
commentary that um there's a lot of
money being spent on these Juno
Association studies and nothing was
really coming out of them
um the small effects are still maybe the
norm um so uh a lot of the things that
flow Downstream from genomite
Association studies are are now built to
take advantage or uh you use the small
effect genetic variants that are found
um in you
know in in in many different
ways all right so now I'm going to get
into an example of a modern genom
Association study this is a publication
that just came out La uh two or three
months ago um from the um million
veteran the VA million veteran program
and um this is
uh this is a group I I know many of
these investigators well and so I was
really happy to see the when when this
this big paper came out a single cohort
whereas often like I said these
metaanalyses will be performed to
combined many many different uh cohorts
into a single meta analysis but here we
have an anal um a depiction of of
2668 traits being studied um in the
million veteran program um and uh
particular analysis uh is important
because
um the entire spectrum of of uh you know
of diversity within the human or within
the United States I would say um could
be better represented in the sample from
the veterans program so overall the
number of people contributing this
analysis are six 635,000
69 it's just so cool to see
this um their particular um you know the
the traits that they're trying to use
the heritable traits that they're using
in this analysis had to do with um fee
codes which are just medical record um
codes uh or outcomes or diseases that
are um derived or um obtained from
medical record data they have laboratory
measures
Vital Statistics and then survey
questions so the the type of variable uh
the type yeah the type of variable
outcomes being studied here can can vary
and this is a good u a good example of
of a the type of data you can use as
outcomes in a genome Association
study
um let's see they
the um
this is a kind of a depiction of the
traits and the frequency of um of the
binary traits on the left um and the
sample size is available for the um for
the quantitative traits on the right and
so here I I guess I would flag that even
in a single sample studying a trait
you're not going to have the same sample
size for every trait because you are
subject to data
availability but it was really cool to
see how there's more than a thousand or
10,000 or 100,000 individuals with a
particular condition um being studied
here so uh we have
the
um Manhattan plots of their binary trait
results and then their quantitative
trait results um and then the uh on the
right hand side is is the genetic
architecture plot um where uh they've
taken the minor Al so for any variant in
the genome the minor Al is defined as
the less frequent Al and and then
plotted the effect either the beta in
the case of the um oh yeah flipped these
because I have beta up there and then
odds rati down here so um the the odds
ratio goes up with the binary traits but
the point being is that it shows how um
you can find common and rare variant
which with large effects on the um on
the uh either the the outcome on the
odds ratio scale or a trait um on a
probably some normalized scale here to
put all the traits in the same plot
you'd have to normalize the the the the
scale or the the unit of the the
betas so I mean you can see here that
that variants in that harded de region
are you know are
here um and and that really shows the
showcases the power of a genomite
Association
study okay I'm G to wrap up with one
more example um uh yeah all right so
this is our toolkit and I've gone over
most of all all of these have a little
plug for some good resources that people
could use um that are up to date a very
small vignette is analysis run by a
postdoctoral fellow in my my lab um or
actually she's now been promoted to as
instructor so magdalina svia Gonzalez
ran an analysis to to detangle the
heterogenity of hyperinsulinemia so this
is fasting insulin levels along with my
colleague Miriam udler who's also an
associate member here at the road
Institute and here um I'm G just GNA go
skip through some of the basics but our
aim here was to use the genetic approach
to elucidate or explain the mechanisms
that underly the relationship between
insulin concentrations so and
cardiovascular risk so the gist of is we
that there are many reasons for a
fasting insulin to be increased in a
person and we want to understand what
those reasons are and and we took an
approach where we we found a set of
variants ass associated with fasting
insulin we leverage the type 2 diabetes
knowledge portal which is a wonderful
resource that came out of the broad
Institute and now a you of a worldwide
success um for curating um the results
of associate genetic
analysis um but then we took traits that
were from all these other or we took
gwas results from all these other traits
and and we're going to leverage this um
concept of plat tropy um to find
similarities of in associations so this
is just a depiction of a heat map
showing the effect
of these we know these Snips are all
associated with type two di with fasting
insulin um but now we're looking at what
they're the associations are with all
these other traits and we see a place
you know a something that's kind of
different um what I'm highlighting here
is a particular variant which um has an
association with triglycerides level um
and a bunch of other traits but in an
unexpected pattern so most all the other
snips if they're associated with
triglycerides might have been a you know
associated with increased triglycerides
but this particular snip is associated
with decreased
triglycerides and Pat tropy is is
defined as a an observation of a
particular variant being associated with
many different
traits um and then there's a whole field
of of trying to understand how how that
works if it's one trait affecting
you know many traits or if the variant
through different mechanisms are
associated with these different traits
here our hypothesis is that there may be
a common mechanism so another set of
variants who with we found having some
pattern of associations across many
different traits we found that very
interesting and so we we're using this
as a a starting point for a more um
in-depth
analysis all right
so so I'm going to stop here because I
and we have a time for a few
questions and um I think then we'd wrap
up around 9:25 between 9:30 and then
people can go over to the MBT lecture hi
thank you so much um I was wondering is
it possible to bring um gwas approach to
bear on larger mutational events like
structural variants and if so how would
you do that so that that is an extension
of gomide Association studies where um
you would want to have a cohort multiple
coant where structural variants were the
alals um that were being studied so
structural variants are defined as um
insertions or deletions in the human
genome that are greater than 50 um base
pairs long so as I was mentioning
earlier in this talk that we have now
the ability to see these insertion and
deletions as um uh alals in our um in
our sequence um there's also now uh some
techniques um getting better every year
I think this is an area of really rapid
development in human genetics um to to
look for large scale uh genetic
variation and so um in the case that you
have a data set where you have
structural variant calls in a cohort you
can perform a genomite Association study
just like um that I've shown here so you
just you're just starting with a
different sort of alals but the real
challenge in the field right now is
getting these structural variant
um that uh created using the available
genetic data that you have in a sample
and there are a lot of nuances about
that um having to do with the the um
kind of the technique that uh we use
typically to get from a person's DNA
sample cut we cut it up into tiny little
pieces and then there's a you know a
process through which the the genotypes
are read out and so so that process of
cutting up the DNA uh interferes with
the detection of large scale changes um
so at a very small scale there there's
these long read sequencing techniques
that are being employed and hopefully
there'll be some impr um new methods and
new approaches that will allow um many
different cohorts that have student
typing data to leverage kind of the
maybe a reference panel of this this
long read sequencing to to kind of
impute
the long read read type structural
variance in their cohorts so just a it
an exciting extension to genomite
Association studies hello uh so one term
that I see often in ja literature is the
liability scale I wonder if you could
like comment on the idea behind
converting a trade value to the
liability scale I I
think it's a I thought about putting
something like this uh in the
heritability piece um uh because um you
can technically only calculate
heritability of a binary trait on a
liability scale um I I think it's it's
more slightly more advanced concept but
a
liability
um uh the the concept behind liability
uh U assumes that there's some
underlying distribution
above which when a threshold a person's
value for that whatever whatever
underlying trait passes some threshold
and they're going to be diseased or
there's a pathologic like there's a
there's a consequence and so there's a
lot of statistical um work to to explain
this so I'm not not going to do a very
good job on the Fly um the books that I
actually uh have you know used as
references have much better detail
explanation
um there's more to be
said about and and it really has to do
with the underlying model like the
assumptions that between um of how how
you get to this uh you know disease
status and what underlying how you can
measure the underlying causes um which
are typically unknown