Good morning, everyone.
I'm Mark Gorenberg.
I'm Chair of the MIT
Corporation and Founder
of Zetta Venture Partners.
It's a pleasure to be with
all of you here today.
I'm especially delighted
to have the honor
to welcome Yann LeCun to MIT.
Yann is the Chief AI Scientist
at Meta, professor at NYU,
and one of the true pioneers of
modern artificial intelligence.
His work on convolutional
networks and deep learning
has transformed how
machines see and learn,
and how they listen and
understand the world.
And that earned him
the Turing Award,
which is essentially the
Nobel Prize for Computing,
in 2018 alongside Geoffrey
Hinton and Yoshua Bengio.
By the way, if you
go to Wikipedia,
you'll see Yann has received
so many honors and awards
that it would take our
entire session if I
walked through them.
So I'm going to send you there.
So instead, over
the next half hour,
we'll explore some
of the foundations
of this field and
future directions
in what promises to be a
fascinating discussion.
So Yann, thank
you for being here
to open the MIT Generative AI
Impact Consortium Symposium.
A real pleasure.
So in your life, frankly,
you've always been ahead
of the conventional wisdom.
As far as I can tell,
you've always been right.
And let's talk about that a
few times in this half hour.
So, if we can go back and
start at the beginning.
So you did your PhD back in 1987
at what now is the Sorbonne.
I don't French, but in English,
it translates to "connectionist
learning models."
It essentially established
the backpropagation learning
algorithm for neural nets.
And frankly, at the
time, most people
were chasing things
like expert systems.
So what inspired
you to have the idea
and how did this
propel your career?
So maybe it's naiveté
or ignorance when I was
an undergrad, when I discovered
a little by accident that people
in the '50s and
'60s, including MIT,
actually had thought about the
problem of self-organization,
which eventually gave rise to
early ideas that machines can
learn.
And I found this
idea fascinating
because I think
biology is really
an inspiration for a lot of
engineering feats that we do.
And certainly in
nature, everything
that lives is capable of
adaptation and everything
with a nervous system can learn.
And so maybe I thought I was
not smart enough to conceive--
or that humans in
general were not
smart enough to conceive
an intelligent system,
that an intelligent system
will have to build itself,
and that's kind of what
directed me to machine learning.
And being naive and ignorant,
I didn't know that at the time,
the main approaches to AI
were not at all interested
in machine learning.
It was, as you said,
expert systems.
People basically transcribing
the knowledge of experts
into rules and facts and then
hoping this would be useful.
We're facing a little
bit of the same problem
today with LLMs where the
transcription of human knowledge
into a machine that we can
interact with or talk to now
is done through learning,
but it's still very much
a bottleneck of
transferring knowledge
from humans to machines.
So I discovered that this
was a very non-popular idea,
but I felt very strongly that
this was the right thing to do.
I had a very hard time finding
a PhD advisor because nobody
was working on this.
So I found a very nice
gentlemen, Maurice Milgram,
who said, well, you
look smart enough.
You don't need any
funding because you
have some in the country,
from my engineering school,
and he said, I can't
help you technically,
but I'll sign the papers.
Wow.
That's awesome.
So you went on to Toronto to
work with Geoffrey Hinton.
You went on to Bell
Labs, you went on to NYU.
The industry went
through the AI winter
in the '90s and into the
2000s, and then in 2013,
you joined Facebook,
created FAIR--
basically Facebook AI Research.
And changed the name
from neural nets,
effectively it became-- the
industry started to recognize it
as deep learning.
So I went back and I
watched this seminal talk
that you did at NeurIPS back
in 2016 on predictive learning,
and you moved the industry again
because the industry was really
very focused on
reinforcement learning.
And you used the
analogy of the cake,
and you move the industry to
what you term self-supervised
learning.
Can you tell us a
little bit about that?
Yeah.
Well, I think at the time,
we're talking 2016, '15,
this was just when it was pretty
clear that deep learning had
revolutionized computer
vision, speech recognition,
and it was just about to
revolutionize natural language
processing, but it was
still pretty early.
And what the industry was
using was supervised learning.
At the research level, a
lot of people believed--
for example, DeepMind was really
completely engaged in this.
They believed that the path
towards a more powerful AI
system was through
reinforcement learning.
And I never believed
in this because--
and reinforcement learning
is the main component of this
because it's incredibly
inefficient in terms
of the number of trials
that a machine has to do.
So I showed the analogy of
the cake, which actually
is a little interior to this.
This was in a symposium at
NYU that I organized in 2015
that I first showed this
thing, but I tried to brainwash
the community in 2016 with a--
Everybody loves cake.
Right.
So the analogy is that if
you think of AI intelligence
as a cake, the bulk
of the cake would
have to be self-supervised,
unsupervised learning,
predictive learning, as
I called it at the time.
And then the icing on the cake
would be supervised learning,
and then the cherry on the
cake is reinforcement learning.
You want to use reinforcement
learning as little as possible
because it's so inefficient.
You don't have a choice.
In the end, need to
have some sort of way
of correcting yourself,
but really, it
should be a last resort.
And the thing I
advertised at the time--
so this is 10 years ago, is
we should train a machine
to capture the internal
dependency of the data
without training it
for any task so that it
can represent the world.
And then on top
of this-- and that
only requires observation
from unlabeled data.
And then on top of
this, you can train
a system using the
representation learned
by the system.
You can train a system to
solve a particular task
or any particular task.
So that whole idea of
self-supervised learning,
some of us started working
on it in the 2000s,
but it was under the radar, and
the techniques we were using
were not that great at the time.
We tried to apply this--
I tried to apply this in the
late 2000s on video prediction.
So just take a video and
try to train a system
to predict what's going
to happen in the video.
And it basically didn't work.
But where it did work, beyond
our wildest expectations,
was for natural
language understanding.
So take a sequence of
symbols and then try
to predict the next symbols,
and that works really well.
Now why does it work for
text or symbol sequences
and it doesn't work for video?
And the answer is you can
never predict the word that
comes after a sequence
of words, but you
can predict a distribution
over all possible words
in a dictionary, or tokens, if
you want to call them this way.
Because there's only a
finite number of them,
so it's easy to
represent a distribution.
But when it comes to predicting
the future of a video,
there's so many plausible
futures in a video
that it's basically
impossible to represent
all of those possibilities.
If I take a video of this
room and I pan the camera
and I stop here, and I ask the
system to complete the video,
there's no way
you can figure out
what everybody looks like here,
or how many people are sitting
and what the size
of the room is.
It can certainly not predict
the texture of the ground
and things of that type.
So there are things that are
just completely unpredictable.
And if you train a system to try
to predict all those details,
you're basically killing it.
You're not-- it's
not going anywhere.
So it took us a number of years,
going back maybe five years,
five years ago, to realize
this was never going to work
and we had to invent
new techniques.
Well, so-- and self-supervised
learning, the work
that you did there, the seminal
work there with the transformer
technology paper, I mean, that's
the basis for almost all LLMs
today.
And so it's really changed
the whole industry.
And in fact, if we
fast forward to today--
so the world changed with
ChatGPT at the end of 2022,
and then you came out
with Llama in early 2023.
Now you have something like
a billion monthly users
for Meta AI based
on Llama technology,
well over a billion
downloads of Llama.
So it has really
democratized AI.
And I have a confession
to make, which
is that I was not involved in
Llama at a technical level.
This was-- the first
Llama was actually
a bit of a pirate project.
Oh, interesting.
In parallel with a more official
LLM project at Meta in late
2022--
or mid-2022.
And this was a small group of
about a dozen people in Paris
who just decided
that they wanted
to have a lightweight, efficient
LLM, and they built it.
And that became the workhorse
eventually early 2023,
and led Mark Zuckerberg to
create the GenAI organization,
which is now called Meta
Superintelligence Lab,
to basically productize it.
But at a technical
level, I personally
had very little to do with it.
But it is always the skunk
works that emerges anyway.
Oh, absolutely.
And the CapEx that's going
in by these big companies now
is 323 billion I think this
year, about the top four
companies, including Meta.
Yet even with all
that success, you've
said that LLMs are effectively--
I'll paraphrase, a deep end
for human-level intelligence.
Can you clarify why all this
scaling can't solve the problem?
Well, so that connects with
what I just talked about.
Here is an interesting little
calculation you can make.
A typical LLM-- so
something like Llama 3--
is trained on the order of 30
trillion tokens, 310 to the 13.
A token is typically
3 bytes, so that--
about 10 to the 14 bytes
to train a typical LLM.
It's more now because people use
synthetic data and everything.
That's for the
pre-training phase.
It would take any of us on the
order of 400,000 years or half
a million years, to read
through that material.
It's all the publicly
available text on the internet.
Now, compare this with
the amount of information
that gets to a visual cortex in
the first four years of life.
A four-year-old has been awake a
total of 16,000 hours, roughly.
And there's about
1 byte per second
going through our visual
cortex, through each fiber
of our optical nerves, and
we have 2 million fibers.
So that's about 2 megabytes
per second, times 16,000 hours,
it's about 10 to the 14 bytes.
A four-year-old has
seen as much data
through vision as the
biggest LLMs trained
on all the publicly
available text.
And that tells you
that, first of all,
we're missing
something big, that we
need AI systems to learn from
natural, high-bandwidth sensory
data like video.
We're never going to get
to human-level intelligence
by just training on text.
This is not happening.
Despite what you might
hear, for some people who
are in the cult in
Silicon Valley who
are going to tell
you, by next year,
we're going to have
a data center--
a country of geniuses
in a data center--
I'm quoting, OK?
I won't say who.
I mean, this is
just not happening.
Yeah, you will have
useful artifacts that
can help people in
their daily lives
and maybe feel like they have
the intelligence of a PhD,
but it's because they would
be regurgitating things that
have been trained
on, and those systems
won't have actual intelligence
of the type that we expect.
Not just from humans, but
even from your house cat.
So, I mean, house cats
have an understanding
of the physical world that
is completely amazing,
and they only have 2 billion--
800 million neurons in their
brain, it's not that big.
And they certainly have
a very good understanding
of the physical world.
They can do complex
planning of complex actions.
And we are nowhere
near matching this.
So that's what
I'm interested in.
How do we bridge that gap?
How do we get systems to learn
models of the physical world?
And that will require
new architectures
that are not generative.
So I'm telling people that
don't work on generative models,
so they will think I'm crazy,
but I really believe this.
And as you say, I'm trying
to be ahead of the game.
Right.
So you're ahead of the
conventional wisdom again.
You've already
started working on it.
You call it JEPA.
JEPA, yeah.
So tell us, how is
JEPA fundamentally
different from LLMs?
OK, so JEPA stands for
Joint Embedding Predictive
Architecture, and we've been
working on this kind of stuff
for five years or so.
I published a long
paper, which is
kind of a vision paper for
where I think AI research should
go over the next 10 years.
I published this in
2022, it's on OpenReview.
And it's called "A Path Towards
Autonomous Machine Intelligence"
where I basically lay the
groundwork for all of this.
And since then, we've
been making progress
towards that plan with
many of my colleagues
at Meta and at NYU.
And if you type "joint
embedding architectures"
between quotes on
Google Scholar,
you'll get on the
order of 750 hits.
So there's a lot of people
working on this, mostly
in academia.
People have been very quick
to dismiss the contributions
of academia because
all of AI research
is in the hands of industry now.
That's false.
We don't do that here.
No.
But academia basically
tends to work
on the next-generation
thing that industry does not
realize it's going to
have a big impact on what
they do in five to 10 years.
So, OK, so what is the
difference between JEPA and LLMs
or generative architecture?
Generative architecture,
you give it-- you
take a piece of data, let's say
a sequence of words of text,
you corrupt it in some way
by removing some words,
for example.
And then you train a
neural net, big neural net,
to predict the words
that are missing.
In the case of LLMs, this is
a-- or the GPT architecture
in particular, there's a trick,
which is that you don't actually
need to corrupt the text.
The architecture is
such that it is causal,
so to predict a particular word,
because of the architecture,
the system can only
look at the words that
are to the left of it.
And so implicitly,
when you train
the system to just
reconstruct the input
sequence on its
output, you implicitly
train it to predict
the next token.
And it's very efficient, it's
parallelizable, and everything.
OK, so that's
generative architecture.
It works because the
tokens are discrete,
there's only a finite
number of them,
and you can train the system
to produce a distribution
over all possible tokens.
That's how LLMs are done.
And then you can use it to
do autoregressive prediction.
Like, you have it
predict the next token,
shift that in into
the input, and now
you can predict the second
token, shift that in, et cetera.
That's autoregressive
prediction.
OK, now what I'm arguing for
is you can't do this for video
because if you tokenize video,
they're still going to be a lot
of things that are
just not predictable,
details like what
everyone looks like here,
that you just cannot predict.
So the idea of JEPA is
you take your video,
but you encode it into
a representation space
where a lot of details
are eliminated,
and then this
autoregressive prediction
that we were previously
doing in input space,
now you're doing it in
this representation space.
Now the trick is--
and the reason why it
didn't pop up earlier
is that to train the
encoder and the predictor
simultaneously is very tricky.
The reason being that it's
very easy for the predictor
to basically force the
encoder to not do anything,
to ignore the input and
produce a constant output
representation, another
prediction problem
becomes trivial, but
it's not a good solution.
And so you have to find ways to
trick the system into carrying
as much information
about the input as
possible in the representation,
but at the same time,
eliminating some of the details
that are not predictable.
So the system finds a
trade-off between carrying
as much information as
possible about the input,
but only the stuff
that it can predict.
And that's the basic
concept of JEPA.
It's not-- in terms
of architecture,
there is the encoder, which
is different from what
you see in LLMs.
And the trick is in finding good
training algorithms, basically,
or procedures or regularizers
to get the thing to learn
interesting representations.
Now, it wasn't clear
until fairly recently
whether this type of
joint embedding method
to learn representations
of natural data,
like images and video,
would ultimately
be better than techniques that
are trained to reconstruct
at the pixel level.
But at FAIR, we had
basically an A-B comparison
where a big group was working
on a project called MAE, Masked
Autoencoder, and a
video version of it,
which was basically
take an image,
corrupt it, and then train
some gigantic neural net
to reconstruct the full
image, or the full video.
And it didn't quite work.
And in fact, at MIT, you
can ask someone about this.
Kaiming He.
He was one of the
principals in this project.
And he was a little disappointed
by the results, and in the end,
he reoriented his research,
left FAIR, and joined MIT
on the faculty,
associate professor,
and now he's at MIT at CSAIL.
So in parallel, there
were other projects
that tried to train the
joint embedding architectures
without attempting
to reconstruct-- so
non-generative architectures.
And they turned out
to work much better.
OK.
And so it was clear
empirical evidence
that, for natural
sensory data, you just
don't want to use
generative architectures.
And now we have also data that
shows that those systems surpass
in performance, even
supervised models in images,
which wasn't the case
until about a year ago.
Wow.
Which applications are starting
to show that early promise?
Well, there is an
open-source system
put out by some of my colleagues
at FAIR in Paris called DINO.
I mean, they
pronounce it "deano."
It's DINO, but they're
French, so they say "dino."
And this is DINOv3,
the third version just
came out a month or two ago.
And so this is basically a
generic self-supervised vision
encoder, image
encoder, which you
can use for all kinds of
downstream applications,
and there are basically
hundreds of papers
of using the DINO
system, previous versions
and current ones, for
all kinds of stuff.
Medical image analysis,
biological image analysis,
astronomy, and then just
everyday computer vision.
So I think this is really the
self-supervised learning model.
Took a long time, but it
finally won the battle
if you want for image
and video representation.
Another project that I was
more directly involved in
is called V-JEPA, that
stands for Video JEPA.
And it's done by
a group of people
in Montreal, Paris, and
New York that I work with.
And this system is
trained from video.
So you take a video, corrupted
by masking a big chunk of it,
and then train an architecture--
so run the full video
and it partially maps
one through two encoders
that are essentially identical.
And then simultaneously
train a predictor
to predict the representation
of the full video
from the partially
masked, corrupted one.
OK, that's the first
phase of training.
We've trained this
on an amount of video
that corresponds to
about a century of video.
This is an insane amount--
Century of video.
Wow.
Yeah, So it's not as efficient
as a four-year-old, clearly,
but those systems
basically can show
that they've learned a
little bit of common sense.
If you show them a video where
something impossible occurs,
like an object spontaneously
disappears or changes
shape or something,
the prediction error
goes through the roof.
And so they can tell you
something really unusual
occurred that I
don't understand.
And so that's the first sign
of a self-supervised learning
system, having acquired
a bit of common sense.
And you're already seeing some
early success in robotics?
Yeah, that's right.
And so you can have a
second phase of training
where you fine-tune a predictor
which is action-conditioned.
And now what you have out
of this is a world model.
So what is a world model?
Given a representation of the
state of the world at time T,
and given an action that an
agent would imagine taking,
can you predict the state
of the world resulting
from taking this action?
That's a world model.
If you have a system
with such a world model,
you can use it for planning.
You can imagine taking
a sequence of actions,
and then using the
world model, predict
what the outcome of
this sequence of actions
is going to be.
And then you can
have a cost function
that measures to what
extent a particular task has
been achieved.
Have you made
coffee or something?
And then using basically what
amounts to optimization methods,
search for a sequence of actions
that optimize this objective,
minimizes this objective.
This is classical planning
and optimal control,
except that the model,
the dynamical model
of the environment
that we use, is learned
through self-supervised
learning, as opposed
to written down as a
bunch of equations,
as is done in robotics or
classical optimal control.
So this is really
what we're after,
and we've shown that we can
do this with representations
of the state of the world either
derived from things like DINO,
or learn from scratch, or
on top of V-JEPA V-JEPA 2.
And you can show that you
can use this to get a robot
to accomplish a task zero shot.
You don't have to train it
to accomplish this task.
There's no training whatsoever.
No RL.
The training is completely
self-supervised.
And in the end, the system
has a good enough world model
that it can imagine how to
accomplish a task without ever
being trained to
accomplish this task.
Wow.
So I saw that you
had one robot that I
think it trained on 62
hours of tasks on its own,
and then it did
self-supervised work.
So that training of 62 hours
was not for a particular task.
It was basically, here is the
state of the world at time T,
here is an action,
and here is what
the world is going to look like
as a result of this action.
You can do this with simulated
data, with a robot simulator,
or with real data where you
have a robot arm moving around
and you know what
action was taken.
So this notion of
world model, I think,
which I already talked about
in my 2016 Keynote at NeurIPS,
I think is going to be a key
component of future AI systems.
And my prediction has been--
I've been not making friends
in various corners of Silicon
Valley, including
at Meta, saying
that within three
to five years, this
will be the dominant model
for AI architectures,
and nobody in their right mind
would use LLMs of the type
that we have today.
Right.
So that'll propel this to
be the decade of robotics
basically coming up.
Yeah.
But on that point,
there is a large number
of robotics companies
that have been
created over the last few
years building humanoid robots.
The big secret of the industry
is that none of those companies
has any idea how to make
those robots smart enough
to be useful--
or I should say, smart enough
to be generally useful.
We can train those robots
for particular tasks,
maybe in manufacturing
and things like this,
but your domestic
robot, there is a bunch
of breakthroughs
that need to arrive
in AI before that's possible.
So the future of a
lot of those companies
essentially depends
on whether we're
going to make progress,
significant progress,
towards those kind
of world model
planning-type architectures.
It's OK, we're not worried
about those companies.
We're a huge believer
in entrepreneurship
here, by the way.
We're going to have a whole new
set of companies that are going
to come out of these new ideas.
The other thing is that
you've been a huge optimist.
There's a lot of
fearful people about AI
today, the ethics
of AI, et cetera,
and you've been a huge optimist.
Why do you think
these systems are not
going to escape our control?
What's your gestalt
on all of this?
OK, so the overall
architecture of AI systems
I've been advocating is one
that I call objective-driven.
So this idea that you're
going to have a system that
has some mental
model of the world,
it's going to plan a sequence
of actions to arrive--
to satisfy an objective,
to accomplish a task.
And by construction,
that system can
do nothing else but producing
a sequence of actions
that optimizes that objective.
Now in that objective, you
can hardwire guardrails.
So let's say you have
a new domestic robot
and you ask the domestic
robot, get me a coffee.
And it gets to the
coffee machine,
and there is someone
standing in front of it,
you don't want that robot
to slash and kill the person
in front of a coffee machine
because it's only objective will
be to fetch you coffee.
And so-- and by the
way, this is an example
that people like Stuart Russell
use as an example of how you
could build dangerous machines.
And I've always dismissed
this, and he always
thought I was stupid.
He actually called me stupid
publicly in some interviews,
so I'm used to it.
A lot of people call
me stupid, that's fine.
We'll have to have the
two of you back together.
That's OK, but go ahead.
At some point, perhaps.
But the point is, you can--
if you put guardrails in
the objective functions
of the system,
hardware guardrails,
that can be very low-level.
Like you can have a--
I don't know, a
domestic robot that
can cook, you can have a very
low-level guardrail that says
don't flail your arms if
there are people around
and you have a knife in your
hands, things like that.
So, we're going to have to
design those guardrails,
but by construction,
the system will not
be able to escape
those guardrails,
it will have to satisfy them.
And so I'm not saying that
designing those guardrails
is going to be an easy task, but
we are used to this with humans.
We design laws.
Laws are basically
objective functions
that change the landscape of
what actions you can take.
The cost of each
action we're taking,
we're making-- we make laws to
basically align human behavior
with the common good.
We even do this with
superhuman entities
called corporations with
limited success, I admit.
So, I mean, we're used to this.
We've been used to this
problem for millennia.
And I would argue, it's not a
more complex and challenging
problem than, I don't
know, designing turbojets
that can fly you halfway around
the world in complete safety.
I mean, we can do amazing
feats of this type,
so I'm really not worried.
I'm not saying it's
an easy problem.
I'm just not--
I don't think--
But you're not worried it'll get
out and be out of our control?
Right.
So I have like a hundred
more questions to ask you,
but we're almost out of time.
I do want to say, I know
that you should definitely
come back to MIT and
spend a lot more time.
I know that you love sailing.
We're here, we have
a great crew team.
I'm sure there are some
here in the audience,
and we're here on the Charles.
You and your brother
build airplanes.
We have the number one
Aero & Astro Department,
so please come back.
And I know you're
a huge fan of jazz.
Yes.
Right?
And we just built a whole new
Music and Theater Arts Building.
It's one of the best--
It's hard to beat New
York on that dimension.
Ah, we're-- we're willing
to sit and compete.
But let me ask you
the last question
and just go full circle.
So we started with your
PhD you were working on
roughly 40 years ago.
If you were an MIT PhD student
today, what would you work on?
This is a question I get a lot.
What would you study if
you were an undergrad?
What would you work on?
I mean, I think for
the last 40, 50 years,
I think discovering the
mysteries of human intelligence,
and MIT is very
engineering-focused.
As an engineer myself, I think
the best way to understand
something is to build it.
Richard Feynman said
that, actually, as well.
Well, he didn't mean build it--
build a physical
artifact, but he
means deriving the ideas is
yourself and appropriating them.
And so I think that if you are
a ambitious young scientist
or engineer, there are three
big questions to work on.
One is, what's the
universe made of?
What's life all about?
And how does the brain work?
So three scientific questions.
And those on the
engineering side of it,
at least for the last
one, is how do we
build intelligent machines?
What are the
essential components
that constitute intelligence
and the minimal set of things
that-- people were working also
on similar fields in biology
and synthetic biology
and things like that.
So certainly I would
probably work in this domain,
as I decided to do 45 years ago.
That's right.
But if I was an undergrad,
people are asking this question.
AI is going to come up and it's
going to do all kinds of stuff
at a low level that we may
not need to learn anymore.
I think there are things that we
shouldn't learn as engineering
or science students anymore.
And there are things--
those are things
that have a short shelf life.
So the joke I say is that if
you're studying computer science
or engineering of
some kind, and you
have a choice between a
course that teaches you
about a piece of technology
that is currently fashionable
like, I don't know, mobile app
programming or LLM prompting
or whatever it is--
I'm sure there are equivalent in
various engineering disciplines,
don't take those classes.
If you have a choice between--
There you go.
--between mobile programming
and quantum mechanics,
take quantum mechanics, even if
you are a computer scientist,
because you will learn about
things like, I don't know,
path integrals?
I mean, it's a
general method that
is applicable to all
kinds of situations.
It's a concept that you can
connect with other things.
So it turns out, how to best
decode the sequence of words
that you most likely in a
speech recognition system,
for example, it's
actually a path integral.
It's discrete, but it's
basically the same concept.
I mean, there's basic
theoretical concepts
like this that turn
out to be abstractions
that are applicable to a
wide variety of things.
So take those challenging
courses, and that
will put you on a good path.
And maybe future AI assistants
will take care of the low level.
And so think of yourself.
Think of the situation
currently of a PhD advisor
with a pool of PhD
students, and the big secret
is that the students
teach the advisors,
not the other way around.
You will be in the same
situation as a student
where during your PhD,
you will have a staff
life of virtual people working
for you, AI assistants working
for you.
It will move your own level
of abstraction a couple levels
up so that there
are a lot of things
you won't have to take care of.
It used to be that you could
do a PhD sequencing DNA.
Not necessary anymore, we
have machines to do this.
It used to be that
you could have
a career as a mathematician
calculating logarithm tables
and trigonometry tables.
Not necessary anymore, we have
calculators and computers.
Or solving differential
equations symbolically by hand,
we solve them numerically.
So there's a lot of--
I mean, it's just a
natural continuation
of technological progress
that humanity moves up
the hierarchical ladder and
leaves the low-level stuff
to machines.
Well, the future is going
to be very exciting.
Yann, thank you for such an
inspiring set of comments today.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]