yeah thanks so much for having me today
and and after the the prior I think
really excellent talk for what it's
worth I think I rarely see that topic of
um kind of AI and data center um energy
usage and climate impacts covered with
so much Nuance so I'm really
appreciative of the the previous speaker
talk um and so during my time I want to
to spend some time maybe also zooming
out and talking about kind of
holistically how is it that machine
learning and climate change interact and
of course I probably don't even have to
motivate this right but you know climate
change one of the biggest issues of our
time impacts are being felt globally um
this involves a need for both you know
Net Zero greenhouse gas emissions by
2050 across many different sectors as
well as large- scale adaptation efforts
uh that are inherently local at a global
scale and so of course it becomes very
natural to ask the question of what is
the role of machine learning in this
overall
picture and machine learning and climate
change have actually a relatively
multifaceted relationship covering both
ways that machine learning is being used
to enable climate action but also as we
heard about just now the impacts from
machine learning computation and
Hardware while this is often posed as
the whole picture in general you know
machine learning is good because we can
use it for good things and machine
learning is bad because it has direct
impacts this isn't the whole story
machine learning is also used in ways
that are actively negative for climate
both for applications that increase
greenhouse gas emissions and in in ways
that kind of induce broader system level
changes and um that actually have huge
implications for our ability to address
climate change so I want to spend some
time digging into each of these
aspects so first machine learning for
climate
action so um several years ago a group
of collaborators and I um kind of
surveyed this space and um tried to
identify you know where is it that
machine learning can actually help
address climate change across a variety
of different sectors across electricity
systems buildings um industry climate
science and so forth and for those who
are interested I'd encourage you to
check out kind of the full report but I
want to spend some time highlighting
some common themes that came up across
these different applications as as we
looked
through so one kind of big category of
applications is distilling raw data into
actionable insights there are many
scenarios where we just wish we had a
more targeted picture of greenhouse gas
Emissions on the ground or where
deforestation is happening or the Energy
Efficiency characteristics of buildings
at a city scale but where we for
whatever reason have not had the
opportunity or ability to do kind of on
the ground data collection and surveying
at the scale we would like in those
situations uh sources like satellite
imagery and aerial imagery can provide a
way to get a proxy for that information
by basically taking satellite imagery
labeling it on a selection of instances
learning what it means for something to
look like deforestation or something to
to look like a kind of power plant that
is on and then actually extrapolate that
to to kind of around the world and so
the um image on the slide is from a
coalition of nonprofits called climate
Trace which is specifically trying to
compile independent um independent
greenhouse gas emissions inventories um
for as kind of input to the UN climate
change um negotiations by basically
taking a combination of satellite
imagery and on the ground data in order
to assess in different sectors what are
the emissions at the entity level at
from the power sector from from the
industrial sector and so
forth another theme that often comes up
is improving predictions so doing
something like using information like
historical data about solar power
production and using that to forecast
what solar power production will look
like in the near future and this kind of
thing can actually help us to better
manage for example power grids with
large amounts of Renewables by allowing
us to maintain balance between the
amount of Supply we have and the amount
of demand and the kind of powerful thing
that machine learning techniques can do
here is that they can take in different
modalities or different types of data
and learn relationships between them in
a way that's very powerful so the image
on the slide is from a nonprofit called
um open climate fix which is working
with the UK power system operator to
improve their forecasts of um energy
supply and demand and what they're doing
is combining information like
um historical um weather data historical
power production with the outputs of
physical kind of weather models that are
providing um information about what the
weather will look like with things like
information about the cloud moving
movement overhead that might be provided
by satellite and aerial imagery and
combining that together and learning
relationships between it in a really
powerful way that allows more accurate
and targeted forecasts of solar power
production so while the last two themes
have to in some sense do with kind of
providing information to a decision
maker there are many places where
machine learning itself can can play a
role in automated decision making so for
example when we think about the heating
and cooling systems in our buildings
there are many opportunities to make
these more efficient by taking into
account things like what the weather is
outside is the building occupied what is
the actual temperature of the building
right now what are the physical
characteristics of the building and
machine learning has been used to
basically take in all of this real-time
information and come up with better
strategies to actually optimize heating
and cooling systems in a way that kind
of keeps the thermal comfort of a
building intact while also reducing
energy usage and this kind of thing
happens not just in kind of heating and
cooling systems in buildings but also in
kind of refrigeration systems in data
centers and Industrial facilities and so
forth a kind of similar but maybe much
less um flashy set of applications is in
predictive maintenance so basically
trying to identify when a system has
broken or is about to break in order to
kind of preemptively fix it and avoid
any inefficiencies that result from that
so the German rail operator do Shaban
for example uses machine learning to
identify faults in the switching
infrastructure in the railways in order
to then actually help fix those
preemptively and allow the cranes to
keep running on time now I know a lot of
Germans will complain that Doan does not
run on time but it would maybe be even
worse without AI um another kind of
similar um area is the detection of
methane Le leaks in natural gas
infrastructure where as natural gas is
transported from where it's extracted to
where it's used um it may leak from the
pipelines or the compressor stations and
so machine learning has been used to
both using aerial and satellite imagery
but also in some cases even sensors
outfitted along that equipment identify
where there may be anomalies or
something that is about to go wrong in
order to fix
that in addition to helping with
existing operational systems machine
learning can also play a role in
actually helping with the kind of you
know science and engineering processes
that are helping us figuring out how to
kind of create new technologies or
transition our system in the future so
for instance machine learning is very
commonly used to accelerate the practice
of a scientific discovery um and I know
people have different and nuanced
opinions about it but actually there was
a Nobel given for for this General enal
idea where you are um analyzing the
outcomes of past experiments where
you're trying to for example synthesize
a molecule or a battery or an electr
fuel or a CO2 sorbent and you're using
that uh the recommendations that are
that are gained by analyzing those past
experiments using machine learning in
order to guide your process of
experimentation going forward and that
can help cut down on the number of
design Cycles or experiments or kind of
like physical synthesis runs that you
actually to do before you maybe come up
with an impactful material or impactful
technology machine learning is also used
in the science and engineering realm to
help approximate time intensive
simulations so the image on the slide is
from an early paper in 2019 that was
proposing the idea of using machine
learning to approximate the physics of
clouds within a climate model each
individual cloud in a climate model has
really complex physical interactions
going on where somehow clouds have a
cooling effect and some clouds have a
warming effect and you can imagine
putting a bunch of really complicated
Cloud models in an already really large
climate model blows up the computational
intensity of that model and makes it
hard to run and so there have been a
number of Works proposed that say can we
approximate things like individual
clouds or individual parts of these
models and stick that back into the
original model in a way that allows us
to run the overall model faster um and
at higher resolution which means for
example like
in in the past we might have only had a
climate Insight where we had one data
point for the entirety of Massachusetts
maybe we now actually understand what
might happen in Cambridge and as a
result what can we do about that um and
since then um there have been kind of a
number of advancements where not even
part of the model but maybe where entire
weather models or entire climate models
or entire subsystems are being well
approximated using Ai and machine
learning as so this is a really kind of
active area of research and engagement
at the moment
so last but not least um we often think
of you know machine learning as being
something that takes data in and that's
true but interestingly machine learning
can be used to actually help manage data
um in ways that are helpful in climate
change related workflows so for instance
not pictured on the slide is um there's
a Cooperative called the CL Catalyst
Cooperative which is actually using
machine learning to help match and merge
different energy data sets that are
published by the US government where
those different energy data sets are
describing the same power generators but
the kind of way in which those power
generators are labeled or referenced is
not consistent um between these these
sources and so they use machine learning
to identify when is it that two
different records in these two different
data sources are actually referring to
the same entity to the same power
generator in order to automate that
merging process um and the image on the
slide is um from a group at the
University of Washington which is using
machine learning for scenario generation
so thinking about in the
future when you when you run a model to
for example plan your future power grid
you do this based on having a bunch of
different scenarios of for example how
much wind power do you think will be
produced in the future and so what they
did is they used machine learning to
analyze historical wind power data learn
kind of like a probability distribution
over it understand how do we think that
probability distribution will shift in
the future because some places may be
windier some won't so they actively
tweaked those parameters
and then they use that to sample from
that new distribution in order to get
kind of future win
scenarios so there's a lot of really I
think cool and impactful stuff going on
in the realm of of machine learning for
climate action and one thing I want to
highlight is across these different
applications I've talked about the
diversity of approaches and techniques
that that are here many of these
applications for example are not text
many of these are not using large
language models or generative models
while these models can be impactful
they're only one piece of the the puzzle
and in fact you know the the kinds of
settings we think about when we think
about climate action are really diverse
and those require diverse approaches
today when we think about the dominant
Paradigm of machine learning we're often
thinking Big Data big compute you only
need data you can throw out any other
knowledge or information you had and the
only metric we care about with respect
to Performance is the average accuracy
of the model in reality in different
climate related settings we might have
less data or you may have a lot of data
but it might be hard to move to where
you actually need to do the computation
this is true in for example power grids
you might have less compute due to kind
of um organizational constraints for
example you might be needing to do
Computing on an edge device or a sensor
you might want to reduce energy and
Emissions for obvious reasons you might
have useful knowledge already that you
don't need to relearn from data and my
own work is in the electric power sector
where we know something about the
physics of the power grid and we can
combine that information with data
rather than assuming that information
doesn't exist and depending on the
setting you're looking at there's a
diverse set of metrics we should care
about maybe in some cases you care more
about protecting a particular group that
for example is is unusually harmed or is
underrepresented than caring about kind
of group average accuracy you might care
about metrics like safety or robustness
if you don't want to black out your
power grid interpretability if you're in
a decision critical setting so there are
lots of different metrics and lots of
different kind of there's there's a huge
heterogeneity of assumptions in the
settings we're looking at um and that
means that there are lots of different
opportunities for Innovation across a
lot of different settings including kind
of physics informed and robust ml
interpretable machine learning energy
efficient machine learning we heard from
the last speaker about autom automl so
kind of Designing models automatically
that are less energy consumptive and
will produce uh better results for your
area um and I think it's important that
as we hear claims about hey we should
continue investing in kind of the
predominant Paradigm of generative AI
because generative AI is going to be
good for the climate I'm not writing off
that generative AI will be helpful for
the climate but when we talk about Ai
and climate there's a much wider variety
of techniques at play and so we should
moderate our our kind of enthusiasm and
understand accordingly where Investments
should go in order to make sure that
we're actually fostering a really
diverse ecosystem of AI techniques that
can really meet this diverse set of
challenges rather than kind of
conflating one particular set of AI
techniques and one particular AI
Paradigm with the broader AI e system
here so my own work just really briefly
looks at kind of one of these specific
paradigms of physics informed machine
learning so my group's work thinks we we
look a lot at you know how do you
actually optimize and schedule power on
power grids in a way that allows us to
integrate Renewables and this is a tough
challenge because power grids have lots
of physics and hard constraints and
decision-making procedures going on all
the time where if you don't satisfy
those you're going to black out your
grid traditional optimization and
control techniques um end up what they
do is they write down the physics of the
power grid explicitly um in a way that
allows you to make sure you're doing
something that's reasonable for your
grid but is really slow to solve for
which means that we are needing to
manage grids at greater speed and at
greater scale that doesn't work but
naive machine learning techniques even
though they're fast and
scalable are naive about the physics of
the power grid and so they're not able
to deal with that and so my group's work
looks at how can we actually merge these
two paradigms how can we combine
physical knowledge that we already have
about power grids with data driven
techniques and the kind of for for those
who want to nerd out about this later
the key idea is that in the context of
machine learning models and specifically
neural networks you can think about
neural networks neural network is a
bunch bunch of functions composed
together and so we basically find ways
to take the kinds of you know physical
equations and Engineering constraints
that we care about in power grids and
write them down as the kinds of
functions or relations that we can
actually stick into a neural network and
that way you get neural networks that
enforce physical constraints you care
about on the power grid as well as um
being able to learn from from data and
use that for various things like
decision cognizant forecasting for
approximating power grid optimization
models and for doing distributed control
via reinforcement
learning all right so I spent most of my
time uh talking about this bucket of you
know places that I think machine
learning can be useful for climate
action and again I think there are many
places it can be useful um and that all
of these applications in order to do
them well you have to really contend
with what the needs are on the ground
and work with a diverse set of
stakeholders in order to make sure that
you're actually capturing and satisfying
those
needs but I do want to spend a little
time talking about again this bigger
picture of you know where is it that
machine learning interacts with climate
change as we heard from the last speaker
machine learning has various impacts via
its computation and hardware and I'm
going going to go through this part
quickly because I think there's some
some overlap in what was discussed but
as we heard from the last speaker
machine learning has impacts directly
both through its operational impacts
when you're actually running a machine
learning model what are the for example
energy and water consumed when you do
that and also embodied impacts and
materials impacts that come from the
hardware itself so what were the carbon
emissions associated with producing and
transporting that Hardware what happens
when you dispose the hardware and so
forth and as mentioned by the previous
speaker in something like 2020 data
centers and the uh information and
communication technology Center as a
whole made up between 1 to 2% of global
greenhouse gas emissions of which AI was
some unknown fraction that number has
changed but we don't know what it's
changed to because there often is a bit
of a lag in this data coming out as well
as honestly lack of transparency among
providers of um of compute into in order
to to compute these but it has
undoubtedly gone
up and from the AI side um where these
uh from the AI and machine learning side
where the energy use specifically comes
from is through a mix of the process
that is C that is um uh developing the
machine learning model then training the
machine learning model so kind of
running it on a bunch of data to get get
some good parameters and then using the
the machine learning model the inference
space and what we're seeing is
that the electricity of demand here is
growing so this is a um uh kind of
projection from the um iea Global
electricity demand from data centers Ai
and cryptocurrencies and we've seen an
approximately two times increase in the
electricity demand from this group of
Technologies um from 2021 to
2026 again there's a lot of uncertainty
in these numbers but I think it's useful
to put this in this in the historical
context where we see again this 2x
increase between 2019 and
2026 and if you look back the similar
number of years say from 2010 to 2018 we
saw only a 6% increase in electricity
demand despite an almost six times
increase in compute instances so we were
using a lot more compute it's just that
Hardware was getting much more efficient
in a way that was compensating for that
and that trend has been true for a while
the fact that that Trend doesn't seem to
be true right now that objectively raw
electricity demand is rising means we
are in a new realm at the moment and so
it is something that to pay attention to
and make sure that we're we're actively
doing something
about and there's some nuances here in
terms of the kind of Dynamics and trends
of of what's going on so um for example
this is a um graph um that comes from an
examination of the emissions of
different machine learning models at
Facebook and what they eval evaluated is
they had kind of old recommender system
models that were being used across their
workf flows and then they have new kind
of large language models type things
that are being used for similar
purposes and what they found is that for
their prior recommender models the total
carbon footprint was coming about 50/50
from training the model versus using the
model so training a model is a much more
carbon intensive thing to do but you
tend to do it fewer times using a model
when after it's already trained is a
less carbon intensive thing to do per
use but since you're doing it many times
that kind of total kind of carbon in
carbon emissions might increase and so
for older recommender system um
recommender systems it was a kind of
about 5050 that things were coming from
for their large language models what
they found is that inference dominated
training so the kind of number of uses
that were happening and the specific
nuances of what even one use means means
that the use phase was more carbon
intensive in total than the um the the
training
phase and there have also been studies
that have shown that for example as we
move and have this trend in society
where specific tasks we used to use task
specific models for them and now we're
using more general purpose models that
each inference each use of a model is
actually more intensive than it was
before because we're choosing to use
bigger models even though we didn't do
that before and so per inference
multi-purpose models can be orders of
magnitude more specific than task
specific model so even potentially by
choosing quote unquote the wrong models
or different models we're blowing up the
the the um kind of total uses usage
associated with our old use cases as
well so understanding these Dynamics and
Trends is super important to
understanding what we actually do about
this and so this is where really
increased transparency and data
collection among those who are running
and running these models and who are
providing the computational
infrastructure becomes exceedingly
important
an argument that's often used is okay so
you've talked a lot about energy and you
talked a lot about carbon emissions why
can't you just green the power grid and
hook Renewables up or move your
workloads to times when when carbon is
Le when the carbon intensity is less
this is important but insufficient so we
uh kind of as part of our Global
strategies to decarbonize the energy
sector we need to become more efficient
and reduce energy usage not allow it to
grow and this is something the previous
speaker mentioned as well so this
applies to kind of AI induced energy
workloads as well in addition uh kind of
AI workloads have water related impacts
particularly many data centers are in
water stressed regions and of course as
we've talked about there are minerals
and resources that are necessary to
build computational infrastructure um
that doesn't just go away when we put
renewals on the grid so Greening the
grid is really important but there are
many other things we need to do which
include uh making things more efficient
and reducing waste sort of assessing
when particular runs or applications are
actually not
necessary so in my last few minutes um I
want to talk about these last two
buckets of kind of ways that machine
learning is used that I think have
either kind of negative or uncertain
implications for climate so very kind of
um uh prominently machine learning is
often used to accelerate emissions int
of Industries like the oil and gas
industry so for instance a report that
came out in 2020 noted that Ai and
machine learning boosted oil and gas
production levels in some cases by as
much as 5% and generated or was
projected to generate you know something
like $400 billion dollar in value for
the oil and gas sector in a way that
kind of entrenches the role of that
sector um and I will say this is still
kind of ongoing with a number of leading
tech companies still actively marketing
to oil and gas companies and building
active businesses around the practice of
accelerating oil and gas exploration and
extraction but it's not just oil and gas
there's for example uses of machine
learning and AI to do things like um
optimize the internet of cows um to to
kind of manage livestock at scale um and
these are multi-objective problems on
the one hand making the lives of certain
Farmers much easier helping increase
profits and productivity for Farmers but
also entrenching the role of bad and
agriculture in a way that might be
carbon intensive
and while these applications are easy to
point to and say you're actively doing
something that's red that's increasing
greenhouse gas emissions there are lots
of more subtle but transformative
effects that machine learning has that
we should really be paying attention to
in the context of climate for instance
as we increasingly think about machine
learning as a driver of autonomous
vehicles we need to think about the
effects that autonomous vehicles
potentially have on the transportation
sector where an individual autonomous
vehicle um might be kind of more
efficient in in terms of uh kind of um
energy per mile traveled because of
efficient driving strategies that might
cause a rebound where people also drive
more and also have a lock in effect
where we entrench the role of kind of
privatized and and privatized
Transportation rather than necessarily
thinking about how do we better
facilitate multimodal Transportation
this isn't a given but we can actively
make choices where we're developing
these Technologies to try to facilitate
transformation of the transportation
sector rather than lock in and is is
something we need to be really cognizant
of machine learning also increases
societal consumption via things like
personalized advertising and On Demand
delivery in ways that don't always
increase happiness but do increase
emissions and consumption and in ways
that we really should be thinking about
machine learning changes how we consume
information online through things like
content personalization and
amplification of polarized views machine
learning can also be a kind of asset in
terms of serving more Target information
or finding misinformation but again we
have to choose to leverage it in that
way um rather than for example
optimizing for clicks on social media
using machine
learning and machine learning techniques
are often at this point largely
developed and vended by a small set of
players in a small set of countries and
contexts and they're evented to a wide
variety of players across the world for
example many kind of consultancies and
Tech compan companies that are the kind
of main Solutions provider to to small
cities and Smart City initiatives and
that can cause lock in for those Smart
City initiatives to a particular
Solutions provider it can mean that the
agenda of that particular Smart City
initiative is driven by the solutions
provider so we really need to be
cognizant of the ways that our
trajectory of AI and machine learning
are really causing different people in
society to have more or less um Power in
the conversation and what we need to do
to actually shift that agency
so with that you know what can we do
there's a lot we can do in terms of you
know making sure that we're investing in
you know heterogeneous paradigms of AI
and machine learning working on good
applications adopting individual and
organizational practices like organ
organizational carbon pricing covering
Scopes one two and three um and um kind
of making sure that we're appropriately
communicating about the benefits and
risks of AI in an appropriately kind of
nuanced and grounded way rather than
necessarily hyping it um and there are
many levers that the climate and policy
Community can take as well to um both
Foster the use of AI for climate action
in a more Equitable and democratized Way
by kind of providing better you know
data and digital infrastructure
targeting research funding and creating
Pathways to deployment as well as to
kind of mitigate the negative
implications of AI and machine learning
for climate for instance by building
kind of climate cognizant reporting and
assessment into AI Strate IES to make
sure that as we think about how are we
moving AI forward that we're actively
accounting for both ai's direct impacts
and the implications of the different
applications we're using it for both
kind of AI for good applications and the
business as
usual so with that I would definitely
encourage you to if you're interested in
these topics um kind of plug into the
climate change AI Community climate
change AI is a nonprofit I co-founded
and we have you know a lot of people
actively engaging in these kinds of
discussions and trying to figure out how
to push forward ai ai in a way that's
aligned with climate action so I'd
encourage you to check out the
educational resources funding programs
conferences and so forth um and with
that I know I am over time and so uh
thanks so much and um if we have time
for questions look forward to it
otherwise please feel free to to catch
me offline or uh via email thanks
[Applause]