we have now another panel with uh rock
stars that we present you in a second
it's a pleasure to to introduce to the
panel named triple Innovation for a
sustainable future technology policy and
business models the session highlights
the need for Innovation to boost
sustainability across Industries the
panelists will explore how Advanced
Technologies public policies and
business model work together and will
help us uncover practical strategies for
a more sustainable future to uh moderate
the panel I will invite ameritus
Professor dong lar he is the AEK found
Foundation professor of International
Management and professor of system
engineering at MIT Don advises companies
governments and universities and
continues his research on global
strategic management and very large
scale project management on a personal
note it's is a pleasure to see Don again
he was my professor many many years ago
so uh don please take it away thank you
okay great uh let's see if we can keep
the energy of this morning uh the point
of this panel is you you come to MIT for
technological innovation but Innovation
and change requires policy technology
and a change in business models we want
to see those three we've got a panel
that represents those three beautifully
uh Elizabeth Reynolds who is a professor
of practice in the department of urban
studies and planning
focusing on systems of innovation
manufacturing and Industrial
competitiveness she was Special
Assistant to President Biden on the
national uh for manufacturing and
economic development for the National
Economic Council and was responsible for
a lot of the developments in US
industrial policy prior to work at the
White House she did some uh pathbreaking
research again on Industrial policy
through the uh industrial performance
center here at MIT uh yet M Chang is
a star technological innovator he's got
several billion worth of firms that have
come from it what I really like today is
he's got oh well he's Professor uh of
heera Professor of Ceramics professor of
Material Science and Engineering elected
member of the National Academy of
engineering he's brought several
laboratory discoveries to
commercialization including high-powered
lithium ion batteries more efficient
battery processing batteries for long
duration electrical chemical cement and
most recently electrical Aviation so
long span of sustainability oriented
Innovations and then Joe hicken who is
the vice president for business
development uh of sublime systems which
is a company using yet Ming's uh
Innovations on cement is going to
replace the process of cooking Limestone
with heat to Rel re re-release CO2 so uh
if you look for reducing embodied
emissions there's no better example so
we'll go right into it uh Liz you've
played a key role in crafting the return
of industrial strategy can you tell us a
little bit about how the policies really
changed in the last four years what were
the most important accomplishments in
that what's the real unfinished business
and I know a lot of your focus is for
getting us firms to work on developing
technology in the US that's that's right
um I uh I should say first I went I went
down to Washington as special assistant
to the president for manufacturing with
a whole host of ideas and focus
particularly scale up as a as a key
issue um the reality is from day one to
my last day there I was working on
supply chain crises during the pandemic
of All Sorts um but the flip side of uh
you know building resilient Supply
chains is in part building domestic uh
capacity and and um very much so in the
last couple years I think it's fair to
say the US has really put itself on a
new trajectory around Industrial
strategies focusing on uh resilience uh
investment in semiconductors clean
energy critical minerals uh quality jobs
um and building a more vibrant uh
manufacturing ecosystem not only for our
existing uh Industries but also for the
sort of Frontier Industries which are
represented here uh on the on the dis
but what I would say is that I think the
the goal in all of these was was with
all of these goals about building you
know building more capacity and and
focused on critical critical
Technologies and and for National and
economic security the the mechanism for
doing that has always been how do we
crowd in private sector investment
because there's no possible way uh a
federal government is going to actually
make you know have enough to invest in
so if you were to only use that measure
uh over the last couple years you'd say
that these policies have been a huge
success in the US because they have
actually attracted a lot of private
sector investment um over 500 uh billion
at this point between semiconductors and
clean energy and so if that were our
only measure of course it's not our only
measure but we'd say that we're on the
right track in terms of creating an
environment for greater investment for
building you know some of these critical
um critical Technologies and and
companies um I also think that when we
look at what's what's been going on
another major um effort here has been to
figure out ways in which uh workers and
Technology are uh are working are kind
of coexisting and Investments happening
on both sides because if we look
historically at at the trajectory again
for the country we've seen this growing
inequality that's had a lot of negative
repercussions uh on the economy so I'd
say that has also been I'd see built
into a lot of the policy and The
Unfinished Business oh well unfinished
business so it's funny you should
mention it um been working with Brian De
uh who's an innovation fellow here as
well as Simon Johnson a recent Nobel
laurate as of last week on sort of what
is the next wave of industrial strategy
and and certainly I think there's three
categories of ways to think about this
um one is Frontier Technologies where we
are still um in in Need for significant
investment not only in the R&D but also
in deployment so biomanufacturing and
Quantum might fit in that um investments
in areas that we think uh are important
but we haven't really formalized that so
I'd say critical minerals Advanced
manufacturing and then the unfinished
business around um the the first steps
we've taken on semiconductors and clean
energy as a country um there's obviously
you know I keep saying we have to land
the plane uh on these billions of
dollars that have uh are being spent and
obviously you know we won't see you know
perfect uh success for another decade or
two but we have to really uh be
monitoring and figuring out what are the
obstacles to to ensuring that those
those uh those areas you know reach
their goals great thank you yet Ming
you've been at this at this game for
what 25 years or so A123 and 24m and for
energy and Sublime systems and what
what's changed in the policy environment
for a technological innovator and
Company founder over this time let me
first uh Riff Off something that liist
say she said you know one of the roles
of policy is to stimulate private
Investments I've been a huge beneficiary
of that
and uh if you for instance in the early
stage you know the kind of research I'm
mostly involved in here at MIT you know
uh RP as an example as a government
agency that in clean tech is considered
by many to be you know uh the smartest
people in the room and if you're out
raising Capital uh private Capital uh
that the government support is a huge
positive indicator and a lot of cases if
you don't have it they say well why
don't you have it you know what's wrong
with your idea that the federal
government hasn't funded it yet right
and so uh that's that's been huge but uh
so what's happened in the last decade or
so I would say that so first of all you
know we uh actually do have industrial
policy
now uh if I go way back and more than a
decade ago to uh 2008 uh The Recovery
Act funding
A123 what was not funded what was funded
was Capital to build uh battery
manufacturing plants
there was almost no effort to on the
market side and so even a uh a lead
customer like General Motors who had
just been bailed out by the federal
government uh was not even encouraged to
Source
domestically for their
first H big change that's a big change
yeah and so that would never happen
today right and so that that that I
think is huge uh the other so maybe I
can say something about more General
about you what is the role between
technology and policy and I've uh I'm a
believer that
technology uh is when technology shows
an approach to be plausible that's when
policy starts to act you we don't have
policy right now on geoengineering for
example right good reason nobody knows
whether it's plausible someday we may
have policy on Geo engineering when but
uh uh when you show something is
technologically possible then the policy
follows I'm not going to use any Sublime
examples I'm going to leave all those to
Joe but I'm going to give you one uh
form energy example in this area for the
last several years there's been a lot of
attention to something called long
duration energy storage problem has been
nobody knows what long duration means is
it there was a time when 3 hours was
considered long duration is it 3 weeks 3
hours uh poorly defined so form energy
starting about 5 years ago realized that
it was important to define the category
where the the biggest impact would be
and so uh just within the last month it
said the California p uh now has a
mandate that by
2026 uh there will be procurements for a
gigawatt each of something called long
duration storage and something called
multi-day storage now long duration in
this case has been defined as greater
than 12 hours multi-day storage has been
defined as something greater than 24
hours multiple days and that second one
exists because for manag put the effort
into developing that policy working over
several years and just to put a number
on you know what's a gigawatt for the
battery that for energy is building and
we have we building a gigafactory right
now in wton West Virginia that's 100
gwatt hours of of storage it's huge a
gigafactory is something over 50 gwatt
hours a year so it's a couple years
production of the plant that's going in
right now
yeah so um going forward what aspects
are going to be most important in policy
again you had nothing nothing to support
the demand in those early years now we
have more demand support yeah and I and
I think uh you know so we're developing
these Technologies because we see a need
there and to help help it scale to make
it real the kind of support you need is
policy that I identifies that as a as a
need a good thing and you know uh some
cases subsidies but other cases other
mechanisms right so great super
important great so now turning to Joe
and Sublime systems is is going to
replace cooking Limestone um to what
extent are you a taker versus a shaper
of policy following this last point and
you know going forward how do you think
about the scenarios of the policy
context you're going into and how does
how does that influence your business
strategy absolutely so I think the the
answer is uh unfortunately both uh both
Taker and shaper uh I think I was two
months in on the job at Sublime systems
and the inflation reduction act kind of
arose From the Ashes and was passed and
yet said where's the production tax
credit for low carbon
cement um and that was uh okay all right
uh time to get to work um there were
there were other policies included
within the inflation reduction act that
have lifted sublim system systems uh off
I think the the investment from the
office of clean energy demonstrations
they selected Sublime systems for an $87
million uh investment to help us scale
our first commercial manufacturing
facility in Western Massachusetts um and
so not only is the cash and fusion
critical um but also as yet was
mentioning the diligence from the
federal government putting you through
that full rigorous uh review process
establishes credibility in the you know
the viability of the technology the
viability of the business um and then
the you know the the the end users and
the engagement with the commercial
Market demonstrating that you've got a
thing that can be scaled um but that
said right uh the inflation act
reduction act had you know a couple
components but it can go further and we
need to go further to decarbonize
Industry especially cement and concrete
and and therefore uh being very
proactive on policies such as advocating
for a production tax credit um that that
provides incentives at the point of
production right reducing the economic
um risk to traditional project Finance
for these types of Technologies is so
key to get these lifted off um and then
and then additionally right the the
public sector in the case of cending
concrete and building infrastructure
they're the sponsor of of about half of
the concrete that's deployed um in the
nation every year so not only are they
policy maker that can accelerate
industrial decarbonization but they also
play a role as major buyer and purchaser
through a very long uh protracted value
chain from the point of cement at the at
the concrete missing truck all the way
to the point of actually building the
building the bridge or the or the
roadway um and so at Sublime systems
right um we've got many bets uh kind of
inlight right now and some of these some
of these are are Innovative commercial
transactions with private sector
partners that are leveraging um what you
would think of as a public sector sort
of policy structures to get to Value
sooner um a terrific example of that was
just recently we announced that we
signed anou with the intent to close a a
binding off-take agreement um that's
inlight right now um but with the
Microsoft to purchase the environmental
attributes of the cement that we'll be
manufacturing at scale separate from the
actual cement itself it doesn't make
sense for sublim systems to ship um
thousands of tons of cement from Western
Massachusetts to a Microsoft campus in
Redmond Washington for example um and so
instead we can kind of separate out um
and virtualize the the value of that
lowc carbon construction material deploy
it locally in some structure that would
use otherwise high carbon cement um and
and Microsoft would uh own the the
environmental attribute of that
transaction so so I think innovating
business models uh engaging with policy
makers on on both uh uh uh Financial
structures and incentives as well as
carrots that help kind of nudge us along
forward is going to be such a key um you
know a key gating Factor on how fast we
decarbonize and yeah go ahead I was just
going to say on the carrots front I mean
I think what's really profoundly
different is that the effort this time
is really about a carrots rather than
sticks approach and the use of tax
credits has been you know uh one in
which they've been very structured for
companies to get a basic tax credit but
then they they augment depending on
these different incentives are you
providing apprenticeships are you
investing in a stressed area you know um
all of these things that are actually
providing an incentive for companies to
lean into those Investments so that we
switched the challenge now before we you
know it was a supply side challenge now
it's a demand side challenge we have a
more you know more demand than we can
actually uh respond to right now in the
country so that's that those are
profound I think in terms of the
strategy yeah and Joe the the B clean
aspect how does this work to yeah so B
clean is actually an example of of of
great intention policy but the signal
hasn't trickled its way down to a
company like Sublime systems quite yet
um and that's not to disparage the the
intent behind the policy I think the the
The Architects behind that structure see
this um and in fact you can you can see
a great example um the bclean folks have
a pot of money in the inflation
reduction act for the GSA and a pot of
money for the fhwa the federal highways
admin Administration um the signal from
the federal highways Administration has
made its way Belin to sublim systems
very effectively the implementation of
the GSA Federal buildings money the the
vertical construction has not made its
way because of the way that the policy
structured in terms of at what point
does a contractor get rewarded for using
low carbon materials the RFP process
there's 100 points how many points do
you get for using low carbon materials
you only get two extra points for using
the clean concrete on planet Earth right
um so so low carbon is good enough and
then we satisfy some low carbon as
opposed to really low carbon that's
exactly right so the how right uh and
the incentives right change Behavior a
great deal so the fhwa implementation
has led to mot signaling requesting a
quote from Boston sand and gravel the
local concrete producer in the region to
supply their low carbon uh projects in
Boston s and gravel entered into a
non-binding reservation agreement with
sublim systems and that was all
triggered by the inflation reduction act
through fhwa so that's an an example of
a policy that did flow down well and
yeah go ahead oh I was just going to
make the point that uh you know Sublime
is a four-year-old company having a
person like Joe at a four-year-old
startup is a pretty unusual thing yes
we've learned to do that uh you know a
startup engaging the policy right that's
right and in the past by the time we got
around the policies I wish we had
started that a couple years earlier
we're getting smarter about that we have
guys like Joe now right uh working on
this already to pave the way and uh I
also want to just say Joe you didn't
tell him about the uh the party we had
last night oh yeah last night uh we we
had a a retirement party a very uh a
very boisterous retirement party
respectful uh for we were retiring
ordinary Portland cement it was the 200-
year anniversary of the original filing
of the patent uh for for traditional way
of making C man Joseph
October 15th
1824 so I'll end with a business model
question I don't know whether it's for
you y Ming or for you Joe but you know
when when Sublime grows up is this going
to be a global cement company like holom
or is it going to be Sublime
inside I mean uh the jury's still out uh
and I think that's a you know our
mission is to have a Swift and massive
impact on climate changing emissions um
you know the question is what's the
fastest path and who are the partners
that get to yes fastest um I think for
us we've got a really cool manufacturing
uh technology a great engine so far
we're going to build our first
commercial plant it's going to be a
Sublime plant we'll continue with the
process of building Sublime plants but
the reality is the the the folks that
man manufacture cement today it's not
just about the manufacturer of cement
it's about the mining and the coring of
the Raw Feed stock and it's about the
distribution of that material after the
point of manufacturer to the end user
that's a
mind-bogglingly complex uh
infrastructure we respect that and we'd
be very eager to um to engage uh uh
thoroughly with the folks that have
built these uh these arteries in the uh
globally through decades if not
centuries and recently we announced uh
investment from pulam and CR um that
involved Equity uh off take as well as
exploration of of joint development and
and and and Joint buildout so um so we
look to explain both and maybe for for
the folks in the audience who may not uh
have seen the scale of cement production
you know a fullscale cement plant is a a
million tons a year the US has about 106
of those and so that's the domestic
industry uh our first commercial plant
in Holio Massachusetts in one of those
distressed communities uh is 30,000 tons
and that's the roughly the annual
consumption of a ready miixed producer
one of the local produc such as Boston
stand and gravel and so that gets us the
scale of you know True commercial
demonstrations yeah and you know we feel
like we have to get through that phase
to show that uh it all works right and
then your question you know which way do
you go hopefully we have optionaly and
we'll figure it out that's
right okay even though we had three
speakers we have uh 10 minutes for Q&A
so we'd be delighted to have questions
from the
audience I know it's after lunch but
somebody must have a
question I'm just GNA I'll just keep
talking until somebody raises their hand
um I think there's one of my favorite
quotes that the journalists made is that
to decarbonize we have to
reindustrialize and so this moment is uh
important obviously from a
sustainability point of view but it's
converging and I'd be interested in
hearing your guys when you're building
facilities it is converging with a
moment where we also have advanced
Manufacturing Technologies where we can
manufactured differently now I think
than we have in the past and so this is
you know the challenge of the industrial
transformation is it's in the weeds of
these policies but it really is a much
larger you know we've got this
convergence of supply chain issues
climate issues geopolitical issues uh
and then we have the policy at our way
you know at our backs and then we have
the technology that's also making this
you know quite quite possible in a way
that we wouldn't have seen it 10 years
ago great we have a great question for
the audience so how can the value of
sustainability be economically modeled
as a profit or investment and not just a
cost and I'll start with the academic
answer and then I'll let you guys give
the real answer but it's think about the
value proposition think about value
delivery which is the cost in the
process and think about value capture
which is where you stand competitively
and if you don't go through those three
you don't have an economic model right
you're going to start with me okay well
because I don't know the answer to that
question
[Laughter]
and um and I I really don't know the
answer to that question but in all the
industrial decarbonization efforts that
I get involved with the projects that
attract me are the ones where you can
see a path to you know form fit function
replacement at Cost parity decarbonized
yeah right if you can do that there then
you know then the Tailwind are with you
and and uh getting valued in other ways
is just gravy so if it's not right if
it's not uh profitable it's not
sustainable right Joe anything on that
or um I mean I think this gets the the
point actually the a lot of the
companies that yet have spun out and
maybe we'll discover as self-cloning
company uh down the road in terms of his
ability to be everywhere all the time um
but but I think it's it's a much broader
and much more massive value proposition
now the trick is landing that value
proposition amongst the various users
and the the value chain so in the case
of cement and concrete right we care
about the asset owner who owns the
actual building or or Bridge um how are
they monetizing or valuing that asset
because they're they're you know some
are monetizing and leasing space some
are conducting a business activity
within the space uh brand matters
especially more and more young people uh
in terms of human capital and human
capital retention folks are focused on
climate companies want to be competitive
and they want to retain the best um
Talent um and so they want to attract
those types to their companies um that's
just one you know in user and then
there's the general contractor that
wants to be known for uh being at The
Cutting Edge of of of design and
construction Architects want to always
build the the latest kind of visionary
um structures um and then youve got the
the Ready miix Concrete producers that
are mixing the concrete and uh you know
they want to be value adders not simply
just U tolling entities within the space
and we get that a lot with with the
folks that we engage with and so it's
difficult to say okay this this
intervention has X specific dollar
attached to it for each of those actors
but in aggregate we get a lot of
Engagement because they're they
incentives are kind of aligned with the
sustainable interventions and and the
functional versus the emotional eror
with the brand I mean really the two
aspects absolutely yeah um another
question uh what are the iMed mediate
challenges and long-term challenges so
that can go to anybody right that's for
policy that's for invention that's for
execution November
five see who Rises to that one most
that's a tough question right I mean I
will just maybe I'll talk I'll start
with the long-term challenge which is or
maybe immediate and longterm so one so
again we've created this great
demand um we've emphasized through these
tax credits and things deployment that
that is the quickest way for us to
iterate and Advance these Technologies
and hopefully spread them uh globally
and then and but then we recognize that
our infrastructure is not actually up to
the task right we have a grid challenge
um and so how we upgrade and Advance our
our connectivity and transmission Etc
seems like a very immediate Challenge
and one in which we're facing you know
challenges in terms of Disconnect across
regions and and things like that um I
think longer term challenges is again
from the perspective of you know
decarbonization the the challenge we're
making progress in the US and we'll
we'll move the needle importantly over
the next uh you know for our 2050 goals
but really what we need to see is a lot
of movement happening in uh the
developing world and so how are we
thinking
about again scaling these Technologies
and then deploying these Technologies
globally where we don't have at this
point in time really a fi Financial
mechanisms at the scale we need for that
kind of deployment people are talking
about a Marshall Plan you know uh is
kind of one of the ideas out there um
there's a number of different ways in
which people are really trying to think
long term you know to the extent we're
successful these these guys are
successful how are we're going to take
that technology and really be able to
scale it globally yeah all right so I'm
G to give you an answer which may
surprise you because it's not about
technology right uh you know I live
through clean tech 1.0 we're in kind of
The Sweet Spot of 2.0 uh but uh I I feel
that it's really important that uh clean
Tac the things that we're doing end up
providing a return and to all all the
stakeholders but uh certainly the the
the private Capital right you know I'm a
person who's spent his
entire life doing what I want to do with
other people's money starting from when
I was a graduate student I funded my
research funded by Doe and so all the
things that I want to do I I do it with
other people's money whether it's the
government or private capital and I feel
very that in this phase we're at we
really have to show that clean tech can
be profitable in order to keep that uh
enthusiasm
going um I think at least for sublim
systems uh our manufacturing process is
all electric uh we're going to need a
lot of clean electricity so we need to
do um part of the course of voices
seeking to decarbonize the grid across
the board and create new um zero carbon
energy generation across the board
that's going to be the long-term
challenge near term just building our
first plant wrangling General
Contractors it's a big
task great so now a series more
questions Joe you talked about Microsoft
you know purchasing the the carbon
Savings of of your cement
um are there other sectors we see this
type of thing becoming important and
yeah this is actually uh borrowing from
the sustainable Aviation fuels uh sector
very specifically um which is borrowing
directly from virtual power purchase
agreements okay so Advanced off takes of
of a production process that you don't
quite have access to in your own supply
chain um and so Microsoft is essentially
borrowing that that Playbook and using
that to inform the you know the the the
market across the board they're not
looking to be the sole uh one
transacting in this regard very engaged
with this new center for Green Market
activation to build a really a scaling
across Industries and applications of
this technology really a technology of
grabbing the credit and the and the
reality is that it's not it's not for
trading it's to purchase that
environmental attribute and immediately
retire it as different from say carbon
markets which are far more squishy and
less tied direct to like a a commodity
or intervention and a an environmental
attribute associated with that there's
another question here which I'd like to
take in almost two parts can we
decarbonize industry by electrification
boss it's a good question and then with
without big industrial policies or
government subsidy so it's really both
parts
right because electrification alone yeah
maybe you guys will make it but a lot of
Industries still won't get there with
just electrification that's right you
know uh
so the technical sies electrification
generally we're talking about not just
providing heat through electricity
that's actually pretty inefficient it's
carrying out a chemical reaction right
so we had the bricks this morning that
said here's a way of beating that but
yeah yeah so yeah electrochemistry I'm
an electrochemist electrochemistry is
not the answer to all your uh hopes and
dreams and uh and you know so if you'd
say you know what what are what are some
of the limitations of electrochemistry
well it takes place at interfaces it's
not a volume reaction that's one thing
that we have to realize so you know what
what we've found are there are places
where so let's just take the sublime
cement example um we're not just
electrifying it we're reducing the total
energy required to make that cement yeah
and that's that's the key that's how we
will get it to cause parody and so we
don't take it through that huge thermal
Excursion which requires fossil fuels
and also you know the problem with
important cement where the reason we're
retiring is is that you know it uh you
go through this
huge energy expenditure to create a
super dry product that and you then
hydrate it you hydrate it when you
hydrate it gives off heat but you're
never able to use any of that heat so
this huge energy Excursion we looked
that said that doesn't make any sense if
you're going to make a hydrate as your
final product how about you start off
with something that's partially hydrated
that's what we do efficiency not
electrification exactly exactly and the
electrification helps with the
efficiency but at the end of the day is
the Energy Efficiency that matters uh
our clock is telling us we're out of
time we're just starting but this is
great fun so think about always the
triangle on on Innovation it is
technology policy and business models
thank you very much thank you than
[Applause]