The following content is provided under
a Creative Common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
>> Today is pretty much just set aside for
brainstorming. So, we're probably going
to do about an hour of that uh just to
like throw the ideas that people already
have in their heads about what could be
with the problem space that we're
working on. I mean, this this whole
preparing people to deal with violence
uh and uh uh with with folks suffering
from mental uh illness and you know
there's a whole bunch of different
things that people might be interested
in working on. And the idea is that we
hope hopefully if we can get this all
out then um that we can spend next half
hour and frankly the rest of this week
uh trying to figure out who's in which
team uh you know who's who's
collaborating on similar topics and
who's interested in working.
Um and did anyone actually manage to get
through any of the readings that I had
put up? Okay. Right. So so there's a few
things in there. I realized there wasn't
a whole lot of time to read uh to read
and there's probably more stuff up there
to read than it needs to be necessarily
but it's all there as resources any any
ideas that people thought might be
interesting to work on uh going uh
Andrew and then
>> so one of the basic issues I heard from
the presentation and papers was
communication
>> so I guess uh the brainstorm simulation
but the real world system would be
communication between the psychiatrist
and the like the
>> patient patient
>> patient yes the patient along with the
psychiatrist with the person uh above
them
>> psychiatrist patient communication
>> yes
>> what's I for what they call
>> patient
>> person not the patient but patient
psychiatrist person
>> orderly
>> nurse
>> what what function do they have
>> give us more information our system is
under constraint
>> mind psychiatrist patient for Yeah. But
>> but I mean you're not talking about
psychiatrist nurse patient.
>> No, it's like uh
>> psychiatrist resident.
>> Sorry. Maybe like nurse patient and then
nurse reporting instant to
>> supervisor. Three levels. So
>> yes, that's the one.
>> So like you have a supervisor,
>> you have a nurse.
>> Yeah. Sorry guys.
>> And you have the patient. Like those
kind of like reporting up, reporting
down. Great.
>> All right. Uh yeah. So I have a couple
ideas. One of them was maybe an idea
like uh you have there's a patient and
there's two uh I guess doctors
psychiatrists
>> and so one one psychiatrist is one
psychiatrist is trying to calm the
patient while the other is doing the
opposite and trying to make this patient
as angry as possible. So the way I'm
thinking is with the one that makes you
the psychiatrist is trying to uh enrage
the patient that's kind of training in
what not to say
>> while the patient or the doctor is
trying to calm them down is
>> so so by showing how you can how what
was the worst possible way to get
>> Okay. So I couldn't call that good bad
cup.
>> Yeah. And then another idea I I had
which I thought with bashing yesterday
was um maybe have like have a team of
psychiatrist working with one patient.
But in interace in one of the uh
psychiatrist is like a saver trying to
is trying to enrage the patient.
Remember the target audience is going to
be psych like actual residents in so so
so but but I'm going to like I I I just
going to say several and a group
>> of psychiatrists
maybe an idea of the dynamic that we can
play with. Okay. Uh John
>> uh so three quick things. One would be
I'm not exactly sure how this fits into
a game, but uh simulating people who are
delusional schizophrenic by either
having every player have a a separate
like audio track playing in their ear as
they play. So there's like voices
speaking to them and they have different
audio experiences or having just one
speaker that everyone can hear that uh
that is playing audio. just
incorporating audio into the experience
to simulate in some way the internal
thought process and perhaps these
delusional thoughts that sort of you
know the voice that tells you to go kill
your mother and whatnot which isn't you
know documented issue
>> now this particular game doesn't have to
be a board game doesn't have to be a
card game you have a lot more
flexibility on how what what you want to
do I would suggest steering away from
doing anything that requires digital
logic like uh you know but you know MP3
players will be
>> right exactly so something like that um
so that's the first idea second thing
would be a board game where you're in
charge of managing a ward it's just a
logistical making sure that you don't
leave anyone neglected or or forget.
>> Oh, definitely. Okay. So, yeah, people
will
>> So, you know, patients have their
favorite nurse, you know, and they have
sort of hidden issues that you have to
uncover and and deal with. And if you
leave something unattended and someone,
you know, goes over, then they become
violent. And so, you're kind of trying
to make sure. And the the third idea
would be to have uh one player pay as
the patient and to simulate the their
inability to communicate properly for
whatever reason. the information of
their own condition is hidden hidden
from the player. And so, um, try to
create a game experience that is
genuinely frustrating because the the
the player doesn't quite know what's
wrong with them and can't articulate it
properly and the other players are in
charge of of finding it out and creates
some sort of time constraint thing. So,
it gets heated and and like
>> there are a bunch of improv games that
are exactly that. It's like I have
something about me, but I can't tell you
what it is.
>> But, but you know, if the player doesn't
even know that, it can get really
>> right. Yeah. That's like the game where
you have I can't remember what it's
called, but the one where you have you
try to make the other person say a word,
but you can't use a certain series of
like
>> I just wanted to say on the simulating
schizophrenia with audio tape.
>> Um I've been part of RPGs which have
done that well. So like live action role
playing stuff which did which did it
really well. It actually works. So um I
recommend that it's actually quite
>> exploring that further.
>> Yeah. I mean it's been tried in a
setting which I've seen before and
worked really well. So I think it could
work out.
>> Mhm.
>> You can do a refinement on that idea.
>> Uh
>> um so I know one of the main things that
he was talking about is like knowing
what to do and like just having the like
going through the process of like what
happens when somebody does something.
And so that brought to mind like D and D
and how like you have to prepare before
the encounter and then in the encounter
like you have certain actions that you
can do like calm through speech, calm
through, you know, presenting some
object or some idea or whatever. Uh
which I think would map pretty easily to
the D&D space. Um and then you could
also like you know you have certain
abilities that are natural to your
character like you're very charismatic
which makes some things easier and such.
I think that
>> so
>> so simplified D and D to um to handle
interactions with patients.
>> So so tabletop RPG style,
>> right?
>> And the kinds of things that you wanted
to emphasize were things like
preparation uh and sort of playing out
your actual skills,
>> right?
>> You know the things that you're good at,
right?
>> So natural skills
and uh preparation
All right. So, I kind of had an idea for
a game that could potentially be a card
game where the player who's playing as
the patient and the player who's playing
as the doctor are operating under
different rules. And one of the main
points of the game is that they don't
act they're not actually aware of the
other player's rules. So, for instance,
the patient could have certain goals
which he's trying to achieve,
>> but he is unaware which of these goals
is like completely unreasonable to the
doctor. And the game, the doctor has
certain actions he can take and and is
unaware which of these are going to be
threatening to the patient. And so there
there could be an instance where the
patient actually believes the only way
he is capable of winning the game is by
using violence. And so that could be one
of the end conditions,
>> right?
>> So So sure and then you you kind of have
to did you
again to
>> uh I really like the idea that uh a
psychiatrist has to really keep their
composure when they're dealing with a
violent person. they can't raise their
voice, they have to keep them a certain
distance and they can't uh you know seem
upset for whatever reason. So a sort of
a party game idea, you could have, you
know, two people um basically one person
would just have to be throwing insult at
the other person and the person who's
receiving the insults would just have to
stay calm the whole time and continue
talking, which is really hard to do even
if you know it's coming at you.
>> So like keep your cool. I mean that that
that could be a game where you're like
literally insulting someone or it could
be a thing where you're playing a
character with a certain amount of like
composure points or something like that
and you know you're sort of like
planning actions to try to maintain
those
>> uh and different tactics to be able to
increase those or decrease those
>> back uh co-op type game where you are a
bunch of nurses trying to basically take
care of the ward. So, it's a lot like
Jeremy's uh Diner Dash style game,
>> except you have a limitation to how many
you can actually do at once. So, you
will be forced to neglect one every so
often.
>> Patient one neglect one patient, one
patient, one
>> some nurses will get sick and they'll
have to leave.
>> So, so or or rather you have limited
resources uh not quite nearly enough to
deal with every single crisis that's
going to happen.
>> Okay. Um, so I the one thing that I kind
of found interesting in like reading the
stuff is that statistically the amount
of violence that happens like with
mental patients is is not actually like
that different from the amount of
violence that happens in general
population.
>> Um, and you know they talked about how
like people going through this and like
deciding to go into the profession might
actually second guess themselves because
they have this perception that there's
more violence. So I think like
incorporating something where you have
um life in the ward and life outside of
it to just like so you you incorporate
both the things where you're trying to
deal with the patients but you're also
reinforcing this idea that like it's not
it's not like significantly more
dangerous than real life is.
>> None of your patients stab you then you
get in your way home.
>> Yeah. Like something like that like you
know it's it's just life. I mean I mean
one thing one thing that would give you
the uh you may put it up one one thing
that could be really attractive is that
that now broadens your audience to
people who aren't just
psychiatric
>> right
>> so I like the idea of the patient and
doctor having different rules goals
triggers etc. Um, but I also like the
idea of incorporating like an escalation
and deescalation into the conflict
between the two of them.
>> So I feel like part of the thing which
was really compelling about the role
playing scenario that they showed was um
there was there was the sense in which
the doctor can say things which can
escalate or deescalate this the
situation, right? Make it more or less
likely that things will go in a good or
bad way. And like one way which we could
do which that could be done in partially
through roles would be to have like
hidden keywords which the um which the
patient responds to or what have you and
that kind of moves them into a different
state and then like transitioning
between these two states um changes the
goals which the the patient has. They
may be intent upon trying to get nurse
what was the name nurse's name Dave or
>> nurse John but for that as they get
deescalated then they just want to
change their meds but then as they get
dis
um deescalated from that they may just
want to go home or something like that
>> just coming up with the rules that model
what an unreasonable patient
>> Yeah. Yeah.
to give up or or what would be he
willing to give up
>> and and and actually putting somebody in
the shoes of that is actually really
useful to sort of think about what I can
do as a doctor.
>> Uh so there was this game I used to play
in my family where like you're given a
scenario and like a certain number of
words that you can't use but like you
want someone to like guess them. So
essentially like it's like you choose
random words and you have a scenario and
like very similar to what you were
saying where like certain keywords do
certain things but like you have to you
have to somehow create like the best
story or the best like calm down like
passage to read to the patient and then
like there's some arbit like arbitrator
like the GM of the game that like
decides like which of the three people
that were playing like which one had the
best story out of those um to sort of
get you to like have to come up with
something to deal with like you know you
need nurse John right away. Best way to
deal with that for
>> I mean you you you could do a thing
where you had to create a story out of a
randomized collection of elements maybe
cards you know uh but then some number
of those cards specifically the other
player or maybe there's a game master
player specifically just saying that
knows internally that you're not
supposed to be able to use those words
and there some 20 questions type of way
to be able to try to figure out what
those currents are without the language.
So that that that would be like a doctor
trying to figure out what they're
dealing with, you know, while that
>> you could make that game like guess who
where each person like draws a card and
you're allowed to like give a statement
to the other person or ask them
something and then you see whether like
escalate or deescalate and each
individual card has like traits where
you talk about this that's bad, you talk
about this that's good.
>> I I'm not familiar with guess. So, uh,
okay. So, it's not really that much like
Guess Who.
>> 20 questions. Is that
>> the idea thing of is everyone just you
have a whole bunch of character cards
and each of them have traits like watch
this? If you say this, they'll get
upset. If you say this, it's not very
fully fleshed out, but everyone just
like randomly draws traits and you take
turns like speaking to each other and
then the patients either get like will
respond and then either get like more
angry or sing.
>> So, It's almost like your like your role
is a collection of randomized traits or
randomized behavioral
uh rules.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, rules
defined
by randomized rules.
All those people um in the assassin's
guild uh or familiar with the assassin's
guild, there's the concept of cycripts.
Uh things that you're that you as an
individual player uh are are are given
at the beginning of the game as things
that you can do or you have to do or if
you do something you have to do it under
specific conditions. The psych
psychological limitations is what
they're called. It could be something as
simple as you have to speak an accent
all the time or you have to live. It
could be something more like every time
you see blur, you have to run away
because there's a phobia and something
like that. Uh, and some it might be
interesting to think of collection of
those things and that crafts how we
behave. Um, so this makes me think I
should probably do the live action class
at some point and talk about party games
and and
uh I think you have
>> Oh, I hope my hands are up.
>> Okay, your hands are just up.
like
>> um another thing that a psychiatrist has
to do when they're talking to a patient
is to try to get the story out of them
like why why they're upset. So you could
have um a game where the patient has you
know some set of of cards that uh has
some some sort of story with some
keywords and the doctor has to try to
you know get the get these words out of
him but the patient himself can't the
patient himself doesn't fully know his
story. So like he keeps on changing. You
would keep modifying your story as you
go by drawing cards and throwing them
away and you can only really get the
full picture once you get all the cards
that the patient has in his hand. So
wait, so does the patient have all the
cards?
>> The p the patient has his full story,
but it keeps changing.
>> Okay. So Okay. So
ever changing story
>> and and you want to kind of stay on top
of entropy.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Cool.
Um, this isn't a fully fleshed out idea,
but as a mechanic, um, say there's a
doctor and a patient, and the do and the
only the only communication is through
cards. So, the doctor will like give the
patient two cards, and then the third
card is randomly, uh, inserted off of
like a deck and shuffled in, and the
patient receives all three.
>> So, it's like the patient might be
schizophrenic and imagining things and
they like get whatever the doctor's
saying, but they also get like other
random things as noise. So, so as a
mechanic that will be
um man I that's hard to describe two the
idea that you will be adding a
randomized
>> so you get information that is both what
the other person played and something
random and you can't distinguish which
is which
>> so you have a communication channel and
you're handing random noise.
>> Yeah.
[Laughter]
And what is not? Yeah,
I am running out of space. So, it's
okay.
>> Any other
That's creepy.
>> Anyone else?
One concept I thought was interesting
that I'm not really sure how you turn
into a game immediately is the idea of
the
patient and bically the doctor or the
rest of the world having to at the
moment irreconcilable irreconcilable
narratives
>> and the goal of bringing those into some
type of medium in which the patient can
you know comfortably exist with this
narrative that's in with the rest of the
world,
>> right?
>> So the the idea again of that narrative
disruption is kind of why people get
violent in the first place and so maybe
even taking out the question entirely of
what makes is this person going to act
violently, but can you even work
together with somebody to change how
they see the world until it makes sense
on both on both sides? Yeah.
>> Yeah. So that would something I can't
like actually that you would gain for
now be something like okay so you have
the patient's trying to tell this
patient and do doctor patient and doctor
and one person trying to portray a
message that one person the other person
trying to portray to the other but
there's like some something in the
middle that's changing everything
>> and so it's just trying to reconcile
that difference pretty much
>> figure out the connection like the
communication between each other
>> so so you kind of have a situation where
you actually have three people playing
And it's just some one person who's
changing information on
>> either predict unpredictable
unpredictable way
>> like maybe they they have their own
objective in mind.
>> So what they're trying the two people in
the end are trying to like figure out
what the other one's saying and then one
person in the middle is trying to has
their has their own agenda.
>> That's like representing schizophrenia.
So, so, so that there's a noisy
communications channel with an agenda. I
like that.
>> Yeah. I mean, that that could be a
algorithm that could be a person. Uh, it
could be a person running an algorithm
in their head. So, yeah.
>> Yeah. I mean, the noisy communication
channel could represent the actual state
of mind of the the patient. That is the
point, right? But I mean and then
depending upon again they're like the
level of arousal that could change like
how everything gets streamed into being
like very combative. And so like
everything the doctor says is sort of
taken as being
somehow
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. some sort of some sort of variable
that's actually going to affect how
they're going to
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
Um, this meant well, this would probably
only work once the first time you play
through, but again, what you've
concealed from the players or certain
players themselves that
uh what their goals are or what they
believe to be true about the game state
is in fact a delusion or not true. So
you might you might tell them that it's
about this is a game set in 2100 when
you've been wrongly imprisoned in a
psychiatric ward and you must fight your
way out or something like that and
there's a you know voice will guide you
you know whatever and then and then but
you don't you don't tell you don't tell
that player that they're in fact playing
a player who believes you know these
things and you and then maybe you do
some sort of live action role playing or
not I'm not exactly sure but a game
which otherwise are forces with this
other guy who's convinced that this is
what the game is about. So it's like an
unreliable Yeah, I'm going to write an
unreliable scenario. Uh I know the
players don't know that going in, but uh
if folks have seen the film The Cabinet
of of Dr. Kagari, it's an old Germanic
specialist uh white film and I could
spoil it. Does anyone care? It's the old
1920s.
>> Unspoilers. I think you're fine. Uh but
but the basic idea comes down to the
hero of this sort of horror story is
actually just a patient in the in
psychiatric war and everybody who he
believes is part of this story that he's
uh conquering is somebody else in
psychiatric war. The big villain is
actually the person running.
>> Is that like Shutter?
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's like Shutter.
>> Yeah. Yeah. not not not not entirely
unlike a lot of different stories. But
similarity idea of the you know maybe
maybe the information we've been given
is not that they need to be trusting
something that go like that would be I
guess a game mechanic part of that would
be everyone's assigned a different role
and one of those roles is patient and so
you don't know if you're the patient or
not and so you're trying to do your
objectives and then as you play along
you realize you may or start to realize
things aren't actually as what they
seem. So eventually you may figure out
I'm actually the patient here.
>> Right. Right. Who's trying to train who?
And they're almost like fighting for
authority in that sense possibly. Okay.
>> Going along with that. Uh I think an
interesting mechanic would be like the
battle star black sylons method where
you the person knows that they're Sylon,
but they can infiltrate by doing that
voting system at the end. What is that?
It's the with the destiny part.
>> So you know that someone's trying to
sabotage you but you don't know who,
>> right? So gosh, how um
patient.
>> So that's kind of who's the patient from
a different way, right? It's like one is
you know player knows
>> who you know at least at least one
person knows
>> and then the other one is uh player
needs to figure out whether they are it.
>> This is just an interesting mechanic
thing. So there was this again RPG
called Brea the Oblivion that had this
really interesting mechanic for handling
the dark side that each player had which
might be kind of relevant in this
situation. Essentially, you had a
different person who was also playing
another protagonist also play your
antagonist.
>> And so they would either talk to you and
tell you things or they would just
directly control your character like if
you kind of fail the compos the
composure role. And taking the
adversarial side of your character away
from your control kind of um it it means
that you your character is more likely
to behave in a really disruptive way
rather than just a controllably
disruptive way how it would be if you
were had a best interest in your
character.
>> So open takes control of your character.
>> Yeah. Uh and and that might work really
well with some of the ideas of I did a
good cop bad cop ide.
Okay.
>> So, um actually going off of the uh the
like the audio idea of like someone is
is actually hearing voices and this
whole um who was the patient thing, you
could actually have things where you
have uh one player is actually playing a
patient who is schizophrenic
>> and another player is playing the voices
in his head.
So you you but like they don't really
know that like they they're playing this
scenario where you know they they have
some delusion that they're crafted or
whatever. Um
>> Oh.
>> So like like having having like just
have a person actually being the like
like as you were saying like have an
actual person be the dark side of of the
patient.
>> Um
so but neither of them know who's the
dark side. Well, I mean the the patient
Yeah. I mean you could have
>> one way you could arbitrate this is you
could say that the the patient player is
able to just basically do as they please
but
>> with there are rules which govern
whether the dark side character can take
over.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Something like that. Or
>> so and that means that means that the
patient is kind of genuinely driven to
try and reach a compromise but they can
just be overruled by dark side. Yeah.
>> So,
>> and there could also be things where
like it's it could be like more of a
strong role playinging thing where the
voice is actually just trying to
convince him that yes, this delusion is
real.
>> So, but you still think you have a
recorded thing or actually two different
>> You could actually have two people just
actually standing there talking to each
other.
>> Okay. So, two uh people playing one
character.
>> Yeah.
>> It it would potentially require a lot of
suspension of disbelief on the part of
the uh person playing the psychiatrist.
It might be one of those things that's
easier to um mediate by having people
uh talk through a screen or something
like that, you know, uh or even a
microphone and a speaker kind of thing.
Could be a game where you can play on a
phone.
>> Uh that would be
>> I've not seen many games that are
designed specifically to be played on
phones, but function.
I definitely like that idea and I think
it could work well with a card game as
well if you have two players sharing the
same hand and the player who actually
gets to play the cards from the hand is
whoever is in control of the patient and
so as things uh diff as the state
basically changes depending on what the
doctor does uh different players become
in control of the patient's hand.
>> So so it seems like we actually have a
lot of different options on how we could
mechanic uh somebody who's mentally
unstable. uh and um and a bunch of also
a bunch of ideas of how how that state
switch could happen uh or what rules
make up. Uh so that's pretty cool and
that that's not
uh and that's not mutually exclusive
from any other ideas specifically about
a patient and a doctor, right? So all
we're talking about what happens to the
patient. Uh these are the rules that a
patient could be operating under. The
doctor could have a different set of
rules, all rules.
>> I was reading about this and I think
that it turns out most violence in
psychiatric wards happens uh to the
patients themselves or to other patients
by patients much more than it actually
happens to towards practitioners.
>> And I'm just noticing that I don't think
any of our ideas addressed any of those
issues. board management maybe gets a
little closer.
>> Yeah, people start turning on
themselves.
>> So, I was I was just thinking so another
possible way that you could apply all
this a lot of these role playing
multiple role or auditory mechanics is
to a situation. we should we we should
probably do research in what situations
lead to patients coming in contact with
each other and then the encounter
turning violent. And then perhaps just
having
all players be patients that have
various different mental disorders. And
then and just to help you understand in
the as a patient what what kinds of
behaviors and situations would lead you
to uh going violent on someone else.
>> Just sort of one of those like be in
someone else's shoes helps you
understand the situation better,
>> right? So just putting them in uh in a
situ uh putting them in an environment
where everything that is necessary for
your charact for a certain character to
become upset environment and then just
seeing how that naturally occurs without
necessarily saying and now you
>> okay
a game of persuasion that's a cross
between like BS and Uno. So, you have
two doctors who are trying to get rid of
cards in their hand. Um, and then the
patient wants a certain set of cards and
he's saying, "I'm looking for John." And
the two doctors pull out a card, they
say, "Oh, this is John." Or they can be
like, "This isn't John, but I can help
you out later."
>> Oh, so this is a this is that almost
seems like an educate um intended to
teach people not to.
>> So, um so I'm going to say
fish.
>> Yeah. Honest honesty.
So, we got a pretty good pile here. Um,
a lot of these
uh can obviously be combined and there's
no reason why multiple groups couldn't
attempt to do similar topics. Uh, in
fact, you could take exactly the same
set and I'm pretty sure two different
groups are going to come in the same
way. So, that's fine. Uh, again, a lot
of live of things that could probably be
easier done live action or at least
easier to prototype live action. the um
the the the folks who were here on
Monday um they are actually
uh focused mostly on trying to see what
could be moved out to more people uh
more resident trainee uh in uh in the
future. Your games don't necessarily
need to do that but uh but you might
want want to keep that this this
assignment is game for a client after
all. And you know, if you manage to
address that need of the, you know,
here's something that doesn't require
one person from the original GMT
to do it. And you can imagine like you
know the acting exercise that that that
that they ran through you know Dion's
particularly talented uh at improvising
to speak but you know requires
requires uh you know people requires
resources that not necessarily um every
every training environment is going to
have something that can be turned into a
fairly understandable set set of rules
or use or using technologies that are
fairly accessible. um you know, if
you're going to play your voice in
someone's ear, it's going to be a lot
easier if that was using uh something
recorded or something like a phone as
opposed to
that if it was if it was a phone
conversation actually going like so it's
live and people are in different rooms
and actually talking to each other over
the phone over Skype or something like
that. But but you're talking to someone,
you have a phone up so then the other
person can hear what you're saying and
be the evil voice
>> like you know.
>> Yeah. such a thing that you don't even
need to do on Skype, right? You just get
two cell phones to hit with with
handsree sets and and now the technology
just becomes that much easier for for
users to
two phones and two two headsets. It's
almost
>> I mean or you could make it that like
for some game that two people are
playing that like two groups are playing
the same game but they both hear the
other group like this group would hear
the other groups playing the game. So,
it's not even just like a random
conversation. It's like they're playing
the same game you're playing, but you're
hearing the other group playing the
game. So, you get to
>> Wow.
>> Uh deep.
>> I would say two groups
uh you drop in the same game.
So, I just wanted to say
that I think the thing which is really
hard if you don't if you're working with
people who like don't really want to do
a role playing thing
>> is like building a level of emotional
intensity and the fear of violence.
Um, which is kind of the point of the
training like you want to be able to
deal with that kind of emotional stress
on your feet.
>> Yeah. Um, so I was just wondering
because I don't have any good ideas if
anyone could think of something which
which works out
>> which can like genuinely create a
situation where a monkey would be afraid
of violence.
>> Yeah.
>> Without actually without somebody having
to threaten another person.
I don't think he's going to be able to
color on
>> well well if one player's role is
actually
not to understand but to provide the
experience for the other
>> and they're hearing a recording that is
giving them cues as to what to do and
one of their cues is eventually like and
no player is not brief this and one of
their cues is like and now you know
grabbing the player by the shoulders and
like shake them violently and say you
know say something you could you could
possibly create a situ situation where
you're like, whoa, you know, buddy,
>> but the problem is you have to be able
to get somebody who can do that without
like cracking up in the middle of it
because like people do that when they're
nervous and uncomfortable. Like you so
you pretty much be reduced to finding
professional actors and that's a limited
resource that like limit puts a
limitation on on how widespread your
game
>> even people will take things seriously
resource you have.
>> I have a thought where you have like
it's a patient patient interaction. So
you have two people in different rooms
on the phone with each other trying to
negotiate something. I don't know what
what it would be and have two other
people in each of in each of their rooms
that are like talking in their ear and
trying to distract them from the
conversation.
>> Okay. So so patient talking to patient
uh maybe can like
medicine
uh with uh voices in person. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh there is a specifically an article on
that I think. So actually
Patrick.
>> Um so I was thinking something along the
lines of of like battleship if you have
um like a doctor player and patient
player and they're both looking at this
um their own version of the same board
>> and if the uh the patient wants to get
from one end to the other um and the
doctor has to allow whether or not they
can make their move but on the doctor's
board they have like different obstacles
and so then um like the patient will say
I want to move from here to here and the
doctor says I can't let you do that I
can let you go from here to here um it'd
be a game about a compromise
>> okay so sort of uh okay um doctor
mediated movement okay
forward movement
>> and and the battleship analogy is good
to help us remember.
>> Yeah. Uh to address something that Owen
said about the trying to simulate u
fear. Uh I mean if you can add time
pressure to any game then I think that
that strong of a stress situation it
could kind of almost be fear. It could
be a spider
>> because what what you're really going
for is stress
you're going to make decision
>> falling creating.
>> Yeah.
>> Anyways,
>> uh
>> um so kind of like an idea of how to
take the the doctor mediated board and
move it into the real world is that you
could have we're talking about these
like phoneto phone conversations. You
could have the patient is like um in a
room but he's blindfolded
>> and like he's trying to like move
through the room like towards an exit in
the room or something and the doctor has
like some limited information about the
room and has to like help him like
navigate through the room and he'll say
like I want to move you know forward and
he's like well you yeah you I can't
really let you do that because there's a
pit of spikes in front of you. So you
wouldn't necessarily actually have a
real pitull of spikes in front of them,
but like that that kind of thing where
you're trying to like gather information
and and help them through this and it
you can like even put time pressure on
it and say like, well, you know, I have
to make a decision now because he wants
to move now,
>> but I might like accidentally move him
into an obstacle and like how to deal
with that. that or you could have a
thing where no or you can combine it
with some things that there are things
that the that the patient needs to do
that the patient can talk about.
>> Uh and you know it might be something
like the patient has to move every 10
seconds and only the patient knows this.
The doctor doesn't
>> the patient has a fear of moving to the
left
>> or something like that. Things like that
patient has moved left. And I think it
it also emphasizes the thing that um
they were talking about on Monday in
that you are both trying to to not like
if if a it gets to the escalates to the
point where violence happens,
>> you're both trying to not let yourself
get hurt, but you're also trying to not
hurt them as well.
>> And I think incorporating that some way
would be cool.
>> Definitely a lot of these ideas and sort
of like mechanicking the patients
limitations are really really cool. uh
but again remember the audience is the
resident. So understanding what what
what what patient going through is
useful but also understanding thinking
of rules that help uh resident
understand what they can do uh is also
really important. So don't don't don't
just think about throwing tons of
limitations on them without also giving
them abilities uh you know things that
they can actively do that you can
actually carry out. So ripping off the
time pressure thing, I think that it
might make sense for these kinds of
escalation negotiation type situations
for the um for the person who is
controlling the patient to kind of know
what their triggers are and every time
like a bad thing is said then the they
just reduce the amount of time that the
doctor has to deal with them
>> and like and they say that okay they
just say like minus 10 seconds and like
and the they have a timer and ticks down
to reach the conclusion, getting the the
doctor, getting them to where they want
to be.
>> Um, and and so rather than like raising
their voice or being physically in some
way, they just like adjust a timer and
when it gets down to zero. So,
>> yeah, I can see that I wrote equals
reduce time variable
actually equals.
>> Okay. Um,
just to say that way you can make your
players feel pressure is to give them a
really flat goal hierarchy, right? So, a
good example is missile command. Does
everyone know that game? So, missile
command is you have like six cities and
there's missiles coming and you have to
shoot them all down and each city is
equally valuable. So, if you lose one,
you're in drastically reduced position.
Um whereas games that tend to have like
a more structured goal hierarchy will
have like basically means you can afford
a loss, right? So like chess is a good
example. You say, "Okay, I can afford to
lose this." Whereas a missile command,
you can't afford to lose anything. So by
really capping,
you know, what the player has and what
they're what they can afford to lose.
And then making sure that, you know, all
of their goals are equal value, that
means that every loss and every failure
is felt much more strongly. And I I felt
like at least Dion when you were doing
your the role play um there was this
sense especially coming from Caesar that
you know any one thing that goes wrong
is really bad. There's like a really
thin line there.
>> I mean that's especially applicable when
you're talking about the doctor's goals,
not necessarily the patient's goals.
>> Yeah. Yeah. From I mean from the
doctor's position, right? There's you
can't really afford a lot of mistakes in
these situations.
Um, I'm kind of the guest, but I was
listening to what you're saying and um,
I've had a thought on how you could
combine lots of these different ideas.
Um, I'm envisioning a game where there
would be two types of players like you
were mentioning, um, doctors and
patients. And there would be one doctor
and multiple patients. It would be a
turn-based game where you'd go around,
give each person a turn. and the doctor
would always be in a relationship with
each individual one and um limited
vocabulary I thought was important. Um
taking that from a couple of the ideas,
the patient and the doctor each have
their own set of vocabularies and the
clash of that would introduce some um a
mechanic there where the patient has um
their own vocabulary describing to the
doctor what they like, what they don't
like. Um they know what they like, they
don't like. you you could abstract it to
um describe uh maybe
anything that the doctor would have in
their vocabulary. So, uh as one example,
the doctor could give the patient a card
with a shape or um some item on it and
the item has attributes like color,
shape, something that um somebody could
like or dislike in their list. um they
would look at this and see um one of
these things clashes with something in
my list of dislikes. I don't like that
card. I'm going to escalate my um my
anger, my uh displeasure with the
situation. And so the doctor has a
limited amount of time to deal with each
patient. Um as the patient's escalation
increases,
they have less and less time to be dealt
with. After a certain point, the doctor
loses that patient. So you have that
loss brought in. Um and then after all
the patients have been lost, the the
game is over. The way that it would be
won is that the doctor is discovering
the profile of each patient because they
are trying to um like in a normal
setting in a in a real life setting,
you're trying to discover the the
profile that allows the doctor to um
deal with the patient in the best
possible way so that they aren't
violent. Um and yeah, so so so that that
seems to play off the um the patient and
doctor have different ro rules and goals
and triggers. You know, you've got a
situation where in in uh in what he was
suggesting, you have one doctor to
multiple patients. Um which is which is
accurate. I'm not quite sure that that
they'd be dealing with them
simultaneously, but that might not
matter for the purposes of strategy. Uh
and uh and
and yeah, it might be it might be kind
of like those like those improv things
where if you manage to figure out uh if
you manage to figure out before time
runs out what a person's profile is,
that could be the win condition. So it's
equal win uh if you manage to succeed is
an equal loss if you don't manage to get
it by time. combine it with something
like the uh give a trigger and reduce
the amount of time that you have
available. Number of turns available for
doesn't have to be real time. Um so yeah
so so that so you can present with
multiple patients.
>> So like that doesn't even necessarily
have to deal with uh actual talking
about actual psychiatric warrant
situations. That could be something
like, you know, objects and colors,
right? You know, it's more of a guessing
game, but uh that might be too abstract
possibly because because in the end, you
kind of still want people to be able to
tie it back to the experience of uh like
to be able to make make an easy
connection with uh what it's like to be
a resident or what's going to be like to
be a resident. Um so, uh this is where
the theme needs to be pretty clear. Um
but then like Clara, you know, is not
meeting. The meeting has also done tied
pretty well with young mechanics. Um so
uh that's just something to keep in
mind.
Um
okay. Um so we've got about another half
an hour plus. Uh
I think the plan was just to let
everyone kind of like figure out what
teams you wanted to be in. you know,
this is kind of pre-class time to talk
uh to talk with each other and um see if
there's stuff in here that people were
really psyched about. Is there is there
anyone in this class that's already
like, you know, this is something I
really want to do? Um
>> well, my preference is towards the
management.
>> Okay. So, what award management.
So yeah, just one.
>> Yeah, I don't really have any plans for
this.
>> I'd be interested in in uh in voices and
hidden information. So
fooling players in in and that results
in them behaving in erratic ways as from
the point of view of other players and
then from the point of view the player
who's behaving radically other players
behaving erratically because it's not
fitting with what they think is actually
going on
>> or voices or both or something like
that.
>> So that's that's kind of the general
territory that you're interested in
anyone who wants to
>> I'm very interested in the escalation
deescalation by hidden keywords.
I like uh I like basically hidden rules,
goals, and keywords and two different
players uh playing the same character.
Two mechanics I really like.
Okay, we we have a couple of seeds out
there and uh you know the caffeine helps
us a bunch in the
um what do we have on Friday?
>> Um Friday we mostly just have
brainstorming and team building
schedule. I mean I think that time is
pretty flexible.
>> So what I can do maybe if folks can plan
to come into Wednesday with the team
then what I might do is I might move my
my
>> Friday. Friday.
Yeah. Then um then I will I'll move my
live action talk up till Friday instead.
>> So So Wednesday we can just follow. It
seems like a lot of people are going in
that direction.
Yeah. Okay. You don't have to do a live
action game, but it's one of my favorite
games. So