Hello.
Uh, my name is Andrew Dorne and I'm here
today to talk about Nominal, the future
of test.
Um, I'm head of engineering at Nominal
and uh, class of uh, 2014 here at MIT.
Um, we're fortunate to have uh, two MIT
co-founders uh, Cameron and Jason. Um at
nominal we're building the connected
suite of software for hardware test and
validation.
Um we're fortunate to have built a team
of a hundred of the best operators um
from across the world um from the likes
of Loheed Martin and Applied Intuition
and Palunteer. Um and we're backed by
some of the best investors. Um, we've
been fortunate enough to partner with
some of the best engineering teams
across both commercial and the DoD.
At Nominal, we believe that test and
validation are the critical bottlenecks
of hardware. Test velocity defines
program timelines, manufacturing
capacity, and operational performance.
And today's best hardware teams test
early and often with real-time
automation, rapid field validation
across development, production, and
operations.
And we also believe that the future of
hardware test is connected. Engineers
want to be thinking about paradigms
exactly the same throughout the entire
operational life cycle of hardware test
and development from manufacturing
integration test system test field test
and validation and finally live
operations and with nominal you can do
this all in one centralized place.
The current software stack for hardware
test is fragmented and isolated.
Engineers burn hours upon hours merging
files, trying to correlate logs, and
running one-off scripts that often they
didn't even write. Ultimately,
ultimately resulting in delayed
milestones, cost overruns, and
unreliable results. With Nominal, you
have a unified software stack across our
two main products, Nominal Core and
Nominal Connect. It is truly the modern
tool chain for real world engineering.
Nominal core is our unified multimodal
cloud-based offering for high-scale
data, real-time operations, operational
procedures, and asset management.
Enominal connect is our edge-based test
stand focused uh product around command
and control as well as syncing data back
to the cloud back to core. I want to
talk through an example use case of
nominal in the field with one of our
partners, Hermus. Hermes is trying to
build a hypersonic aircraft, the uh Mach
1. They go, they fly the test. Uh they
want to upload the data into nominal VR
APIs. They're able to easily generate
and automate templatized analysis VR
workbooks. And they are also able to
collaborative collaboratively identify
test points and anomalies with their
teammates ultimately leading to faster
triage of results with the ability to
modify the system more quickly and then
go test again.
We found that with nominal uh the Hermes
engineers were 80% faster going from
data generation to data analysis
enabling their first flight in just
seven months and the CEO of Her Hermes
thought that this was a critical part of
their hardware development life cycle.
Finally, if you're developing,
manufacturing, testing, deploying, or
operating complex hardware, please reach
out. We're working across a variety of
industries, aerospace, defense, autonomy
to name a few. Again, my name is Andrew
Dorne. I'm here with my partners, Wesley
Gao. Uh, please reach out. We'd love to
talk. Thank you.