Thank you everyone. Um I'm Sake. I'm the
co-founder and CSO at Blue Shift. And
I'm joined by my co-founder and CEO
Deep. And we are working on um AI
powered crit AI powered electrochemical
systems for critical minerals
extraction. What that means is
the demand for lithium, nickel, raers
and copper is increasing but the orgrade
quality is decreasing. And so what that
means is we need to put in more energy
to extract the same amount of materials.
We need to move more earth to extract
the same amount of materials and meet
the growing demands.
Um and in addition um the US is
dependent on external or foreign sources
for a lot of our critical mineral
supply. Um and these rare earth elements
are essential to a lot of different
applications particularly relevant for
the defense and tech sectors. So what
are we doing here? Our tech stack takes
inputs such as industrial waste,
electricity and brines. And we have a
profitable autonomous and electrified
solution that converts these waste
materials into minerals, non-hazardous
waste and building materials. The way we
do that is we have uh a combination of
an AI ML model, an electrochemical cell
and a sequence of intensified unit
process operations. Our AI model will
help us design our flowheets smartly,
optimize our operating conditions and
run our process autonomously. Our
electrochemical cell allows us to
generate acid and base on demand
reducing the operational expenses and
splitting salt without using
electrodialysis. Our sequence of unit
operations is intensified that allows us
to deploy a plant for much lower capex
and much lower opex in a more lean
fashion.
Um in terms of our timeline, we are
targeting a pilot uh in early next year
followed by a demo scale plant in 2027
and a large scale plant in 2028.
Now you may ask why can we do this? The
simple reason that we can do this is
because sub1 billion units are
uneconomical for mining majors to
extract materials from. Um and we are
using industrial waste feed stocks and
so we can avoid uh relying on permits
because it's secondary mining. It's
pre-permitted
and our selective leeching allows us to
extract from lowgrade or so because of
this we can now intercept the declining
primary ore grades and translate this to
primary uh ores as well. This allows us
to unlock historically unavailable
resources.
And with this uh in terms of commercial
traction and partnerships, we are
seeking feed stock partners for joint
development agreement for different
kinds of feed stocks like coldfly ash or
redmud as examples. And we are also
looking for product offtakes for all
three uh comm all three product uh
families. high value off takes, medium
value takes and our uh bulk products.
With this uh yeah, that's all us.