after checking in the students get
introduced to a technique called nuclear
magnetic resonance or NMR for short NMR
helps chemists piece together a molecule
structure the students put their mystery
molecule into a thin tube and lower it
into a very powerful magnetic field this
forces certain atoms in the sample to
align themselves either with or against
the field aligning with the field takes
less energy so there are a few more
atoms aligned with than against the
field a pulsive energy makes the extra
atoms aligned with the field flip the
computer measures how much energy this
takes and produces a spectrum the amount
of energy it takes to flip an atom
depends on what other atoms are next to
it that means you can tell which of the
atoms are connected and put together a
picture of what the whole molecule looks
like for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow