okay so good
morning we're still uh playing with
mixtures properties of multicomponent
systems and
um we've done we've defined
uh some ideal Behavior like the Gibs
Dalton mixture that applies for ideal
gases and today we'll extend that to the
case of liquid
mixtures remember this we was last uh
last slide of the last
lecture and we were discussing this uh
Leonard Jon's
interactions between
particles and remember that in the gas
phase when we can apply the ideal gas
model the
particles uh on average leave far away
from each
other they do experience the Collision
uh very often and so very often they do
experience this acceleration towards the
other particle and then the the uh
repulsion that pushes it back and then
finishes the uh the Collision but uh uh
the time that they spend in this area is
much smaller than the time they spend
far away from each other and therefore
uh for the calculation of the average
properties at stable
equilibrium
uh each particle is behaves as if it
work by
itself and in fact that's the behavior
that we have observed also for
mixtures and uh so also for mixtures
whether the particles are closed to
similar particles or to different
particles uh if we are in the Gibbs
Dalton mixture uh
limit the same holds also for different
particles but you can see that if there
are uh mixtures in which for
example uh the individual components
when
pure uh stay far from each other but
when mixed like to stay
close in that case you would have a non
ideal
Behavior because if they spend more time
in this uh close by area then uh this
will influence and you cannot neglect
anymore this energy of
interaction okay now
similar
to uh the Gibs Dalton mixture Behavior
we can Define also an ideal solution
behavior for the liquid
phase like sketched here so in the
liquid of course the particles live very
close to one another and so they live
very close to this dip in the um Leonard
John's
potential
but we can consider an ideal situation
uh hypothetical of course uh but it's a
good start for any kind of modeling
uh uh or it could be also taken it's
actually taken typically as a reference
and then we we
will describe U uh actual real solution
Behavior as uh
departures uh with respect to the ideal
solution Behavior okay this ideal
solution behavior is one in
which
um this effect of the energy of
interaction is
alike for the particles for the say for
the a particles and for the B particles
and it's also alike for the A and B
particles so essentially these particles
are very similar to one another
and they don't really care if the
neighbor is similar or
not and that in that limit therefore
there is no
contribution to um the enthalpy of
mixing because you remember the enthalpy
of mixing has to do with the fact that
for example here if you if I take a um a
gray particle and I put it in a in a a
container full of black
particles uh the enthalpy of of mixing
is the change in the
energy uh if I keep the same temperature
and pressure uh due to uh mixing adding
one mole of that gray substance into the
black uh uh
bulk and um so
if the if the if the particle lives in
this
area the enthalpy of mixing will be
related to this uh deep in the
energy
uh now this other uh case for the liquid
case we are somewhere here so so the the
energy somewhere here but it's the same
for all and
so uh
even if you add uh one more gray
particle it doesn't really make a
difference for the energy it doesn't
really make a difference for the volume
also because being at the same living at
the same distance the volume also
doesn't change for the mixture but it
does make sense I mean
make a
difference uh regarding the entropy
because as you uh remember uh when we
did this entropy of mixing uh
idea um the fact that
uh you have added one more gray particle
you have
diluted uh the
mixture so you have
changed say what we call the uh the
surprise when you see a gray molecule
now you've changed the probability of
seeing the gray molecule uh with respect
to the to the to the black one and that
is accounted for by the entropy of
mixing that's
why the entropy of mixing does is the
only effect so in this ideal solution
Behavior we only have this uh entropy of
mixing
effect now if you remember uh the
chemical
potential
for any
constituent was written this way as the
chemical potential of the pure component
at the same temperature and pressure of
the
mixture plus the enthalpy of mixing of
that component minus the temperature
times the entropy of mixing and we've
use this relation already a few
times so if I
substitute the three assumptions up
here all right so let me do first the
volume okay for the volume I have to
remember that the volume of the mixture
is given as we have proven by in general
as a weight at sum of the partial
volumes of the constituents in the
mixture and the partial volume volumes
can be written as the specific volume of
the pure component at the same
temperature and pressure of the mixture
plus the volume of mixing so in in this
case the volume of mixing is assumed to
be zero for the ideal solution
behavior and so all we are left is that
the volume is given by the weighted sum
of the volumes that the single pure
components would occupy at the same
temperature and pressure and this is
amagat law of additive
volumes something that we Pro we we
proved this satisfied also by a Gibs
Delton mixture of Ideal
gases for the chemical
potential so Delta X mix oh yeah here
there should be an equal
zero I thought I corrected this all
right uh so equal Z and equal Z
so Delta x uh Delta H is equal to zero
and Delta s is equal to minus r log of Y
which is the surprise multiplied by the
bolman
constant or the gas constant H so the
minus and the minus become plus and so
the chemical potential becomes plus RT
log of
Y at this
stage a the solution behavior is when
this happens for all uh
constituents and this is a very rare
practical situation but again it's a
good starting point a good reference uh
situation on which you can make some
calculations
now this ideal uh mix
solution Behavior can be used to derive
uh an
important aspect of equilibria across
semi-permeable membranes which is the
osmotic
pressure
concept and osmotic
pressure was nothing by about the
difference between the pressure of the
mixture and the pressure that the pure
component has when in mutual equilibrium
on the other side of a
membrane that is permeable only to that
component so it's p minus Pi I
I
and
now the expression that I just uh uh
reminded us uh uh on the other slide
just
uh just behind this uh is uh is
Rewritten
here by remembering that
U of course across that
membrane there is a equilibrium Mutual
equilibrium and the condition for Mutual
equilibrium is that the chemical
potential of the constituent in the
mixture is equal to the uh chemical
potential of the pure
constituent uh on the other side of the
membrane so up here where the pressure
is the partial
pressure so
this and also here I see um another
error to be corrected on the slides this
would be double I here and double I
here um so this is equal to the this is
the chemical potential this is equal to
the chemical potential of the
constituent in the
mixture uh but it is equal to the pure
chemical potential at the partial
pressure so as you remember when you we
calculate this uh difference
since uh we know that the the derivative
of chemical potential with respect to
pressure is the is a specific volume
this integral can be easily done once we
know the equation of state of the
substance of the pure
substance
okay so this is nothing uh new but it's
the starting point of this observation
made by Ian
Toof namely that when
uh we have a solution
and we have a dilute solution so a
dilute solution means that there is a
lot of a substance think of say a lot of
gray
particles and a few solutes so the one
is called the solvent and the other the
others are called the
solutes and the solvent is the
predominant
amount so that means that the mole
fraction of the Sol is very close to
one and one
minus the mole fraction of the solvent
which is equal to the sum of the mo
fractions of the
solutes is much less than one so that is
a dilute
solution now in a dilute
solution
um if you put in
a um a gray
particle in the Box in which there are
already many many gray
particles it's very likely that that
particle will end up with neighbors that
are
gray so in this
situation there is no enthalpy of mixing
there is no change in volume of mixing
so it's exactly the kind of behavior
that uh describes the ideal solution
behavior for the solvent only
though so what we are saying is that of
one tough observations is that in any
dilute
solution even if we are not in that
limiting situation in which the blue I
mean the the dark and and gray
particles um are
identical in terms of interact
intermolecular
interactions uh even they're very
different but the fact that there are
few uh black particles makes the makes
that the addition of a gray one doesn't
doesn't change the uh the the energy and
the volume of of the mixture so in other
words the solvent of a dilute solution
behaves according to the ideal solution
model
and of
course that doesn't mean that there is
no effect in adding the gray particle
because again if we add the gray
particle it it is going to
dilute further uh the solution and that
will have an effect on the entropy of
mixing for example if you take the
entropy of mixing here which is that
expression that we derived and
you write
it for this solution
here um see the reason I want to write
it carefully is that U I want to compute
the entropy of mixing and that is that
the derivative of
s not with respect to the mole fractions
but with respect to the amount or
consitent I one which is the
solvent and so I have to uh M write
explicitly how the mole fractions depend
on the amount and you see uh there is an
N1 in the numerator but there is also an
N1 in the denominator so when you take
the derivative you have to be
careful and so uh well if you do
it it turns
out that the change in this entropy of
of mixing by due to the addition of a
small amount of N1 is indeed equal to
minus r log of Y and that is the
surprise so this backs up V's
observation so at least for the solvent
we can use
um the ideal
the ideal mixture
uh solution so we can set Delta H equal
to zero here and Delta s mix equals to
minus r log of Y so this becomes a plus
RT log of Y and here it
is and for the other side you see this
integral now if we apply it to a liquid
so if we talking about out a dilute
liquid
solution the specific volume of a liquid
under the
incompressible
ideal uh fluid is is constant doesn't
change with temperature and pressure so
this V goes out of the integral and it
becomes
um the specific volume of the solvent
times the difference in the in
integration limits and that's the
osmotic
pressure so we got the expression here
for the osmotic
pressure uh actually van makes an
additional
approximation noticing that
since
the the assumption is that the solution
is dilute it means that uh the mole
fraction of solute is very close to one
so we can write it as one minus the mole
fractions of the solutes
and uh and then we can take the first uh
term in the tayor series expansion of
log of one minus X which is minus
X so this becomes
simply uh the summation of the solutes
and finally we we have this expression
which is the V relation says the osmotic
pressure of the
solvent is equal to RT divided by the
specific volume and again here this
should be a
v11 another
error uh um
times the mole the sum of the mole
fractions of the
solutes notice that it doesn't really
matter what the solutes are can be any
molecule could be sugar could be uh
chlorine and so on could be salt except
that U
as we will see in a moment because that
is the uh important application that we
want to
discuss as you know some molecules for
example salt when you put it in water
they separate they dissociate and then
they get solvated they
hydroly and uh and
so
uh you have to be careful when counting
the
molecules because when you have uh for
example uh the mole you put in a certain
fraction of of salt and then you um
uh
um it gets dissolved for each mole that
you put in you get two moles of
solutes so you have to double
this now
clearly this issue of uh uh osmotic
pressures is important in biology and as
I told you several times I no expert in
biology so I don't want to talk about it
because um it's too risky to say wrong
things but I can point you to a nice
YouTube um lecture where you can learn
about osmosis in biology
and it tells you how cells uh
um receive
exchange across the
membrane um molecules depending on
whether uh there is a the chemical
potential is if there is equality of
chemical potential of course you're in
equilibrium but if the concentration are
are are different than those that you
are at equilibrium then depending on the
sign of the difference in the chemical
potential you can have a a flow in One
Direction or the other and that is
helpful in uh regulating the metabolism
of the
cell and in this video you also are uh
brought to understand what the
difference between plant uh membranes of
plant cells and animal cells are they
are kind of different and they um they
behave behave in different uh ways in
the plants they can sustain more
pressure in the animal cells they are
more fragile so to speak and they can
break there are also uh important uh
applications
in chemical engineering for
example recently of course there is this
um U big uh
topic
of developing lithium ion
batteries
and here you have um this lithium
ion molecules these
pinkish molecule that
are um in dilute Solutions of solvents
and these solvents for example in this
case are some kinds of
carbonates so the osmotic
pressure of course you are if you are at
the osmotic pressure you you are in
equilibrium and nothing moves on average
but uh if you do not have the same the
concentrations that deliver the osmotic
pressure then you can have osmosis which
is the movement of the ey ions uh in
search
to better
equilibrium so let's uh talk about
seawater as the example as you
know
seawater on average per kilogram of sea
water has 35 grams of uh
salt and of
course there is this um fact that
the the salt dissociates and so you get
ions
of sodium and I ions of chorine chlorine
that gets hydrated meaning that the
molecules of water which are polar get
attracted attracted from one side the
oxygen side is negative so it's
attracted by uh the by the sodium which
is a
positive charge and the hydrogen side is
is is positive and is attracted by um
the chlorine ion and so uh you get
this molecules typically around six
molecules on average are around each
ion however not
all
um uh
ions get so far apart sometimes they get
also they form ion pairs in other words
they they they also attract still
attract each other and they are still
also surrounded by water
molecules so suppose we apply the vof
equation by
neglecting these ion
Pairs and
assuming that uh 100% % of the
salt goes into into this hydrated ions
forms so that means that now I have to
do the the counting in order to see how
much solutes I have so for each molecule
of salt that I put in solution I get two
um molecules that are um of the ions
and but in some sense you should also
account for the fact that U these
hydrated or solvated uh
groups
um uh since they like to stay each other
they could be also thought as like a big
molecule so so part of the water
molecules that are in
solution um get engaged in the these
solvation groups and so they're not
available anymore as to play the role of
the of solvent okay so their mole
fraction of water also changes because
you lose six molecules per
ion uh that is formed
here
so let's see yeah so the number of
molecules of water initially are
uh the mass which is 1 kilogram minus
the 35 gram so it's 965
grams and if you divide it by the
molecular weight you get how many moles
of water you have
initially and then uh for the ions their
amounts are the 3 5 gram divided by the
molecular weight of the salt of the salt
not the ions which is gives this much
moles so these are how many molecules of
salt you have put
in and then um you assume that the mole
fractions
uh that as as they go in you double this
amount all right so in the end you you
can compute uh the mole fraction of
water
and minus its
logarithm you can check of course that
the tailor series approximation is good
because this is a small
number this is the mole fraction is 978
so it's very close to one so that
approximation but if you do the
calculation there is a little difference
1 minus y is a little different from
minus log of
Y so let me just keep minus log of Y
without that approximation which since
we can do
logarithms and and we can compute
therefore the partial pressure I mean
the the osmotic pressure using uh
v r
I assume 298 just to put a number here
the specific volume here is correct is
with a double I double one is the
specific volume of pure water so it's 10
cubic Met 10 the minus 3 cubic meters
per
kilogram but since we need it in moles
we have to multiply times the molecular
weight of water
and in the end you can compute this in
terms of kilopascals or bars depending
on what makes you uh have a better
feeling of how much this pressure is you
know atmospheric pressure is one bar
more or less and
so the osmotic pressure this osmotic
pressure is 30
bars you can measure it in terms of a
column of
water the the weight of a colum of water
gives a pressure it's 300
M now it turns out that this number is
not precise because there we've made
some approximations here for example we
have neglected these ion
pairs uh the true
number first of all it
varies uh from place to place for
example in the Mediterranean it's higher
than than in the Atlantic or in the
Pacific or in the Arctic is even lower
so there is a range of values of
salinity that go between 30 and
38 and the measured
uh osmotic
pressures are
between 220 and 290
mters still it's not too bad but you we
can do
better so here is um sorry for the fine
print but I have U I
will uh put on um canvas the
um this Excel
file in which I've done the calculation
so this First
Column um gives that calculation that we
have just seen and that leads to a 310
uh meters
of of osmotic
pressure and we have assumed 100%
hydration and 0% ion Pairs and also we
have assumed no
water forgot to say it but we assume
that U uh I'm not counting for the water
molecules that are lost because they go
and formate these uh
groups now in these other uh column I do
the same calculation by assuming six
molecules per uh per per
ion uh and also by assuming that some of
these
18% of the ions are grouped in ion
pairs which are also surrounded by six
Waters okay if you do if you take that
now why did I take 18% that was just my
only uh fitting parameter in order to
get the measured value of
288 so if that were only the effect then
my model would would would get the
actual measured value by assuming this
percentage of ion pairs with respect to
the hydrated
ions and these other two columns give
you the same calculation with the same
parameters
but in the Mediterranean for example in
Naples you have this much
316 whereas in the Arctic Ocean uh it's
242 because the the because of the
changes the percentage of um of salt
that is dissolved
there now
first of all let's let's view it uh in
this
way so imagine you have
a a long
pipe so this is
air this is uh z =
z and this is Z = minus
H
so if the
density of of sea water is
approximately
uh equal to the density of
water and if I have here the pressure PA
a here what pressure do I have
okay that's the static
uh ber equation or whatever you want to
call it
okay all right
so now this is a porous plug semi
permeable to
um to just
water so suppose I want
to have
uh this level let's so this is called
let me call it minus H
uh one and this is H zero
okay so on the outside so below here I
have the pressure that I just said in
the sea water at that level that's the
pressure and it's
H1 on the other side of the
membrane I have a pressure that is given
by
um I assume that also
here the pressure is equal to
atmospheric it's it it's a bit higher
because of the column of air but we can
neglect the density of air of course and
so here is it's
PA plus
row it's again I assume that it's the
same row G
h0
okay so
across the membrane I have a pressure
difference right so the pressure
difference is row
WG H1 minus
h0 and if I am at
equilibrium at the temperature that
prevails
there uh that is equal to the osmotic
pressure so that would
be uh the equivalent of row WG *
288 m
okay so there is a a a huge difference
in pressure there so this porox plug
must be must be able to sustain that
that that
pressure and in fact this is
why um as you know in many countries the
production of fresh water from uh sea
water or from other saline saline saline
Waters is
done
precisely this way uh it's not
really uh done in this you can do it uh
in a more
practical way this by having a you take
some water you take a
piston and then you push you generate
a high pressure
here so this is sea
water and
out on the other side of the membrane
you get uh fresh water in order to for
this to happen you have to
impress a
pressure if you want fresh water
atmospheric pressure here you need at
least 288 you need you need more if you
have just do 288 you you get a drop uh
if you uh put higher
pressure uh you get a
flow of course you need a membrane that
is capable like in the new graph capable
of sustaining those
pressures and that's why you need part
of the job is
to uh make the membrane and part of the
job is to sustain the pressure so that
the membrane can resist that that
pressure and that is how uh you make see
water now you could also ask yourself
what is the minimum work uh needed to uh
do this job because this is a very
energy consuming uh
activity uh and if
you and there are various uh there are
uh more than 20 different methods that
people have devised in order to separate
fresh water from seawater because of
course it's a it's a matter of survival
so it's
uh people have developed uh many ways
even in the old times when you didn't
have
electricity uh and
so you each of the methods has an
efficiency and if we talking about
second low efficiency like we like to do
in this course you'd have to compare
what you spend with the minimum you
could have spent and so what is the
minimum that we could we we need to
spend in order to produce one liter of
or one kilogram of fresh
water and uh
well you have it in front
here because suppose I had this long
pipe then and uh and this is my boat and
the guy takes a a bottle of an empty
bottle P pulls it
down uh or a bucket maybe it's easier
Take the bucket fill it with this water
which is fresh because it's on the other
side of the
membrane and pull it
up and then after a while this will be
replenished and you can get some
more so how much work do you need to do
that it's just the work for
lifting from here to
there so it's r
g essentially
and it turns out that it is
about I think I have it in I think it's
about one or I mean
uh
yeah well G is is about 10 row is about
uh one or so it's
about
20 and this I think is kilj per
kilogram is it kilj or is it Jews that's
the
question
uh because row is say
one uh kilogram
per
cubic sorry row
is uh 10 the 3 Kil G per cubic met G for
Simplicity let's call it
10 m per second
squared and then the other is
M
so
uh
that's anybody wants to
help uh
so this is kilogram per that's Newton
kilopascals no this is pascals time 10^
3 is kilopascals per meter so this I
think it's
kilj well you check it
um there are other
ways in which for example if you I
didn't want to put because this is a
commercial product but if you go and uh
look up U uh solar
steel you find um an inflatable survival
object which has something like this so
this is an inflatable like donut shaped
uh thing with with a plastic Dome and
here is the seawat
so you get uh sunlight coming
in which makes some of the water inside
evaporate like in a green
house uh the the water vapor that
evaporates the salt remains here so so
what evaporates is just water so the
water vapor goes and uh uh forms and
condenses on here because you also
typically have some Breeze or some wind
that will cool that Dome and then the
drops by
um by capillarity stay uh and and get
collected on this side here So
eventually you get some water on this
side and you put a a little pipe and a
little bottle and you collect the your
water so that's a survival
kit for the
fisherman and
um what kind of efficiency would that
have that will also help me figure out
if this K should be there or
not how much energy how much solar
energy do I need in order to evaporate
one kilogram of
water it's the
enthalpy of vaporization of water which
is of the order of 200
KJ per
kilogram okay so I take this K away
because I know that the answer is that
uh that thing has an efficiency of uh
0.1% so it consumes a thousand
times uh the the minimum
these
ones um the
commercial let's see do I have it
somewhere yeah the commercial ones
uh
uh okay this is these are the most
typical most important uh um Industrial
Technologies uh one is called the
pressure osmosis which is
exactly like that and the other is
called um revers
electrodialysis which uses the fact that
since the ions are electrically so if
you put an electric field you can
separate the ions and and and therefore
take them away from the water so that's
one way of
separating which is a less efficiency
there is a factor of two of inefficiency
there because you have to separate the
two ions for each uh amount of water and
so uh I think that is the reason why
there is a this this factor of two in
the theoretical uh uh maximum efficiency
that or Min or minimum power that you
need to spend here it's for to treat um
one 1,000 cubic m second Okay the reason
I
was interested in this is because of
uh the
fact
that uh you
see uh here you have fresh water in
equilibrium with uh so this is an
equilibrium situation okay so that's the
fresh water if you add some fresh water
from from from from
above that uh fresh water this will add
to the pressure on the membrane and
therefore the water will flow into the
ocean okay so that's one
way that is would be an intelligent
way
to put fresh water in the in the
sea when do we put fresh water in the
sea why would you want to do it not the
fisherman because he wants to drink it
but the rivers rivers bring fresh water
to the sea no and uh and usually they
just dump it at the same level that's
dissipated the the best way would be to
take that water once for example one
bucket at a time I I take that that
water from the from the river I put it
in my bucket then
I let the backet go down
so while doing that with a pulle I have
an an
engine produce
electricity so and that is we know how
much
work we get this much work per kilogram
of water that we put down and then at
this level when when it is at this level
it will cross the membrane
spontaneously and I don't I don't need a
a big difference in in pressure to make
it
flow of
course I do need some different
impression otherwise the flow will not
be able to win the pressure drops in the
poros
plug so I do cannot obtain 100% of this
this would be zero power situation if I
need power so I need to do it at a
certain rate I need instead of being
here let's say being
halfway so I use this much head in order
to push the fresh water into the uh into
the into the sea in any case this is
what is called Blue
energy and it is a an enormous
uh uh
potential and it is of course a
renewable kind
of energy it has an enormous potential
in if you look at the what the rates are
for
Rivers so even if I take just the uh
this small contribution for the PO few
for for Po River in in Italy which is
only 6,000 cubic met per second
you see uh we we with with pressure
osmosis power
plant we could
make uh 6 times 3,000 Mega so that's
18,000
megawatt that's like uh a
lot
okay and people have tried to do
this there are pilot plans but the
problem with these technologies that
have to do with that need
membranes is that
membranes get
clogged fresh water from the river it's
not really just water there is mud there
is dust uh so
you you need to keep these membranes
clean you need huge surfaces in order to
treat this kind of uh flow rates and
therefore uh up to now it hasn't
developed yet in a any reasonable
uh even small fraction of the
electricity
[Music]
produced yeah this map also shows the
salinity differences
in in the various oceans and seas here's
a Mediterranean that's about
38 here's the Arctic is below 30
33 now
the the idea of
um the this idea with you using the
pressure osmosis uh
is this and there there were there was a
a power plant in nor in Norway that
tried to do it but I think they closed
uh and I don't I think that there is
somebody else who was starting another
project in trying these
things so you get uh water from the
river and instead of putting it directly
so I put a nice wall here and the water
does uh have to go a different path it
has to
go into these pipes so these are pipes
made with uh porous material permeable
only to fresh water to to just the water
molecule okay so what I do is uh to put
inside on the inside I put seawat
uh
pressurized
uh not to the uh osmotic pressure
because otherwise we would have no
flow but to a pressure which is um sort
of
halfway the osmotic value that way there
there would be the driving force that
would uh push water through the porous
medium and so this pipe will U need to
be uh in with an enlarging crosssection
so as to accommodate this increasing
flow of water so here is the sea water
that gets in and what gets out is that
sea water plus the water fresh water
that has been added and then it goes uh
here now of course in order to
pressurize the seawat I have to consume
energy with the
pump and that
pump is the work the power is is the
product of
the
uh pressurization that I have managed to
obtain times the volume flu
rate and uh
there should be a DOT there
and and then the What flows out is again
at that
pressure perhaps a little less because
of pressure
drops and so it I don't just put it in
water but it is a I put it in a turbine
hydraulic turbine which is going to
elaborate the uh higher volume flate
because uh it's not only
recuperating uh the volume fluorate that
I have pumped but it also gets the
volume of of of fresh water that has
been added and so it's on the difference
between this volume flu rate that I gain
and again the the the net power is going
to be the the difference between what I
obtain from the turbine and what I spent
from the uh pump all right so in
principle this is relatively simple but
again the problem is these uh uh
porous medium and porous uh
membranes okay so talking about
um see this is a work this is
this number that we obtained here is the
work of separation of the some solvent
from this dilute
solution
um in
general the problem of separating stuff
is important for many applications for
example in the nuclear uh Power industry
you have to
uh separate in order to uh concentrate
uranium
235 uh you do you need to you make it
into
gas
and EXA EXA Florine EXA Florine of
uranium and and then you separate the
gas uh using the fact that the molecules
are
different uh because they have a
different
um different isotopes the 238 from
235 and and and so that is a consuming
um energy in order to do this uh this
separation okay so we know that
we we did something very similar
earlier so I'm going to to go quickly on
these uh energy balances and entropy
balances but the idea here is that we
have a mixture in
general given
composition initially I mean in given
temperature and pressure so now I'm
going to operate at the given
temperature and pressure which is could
be for example the atmospheric
Reservoir and I want to
obtain a fully separated uh pure
components
of course in order to do that I need to
spend some work that's represented by
the weight that goes
down so I
do volume balance uh for the overall
system including the
reservoir
uh here I call B and A B is the final
State and a is the initial
State uh so the energy balance the
entropy
balance and then the
equation for the stable equilibria of
the uh this Reservoir with a variable
volume which is
this then I combine as usual these
equations by eliminating the
reservoir
variables and here I'm also using the
fact that the final since we are in in
equilibrium with the
reservoir uh it fixes also the final
temperatures of the pure components at
the end so t b t a is equal to
tr and the linear combination of these
balances yields this expression for the
work with is one of those characteristic
functions I think it's the one that we
called with the letter uh
fe uh and then there is a plus T times
the entropy generated so if I do it in
an irreversible process this will uh
make me consume
more but let's talk about the limit in
which I do the best so this is not there
so that would be the reversible case
and then I recognize that this linear
combination of properties is just the
Gibs free energy so essentially the
minimum work for separating at constant
T and P is the difference between the
Gibs free energy of the final separated
State and the Gibs free energy of the
initial
mixture now since we know how to do uh
things we know how to uh we know first
of all that
uh the Gibs free energy now in general
it's not an additive property but if you
if all the systems are at the same tnp
then the gift free energy is
additive and so in the final
State uh the GS free energy of the
composite is equal to Simply the GS free
energy of uh the sum of the gsy energy
of the
parts and again here I've used the fact
that the Gib free energy of the pure
component is also equal to the chemical
potential of the pure
component whereas for the
mixture the Gibs free energy due to the
oiler relation is related to the
chemical
potentials so it's the weighted sum of
the chemical
potentials and up to here we made no
assumptions if we further make an
assumption of either U being in a case
of a Gibs Dalton mixture of Ideal
gases or an ideal solution and this time
it's ideal in for all components not
just the
solvent then if we apply the rules that
we have seen uh so many times now this
gives us a formula which is similar to
the uh entropy of mixing
okay so suppose for example that we want
to separate uh
air we want to separate air into its
components now air is a mixture of many
gases it's not just nitrogen and
oxygen the typical
composition at sea
level is this one 78% of
nitrogen almost 21 of oxygen
.9% almost 1% of
argon and
0.04% these are the 400 ppms of
CO2 so I
can I want to compute this
uh this
summation and it's simple
uh and then I want to divide it also
by uh n m so that I get the result per
kilogram of air so I have to divide by
the molecular weight and the molecular
weight is the weight at sum of the
molecular weights of uh the VAR
constituents weighted on the mole
fractions so it's
28.97 with this
composition and then I choose a
temperature say
298k and here comes uh so the minimum
work to separate air into its components
one kilogram is
48.5
kilj we could have modeled air in a
simpler way suppose air is just made of
suppose we we have a a mixture in which
I have only nitrogen and oxygen with the
same relative composition as they have
in in the actual air but there are no
other
components if it were only those
two then they do the same calculation
and see that the the work for separation
is
44 it's quite a bit of
difference and this
additional about 4 KJ per kilogram here
uh are needed because here I have
insisted in separating all including
argon and
CO2 and those
are uh very few molecules and they
require uh a
lot for separating per unit of amount
that that you want to
separate okay so this formula applies
not only in the gas phase you could also
apply for solution liquid
phase for example let's take a mixture
of uh water and ethanol which at the
appropriate mole fractions is like wine
okay I a model for wine of course it's
not just these elements but
um so if I take a wine 14 Dees um
uh by volume that's Fe is the mole
fraction it's is the volume fraction of
alcohol in in
wine um that makes you do the
calculation to go to pass
from volume fraction to mole fraction
it's 4.7 mole
fraction and if you want to separate
entirely the water from the
alcohol you apply this
formula and again if you want to do it
for 1 kilogram of wine it it it's 24
kilj what you
spend
now the question
is well if I want to separate for
example if I want to produce
oxygen because because I need it for
medical applications or I want to
produce nitrogen because I need it for
agricultural
applications or if I want to produce
argon which is needed in the
lab or if I want to separate CO2 from
the atmosphere because I want to
segregate it which is something that
people are uh considering in these
days how much do I do and do I have to
separate entirely my my mixture well the
answer is
no what you could do you could you could
do exactly just what you need not more
if you do something if you separate
something that you don't need then you
spent energy to do the separation uh and
you're left with something that since
you don't need it you mix it again so
it's
wasteful so concentrate on what you need
so for example ex take your initial
mixture say air and suppose uh you want
to
extract some
oxygen so the best
way the minimum expenditure would be to
extract uh a little bit of
oxygen with not the not the entire
amount of oxygen in your air so you
treat a volume of air and extract only a
fraction of it a fraction of the oxygen
that is present in that
air so you put out air which is linear
in
oxygen uh and you have your oxygen here
all right so so essentially this is what
we're doing we
take lots of oxygen little oxygen and
then the little you separate and the lot
you leave it with the air and the other
components you leave it
there
okay you do the energy balances and the
entropy balances and the volume balance
is again and again you you find that the
difference I mean the minimum work of
separation is given by the difference in
the GBS free
energy of the final
situation minus that of the initial
mixture now the final situation or the
final composite of mix plus the
pure as uh therefore two contributions
this is for the
mixture which now has a final
composition why mole fractions B which
are different from the mole fractions
that you started with plus you have the
Gibs free energy of the pure component
here and again remember that the
chemical potential is for the pure
substance the GS free energy and again
we are using additivity for GS free
energy because the two subsystems are at
the same temperature and
pressure for the mixture
here I would have to write that the from
the oiler relation that the GI free
energy is simply the summation of the
amounts times the chemical
potentials I have to be careful though
that when I get to comp component I in
the summation there is this extra little
piece so I'm I'm going to write uh this
summation in two pieces one is with the
ends that remain
unchanged and the one that is separated
I contribution it's multiplied by the
same kind of same chemical potential but
I put it outside so component I I will
find it outside of the summation for the
amounts that I separate and inside the
summation for the amounts that remain
s
okay then I
use ideal solution or ideal gi gi Dalton
mixture Behavior so that I can
express the chemical potentials of the
mixture in terms of those two component
times RT
log Y and we doing that substitution I
obtain this expression so this is the
general expression for the
work in
terms of the uh initial
amounts and of the amount that I have
extracted of component
I now there are several cases that may
be interesed interesting for example I
could consider the complete removal of
constituent I so a case in which I I do
want to take for example
CO2 maybe I want to extract it all so I
don't want to be uh that to be left with
any in in my final mixture so ni I
should be zero that's complete
removal and that expression here gives
us this result
and there is an interesting uh possible
limit uh which is one in which the mole
initial mole fraction of my component
like for example the CO2
case the the initial mole fraction is
very
small because CO2 we said is four uh
0.04%
uh so that means very less than one in
this case the second contribution goes
away and so the minimum work is just
minus
log of the mole fraction the minimum
work per unit
amount
extracted or you could use a partial
removal in which I don't extract it all
I exract only a fraction I could call
this fraction key the amount that I have
initially I want to say I want to
extract only a fraction key of the uh of
the of the initially present
amount so that expression rewrites this
way and here also there is a
limit which uh is the same result
but which obtains in the opposite
situation when I extract when I separate
only a minute fraction of the originally
present amount this is typically used in
the oxygen or
nitrogen separation
case
Okay so if we do
again assume this same um air that we
considered standard
conditions and suppose
we want to do a minute or minor removal
so that this fraction key is small so I
can apply this formula
here so if my objective is to extract
one kilogram and these are per kilog of
the molecule that I want to extract so I
want to extract 1 kilogram of nitrogen I
spend
21.9 KJ if I want to extract 1 kilogram
of oxygen I spend
121 it's more because oxygen is more
rare it's by four times uh less if I
want to extract argon it's 20 2
290 if I want to extract CO2 is
440 now of course so there
are if I want
[Music]
to I want to make sure that I cannot
build
a perpetual motion machine of the second
kind that would be something in which I
use
uh this method of
separation and then once I have SE
separated then I mix them again and we
know that by mixing you can extract
work so clearly if I start from Air I
separate it and I spend so much to
separate it then when I mix it gain the
maximum work I can separate must be
equal I can obtain must be equal to the
minimum work uh of uh of of of
Separation so for example if I
take
uh the right amount of
nitrogen that is needed to form
again H uh the the air original
composition I have this is the right
that right
amount uh
so I have to multiply these ones times
those
amounts and then of
course the sum of these works properly
weighted by those amounts gives me the
same uh work that I can obtain by mixing
which is so this 48
.5 is uh the same work of Separation
that we have used in the complete
separation case in the previous slide so
this is just a consistency
check also here I have another uh Excel
file that I will
share in which these calculations
are are
done and uh for uh so so this contain uh
uh this is where I I took those uh those
results um and
it and for example the checking yeah the
check okay see this this is the partial
removal partial removal
separation uh these are
the amounts
of the the mass percentages of uh the
various constituents in air so if I take
the weighted sum of this times that I
obtain the same as if I did the complete
separation okay now this
also is a the same or another Excel file
there is this calculation of the alcohol
content and the preparation for
wine it's interesting
that takes a while to we have to be
careful with the volume fractions Mo
fractions Mass
fractions can get uh confusing but
eventually you figure it
out so this is already the result that I
mentioned before what was the
number yeah 21 KJ per liter if I take
wine uh yeah this is a
12 12 12 degrees 12 um volume fraction
of
ethanol
12% uh we in this other thing is an
application of the partial removal
case in wine making
sometimes uh
in in wine makers in the north of Europe
where there isn't so much sunshine you
the the alcohol content the natural
alcohol content that you obtain is low
and you have to find ways to raise it
one way is to buy uh wine it used to be
that they it was used to be cheaper to
buy wine from uh south of Italy or from
Greece or from Spain because uh there
you get a lot of sunshine and so the
alcohol content is high and it used to
be called The Cut wine to cut the the
poorer wines of the
north but now also the people uh in
south of Italy Greece and so on have
learned to make good wines and so they
don't sell it for for for LW anymore so
uh an alternative is
to uh separate take a little bit of
water
away from the uh so for example suppose
you have a 12
degrees uh wine and you want to bring it
to
14 all you need to do is to take some
water away of course you have to you
cannot boil it otherwise going going to
ruin the one but maybe you can Flash it
uh low pressures so that at room
temperature you get some so there are
ways in which you can extract without
ruining the uh the rest of the good part
of of the wi and so this calculation
gives
you with the formulas that we've given
it U all you need to do is to figure out
how much water do I have to take
away and so this is the the Delta n N1
that I need um if you look inside there
is a Formula that shows you how I
calculated
that and once I I determine that I can I
I I can
apply um I can find the key so the the
cut fraction
that we defined in the slide and we
apply those formulas and uh it comes out
that we need to spend 86
kilj per liter in order to make this
little Improvement in the alcohol
content and of course therefore you find
that the wine if you do this way you
find that the wine making becomes also
an energy an
energy energ how do you say
energ an indust energy consuming
industry
yes right okay
okay
so let me move on to uh
another interesting application it has
still to do with
air it has to do with
stratification of
air as you
know um
air is
stratified uh as you go up to high
mountains for example top of Mount
Everest uh you can read books about what
they call thin air so why is it thin
okay it's thin for two reasons it's thin
because it uh the the overall pressure
is
low Maybe 1 third of the atmospheric
pressure at sea level and it's thinner
also because the oxygen
content percentage wise is
less why less because the oxygen
molecules are molecular weight
32 nitrogen molecules 28 so the oxygen
is heavier and St like likes to stay
more towards the sea okay so the
stratification is due to these
differences in molecular weights of the
molecules and since we are so interested
in CO2 CO2 is 44 molecular weight so
even more there is there is a
stratification for
example when we
say uh ah the CO2 concentration at manua
which is the place where they measure
measure CO2 uh is a mountain that
mountain is at 35
M
altitude okay it's also maybe
representative of the content of the
average content in the atmosphere but
the point is that if there there is 400
and 26 PPM for example
today uh it's means that at C Level you
have 500 and something we'll calculate
it in a
moment so it's there is a big difference
due to this CH the differences in
molecular weights of the
molecules so how do we go about and do
this
calculation we need a model as as usual
and the the model that we we
make uh is very
similar to the model that we have
made for bulk flow you remember for bulk
flow we said if you have a fluid
element which finds
itself at elevation Z in the gravity
field and which has uh a
velocity let me call it
w um
and it has a mass
m
okay when we do fluid
mechanics uh this is a fluid element or
a fluid parcel called for and we assign
the properties in the in the local
equilibrium uh assumption we assign the
properties of this uh fluid element by
assuming that it's uh
energy is the energy that it would
have with the
same composition volume and
entropy in a stable equilibrium
State plus we add these mechanical
effects that are the kinetic
energy and the potential
energy
okay and yeah we'll the next time we'll
assume also that this particle has a
charge electrical charge and that finds
itself in a uh for example an electric
field okay in that CA or yeah an elect
electric field is really minus the
gradient of
a electric
potential and so here we will add uh Q
times
Fe it's
another it's another mechanical kind of
effect so the thermal aspect of the
properties are still contained in the
fundamental
uh relation for stable equilibrium
State and these are other additional
contributions now for the problem of
stratification in the atmosphere
here all we need to do is to forget
about motion so we we are talking about
a Ste atmosphere of course it's a model
and not charge
so we have this potential energy and
M is the
bass of uh the fluid uh element which
may vary we're going to assume that it
may vary here
because since the composition changes
with elevation also the mass changes
so the mass is given by
the
moles times the molecular
weights okay so this is the C Level this
is the generic layer at elevation
Z where we assume that there is a
temperature a pressure and the
composition and there is a adjacent
laser lay layer which at Z Plus DZ with
a different temperature different
pressure and different
composition now when we have this kind
of uh
energy
uh you remember then when we talk about
U when we derive the conditions for
Mutual
equilibrium uh the conditions for Mutual
equilibrium
where equalities between some partial
derivatives of the energy uh of the
fundamental
relation that precisely because they
appear in these conditions for Mutual
equilibrium are important and that's why
we give them names temperature pressure
chemical
potentials but here when we take the
derivative of energy with respect to S
and V it's we still get temperature and
pressure but in in a model like this
when we take the derivative of e with
respect to the amounts I have the
amounts here which give me the CH
chemical potential contribution but I
have the amounts also inside the mass
which gives me an additional
contribution which is a gravitational uh
contribution if I had the charge which
we'll do next time we'll have also a an
electrical contribution so we will have
uh today we so this more General kind of
chemical potential potential that uh so
far we've called chemical we will call
the total potential because it has
several contributions and when it is
only chemical plus electrical it's the
electrochemical
potential uh today for the
stratification problem you could call it
[Music]
what is
electrochemical gravito chemical okay
gravito chemical
potential whatever the name doesn't
matter what's important is that you this
total potential is given by the chemical
potential so it's the derivative of this
one plus the derivative of M and so that
brings up the molecular uh weight of the
molecule with respect to which you are
taking the
Der so I think we we're done today but
the idea is that uh we will obtain our
results and there the the distribution
in
concentrations by
imposing chemical potential equality
between layers because the layers are
attached to one another so they are in
mutual
equilibrium in practice they are not
because as you know the temperature in
the atmosphere is not uh
uniform we will
assume that this changing temperature in
the
atmosphere uh can be neglected locally
but not globally okay so with that will
be a little bit of an assumption so we
assume that we make an equilibrium
between these two assuming that t zdz is
equal to T at
Z but we will not assume that the
chemical potentials are and that's how
we will get our
results but the time is up and so I
think I have
to Simply wish you a good uh spring
break and see you in 10 days