okay good
morning so let me remind you where we
were we dealing with systems with
chemical
reactions we talked about the role of
the activated
complex in the mechanis
of converting reactants into products as
a result of
collisions and
uh in order to do
that then we did the chemical
equilibrium derived from the principle
of Maximum
entropy so if you remember one of the
key modeling assumptions that we had to
make was to
integrate the what we call the simple
system
model which uh others call the
thermodynamic limit or the many
particle
model in which you remember that uh the
idea was that essentially we could uh
add or remove partitions in in our
system without it affecting the
properties here we add also the fact
that we add and remove or say turn on
and off very conceptual idea the
chemical uh
reactions and that doesn't affect the
properties of course it affects the time
Evolution because it will inhibit or
allow chemical reactions to proceed but
for the in instantaneous picture that we
take you know when we measure properties
of our mixture with chemical
reactions uh that the reactions are on
or off doesn't make a lot of a
difference because uh for many particles
because the uh role of the activated
complexes um
is uh
minute since they're few since they're
very
shortlived and
also
because the uh
collisions that uh produce chemical
reactions
are much fewer than uh the collisions
that
simply um
redistribute energy among the molecules
uh and and so
um as part of our assumption here that
we can model the properties as if it
were a stable equilibrium state with the
actions turned off is uh also the
assumption that
the that the nonchemical collisions are
much faster are much more abundant and
therefore equilibrate uh energy much
faster than the the the effective
chemically chemical
collisions so that all is uh in order to
allow us
to
essentially
uh
represent this family of um would be
equilibrium States if you didn't have
chemical reactions the blue curves
and this family has
a one parameter if you have one chemical
reaction or as many parameters as um
there are chemical reactions so you
shift from one to the other by changing
the reaction coordinate
Epsilon and the envelope of these uh
stable equilibrium State curves is the
stable equilibrium State curve for the
system with chemical reactions that's
where
the stable equilibrium states
are with the reactions
on and that's where we
calculate the maximum we apply the
maximum entropy principle and the
maximum entropy principle implies that
the these derivatives of how the entropy
varies with respect to those parameters
must be zero
and these derivatives are what we called
the
affinities these are the entropic
affinities some others call
Affinity U these times uh minus the
temperature that would be
the energetic
Affinity okay uh so
and then by
applying the definition the simple
definition of affinity which is this one
and uh
applying the expressions for the
chemical potentials that we have uh
worked out in several uh
cases we end up with the law of mass
action this is a general so it's a non-
equilibrium law of mass mass action
which becomes the equilibrium one when
uh you set the Affinity is equal to
zero and as you have seen we
defined
various various forms that we call all
call equilibrium constants for example
this one is a dimensionless equilibrium
constant which is simply uh e to the
minus the GBS free energy of the
reaction divided by RT
um this other
one is the equilibrium
constant in terms of temperature and
also pressure for a
gas this this is for the gas and so this
is the pressure
dependence or you often work with
concentrations the marity so how many
moles per volume you have per
liter and um so you you use this symbol
for those concentrations and uh and then
you have this form so we'll um we
proceed using more often now this this
form
here and of course these various forms
of the chemical equilibrium uh
constantes are related to one
another as an example
before we proceed I wanted to just uh
mention this one which is that of
U that which happens in in pure
water the fact that
water
uh ionizes itself and so there is an
equilibrium
between um the water molecules and the
formation of the hydronium or the hydro
oide
ions and as you know the the abundance
of these
ions
defines the scale of acidity
of of a of a of a of an aquous
solution in fact we what we call
pH is minus the log base 10
of the concentration of the h3o plus
ions and sometimes you call also
p uh minus the log of of these
concentration now since this is a
concentration so it is dimensional it it
is mole per liter you have to divide
here by the the dimension so it's this
is kind of a you put under the logarithm
number which which is dimensional so you
have to take the dimensions away or use
the convention that you're always going
to use those
Dimensions because usually logarithms
like to have non non-dimensional numbers
as
arguments
um here is how the law of mass action uh
looks when you write it for that
equation see the stochiometric
coefficients are minus two for water so
when you get to this exponent here it's
a minus two so that's why the
concentration of water goes to the
denominator and then plus one and plus
one for the other
two uh
molecules ions so that's they go to the
numerator with a power
one so this is the product of those
and that has to be
equal to the at equilibrium has to be
equal to the equilibrium constant based
on
concentrations now in this business
therefore you need to compute the
concentration of water of pure water and
that's defined by how many molecules you
have per liter you can write it as the
density over the molecular weight and
for example at 25 degrees
C density is 997 gram per liter
molecular weight is
18 gram per mole and so that
concentration is 55.3 moles per liter
you need it
squared so in order to not to carry this
along in in in the practice of chemical
uh engineering
often it uh almost always you find uh
this product of the this equilibrium
constant times the square of the water
concentration you find it called the KW
the equilibrium constant for
water and then therefore this equation
rewrites this way that the the product
of the concentrations of the hydronium
and the hydroxide ions
is equal to this constant which constant
is not because you remember that
equilibrium constants vary a lot with
with
temperature
so um and also this constant has
Dimensions because uh for this
particular uh
reaction uh usually also
the equilibrium constant B on
concentration is dimensional it has
dimensions of the overall
concentration to the to the power equal
to the sum of the stochiometric
coefficients now for this particular
reaction the sum of the stochiometric
coefficients is zero because minus 2 +
1+ one is zero so this uh is
dimensionless it coincides with the
equilibrium constant KT without the
C so this is dimensionless but this is
not so the KW has dimensions of mole
squar per liter
squar at 25° C it is almost exactly
equal to 10 Theus 14 in those
units and if you
have
um a neutral solution in which there is
no
um acid or base dissolved that would
capture some of these ions they would be
uh
equally populated so you their
concentrations will be equal and
therefore each one takes 10 the minus
7 10us 7 * 10 10us 7 gives 10 Theus
14 and 10 the minus 7 put into the log
base 10
with the minus in front makes pH equal 7
and that pH equals 7 is therefore this
the the the notion of
um
neutral so like pure water is neutral
and it has a pH equal
7 at 25 C though because if you go at
different temperatures for example you
go here you you see how for example at
at Body temp temperature which is 37°
C the KW is not 10 to the 4 minus to 10
to the minus 14 but it's three times
three 3.55 times and that makes the pH
for neutral 6.7 at 100°
6.17 or at 0 degrees is
7.47 okay so this is a one of the
applications of equili of course is just
one of the many
examples so now we already talked about
the elements
of CH the model for chemical kinetics
and we want to develop more details as
you see we are transitioning from the
SEC second part of the course to the
third part because we've already been
talking about non equilibrium uh from
the first lecture I believe
so uh well but the more we advance in in
and we get close to our uh stable
equilibrium which will be the end of the
course uh we'll uh talk more and more
about non-equilibrium
States you remember this picture in
which we
presented uh the idea of a potential
energy
surface and that's where we we what we
used to define the activated complex the
potential energy surface
represents uh the energy at zero
temperature of the various
configurations with which you can find
the reactants or the
products uh for example these are the
reactants these are the products and
here um in in this
scenario um along a path of
steepest Ascent here and steepest
descent here or vice
versa you find the sdle point which is
the
lowest uh point that allows you to go
from one Valley of
this landscape to this this other
Valley
now that's a zero
temperature if there is uh temperature
it means
that part of the energy of the molecules
is in their other uh in their degrees of
freedom translational rotational
vibrational
electronic they all are capable of
storing energy in in the
molecules uh at low temperatures most of
the energy is stored in the uh let's
call them easy uh degrees of freedom
which is the translational the
rotational uh as you increase in
temperature also the vibrational become
important and if you go even higher also
electronic uh you can excite the
electrons and therefore they could jump
uh up and down from the various uh
orbitals that represent the energy
levels of of the
molecule
so if uh therefore there is a kinetic
energy first of
all we this we we've seen that there is
there are collisions so molecules by
having kinetic energy uh undergo uh a
lot of
collisions and as a result of these
collisions they put put together their
kinetic energy and they form um these uh
activated complexes sometimes sometimes
they don't form the activated compx
sometimes they just jump uh on the sides
of the of the valleys which have higher
energy but then they they they go back
so they they bounce in the valley up in
these higher
Energies so the result of collision may
be the formation of things that look
like almost activated complexes but
they're not uh this particular one uh or
things in this area that would allow
going from from reactants to products
and vice
versa
okay and also we've seen that uh
as a result of collision the kinetic
energy gets momentarily transformed into
um elastic uh uh energy like two Springs
that
Collide uh so they store the energy for
a while and then they explode back and
and uh
and shoot the fragments of of of the
fishion of these um uh activated complex
in in various directions these fragments
will will have a a higher energy than
the neighbors and therefore by the other
collisions the non-chemical collisions
that energy will get redistributed and
we it will either heat up if they have
higher energies but sometimes it also
they also have lower energies because
some of the energy uh if the the
reaction has been uh effective uh have
uh has been um
uh retained by the new configuration of
the molecule as in the form of of
potential
energy like like here so if you
go uh from
here to this in this direction so from
left to right here uh this potential
energy uh is stored in the new
configuration so it came from kinetic
energy went up to form this complex then
as you go down you release so this this
difference from here to here will be the
kinetic energy that is released by The
fragments of the explosion so to speak
and uh whereas this other difference is
not anymore available as kinetic energy
because it do become potential
energy now the
um
collisions are governed as you know
by the Maxwell bolman distribution of
velocities uh this this distribution
[Music]
uh
maybe later on if I have time I'll I'll
show you uh how it uh can be
derived from the maximum entropy uh
principle so it is the distribution that
maximizes the entropy given certain uh
constraints
and
U so that means that the these
molecules do not all have the same
velocity okay and also this nice GIF
that I took from Wikipedia uh shows uh
it starts if you look it um carefully it
starts from a non-equilibrium situation
in which there are some particles that
are
that have higher velocities than other
so it's a
skewed slightly skewed distribution and
it shows how quickly it will the many
collisions will redistribute and return
the distribution uh back to uh Maxwell
B this is to uh to this is like
a victorial representation of of the
idea
that non-chemical
collisions is a fast Dynamics because
collisions are many and uh and occur
many more than than chemical ones and
therefore you can assume that this
distribution is almost uh
immediately uh uh returns almost
immediately to
maxan uh after each chemical reaction
has released or absorb some local
energy so now let's go back to
this uh path from the reactants uh from
the bottom of the reactants Valley to
the activated complex the sdle point to
the bottom of the uh products
Valley and here on the side
I have
drawn not exactly the Maxwell bolman
distribution but a distribution that uh
can be obtained from the Maxwell
balsman H and it is the distribution of
the kinetic energy that is made
available upon Collision
uh because what we need in order to
climb this diagram here this valet to go
to the sdle point we need enough energy
for the
Collision as a result of a
collision and so
this
curve U represents the probability
density function not for velocity but
for kinetic energy of particles in in in
a from the Maxwell balsman distribution
of velocity
so as a function of kinetic energy which
is plotted this
way that's the
PDF in order
for a chemical
uh Collision to be
effective we need that it has at least
this much kinetic energy so as to climb
up here so all the collisions that have
energies above
that are good so if you do this the the
area under the this probability
distribution function which is the
integral from this energy to
Infinity
that's uh the overall
probability that your Collision as a
kinetic energy higher than this value
Delta
H so the that's the result of the
integral so if on this side I need that
to be um therefore the the kinetic
energy that I need is the
um
enthalpy of the uh forward reaction or
forward half reaction of formation of
the activated complex from the reactant
on the other
side I start
lower I'm in the same box so to speak so
the molecules are in the same mixture
same maxion distribution same
temperature so this curve is the same as
that one only that it starts below
here
therefore uh if I want to form to form
the activated complex from this side I
need this much energy the enthalpy of
reaction of the
backward half
reaction and and so the probability to
have the necessary uh energy as a result
of the Collision is this one this area
which is equal to this uh exponential
formula and this exponential formula is
uh what is called the arous
law and of course from this side it's
smaller so there is more probability to
get up here from the reactants than from
the products in this case
because
uh because the because the because of
the because the Delta h plus is smaller
than the Delta Delta H minus okay so
this is one of the
ingredients in order to uh
formulate a a theory or a
model for the rate of U chemical
reactions for the rate at which chemical
reactions
proceed and in our language therefore
it's for the rate at which the reaction
coordinate changes with time I Epsilon
dot so the bottom line is is here
Epsilon dot will turn out to be the net
result of how many of of the Epsilon dot
of the forward half reaction and the
Epsilon dot of the backward half
reaction and these
ones are done in here so this column
does the half reaction this column does
uh the forward and this does the
backward so we talked about we can view
this thing in terms of this uh in terms
of
probabilities so the
arenus formula gives us as we've
discussed the probability to have enough
Collision enough ktic energy from the
Collision so that uh we form the
activated complex
then we need another
probability once I have the activated
complex which is that Springs that are
or compressed
and short leave and ready to explode the
the question is will it explode towards
the reactant Valley or towards the
product Valley
that depends also on how the molecules
have collided it's not just kinetic
energy it is also the angles with which
they Collide that might makes is
important because that
uh allows to have uh the right
vibrations uh vibrational modes to be uh
triggered and and and and therefore form
the new
configurations so it's so it is complex
uh reasoning about that it's not simple
to make theory about this part of
the of the
probability and therefore you just say
all right let's call it a
probability let's call it um a and there
is one for the forward and one for the
uh backward
but then you also need
uh
another
uh situation to occur that it's not
enough that the particles have the
proper kinetic energy but you need the
right particles to
collide I need for example uh two
hydrogens and maybe something else so
there'll be a three body reaction so
because if I have collision with the
right energy but the wrong molecules
that's useless okay so you remember
that the probability to have a molecule
uh in a mixture uh is the mole
fraction a nice number between zero and
one which represents how many you have
and so the chance that you have those
molecules is uh is the probability and
the chance that you have a uh
several of
them it's the multiplication of the
probabilities and if I did if I
need two molecules of the same kind then
that probability counts
twice so it's the mole fraction to the
power
two and those amounts are precisely what
these doomric coefficients are so that
is why this product is a product of
probability and the exponents the
stochiometric coefficients which count
properly how many times you need that
kind of molecule to be present in a
collision most of the times effectively
the most probable collisions are two
body just two molecules that Collide
already the three body reactions are
much fewer and going four and and so on
it's almost
irrelevant so so this is is a bit
hypothetical
U again it's uh that colleague of mine
would call it
Disneyland uh
but for a theory that's that's uh
okay for the practice it
means that you will never going to work
with an overall chemical reactions
scheme but you will split the chemical
reaction in many uh steps so that is why
we need so many reactions like we will
see again in the hydrogen will be 24
reactions just for the oxidation of of
hydrogen it's not just one
reaction and those uh detailed kinetic
schemes are mostly done with uh two body
or three body
reactions okay okay well
anyway these are
probabilities we assume they are
independent events so we can multiply
the
probabilities and uh yeah we can also
rewrite the mole fractions because here
we want to write it in terms of uh the
concentration so the mole fractions can
be written in terms of
concentrations so we multiply this that
and that that and we say all right we
assume that the rate of uh change of the
forward half reaction uh is given by the
product of these
probabilities and this is the formula
this is the
multiplication and then the traditional
naming is uh
that yes you have this product of
concentrations to to the stochiometric
coefficients
that's singled out and the preactor of
that is called
[Music]
reaction the rate
constant which is not really a constant
again it's a function of
temperature and it is an arous Factor
times a preactor
here clearly what I've done for the
forward I can do also for the backward
so you just change the minus the pluses
into minuses and you get the backward uh
rate of course the arus here is the
arous um term that uh is important for
the kinetic
energy and here are the
concentrations based on the
uh backward Co static coefficients so in
the end the net
reaction rate will be the difference
between the forward and the backwards
and when we are at equilibrium they will
be equal to zero I'm sorry not equal to
they will be equal to one
another
okay notice also here just we need to
remind it later on that the way we have
defined
the half
reactions these stochiometric
coefficients with the plus and with the
minus are positive
numbers
okay and they are related to
the uh overall reaction stochiometric
coefficients in the this
way the one of the backward minus the
one of the forward at least according to
our convention that puts everything on
the left hand side and with a plus with
a positive stomry coefficients for what
we call the
products of course you can always switch
a a point of view and call what the pro
the products call them reactants and
then you'll you'll change the all the
signs
okay so for example here is
the uh rate
constants for the set of 24
reactions that we already uh mentioned
that
does uh that is
the most
trusted uh detailed kinetic kinetic
scheme for the oxidation of hydrogen in
pure
oxygen as you
see uh here they are
listed um from number
11 to
24 they are two body reactions you see
in both sides you have two
molecules so so in order for this
reaction to form its activated complex
you have to have a collision of an
oxygen atom and a hydrogen
molecule and if it is effective that
will form a hydrogen atom and an
O and here
is the
prefactor actually the preactor what we
call the a of T now here it is written
as a
constant times
T to a power and B this is the power of
the temperature these are experimental
values and the activated the activation
um uh energy so the
arous threshold is listed here
it is also not worthy that this the U
three body reactions instead you see on
the first 11 first 10
reactions have three require three
bodies three body collisions on either
one side or the other or both like no
just one side or the
other and they represented with zero
activation
energy
okay we'll actually have later on
hopefully today another example in which
this list of reactions will will be
analyzed
somehow
now let's see what are the consequences
of this model that we have uh developed
so
we just said we want to represent the
reaction rates this
way forward and
backward notice that all the
ingredients are positive because they
after all it's a product of
probabilities and you cannot have
negative probabilities so so these are
both positive Epsilon plus and Epsilon
minus are are positive
remember also that we defined and we
just recalled the non-e equilibrium law
of mass
action
okay so let's now compute the
ratio between the uh backward and the
forward reaction
right so we substitute from up
there we
notice that this product on the
numerator and the denominator you can
also write since
the the the argument of the exponent are
the same you can also write it as n i to
the uh new minus minus new plus that's n
to the uh new to the stochiometric
coefficient of the overall reaction so
you can make this
step and then we can substitute from the
non equilibrium law of mass action which
because this is valid
always and you get this expression
here now this expression here is General
at least given this kind of modeling for
the
kinetics is General therefore it applies
also at equilibrium so also when the um
a is equal to
zero so when the Affinity is equal to
zero this e to the 0 is
one and also at
equilibrium the rate of the backward is
equal to the rate to of the forward they
are not zero but they are equal to one
another so it's a sort of a dynamic
equilibrium so this is one and also so
the left hand side is one at
equilibrium and so that gives us a
relation
between uh the backward forward react U
right constants and the equilibrium
constant this is called the principle of
detailed balance
it's useful
because you don't as you have seen for
example didn't mention that but uh uh in
the list for the that I gave for the for
the hydrogen
rates uh we gave only the
k+ the
forward yes that's because uh from the
equilibrium constant which which you can
compute from the thermodynamic
properties like gives free energy of the
reaction you given the the forward rate
you can compute using this uh principle
uh the backward right so they're not
independent that means I can uh say well
that means that this combination here
this prefactor of the exponent is equal
to one
okay and so in general I obtain that the
ratio of
the backward to the forward
rate is equal to e to the minus the
Affinity over the gas
constant if you take the logarithm of
that or actually if you take the
logarithm of the inverse of that so the
logarithm of the
forward to the
negative uh
right which by this formula is equal
therefore to the Affinity divided by R
uh we typically call that the degree of
this equilibrium of the
reaction so in other words it's another
way of so you can call it Affinity but
you also call it degree of thise
equilibrium
and it's related to
this
ratio clearly when the ratio is equal to
one at equilibrium the logarithm is zero
and the degree of this equilibrium is
zero and the degree of this equilibrium
can
be positive and
negative okay so let's turn for example
to to
um uh other results that follow from
that what you you just
seen think of the energy balance for a
system in which uh for an isolated box
in which there are chemical reactions
going on but there are no
exchanges of energy uh or particles with
the outside
nor entropy also so uh the rate of
entropy change is equal only to the rate
of entropy produced by
irreversibility now the rate of entropy
change it's the partial of the entropy
with respect to time now in that
scenario for the model that we have
given uh we just reviewed in ear slides
today uh the expression for the
entropy in our model in our simple
system model it's a function of many
things including the uh the epsilons the
reaction coordinates if the epsilons are
the only things that change with time
because the energy the volume and
everything else is is
fixed then the rate of change of the
entropy is the partial of s with with
respect to Epsilon time
Epsilon uh dot but the partial of s with
respect to Epsilon is the
Affinity so we have this expression
here and if the since the system is
isolated that also represents the
entropy produced by
irreversibility and uh it better be non-
negative in fact
if you write Epsilon dot like we have
written
as plus minus do
minus multiplies by the Affinity if you
remember that the Affinity we just
defined it as equal to we've not defined
we just discovered that it is equal
to R
times uh the degree of this
equilibrium we get this expression which
gives us the rate of entropy change
which has to be equal to the rate of
entropy produced by irreversibility for
the Clos system for the isolated system
and this one in fact is a combination of
of of numbers that is
always uh positive you can find that for
any X and Y
uh you have this
inequality all right so at least we are
happy that um we are not violating U the
principle of entropy non decrease and
therefore we accept this model as a
reasonable one otherwise people would
not be using
it we can also look at this expression
here and notice that we could
call see so the the contribution of to
the entropy change or the entropy
production in this for the close system
of the isolated system
is as a positive term and a negative
term or at least a term with a plus sign
and term with a minus
sign so and actually since
we said that these Epsilon pluses and
minuses are always
positive whereas the Affinity can be
positive or
negative all right so what we do we call
these two contributions this way we call
it s+ s do plus and S do
minus so we rewrite that expression for
the entropy change as s do+ minus s do
minus
of course you've we've we've we've not
we've noticed here that the these
results in always being uh
positive
but sometimes it's
positive because uh s+ is greater than S
minus but sometimes it's positive
because s minus is more negative than
s+ in fact we
can by this definition we see that s
minus over s+ is also equal to the ratio
of the forward so it's essentially
related to the degree of this
equilibrium of the overall reaction or
you could also take it as the ratio of
the exponentials of the degrees of the
this equilibrium of the
half
reactions expressions of this
sort have in the recent uh literature
let's say 15 years been called
fluctuation
relations there are many of these sort
and here essentially you see that the
the degree of this
equilibrium
governs the
probability that
uh these number be
uh greater or smaller than
one and sometimes
if people push a bit too much the
interpretation they say all right this
is H this is a process that goes against
the second law this one goes uh towards
the second law but the net balance never
violat so it's like saying well one is a
is is is more unusual than the other but
if for the second LW what counts is the
overall net
effect and here is the list of
possibilities if you want that to be
greater than zero which is uh
always uh if you
have a
positive Affinity so a positive degree
of uh these
equilibrium
uh then uh
this is the case in which the s+ is more
positive than the S
minus or if you have the Affinity
negative or the degree of this
equilibrium negative this is the case in
which the S minus is more negative than
the S Plus and of course at equilibrium
they're both equal to zero
there is another
way of getting to the same result to the
same
kinetic
theory theory of of of chemical
kinetics and this is a model based on
equilibrium
considerations so let's start
from the overall reaction that we are
studying like this
one for
which we recall what the definition of
the Affinity is it's the weighted sum of
minus mu / T of the various
chemical
potentials and
here is the law of mass action
the non equilibrium low of
massage
now let's consider also the half
reactions of formation now here for see
for compactness I put I call them plus
and minus so this represents two
reactions that the half forward and the
half
backward of formation so they are also
written in that same format with
everything to the to the left of the
equal
sign so that's the activated
complex this being a reaction as any
other I can Define its affinities so I
can Define the Affinity Plus or the
Affinity of the minus reaction I have to
be careful that the tetric coefficients
are not only these ones but also there
is a sotic coefficient equal to one in
front of of the activated complex so
that's this contribution so I need to
know or at least to uh in theoretically
assume that we are able to uh uh know
the chemical potential of the activated
complex whereas these are the usual ones
I mean those are the reactants and the
uh
products and
clearly Al for this reaction I can write
a a non equilibrium low of mass action
exactly like that one only using
properly these doomric
coefficients this the the concentration
of the activated complex goes on top
because it has a plus stochiometric
coefficient and this
summation uh I put it at the denominator
because otherwise I would have to put it
at the numerator with minus uh new plus
minus okay so that's and clearly uh I
also need to compute a an equilibrium
constant for the forward and for the
backward reaction all right so that's
that's uh pretty General know not
assumptions so
far we can also compute therefore
the
equilibrium now here's the trick we we
are going to
assume equilibrium partial equilibrium
only either for the forward or for the
backward reaction so we say all right
suppose
uh the backward reaction is at
equilibrium we set the it's Affinity
equal to zero
and from this law of mass action this
becomes one and we
compute what would
be the concentration of the activated
complex if it were in equilibrium with
the
reactants only I'm sorry with the
product because that's the backward
reaction so only on that side of the
valley there is equilibrium and that
gives me n star uh minus
I do the same also on the other side and
that would give me another value for the
concentration the actual concentration
of the activated complex is related to
those
ones through the degrees of this
equilibrium of the forward and backward
reactions because uh I can simply uh
recognize that this K and this summation
appear up here so if I substitute these
two in here it it brings me uh this
relation I also noticed that the ratio
between what would be uh the equilibrium
concentration of the activated
complex uh for the minus or for the plus
the ratio of the two is equal to
again the degree of the
equ or the exponential of the degree of
so the degree of the equilibrium can be
written also therefore as the logarithm
of those would be
concentrations meaning that at
equilibrium those
concentrations are equal if if they are
both uh that overall equilibrium so
equilibrium for the overall action
then
also uh the forward and the backward are
at so the idea is all right so that
means
that I have an indicator which is
this
ratio of the
unbalance can think of this equilibrium
concentrations as the um the sort of the
rate at which the reactants form the
activated complex and if that rate those
rates are unbalanced there is more
formation of activated complex from one
side and from the other and therefore
there is more chance uh that the
reaction proceeds uh in order to balance
this that is
why we can assume that the reaction uh
rate the of the forward reaction of of
the forward is equal to the forward
equilibrium of the activated complex
times a a coefficient which represents
the uh the frequency with
which uh the activated complex decays in
the forward
Direction and conversely for the minus
so that is the
Assumption and with that
assumption we get if you substitute this
equilibrium expression you get
this U formula which is very similar to
uh it has some something that depends on
temperature which is still what we
called the the rate constant so it's
another way of writing the rate constant
essentially
from a different
reasoning not in terms of probabilities
but in terms of
equilibrium
and of course we can apply we we can do
the same as same ratio that we did in
order to compute the principle of detail
balance
at so this is in general if you evaluate
this at equilibrium when Epsilon minus
and plus are equal and they are equal to
epsilon0 so this is equal to
one the Affinity is equal to uh zero so
e is equal to one
that
implies that K minus must be equal to k+
so that this frequency of forward and
back or Decay is equal on both
sides
symmetrical which which which gives us
some nice uh
uh understanding of so we could have
used here a single a single
K and
therefore you see that uh these forward
and backward reactions are propor
portional by the same constant uh to
these would be concentrations of the uh
activated complexes
let's return to the rate of entropy
production
and this
is for the case in which we did it
before for the case in which we have
only one chemical
reaction most of the times we have many
chemical reactions
like the 24 for hydrogen or the 350 for
methane and so
on
so we don't have only one Epsilon we
have many epsilons and Z is the number
of
reactions so the rate of change for the
entropy which for the for the isolated
system is also the entropy produced by
reversibility is a
summation of affinities each multiplied
by each right which we can write also in
this Vector
form now
here
sometimes uh we
realize
that uh not all reactions have the
are are important in the same in the
sense that U uh we need to describe
their
kinetics because some reactions are so
fast
that regardless of the kinetics they go
they
equilibrate very
quickly so we
can save ourself some time or
complication if we assume that they are
at equilibrium so essentially what we do
is to split the set of Z reactions into
a set of slow and a set of fast
reactions so I split the summation into
two
summations of
course the proportionality relation is
this one it's also a summation so uh the
we have split the summation also in here
and the this law means
that we can assume that this part of the
composition is slowly
varing as compared to this contribution
here of the fast
reactions and then we
assume that the Epsilon of the fast
reactions are at any instant of
time the equilibrium
epsilons so we use the law of mass
action to compute the equilibrium
composition only of the subset of fast
reactions assuming that the slow ones
are
frozen we temporarily
froze freeze the uh uh the slow
reactions so that fixes this part of the
composition and we say all
right for this so these become the
initial amounts like the
N uh so the for these initial amounts
what would
be the equilibrium
composition for the stomri efficients of
the fast reactions and that's what we've
been doing we apply the law of mass
action in order to compute uh uh
compositions which can be cast as uh
values of the reaction rates the Epsilon
zeros
right of course this has to be done at
every instant of time because
slowly uh the slow reactions do Advance
Al They also advance
actually they are the the bottleneck of
the mechanism they are the rate
controlling reactions the slow ones are
the ones that control the rate of the
others now like when you have a a car
Jam uh the low U cars ahead um impede
the the ones behind to go faster even if
they are faster but they can as soon as
they get there they they get stuck okay
so essentially this is is what the fast
reaction do they get stuck uh in Q of
they wait for the slow reactions to
change something and then immediately
adapt
okay so you may say Ah that's
interesting so but if the reactions the
fast
reactions are at equilibrium it means
that their affinities are equal to zero
so in the expression for the entropy
change the affinities of the fast
reactions are by this model assumed to
be all equal to
zero which is
true but one one might be led to
conclude oh so the so the First
Reactions don't contribute to the
entropy production because this sum is
equ Al to zero no that would be wrong
conclusion
because this
assumption makes the uh epsilons of the
fast reaction
appear in the affinities of the low ones
and here is
um so here this says that the the
Affinity of the fast reaction is equal
to zero which is the this the the set of
equations that you have to solve in
order to compute these Epsilon zero
fast once you find it you put it in uh
the expression the analogous expression
for the slow reactions which depend on
energy volume and the amounts now the
amounts are given by the proportionality
relation here with the absolute
instead of being now a function of time
this way it is a function of time this
way so I substitute this
Epsilon with the result of the
equilibrium
computation and so now you see that uh
the fast
reactions advance so these Epsilon Zer
Advance following the slow ones and
their Advan advance changes the uh
affects the affinities of the low
reaction so essentially we have moved
the effects of this summation which is
actually fast so it's producing uh
immediately the entropy uh so it's and
it's it's we built it in uh the
affinities of the slow reactions
all right so with this model at least
you
have you you you know you find that it's
useless to know uh the reaction uh rate
constants so the arous factors and all
all of that for the reactions that you
feel are uh
faster and therefore equili equilibrated
so here's an
example
uh of a nozzle
expansion so here we have
um be at the entrance before this throat
of the no nozzle this is a supersonic
nozzle this uh throat has on the left
hand side not drone here the a
combustion chamber in which you have
produced
the you've burnt a hydrogen in pure
oxygen and so you have the products of
combustion essentially water and few
other uh F the other eight species that
are in that scheme that will appear
again in the next
slide so these products of of combustion
are at an adiabatic flame temperature
they are certain
pressure about 25
atmospheres and uh the
throat is so designed to so as to
achieve the maximum speed you know that
when you have mac number uh so the sound
when the flow is
a Mac number equal to one that's the the
the maximum speed allowed
by the combination of the entropy
momentum and energy balance plus the
equation of State for the
gas
that's fluid
mechanics and combined with
thermodynamics but in any case so you
have Mac one and then as a result of the
expansion
here uh if you have a welld designed uh
nozle the fluid will accelerate and
become
supersonic example here it would exit at
the Mac
Four of course that means
that uh
the uh thermal
energy gets transformed into kinetic
energy so the gas cools down and also
the pressure goes
down okay
this uh occurs pretty quickly because of
the high
velocities is
expansion and uh the rapidity is
important here
because
uh the time that um the collisions
require to reequilibrate
energy uh is not U is not is um is not
enough given the residence the short
residence time those
collisions uh cannot keep
up with
equilibrium
uh here at the entrance of the nozzle we
have chemical equilibrium
so the composition here is that of
chemical
equilibrium and this is the uh the
temperature as as it
expands you would think
that the chemically effective collisions
are fast enough to keep up and maintain
chemical equilibrium if they
did you would
follow this blue dotted line
line a dashed
line in reality they
follow the red
line that's at least according to the 24
reactions say species detailed chemical
schin they are not completely Frozen
though some reactions do occur because
uh if you try to compute uh assume that
uh the
composition uh here Remains the Same all
through you would do you would obtain
this uh result that's when you assume
all the reactions
Frozen so they are not frozen they are
active so here are
the 24 reactions that we uh
have
seen and
now we look what each one does by
looking at the individual degree of this
equilibrium that we have
defined and we find something uh which
is a bit surprising if you if
you if you don't think a lot about
this
that yeah what's not surprising is that
you have some reactions for which the
degree of this equilibrium remains
practically
zero so they remain at equilibrium these
are the
ones that are pretty
fast and if you group them here like 11
13 14 18 20 21 23 it's these
ones they are two body reactions
[Music]
uh of they have certain feature this fo
minus
FV uh fo represents the free oxygen and
F the free valence of the
molecules and this difference turns out
uh I frankly don't know why that
particular difference I'm not uh enough
chemical engineer to or a chemist to
understand that you I wish Professor kek
was here to tell
us what's surprising here is that there
are other groups of reactions so the
reactions behave like groups
for
example S 8 n and
10 build up degree of this equilibrium
so that means that the kinetics cannot
uh keep up and therefore you build uh
keep up with the to reach equilibrium
and therefore you
build uh dise equilibrium that's the
degree of dis equilibrium they as you go
downstreams but these four reactions
which are very different from one
another uh yet they follow the same uh
the same um the
same
uh departure from from
equilibrium and notice that these one
are three body
reactions these are reactions that
require the Collision of three molecules
they are much less frequent and that is
why this doesn't occur fast enough to
keep up with the
equilibrium
but they do not change the difference
between free oxygen and free
valence so essentially these
reactions are subject to what we would
call A
a bottle the same bottleneck which is
the the three body reactions you need uh
a three body reaction to for them to a
three body collision and those are in
infrequent and that is characterized by
a change in the uh overall molecular
number because you see you go from three
to
two so you you have Collision of three
particles and uh after the activated
complex
uh breaks down it it produces two
fragments then we have another set
another group which is these ones these
ones these are two body
reactions but their bottleneck is that
uh these reactions
change this magic difference between uh
free oxygen free Valance they change
them the change it by the same amount
to that this is what they have in
common it's the same so they have to
face the same bottleneck changing that
and apparently
that requires
probably
uh something of of of of
the of the mechanism that is common even
if the molecules are different um that
difference plays a role in the kinetics
and it's slow it slows down so those
cannot cannot keep
up and then you also if you look uh long
enough you may recognize that the this
other group follows a curve which is the
sum of the curves below so if you take
the sum of this curve and the sum of
that curve
uh you get
that so the degree of dis equilibrium of
these ones at any instant of time is
equal to the sum of the degrees of the
equilibrium that has built up for the
other two mechanism and in fact this is
the group of reactions here that is
subject to both bottlenecks they require
three collisions mean three body uh
Collision Plus they require to change uh
the difference between free oxy and free
valence and that's why they pay double
duty so to speak and they remain behind
by the sum of these degrees of this
equ so the idea of um if you go back one
moment the idea of the ra control
constraint equilibrium model is to
assign instead of of using all the 24
reaction rates uh it shows and actually
here this shows that you get very good
results with
only uh uh rates for four
constraints two are just the element
conservation and the others are one is
the number
of molecules conservation which is
conserved uh uh by the two body
collisions and not by the three body
collisions and the other is the that
difference between the free valence and
free
oxygen and that means that you can
obtain the exact match of the
experimental results instead of solving
24 right equations so you just solve 2 +
two so that makes
four with a big gain especially
if you're doing if you're doing also
computational fluid mechanics and
therefore in addition to the chemical
kinetics you have to uh solve the the uh
the fluid mechanics of of the problem H
where if you uh if you have to deal with
turbulence and so on uh makes the
problem already complicated enough that
Savings in the number of different
differential equations you have to solve
simultaneously makes a lot of a
difference now this same
idea also
applies uh here again a nozzle you take
products of
combustion of some other
fuel uh so that you obtain
here a mixture at
equilibrium in which you have carbon
dioxide
nitrogen and a little bit of water so
90% nitrogen about 10% CO2 and 1% water
water I
think acts as a catalyzer what of the
reactions that we're going to describe
here now also at in this
nozzle the important uh effect is that
there is a degree of dise equilibrium
that builds up like we have
seen only that here the the dise
equilibrium is not between molecular
species or the certain chemical reaction
it's within the molecules in particular
the molecules of of
CO2 which which are the key molecules
that are interesting in this
application it's the balance
in how the energy is distributed between
the translational rotational and
vibrational levels of the CO2
molecule what happens here is that as uh
the um rapid expansion occurs
also here we have Sonic and Mac 4 at the
exit so it's similar to the other
problem what happens is that here you
have a lot of random kinetic
energy of the thermal agitation of
molecules and the nozzle takes that
kinetic energy and transforms it into um
stream the kinetic energy of the flow
like a a bulk
velocity and if the uh Collision
mechanisms were very
effective uh as soon as the the
translational degree of Freedom uh uh
cool
down because of the expansion you see
the temperature goes from high to low so
that means the the thermal kinetic
energy cools down it transforms into um
flow kinetic energy you you can see that
here this is the flow kinetic energy
goes up and this is the thermal kinetic
energy that goes
down and this is the uh vibrational
energy the energy in the vibrational
modes of the
molecules those also if the effective if
if the effectiveness was very high
would would lose energy quickly and uh
and trans and transfer the the the
vibrational energy into the uh kinetic
and rotation
and but this mechanism is relatively
slow
so the degree of this
equilibrium builds up in the
vibrational levels
for example this is the lower level it
gets cool
down but there is a an upper
level upper vibrational level that
remains sort of Frozen for a long time
Downstream so why is that important for
this
application for this application what
count counts is is the vibrational
levels of the CO2
molecule and the CO2 molecules
can being a molecule aligned this way
can vibrate in various
ways
uh this is a symmetric U
stretching this is a bending
mode and this is a asymmetric so it goes
distance from one side and while it goes
shorter on the other side and and keeps
going like
that now these each of these modes have
frequencies and these frequencies are
quantized because we live uh in a
Quantum world and that's
uh uh these
are like harmonic oscillators Springs a
mass and a spring according to Quantum
Mechanics cannot live in a continuous
set of levels but the levels are
quantized and so the molecule if you
give more energy to the
molecule you need to give it enough to
jump to the to up to another
level you cannot give it continuously
and the same is if you have excited some
high level in order for that to uh
release energy it has to jump down to
another
level uh the important one is this level
here which is at this
uh
wavelength wavelength is a frequency you
know there is a relation between
frequency and wavelength so the
frequency of
vibration uh is related to the
wavelength of
and here it is important to look at the
wavelength
because because of photons because of
light we will see in a
moment so the important uh thing that
happens here is that this vibrational
level which is a high level would we say
up somewhere
here is uh relatively highly populated
in the hot gases before the they enter
the nozzle because we are at high
temperature uh not only
uh that
level
is uh very close I mean the the that
level for CO2 is very close to a similar
level for nitrogen
molecules so by simple Collision the
nitrogen molecules can populate the CO2
that CO2 particular level because they
are tuned so to speak they are exactly
the same height so it's there is a good
chance that you
transfer the energy of one to uh to the
other
one and that's why uh they chose
nitrogen and CO2
and this one when it
decays it decays to this
level now every time a vibrational level
decays to a lower level it emits a
photon if that
happens
in uh
just random
situation those photons would go would
go in U uh in all directions randomly
that is
called spontaneous
emission but if that uh Decay happens uh
in a in a situation in which there are
other photons with the same frequency so
other photons that have are exact
exactly the same
frequency uh these other photons
stimulate the emission of these uh uh
Decay by producing photons that have
exactly the same uh frequency and
direction this is what uh happens this
is called stimulated
emission and this
is the object of uh uh the objective of
of of this entire construction because
by doing that let's see if I havea oops
by doing that this picture shows you uh
the details of how big this is thing
this thing is so the nozzle is about um
a
meter a meter here
um so what they do essentially is to put
um I'm sorry this is the diffuser the
nozzle uh the good part the the nozzle
is
here these are the nozzles so several of
them this is the expansion and this is
the downstream area in which we have the
uh that degree of dise equilibrium so in
which I have populated still populated
the high levels this is called inversion
of population it's the it's the inverse
of what you would be at equilibrium at
the local values of of temperature
but uh with that
inversion uh it turn turns out if you
have an inversion of population means
that this one is more populated and
therefore the rate at which um you
produce photons by
Decay is higher than the typical rate at
which photons get
absorbed uh uh in order to repopulate
that one so you have a net release of
photons and if you put that between
mirrors
so that these photons go back and forth
and stimulate the emission then you get
the building up of light coherent light
photons with the same frequency same
direction so that's a
laser and this is actually a power laser
because usually the lasers that you have
you use for like pointer laser for
PowerPoint is uh I don't know micro
microwatts or mwatts I don't know very
small power
but with this one and we're talking
about
1970s the output was continuous output
of light of 60 kilowatt which is a huge
amount of of power especially if it is
that's the kind of light with which you
can do laser cutting of
metals okay so and this is all due to
the fact that you managed to establish
the degree of dise
equilibrium and I think I would stop
here for today