[Music]
Hello and welcome back to Today I
Learned Climate, the climate change
podcast of the Massachusetts Institute
of Technology. I'm Laura Hessie Fischer.
If you asked me, how do we make our
electricity cleaner and cheaper? I would
probably talk about solar and wind and
batteries and the promise of geothermal
and nuclear. I wouldn't start by talking
about the power lines running into the
homes along my block, but our guest
today makes the case that maybe I
should.
Look, transmission is not a sexy thing.
You know, it it doesn't have windmills.
It doesn't have cooling towers. It's a
nuisance. No one wants to look at the
lines. But I think it's probably the
single most important piece to improving
reliability and reducing costs.
That's Joshua Hajj. I'm the executive
director at the center for energy and
environmental policy research here at
MIT as well as the research director for
the MIT climate policy center. Mr. Hajj
is here to talk about upgrading our
transmission system. Basically, that
means building more and better power
lines in the right places. And there are
at least three big reasons to do that.
To make our power more reliable,
cleaner, and cheaper. But first, we have
to explain what exactly transmission
does because we usually focus on how
electricity is made, say by a coal plant
or a wind turbine or what it's used for,
like in our homes and businesses. Mr.
Hodgej is going to call these generation
and load. The transmission connects the
generation to the load. And those power
lines outside my window, they're just
the last stop on the way. More important
are the high voltage transmission lines
that you might see along the highway.
Strung from giant steel towers and
served by an immense network of machines
that direct and convert electricity over
hundreds of miles. And all of that
equipment plus the power plants
themselves need to work together to
perform a remarkable balancing act
to ensure continuous power to ensure
what we call reliability. Total
generation on the network must be
continuously and precisely matched with
load. If it's not, you risk outages and
blackouts.
You know how if you try to force too
much water through a hose, it just
spurts everywhere? Well, generating too
much power means electricity has nowhere
to go, and that can cause problems. It's
the job of transmission to make sure
that we always have exactly as much
power as we need. No more and no less.
People don't realize that we have
transmission lines stripped all the
time, but they almost never result in a
blackout. That's because these systems
automatically disconnect from the grid
when that happens and they have to
isolate those faults in milliseconds.
A bigger grid means you have more
options to reroute power when something
goes wrong. That's why upgrading our
transmission system gets us more
reliable power. And as cyber attacks
become a bigger threat to our energy
system and climate change brings more
big storms and wildfires that can wreck
power lines, we have more reason than
ever to brace for the unexpected.
And reliability requires that all parts
of the system operate as a single
machine from the generation plants on
one end to the load on the other and all
the equipment in between.
A single machine that is so large that
it crosses states and even countries. A
machine in which our power plants are
just tiny cogs. And it's a thinking
machine that's constantly solving
thousands of problems just so you can
turn on your dishwasher.
It's quite sophisticated and I think
generally underappreciated.
So it's really good at supplying power
for the early 20th century American
economy. I mean exceptionally good at
it. So it efficiently moves electricity
from large centralized power plants like
coal, nuclear and gas plants to urban
industrial centers or centers of load.
But today our economy is looking less
and less like that 20th century model.
For one thing, our electricity needs are
growing fast. Take the rise of AI which
needs big energy hungry data centers.
That is significant potential new load
that many regions don't have the
capacity to accommodate.
And at the same time, more people are
switching from fossil fuels to
electricity to heat their homes and to
power their cars. Now, that's good for
the climate and for our wallets, but it
adds even more to the load. And the new
power that we're building to meet this
demand. Well, in 2024, more than 70% of
it came from wind and solar. That is
very different from traditional coal and
gas and nuclear power, which can be
built right next to where it's needed.
So, you know, most of our wind
generation in the US is in the central
US, not necessarily close even to load
centers in those regions, let alone
other regions. Our best solar is in the
southwest, pretty far from every load
center except the big cities in the
southwest. But we lack the transmission
capacity to deliver that high quality
renewable generation to where it's
needed. And so, you know, the bigger the
transmission system, the more diverse
wind and solar resources you have access
to, the stronger likelihood you have
access to electrons somewhere where the
wind's blowing and somewhere where it's
not cloudy.
This is why a bigger transmission system
can give us cleaner energy. We can build
as much wind and solar power as we want,
but if we can't get that energy to where
it's used, we're still going to have to
fire up our coal and gas plants to keep
the lights on. In fact, if a solar and
wind farm can't deliver electricity to
where it's needed, it shuts down. This
is what energy experts call curtailment.
There is a utility in Missouri that I
work with that has a lot of wind
generation northwest corner of the state
and they're continuously curtailing it.
I think it's almost just a nuisance for
them cuz again I mean if the wind was
blowing during a peak time and or the
wind was close enough to the load center
then then you'd be using it. And this
gets at why building out transmission
can make our power cheaper. Because the
larger the grid, the more easily it can
pull from the cheapest sources of
electricity, whatever and wherever they
may be. Today, the cheapest power is
often wind and solar, at least when we
can get it. But even when our power
comes from coal and gas, more
transmission helps us get cheaper
electricity from these sources. And this
flexibility is especially important when
the power is most expensive.
So I think you know big cities during
heat waves or big cities during
snowstorms right prices get very very
high. By expanding one's transmission
system you can access more sources of
generation and indeed in many cases
lower cost forms of generation which in
turn enable lower retail power prices.
So as a country, we must be in a big
hurry to build more transmission, right?
So it turns out that irrespective of how
people feel about climate change,
they're very reluctant to have any
energy related infrastructure built near
them, whether those are solar panels or
wind turbines, certainly high voltage
transmission lines.
Let's give you an example of what's
happening now in 2025 in the Northeast.
There's New England Clean Energy Connect
under construction right now in Maine to
bring hydro power from Quebec into
Massachusetts.
This is a good deal for the places at
either end. Massachusetts wants more
clean power sources like hydro, and
Quebec has more than they can use, but
most of the power lines are being built
in Maine, the state in between. local
and rural lawmakers, even if they
support energy development, they may
oppose running lines through their
districts if the local benefits aren't
clear. And that is something that we see
frequently with new transmission
projects. Siding and permitting is
mostly state level, which means crossing
multiple states can require permits and
approval from each other. Local
opposition such as environmental
concerns, land use disputes can delay or
kill projects. And you know, I had a
front row seat to all this in Maine
because I co-authored a paper on this
topic. And um a lot of people were
really upset that our paper showed this
line as reducing the cost of
decarbonization
in New England because from their
perspective, cutting down trees to build
a transmission line inherently hurt the
earth. So they would say things to me
like, "What you're saying doesn't make
sense. You can't save the earth by
destroying it." New England Clean Energy
Connect was permitted years ago. They
were legally allowed to to build it, but
it was delayed by years by lawsuits.
This is complicated. The people filing
those lawsuits were looking out for
their state, the towns and the forests
that the transmission lines are passing
through. That's more important to them
than getting clean electricity to a
different state. So, whose job is it to
look out for the transmission system as
a whole?
You know, a key challenge here is no
single entity can mandate or centrally
fund long-distance transmission is
pieced together regionally.
Even though transmission has to work as
a single machine, no one's in charge of
building or running the whole thing. And
when lots of utilities and grid
operators are each looking out for their
own areas, none of them are motivated to
fight or pay for new power lines. More
often, we build new transmission when
the system is on the verge of breaking.
When we've got a backlog of new power
waiting to come online, or a new batch
of AI data centers straining the grid,
we're reactive, reactive, reactive,
reactive. In fact, reactive is probably
being too gentle because we're reactive,
you know, many years after the the in
many cases the generation is ready to be
connected. Right now, we have thousands
of projects, mostly wind and solar,
waiting to connect to the grid, but they
can't because they're stuck because
there's not enough transmission
capacity.
Yeah. Right now, developers build wind
and solar where it's easiest and
cheapest, not necessarily where the
lines exist to carry that power. But
what if we planned ahead for this? What
if we made sure wherever energy is
cheapest, the transmission is waiting to
meet it?
uh positive example what can be done is
the competitive renewable energy zones
in Texas called Texas K.
KE was dreamed up in the mid 2000s when
there was hardly any wind or solar power
in the United States. But Texas
lawmakers noticed that windy West Texas
had a ton of energy potential. So they
put out a call for big transmission
lines leading out to this region even
before there was anything for them to
connect to. So it was completed over a
decade ago and
it was essentially built so that wind
generation in Texas was economically
feasible. Texas leads the US wind
production. It's got over 40,000
megawatts install capacity now which is
like over four Massachusetts worth of
power. And the whole reason that is the
case in Texas is because they were able
to come up with a pretty diverse
coalition that got something very
ambitious built. If this has worked for
Texas wind, can it work across the
United States? Well, after all, the US
has built big continent spanning
projects before. Take the railways or
our highway network. Both of which
wouldn't have been possible without a
big push from the federal government.
You know, we did it with the interstate
system. It's probably the best precedent
we have. And there the federal
government did a very good job of
convincing the states of economic
benefits of enabling facilitating this
interstate buildout. I think in a
regional grid across North America
enables us to imagine things like sun
electrons from Arizona going to Seattle
on a cloudy day. offshore wind electrons
in Massachusetts, enabling Quebec not to
have to use its hydro when the wind's
really blowing like crazy here and it's
super cheap. And then when the wind's
not blowing here, you can bring the
hydro down from Quebec. And you know,
because there are so many
economic benefits of expanding
transmission, I would love to figure out
some way to build stronger bipartisan
understanding. Hey, we may not agree on
how we're going to power this system
entirely, right? But we're all
interested in a more flexible, more
reliable, but most importantly, a
cheaper power system.
That's our show, but there is plenty
more of today I learned climate at
tilclimate.mmit.edu.
I have some important news to share
today. This season is my last as the
host of Tilclimate.
It has been an incredible joy and a true
privilege bringing the show to you all
for the past 60 episodes and I can only
hope that you've learned as much as I
have and had half as much fun learning
it. But this won't be the last time that
you hear my voice. We are planning some
bonus content to round out my time here
and also to introduce our new host
because tio climate is not going
anywhere. So, please stay tuned to our
feed for more. TIO Climate is a climate
change podcast of the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology. Aaron Kroll is
our writer and executive producer. David
Lashansky is our sound editor and
producer. Michelle Harris is our fact
checker. Madison Goldberg is our
associate producer. The music is by Blue
Dot Sessions. And I'm your host and
senior editor, Laur Hessie Fischer.
Thank you to Joshua Hajj for speaking
with us. And to all of you for
listening.
[Music]