But yeah, we are very glad to have John
Hull with us here. So, John, please.
>> Well, thanks very much. It's a real
pleasure to be here. Um, let me just say
a little bit by way of introduction. I I
I've probably got a similar background
to many of you. Math was always my my
best subject at high school.
That was uh that was in the UK and um I
not surprisingly ended up doing a math
undergraduate at Cambridge. Um
and you know after
graduating I decided that I wanted to
apply my math in business. So I did a
master's in operational research which
was a fairly new thing in those days. Um
but uh and then an amusing little
factoid, I I I worked for two years
after graduating with my masters. I
worked for two years for a shoe
retailer. Everybody sort of bursts out
laughing when they hear this. Actually,
it was a large shoe retailer in the UK.
It had 2,000 outlets. And actually, it
was a pretty interesting job. I mean it
was all about deciding which outlets
should stock which shoes in which sizes
and so on and then you know which
outlets should be closed and where we
should look for new outlets and that
sort of thing. So there's lots of
interesting stuff
but um after two years
I with this company I sort of moved back
into the academic world.
I
I I won't uh I won't bore you with all
the details, but uh I wound up I got got
my PhD and ended up teaching here at
University of Toronto in what we call
the Joseph L. Rottman School of
Management. And I've been been at
University of Toronto for about 30 years
now.
probably
um
probably I'm best known for my work on
derivatives which I understand you guys
have had quite a bit of instruction in
but um
and you know most of my 30 years has
been spent doing research in derivatives
but about I guess it was about seven
eight years ago I
began to see that uh you machine
learning
and AI were becoming really important to
our students. And so
I sort of switched my focus and in fact
all of my teaching is now in the machine
learning area and pretty much every
so let me advance slide. pretty much
every um
course that we offer at Rottman actually
has either a compulsory course or an
elective in machine learning. So it's
not just me that teaches machine
learning. Now got quite a few colleagues
who who who do so as well.
I I wrote a book which is now in its
third edition um machine learning in
business an introduction to the world of
data science and um you can you can find
out more information on the book from my
website but I'm not saying you should
buy the book now um in fact
re the reverse is true because the
fourth edition will be coming out in
probably about two months.
The fourth edition is going to be with
three co-authors who are actually the
other people who teach uh teach machine
learning here at Robman. So, you know,
the fourth edition is going to deal with
um you know, I mean, third edition came
out in I think it was 2021.
And since then, of course, we've had a
lot of things happen in uh natural
language processing, large language
models, that sort of thing. So I wanted
to you know bring the book up to date
and my colleagues have helped me do
that. So um you know I'm going really
today's presentations in three parts.
I'm going to talk about the nature of
machine learning. Um then I'm going to
move on to talk about applications of
neural networks and finally what I've
been working on quite a lot over the
last little while applications of re
reinforcement learning. Okay. Um, I
don't know whether there's any easy way
you can interrupt me to ask questions,
but I'm I'm happy to be interrupted with
any questions you have as we go along.
Is is it possible for them to interrupt
me with questions?
>> I will I will hear them.
>> Yes, I think you will.
>> Good. Good. Okay. No, I don't mind being
interrupted at all. Okay.
So
uh next slide please.
So what is machine learning? It's uh
it's a branch of AI and the idea
underlying machine learning is is that
we give a computer access to lots of
data and just learn let it learn learn
about the relationships between
variables and make predictions.
Some of the techniques of machine
learning date back to quite a long way.
The key thing that's different today is
that computers are really fast. So we
had all these techniques for doing what
we call machine learning quite some time
ago, but really computers weren't fast
enough to make them a practical tool.
We're now reaching the stage where all
of these ideas
suddenly become practical tools because
of the speed of the machines. Okay. I
think you know it's important to
distinguish between machine learning and
all the automation that's gone on before
it. I mean computers have been used for
many years to automate many business
decisions, payroll, sending out
invoices, so on.
This is what we could call the third
industrial revolution.
Okay. And uh machine learning is central
to the fourth industrial revolution.
You want a bit of background here. The
first industrial revolution was steam
and water power which was uh about 1760
to 1840. The second industrial
revolution was electricity and mass
production.
This is gen this is this is not me. This
is what's generally considered to be the
case and this was 1840 to 1920.
Then
basically computers and digitization
were the third industrial revolution and
we've really had you know we now know
how to use computers to automate things
that human beings do. Um
and uh
I say we can call that computers and
digitization.
And that you we could say that went from
maybe 1950
to the year 2000.
And then
we're now living through the fourth
industrial revolution and we'll be
living through it for quite some time
which is really
you know AI machine learning and
everything
we're going to be talking about today.
Okay ne next slide please.
So if you want to
let's go back to six slide six. Um if
you want to sort of distinguish between
um
the third and the fourth industrial
revolution um
one example I use is with loan
applications. I mean let's suppose we've
got loan officers in a company and there
are certain rules they use to decide
whether a loan should be accepted or
not.
and um
those those rules have been worked out,
then we could automate their activities
and that would just be the third
industrial revolution. If we didn't know
the rules,
we could actually use machine learning
to determine the rules.
We'd collect a lot of lots and lots of
data on loans that
came before the loan officers and the
decisions that were made and it would be
an application of machine learning.
We could go one step further though and
we could also say well let's try and
improve on the rules. So then we could
collect lots of data on decisions that
were made by the loan officers and how
those decisions worked out and u
try and improve the rules for accepting
or rejecting loans.
So the first bullet point here is the
third industrial revolution digitization
fairly straightforward and then the last
two would be applications of machine
learning. Okay, next slide.
So uh I'm sure you've all been trained
in statistics
and we all know that what we're supposed
to do in statistics is
sit down
comfortable chair
not look at any data and develop a
hypothesis.
Then we collect data and test the
hypothesis. That's the sort of standard
way of doing things in statistics.
Machine learning is different. What we
do, we don't develop any hypotheses in
machine learning. We go out and we
collect the data
and we try and explain the data. We try
different models
and we find
patterns in the data or try and develop
predictive tool or something like that.
The key difference between machine
learning and the traditional
statistics
um statistical approach is that in
machine learning
we
collect the data first where in
statistics you're not supposed to
collect the data first. You're supposed
to develop the hypothesis before you've
even looked at the data.
Okay. Um
uh next slide.
So
there's various types of machine
learning algorithms.
Unsupervised learning which is basically
just looking for patterns in the data or
clusters in the data. Um supervised
learning which is where we're trying to
predict something or classify the data
in some way. And then reinforcement
learning which is multi-stage decision
making which we'll be talking a bit
about later on.
And there's you know there's other ways
of subdividing the algorithms but um
you know this is
this you know this is one quick
classification if you like. Machine
learning has its own terminology.
Um and actually this when I first got
into machine learning as I say it was
something like seven or eight years ago
I was pretty confused because the
terminology is different from statistics
you know in um
statistics for example we talk about
dependent variables independent
variables and so on. uh whereas uh
in machine learning we talk about
features
and targets.
Targets as its name implies is the thing
you're trying to predict perhaps and
features are the independent variables
you're trying to predict from. You know
think things like labels, activation
functions and so on. In fact,
when I when I wrote my book, which I
showed you earlier, I have a whole
section, I think it's about 10 pages
long, showing all the terminology
which uh you know, which machine
learning uses um
some of which is quite different from
the terminology that statistics uses and
and other branches.
It's uh
It's one of the things that you know
just takes a bit of getting used to. Um
and you know these this terminology
unsupervised learning supervised
learning for example I mean where does
that come from? Unsupervised learning
well with unsupervised learning you're
just looking for patterns in the data.
So you could say, you know, you don't
really need to
you don't really need any supervision
because all you're doing is just looking
for patterns.
And
so you just all you need to do is to
throw the data at the at the software
and the software will find patterns for
you. Whereas supervised learning, you've
got to do a bit of supervision because
you got to tell
you got to tell the computer what you
want it to do with the data. You want it
to predict something, classify data in
some way and so on.
So
okay, sorry uh next slide.
So just you you one slide on
unsupervised learning then. So in a
typical application what you're asking
you know you
you give the software data
and you ask it to divide the data into
clusters so that observations in the
same cluster have similar feature
values. Okay. So a typical application
would be a company wants to understand
its customers better.
So it collects attributes of its
customers. There may be you know
10 10 different attributes that it
collects you know like how much the
customer spends every year um how many
different products the customer buys
where the customer is located and so on
and so on.
And
basically
you you give the uh software a list of
your customers with those sort of
attributes and it will
classify them or cluster them. So you
say, "Oh yeah, we've got customers that
look like this. We've got customers that
look like this. We've got customers and
and and so on."
And I'm told that, you know, this is
actually quite a powerful tool because
sometimes you get to find cluster
clusters of customers that you never
really thought of as being a cluster of
your customers before, but you know,
this tool has actually enabled you to
sort of find find the clusters.
Okay, next next slide.
So supervised learning is where you are
you're not just trying to understand the
data and create clusters from your data.
You're actually trying to predict
something typically.
And what you do
is you divide your data into three sets.
Training set, a validation set, and a
test set.
Because remember what we're doing here
is not we haven't got a hypothesis.
you've just got a lot of data.
And so you typically you put about 60%
of your data into the training set, 20%
into the validation set, and 20% into
the test set. And hopefully you've got
quite a lot of data.
Okay? So
you develop different models
using the training set.
So you try out different models
and we'll see some examples of this in a
moment and
you compare those models using
validation set say well this model seems
to do better than this other model when
test when tested on you know the
parameters of the model are determined
using the training set
and then you can see how well the models
work on the validation set and uh
decide which seems to be the best model
for explaining the data.
Typically, you know,
you can find a really complex model
sometimes anyway that will explain the
data in the training set, but then it
does not
do well on the validation set. So, the
model can be too complex
as we'll see. So you you want to
typically you want to a rule of thumb is
you want to increase model complexity
until the model starts to perform worse
on the validation set. So once you've
chosen a particular model, you can
increase its complexity and the
parameters and so on, but as soon as it
starts to perform worse on the
validation set, you know, you've
overfitted the training set
and then the test set is sort of kept to
one one side and it's, you know, it's
not being involved in the selection of
the model or anything like that. And so
it provides a good final out of sample
indication as to how well the chosen
model works.
Yeah, next slide please.
Thanks.
So this is this is an example that I use
in the book. It's a pretty uh trivial
example in a way, but it's for
predicting salaries for people in a
certain profession in a certain area as
a function of age and we try out
different models
um
didn't have a huge amount of data for
this particular one. We try out
different models which are
just polomials polomials
of the person age. So the first the
extreme left model is a fifth order
polomial and it fits it fits the data
pretty well.
But actually
what it
what is fitting is the um
first
60% of data that you use to compare your
models. Okay, it doesn't fit the
validation set well.
So it's overfitting. You find
the linear model is underfitting and the
best model actually for the data that I
used was um was a quadratic model.
So salary increases and then sort of
slightly tails off as you get older.
So it's an example of you know if you
just it depends how much data you've got
of course
for um for comparing your models but it
you know but it it quite often happens
that you wind up overfitting
a model and
maybe we just go back a slide or
to uh
yeah so training sorry so the training
so you use the training set but it's you
know you find that you have actually
fitted the training set really well but
the model
doesn't extend well to the validation
set so you then say you've overfitted
the training set okay so that's example
of what I'm talking about increased
model complexity until the model starts
to perform worse on the validation set.
Thanks, Peter. Let's uh let's move on.
Neural networks. Well, maybe I I'll just
stop there. Are there any questions that
uh anybody really wants to ask or points
anybody wants to make before we move on?
Okay. If not, um, okay, let's move on to
the next slide. And the next slide. So,
we're now going to talk about neural
networks.
And here's a picture of an artificial
neural network. It's abbreviated ANN.
So basically what we're trying to do is
to in this example predict something
from certain variables. So the input
layer would be the variables
that we know.
Okay. And the output layer are the one
or more things we're trying to predict.
Now I know I've got multiple variables
in the output layer here. Typically
though
in many applications there's only one
thing you're trying to predict. So let's
think in ter I mean if there's multiple
things you're trying to predict then
obviously you've got to
in terms of your objective you've got to
wait how important is it to predict this
one how important is it to predict that
one and so on. So let you know let's
just for the moment assume there's only
one variable in the output layer.
The models that you're most
familiar with are models that
predict
the output from the input in one go as
it were. Linear regression
uh would be a classic example. Um
but you know
any any more complicated model is is
also likely to you know predict the
output directly from the input. The key
thing that we're doing with an
artificial neural network is we're not
doing it all in one go.
We're get we're using the input layer,
the variables
that we know
to predict
these variables in the first hidden
layer. V11, V12, V13 and so on. And then
we use those variables in the first
hidden layer to predict variables in the
second hidden layer. V21, V22, V23 and
so on. And then the third hidden layer.
So the key thing is about a neural
network is that you're going through a
number of stages in predicting the
output from the input.
It's not all done in one go. So we're
not we're not writing down a nice neat
equation
for the relationship between the output
and the input and predict predicting the
parameters of that equation. We're
saying there's a number of stages we go
through
in getting from the input to the output
and
um
that makes the model of course a lot
more flexible.
Uh next slide.
So
what's the relationship between
the values in one layer and the values
in the previous layer?
Well,
what we're doing is we're relating the
values at one neuron to a linear
combination of values in the previous
layer. And
we're using these things called
activation functions to do it. Maybe we
go back a slide. Uh now, Peter, if we
could. And so
if we look here, V11 is related to the
variables in the input layer, the
variables we know, V 01, V 02, V 03. And
what we do, what we do is we apply
weights to those variables. So we have a
weight times v 01 plus a weight time v
02 plus a weight time v 03 and so on.
And then once we got this weighted
average
of the v 01, v 02, v 03, we apply a
function to it to get v11. And then we
do the same thing for v12. We take a,
you know, a weighted average of V 01, V
02, V 03 and so on different weighted
average and apply a function to it to
get V12 and so on.
And then to go from the V1s, V12s, V13s
to V21, V22, V23, we do the same thing.
So V21 for example, we take a weighted
average of
V11, V12, V13, V14 and so on
and apply a function to it this
activation function to get V21.
Okay. And then so what are the thing is
what are the parameters of this model?
the parameters of the weights. What
weights
what weights do we apply to the V's
in going from one layer to the next
layer. Okay? And you know there's a lot
of weights in this example that you got
in front of you there because when we're
determining V11, we've got a weight
associated with V01, V 02, V 03, and so
on.
But if even if there are only three
inputs, that's three weights. And then
V12 is another three weights. V13 is
another three weights and so on. So you
can wind up with a lot of weights. But
those are the variables that uh those
weights
are are the variables you're trying to
determine. And then the activation
function is something you apply after
you've applied the weights.
Okay. So, can we move on to the next
slide now? So, you see
a number of different activation
functions that you could use. FY fy
equals y means that you've just applied
weights to the variables in the previous
layer and then you've just haven't done
anything else to them. You've just said
that that's going to give you the value
in the new layer.
Now if throughout
the whole
neural network you just use the identity
if you think about it you would just
have a linear model.
Okay.
So if uh you know the variables in the
first layer were a linear function of
the input layer, the variables in the
second layer were a line were linear
functions of the variables in the first
layer and so on and you went all the way
through then it would just be a linear
model and that wouldn't be very
interesting because if we want to have a
linear model we don't have to go through
all this. However,
as we'll see, you often use the identity
just for the final layer.
You see, sigmoid is a a popular um
activation function. So sing the so once
you've uh determined
the uh weighted average
of the variables in the previous layer
you you take one 1 - 1 + e to the minus
that
to get the value at the new node and so
on. hyperbolic tangent ru and so on lots
of different activation functions. So
you get the idea you've
you're really saying that the
relationship
with between the output and the input is
a kind of a convolution
of a lot of these activation functions
applied
to weighted averages.
Okay, next. Um
so uh
how do we actually solve the model?
Well,
basically
you've got lot typically in in these
in models you've got lots of parameter
values all the different weights that
you're applying
and uh
you say well you start off by assuming
some values for the weights probably not
very good values but you assume some
values and then you calculate gradients
you say Well,
we're perhaps we're trying to minimize
some value or or minimize a function.
So, we're trying to determine the input
values that will minimize some function.
So, we calculate gradients to determine
the direction in which the parameter
values should be changed
to improve things to actually make the
function smaller. And then you take a
step
and then do the whole thing again.
Calculate the gradients
and
move the parameter values again in a
certain direction and so on.
So
it's it's it's a case of
Phoenix somebody trying to call me. Um,
so
basically what you need is you're trying
to minimize some function. What you need
is the partial derivative of that
function with respect to all these
parameters, all these weights that
define your model.
Now that seems a pretty tricky task, but
actually
um
there was I mean clever maybe you could
say almost obvious way of doing this is
to say what we're really talking about
with this model is
the final thing that we're interested in
being a function of a function of a
function. In other words, if you know,
we're we're a function of the final
weights and those final weights are a
function of the
weights that come immediately before the
final weights and then those final
weights, you know, so each weight
and of course in in calculus we know how
to calculate the gradient of a function.
of a function of a function. So there
are some clever shortcuts
or um
you know for calculating these gradients
that you need
to to sort of move the parameters in the
right direction. Okay, you're not
starting from scratch in terms of
calculating each gradient.
Uh next next slide please.
So this is a very simple example but it
illustrates the nature of what you're
doing. I mean let's suppose you wanted
to calculate the value of x that
minimizes
this function
y = x^2 - 8x + 20. Of course you know we
could all do this with calculus very
quickly and x= 4 is the answer. But
suppose we we were doing it in the way
that I just described.
Then we'd start with some estimate of x.
It might be x= 1. Not a very good
estimate. And then we'd look at the
gradient
of um
of this when x= 1.
And what is it? It's you know 2x
minus 8. So it's the gradient is minus
6. So we move
you know you know we move the value that
we're looking at in the direction which
minimizes
um
y which you know the gradient was minus
6. So we take the negative of the
gradient because we're trying to
minimize something and
move it in the direction indicated by
the gradient
by a certain amount and we see that
we're then at a little bit more than
two. Then we calculate the gradient
again. Move again. Calate gradient
again. So you can see how this method
would work
in this very simple example where
there's
when there's only one thing that we
we're having to estimate.
Okay. And
obviously when there's many things we
want to estimate um it's the same basic
principle except we're we're working in
many dimensions.
Okay. Uh next slide please.
So we continue training the model until
the results for the validation set
diverge from those for the training set.
We don't want to overtrain.
Choosing the learning rate is important.
The learning rate is how far we move.
Once we've once we've estimated the
gradient,
we have we have to uh decide how far we
want to move in the direction indicated
by the gradient. And um
that's uh well there are you know there
are some clever ways of determining the
the learning rate as it's called but
clearly if we could just go back to the
previous slide a moment um you can I
think you can see here if you choose a
really
small learning rate
then I mean the gradient at one would be
the same but you'd move only very short
amounts and then you calculate the
gradient again and move a very short
amount and so on. You'd never actually
reach the bottom of the you never in a
reasonable time reach the bottom of the
curve. If you made the learning rate too
small because the learning rate is just
is determining how far you move once
you've determined the gradient. On the
other hand, if the learning rate is too
big, you could oscillate and sort of
move from above the minimum to below the
minimum to above the minimum to to below
the minimum and so on.
So determining the learning rate is
important and some you know you can do
it by trial and error as I say there's
some clever ways of of doing it as well.
Okay. Um next slide please. Um it's also
turns out to be best to scale the
variables.
When you're doing all of this and back
propagation is used to calculate the
partial derivatives that that's what I
mentioned before, which is really just
saying the partial derivatives, you're
talking about taking the partial
derivative of something which is a
function of a function. We've known how
to do that in calculus for quite a long
time.
Okay. Uh next slide, please.
So here's, you know, one application
that we've used it for. We may may seem
a little artificial, but actually it's
not as I'll explain in a minute. But
basically, I generated 10,000 call
option prices using the black shells
model and added a normally distributed
error. So I I generated a lot of data. I
said that you know
the asset price S the strike price K the
risk-free rate
um the volatility sigma and the time to
maturity uh you you can see in the
second bullet point there what I chose
as the um
as the ranges there. So we we we we
sampled parameters randomly and then
added
a normally distributed error term
to the black shells model and then said
you know
let's see how well the model can
actually determine
what the function is
and actually use three hidden layers 20
neurons per layer
and sigmoid activation function
except the final layer and this is a
point if I'd used the sigmoid activation
function everywhere it wouldn't have
worked because
sigmoid activation function gives you a
value between zero and one and of course
the black shells m price is not between
zero and one so
I I I used the um
identity activation function for the
final layer. And that's not uncommon to
use the identity activation function for
the final layer because the activation
functions you're using for earlier
layers may be constraining the answer
you get.
And you know divided the observation
between the training set validation set
and the test set in the way that we were
discussing earlier. 6,000 for the
training set, 2,000 for the validation
set, 2,000 for the test set.
Uh we have the next slide please, Peter.
So you can see
um what happens the epoch of the
training set is increased which just
basically means you know we continue to
try and match
the training set data as closely as
possible.
It imp improves things
for the validation set up to a certain
point and then
starts to get worse. See what's go going
on better. Um, next slide
we can sort of take a moving average.
And this is so you can see what's going
on here. We uh keep trying to improve
the model but we stop after 2575
epochs. Just think about the epoch as a
trial. Okay. So you can see that
things improve
for
the validation set up to a certain point
and then they then they seem to get
worse. So it's best to stop. So the
model that we actually wound up with was
the model after 25
75 epochs.
Um, next slide, please.
So
we only had 10,000 observations, but we
found that the neural network actually
imitated the black shells mer.
In other words, the random noise that we
added to the black shells mer prices
didn't, you know, it managed to overcome
that random noise pretty well.
Okay,
there more details about that in my
book.
So, the next slide.
Now, you may say, well, that's a pretty
artificial example. We don't need a
model to
you know we don't need to use neural
networks to determine the black shells
model um because we have a formula but
it turns out that actually derivatives
companies are are using neural networks
to value exotic derivatives. There are
some derivatives which can only be
valued using Monte Carlo simulation
and Monte Carlo simulation is slow. It
can take, you know, three or four
minutes to come up with a price. And if
you've got, you know, if you got a
client on the end of the end of the
line, that may not be very good.
So
basically, instead of doing this for the
blacksholes model, you could do it for
some exotic derivatives model. I mean
you run your multiolor simulation many
many times to create data
which relates the price to the inputs
and then you create a neural network to
replicate the prices as closely as
possible and then after you've done that
you have a really fast way I mean
obviously you don't you know if you're
doing this in the way that I'm
describing you wouldn't actually add an
to it. You You just want to create the
prices as accurately as possible. And
once you've got a neural network
that will actually create these exotic
option prices,
you can then very very quickly calculate
any new price you want to because all
you're doing
to work
to calculate a new price is working
forward through the neural network.
So
you know instead of being three or four
minutes it's uh you know almost
instantaneous
because you work as I say you work
forward through the neural network to
obtain the price and this this can also
be useful for scenario analysis because
scenario analysis can be very slow if
you're having to calculate this exotic
option over and over again using Monte
Carlo simulation. But if you can if
you've constructed a neural network
to produce a price then it's you know
much faster
and scenario analysis is is perfectly
feasible.
Um can we have the
the next slide please?
Another thing we've looked at as part of
our research is we've looked at uh the
relationship
between volatilities and um how
volatilities change as the uh return on
the asset changes.
If you know this the standard way of
doing hedging of course is to say well
I mean let's talk about delta hedging
but it applies to other hedging as well.
With delta hedging you say well
how does the price of the option change
when the price of the underlying asset
changes? And we'll assume that the
implied volatility remains the same.
That's the standard assumption. Implied
volatility remains the same. And you you
just calculate delta as the
rate of change
of the option price with respect to the
asset price. Um
but
perhaps there's a tendency for the
volatility to change
as the
um asset price changes. In other words,
if there's a positive return on the
asset, so the asset price goes up,
there's less o overall
the company is less highly levered.
At least in the market value sense, the
company is less highly levered and so
maybe the implied volatility goes down.
Whereas if the return on the asset goes
down,
company becomes more highly levered and
therefore there's a tendency for the
volatility to goes up. So maybe we
should take this into account when
calculating delta.
So can I have the the next slide please,
Peter?
So
we uh
calculated
um the neural network to investigate
this and to see what's the relationship
between the daily asset price return and
the change in the implied volatility.
And
um so input layer had money time to
maturity daily asset price return and
the output layer had change in implied
volatility. Next next slide please.
Um these were all the
um all the details. In the interest of
time let's move on. Next slide please.
And
We can see that
you know
we actually in this particular case
found that uh validation set started to
get worse after 5,826
epochs. You kind of see that see that a
little bit in this diagram. So we
stopped the training after 5,826
epochs.
Next slide.
It wasn't you know at first at first
we're pretty disappointed with the
result of this research because the um
the test set which is final result it
actually only gave an 11% improvement
over a simpler analytic model that uh my
colleague Alan White and I had worked on
in 2017.
So you know it didn't give a hugely
better relationship between the return
on the asset and the volatility.
However,
we played around with it a bit and when
the VIX index was used as a feature,
there was a further improvement of 60%.
And what we found was that the behavior
of the volatility surface was different
in high and low volatility environments.
In other words, if you want to predict
what's going to happen to the volatility
surface, so you know how to change the
implied volatility when you change the
underlying asset price,
you really want to know whether you're
in a high volatility environment or a
low volatility environment. So that this
actually gave kind of an interesting
result
which you'd be unlikely to get just
playing around with the data.
Uh, next slide, please. Okay, so um,
we've got 20 minutes left, so let's use
the last 20 minutes to talk about
reinforcement learning, which has been a
subject of quite a lot of my work over
the last little while. Uh, next slide,
please. So, what is reinforcement
learning? is concerned with finding a
strategy for taking a series of
decisions rather than just one.
So you're you're in some sort of an
environment is changing in an
unpredictable way and you have to decide
well you've had to decide what decision
you're going to take today. But you know
you're going to have to take another
decision tomorrow and another the next
day. you know, you're going to be taking
a series of decisions, not a single one.
And uh
this has actually been a hugely
successful. It's a it's kind of like a
trial and error kind of approach to
this, but it's been hugely successful.
I'm sure many of you have heard of um
the success
that software has had in playing games
like chess and go
that actually we've developed software
that can be the best human players of
chess and go. I used to play a lot of
chess when I was younger and uh in a way
it's disappointing but
you know computers can now do this so
much better than human beings.
Uh next slide please. So the general
model is
you have actions,
states and rewards.
So you take an action
um
you start with a certain state which I
call S0. You take a certain action time
zero
and that moves you to a new state and
maybe you get a reward. Then you take
another action
which will move you to yet another state
perhaps give you a reward and so on.
So you got to look ahead and think of
all the actions you're going to have to
take not just at time zero but at future
times
and the states at future times are
somewhat uncertain.
Uh next slide please.
So one of the fundamental I mean this is
really a trial and error sort of process
but um
if you and obviously you you don't you
don't know anything when you start. So
you're going to sort of be choosing some
sort of a random strategy and and then
slowly over time you learn that you know
doing this in this situation works out
well whereas doing something else in
that situation works out badly.
And this is where exploration versus
exploitation comes in. At any given
time, there's a certain probability that
you'll randomly choose a decision.
Okay? And that's referred to as
exploration. And there's a certain
probability that you'll assume you'll
choose the decisions that's actually
worked out best so far, which is called
exploitation.
So, initially the probability of
exploration is one because you don't
know it. So you're going to randomly
choose a decision
and then over time you'll slowly reduce
the probability of exploration
and increase the probability of
exploitation. And after a sufficient
number of trials,
you know, you'll probably decide that
actually
the probability of exploitation should
be one.
In other words, you've pretty much
decided
that you know you know what the best
decision is in all different situations.
Uh next slide please.
So I don't know whether any of you have
come across this game Nim
okay but uh it's a it's a very simple
game but uh it's a good game for
illustrating
uh how reinforcement learning works. So
suppose we got two two players
and you know so I'm playing against you
and there's a pile of matches on the
table
and we take turns.
Each each of us can pick up one, two or
three matches
and you lose the game if you have to
pick up the last match. Okay. So part of
matches
take turns picking up one, two, or three
matches and the person who has to pick
up the last match loses.
Well,
if you are being good mathematicians,
you'd work out how to play this game
very quickly. Um,
basically, I mean, let's
suppose there are only five matches
on the table and it's your goal. There
are five matches on the table and it's
your go, I'm going to win because if you
pick up one match, I'll pick up three
matches and you have to pick up the last
match.
If you know if you pick up two matches,
I'll pick up two matches and you have to
pick up the last match and so on.
So if I can leave you with five matches
on the table, I win.
Then we can go one stage beyond that.
Let's suppose I can leave you with nine
matches
on the table.
then I can make sure I leave you with
five matches next time because you know
again there are nine matches on the
table.
You pick up one, I pick up three,
you're then left with five matches on
the table.
Okay? You pick up two, I pick up two,
you're left with five matches. And very
quickly you decide that
actually the way to win this game
is to always leave your opponent if you
can with four n + one matches. Okay.
So I mean you know
suppose uh n is five 4n + one is 21. So,
if I can leave you with 21 matches,
I will win
because I'll leave you with 21 matches,
then whatever you do next time round,
I'll leave you with 17 matches
and then the next time round I'll leave
you with 13 matches and so on. So,
okay.
However, let's see how well the machine
does at u
working out this best strategy. And I'm
going to assume there's only eight
matches initially on the table, although
you'll find on my on my website you can
find some uh software for
seeing how well the machine does in a
lot of other situations. But um
we'll assume that there's the reward is
plus one from winning and minus one from
losing and the your opponent behaves
randomly.
I can u
change things so the opponent learns as
well if I want to. But okay.
So basically we start with this state
action table.
Okay. State is the number of matches to
little left one to eight and the action
is the number picked up. Next slide
please.
So basically as I say it's trial and
error.
So let's suppose I mean you don't know
anything. So randomly you choose to pick
up one match. Randomly your opponent
picks up three matches. Randomly you
choose to pick up one match. Randomly
your opponent picks up three matches,
you win.
Okay, so
we can update Q81.
8 being the number of matches on the
table and the one being the number
picked up. So the first argument is the
number of matches on the table. The
second is the number picked up. So we
know from that that
we have a trial where
we win
Q81 leads to a win and Q41 leads to a
win.
So we update
Q81 and Q41.
Okay.
And we have to have a par an updating
parameter. the formula formula for
updating is
is is there and we say well okay we
don't want to update too much
we'll give it 5% weight
so we have the old Q
SA plus 5% of the gain minus the old QSA
and
can we have the next slide
On each trial, we observe certain
states, take action in those states, and
the gain used in updating the cues can
be either the final reward
referred to as the Monte Carlo method,
or it can be the value at the next
state, assuming the best decision is
taken. So, you know, if I pick up
You know if I pick up one match and you
pick up one match then the value and
there are six matches on the table and
in terms of updating instead of waiting
to see whether I win or lose I could
just say how good is it for me if there
are just six matches left on the table
and that would be you know the way we
would do the updating. So we start with
the Q's all zero and then we update them
in the way that I was describing.
Um, next slide please.
And uh, with the Monte Carlo method,
which is where we wait and see whether
we win or not, you can see I mean we all
know that
with eight matches on the table, if it's
our go, we pick up three and leave our
opponent with five matches on the table.
That's the best decision. After a
thousand trials,
it hasn't really found the best
decision. It still looks as though
picking up one match is marginally
better. The Q value is 0.562
as opposed to 522.
After 5,000 trials, it's definitely
beginning to look that it's best to pick
up three matches and after 10,000 trials
for sure.
So, you see what's happening here. We're
just doing more and more trials.
And uh what
what we did here was we had this epsilon
parameter which is determines you know
whether you behave randomly or you use
the best
decision that seems to have worked out
so far. We have epsilon starting at one
and having this decay factor of.9995.
So it it it does appear that uh
reinforcement learning finds the best
decision. Uh next slide please.
And if in fact it finds it even more
quickly with temporal difference
learning. This is where you look to see
you know how much is it how much does it
turn out to be worth to be in the next
situation that you're in after you've
taken the first decision. And it turns
out that as often is the case, temporal
difference learning works better than
the raw Monte Carlo simulation.
But it's definitely,
you know, worked out that uh you know,
it's best it's best to pick up uh three
matches.
It's not and it doesn't look so bad to
pick up two matches or one match because
remember your opponent's behaving
randomly.
So you and when you've learned a lot,
you can behave much better than your
opponent. I've done I've done other
tests where the opponent is learning as
well, in which case you
you know picking up two matches or one
match is going to allow your opponent to
win. Um and so you have you know
negative numbers opposite the two and
the one.
Uh next
slide please.
So
so this is you know this this NIM
game illustrates
admittedly in a fairly simple situation
how reinforcement learning works. Um,
very often you've got a much more
complex
um,
state action table to be sort of filled
in. And uh,
you have to sort of combine
uh, reinforcement learning with
artificial neural networks because you
got this state action table. You're able
to fill in some of the
some of the numbers in the state action
table but not all of them. But you you
know there's some nonlinear general
nonlinear function which is describing
the whole table and you have to do the
best you can with the numbers that you
do have in the table.
Uh next slide please.
Okay so five minutes left. Um what I've
been spending a lot of my time in the
last uh little while on is saying you
know can we use reinforcement learning
for hedging derivatives.
The traditional approach to hedging is
of course Greek letters where you know
you calculate delta, gamma, vega and so
on and you're really you're really
looking a very short period of time
ahead because you're saying
what's the uh partial derivative of the
value of my portfolio with respect to
whatever it is the underlying asset
price
volatility or whatever.
um
reinforcement learning sort of has has a
different approach. It says let's take
let's look several periods ahead and try
and take a decision which will work well
over our over our time horizon. So what
have we found?
Um next slide.
This is my last slide. Um, so what we
found is that, you know, we've found
that, you know, in some situations using
reinforcement learning for hedging, in
other words, looking several periods
ahead and seeing which strategies will
work out best is um
can be useful for vanilla options.
It um
it does about the overall it does about
the same as the Greek letter hedging
but it does save transaction costs
and actually saves significant amounts
of transaction costs because you can
think about it this way you know you're
hedging a vanilla option
I mean let's just talk in terms of delta
I mean you know let's suppose delta is
0.5 right now
and delta goes up to 7
but maybe there's a 50% chance that at
your next hedging date delta will go
back down to 0.5. So the question is
should you
should you uh change
you know should you do your hedging
to reflect delta going from 0.5 to 7
even though you know there's a 50%
chance it'll go back down to 0.5 or is
it better to wait
and see what happens over perhaps two
time periods
and the answer is if there's a lot of
transaction costs
it's better to wait. So we find
reinforcement learning can save quite a
lot of transaction costs even though we
when you don't take account of
transaction costs there's not a huge
saving for for options typically
okay and of course transaction costs are
really important when it comes to vega
and gamma hedging as well
as some exotic options such as barrier
options we find reinforcement learning
produces superior results even when
there are no transaction costs.
And one of the nice things about using
reinforcement learning is that you can
choose your objective function.
Okay? Whereas of course you can't do
that with Greek letter hedging. So
um
you know we've experimented with you
know looking at the tail of the
distribution and var 95 is a shortand
for you want the 95th percentile point
of the loss distribution
to be as high as possible
or C bar 95 is where you want the
conditional value of risk which is the
average beyond on the 95th percentile
of the loss distribution to be as low as
possible.
So, you know, you can have an objective
function that focuses
on the um
things you're most concerned about,
which is the perhaps the tail of the
distribution. We find it's robust, gives
good results during stress periods. And
it's interesting JP Morgan
is you know our main comp competitor in
terms of doing this research is JP
Morgan. JP Morgan's been doing a lot of
um work looking at reinforcement
learning for hedging.
Of course the disadvantage
of reinforcement learning is that it's
much more computationally demanding
than traditional approaches. you
you've got to run these trial and error
programs which you know can take a few
minutes
but they're getting faster.
So whereas it it takes no time at all to
calculate a brief letter. It it will
take you a little while to calculate the
best strategy
for doing reinforcement learning
hedging.
But I think come back to my earlier
point that computers are now
sufficiently fast that um
you know that that it's becoming a
feasible tool.
So uh brings me to my last slide.
Um we're one minute over the four
o'clock mark, but if anybody wants to
ask any questions, I'd be happy to to
answer them. Well, I have a question for
you uh John. Um about the choice of
activation functions
um you know have you found as you did in
this case that I guess it was was it the
sigmoid function was uh was applied in
your example
or was it the reu?
Yeah, we've we've had a lot of success
with the sigmoid function. Um that may
be just chance chance events or maybe
there's something
um special about the sigmoid function,
you know. I mean, of course, there's
nothing to stop you trying
several different activation functions
and seeing which works out best in a
particular situation. Um
and we did that in uh
you know in our implied volatility
research and we concluded that the
sigmoid function works worked out best
as a matter of fact but we we tried
several different activation functions.
So,
but
>> I think I if I remember correctly, all
the activation functions we tried
were
pretty close to each other in terms of
how well they worked out.
>> So, I think choosing the activation
function may not be in many situations
anyway may not be a big deal.
What you also have to think is you know
how many
you know how big do you want the models
to be you know how many neurons
per step how many steps in total and
that sort of thing
I think that's typ typically what
happens
you you know you're going to benefit
from uh sort of building the neural
network with say two layers and then use
the results of that to add a third layer
or is the three layer neural network
just built independently?
>> That's a good question. As far as I
know, you've got to start from scratch
when you go from say two layers to three
layers. Uh you can't
you can't use what you've done with two
layers
as a shortcut to doing three layers.
I may be wrong there, but I don't think
the same way.
>> Right.
>> Actually, for the class's benefit, um I
checked your references um and uh on
your uh Toronto
uh website, you actually have material
like uh the Python code for various
examples in your book. So, I think
students might find that very accessible
and useful.
Yeah. Yeah. There's very I should have
mentioned this. Yeah. There's a lot on
my website, you know, I think
lots of uh lots of different things
we've done at different times on um
you know, on this sort of machine
learning research.
So, if you want to if you want to read
more about it, um certainly my website
would be a good place to go. Um how do
you uh choose the objective functions in
your examples?
Was there um
is some issues involved with choosing
those specifically
>> and what and what was and what was the
difference between them?
Uh yeah, I think
I think every situation is different as
far as that's concerned and you've got
to
you've got to think,
you know, what what objective function
fits in with
with what I'm trying to do um
in in in the particular situation that
you're working on. Okay. I mean, if
you're
I mean, if you're if you got some exotic
option and you're trying to match the
price as closely as possible,
then obviously it's the difference
between
the price you're trying to match
and the price given by the neural
network
is going to be most,
you know, there going to be an objective
that you're trying to minimize.