and thank you all for being here today
to attend this uh talk uh today's primer
is going to be about large language
models and biological Foundation models
I'm going to give some background ideas
about these models and then how they can
be applied to biological
data so 2024 is a very exciting time to
be in AI research uh every day now there
are more and more advanced AI models and
applications and algorithms being
released uh the ones on the slide here
that I've listed are just a sample of
what I've been seeing on my computer
shared around Twitter uh in the past one
or two years um in the past just one or
two years we have had Advanced image
generation models biological models and
very Advanced AI models um generative AI
models coming out of large companies and
the general sense right now is that with
these Advanced AI systems we are now
closer than ever to building General uh
intelligent AI systems and a large
reason behind these recent developments
in AI has been Recent research in large
language models in today's primer I want
to give some more details about the
training architecture and capabilities
of these large language models and then
how these models and other Foundation
models are being applied to biological
data so I'll begin with the question
generally what are large language models
a large language model is a very large
deep learning model that is trained on
text from the internet so imagine all of
the information that you see on the
internet the social media sites user
posts documents uh news articles and all
other human generated information this
is the data that is scraped from the
internet and formed into textual data
sets and this is the base of knowledge
for these very large uh models on the
slide here I have a recent timeline in
the past two or three years of major
large language model releases by large
AI companies this is a very short list
just from some uh top AI companies but
this is a very crowded field so there's
many more llms
available so what can large language
models do now that there are more of
them available than ever before today's
large language models are able to give
accurate and structured responses to a
very wide range of user queries on the
left hand side here we can see that in
response to my query about how can I
improve my programming skills CH GPT
very quickly uh generates a list that is
detailed and structured uh giving a
couple of steps and a couple of um tips
that I can follow in order to improve my
programming skills this generative
ability of these large language models
makes them very useful for tasks like
writing and planning and summarizing
things and it's amazing when you think
that it only took chat gbt a couple of
seconds to generate this response which
is even cut off here and it would have
taken a human like me at least a couple
of minutes to generate this same kind of
response so with this Advanced
generation capability what can we do
with large language models in recent
years there's been a growing ecosystem
of applications based on large language
models and other generative AI systems
now you can find AI companies offering
services for writing assistance coding
assistance um and other content creation
tools uh a favorite one which came out
recently of M is uh Google's notebook LM
it actually lets you generate podcast
audio given a couple of sources that you
upload so we're still in an exploratory
phase of the best uh interactions and
applications for these AI
systems okay so to begin digging deeper
into large language models we need to
understand the background architecture
behind them which is the Transformer
dating all the way back to 2017
which seems like ages ago at this point
um the Transformer is an architecture
that is based almost entirely around two
kinds of operations that is multi-head
attention and then feed forward dense
layers they are colored as orange and
blue on here attention is a mechanism
that highlights interactions between
different parts of your input and then
feed forward layers are standard neuron
Network layers that add more trainable
capacity to the architecture we can see
here that this Transformer uh decoder
architecture it consists of n blocks
each block containing a tension layer
and a feed forward layer and we stack
these blocks one on top of another to
form a very deep uh
Network now aside from attention and
feed forward layers there's only a
couple of other operations happening
inside of this Transformer there are
normalization layers in yellow which
happen after each operation there are
skip connections which go around each of
these operations these skip connections
help gradients back propagate back
through the network during training this
helps us train these very deep networks
uh stably and then the last thing is
positional encoding positional encoding
is added to the input of the Transformer
and it helps tell the Transformer what
order the input information
came so over the next couple of slides
I'll dive into a couple parts of the
architecture which deserve a bit more
detail uh starting with the input
so we are modeling language with these
models which means that we need to
define a process for turning a raw input
text into a list of numerical vectors
which our model will be able to process
the way that this is typically done with
large language models is called text
tokenization in tokenization we are
going to break apart raw input text into
smaller word pieces which are colored
here these word pieces need to be small
word pieces that the large language
model will recognize and that they can
represent
numerically so every large language
model has an Associated dictionary this
dictionary is around 50,000 to
250,000 word pieces which the large
language model understands and the llm
will learn an embedding table which has
a vector corresponding to each word
piece so if I ask for the word in that
is corresponding to the
818th word embedding in the lln
dictionary so all we need to do is when
we receive input text we need to break
apart this text into word pieces and
these word pieces just need to be inside
of the dictionary and the llm will be
able to represent it now at minimum this
dictionary is going to include uh at
least letters numbers and special
characters so the at least what we can
do is break apart the text into
characters and we will be able to encod
it but um we can do better than that
because the tokens uh will also include
words and so we'll be able to use less
tokens to represent the entire
sentence a typical algorithm that llms
use uh to come up with this dictionary
is called bite pair and coding bite
paent coding is where we look at our raw
text we look at which words and
characters frequently occur next to each
other and then we're just going to
iteratively merge frequently incurring
uh pairs
when we merge a pair that is added to
our dictionary and when we do enough
merges we get up to our 50,000 uh
dictionary okay so now we know about the
input to our large language model now
let's look at the output what comes out
of the llm when we put a sequence of
text into the large language model like
on the bottom
left these this list of vectors is going
to go through our n layer Transformer
and then the last linear layer and soft
Max are going to take the last token of
our input sequence and they're going to
Output a probability distribution this
probability distribution is over the
dictionary or the vocabulary of the
large language model and we're actually
predicting here what is the probability
um that any one dictionary entry is the
next token in the sequence so we're
doing self-supervised learning we know
from the data itself what the next word
is and we're going to have the llm
predict what the next word should be
given the input
sentence um this is called Next token
prediction and we usually optimize this
through cross entropy
loss the last thing that I want to
highlight about the Transformer
architecture is something called causal
attention masking this is a detail about
the attention operation that's happening
inside of the
Transformer so we see on the left hand
side here I mentioned earlier that
attention is an operation that
highlights interactions between parts of
your input if we look at these words
here large language models predict the
the first three words actually refer to
the same object llms and so in a perfect
world we would hope that these three
that the llm would know that these three
words mean the same object they they
should interact more with each other
compared to the rest of the words in the
sentence so this is an example attention
Matrix which we would expect where the
first three words are interacting highly
with each other when we look at
interactions in this sort of uh Matrix
format we call it an attention Matrix
and each of the scores in the Matrix is
an attention coefficient telling us
interaction between tokens now when we
do causal attention what's happening is
that we are creating a mask which is a
lower triangular Matrix and we are
zeroing out the top half of this
attention Matrix the reason why we do
this is because our
language modeling objective is next
token prediction we are predicting the
future and if we want to do this over
the whole sequence we don't want a token
to be able to look at the future
otherwise it would know what token comes
next in order to make it a meaningful
objective we need to hide the future
from each token and we do that by not
allowing any one token in the rows to
look at the
future the really cool thing is that
when we do this causal attention masking
we can actually apply our language
modeling objectives to the entire
sequence so the first three words
predict the fourth the first four
predict the fifth but this is all
happening on one forward pass and so
you're getting multiple subsequences of
training examples by doing one forward
pass this actually makes the trans the
training of these Transformer decoders
very efficient which is
nice now that we've gone through some of
the details about the architecture I'm
going to spend the next couple of slides
talking about how these llms are trained
at a large scale there's a lot of stuff
happening on this um on this figure but
I'm going to go through it part by part
there are four main stages of training
large language models there's
pre-training supervised fine-tuning
there's reward modeling where we start
to uh model human preferences and then
there's reinforcement learning where
we're going to tune the llm and align it
to human preferences each of these four
training stages has an Associated data
set which we collect and train on it has
a modeling objective an algorithm that
we train with and then there's a
resulting model which will help
initialize the further training stages
I'll start with
pre-training the pre-training stage uh
is the stage of training which takes the
majority of the compute and time in
large language model development in
pre-training we are our data set is the
raw um the web scrape of the raw
internet so we're the scale which we're
talking about here is trillions of
tokens and words gathered from the
internet so it's a very large data set
uh High quantity low quality because we
cannot F we can only filter the internet
so much we're doing our language
modeling objective next token prediction
over the internet and on the slide here
I have an example of the Text corpus
which was used to train
gpt3 um common crawl is the web scraped
data set which they use we can see here
though that open AI actually included a
couple of other sources of textual data
the intuition here is that you want to
have a large amount of training data but
including some higher quality sources of
information like Wikipedia articles or
some textbook data sets those are higher
quality textual data than random Json
queries which you might find on the
internet so some companies will actually
upwe these smaller but higher quality
sources of textual data during
pre-training now the scale of
pre-training is massive we have a very
large data set and we need thousands of
gpus over several months of training to
actually train in this phase so only
like large AI companies with a lot of
backing can kind of attempt to this uh
stage of
training yeah do you know what the
source of Comm and crawl is is it the
internet yes it's the internet I believe
there's a company which performed common
crawl and they keep adding more textual
data sets so it's an open- Source data
set like I think we could download it
wouldn't that already include
Wikipedia it would but if they want to
specifically process Wikipedia filter it
a bit more and upway it's um like how
prevalent it is in the data set they
might have it separately yeah okay but
um it brings up a good point that common
crawl will include a lot of data sets
that are on the internet so like things
like you know test set contamination and
data leakage is a big problem with LMS
because it sees so much on the internet
okay in the next stage which is
supervised fine-tuning our data set is
going to become uh lower quantity but
higher quality we're going to shift from
training on the entire internet and
we're actually going to um if I'm a
company I will hire a group of labelers
I'll give them a set of prompts and I'll
have those um labelers generate ideal
responses to these prompts we want to
supervise fine-tune this llm to start
being better at answering questions the
base model it's um it's like a
autocomplete engine that's good at
completing text but it's not good at
conversation it now in supervised fine
tuning we are going to actually train it
with the same language modeling
objective to um give better responses to
input prompts this stage takes a couple
of hundreds of gpus and a few days of
training so this is sort of um a smaller
fine-tuning stage and the result model
is called the supervised fine tune model
sft this model is Deployable and if you
ask it questions it will give you some
good responses because we're tuning it
to be conversational now but it's not
the best performing kind of large
language models the best llm models are
the ones that have gone through
reinforcement learning which is the next
two stages of
training moving on to reinforcement
learning this the next two stages is
where we're going to align llns to
generate more human preferred responses
now that's a very tall task like how do
we model what responses humans are going
to like um what we're going to do is in
the reward modeling stage which is the
third stage we're going to shift our
data set collection Focus from
generating ideal responses to actually
ranking existing responses we will have
our llm generate a lot of example
completions or responses to prompts and
we're actually going to start collect in
ranking information if you used Chad GPT
before you might have actually done this
where it gives you two or three
completions and you select the best one
whichever one you prefer when you do
that you're actually providing future
training data for them to train future
reward models what we're going to do is
out of let's say 10 responses to a given
prompt uh they will have professional
labelers rank them in order of
preference so we're Gathering ranking
data which is a a ground Truth For What
kind of responses do humans prefer more
maybe one describes the data better
maybe one had the code commented more
nicely and so
on and what we're going to do in this
reward modeling stage is we are going to
train a reward model this reward model
can be a smaller language model with the
same architecture or it could be another
system all it the only constraint is
that the reward model needs to Output a
score a reward for how much humans are
going to like this
response the way that we train this is
if we will'll assemble an input prompt
into our reward model we're going to lay
out the same prompt and we're going to
put different responses these candidate
responses uh after it we will append a
reward token at the end of the input and
what the reward model is going to do is
it's going to take that reward token and
its job is to predict a scaler value a
score a reward for that response for how
good it is and our loss function is
actually just binary cross entropy for
the preferred response reward minus the
dispreferred response reward we're
actually just maximizing the difference
in score between a good and a bad
response the really cool thing about
this process is that we're basically
training this reward model to give
scores for responses but we're training
it to tell which responses humans are
going to like more when we have a reward
model that can actually model human
prefer references then you can optimize
your llm against it to then get more
human preferred outputs so this this
reward model is really telling um is
really modeling human preferences in
this
pipeline okay now the fourth stage is
reinforcement learning from Human
feedback you might have heard this as
rlf what we're going to do is we're
going to use a reinforcement learning
algorithm to Now update the weights of
our llm and we're going to intuitively
try to get the llm to generate responses
that humans like more this is where the
llm start to be very good at generating
good
responses now in reinforcement learning
usually the terminology we use is we're
trying to optimize a policy to maximize
some sort of reward the reward model we
have because we had trained our reward
model in the previous step and the
policy is actually just our large
language model that's generating text so
the action we're taking is generating
text the space of all generation is
actually just the llm vocabulary that's
our possible actions we can take and all
we're going to do is we are going to uh
train our llm to generate better
responses according to the reward model
now specifically what's happening is
that we are using a reinforcement
learning algorithm typically this is
proximal policy optimization this PO
algorithm is going to update the weights
of our large language model and it's
going to try and boost the
probabilities of next token prediction
of generating good responses so the
first prompt and response here in the
top row it was assigned a reward of 1.1
this is pretty high relative to the rest
of the batch since this reward is high
Poo is going to update the weights so
that the First Response the
probabilities of generating that
response are increased and it'll downway
the other responses that have less
reward so we're literally training the
llm to boost the probabilities of
generating human preferred responses
according to the reward model from the
previous
stud so the last two stages with reward
modeling reinforcement learning were a
little bit more complicated than the
first two steps and so we have a
question on why do we do this
reinforcement learning now in practice
what papers have found is that
reinforcement learning model models they
tend to generate better responses
they're more aligned to the kind of
responses that humans like the figure on
the right hand side is from an open AI
paper in 2022 and they basically showed
that the top two models in yellow and
red uh generate more preferred outputs
compared to supervised fun model in
green and that one in turn is better
than the base model so in practice this
seems to work better and an analogy
which I kind of like to think about here
is that when we're doing pre-training
and supervised f tuning it's sort of
like a student studying from textbooks
you're learning by looking and trying to
study textbooks when you switch to
reinforcement learning that is like when
you go to a teacher and they're grading
your essay or they're giving you
feedback you're getting some
discriminative input from a teacher
that's helping you improve your output
you're modeling to their preferences so
that's sort of like an analogy for
reinforcement learning another sort of
way to think about this is that if
you're trying to generate data yourself
for these stages of llm training
sometimes it's easier to rank between
different responses to generate ranking
data rather than trying to generate
perfect ideal responses to train the llm
so the data collection may be a little
bit easier with um ranking
data okay now that we've gone through
some ideas for uh developing large
language models I'm going to spend the
next couple of slides going through some
ideas for for how llms how do we make
llms uh generate better outputs how do
we make them more efficient more
useful the first major idea I want to
talk about is scaling laws for large
language models this is a big idea we've
developed this large framework for a
training and developing large langage
models now how does this scale how does
performance improve as we throw more
data and compute at it what this study
found is that if you look at the
performance of large language models
which is cross entropy loss on the y-
axis here and you put either compute
data set size or the number of model
parameters on the x-axis as you increase
these things there's actually a very
predictable increase in the performance
of large language models the really
significant thing that they found was
that you can actually fit equations and
really predict how the performance is
going to improve if you train with more
compute or if you give it more data now
some of the general takeaways that they
found was that the relationship between
performance and compute was a power law
as they did more training runs with more
and more um higher capacity models the
loss was uh increasing along this sort
of power law curve and then the other
thing which they found is that there's a
relationship between the amount of data
that you train on and then the number of
parameters of the model basically when
you increase your data set size by a
certain amount you should also increase
the number of parameters you're training
with so that your performance is not
bottlenecked by data or model
capacity the next really big idea is
about Chain of Thought reasoning steps
so these large language models they have
very strong generation capabilities but
if we think for a moment about how
humans how we generate output when I am
sort of generating output either speech
or written text I'm at the same time as
I'm generating I'm also reasoning about
what I've just said or written I can
backtrack I can go back and correct
myself or I can think about what I've
said and so I can have some sort of
intermediate reasoning process but if
we're just giving large language models
input and output like responses it
doesn't get the chance to do that
reasoning process so the idea about
chain of thoughts is we ask the llms or
we encourage them to generate
intermediate outputs this is especially
apparent on mathematical questions where
if we ask the model some math questions
the performance
uh steadily improves if we have the
model output some intermediate
mathematical steps before generating its
final response this was shown pretty
robustly on mathematical and reasoning
data
sets now this first paper which
generated intermediate reasoning steps
was called chain of thoughts this is not
the only way to do chain of thoughts or
re intermediate reasoning processes um
on the right hand side is just a
intuition for we can actually generate
multiple chains
of reasoning processes and we can
backtrack and have the llm go through
different reasoning paths and pick the
best one so this is sort of forms a tree
of thoughts which was another idea
recently and this performs better than
just um no intermediate reasoning
steps is is Tri of f basically what
theyve released with o1 or is that
something else yes it is it is okay so
uh very recently open AI came out with
the 01 models and we don't know the
exact details about how they are
implementing chain of thoughts they you
know keep it within their team but they
are doing some sort of intermediate
reasoning steps and that's why if you
ask 01 a question like I did here how
many houses can we build on Mars it's
there are some intermediate steps that
are very helpful to know what's the
surface area of Mars how many you know
how much space does a usual house take
up and this 01 model it'll spend like
you know 20 30 seconds thinking about it
and you actually have the option to
expand some of the intermediate steps
that 01 thought about before it gave you
the final answer so it was calculating a
couple of these things so oh so we don't
know how the tree of thought works but
for the Chain of Thought like the
earlier version of this idea are they
basically is like part of the model
basically breaking down the prompts into
other prompts sorry other questions and
then generating results for that or do
you know how that works yes so in some
problems like mathematical questions
like for some data sets we do have the
intermediate States and we can really
train the llm that the intermediate stat
should be this and we can train it using
our language modeling objective um we
don't know too much about how like the
01 models do it but we do know that they
use reinforcement learning to do that so
they either do some sort of reward
modeling or reinforcement learning on
example outputs where humans either
humans or well that we've generated the
intermediate reasoning steps to
encourage the model to put out
intermediate reasoning steps before it
generates the final answer so they
likely gathered some data where they put
out a lot of intermediate reasoning
steps and trained it using reinforcement
learning for
that okay some other major
ideas
oh I had a question about um there was
like a recent study where they were
taking these um kind of math questions
and then they showed that if you change
the names of the people in in the
question or you just change the actual
numbers that accuracy just starts to
drop somewhere between a little and a
lot so could you comment on if you're
familiar with that if you could comment
on that or what do you think would be
like the analogous issue that we would
have when translating these to um
biological sequence data type things as
well like where are What are the similar
brittleness that you would expect given
that type of behavior thank you wow
that's a that's a very good question um
if the performance of a large language
model dropped very significantly when
you just swap the name or swap out the
numbers then it might be an indication
if it dropped if the drop was very
drastic it might be an indication the
llm saw that data set before on the
Internet it's recalling rather than
generalizing to the reasoning steps and
so maybe when you throw it out of what
it's already seen on the internet then
it sort of collapses although if the
performance is like not too drastic of a
drop then maybe it's just like um maybe
if you gave the llm more generation
tries it will still do okay on the data
set the analogous problem in biology I
think it might be where the large
language model has seen a lot of
biological Concepts on the internet
maybe it saw certain molecules or drug
names very commonly represented in
online databases when you ask it
questions or you try to do Downstream
tasks with those familiar molecules or
biological compounds it might do very
good and then when you start to use very
rare data or something that's not seen
commonly on the internet then the llm
might be thrown out of what it's
familiar with and then it might see a
similar drop in performance then you
might need more data on that rare kind
of um biological like a sample to make
up for
that
okay so another major idea in large
language models is really important is
long context modeling so we saw before
that we are putting in a sequence of
texts into our large language model and
we are embedding it into some word
vectors now we add positional encoding
to this um to these words and that tells
us the length of our input large
language models have a maximum length a
maximum number of word pieces that they
can accept as input and that's called
the context length this context length
is one of the really big limitations of
large language models because the longer
your context L the more information you
can put into the input prompt you can
imagine if you're doing medical question
answering it helps a lot if you put
relevant medical or biological text in
the context before you ask the llm the
question it helps it generalized um and
give a good answer but if you do not
have enough context length you cannot do
that so llms are limited by their
context length there's quite a lot of
work on how do we extend this context
length and let llms take more things as
input now there are too many um there's
too much research in the idea in the
long context modeling field to go over
but I'll just go over one idea for some
intuition here let's say that we are
doing positional encoding using a
popular positional encoding method maybe
rotational positional encoding or Rope
Rope does positional encoding by
rotating vectors if two word pieces are
very far apart then they will be rotated
far apart it's a continuous rotation
that's applied to the input vectors this
is one way of doing relative positional
encoding now if we trained our large
language model to have a sequence input
length of 4,000 and then at inference we
have some unseen range going up to 8,000
what we can do and what some people have
shown is that you can actually
interpolate and kind of squeeze your
input uh sequence to fit within the
normal range of positional encoding you
can interpolate your rotations and just
uh put more points in between and
because these rotations are continuous
the llm is actually still able to
discern what tokens are in what order
this works for certain positional
encoding methods like rotational
positional encoding um and so this is
one way people have sort of um gone
around this issue there are other
methods like compressive methods but in
general we're trying to find ways that
the llm is able to um accurately
represent what order tokens came in when
it receives longer
cont is the rotation position L coding
something people work Ed for natural
language yes um do you have any
intuition for why
rotational
uh modeling might be helpful here yeah
so with positional encoding what you're
really trying to do is you're trying to
tell the llm somehow how far apart
different vectors are so that when you
do a tension if there's two similar
words right next to each other they're
they have very high interaction score
but if they're very far apart they may
be in completely different documents you
don't want them to attend highly to each
other so a good positional encoding
method should change or should do
something to the vectors so that the
very far apart words don't attend very
highly to each other when you rotate the
input word embedding vectors if you
rotate them far enough in that attention
Matrix they won't be as similar because
you're literally moving them farther
apart in in this rotation space so by
applying rotation matrices so that's
sort of how for the far apart vectors
when they rotated far apart um the
attention score will not be as high if
you're able to change the attention
scores to reflect distance then you'll
the llm will understand these vectors
are far
apart do sorry do these Transformations
work for like biological sequence models
cuz like I like if you have a protein
sequence or a DNA sequence your distance
is a literal molecular distance and if
you're squeezing it in half you're like
doing something physically so have
people tried these on those domains and
do they seem to work that's that's a
really good question if you're modeling
textual biological data then most of
this will still work because you're
modeling language when you start to
model like numerical or other kinds of
biological data I'll like show a few
examples in some further slides um
what you need to do is you need to uh
change your architecture and maybe your
positional coding strategy to reflect
your biological data so some things that
people have tried is that rather than
doing like this language positional
encoding you might if you're working
with genomics data for example you might
add a positional encoding um Vector that
tells the model What gene this is or
what position on the chromosome are you
want if you can devide some sort of um
system for just telling the model how
far things are apart in chromosome space
or like you know what Gene is it as long
as you can identify it to the model then
it can learn on it thank
you okay in the spirit of um efficiency
because now we're getting longer and
longer sequence lens we need to worry
about how does the attention mechanism
itself uh scale the attention mechanism
which we've been talking about has
quadratic complexity and we can see that
when you have an input sequence it's
creating a n byn Matrix for the
attention so this has quadratic
complexity which scales very poorly when
we get to very large models very long
sequence Lens two main ideas which uh
people have tried to improve this
complexity problem is to improve
efficiency with GPU optimization and
then improve the scalability with GPU
optimization what we're really trying to
do is we're trying to utilize our gpus
more efficiently so we're trying to
manage how do we read and write data
from the GPU memory back to the CPU or
back to this um in order to speed up
computations we want to be more
efficient with these Matrix
multiplications so that things happen
faster on the GPU so that there's no
bottlenecks uh flash attention on the
left-and side is an example of this it's
a industry standard by now people use
Flash attention to make the GPU
optimization a bit more efficient on the
right hand side the idea of sub
quadratic attention this is another
subfield where where there's a lot of
research going on the idea is to
approximate this quadratic attention
with other with approximation algorithms
that are sub quadratic we still want to
calculate attention coefficients it's
very useful to highlight interactions
between parts of your input but we don't
want something that has quadratic
complexity because computer scientist in
computer science fighting quadratic
complexity is a losing battle so we try
to get sub quadratic methods and by now
like um the example on the right hand
side is former attention this is a
linear attention method which changes
the Matrix multiplications to calculate
attention in linear
time okay moving on with our theme about
efficiency there are some methods for
doing parameter efficient fine-tuning
the idea here is that when you have a
downstream application maybe you have a
specific biological task or maybe you
have a specific data set which you're
interested in you want to fine-tune the
lln to do this Downstream task however
usually fine tune all of the weights of
the llm for every Downstream task you
want to do is not very efficient and
it's not very feasible because there's
billions of parameters so the idea here
is to tune only a fraction of your llm
weights or your Downstream tasks now
what fraction of weights do you uh tune
and where do you put them is something
that different parameter efficient
methods try to deal with uh the one I
have here Laura is also is a very
popular method that came up in recent
years the idea with Laura is basically
to freeze the pre-trained weight Matrix
in blue here we freeze that and instead
of training all of those weights we're
going to train a smaller subset of
Weights in Orange we're going to project
the data down into a lower Dimension or
a lower Rank and then we'll project it
back up these two matrices they take up
less parameters than the original
weights and we're basically fine-tuning
the llm in a lower rank space this uh
decreases the amount of parameters we
need to tune and in practice it's
performs decently well
um okay and the final thing about
efficiency which I want to mention here
is about quantization so usually large
language models are trained with 32-bit
or 16bit Precision this means that every
single weight in the large language
model is represented using 32 or 16 bits
but what people have shown is that if
you can actually get away with
representing the weights with less bits
if you can go down to 168 or four this
actually lets you use up less GPU memory
it also speeds up your computations and
so people have done studies where they
take different weights three different
weights on the bottom here um in the
subplots and then they try to represent
these weight matrices using less and
less bits starting with 16 bit 8 bit
four bit and what they basically show is
that the performance on this natural
language understanding test on the
y-axis it does not suffer too much
performance degradation until you get
down to 4 32bit quantization so you can
get quite a lot of um efficiency gains
in terms of GPU memory um up until maybe
four bit quantization the cost of doing
this quantization is that you might lose
a little bit of
performance okay the last thing I want
to talk about with large language models
is about multimodal large language
models there's been a this is a very hot
topic of research recently
the general idea when we want to align
another modality of data it may be
images it may be some sort of biological
data or so
on at a high level what we need to do is
we need to one bring the other modality
of data into the space of the large
language model and then the other thing
we need to do is when the llm is
generating we need to provide a way for
it to generate the other modality of
data so input and output if we can do
this then we can give these llms the
ility to interact and input modalities
in other in other modalities other than
language which would be very
powerful there's been a lot of methods
for how do you bring the other modality
into language space the easiest thing
you can do is learn different
projections um which people have tried
um but at a high level we're just trying
to align the two modalities of
information using paired language and
other modality data um and we learn the
encoder and then potentially the
generator if you also want want to
Output the other modalities of
information me move on to the biology
side can I bring up two questions from
Zoom sure um someone's asking if you
could comment on um Good Luck long
context Window performance of the state
space models like Mamba and then there
is one clarification question uh asking
you Flora is similar to fine-tuning
models like with uh let's say imet uh
we can ask for more clarification yeah
okay um so for the first question Mambo
was a very interesting um uh model which
came out recently for modeling longrange
interaction so the Mamba architecture
it's based on stat spased models which
have a little bit more theory behind um
how do you how do you parameterize the
previous context in the models in order
to keep enough information in recurrent
architectures as you keep processing
more and more input um I'm not too like
I'm not deeply familiar with like the
theory behind State space models they do
seem to have very good capabilities for
modeling longrange interactions I think
they've been shown to do pretty good on
like book summarization tasks where
you're trying to summarize an entire
book that's put into context um but it
remains to be seen whether those
architectures will kind of um scale past
Transformers in terms of in terms of
scale and performance um these large
language models they do have an
advantage that they're very very good at
you're it's very easy to parallelize
their computations across gpus and so
companies have been able to really scale
up large language model training and so
it remains to be seen whether the state
spased models can be scaled up like that
and what was the second question asking
if Laura can be used for fine tuning the
way that um people fine-tune imag net
I'm not sure if the question is like
application to image net or do you mean
if they mean like just relating Laura
with fine tuning and uh image models in
general um that's a little unclear to me
too I don't know if they will comment
for more
clarification right in general um Lura
fine tuning is a very good way to
fine-tune uh llms in general and models
in general like um I don't think it can
be applied to other Transformers as well
so if you are fine-tuning on something
like imet it is a it is a valid option
um we're just fine-tuning a smaller
fraction of weights to kind of change
the activations inside of the model so
it is a good way to train even if you're
thinking about training multimodal llms
where you're freezing the original
language llm and then you're training
another modality encoder it is a very
good way to kind of um train a little
bit of parameters in the large language
model while you're learning the other
modality encoder the nice thing about
things like Laura specifically is that
it actually leaves the original llm
weights intact with some finetuning
methods you have the concern that you're
changing too many weights and shifting
away from the original weights which
were good at modeling language already
but with Laura you're actually phrasing
the original weights and you're just
learning some new adap adaptation
weights so you leave the original model
intact which is
good okay for the rest of this talk I
don't think I have too much time but I'm
going to talk about how these large
language models and other Foundation
models can be used for modeling
biological
dat so just like I mentioned on the
first slide right now is a very exciting
time to be in AI Arch there's just as
many biological Foundation models coming
out now on the very short list of them
is Alpha fold which was really recently
just um awarded a Nobel Prize which is
amazing so there's a lot of really
exciting biological Foundation models
also coming out and in general
biological Foundation models they also
train on a large amount of biological
and medical data um it may not always be
language it can be numerical data or
other kinds of data as well um and we
just want to build a base Foundation
model that can be adapted to diverse
Downstream
tasks now in terms of public biomedical
data that we have um available to us to
build these Foundation models there are
some common sources of data that people
use there's PubMed pumm Hub cem there's
the CDC guidelines archive has quite a
lot of quite a large range of papers as
well there are also some really nice
data sets generated here at the broad
Institute like the link X and the link
study and then GTE for single cell
expression data um for protein modeling
people usually look at protein databases
like unit Proto um and in general when
we're developing or we're fine-tuning
large language models and Foundation
models for biological applications
people usually Define some sort of data
mixture which they're interested in um I
think for Metatron which was an llm
released by epfl and meta uh they chose
to do PubMed um as well as some other
General textual data sets
so there's been a growing um there's
been a growing group of models that have
been trying to tune language models in
order to be better at biomedical
applications Metatron which I just
mentioned is a very good example of this
one this is sort of a graphic from their
paper about the development of bi
biology and biomedical focused llms um
since
2020 now the performance on this graph
is in terms of met question answering
data sets Med QA it's a good Benchmark
task for how well these language models
respond on medical questioning and it's
a data set which the performance has
been steadily increasing on in 2023 the
closed Source models like GPT 4 and palm
to from Google managed to get very high
scores on these data sets so over 80%
performance in medical question and
answering uh just last year in 2023 the
open source models mostly based on the
Llama llm architecture started to catch
up but in terms of like fine-tuning
these biological llms the open source
models still lag behind the industry
private models a little
bit I'm going to switch gears now and
get more into single cell RNA sequencing
data which our lab is interested in so
with single cell data um I'm sure we're
all familiar with the Single Cell
sequencing process where we disassociate
cells and then we sequence them to get
gene expression profiles at single cell
resolution the developments in single
cell uh sequencing technology in the
past decade have really increased the
throughput and the amount of data that
people are able to generate and in the
recent few years there's been large
scale data atlases generated such as
human cell Atlas and the cell by Gene by
The czi Institute these single cell
Atlas data is perfect for building
Foundation models it has a very large
diversity of uh expression information
from a lot of tissu
um for multiple species and the first
generation of single cell Foundation
models has been developed in the past
one or two years the first one of these
was
scpt now GPT is in the name so we know
that this is a llm inspired architecture
but they're actually not modeling
language here they're modeling gene
expression information so rather than a
sentence here the input sequence for
sgbt will be a list of gene expression
vectors we will encode gene expression
and then the genee identity into a token
and we'll train this scpt model to model
this expression information instead of
next token prediction we're going to do
Gene um Mass gene expression
prediction so GPT was trained on data
from the cell by Gene U public data
Atlas so it was around 33 million cells
from Mostly humans and mice and they
after pre-training they came up with
their Foundation model for modeling gene
expression data they applied their model
to a lot of Downstream tasks in single
cell analysis they did things like cell
type annotation batch integration and
perturbation response
prediction now around the same time
another Foundation model came out this
was Gene former developed by researchers
also from the broad Institute um this uh
was another Transformer based
architecture it also um modeled gene
expression profiles by modeling a list
of Gene um tokens however they differed
a little bit in the way that they
pre-processed and tokenized the gene
expression information they normalized
the data a bit differently and then they
did a rank encoding of the genes by
their expression information so this
sort of goes to show that multiple
Foundation models have been developed
however there is no consensus on the way
to tokenize and normalize this gene
expression data um to build these large
scale Foundation models that's still in
active area
research now in general when we're
trying to model single cell data at
scale there's a couple of big challenges
which we come up with um a lot of the
challenges in natural language have been
not completely figured out but they're
much more developed and matured um in
single cell data we're still dealing
with a couple of challenges the first
one is multimodality multimodality means
when we look at a single cell sequencing
study there is numerical information
from the gene expression values but
there's also a lot of multimodal
information associated with the study
that gives a lot of important
information about that data you have the
text from the manuscript and the
abstract itself you have cell type
annotations maybe disease labels and
then there's also prior knowledge about
biological Concepts on the internet
these might take the form of gen set
databases or they may be knowledge
graphs on the internet about single cell
Concepts so there's quite a lot of
sources of information which is hard for
one model to integrate by
itself some other challenges which are
more well established in single cell
sequencing data is the sparsity and
noise that's inherent in the sequencing
process and then also the batch effects
between
samples and then the last idea which
I'll kind of leave everyone with today
is about the benefit of pre-training on
text when we're thinking about language
models so when we're thinking about
building Foundation models should you
start from scratch and learn on your
data or should you try to initialize
from a pre-trained model like a language
model um in in natural language
processing it's been pretty well
established for many years now that
building a general model by pre-training
it on textual data and then fine-tuning
it for a specific application it works
better than creating narrow test
specific models the earliest example of
this I found was in 2020 with bioert
bioert took the strongest language model
at the time which was Bert it fine-tuned
it for some biological data sets and it
was able to outperform both Bert and the
state-of-the-art test specific models at
the time for their biological tasks so
this was in 2020 and the language models
have only gotten stronger since then so
it's um in natural language processing
it's pretty well established that
pre-training helps and some intuition
which I kind of hold for this is when we
pre-ra on natural language and when we
train on data from the internet there's
a very large amount of biological and
medical Concepts on the Internet or the
model to learn from on the right hand
side's a visualization of PubMed
literature just one data source on the
internet there is a lot of information
which the model can learn so can can I
just listen
to
sorry okay so there's a lot of general
concepts in information which the model
can learn from on the internet and
building representations about these
general concepts during pre-training
helps the model when it's trying to find
to an adapt for Downstream
tasks okay and with that thank you very
much for listening and I'm happy to take
any more
questions first of all thank you so much
for inviting us uh and uh giving us a
chance to talk about our
work um yeah so
uh my name is David Van djk and uh I run
a lab at Yale both in at the med school
and in computer
science and uh in our lab we build
algorithms to to decode the rules of
life we work with all kinds of large
biomedical data uh but we have a special
interest uh in single cell genomics and
that's what I'm going to talk about uh
today
primarily um yeah so single cell
analysis in the age of LM so sad just
gave an amazing prior uh primer on large
language models and biological
Foundation models and um so we all know
that llms are kind of revolutionizing
the way we interact with information um
and S presented a bit about biological
Foundation models applying these
Technologies the into
genomics um and today I'm going to talk
about several of our projects where we
kind of trying to attempt to do
this um specifically today I would like
to argue that biology has a language or
even multiple languages and we can use
algorithms we can use computation to
understand to decipher this language so
one very good example is the immune
system so uh as you know the immune
system uh is composed of many different
cell types many cells that are
interacting in complex ways and one way
in which cells communicate as you
probably know is using cyto or
chemokines so we can think of those in
some sense as words um but generally
they occur in concerts many different
cyto kindes Chemin together and together
these signals uh you can imagine form
sort of sentences through which cells
communicate with one another so you can
imagine that if we were to understand
this language that means we could listen
to cells we can even talk to them so the
ability to decipher decipher this
language is really important because it
allows us potentially to control the
system right imagine you can talk to
cells and tell them what to do or they
can tell you how they're feeling or
what's wrong right that would be the
dream um so the first project I want to
talk about today is an algorithm that we
developed cot is where we actually
attempt to learn this immune language
using a causal inference framework
um so let me start with a question so
imagine you encounter an on contacted
tribe uh so you're the first to to to
make contact and uh you don't know their
language they don't know your language
and you have to learn to communicate
with them how would you go about doing
this so perhaps first you would listen
right you would try to see kind of are
there any patterns in their in the way
they speak certain sounds um then
perhaps you would try to interact with
them you would make some simple gestures
or words or even simple phrases um you
would make guesses uh and and and
initially and then observe the outcome
and then from there you would improve
you kind of make a model and you would
adapt based on feedback and gradually
potentially you would allow would allow
you to
communicate um we we essentially apply
these same principles to biology so
biology has been on contacted if you
will for billions of years and only very
recently have we started to contact it
and started to talk with it and I would
say in very primitive ways
still um but we apply the same
principles to decoding for example cell
communication we listen we do
measurements right we collect data then
we talk to them we do perturbations we
stimulate the cells in different ways
and see how they react and then with
this feedback we develop models we try
to understand the language in the hope
to communicate with these cells and and
and understand what they're doing and
potentially to to manipulate them or I
mean manipulate sounds bad but to maybe
convince them to change in different
ways so um yeah so so I guess I'm
arguing that perturbing cells is like
talking to them or if you want to talk
to cells one way is to kind of perturb
them stimulate treat them um and this is
something that we do a lot uh especially
uh in an Institute like this uh where
you do large L scale experiments where
you do all kinds of drug genetic
perturbations all kinds of ways to
perturb to stimulate cells and see how
they react and then build your models
and try to learn this
language however there is a challenge
there is a problem because if we take
cells and we stimulate them and we try
to observe their
response and let's say you would want to
do this at the Single Cell level because
there's a lot of heterogenity and every
cell is different so you would want to
know exactly how an individual cell
reacts to a stimulation a drug or
genetic perturbation the problem is we
cannot really track individual cells
across perturbations because
fundamentally the measurement is
destructive the moment you measure a
cell at least you know fairly High
dimensional there's there's of course
you know life cell Imaging but it's very
low dimensional measurements but a high
dimensional measurements such as singles
sna sequencing the moment you measure
the cell C you destroy it so you can
only measure it
once but ideally what you would want is
you want to measure a cell let's say in
a control condition without simulation
and then you want to perturb it with the
drug or genetic perturbation or whatever
it is then you measure it again because
then you truly know the sort of causal
difference causal effect what was the
true effect of that perturbation on that
cell that's not possible what you need
in this case really is a time machine
you measure the cell in the process you
destroy it you take your time machine
back when it was still alive you measure
it
again we don't have a physical time
machine but through inference to
computation we can build if you will a
computational time machine that's what
we set out to do in this
project so what is the solution the
solution is to infer so-called
counterfactuals so
counterfactuals this is idea from causal
inference and it's essentially asking
what would have happened happened
if so through causal inference this
framework which is called the potential
outcome framework we can match cells
across conditions based on confounder
signals and I'll explain in a bit what
that means to identify these
counterfactual
pairs uh essentially pairs of
cells where you can say it's the same
cell or it's essentially the same cell
but in a different
condition so to do
this we focus on separating um
confounder from treatment
signals so there are many sources of
variability in a population of
cells um a subset of
those uh sources of variability are due
to the treatment you know whatever you
perturb the cells with and they change
but some signals or a lot of them have
nothing to do don't correlate with the
treatment for example you have different
cell types there's cell cycle there's
all kind of sources of variability that
have nothing to do with the with the
response to the treatment we call those
confounders so you can kind of imagine
the data uh comprises of confounder
signals and outcome signal so where the
outcome signals um correlate or a result
of the treatment
so the idea is that we want to remove
the outcome signals before we do the
matching because otherwise there's a
bias because when we try to match cells
between conditions ideally we want to
have the same distribution we want to be
able to say okay this is the same cell
across the two conditions but
fundamentally the cells have changed in
response to the pertubation so we
temporarily remove those effects as
outcome
effects and we look at the cells what we
call the confounder space there we do
the matching now we can do correct
matching and specifically you use
optimal transport so now it's
unbiased now we have our counterfactual
cell pairs we can do our individual
treatment analysis so we can ask for
every individual cell how does it
respond so this is a you know a visual
overview of the algorithm so you do your
experiment for example you you have your
control cells you do some
perturbation you do your traditional
single cell analysis then we actually
use independent component analysis to
separate different um sources of
variability we split those in confounder
and outcome signals then as I mentioned
before we temporarily remove the
outcomes we just look at the confounders
we call the confounder space in that
space we perform optimal transport we
match cells we obtain our counterfactual
cell Pairs and now we can perform
treatment effect analysis but truly at
the Single Cell level we can ask for
every individual cell how did it respond
as opposed to asking it for how does the
whole population
respond so the outcome the result are
these counterfactual cell pairs so we
can ask for every individual cell how
does it respond to simulation because
different cells will resp respond
differently or maybe
not now this is where things get
interesting so now that we have this
framework where we
can ask questions about how do
individual cells respond to a treatment
we can ask questions about what happens
when you have multiple
treatments um specifically about Synergy
for example if you have two different
perturbations when you combine those two
perturbations does something different
happen than when you apply those
perturbations separately is there an
interaction and the reason why that I
bring this up is that because is is that
there is a fundamental relationship
between this and
language um in fact I would like to
argue that Synergy some form of a protol
language so let's take natural language
right we have a sentence with words the
meaning of a word is highly dependent on
the context in fact two words when they
occur together might have completely
different meaning when they do not occur
together or occur with other words right
so there's interactions there's
nonlinear effects and of course in
natural language we have you know many
like higher order effects when you have
interactions when you have many words
and it's more complicated but I would
say that this sort of nonlinear
interaction between words to Synergy is
the fundamental building block of
language and that's why we are studying
it here we wanted to ask are there such
interactions in biology um specifically
um in immune
responses so in this case we can measure
treatment effects to individual
perturbations but also combinations and
we can use this idea to quantify what we
call Synergy score so what we simply do
is ask when you take perturbation a and
perturbation B and you add them up do
you get the same as when
you um simulate the cells with
perturbation A and B combined or does
something special happen for example is
a certain gene expression higher than
you would expect or is lower than you
expect any deviation means that there is
an interaction there's a Synergy effect
and again that idea is fundamental to
language sort of a building block I call
it sort of a Proto
language okay so now let's apply this
idea
so we aim to understand the language you
know immune language Lang language of
cyto kindes um and my amazing
collaborator Jeff shisuka um carried out
this experiment while he took um healthy
donor um pbmc and simulated the cells
both acutely for two days or chronically
for seven days
uh with a number of different cyto
kindes both individually as well as
combinations and then measured the
effect through single cell
sequencing and the question there was
how do the cells how do different cells
respond to different cyto and how do
they respond to combinations if there's
something special going
on so we measured individual conditions
as you can see here in AER in aerons Al
Stakes Etc but also several combinations
to specifically ask are there nonlinear
are there synergistic
effects so first of all when you just
look at individual perturbations our
framework our cinemo framework is able
to quantify these individual treatment
effects so the plots on the right each
point is a cell but it's not your
traditional umap we're not looking at
gene expression patterns we're looking
at changes so every cell actually is is
a cell pair is a counterfactual cell
pair so it shows how cells change so
here on the left we see the different
cell typs you're used to seeing the spot
there's B cells D cells monocytes Etc
okay nothing special but here we're
looking at the response space and what
you can see here is
that while there are many different cell
types there are only two classes of
response so there's only two ways in
which a cells can respond in fact
there's one uh cluster where you have
the the T cells and then K cells and
another cluster which is largely
Moniz so this shows and by the way this
is one specific treatment this is
inferent beta treatment but this
demonstrates that we can use our
individual um treatment analysis using
our causal inference framework to ask
how do individual cells
respond um and are there do they respond
a similar different ways and here you
can see there's really only two ways in
which they respond
um but now
um so there we we we you know Quantified
the effect of individual
perturbations um but as I mentioned
we're really interested here in sort of
deciphering this language we're
interested in combinations so let's look
at these uh combos so I introduce this
idea of the Synergy score we can
quantify
how uh combining two perturbations is
different or the effect is different
from stimulating itself separately with
these perturbations or how much deviates
from that and we device a Synergy score
as you can see here on the y-axis here's
broken down by cell type and you can see
very clearly that monocytes monocytes
show very strong Synergy score so in
this case especially monocytes were
synergistic meaning that they had a
different response to cyto kind
combinations than individual cyto Kines
um in fact they particularly showed this
synergistic effect for interferon beta
plus uh these three different cyto such
as tnf Alpha interferon gamma and
L6 and it turns out these so these
combinations essentially trigger um a
synergistic response to multi- Signal
information um and we found that uh this
showed an inhibition of actually
nutrifil chemotactic signaling as well
as induction of monoy chemotactic
programs
so these synergistic effects uh cause
some kind of Downstream uh
chemotactic um
expression
um so what this shows is that our
approach not only can identify responses
of individual cells of perturbations but
it can identify synergistic nonlinear
effects
and in some sense you could call this a
combinatorial logic these
nonlinearity and that is the first step
to understanding a language and we only
measured you know up to two
combinations but there might be higher
order interactions maybe some different
things will go on when you have three
four or five cyto packs of course the
challenge there is that you have this
combinatorial huge comori
space um but I think it would be super
interesting to kind of scale up this
experiment maybe in some clever ways
where we can scale it to really start to
infer the logic the language uh because
I think we just scratched the surface
here
okay so now that we have kind of
establish this idea of biology as a
language why not use state-of-the-art
language tools or natural language
processing to tackle this problem so in
the second project I want to talk talk
about um it's called selto sentence
where we teach large language models the
language um of
biology so sa
just um gave uh terrific introduction
into large language models and
biological Foundation models so I don't
have to convince you I mean even before
that I'm sure you were already convinced
um so the question is can large language
models model biology
well clearly llms are good at language I
mean they're really fantastic at at
modeling language we also know that
they're pretty good at learning new
languages
so an llm that's been trained on English
has a much easier time learning a
completely new language than if you
would train it from scratch because
there are similarities between languages
right I mean of course you might be
familiar with this idea of the universal
grammar chsky um there are similarities
between languages right they have some
fundamental building blocks that is the
same so if you know one language it's
easier also for humans if you know long
one language it's easier to know another
language um so if we assume that biology
has a
language why not use perhaps we can use
llms to learn the language so what does
a biological language look like so in
the previous project I was kind of
talking about cell communications where
the cyto chemokines are kind of the
words they occur together into sentences
but another way to look at biological
language in terms of more sort of
genomic language in the sense that genes
the units of biology um are the
words individual cells you can think of
as sentences right where different words
occur together in a certain
context tissues perhaps we can think of
those as paragraphs or documents Etc so
that might be a natural way of modeling
biological
language so why would we actually use
large language models to model single
cell data so pre-trained large language
models so they been pre-trained on
natural language they are inherently
powerful we know that they're smart
right to a certain
degree
um they are very disappointing so far
incredibly uh
capable and
even though they're trained on language
they're much more than language models
they can do all kinds of Downstream
diverse Downstream tasks right such as
math or you know whatever it is in
addition um the advantage of using large
language models to model biology is that
it would allow for seamless integration
of biological data and textual data so I
had already mentioned briefly that
there's huge amount of sort of metadata
about biology in in the text
form this would potentially allow
integrating all that metadata that we
have with actual genomic data to have
sort of a model that kind of understands
both and can sort of translate or go
back and forth between the
two and another huge advantage of using
LMS is there's that is that we can
leverage incredibly rapid advancements
in LM infrastructure so if you're at
least somewhat following this Fields
you'll know that there's like every week
There's a new model coming out or a new
framework or or you know larger context
or you know billions trillions of
parameters if you were to build your own
models you could never keep up with it
so if we get to leverage these
incredible sort of exponential you know
advancements in LM infrastructure that
would be an advantage I would
think so I would like to argue that you
know instead of thinking about model
design so traditionally we have a
problem uh we have data and then we come
up with a model new model to to to to to
that's designed to capture whatever your
you know data is
about how you want to you know approach
your problem how you to answer that your
questions you create a new a new
system instead what if we turn this into
a data engineering problem we say the
model is already there it's just in
large language mob we're not going to
mess with it instead we're going to look
at our data and we're going to modify
our data engineer it in such a way that
we can feed it to the llm we're kind of
turning the problem around because then
we can use all of this we don't have to
create a new model if tomorrow a new
model comes out great we can just
immediately use it we don't have to
change anything because our data is
already designed to go to to work with
that model okay
so we have started doing this in our
framework is called cellto sentence and
we want to redefine single cell
analysis by using large language models
and this is not just one method it's a
framework that in principle allows you
to do every single cell analysis task
just through
llms and we would like to you know
convince you that this is
better um and there's many advantages to
it and it's an incredibly flexible
framework so just to give you a brief
overview we started with huge amount of
data more data is more better uh we
collect lots of single cell data but not
just single cell data our framework can
work with any kind of data as long as
you can convert into text we also look
at bulk RNA sequencing
data we collect any kind of annotation
that is available you know cell types
tissues drug perturbations as well as
sort of more elaborate natural language
annotations so I think Gene sets is a
great example of like a lot of our
biological knowledge is in the form of
Gene sets right Gene sets is a natural
bridge between biological language and
natural language because literally you
have a set of genes let's say these 50
genes are associated with Parkin dises
that's a bridge between biological
language and natural language and we've
done that literally to translate right
humans have created this because we
don't understand biology genes don't
mean anything to us so we've created
these Gene sets through experiments to
translate between bi biological language
and human language we can all feed this
into our model and then our model can
learn to translate we don't have to do
it manually anymore and of course we
have the papers themselves right if
someone if there's a a data set out
there is usually comes with a paper
where they did the analysis and there's
a lot of information in that paper in
textual form right so that seems like a
natural way to kind of uh see make sense
to kind of to leverage that data so this
is how we collect you know the
data and then the idea of sell to
sentence again it's a data engineering
problem we convert all this data into a
textual
format we train the model multitask it's
a foundation model so just like GPT is
trained on all kinds of different types
of data
um we do the same thing for example we
train our model on um you know gene
expression data plus cell type labels
tissue labels diseases
species everything this is the
pre-training phase and then we have an
inference phase where the user uses this
model to do whatever they want to do for
example they give it a cell and it
predicts label of a cell the cell type
or it interprets a cell or it translates
a Cell between Mouse and human or
predicts the response of perturbation
whatever you want to do you can do that
in fact you can use the system in a zero
shot way you know when you use gep chat
GPT it's zero shot you don't find tun
you just prompt it and it gives you an
answer but sometimes when you have a
more Specialized or more nuanced uh
difficult task you may want to fine-tune
your model on the test we can do that as
well we can find you the model on
whatever task you're interested in Okay
so at the core of selta sentence is uh
converting gene expression into textual
format and it's actually very simple we
simply uh create cell sentences we call
them cell sentences by rank ordering G
names by expression from high to low
that's it so every
cell becomes a cell sentence um in fact
we encode only the express
genes uh single cell data is generally
very sparse so let's say there's
thousand 2,000 Express genes we take
those genes and we rank them from high
to low so s explained that we have
positional encoding which is an
essential part of large language models
now in natural language the positional
encoding exists to
um to to to um encode where different
words occur in in in a sentence whether
they're close together far apart what
order they have Etc in our case
implicitly the positional encoding is
encoding expression because we don't
encode expression explicitly we just
rank order the genes but then the
positional encoding is encoding the
ordering and thus implicitly the rank
ordering is encoding expression so it's
a very elegant way of encoding
expression with these language models
can ask question here um so say talked
about two different Foundation models
one of them was doing the binning one of
them was doing the ranking yeah um so
question one is do you do some sort of
normalization like Med based
normalization type of stuff that so so
yeah for input and and I kind of skipped
over that but we the input is sort of
your standard processing by BL and but
actually a when you think about it a lot
of these processing steps you know like
log transformation they don't really
change the ordering so it doesn't really
matter we do it anyway because we often
already take data that's been
pre-process right we take data from like
CCI cell by Gene or human cell outet
it's already processed so we do that
anyway um but yeah I know that answers
your question J former was doing
something like taking the median of a
gene across all the cells in their
training data yeah um and then
normalizing with respect to that yeah so
yeah that's a good question we've
experimented with sort of normalization
because we figured
okay certain genes are always highly
expressed right so this this ranking is
going to be dominated by uninteresting
signals like ribosomal gen right so we
thought okay if you do some kind of
normalization to it turns out it doesn't
really help and it just adds
complexity
so this simple approach just it just
works so we don't need to do anything
anything fancy I think internally the
model when it sees a lot of data is
doing those things it'll learn that
certain genes are always high and it's
fine it doesn't it doesn't really
matter um
yeah so the nice thing is that we
actually we can also go back so we can
take single cell data convert it to our
cell sentences but actually convert it
back into expression if that's what you
want and the reason why we can do this
is
because the
rank um of the genes is highly
correlated with the expression in other
words converting gene expression to rank
we lose very little information as you
can see by the r squ measure here and
this is just simply using a simple
linear regression you can imagine you
could do a fancier sort of nonlinear
model again it's not necessary the nice
thing about this approach is it's simple
it works
you know why make it more complicated
when it's not necessary and you can see
here on the right we see original
expression um in blue and and overlay on
top of that is the reconstructed
expression and you can see that there's
only you know very minor
differences so this rank ordering
converting to cell sentences is is is a
very it's a good way to encode gene
expression data you lose very little
information okay so once we have you
know encoded our gene expression to cell
sentences we can do all kinds of things
we can add textual annotation to it
because now we're dealing with text
right you can any kind of text um you
can fine-tune your models using
traditional autor regressive next token
prediction llms just predict the next
token as as site was was explaining we
change nothing about that as far as the
model is concerned it's just text like
any other text and it's just predicting
the next word in our case next Gene
which means it's predicting expression
implicitly and then we can do inference
can generate cells from text or generate
text from cells complete cells Etc and
then finally when we have generated cell
sentence we can ALS as I mentioned
before even convert them back into
expression if that's what you care about
if you want to go back to the original
space no
problem so really we can now think about
single cell analysis as
prompting any task that you want to do
generate cells predict perturbations
interpret cells label cells whatever you
want to do it becomes a prompt now just
like you interact with GPT for example
you want to generate a cell from a
certain cell type you say here I have a
uh long lived plasma cell generate one
and it generates the cell sentence the
the the G names in order or we can say
here is a cell what cell type is it and
it will predict in textual form of the
cell type or we can even do complete
natural language insights you give it
one or multiple cells and you ask the
model okay what's going on there what's
the biology what disease am I dealing
what cell types are in my data so it
provides a completely new way of
interacting with genomic
data so we've carried out a lot of these
tasks we have used our model to generate
cells from test text so in this
case uh we provided it with uh a cell
type in a textual format and as generate
the cell you can see here the ground
truth expression of the held out cell
types and on the right the generated
expression you can see it look very
similar um of course we've Quantified
this and we have extensively benchmarked
this with all against state-of-the-art
generative single cell models as well as
Foundation models and we outperform
them um we can also go the other way
around we can generate text from cells
so in this case we gave it a a cell
sentence and ask it to label it to
predict the cell type in text formats
again we uh extensively Benchmark this
now as I mentioned
before
um llms when they're you know trained on
natural language they have an easier
time learning a new language even though
theyve never seen that language before
they understand the principles of
language and I mentioned that that could
be an advantage for learning biological
language because learning biology
starting out with human language might
be easier than starting out from scratch
and we did this experiments we train
model
that were either pre-trained on natural
language or we trained them from scratch
and we very very clearly saw a huge
boost when you start out with natural
language so that raises an interesting
idea that you know natural language
helps understanding biological language
it means that there's some similarity
between our language and the language of
biology which I think is encouraging can
I quickly ask um yeah here is the
accuracy based on reconstructing the
order of the Gen um
I think this is a cell label prediction
task okay yeah but we see this across
the board in any kind of task there's a
huge advantage and we know that this is
the case between other modalities for
example pre-training on text and doing
fine-tuning on images or vice versa we
we we knew that this was the case but we
didn't know it that was the case in
biology so I think that's
encouraging so who here in the audience
is a bioinformatician or does
bioinformatics uh work
yeah so I have some bad news for you
because uh I'm going to take Delta send
is going to take your job
away because we kind of set out um with
the idea to um automate the B
informatician can we use this model to
go directly from raw data to natural
language insights because that's that's
really what we do as B informaticians
and I'm I'm a conversational biologist
myself right we have data use various
tools to analyze that data but
ultimately your goal to write a paper
get it published paper's natural
language right so the goal is what we do
is we go from data to papers right
that's really what we are um so can you
automate that with
llms and the answer is yes so what we
did is we trained our model fine- tuned
our model on data sets the form of cell
sentences combined with natural language
abstracts were associated with the study
but the model learns to associate the
data with the
interpretation and then at inference
what we did is we gave it a new data set
that it's never seen before and ask it
generate the
abstract and that's what we show here
this is one example um and it's is able
to interpret the data and it's able to
meaningfully um you know understand
what's going on in the data and and and
provide it in natural language so we
wanted to Benchmark this it's kind of
hard to Benchmark this because no one
has tried this before so what we did is
we
just uh gave ourselves sentences to Chad
gbt or other language models that were
not kind of trained on our data because
you can imagine that they probably
recognize some of the G names and could
do some kind of interpretation and they
were but it was really bad so this shows
that we can go directly from data to
natural language insights yeah and we
Benchmark this can I ask one more
question one examples from yeah um
was the originating tissue also part of
the training data when you're uh
fine-tuning the model
or I guess how does CS Salto sentence
able to tell that this is from fallopian
tube for example or was it already part
of the prompt it was most likely part of
the pre- training
uh uh well it it it didn't know so it
has it might have seen similar data but
remember we're starting out with a
natural language pre-rain model which
means it knows fallopian tube in natural
language right okay yeah but then in the
fine-tuning phase we're
associating natural language not NE not
this language but other natural to gene
expression it's able to generalize so
it's during training it's never seen
flop Tu data and but it's able to infer
that it's it's this is called
generalization right it has seen some
examples of natural language data and it
can generalize it to New to because it
understands biology it understands
natural language and it can it learns to
make the
connection this
knowledge
thanks so in this natural uh language
large language models there is all sorts
of stuff embedded in them you know
that's why we have dark web whatnot
that's why we have this this is the
control these models and even they're
way more powerful because we use gpt2
and this was I believe GPT 3.5 or
four these models were just changed on
texting that's why we we expected them
to do something not completely random
because they'll recognize some Gene
names and be able to interpret it but
this shows and we did many examples and
we Quantified this that they do a really
poor job at interpreting it and this is
gp4 versus G PT R gpt2 that's fine-tuned
on Cell
sentences um and and and we made sure
that our model has never seen this B
this gene expression data single cell
data so it was not in the training
center there wasn't even single cell
data that was like I mean it probably
was yeah but what is like that's that's
the whole point right yes it has seen
similar things similar cell types
similar panels but that's the whole
point right it can kind of
repurpose that information in a
meaningful way recombine it to make
these new
inferences
thanks so another advantage of our model
is that it's kind of species
agnostic it doesn't care if you give it
a cell sentence that comes from a mouse
from a human cell or a mouse cell it's
just Gene names rank ordered and that's
what we did we train it on Mouse data
and human data
but we gave it zero information on how
Mouse and human are
related so we didn't give it any
information on sort of homology between
genes or anything we just gave it
separately Mouse cells human cells
that's it and then we asked okay what
happens now if you take Mouse and human
cells and you kind of embed them in the
same space
because we can extract latent embeddings
from our model um simply by extracting
really a sentence embedding and this is
an idea that's been used in language
modeling is you encode a sentence and
you just extract the embedding from that
sentence in our case a sentence is a
cell and we can extract that embedding
of a cell regardless if it's a human or
Mouse cell and that's what we did here
so we took data uh this is banre data
that was uh I think measured in the same
lab so it was kind of controlled in a
sense that they use the same technology
to measure Mouse human bankas and we
co-embedded the data this is what it
looks like the first all you can see it
kind of has a similar shape but they're
not overlapping we don't expect them to
overlap because Mouse is not human right
they should be separate but there should
be some similarity and that's what we
see here it's colored by cell types you
can see that they kind of order in the
same way now what we can do is something
interesting because now Mouse and human
exist in the same space and we can think
of translation between species as a
batch correction or matching problem so
what we did is we took optimal transport
which is a way to match the
distributions right as I also explained
or presented in the previous project and
we ask okay try to map the human cells
to the mouse cells and then we ask does
it correctly line up the cell type and
for a large part it does this join space
allows you to align between different
species in a meaningful way and it
allows for a jointed analysis make
things really easy because you don't
have to get think anymore this is mouse
this is human how do you you know oh
these genes relate these don't now you
have a shared space where you can do
shared analysis and kind of derive your
your your insights in a much more
convenient
way um excuse me I have a question yeah
uh can you go back to the slide where uh
you had this gene
expression uh profile and you were
trying to predict the cell type um so
you had a sequence of
genes um um
back yeah this so for for example at
first time uh you would give a sequence
of genes and would the cell type be the
cell type which maximizes the likelihood
of that
sequence no we we simply do inference in
a generative sense so we give it the
self sentence and then ask the model to
complet sentence so it generates the
next tokens the next words and that's we
interpret that as a cell type so it'll
say oh this cell is likely is a cd4t
cell so it just produces text and then
we can look at that text and see is that
the correct cell type or
not just like when you use chat GPT you
give it a prompt and the model does next
token prediction it just completes your
it generates words uh to complete your
prompt which you know can be an answer
to a question or whatever it is we do in
the same way we give it a cell sentence
and then the completion is predicting
the cell type in this case so it's going
to complete the the sequence based on
the cell type that it has learned
correct exactly
exactly
okay we can also do perturbation
response prediction so this is actually
the same data set as I presented before
this is from the Cino paper so this is
the combinatorial cyto stimulation so we
were able to repurpose our own data but
in this case we're using it in a
generative sense so in cinemo we did
analysis right we just looked at the
data and and made some inferences here
we want to generate so what we did is we
train our model or find you in our
cendence model on a
subset of the perturbations and then ask
can you predict the Unseen perturbation
because really the question here is does
the model generalize can it make
meaningful inferences about data or
conditions it's never seen
before right so you might train it on
interferent beta in I6 and then you
would ask okay can you predict what
happens when you can combine them and
that's how we
did um and as you can see here first of
all in general the generated data is
very similar to the ground truth data
they overlap and we can even look at
specific perturbations or cell types
here uh forgot what that was um and we
can quantify it we can literally ask
okay when you predict these unseen
combinations again it was not models
never seen those do the cells look like
the ground truth and they do and we've
extensively benchmarked this and it
works really
well um we've also done this on a mouse
cocine data set so this is uh data
generated um from a paper in by near aen
um so this is a large number I think
more than a 100 cyto kind perturbations
in Mouse lymph noes
so this is not
combinatorial however the labels are
combinatorial because every cell has two
labels it has a cell type label and a
perturbation so we were still able to do
a combinatorial experiment where we
basically split the data these
perturbations into 50 in a 50/50 split
so we train the model on half of the
cell type U cyrine combinations and then
we do inference on the the ones that we
held out and as you can see um it works
incredibly well
well so when you think about language
models um they don't just model
individual sentences right usually you
provide it with at least a paragraph or
a document or S was saying that the test
long context models by summar
summarizing whole
books
context it's all about context the
meaning is in the context right the
meaning of a word depends on the context
of the sentence the meaning of a
sentence depends on the context of the
document you can have two identical
sentences occurring in different
documents or books where they have
different
meanings so
why uh shouldn't we model cells like
this the same
cell might or at least in terms of a
gene expression pattern two cells might
look identical but they occur in
different tissues and they might do
different things one one of the reasons
is because we don't measure everything
right single cell sequencing it's it's a
high dimensional measurement but you're
only measuring RNA right there's so much
you're not measuring
so the context really determines for a
large
part what the meaning what a cell does
the function of a cell now our model our
framework makes it really easy to model
cellular context because instead of
providing it one cell sentence we can
provide it five
or 10 or 10,000 cell sentences Al
together that were collected from the
same data set same tissue maybe a
spatial region when you're doing spatial
transcriptomics whatever your context is
you can encode those cells together in
our model really easily and then the
model will understand it will model the
context and it will learn
relationships between the cells between
the genes between different cells Etc
exactly like how natural language works
so we've tried this and actually we have
built the first
multi-cellular context Foundation model
where we encoded either one three or
five cells in one context and um this
task is a um it's an annotation I think
it's cell type and tissue tissue
prediction task and you can see that the
performance gets a huge boost when
you're modeling cont and this makes
sense right it's kind of obvious if you
give it five cells from a tissue versus
one obviously there's more information
information to five cells so it's
obvious on the one hand but
also um yeah no one has showed this
before and it
works
okay so
um yeah so today I talked about this
idea of bi biology as a language or
having multiple languages uh for example
you know cells communicating through
complex structured signals uh you know
the idea of cyto kindes chemokine
functioning as words and together their
sentences uh genes as words cells as
sentences tissues as kind of
documents and then first I talked about
cinemo this causal inference framework
where we can sort of uncover Synergy
which is kind of a fundamental building
block of
language uh by quantifying these
nonlinear interactions between the cyto
and then I talked about our framework
sell to sentence where we model cells as
text where instead of building models we
do data engineering
um and we're kind of redefining single
cell
analysis by using
llms um which allows us to interpret
cells generate cells predicts
perturbations perform cross species
multi-species analysis and even uh model
multicellular context as I just
showed so with that I want to thank you
for listening and uh thank the amazing
members of my lab collaborators uh
sources of funding we're now
collaborating with Google research to
scale up our models because you can
imagine if you want to go big S it shows
bigger is often better uh we need the
resources uh so we need partners for
that and um yeah code is on GitHub we
share our models and hugging face uh we
have tutorials API so this is not a
single project this is or a single
method it's a new framework so if you're
interested in contributing finding new
applications of our method or just you
know working with us or using it please
reach out we kind of want to build a
community around this technology thank
you e