all right um today we are going to move
on to really we'll sort of start the
second half of the course the first half
of the course was about essentially
following up on lecture one and deriving
domain and Supply curves so you now know
um and and have been painfully tested on
how you can come up with demand and
Supply curves on how you can take the
Primitives of consumer preferences and
the perimeters of production functions
and come up with demand and Supply
curves how you can use those to draw
positive as well as normative
conclusions about welfare and how that
works with different kinds of Market
structure be it perfect competition
Monopoly or oligopoly and that is sort
of the basics of consumer and producer
Theory the second half of the course is
essentially applications of that model
to various questions that you might have
raised as we were thinking through the
basics so for example the next two
lectures three lectures will be about
Factor demand Factor markets and in
particular we're not just going to take
W and R as given but ask where do W and
R come from where where does the wage
rate and the rate of return on Capital
actually come from we just took those as
constants and we did producer Theory I
just gave them to you but now we're
going to actually derive where do we
actually get the wage rate and the
interest rate so as we're going to go
back once again to the basic model but
dive more
deeply okay and in doing so we're going
to get introduced to two new fields of
Economics one is the field of labor
economics which is the study of Labor
markets
and one is finance which is a study of
capital markets so we'll learn about two
exciting new areas of economics in the
context of understanding Factor
markets okay so we're going to start by
talking and by factors once again we
mean capital and labor obviously in the
real world there are many factors of
production we're going to simplify them
into two as we've been doing so far
which is capital and
labor the basic theory of factor demand
applies to both so I'm going to teach
Factor demand independently of capital
and labor then I'm going to come back
and teach labor Supply and then Capital
Supply so Factor demand so demand for
both labor and capital it's the same
model but labor Supply and capital
Supply are different models so I'll
teach them separately okay so where does
Factor demand come
from well let's start with labor demand
although Capital demand and be symmetric
let's start with labor demand and let's
ask
for a firm deciding whether to employ
the marginal unit of Labor they have to
consider the costs and the benefits of
that marginal unit of
Labor so what is the cost of a marginal
unit of Labor well the cost of marginal
labor the marginal cost of a unit of
Labor is the
wage that's what it costs you to have
the marginal unit of Labor okay you have
to pay if you want to hire one more hour
of Labor you got to pay the wage for
that
hour what's the marginal
benefit well the marginal benefit has
two components first of all the marginal
benefit depends on the marginal product
of
labor if you hire one more unit of Labor
how many more Goods will you
produce okay so the cost is what it is
the wage the benefits of marginal
product labor we can't stop
there because first firms don't care
about units of goods firms care about
Revenue so the marginal benefit of
hiring another unit of Labor is the
product of the marginal product of labor
times the marginal revenue of one more
unit of
good so if I hire one more unit of
Labor I get one more unit of output and
then that output itself has a marginal
revenue so think about the simple case
think about this in a perectly
competitive market in a perectly
competitive market then the marginal un
of Labor is marginal product of labor
times the
price so what's another unit of Labor
worth it's worth how much that worker
could produce at times how much I could
sell it
for so it so the in a perfectly
competitive
market the marginal BF equals the
marginal product of labor times price so
essentially what this says for the
competitive market
if you set marginal benefits equal the
marginal costs you want to set the
marginal product of labor times the
price equal to the
wage and that's how you decide how many
workers to hire you basically hire
workers until their
benefits which is the value of what they
produce equals their cost which is their
wage okay once again pretty
straightforward when you when you think
about it so basically the value of a
worker is determined by how productive
that workers or how many units she can
make times what those unit sell for
another hour of Labor making computer
chips is more valuable than an hour of
Labor making potato chips because
computer should sell for more for more
than potato chips okay so basically the
labor you produce is more valuable if
the good sell for a higher price a great
way to illustrate this and I'm sorry for
my Pro Sports bias here um is to think
about basketball players okay think
about the National Basketball
Association um as a set of you know a
set of firms that are trying to deliver
the best basketball products so you're a
firm you're a team in the
NBA and you are trying to figure out how
to set your
payroll to maximize profits you're
trying to decide who to hire on your
team you have 12 slots you're trying to
deire who in those 12 slots you want to
hire to maximize your
profits okay so what you really want is
you want to ask well what's the marginal
product of the next
player times the value of that product
well the marginal product is the number
of wins they produce so you want to ask
how many wins will a player add to my
team and the value is how much more
money I'll make per win they
add okay the worst basketball teams do
not make as much money as the best
basketball
teams so basically by hiring a player
I'm asking how much will that player
include increase my wins that's their
marginal product and what's the value of
a win the price effectively is how much
profit I'll make per additional
win and that's the marginal product of
the additional basketball
player okay so for example LeBron James
makes about $32 million a year LeBron
James is the best you know not so the
best player right now but over the last
20 years the best player in basketball
some would argue the best ever he makes
about $32 million a year okay it's a lot
of money because his marginal product is
enormous he's a great player and the
additional wins are valuable in terms of
additional advertising attendance
Etc now other players don't make as much
how many of you have heard of Nate
Robinson okay good I always like to see
okay mostly gender biased I saw one
woman shake her head hopefully there's
more okay sorry sorry for the gender
biased example but Nate Robinson is one
of the shortest players in NBA history
was 5'9 shorter than me uh in a world
where the typical player about
6667 so he's one of the shortest players
in NBA history but an excellent player
played for a number of teams um very
exciting player but but no LeBron James
let's put it that way by the end of his
career he wasn't great he made about two
million a year you know not bad we'd all
take it but not LeBron James okay he
made about two million a year why did he
make two million a year Well a win was
still worth a win but his marginal
product was low Nate Robinson
contributed less to a win than did
LeBron James Nate Robinson then quit the
NBA he went to play basketball in Israel
Israel's basketball crazy they love
basketball they have their own league
and in Israel he was a superstar he was
one of the best players he had maybe the
highest marginal product in the league
because he was so much better than the
other players over there he could
massively contribute to
wins and his salary went down from 2
million to
300,000 why well his marginal product
went up but the value of a win went way
down okay if you add wins in the US
that's billions of dollars of
advertising revenue or attendance
Revenue in Israel it's not such a big
deal so here's an example where marginal
product went
up but the benefit of hiring went down
and we call that benefit marginal
revenue
product marginal revenue product is the
marginal product times how much it's
worth Nate Robinson in
Israel was worth less a ticket in Israel
the highest price ticket in Israel is
$75 the highest price ticket in the US
for regular season game court side for
the Boston Celtics is about $2,000
okay so basically this wasn't that much
money made from Israel from basketball
Israel z a robbit had a higher marginal
product he had a lower marginal revenue
product which is why he was paid less
okay so that sort of
illustrates the important distinct
between marginal product and marginal
revenue
product okay questions about that yeah
well the firm it's this is a positive
statement on normative we want is a
normative statement The Firm when they
optimize they set for optimization
involves setting marginal benefits equal
to Marginal costs in every state of the
world optimization for consumers
optimization for firms I just said well
instead of deriving this you could
derive this also from firm optimization
I just did a shortcut I said the
marginal benefit of hiring another unit
of Labor is this the marginal cost is
this you set them equal that's the firm
optimization decision
okay all right now that's labor demand
Capital demand looks exactly the
same the only the cost for Capital the
marginal cost is the rental rate what a
cost for rental unit of
capital the marginal
benefit is the marginal revenue product
of capital which is the marginal product
of capital times marginal
Revenue that's the
benefit now this is just harder to
theoretically we're
done conceptually it's a little harder
for two reasons first of all as I said
it's hard to think about Capital as
having a wage rate but once again we
think about Capital think about renting
a machine every period so our just like
hiring a workers essentially renting the
worker we think of hiring a machine is
renting the machine and we'll come back
to that but R is the price but all hard
to think what's mpk what's a marginal
product of capital well it's just what
the next unit of capital produce in
terms of outputs it's the same as
workers it's just if you have one more
incremental unit of machine that costs R
how much does that increment your
quantity just like if you have one more
unit of Labor the cost W how much does
that increment your quality so it's just
like the
MPL it's the effective quantity of the
marginal additional
unit in this case of capital okay
questions about
that okay that's all pretty
straightforward the more interesting
part of today's
lecture is thinking about the supply
side and we're going to start today with
labor
Supply we'll do that for about a lecture
and a half and then next time we'll
start on Capital Supply so let's talk
about Labor Supply this is
both some fun economics and some
relevant economics because you guys have
to decide how hard to work labor Supply
is fundamentally your decision of how
hard to work now your decision has many
components there's whether you work
there's how many hours you work there's
how hard you work every hour there's
which job you take lots of components
okay we're going to simplify things here
into one decision which is how many
hours you work
okay so imagine you're sort of
deciding um you're you're going to work
just deciding how many hours to work and
we're also going to assume you can
choose it freely obviously in many jobs
you can't freely choose your hours your
employer has a role we're going to
assume you choose it
freely okay so we are going to do we're
going to think about you forget all the
other decisions you make about what job
you're going to take and hard how how
much effort you're going to put in just
think about you deciding how many hours
am I going to work okay and we're going
to think about the economics of that
decision okay so we're trying to decide
how many hours
H an individual wants to work okay how
do they make that
decision well on the one hand the more
they work the more [ __ ] they can
buy okay the more hours you work you're
in a wage per hour and so you can buy
more stuff and we like stuff okay more
is more is better so on the one hand we
want to work more because we want more
stuff on the other hand and here's what
gets really hard at MIT normal people
don't like to
work okay we are not normal people here
okay most people actually think of work
as a bad thing I know amazing huh most
people would rather not
work so the tradeoff is work you'd
rather not
work but by not working you have less
stuff so the tradeoff is a bad which is
working against a
good which is
stuff the problem is we don't know how
to model that we don't model tring bads
and goods that's too hard so we're going
to use a modeling trick and the modeling
trick is we're going to define the
complimentary good to work which is
Leisure Leisure we'll just call 24
minus8 you have 24 hours a day the
amount of leisure you take is 24 minus
the hours your
work by modeling Leisure if we solve for
optimal Leisure then we simply use this
simple relationship to solve for optimal
hours but it's hard to think this way
because fundamentally I'm asking how
hard you work but that's not what I'm
going to model I'm gonna model how hard
you party okay I'm gon a model
Leisure okay and work is going to be
residual we're going to solve for I'm
going to make the mistake occasionally
slipping into saying it's a choice of
work it's not it's a choice of leisure
and if you don't think that way you get
the modeling wrong the modeling is
because we once we put in two good
framework we're back to Consumer Theory
we know what to do we not how to trade
off two goods we doing that our you know
all
semester so we have two goods now
Leisure and
stuff okay and that's the trade-off we
want to make okay and that's the general
modeling trick is instead of modeling a
a bad we model the compliment very good
yeah um you know that is uh yes that
that is a similar straight off if you
think about sleep as Leisure you know
Leisure includes sleep you got to sleep
in this 24 hours sorry guys you do have
to sleep in that 24 hours so that's a
similar thing okay so basically you have
this tradeoff
so basically we are going to
model this now what that means is we
need to model we don't had to model the
demand for goods we've been doing that
for weeks but how do we model the demand
for
leisure so we're going to model the
supply of
labor by inverting it and modeling
demand for
leisure and we know and so we're going
to basically take our standard model and
instead of trading off between pizzas
and cookies you're going to trade off
between Leisure and stuff and that is
figure
151 figure 151 and I've put all the
stuff in one graph instead of walking
you through it okay on the Y AIS is
consumption now when I think of
consumption think of consumption as all
the stuff you're going to
consume your pizza and your
cookies okay on the xaxis is leisure
you have a 24-hour
maximum so you can take between zero and
24 hours of leisure so as you move to
the right on the xaxis you're modeling
Leisure of course that means that hours
you move to the left on the x-axis once
again we're not modeling hours modeling
Leisure Hours we just get at the
end okay so you then have a budget
constraint which is you can take 24
hours of leisure and consume nothing
that's the x intercept
or take no leisure and consume 24 times
your wage that's the Y
intercept now let me just make one point
the y axis is vague what is consumption
and here's I'm going to come back to
something I mentioned earlier in the
class we have complicated
multi-dimensional decisions we do them
sequentially earlier I gave you income
remember I said consumer theory is
easier than producer Theory because
income is just given to you now I'm
deriving where that income com comes
from so the idea is You' use a model
like this to solve for your income and
then given your income you go back to
your cookies versus Pizza model so right
now you're solving for how much Z work
versus how much stuff I have later I'll
decide how to spend my money on that
stuff right now I'm deciding how much Z
work versus how much stuff I'm gonna
have in total okay so think of the
sequential decision we're now going back
and taking that y that I gave to you and
making a decision
variable
okay so that is the budget constraint
what is the slope of the budget
constraint the slope is minus
W the slope is minus
W okay um what does oh I'm sorry we're
going to make one other assumption to
make life easy we're going to assume the
price of consumption Goods is one that
is there's some aggre consumption good
you're buying with a price of one this
is a trick we call making a numer rare
good it makes life easy otherwise we'd
have to track the price of consumption
throughout remember we did pizza versus
cookies you need to track the price of
pizza versus the price of cookies in not
ratio by setting PC to one we no longer
of a ratio to track just a level so the
slope of the budget constraint is then
instead of being minus W over PC it's
just minus W technically it's minus W
over PC right is the slope of the budget
constraint but we're setting PC to
one okay so slope of the bud constraint
is minus W what
what does that mean that means that the
price of
leisure is the
wage in what sense is the price of
leisure the wage why is the wage the
price of
leisure
yeah not which we call opportunity cost
because the oper this is why economics
is annoying because now every time you
sit down and watch TV I want you to
realize you are paying something to
watch that TV you're paying the
opportunity cost of not
working okay Leisure has a price the
price is the wage what you could have
been making by working during that hour
so the price of leisure Leisure is a
good just like cookies are a good it's a
good with a benefit and then it makes
you happy and a cost in which you have
to pay for it here you don't pay
explicitly I don't charge you to watch
you pay an opportunity cost which is
you're not working you could have been
working instead okay questions about
that so that's your budget
constraint now against this you say you
have a well- defined utility function
we're toity function is U equals F of
consumption and Leisure that is there's
two things you care about in life how
much stuff you have and how much Leisure
you have that's the two positive things
you care about you want Leisure remember
this is not
MIT okay you want
Leisure okay those are the two things
you care about in life and that's the
trade-off you make and we know how to
then maximize this utility
function okay so for example suppose we
write this in our Fame in our favorite
form square root of C * L let's say
that's utility
function what's your budget
constraint well your budget constraint
is that your
consumption the total amount you spend
in consumption this is really
consumption times price of consumption
but we set that to
one okay your consumption times the
price of consumption that's what you
want to spend
equals 24 minus L times your
wage this is what you're
spending this is what you're making
remember we're still assuming no savings
we said that early on in this world
we're assuming people don't save so
every period you're going to spend what
you make
this is what you make 24 lusus L * W
this is what you
spend okay so that's your budget
constraint okay we know how to optimize
we know how to solve this consumer
optimization
problem which is we know
that to optimize you want to set the
margin
utility the ratio of margin utilities
equal to the ratio of prices or the
slope of the budget constraint so you
want to set minus the margin utility of
leisure over the margin utility of
consumption equal to minus the wage once
again over the price of consumption but
price of consumption would normalize to
one okay so you want to set the margin
ility of leisure of the marginality of
consumption equal to the
wage that's the optimization condition
that's just back to pizza and cookies
guys same thing said of pizza and
cookies it's Leisure and
consumption okay given the square root
function we know how to solve this which
is we know that this is that the this
MTI margin utility is going to be minus
C over l so we set minus C over L the
minus W to solve this just plug in do
marginal Roots we've done it a million
times for the square root function okay
so that's your optimization condition is
that minus C overl equals minus
W okay we can then plug that into the
budget constraint plug this into the
budget we have two equations and two
unknowns
this is the budget constraint this the
optimization condition so it's two
equations and two unknowns we solve it
and we get that um if we for example uh
so we solve that and we get that um
leisure in this
case right we get that Leisure equals
12 the amount of leisure does not depend
on the wage in this for this particular
functional form of utility it's
generally not true Leisure will
generally depend on the wage but for
this particular model it doesn't so we
get Leisure equals 12 we take 12 hours
of leisure and
consumption did I do something wrong one
second
sorry equal 12 w yeah that's right um uh
Leisure equals 12 so for this particular
case you always choose the same amount
of leisure and consumption therefore is
12 *
W you work so you take 12 hours of
leisure you work 12 hours and you get 12
times W in
consumption that's mathematical we can
see it graphically in figure
151 you have an indifference curve which
come which is the ratio of margin
utilities where that is tangent to the
budget
constraint is at 12 hours of leisure and
12 w consumption that is your optimal
Choice you're done how hard do you work
well we have this equation you work 12
hours but we didn't get to that till the
very end we only cared about Leisure
through the whole model okay question
about that
optimization now what
happens if the wage rate
changes well we can't understand that
without coming back and thinking about
income and substitution
effects okay to understand the effect of
a wage rate
change we need to come back to income
and substitution effect so to do this
this is sort of an uninteresting case
because this doesn't Leisure depend on
wage I'm going to come I'm going to now
move to a different case I'm not going
to do the math or so graphically where
Leisure does depend on wage so now we're
going to come back to how do consumers
react when a price changes well we know
consumers react when a price changes
there's substitution income effects so
let's go to figure 152 we have the
original budget constraint 24 times W1
and let's say the wage now Rises to
W2 the wage Rises to
W2 okay the budget straint pivots
outward you have the same consumption
which is zero if you don't work but with
every hour of work you get more
consumption the slope is steeper
what effect does that have on how hard
you work don't look at the graph for a
second if I said to you hey the wage
went up you're going to work harder or
less hard most people would
say what would somebody said tell me
what you think
yeah
why fascinating okay most people say the
opposite actually which is gee I can
make more so I work harder there's a
more return to work
but you've also given a sensible answer
too which is let's imagine I needed a th
bucks to buy a computer if my wage just
went up from 20 to $40 an hour I need to
work Less hours to buy that
computer what you've just Illustrated is
that when we comes to labor Supply GIF
and goods are not
rare okay when we didn't come in
substitution effects remember the
substitution effect always went the
opposite opposite direction of the price
increase okay the income effect
depending on whether the good was normal
or
inferior now that's not going to be
true the substitution effect now for
leisure will always go the direction of
the price
increase why because a price increase
I'm sorry the the substitution was still
go the opposite direction of the price
increase I'm sorry the substitution
still goes the opposite direction of the
price increase so let's do the
substitution effect the price of
leisure's gone up okay so let's look at
this graphically the price of leisure's
gone up why because you you give up more
by having
Leisure we can do the substitution
Factor Remember by drawing the imaginary
budget constraint BC
Prime that is tangent to the original
indifference
curve but at the new price ratio and
what you see is the substitution effect
is negative like it always is when a
price goes up you want less of
something subst effect is always
negative when a price go up you want
less of something in this case the price
of leisure went up you want less of it
and that's the standard intuition many
people have most people if you say if
the if you can earn more at work I work
Le less hard or more hard people say I
work more hard because like I get more
return from my
work but the income
effect now goes the other way even if
Leisure is normal
before to get the income effect to go
the other way we need pizza to be
inferior that's not true anymore why
because think of what the income effect
does here the income effect is as the
wage goes up I'm
richer when I'm richer I want more of
all normal
Goods Leisure is a normal good so I want
more of
it so if Leisure is a normal good as is
for everyone except MIT students
that as your income goes up you want
more of it so here the income effect
offsets substitution effect without
having a weird case you don't need to be
Ramen you don't need inferior good for a
normal good the income effect offsets
substitution effect and that's why we
learn the [ __ ] income substitution
effects they're pain in the ass so like
it didn't matter for Consumer Theory
right because I said they're no giving
Goods that's why we learn them because
they do matter when it comes to factor
supply income Sol effects do matter so
in fact it's natural that think of ass
effects that offset each other let's
once again review what these effects are
the substitution effect is G every hour
of work makes it more costly to sit at
home so I'm going to work
more the income effect is wow I'm richer
now therefore I want more of all normal
Goods Leisure is a normal good so I want
more Leisure so I'm going to work
less and the best intuition I find that
effect very hard to understand
I think the best intuition is what we
call the target income model which is
what I use the example here imagine you
just simply want to work hard enough to
buy X you have a Target
income in that case by definition a
higher wage caus you to work less hard
that was the intuition that was given
here that was a Target in that was a
Target income intuition that's the
income effect dominating the
substitution
effect so whether a higher wage leads
you to work harder or less hard
or in terms of the model leads you to
take less Leisure or more Leisure will
depend on the relative size of the
income and substitution effects so in
figure
152 we've got a substitution effect
that's larger than income
effect therefore Leisure overall goes
down the higher wage caus you to take
less Leisure and therefore to work
harder but in figure
153 we have the opposite
we have an income effect that dominates
substitution
effect therefore a higher
wage causes you to take more Leisure not
less this is think about this this is a
gif and good this saying a higher price
caus you want more of something right a
higher price of leisures caus you want
more of it but it's not a weird case it
seems sensible in fact that was the
intuition that was given to me
first so here giv goods are not rare and
mythical they're real because the income
effect you don't need an inferior good
it's just the Classic case the income
effect offsets a substitution effect
okay let me pause there that is a hard
intuition and let me see if people have
questions about
that okay so here's the key
point if substitution effects
dominate then a higher wage leads to
more leads to less
Leisure so therefore if we translate
that to a Leisure demand curve that
translates to a downward
sloping Leisure demand curve demand
curve slopes down right so if you've got
I put put in the handout but if you've
got a Leisure demand curve whereas
here's the amount of leisure and here's
the price of leisure which is the wage
then it slops down
okay basically the the higher the wage
the less Leisure you
want but we don't care about leisure in
the end we care about Labor this
translates when we do labor to wage to a
rising supply
curve that as the wage goes up you get
more
labor so once again we model this but we
we care about this we're talking about
Labor Supply remember at the end of the
day that's what this part of the lecture
is
called so what it's saying is if
substitution effects dominate we get the
typical upward sloping supply curve we
know and love indeed I already when I T
about when we talked about Labor marks
before that's what I
assumed but in fact that doesn't have to
happen if income effects
dominate then in that case if income
effects dominate you're going to get a
downward sloping demand
if income effects dominate you get a
main curve that looks like
that and a supply curve that's backwards
you're going to get a downward sloping
supply curve which is pretty
screwy but that's the
implication if income effects dominate
then higher wages lead to less
work which is pretty crazy okay even
though it was the initial
intuition we were just used to Upward
sloping Supply curves this class this
would end up with a downward sloping
supply
curve okay questions about
that okay so this is very this is really
really
important because
fundamentally one of the key policy
issues in America is about how much
workers get paid for example should we
tax work should there be a minimum wage
what about Unions that's all about how
much workers get paid well it's sort of
hard to evaluate that issue if we don't
know what effect that's going to have if
paying workers more is going to cause
them to work more hard or less hard
that's pretty fundamental to understand
the implications of raising the
wage so what do we actually know well
the evidence is actually fascinating
what do we know about Labor Supply it's
fascinating what I'm going to do to
understand this is I'm gonna talk about
two
groups prime age that is like 25 to 64
year old married men and married
women obviously other groups inide let's
just focus on those for a second I want
you to start by casting your mind back
to 50 years ago when I was a kid when I
was a kid almost every Prim AG man
worked and fewer than half Prime AG
women
worked okay it was a very different
labor market than it is
today okay so what I want you to think
about in that world I want you to think
about an to it the size of substitution
and income effects so let's talk about
married
men and married
women and let's talk about their
substitution
effect and their income effect and I
just want you to think about relative
sizes so let's start with the
substitution effect who do we think
would have a bigger sub in the world of
50 years ago the typical sort of sexist
world where men were were the bread
winners women still work but much less
than men who do we think had the bigger
substitution
effect and why think about what drives
the substitution
effect and they help give the
answer yeah
Al well not better is normative there's
an alternative men there's no
alternative if you were a man good Lord
you didn't spend time with your children
no man did that and you couldn't go
golfing because your friends were all
working basically men 50 years ago like
golfed and worked it's kind of what they
did okay so basically there's no
substitution you got to work what else
are you going to do women had
Alternatives they were the primary child
rearing or even if they weren't many
women without kids just simply work that
was an alternative it wasn't viewed
negatively
socially maybe not 60 years ago uh but
it was the alternative so the
substitution effect could be quite big
for women because they have Alternatives
so they can decide gee when the wage
goes
up that makes Leisure more expensive
might want to work more whereas the men
they were already working there wasn't a
lot of decision to be made yeah oh women
sorry I that's backwards
small small big okay
okay now here's an even harder one what
about the income effect I'm not going to
ask this one because it's
hard the income effect is tricky because
the income
effect is not just how responsive your
work is to income but it also depends on
how much you're already working if
you're not
working if you are not
working then there's no income
effect because my income doesn't change
when the wage goes
up right so my income changes more the
more I'm working so the income effect is
really technically it's measured as
DL or
DH
Dy times y0 times initial
income well if you're women many of them
didn't work so they had a small income
effect men they worked so income effect
was bigger now maybe not big but bigger
so you might say here the income effect
is
bigger because women didn't have an inum
effect because they weren't
working so you got a situation where
men
have I'm uh I did this wrong again [ __ ]
bigger okay so we have a situation where
men have a small substitution effect and
plausibly a bigger income effect women
have a big substitution effect and not
much of an income effect based on that
what should be the relative shapes of
their labor Supply
curves whose labor supply curve should
for sure slope up and whose would be
more uncertain
yeah women's Curve would slope up
because the substitution effect would
dominate men's we don't know sub small
the income effect might be big it's Sly
bigger than for women we don't know so
in fact we'd expect intuitively that
women would have an strong upward
sloping supply
curve and then we wouldn't
know probably backwards yeah
effect why isn't the income effects for
men kind of small because they're going
to work it might be small that's why I
saying it's uncertain it's bigger but
still probably
small
okay so so we have for women a clear big
you know we'll call this zero okay with
a clear big substit effect zero here we
know which way it goes men it's not
clear well what does the evidence say
the evidence exactly lined up with their
intuition which is women's labor Supply
curves were very strongly upward sloping
women had Fairly elastic labor Supply
the elasticity of Labor supply for
married women was about
0.5 that is for every 10% increase in
wages women were 5% harder for men it
was approximately zero maybe a little
bit negative but approx roughly speaking
zero so basically labor supply curve
shapes comported with the intuition we
get from Theory
now what do we think has happened to the
shape of women's labor supply curve over
time and
why um uh let let's Okay you sort of
skip to men let's focus just on women
what's changed for
women right but does that made their
substitution options better or Worse do
do women do do are women Freer in some
sense or less free to decide whether to
work I wouldn't say so I mean certainly
female labor participation has gone up
from less than 50 to
80% I would say if you ask many women at
work they wouldn't say they do so
because it's free they'd say do so
because they need to the family needs
the money or it's just women's work has
become in some like men's work it's sort
of socially unacceptable just hanging
out at home if you're a woman
like it was social unacceptable for a
man so in substance their substance
effects gone down because it's become
more like like men they basically now
working sort of
default the women in this class all
expect to go to work when they graduate
that was not true 60 years ago maybe
here at MIT but not most
places okay so there's sort of not much
of a substitution effect because you're
going to
work likewise your income effect has
gone up because now you have income so
women's labor supply curve has gotten
steeper they've start their labor Supply
looks more like men the amount they work
looks more like men so their lb fly
curve looks more like
men now let me come back to that answer
because part of the reason why is that
you're wrong about one
thing you might think well gee then
men's labor fly curves must be getting
flatter but they're not because men
still don't take care of the
kids okay so basically women work hard
and men work hard the difference is the
kids are now in child
care okay so your intuition which is G
women men will trade off men will become
more flexible that's wrong women became
more inflexible and Men stayed
inflexible okay and the difference is
child growth in child care okay so
basically it's a fascinating your
intuition what happened to women and
once you once they gave you the manactor
you sort of get the intuition of Why
women's labor Supply became more
inelastic became more vertical but but
it partly it's because men's didn't
adjust either and when now in World
basically in almost all couples both
Partners
work okay questions about
that okay I want to end with an
interesting
application from one of my really
favorite interesting empirical studies
in
economics which is thinking about free
trade we haven't talked about trade yet
we'll come to that in a few lectures but
I'll use some basic intuition and the
impacts on child
labor now um what I want to do is I want
to set up the problem but I don't want
to rush so we'll solve it next time so
Andrew let's have these last couple
diagrams be the first couple diagrams in
the next lectures hand out so I want to
set up the problem but I want to rush to
solve it because it's a really important
intuition okay a common criticism of
free
trade is that will induce child labor
they will say people will say gee if
there's more free trade that means
country want to sell more stuff that
means kids are going to have to go to
work and that's a major reason to not
allow free
trade so we can actually Analyze That
and show that intuition intuition may be
wrong to see that let's talk about the
country of
Vietnam I was just in Vietnam this
spring before before the early
1990s
Vietnam could not export its main crop
which is
rice because there was all these because
war was going on the US was still mad at
Vietnam there was a lot of
barriers so Vietnam could not export its
main crop which is rice so let's look at
figure
154 to show what effect that has and
also Vietnam also wouldn't let Farmers
export R it wasn't just other countries
wouldn't want it Vietnam wouldn't let it
be exported Vietnam said no we need the
rice here for our people we won't export
it so the rice Market in Vietnam is
described in figure 154 on the XX you
have quantity of rice on the YX you have
the price you have a supply of rice
that'll be unchanged for this example s
subv that's a domestic supply of rice in
Vietnam and you had a domestic demand
for Rice that's D
subv and the government said we have to
we cannot export R so what that meant
was the rice Market will be forced at
equilibrium at that quota line at a
quantity QV and a price PV that would be
the government enforced
equilibrium okay what happened after
1989 is they left Vietnam export RS and
in particular after 1994 when the US
normalized relations with
Vietnam um they could export RS to the
US what happened was that led to a
massive increase in demand for race
because the the rest of the world now
wanted cheap Vietnamese rice that
shifted out the demand curve from DV to
DW now it's the world demand for
Rice okay shift after dvdw which meant
that Vietnam now produced more rice at a
higher
price and the criticism is well GE to
produce more rice you need more labor
and a lot of that labor comes from kids
and we see that criticism in a diet
in figure 155 I think I will get through
this now just bear with me might go one
minute late figure 155 is diag for child
labor in Vietnam on the x-axis is the
amount of child labor on the y- axis is
the wage and pre-trade we're in
equilibrium with L1 kids working W1
working at a wage of
W1 now we have free trade what free
trade does is it increases the demand
for labor the price has gone up so if
you flip back to figure 154 you need
more rice Q subw is higher than QV how
you produce more rice you have more
workers some of those workers are kids
so that shifts out the demand for child
labor from D1 to
D2 and therefore increases the amount of
child labor from L1 to
L2 and that is the story for why free
trade increases child
labor what do it
Miss what it misses is the price of rice
also went up and when the price of rice
went up what did that do it made the
Vietnamese richer as an American I was
quite frankly as someone who grew up
during the Vietnam War I was a little
sort of afraid to go to Vietnam what
would they think of Americans they love
Americans and their hero is Bill Clinton
why because Bill Clinton normalized
trade with Vietnam and let them sell the
rice in America and their wealth went up
enormously what do you do when you're
richer you buy nor of normal Goods
what's a normal good your kid not
working people want people Vietnam care
about their kids they want the kids in
school not working so while it's true
the demand for child labor went up the
supply of child labor decreased because
people didn't have didn't want their
kids to work so there's an opposite
inward shift of the supply
curve and indeed if that shift was big
enough you see shift from S1 S2 if it
was big enough all the way to S3 child
labor Could Fall In other words even
though there was more demand for child
labor the Vietnamese were so richer so
much richer they said we don't want our
kids to work so there's an increase in
an reduction in child labor Supply that
offset the increase in demand and you
could actually see child labor falling
there was a careful empirical study done
of trade liberalization Vietnam and it
found exactly that that Freer trade led
to less child child labor not more a
fascinating example how you can use
basic economics to overcome a sort of
what you might think is an easy
intuition all right I'm going to stop
there sorry to go long we'll come back
and talk about the minimum wage and
capital Supply next time