Good afternoon, all.
Thank you for attending this
exciting session on translation.
This session is all about how
we get our discoveries out
of the lab and to the clinic,
into the hands of patients
and doctors and into companies.
My name is Ellen Roach.
I'm an associate professor
in mechanical engineering
and the Institute for Medical
Engineering and Science.
And I have the privilege of
chairing today's session.
We are so lucky to have four
distinguished speakers today
who will speak to us about
different aspects of translating
their science and technologies.
I could listen to these
speakers for hours,
but we have a short
amount of time,
so I'll introduce
everyone at a high level
now and keep the talks
moving afterwards.
So first, we have
Professor Andrew Lo.
Professor Lo is the Charles
and Susan T Harris Professor
of finance at Sloan and the
director of the Laboratory
for Financial Engineering.
Professor Lo will speak with
us about financing translation,
describing the inflection
point of biomedicine
and proposing new business
models to translate technology.
Next, we'll hear
about translation
through multiple startups
in the area of nanomedicine.
Professor Sangeeta Bhatia is
the John and Dorothy Wilson
Professor of Health
Sciences and Technology
and electrical engineering
and computer science.
She is a Howard Hughes
Medical institute investigator
and directs the marble center
for cancer and nanomedicine.
Professor Bhatia
will speak to us
about translating nanomedicine
technologies for cancer
detection and describe her
prolific co-founder timeline
in translating technology
out of her lab.
She will then describe how
she supports other faculty
in translating their technology
and the incredible impact
and success of the
Faculty Founder Initiative
she has created.
Professor Hugh Herr
will speak next.
Professor Herr is a professor
of media arts and sciences
at MIT Media Lab and the
co-director of the K. Lisa Yang
Center for Bionics.
Professor Herr's work
melds human physiology
and electromechanics
to produce systems
that emulate human biomechanics,
improving mobility for those
with paralysis and limb loss.
He will speak about how he
has translated technology
from the Biomechatronic
Mechatronics Lab
to enhance human
physical capability
through for-profit and
non-profit mechanisms.
Finally, Professor Alex
Shalek will speak to us
about engineering our biomedical
ecosystem for global impact.
Professor Shalek is the
J.W. Kiekhaefer Professor
in the Institute for Medical
Engineering and Science
and the Department of Chemistry.
He is also a member of the Broad
Institute, the Koch Institute,
and the Ragon Institute,
and the director
of the Institute for Medical
Engineering and Science.
Alex will describe how his
group develop and apply tools
to understand balance
in tissue ecosystems.
He'll describe the
opportunities at MIT
for translation, how we can
engineer the right solutions
to key problems, leveraging
global partners to scale
and addressing
systemic challenges.
He will conclude the
session describing
how this is achieved through
broad collaboration, which
will create a natural segue
into the next session.
I do hope you enjoy these talks
and you are inspired by them.
I thank the speakers in
advance for sharing examples
of their work and for imparting
their wisdom and philosophies
on biomedical translation.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
So I'd like to start
by thanking Ellen
for that generous
introduction and for chairing
the session and
President Kornbluth
for putting together this event.
Thank you all for
being here as well.
I'm a financial economist
by training and trade.
And you might be wondering,
who ordered that?
What am I doing here in an event
of otherwise serious scientists,
clinicians, and
biopharma leaders?
Well, no matter what
field you're in,
no matter what you're
doing, no matter
what your goals are, at
some point or another,
if you're looking to
affect patient lives,
you will need money,
and that means
you'll be speaking my language.
[LAUGHTER]
So what I'm going
to be talking about
is how we engage
in the financing
of translational medicine.
And to begin, clearly we are at
a biomedical inflection point.
And I'll give you two
illustrations of that.
The first comes from
my world of finance.
This is a chart of the 30
best-selling drugs in the year
2000.
I'm sure you can't see
the specific drugs.
But highlighted in
blue are those drugs
that came out of
academia or biotech
four 26 out of the top 30
came out of big pharma.
And in the good old days,
that's how translation occurred,
really through big
pharma efforts.
Fast forward 18 years
to 2018, and now here
are the 30 best-selling
drugs in that year.
Highlighted in blue
are those that came out
of biotech and academia--
24 of the top 30, nine
out of the top 10.
Medicine has changed.
The second way.
We know that
biomedical advances are
at an inflection point is
because my MIT colleagues told
me so.
[LAUGHTER]
In particular, Susan Hockfield,
Tyler Jackson, Phil Sharp
in 2016 published a report
titled Convergence--
The Convergence of the Life
Sciences, Physical Sciences,
and Engineering.
All of the different
fields are coming together
to produce remarkable
advances for medicine.
And the insiders
in this industry
call it the omics revolution.
Every one of these omics has
experienced tremendous advances
over the last even five
years, never mind 10 or 20,
with the exception of one.
There's been one omics that's
been a bottleneck to progress,
and that is economics--
[LAUGHTER]
--because we got to
pay for this stuff.
And the business
models that we're using
are still tied to the
past and haven't really
taken into account all of the
innovation that's going on.
So I want to talk to you
about that omics economics
and, in particular, describe
how translation occurs
at a high level at a
caricature from my perspective
as an economist.
So what is the life cycle
of biomedical innovation?
Well, it begins here
in the laboratory
with a researcher and an idea.
And that idea sparks,
usually, a collaboration
of additional experts that come
together to take that idea,
round it out, put it into
various different tests,
experiments we call them.
And ultimately, when
all is said and done,
and you collect the data,
and you've got the results,
and it looks like
you've got something
that might one day help a
patient, what do you do?
You publish a paper, right?
[BUZZER]
Well, wrong.
[LAUGHTER]
Do not do that.
What you are supposed to do--
and it's remarkable how many
life scientists
aren't aware of this--
you file a patent disclosure,
after which you are totally
free to publish our paper.
And this is important because,
while many people think
that filing a patent is
somehow dirty and too
commercial and
pecuniary, and you're
getting involved in the world
of money, what you're doing
is reserving the right for
somebody else, typically
an investor, to basically
benefit, get a rate of return
for deploying capital
to take that idea
and translate it into medicine.
So after you publish a paper,
do some more experiments.
You're able to now
demonstrate, perhaps
in animals, that maybe this
actually might turn into a drug.
And so at that point, you're
able to get your patent,
be able to create a
company, perhaps rent
some space at Lab Central,
and then ultimately start
going through the very
long and important process
of clinical testing, at
the end of which you might,
if you're lucky--
[CHA-CHING SOUND EFFECT]
--get a drug.
But more often than not--
[EXPLOSION SOUND EFFECT]
--you will fail.
And that, in a nutshell, is
what translation is all about.
What makes this process
very challenging
is that you need money
every step of the way.
And if that money is
interrupted for any reason,
then the whole thing
pretty much ends.
Biomedical innovation is
binary, and that kind of risk
is something that most
investors are simply not
able to withstand, so we
need better ways of financing
translational medicine.
And that's what I would like
to talk to you about today.
Here's an idea-- instead of
developing drugs one at a time,
why not pool these
various different drugs
into a portfolio, maybe
even across universities?
Imagine, for example,
a business model
that looks like this, where
on the left hand side,
you've got multiple
universities pooling
their intellectual property to
create a vehicle that investors
can participate in.
Why multiple universities?
Well, because MIT
can't do everything,
and so we have to leave
room for some other folks.
The bottom line is that we don't
know where the next breakthrough
is going to come from because
of the complexity of the life
sciences, and so we
want to be able to have
multiple shots on goal even
beyond a single university.
But if we can construct
that portfolio,
manage it, create programs
around the most promising ideas,
not necessarily requiring
faculty to give up tenure
and become CEOs when they
really don't want to do that,
and they want to
do their research
and let other folks who are
ideally suited to manage
the businesses
grow that business,
that's really what
we're talking about.
With this kind of
business model,
all of the various
different stakeholders
will get what they
want, and they
will be able to
contribute what they can.
What do we call
this business model?
Well, I call it
tech transferase.
[LAUGHTER]
And for those of you
who are laughing,
you are critical for the
success of this business model.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Hi, I'm Sangeeta.
I'm trained as a
physician and an engineer.
And I'm going to
tell you a story--
a case study, really,
that came out of my lab
in the field of
nanomedicine-- and use it
to illustrate how you can
translate through startups,
in the way Andrew described, and
how it helps to advance things
to patients, but also how it
can drive the next generation
of innovation here at MIT.
And then I'll close
with some ideas
about how we hope to
enable more faculty to do
in this next chapter
that MIT is embarking on.
So to begin, I want to tell
you what nanomedicine is.
It's nanotechnology
applied to medicine.
And nanotechnology
itself is a field
of materials that are
smaller than 100 manometers.
Human hair is 100 microns, so
this is 1,000 times smaller.
Now, this is a field
with two origin stories.
On the left, you see microchips,
semiconductor fabrication.
These drive all of
your smartphones.
And you may know the
new NVIDIA chip has
feature sizes of 4 manometers.
So using what we call
top down fabrication,
we can make very
teeny, tiny things.
The other origin story comes
from the world of chemistry.
On the right, what you
see are quantum dots.
These are when you
assemble nanomaterials
by collecting atoms and
creating emergent properties.
And this is an example of
quantum dots, something
that Moungi Bawendi shared
the Nobel Prize for chemistry
last year here at MIT.
And these materials
are really cool.
They're exactly the
same composition,
but they glow different colors
simply based on their size.
So there's a whole world of
material science and physics
happening at the nanoscale
where properties-- electronic,
magnetic, optical-- emerge
when you make them small.
And what's really
exciting in this moment
is that if you think about
what that does for medicine,
it turns out there's also
biological properties
at this length scale.
And if you think
hard about it, it's
not surprising that
this is the case,
because if you look at this
molecular ruler, actually,
the nanoscale is the scale at
which biology communicates.
DNA is 2 manometers in width.
A receptor is 10
manometers in size.
A virus is 100 manometers.
So that is the scale that
all of the interesting things
are happening.
And in fact, the field has
made many, many nanomaterials
that have been in clinical
trials and in humans.
In fact, many of you got
one of these nanomaterials.
The lipid nanoparticle
on the top
there was the encapsulation
for the mRNA vaccine,
both of the mRNA
vaccines for COVID.
So these materials have now
been in millions of people
and been proven to be safe.
And as a community, over about
20 years now around the world,
people have been
working in nanomedicine
and discovering what is the
biology of the nanoscale.
And I'm not going to go through
everything on the right,
but just to say that we're
finding out all kinds of things
about the size and shape of
a material, dictating how it
interacts with the human body.
So in my lab, what
we've been doing
is trying to think about what
could this do for cancer.
Now, cancer is a
disease that you
know could be
really best treated
if we could find it early.
And some cancers, unfortunately,
can grow for eight to 10 years
before being detected even by
the best screening technologies
that we have today.
So we had the idea, what if
we can make a machine that
can travel through the
bloodstream, look for cancer,
and when it finds it, report
it to the outside world?
This is how the machine works.
So here you see
100-nanometer particle.
It's circulating
in the bloodstream.
And it's going to leak out into
the surrounding tissue, which
is a tumor.
Once it's inside the tumor,
it's designed to detect enzymes
that tumors make.
Those of you who are
biologists, these are proteases.
They're depicted here in yellow.
And these enzymes can
activate these materials.
Because it's a
catalytic reaction,
each enzyme can release
1,000 reporters.
So this is an amplification.
And those reporters are now even
tinier than the first material.
These are about 3
manometers in size.
So when they get back
in the bloodstream,
now they are small enough to
be filtered and concentrated
twenty-fold by the
kidney into the urine.
So this starts out as a shot.
And an hour later, you collect
something in the urine that is
20,000-fold amplified for
every copy of an enzyme.
So we've been working
on this in the lab.
The first paper was
published in 2013.
We started a company
called Glympse Bio, like,
get a glimpse inside the body.
And we did exactly what
Andrew directed us to do.
We first filed a patent,
then raised the capital.
I co-founded it with
my postdoc, Gabe Kwong,
who is now a full
professor at Georgia Tech.
And that company did things at
a scale with dedicated teams
that we couldn't do here at MIT.
We did scale-up manufacturing.
We went to the FDA.
[INAUDIBLE] two
species toxicology.
We did human clinical trials.
And now they're on their
way in liver cancer,
trying to show that
this could work
to find liver tumors
in patients that
have advanced fibrotic disease.
So that's been very exciting.
That's been happening
outside of campus since 2015.
But what's exciting about this
is that the students in the lab
now are unlocked.
They can see that
this can happen.
There's a path to patience,
and they get more innovative.
And so what did they
start thinking about?
Well, what if you could make
a urine test like a pregnancy
test?
What if it could be on paper,
and you could read out a cancer
test at the point of care?
So we invented that.
What if you were
interested in lung cancer?
You could breathe out like a
breathalyzer in 10 minutes.
So we invented that.
What if you could find
out where the tumor was
and if it had spread?
So we invented a
version like that.
And what if you could use AI to
design these materials with--
by design instead of creating
libraries like we used to?
And so we're about to publish
a paper with Microsoft on that.
So there's all kinds of
things that the translation
into the company then
fed back into MIT.
Finally, we have physicians in
the labs, not just engineers.
And they decided that this would
be good, not just for cancer,
but for something that may
be surprise all of you--
pediatric pneumonia.
When you have a child in
the ER that has pneumonia,
the best thing to know is do
they need antibiotics or not?
Is it bacterial or is it viral?
So we're working
on a breath test
to be able to detect that in 10
minutes with foundation support.
And this whole
field now has a lot
of investment coming
in from places
like ARPA-H. So
the innovation is
keeping going by
virtue of having
done the start up company.
So Glympse here I
started in 2015.
I want to just say that
MIT is an incredible place
to start companies.
And as an academic entrepreneur,
you learn as you go.
This is a muscle.
You can see that my
entrepreneurial journey
accelerated over time.
And I feel very lucky to be
here, not just geographically,
but with colleagues like
Bob Langer and Phil Sharp,
who gave their time and
their wisdom and advice
about how to stay a professor
and be an entrepreneur.
Now, I will say that in
this next chapter of MIT,
I hope we can do even more.
And that's because,
as I did this,
I found that very
few of my women
colleagues had a
foot in both worlds.
And in fact, MIT is
an incredible place
to make that observation
because we really
have a playbook for how to
handle gender disparities, which
are documented in this amazing
book if you haven't read it,
the playbook is--
make a team of people
to address the problem,
gather the data, which we did,
find institutional champions
like Anantha Chandrakasan and
Maria Zuber and now Sally,
and talk about what addressing
this gap would address.
So we've been doing that.
Finally, do experiments.
So we have the Faculty
Founder Initiative started.
It's just celebrated
its three-year birthday.
And I'm happy to tell any of you
who want to learn more about it
how we've been helping these
21 amazing faculty unlock
their own inventions.
19 of them are now
building startups,
and we hope that all of them
become serial entrepreneurs
in this next chapter.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Good afternoon.
My name is Hugh Herr, and here
you see my beautiful legs.
From the knee down, I'm a
bunch of nuts and bolts--
three computers the size of your
thumbnail, six sensors, a muscle
tendon-like actuator.
These devices
propel me as I walk,
and I'm actually able to
walk in a normal fashion.
Years ago, I founded a
company called Bionics Medical
Technologies that translated
the prosthesis outside of MIT.
Today, they've been fit
to tens of thousands
of people, many wounded
US soldiers as well.
So at the New K. Lisa Yang
Center for Bionics here at MIT,
we're taking the next
step, pun intended.
The legs that I'm wearing
are intrinsically controlled.
They're not connected
to my brain.
So there's algorithms
running on chip.
So what we want
to do is actually
link the next
generation of prostheses
to the brain, to the spinal
cord, and central brain
via muscles and tendons.
So we're actually
not only manipulating
bone and soft tissues
and surgical designs,
but we're actually putting
hardware inside the body.
This is an
osseointegrated prosthesis
where there's a titanium shaft
going through the skin membrane
into the residual limb bone.
It's a mechanical
anchoring point.
And as you can see, you
see an electrical connector
where we can pass 16 fine
wire leads from computers
on the external limb
to, for example,
electrodes inside the body
and bidirectionally singles.
So this is not a
wireless approach.
It's a wired approach.
We recently got a paper
published in Nature Medicine
a few months ago.
This is the first
bionic limb that's
completely controlled
by the brain that
restores natural movement gait.
So all these movements that you
see, all the nuance of movements
that occur biomechanically
when a person goes up and down,
steps are being mediated
through the electromechanics.
So we were also
applying our techniques
to the upper extremity.
Sorry, let me go back.
Tricky.
Well, let me try once more.
Doesn't quite work.
There we go.
This is a blocks and
blocks demonstration.
The task is how many
blocks can this person
put in the box in 60 seconds?
So we currently have the record
with our neural interfacing
technologies.
We're not only doing
brain controlled limbs,
but we're also closing the loop
where we reflect proprioception,
the sense of position, movement,
and load, and cutaneous signals,
the sense touch,
from the prosthesis
back into the nervous system.
This is a first
human subject that
received a cutaneous
interface design put forth
by my group called the
cutaneous mechano interface.
Basically, surgically, we took--
when her limb was
amputated, we took skin
from the bottom of
the foot, and we
put that skin inside
her amputated residuum,
wrapped a muscle around it.
And then we're actuating
that muscle via computer,
via the 16 fine wire leads.
This video is shot
immediately after we
stimulated the constructs,
and this is her response.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- So fascinating.
[MAN CHUCKLES]
This is just so
different from everything
else I've been feeling
the last day and a half.
- OK, so this is definitely
not residual limb--
- No.
- --or muscle stimulation?
This is pure phantom
limb sensation.
- Yeah.
I'm not feeling anything
in my limb at all.
[END PLAYBACK]
That was wonderful.
Obviously, the constructs are
physically in her residuum.
She didn't feel anything there.
She actually felt the bottom of
her foot that's no longer there.
So obviously, we're going to
put one of these devices on her,
put pressure sensing that
senses pressures as she walks
and then reflect that
into her nervous system
so she can feel the ground.
So that's the neural interfacing
part, the prosthetic part.
There's a startup company
called Muscle Metrics that's
being launched outside of MIT.
This is a technology--
so that's an exoskeleton.
It's a bionic shoe,
kind of like an e-bike
for legs, that augments
walking, running, and jumping.
This is a company I
co-founded, called
Defy, that's not only
focused on rehabilitation,
but human augmentation,
extending capability
beyond nature.
So we're using
this platform today
to also address medical needs.
So using small magnetic
spheres into weak muscle.
In the calf, for
example, after a stroke
and using magnetic
arrays on the skin,
we can track weak
muscle dynamics
and then reflect those to
control a motorized exoskeleton
to augment strength.
So I think we'd be very remiss
if the only thing we did here
at MIT is expand the
boundaries of technology.
Sadly, there's so many
areas of the world
that do not have access to
prosthetics and orthotics.
Arguably, the area of the
world with the greatest need
is in western Africa
and Sierra Leone.
As many of you know,
there's a civil war there
that ended in 2002, where
rebel forces hacked off
limbs with machetes.
Now there's tens of thousands
of people with limb loss.
So as part of the K. Lisa Yangs
Center for Bionics here at MIT,
we're actually building a
prosthetic and orthotic sector
in this war-torn nation.
What is our goal?
Sustainable care and delivery
of orthotics and prosthetics
services in Sierra Leone.
We want to increase annual
production of prosthesis
by an order of magnitude.
Our approach that
we call SCITT--
an acronym that stands for
Supply Chain Infrastructure,
Technology, and
Education-- we feel only
by having results
in all four pillars
can we introduce
sustainable change.
We're three years
into our program,
and we're experiencing
tremendous success.
We have many glorious stories.
I'll end with one such story.
This is Mohamed [INAUDIBLE].
Like tens of thousands of
other citizens of Sierra Leone,
he lost his limb
in the civil war.
As a young man, the rebel forces
were attacking his village,
and he ran, and he stepped on
a land mine and lost his limb.
We just fit a prosthesis to him.
Now he can walk freely
for the first time
without crutches or canes.
He's passionate about
soccer, and he can freely
be seen on the soccer field
enjoying his favorite game.
So just to finish up, restoring
quality of life and independence
of living for people with
physical disability is,
I believe, a moral imperative.
Disability experienced by
a friend or family member
is so common that
we just view it
as part of the human
condition, but it
doesn't have to be that way.
A great narrative in this 21st
century will be the emergence
of humans with technology,
resulting in the mitigation
of disability and unleashing
humanity's greatest potential.
Thank you so much.
[APPLAUSE]
Hi, everyone.
I'm Alex.
Thank you very much for
the opportunity to present,
and I definitely don't have any
videos that are quite that cool.
What I was hoping
to talk about today
was what I really think today's
event is all about, which
is the opportunity to come
together to really engineer
our entire ecosystem to have
global impact, as was very
beautifully illustrated by
the talks that just occurred
from Sangeeta and Hugh but
also from many of the ones that
came earlier this morning.
So before I begin, I
thought I would just
tell you a little bit about
what we do within our lab.
And fundamentally, what
our lab is interested
in is this idea of
homeostasis and tissues.
Now at MIT, I
teach 560, which is
thermodynamics for those of you
that haven't had to take it.
And as a chemistry
professor, if you gave me
a pressure and a
temperature, I could tell you
what equilibrium is
for any given reaction.
But if you ask me what
balance is in a tissue,
I wouldn't be able to tell you.
I can't tell you what that
means molecularly or cellularly.
But I know it's
important because if I
get too much of an
immune response,
I can get tissue
damage and death.
Like, I might see in an
autoimmune condition.
Or if I have too
little, I can become
susceptible to
opportunistic infections
or the outgrowth of tumors.
So a lot of what we try
and do within the lab
is to understand,
through studying
different human contexts, what
is it that defines health?
What are the deviations
that are induced by exposure
to environmental perturbations
like pathogens or pollutants?
And how could we rebalance
the system therapeutically
or prophylactically buffer
it through something
like a vaccine in
the first place?
And the reason that
it's such a good time
to think about these
sorts of questions
is that we can now
develop tools that
will let us study these
cellular ecosystems
at incredible resolution.
So just to give you a sense
of what is now possible,
because it seems relatively
science fiction-like we can take
a very small amount of cells--
so 50,000 cells, 20,000 cells,
the kinds of things that you
would have in fluids that
you might not even be aware.
So imagine scraping the
inside of your cheek.
Now rather than
saying that's too few,
we can actually load them into
innovative technologies-- many
of the ones that
you've seen earlier
that rely upon things like
microfluidics and new chemical
capture reagents.
And with these, we can actually
measure not one thing or two
things, but look at 20,000
plus variables at a time.
So really get a comprehensive
view of everything
that's happening in every cell.
And this gives us
the kinds of big data
that Caroline was talking about
earlier where we can actually
get a trillion data points just
from one individual sample.
And so just to make this a
little bit more real, what
you can do is you
can take a tissue
like the retina, where it has
this beautiful multilayered
structure.
And you can see there's
multiple different cell types,
but we don't really know
what the components are.
We don't know what
their markers are.
We can load it into
one of these devices.
And for each cell,
we can measure
thousands of different genes.
And here I'm showing
you expression
of a gene being high as white.
Black means off.
What we can then
do is we can take
a set of cells that express
the same kind of programming.
And this, we think, might
be a specific cell type.
We can take one
of those markers,
go back and label it using
standard molecular biology
approaches, and
characterize it in situ.
And so what this
does is it takes us
from a place where it would have
taken us 30 years to identify
a cell type, its markers,
and characterize it
but now do it in a week.
But what's so impressive is that
we don't just do this one cell
type at a time.
Instead, we can look at every
single cell type that's up here.
So we're not compressing 30
years of research into a week.
We're compressing hundreds
of years of research
into a single week.
So when you look at
something like this,
you can easily imagine why I
had to be at MIT as a professor
and was lucky when I
had the opportunity.
It's because I need incredible
multidisciplinary scientists
that are chemists, that are
engineers that really understand
how to apply this to
different contexts, that
can analyze the resulting data.
But it wasn't just MIT.
It was really that
I needed to be
embedded in this
incredible ecosystem
that you're all part of.
As you probably all know from
Phil's talk this morning,
MIT is surrounded by
this incredible community
of biotechs, of other
institutions, of hospitals,
of academic medical centers.
And what this does is it
creates an incredible ecosystem
in which to innovate.
And that's because,
like Colin said earlier,
the most important question
when you engineer is why?
And I interpret that a
little bit differently.
I think about that as exploring.
And what I mean by that
is really taking advantage
of this incredible ecosystem
and its willingness
to collaborate, to
go talk to people,
to identify problems
that matter.
So for example, by
talking to Sara Fortune
over at the Harvard
School of Public Health,
she said, well, that's great.
Have you ever thought about
applying it to something
like tuberculosis? which
you heard about from Brian
this morning.
Brian said 4,000 people a day.
It's 1.6 million people a year.
So that's more than any
other infectious disease
except for one year in COVID.
And this is literally
happening every year
and has been happening
for hundreds of years.
And about a quarter of
the world's population
is latently infected.
Now, the reason we don't
think about it quite so often
is because it happens that
the majority of infections
are in sub-Saharan Africa
and Southeast Asia,
as you heard about a
little from Bruce today.
So when you think about
the kinds of technologies
that you need, if you want
to tackle these problems,
well, you need things
that are deployable,
that can go out in the field.
You need them be scalable
so you can run them
across lots of patients.
You need them to be
low input, and you
need them to be
cheap so that they
can be used in all the different
contexts around the world.
And so once you have
the design constraints,
it's easy to go find incredible
partners like Chris Love over
at the Koch Institute
in chemical engineering
to take these really
cool machines that
look nice in our labs
at MIT, but could never
go out to where the
problem sites are
and re-engineer them into
really simple technologies that
accomplish the
goals that we have.
So we can take the
same kinds of things
that enable this
incredible discovery
and adapt it into really
simple portable chips that
can literally go
anywhere in the world.
What that does is
it then puts us
in a position where we
can go hop on a plane
and fly down to places
like South Africa--
and this is actually in
Durban, right at the site
that you heard about from Bruce
Walker earlier this morning--
and look at what's different
between individuals
that have more
mild or more severe
tuberculosis to find new
cellular targets that we
can use for therapies
to improve outcomes.
You don't just have
to go to South Africa.
You can actually start
applying these sorts of things
to all kinds of problems,
like pediatric stunting
due to malnutrition and
environmental infections
like environmental enteropathy.
And you find really
interesting things--
like, in the gut
right here we're
looking at the small
intestine-- and we're
finding that there are cells
that normally only show up
in the stomach, arising
in the small intestine
and preventing
absorption of nutrients.
And it gives us a
new idea of what
we might do to counteract it.
We can similarly go hop
on a plane to Thailand
with Sangetta's team,
who you just heard from,
and go and identify
new targets that we
could use to try and combat
specific stages of malaria
infection.
And what's really
cool is that when
you can do this, flying
all around the world
that your students get to
go-- and as I heard somebody
behind me say earlier,
it looks like that course
that Bruce teaches is really
fun, and it is really fun.
But you can also
improve everything
that we do here in Boston
because you make it simpler
to do things like partner with
people over at the Dana-Farber
to identify distinct
states of pancreatic cancer
and therapeutic treatment
regimes that will work better
for each.
And so engaging
people is important.
But a lot of what our roles are
as educators and in connecting
with people, as you
heard about from Andrew,
is to really empower.
And so what I like to think a
lot about is how we can go out
into the world inspired
by models like the one
you heard from
Bruce Walker today
and train people in
these technologies
so that they can apply
them to their own science
so that we can do more than
we could do independently
in our own lab.
And so I've been lucky enough
to go to a lot of places
with the team to train
individuals in places like Ghana
and Senegal in some
of these technologies
and to share what we've
learned along the way
so that others
that are interested
feel like they have at least a
place to start as they begin.
And another part of
really empowering people
is not just going out
and teaching them.
It's also working with the
innovation ecosystem around here
to take the widgets
that we build,
harden them and then sell them.
And I think that
commercialization
isn't the dirty secret.
And patenting isn't
the dirty secret.
There are things that
we do really well here.
We do that zero to one and
sometimes that one to 10.
But academia is a place that's
hard to go sometimes from 10
to 1,000.
And that's where partnerships
with local biotechs,
local industry,
with venture firms
becomes really critical to
having the kinds of impact
that we want to have
and, most importantly,
figuring out what
the right targets
are to accelerate good
outcomes for patients.
So I think that, to me,
what's so powerful about being
MIT is this
opportunity to explore,
to identify good problems.
So what are you going to do?
The opportunity to engineer
with incredible colleagues
solutions that will work.
And then to engage
others in fun science,
and then to empower others to do
the same in their own research.
And I think that
this model needs
to be extended to a place
where we can tackle all
of the emerging problems that
are showing up in the world
today.
You heard about
some of them earlier
from people like Linda,
issues with women's health.
Unfortunately, this is
probably not the last pandemic
we're going to see.
We need to think about
children and their thriving.
We have issues at
the intersection
of global of human
health and global warming
that we have to work
our way through.
And we have places
where we need to think
about how to care
for the elderly
and deal with
chronic conditions.
But I think that this model
that we can have here at MIT
taking advantage of this
incredible ecosystem
of biotechs, hospitals, and
surrounding academic centers
like HMS, puts us in a position
to actually really go after this
and to have transformative
impact for everybody everywhere.
And so with that, I just want
to thank some of our funders
and some of our collaborators.
There's too many to
throw on the screen.
But it's incredible
to be in a place
where this kind of
cooperation and partnership
is something that people love.
It's not should we do something?
It's can we do it
together and how?
And so thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]