um today we're going to turn to a new
topic remember sort of in the topics
part of the course now we talked about
Factor markets and things like investing
decisions and interest rates and things
like that now we're going to come to a
new part of the course which is talk
about international trade international
trade is one of the central econ issues
in all of economics as with every topic
we cover in this course we won't do
enough Justice we'll just do two
lectures but if you find it interesting
we have an entire course called 1454
which is all about International Trade
so sort of to give you a taste of how we
can apply the tools of basic
microeconomics to important questions
one of which is trade now here's a
question for yall how many of you have
ever given or received roses on
Valentine's
Day the unromantic MIT crowd never fails
to amaze me okay well uh turns out
Valentine's Day is uniquely badly
positioned for the us because it's in
February and that's a hard time to grow
roses so for years what we did if you
want to give roses in February had to
buy them from a especially grown from
hot houses that were specially set up to
grow roses so have them available in the
winter to deal with this inefficiency of
a flower-based holiday being in February
AR we had to have special special
production of roses well that changed
because it turns out that the perfect
place in the world to grow roses is
right around Colombia and Ecuador in
South America they're perfectly tempered
they're on the equator you can always
grow roses there very coste effectively
indeed when I visited Colombia and was
driving around there are these enormous
Rose Farms they got to stop at one they
have 15 literally this Rose farm we sto
that shipped shipped out thousands of
roses every single day to all over the
world they even had different sections
for different countries so in Russia
they like long stem roses they had a
Russian section with long stem roses
they had a Us section with the kind of
roses we like it was an incredible
production and it's easy because it's
warm there all year so the question is
is that a good thing or not on the one
hand we get cheap roses and if you all
were a little more romantic you might
value that you might value having
cheaper roses that you could buy or
maybe you would be more romantic maybe
you're just romantic but fiscally
prudent with cheaper roses maybe you can
give more roses to your loved ones on
the other hand all the guys who had jobs
producing roses have lost their jobs
there were presumably hundreds not
thousands of people involved in growing
these roses in the US they're not out of
work because we get them from
Colombia this debate over the fact that
consumers get Goods cheaper but
producers lose their jobs is the heart
of the debate over International Trade
okay this is a particularly important
topic right now because
traditionally The Divide over
international trade as I mentioned when
I talked about voluntary export
restraints was strally broke down along
party lines with Republicans favoring
free trade and Democrats opposing free
trade that's sort of reversed over the
last several decades the largest free
trade initiative of the last 50 years
was Bill Clinton's NAFTA a Democrats
Bill the North American Free Trade
Agreement which opened up trade between
the US Mexico and Canada in a very free
basis and the biggest opponent of free
trade in the white in the over office in
the last 50 years was Donald Trump who
used TR Tools of trade to go after China
to clear sort of economic war of China
in particular um Donald Trump imposed a
tariff which is a tax on imported goods
from
China um so in fact parties reversed now
it turns out basically now we a
situation where everybody's against free
trade indeed presid President Biden has
kept in a lot of the Trump anti-trade
practices that were in place free trade
is very unpopular right now okay now the
extent to which countries participate in
international trade is is described by
two quantities there's
exports those are Goods produced
domestically but consumed
abroad and there's
Imports which are Goods produced abroad
and consumed
domestically so exports are Goods that a
country sells to the rest of the world
Imports our Goods a country buys from
the rest of the world currently in the
US we have about two trillion do worth
of exports we currently export about $2
trillion doar worth of goods and we
import about 3.2 trillion so exports are
trillion Imports are 3.2 trillion
ion the difference Imports minus
exports Imports minus exports we call
the trade
deficit so we have a $1.2 trillion trade
deficit that means we import about $1.2
trillion more worth of goods than we
export this was a large focus of the
Trump presidency and of many
politicians as a sign was it was as a
sign of us weakness that we have this
giant trade deficit with other countries
they were exporting quite more than they
were importing but in fact that
intuition is completely
wrong and to see why let's start with a
simple
example okay suppose you and your best
friend both love
Pokemon and you love all the Pokemon
equally you want to collect them all
okay you got to catch them all you got
you love all the Pokemon equally you
love Pokemon your friend Lov Pokémon and
you valow them all pretty equally so
let's say that uh you have two Pikachus
and your friend has two jigglypuffs and
let's say you and your friend think
Pikachus and jigglypuffs are pretty much
worth the same thing I'm not a Pokemon
if it'sit youan enough to know if that's
true but let's say they're roughly worth
the same thing so let's say you go to
your friend and say look I have two
Pikachus you have two jigglypuffs I'm
GNA trade you one Pikachu for one
Jigglypuff and your friend says yeah
that's great I'd love that deal I don't
have any jiggly I I don't have any
Pikachus so you make the trade and you
go from two Pikachus and no jigglypuffs
to one Pikachu and one Jigglypuff and
your friend goes from Two jigglypuffs
and no Pikachus to one Jigglypuff and
one
Pikachu now what you've just done is
created a Pikachu trade
deficit think about it you used to have
two Pikachus you in I'm sorry you you
you've just created I'm sorry a
Jigglypuff trade deficit you've just
imported one jiggly
puff and you've exported zero
jigglypuffs so you've created a
Jigglypuff trade deficit you could see
you know presidents ranting about the
Jigglypuff trade deficit America will
always be a second class Nation as long
as we have a Jigglypuff trade deficit
you might say well that's silly and
you'd be right that is silly but it's no
sillier than worrying about the general
trade deficit indeed let's just um
imagine
we replaced you with the United
States your friend with
Columbia Pikachu's with dollars and
jigglypuffs with
roses then we just made the same trade
we just sent them dollars to buy
roses it made us better off because we
wanted the Roses it made Columbia better
off because they want our dollars so who
lost no one
lost it was just a trade that make both
sides better off which is what trading
does we've we've increased we've created
a deficit with
Colombia but only because the deficit is
measured in dollars not in
welfare yes we have a trade deficit but
we also have a rose
Surplus okay and just like we don't care
about Jigglypuff deficits versus Pikachu
surpluses we don't really care about
dollar deficits versus good
surpluses okay we're happy to make this
trade and indeed blocking this trade
would lower social welfare for the same
reasons that blocking any
trade where the marginal benefits exceed
the marginal cost lower social
welfare okay that's a fundamental
initions of the First Fundamental law of
welfare
economics which is that basically
anytime there's a trade where the
marginal benefits keep the marginal
costs you should allow that trade to be
made if you don't welfare is lower and
that in a nutshell is why economists
support free trade that's it and we'll
go through the math and stuff like that
through this lecture but that's really
the intuition is that economists support
free
trade because if there's a trade that
both parties want to make uh we should
let it
happen okay now of course this is much
more complicated in
reality one complication arises because
the issue we've just been discussing in
the last few
which is market
failures trades only make both parties
better off if you're in a perfectly
competitive market if not they might not
make both parties better
off another issue is that we might care
differently about winners and losers
remember I've discussed in this class
how the classic definition of social
welfare simply adds up producer consumer
surplus we said that has some nasty
implications like for example we're
totally indifferent between a perfectly
competitive outcome and a perfectly
price discriminating monopolist outcome
we're perfectly indifferent between
consumers getting some Surplus and
consumers getting no Surplus that
doesn't feel
right likewise we might not be
indifferent between people getting
cheaper roses and other people losing
their
jobs okay and as a result the standard
model might not work in reality but it's
important to understand the standard
model first it's important to understand
why Economist favor free trade and then
we can talk about in the real world why
there might be rationals for opposing it
okay so that's the setup what we want to
talk about International
Trade I'm then going to to understand
naal trade I'm going introduce a new
tool into our toolkit which is the
production possibilities Frontier the
ppf the production possibilities
Frontier
the production proess abilities
Frontier is going to A New
Concept we've talked about economies of
scale economies of scale is the idea if
you get twice as big or do you produce
twice as
much now we're talking about A New
Concept economies of
scope economies of scope are relevant
when you the firm produces multiple
different
Goods an economy of scope arises when
producing one good makes you more
productive at producing the other good a
dis economy of scope arises when
producing One Good Makes You worse at
producing the other
good and we illustrate this economies of
scope or dis economy scope through a
production possibility Frontier as an
example let's go to figure
181 F figure
181a okay here we have an economy scope
so let's let's think of a simple example
as always it's good easier with two
goods let's think of yourself as the
firm you're the firm and you produce two
things you produce exams and problem
sets Okay that's what you do you're
producing that's life at MIT right your
firm in MIT produce exams problems
that's set your life for four years okay
now imagine that um you have a certain
amount of inputs and obviously you can
vary your inputs and that could lead to
economies of scale twice as much time
studying could double your score or it
could less than double your score that's
economies of scale okay but now I'm
saying let's hold the time constant say
a certain amount of time you want to
spend studying now the question is on
how much time you spend studying which
is the economy of scale question but how
you devote your time which is economy of
scope
question and let's say for example that
the course has 10 problem sets worth 20
points
each or one exam worth two worth 200
points that's the way the grading in
this course works and your goal is to
get the best possible
grade well you can decide how to devote
your time between working on problem
sets and studying for the
exam imagine it's multiple exams with
200 to make it a little more continuous
okay there's multiple exams worth 200
points total so you can decide how to
devote your time between throughout the
semester by working on problem sets or
studying for the
exam so let's say for example you decide
you're going to spend all all your time
studying for the exam and none working
on problem sets then you're at the x
intercept in in the linear PBF you get a
perfect score in the exam but zero on
problem sets
likewise if you decide to spend all your
time on problem sets you might get a
perfect score on problem sets but you'll
get zero on the
exam okay the question we've drawn the
first graph is it's linear literally
it's a equal tradeoff every point you
give up on an exam you get in a problem
set but in fact there's strong reasons
to believe that there' be economies of
scope between doing problem sets and how
you do the exam or studying for exam
doing the problem sets because the same
work the more time you spend on problem
sets the better you might do in exams
the more time you spend studying for
exams the better you might do on problem
sets that would lead to an economy of
scope and an outward bending
ppf okay that lead you on scope and and
basically uh you'd have a convex
production possibilities Frontier the
convex production possibilities Frontier
arises when it's more efficient to
produce Goods
jointly than it is to produce them
separately so it's ever more efficient
to produce Goods jointly than separately
then that will give you the convex
production possibility Frontier we call
that an economy of scope okay it's more
effici do stuff together than do them
separately question about
that now you can also get dis economies
of
scope okay that would be Illustrated in
figure 181b that would be a
concave um production possibility
Frontier where literally you're better
off doing one or the other but the
combination of the two makes you
worse now it's hard to see that in our
example let me give you an examp real
world example of this which is when I
was an MIT undergraduate I was a pretty
good tennis player as on the MIT tennis
team JV okay wasn't great but I was on
the tennis team okay and but I'd never
tried squash before and people said
you're a college you know you're you're
an elitist East coaster you got to play
Squash okay so I decided fine I'll go
try squash Well turns out tennis is all
about not using your wrist and squash is
about using your
wrist tennis you're about trading that
ball flat squash you're about sort of
slicing it and hitting using your wrist
and it turned out the more I played
squash the more screwed up my tennis
game and the more I played the more
screwed up my squash game that was a
diseconomy of scope if I can use such a
sort of an elitist example of a
diseconomy of scope okay where doing one
made me worse at the other
one okay so both things can be true you
can have both economies of scope and dis
economies of
scope in your production possibility
Frontier questions about
that okay with that in mind now we want
to turn to our classic Model of trade
we're going to talk about this is really
one topic sorry I wrote this with a thin
chalk it's it's hard to see comparative
advantage and models of
trade so we're going to turn to the
topic
of comparative
advantage and
trade okay now let's we're going to the
way we think about international trade
in convenient way is we use what's
called 2 by two models this is the
Workhorse of international trade if you
st 15 1454 this is where you'll start
1454 two by two trade models two
countries with two
goods there's no money in these models
it's two countries two goods so let's
for example imagine our two countries
are the US and
Colombia and our two goods are roses and
computers so imagine world with just two
goods in them roses and
computers and just two countries that
produce those goods the US and Colombia
the idea is Colombia it is relatively
easy to grow
roses because the weather conditions are
such but in the US it's relatively easy
to make computers because we have highly
skilled
workers so that's the setup of the model
so we're going to put particular
examples on it here's a particular
example this is the way a 2X two model
looks so for example let's say we have
two goods we have
roses and computers let's say we're
talking about a dozen roses versus a
computer okay so this is a dozen roses
versus a
computer okay and then we have
Colombia and the
US okay and let's say that the only
input to producing these Goods is labor
obviously untrue certainly with
computers there's a lot of capital
involved but once again we're going to
start with this easy model two goods two
countries one input obviously all those
numbers can expand you can have two
goods two countries six inputs or six
countries eight Goods four inputs
anything can go on but life can be
easiest if they have two countries two
goods one input the input is
labor and that input produces we're
going to have a constant return scale
model where basically we're going to
Simply say that produce to produce one
carton of roses in Colombia takes one
worker okay takes one
worker okay uh I'm sorry takes one hour
of Labor these are hours of
Labor so there's one carton of roseen in
Columbia takes one hour of Labor is one
computer takes eight hours of Labor
in the US to produce one carton of roses
takes two hours of
Labor and to produce one carton and one
computer takes three hours of
labor now based on these numbers we can
draw the
ppfs for the US and for Columbia and
they're going to be linear I haven't put
any economies of scope in here I've just
made them linear so if you look at
figure
182 here are the PPS for Columbia in the
US in a given day if we think of a
budget of 24 hours so imagine we're
going to do the ppfs for a given
remember ppfs are about for a given set
of inputs here this inputs is going to
be 24 hours of Labor before it was two
it was a certain amount of time you had
studying now it's 24 hours of labor for
a given set of inputs which is 24 hours
of Labor what can we produce well in
Colombia with 24 hours of Labor we could
produce 24 cartons of roses or three
computers or some combination of the
two in the US we could have 12 carts of
roses or eight computers or some
combination in
between the line connecting those is the
ppf the ppf shows you the combinations
you can have for a given level of inputs
and in our example it's linear just to
make life easy you could obviously make
it more complicated the economies a
scope but this econom a scope but it's
easiest if it's linear so i' got these
simple prod simple linear production
processes one
input constant marginal
cost okay it's just literally constant
marginal product I'm sorry constant
marginal product of labor constant
marginal product of labor literally
every time you want to produce uh
another row it takes one unit of Labor
in Columbia two in the US okay so lots
of assumptions floating around here
constant marginal product of labor one
input two countries to Goods okay
questions about that let me pause this
is a hard but important model let me see
if there's questions about how this is
set
up
okay
now we want to ask who has the
advantage in producing these goods and
the way we want to ask it is through the
lens of
comparative
advantage that is we don't want to ask
who's better at it we want to ask ask
who's relatively better at
it so for example who has the
comparative advantage in roses well
Colombia we to answer this question we
go back to opportunity cost and the
reason we think of things in relative
terms because then we can express the
opportunity cost mathematically what is
the opportunity cost of producing a box
of roses in Columbia what do you have to
give up to get a box Rose in Columbia
what do you give up yeah yeah what Hour
1 hour but what does that give up but
it's all the hour time
yeah in Colombia you give up uh you give
up 1/8 of a computer that's exactly
right so it's time okay I love the
celebration we got the answers right
that's good you celebrate that you're
doing a great job okay so in Colombia to
the opportunity cost of a box of
roses which takes an hour is 1/8 of a
computer which also takes an hour in the
us now person us an hour what's the
what's the opportunity cost of a box of
roses two-thirds of a
computer okay so the opportunity cost of
a box of roses in Colombia the
opportunity cost of box R of Columbia
is8 of a
computer the opportunity cost of box in
the US is 2third of a
computer so what we say is since
Columbia has a lower opportunity cost
they have a comparative advantage in
roses Colombia has a comparative
advantage in Rose production why because
the opportunity cost is relatively
lower flipping that okay so let me stop
there so Columbia is a comparative
advantage in
roses now let me be clear for a second I
want to distinguish comparative
advantage from this the term advantage
or what we call absolute advantage
I want to distinguish those and the best
way to distinguish those is of course to
think about LeBron James mowing his
lawn okay let's think about LeBron James
mowing his lawn now LeBron James does
two things play basketball and mo is
lawn okay and let's assert LeBron James
is better than anyone in the world of
both playing basketball and mowing his
lawn LeBron James be an awesome I mean
the guy's built right he just crank on
that lawn okay so let's assert LeBron
James is the best person at both mowing
his lawn and playing basketball he has
an absolute advantage in both
activities but he has a comparative
advantage in playing basketball in other
words he's way better let's take LeBron
James versus me now there's two goods
playing basketball and mowing lawns and
two countries LeBron James and Gruber
okay LeBron James has a massive
comparative advantage in playing
basketball I suck at basketball okay
he's a un a billion to one compar
advantage in playing basketball mowing
laws he's maybe five to one he's
certainly better than me at mowing aan
but is he more than five times could he
do it five times faster than me probably
not so LeBron James is an absolute
advantage over me in basketball and
lawnmowing but his comparative advantage
is basketball LeBron James should and
this will be the hint of where we're
going LeBron James should specialize in
basketball let mimo the
lawn now in fact I shouldn't know the
lawn
either CU Let's Take Me versus a a uh L
landscape contractor and let's do
economics and
lawnmowing I am certainly better than
the land the average landscape
contractor at
economics I'm probably worse at
lawnmowing so I should then hire the
landscape contractor it's all about
comparative advantage it's what are you
relatively better
at okay now let's go back to another
example who has the comparative
advantage in computers and why which
count is compar advantage of computers
and
why which of these two countries has the
comparative advantage of computers and
why
yeah right so what's the opportunity
cost of a computer in the
US yeah go ahead three halves for
computers this is
roses for computers the US opportunity
cost is three halves what's the
opportunity cost in Columbia
eight so the US has a comparative
advantage in computers a lower given the
fifth bump go ahead the lower
opportunity cost in computers the US is
a comparative advantage in computers
okay so in this model Colombia has the
comparative advantage in roses the US
has the comparative advantage in
computers okay now let's go back now
let's let's add one more wrinkle to this
exam to this example I've already made
it simple enough I've said look
constant uh you know constant marginal
product of
labor okay one input now let's go
further let's imagine these goods are
perfectly com in perfectly competitive
markets let's imagine the goods are per
are bought in perfectly competitive
markets and let's start with a simple
example of what we'll call sort of a
weird word but I don't know why we call
it
autarchy art
autarchy a u t a r k y autarchy it
simply means no trade I don't know why
we use that fancy
word okay but basically you know this is
the secret to why economists are
successful and wealthy is they would
make up fancy words for really easy
Concepts it makes it sound smart so we
call it autarchy but it just means
there's no trait okay in a world of
autarchy each country has to produce its
own own computer and Roose computers and
Roses now let's ask in a competitive
market let's say there a competitive
market for goods and for labor and the
wage rate is W the wage rate in this
competitive market is
W
okay
now you can then tell
me and let's say W's the same both
countries
there's a wage rate W you can tell me
what
price roses will sell at in the
US at what price will roses sell in a
perfectly competitive Rose Market with a
perfectly competitive labor market and O
HW what will be the price for roses in
the
US well what what is what is price equal
in perfect competition don't raise your
hand and tell me yeah marginal cost
what's the marginal cost
to W so we know that roses the price of
roses in the US will simply be two w
we're done all I had to give you was
this and like you could tell me the
price we know the price for computers in
the US will be 3w we know the price of
roses in Colombia will be one W and we
know the price that's roses I'm sorry
yeah Pros in Columbia the price of
computers in Columbia will be 8w we know
all the prices simply because we know
under perfect
competition okay we know under perfect
competition what how prices relate to
Marginal
costs okay so basically in the US if the
US simp if you cannot
trade then in the US computers Will T
will cost one and a half times as much
as roses
the price of a could be one and a half
times the price of roses in Columbia
Computer cost eight times as much as a
rose so if you can't trade we know what
the market is going to look like in each
of these
countries okay we know what the Market's
going to look like in each of these
countries so
now let's
imagine that we actually allow
trade well if you allow trade here's the
miraculous piece by allow trade you
create economies of
scope allowing trade creates economies
of scope to see why I go to figure
183 imagine that both countries oh let's
go to figure
183 and um if both countries only
produce roses they set their work
workers to work 24 hours a day producing
roses then we end up with 36 roses how
do we know that well look at figure 182
if both countries only produce roses we
get 36
roses 24 in Columbia 12 in the US if
both countries only produce computers we
get 11
computers eight in the US three in
Columbia okay now but what happens if
the country
specialize what if the us only produce
computers and Colombia only produce
roses well how many computers we we get
we get eight
computers how many roses would we get we
get 24 cartons of
roses if you graph that you get an you
get a outward bending
ppf you just created economies of
scope not through any
magic but simply
through comparative advantage yielding
specialization and that's the key
Insight of trade Theory the comparative
advantage yields specialization LeBron
should just play basketball I should
just do economics my lawnscape
contractor my lacap contractor should
just mow my lawn LeBron shouldn't mess
with Mo in his lawn I shouldn't mess I
shouldn't mess with Mo in my lawn okay
and the bottom line is if you've
comparative advantage in a certain
activity you should specialize in that
activity by doing so you
create you create economies of scope
which we also call gains from
trade gains from trade you create gains
from trade by allowing folks to
specialize okay so to see
that further let's
imagine that let's imagine that the
relative trading price of computers is
four now you know what the relative
prices are with art tarkey once we open
up the trade is going to depend on
Demand right you I you can't tell me the
world with trading what price is going
to be I'm gonna have to choose the
demand curve okay in art tarkey it
doesn't matter what demand is Right
perfect competition dictates this with
trading it matters it depends how much
we want computers roll to roses and we
don't know that yet so I'm going to make
life easy I'm going to come back to this
I'm going to start by just
assuming that the price of computers
there's free trade and on the World
Market the price of computers equals
four times the price of roses I'm just
going to assume that in the World Market
that's what happens I'll come back to
how you get there but for now it's easy
to start with assuming that so we open
up to trade and let's assume the price
for computers is four time the price of
roses okay well what you can see is that
by specializing
we open up new consumption opportunities
go to figure
184 the red line in figure
184 was the artar possibilities we saw
that already the blue
line is with World Trade at a price of
four the trade
possibilities the blue line is
everywhere outside the red line each
country can do better with trade or they
could do no worse so if Colombia only
wants roses they're no they're no worse
off with trade but if they want any
computers they're better off why because
they can produce roses cheaply and trade
them for
computers the us if it only wants
computers is no better off at trade but
if wants any roses it's better off
because it can produce computers
efficiently and then sell them cheaply
for roses
so by allowing each country to
specialize we can allow for expanded
production
possibilities by allowing each Char to
specialize we can allow for expanded uh
production
possibilities okay so basically what
this means is as long as with the price
of with a price ratio of
four okay as long as country want some
of what the other country has you are
better off with free trade than with our
turkey and that's the
proof you're better off to trade with
arkey and simply the magic it's the all
the the magic that's happening here is
simply by allowing countries to
specialize you get them take you get
them to use their competitive advantage
and produce more with artar we didn't
the US was inefficiently forced to
produce roses it's much more efficient
to produce computers and trade them for
Roses so by allowing that that trade we
allowed more consumption
possibilities in both the US uh and in
Columbia questions about
that now in this
example I made up the price so let's
think more
generally yeah I'm
sorry great question so so what I've
missed from this model is the whole
demand
side what they decide to give themselves
what side of trade is going to depend on
the relative demand for computers and
Roads across the countes that's going to
yield this price which I just made up so
basically what they're going to decide
to do is going to depend on how much
each country wants computers and
Roses okay so to see that let's go to
figure
185 which is a little confusing okay but
basically what this says is point let's
start at point
B
okay let's imagine where at point B at
point B okay um the price ratio is
four okay four cartons of rows yield one
computer okay but let's say that at
point
B there's an overall increase in World
demand for
computers folks want more computers than
point B so point B yields eight
computers a day and let's say the the
world in general wants more than
that okay so in that case you would move
down from point B along that slope
segment towards C Colombia would then
say look I'm going to start producing
computers okay it's relatively
inefficient but if the world really
wants them that's what I'm going to do
I'm still going to
trade but I'm not going to purely
specialize so pure specialization is is
a special
case in general countries whether
they'll only purely specialize under
certain conditions generally countries
will produce some of both but they'll
still relatively specialize in the thing
they have a comparative advantage at let
me say that again pure specialization
only emerges as this particular case in
general countries are will shift once
you open up to International Trade
countries will shift towards producing
the goods they have a comparative
advantage in they might not go all the
way it won't be as Extreme as my pure
special a example but the direction is
clear now at some point that will
end okay imagine that we get to a
point where the price of computers Rel
to roses is
10 imagine demand for computers as such
Rel to roses the price of computers Rel
to roses is
10 well basically that would say a
Colombian producer says look I have a
choice I can give up
one box of roses and get
10 computer and I I'm sorry basically if
I produce one computer it will yield 10
box of
roses if the world price gets to 10 10
box of r at that point columia will say
forget it I'm just going to produce
computers too
okay so you can imagine a world where
everyone specialized computers likewise
the price of computers is low enough
everyone could specialize in roses so
where you end up on this graph depends
on the relative
demands that is much more complicated
I'm not going to model that I go back
and forth way I should model that but
take another half hour it's not worth it
I think we can get the intuition without
the model OKAY the basic intuition is a
for prices in a broad range from a price
of three halfs to a price of eight price
in that range there'll be some
specialization as long as you are
somewhere on that ppf there'll be some
specialization if prices get too low or
too high you want a specialization
anymore but in general you get
specialization how much specialization
you're going to get is depend on the
relative demand for the two goods if the
world mostly wants computers then NE
also will produce more computers than
Columbia Columbia will still produce
some if the world's mostly wants roses
then Columba will produce more roses in
the US but us will still produce some
okay okay questions about
that so the bottom line is comparative
advantage yields specialization and
that's yields gains to trade so that's
the thought linkage okay comparative
advantage means that folks want to
specialize which yields gains from
trade if there was no trade LeBron would
have to mow his
lawn okay think about that if there was
no trade LeBron because LeBron still
cares about his LA to mow is
lawn that would be giving up basketball
we all value at many many times his
mowing his lawn that's
inefficient we are losing we are happy
to trade me mowing LeBron's lawn for
getting to watch LeBron play basketball
we're all happy to make that trade
probably even me okay I like basketball
okay we're all happy to make that trade
so by not allowing that trade we make
Society worse off that's why free trade
Mak Society better off because without
free trade people can't take advantage
of what they're best
at and that's why we like free
trade okay questions about
that now that raises the really
interesting
question of where does comparative
advantage come from if comparative
advantage is so important where does it
come from well as LeBron examp they
really can come from two
places as the LeBron example illustrates
the first placeing comparative advantage
what we call Factor
endowments basically who's born with
what LeBron was born with an innate
ability to better basketball than I am
there's you know I'm not saying if
LeBron never tried and I spent my whole
life I couldn't be better than him but
he has an enormous Advantage physically
Over Me In Playing
Basketball okay his Factor endowment
likewise Canada was endowed with massive
amounts of forest
land so they have a comparative
advantage in producing
Timber China is endowed with 1.5 billion
people so they have a factor endowment
compared advantage in producing labor
intensive
Goods okay basically countries certain
times countries have Factor endowments
that give them an advantage like timber
in Canada or labor in China but
comparative advantage can also be
created through
technology there's no reason the
US is better than I don't know Indonesia
at producing computers the US isn't that
much bigger than
Indonesia okay but we are we've used
we've we've pushed along the
technological Frontier lar through
investing in human capital to give
ourselves a technological competitive
Advantage compartive Advantage versus
Indonesia does not come from anything
innate there nothing about the land of
the US makes is better producing
computers you don't grow anything we're
better because we've moved further along
the technological
Frontier so another way so comparative
advantage can be innate or it can be
produced and that is why a huge debate
around international trade is basically
how do we get ahead of other
countries if you think about the the uh
President Biden's um uh chips and
semiconductor act chips and science act
a lot of what that act did it put 52
billion dollar into subsidizing the
production of semiconductors in the US
maybe you may not know about the
semiconductor Market semiconductor
Market while semiconductors were
invented here in the US and we still
lead technologically in The Innovation
semiconductors we don't produce
semiconductors indeed a somewhat scary
fact if you're if you follow G politics
is 75% of all 7 conductors in the world
are produced within 100 miles of
China now if you think that you're
worried about a war with China then
that's kind of a worrisome
fact moreover there's the view that GE
we we don't have a compartive advantage
in trading semiconductors because China
produced them all what if we produced
sem what if we invested in the
technology of manufacturing rather than
investing in technology of invention
what if he invest in the technology of
manufacturing we got better at
Manufacturing in China then we would
have a comparative advantage of
producing semiconductors which Not only
would help our national security be
vital economic Victory and that's the
idea of the chips and science Act is
let's put money into invent investing in
cuttingedge manufacturing not just for
Economic Security but eventually give us
a technological comparative
advantage okay so that's another source
comparative advantage but there's a
third Source I should said three there's
a third
source which is not so happy and we
might call it sort of it's not going to
I don't know have a good label for it we
just call it destructive
routes destructive routes to comparative
advantage let me give a simple
example one
reason that China has a compartive
Advantage not only in things like
producing textiles butting things like
batteries is because they have really
weak environmental regulations
so in the US if you want to set up a
battery Factory you have to pass a
battery of tests to show that you're not
doing environmental damage you're not
harming the people around you in China
you don't so in China One of the leading
bad battery manufacturing plants was
leaking the materials that made to use
batteries and PE many hundreds of people
died or got sick in the nearby
Villages now China had a comparative
advantage for using batteries you can do
it more cheaply than we we could so
we're buying Chinese batteries but at
what
cost at the cost of making our
environment worse and harming people
around
them you can go further we often heard
the term sweat shops is a term you hear
the idea people are getting poorly paid
to do hard jobs many people would argue
that China has a comparative advantage
in producing things like textiles
because their workers are working in
terrible conditions and leading horrible
lives now we'll come back to that next
time and ask if that's really a valid
criticism but people might call that a
destructive route or think about child
labor in the US child labor is banned
rightly in other countries it's not so
if other countries use child
labor as a way to get a competitive
Advantage we might not like that so much
so that's where we start to next time
we'll get to this more that's we start
to see G maybe free trade isn't always
cracked up to be if the way you get
Advantage could be destructive then
maybe we're a little worried about free
trade
we add on top of that the fact that free
trade means that we get cheaper roses
people in the US lose their jobs and we
care about jobs that's another reason we
might be a little worried about free
trade so next time we're going to start
to ask how do we think about the weal
for economics of free trade and are
there arguments against it and what
should governments do if they if they
don't feel free trade is working to the
best advantage of the world okay we'll
go there next time