So we're going to go to our next speaker
Dr. Takuya Kitagawa and he is the
president of Cuera computing. Kiara
computing is work on the neutral atom
based quantum computer and so it's all
yours Takuya.
>> Thank you Hong. Um thank you for
inviting me to this seminar. You know
that was a fantastic lecture by
professor Oliver. Um so I want I'd like
to actually introduce you uh to Quera
and also explain already press Oliver
cover many grounds but you know I want
to explain why this is a very special
moment for uh quantum computing
industry. So my name is Takuya. I'm the
president of Quer computing. It's called
Quer because it's a quantum era. So you
know it's pronounced as as Quer. Okay.
Okay. Uh so Quira uh develops quantum
computers based on neutral atoms and
professor Oliver already gave a very
nice introduction to this modality. Uh
it was founded in 2018 uh by uh
professor from MIT Blitic and Harvard
University Mish Lukin Max Grer and also
you know Dur England was involved in a
founding of this company. Uh we already
have a a very good commercial
attractions uh including more than $40
million of bookings and and we raised
$230 million uh beginning of this year
uh from strategic partners such as
Google, Nvidia and Saltbank Vision Fund.
We have our first generation quantum
computer on the cloud from 2022 November
uh on AWS and we have delivered the
second generation quantum computer in
2025 to Japan. So just this is just to
say you know uh the quantum computers
already real and people can access those
quantum computers from quer uh on the
cloud.
So just you know a quick glance at you
know uh uh the you know form factors of
our quantum computer on the left you
know uh the picture you're looking at is
the machine we deliver to Japan ICE this
is national laboratory in Japan uh uh in
2025 March and on the right you see you
know ex you know uh uh you know tweet uh
message from u previous prime minister
Ishiba Japanese prime minister and uh
you know uh he got to see uh you know uh
our site and this really shows you know
um the interest uh into quantum computer
is across the world uh from you know uh
uh top government uh you know policians
and and and bureaucrats uh around the
world. So this is very exciting uh
period.
Now before I go into explaining you know
uh you know what kind of breakthrough
quer has been making uh I just wanted to
you know show you what our quantum
computer looks like. On the left is a
core part of our quantum computer.
Inside of this brown coil is the glass
cell you can see and we make this you
know inside glass cell vacuum and we we
put rubidium atom inside of it and we
use we we laser cool and trap them and
manipulate them using lasers. Each
rubidium atom corresponds to cubit the
memory of quantum computers and on your
right you know the movie you're looking
at is exactly how we actually do a
quantum computations. So each dot
corresponds to a cubit and then we
actually do a manipulation and when they
are getting close to each other we
actually pulsing another you know set of
lasers to do you know quantum
computations.
Now I already press Oliver you know
touch on this um you you know you've
heard you know many big companies like
Google, IBM, Microsoft uh as uh have
been investing a lot of money into
quantum computers in the last 15 years
but yet you know uh uh one of the
fundamental issues you see with quantum
computer is error rate you know uh
there's tremendous you know promise of
quantum computer for example once it's
scaled maybe you can replace you know
some of the experimental science with
computational science and you can accept
accelerate the scientific discovery by
you know 10,000 times because you can
reproduce some of those you know quantum
mechanical experiments in the computer
rather than in the lab. Um but however
currently you know uh the best of the
best quantum computer can execute maybe
1,000 steps because you know uh uh the
error rate of each step was about 0.1%.
So if you take a inverse of it it's
around 1,000 maybe you can stretch it to
10,000 but that's that's pretty much it.
But however you know to get to this UTD
scale quantum computer that can really
you know do this you know tremendous
work in experimental science um you need
trillions of computations which is 10 to
12. So because of this nine order
magnitude difference people thought you
it would take uh about 50 years to get
to that point. However, you know, here
at MIT, you know, uh uh you know,
precious shore came up with this
fantastic idea of quant correction 30
years ago. And you know, this contra
correction can potentially exponentially
lower the error rate. And the
breakthrough that happened in 2023 was
you know a few companies including the
group of you know MIT and Harvard uh
together with Quera have realized you
know uh you know this quant correction
in experiments. you know theoretical
proposal was done by pressure shore 30
years ago by experiments was you know
for the first time done in 2023 and
other companies who have realized
economical correction was you know
Google and continum so uh the movie
you're looking at on on the right is
exactly uh this experiment uh by by
Harvard University and MIT uh of doing
this you know content correction now by
watching this movie you actually notice
a few you know distinct advantage of our
you know neutral atom system one is you
see a lot of parallel operations you
know you you see you know a lot of atoms
moving together and actually doing
operation together. Uh second is you
know you see a lot of you know empty
space uh in the movie and you think okay
maybe you can pack more cubits into this
space and you can increase the number of
cubits and also as Oliver said you know
in order to actually do a quant
correction you need to pack a multiple
cubits into you know one pocket called
logical cubit. So you actually need a
lot more number of cubits to realize you
know a compar correction and as as it
turns out you know you know this new
trans system does have advantage in
increasing the number of cubits and you
know this experiment was done already
within this year uh uh and they you know
MIT and Harvard successfully implemented
you know more than 3,000 cubits more
than two hours so this is you know you
know a large number of you know cubits
that you know no other you know modality
have ever realized.
And you know uh we we think you know
because of this you know neutral atom
system uh have you know tremendous
advantage for going into logical QBT era
as opposed to you know physical QT era.
Now I also wanted to talk about you know
one another innovation that you know
quer is really pushing for uh which is
you know uh combination of AI and
quantum. So there are two direction you
know that that could be very
interesting. One is AI for quantum, the
other one is quantum for AI. AI for
quantum is an approach to integrate AI
into the architecture of quantum
computer such that you can enhance a
quantum computations by a large amount
and and this is the place for example we
are collaborating with Nvidia. You know
one idea for example is when you
actually you know doing quantum error
correction you detect errors uh in the
system and then you need to translate
that you know error signal into error
you know error correction operations
that translation is called decoding and
you know it actually takes a lot of you
know classical computation power to
figure that out and you know if you do
this you know decoding really well as it
turns out you can enhance uh the quantum
computation by a large amount and we've
already demonstrated that using AI you
can actually do a decoding uh much
better and then you can enhance the you
know computitional uh uh power of
quantum computer by 10 to 100 times.
Another direction is quantum AI. You
know, uh uh you've heard many examples
of AI for science already, you know,
including alpha fold and other
approaches of using AI to to accelerate
the discovery of science. Now, when this
science touches quantum science such as
material discovery or you know uh you
know catalysis, then you actually need
some simulator that can produce high
quality data to train AI. Now there's
nothing else uh better than quantum
computer that can simulate uh quantum
mechanics of the world and therefore
quantum computer can be used to provide
a high quality data to train AI and this
combination of AI and quantum I believe
will accelerate you know uh the use
cases of quantum computers by a couple
years. So these are very exciting
directions. Okay. Um so you know this
world is really exciting right now and
uh you know we always welcome very
talented you know uh people from MIT uh
to join. So if you're interested in any
of our work you know please do contact
me.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Thank you so much Takuya. I know you uh
uh you need to go right now. So um
please uh let us know all the exciting
progress and wish you good luck. Thank
you.
>> Thank you so much.