the MIT energy initiative presents
explained the 1.5c climate Benchmark
after a summer of weather extremes where
does the world stand in its gold to stem
Rising temps written by Jennifer Chu for
MIT
news the summer of 2023 has been a
season of weather
Extremes in June uncontrolled wildfires
ripped through parts of Canada sending
smoke into the US and setting off air
quality alerts in dozens of downwind
states in July the world set the hottest
Global temperature on record which had
held for 3 days in a row then broke
again on day four from July into August
unrelenting heat blanketed large parts
of Europe Asia and the us while India
faced a torrential monsoon season and
heavy rains flooded regions in the
northeastern us and most recently
whipped up by high winds in dry
vegetation a historic Wildfire tore
through Maui devastating an entire town
these extreme weather events are mainly
a consequence of climate change driven
by humans continued burning of coal oil
and natural gas climate scientists agree
that extreme weather such as what people
experience this summer will likely grow
more frequent and intense in the coming
years unless something is done on a
persistent and Planet wide scale to rain
in global temperatures just how much
raining in are they talking about the
number that is internationally agreed
upon is 1.5° C to prevent worsening and
potentially irreversible effects of
climate change the world's average
temperature should not exceed that of
pre-industrial times by more than 1.5° C
2.7 de f as more regions around the
world face extreme weather it's worth
taking stock of the 1.5° bar where the
planet stands in relation to this
threshold and what can be done at the
global Regional and personal level to
keep 1.5
alive why
1.5c in 2015 in response to the growing
urgency of climate impacts nearly every
country in the world signed on to the
Paris agreement a landmark International
treaty under which 195 Nations pledged
to hold the Earth's temperature to well
below 2° C above pre-industrial levels
and going further aim to limit the
temperature increase to 1 1.5° C above
pre-industrial levels the treaty did not
Define a particular pre-industrial
period though scientists generally
consider the years from 1850 to 1900 to
be a reliable reference this time
predates humans use of fossil fuels and
is also the earliest period when Global
observations of land and sea
temperatures are available during this
period the average global temperature
while swinging up and down in certain
years generally hovered around 13.5 C or
56.3 de F the treaty was informed by a
fact-f finding report which concluded
that even global warming of 1.5° C above
the pre-industrial average over an
extended decades long period would lead
to high risks for some regions and
vulnerable
ecosystems the recommendation then was
to set the 1.5° C limit as a defense
line if the world can keep below this
line it potentially could avoid the more
extreme and irrv ible climate effects
that would occur with a 2° c increase
and for some places an even smaller
increase than that but as many regions
are experiencing today keeping below the
1.5 line is no guarantee of avoiding
extreme global warming effects there is
nothing magical about the 1.5 number
other than that is an agreed
aspirational Target keeping at 1.4 is
better than 1.5 and 1.3 is better than
1.4 and so on says Sergey PV deputy
director of mit's joint program on the
science and policy of global change the
science does not tell us that if for
example the temperature increase is 1.51
De C then it would definitely be the end
of the world similarly if the
temperature would stay at 1.49 De
increase it does not mean that we will
eliminate all impacts of climate change
what is known the lower the target for
an increase in temperature the lower the
risk of climate
impacts how close are we to
1.5c in 2022 the average global
temperature was about 1.15 de C above
pre-industrial levels according to the
World Meteorological organization wo the
cyclical weather phenomenon lenia
recently contributed to temporarily
Cooling and dampening the effects of
human induced climate change lenia
lasted for 3 years and ended around
March of 2023 in May the wo issued a
report that projected a significant
likelihood 66% that the world would
exceed the 1.5° C threshold in the next
4 years this breach would likely be
driven by human induced climate change
combined with a warming El Nino a
cyclical weather phenomenon that
temporarily heats up ocean regions and
pushes global temperatures higher this
summer an El Nino is currently underway
and the event typically raises global
temperatures in the year after it sets
in which in this case would be in 2024
the wmo predicts that for each of the
next four years the global average
temperature is likely to swing between
1.1 and 1.8 de C above pre-industrial
levels though there's a good chance the
world will get hotter than the 1.5 Dee
limit as a result of El Nino the breach
would be temporary and for now would not
have failed the Paris agreement which
aims to keep global temperatures below
the 1.5° limit over the long term
averaged over several decades rather
than a single year but we should not
forget that this is a global average and
there are variations regionally and
seasonally says alphat elah here the HM
King boom pool professor and professor
of civil and environmental engineering
at MIT this year we had extreme
conditions around the world even though
we haven't reached the 1.5c threshold so
even if we control the average at a
global magnitude we are going to see
events that are extreme because of
climate
change more than a
number to hold the planet's long-term
average temperature to below the 1.5°
threshold the world will have to reach
net zero emissions by the year 2050
according to the intergovernmental panel
on climate change ipcc this means that
in terms of the emissions released by
the burning of coal oil and natural gas
the entire world will have to remove as
much as it puts into the atmosphere in
terms of Innovations we need all of them
even those that may seem quite exotic at
this point Fusion direct air capture and
others Pelt SV says
the task of curbing emissions in time is
particularly daunting for the United
States which is second only to China in
generating the most carbon dioxide
emissions in the world the US's burning
of fossil fuels and consumption of
energy is just way above the rest of the
world that's a persistent problem Ela
here says and the national statistics
are an aggregate of what a lot of
individuals are doing at an individual
level there are things that can be done
to help bring down one's personal
emissions and potentially chip away at
Rising global temperatures we are
consumers of products that either embody
greenhouse gases such as meat clothes
computers and homes or we are directly
responsible for emitting greenhouse
gases such as when we use Cars airplanes
electricity and air conditioners PV says
our everyday choices affect the amount
of emissions that are added to the
atmosphere but to compel people to
change their emissions it may be less
about a number and more about a feeling
to get people to act my hypothesis is
you need to reach them not just by
convincing them to be good citizens and
saying it's good for the world to keep
below
1.5° but showing how they individually
will be impacted says Ela here who
specializes on the study of regional
climates focusing on how climate change
impacts the water cycle and frequency of
extreme weather such as heat waves true
climate progress requires a dramatic
change in how the human system gets its
energy Pelt says it is a huge
undertaking are you ready personally to
make sacrifices and to change the way of
your life if one gets an honest answer
to that question it would help to
understand why true climate progress is
so difficult to achieve