the MIT energy initiative presents
responding to Ukraine's ocean of
suffering former MIT energy initiative
researcher Ian Miller sm19 along with
Evan Platt sm20 is funneling Aid and
expertise to the front line written by
Deborah
halber within 72 hours of the first
Russian missiles striking ke Ukraine in
February 2022 Ian Miller sm9 boarded a
flight for Poland later he'd say he felt
motivated by ke's tragic ocean of
suffering and Ukrainian president zin's
please for help but he arrived with a
little notion of what to do as he'd
anticipated his hotel in xov turned out
to be a hub for Aid workers and
journalists Miller was on his laptop
using the lobby Wi-Fi to work remotely
as an MIT energy initiative Mighty
project manager when he overheard a
reporter interviewing a finish man about
his efforts to get Bulletproof bu and
helmets to the front lines Miller soon
found himself loading supplies onto
trains that had brought huge numbers of
refugees mostly women children and the
elderly to the station in xiu the trains
ran back at night their empty seats
filled with medical supplies generators
and baby food their lights dimmed to
reduce the chances of attack in April
2022 Miller and volunteers from a half
dozen countries planned and drove a
convoy of trucks packed with tourniquets
bandages and bulletproof vests across
the border
arriving at the site of the bcha
massacre soon after the Russians
retreated Miller peered into a mass
grave they were still Excavating it and
those weren't soldiers you know he says
I try to avoid looking at things like
that too often because it doesn't help
us save lives to be horrified all the
time he downplays any potential danger
to himself telling his family he's safer
where he is than in parts of the United
States soon after his first trip across
the border Miller convinced his former
MIT roommate Evan Platt 20 to come help
just for a week he told
Platt inspired by
energy Miller and Platt met in 2008 in
Washington DC where plat was interning
at the White House and Miller was about
to start his senior year at Georgetown
University Miller majored in government
but his interest in energy policy and
Technology grew during the years after
graduation he spent teaching science to
primary and secondary school students in
New York where he grown up in Boston and
in kalala Uganda some of the most fun
inspiring engaging lessons and modules I
did with the kids were focused on energy
he recalls while pursuing an MIT master
of science and chemical engineering from
2016 to 2018 he started researching
photo voltaics and wind power he held
leadership positions with the MIT energy
conference and the MIT Energy Club after
joining Mighty Miller worked on electric
vehicles EVS EV charging patterns and
other applications he became project
manager and research specialist for the
sustainable energy system analysis
modeling environment Sesame Which models
the levels of greenhouse gas emissions
from multiple energy sectors in future
scenarios Miller and Platt reconnected
and shared an apartment for 3 years
Platt studied systems design and
management through a joint MIT School of
Engineering and Sloan School of
Management program then stayed on to
work for the MIT technology licensing
office plat left MIT to pursue other
interests in 2020 the next time the two
would see each other would be in Poland
it's it's not easy living and working in
an active combat zone plat says there is
nobody on Earth I would rather be
navigating this environment with than
Ian navigating The Last Mile in jeu and
Ukraine Miller and US Air Force veteran
Mark linquist oversaw fulfillment for
the new team with the help of Google
translate their phones exploded with
encrypted texts to and from polish
Customs agents and Ukrainian Warehouse
operators plat and two Ukrainian team
members took the lead on a needs
analysis of what was most in demand at
the front another team member LED
procurement their efforts crystallized
in the creation of zerol line a tax
exempt nonprofit that works closely with
Ukrainian government at the front line
aka the zero line with plat on board we
got more rigorous and quantitative in
terms of live save per dollar Miller
says $100 buys four tourniquet $1,000
adds crude steel armor to a Jeep $2,000
provides a small observation drone or a
satellite phone equipment that locates
Russian Artillery and detects Russian
attacks Russian Artillery shells are the
number one killer of ukrainians causing
around 80% of casualties he says
tourniquet save people injured by
Russian shells Vehicles help evacuate
them and Communications equipment
prevents deadly injuries from occurring
in the first place Miller's skills in
transportation and power system modeling
developed at Mighty under principal
research scientist emry genser helped
the team transport more than 15 used
vehicles Nissan Pathfinders and vans for
moving civilians away from the front
Ford pickups for transporting
anti-missile defense systems and
hundreds of batteries generators drones
bulletproof vests and helmets to the
front through nightmarish logistical
bottlenecks typically supplies from the
United States Asia and elsewhere in
Europe move through Gdansk and Warsaw
then proceed via train or vehicle to
warehouses in Lviv around 70 km east of
the Border next is the 7-hour trip to ke
or the 12-hour drive to nepro the
current Southern edge of the safe green
zone and the final 200 km to the front
here says Miller drivers with training
and protective gear often members of the
Ukrainian military take vehicles and
supplies to Frontline end users from day
one we asked our Ukrainian members and
partners for introductions and we're
constantly looking for more Miller says
when our vehicles reach the front lines
Evans team always does interviews about
needs and what's working what's not
what's saving the most lives
from my early days with Ian it's clear
he was always looking for ways to help
people connections were really important
to him says Mighty director Robert C
Armstrong when war broke out he found
the call to answer human need
irresistible I think many of us think of
doing that but we get bogged down in the
mechanics of everyday life he just
picked up and went Ian is just a
terrific person and a great role model
Armstrong
says accelerating
peace from the time Miller arrived in
late February through October 2022 he
continued working remotely for Mighty he
now works full-time as co-director of
zeroline for the foreseeable future
Miller will remain in Ukraine and Poland
he wants to see ukrainians follow in the
happy free prospering footsteps of other
ex Soviet States like the baltics he
says he'd like to see the supply chain
Innovations he and plat achieved applied
to humanitarian crisises elsewhere to
date zerol line has raised more than $5
million in donations and delivered
hundreds of tons of high impact Aid a
key part of our approach has always been
to support ukrainians who excel in
Saving Lives Miller says to that end the
group works with Ukrainian software
programmers and military units to create
digital maps and processes to replace
paper maps and operations reminiscent of
World War II plot says modernizing the
intelligence infrastructure to
facilitate better military operations is
an important part of how a smaller
military can beat a larger more powerful
military the fact the fact that energy
underlies so many aspects of the war is
never far from Miller's mind Russia cut
off energy supplies to Europe then
targeted Ukraine's energy infrastructure
on one hand he understands that billions
of people in developing countries such
as India need and deserve affordable
energy on the other hand he says oil and
gas purchases by those countries are
directly funding Russia's War Machine
everyone wants cheap Renewables and
we're getting there but it's taking time
lowering the costs of Renewables in
energy storage and supporting nent
commercial Fusion that's a very
important focus of Mighty in the long
run that'll help us reach a more
peaceful world without a doubt work at
Mighty and at zero line Miller says
truly could accelerate peace