Let's get started. So, we're in the home
stretch. We've got uh one more of these
topics in coding theory. Uh Peter will
be covering a related topic next week,
but that'll be a bit of a different
flavor. So today we're going to cover
you know one of the other great results
in coding theory which has to do with
error correction. So so far we've been
exclusively talking about compression.
You know how you can take a message and
reduce the number of bits you need to
transmit in order to reliably be able to
recover what was the original message.
Now today we're going to talk about a
very realistic scenario which is when
the way that you're transmitting
introduces errors. So there's a very
simple model which is a good way to get
started
which is called the binary symmetric
channel or BSC for short. The way that
this channel works is that every time
you input a bit which is either zero or
one then it has some probability of
flipping the outcome the output of the
bit. So this BSC channel is going to be
governed by some parameter P
and it's going to have the property that
with P probability it ends up flipping
the input and output
and with the remaining probability 1
minus P it just sends through whatever
bit you sent along the channel. The
trouble is that you don't know when and
where these errors have occurred. So the
question is, you know, you can think
about P just for concreteness as being
something like a third. If I'm trying to
send a message along the channel to you
and I've already done my compression to
get it down to the shortest possible
string of zeros and ones. Now when I
send it along to you and each bit gets
flipped independently with probability a
third you know what hope do you have of
recovering the original message and what
are schemes you can design that combat
the fact that you're anticipating
there'll be errors.
So, you know, just to be clear, we're
talking about each bit
is flipped independently
with this probability
P.
And now we can ask all of the natural
questions
about communication and the presence of
errors. So the main thing we care about
which will be what we'll address today
is you know is it still possible to
transmit
information
reliably.
So you know let's um
let's think about you know what this
question means uh with some simple ideas
for how to combat the errors right. So
one simple example you can come up with
uh for how to transmit along a noisy
channel is to use what are called
repetition codes.
So here the idea is that I take my
original message
Let's say it's a string of you know
zeros and ones. And what I'm going to do
for what I'll transmit along the channel
is I'm just going to keep repeating each
input bit a certain number of times so
that you know even if some of them get
corrupted maybe it's okay. So, I'll take
my first bit, which is a one, and I'm
going to repeat it t times.
And I'll do the same thing for my next
bit. That's a zero. I'm going to repeat
it t times.
And I'll do the same thing for all of
the bits in my original message. Right?
So now you can see that already the way
that I'm combating the fact that the
channel is introducing errors is that
I'm increasing the length of my
transmission. I'm padding it with extra
information in such a way that hopefully
I can detect and correct whatever errors
the channel has introduced.
So the name of the game you know for
today will be what are the best possible
schemes for how to pad the extra with
extra information in such a way that I
can reliably figure out what my original
message was.
So you know just to think about this
right? So let's say that the original
message had length K. Then what I can do
is I claim a good choice for you know
how many times to repeat each message is
maybe something like you know 100 log K.
So my original message was length K and
then each bit I repeat 100 log K times.
So intuitively, if I took this
transmission and I sent it through the
channel, you know, some of these ones
get flipped to zeros independently, some
of these zeros get flipped to ones
independently.
How would you try and decode what you
receive to figure out what the original
message is?
Any ideas?
And keep in mind, just to be concrete,
you can think about the failure, the
flip probability as being something like
a third. So maybe a bit is, you know,
more likely to come through in the clear
without being flipped than it is being
flipped. So if I sent you this long
padded transmission, how do you think
I'd figure out what the first symbol is
based on what I receive?
Any ideas?
Yeah,
>> the majority of the block.
>> Perfect. The majority vote, right?
Because intuitively, you know, if I'm
repeating this t times, then I would
expect that, you know, the number of bit
flips that I have is around t over3.
And so that means the majority of them
should actually correspond to what my
original bit was. In fact, what I care
about is not just what the expected
number of bit flips are, but I care
about getting bounds on how likely it is
that my decoding rule would fail. So,
what kind of tool that we've talked
about earlier in class might be relevant
here. So, you know, if um I started off
with bit flip probability a third and
then I sent this bit through the channel
with a repetition code. Now, my chance
of getting the wrong bit for my majority
vote decoding is the chance that the
expected number of flips is a third. But
really, the true number of flips is much
larger because it's larger than a half.
That's the only way I would get the
wrong decoding for this bit is if I
ended up with half errors instead of a
third. So what kind of tool that we've
covered earlier in class might be useful
to get a bound on the failure
probability the chance that my decoder
fails here.
>> Yeahov
>> marov would do it. Um so I could
certainly use marov. That's an example
of a tailbound.
Now one problem though is that marov
uses very little information about the
random variables. So if I did this
right, what I care about is like what's
the probability that I fail uh you know
for this bit what's the probability that
I fail for this bit and so on. And it
turns out that if you used marov if you
wanted to argue that you know with a
good chance I fail on none of these bits
and I use the union bound I would end up
having to pad the length of the message
by a factor of k instead of log k. So
are there any ideas for how I could hope
to get sharper bounds on how much I need
to increase the padding by? Yeah, turn
off. That's right. So the key point is
that you know if I have this repetition
code and I do it 100 log K times I can
use the turnoff bound.
See remember the way to think about the
turnoff bound is that the error exponent
goes down exponentially in the length in
the number of independent samples you're
taking. So the probability that I have
too many uh you know flips that I was
expecting a third flips and I get a half
is something that goes down
exponentially with log k. So if I choose
this constant in front of it the point
is that my failure probability is
something like 1 over k squ and then I
can say that I don't fail on this bit I
don't fail on this bit. I don't fail on
this bit. I don't fail on any of the
bits. So that's exactly right. You know,
if we use the churnoff bound, we could
then take the majority vote in each one
of these blocks and we could show that
the majority vote succeeds
with probability
let's say 1 minus little O of one. So
maybe I fail with some probability one
over K, something like that. So we're
not going to fully prove these things
right here because we're going to design
a much much better coding scheme. So
repetition codes the first time you see
this problem of communicating on a noisy
channel is the first scheme you come up
with. But the big surprise is that you
can do way better than just repeating
your message. So what I'm going to do
right now is I'm going to tell you about
you know what are the deserata. So what
are the things we want out of our code
and then we'll talk about you know
Shannon's noisy coding theorem and we'll
prove it. Okay. So I claim this code is
pretty good but not really the kind of
thing that we're aiming for.
So let's make precise some of the things
that we talked about intuitively. Right?
So we can talk about the rate of a code.
The rate just describes you know however
long my transmission is. How long is
that compared to how much information
I'm actually transmitting right? So in
particular what it is is the length of
the message
divided by the length of the
transmission.
So in particular what do we get for
repetition codes?
How good are they according to this
deserata of having a good rate? Well, we
can check that the rate that we get is 1
over 100 log K, right? Because you know
my original length of my message was K.
My new length of my message is K * T and
I set T to be 100 log K. So I get this 1
/ T type of rate. So the trouble with
this is that you know this rate if you
look at it right as the length of my
message K goes to infinity my rate is
going to zero so that's the question
that's the main question really is is
that necessary so when we send longer
and longer transmissions does it mean
that I'm communicating asmtoically very
little negligible information when I'm
sending things to you or is it possible
to achieve a constant rate that's
independent of the length of the
message.
So this came as a pretty big you know
surprise and this is our main guiding
question for today.
Let's ask can we make
the probability of getting an error and
what I mean by that is the probability
that we don't successfully decode the
message we started from. I want the
probability of my error going to zero
[clears throat]
but I want to keep
the rate constant
and here what I mean by going to zero is
we're taking the limit as the length of
my input message K is going to infinity
so is it possible to do much better than
these repetition codes we got you know
error probability ility of error was
going to zero that's fine but we were
transmitting very little information at
the end of the day
so in fact I need to make some other
notions precise too because we have to
talk about
what is our coding scheme see for the
repetition codes I did this all
informally right but really what there
are there are two pieces to the puzzle
one is you know the encoding which is
how you go from the message to what you
actually transmit along the channel.
It's the way that you're encoding the
information. Repetition is a very simple
way to do that just by repeating myself.
And the other piece of the puzzle is the
decoding which takes you know whatever
is the output of the channel where some
of the bits have been flipped and we try
to go back to the message we started
from. So in our case the encoding was
repetition and the decoding was majority
vote. But in general we could think
about you know very different kinds of
schemes right so we'll say that a
rn n encoding
is a function
and which we'll write as ink
that goes from 01 to the rn
to 01 to the n. So r here represents the
rate and it's something that you know
for us will be between zero and one and
you can see that I'm going from a
shorter message. This is my k right here
is the RN. This is the input that I want
to send to another party. And then I
decide how I'm going to transmit it
along the channel using a longer
message. Right? So it goes from Rn to N.
So that's the first part is that this is
our encoding and you can see that you
know r right here is literally the rate
of my code. So that's a parameter I'll
care about and moreover a rn n decoding
is also a function.
All it does is decode goes from a
received message RN
back to oh sorry N back to what we think
the person was transmitting to begin
with. Okay.
Now the key point is um you know how
these two functions encode and decode
work in the presence of errors and bit
flips like when we send it along the
binary symmetric channel. So in
particular we'll be interested
in the following quantity.
This is a bit of a mouthful. So let me
write it down and then we'll parse it
together.
So if you give me two parameters, R,
your target rate, and N, which is, you
know, how long you want the transmission
to be, well, I'm going to look at the
min over all RN
encoding and decoding functions
of the max
over messages M which are in 01 to the
Rn of the probability ility that m tilda
is not equal to m where we think about
it according to the following picture.
So we start off with our message that
gets turned into some transmission which
is just the encoding of my message given
my encoding function. We send this
through the binary symmetric channel
and we receive cilda.
We pass C tilda into the decoding
function to get back what we think was
the original message.
And the question is, you know, how often
do we have the property that m equals m
tilda. So this is a lot of notation, but
it's really very natural, right? So
inside right here, I just care about the
probability that I successfully decode
the message you were trying to send to
me despite the fact that the binary
symmetric channel has introduced errors.
Now uh I want this probability the
probability that I fail to get the
correct message to be small uh to be
small irrespective of what message
you're sending. So I look at how bad the
failure probability can be in decoding
in the worst case over all of my input
messages, right? And then this latter
thing is I want to create an encoding
and decoding scheme that is good for all
possible messages. So I don't want to
choose an arbitrary encoding decoding
function like these repetition codes but
I want to figure out you know what is
actually the best encoding decoding pair
uh in terms of you fixed what the rate
is how small can I get this failure
probability to be? If I fix the rate to
be a constant like a half or a third can
I get the failure probability for all
messages to be going to zero as n goes
to infinity. So, this is a bit of a
mouthful. Uh, let me give you a moment
to parse this thing, but are there any
questions about the terminology or what
I'm asking for here?
Give me a thumbs up if this makes sense.
Okay, awesome.
All right.
So, let me tell you Shannon's second
main theorem.
Shannon's noisy coding theorem
also proven around the same time and it
asserts two things which are upper and
lower bounds that meet.
So what I claim is that if the rate that
you're trying to hit is larger than one
minus entropy of P then what I claim is
that lambda star RN
the best you can do for encoding and
decoding functions that error rate goes
to one as n goes to infinity.
That's the first part for the theorem.
Let me state the other part. We'll talk
about you know what this tells us and
how to connect it back to our intuition.
So on the other side if r is less than 1
minus entropy of p then
what I claim is that lambda star r n is
going to go to zero as n goes to
infinity.
So let's parse these things together,
right? Because to really unwrap what
this theorem is stating, we have to go
back to this, you know, minax
formulation.
So you know what this is saying is like
think about P as being a third in our
binary symmetric channel. H is the
binary entropy function. We talked about
what that expression is. You know minus
P log P plus 1 minus P log 1 minus P. So
you can just plug in for P is a 3 and
compute numerically what entropy of P
is. It's some constant. And now the
point is that if you're trying to
transmit at a at a at a denser rate than
one minus entropy of P, you're going to
fail. You're going to fail. Why? Because
no matter what encoding decoding pair
you choose, there will be messages where
the probability that you successfully
decode the message is actually going to
zero. the probability that mild is not
equal to m is going to one.
So when you're trying to transmit at too
high a rate, you never decode the
correct message.
And on the other side, if the rate at
which you're trying to transmit is less
than the same quantity one minus entropy
of p, then what this means is that there
is a good encoding decoding pair. We'll
have to talk about what this pair is and
how does it work. that the error
probability goes to zero as n goes to
infinity. So this is a really striking
theorem because usually what you what
the the terminology is that you call one
minus entropy of p the capacity.
It's just some kind of rate that the
channel admits for you know how densely
you can communicate with someone else.
In fact, what's amazing is that, you
know, these types of theorems are true
not just for the binary symmetric
channel. But if you invent, you know,
your favorite stochastic channel, you
know, something which maybe erases
symbols or deletes them or has some
hybrid model between these things, they
always have a well-defined capacity that
if you're above the capacity, your error
rate is going to one. If you're below
the capacity, you can get the error rate
going to zero. But the interesting quirk
is that in a lot of cases the channel
you write down even though we know there
is some line in the sand that you cannot
cross. We don't actually know
numerically what it is because it turns
into an extremely hard math problem to
give an explicit characterization the
way that we have one here. Okay. So
let's um you know this is a lot to
digest. Uh let's try and get some
intuition for this.
So you know I told you h of p is the
binary entropy. So recall
that the entropy of p is just minus p
log base 2 of p min - 1 - p log base 2
of 1 - p.
Okay. So in particular,
you know what this function looks like
is if you choose P is a half, right?
What's going to happen is that your
entropy
of P is one.
So what you can show is that this binary
entropy function it's this nice concave
function
and it's maximum value corresponds to P
is a half at which point it equals the
value one.
So let's figure out what Shannon is
saying here and see if it makes sense.
Right? So you know I have my binary
symmetric channel and um you know if p
is one then I can compute the channel
capacity that's 1 minus one so that's
zero. So Shannon is telling me that you
can't communicate at any positive rate
when your flip probability for your
binary symmetric channel is a half.
Does that make sense?
Let's think about that one.
So why is that reasonable that when P is
a half that I can't actually transmit
information to another party?
>> Yeah.
>> That's right. So if you just look back
to my definition of the binary symmetric
channel, well one minus P is a half. P
is a half. So what that means is you
know you sit there and you receive my
first symbol which is a zero or one. It
has the same probability of being zero
and one irrespective of whether you were
sending a zero or one to begin with. So
literally my channel just doesn't look
at the message and it just spits out
random bits. Of course there's no way to
communicate right when P is a third.
Shannon's theorem is telling us that we
can do way better than the repetition
code because this will be a constant
because you know we'll be somewhere here
and whatever that value is numerically
is the fixed line in the sand. We can
communicate at that rate and know better
and we don't have something like the
repetition code where the rate is going
to zero. It's actually a universal
constant even though the error
probability is going to zero. Right? Let
me test your intuition again. Right? See
what's interesting is that the you know
this entropy function h of p is
symmetric around p equals a half right
because when I substitute p with 1 minus
p it doesn't change the expression so
the same thing is true for one minus
entropy of p so what shannon's theorem
is telling me is that when my bit flip
probability is 2/3
I can also communicate at some positive
rate why is that intuitive
You know, if I use something like the
major uh the repetition code, majority
vote doesn't work anymore, but something
else does. What would work if my bit
flip probability were two/3s? Yeah,
minority. Exactly. All I do is I'm
thinking that there'll be two/3 flips
here. And so I take the opposite of the
majority vote. Okay. So, you know, this
theorem is pretty deep. Uh it takes a
little bit to you know wrap your head
around it but so far it makes sense. P
is a half makes sense. The fact that
it's symmetric and p interchanging p and
one minus p makes sense. Okay. And we're
going to prove this theorem today.
And uh
let me give you the proof right here.
I'll put proof in quotes.
So really the question is like you know
repetition codes didn't work for my
encoding function
what should I use for my encoding
function.
So what you do
is you let encoding be a random function
and that's it. That's the proof. The
entire rest of today's lecture will be
removing the quotes around this proof
because in order to actually analyze
what happens when we choose encoding to
be a random function, well, we're going
to have to get into a lot of tools from
the probabilistic method.
So, you know, this is our strategy. Uh,
let me introduce a bit more about what
the strategy is. So what we're going to
do is we're going to prove
this second statement first which is of
course you know the the um positive
statement that we really can communicate
at some positive rate. So let's prove
two first
and let me be more precise about what I
mean by encode.
So I'm going to choose
M capital M equals 2
times 2 to the Rn strings
from
my domain 01 to the n uniformly
at random.
So if you think back to what's going on,
right? What is an encoding function?
Well, it's mapping each of the possible
messages and there are 2 to the Rn of
these to strings in 01 to the n. And
what I'm doing here, it sort of looks
like I'm looking I'm choosing the images
of what those messages would be. There's
2 to the Rn messages that I could want
to encode and I'm just going to encode
them with a uniformly random string from
01 to the n. For each one of the
messages, I just choose the bits in its
output completely at random. I have this
extra factor of two for reasons that
will become clear much later because
this scheme by itself won't quite work.
We'll have to remove some of these
strings to really get by and we'll talk
about that later. But that's, you know,
at least the intuition.
And here I'm going to define the code
book script C.
That's just all of these different
strings that I've chosen. C1 up to CN.
All right.
So now, uh, [clears throat]
let me tell you one more key definition
and then we can get to at least the
statement of some of the key lemas.
So the last key definition I need
is the notion of a ring
of width gamma around some point C. So C
here is a vector in 01 to the N. And I'm
going to let this ring be the set of all
C tildas
such that
the Hamming distance I'll tell you what
I mean by that in a second in case you
haven't seen this term the Hamming
distance between C and C tilda minus NP
is at most gamma N. All right. So let me
be precise. So the Hamming distance is
just the number of coordinates
I where
CI is not equal to C tilda I. So my ring
is going to be centered at some vector C
and C right here remember is a vector in
01 to the N. And my ring is going to be
a subset of 01 to the N. It's the set of
all C tildas that are the right distance
from C. In particular, I look at how
many coordinates between C and C tilda
are different. NP is maybe the expected
number of coordinates where they would
be different because I'm sending C along
the binary symmetric channel and it
flips each bit independently with
probability P. So in expectation if c
tilda is the output of my channel I
would expect the hamming distance to be
n * p. And here I just added a bit of
slack. You should think of gamma as
being something really really tiny
that's going to zero. And it just adds a
little bit of slack because my ring now
just looks like you know not the set of
things at some fixed distance but within
some tolerance of that distance. So the
way to think about it as a you know ring
just pictorially is that I have my
vector C here and then I'm looking at
some you know dis around it of radius PN
in terms of you know how many
coordinates are difference between C and
C tilda and then I fatten this ring a
little bit by some width gamma and this
shaded region in between them is exactly
what the set ring gamma around is so it
has a center and it has a thickness.
Okay. So any questions about that?
This is just the definition. All right.
And so now let me tell you the key lema
which is going to tell us you know it'll
be the key for proving the second part
of Shannon's theorem and it'll even tell
us you know what the decoding function
should be. We'll have to work up towards
proving this lema but I can already
state the lema right now. So here's the
key lema.
The probability
that
if we take C and we send it through our
binary symmetric channel and we get out
C tilda.
We want it to satisfy two conditions. We
want it to satisfy the condition one.
that C tilda belongs to the ring
around CI of some width gamma.
And we want that C tilda does not belong
to any other ring
of with gamma around any other CJ for
all J not equal to I. Well, I claim that
this is at least
1 minus epsilon
and this will be true for appropriate
choice of gamma and as n goes to
infinity. So let's parse this thing.
This still requires a lot of you know
digestion to understand what's going on.
So I'm punting on the question what is
gamma? We'll deal with that later. Okay.
And all of these things I care about is
really you know asmtoically as a
function of n. All right.
And you know ultimately I'm going to
want this epsilon actually to go to zero
too. So you should think of epsilon as
something that's going to zero as n goes
to infinity. So I haven't told you what
gamma is. We'll deal with that later.
But each of these c's right are uh
actually sorry I should say ci here.
Each of these CIS are the messages from
my code book script C. Remember there's
capital M of them. And what I'm saying
is when I choose my encoding scheme that
way where each of these CIS are a random
lengthen string what I'm saying is when
I pass that message through the binary
symmetric channel and introduce flips
and get C tilda well with you know high
probability
CI belong uh C tilda belongs to CI's
ring right and he belongs to no other
ring. So if this event really did happen
with you know all but vanishing
probability I would be in great shape
because it would give me my decoding
algorithm. So once I've chosen this
encoding function where you know each of
the messages the two to the Rn of them
goes to a random image one of these CIS
then all I have to do is I pass my CI
through the channel I receive C tilda
and my decoder is just going to check
one by one each of the messages in my
code book you know which ring C tilda
belongs to and the point is that the
only ring it will belong to is the
actual message I started
if both of these conditions hold. So
that's the main point is that you know
if this event happens I'm golden. So
does everyone see why decoding would
succeed if this happened?
Does this make sense?
Yeah.
I saw less vigorous head nodding.
Yes. No. Okay. All right. [laughter]
Okay. So, we're going to have to prove
this lema. That's uh one of the key
things we're going to prove today.
A bunch of these things I'm trying to do
the calculations in a way that makes
them as uh unpainful as possible.
Um but there are limits.
Um so the first thing I want to do is I
want to tell you a back of the envelope
calculation you know because all these
things like this binary entropy h of p
is going to have to show up and somehow
it shows up from the cominatorics when
we look at the size of these rings. So
let me tell you a back of the envelope
calculation which will be very useful
for us
and you can make all of this precise
but let's do this a little bit more
heristically.
So we know from Sterling's approximation
that n factorial behaves like n e to the
n time square of 2i n. Now
I'll tell you right now what I want to
do is I want to figure out what the size
of the rings are. So I want to use
Sterling's approximation to figure out
uh some sort of expression for a
binomial coefficient. And that's where
the entropy is going to pop out. Now I
can tell you right now that for
Sterling's approximation when we apply
it to the thing I'm about to do this
term doesn't matter. So if you want you
can just ignore it. I'll still keep
track of it. But you know let's progress
right? So let's move on. So what I
really care about is understanding the
behavior of n choose pn.
This makes sense, right? because you
know I start off with a message which is
say all zeros the let's say that's the
transmission that I send along the
channel and what I could care about is
you know how many outputs are reasonably
likely right certainly if my trans uh my
flip probability on the channel is a
third then I should expect that my
output started off with no ones and
after I send it through the channel
maybe I end up with n over three ones
That's just p* n and what I care about
is how many you know outputs I'm
reasonably likely to get from my
channel. So I care about what are the
asmtoics of this quantity right and I
can use the fact that I can express the
binomial as ratios of you know
factorials
and I'll get out when I plug in
sterling's approximation I'll get this
you know mess of an expression that I
can simplify. So I get n / e to the n. I
get n p over e to the np. I get n * 1 -
p over e to the n * 1 - p. And then I
get some other stuff that I already told
you isn't going to matter, but let me
keep track of it anyways.
Okay.
And this is not mysterious, right?
Because you know this binomial is just n
factorial over pn factorial times 1
minus p n factorial. And these are the
leading order terms because these are
much much smaller.
Now what I can do is I can cancel things
out because this n the n cancels with
the n the np time n the n uh 1 minus one
p uh 1 minus p. This e to the n cancels
with the e down here. Uh the only thing
that'll be left over is I'll get 1 over
p to the np * 1 - p to the 1 - pn.
And then I can cancel a bunch of these
expressions if I want to. This is 2
pi n p * 1 minus p. So just some
algebra. Nothing fancy so far, right?
And now I'm in good shape because I can
take this expression and I can take the
log and divide by n. So what this tells
me is that 1 / n * log of n choose pn.
Well, this is exactly where the binary
entropy pops out, right? So, I get minus
p log p minus 1 - p log 1 minus p and
then all the other terms are much
smaller order because they behave like
log n / n. They're tiny compared to it.
So really what's going on is all of the
terms that don't cancel when I take
their log and divide by n that's exactly
where the binary entropy pops out
and that's why entropy shows up in
Shannon's theorem. So this is really
just saying that the limit
as n goes to infinity of 1 /n time log
of this binomial coefficient n choose pn
behaves like the binary entropy of p.
So this is a key you know algebraic fact
that we're going to appeal to in our
proof of correctness and our proof that
lema one holds is just this fact. We're
going to see a bunch of binomials in
there and I'm just going to think about
them in terms of the binary entropy
instead. Right?
All right.
So now let's go back to you know this
lema one and let me tell you some basic
facts that are going to be key
ingredients on the proof of lema one.
This part is really just calculational
to get to the proof of lema one. But
let's state, you know, one of our key
facts. Fact one. Well, I claim that you
know ring
gamma of C, the size of it, the number
of strings that are contained in this
set is bounded by like 2 to the entropy
of P
plus or minus gamma
time N.
So all this is is really it's related to
this fact, right? Think about the case
where you know gamma is zero for our
definition of the ring. All that's
happening is the number of things that
are in our ring is n choose pn.
And so our fact tells us that in that
case when gamma equals zero it behaves
like you know 2 to the entropy of p * n.
That's literally what this expression
means when I multiply through by n and
take you know everything to the uh in
the exponent of two. And as I take this
thickness gamma to be something but you
know ultimately I'm going to care about
this thickness going to zero as n goes
to infinity. It's only going to be some
fudge factor in the exponent. So you can
write down this fact more precisely.
It's a bit tedious because it involves a
lot of algebraic expressions, but this
is really how the size of the ring
behaves up to some fudge factor that
depends on the width of the ring. It's 2
to the entropy of P * N. That's our
first fact, right?
And so now um
what I claim is that uh you know we can
get into these questions like how should
I choose gamma? What I claim is that
there
is a gamma
such that with probability
at least 1 - epsilon / 2
p minus gamma n
and that is a lower bound for the
hamming distance between c tilda and c
and p plus gamma n is an upper bound.
So we can forget about how we're
connecting this to coding theory right
now. This is a purely probabistic
question. I take any message C of length
N and I send it along the channel and
then I observe C tilda and remember that
C tilda just comes from flipping each
bit independently with probability P. So
I can care about you know how many flips
were introduced. This is really just the
standard coin flipping question is I
want bounds on the probability that the
number of times I flipped the bit is
larger than its expectation or is
smaller than its expectation. And if my
gamma is some appropriately chosen
slack, then I can guarantee that you're
not outside of these bounds with all but
some tiny failure probability. Okay. So
all this is is this follows
because we've proven things very much
like this. It follows from you know
chebbev [clears throat]
or the weak law of large numbers
because as n goes to infinity you expect
the empirical number of bit flips you
get to be very very close to the
expected number p * n.
So with these two facts, we're now in
good shape for trying to prove lema one.
So let's put these things together and
prove lema one.
So how does the proof of lema one go?
Our key lema and Shannon's theorem. So
first of all, you know from fact two
We have
the probability that C tilda, how did I
write it there? C tilda belongs to the
ring for some appropriately chosen gamma
around CI
is you know at least 1 minus epsilon /
2. So my failure probability is at most
epsilon over two.
And now what we can do is let's bound
the other probability.
So let's bound the failure probability
of the other event
namely that C tilda belongs to some
other guy's ring.
And so what we can do is we can fix
J not equal to I. So one of the other
code words in our code book
and what we can do is you know in that
case
the probability that C tilda belongs to
the ring of some width gamma around CJ.
Well I claim that this is the same
thing. This is one of the key tricks in
here is the same thing as the
probability that CJ belongs
to the ring of C tilda.
So this looks like a pretty obvious
statement, right? Because this notion of
ring is just symmetric, right? It
doesn't, you know, whether if C tilda
belongs to CI's ring, that's the same
thing as vice versa, right? if CI
belongs to C tilda's ring but what's
going on here is we have to go back to
how exactly we chose the code book to
see why this is important right is that
you know app priori this might seem like
a fairly complicated event to analyze
right because I have you know some um
you know message that's received by my
decoder that's cilda
what's the chance he belongs to some
other ring around CJ J. The key point is
that when I express the probability this
way, remember I chose each of those code
words randomly.
So what I could do is I could run the
whole experiment in my head but be lazy
about when I choose CJ. So you tell me
you're sending CI along the channel.
Fine. You tell me you're sending that
particular message. I fix what CI is. We
send CI through the channel and we
receive C tilda. But only now after I
receive C tilda do I pick what CJ is.
And you know the chance that CJ if it's
a uniformally random string lands in
this particular ring I can bound that
based on the size of the ring. So now I
can appeal to fact one right. So you
know uh we can upperbound this
probability by
you know this 2 to the entropy of p plus
or minus the slack gamma n over 2 to the
n just because that's the size of the
ring c tilda is exactly this quantity
from fact one and we're choosing cj
uniformly at random from all of the
strings of length n that are binary. So
we get exactly this expression.
And so now we're in good shape because
we can appeal to a union bound
because we don't care about this just
for one particular J. We care about it,
you know, for all J not equal to I.
Right? So now by a union bound
the probability
that C tilda belongs to any ring
around a CJ where J is not equal to I.
Okay, the probability that's true for
any J is at most the size of our code
book times this probability 2 to the
entropy of P plus or minus gamma N over
2 to the N. So this is just a simple
union bound right
and now what we can do right uh if you
ignore this gamma what's going on is I
have you know um my code book remember
looks like uh 2 to the 1us entropy of
you know it looks like you know this
code book right here is 2 * 2 to the rn
and we're assuming that r is strictly
less than 1 - entropy of P. What's going
on right here is I have you know 2 the
minus 1us entropy of P. So the point is
that you know once my rate is strictly
smaller than what's happening in the
exponent over here then I'm in good
shape because this probability goes to
zero as n goes to infinity.
So that's the proof of our key lema,
right? It's really just the counting
argument at the end of the day is that
you know my code isn't so large like I
union bound over all of the things in my
code book. I look at the size of each of
these rings compared to the size of the
underlying domain. And as long as the
size of my code book times the size of
the ring is strictly smaller than my
domain even you know asmtoically then
I'm in good shape. Right? So this proves
these two key facts. We know that the
probability you don't belong to the ring
you start with is very small is at most
epsilon over two by the weak law of
large numbers.
And we know by a unionbound an
accounting argument that the probability
that you belong to any other ring is
very small. And the key, you know, step
that we used was really this
transformation right here. That the
probability that C tilda belongs to
another ring because the CJs are chosen
randomly. That's the same as the
probability that my newly sampled CJ
belongs to the ring around C tilda. So
are there any questions about this? This
is one of the key proofs for today is
the proof of this key lema. Any
questions?
Give me a thumbs up.
Good. All right.
So now let's use this lema
and there'll be another trick. It's a
subtle trick, but it's a cool trick. So,
I need a little bit more terminology and
then we're going to be able to prove
Shannon's theorem
because one of the things to think about
is that so far our attempt at proving
Shannon's theorem, we're choosing a
random code book, right?
And that code book then defines you know
what the encoding and the decoding
functions are. Our encoding sends each
message to one of those you know
randomly chosen code words in our code
book. Our decoder just looks at you know
which messages ring you belong to. But
at the end of the day to prove Shannon's
theorem I don't want to argue that a
random code is usually good. I want to
show that there's a code that's always
good.
So that subtlety is really where the
probabilistic method is going to show
up, right? Is because we have to argue
that there actually is one fixed choice
of this random code book that makes
everything small. And this is a little
bit subtle to really prove this
statement. But I need some more
intuition, right? I need some more
notation. So I'm going to let EI of my
code book script C be the event
that everything goes well that you know
I send in my if code word from my code
book through the binary symmetric
channel.
I get out some received message C tilda
I and I have exactly the properties that
are promised to me in this key lema lema
one. I want that my received thing
belongs to the ring
around CI and it belongs to no other
ring
and this is true for all J not equal to
I. So notice that this event now is a
property of the actual code book too,
right? It's a property of what errors
the uh channel introduces and a property
of the choice of the code book.
And what we're going to do is we're
finally going to let lambda I of C
denote one minus the probability that
this event happens.
So it's really the probability that
there's a decoding failure. But notice
that the decoding failure then depends
on what the original that probability
depends on the choice of the code book
and it depends on which message we're
sending. All right.
And so what I claim we just proved
through lema one is the following
statement.
We proved that the average over all of
the possible code books
because we're choosing these code books
uniformly at random.
The average over all of the messages
that we want to send
of having a decoding failure is small.
So what does this thing say? Right?
Let's parse this in English. When I
choose a random code book, this is the
average over a random code book. When I
choose a random message that I want to
encode, the probability that I have a
decoding error for that codebook and
that message on the binary symmetric
channel is at most epsilon. Right? This
is not the same thing as saying that
there exists a code book that's always
good for every message.
And that's exactly what we have to try
and twist the statement into. So we
proved through lema one was this. And we
really need something else that gets rid
of this average over code words, right?
And so what I claim now is you know by
the probabilistic method
we claim that there exists a code book
with the property that the average over
all the messages
of the decoding failure probability is
at most epsilon. So the probabistic
method is one of these things where you
know it looks very natural sometimes
when you state it but other times when
it's happening you know with other
layers of abstraction it's a bit harder
to wrap your head around right so you
know like we use the probabilistic
method to show things like um you know
if we choose that there's a graph that
has no large clique or no large
independent set we'll talk about that I
guess later and um you know here we're
really using the probabistic method the
same way that I know that this
expectation of this quantity inside is
small over a typical code book. So there
must exist one code book where it's
small as well. Right? So does everyone
see how I got from here to here using
the probabistic method. Is that all
right? Yeah.
Okay.
So uh now we're in good shape and I can
tell you you know how to finish the rest
of the argument.
Let's see how much space I need. Not too
much.
So now we're starting to make progress
because instead of saying over a random
code book over a random message our
decoding failure is small, we know that
you know we have a code book where the
average over the messages the decoding
error rate is small, right?
Um, but we really care about back to our
original statement of what we wanted to
prove was we want that there's a code
book so that every message can be
decoded well not a random message. So we
have one remaining expectation that we
want to prune which is this average over
m right and now we're going to do it in
a kind of cool way which is you know I
claim by markoff bound
We know that at least
half
of the eyes
satisfy
the bound that lambda i of c is at most
2 epsilon.
So this is our old friend the marov
bound, right? Because you know we're
looking at random variables that are 01
valued like did you have a decoding
failure
and if the average over these messages
one through m that we want to send has
the decoding failure probability bounded
by epsilon on average we know that for
at least a half of the realizations the
probability that they're larger than 2
epsilon the decoding failure probability
is you know is small right so this is
the usual thing that if this weren't
true then the expectation would be
higher because these are non-gative
random variables. And so now what we can
do is we can let C prime our eventual
code book be the code book
restricted
to just these messages
just these code words
the ones that satisfy this condition
right here that their lambda I for that
particular choice of the code book is at
most two epsilon.
So what does this mean? Just you know
putting this back into English, right?
It means that this new codebook C prime
is itself an R N
encoding.
That's exactly why I started off with my
original code book was on capital M
things where M was equal to 2 * 2 R N
right was exactly this extra factor of
two that I was going to have to give up
when I went from C to C prime. So
whatever's left is still an RN N
encoding because there are two to the RN
things in it. And we know just by
unwrapping the definition of what lambda
IC is. What this means is the
probability that you know C tilda I is
not equal to
uh sorry uh that the probability that M
tilda is not equal to M is at most 2
epsilon because literally the way we
defined this was you know how often we
expect for the given code word to have a
decoding failure probability on that
particular message.
So the only you know code words that
survived were exactly ones who when I
fix the codebook and I fix the message
have a very small failure probability of
getting the wrong decoding.
So this proves you know the the most
interesting part of Shannon's theorem
that we can get positive rate and error
probability going to zero. So we can
drastically improve upon uh you know the
uh repetition code. If you actually work
out the details, what ends up happening
is that it's not just that the
probability of failure goes to zero. The
probability of failure actually goes to
zero exponentially fast, which is really
cool. So it's way better than the
repetition code on a few different
fronts. If I wanted the failure
probability to be exponentially small
for my repetition code, I would have had
to increase it way beyond this log K
blow up. So a bunch of people at the
time really thought that, you know, the
repetition code was optimal. So this
came as quite a surprise uh that this
was not true.
Um I will briefly give you the intuition
behind uh you know the sec the first
part of Shannon's theorem and then we'll
call it a day.
So remember that the first part of
Shannon's theorem
was that you can't communicate at a rate
larger than the capacity 1 minus entropy
of P. If you do the um you know the
probability of getting the correct
message is going to go to zero. Right?
And so let me give you very briefly the
intuition. So let's suppose that we had
a coding scheme where the rate was
larger than the capacity 1 minus entropy
of P.
And let's suppose for the sake of
contradiction that it really wasn't such
a bad coding scheme. Maybe the
probability that it successfully decoded
the message is at least some epsilon
like 0.01 let's say.
Well, what we're going to argue is that
um you know we'll prove a contradiction
that the rate really cannot be this
large. So the main point is that
an epsilon over 2
fraction
of ring
gamma CI
must be decoded
to CI.
So you know here the point is like
originally our decoder was just based on
the ring right but now we have no idea
what the decoder is but the same way
whatever our decoder is we know that you
know when we pass through this
transmission along the channel we're
going to end up in this ring right
because that was you know the first part
of lema one was just that we land in the
ring with all but very small failure
probability and once we're in this ring
because that's always where we land. The
fact that we're successfully decoding
the original message is just saying
that, you know, among these outputs that
we often reach, well, you know, many of
them must be decoded to the correct
message, right? That's just the
definition of that's just the
translation of what this statement
means.
But now the point is that
but the C tildas
that are decoded
to different CIS
must be joint right
because your decoding function has to
map you to a unique original message. So
if I look at you know over all these
different messages which things are
decoded to it is you know each of these
sets are disjoint. And so what does this
mean? Well if we add up just the total
volume of these sets right we know that
they're at least an epsilon over two
fraction of the ring. We know that
there's one of these rings for each of
the code book. We know that the ring has
size 2 to the entropy of p * n. But you
know this cannot be larger than 2 to the
n because that's the number of possible
c tildas there are period right and so
when we rearrange this bound we'll get
exactly the thing we wanted that the
size of my code book is at most
something like you know 2 to the 1 minus
entry of p times n. So this is just
meant as a sketch because really to do
this precisely I would have to prove a
lot of you know the helper lemmas here
and give similar kinds of bounds but you
know the intuition is much simpler and
we're only going to ask you about really
the second part for Shannon's theorem.
So are there any questions
about this?
>> Yeah sorry
>> yeah that's right sure. So what is the
statement saying right here is that at
least an epsilon fraction. So if I look
at you know when I start off with CI
and I look at you know the output after
the binary symmetric channel then at
least an epsilon fraction of those
outputs must be successfully decoded to
the correct original message. Now almost
all of the outputs live in the ring. So
if we just throw out all the things that
aren't in the ring, we're not really
changing, you know, what the output
distribution looks like from our BSC.
And that means that we still must have
at least a large fraction of this ring
must also be successfully decoded. To
fully prove this would be a lot more
work and would be a bit tedious, but
that's the intuition.
Any other questions? Great questions,
though.
Okay, so um let me end with a little bit
of a historical perspective. So this
Shannon theorem is quite amazing. Um
it's actually not uh such a perfectly
ideal scheme. So we have the same kinds
of issues that we had in you know
Shannon's uh noiseless coding theorem
right so we proved Shannon's noless
coding theorem about how well we can
compress a first order source but then
the thing I complained about was the
fact that really if we were to execute
the scheme I would have to write down
the full uh set of you know encodings
and that would be gigantic I'd have to
anticipate everything you could want
ever want to compress and write down
this code book of what to compress it
to. Same problem happens here that you
know choosing this code book uh script C
randomly is very convenient for the
proof because it makes it easier to
reason via the probabilistic method. It
makes it easier to reason about you know
failure probabilities of events because
it boils down to some combinatorics of
the sizes of rings. But the trouble is
that this would be a horrible coding
scheme if I really had to write down
exponentially many things and define my
code book. So what Peter is going to be
talking about on Tuesday is a very
powerful paradigm which is called a
linear code. So instead of explicitly
writing down all of the codes in my code
words in my code book, I can instead
implicitly describe them as matrix
vector products. All of my messages are
vectors and my code book describes a
matrix and when I want to encode some
you know message as you know what it
maps to as the code word I just take the
matrix times the vector. So this now
becomes a much more concise way to you
know define the code book. So he'll tell
you about um you know linear codes.
And then the other thing which you know
that next lecture will touch on is that
right now the crucial assumption that we
used in the proof of the theorems today
was the fact that the binary symmetric
channel introduced flips randomly.
So bit by bit it had a third probability
of introducing a flip. Now it turns out
there are other models for codes where
you could instead think about worst
case. What if sitting on your channel is
an adversary who gets to corrupt a third
of your bits, but they get to choose
when and how to corrupt those bits?
That's called adversarial coding. And we
can get similar semantics there where we
want an encoding and decoding function
that now works even if the channel is
not stochastic but is bounded in terms
of its budget of corruptions. So for
those types of problems in general, we
don't understand such uh tight
trade-offs as we do for Shannon. but
he'll tell you about linear codes and
he'll tell you about adversarial
decoding. And then after Peter's done
with that, I'll tell you about some
other topics it's connected to, namely
cryptography and secret sharing. And
then the semester will be over. So just
to give you a little bit of a preview of
uh what we're going to cover in the
remaining lectures. But let's stop here
and I'll take any questions you guys
have offline. Thanks.