All
right. So today's lecture introduction
to neural networks and deep learning. Um
so we'll start with a very quick intro
to these things. Um and then we'll
switch and dive deep into neural
networks. All right. So the field of AI
originated in 1956. Sadly didn't
originate at MIT. It originated at
Dartmouth because all these people got
together at Dartmouth. I guess it's it's
got a nice quad or whatever. They got
together. They defined the field. But
fortunately for us, MIT was very well
represented. So we have Marvin Minsky
who founded the MIT AI lab. John
McCarthy who invented lisp and then
later defected to the west coast and
then Claude Shannon who invented
information theory right who was a
professor at MIT. So MIT was well
represented. These folks, you know,
founded the field and they were so
bright. They thought that AI was going
to be substantially solved quote unquote
by that fall.
Okay. Now, obviously it turned out a bit
differently than what they expected. Uh
so it's been whatever 67 68 years since
its founding. So it's gone through
essentially in my opinion three seminal
breakthroughs. Um starting with the
traditional approach then machine
learning, deep learning and generative
AI. So let's take a very quick look at
each of these breakthroughs and what
motivated them. So let's start with the
traditional approach to AI. And so what
is AI? AI informally is the ability to
imbue computers with the the the ability
to do things that only humans can
typically do. Cognitive tasks, thinking
tasks, and things like that. And so the
most sort of common sensical way to do
that is to say, well, if I want the
computer to do something complicated
like play chess, I'm just going to sit
down with a few chess grand masters,
show them a whole bunch of board moves,
and ask them how they figure out how to
respond, how to play the next move. I'm
going to sort of sit down, talk to all
these people, and then I'm going to
write down a whole bunch of rules. If
this is the board position, move this.
If this is the board position, move
this, and so on and so forth. Or I might
sit down with the cardiologist and tell
them, okay, how do you actually
interpret an ECG? they will give me all
similarly a bunch of if then rules I
will take all these rules I'll put them
into the computer and boom I have a
system that can do what a human can do
right now this approach even though it's
common sensical and kind of makes sense
it had success in only a few areas u and
so the interesting question is why was
it not pervasively successful why was it
not pervasively successful it seems like
a pretty good idea to me right and the
people who came up with these things are
smart people they're not dumb people
they know what they're doing so why did
it not book
>> because because it's time in intensive.
So it means that you have to run through
all the scenarios that can ever exist
and still some new scenarios can come up
that you didn't cater for in
>> Right. So there are two aspects to what
you said which is the first aspect is
it's time intensive that as it turns out
is not a big deal because computers are
getting faster and faster
[clears throat]
right the second thing is actually the
key thing which is that it doesn't
generalize to new situations very well
right the problem is there are an
infinite number of things that you're
going to see when you deploy these
systems in the real world by definition
what you're training it on is a small
sample of rules so these rules are very
brittle but there's actually an even
more interesting reason and that reason
is that we know more than we can tell.
This is called Polani paradox. So the
idea is that if I come to you and say,
"Hey, uh here's a picture. Is it a dog
or a cat?" You will tell me within I
believe they've measured it like 20
milliseconds or something, you know,
it's a dog if it's a dog or a cat. And
then if I ask you to explain to me
exactly how you figure that out, you'll
come up with a bunch of sort of reasons,
right? Alleged reasons. Oh, you know, if
it has whiskers, I think it's a cat or
whatever. But the problem is that you
actually first of all can't really
articulate what's going on in your head.
how you do these things and number two
even if you articulate it often times
your articulation has no correspondence
with how your brain actually does it
so you're incomplete under a liar
so this is polanous paradox so if you
can't even tell me how you do something
how the heck am I supposed to take it
and put into a computer doesn't work and
second is the fact that we can't write
down these rules for all possible
situations edge cases corner cases etc
and the world is full of edge cases so
for these reasons this approach didn't
work and so a different approach was
developed and this approach was well
basically said hey instead of explicitly
telling the computer what to do why
don't we simply give it lots of examples
of inputs and outputs chest positions
next move right ECG diagnosis right
inputs and outputs and then why don't we
just use some statistical techniques to
learn a mapping a function that can go
from the input to the output okay that
was the idea and this idea is machine
learning okay so machineing learning is
basically just a fancy way of saying
learn from input output examples using
statistical techniques.
Good. All right. So, um, now there are
numerous ways to create machine learning
models and if you have ever done linear
regression, congratulations. You've been
doing machine learning.
Okay? And only one of those methods
happens to be something called neural
networks. There are many other methods
and in fact you probably have done these
other methods if you have done the a
course like the analytics edge or
something similar.
Okay. So, machine learning has got
tremendous impact around the world,
right? It's like at this point u it's
widely accepted. It's a very very
successful technology. And in fact,
whenever people are actually talking
about AI, chances are they're actually
talking about machine learning. It's
just that AI sounds cooler.
The only problem is for machine learning
to work really well, the input data has
to be structured. Okay? And what I mean
by that is data that can essentially be
sort of numericalized and stuck into the
columns and rows of a spreadsheet.
Right? So for example here, let's say I
want to put together a data set of you
know uh patients, their symptoms and
their characteristics and then in the
following year after they showed up at
the doctor's office whether they had a
cardiac event or not, I might create a
data set like this with age, smoking
status, yes, no, exercise, blah blah
blah blah blah. Right? And so either
these numbers are numbers, they're
numerical. Or if they're not numerical,
they're categorical,
right? Yes, no. Uh smoking, yes, no,
things like that. Which means that if
you have categorical variables, you can
just numericalize them pretty easily.
You folks have done the some machine
learning before. So you know things like
one hotend coding and stuff like that
can be done to make them all numerical.
So the point is you can just render the
data into the columns and rows of a
spreadsheet pretty easily, right? That's
what I mean by structured data. So when
you but the situation is very different
if you have unstructured data. So if you
have an image of you know a cute puppy
this is my puppy by the way um uh from
many years ago sadly he's no more um but
his name was Google.
So yeah anyway uh uh my DMD alums know
Google well. So this is Google right? If
you want to take Google uh this picture
and figure out how to sort of
numericalize it, the first thing you
want to need to understand is that if
you actually look at how this picture is
represented inside uh digitally in the
computer, basically every picture like
this is represented using three tables
of numbers. Okay? And these and we'll
get to what these numbers mean later on.
But the point I'm making is that each
number basically represents the amount
of light,
right? on a scale of 0 to 255 the amount
of light in that location in that pixel.
That's all the amount of light. So
basically the this table is the amount
of um sorry
this table is amount of red light,
amount of green light, amount of blue
light. Okay. Now you will agree with me
that if you for example look at
something like this and say okay 251 at
this location there is a lot of blue
light because it's 251 out of a possible
255 right maybe a lot of blue light
somewhere here there's a lot of blue
here
whether that area is blue because of a
piece of sky some water or a bunch of
blue paint could be anything it's going
to say 251. So the underlying reality,
the underlying object that's being
described has nothing to do with the
251. Right? So that's the whole problem.
The raw form of the data has no
intrinsic meaning with the underlying
thing. So given that there's no
connection between the number and what
it's describing, how the heck can any
algorithm do anything with it? It can't.
Right? So what you have to do is
something called feature engineering or
feature extraction. Right? where you
have to manually take all these things
and create essentially a spreadsheet
from them. So basically, let's say that
you have a bunch of birds, right? And
you're trying to build a bird classifier
to figure out what kind of bird species
it is. You might actually have to take
this picture and then you have to
measure the beak length, the wingspan,
the primary color, and so on and so
forth. So you're basically structuring
the unstructured data manually, right?
And this process of structuring
unstructured data is basically called
we use the word representation. We take
the raw data and we represent the data
in a different form. And the the reason
why I'm sort of focusing on the use of
the word representation is because it
becomes really really important a bit
later on when we get to deep learning.
Okay. So we have to represent the data
in a different way for it to work.
That's the basic idea. All right. So
what that means is that u historically
researchers would manually develop these
representations and once you develop
them once you representations you could
just use traditional linear regression
or logistic regression get the job done.
So the whole name of the game is the
representations. So in fact people doing
PhDs for example in computer revision
would spend like four years developing
amazing representations for solving one
particular little problem. Right? we
have a bunch of say cat scans and we
need to take the cat scan and figure out
whether a particular kind of stroke
there is evidence for it in the cat scan
right they might actually sit and
develop all kinds of representations and
test it and so on and then they'll
finally declare victory and say yay I'm
done with my PhD here is this amazing
representation and you can build a
classifier with it to predict a
particular kind of stroke with high
accuracy okay so that was that that's
where the world was uh now as you can
imagine developing representations
because it's so manual Well, is this
massive human bottleneck and this
sharply limited limited the reach and
applicability of machine learning as you
would expect
to address this problem a different
approach came about and that's deep
learning. So deep learning sits inside
machine learning. Okay. And deep
learning can handle unstructured input
data without upfront manual processing.
Meaning it will automatically learn the
right representations from the raw
input. Automatically is the key word.
Automatically learn representations.
Which means that you can give it
structured data, you can give it
pictures, you can give it text, you can
give it anything you want. It'll just
learn it. Okay. um it can automatically
extract these representations and since
it's being automatically extracted you
can imagine sort of a pipeline where the
raw data comes in you have a bunch of
stuff in the middle that's learning
these representations automatically
without your help and then boom you just
attach a little linear regression or
logistic regression at the end problem
solved
that in a nutshell is deep learning
input a whole bunch of representations
being learned and then piped into a
linear or logistic regression model okay
you So the amazing thing is this simple
idea, this simple idea is just
incredibly powerful, right? That idea
has led to Chad GPT has led to Alpha Go,
Alpha Fold and so on and so forth. And I
I kid you not, I'm sort of I I've been
doing deep learning for about 10 years
now. And every time I look at it, I
literally get goosebumps every so often
that that something so simple could be
so powerful, right? It's really like
boggles the mind. I'm like I'm just so
lucky to be alive and working during
this period.
Okay. And you know coming from people
who have been in the industry a long
time this sort of breathless exclamation
is not very rare particularly because
I'm not in marketing.
Okay. I actually mean it
with all your apologies to various
marketing folks. So just realized it's
being taped. So uh okay. So so this
demolished the human bottleneck for
using machine learning with unstructured
data. uh and so it comes from the
confluence of three forces uh new
algorithmic ideas a whole a lot of data
and then very importantly the fact that
we have access to parallel computing
hardware in the in the form of these
things called GPUs graphics processing
units u and these three forces came
together and they were applied to an old
idea called neural networks and that's
basically deep learning and I'll go
through it very quickly because
obviously we're going to spend half the
semester looking into this thing in
detail uh so what's the immediate
immediate application of the ability to
automatically handle unstructured data.
What is like the no-brainer application?
It's okay if it's obvious. Tell me
>> sorry.
>> Um, image classification,
>> right? So, image classification. Yes.
So, you can take an image, a good
example of unstructured data, you can do
some classification on it. But more
generally, more generally, what I'm
getting at is that every sensor in the
world can be given the ability to
detect, recognize, and classify what
it's sensing. Every sensor because
remember what is a what does a sensor
do? A sensor is just a receptacle for
unstructured data. A camera is a
receptacle for unstructured video or
unstructured, you know, still images,
microphone, unstructured audio, right?
So every sensor you can you can imagine
taking a sensor and sticking a little
deep learning system behind it and now
suddenly the what comes out of this
center of the deep learning system you
can count you can classify you can
detect you can do all kinds of stuff in
short you can analyze
and you can predict right and this is
the way I'm describing it right now
you'll be like yeah duh obviously
but you know what this obviously thing
is actually not at all obvious in terms
of whether it'll help you find
interesting applications or not. Okay,
so here is something I literally saw
last week. Okay, actually I have another
slide before that but we are coming to
that. So for instance, every time you
use Face ID unlock your phone, this is
the basic principle at work, right? The
the camera and the iPhone is the sensor
and they stuck a deepline system behind
it to do image classification, right?
Rama, non-RAM, right? That's what it's
classifying. Um and so here right you
have a breast cancer this is the breast
cancer detection system from a mamogram.
Uh by the way this picture is a very
interesting picture. So uh there's a
professor in WCS uh Regina Barceli who's
a very well-known expert in this field
and uh she actually has built a breast
cancer detection system which is which
has been deployed at Mass General
Hospital and turns out she's actually a
breast cancer survivor and uh she was
know she's she's she's good now all good
but when um after she built her system I
heard that she actually ran that system
against the mamograms from many years
prior when she went for a mammogram and
was told that everything is fine. She
ran the system on that mamogram and it
came back and said here's a problem. So
a very interesting example where a deep
learning system picked up something that
a radiologist could not right. So these
things are can be quite powerful. Um
obviously any self-driving system has
numerous deep learning algorithms
running under the hood. you know,
pedestrian detection, you know, stop
light detection, zebra crossing
detection, so on and so forth. Um, you
know, it's being very heavily used in
visual inspection manufacturing. Uh, you
have various cameras now in which people
looking at saying, okay, there's a dent
or there's a scratch. They have a little
system which is a dent detector, scratch
detector and so on. That's that's going
on right now. And now I come to the
example I saw last week which is um so
this is an example of you can create
dramatically better products if you
really internalize this idea of okay
it's almost like you're looking the the
world and saying oh there's a sensor can
attach a DL thing behind it that's the
way you should be looking at the world
okay for startup ideas. So, here's an
example. Okay, these apparently are the
world's first smart binoculars.
Okay, this is the binocular
2 weeks ago where you look at the bird.
You look at the bird and now it tells
you what kind of bird it is right there.
It's a simple idea, but imagine, right?
Imagine you are the first out of the
gate with this feature. You'll have a
little bit of an edge till everybody
catches up like 3 months later.
Let's be very clear. There are no
long-term monopoly windows in the world.
There are only short-term windows. So
the the the hunt is always on for a
little monopoly window. So here's an
example of that. Right? So I encourage
you to always think about the world as
you know where are the sensors here and
can I attach something behind the sensor
to do something useful with it. Okay?
All right.
Now let's turn our attention to the
output. You have been talking about in
structured data, unstructured data and
how deep learning has sort of unlocked
the ability to work with unstructured
data. But you've sort of been neglecting
the output side of the equation. So
traditionally uh we could predict single
numbers or a few numbers pretty easily,
right? So you've all done the canonical,
you know, uh should this person be given
a loan application in machine learning,
right? So it just predicts the
probability that a borrower will repay a
loan based on a whole bunch of data or
supply chain you predict the demand for
a product next week or you can predict a
bunch of numbers. So given a given a
picture you can say okay does it which
which one of the 10 kinds of furniture
is it right? You can predict 10 numbers
10 probabilities that add up to one. You
can predict a whole bunch of numbers
that don't have to add up to one such as
the GPS coordinates of a of an Uber
ride. So these are all simple unstructur
sorry simple structured output just a
few numbers right what we could not do
very easily was to actually generate
pictures like this
we could not generate unstructured data
we could only consume unstructured data
right u you couldn't generate text you
can generate pictures and so on audio
and so on and so forth so with
generative AI that problem is gone so
generative AI is the ability to actually
create unstructured data right and
therefore it sits within deep learning
It still runs on deep learning, but it's
just one kind of deep learning.
Okay, there's plenty of stuff going on
in deep learning that's got nothing to
do with generative AI. Nowadays, of
course, you know, if you're a
self-respecting entrepreneur who wants
to ride this craze, you'll probably
declare whatever you're doing as
generative AI, right? Um, and some VCs
may actually be ready to fund you. Who
knows? But the point is there's plenty
of stuff going on in deep learning
that's got nothing to do with genative
AI. Uh, but this is the overall picture.
Now here uh we can produce unstructured
outputs like pictures. You can take this
thing and then you can actually you know
come up with a nice picture description
of it. This actually is a very famous
picture by the way in uh in the world of
computer vision. So we are actually
going to be analyzing this picture a
little later on in the semester. Uh you
can obviously go from a very complicated
caption to an image. Uh you can go from
text to music.
Can people hear it? Okay. Yeah. Yeah.
All right. So and of course we can go
from text to text i.e. chat GPD. Uh and
then uh as of a few months ago things
have gotten even more interesting where
you can actually go you can send text
and an image in and you can get text out
right and in fact as of a few weeks ago
you can send text image text image text
image in an arbitrary sequence into into
the system and it actually come back to
you with text and image. Right? So
things are becoming multimodal and I
just want to share it with you like a
really fun example I saw uh recently. So
this person sends this picture. Can
folks see this? This is very complicated
parking sign apparently in San
Francisco. And they're like, "It's
Wednesday at 4 p.m. Can I park here?
Tell me in one line." Because you really
didn't want GPD4 to be giving you a big
essay about this. Like you literally
want to park. So GPD4 comes back and
says, "Yes, you can park here for up to
1 hour starting at 4 p.m." And folks, I
double check this thing. It's correct.
We all know these things hallucinate,
right? Can you imagine getting a parking
ticket and telling the judge, "I'm
sorry, I didn't realize it was
hallucinating." So, so you have to
double check it. So, yeah. So, things
are getting multimodal very quickly. Uh,
and so the picture here is that within
Genai, we used to have these separate
circles, text to text, text to image,
text to music, text to this, text to
that, so on and so forth. Those are all
beginning to merge now inside Jai
because multimodal models are going to
become the norm this year, right? We
already have really good closed models.
We really have, we actually already have
very good open source multimodal models.
And so my feeling is that by the end of
the year the idea of using a texton
model is going to be like really you do
that still right it's going to become
like a quaint oldfashioned thing I think
multimodal modality is going to become
the norm. So that's where the world is
and this is the landscape. So any
questions on the landscape
before we actually start doing some
math.
>> Okay.
Yeah.
>> Um not related to the landscape but it's
more related to the breast cancer
question. So how did how did she know
that it was actually like there is a
training that you can do and you there's
a testing you can do which is based on
the existing breast cancer samples but
he or she was taking the mamogs from
past 6 weeks past also which is probably
a smaller version which was not there
right like I mean there's an answer
>> you mean the the the evidence of that
being a problem would have been smaller
>> so how do you know your model is great
enough that it can correct it to give
you correct answers. So
>> yeah, so I think the so the question is
that in general how do you train your
model so that it gives you right answers
given that over the passage of time the
amount of evidence in this data could be
very highly variable. So in this
particular case of um you know the
professor I talked about um you
everything at that point was going
through an expert radiologist. So five
years ago this mamogram was seen by a
radiologist and that person concluded
there is no problem. So that was the
training label right the wrong training
label. Uh so typically what happens is
that training labels could be wrong some
small fraction of the time. So you need
to have systems that are robust. So your
data needs to be complete. It needs to
be comprehensive. It needs to be have
correct labels. If these ideas are not
met your systems are not going to be
that good. But as it turns out with
neural networks even with some amount of
noise in the labels they still do a
pretty good job. Right? So that's sort
of the general idea. So there has to be
some verification.
>> The ver the verification comes from the
human. So every remember when we look at
radiology data the the data we working
with is the input is let's say an image
like a radio a mamogram or something and
then a human radiologist or a set of
radiologists have said this has a
problem or does not have a problem. So
that is called the ground truth. So it
is this ground truth image and label
this combination that's being used to
train these models.
Yeah.
>> Embodiment. So, so are we are we going
to cover embodiment? So, the the the
embodiment here refers to the fact that
uh if you have robot robots, right? Uh
they need to actually operate in the
real world. And so, robots are an
example of what's called embodied
intelligence. So, unfortunately, due to
the constraints of time, we're not going
to get into robotics at all. But I will
say that a lot of the deep learning
stuff you're going to talk about, those
are all fundamental building blocks in
modern robotic systems.
All right. So um so in summary, X and Y
can be anything and it can be
multimodal.
Okay, I literally could not have put up
this slide maybe two years ago, right?
So it's very simple in how it looks, but
it's very profound. You can you can
learn a mapping from anything to
anything at this point very easily as
long as you have enough data. Okay. So u
now note that all this excitement that
we see around us is everything stems
from stems from deep learning. Okay.
Everything everything depends on deep
learning. And so if you understand deep
learning a lot of interesting things
become possible. So let's get going. All
right. So we'll start with the very
basics. Uh what's a neural network? Uh
now recall logistic regression from back
in the day. So what is logistic
regression? You send in a bunch of
numbers, a vector of numbers and you get
usually get a probability out, right?
Between zero and one, what is the
probability of something or the other?
Okay. Uh and so this logistic regression
model is also represented in this form
if you'll recall. So basically what we
do is we take all these numbers, we run
it through a linear function, right? We
run it through a linear function, you
get a number and then we take that thing
and run it through 1 / 1 plus e raised
to minus that. And that's guaranteed to
give you a number between zero and one
which can be interpreted as a
probability and that's logistic
regression. Okay. And the canonical you
know uh loan approvals things like that
all fall into this sort of convenient
bucket.
Okay. So this should be super familiar.
All right. Now we're going to actually
look at this you know simple modest
humble little operation
using the lens of a network of
mathematical operations and the reason
why we do it will become clear a bit
later so we'll take this very simple
example where we have uh let's say two
variables GPA and experience right this
is the GPA of some graduates uh number
of years of work experience and then
this is the dependent variable which is
either zero or one and zero if they
don't get called for an interview, one
if they get called for an interview.
Okay, it's a two input variable, one
output variable problem. Okay, and it's
a classification problem because we
classifying people into will they get
called for an interview, yes or no.
Okay,
and so that's a setup for this problem.
And let's say that we actually run it
through any, you know, we actually try
to fit a logic regression model to it.
So if you're familiar with R for
example, you would use something like
GLM to fit this model. Um if you use
something like stats models in Python,
there's a similar function for it.
Scikitlearn, there's another function
for it. You get the idea, right? This
you can use whatever favorite methods
you have for logistic regression
modeling to get this job done. And if
you do that with this little data set,
you're going to get these coefficients,
right? The point 4 is the intercept 02
is the coefficient of a GPA 0.5 for
experience and that is a resulting
sigmoid function. Okay. All right. Cool.
So now let's actually rewrite this
formula as a network in the following
way. So first what we'll do is we'll
take GP and experience and stick it here
on the left side and we'll put little
circles next to them and we'll call them
the input nodes. Okay. And so imagine
that somebody puts writes a GPA into the
circle 3.5 or you know years experience
2.0 zero and then it flows through this
arrow and as it flows through it gets
multiplied by its coefficient 2 the 2 is
coming from here
similarly experience gets multiplied
by.5 it comes in here and this node as
the plus indicates is adding everything
that's coming into it so it's adding2*
GPA.5 time experience plus the intercept
which is a green arrow coming from on
its own it comes through here and what
comes out of this is just a single
number and that number goes into this
little circle circle
and then out pops a probability. Okay,
so I've sort of done this ridiculously
long way long winded way of writing a
simple function. Okay, and the reason we
why I'm doing it will become clear in a
second.
Okay, so this is a little network of
operations for the simple function. And
so for instance, how you would use it is
you to make a prediction, you'll let's
say someone has a 3.8 GPA and 1.2 into
user experience. You just plug it in
here, do the math, you get 76. Same
thing here, comes in here, add them all
up, you get 1.76. You run 1.76 through
the sigmoid, you get 085. And that is
the probability that that particular
individual may get called for an
interview. Okay? At this point, we're
just doing logistic regression. Nothing
more complicated.
Okay. So, um, now if you have many
variables, not two variables like X1
through X K, you can the same sort of
logic applies. Each one has some
coefficient and then there's an
intercept. They all get added up here.
Run through a sigmoid and out pops this
number. Okay. Notice how the data flows
from left to right.
Okay. All right. Any questions on this?
All right. Good. So now terminology. Uh
so you will actually you'll discover
that the world of neural networks and
deep learning has its own terminology.
they have their own ways of referring to
things that we the rest of the world has
been referring using something else for
the longest time right it's kind of
annoying sometimes but it's the way it
is so uh
remember in regression we used to call
those numbers next to each variable as
coefficients and the constant thing as
an intercept well guess what in this
world these multip those coefficients
are actually called weights
and the inter are called biases so in in
the neural network world these are
called weights and biases and sometimes
if If you're a little lazy, you may just
call the whole thing as weights. Okay,
so when you see in the newspaper that
you know, oh my god, this amazing
model's weights have been leaked
on the internet or on Bit Torrent or
something, that's what's going on,
right? All these coefficients have been
leaked because once you know what the
coefficients are and what the
architecture is, you can just
reconstruct the model.
All right, so that's what's going on
here. Now, why did we do this network
business? Why did we write it as a
network?
Yeah. What is advantage? Any guesses?
>> When you have multiple functions,
so it's just easier to see it that way,
>> right? If you have lots of things going
on, it's easier to see it if you
actually write it in graphical form.
Yes, correct. But so is it only like a
usability advantage?
The other thing is you want different
functions for different layers of
>> okay so maybe we want to use different
functions in different layers but I
think there's actually even a larger
sort of a more basic point which is that
then when you the moment you write it
down you suddenly realize that I could
have lots of things in the middle
I don't have to go from the input to
output directly I could do lots of
things in the middle right that's sort
of the key idea so what you do is so
Remember the notion of learning
representations of unstructured data,
right? Where you take the picture and
say beak length and things like that,
right? And remember I said deep learning
actually automatically learns these
things. Where is that automatic learning
coming from?
Well, this is where it's coming from. So
what we do is we take this thing, right?
This just a logistic regression model.
inputs get multip added up as a linear
function or run through a sigmoid and
then we are like hm if we want to learn
representations of the raw input we
better be doing something in the middle
here
because the output is the output that
that's not going to change you know it's
it's either a dog or a cat you don't
have any choice as to what it is okay
the only agency you have at this point
is you can take the raw input and do
things in the middle with
You can do a lot of stuff in the middle
and then run it through something to get
the output. Okay. So in any in in any
mathematical discipline, if someone
comes to you and says here's a bunch of
data, I want you to do something with
it. What should the what is like the the
most basic first thing you should do?
Run it through a linear function.
The most basic thing in math is a linear
function. So given anything, just run it
through a linear function. See what
happens.
So that's exactly what we can do. So the
simplest thing we can do here, we can
insert a bunch of linear functions. So
we do is we take all this input and we
just run it. We we do a linear function
on it. So think of it this as x1 * 2
plus x3 * 4 and all the way to xk * 9
plus some intercept and boom, it goes
out the other end. So this little circle
here with a plus in it is just
thank you. uh that this is just a linear
it's a shortand for a linear function.
So whenever you see a circle with a plus
it's just a short hand for a linear
function. Okay. So you can take this
whole thing and run through a linear
function and when you do it you'll get
some number right there. You'll get some
number. So you have taken these k
numbers and you have sort of compressed
them in some way into one number. Okay.
But you don't have to stop at one
number. You can do more. So we can have
a stack of linear functions in the
middle. Right? There's a linear function
here. Another one here. Another one
here. At this point, the K numbers you
have K could be, for example, a
thousand, right? It's just the size of
your input data. You have taken these K
things and you've compressed them into
three numbers at this point. Okay? So,
okay, maybe three is the right number,
maybe 10 is the right number. We don't
know. And we'll get to how do we know
what the right number is later on. So,
we can stack as many linear functions as
we want. So, we have transformed this K
thing into a threedimensional vector,
right? K numbers become three numbers.
Um and now we can flow this three these
three numbers through some other little
function.
Okay.
And as you will see in a few minutes
that function is called an activation
function and it's chosen to be a
nonlinear function because if you don't
choose it to be a nonlinear function all
the effort we're doing is going to be a
total waste of time. Okay. For now, just
take it on faith that you need to have
nonlinear functions here. But note that
the three numbers here are still three
numbers. They are three different
numbers, but they're still three
numbers. And once we do this, we'll be
like, you know what? This was fun. Let's
do it again.
Okay? So, you can do it again.
And you can keep on doing it. You can
keep it 100 times if you want. And the
key thing is that every time you do it,
you're giving this network some ability,
some capacity to learn something
interesting from the data, to learn an
interesting representation. Now, of
course, you're thinking, well, how do we
know it's interesting? How do we know
it's a useful thing? And we'll come to
all that later on, right? We're just
giving it the capacity, the potential to
learn interesting things with the data.
Whether it actually lives up to its
potential, we don't know yet. Okay?
we'll give it the potential because the
more transformations of the input data
you make, the more opportunity you have
to do interesting things with it. If I
don't even give you the opportunity to
transform it once, you don't have any
opportunity, right? If I give you 10
chances to transform things, you have 10
shots at doing something useful.
So, you can you can do this repeatedly.
And once we are done doing these
transformations, we just pipe it through
to our good old logistic regression
sigmoid here and we are done.
Okay, so this is the basic idea. And so
just to contrast it, this was good old
logistic regression where we take the
input, we run it through a linear
function and pop out a number, a
probability number, but after we do all
this stuff, the input stays the same,
the output stays the same, but in the
middle, we just run it through a whole
bunch of these functions, you know,
these layersoop boop, and then we get
the output. Okay, that's all we have
done. And this is a neural network.
A neural network is nothing more than
repeatedly transformed inputs which are
finally fed to a linear or logistic
regression model.
Any questions?
>> Two question.
>> Could you use the thing so that everyone
can hear? Yeah.
>> Yeah. Two questions. Firstly, so maybe
say that there is a challenge of
explanability. Is it that we don't know
which arrow it went through? That's one.
Second, uh who's controlling the number
of iterations or the number of
functions? That's up to us. Or how is
that?
>> Right. So yeah. So the the first
question um explainability we actually
know exactly for any given input input
uh data data point we know exactly how
it flows through the network. So there
is no problem there. The problem is in
ascribing okay this we we think this
person is going to be uh repay the loan
because of this particular attribute we
don't know that because those attributes
all get enshed together and goes to this
complicated thing so we know exactly
what happens we just can't give credit
to any one thing very easily I'm again
I'm just standing on the brink of this
vast ocean of something called
explanability and interpretability uh
which I'll get to a bit later on in the
semester but that's sort of the quick
kind of rightish kind of wrong answer.
Okay. Number two um uh we decide the
number of layers we decide a whole bunch
of things and as we'll see in a few
minutes uh that is something that's
given to us and something we get to
design and I'll make it very clear which
is which
yeah
>> did I say your name right?
>> Yeah. So which functions have to be
linear and also like why does it have to
be linear?
>> Yeah. So these functions uh the f ofx
here they have to be nonlinear. As to
why they have to be nonlinear we'll get
to that in a few minutes.
Okay so these are called neurons. Okay
these things where you basically there's
a linear function followed by a little
nonlinear function right this is a each
one of these things is called a neuron.
Um, by the way, you know, this is
loosely inspired by the way how, you
know, neurons work in human in mamalian
brains. But the connections between
neuroscience and deep learning are very
heavily argued. So, I'm going to like
stay away from it. Okay? Uh, suffice it
to say, it's I I just think for for
building practical deep learning systems
in industry, you're you don't have to
worry about this. Okay? All right. Let's
move on terminology. Uh this vertical
stack of linear functions or neurons,
right? This vertical stack is called a
layer, right? This a layer, that's a
layer. Uh and these little nonlinear
functions, which we haven't got into
yet, are called activation functions. Uh
and we'll get to why they are called
that in just a second.
And
the input is called an input layer. And
I have the word layer in double quotes
because like it's not really doing
anything, right? It's just the input.
So, but we call it the input layer. And
what the very final thing that produces
our output is called the output layer,
right? Obviously, and everything in the
middle is called a hidden layer.
Okay.
So, the final piece of terminology is
that when you have a layer like this in
which say three numbers are coming out
and there's another another layer,
right? If every neuron in this layer is
connected to every neuron in this layer,
it's called a fully connected or dense
layer. So for instance here this arrow
that's whatever the whatever number is
coming out. Let's say the number three
is coming out of this thing here that
number three goes flows on this arrow to
this thing flows on this arrow to this
neuron and flows on this third arrow to
this neuron. That's what I mean. So
every neuron its output is being sent to
every neuron in the following layer.
Okay, that's we call it fully connected
or dense.
And then if you look at logistic
regression, right, this is just logistic
regression. You can see basically
logistic regression is a neural network
with no hidden layers.
So in some sense, logistic regression is
like almost the simplest possible
network you can think of. Like barely a
neural network, right? It's got no no
hidden layers. That's what makes it
logistic regression. And so as you might
have guessed by now, deep learning is
just neural networks with lots and lots
of
of what?
>> Yes, layers. So here are a few
uh and by the way, these are not even
considered all that, you know,
impressive these days. Okay. Uh but I
put them up because this uh this thing
here is called RestNet. And it's famous
because the restnet neural network was I
think the first network to surpass human
level performance and image
classification.
Sort of it's sort of like the Skynet of
image classification. Okay, it surpassed
human level performance and I'm putting
it up here because we'll actually work
with RestNet on Wednesday next next
Wednesday and we'll actually take restn
net we'll fine-tune it and solve a real
problem in class.
All right. So it's got lots and lots of
layers. Uh now let's turn to these
activation functions. We've been
ignoring these little guys right so far.
So the activation function at a node is
a first of all it's a function that
receives a single number and outputs a
single number right it's not very
complicated right it receives basically
this this is a linear function which
receives all these inputs. It could be
10 inputs, a thousand inputs, runs it
through a linear function, outputs a
number, and that single number, a
scalar, goes in here, and it comes out
as another single number. Just just just
remember that. And so these are some of
the most common activation functions. In
fact, the sigmoid we saw, which is
actually be used for the output, is
actually a kind of activation function
where a single number comes in and it
gets mapped into this curve because of
this thing. So the single number that
comes in is a and it and it gets
transformed as 1 / 1 plus e to minus a
and you get a shape like this and it's
called the sigmoid activation function
and and as you can see here for very
small values for very negative values
it's going to be pretty close to zero
meaning it won't get activated
and for very very large values it's
going to be pretty close to one. All the
action happens in the middle. When your
when your when your values are somewhere
in this range, there's a dramatic
increases in what comes out. Okay? So
that little thing in the middle is a
sweet spot for these functions. Uh and
this, you know, I'm also embarrassed to
call it an activation function because
it's literally not doing anything. It's
sort of getting a nice label for free.
Um right, you basically it says you just
get a number, you just pass it straight
along. It's a linear activation
function, but just for completeness, I
want to put it here.
And then we come to the hero of deep
learning which is the rectified linear
unit right rectified linear unit it's
called relu uh and relu is going to
become part of your vocabulary very very
quickly uh and so relu is actually a
very interesting function so you write
it as maximum of whatever number and
zero which is another way of saying if
the number is positive just send it
along unchanged if the number is
negative send a zero instead squash it
to zero. So which means if the number is
negative nothing happens. If the number
is positive it wakes up.
So what happens is that you could have a
very complicated linear function with
millions of variables and then it puts a
single number and that number
unfortunately happens to be negative.
The rel is not impressed. It's going to
sort of zero out. Okay. It's a very
simple function and many many folks who
have been in deep learning for a long
long time believe that the use of the
relus is one of the key factors that led
to the amazing success of deep learning
because it's got some very interesting
properties uh which we'll get to
hopefully on Wednesday.
Okay. So the short hand here is that um
whenever you see this thing it's just a
linear activation linear function
followed by just sending it straight
out. If I if you do this this if I put a
relu in here I'm going to denote it like
that which mimics the graph uh how it
looks. And if I'm if I put a sigmo it
I'm just going to use this thing here.
Okay just a visual shorthand
[clears throat] there are many other
functions activation functions by the
way. There's something called the
tanhage function, the leaky relu, the
gillu, the swish. I mean it's like a
like a menagery of activation functions
because very often researchers will be
like well I don't like this activation
function. Here's a little modified
version of the function which is going
to be better for certain things. So you
know people's research creativity is
sort of at this point has gone unhinged.
Um so lots of options but if you just
stick to the reu for your hidden layers
you can basically get anything done
practically right? You don't have to
worry about anything else. So we'll only
focus on ReLUS for all the intermediate
stuff. Uh yeah.
>> Yeah. How do you gauge which activation
function is more suited for your use
case?
>> Yeah. So the rule of thumb here is that
for your hidden layers, use ReLUS,
right? Because empirically we have seen
that they they do an amazing job. For
your output layer, your very final
thing, you actually don't have a choice
because what you have to use depends on
what kind of output you have to work
with. If it's an output which is a
probability number between 0 and one,
you have to use a sigmoid. U if it is
say 10 numbers all of which have to be
probabilities and they have to add up to
one you got to use something called the
softmax which we'll get to on Wednesday.
So it really depends on the output and
the nature of the output dictates what
you use in the output layer.
Okay. So coming back to this, so if you
want to design a deep neural neural
network, uh the input is the input, the
output is the output. And so you get to
choose everything else. You get to
choose the number of hidden layers, the
number of neurons in each layer, the
activation functions you're going to use
and uh for the hidden layers. And then
you have to make sure that the what you
choose for the output layer matches the
kind of output you want to generate.
Okay. So this is this sort of this is
all in your hands. You decide what
happens. But you will there's a lot of
guidance for how to do these things
which you'll which we'll cover as we go
along. Did you have a question
>> kind of but I guess I'll do it. Um
is is there also exploration in kind of
dynamic uh setting of layers so that a
user isn't determining the amount of
layers itself
layers.
>> Yeah. So there's a whole field called
neural architecture search NAS where we
can actually try a whole bunch of
different architectures uh and then use
some optimization and in fact
reinforcement learning which we won't
get to in this class as a way to figure
out really good architectures for any
particular problem. uh but the you the
question of okay when I'm training a
model with a particular kind of data the
first pass through the training data I'm
going to use two layers the second pass
I'm going to do seven layers that is not
done uh and the reason it's not done is
because of certain other constraints we
have and how we can do the the
optimization and the gradient descent
and stuff like that but what you can do
and we will you we'll look at this thing
called dropout for certain layers you
can actually for each time you run it
through the network you and decide in
this layer I'm not going to use all the
nodes. I'm going to drop out a few of
the nodes randomly and it's a very
effective technique to prevent
overfitting and we'll come to that a
little later on. Uh yeah,
one question regarding like uh neural
networks is about the coefficients to
decide not or we have user deficient for
the brain system. No, the whole trick
here, the whole name of the game is we
use the data, the training data and
something called a loss function, which
I'll get to on Wednesday, along with an
optimization algorithm. So the the
network figures out by itself what the
weights need to be, what the
coefficients need to be so as to
minimize prediction error. And that's
the whole thing. And the magic here is
that we don't have to do anything. We
only have to set it up, sit back often
for many hours and watch it do its
thing.
Yep.
>> Just one last question. Um, you
mentioned nodes just now when you were
answering Rolando's question. Can you
just confirm exactly what a node is? I
have an idea that it's basically any
circle, but you've just added a lot more
detail.
>> Sure. No, when when I'm referring to a
node, I'm literally referring to
something like this, which think of it
as a linear function followed by a
nonlinear activation. So it it re a
bunch of inputs runs it through a linear
function and pass it through like a relu
or a sigmoid or something and out pops a
number. So in general a node will have
many numbers potentially coming in but
only one number going out. Now that one
number may get copied to every node in
the next layer but what comes out of
that particular node is just a single
number.
All right. So uh so let's use a DNN for
our interview um example. So in this
problem we had two inputs right GP and
experience the output variable has to be
between 0ero and one because you're
trying to predict the probability that
someone gets called for an interview. So
the output size is fixed the sorry the
input size is fixed the output is fixed
u and we so since it's really only the
very first network we're actually
playing with uh let's just start simple
right we'll just have one hidden layer
and we'll have three neurons right and
and as I mentioned to Tomaso's question
from before if you are choosing
activation functions in the hidden
layers just go with the relu as a
default it usually works really well out
of the box so we'll just use a relu and
Since the output has to be between 0 and
one, we don't have a choice. We have to
use a sigmoid for the output layer.
Okay, that's it. So we have those those
are the design choices. And when we do
that, this is how it's looked like,
right? We have two inputs x1 and x2 gpn
experience and then it goes through
these three uh reloosmo
and we get a probability y at the end.
All right, quick question concept check.
How many weights how many parameters
both weights and biases does this
network have? Just take a moment to
count.
All right. Any guesses?
>> Yeah.
I think you're almost there.
Um,
are folks going to be doing a binary
search on this now? Okay.
>> Uh, no.
>> Yes.
>> 13.
>> Yes. Very good. So, that's 13. And my
guess is that the reason you came up
with 12, and I made the same mistake,
that's why I know it is you probably
forgot this green thing here.
Um so so what folks often forget is the
bias right we all count the things right
okay and the easy way to do it is okay
two things here uh three things here 2 *
6 3 is six uh 3 * 1 is 3 another nine
and then you have to add up all the
intercepts
right so you get 13 and so when we get
to very complicated networks the the
first two or three times you work with
very complex networks uh and we'll do it
you know starting very soon just get
into the habit of hand calculating the
number of parameters just to make sure
you understand what's going on. Once you
get it right a couple of times, you
don't have to do it anymore. Okay, the
first couple of times hand calculate to
make sure you get it. Okay, so yeah, so
let's say that we have trained this
network using you know using techniques
which we'll cover on Wednesday and it is
it comes back to you after training and
says okay these are the optimal the best
values for the weights and the biases
that I have found. So now your network
is ready for action is ready to be used
and so so what you can do is let's say
that you want to predict with this
network um you know if you have x1 and
x2 what comes out of what so what comes
out of the stop neuron right let's call
it a1 it's basically this
okay that's what's coming out of this
thing for any x1 and x2 this is what's
coming out similarly for a2 and a3 okay
and then what comes out at the very end
is basically a1 * that plus a2 * that
plus a3 * that plus 0.05 and the whole
thing gets run through the sigmoid and
that's what you get. Okay, so this slide
and the one before just make sure you
look at it afterwards and to make sure
you totally understand the mechanics of
it because this is really important. If
you don't if you don't fully understand
like internalize the mechanics when we
get to things like transformers it's
going to get hard. Okay. So just make
sure it's like automatic at this point.
It should be reflexive.
Um okay so yeah and so when we when you
want to predict anything you just run
some numbers through it you get all
these things uh and boom you calculate
it turns out to be 22.6 fixed. That's
the answer.
All right. So, uh I just want to say
that let's say that you built this
network and now you're like, "Hey, um
given any x1 and x2, I can come up with
a y, but I'm feeling a little matty. Can
you actually write down the function?"
Yeah, you can write down the function.
This is what it looks like.
Super interpretable, right?
So this goes to the comment that it made
earlier on where the act of uh depicting
something using this sort of graphical
layout makes it so much easier to reason
with and to think about uh compared to
trying to figure out what this function
is doing. Right? The other point I want
to make is that um this contrast what we
just saw with the logistic regression
thing we saw earlier which was this
little function. And so here
even this simple network with just three
hidden layers sorry three nodes in that
single hidden layer right it's so much
more complicated than the logistic
regression model so much more
complicated right and it is from this
complexity springs the ability of these
networks to do basically magical things
right that's where the complexity comes
from that's where the magic comes from
so and here in this case the number of
variables hasn't even changed it's still
only two,
but we can go from the two inputs to the
one output in very complicated ways as
long as we know how to train these
networks the right way. That's sort of
the m the secret source which we'll
spend a lot of time on. So yeah, to
summarize uh this is what we have. It's
a deep neural network. Uh by the way,
this kind of network where things just
flow from left to right is called a feed
forward uh neural network. uh in
contrast to some other kinds of networks
called recurrent networks which we won't
get to uh in this class because
transformers have actually proven to be
much more capable than recurrent
networks and those have become the norm.
So we'll just focus on those instead. Um
and so this arrangement of neurons into
layers and activation functions and all
that stuff this called the architecture
of the neural network and as you will
see later on the transformer the famous
transformer network [clears throat] is
just an example of a particular neural
network architecture much like
convolutional neural networks which
we'll get to next week for computer
vision or another example of a
particular network of architecture. So
uh we will focus on transformers they
are a particular kind of architecture.
All right. So in summary, that's what we
have. Um, you know, you get to choose
the hidden layers, the neurons,
activation functions, and stuff like
that. Uh, then inputs and outputs are
what you have to work with. And so we
will actually take this idea and then
use it to uh to actually solve a problem
from start to finish on Wednesday. So I
think I'm done. I give you three minutes
back of your day. Thank you.
[applause]