We're lucky to have MIT in Boston and
we're lucky it draws the people that it
does. People like you from around the
world. This world has some problems that
we need you to drop everything and
solve. There is a lot of trouble out
there, MIT. But there's a lot of beauty,
too. And I hope you see both. But
whatever you do, just keep listening,
even to people you don't agree with at
all. I love what President Obama said at
Howard University's commencement last
month. He said, "Democracy requires
compromise even when you are 100%
right." I heard that and thought, "Here
is a man who has been happily married
for a long
time. I hope you'll turn toward the
problem of your choosing. I hope you'll
drop everything, and I hope you'll solve
it. This is your life, class of
2016. This is your moment, and it is all
down to you. Thank you.
Congratulations."
For more MIT moments from MIT Open
Learning, like, subscribe, or