Hey, everybody.
I'm Sam Madden.
I'm very pleased to have Tye
Brady here from Amazon Robotics.
Thanks, Sam.
We're just going to learn
a little bit about how
AI, and generative
AI in particular,
is affecting the
robotics industry.
So let's just--
maybe, Tye, you want
to say a little bit
about your background.
First of all, it's just great
to be back on campus here.
I'm a graduate.
I spent about a decade
here in the '90s.
I was here when the internet
came to be a thing here
in the '90s.
I started programming in
the '70s, personal computers
in the '80s, here
at MIT in the '90s.
I've done a fair amount of
automation and robotics.
What I do-- my title is
I'm the Chief Technologist
for Robotics at Amazon.
We have the world's
largest fleet
of industrial mobile robots
out there in the world.
Very applied, very
practical is what we do.
We really believe in a
collaborative philosophy
of people and machines
working together.
And the age of
physical AI is here.
We have grown quite considerably
over the last decade.
We ship billions and billions
of packages every year--
billions.
About 75% of every package
that's delivered actually
goes through one of
our robotic systems.
We're really proud to be here
in the greater Boston area.
Our world headquarters are
here in greater Boston area.
And what a time to be
in robotics, for sure.
Awesome.
Cool.
Well, I'm excited to
hear more about it.
So I think maybe we'll start off
by just talking about, what's
the state of robotics today?
And then we can
transition into--
Yeah, I brought a
little home video,
if you like, just to set
some context, really,
about this application
of physical AI systems.
So it's the mind and the
body coming together.
We've had robotic
systems for a while,
but it's really a
new era where we
can bring AI, machine
learning, generative AI
to our robotic systems.
So I have a video
just showing really
the practical side of what
we do with our robotics
and how you get your
deliveries to your door.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So we had a little bit
of what we do there.
I don't know you caught
it in the beginning.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks.
I'm really proud of that.
Thank you.
Amazing team that we
have here-- a lot of MIT
graduates, a lot of folks
in the greater Boston area.
I'll tell you, if you
caught it in the beginning,
the manufacturing of those
drive units in particular,
we do all of the manufacturing,
actually, for those drive units
right here in Massachusetts.
Like I said, we've manufactured
more than a million drive units
here in the Bay state.
We have about 18,000 employees
that we employ in Amazon inside
of Massachusetts, put about
$18 billion into the economy.
So I'm using those
stats just to show you
that this practical side,
the very applied side of AI
and robotics, when you
are solving problems
that people need, it
really kind of advances
the state of the art.
Yeah.
I mean, what I thought
was really cool about that
is that he's got
these arms, which
you think of industrial
robotics being
arms that move stuff around.
But then you had
these little, I guess
you call them drive units,
scooting on the floor,
with people there.
Can you talk a
little bit about how
constrained the environment
that these things--
are they making
autonomous decisions,
or are they following fixed
paths that are preplanned?
I mean, can you talk a little
bit about what's happening?
It's a great observation.
We've been, first of
all, the philosophy
that we believe,
again, as we put
people at the center
of robotics universe
is that collaborative
environment, so we
want people and machines--
we want to augment and
amplify human potential
through our machines.
That's our core philosophy.
And to do that, we do
technology development
with project context.
I mean, that's the best way
anything is going to get done.
You need a real problem-- what
problem you're trying to solve--
in order to focus the technology
to work at a high reliability.
And when you ship
billions of packages,
even if it's just a billion,
remember that 1% is 10 million.
I can't have 10 million
defects out there
that we're going to
have to go chase down.
So what we're doing is
we're actually achieving,
let's say, a
world-class capability
in mobility and manipulation,
in identification and storage
and sortation and PAC-- just
real core fundamentals when
it comes to robotic systems.
And our generative AI
systems, our machine
learning systems, our
AI systems that we have,
have really brought-- where
we had the body before, we
have the mind and the
body now coming together
at a really accelerated pace
in the last three years.
Let me just talk a little bit
about the manipulation space.
So like I said, I
was a young Jedi
in the '70s and the '80s, and
I really enjoyed computers.
I really enjoyed programming.
And the state of
robotics was very fixed.
It was really-- in the
manipulation space,
it was maybe for welding for
the automotive industry-- very
fixed, precise patterns
of what it needs to do.
And if there's any
irregularities, forget about it.
It's out.
And we've come a long way over
I'd say a number of decades
here, where we're much
more adaptive, much
more modular in our approach
of how we're doing robotics.
So for example, the drive
units that you saw there-- we
started with the fabric pods.
Again, I'm missing
the basics here.
What we do is we're a
goods-to-person fulfillment
strategy.
What we used to have
inside of Amazon is
a person would have a cart--
you could see there--
we'd have a cart, and you
would walk for a long distance,
grab the item, put it into
a cart, go to another.
I'll grab the item, put it into
a cart, and then come back,
pack the item out, and
off goes the order.
And Amazon did that
for a number of years.
Actually, Jeff Wilke, who's a
graduate from the Sloan School
here, really brought these
lean principles to mind
and started to
optimize that process.
Well, around 2010, Jeff saw this
kind of remarkable new idea,
which was a goods-to-person
type of fulfillment center--
fulfillment process path.
And instead of a person
going to the goods,
the goods can come
to the person, OK?
And that was a really giant
deal because not only was it
better for our employees because
they didn't have to walk so far
or remember everything
that they needed to pick,
but it was much more
efficient in terms of time,
but also in storage.
Because if you didn't need
those human aisle ways
and you can pack things
like the advanced library
does or pack them in as
when you go to Fenway Park,
all the cars there,
I can pack about 40%
more goods in that
same footprint, OK?
So robotics has really
enabled this revolution
where I can have many more
goods in the same footprint
and also increase the
efficiencies while making
it safer for our employees.
Aha.
So that worked.
So that was about a decade ago.
We started in what we call
a structured field approach.
So a structured field
means that there's
fences around the
robots, right, and we're
moving those goods at
will to pick stations
in the interface of
people and machines
is kind of at these stations
that we design and build.
And that is actually
very efficient
and has really changed
the game for Amazon.
For example, in terms of
productivity, over a decade,
we've hired hundreds
of thousands of people.
We've created hundreds,
hundreds, literally hundreds
of new job types
because of robotics.
So we gain this productivity.
But also, I don't know
if you saw in the video,
we had these little
green robots,
and what that signifies--
we actually wanted
a different color,
very intentional,
because they are
collaborative robots.
They don't use fiducials.
They're not behind fences.
They're safety certified, and
they can move goods at will.
Yeah.
Again, just the very basics--
moving things at will around
people in a safe manner.
That we rolled out
a few years ago,
about three or four years ago,
and we're using at our inbound
and outbound docks.
Very practical
application of just--
I got a stack of
stuff over here,
and I need it to get
to the right truck.
And we've had robotic
systems and AI systems
that actually help
sort those goods,
but just move it
from here to there.
But there's a trick.
I need you to move
it around people.
And I need for people to
understand what they're doing.
And I need the
machines to understand
what people are doing so that we
can better collaborate and work
together.
That is working.
One question about that.
I was thinking, as
these robots are-- like,
this is an incredible
planning problem--
just the logistics of there's
billions of packages coming
in and then billions of packages
that have to go out every day.
This is a central-- is this a
centralized planning system,
or is it-- do the
individual-- are
the individual robots
autonomously going and figuring
out what package
they should move now,
or how does it all
get coordinated?
It's a little bit of both.
First of all, there's
beauty in billions.
There really are.
There's beauty in
billions, right?
Because if you're achieving
that billions like of whatever
operation that
you're doing, you're
going to get pretty good at it.
You're going to get good at
it because truly, it's going
to become much more autonomous.
Now, there's no such
thing as 100% automation.
It doesn't exist.
That just does not exist.
But you want to have
high reliability systems,
much like aerospace systems,
where you have high reliability.
In terms of the
planner, it's a mix
of what we call our edge
devices and our cloud.
And now we have, I would say,
the world's best cloud system
out there.
We've been doing
it for a long time.
We have a tool set.
The same tool set
that we use inside
of our fulfillment operations
is available to many, many
businesses, and
many, many businesses
are using that tool set,
where it's a safe, secure,
authenticated AWS
stack that allows
us to do generative AI solutions
at will at really low cost.
So the planner
that we have is you
can think of it almost
like a flight controller
over at Logan, where
we can see and we're
saying what bots we
want to go at what time.
And that's all.
It's a massively
parallel operation.
And we do that all in the cloud.
But that's not good enough.
Now, there's latency between
the cloud and whatever robot
that you have.
So the robot needs to
be able to understand,
is there an object in my way?
It needs to understand, do
I have a potential collision
coming in my way?
And that's starting
to be embedded into--
or is there a person in my way?
Is there somebody
who's doing servicing?
That's all now
happening at the edge.
So there's this balance that
we do inside robotics of,
how much smarts do I
want to put on the edge,
and how much do I want
to put up in the cloud?
And as we progress more
and more in robotics,
we're seeing that the more
unstructured that you go,
the more details
and smart you're
going to have to
get on the edge.
Sure, sure.
But when you start
to get in the edge,
now we're talking
about you need what?
Lower power embedded computers
that can have their own models.
Maybe you don't even have the
connectivity back that you want.
And these are real, real
challenges that we're looking at
and we're starting to
solve inside of Amazon.
So it's really incredible
to see literally 3,000,
4,000 of these bots working
together with each other,
learning from each other,
learning where they can be
stronger, learning where
they can be better,
and then often you see the
system be optimized right
in front of your eyes.
It's incredible.
That's amazing.
Let's talk for a
little bit about how
generative AI has changed.
I mean, you've alluded
you're using generative AI.
And I can really imagine how
the vision models, for example,
like you have these vision
models that can look at a scene
and understand
where objects are.
Check.
Can you talk a little bit about
how generative AI has affected
other aspects of robotics, like
these manipulation questions?
I mean, has generative
AI had impact
in other areas or planning?
I mean, other areas as well?
I will say this.
Like I said, I know you're all
shocked because I said I was
programming in the '70s, and I
look so young, so I get that.
But I will say this.
I'd say generative AI is
probably the most impactful
technology that I've witnessed,
throughout my whole robotics
career.
And I tend to think
of it in three bins.
I'll just throw this out there.
I love being on campus again.
Again, it's great.
So maybe I'll get my academic
juices going again here.
Please no problem sets tonight.
Thanks.
I really think of it
in three categories.
There is, I would say, kind
of the collaborative AI,
language-based, language
in, language out,
help me summarize this
document, write for me
a prose that compares and
contrasts these thoughts.
That is language in, language
out, and that really--
we all should be
using those tools.
It just makes our
jobs that easier.
And we are right.
Then the next
bucket that I put is
kind of creative generative AI.
And this means that the
generative AI solution
is giving us designers
insight, and maybe
that we haven't had before.
So inside of Amazon,
I can give you
an example, a very
specific example,
is that we think
about process flows,
we think about material flow
throughout our buildings.
And this kind of creative--
we can ask our AWS-based
generative AI tool sets
to say, hey, could you
tell me a better way
that material should
flow, given all this data
that we've given you?
Where are the choke points?
And what our designers
see is they see something,
and it's never quite right.
It's not going to be perfect,
but it might inspire you.
That's not-- In no way
could I ever build that.
Yeah.
But they see--
they begin to see,
like oh, I didn't realize
that that is actually
the main choke point,
or I didn't really
realize that we had
that much volume
at this particular outbound dock
or this corner of the building.
And that insight gives them a
better way to design a solution.
Now it's their solution,
and then out comes
a new next-generation
fulfillment center.
Yeah.
OK.
Seeing that-- actually,
again, I think
I'm going back to my MIT days.
I was here on campus at the
Center for Space Research,
and we did an algorithm,
a genetic algorithm,
to design an antenna.
This is another good
bucket for this creative.
And it had many, many
generations of antenna.
And it ended up like
you could not physically
build the antenna--
like, you can't.
We didn't have any processes
to actually build that antenna.
But it gave our RF
engineers like, oh my gosh,
I see why it's working.
And he built this antenna
that we put on a spacecraft
and off it went,
which is awesome.
So that's the second bucket.
But the third bucket
is really where
I think there's a great
amount of challenge,
and I just call it
operational GenAI.
And I have examples of this.
So that fleet of bots
that are out there--
for example, we just announced
what we call DeepFleet,
and it's a generative AI
solution that is continuously
running to say, I know what
your algorithm is right now
that we've used for a decade.
I'm going to take that algorithm
in, and based on the data
that I'm seeing and
based on the real time
conditions of the
fleet right now,
I'm going to optimize
that a little bit better.
It's going to see the
patterns inside it,
and it's going to
suggest-- it's actually
going to generate,
purely on its own,
a better route for
one particular drive.
And it does that across
thousands of drives.
And then suddenly everything
is blended together.
We really like that.
We saw that this past year.
We just announced
this a few months ago,
and we're deploying it
across all of our fleets.
What it does is it gives us
a 10% efficiency in drive
time, and 10%--
It is a lot of dollars.
These buildings are 3
million square feet.
There's thousands and thousands
and thousands of drive units.
It's a really big deal.
When we put these together--
again, I want to just bring this
back to what our customer and
why this matters-- is you
put these systems together.
For example, we have our latest
generation of fulfillment center
in Shreveport--
2,500 new jobs we
put down there.
We're seeing that we can
process entire orders 25% faster
throughout that building.
We continue to hire, but we're
also seeing productivity gains.
We're seeing efficiency
gains and productivity gains
inside that
building, and we also
see the jobs changing inside
of that fulfillment center.
So again, very practical,
very real world,
and embedded into
the operation itself.
I'm wondering, Tye, if
you could talk a little--
as you're talking, I'm thinking
about this job question.
A lot of things that people
are worried about with AI
is it's going to replace people.
Yeah.
You're pretty far ahead, it
seems to me-- you're pretty--
this is--
I think that we're
pioneers in this field.
--a high degree of automation.
You've already deployed an
autonomous-- these robots
pretty extensively.
How has your human
workforce changed over
the years in terms of-- you talk
about numbers of people employed
in these fulfillment
centers or the types of jobs
that people are doing, or can
you talk about that a little.
Absolutely.
I can 100% talk about that
because I'm very proud of it.
When you give people the right
toolset, when you give people
a mindset of augmentation
and amplification
of their job, when
you can eliminate
the menial, the mundane, and the
repetitive out of people's jobs,
it frees them up a
bit, and it allows
them to focus on
higher order things.
It's a very hard job
to do that, by the way,
because if it's
not really useful
and you have a job to do--
Yeah.
You're going to
put it over here.
If it's really useful
and you have a job to do
and you're like, OK, I like
that, you as a designer
really need to pay
attention to the signals of,
what do you like about that,
and why is this useful to you?
All right.
So how jobs have changed
is that we're seeing,
and also I think we all have
a responsibility, especially
a large tech
company like Amazon,
to upskill our employees.
And we have put more than $1
billion into upskilling more
than 700,000 of our employees.
We have something
called career choice,
where right in our
fulfillment centers,
folks can learn
about AI systems,
about robotics, folks
can learn-- they can
actually take any college
course that they want on it,
and we really believe in that.
We also believe
that, and we've seen
this where people,
when they're using it
as amplifiers in augmenting
their work, they really--
they like it, and they want
to be more involved with this.
So we have what we call
a robotics apprenticeship
program, very successful,
that we've rolled out
through our fulfillment
centers, where
if folks want to get
involved with robotics,
we will teach them
how to service them,
how to maintain them, what
to look out for example.
And we've seen a
pretty good increase
in the folks that
are doing that.
Why?
Well, first of all,
it's 40% more pay.
It's great pay.
Secondly, you're working
in the tech field,
and it's a great career.
So we're seeing that.
If you want to pop up
one level, my philosophy
is that we are
pioneers in this field.
We are pioneers when it comes
to collaborative robotics,
when it comes to building
machines that allow
folks to be more efficient.
And I say that because
we have a huge advantage.
We're in e-commerce.
We kind of invented this
goods-to-person fulfillment
strategy, and we have a
semi-structured environment.
More than 300 of
our buildings are
robotics, like what
you saw in the video--
robotics-enabled buildings.
It's a huge number.
And when we try something,
we think of something,
we convince ourselves
that this is
going to be good
for our employees,
it's going to create a safer
environment for our employees,
we will build it in the lab.
That's what we do.
That's cool.
But that's only the beginning.
You build it in
the lab, and then
we'll take one quarter of
one building and one floor
and then try it in
the real environment,
and we'll see how that works.
And you iterate.
We iterate our AI systems.
We iterate the mechanics.
We iterate the robotics.
We listen to the
voice of the customer.
And what it does
is it allows you--
suddenly you're uncovering like,
oh, I didn't think of that.
Oh, I didn't think of that.
Oh, I didn't think of that one.
And then it gets better,
and then we get one floor.
OK, great.
And then we roll it
out and we're like, OK,
it's actually working now.
That's-- oh, wow.
Wow, OK.
It's good.
And then I usually look
for the big clue, which
is the general manager
of the building will say,
oh, no guys probably
shouldn't release that yet.
I'm like, why?
Why is that?
Because they're
gaining efficiencies,
and compared to their
other general managers,
they're like, hey, I don't
whatever you guys have,
but I want that cup of coffee.
That one looks pretty good.
So then we roll it
out more generally.
Awesome.
Maybe let's turn to a little
bit sort of visionary here.
And hearing you
talk, you said it's
a semi-structured
environment, which
I take to mean you know the
floor plan of these buildings,
and you have to
watch out for people.
And sometimes there's
things that aren't where
you expect them to be.
But it's not like walking around
the MIT campus or something.
Yeah, and we've heard about
drone delivery or whatever,
but I'm wondering,
looking forward,
I mean, how far away are we
from the idea that I might have,
a robot that's like, Amazon
is delivering my packages
with a robot that rolls up to
my office or rolls up to my--
walks up my front steps
and drops my package off.
Is that going to happen soon?
I will say that we will innovate
in every way for our customers,
for sure.
I will tell you
that we are already
involved in the majority
of deliveries out there.
The robotics, GenAI,
machine learning-- we've
been doing machine
learning from the get-go,
if you think about the
product placement out there.
We're there, but
never satisfied.
We want to have the ultimate
in customer convenience, which
means the world's largest
selection of goods
at a low cost, delivered
right to the customer's door.
That's what we do.
That's just what we do.
That frames everything
that we do inside
of our robotics and automation.
And to do that, you
really need to understand
the scale at which we
operate and the pressure that
puts on a robotic system
that actually works.
It's not a YouTube moment.
It's not a backflip.
It's not parkour.
It is getting goods
to customer's door.
And that is in itself a
remarkable achievement.
And when you talk about
the vision that we have--
I genuinely believe
this, I really do.
This is why I'm so proud of the
women and men that work inside
of Amazon each and every day
on these really cutting edge,
whether it's the GenAI--
the new foundation
model that we have,
whether it's in the hardware
stack or the software stack,
that what we're doing
inside of e-commerce
through practical, everyday
applied robotics actually,
I believe, will start to
transcend into other sectors,
whether it's agriculture
or it's automotive
or it's in health care.
The basics of-- I
mean the basics--
moving stuff, manipulating
stuff, identifying stuff,
sorting stuff.
Those are the basics,
and we're just
starting to do that at scale
with reality, that now we're
going to go into other
sectors and then we
get the holy grail, the
part that really puts
a smile on my face, is
because then that's going
to start to work its way
into every home, every home
out there--
allowing people to focus
more on what matters,
allowing them to focus on their
loved ones in their house,
allowing them to do
other jobs and have all
the menial, mundane
stuff done for them.
We've seen Elon Musk, I
guess, kind of famously
say that bet on humanoid
robots and say Tesla
is going to be a--
whatever it is--
$25 trillion
company on the backs
of this humanoid robotic bet.
Would you bet on
humanoid robots,
or are you imagining
more in the home
that these kind of things
that we saw in your video
are more small-scale,
human-friendly things that
move stuff around for me?
Or like, what are your--
It's funny.
Again, I'm on campus, so
I'm inspired here, for sure.
First of all, we have millions
of robots already out there.
So it's not about this is
what we're going to do.
This is what we are doing.
And they have a very
practical purpose.
We always start--
I always start-- what problem
are you trying to solve?
First and foremost, what
problem are you trying to solve?
And I would say that to
everybody, every single person
out here, if you're thinking
about some technology,
you should start
with, what problem
are you trying to solve first?
Because if you're just
technology looking
for technology's sake and
how am I going to apply this,
it's not going to
work out so well.
So start with what problem
I'm trying to solve.
From that, I generate function.
What functions will I need in
order to solve that problem?
It's not form but function.
So humanoid is a form.
If you start just
in the form and say,
I think you're
starting to fall--
you fall into this trap of,
OK, how can I apply this?
And there's a thought, and I
get it, and I understand it,
and I appreciate it, of well,
it's going to do everything.
It's going to be general.
You think of it
and it can do it.
Anything-- anything a person
can do, it can do better.
I don't believe in
that philosophy.
I believe that it's a system
of people and machines
working together.
We should have the
strengths of machines
doing repetitive motion,
lifting heavy objects,
calculating huge numbers
for us, understanding
where all our inventory is.
That's what machines
are really good at.
And let people have
common sense and use
their instincts and the
ability to problem solve
and understand the overall
flow of what happens,
and bring those
together in a smart way.
And at this conference, like
I'm very excited to be here
because to bring that
intuition and the common sense
in a human, relatable
way is where I think
that we need a lot of work.
I think that we
need a lot of work
there, not as a
combative or a versus
but as a collaborative, a
collaborative way, so that
allowing us to use
our machines better.
Cool.
I'm wondering, let's just--
we got a minute and a half left,
so maybe I'll give you one--
That was fast.
I'll just ask you one question,
like, is this the good one?
Is this the good one?
Just zing me with this one.
I'm ready.
I'm prepared.
No, I don't think
I have a good one.
I'm sorry.
All right.
Maybe just as you
think about-- there's
probably a bunch of MIT students
and researchers in the audience.
What would be the-- if
you could say, like here
are the three
things that we need
in robotics, what would be the
big breakthroughs that you would
want or you think are needed
before we get to this, whatever
it is, Elon Musk, and
do that in 55 seconds.
I'm ready.
All right.
You ready?
I'd say we need to
I would say much
more in human-machine
interaction--
more research there.
In the hardware
stack, I really think
that we need to break through in
low-power embedded, maybe even
neuromorphic, computing, so that
we can carry a little bit more
on the edge from the
hardware point of view.
And also the system point
of view, if it's humanoids
or if it's wheels or it's four
legs or it's one leg or six
or whatever, once
you get to a spot,
you then need to interact
with something, so I'm also--
I really love the
work that's being
done, particularly on campus
here, in dexterous manipulation.
That's my research.
If you gave me grand
challenges, they're
going to be very practical.
Do you see that laundry
basket over there?
You can imagine there's
a laundry basket.
I want you to do the laundry and
then put it into the drawers.
Yeah.
It's a ginormous challenge,
if you just think about it.
OK, that would be one.
Second-- shout out
to my MIT homies
out here, and John
Hao, Professor Hao,
if he's out there somewhere--
we thought of this one
together years ago.
Just take a robot and carry
a couple of Amazon packages
and go from the end of
the Infinite Corridor
all the way out to Kresge here
when we're changing classes.
That's all I'm asking you to do.
But just don't hit-- and
don't hit any people.
Don't hurt anybody on the way.
Yeah.
And make your way through
that little corridor.
I had a hard enough time
doing it as a student.
That's going to be
a really hard job.
That's a great one, yeah.
And then the third--
I love sports.
Red Sox are kind of eating it
a little bit, but just play
an entertaining
game of baseball.
Just entertaining.
That's awesome.
That would be my three
grand challenges.
So someone bust those out.
Please, please connect
with me on LinkedIn
if you have any solution
to any of those.
Sounds good.
Well, Tye, we're out of
time, but thank you so much.
Thank you.
It was really a pleasure.
Thanks, everybody.