So I'm Sur. Uh nice to meet all of you.
Thanks for coming. Um so yeah as uh been
introduced I'm a machine learning
scientist in Gren's group at Genitech
and I'll be presenting our work on uh
that we call Nona. It's a model for
unifying functional genomics. That's how
we see it through multimodal masking.
And uh I'll just set up what that means.
But before that, I'd like to thank all
my amazing colleagues at Gentech who
helped me through different aspects of
this work.
So, as Gchin alluded to in his awesome
primer, um you can kind of split the
main categories of um of of models for
regulatory DNA into broadly these three
subsets. the sequence to function
category which is uh has seen a lot of
interest in the last few years where you
um make predictions from sequence alone
and as cockin mentioned there are models
that they can starting from about 500 to
a,000 bases to models like inform and
bordoy that taken DNA sequence windows
as long as um half a megabase in some
cases there's also variations of these
frameworks where instead of predicting
from sequence alone you might predict
from sequence plus one or other
functional tracks
Um and one example of this could be
where you're trying to predict um gene
expression in a specific cellular
context from the DNA sequence and the
attack or some notion of chromatin
accessibility in the same cell type. And
then more recently what's really
exploded is is language modeling both
auto reggressive and mass language
models models like DNA bird caducious
EVO uh EVO 2 a nuclear nucleotide
transformer. There's all kinds of
different ways in which um people
tokenize, people uh design the the the
the masking objective. Um auto
reggressive versus
um masking based alo what species you're
training on can be completely different
species can be different individuals
within the same species. A lot of
different modeling challenges that are
involved in training these kinds of
models. So what we started thinking
about and what Gong should mention was
that all of these are being developed in
in in silos almost especially like
language modeling and sequence to
function models and if there's any way
to start unifying these models if you
were to train today a language model
you'll have to go to a completely
separate uh part of the internet or of
GitHub I guess and and set up uh a bunch
of tools and then get started with
language modeling going to do sequence
to function you do a completely
different set of data processing and and
training um for these. So as we start
thinking about the process of unifying
these almost disparit
um modeling approaches, we realize that
in the process of unification, we can
actually start doing uh things that are
actually none of these. we can start
going beyond um these these um highly
siloed classes of models and we can do
something that's more interesting uh and
spans and is is almost some kind of
hybrid or um hybrid approach that you
wouldn't classify into any one of these
categories. So maybe to motivate that a
bit further um I want to show you uh an
example of a text vision uh multi
multimodal mass model. is one of the
places where we draw our inspiration
from. Um, and the way these models work
is you have pairs of images and
captions. And you can think of
arbitrarily masking patches in your
image um or or tokens in your text and
then filling those in. And the model is
able to look across modalities and look
at correlation between the text and the
images and fill those in um going across
modalities. And what's nice about this
kind of framework is it captures the
more common separate models that you see
um things like captioning an image right
this is an entire class of models on its
own but is encompassed in this broader
framework of multimodal mass modeling
where you could um for example train a
model by simply masking all the text
tokens um and predicting them condition
on the image or you can go the other way
around where you try to generate an
image given um tokens in the text,
right? But you can also go beyond this.
You can do some interesting things where
you're editing the text. You're masking
specific patches of your image that help
you edit uh the image itself. So, it's
it's not exactly captioning or image
generation. It's some kind of an in
between task, but also interesting in
its own right. And I think if you tried
um giblifying your images, you kind of
know what I'm talking about uh from the
last week. So this is where we draw our
inspiration from and coming back to um
functional genomics you can really think
of two broad modalities. The first is
DNA sequence and the second modality is
all our functional tracks. Although you
may also wish to call RNA seek a
completely different modality from
attack seek which um it probably is but
for now you can think of it broadly as
DNA sequence and all your functional
tracks. What's nice and it's a little
different from the text um and image
case is that these share a common
coordinate system right? So when you do
attack or RNA seek you get reads you
align these reads to the genome and then
at every position in the genome every
base you get some um read count for your
asset right. So it's really nice and you
can represent it in this matrix form
where you have sequence typically one
hot encoded um for four channels for ACG
and T and then the tracks you're
considering uh as as a one-dimensional
vector uh with the same length as the
length of the sequence and and nicely
aligned for you.
So the crux of Nona really is a
multimodal masking based model um where
we have our matrix of of uh different
different functional tracks and DNA
sequence and in theory we can
arbitrarily mask individual pixels um
both across the tracks or the tasks um
and the DNA and then kind of jointly
fill those in fill in the missing pixels
based on what else you see. Right? So
this is um
seems to be like crazy flexible approach
which it is and I'll try to now make
more sense of it in the next few slides.
Um but I hope you can start to see how
this is already unifying different
approaches in one larger class of
models.
Great. So you can now start thinking of
how you can encode the first you know
three different classes of models I'd
shown you within this single framework
and then I'll also show you how we can
come up with entirely new classes of
models or or or um or types of models
that don't fit neatly into any of the
the first three buckets I've shown you
right uh operationally the way Nona is
working is we have our data matrix um
and we mask out positions in our data
matrix with zeros. So if there was some
non-zero value, it becomes zero. If
there was a base there, there will be a
base there or unless I guess there's
issues with the reference genome. You
convert that into zeros with an n. And
then in addition to that, you also
append a a mask matrix. It's just a
binary matrix of ones and zeros where
it's one where uh the specific pixel was
not masked in the input. The reason for
doing this is so that the model can
differentiate between zeros in the data
matrix caused from masking versus zeros
that um are actually observed uh at this
specific position.
So sequence to function modeling now
just becomes um an instantiation of an
owner model where you mask all your
tracks uh and you keep your sequence
unmasked. Right? So very simple case
where um during training what you can do
is have a bunch of tracks you mask all
of them out and you only predict those
from sequence alone.
If you want to add more tracks to your
sequence you can simply do this really
in a dynamic fashion right you can
dynamically unmask different tracks um
when you're training or during inference
and then predict the rest. So you can
have perhaps sequence plus attack seek
in skin cells and then try to predict
the gene expression in skin cells or all
and or all other cell types as well. Um
language modeling in the case of
language modeling here what you could do
is either remove all your tracks or if
you have some tracks you can completely
mask them and then ignore them in terms
of your loss function. Um and what you
then do is just mask at specific bases
here. Um, and this this kind of
recapitulates um your masking uh your
your masking based uh language modeling.
So pretty straightforward. But now that
we've set this up, we can actually do a
lot more than just these three things,
right? I'm going to show you some
examples of of of things that we've
thought about that um have been
specifically motivated by downstream
applications uh in functional genomics.
So one thing we've been thinking about
is what we call contextaw aware
prediction in which the input of the
model is not just the sequence but also
the functional measurements adjacent to
some region of interest and I'm going to
talk about this specific mode in more
detail in the next section. Um but just
to set this up it's it there can be use
cases where you might want to factor in
uh information beyond just the sequence
itself. We have all our attack and RNA
seek measurements across cellular
contexts. other ways to make better use
of them when when you're trying to make
um predictions in a region of interest.
Um, another interesting mask we've
thought about is what we call positional
masking where we mask out these
functional tracks um at specific at at
random at at bases at random. Um, and
what this kind of a mask can help us
potentially is is filling in what's uh
these functional tracks at these
specific positions from the sequence,
but also the functional measurements at
other bases. And you can think of ways
where this might be useful for denoising
tracks, especially those that have um
either high noise or or or low read
depth.
And we can also extend uh traditional
sort of vanilla mass language modeling
into what we call functional language
modeling here. Instead of completely
ignoring all the functional tracks and
the wealth of data we have uh we can
actually factor those into our mass
language modeling approach. So instead
of masking out all our tracks, we also
provide the model access to our tracks
only mask out specific bases and fill
those in not just from the sequence but
also uh from the tracks that we
observed. But hopefully I'm starting to
convince you that this is a fairly
flexible worst style approach uh almost
a Swiss army knife of sorts of function
genomics. If you have an interesting
application in mind, you can come up
with a nice masking strategy and train a
model uh that hopefully tackles um the
use case you have in mind. going to
pause here but what I'll be doing in the
next few uh minutes I guess the next
half an hour or so is walk through three
completely different use cases of of
Nona in which we'll be training three
very different kinds of models so it's
almost like three flash three different
flash talks unrelated from each other so
hopefully you can get a sense for the
versatility and breadth of um the
approaches we have but good time to ask
questions if any
did you try training three tasks
together. Can you see generalization
across different tasks when you do that?
It's it's a great question. So we have
um in today's talk I'll be showing you
cases where we just train on one kind of
mask at one time. We have experimented
with training multiple uh kinds of masks
in the same model and that does work to
some extent. Um so far what we've seen
is that if you want optimal performance
on any one specific kind of masking it's
better to either fine-tune on that or or
train exclusively on that. I don't think
we have seen some instances where we can
generalize across masks. So if you have
a mask that you haven't seen during
training that is somewhat related that
is some sense of but we haven't really
gotten into that in detail.
Um so in the multimod like vision tech
stuff people um many models like
tokenize the modalities yeah separately.
Um
I guess you'll talk more about that kind
of thing and do do you see that as the
tokenization etc being constant
throughout these different section or do
you think it like depends on the yeah so
I think as I mentioned we're sharing a
common coordinate system which uh almost
makes it easy to represent what's going
on locally within an within a genomic
window. Um
and I think this just keeping in spirit
with the kinds of models you've seen in
the space where we just either doing
sequence to function prediction without
any kind of tokenization predicting from
raw DNA sequence itself. It's an
interesting we've thought about it but
yeah I haven't explored that in
might be jumping the gun a bit but uh we
heard that in sequence to function
models um they're somewhat limited by um
the counterfactuals being on the
sequence the perturbations. um is
another motivation for this model also
being able to perturb the tracks and
seeing changes. Yeah, exactly. Yeah,
I think it's a bit related to Sil's
question. Um I mean there's not an
implicit tokenization in inform but the
convolutions to that and reduce the the
size to 128 bases, right? Where there's
the the scale the functional scale where
I don't know chips would might vary. I
mean, doesn't that constrain a lot the
size of your sequences and the size of
your inputs? Um, so I guess it would
kind of make sense. So the models I'll
be showing you today, some of especially
in the first subsection in the first
section are really long about 200 KB and
we're able to model these at base
resolution. So within our unit
architecture, we can go all the way back
to single base resolution. And you're
right that there are some constraints.
We probably can't model a few thousand
or tens of thousands of tracks. Um, but
in the range of a few hundred, it's
quite doable.
Great. So I'm going to move ahead uh
into the first um section. Thanks for
the questions. Um into what we call a
context aware uh nona model, right? So
to set this up, sequence to function
models predict these assays like DNA
seek attack seek RNA seek from sequence
alone. What if we provided the models
more information? Could there be cases
where this might be uh useful?
uh especially if there's some event of
interest that's somewhat localized um
some kind of integration or or a
mutation for example
um so maybe one way to think about it is
let's say you have a reported gene of
interest and you know you're going to
integrate it at some specific locus in
the genome but you want to predict how
much once upon integration what the
expression level of this gene is going
to be right
um and so this would be a function of
the promoter sequence of the gene and
also the genomic environment or the
sequence um and the accessibility and
other factors and chromatin state of the
locus into which it's integrated. Right?
Other enhancers may interact with the
promoter once it's um inserted into this
um specific genomic coordinate. The
sequence to function way to make this
prediction would be to take the sequence
of the site of integration, insert the
sequence of the reporter gene um and
then run it through a model like boroy
or infirma and look at the predicted RNA
seek or cage um values in the cell type
of interest. Right? But the hypothesis
we have here is can we do better if we
add additional information. So we
already know something about this
specific locus beyond the sequence
itself from our measurements. So we
perhaps know that there's an attack seek
peak 20 KB upstream of this and another
one 80KB downstream. Is there any way to
factor this in um in this specific uh
make these kinds of predictions? Right.
So to test this we trained um a context
aware model for K562 uh the K562 cell
line. Uh and in this model we have nine
tracks, seven DNA seek tracks and two
gauge tracks um which a subset of the
larger set of tracks that enfor
um and we train our model in two stages.
In the first we this is all done within
the nona framework. So you can just
switch the masks up um at different
stages of your training really. So in
the first stage we're doing a sequence
to function training with a 196 uh KB
input window and nine tracks. um and
these nine tracks. In the second stage,
we fine-tune this model with our context
aware masking mode in which we're
masking only the central 4KB. Um and so
the model has access in these
predictions to the sequence um and 192
KB of measurements around in regions
adjacent to the the central um mast
area. Um and it's trained on the same
genomic regions. So both these models
are trained. What's the only thing that
changes when you go from part one to
part two is the masking, right? Nothing
else really changes. The loss and
everything else stays more or less the
same.
And so what we can see here is the
prediction on the test set for these
nine tracks uh when you're predicting
with just the sequence only mode of of
Nuna or the contextaware mode of Nona.
And you can see across the board um
pretty uh decent increase in performance
for all the DNA seek um prediction tasks
as well as the gene expression um gauge
tracks which suggests that as you'd
expect adding the um context information
does give you a bump over the sequence
only. Um I just um curious about what
happens if you don't include the
sequence. So if just context only
prediction do these are these better or
yeah what what are the what are the
numbers here like yeah uh don't try that
explicitly I would imagine it's uh
somewhat lower because you would need to
know for example if there's a DSS of a
gene in the central mast region right if
you don't have access to the sequence
you wouldn't even know if there's a TSS
of a gene so you may not be able to
predict gene expression in the first
case so Um my expectation is it'll be
fairly low.
Great. So um when we look at the
differences between the predictions of
these two models for one specific track
in this case DNA seek and K562 you can
see that the predictions are more or
less tightly correlated except for this
set of about 2% of regions where the
predictions of the context aware model
differ significantly from the sequenceon
model. in fact in this case um are much
lower than the predictions of the
sequence only mode. Um and this one
specific locus where we see this
phenomena um at this specific locus the
sequence only model predicts kind of
across the board high regulatory
activity. So it thinks there's a strong
uh DNA seek peak chromatin access region
of accessible chromatin here another one
here and another one here. But if you
look at the actual data and this is a
test set example. So if you look at the
actual measured data, you see there's
there's no regulatory activity here,
very little regulatory activity in the
other positions and also in the central
uh 4KB. So if you kind of zoom into the
central 4KB, you can see that the model
really thinks there's a lot going on
here in terms of accessibility, but
there just isn't as much going on. Um
and so what the context aware model will
do in this case is have access to the
same sequence as the sequence only model
but also look at the fact that there's
overall reduced accessibility
um in the in the adjacent flanking
areas. And so when you use the context
aware model it seems to reduce its
prediction compared to the sequence only
prediction. Although not completely
ablating it entirely it does seem to
move towards the right direction. And
for those of you fairly familiar with
chromatin states and and and the like,
what we see is that this specific locus
seems to be enriched for hetrochromatin
marks. These are just chromm state um
tracks for a bunch of K562 samples and
see a lot of enrichment for
hetrochromatin and and and ZNF repeats.
But overall we seem to uh if when we do
this analysis more globally we do see uh
an enrichment of of heterocchromatin or
other repressive marks in region where
the context aware models predictions
differ from the sequence only model.
So um we try to do a a different kind of
evaluation a one that reflects um how
we'd like to use this model for a
downstream application. Um and the kinds
of data sets um that are a good fit is
something called tripseek
um I think it's called thousands of
reporters in parallel assay. Yeah,
that's why it's called tripseek. And the
the way trips works is you have some
promoter and reporter gene construct
that you insert randomly um at basically
a different loi in different cells
somewhat at random um and then you
measure the expression of the promoter
and reporter gene once it's been
integrated into those contexts. And so
the differences in expression would
largely be driven by um the the
chromatin state or the genomic
environment within which this uh gene
was integrated into. Okay. And so what
we end up at the end of this experiment
is the coordinate of integration and the
gene expression measurement um for this
reporter gene. Right? And we people
typically integrate the same promoter in
a few hundred to a few thousand
different positions, make these
measurements and then also repeat this
for a bunch of different promoters. So
housekeeping versus a um a more cell
type specific promoter.
Um and the way we would run these
through our models is simply the
reporter's sequence is about 2kb in
length. So we can um integrate that in
uh we can insert that into the sequence
of interest at the site of integration
um in the case of a sequence only model.
In the context aware case we will append
the measured functional tracks outside
the 4 KB uh in the center which will
contain 2 KB uh from the reported
sequence itself. So here the model
seeing the sequence post integration and
then also seeing prior to integration
what the chromatin landscape look like
and kind of assuming that that doesn't
change much after integration. Um
and so what you can then do is look at
the prediction of the models um with and
without the context information. So for
this one specific promoter that was
integrated in about 600 sites in the
genome, you get a bunch of um gene
expression measurements um and then you
get predictions from both our models.
And you can look at the correlation
between the measurements and the uh
prediction in both of these cases. And
we see reasonable increase in in
accuracy going from the sequence only
mode to the context aware mode. And you
can repeat this for a bunch of promoters
and we see a similar pattern on average.
There are some promoters that we don't
seem to do better on, but there are
others where we um see reasonable gains
on. And then you can also repeat this
with another more recent uh data set um
and you more or less see the same trends
where adding information about the
context seems to help you predict the
expression levels of integrated
reporters um better.
So that was the first um flash talk I
guess um and I've hopefully shown you
that a context aware nona model uh can
integrate information beyond the
sequence and specifically integrate
information about functional
measurements around the central region
of interest. Great. So we're going to
switch now to functional language
modeling. Um and as I mentioned before,
what we're doing in this mode is
extending mass language modeling um by
conditioning on additional functional
tracks. In this case, let's start off
with a simple one track example where
you have measurement from one track.
Let's say attack DNA seek in one
specific cell type. You mask um some
fraction of bases. Then you fill those
in. In all of these cases, you're
presenting the entire track to the
model, but you're only masking some
bases in the sequence. Doing this at
single base resolution.
And so we started training some of these
models to see what they're aarning and
then what we could do with these um
kinds of mass language models that are
aware of that are that are functionally
informed. Uh
and so we started off with a 512
baselong model, fairly short. Um and the
track of interest in this case was DNA
seek in in GM12878 which is a blood
derived cell line and what we do during
training which is a little distinct from
how models like BERT are trained is we
used a uniform masking rates so uh
uniform between zero and zero and one
and so in some examples you might mask
as high as 90% of your bases and in some
you might mask as low as 5% of your
bases and I'll show you why this is
useful when we talk about how we can use
these models to generate regulatory
elements.
So the first question we have is is what
are these functional language models
learning? Are they even different from
what mass language models are learning?
And uh if we can make any sense of them.
So the simplest thing we thought of was
to just mask one base at a time and then
look at the model's predictions for that
base. So conditioned on some profile of
um DNA seek in this case GM1287 GDNA
seek. Let's say we know this region is
an accessible region in in uh JM1287A
and given everything except one base in
this um at this locus what do the
model's predictions look like and we'd
like to differentiate between two major
cases where the model is kind of unsure
or it's just giving you the base the
baseline distribution of AC's gs and ps
versus where the model is quite
confident of the base um at this
position. So whether it's a flat
distribution versus somewhat peaky and
we can quantify this by just looking at
uh 2 minus the entropy at this site
which would be higher for cases where
distribution is more peaky and uh lower
where it's flatter and the entropy here
is just the standard sum of negative sum
of p and p log p
and so the way you would run this
interpretation analysis then would be
for the same uh locus so the same track
and the same sequence. You you mask one
base at a time. So you go across a
sequence masking one base at a time. You
compute this two minus entropy value and
then you just concatenate them all
together to get some sense of what
positions in this input sequence is the
model paying more attention to or or or
has stronger predictions um as is making
more confident predictions about.
And so I'm showing you one specific 512
long sequence which you can't probably
read which is totally fine at this
point. Uh and then the the GM12878
signal. So you can see there's a peak.
So this specific sequence comes from an
accessible chromatin region in GM12878.
And now what you can do is scale each
base in this uh very small sequence or
very narrow sequence by the two minus
entropy values that I showed you before.
And when you do that, it kind of starts
it clears up, right? So you see um
higher scores kind of localized almost
DNA words in some sense um shooting up
and we're just centering the two minus
entropy scores subtracting the mean to
make it a little more clean. Now I'm
going to zoom in now so you can finally
read the sequences especially those of
you that can recognize transcription
factor motifs by I is a good time for
you. Um, but what we're seeing is that
the model is picking up on on on
specific DNA words. Um, and I'm going to
show you actually these are well-known
features of DNA and these are quite well
annotated. I'll just tell you what these
are. So the first one is actually a
simple repeat. It's a micro satellite
and you can see the sequence is a GCC
GCC repeat about seven or eight times
it's been repeated. Um, and then it
makes sense, right? These kinds of
simple repeats are scattered through the
genome. If I just mask one base, if I
just mask this G here, it's going to be
pretty easy for me to predict that yeah,
there should be a G here because I'm
seeing the GCC pattern repeat on both
sides. Right? So that quite that very
simply explains why the model is able to
be more confident in its predictions at
this microatellite
um or this microatellite sequence or
motif if you will. Um but this just like
some kind of idiosyncrasy of the genome.
It's not really functionally relevant.
It's not that it's a transcription
factor binding site in this case that's
that's causing the uh the region to be
accessible in in GM12878.
But what's even more interesting is
these other DNA words or motifs actually
correspond to known transcription factor
binding sites. So this GCC and GCC's is
is an SP or a KF motif and these others
are are NFY motif. So these are quite
well annotated. So have you compared
these motifs that are picked up here
versus the motifs that would be picked
up with the gradient times method and
how do they compare and happen? I don't
have the slides here but yeah the short
answer is you see these SP and NFI
motifs but not the micro satellite and
do you have any intuition as to why? Um
so yeah I mean the SP and FI motifs are
known to cause accessibility right so
they are associated with increased
accessibility having this motif means
that a transcript factor is binding
there and is bringing other
transcription factors and keeping the
region open and accessible. There's also
a um a promoter sequence actually. So
you can see so if you look at a sequence
to function model um and make
predictions with it you're going to see
mostly these motifs but not the micro
satellite.
Um I also have a related question which
is do you see what are some of the
motifs that like you feel like you can't
actually like learn and uncover because
obviously there are things that are easy
to find and there are things that maybe
are a little bit harder. Yeah. Uh I mean
I don't think they're specific to these
language models but there are certain
zinc fingers for example that don't bind
a lot. They maybe bind
tens or a few hundreds of sites. I think
those are some kinds of sequence
features that you wouldn't be able to
learn just because it's a very rare
event. But any transcription factor
that's fairly pervasive binds promoters
or enhancers you should and we have seen
in many contexts you are able to pick
these models. Um given that you know
like the uh DNA language models are like
zero shot predictors. Yeah. Have you
tried doing this entropy but with just
the next slide. Yeah. Thanks. So yeah we
looked at Kaducius which is a mass DNA
language model completely unconditional.
Uh and what's interesting is it does
pick up the micro satellite but not the
transcription factor binding sites. Um
which somewhat makes sense. These are
well you would so we we do know that
these DNA language models pick up
features like start codons and um
sometimes even a CTCF motif um but don't
really pick up much beyond that. And
yeah one reason for that is they aren't
really informed by any functional
measurements. Um and as Gokchin
mentioned the transcription factors
relevant in different cell types are
different and they aren't necessarily
under strong constraints as much as say
a start codon is or or um genic features
are. Um and so I think that might
explain why a language model like
kadouch is not able to pick this up. So
once we've established that our model is
learning meaningful uh features of DNA,
not not just the idiosyncrasies like
microatellites and other repeats but
also motifs. uh we wondered if we can
repurpose this mass language model uh
for designing regulatory elements and as
Gobchin mentioned um synthetic
regulatory element design has kind of
taken off um in the last few years many
approaches um across organisms and even
different ML methodologies including
some from our group as well have have
been demonstrated in this area and
overall quite exciting and there's a
very simple way to um
uh to to generate sequence is from a
mass language model. And this hopefully
ties back to the fact that I mentioned
the fact I mentioned about using a
uniform masking rate. Since the model is
more or less uh comfortable with any
masking or dropout rate, you can then
use it in in uh in a sequential way to
generate sequences from scratch. So
conditioned on some specific profile.
Let's say we want to generate something
that's um a peak in a specific cell
type. You can start off with a
completely empty sequence. So you mask
all the bases in your sequence and then
you make a prediction with your model.
You pick a position, look at the
predicted distribution, sample from it
or do something more interesting
potentially. Now you selected one base
and then you send that back into the
model, make predictions again, choose a
position, uh sample the base, then
repeat this till you've essentially
generated the full sequence. Um
and you could choose which position to
unmask randomly or you could use the
model to guide your um position where
you unmask. You could look at the
confidence for example from the models
or the two minus entry to select the
next position that you choose to unmask.
So to demonstrate this more concretely
we turn to a more interesting case where
we have not just one track but we have
three tracks uh coming from three
distinct uh cell types. So GM1287 as
before but also dermal fibroblasts um
and H1 H embionic stem cells kind of
stem cell um population use a thousand
train on thousand base regions and again
with a uniform masking rate during
training and so once you've trained this
model we can then almost prompt it with
um profiles that of of of peaks across
cell types um that we would like the
generated sequence
um to have in in different cellular
context right so here we can prompt it
with a cell type specific regulatory
element so we can say I want high
activity in GM1287 that even looks a
specific way so it's somewhat narrow and
and uh at the center of this regulatory
element and maybe no activity in fiber
blast and H1C's and then what Nona will
do is generate not just one but you can
run you can keep running this multiple
times generate a bunch of sequence
candidates
um that hopefully have the desired
functional properties and then you can
pass each of these sequences through a
sequenceto function oracle model. In
this case just to keep things uh
independent we use a model like boroy
and boro also predicts the profile of
activity across the same cell types. So
in this case you can see that upon
specifying a sequence to have activity
specifically in GM12878 NA designs a
sequence which is also predicted to have
uh activity in GM12878. So it's kind of
fulfilling the design objective if you
may and we see more or less um this
across the sequences generated we see
that it's able to recover this kind of
cell type specific activity. There are
some hits but there are some misses but
on average you can see that the
generated sequences have GM12878
specific activity in this case and you
can repeat the same thing with
fiberblast or H1C's and it's able to
generate regulatory elements specific to
these cell types or you could prompt it
with something that's a bit more
ubiquitous. you let's say you want a
regulatory element that's shifted to the
right uh accessible in all cell types
and by and large it's able to do the
same uh it's able to design what you ask
for um you can also what we start trying
to do is prompt to more complex profile
specifications in this case you have uh
kind of a biodal distribution fiber
blasts and a left shifted one in GM12878
but the centers of the peaks aren't
really aligned between GM1287 5 plus and
no activity in ESC's and you can see at
least some examples though not all seem
to um recover the kind of expected
profile specifications. So this a
prototype of sorts but you can imagine
if you start throwing in other tracks
like gene expression or cage you can
think of designing entire regulatory
domains where you have um some desired
um chromatin accessibility across cell
types and potentially even gene
expression in different cell types.
Um and we also looked at motifs that are
typically enriched within these
sequences. So for example the fiber
blast specific sequences that Nona
generates um you would find more AP1
motifs in them which makes sense. AP1 is
a like the June force family of
transcription factors um are known to
have high activity in five blasts. You
see similar patterns across the board.
The ox motif um plays a crucial role in
in stem cells regulation in stem cells
and that seems to be enriched in um H1C
specific generated sequences.
So to wrap up this section um what we're
seeing with functional language modeling
is that we're able to learn meaningful
regulatory DNA features um and also
generate sequences with with desired
profile specs.
All right. So, I I'll start with the
last part which actually touches upon a
completely different aspect of of genome
privacy. Um, which which I was shocked
was something that we could even get
into with these kinds of models. Um, but
what I'm going to show you is is that we
can actually use an instantiation of
these function language models um to to
ddidentify attack files, fragment files
specifically. Let me show what I mean by
that. Um so if you worked with attack
data of any kind uh or or really any
sequencing data once you get your fast q
files from the sequencer you align them
to your reference genome um and you end
up with a bam file which contains
information about where each read aligns
to as well as information about any
potential mismatches to the reference
genome. So in this case you're seeing
that there's an attackseek peak here and
um all the reads from this specific
individual contain a mismatch at this
position which suggests that the uh
genotype of the individual here is is
not the same as the reference here. It's
it's this individual has um a variant at
this site in this case a homozygous
alternate variant. Um
another way to represent a tax seek
which has gained popularity with the
advent of single cell attack especially
is what we call a fragment file. These
are just um three column you know tab
separated files where instead of um
supplying a lot of information about the
reads you just specify the chromosome um
and the start and the end coordinates.
So for example for this specific read
you just say it starts here and and it
ends here and uh there's no information
beyond that except just a list of
alignment start and end coordinates for
uh for each read right so in theory it's
deidentified because any information
that BAM files contained about mismatch
mismatches indels or other complex um
sequence mutations is not really
captured or is not kept in these
fragments um in principle
Um and so the question we asked is if we
can actually predict the genotype simply
from a list of coordinates. Right? So at
first it sounds like I'm not even making
sense uh because this information is not
there. But if you start digging into
attack data more closely, you'll see
there's actually something interesting
going on. So when you look at attack as
you might have over longer regions of
DNA, you'll see regions with enrich
which with enhanced signal. These are
regulatory elements that we've been
talking about all morning.
But once you zoom into a specific
regulatory element and look at say 100
bases um around it um and when we just
look at the start so we just make u look
at the starts and ends of these
coordinates and count how many starts or
ends of any of these files of any of
these reads we have at uh specific
positions. What we'll see is that attack
seek at base resolution is actually
quite spiky. So what it means is that
within this regulatory element of 100
bases uh you're seeing more cuts at this
specific position compared to the
positions around it. So it's it's not a
uniform way of cutting but it's almost
like it's preferring certain bases for
cut over others. And the reason behind
this is that the TN5 transpos transpose
enzyme that's used in attack has a
sequence preference. What that means is
it's more likely to cut at positions
where there's a G4 basis um upstream and
a C4 basis downstream. It's not a very
hard preference, but it does end up
reflecting um this kind of spikiness and
it's it's manifested this kind of
spikiness in attack profiles and and the
recent preprint from my PhD adviser
Anupra Pandaji's lab on Chrome BPE uh is
something you should check out if you
want a more detailed treatment of what
this bias looks like. But the high level
takeaway is that the DN5 enzyme has a
sequence preference and if you alter the
underlying DNA sequence with a mutation,
it might alter the uh the pattern of of
cuts. Right? So just to illustrate this
in more detail uh what we did is we
looked at attack seek from the AFGR
project the African genome resource
project subset of the thousand genomes
um uh people and at this specific
variant on chromosome one uh if you just
add up the reads from 32 people that
have a TT genotype at this specific
position this is uh the pattern of reads
you get um and then there are 15 people
that have an AA genotype and here is the
pattern of reads from those people. And
both of these have been appropriately
normalized. And you can compare the
numbers in the light on the left and
right panels. And so I'm going to pause
for 10 seconds and make this a game of
spot the difference. And I hope you can
find some positions where there's
differences between these plots. It's
kind of subtle, but um take a squint, I
guess.
So hopefully you saw a few of these uh
positions where there's differences
caused just by by the variant. Right? So
the one I my eyes went to immediately
was this tall bar here is reduced um to
some extent here. There's also changes
at at these three positions. The shape
changes from high low to high low high.
Uh and even around the variant you see
some local changes in in the cutting
patterns. Right? So these aren't
actually necessarily variants that
affect chromatin accessibility entirely.
Uh these are just affecting the local
cutting patterns around the variant. So
they don't necessarily have to sit
within a transcription factor binding
site to affect chromatin accessibility.
They just can be really any variance
within a highly accessible region.
Right? And so I think it stands to
reason that if I were to give you the
profiles
um of around around the variant of
interest, if you squint at many of
these, hopefully eventually you'll be
able to predict the genotype from just
the patterns uh just these sort of
cutting patterns of attack and nothing
else, right? And so to test that out, we
trained a nona model, a very small 128
baseline nona model with the same
functional uh language model loss. So uh
we have the functional tracks here which
is attack seek from GM1 to878 at base
resolution and then we're masking with a
variable masking rate when we're
training. And another important point to
note is that we're actually just
training still with the reference
genome. So when we're training this
model, we don't require access to any
individual specific variants. Just the
fact that
most positions in the genome are not um
are not don't differ across individuals
is enough for the model to latch on to
relevant features. And once you're done
training, we can go from snip to snip
especially in regions with high
chromatin accessibility
and try to predict the genotype from the
surrounding DNA sequence um and the
attack seek base resolution signal.
Right? So once you train this model, I'm
going to see if it can actually do
exactly this, right? Can it predict the
individual variance? And the most
interesting positions for one specific
individual would be where the individual
has a variant that differs from the
reference, right? So in this case, we're
we're going after homozygous alternate
variants where the reference, for
example, says there should be a G here.
Um, but the the specific individual has
two copies of NA, for example. Um, and
these could also be in the training set
and the model is almost trained with the
wrong label with a G here. Or they could
be in the test set where it's not seen
them before. And so we asked, you know,
in how many of such cases can the model
correctly genotype this individual just
from the attack C cutting patterns? And
it turns out at least in regions with
high chromatin accessibility in the top
thousand strongest peaks, it's almost as
high as 90% for for homozygous alternate
variants. So we can't really distinguish
between hetererozygous versus homozygous
at this point. But you subset the
analysis to homozygous alternate
variance. You can see you can actually
very accurately predict the individual's
variance just from the cutting patterns
of a taxi which were derived from a
fragment file which in theory didn't
contain any personal identifying variant
level information.
So um go a step ahead and let's say we
had access to a database of individuals
and their genotypes. Let's say there's a
malicious actor that's uh that's
collected this and then we get the
attack C fragment file from Bob. We can
go from variant to variant and make
predictions at each position. And let's
say at this specific position we have a
prediction of 7 for C. We see indeed Bob
has you know two copies of C here. Um
would it be possible to link this attack
sample from Bob uh to Bob's genotype?
That's the question we ask. Um and so we
can come up with simple scores that
match the similarity between each of
these genotypes and the predicted
probabilities or the predicted genotypes
from a taxi. You could simply look at
the likelihood of observing this
genotype under this model separately for
each of these people and then rank
individuals that have the highest math
score. Right?
So we did this uh what we did then was
we looked at 3,200 genomes from the
thousand genomes project and then for
this one specific individual named
NA12878
from their attack seek um track we
predicted their genotype and then we
tried to match it against these 300
3,200 individuals. This is a histogram
of scores you get. Um, these are math
scores of attack from from NA1 to878
with 3,200 genotypes. And it turns out
the the math score of the attack seek
from NA1 to878 the genotype with of one
NA1 to878 is is really high and it's
like a strong outlier and these are the
other individuals in the data set. And
what this is really suggesting, it's
super easy to identify that the sample
came from NA12878
and not the other 3,200 individuals. And
so we repeated this analysis for attack
samples from 83 individuals in the AFGR
project and tried to link them against
the 3,200 or so genomes um in the
thousand genomes database. And turns out
we can link each sample perfectly.
Right? We call this a success if you're
able to rank if you're able to rank the
person from whom the attack sample came
as the top uh match for our attack
samples. And so we're able to do this
with almost perfect accuracy for for all
of these 83 individuals. But if you
start subsampling the attack seek within
each of these uh from the samples of
each of these individuals, so you're
basically reducing your signal. uh there
is a point of about 5 million reads
below which we start losing our
accuracy. Or maybe another way to look
at it is even if you have 500 cells from
some individual and you have a fragment
file corresponding to that, it's enough
for us to be able to genotype them in
this specific situation.
Um
yeah, so so to conclude this part um
show a nona model that's able to sort of
didentify attack fragment files. And
today if you go on Jio and you look up
data set releases from different papers
you will find papers where um fast cues
and other sensitive files have been have
been sent to dbgap for access control
but you can find fragment files from a
tag seek uh publicly available. So that
does seem to highlight um potential
privacy risk.
So these are just three applications I
covered but as I mentioned this is a
very flexible framework. you can come up
with the mask of your choice and attach
that to the task of your choice and
hopefully do something really
interesting. Um, and you're potentially
just scratching the surface of what's
possible with this. Um, so Nona is a
mass modeling based framework for
function genomics and unifies common use
cases like sequence to function and
genomic language modeling. Um, but also
is seems to be able to open up entirely
novel applications. Um, and what's
really nice is we can flexibly and
dynamically change inputs and outputs
across modalities which in this case are
DNA sequence and and functional tracks.
And this is a question that was asked
and in theory we can support multiple
masking modes in the same model. And
this does seem to work to some extent,
but um it's it's still a pretty
interesting direction.