Okay. Yeah, thanks for having me. Thanks
for being here. So, I'm going to talk a
little bit today about some of the work
that we've been doing on trying to
understand how different agents in some
sort of multi-acctor system broadly
construed have access to different
pieces of information and what impacts
that that's going to have on the overall
outcomes of that system. And so, the
main question that we're going to be
trying to ask and answer today is what
is the role that heterogeneous
information play in in AI systems? And
there's a couple ways we can think about
this. Um I'll talk about one in
particular today. One perspective on the
sort of multi- or information
heterogeneity and AI systems comes from
human AI collaboration. And often the
goal there is you say well my uh my
model my AI system knows something. The
people I have know something else. And
hopefully they can make better decisions
together. And so my goal is to say can I
combine these information sets into some
productive way and get something that is
better than either in isolation. Okay,
that's not what I'm going to talk about
today, but we have some interesting work
on that if you're if you want to talk to
me more about it. A different
perspective comes from what happens when
I have lots of different AI models
acting out in the world somewhere. So I
have lots of little robots. They're
maybe going around and doing things.
They're producing stuff. They're setting
prices. They're making decisions.
Whatever it might be. And I might think
that I'm getting a lot of benefits
because I have lots of different robots
running around doing things, but it
might end up being the case that they
all have access to the same underlying
set of information and that's going to
correlate their behavior in
unpredictable and perhaps problematic
ways. And so this is the thing that
we're going to be focusing on today.
Now, one thing that you might hope for
is in this world, maybe it would be
actually be better if I had a different
little model come. Maybe this guy's, you
know, not very good, maybe it's not very
powerful, but it has access to a sort of
a different information set relative to
everybody else. Okay? And so in a world
where everybody's behaving the same way,
it might make sense for me to try to
diversify in some way. And so we're
going to look at settings where that
might be the case and try to think about
what is the right way to analyze them.
Okay. So I'll talk about a few different
papers today sort of jointly together.
This all started with work that uh we we
started thinking about in 2021. uh
around what happens when we get
monocultures of algorithmic systems and
how should we think about that. Okay, so
what is a monoculture? Well, the
traditional agricultural notion of
monoculture says, you know, if we bu
plant lots of different crops, those are
going to be resilient to different
things. They're going to fail in
different ways. And so hopefully that is
going to be a resilient overall system.
And I'll contrast that with a
monocultural system in which I only
plant the same crop over and over again.
The problem with this is, you know, even
though this is a pretty hardy plant, it
survives with probability 0.9. If
there's some virus that's going to come
out and target this particular plant,
all of my crops are going to die and I'm
in trouble. It would have been better if
id planted a bunch of different things.
Even if some of them were weak, some of
them were going to fail under different
conditions simply because the
probability of catastrophic failure is
lower, right? They're not all going to
fail simultaneously. And that is good
for my system, even though any
individual plant might actually not be
as good as the best plant I could think
of. Okay? So this is a common problem
that people think about in agriculture.
It turns out the analogy actually
extends really nicely to uh computer
security. So people think about
monocultural issues in computer systems.
So if you think we're all running the
same operating system, it's we all have
vulnerabilities to the same bugs. And so
therefore, if someone designs a virus
that targets my Mac, it's going to
target all of your Macs and we're all in
trouble. But maybe if some people were
using Windows, maybe if some people were
using different Linux distributions,
whatever it might be, we would have a
more resilient overall system. Uh we
actually saw a good example of this.
This is a sort of a tangent, but I was
I'd gone to the the urgent care because
I thought I had broken a bone uh a few
months ago. And so I went in and I got
an X-ray taken and the I come out to the
doctor and she's like, "Well, actually,
we can't do anything with this X-ray
because all the Windows machines are
down. We can't send this to our lab
where they would normally analyze it.
So, you know, wait a few days and we'll
try to look at it and we'll call you if
something bad happens." And never called
me, so hopefully that means I was fine.
But this is a system where all of you
may remember this. This is a few months
ago or maybe was it a few months ago?
Yeah. Everybody's Windows machines
crashed. Nothing was working and all
these legacy systems that were built on
it were therefore vulnerable. Okay. So
that's an example of how we might see
monoculture in computer systems. More
recently, actually there's a Gary
Gendler who's a former I think treasury
secretary um SEC sorry SEC. Yeah. He had
a lot of stuff to say about monoculture
in uh AI systems in finance. So if
people are you know you have a trading
algorithm that's going to make decisions
on your behalf based on the information
it has available to it and if everybody
is running that same algorithm if
there's some mistake some weird
condition leads to unexpected behavior
that could trigger some sort of
catastrophic failure throughout the
financial system just because there's
some sort of weird failure that mode
that all these things are simultaneously
uh running into. And these are problems
that you don't have with human traders
necessarily because yes, they're going
to fail, they're going to make mistakes,
but the whole point of the system is
that people make different mistakes from
each other, right? There's independence
across actors and that actually creates
resilience in the system. Okay, so how
should we think about monoculture when
it comes to algorithms and AI decision-
making uh prediction and so on? Uh when
is it a bad thing? What sort of risks
are we encountering by increasingly
adopting AI models? and what are the
forces that are going to push back
against monoculture in the the world
that we have today. Okay, so I'll take
you through a few examples. So one is
this initial setting that we started
thinking about a few years ago which is
think about a decision-making setting.
So we were thinking about in the context
of uh like resume screening algorithms
sort of these uh models that are
designed to make predictive decisions
about people's potential for employment
and firms in this world often face a
choice. Sometimes they, you know, in in
reality they use a combination of these
things, but for for simplicity to say
you face a choice. You could hire a
bunch of people to screen rumés or you
could buy some model that somebody sells
that screens rumés for you. Okay? And so
there's lots of these third parties that
now offer uh machine learned models that
say give me a resume or give me some
information about a candidate and I will
predict how good of a candidate they're
going to be. Okay? So we could choose to
adopt that those models instead.
Forget about the difference in how fast
these things operate or how much they
cost or whatever. I'm gonna ignore that
for now and just think about what is the
information they have access to, how
much correlation is there going to be in
their decisions and what sorts of risks
will that introduce. Okay? And so a
caricature of what this might look like
is in a non-algorithmic world, all of my
human HR managers have different
information sets. They have different
biases. They have they make different
mistakes. And so what that means is
they're unlikely to fail all at the same
time, right? Another way of saying this
is if I go apply to a bunch of jobs and
there's a bunch of humans sitting on the
other side of that, some of them might
like my resume, some of them might not,
but at least I'll have opportunities
somewhere. Okay? Now, as we start to use
more and more algorithms in this space,
maybe it's okay if some people are using
uh human screeners and some people are
making decisions algorithmically because
I still have some opportunity there,
right? I might find a human who likes my
resume or maybe this particular model
likes my resume. But you start to
encounter problems when everybody is
reliant on the same algorithms, right?
If everybody's just using the same
resume screener, then if I get rejected
from one job, I'm going to get rejected
from all jobs. A different example of
this is if my credit score is low, if
this bank rejects me for a loan, then
every other bank is also going to reject
me for a loan, right? And you could say,
well, that's the whole point of a credit
score. It's supposed to measure
creditworthiness. But obviously, there
are idiosyncratic errors that it makes,
right? Some people just have thin credit
files. They are truly creditworthy. They
have low credit scores and they're going
to be systematically denied opportunity.
Okay. Now, so you can see how this might
be bad for individuals. The interesting
thing that we found when we we sort of
modeled this out uh more formally is
that this can actually be bad for the
decision makers themselves and yet it is
still in their best interest to switch
over to using algorithms. Okay. And the
intuition I'll give you for this is as
follows. For me as an individual, if I'm
a firm deciding what to do, it might
make me better off individually to start
using this algorithm. Right? it is sort
of marginally better than my the the
humans that I'm using instead. But when
I start using this algorithm, it's
actually going to make everybody else a
little bit worse off. All the people who
are also using the same algorithm as me,
I'm going to have an externality on
them. So my predictions get better,
theirs get slightly worse, right?
Because we are converging on the same
information set. And so if we all make
this same decision, I'm going to get
slightly better, everyone else is going
to get slightly worse. On average or
across the entire system, everybody
still ends up slightly worse off. Okay?
And so this is a somewhat
counterintuitive result. It's sort of
hard to wrap your head around this, but
for me it was a a clear indication that
there's some value in information
diversity, right? That creating these
monocultures is actually a negative for
society and it is still a path that we
might go down even if everybody's
behaving rationally. And that seemed
like a sort of a strange place to
be. Okay. So the key observation here is
that the negative impacts of monoculture
come from these externalities that when
I make a decision or I choose to adopt
some some algorithm, it's going to
affect everybody else who was also using
that same algorithm. It's going to make
them slightly worse off because I'm
doing the same thing as them. And as
long as that is in in in many of these
cases, that ends up being a bad thing.
Okay? So these links between people or
the the interactions between people is
really going to dictate what are the bad
things that happen when we all start
doing the same thing. we all start
behaving in the same way. And so there's
some key questions that in the next five
minutes and 29 seconds I'm going to try
to to explore here. When does us
behaving similarly lead to these
negative externalities? When is it bad
to have similar behaviors as your
competitors or your cooperators,
whatever it might be? What are the
implications for this? And where in
which settings should we expect to see
more or less monoculture? Okay, so I'll
give you two very quick examples that
we've been studying throughout this uh
this last couple years. One is on
algorithmic pricing. So how when people
are using algorithms to set prices, what
are the implications there? And the
second is on content generation. So when
we're using AI to generate some content
again, what are the impacts of
monoculture
there? Okay. So the the example I'll
give you to to sort of motivate this
notion of algorithmic pricing is you're
increasingly seeing people try to
predict willingness to pay and use that
as a factor to set prices. Okay? So, for
instance, you see this a lot on like
travel booking sites, like depending on
your location, depending on the device
you're using and that kind of thing,
they'll set show you different prices
because they're trying to effectively
estimate your willingness to pay and
then charge you as much as you're
willing to pay. And there's two
competing forces here. One is that firms
want prices to be high, right? High
prices mean more profits. But the second
force is firms also want to undercut
each other, right? If you know, Lyft is
tra charging $10 and Uber is charging
$9, then I'm gonna go to Uber and that's
probably good for them, right? And so
the question is, what is the impact of
monoculture on these competing forces?
So in this example, uh, Lyft gets to
decide when they're going to give me a
10% discount. Uber gets to decide who
they're going to give a 10% discount to.
People are sort of varying degrees of
price sensitive, and they're going to
make decisions accordingly. And the
question I'm going to ask is, as their
strategies for offering these discounts
become more correlated, what does that
do to the market? Is that good for me as
a consumer? Is it bad for me? Uh,
spoiler, it's going to be bad for me,
but for interesting
reasons. Okay. And so the the punchline
is firms may actually prefer to use the
same pricing algorithms as each other
because that allows them to effectively
collude on keeping prices high. Right?
If I know that you're not going to
undercut me because I know that we're
using the same algorithm, we can both
raise our prices. Okay. And so this
shows that firms in in this sort of
pricing setting actually have an
incentive to correlate their predictions
as much as they can. Right? Now this
should worry you a little bit. This is a
setting where you know if they were
using different pricing algorithms I as
a consumer could choose my favorite
price. I could be a sort of shop around
and choose the lowest price and
therefore I win as a consumer. And their
goal is to say actually can they just
use the same pricing algorithm? And if
so I don't have any choices anymore and
they can raise the floor on that price.
Okay. Now the this is sort of comes from
uh from from fairly standard economic
models. The interesting things for us
here is the the legal implications
actually. So I I mentioned the word
collusion before. You might think of
collusion in pricing as sort of vaguely
familiar as something that antitrust law
is designed to prevent us from doing.
Right? Antitrust law says that uh two
firms can't illegally collude to can't
uh to fix prices or to set prices to be
high.
But it doesn't really appear to apply to
this form of algorithmic collusion.
Right? If if firms make rational choices
that still, you know, lead me and my
competitor to adopting the same
algorithm, those might still be
individually rational choices. And as a
result, antitrust law actually doesn't
have a lot of teeth there, but it can
still result in these same collusive
outcomes that are as if they were able
to collude and keep prices high. And so
this represents a frontier of antitrust
law that the government is actually
still grappling with today. And when I
say today, I mean like in the last five
days, um the state of New Jersey joined
like 10 other states uh in filing a
lawsuit against Real Page, which is a
provider of software for rent pricing.
Okay, so Real Page goes out to a bunch
of apartment complexes and says, "We're
going to provide you some software. You
can use this to price your apartments."
And so instead of a world where every
apartment is going to be doing their own
independent pricing and I as a consumer
can come in and say here's the price
that I want for the apartment that I
want, you now see everybody sort of
hiding behind the same algorithm, right?
And saying we're all going to use the
same algorithm to set prices. And as a
result, we might be able to use those to
illegally or potentially illegally set
prices uh to be uh above their
competitive rate. And so this is what's
getting litigated right now uh between
the states and real page.
Okay, I will very quickly give you the
the second example of what happens when
we what what should we expect to see
when it comes to monoculture in content
generation. The stylized fact that I
found particularly intriguing recently
is you can find a bunch of these studies
that effectively find the the the
following. As people start to use
generative AI more and more in their
processes, you start to see a
convergence of the stuff that they
produce. Okay? So you see this in
creative ideation and writing and art
production and so on. The the picture
version of this is if I ask people to
come up with a bunch of creative ideas
in a condition without AI, they come up
with let's say two ideas each. If I give
them access to AI, maybe they come up
with three ideas each or more detailed
ideas or whatever. And I might look at
this and say, great, AI has helped. But
then you actually analyze those those
ideas and they all kind of turn out to
be the same. So even though each
individual seems to be producing more,
the set of things produced has has
gotten
smaller. Okay. So what how should I
think about this? There's there seems to
be at least from my perspective a force
pushing back against this which is if
we're all trying to come up with you
know creative business ideas or whatever
it is not just in my interest to come up
with good ideas it's in my interest to
come up with good ideas that nobody else
has had right I am worse off if we all
pick the same uh the same ideas or
whatever it might be and so shouldn't
that be a force pushing back against it
shouldn't I be trying to diversify my
creativity in some way okay so these are
uh going back to these externalities
that we mentioned this This is a setting
where us producing the same thing
creates negative externalities for us.
It makes me worse off if I do the same
thing as you. So how does that propagate
back to the way that we're going to use
AI? Without going too much into the
details, at a very high level, what we
find is that uh more competition
incentivizes more diverse production. So
the stronger our competition is, the
more that my behavior impacts yours and
vice versa, the more incentives we have
to diversify what we're doing.
We also find that the quality of an AI
model is therefore multi-dimensional.
Okay, in a world where I'm not
competing, maybe one model is is
particularly good. But in a world where
we're competing with each other, I might
actually just want to sample from a wide
range of good answers. I might not be
interested in the one great answer
because everybody has that one great
answer. And so some models are good at
giving you that one great answer. Some
of them are better at sort of exploring
out into the tail. And it's actually not
clear which one uh just given a set of
models, which one is going to be better.
And so what that means is that the
market for AI tools is going to
incentivize information diversity in a
sense you get some benefits out of
filling a gap left by other tools.
Right? You see this sometimes where you
know I have a coding question I go to my
favorite model it gives me the wrong
answer. So I'm going to go find a
different model and see if that try if
that fixes my bug and if that doesn't
work I'll go on to the next one to see
if that works. Right? It is helpful for
me that those three models are doing
different things. If it's the same model
over and over again it's going to get my
you know it's not going to be able to
fix my bug repeatedly. that's not
particularly useful for me as a
consumer. And so what I'm hoping is that
we end up not with a market that looks
like this where everybody's using the
same tool, but actually a market like
this where people just have very
different tools uh that sort of span the
spectrum of things that people might
want. Okay? And so I'll leave you with
this. This is sort of I didn't get to
talk about this uh due to for time
reasons, but there's sort of two nice
ways I like to think about information
diversity playing out in AI systems. One
is trying to leverage the
complimentarity between humans and AI,
right? So what do humans know? What do
AI models what are AI models good at?
How do we put those together? And the
second is how should we think about a
diverse ecosystem of tools that have
different strengths and weaknesses and
allow us to select the thing that works
best for us as opposed to a monoculture
where everybody's just using the same
product. So if you want to know more
about that, there's some QR codes at the
top to look at the papers. These are my
wonderful collaborators and thanks so
much for your
time.
Awesome questions for Manish.
So the um the idea is that the the
monoculture is just one model. Everybody
is sharing that. What if the world we
are in is like by or dur uh culture. So
there are two parts. You're either this
way or that way. You hate each other.
you don't believe in each other then
what's going to be happening that way
with AI
good okay so
there's maybe one so one way to to sort
of interpret what you're saying so
there's some polarization perhaps in the
world some people believe this some
people believe that and there's
polarized sets of demands of what people
want so I might want a model that aligns
with my beliefs somebody with different
uh different beliefs might want a model
that aligns with theirs I think you're
starting to see that a little bit right
So, it's a combination of things. When
we build these models, especially the
sort of big pre-trained models, they're
often pre-trained on whatever data we
could find. And as a result, that
pre-training process ends up being
pretty similar for a lot of these
models, right? There's only so much data
on the internet. If we all scoop up that
same data, we're going to end up with
things that look very similar. But on
top of that, we have more and more of an
ability to steer models in a direction
that we want them to go. So, if I want
this to be very good at coding, I'm
going to make it very good at coding.
and I'll get a bunch of data that uh
sort of makes it good in that direction.
If I want it to speak with a particular
tone, I'm going to collect data of that
form. So that gives a designer actually
a lot of degrees of freedom to say I'm
going to specialize the model in this
direction and maybe it's going to get
worse at some things, but it's going to
get really good at the thing that I want
it to do. Now, is it a good thing for
society if we start to polarize where
people can sort of find the echo chamber
model that reflects their own beliefs
and reflects that back to them? No, I
don't think so. It's not clear to me.
And I think this just is a reflection of
a lot of the problems that you see with
polarized media broadly speaking even
before AI, right? So you you know
polarization was a a problem that people
started to talk about in social media in
like the 2010s long before we had
generative AI. I think some of that is
feeding back into these models. Right
now actually the the fact that it is so
hard and expensive to train them means
that you don't actually see that much
sort of split and polarization between
them yet. But there's a chance that as
they become cheaper to to train and
people can really self- select the model
that agrees with their beliefs the most,
you'll actually see more polarization
than you do in social media simply
because media require has a sort of
aworked effect. Right? So in order for a
social media platform to be useful,
there needs to be enough other people
using it otherwise it's not a useful
media platform. But that's not
necessarily true with AI models, right?
If I'm just interacting with this model
over and over again, I don't need
anybody else to share my beliefs. I
don't need a, you know, platform, a
cohesive group of people who all feel
the same way. I just need, you know, a
small number of people who are willing
to train the model to behave that way.
So, I think there's actually a potential
for it to get worse than it is on social
media, but I I don't really have a good
prediction as to whether that's going to
happen.
Um, thanks for the interesting talk. Um,
I'm I'm wondering more on the content
generation sort of side of things. Um I
guess one argument could be that um you
know even if you have the same AI being
used by everyone everyone is using it
differently right so as long as you have
sufficient variation in the inputs to
the AI even if it's the same AI the
outputs can be still dramatically
different
um so so in given that how different
would this be say to like just using a
search engine which would also you know
sort of give similar results to people
if you input the same things it um like
where is the where's the key difference
here between yeah so this is a great
question the
so a lot of the variation that you're
going to get if people are interacting
with different ways are variation in
sort of the dimensions in which people
know that they want differences so if I
ask a different question from you we're
obviously going to get different answers
and we have to sort of communicate the
fact that we want diff that we are
asking questions different questions in
the first place I'm more sort of
interested in the subconscious choices
that get made. So one way of viewing
what these models are doing is sort of
decompression of the inputs, right? I
provide some very concise question or
something like that and it blows it up
into a very long response. In order to
do that, it has to make a bunch of
choices on my behalf, right? I didn't
specify, you know, what I wanted the
variables to be named when I asked it to
solve a math problem. And maybe I don't
really care that much about that. I
didn't specify, you know, the style or
the tone that I wanted it to use when it
responded to me. It just sort of made a
decision on my behalf there, right? And
so it's less the higher order bits that
I'm worried about like the actual intent
of the query that I'm producing. It's
more the lower order bits of the things
that get left unsaid, right? The things
that I'm not specifying and it's doing
this lossy decompression. It's going to
infer a bunch of stuff on my behalf. I
think it matters to some extent whether
it uh whether there's heterogeneity
there, right? Like I say, you know, make
me a clip art that I can use in my uh my
talk here and it's going to do that in a
certain style. It would be nice if
different models actually did that in
different styles. So there's some more
sort of information diversity in the
world. That's the kind of sort of
diversity that I would see there and
that's even conditioned on us you know
communicating our intent with the right
questions. Okay great.
Uh thank you for this presentation. It
was very interesting. I would like to
ask one question about an example you
made about the rental units. So if there
is an AI model which can basically set
the price for a unit. How would you get
diversification in this area since most
of the owners would just use a model
which would maximize their profit? How
would you tackle this issue? Oh,
absolutely. I I don't think the unit
owners or the the building owners
actually have strong incentives to
diversify there and that's what the law
is supposed to do basically. So the
question is is the law is antitrust law
sufficient force to push back against
that and I think the current answer is
maybe and it depends on how these cases
go right. So if you know the courts find
that actually all these states suing
real page have no grounds and you know
real page is just doing something that
is sort of economically rational for
them and not illegal then yeah antitrust
law does not have the force uh required
and at that point I don't really know
what the answer is. I think then you end
up
with incentives to create a monoculture
and no legal recourse for people who
think that's sort of bad for consumers.
I'm afraid it's 1210. So, uh, lunchtime.
Thank you so much to Manish.