(bright music)
(upbeat music)
(David laughing)
(upbeat music continues)
(vehicle whirring)
(electronic music)
- Something like this.
♪ FNAP ♪
♪ Facts not assertions please ♪
♪ FNAP FNAP ♪
Something like this.
♪ FNAP ♪
♪ Facts not assertions please ♪
(upbeat music)
(David chuckling)
(vibrant music)
Hello, everybody.
- [Audience] Hello.
- Hello, I'm David Wallace,
a mechanical engineering
design professor at MIT.
So FNAP, facts not assertions, please.
My father once said to me,
"Have a plan and be ready to change it,"
and that really stuck
with me from an early age.
The ability to be flexible
and pivot when something
isn't going the way we planned
is crucial to the design process
and really is a skill
that we try to foster
in each of our design students.
In our product design class at MIT,
teams explore hundreds of product ideas,
you might say plans,
before deciding which
final single product
direction they'll take.
Next week, you're gonna
be deciding on your
product direction
for the rest of our product
development process.
It's about working together
and really making the best
informed decision that you can.
(students cheering)
(lively music)
Welcome to our Sketch 1 review.
In this process, every
team member will invest,
really believe in ideas that
end up on the cutting board.
Each team member will have
plans and then change them.
How do we make these decisions?
This is a hard question,
but FNAP is one thinking
tool that we provide.
So FNAP, what that means is
facts not assertions, please.
And so, a fact is something
that's really a known
or demonstrated truth,
and an assertion is really
something we believe in
that we can often very convincingly
make sound like a fact.
- [Student] Okay, big yay, yay.
- [David] FNAP really
comes to the forefront
in one key decision making meeting.
(upbeat music)
Up until now, the larger team
has been broken into four sub-teams,
each with their own product idea
that they will be pitching
to the team at large.
(upbeat music continues)
They've poured a lot of
energy, thought and care
into these products,
so they're highly, highly
invested in each of their ideas.
But now they need to come
together to look at the facts
and set aside assertions to
choose the final product idea
that they'll all rally behind
for the final prototype launch.
- [Student] That was a 50/50 split.
- [Students] Oh!
(upbeat music continues)
- [David] We actually have
signs up in our meeting room
with giant letters, FNAP, when
teams are making decisions,
- We all remember our FNAP principle,
what does it stand for?
- [Students] Facts not assertions, please.
- And we almost make it like a chant,
perhaps like a game, a dance, a song,
FNAP that you can remember.
(students applauding)
Some teams make FNAP hats,
and so when somebody in a meeting
is starting to make
assertions stated as fact,
they get the hat.
- I just think there's no way that
this steal would ever bend.
- [Students] Oh! The hat!
(upbeat music continues)
- So it provides a really fun
and kind of tension relieving way
to have this hard discussion of,
okay, what do we really know?
What are the things that we hope we know?
And agree on how to sort
them out to balance the risks
or, you know, the knowns
where we feel like we're safe.
And you have to take some risks,
but you have to have a kinda
reasonable handle on that
before you commit too much.
- We're gonna vote and we're
gonna vote for the one we want.
Heads down, heads down.
Okay, slimsuit, raise your hand.
Auto sketch, raise your hand.
Okay, here you go.
Chosen slimsuit.
- [Students] Whoo!
- [Student] Get everyone's hands.
- [Students] Whoa!
(students applauding)
- [David] This year's yellow
team reached a consensus
to move forward with one
of their proposed products,
but after learning about
a critical shortcoming
related to user needs,
they pivoted to another
of their product ideas.
Then after getting some user feedback,
they pivoted again back to
one of their original ideas,
the fish feeder.
- For testing purposes,
I'm in contact with three fish farms
who have all said that they'd
be willing to help us test.
(upbeat music continues)
- It's really easy to go down a path
following things that
are asserted beliefs,
rather than facts, and
it can lead to trouble.
And in design teams in our class,
that happens from time to time
and the students eventually realize it
and then after some struggle
become very good at pivoting.
And that's really the lesson of FNAP
where you've learned
it and internalized it
and you're gonna remember it.
Sometimes, despite our best
laid plans, ideas break.
It happens.
It's the cost of doing business
in a messy physical world,
but in our quest to tame it
and forge a better world,
we must be open, humble,
and confident enough
to recognize when to change course.
Can we all apply the idea
of FNAP to work together
and be more open to change?
To have a plan, but remain
flexible enough to change it
when presented with the facts?
I'll assert, yes, I think we can.
Be on the watch to identify assertions,
diligently search for facts, known truths,
make choices understanding
which information is fact
and which is hope.
Be honest with yourself,
challenge your ideas,
have a plan, and be ready to change it.
And as always, keep playing seriously.
(electronic music)
(upbeat music continues)