Um, hi. Can you hear me? Great. Thanks.
It's um, it's a pleasure to be here with
you all this morning and with Zayb who I
have known now for I don't know 10 years
or something like that. three mothers
out front. Um, so I want to talk to you
today about something that's maybe a
little bit different from what others
will be talking to you about over the
course of the day. Uh, and that is
power. Not the kind of power that you
spent a lot of the day talking about and
we'll be talking more about this
afternoon, but people power.
Um, and I want to encourage you to think
about climate change as a ultimately a
problem of political power. So when we
take a step back and we think about why
it is that after decades and decades of
science and consensus in the scientific
community that we are indeed heating the
earth and with catastrophic implications
for life on this planet as we know it
have to think about what it is that is
preventing us from making more progress.
And we need to think about the powers on
the left hand side of the scale which
represent the fossil fuel industry, the
prochemical industry, uh the banks and
investors that make money from the
industry, the politicians that are being
heavily influenced by the industry. I
think the oil and gas industry spent
$230
million or so getting Trump elected,
probably more than that. Um and then of
course just status quo like people are
kind of resistant to change in general
and we have an entire economy based on
uh that's built on uh fossil fuels. Um
so the question is what do we do about
that? And what we do at mothers outfront
is we talk about building power and we
engage in the process of building power.
So ultimately it's the question is how
do we drive transformational change of
the level that we need in order to shift
the scale so we can actually win
campaigns and uh create the conditions
for network geothermal and other
important technologies to come in etc
etc and to do so in an equitable manner.
So, as it turns out, transformational
change throughout American history and
around the world has really largely been
possible because of social movements.
So, it's large large numbers of people
coming together out of a sense of shared
values and a sense of outrage at the
disconnect between the world they people
want and the world as it is and people
coming together, learning how to
organize together and drive campaigns
for change. So that has been the case
whether it's the civil rights movement,
women's rights, abolitionism before
that, LGBTQ rights, the early
environmental movement, and we're seeing
bits of it and not enough of it yet with
sort of the what you see of the climate
movement across the country. So how does
this relate to Mothers Outfront? Um I'll
tell you a little bit about my story
which is uh I am the mother of two
daughters and when they were quite young
I had one of those moments of absolute
despair uh looking at the climate crisis
through the lens of the for the first
time of being a mom and thinking about
the kind of world that my children would
be growing up in and thinking well that
I can't not try to do something about
this but I don't know if I can go back.
Yeah, but I was the little person on the
right hand side of the scale. I was one
person, a mom, not a scientist, not an
elected official, not a policy expert,
wondering what could I possibly do to
affect this enormous overwhelming set of
challenges. And around that time, I had
the opportunity to meet a man by the
name of Marshall Gans, who teaches
organizing at the Harvard Kennedy
School. And I called him up and I said,
"Will you please meet with me?" And he
graciously said, "Yes." He had no idea
who I was. And in about half an hour of
meeting Marshall, he explained to me the
power of social movement building, its
role in American history. And
importantly, that organizing to build
social movements is a practice that
anybody can learn. Any one of you can
become an organizer.
And so I teamed up with a couple of moms
and we started getting together with
other moms. We invited we had one-on-one
meetings. We invited them to house
parties and we started forming teams of
moms and providing a structure that
allowed them to come together, think
about what they wanted to work on
together and start implementing
campaigns.
So we were starting to build the right
hand side of the scale and Zanb and Ania
who was supposed to be moderating the
session and unfortunately had to leave
um were both integral parts of the early
days of Mothers Outfront as was Nathan
Phillips.
So we started organizing about 12 years
ago and our downtown Boston team led by
Aniia among others
was trying to figure out what it is that
they wanted to work on for their
campaign. And lo and behold, this
article comes out in the Boston Globe
about a study that Nathan Phillips was
involved in um indicating the role of
gas leaks in killing trees and
highlighting the number of gas leaks all
across the Boston area. And it was
shocking. And that is when our downtown
Boston team of moms said, "Aha, this is
what we want to work on. It's a concrete
thing. It's killing trees up and down
the blocks in our neighborhood. We want
to take this on.
And amazingly, this little organization
called HEAT had created maps show they
had taken the data available publicly
available information, input it into
spreadsheets and created maps of of of
different neighborhoods across Boston
showing just how many leaks there were.
This is a perfect organizing tool
because it allowed us at Mothers
Outfront to take something that was
invisible to everybody and make it
visible.
And so what happened next was that Ania
and others took it upon themselves to go
out and reach out to other Mothers
Outfront teams that we had formed across
the state by then. and they
all 16 of our teams got involved
and Aniia and others made presentations
saying you need to know about gas leaks.
This is why they're bad. Yes, they're
killing trees. They're also bad for our
health and they're major drivers of
climate change. And that was the process
of engaging the other teams that we had
done the work of creating all across the
state of Massachusetts
in this fight against the gas leaks.
So, this was um this was a very cold
January day when a bunch of us got
together under Ania's direction and
equipped with the maps of where the gas
leaks were. We fanned out across Boston
and we tagged, physically tagged every
gas leak in the city. And this exercise
of physically tagging gas leaks was
repeated in communities across the
Boston area, thereby again making the
invisible visible. And people for the
first time were making this connection
between gas leaks killing my trees that
I sort of know about because I smell
them when I walk around and and where
they're located and what we can actually
do about it. So, we called attention on
all the tags to the responsible company
and all the gas companies started
getting harassed by lots of people very
upset that there were these gas leaks
all over the place. So, the people in
orange, in case you're wondering,
they're supposed to be gas leaks
themselves. So, anyway, we had a little
fun with it, too.
So there we are tagging gas leaks
and in the process during while we were
also tagging gas leaks it was part of a
broader campaign. It wasn't just about
tagging gas leaks. It was a whole
strategy. So we met with elected
officials in various towns and cities
across the state.
We rallied rallied in front of the state
house. We rallied in front of what's
that? That's I think the Cambridge um
Cambridge state house.
We spoke up and we testified. We
testified at city city city meetings in
the city of Boston. Um you can see Zanab
there. That's a knee on the far left who
was supposed to be here. Nathan Phillips
joined us for a lot of these activities
and we collaborated. We teamed up with I
mean we never work alone because you
cannot achieve your goals as a
relatively small organization. So we
knew we needed allies. Of course, we had
heat working with us because we used
their maps. You can see Nathan Phillips
down here. And we created we brought in
as many allies as we possibly could and
in the process even created a whole new
organization that then was called the
Gas Leaks Allies and is now called the
Gas Transition Allies. Um and that is a
group of organizations that continues to
meet on a regular basis to talk about
how we drive important policy forward in
the state.
We also sought out unlikely partners and
this is where geothermal networks come
in. So Zanb was part of and the arrow is
pointing to um what was her name? Mary
>> Marcy.
>> Marcy Reid, thank you. who was then um
the president of National Grid in
Massachusetts. And um this is actually a
funny story. So Marcy was refusing to
meet with us. And we all were tweeting
with her the day that we were tagging
gas leaks across the city of Boston. And
by the end of the day, she's like,
"Okay, okay, okay. I'm going to meet,
you know, I'll meet with you." Um so it
was very effective. But when we went in
to meet with the CEO of Eversource, it
was Zanb and a few others from Mothers
Outfront and I think Audrey from HEAT.
And they went in and they sat down with
Bill Aley who was asked before the
meeting if he thought he needed security
because he was they were so accustomed
to the company coming under sort of
pressure from advocacy groups. And he
said, "No, I don't think I need
security. It's a group of moms." and he
sat down with a group of moms and Zayan
and the others in the room started by
talking about why they were there which
was for their children and Zay said I
have three children these are their ages
this is why I'm here I'm worried for
their future
and Aley sort of paused and he said oh
well I have three children too and they
they form this connection around their
shared concern about their children he
said of course I'm concerned for my
children too and it it it created an
opening and an opportunity for
collaboration and that was the beginning
of the reason why you're all here today
to learn about geothermal networks. So
I think the lesson in all of this is
that building power is absolutely
essential for creating the conditions we
need for the level of transformational
change we need to create the future that
we all want for our children and our
grandchildren and future generations.
Uh, and I think every time you think
about the climate crisis, I would always
I would encourage you to always think
about where does building power fit into
my thinking here because it's a
critically important piece and we all
have to be thinking about it and
hopefully be part of building that power
and implementing that power. So, thank
you very much.