the MIT energy initiative presents via
separations Mighty spinoff takes aim at
industrial
decarbonization written by Katherine M
O'Neal if you wanted to get pasta out of
a pot of water would you boil off the
water or use a strainer while homecooks
would choose the strainer many
Industries continue to use
energy-intensive thermal methods of
separating Outlet liquids in some cases
that's because it's difficult to make a
filtration system for chemical
separation which requires pores small
enough to separate atoms in other cases
membranes exist to separate liquids but
they are made of fragile polymers which
can break down or gum up in industrial
use via separations a startup that
emerged from MIT in
2017 has set out to address these
challenges with a membrane that is cost
effective and robust made of graphine
oxide which is a cousin of pencil Le the
membrane can reduce the amount of energy
used in industrial separations by up to
90% according to Shrea dve PhD
2016 the company co-founder and
CEO this is valuable because separation
processes account for about 22% of all
in plant energy use in the United States
according to the Oak Ridge National
Laboratory by making such processes
significantly more efficient via
separations plans both to save energy
and to address the significant emissions
produced by thermal processes our goal
is eliminating 500 megatons of carbon
dioxide emissions by 2050 dve says via
separations is piloting its technology
this spring at a US Paper Company and
expects to deploy a full commercial
system there in the spring of
2022 our vision is to help manufacturers
slow carbon dioxide emissions next year
dve
says Mighty seed
Grant the story of via separations
begins in
2012 when the MIT energy initiative
awarded a seed fund Grant to Professor
Jeffrey Gman who is now the Morton and
CLA goulder and family professor in
environmental systems as well as the
head of mit's Department of Material
Science and Engineering Grossman was
pursuing Research into nanoporous
membranes for water
desalination we thought we could bring
down the cost of desalination and
improve access to clean water says dve
who worked on the project as a graduate
student in Grossman's lab there she
teamed up with Brent Keller PhD
2016 another Grossman graduate student
and a 2016 through
2017 Exxon Mobile MIT energy fellow who
is developing lab experiments to
fabricate and Test new
materials we were early comrades and
figuring out how to debug experiments or
fix equipment says Keller via
separations co-founder and chief
technology officer we were fast friends
who spent a lot of time talking about
science over
burritos dve went on to write her
doctoral thesis on using graphine oxide
for water desalination but that turned
out to be the wrong application of the
technology from a business perspective
she says the cost of desalination
doesn't lie in membrane materials she
explains so after dve and Keller
graduated from MIT in
2016 they spent a lot of time talking to
customers to learn about the needs and
opportunities for their separation
technology This research LED them to
Target the paper industry because the
environmental benefits of improving
paper processing are enormous dve says
the paper industry is particularly
exciting because separation processes
just in that industry account for more
than 2% of us energy consumption she
says it's a very concentrated high
energy use
industry most paper today is made by
breaking down the chemical bonds in wood
to create wood pulp which is the primary
ingredient of paper this process
generates a byproduct called black
liquor a toxic solution that was once
simply dumped into waterways to clean up
this process paper mills turned to
Boiling off the water from black liquor
and recovering both water and chemicals
for reuse in the pulping
process today the most valuable way to
use the liquor is as bio Mass feed stock
to generate energy via separations plans
to accomplish this same separation work
by filtering black liquor through its
graphine oxide membrane the advantage of
graphine oxide is that it's very robust
dve says it's got carbon double bonds
that hold together in a lot of
environments including at different pH
levels and temperatures that are
typically unfriendly to
materials such properties should also
make the company's membranes attractive
to other industries that use membrane
separation Keller says because today's
polymer membranes have
drawbacks for most of the things we make
from Plastics to paper and gasoline
those polymers will swell or react or
degrade he says graphine oxide is
significantly more durable and Via
separations can customize the pores and
the material to suit each industry's
application that's our secret sauce dve
says modulating por size while retaining
robustness to operate in challenging
environments we're building a catalog of
products to serve different applications
Keller says noting that the next target
market could be the food and beverage
industry in that industry instead of
separating different corrosive paper
chemicals from water we're trying to
separate particular sugars and food
ingredients from other things future
Target customers include pharmaceutical
companies oil refineries and
semiconductor manufacturers or even
carbon capture
businesses scaling up dve Keller and
Grossman launched via separations in
2017 with a lot of help from MIT after
the seed Grant in 2015 the founders
received a year of funding and support
from the jws solutions program to
explore markets and to de velop their
business plans the company's first
capital investment came from the engine
a venture firm founded by MIT to support
tough tech companies which are Tech
businesses with transformative potential
but long and challenging paths to
success they also received advice and
support from mit's Das Pond Center for
technological innovation as well as the
Venture mentoring service and Technology
licensing office in addition Grossman
used to serve the company as Chief
scientist we were incredibly fortunate
to be starting a company in the MIT
entrepreneurial ecosystem Keller says
noting that the engine support alone
probably shaved years off our progress
already via separations has grown to
employ 17 people while significantly
scaling up its product our customers are
producing thousands of gallons per
minute Keller explains to process that
much liquid we need huge areas of
membrane via separations manufacturing
process which is now capable of making
more than 10,000 square ft of membrane
in one production run is a key
competitive Advantage dve says the
company rolls 300 to 400 ft of membrane
into a module and the modules can be
combined as needed to increase
filtration capacity the goal dve says is
to contribute to a more sustainable
World by making an environmentally
beneficial product that makes good
business sense what we do is make
manufacturing things more energy
efficient she says we allow a paper mill
or a chemical facility to make more
product using less energy and with lower
costs so there's a bottomline benefit
that's significant on an industrial
scale Keller says he shares dav's goal
of building a more sustainable able
future climate change and energy are
Central challenges of our time he says
working on something that has a chance
to make a meaningful impact on something
so important to everyone is really
fulfilling