Uh now I'd like uh to join me in
welcoming Dr. Brandon Fields, co-founder
and chief science officer at Fieldstone
Bio. Fieldstone Bio creates
highresolution heat maps of targeted
elements through microscopic bioensor
signals. Welcome.
>> Thanks for the introduction, Trisha. And
so again, my name is Brandon Fields. I'm
the chief science officer of Fieldstone
Bio. And today I'm going be talking
about how we're measuring Earth's
microscopic elements at mining scale.
And so just a bit about us uh field was
born out of MIT in 2023. I have a PhD in
genetics and I did my posttock in the
synthetic biology center at MIT under
Dr. Chris Voit who's one of the world
leaders in synthetic biology. And
together with Patrick Stone, we teamed
up to translate this technology being
done in the lab at MIT to solve some
real world challenges. And today I'll be
talking about aspects of this technology
we're applying to the mining industry.
And I really want to focus today on the
fact that uh data drives decisions in
the mining industry. For example, in the
exploration phase, trying to figure out
where to mine, right? Where are the
enriched metals underneath the surface
of the earth, right? Operations phase,
right? What materials to mine, right?
Deciding which materials are worth
proceeding with or not uh producing at
all. And then entailings management
right what are we leaving behind both on
the pollution side of what are the
pollutants that are being leeched in the
environment but then on the economic
side right where are the good minerals
that are still available right and be
able to purpos uh potentially remine
uh and so one of the key bottlenecks
right now is that this data is limited
and that's really based on the
technologies we have to generate that
data so the gold standard here is
lab-based analysis right methods that
are very specific specific but costly
and low throughput. So think of the
example in the exploration phase, right?
Taking core samples out of the earth,
right? And to get that specific
analysis, you have to do destructive uh
destructive uh lab-based testing where
you grind up some samples and send it
out for analysis, right? So not only is
that costly and takes time, but you're
really limited in spatial resolution.
You're only getting data for that
average signal across the region
measured. And then we think of the scale
of all these operations, right? The
exploration phase, they're taking
kilometers of core samples. The
operations phase, just all this material
and the tailings management, right? We
need technologies that can scale to
generate more high resol resolution data
across really large materials. Another
approach here is imaging based
approaches. And I use the term imaging
to cover an umbrella of different, you
know, spectral-based technologies,
right? These these do match that high
throughput need, right? where you can
generate lots of data across really
large scales, but they're not as
specific. Right? The challenge is it's
often limited to indirect readouts or
correlations with signals, right? And so
at Fieldstone, what we're working on is
a technology to uh combine uh the
sensitivity of lab-based analysis with
imaging based approaches to get the best
of both worlds.
And we do that using biology. And so I
love showing an image like this because
it highlights the scale of mining
operations. But I think about this on
the microscopic scale, right? In the
fact that nearly every surface of our
planet is covered in microbes, right?
Small organisms that cover these
surfaces and do tremendous biology.
Okay? And so uh in the mining example,
right, you have microbes. You may have
heard of biomining applications where
folks are using biology to extract
metals out. And this is because life has
found ways to interact with metals in
their environment contributing to the
geologies that we all talk about. And we
view microbes as these microscopic uh
computers, right? And so microbes have
evolved ways to sense and respond to
metals and other chemicals in their
environment to make decisions. Okay? And
so can we harness this uh aspect of
biology to be able to sense and report
on the minerals in our environment?
And so here's how we do that. We
engineer the actual DNA of the microbe,
right? To encode these sensing uh
programs, if you will, that are specific
to different critical minerals and
create an imaging based readout. Now,
this first part, engineering a microbe
to sense metals and other chemicals, has
been around for decades. That's not the
breakthrough here, right? Plenty of
people have demonstrated in labs you can
get microbes to sense and respond to
chemicals and produce responses. The key
bottleneck and why this hasn't been
applied in in the environment is how do
you visualize that activity? Right?
These little tiny microscopic organisms
typically you need heavy machinery or
microscopy based methods to see on their
scale. The key breakthrough for us is
creating an output when the micro senses
the metal that's compatible with imaging
based technologies such as hyperspectral
imaging, right? imaging technologies
that are already used in the field and
that could be put on uh on the surface
drones, planes and even satellites.
Right? So, a way to visualize these
microbial sensors for the first time
from far away. Okay? Now, one of the
benefits of the microbial bioensors is
they're once we do the initial
engineering to build the sensors,
they're really cheap to produce. Think
of growing uh yeast for beer. It's the
same process. We can grow these up at
large scales to be able to meet the
scale required in the mining industry.
Microbes are also uh don't require any
electricity and they can sense metals at
parts per billion concentrations on
millimeter resolution with our
technology. So again, it's really
combining this idea of the uh
specificity of lab-based analysis with
the high throughput and spatial
resolution of imaging.
So how does this actually look? Right.
So on the left is one of our products
where we have a microbial bio sensor
that senses gold and specifically gold
and then turns on the reporter that we
can visualize with the cameras. Okay.
And in this case, this is an example in
the lab of a contaminated soil with gold
in it. And you this is just harvesting
the core sample and then spray our
microbial bio sensor over the surface of
the area and then we can image and
analyze within hours. So, we get data on
the same day. And by eye, when you look
at this photograph, you really can't see
much, right? You see the core sampler
and you see uh the material that we're
investigating, but there's actually
billions of these little tiny
microscopic sensors embedded in the
material. And so, when we do our imaging
with hyperspectral analysis and using
our AI algorithms to identify where the
microbe is sensing the chemicals, we
generate these heat maps like on the
right. Okay? So these heat maps are
showing where the microbe has identified
where the gold is and has translated
that signal into an easily identifiable
spectral signature that the camera and
our algorithms can identify. And it's
not only where but how much. So you can
see the heat map going from blue to red,
right? And how much of the intensity
scores there correlate with the gold,
right? So really showing that we can use
uh mic microbes to do rapid spatial meta
metal analysis on samples.
And so we're currently uh in in our lab
we've built microbial bio sensors for
gold, copper and arsenic. And we're
currently working with customers in all
these different areas. Right? So in the
exploration phase some of the ideas here
are early core analysis on site same day
analysis. And so we're not only
improving the density of data through
our tech to guide the drilling
decisions. Then you have the operations
phase, right? Blast fragmentation and
detecting concentration elements over
the surface and or grade control and
sorting support chemical decisions
during the milling process. And then on
the tailing management side, right, it's
can we detect shifts and changes in the
tailings for the bad chemicals or metals
that we we don't want being leached in
the environment, but also the good ones,
right? Is there uh good gold or copper
or other metals in these piles to be
able to repurpose them and mine them?
And again, it's taking our technology to
generate this type of data at scale
required to drive all of these
decisions.
And with that, thank like to thank
everyone for the time and happy to take
any questions.
>> Thank you so much. Fantastic
presentation, Brandon. Um we do have a
few audience questions that we can um
get to. for interested companies. Is
there a way for you to demo your
technology on their materials?
>> Oh, yeah, definitely. So, one of the
things we like to talk especially with
some of these unique applications, bring
customers into hearing their pain points
and seeing how our technology can be
applied across the different areas
because like I said, once we've
engineered the micro uh there's some
specifics to applying to different
materials and things like that. Um, but
really it's up to uh different ways the
users can take advantage of this and
we're really excited to hear what people
have. And the way we start with that is
having uh folks send us these materials
and do these demonstrations and then
scaling up from there.
>> Excellent. Well, that's great. Great to
hear. And what are other metals you are
developing sensors for?
>> So, currently in our pipeline, like I
mentioned, we have the gold, copper, and
arsenic. Uh we have short-term uh goals
to build malibdinum and silver as well
as into the rare earth metals. Uh but
again, one of the things we offer
customers is as we're talking uh finding
out what they're interested in building
and building sensors specific to those
problems.
>> Excellent. And one last question. Um
what is the what is the limit of
detection for these microbial sensors?
So what levels of the metals can you
sense?
>> Great. Yeah. So in in our our testing,
we can get down to parts per billion
sensitivity. Um it varies, you know,
between the specific metals, but uh it's
in that range. And one of the reasons I
highlight this is, you know, we're
taking the fact that nature's already
doing this, right? And so life has
evolved to deal with the metals in these
all these samples I talked about, right,
at their natural levels, right? And so
we're just harnessing that ability. Uh
really showing how we can get real world
sensitivity.
>> Excellent. Well, thank you again,
Brandon. It was wonderful to have you
and feature you and thanks again for the
talk. Y
>> Thank you.