today we're going to uh continue we're
going to talk about a new notion a
really really interesting notion in my
opinion uh called probabilistically
checkable proofs I'll explain what it is
so we'll we're going to Define this
notion and we're going to construct it
uh from the GK protocol so you'll kind
of see not only the definition but
you'll be able after this class the hope
is that you'll be able to construct a
PCP if you need to construct proof
you'll be able to do that so that's
going to be the first part of today's
lecture and the second part of today's
lecture is actually going to be the
first time we actually use cryptography
so so far this class has not been at all
about cryptography it was everything was
information it was actually complexity
Theory uh but today is going to be the
first time we're going to move
into uh
cryptography and uh as we'll talk we'll
see that doing this information
theoretic proofs where you say okay no
Pro can create a give you a false proof
that is limiting okay we can do
everything we want using that uh a this
notion and therefore we're going to go
into a new notion of soundness which is
what we call arguments or computational
soundness and we're going to relax the
prover and say an all Power Pro an all
powerful approver may be able to cheat
but the guarantee we give hey Tony is
that a computationally bounded PR cannot
cheat okay that's going to be the
guarantee we get and we'll see once we
relax the soundness requirement to a
requirement that's only computational
sound then we'll be able to get a lot
more and kind of uh you know the life
will kind of open for us and we're going
to have a lot a lot of new uh kind of
constructions and things that we were
unable to do information
theoretically so this is uh the plan for
today questions before we start I
haven't seen you guys in a
while so it's good to see you a lot of
things changed since the last time I've
seen you I'm probably going to be a bit
distracted today so I'm sorry
okay okay let's start so what are no
questions okay so let's start with pcps
what are probity checkable proofs
so these are the idea of probability
checkable proofs is to take a proof like
a classical proof think of NP in NP we
have a instance X and A Witness this
witness is like a proof for X being in
the
language to verify this proof you need
to read the entire thing and do some
computation like this verification
circuit you know a that checks that X
and W is in the relation there's a
circuit that checks this
okay what is the idea of a probability
checkable proof the idea here what we
want is to take this proof and convert
it into a new proof it may be larger
actually than the original proof so
maybe you know the original proof was of
size M let's say the instance of size n
this may be of size much bigger still we
want it to be polinomial in n&
M but now so we just made it bigger so
what's what's good about it so what's
nice about this proof is the IDE is you
don't actually have to read all of it to
check it and that's weird so the idea
here yeah the proof may be a little
longer polom longer but you only need to
read a few
locations to and to check that it's
valid so to verify often pcps are
denoted by pi uh to verify PCP proof
given X all the verifier needs to do is
query doesn't actually need to read
these things he queries a few locations
a few bits checks a few bits of the
proof and then applies a verification
circuit that depends only on these
bits okay and importantly the bits he
chooses are random the the prover
doesn't know otherwise he will it's like
shrinking if he knew the prover knew oh
the refer is going to only check in bit
17 22 and 25 then he would just give you
it's like you'll have a succinct witness
and of course we can't take arbitrary
Witnesses and just make them 16 if you
don't believe that's possible yeah so
it's a PTP then only used for as m is
much greater than M okay so the question
was is a PCP used if m is much greater
than n and the answer is no actually we
can think of it we can even use it where
M the length of w is n to the Epsilon
okay even less than n to the EPS even n
to the little o of n now you this will
still be polinomial in N so actually you
you took the proof and make it actually
more than polom larger because it's
polinomial an n and M and if the proof
here is smaller is n to the little of
one then this is polyn it's actually
more than polinomial bigger but so
you're saying what did we gain we took
us a short proof made it so much bigger
what did we gain and what we gained is
the Hope is that you can query this the
verif can query this in very very few
locations read only very very few bits
of this proof okay okay verifier also
have to Rex that yeah the verifier all
of so yes good so the question that's a
good question so the question was does
the verifier have to read all of X and
because I said he only needs to read a
few location the proof does he need to
read all of X and a prior of course he
needs to read all of X because even if
there's one bit in X that he doesn't
read you know what if that bit is it's
actually what the state what the
sentence is what the statement is you
know the Prov need to know what am I
reading what am I what are you proving
to me but there are extensions called
called PCP of proximity which I'm not
going to get into in this class where
actually the verify the verifier also
doesn't read all of X but the guarantee
is not that X is in the language it's
the guarantee is that kind of it's a the
Oracle that is given to the verifier
there is something close to it that's in
the linguage so it there is a notion of
extension of this notion of the PCP
where the verifier doesn't even need to
read all of X the guarantees there are
not very easy to state but it's a very
useful notion actually it's used a lot
it's called prob uh pcps of
proximity okay
so okay so that's what we're going to do
today okay and let me just mention
before even we start the formal thing
let me just say this is really an
amazing line of work today we know how
to take any witness convert it to a
probity checkable one that the verifier
only reads three bits three three bits
of this
uh proof and is convinced with cut and
probability 78 is the the parameter but
and then if you want more of course you
repeat but even with just three bits you
get uh some soundness that's really
amazing so we're not going to see the
three bit proof but we're going to see a
poly Logan proof so what we're going to
show what what the construction we're
going to see today is how to go from a
witness to a probability checkable one
that the verifier only needs to read
polylog
n of this of these uh bits and verify
and to go to the constant there's an
additional tricks of recursion and so on
that one needs to do to get there but
we're not going to cover that
part okay ready to roll
sleeves okay
let's okay so let me just Define the
complexity class people often think of
it as a complexity class even though for
us because this is more of a proof
system cryptography I know class we
always want efficiency we want we don't
care just about complexity we want to
say that actually you can take any
witness and efficiently convert it it's
not just about existence we want to
actually use these things and let me
just jump ahead and say that these
things are used it's not just a
theoretical uh you know even though
everything we've seen so far in the
class is like very just beautiful
mathematically it seems a very um a you
know uh a
kind of low like a very uh away from
very far from practice you know and but
actually it's not all these things that
I've shown you so far that you've seen
so far are things that actually are used
and uh so and and the PCP as well uh all
this Machinery are things that too so we
actually do care about efficiency but
let me first kind of Define it as a
complexity class so we defined the
complex the complexity class PCP C for
for completeness parameter s for
soundness parameter R for Randomness
parameter and Q for query parameter so
this is a class this is the
class of all
languages
L A that
have a probabilistically able proof but
I'll explain exactly what I mean uh okay
so actually let me say a okay these are
all the let me write it
formally for which these are all the
languages L such that there
exists uh PPT a probabilistic polinomial
Time
verifier
a actually it's a a PPT Oracle machine
because it takes the PCP is an oracle
Oracle
machine v such
that okay so the
completeness here's the condition the
completeness says that for every X in
the language there exists a PCP Pi such
that the probability that V the verifier
given Oracle access to this PCP pi and
input the instance so for every instance
there exists a PCP so that the verifier
will accept it will output one with
probability at least C that's the
completeness parameter for us the PCP
will see we'll have complet this
parameter one okay so we'll see so we
want to say that a class that a language
L has such a PCP if there's a verifier V
efficient verifier it takes Oracle axis
so if x is in the language there exists
in PCP so I to verify with Oracle axis
of this PCP given this input outputs one
with probity C yes maybe I'm jumping a
bit but what does the Oracle look like
like what are the inputs okay good good
good so this okay oh good no you're not
jumping so good good question so this Pi
you should think of it as a
string it has bits B1 maybe I call it Pi
1 Pi 2 up to Pi I don't know
n and uh the verifier can ask give me
like Pi 1 give me pi 2 give me pi 3 so
he just has Oracle queries he can query
this string okay that's what Oracle it's
not really don't think of it as a
function he has Oracle access to the
string and he can just ask for specific
bits from the string great question
thank
you okay uh good and the sound is
guarantee says that that for every X
that's not in the
language any any guesses by the way what
would you okay so you need to define a
PCP here how would you define
sonus yeah for
all
wonderful exactly you want to say that
for every Pi star this know how we do
note bad things Prime will do too uh for
every bad now there's a cheating Pro he
tries to fool the verifier he cannot so
for no matter what he tries to give him
the verifier will reject him with
probability or a will accept probability
smaller than
S that's the soundness guarantee okay
and ideally we want to push the
completeness to one the soundness to
zero great and then the a the
complexity uh is now we want to say in
terms of complexity now we'll go to
the the V
uses our bits of
Randomness and Q Oracle
calls and moreover we'll see this is
important for us this is often in the
definition though not always but often
this is part of the Q
nonadaptive what do I mean by
nonadaptive what I mean is the way V
Works he gets input X he gets input X he
then chooses kind of
i1 up to
IQ locations in the PCP okay so here's
the v v he doesn't even look at the
Oracle yet he has an input X
he first computes Q
locations he then goes to the Oracle
asks these Q locations and then so V1
just just these locations and then V2 so
you can think of v as being like V1 and
V2 V1 doesn't look at his Oracle he just
looks as an
input and using Randomness chooses Q
locations and then
V2 kind of uh just given
X i1 up to IQ and Pi i1 up to Pi
IQ decides if to like uh accept or
reject okay so this is the how you
should think of the of the verifier the
verifier has access to the proof Pi but
what he does he does he because a more
General verifier will have X decide on
location first location 3 i1 look at Pi
1 then hm interesting okay in that case
I want to see location I2 h i get Pi I2
interesting given Pi I2 I want to see
location that would be an Adaptive
verifier okay but often in the PCP
literature when we Define PCP we require
the verifier to be
non-adaptive and this non- adaptivity is
kind of uh is it's a property that we
like for applications and we'll see that
today uh why an example for why when
we'll construct succinct arguments we'll
use the fact that it's non adaptive but
let me just say most PCP all pcps I know
are nonadaptive maybe there other was
that your question yeah so I don't I
there may exist I'm not you know I'm not
uh I didn't do a full literature search
but the pcps that are you know the most
common ones that we talk about are all
non-adaptive yeah did V get to know what
capital N is yeah yeah yeah yeah so V
yes V knows yeah so V good very good
question let me repeat for the uh video
uh so the question was does v know what
n what capital N is so the answer is yes
and the V knows uh V knows the language
so he knows what small n is well he got
small n he knows small n the language
has like is there's M so he V get small
n so he knows what an N is the language
is associated with the witness size M of
n so he knows that because he knows n so
he knows the witness size and the PCP
itself is associated with n which
is you know you can think of it this way
so so the answer is yes these are kind
of fixed these uh M and N are fixed
parameters that are defined by the PCP
and the prover knows them the verifier
the pro they yeah yes we gain
orose yes good good good so the question
is do we lose something and the answer
is we do uh okay so what do we lose and
what do we gain is your question what we
lose is for application so we you when
we'll go to in the second part of
today's class we're going to construct
succinct arguments and we're going to
construct them from pcps and you'll see
that if our PCP is adaptive this becomes
the problem so we do gain now you're
saying what do we Lo and so we do lose
sorry we do lose if we make it adapted
now you're saying but maybe we gain
something maybe we construct pcps that
are much better if you make them
adaptive and I I don't think so but I'm
not sure maybe maybe one can actually
argue that you don't gain anything but I
haven't thought about it um but it's not
something that making it nonadaptive
that for all we know is not a price it's
just our pcps happen to be that way
yeah good good good very very good
question so uh I think I I think maybe I
misunderstood but maybe your question
was is it clear that these have to
depend on X can they even not depend on
X and the answer is yes actually in the
pcps will see they don't depend on x
okay the pcps we know actually these
they only depend on you know n and the
instance size or or again it's but they
don't actually depend on the instance
and the PCP I'll construct today you'll
see that so we'll get back to that that
really really great questions
yeah does that
think knows what indes you're going
Advance you could construct a of course
of course great wow guys you're really
Lifting me up this is great thank you uh
yeah 100% so you're what you're saying
is of course if the ver if the prover
knew the locations you're quering he
will cheat the thing is these locations
are random the prover doesn't know what
they are they just don't depend on X
okay okay but they they come from a
distribution it's very important if
these were deterministic there's no way
if you can do a PCP where these are
deterministic it's like you took NP and
you just made it end time much smaller
like we don't believe that that can
happen in so no it the there's no way we
believe you can construct pcps for which
the qu the query distribution is
deterministic it's like just fixed this
has to come from a distribution but the
question is does this distribution
depend on X or does it only depend on
the parameter n and then and what we'll
see it actually only depends on N it
doesn't depend on X so that's what we'll
see a in a
minute great question guys any any more
questions before we
yeah so okay good so actually V1 you can
think of usually V1 is randomized and V2
is
deterministic uh so you can think of it
that way that V1 is randomized V2 is
deterministic okay
uh great so now let me tell you what we
know and what we're going to construct
so here's what we're going to prove
today um here is a theorem that we're
going to
prove that
PCP with a let's say completeness one
I'll put S as half we can get smaller
any con and smaller but I'll just put
half because by repetition uh it doesn't
really matter you can get a PCP where
the query
complexity is so okay we can get a PCP
with poly log n query complexity and
poly a
login H sorry poly log and Randomness
complexity and query complexity for all
of
NP that's what we're going to see today
so we're going to see how for any NP
language we can construct a PCP where
the verifier the amount of Randomness he
uses is polog and bits of Randomness and
polog and queries and then we get
completeness one and sound as half
yeaha
usually right right right yeah yeah yeah
so you're right so often uh okay you're
right the way I wrote it here uh so okay
why do people care about Randomness
complexity one can say who cares about
the random complexity and usually the
way the way I Define PCP and this is
that's why I said it's a complexity
Theory this is how it's
defined if if the verifier has only log
and bits or order lend bits of of
Randomness then it means that the PCP is
only polyn size because look go over all
the PO and all the log and bit random
there's only n of them so that's as much
as you can uh kind of query so uh so
that means the PCV is aized and that's
all we care about okay for me I'm going
to care about so actually for me I'm
going to add a a requirement actually I
didn't write it here because it's
usually not defined but I can add a
requirement that says this a I'll okay
I'll add it here in tiny this is a a
requirement that we add in in
cryptography often what I'm writing now
is not added in the in in the
definitions but let me write another
cryptography another that given for
every
X in or X for for every X in l and
witness if it has a
witness W okay so suppose this is a
language in N time I don't know NP or n
time T so it has some witness I want it
to be the case that given X and W you
can
efficiently compute Pi so not only there
exists Pi of of poly and size you can
actually efficiently compute it and
because I require efficient Computing I
actually don't care anymore so much
about the randomness the amount the
number of Randomness uh bits but yeah
that's a very good point Thank you guys
thank you for the question this is
great H okay so that's what I'm going to
prove even though let me just mention
what is known is you can make this order
login and you can make this
three okay so it's really remarkable if
you think about it wow you can take any
proof so you know how I don't know take
a foras last the take the hardest proof
that we know in mathematics you know one
can write them in a pro propos checkable
way they you can just take three bits
and verify and if you're not happy with
probability half repeat it as many times
as you want you want prob you want to be
sure that he can cheat with probability
only one over two to the 500 repeat it
500 times and each one it's like a very
simple check it depends on three bits so
it's really
remarkable no never
mindo I guess it doesn't matter
to all oh you're saying it's too big
because for theory for practice Yeah but
we're still in theory land yeah in
practice these pcps you want them to be
like linear that's the ideal the Quasi
linear even if they're quadratic people
don't like them you really want linear
quasi linear pcps for for practice but
for here PA is fantastic we're you know
we're not we're not the let us stand the
cloud a little bit okay so uh so okay so
let's uh let's construct
this ready okay so okay so we have the
three but we're going to construct for
the polog polog and what actually here's
what you what's amazing you actually
already know how to construct the PCP
you just don't know that you know and
how do you construct the PCP it's really
only the GK protocol that's it so you
can unfold gkr and I'm going to show you
exactly how to make it a
PCP okay so to do that but before and
I'll recall the GK in a second on that
board but to do that let's first let's
first so I want to say any any language
has a PCP let's con let's
focus on on three set
okay so thre set is an NP complete
language let's just construct a PTP for
three set and what's nice about three
set is that I mean any NP language you
can convert to three set so it's nice
any NP language is that you have a
circuit a verification
circuit so a circuit verifying so you
can think of it uh given W verifying
that it's a valid witness of very small
depth okay poly and depth and this is
important because if you remember the GK
protocol which we're going to use to
construct this
PCP kind of the number the communication
complexity grows with the depth so we
want the depth of the circuit to be
small but any NP language you can
convert into a three set and thre set
has actually it's like the depth of
three set is like actually only two but
like you need to do you know uh little
ores and then one big end but if
remember gkr we wanted fan in two
so once you have F in two it's like
order log okay so this is depth you can
think of it as being uh a like log in or
I'm okay with poogan it doesn't
matter the point is it's
small and uh the reason why I write also
polog is because uh it's actually log
however uh this circuit is also any kind
of the circuit is and this I'm not going
to get into but it's log space uniform
and now you can consider the circuit
change it a little bit the way Rachel
taught you two weeks ago if you don't
remember it's not it's okay you can take
it as a black box uh you can assume that
The Circuit by kind of looking at a
universal version of it you can assume
that it has like the gates add I and
multi are efficiently
computable and that's what we'll need so
we can so if if you don't remember uh
things from weeks ago it's okay I'll
remind you what add I in multi in a
second but you take any three set you
can convert it uh or convert to 3 CNF so
now given a witness you just check that
it verifies hi hello hey wow all my kids
come coming
in okay so uh
a you just uh we talking about how to
construct pcps from gkr right
now so what we're proving is that we're
going to show how you can take any NP
language in particular we're focusing on
three sat and we're going to show how
you can convert three sat into a PCP
where the query complexity is poly Logan
so converting to PCP the verifier needs
to query only poly Logan uh locations we
know you can do go all the way down to
three but we're not uh today we're going
to so polog this is the randomness
complexity this is the query complexity
we're focusing on completeness one sound
is half okay so we're going to now
construct the PCP and uh before we conr
the P the PCP essentially uses gkr so
let me first on this board remind you
quickly what gkr looks like because
we're going to use it to constuct the
PCP okay you're cameraman it's okay to
move okay okay
um good so let's let's just recall the
gkr how does it work we have a
circuit there's an input W we're going
to think of w here as the the satisfying
assignment okay remember in the DK we
assume the verifier has W in his hand
the W the input in his hand here he
doesn't W is going to be the witness for
the satisfying assignment but that's
okay now here's what so I'm I'm GNA
construct the PCP proof okay I have my
witness my satisfying
assignment I'm going to construct a
protic I'm going to convert W into a PCP
into a protic checkable proof okay
here's how I do it I look at the kind
the circuit that checks that uh W
actually you can if you want to think of
it's completely new form you can think
of having X and W so X and W and it
checks that uh kind of fe uh sorry that
or okay X which is Fe and it checks that
F of w is one okay this is a log space
uniform uh circuit and uh okay now what
do I do so here's me I know W every we
both know the three set
formula what I
do I and and we assume that this circuit
is kind of has addition Gates and
multiplication
Gates what I do for every
layer I compute the values of the layer
okay so I compute for every layer
remember I have VI the I assume every
layer let's say has size let's say the
same size without L of generality we
said size s we called it s so each layer
has s
[Music]
wires and uh and we ass and we write we
compute all these wires for every layer
I we think of this wire as go as going
from H to M to 01 so H is some set and
we assume that H to the m is s okay so
we just encode these s wires in a kind
of cube uh uh M dimensional cube of size
H and we just write all the values of
the
wires okay and then what we do we look
at the extension V Tilda which is
extends to a field F to the m to F and
this is kind of the low degree extension
so we take any F that can contains the
set H and we extend VI via the low
degree extension so these are things we
covered okay now now is the first time
you remember when I when we taught gkr I
told you okay why I do why not do 0o one
to the m you know 0o to the log in it's
much natural to think of binary
representation of s as opposed to this H
to the m which is what H and I told you
how often we like parameters we like to
think of H as
login ah sorry log n and M is log n over
log log
n uh and if you'll see H to the m is
just becomes n because uh you can think
of a so H to the
[Music]
m is log n to the N but log n is just
like two log log
n to the n and the log log n cancels out
so you have two to the
again so you have uh oh I did everything
everything is s sorry
s the N here is s s s
s so you have S now remember I told I
told you oh we'll need the set of
parameters as opposed to say 01 it's
natural to think of H as 01 and M is log
n that's much more natural uh we used as
computer science to think in binary now
we're thinking of like log ass it's like
really how how annoying can you be and
the reason is it's for this now now we
need it why now we take F that is going
to
be it's going to be extension of size
poly
logus okay we'll see the poly will need
to be big enough we'll talk about in a
second but the field we don't we don't
want more than poly log s and the reason
is we want
F to the m to be
polys okay so we know we know that H to
the m is s if if uh f is only poly
bigger then we have this is poly
s okay and that's important for us okay
note if H was just 01 so the size of H
was two
we couldn't keep F poly and to we
couldn't keep F constant you'll see F
will need to grow with m m f so for
soundness m f will need to be
bigger than M *
H actually there's also D that will come
in it's significantly bigger so if we
take H to be two we'll need to take F to
be at least log n and then we'll have F
to them is log to the power of log n
that's more that's super
poly and I want after them to be
poly okay so we do this so now I so what
is the PCP the
PCP so actually I'll write there the PCP
but uh now let's let's just finish
recalling the GK so what does the
verifier do in the GK the pro do in the
GK he computes all these low degree
extensions and then the GK consists of D
phases going from the output layer to
the input layer layer where in each
phase we run two Su check protocols in
parallel where the verifier uses the
same Randomness and what what the
subject protocol does is it it reduces
from checking two values here to
reducing checking two values in the
layer below and we kind of go kind of
from checking uh until we get to the
input and then input the verifier can
check on his own that's the
idea
okay okay now let's just Rec in a
subject protocol here each subject
protocol if you uh remember maybe you
don't it's not the details are not so
important right now but it's kind of you
go from VI inex tension which is let's
say VI Tilda of some
Z and you write it as this is kind of
sum
of uh points in the in h to the m
because that's the definition of
extension times some k p uh Z this is
the function that checks equality again
it's not important but what's important
to me to show is that and then you do
sum over P W1 W2 in h of
M and you convert VI to either kind of
uh a if if if this is a plus gate you
convert it to uh like um the plus of the
of the wires below with multiplication
you check the multiplication so in other
words what this
is what this is or I should say what
this is let me just open this what is VI
P it's if it's an
ad if it's an
ad P W1 W2 so if Point p is this just
the addition of the two wires below then
you replace p with W1 with v
ius1
W1 plus VI -1
W2 and plus if it was not an adgate if
it's a
mgate then you replace it with the
multiplication of vi- 1 W1 Time vi- 1 W2
so just uh right the idea was and all
this is times
uh this
Kai k
p z but again how do we go from layer I
toay to one layer below we take that
element in the extension we think of it
as a sum that's the definition of lree
extension it's sum of the elements in
the circuit itself with some with some
function uh with some weight and now
look at the at the value what what is
the value of this gate well if it's an
and if it's an add gate it's the sum of
the two children and if it's a mgate it
should be the multiplication of the two
children and so add I just outputs one
of these if you know W1 W2 are the
children of P zero otherwise similarly
malt and but we do everything in the
extension uh we look at everything in
the extension because we want to think
of it as a polinomial and once we think
once we these are all pols then this is
just a sum
check okay and we saw a sum check how to
do it efficiently so now the point is G
consists of only these two D Su checks
so now let me go to my
PCP a is this so here's uh our PCP
essentially my PCP is just gkr but
opened up completely completely
unraveled so okay so here's my PCP I
have my X in W here's what I do I'm
going to
compute all the V1 V VI Tilda the
extension of the values of each of all
the gate in each wire for every
Z for every Z and F to the
m it's
important this is going to be all this
is going to be part of the PCP so if F
to m is more than polinomial my PCP is
super
polinomial okay so after to them has to
be polinomial this is a ready sized
polinomial
yeah again sorry we have
the oh yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
okay good good good yes so for gkr we
had a restriction that the
circuit to do gkr we said gkr is like is
proving that uh bounded depth circuit
and put x equals y and we had a
restriction that the circuit has to be B
bounded uh space uniform or in other
words we needed to ensure that add I and
mul this ex extended Andi and extended
multi are computed computer
efficiently threat has that property
okay I again I did go into the details
but uh the threet is it's a very unifor
you know given a FNX it's very uniform
to check it's a very it is a loog space
uniform and then we can convert it as
Rachel uh did two weeks ago uh to kind
of one that has uh by increasing the the
depth by poly factors uh so keeping it
poly log you can make at I at till and
multi be efficiently computable so yeah
great that's a very good question uh so
yes good so this is going to be part of
the uh PCP but that's not all uh by the
way we should also give uh this we give
this for every I from the input layer
zero one up to D this is
output and this is the input layer
we have to give him the input layer
because the poor verifi verifier doesn't
have W so he doesn't have actually the
input before he and do you care he had
the input here he doesn't have the input
but we're going to give him the Lo
extension of this W okay good now but
okay so I'm the verifier what do I do I
need to verify the sum checks who do I
interact with Su checks I'll put all the
possible answers in the Oracle so now we
do two DM checks okay so okay so for
every pass possible for okay for every
ey and for every
[Applause]
Z in the GTR protocol we may need to do
a sum check because in the sum Che
protocol what is in the GK what does it
how does it look like the ver the
verifier first decides okay prove the
output layer is correct let's say the
output the Z is fixed fine then he
chooses Randomness Randomness Randomness
in a some check it reduces is the
checking Z D minus one in a random
Z the the Z is determined by the random
coins of the
verifier so which Z do I put and I want
to show something for every possible Z
so for every possible I for every
possible Z I'm going to put in the PCP a
sum check a sum check so I'm going to
give a a su check I'm going to add kind
of all the possible
transcript for some check corresponding
to
VI which VI
Z or maybe to v i equals VI till the Z
so for every I and Z I'm going to give a
some
check with respect
to Randomness R from the from the
verifier so for every I for every Z and
for any Randomness R of the verifier now
what is how much Randomness that the
verifier use in a sum check protocol so
remember the sum check is sum over H to
the 3M kind of variables okay sum over p
p W1 W2 all of them in h to the m so the
r is going to be for every R in F to the
3M because in the subject protocol what
you do is every single H you every
single kind of uh you have three M
variables every one you give a random
field element to kind of reduce get rid
of one of the sums so the verifier will
use will choose kind of R1 up to
r3m so 3M field
elements so for every Poss for for every
hour I'm going to actually give you the
transcript so now I know I'm going to
give you the entire
transcript okay but here's the thing I
so I'm gonna have a su check for for all
of them and now the verifier okay but we
need to be careful we don't just give
for every R subject if I knew R I would
cheat so what I what what I mean here is
for every Su check for every Z
VI for every our so so uh for every
R1 I'm going to give all the outputs for
R1 like all the kind of answers of the
Su check for R1 then for each one of
them for every R2 I have all the
possible answers so no competition you
can't have two different element you
can't have one value if you had R1 R2
but later different RS or R1 R2 it for
every for every possible partial
transcript you give a value that's what
the PCP has in it okay so for every so
yeah I should say yeah so for every eye
for every Z and for every maybe I should
write it
as R1 up to
r3m I have a
transcript all the part I I should have
all all
partial
transcripts of sum
check with with respect to VI IAL v
z and
Randomness no R1 up to RJ for every
J okay between uh I don't know
one and 3
m okay so for every for every for every
I for every R1 I will say what would be
my answer so now I have F to the m
answers for every one of these answers
for every R2 I'm going to tell you what
is the answer for
every sorry I I said I said it wrong for
every R1 I would give all the answer I
have F each one each one is one field so
for every R1 I'll tell you the answer
that's F options because there are F
options for R1 and then out of these f
for each of these FS for every R2 I'm
going to give you what the prover will
send that F that's f squ and then for
each of these I'm going to give you R3
so really what this PCP for every VI for
every such VI or for every kind of v i
z for every possible R1 I'm going to
give you this is over R1 I'm going to
give you the possible answers in the sum
check protocol like if the pro in the Su
if the verer in the sum check protocol
the first Randomness was this R1 this R1
this R1 I'm going to write all of these
in the PCP and then for each R1 and
every possible R2 I'm going to write my
answers and then for each R1 R2 for
every possible R3 I'm going to write my
answers it seems like an exponential
tree and it is an exponential tree but
that the depth is so small so this is a
huge tree but this tree is only of size
F to the m or to the 3M
sorry which is polinomial it's it's uh s
to the 3 and you're right that you know
this is not good enough for practice but
uh
then there's a lot of optimizations on
the gkr that make it quasi linear and
today even linear so you can actually
optimize this to get uh you know uh
linear time but uh but or uh but or
quasi linear as a PCP but but for now we
don't care about these a polinomial is
good enough for
us okay so for every I and for every Z
we give this
tree that's the
PTP that's it
okay so again
yeah good good good good good fantastic
you're like wait that's a problem do we
if I require F to be small do we even
get soundness that's a great question so
the answer is barely but yes so let's
see what's the okay what is the
soundness that we get for to be sound
each Su check so the the okay so let's
talk about
soundness maybe I'll put it
here let's talk about soundness here for
a second because you rais a very but you
know what actually before we talk about
soundness I I'll jump to soundness you
have a very good point I'll we'll talk
about soundness but just to make sure
the construction is clear okay so let me
just reiterate one last time I'm a PCP
prover I want to convince you guys that
I have a satisfying assignment to a
threat formula I have my w what I do I
construct low deegree extension of my w
my witness but also I have this entire
circuit that verifies this witness and
I'm going to construct a low degree
extension of each and every layer in
this circuit now the way I wrote it
actually I will construct a low degree
extension of X and W that's kind of if I
think of the input as X and W I need the
constru L degree extension of both but
you the verifying Knows X so if I
construct a low degree extension of w he
himself can construct a low extension of
X and W together so in the PCP because I
don't want to in the PCP I don't want to
put X in there the verifier has X and if
I have the freedom to put X in there and
you don't read it then I can put the
wrong X so I'm just going to put
v0 is just going to
be of the witness I'm going to think of
X as fixed so I'm just going to
construct the loading extension of W and
then I'm going to construct the low
degree extension of each and every layer
of the of the
circuit and I'm going to go for every
layer and for every Z I'm going to
construct all the
possible Pro messages in the Su protocol
now because the randomness the options
for the for the uh the number of
possible random bits for the from the
verifier is only F to the 3M because
there's 3M
uh
a variables and F is the field so it's
only F to the
3M then this tree is only going to be of
size after the 3M so it's not too
bad and I put all of them I put all the
possible Su checks in there so sorry
it's F to the 3M for every I have this
size for every I and for every Z okay so
for every I I is only D this is small
and Z is another F to them I pay fine so
after to the
4M okay so for every Z and for every I I
have the sum
check now what the what is so that's
that's the PCP but now what's what does
the verifier do what does v I need to
Define I told you how to construct this
Pi efficiently and it's uh but what does
v do so what does what V
does he says I'm going to pretend that
I'm I'm interacting with the gkr prover
so he says look what is out he's going
to read the output
VD and he's going to expect a one if he
sees a zero so that's one query I'm
going to read the output is it's one
good I'm happy okay now he's going to go
from verifying D to verifying D minus
one D minus 2 D minus 3 now he he wants
to talk to aover he said okay here's my
Randomness my first message in the sum
check give me back something okay he
this is the approver the Prov is fixed
in the PCP okay so he gets back an
answer good now here these at the end
this defines V IUS one Z this this
should be all kind of uh elements in V
minus one Z now actually here what you
have here is at the end of the gkr
protocol you're left with two two two V
two v's right so if you verify here
you'll have like at the end you'll have
like V I don't know zero and v z z0 and
Z1 you know you'll verify you need to
verify two points because we did two
something called ways so fine he sees
these two he checks there's these he
checks that they're equal this is only
one okay so we're giving him all the low
degree extension of VI minus one he
checks oh yeah this is corresponds this
corresponds this is just to ensure that
he doesn't put different ones in
different you know here he may uh you
know and in this Branch he may put the
value of z0 to be something and in this
Branch you may put the value of z0 to be
something else that's
that's not not good for us so we just
check because he put aside all the low
degree extensions so we check that it's
equal to what he gave us and we continue
with
that okay
um one second actually I'm not sure
maybe what I said is incorrect I'm not
actually sure that this is a problem
even if he gives us different let me
think about it for a
second
a yeah actually I'm not even sure that
we need we can just put the Su checks
even if he gives us even if he gives
us a
no okay yeah I want to say even if he
gives us in this branch and this Branch
different things uh why do we care it's
like we run the sum check the sum check
is sound but we we do care a little bit
because then in the next
round
which let me think you know what I'm not
actually
what lay
theand exactly you you let all the verif
so yeah so I don't think actually you
need to give these specific you can just
give give for every VI Tilda you give
but it's the same because you give for
every VI Tilda so actually I think these
two are the same so I okay what I I
guess what I said is uh you know these
can be maybe V uh VI minus one of z0
appears here and it appears here and
they're
different are we worried we're not
really worried because it's like you
think of it it interacts with the prover
the prover the cheating prover may give
him different Z here and different Z
here but later the point is later you'll
have in VI minus one you'll just
continue so actually you just need to
give but but but really I think the two
are equivalent so it doesn't really
matter a okay so this is the pp and
that's how you verify and at the end at
the end of the end of the gkr the
verifier needs to read the input he
needs to check the input and some load
in some locations he doesn't have the
input but he does because we gave him
the low degree extension of w so once he
has the low degree extension of w he can
compute anything uh he so the verifier
needs to
compute a low degree extension of X in W
but any point in the low degree
extension of X and W is a point in the
low degree EXT is a sum of points in the
low degree extension of X and point in
the Lo extension of w so every every
point in the low degree extension of X
and W you can write as a weighted sum of
a point in the lowre low degree
extension of X and a point in the Lo
extension of w so you know once he needs
to read the point in the Lo extension of
w he has it here so that's all that's
all the verifier does so he really he's
it's interesting this PCP he as if he's
talking to the prover but the prover is
sitting in the sky in the
PCP the pro strategy just kind of opened
up in in the
Oracle okay okay great so now any
questions before we talk about
soundness
yeah so right so uh okay good good good
good good question the verify great
question the verifier needs to check
also that all these things are actually
low deegree extension okay so what if I
I I said here oh put um you put VI Tilda
Z how do I know that you actually put a
low degree extension maybe you put a
very high degree polinomial there maybe
you just put an arbitrary truth table of
size after
them that would be
problematic so you're totally right the
verifier so let let me write what the
verifier does uh maybe before the sound
is yeah
so let me actually write it okay so the
verifier
okay he
runs first thing he does he runs V of
gkr with its
Oracle okay so he runs the just the gkr
but he thinks of kind of the Oracle part
as kind of the the prover he's talking
with and the other thing he needs needs
to do is he needs to
check that for every
I VI
Tilda is of low degree is
doesn't
um yeah what you're saying is that if
you're right so what you're saying is a
okay what you're saying is if he comp If
he if he gave VI Tilda that was high
degree then you're saying that GK would
fail you you would be rejected by the GK
should
bewi it should be rejected by the GK a
I think you may be right but actually
I'm not 100% sure now
uh yeah that
ISE yeah so here's here's the concern
here's the concern the concern is we
want to make sure that the
verifier is uh
behaving like that we want to okay we
want to make sure that this VI Tilda
is of low
degree
why sorry one second
um yeah actually I I
I don't think we need to check that via
is a low degree because I I agree that
we need to check that VI is a low degree
but I think gkr checks that the vi till
there's a low degree so I actually don't
want to recheck it so all I want to do
here I think GK test tests it for you so
we're convinced that the gkr is sound
let's not recall why it sound but let's
remember we we learned that it sound so
GK is good now what are we doing I
essentially what we're saying is
verifier I'm giving you all the possible
answers of I'm what is the prover the
prover is a tree you can think what is a
cheating prover a cheating prover for
every possible you know for every
possible question he gives you an answer
for every question he gives you an
answer that's what it does so now you're
saying look I'm going to give you the
tree now in general this tree is really
really big and even in gkr if you give
the entire if you just open like GK has
D rounds D rounds of su Che if you just
open the S Che it will be terrible
however
a gkr has this property that it's kind
of memory lless what do I mean by memory
list you can compute the first Su check
then you don't care what happened before
all you care is what is VI minus one
that you cut and you check
those so now I'm saying so you know
actually for let's think about this
first of all we can say open gkr to a
huge tree okay any pro this is true in
in general if you had any interactive
proof you can think of a pro write all
the possible answers like think of its
kind of H strategy as a huge huge tree
right the tree now of course you get
sound this you interact with the
approver what's the difference okay you
can do that with G but of course if you
do this huge tree it's going to be
gigantic because GK consists of d kind
of um
a uh subprotocols each one is a su check
so now if you think of like a D Cab then
you'll be too big but I'm saying we
don't need to because gkr has a property
that actually it consist of this
subprotocol and then all you need to
remember you don't need to remember
which branch you're on here all you need
to remember is what are the values here
that's all you need to
remember so there's no point in
repeating it's like you're repeating the
tree for no reason so all you need
there's a way to open kind of this Pro
in a more efficient
way so by not giving the entire tree and
giving kind of a more efficient kind of
opening where all the vi Z all the vi
IUS one Z I'm going to say okay forget
about it let's just go from VI minus one
Z and continue why do you need to repeat
this kind of tree a 100 times it's it's
but it's you can go go from here to kind
of simulating an entire GK
approver yeah if I understand correctly
you're saying like actually the tree of
gkr is such that most of the parts cof
right and so you don't need to repeat
the copies you can just look it up
exactly exactly
exactly
exactly actually in some sense we're
restricting the prover here more than
he's restricted in
gkr exactly because in gkr he can be you
know what I'm going to remember the RS
if he's cheating and based on the RS I'm
going to give you a different strategy
whatever here we're not even letting him
do that we're telling look you tell me
what you are here from here now you
forget Ours from VI minus one what's
your strategy and now you forget from
here what is your
strategy so we're really just doing gkr
now you're right at the vi minus one do
till they do need to be of low degree
but do the Gare test this for you so you
don't need to do it on your
own but you're right it's confusing a
little bit because if you if any if
anyone is familiar with the PCP
literature there's always a low deegree
test in it so it's kind of interesting
this this kind of is hidden with within
the Gare
protocol this kind of transformation not
only as as there is efficient way to
change the into a sequence that the know
where
to exactly exactly so yeah this this
proof holds it's not specific to gkr
it's kind of you can take any sixing
protocol and and interactive protocol
and lay it open however let me just
mention we have very few actually kind
of two examples of suing protocols so it
sound like you can take any of your
choice yeah any but we don't have much
choice so uh you know a coming up with
these succinct interactive proofs is a
super interesting question I'll I'll
talk a little bit more about this after
we do the analysis of the
PCB okay so great
uh any questions before we move to
soundness okay so let's talk about
soundness and the question that was
raised which was a great question is
Wait f needs to be big to get soundness
so let's really understand what the size
of f needs to be so to get soundness we
do 2D Su check
protocols each Su check protocol needs
to be pretty sound because it's enough
that you cheat on one of them and we're
dead right
so now each Su Che protocol this is this
is just
recall that
each Su check
protocol has sound
is which is
H over F times M the number of variables
but for us it's 3M because we have 3M
variables okay this is just the the each
subject protocol now for us so you can
cheat but with this
probability now for us we have 2D D is
poly Logan like the depth of the circuit
so for us our sound
is is I'm just doing a union bound so to
cheat there exist needs to be at least
kind of uh one subject protoc for which
you cheated on so you get by Union bound
so we have 2D sum checks and then
therefore the
soundness is 2D * 3 m h divided by
F so now if we want sound this half
let's say which is what we want after
that you can repeat to increase the
soundness all we need is that F so if we
want this to be smaller than
half then we need F to be bigger than uh
12 D
MH but that's good this is log N I don't
know if you guys can see H log s sorry
this is smaller than log
s this is some poly log s okay so just
make it bigger than all of them it's
still
polylog and polylog S is good enough
because then after them is
polys okay so this was sound
is oh oh good why do we need you're
saying why can't it be bigger because
good because we want our PCP to be of so
the question is just to recap why do we
need why do we insist that f is not
bigger why does it have to be poom
related to F and the reason is we want
the PCP to beide polys we want the ver
we want the PCP a to be not we want it
to be efficient we want to efficiently
convert a witness to a PCP and the PCP
grows with f to the m much more it's
like f to the 3M and it needs to be
repeated and F to the m is poly so okay
it's if this is bigger than poly if f is
more than poly H then F to the m will be
more than poly H to the m so that's why
we want we want it to be it's for the
sake of efficiency for the for the PCP
to be small or palomi related to the
Circuit um so here you saying that the
randomness complexity is poly now
normally you'd be like okay the pro size
is just two to the random but You' like
more right you found a way to make than
it would be okay good good good so now
let's go to the we didn't do the
complexity yet but yeah you're a bit a
bit ahead of me but you're you're
totally right so now so so far we talked
about soundness completeness is one
because the G is complete has
completeness one so we the Su check has
completeness one so we're good we talked
about Su checks any question about
soundness any question about the
soundness okay uh let's talk about the
complexity the so uh the randomness
complexity in the communic in the query
complexity so how much query and
Randomness do we need so the randomness
complexity is well there's 2D a so let's
put here
Randomness so there's 2D sum check so
the verifier kind of he interacts with
his Oracle on 2D sum checks so for each
2D sum checks he needs to toss coins now
how much coins does he toss well he
needs to generate our random in F to the
3M that's a su each Su check you need so
it's F to the it's like 3M log F bits of
Randomness now this is really poly log F
it's it's it's uh it's like poly s it's
not log s okay this is really poly not
not poly log s not just logs so one can
be wait we need to be careful because uh
are we sure we're getting an efficient
PCP here it's a lot of Randomness are we
sure there's no blow up in PCP and the
reason there's no blow up the reason we
have large Randomness yet the the PCP is
small is exactly because GK has this
property of forgetting this uh the fact
we actually don't need to open the
entire tree because of that we use kind
of an additional property if the point
is if you know nothing about the
PCP then of course as I said if it's
order log as bits of Randomness it's
always the size PS but the fact that
there more bits of Randomness does not
necessarily Force our PCP to be bigger
we're just not going to open it like
trivially like oh if if we did open it
trivially then we would look at all the
around it would be a huge tree like the
depth but because we do it kind of we
pack it efficiently we're able to get a
small PCP even though we have a lot of
Randomness is it because you're saying
each tree is size poly and po exactly
each tree is size poly and they're poly
trees and we're not like there's a more
kind of straightforward way to do it is
for each tree a pen a p like in no we're
we're kind of doing them in chunks uh
and so we get the the
efficiency okay uh let's go let's go for
the uh query
complexity okay I'll just put it
here so let's see so for again what's
the query he does gkr so he does
2D sum checks for each sum check he
needs to read kind of what's what what
the answer is each answer so there's
three M rounds that he needs to read in
each answer he gets kind of a univariate
polinomial of small degree so he that
each answer is not just one field
element it's actually a few field
elements
um a
so it's so he gets log F
elements times a
um the degree which will be in each Su
check like poly
H and most and this again goes back to
the gold what's exactly the degree of
the a multi it's polinomial so I'm not
it's polinomial in h it's poly log H I
don't want this is kind of the
degree of uh each of the Su check
polinomial
and the degrees affected by the ADI and
multi which we assumed are the degree is
like
poly uh but it's still again polylog so
this gives so okay so before we take a
break H let
me where where where are we now uh so
you know we studied the we started
actually this this class by looking at
some check so I started this class by
telling you look some Che is a miracle
like giving some Che it gives you
everything everything and I hope that
now you see why so we surve some Che and
we looked at some like who cares okay
this it seemed like why would we need to
some over so many very multivariate
polinomial where does that come up I
don't know it was like okay why am I
learning this but you know so now where
what did we do with it we start with
with Su we saw
oh just by doing something
repeatedly you can verify any low depth
computation that's pretty amazing and
then we saw that actually you can
recover the IP equals P space theorem
that GK actually gives his IP equals P
space theorem and now we see gkr
actually gives you
PCP and what is GK is just Su
checks okay so just these Su checks you
kind of unroll them unravel them and you
get a PCP with polog and
queries and not and it's like efficient
you can take your input effic your
witness and efficiently generate this
PCP and in a very
a like a straightforward way in a sense
you do your computation you have your
witness you do the computation you do
all the lree extensions and you convince
round by round you just lay it out
that's it and you have a
PCP okay any any questions about
yeah that relies on just the fact that
it consists of these kind of like
independent subs or also the fact that
some itself that each is just random
good good good so the question is again
let's understand why do we get this PCP
that's efficient okay why do we get only
poly siiz PCP and the reason we get is
to both twofolds you you said both
reasons reason number one that when we
do each sum check after that we can
forget about this Randomness and for
each VI consider so we really need to
write down only kind of D times F to the
m sub checks okay that's D the depth of
the circuit time F to the M Subs that's
number one but number two why is the sum
check can we write out all the sum check
I mean the sum check is also an
interactive protocol can we actually
open it up and write the entire thing
and the answer is well yeah but at a
exponential cost and but an exponential
cost in M the number of variables but
here the number of variables is
log that's important we if M was polog
we would have been
doomed but M or I mean okay uh it's not
just log it's it's we set the parameter
so that it's okay that's what we needed
that's exactly so why can we open up
this entire sum check it's because we
set F to be poly H and H to the m is s
so we we set it up so that you know
opening the sum check
requires F to the m kind of answers uh F
to the m answers each one is kind of a
low degree polinomial but that's that's
fine but F to the m of them or F to the
3M here because we have the number of
variables is 3M
uh and we just need to make sure that
after the 3M is polinomial and to ensure
that we did do some parameter
engineering that's why we didn't go the
natural route of taking H to be two and
M to be log s that would be natural but
then we would not get so we actually did
need to do some kind of Engineering in
parameters uh like an annoying fiddling
of parameters uh you know this uh this
setting of parameters that you see over
and over in any PCP construction this is
you know we're not the first so we're
actually the last if anything to come to
use this this was used in the '90s in
the early PCP constructions and um and
it's when you look at it first like oh
really like log n over log log n are you
kidding me like couldn't you find
something nicer but this is this is why
because we want these parameters to be
poly yeah so since you're essentially
asking for this for this to be like a
nonadaptive can you just like use the
same for and get
the so sorry so you're saying sorry your
question is you're saying you are you
talking about the non the fact that this
verifier is nonadaptive or or that
theover is nonadaptive right the prover
in the yes M like it's not adaptive in
the previous in the previous uh Su
checks previous Su checks yeah so then
what can you use the same Randomness for
each round like what would happen if you
theand no okay okay okay that's a good
question so you're asking you're saying
look we're doing the sum check D times
can't we use the same Randomness and the
answer is we cannot why because you
should think if you use the same
Randomness for different rounds then you
should think of I'm aover I'm like oh I
I'm you're going to use the same
Randomness for all your rounds I know
that because you're telling me already
that you're going to use the same
Randomness so now in the first round I'm
I'm going to behave honestly just learn
your Randomness give you so I'm sorry
I'm not going to be I'm going to cheat
in the first round okay so of course I'm
going to I'm the output is one even
though it's zero I'm going to manage to
convince you in the first kind of in the
first Su check I do yeah because I'm
just going to lie consistently with
myself arrive to VI to the next layer
and the wrong still inconsistent but now
I know the randomness that cuz you're
going to reuse you see here the point is
that the following the verifier here
should behave like a like an honest
verifier in the gkr if the verifier here
you cannot if when you use this verifier
he
essentially behaves like a GK verifier
so now you're telling you're saying look
why doesn't he use the same Randomness
for the different uh subprotocols
because if he didn't gkr then he would
fail then you the a cheating prover can
can take advantage of him is isn't there
the difference here that this is
nonadaptive like it doesn't remember the
randomness all it depends on
is right so you can't just be like oh
this is the random oh I see you're
saying I see I see okay okay now I
understand your question you're saying
this guy this uh prover is stuck okay
okay sorry now I'm I understand what
you're saying you're saying look you're
tying the hand of the prover the prover
in
gkr he has power he sees your Randomness
and based on that he can continue the
honest Pro of course won't do that but
the cheating prover May here you're
saying I'm not going to let the prover
do that to me I'm G to force him to
forget because I force him to forget can
I think of using the same Randomness
that's a good question
actually a great very good question I it
took me time to understand what you're
asking a
can you use the same it's great qu great
point verif just said to break that well
no because what okay so I'm so okay so
we are pointed the F said you know what
use the same Randomness in all the
subprotocols now in the gkr it's a big
problem because the prover he knows what
you saw and he'll use that like he know
the but in in the PCP the
PCP gkr prover his hands are tied yeah
but the fact like if the Prov knows that
you're going to do this then he might be
able to engineer all of his responses in
a way that like takes advantage of the
correlation of right like by exactly
using the same verifier you said like
you pretend you have that verifier that
cheats you use the same Randomness now
this tree follows that verifier
strategy
shouldn't yeah I mean it is it could be
some but like there's this correlation
between the randomness the would know
about it in advance right so even though
he can't remember the random he can
engineer the strategy to take advantage
of the fact the
Rand okay let me say the following um to
close this discussion a the discussion
is super interesting the question you
raised is super
interesting you know we have one pet in
this
class you gave me a great uh idea for a
question a a by the way um before we
break I just want to make a quick
announcement so I wrote in the in the
website that the pet will come later in
during this class because I thought it
would be good to cover more
material but uh I know that I wrote it
pretty close like to the break and maybe
that's so okay so maybe I'll I'll put it
out earlier give you two weeks and just
because I don't want to sit with it too
long it's just annoying but if you feel
like the time is doesn't work and you
want an extension just let me know
I don't really
care I just want you to think about it
and have fun with the you know with the
material yeah the way we all do sound is
are we using un bound like yeah exactly
we're doing a union bound yeah yes
exactly because the in the soundness we
say the following we say that
uh uh in the so essentially we're we're
talking with a prover and GK prover and
we're saying for the GK even like a tied
GK Pro as you as you mentioned even it's
a gar prover with tied hands so for this
for this prover to cheat he need so the
output is false that's kind of he
cheated so somewhere he needs to cheat
in one of the gkrs one of the one of the
sum checks he needs to go from false to
True somewhere because at the end you're
verifying you verifying that you know he
put here a witness so he put in the sky
a witness that witness is false because
there's no satisfying assignment so he
put something that's actually
false oh one second there is something
okay sorry now I remember there is
something there is a low deegree test to
do we'll get back to that sorry uh we'll
get back to the low degree test but uh
there so you're talking with a um a
you're talking with a GK prover and this
prover the only way he can convince you
is to go from like a false statement to
a true statement because at the end you
ver you and to do that you need to break
one of the sum checks so to break one of
the Su checks you have two Su checks and
now I'm using a union bound to say that
the probability that you kind of manag
to break one of them is two to the D
times the probability that you manage to
break one of
them okay but then back to discussion
where like like sharing Randomness so
does un help
here you you're saying oh you're because
of
theend okay so this is is this related
to this qu okay okay actually I don't
think so because Union Bound in general
it it can be correlated a union Bound in
general says that the probability that
this or this I don't care how they're
correlated it's smaller or equal the
probability of this plus the probability
of this so the correlation here the
union bound is
very uh easily used in any situation you
know just at the probability that you
have an event you CH you cheated on test
one you cheated on test two you cheated
on test three I don't care how they're
correlated the probability that you Che
on one of them is small or equal
then yeah but actually before we break
sorry there is a some there is a low
degree extension
what
exactly you can just
use good okay okay okay
sorry good uh I love you guys uh so uh
yeah
V uh okay
check v0 Tilda is low
degree because in
gkr the verifier has the W the the input
which is the witness he computes the Lo
extension by
himself here the poer is giving it to
him what if you didn't give a low degree
so we do need one low degree test in the
input other than that it's GK black box
but we do need this and by the way note
that we're using the gkr the gkr has
actually um properties and now I want to
go back to the succinctness because
actually you're saying can't you do it
with any succinct protocol and the
answer is maybe but there's also this
point which is problematic that in gkr
it's nice because you just check one
point in the low degree
extension and we can verify that you do
the low degree
extension there there's a low deegree
test that I didn't talk to you about but
we'll mention that after the break so
there's a uh gkr you can verify the
verifier to verify all he needs to do is
take his input and compute only one
point two points in the low degree
extension of that
input this is actually used here
because now the ver the prover the
verifier doesn't have the input the
witness the prover has it he's going to
put it in the in the sky and now you
can't read the entire input that's a
witness but you can read like you know
what the what what the kind of succinct
protocol tells you to read you know and
so this this part is is important in the
G
okay a questions before we break okay so
after the we'll take a five minutes
break and then we'll talk quickly about
the low degree test wrap up the
information Theory and go to
cryptography okay