Welcome to the MPG Medanox series
primer. Today um our talks next week we
have genetic therapies for rare disease
Maline Odin and we also have AI in
medicine the following week with Mah
Chudich
and today I'm so excited for this talk
uh illuminating variant impact with
images um and this will be given by two
people so lucky you guys uh an
Carpenter. She earned her bachelor of
science from Purdue and her PhD from the
University of Illinois. She is a senior
director of the imaging platform and an
institute scientist here at the broad um
where she leads development of
open-source image analysis tools like
cell profile and the cell painting
assay. She also directs consortium in
including the jump cell painting and
oasis and is an NIH mirror investigator,
an NSF career awardee and a royal a
royale microscopia microscopical
society fellow. Um and joining her today
is uh Reni Shen. He's a posttock in the
carpenter singing labag and he earned
his PhD in computational biology from
Cornell studying population genetics and
evolution. Here at the broad he develops
computational methods to analyze cell
painting data uncover how genetic
varants change cellular states and also
identifies potential therapeutic
targets. Um I'm very excited for you
guys to be here. I'm excited to see all
these images. Um ask questions
throughout please. There's a hot mic
right in the middle here. You could just
come right up to it. If you just start
asking your questions from your chair,
the folks on Zoom will not hear. So,
either flag me down or come to the
microphone and let's go.
>> Thank you so much. Really happy to be
here to talk with this group today. I
think it's always so exciting to um to
see our technology being used in the
space of genomics and it's kind of a new
new direction and um just want to let
you know the slides are available at the
download. I think they are. Maybe we
forgot to upload them. Within an hour,
the slides will be uploaded um at that
location and um and you'll be able to
grab them um and or take pictures,
whatever you like. Everything can be
public here. So, we're um going to start
uh let me give you a bit of an overview
about what we'll talk about. I first
want to give some background. This is
the primer series. So, this is intended
to be more tutorial and and make sure
that everyone's on the same page. So, if
you know nothing about imaging, um you
should be in good shape. I'll explain a
bit about um how images yield single
cell profiles just like single cell mRNA
profiles or proteomics. Um and then
we'll talk about four different ways
that we can use this kind of image based
data and um and you can see here what
looking at gene function trying to
figure out disease mechanisms and do
drug screens and then looking at various
variant impacts and so we'll be talking
through that and Runi will especially be
taking over the coding variant part of
this talk. So let's get started. Um the
basic premise of us using images for
data is what if a disease cell could
just tell us what's wrong with it. What
if there was enough information in the
structures and the organels as their
image that could tell us that this
certain pathway is disrupted or this um
this patient has this disease or not.
And uh of course that must be true at
some level because we know it's true at
at larger scales. So, for example, if
you look at the structure of a human
face, you can often diagnose a disease
straight um straight from the the image.
And pathologists use this concept all
the time, except they zoom in a bit. Um
they might look at your skin and look at
a funny looking mole to see if it's
cancerous. They might zoom in to extract
cells from you and then look at their
structure because fundamentally our
biological structures tell us something
about biological functions and there's a
usually a tight correlation and often
diseases can be revealed in this way. So
that's the basic concept that we are
taking here except we are using cells
growing in a dish because they're much
easier to manipulate. And when we say
we're using the cell painting assay,
what I mean is we are taking cells um
either from straight from patient
samples or cells that have been
manipulated in in the dish somehow
engineered somehow to reflect a
particular disease. We're putting them
in culture and then we're staining them
with a number of different dyes that are
shown here. And these dyes are every
cell biologist's favorite u organels and
they are really informative about what
the status of a cell is. It seems like a
very simple assay and that's because it
is um it's very inexpensive. Um it's the
reagent cost is less than a dollar per
sample and um when we do all the image
analysis it it produces a remarkable
amount of information and I if you don't
quite believe how is that possible um I
hope to demonstrate some examples of
this today. So the basic kinds of
experiments that we do using cell
painting involve somehow preparing some
samples and those could be again patient
cell lines or genetically edited um cell
lines or they could be cells that have
crisper knockdown or an overexpression
of a gene or so on. So we prepare some
samples that mean something to us in the
context of the disease that we're
studying and then we measure everything
about those cells and we use image
analysis software such as cell profiler
which was um an invented
by my lab and here at the Broad
maintained for the past 20 years um and
kept up to date with all kinds of um new
algorithms that allow us to really
accurately identify the nucleus of the
cell or the borders of the cell from
every individual image. So we measure
not just how big is each object um and
we we're not just counting cells. We're
doing things like measuring the um the
the characteristics of the shape of the
cell gorder of the nucleus. We're
looking at the intensities and textures
of all the different scenes that we have
present looking at their correlations
and relationships as well. So we end up
with thousands of features for every
individual cell that has been measured
in the image. So we can use classical
techniques um in order to extract those
measurements that have some biological
meaning to us area shape and texture. We
can also use deep learning fe feature
extractors. And I won't go into detail
here, but the basic idea is you put in
the raw image of um of the pixels and
you allow the deep learning network to
learn what are important features that
exist within the cells maybe beyond the
things that biologists think about. So
the good news is it can capture a bit
more than our human our set of thousand
features that we typically measure with
cell profiler. Um it can capture a bit
more. The the downside is those features
are not very human interpretable. So we
we don't have great ways of figuring out
what exactly they're measuring. So
either way we end up for every
individual cell we get sort of a row of
this data matrix. A typical experiment
would have uh 10,000 times big more data
than is shown here because we have um
thousands of single cells for every
sample. We might have thousands of
samples and then we have thousands of
morphology features. So what do why do
we use imaging um and why are we so
excited about this as a data source is
because it's so much cheaper than um
mRNA and protein profiling and yet we
find that it has pretty similar
predictive success in a in a number of
different tasks that we've um attempted
over the past decade or so. We find that
um mRNA and images are typically equally
powerful protein protein profiles as
well. Um, and even more exciting is
they're complimentary, which means some
information you could get using either
technique, but there's a lot that you
can get. It's usually about a third, a
third, a third. Um, that a third you can
only get with mRNA, a third you can only
get with images. So, it's really nice
when we have multiomic um data sources
together with imaging to really capture
a lot of what is going on with a given
sample that we're trying to to model.
Okay. So this is the again the basic
concept of image profiling is we take
images we turn them into numbers in
single cell profiles and then we do
stuff with them and today's talk is um
mostly going to be about what do we do
with those um profiles we can basically
measure are these two samples similar to
each other or different from each other.
We can answer questions like which of
those features is predictive of some
other property that we care about about
the samples and so on.
Any questions so far? Um that's the
that's the uh the end of that little
chunk. Yeah, please.
>> Sorry. Thank you. Can I ask just a very
quick question actually? Um are are
there ways that are already defined in
which in which ways we can integrate
basically u the imaging data of a given
data set plus the mRNA or
>> ah so data integration across modalities
is a really fascinating problem. I think
it's a little um maybe easier to grasp
in if you're using multiple molecular
techniques but then images are just such
a weird data type compared you know at
least mRNA and epigenomics and um
proteomics they map to particular genes
whereas images is just a very different
kind of data. So very different equals
great because now we have more
information but also more complicated.
So there's two ways um I mean there's
two classes of ways to integrate data.
Um one is called early fusion and the
other is called late fusion. So early
fusion would just say, "Hey, if I've got
a certain sample and I have this many
morphology features, I'm going to just
tack on a bunch of mRNA features and a
bunch of proteomic features or
epigenomic or whatever else you have and
just put all the raw features in and you
know do whatever task you trying to do,
giving it access to everything kind of
equally. Um, and then the other approach
is called late fusion which is um
analyze each modality independently to
make some kinds of predictions and then
combine the predictions at the end. Um,
and we usually find late fusion works
better, but I think that's only because
um, not enough people are working on
this space and there's there's got to be
more clever ways of um, integrating the
data types earlier.
>> And and just out of curiosity, when you
say this oneird oneird oneird of
explaining something about the the cell
biology, it's using the early fusion or
the late fusion or
>> uh, that's using each of them
independently. Yes. So if we use them
independently then um then um using both
types independently um one or the other
one or the other will get a third and
then both of them will get a third of
the correct answers. And then you're
asking like what if we actually combine
them and integrate them. We so far have
not found that integrating the data does
much better than treating them both
separately. So in other words late
fusion seems to work better that
>> very complimentary.
>> Yeah. Okay. Thanks.
>> Yeah. Thanks for those questions.
Anything else before we get to the
actual what what are we going to do with
all these profiles?
>> Yeah, one question.
>> Sure.
>> Is there a sweet spot uh comparing the
imaging resolution and the imaging
speed?
>> Ah, yeah, for sure. So, it's it's
exactly a trade-off between how um high
resolution are the images and um how how
long is it sitting on the microscope and
that really adds up. It's actually a
significant cost of the assay is just
renting the microscope per hour if
you're at a place where you actually
have to pay for it. Um, so what we find,
um, weirdly enough, you would think the
higher and higher resolution go you go,
the better the data quality will be. It
turns out there really there is kind of
a sweet spot around 20x um, objective
lens is um, is pretty good. And um,
apparently going further than that, you
you get a bit more detail about what's
going on within the cell. At some point
you hit the limit of light microscopy
and you're not really getting anymore
anyways. Um, but I think the real issue
is that the more uh the the more you
zoom in on the cells, the fewer cells
you capture. And so, um, you have to,
um, you have to capture a lot more
fields of view to get the same number of
cells. And at some point, it just sort
of deteriorates. So, we found 20x to be
a really good trade-off.
>> Thank you. Thank you.
>> Okay. So, let's go to one of the first
applications. I want to understand
disease mechanisms and make a cell-based
functional assay for my disease. Why do
you want to make a cell-based assay for
your disease? Because then you can do
all kinds of things. You can screen
drugs. You can also do genetic
manipulations. You can try to figure out
what's going on um your with your
disease mechanisms. Okay. So, what's an
example of this? We have this vision of
the future where we could find a
cell-based phenotype for every disease
and that would be quite delightful.
Here's one example where you have cells
in a healthy state um and then cells in
a disease state. In this case, it was a
crisper knockdown for a loss of function
disorder. And you get some kind of
visual change. And once once that
happens, you can then find drugs that
reverse that disease phenotype by taking
cells that are in the disease state,
testing drugs one by one, and seeing, do
any of these drugs make the cells look
healthy? Again, that's a basic concept.
And so, here's that particular example
actually comes from the University of
Utah. And um and the the basic idea this
wasn't they weren't using cell painting
but they were using a few dyes that you
can see here. And when they knock down
this gene that causes a human genetic
disorder cerebral cavernous malf
formation you see a very obvious visual
change. And of course that can be
quantified very readily by image
analysis. And then they tested a bunch
of drugs and long story short eventually
went to clinical trials and launched
this company recursion which takes this
basic approach of knocking down loss of
function disorder genes and then um and
then uh screens drugs to to um repair
the cellular mechanisms that have gone
wrong with that disease. Um so they now
have multiple clinical trials running.
That's one example. Um another example
comes from Molina Clausniter's lab.
Sorry that all the um credits are are
covered by the um closed captioning
here, but um from Molina Clauser's lab
um they took a different approach of how
do we create a disease in a dish. Here
they took patient cells that were at
high risk or low risk of developing
metabolic disorder. So they weren't
necessarily experiencing symptoms
currently, but they had the genetics
that would indicate that they're going
to be susceptible. And that is scored by
a polygenic risk score. So you have high
and low risk patients. And they just
took the tails of each um took patient
samples um primary cells from them
adiposytes and then looked at at them in
the dish. And what they found is that um
again a very obvious difference here.
You can see the lipid droplets. Um they
chose to replace one of the cell
painting dyes with um with lipid
droplets. Um and you can see a very
clear difference here. Interestingly
though um they actually you don't have
to label the the lipid droplets
directly. uh there's enough information
in the other channels of cell painting
to have revealed this disorder. We just
didn't know that until we did the
experiment. So that's kind of a neat
side effect is that you don't always
have to stain for something obvious that
you think is going to be disease
related. Sometimes the data in the um in
the assay just tells you um something
new that you might not have realized you
were looking for. So those are some
examples of how we find disease
phenotypes so that we could eventually
do drug screens and so on. Another thing
you can do with images if is figure out
what a gene does. Yeah, please go ahead.
>> I have just one more and actually just
because of the previous slide it makes
me think so I know this is actually
combining polygenic information and for
one individual but it makes me think
about EQTLs or any sort of QTL where we
can actually map the effect of a variant
uh to a given phenotype and so is there
any phenotype that we can actually map
to snips uh in that way?
>> Absolutely. And that'll be this that'll
be the subject of like this the next
application after this. Exactly. Yeah,
you're you're thinking exactly the right
direction. Okay. Um so I know what this
gene does. I want to know what this gene
does. Um here I'm sorry I don't have a
ton of visuals about it, but I just want
to point out that we have collected a
ton of data that allows you to ask ask
answer this question for about 75% of
the genome. So if you've got a gene and
you don't know its function, um 13,000
of them we've overexpressed, 8,000 and
and you can't do more than that because
at some point the genes are too large to
express well. So that's kind of the
limit on overexpression. We could have
done more knockdown if we had more
funding. Um but we did 8,000 there. And
then collectively that covers about 75
um% of the genome as well as a ton of
small molecules. And what we did for
each of these, we turn up each gene,
turn down each gene, and then take a a
cell painting um set of images and
extract the profiles and so on. All this
data is now publicly available. This was
a large consortium with a number of
really great pharma partners who helped
to collect the data as well as of course
some data production here at the Broad.
And this is um you can you can go to
broad.io jump and figure out how to
access the entire data set if you're
computational and want to do that. But
we also have these interactive tools um
from Alon Fernando Munos Gonzalez in the
group. He uh postto he created some
tools that make it very easy to answer.
You know, type in your favorite gene and
you will get pictures that shows you
this is how the cells look when that
gene is knocked down or overexpressed.
And then it will also tell you what
other profiles are the most similar. And
that's super valuable because if you
have a gene with unknown function and
you find that it's highly similar to
three other genes, you can then go and
see what do those three other genes do?
what are their annotations? And it
starts to give you some clues, some
hypotheses that you might pursue for
your gene of interest. And it and it can
also answer um these tools online can
also answer what are the most
distinctive morphological features when
you knock down your gene or overexpress
it. So in any case where you're digging
into a gene um and putting together a
story about it, this might be a useful
additional piece of information to add
um to a paper where you can say um and
also the the gene is messed up in terms
of its mitochondrial shape or its
nuclear size or some other parameters.
And we're happy we have office hours
routinely at the image imaging platform
happy to help you interpret what do
those features actually mean um if
you're using tools like this. Yeah,
quick question. What um tissues or cell
types are?
>> Ah, yeah. So, this experiment was done
in U2OS cells. That's an osteocaroma
cancer cell line because it's um easily
cultured and grows at um densely enough
but also nicely flat enough to get good
measurements from. So, so far we've only
done one cell type with this. You can
imagine repeating this for a neuronal
cell type or hypatocytes and so on. That
would be quite lovely but also
expensive.
All right. Next we will move on to I
want to know this non-coding variance
impact getting to the QTL question that
was asked before. So here um you know in
my vision of of broad's future this is
something we've been talking about for
for quite a while is um we we started
out with a strong history in um in in um
sequencing genomes and it's led us to so
so many variants that now need
characterizing. So what comes next after
we have variance um non-coding or coding
and we would love to see there's so many
technologies at the broad cell painting
as well as transcrytoics and proteomics
can we do a full suite of
characterization on tons of variants in
parallel so that we end up with um being
able to at the very least classify
variants um we might not know what the
classes mean or do but at least um if
all of your variants for a disease fall
into three classes you can pick one from
each and then pursue them for example um
But it also provides us with phenotypic
insight. Sometimes we get real
mechanistic insight from looking at the
data of these different kinds of
profiles and eventually this hopefully
will lead to therapeutics.
Okay, so that's the basic concept. Um
most people in the room know about more
about QTLs than I do, but it's a locust
that correlates with some quantitative
trait. And so um those traits
historically have been gene expression,
the most predominant one, but they could
easily be cell morphology. And so we
worked together with a whole team um
that is shown here um Shomo Rajuri and
Raldon Name's group um and you can see
all the folks involved in this uh where
we they took um IPS-C's um and plated
them which is really not easy to get a
lot of cell lines growing together. So
it's very easy to take one cell line and
add a lot of perturbations because
everything's kind of consistent and so
on. But getting 297 cell lines to grow
independently but try to keep them
growing at the same pace so that they're
all at the same um crowdedness when it's
time to image them is is really quite a
challenge. But um Matt Tagmire was up to
this challenge and made this work to the
point where we then um did cell painting
and there was genome sequencing of these
same cell lines and then we just asked
can we take those morphology features
and correspond them to any particular
variance. And so um again the the
citation is right under the um captions
but you can download the slides later
and um see the paper where it goes into
great detail about what we found. And in
the end we found that these 297 cell
lines were just barely enough to start
seeing both rare and common variant um
associations here. We call them CMQLs
for cell morphology uh Q QTLs. And I
think it's because MQTTL was already
used for something else. I forget what
it is but not morphology. So um so we
call them CMQTLs.
And then lastly um the last big
application which I'll turn it over to
Renie is um having to do with coding
variance. So I'll start with an older
story from our lab where we found uh we
took alals that were found in lung
cancer. So there's sematic gen genetic
variation. Um, we took 353 alals that
were found in lung cancer where it
wasn't known which ones are actually
causal and actually really doing
something and which ones just happened
to be passenger mutations in the cancer.
We did cell painting and then um and
then the image analysis to create these
profiles and then did clustering on
them. And as you can see the different
clusters in this morphology space have
different phenotypes and the cells look
different in each one. So um in fact the
majority of leals actually did have a
phenotype. they were distinguishable
from negative controls and genes in
known pathways actually cluster with
each other which was another exciting
outcome from this and here's just
another way of looking at that same data
but just zooming in on one particular
gene so this is just BFF and we had a
dozen or so alals here and it was pretty
exciting because you can see the normal
version of BFF it's down here the marked
wild type um down at the bottom it
actually clusters with empty which is
our negative control here so normally
when you overexpress BFF the cells don't
you don't notice it by cell painting.
There's no particular um morphological
change. But when you overexpress
one of these other guys, um these are
all some of the the nasty driver
mutations for cancer. Um you see a whole
cluster of these guys together, but then
you also see a separate little cluster
um which are known functionally to to be
not constitutively activating mutations.
And so if you were to um it now becomes
possible to test every gene, every alil
that you could possibly get in BFF all
at once um cluster them like this. And
if your mutation in your cancer has
never been seen before, it's at least
useful to know does it fall into this
category and therefore might be helped
by medications that are useful for some
of these other guys or does it fall into
that category. So that's a basic
concept, but of course across all the
genes and all the variants. And so we
really love the idea of scaling this
kind of an experiment up to be able to
produce cataloges that allow us to um
more readily predict variant impact. And
that leads us over to Runi. So I'll hand
it over now.
>> One quick clar clarifying question
online. Are there enrichment libraries
for genes that have similar profiles
after they've been interfered with from
crisper?
Are there separate libraries of
>> are there enrichment libraries for genes
that have similar profiles after they've
been interfered with via crisper?
>> Oh um well I I'm not sure I know what
what is meant by enrichment libraries in
this context.
>> I think it was back when um you were
talking about the jump and that there
was enrichment libraries where you could
look up genes that were behaving
similarly.
>> Yeah. So um we have the data for the
whole set. And so if you type in your
gene name, you will get the the
rankordered list of the genes that are
most similar to your particular one. So
we don't have physical libraries
prepared like for each gene. Here's its
neighbors or whatever, but um but you
can see what those genes are and then
you know hand cherry pick a library as
you like. Yeah.
>> Is there anything else online?
>> Um no, that was it. And feel free to
clarify that question Jared if that
wasn't correct.
>> This is Pam. Can you hear me? I actually
have one question about jump data. Um,
how transferable are the like expression
or knockout findings from the U2 O2
cells to other cell lines? I mean, I
guess it depends on the gene, but do
main features of the cells change in a
similar way in in different
>> Yeah, I'm I'm glad you asked this
question because you everybody would be
quite right to be a little skeptical
like gh what's the point, you know, you
knock down and overexpress these genes
in a single cell type. Um, but that's
really unfortunate because I study
neurons or um a liver disease or
something else and like how what are the
chances this random bone cancer cell
line is going to have the right
phenotypes. And I guess the reassurance
that I have um so of course sometimes
you will not see a phenotype in this
cell line whereas you would if you used
a more specific cell type. But as
reassurance that it's not hopeless, um
we actually find that um something like
um I'm sorry I don't remember exactly,
but something like 30 to 40% of human
genes when knocked down or overexpressed
produce a phenotype in the cell line
with the cell painting assay. So 30 to
40% is not bad coverage um for a single
very inexpensive assay. Um and we also
find that something like 70% of FDA
approved drugs um actually produce a
phenotype in a single cell line. those
FDA approved drugs are for all kinds of
different disorders and so we are
capturing a broad spectrum of of biology
that is in many cases conserved from one
cell type to another. Um so we h we
certainly have specific examples of um
brain diseases where we see a phenotype
in a random um epithelial cell line. Um
so it's it's not it is definitely not
hopeless. In fact, more often than not,
we really do see things in the quote
wrong cell type for a given disease. So
it's at least worth a shot. It's low
hanging fruit. it's worth a shot. Um,
but we would love to also be expanding a
lot of these experiments to fancier cell
types.
>> Okay. Uh, cool. Well, uh, first thank
you Dr. Cover for a excellent overview
of how we can use a cell painting essay
to tackle all different kinds of
biological problems in general and also
in the genetic research which also sets
perfect stage to what I'm going to talk
about next. But before I start it, I
just want to express my thanks to both
the organizer today and also my PI for
having me here and also it's a pleasure
to be here today and then present my
work at the MPG primer series. Cool. So
going forward from Dr. cover has just
talked about regarding how we can use
the cell painting essays to decode those
coding variants. I'm going to dive into
a specific project where instead of
focusing on specific variants in a
disease or a single gene, we're trying
to capture and test the functional
impact of thousands of variants at the
same time. So this is actually a part of
the var initiative funded by the NIH
where we're aiming to characterize the
functional impact of more than 30,000
genetic variants across more than 2,000
rare disease genes across a whole human
mandelian protein. And the idea behind
this is because in the genetic research
right now even though we have found so
many different associations between the
varants and the disease phenotypes we
have limited knowledge about how these
variance is impacting the disease in
different biological mechanisms. And the
idea of our project is to use multiple
different kinds of essays to give a
comprehensive picture of the functional
impact of this variants. So here we're
doing a lot of different tasks like
we're doing this protein stability essay
to test whether the protein will be
degraded or not after mutation and we're
using protein protein interaction essays
to detect how the protein protein
interaction is going to be disturbed
after mutation and of course we're also
going to do a lot of imaging stuff as I
will talk about today and eventually the
idea is that we use all these different
kinds of essays to give a comprehensive
picture of the functional impact of
different variants and then combine them
with some kind of AI predictor such as
alpha miss sense to predict those
missations effect and then use our essay
to help us understand the biological
mechanisms underlying those predicted
variants and see if we can understand
those understand them in a better way.
So as you can see here so far in this
project specifically we have profiled
more than 1,000 variants variants across
the whole thing and if we look at the
clinical var annotations of all these
variants we can see that more than a
quarter of them have no clear clinical
annotation regarding their clinical
significance which basically leave all
the doctors and the patients who are
diagnosed with this variant to be
uncertain about their diagnosis. At the
same time, even though more than 50% of
them are pathogenic, we still have no
idea most of them are doing with
regarding their pathogenicity.
So in this case, using our imaging
essay, we can detect their phenotype
such as protein misloization, which is a
very nice representation of their
biological function. For instance, in
one of our pilot study conducted by
Tapoli lab at the University of Toronto,
we find some mutation from the LZTR1
gene which had a very prominently
different phenotypes compared to their
reference. And this variant is actually
assoc associated with a rare disease
called non syndrome which typically
happens in the babies where it stops the
typical development of different human
bodies. And after such phenotypes has
been identified, we can then use
different drug screening to find the
drugs that can reverse the phenotype
backs to their original state.
And in this specific project, we
actually optimize our essay to capture
the protein localization better. Unlike
the traditional cell painting essay
where we use five different channels to
capture the general cell structure, we
actually replace one of the channel with
a green fluoresence protein where we can
attack the protein of target and then
using the other three channel to capture
the general morphology of the cells in
general. So in this case we can use this
variant painting essay to capture both
the protein localization effect as well
as cell morphology to give us a more
comprehensive picture of the cell
phenotypes after mutation happens.
And in our general workflow uh both
experimentally and computationally in
this project is that first we're going
to overexpress a single al either its
variant or its uh reference alo in on
the U2 cells and then put them into
hundreds of different 384 well plates.
After that we're going to stain each
cell with different type of stains that
we get from the variant painting essay
and then take the microscopic images of
each cell in there. And then we will do
the computational analysis where we use
cell profiler to do this imaging uh
image segmentation to help us identify
each single cell in there and then
extract all these different features
like Dr. Cumber has just talked about
regarding their counts, shapes, size,
textures and all this stuff. So
eventually this will leads us to about
2,000 features per each cell for our
downstream analysis.
And with all this informative cell
morphology and protein localization
features, we then develop an automated
machine learning framework to detect if
the variant cells have any protein
misoization effect or alter cell
morphology. And the hardest part with
this problem is that even though we're
able to use such kind of framework to
detect whether a varied cell is
different from the reference cells, it's
very hard for us to tell if it's from
simple techn technological confounding
factors such as well position effect or
some microscopic lining conditions. And
to address this issue, we train this
extra boost classifier to basically
train the cell train the classifier
using the single cell profiles from the
from the same alals from different
control imaging wells as well as using
the different alals from different
wells. And then we're going to use the
AOC metric of this classifier as a
surrogate to describe how different the
single cell profiles are from different
al pairs or well pairs. In this case, if
it's a higher ARC, means that our
classifier is able to learn the
distinguished features between the
variant and the reference, which means
that there is a more significant effect
of protein misloization or changing cell
morphology. And in order to address the
technical variations we observe due to
wellposition effect or uh the lighting
conditions, we actually use the
distribution of the AOC that we obtained
from training the classifier on the same
web pairs but from different imaging
walls. and then use the 15 the 95th
percentile of the ARC as the cutoff for
us to call the significant hits of
either protein misloization and alter
cell morphology
and using this method we're able to
identify more than 43% of the genes that
we have profiled so far have at least
one variant that cause a significant
protein misloization which leads to
about 15 15% of variants in total as
well as about 2% of the variants a
significant change in cell morphology.
Since the AOC profile is a continuous
metric to describe the the degree of
difference between the variant and the
reference, we can actually see that in
the protein misloization profiling
specifically all the pathogenic variants
are much more likely to cause protein
misloization than the benign variants
where the conflicting variants and the
VS variants where we have no idea what
their clinical significance exactly is
sitting between the benign and and the
pathogenic. But our ability to detect
the cell morphology right now is is not
so distinguishable as we can detect the
protein localization. And we're still
working on this to make it uh better in
the future.
And when we're examining the protein
structure for uh when we observe all
these variants, we also observe that all
the variants that happened within the
core of the protein show higher mis
localization than the surface exposed
variants which can be captured by the so
relative solvent accessibility matrix
where we can see that all the var in the
protein core have much much higher
misoization score than the protein that
is on the protein surface. And to
visualize this in a very nice uh 3D
structure from a example protein called
factor 9, we can also see that all the
variants that are misloized are more
likely to be contained within the
protein core rather than on the protein
surface.
So after we have identified all this
misloized variants, the next natural
question will be where do this variant
move the protein. So in some cases the
direction of movement is very
straightforward. basically move the
protein from one cellular compartment to
the other like we are showing here using
the example of the rodopsin protein
which the mutations in this protein is
very so is very closely related to
disease like night night blindness and
in this case when we're using the cell
profiler features to analyze the protein
collocicalization patterns we can
observe that there is a significant
increase in protein collocicalization
between the GFP channel and the
mitochondria channel in the cytoplasm
As well as when we're looking at the
images, we can we can also observe the
same trend of this gradient of change
between the variants corresponds to
exactly the feature we observe on the on
the left hand side where initially in
the reference we see the protein is miso
is localized generally in the plasma
membrane. Well, in the protein where we
have the the proline to therronine we
have the kind of least misoization from
the the plasma membrane to cytoplasm.
Well, in the last case in the cyine to
tyrrosine, we have the most strongest
significant effect of misoquization into
cytoplasm. And even though all the four
variants that we have shown here has
been annotated at pathogenic variants in
cleanar only one of them which is the
cyst to tarning has been annotated with
the function of er retention in previous
literature literature'ses. However, with
our assay right now, we can identify the
exact functional impact of more variants
and annotate them with similar
functional impact.
But however, in a lot of cases, not all
the variance impact can be visually see
exactly. So a lot of the patterns that
we observe can only be detected by cell
profiler features such and using the
unbiased quantitative matrix to evaluate
how this protein or how this variant
changed the misoization pattern of a
protein. For instance here uh take the
example of this CCM2 gene which is known
to be associated with the vascular
malfunction in the central nervous
system. We have profiled more than a 100
variants in this gene and successfully
detect the top seven most significant
misloization uh misloized variants of
this gene and even there are only seven
of them there are they are forming three
different types of patterns of
misloization for this specific gene in
the first cluster we observe that there
is a significant increase of the protein
collocicalized with the DNA channel and
also in the nucleus which means that the
protein is more the protein varants
cause a more localization in the nuclei
than the reference. And in the second
cluster, we observe the same thing of
increased protein expression in the
nucleus, but we also observe a
significant decrease in expression in
the cytoplasm compared to the reference.
Well, in the third cluster, we observe a
different patterns of specific protein
spatial expression at the edge of the
cytoplasm. In general,
when we're looking at visualize
everything into a cell painting
pictures, we can also see that in
general in the CCM2 reference gene, it
is localized in the mitochondria and
mostly in the cytoplasm. But the first
cluster we identified is actually
misloized this protein from the
cytoplasm into the nucleus. While the
second cluster which is a mutations
happen at the start codon is having a
dramatic effect. Well, instead of moving
the nucle moving the protein from the
cytoplasm to the nucleus, it only
present the protein in the nuclei but
not the cytoplasm anymore. And in the
third cluster, even though visually we
cannot tell the exact difference between
the images from the variant versus the
reference, we can still use the
distribution of the subprofiler features
to see that the texture of the protein
expression in the nucle in the cytoplasm
as well as the expression of the protein
at the edge of cytoplasm is much higher
in the reference than the than the
variant. And the peculiar case with the
last val 53 to is uh to the isolucine
example is that this variant is actually
a benign variant on the clean bar and it
had it had about 6% of population
frequency in the caucasian population.
However, in our studies, we find that
this variant is actually is going to
increase the risk in the central nervous
system related CCM2 diseases which shows
that different variant is actually going
to have different cell type and also
disease type effect that going to have
even though the functional impact will
be the same the eventual results of this
variant in dise in different disease
context will be very different.
And the last one I'm going to show is to
show that our cell cell painting essay
is actually going to show reveal more
details regarding different patterns of
uh this localization change than other
some kind of essays. And in this as in
this specific study, we're collaborating
with our collaborator from the uh
University of Washington where they
focus on a specific gene called a factor
9 protein which I also showed the
protein structure previously. And in
this protein they focus on they use a
multiplex essay where they can hyperput
capturing the functional impact of
different variants of this protein on
the scale of thousand of variant at the
same time and they focus on the protein
secretion and the post-transational
modification of this protein because
these are the necessary functions for
this protein to stop bleeding and also
achieve hemostasis in the human bodies.
And when we are comparing our imaging
results with the protein secretion essay
and their post-transational modification
essay, we can see that both our
misloization scores have very strong
correlation with either protein
secretion and also their post
translational modification essays.
Especially most variants with very low
protein secretion also showed a very
high misloization score. However, we
also do see that there is still kind of
limitation of our imaging essay where we
could not exactly detect the
post-transational modification of these
two glue 73 variants with normal protein
secretion which also it's showcased that
we also need to have a more
comprehensive picture like we did in the
varian project to use different types of
essay to to characterize the functional
impact of different proteins.
But even though we have very nice
correlation between our score with the
protein secretion scores, we still
detect two different patterns of protein
misoization.
For example, the one that happened at
the signal peptide sequence of the F9
protein, the CIS 28 arch is actually
having a very different protein
misloization phenotype than the other
detected misloized variants where there
is more shift in the protein expression
in the nucleus where all the other
variants mostly only shift the protein
expression in the cytoplasm which shows
that our essay can review more
biological details and higher
granularity of the biolog biological
information compared to simply a protein
secretion essay.
And with all that being said, uh the
eventual goal of this project is
actually to construct a comprehensive
cell map or variant map of different
types of variants across all the
different genes and then we can help
people uh curate everything online using
our portal to see what are the common
common features or the differential
features among different variants,
different genes in different disease
contexts. uh which is going to be which
going to be public after we have
profiled all the 30,000 variants but
still for now uh thanks to the
generosity of doc and leasita our
collaborator at the Washington
University of Washington we also publish
our current 1000 variants mis
localization score onto their mdb
database where you can simply go on
there and search for the variants or the
gene that you're of your interest and
then look at the morphological uh
alterology score or misloization score
on the gene of your interest and feel
free to contact us regarding the images
of those variants as well.
So after we have identified all these
variants and their functional impact uh
like Dr. Cover just showed the next
natural steps will be to find the drugs
that can reverse those phenotypes. And
so far, combined with our current var
study as well as a pilot study, we have
profiled more than 40, and 500 human
genetic variants across 250 disease
phenotypes. And we're very excited to
further extend this initiative by not
only finding more uh finding the other
30,000 new variants as well as
establishing a consortium called Vista
where we're partner up with the people
from the pharmaceutical industry to see
if they can found interesting drug that
can be repurposed to just cure this
disease or reverse the phenotype
directly.
And to just show you guys the concept of
reversing drug of reversing the disease
phenotypes using drugs is going to be
successful. We are showing this two
example here where successful drugs can
actually reverse the disease
misloization. On the top here we have
the premature aging disease called
progeria where the initial protein
expression of the lemon is kind of like
speckly in the in the in the cell but
when a mutation happen it will lose its
speckly expression in the cell and makes
the nuclear a little bit blabby but the
blockbuster drug lenaparnep is actually
able to reverse the phenotype and then
make it more looking like its original
healthy status. The other example at the
bottom is the CFTR protein in the cystic
fibrosis where the protein is in
initially localized in the plasma
membrane. It's not in this CF disease.
However, the blockbuster drug from the
Vertex is actually able to push the
protein back into its original plasma
membrane disease, plasma membrane
localization and kind of help the
patient to have a speed recovery from
the disease and then even extend the
lifespan of this cystic fibrosis patient
to their 60s right now.
And even more, in order to accelerate
and also scale up the experiments more
efficiently, we're actually adopting a
new technology called full image based
profiling developed by Bleini Lab and
Neil JT Newslab at the Broad Institute.
In this case, instead of doing an array
format where in each imaging wall, we
only have one specific variant tested,
we're actually going to put thousands,
tens of thousands of variant in a single
imaging wall as long uh along with a
specific FDA approved compound. And in
each of the single wells, it can express
either one of the 400 possible genals
that we're going to test in there. And
in order to deconvolute the cell
morphological change or localization
pattern of each single cell, we can use
a s in situal barcoding to help us using
simple microscope to identify which cell
have carry which type of specific
variants and then use that to help us
efficiently detect whether for this drug
treatment in this wall how many variants
can be successfully reverted to their
original phenotype. And in this case, it
will help us speed up the whole process
of drug repurposing in a much faster
fashion.
And in the end, I hope you have enjoyed
a full journey of how we can use cell
printing essay to tackle different
biological problems as well as its
application in the genetic research. But
other than we have talked about before,
there are still a lot of different kinds
of other applications of cell painting
such as we can use them to identify the
MOA of different drug compounds uh
predict the drug toxicity of target
effect side effects and even use it to
stratify patient with uh for more
precision medicine. At the same time,
there are also a lot of questions that
are pending to answer such as can we
speed up the process in this experiment
or computational pipeline using
automation, a clever biotech or maybe
some AI agent and can we surpass the
human capabilities of understanding
those images using deep learning models
to help us extract more meaningful
biological context or insight for
different downstream tasks. And if you
are interested in looking into our
research a little bit more, you can also
refer to all the nice review papers we
have published in the recent years and
then talk to us afterwards as well. And
you can find our slide deck here on the
on the bottom of the link here. But in
the end, our hope is that collectively
we want this kind of technology as well
as all the other kinds of AI innovations
in the drug development can help us
break the curve and then cut the cost
and the time for drug development and to
develop better drugs to treat more human
diseases.
And last but not least, we would like to
thank uh all our lab members for all the
work they have done so far and also our
collaborators especially the image an
analyst in the best simul also in the
uproad imaging platform without their
effort none of this project will be
possible and also our amazing fund uh
funding resources as well uh without all
these people and all this money I don't
think we can achieve anything here. So,
with that all being said, we also have
our uh contact info here at the bottom
and also uh here again the slide link.
Feel free to contact us and look at the
slides afterwards and we're free to take
any questions you have. Thank you.
>> Um this is Pam online. I have a
question.
>> Um yeah. Um so, Nunan syndrome, it's
part of a spectrum of
neurodedevelopmental disorders. So there
are several other genes that cause it
and some other um
other genes that cause nunin as well as
like related syndromes. Um I'm guessing
this hasn't been done yet but have have
any of these other genes been tested in
the and seen the same to like replicate
the uh findings with LDTR1 because
>> that's a great Yeah, that's a great
question. I think we've only looked at
that one variant so far. So I love the
question but I don't know the answer.
Yeah,
>> you showed a couple examples of um cases
where something in some gene change
leads to some self morphology change,
but I'm wondering if um you know of any
examples where there's a cell morphology
change, but at the tissue level, it's
not clear what's going on. And um so I
it's like a negative case of using self
painting
>> like where where there is a change at
the cellular level but it's not seen at
the tissue level is
>> yeah or where um it's clear what's going
on in the cell at the cell level but at
the tissue level it becomes unclear
what's actually going.
>> No we have we have not done most of what
we've done so far has been really high
throughput like looking at thousands of
variants at once. So we have not um
followed up on very many things um at at
the tissue or organism level. So it's
it's a great question. I think that if
if you found some I mean we're just sort
of generating all these hypotheses. I
think if you found something that looked
interesting that would be a fantastic
question to go and follow it up.
>> Thank you for your wonderful talk. I
just have a basic questions is out of
curiosity when you do the model training
and decide whether there's um protein
mis localization comparing the the cells
with the mutation and the reference
cells have you compare or did you
compare the cells have similar genetic
background say like polygenic score
using this kind of score decide whether
these two cell uh the the cell with
mutation and the cell with the reference
uh the reference cells have similar
similar genetic background overall
generally speaking and then do the
comparation to decide whether it is the
protein misloization.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So the the cells in both
cases are exactly the same. They're
cultured cells. So they're you know as
identical as as cultured cells can be
over time. So we're we're putting
separate samples in different wells and
we're overexpressing the protein. These
are only coding variants. So we're
overexpressing the protein with and
without the mutation. Um so it's not at
the endogenous locus. um I think is what
you're you're getting at. Yeah. So the
genetic background is identical and it's
the only intervention is add a protein
with or without the mutation.
>> Got it. Thank you.
>> All right. Let's thank our speaker one
more time. Speakers,
>> thank you.
>> Um good news. You don't have to move.
Just refill your coffee and stick around
for the seminar. Thank you everybody.
See you next week.