Thank you so much. It's such a pleasure
to be here. Thank you for the
invitation. It was lovely to have a
reunion uh yesterday night. It's as a
former my former life. I was doing human
genetics. I'm not an active member of
the V2F community, but it's such a
pleasure to get to meet all of you
today. was honored to come and share
with you some of the work resources and
tools we are developing as part of um
our work done in the humanlas initiative
where I'm currently the vice co-chair
and so while I do my favorite cells are
immune cells I'm hoping that some of the
frameworks I will present can be useful
to your community here these are my
financial disclosures and so this is a
quick outline so you know where I'm
going to go with the presentation I want
to tell you about some for our first
large human blood at list which is
compiling over 40 million cells across
40 different conditions some of the
challenges we had to overcome to
integrate so many different data sets uh
how we're tackling sanitation challenges
and how we're deriving novel biological
insights and I promise I have some
snippets that are relevant to varant to
function in there so kind of bear with
me so why did we start with blood right
you can say oh this is the most boring
tissue actually when you think about
translating our findings clinically. It
is a window in human health. It is
easily sampled. It's bio bank everywhere
in the world across all clinical trials.
Very easy to collect in the clinic. When
you think about methods development for
single cell multiomics, in this case
we're going to talk a lot about single
cell RNA sequencing. These are the
largest data sets that are out there
right now. And so there's an opportunity
to try to uh go beyond every individual
studies that have been published
bringing them together to derive more
powerful insights. And so what we
hypothesized coming um through this
project is that if we could integrate as
many D cell as possible would saturate
the signal that can be detected in the
blood uh with the hypothesis that
there's going to be a finite number of
distinct cell subset identity in the
blood and some of them will be conserved
across disease and that could help you
hone in on some of these conserved
cellar programs
and so I'm going to show you some
highlights of how we've been working
towards 40 million cells. I'm like the
hungry hippo. I always want more cells.
And so I told my lab, it would be so
much better if we I think some of them
are in the other room. There's a
witnesses here at like 50 million. We're
working towards it uh across over 5,000
samples and 40 different immune
conditions. And I'll walk you through
for in case there's some immune lovers
in the room of the different data sets
we've compiled. So starting with some
four large integrated immune atlases.
One of the ones we're currently wrapping
up which was tied to a lot of um
computational methods development is
tied to the human atlas in case you've
never heard of it. It's um an
international endeavor that includes
over 104 countries across uh four 4,000
members across 104 countries. And our
mission is to create a comprehensive
reference map of all the cell types and
properties of um human cells and human
body health and eventually disease. And
so these are the members of our version
one uh means Atlas. Uh we have groups
represented across Singapore, UK,
Germany, um uh Spain and of course
Boston with trainee across all of these
different sites. And some of our initial
goals are to establish a detailed
reference of all circling cells so that
when we move to tissue which we are
moving to tissue becomes very easy to
distinguish resident from circling
cells. it turns out to not be trivial to
uh integrate so many data sets. So we're
optimizing computational frameworks to
do so and um I don't know how it is for
other communities but imunologists are
very passionate about how we call cell
types and so there's actually a need to
come together with the same data set to
have this conversation in a more
productive way. I'm going to show you
how we're doing this and of course we
want to support downstream biological
queries. Some of our goal of cell atlas
is to have a comprehensive globally
represented atlas. So we actually have
data sets from all around the world in
there. So you can also see how genetic
diversity can shape seller identity. So
uh I should say the first one let me go
back if I'm capable of doing that um
focuses on healthy and covid. That's
mostly because we needed data sets with
the same pathology across multiple
institution. We've also teamed up with
Dr. um Hogar Hines from um Synak in
Barcelona who has now this data set in
preprint and their whole goal is to
build a disease classifier using blood.
So if you you know select you know a few
drops of blood can we tell which disease
you have. So we've integrated their
data. There's also beautiful studies
that have been published uh in preprint
from the institute and um from UNL where
we've also integrated their data and
that's how we get to 29 million cells
across over 3,000 donors. We've also
went through everything that's been
published in the literature and gathers
across healthy infectious disease
autoimmune disease and adverse events to
checkpoint. We got another 5 million
cells and my lab uh contributed another
8 million cells of unpublished data
across healthy infectious disease
autoimmune disease and adverse events to
checkpoint and that's the breakdown on
the yeah you're left uh of the different
groups of disease autoimmune disease
infectious adverse events. You'll notice
we don't have hem malignancy. We're
really focused on trying to understand
the biology tied to the host. And so
with that we have data across single RNA
sequencing we have um surface protein we
have single cell TCR sequencing and I'm
sure somebody's going to ask me where's
the genotypes I this study was not
designed uh it's retrospective data so
we don't have a lot of genotype data but
I'm going to show you how we can still
try to pinpoint similar context that may
be relevant to G-W was and this is the
amazing team we have here bridging
between uh the broad institute and M
General Hospital. It's an effort that
I'm uh co-leading here with Gary
Reynolds um in leading the integration
and leading the data generation across
all of the all of these disease. And so
we have four main objectives. The first
one is to create that foundational
resources, right? We want to be able to
uh create a resource that anybody can
use to map annotation for circling cells
moving forward so you don't have to
reenotate over and over again. We also
want to benchmark better ways of doing
cell notation from a translational
perspective. We want to try to start
mapping the similar molecular programs
that are share cross disease. I realize
this is blood, but you might be
surprised. I'm going to show you that
even in blood uh where the disease is
not unfolding. Some of them are systemic
disease, you do find these share
programs and and start thinking about
potential targets here.
So I'm going to spend the next few
slides telling you how we optimize our
computational framework. It's actually
not trivial to do. So it would be so
much easier if we had generated these 40
million cells in a single institute. But
this is hundreds of studies. So we had
to optimize the framework using a subset
of studies and we picked autoimmune
disease to do so. Why? So well they're
tractable cell number. We know the
biology. So we know some ground truth.
there was moderate batch effect because
we generated a lot of data locally and
um you know we had to figure this out
because the current computational
workflow that existed when we started
this this project um couldn't handle
that many cells and so why for those of
you who don't think like me about
autoimmune disease all the time why
start there well we already know there's
a lot of commonalities across autoimmune
disease you know we know in terms of
organ involvement there's a lot of
organs that are involved in different
autoimmune disease we actually know that
some disease responds to the same
treatment. Also hinting that there's
some commonalities and for all of you
with the V2F community, you probably
already know that there's a lot of
genetic varants that are shared across
the disease also pointing out to
commonalities. And so this is where we
started. What were the main challenges?
Um uh so first integration we spent over
two years on this. I promise this is not
going to bore you with this because it's
very dry but uh we're going to release
all of our code so that people can see
how we've done this. We spent a lot of
time optimizing how we do quality
controls for raw data and uh processing
and pistic processing. How do you
optimize integration strategy in terms
of feature selection when you have to
deal with disease and normal tissue? And
so thinking about highly variable gene
selection, we actually didn't take the
first integration tool out of the box.
We actually benchmarked five different
integration strategies, optimized
different parameters only onto two of
them uh harmony and SCVI and and the
winner for us has been harmony. And then
we did uh hyperparameter tuning on all
of these features here. And to take a
decision we had to develop both um
qualitative and quantitative
assessments. So on the left you have
quantitative assessments. uh so that
meant like looking at distribution of
source data set chemistry uh cell range
of version gender donor and so forth. We
also wanted to make sure that the
biology was conserved. So we know so
much about immune cells is a great place
to start. So for example we could tell
that some of these plasma cells we
couldn't um split the IGG from the IG
plasma cell. So for example this would
be an example of you know an embedding
would be rejecting. We use the SCIB
framework developed by the TI lab, but
we also been developing new metrics that
really assess a bological conservation.
For example, if you know groups of cells
like T-Rex are supposed to
collocicalize, you can actually quantify
this and kind of speed up identifying
the right set of parameters. So this is
the extent I'm going to bore you with
systemic assessment of integration, but
if you're curious and trying to tackle
this, please do reach out. And once we
have some embedding. So this is an
example of monosets and and a type of
dendric cells where we have unique
markers. We just make sure that across
all the different cell subs that
represented here. Um on the x-axis we
have good distribution across disease
type of in this case 10x chemistries
because we had over six different types
and across all studies. So this is an
example of like a you know a final
product here. The second challenge we
had was scalability in every sense of
the word. But in this case, I'm going to
talk about annotation. You know, if you
start processing tens of millions of
cells, you cannot easily annotate this
manually. Uh the traditional pipelines
are resource limited. And so we needed
to kind of find a way in in between what
imologists would accept and um what
computitional biologists would be
willing to work with. Uh and so we
develop SC tiger. You can imagine lab
spent a lot of time thinking about the
acronym here. It's for single cell
transcriptional imoprofiling guided by
expert resoning. And so the work the way
it works is you know there's a lot of
that that is known already about the
immune cells. Nobody's going to come and
argue with me about what is a naive tea
cells or an aector tea cells but we want
to be able to quickly get to the
non-contentious label and then do the
discovery of of cells. So we built a
classifier uh and this is an this is not
exactly the classifier because it didn't
fit on the slide but essentially uh you
can split based on lineage um uh using
surface markers and we've developed sets
of gene program genes so that within
minutes we can get to non-contentious
buckets of cells um like the naive the
factor memory and so forth and from
there we do um unbiased clustering that
seems very logical for those of us that
do iminology technology. Um, but these
tools were not in place and so we did
our competition biologist against SC
tiger. They got to the same conclusion
except that biologist took two weeks
shuffling cells between bucket and SC
tiger took a day. And so this is what
we've implemented. So SC tiger in action
if you put this on half of our cells 20
20 million cells across 4,400 samples
and a little bit more than 40
conditions. This is what it looks like.
So uh you can start with the lineage
level the top level of the hierarchy we
can find our lineage you can do another
level of annotation and a third level of
annotation at which point these are the
different number of cells per cell
subset you can also look at them across
know the different conditions and once
we get to this point this is where we're
ready to do um cell type discovery and
so uh I'm going to do a little plug here
for another tool we've been uh
developing for sake of time I don't have
to do demos but I want to tell you about
how we're going to resolve annotation.
So you know if you give me 5 million T
cells to annotate and I give them to a
friend of mine the same 5 million T
cells I promise you we're going to get
to different results and different
annotation and different names. We might
regroup the cells the same way we might
not. We might give them the same
markers. We may not. It's a huge problem
in the community. At least I can talk
about the immune cell atlas community.
So same data same pipeline different
answers. How do we resolve this? And so,
uh, we're launching a cell edition
jamberee. If you're interested, you're
welcome to join. I'm going to show you
about the platform we developed for
this. Everybody's going to be getting
the same, uh, 10 to 15 million cells.
Um, and you will have to provide an
annotation solution. We also have a
challenge tied to providing solution for
cell spectrum and characterization
because these cells are not binary in
nature. uh and we you know there's
always a question of how many cells we
really need to profile to identify
unusual cell types. Now we have so many
cells we can answer this question of how
many donors technologies processing
modalities you need to identify all
predicted cell types over the last four
years with support from Schmidt future
at the broad institute we've actually
developed a cell annotation platform
this is a userfriendly interface where
that is meant to create explore and
store annotation uh we have created the
infrastructure to accumulate and analyze
annotation as I'm going to show you
we're developing um products to offer
automated annotation and it's meant to
get the community to work towards
understand notation. So how does it
work? First you need to move annotation
to be uh subjective to more objective
than definition. So we've defined
clearly 12 annotation metadata fields
that are listed here. So you go beyond
the cell label the full name. Uh we want
the canonical markers but we also want
the markers that you use to define a
cell type. We want to know if there's an
ontology term that exists or what is the
um closest term and these are extremely
well defined metadata field.
And this provides you the necessary
context to more consistently and
reproducibly construct atlases. But also
by having everybody provide these
annotation metadata fields, we can now
properly compare a contrast annotation
between groups and provide feedback. uh
for sake of time I won't do a demo but
um it's actually an interactive tool you
can do rounds of votes you can agree you
can disagree you can split merge
clusters provide your annot annotation
you don't need to know how to code and
these are the type of modules you can do
it's a bit like a Google doc if you wish
you can work in private space and invite
anybody you wish to work with you uh we
actually this is not just precomputed
you can actually do live compute on this
browser which makes this portal
different than other portals. And so you
could come and with our widget you could
actually select cells. It will recmp
compute gen gene expression. It will
recomputee marker genes for you. We can
do gene signatures um differential
expression. You can we're going to be
implementing automated annotation. You
can look at relationship between data
sets. And ultimately the goal is to have
the equivalent of gene card and
summarize annotation post um post
feedback. So this is a quick plugin. If
you want to hear more and see demos, do
reach out. Okay, I'm going to now move
to the more interesting part which I'm
sure is more interesting to you. But I
wanted to kind of plug in what we're up
to. So let's move to biology. And so
okay, we have oh all these millions of
cells. What can you learn from this? Uh
well of course we could try to
understand if there's shift in abundance
across disease gene programs or so much
more. And so um what did we find? These
are examples of analysis we can do. So
abundance resell context which I'm sure
it's the only vignette you want to hear
about. These are analysis engine
programs. But let me tell you a bit
about each. For abundance analysis again
this is with our path for autoimmune
disease broadly. Can you can we find
some some cell subset that shift in
similar way across disease? And I will
admit that um this is a bit generalized
and and one should ask me how these
samples were selected uh later in the
question period so I can expand on this.
So but PDC's we can see in several of
our severe patients are up in many of
these autoimmune disease are done in
many of these autoimmune disease and
some of it is known. So it's it's it's a
good way of assessing
um how good our pipelines are. But you
can also find subset we didn't know
about that are associated with specific
disease or multiple disease. So for
example, we could find proliferating
plasma cell expanded specifically in
lupus here in blue. I should say the
legend here is here on the far right. We
also find a new bell subset we didn't
know about that was specifically
expanded in lupus rare arthritis and
type 1 diabetes has very specific
markers. And when we look at the
embedding, this is this this specific
cluster which we know very little about
that was specifically associated disease
which we're now following up on. Um
I I know the script doesn't need any
introduction to this and so in the
context of autoimmune disease there's
been hundreds of low sides associated
with autoimmune disease. You can ask
very broadly what have we've learned?
We've learned a great deal that there's
a lot of the these risk varants have
very low risk relative risk associated
with them but they tend to be enriched
in a similar biological pathway. And so
the question here is what is the
relevant cellar context to study and you
know as opposed to targeting some of
these specific gene variants that are
have very small relative risk. Could we
think about the cellar phenotype that we
could be targeting instead? So how can
we look at this in the context of the
data sets we are gathering? So first you
know where you you obviously you collect
your risk variance with the highest
predicted effect. In this case for sake
of proof of principle we use those from
open target and we use a method
developed by Zang and all published in
nature genetics in 20 uh 2022
uh to identify the cell types in which
these variants predicted to be active
using what they develop being the single
cell disease relevant score. So the way
it works is that you assess whether a
given cell has excess expression level
of a set of positive risk variance from
you know any G was you wish and we use a
match empirical n distribution to
estimate the walate p value which you
can compute um based on the pool
normalized control score across all gene
sets. So for sake of um demo here I'm
can show you that we see enrichment of
some of these variants associated with
lupus in PDC's.
Now a lot of these um uh genes tied to
different disease susceptibility are not
independent from each other, right?
They're co-expressed with other genes.
So here I'm showing you some example
with traumatator arthritis where we look
at the co-expression
of the different risk genes and
identified several modules across our
data sets. And then we wanted to know
where these modules were expressed if
they were specific and we saw different
patterns. For example, if I take program
five, which is here, you can see it's
expressed across most cells. And I'm
going to show you more detail next
slides. If you look at program three
here, it's actually a little bit more
specific to myoid cells. And program two
here is specific to a very particular
cell types. And I was just going to zoom
in to show you. So I show I mentioned
program five is across all cell types
here. These are this is not a fine grain
annotation. This is just made out of the
pass of optimizing a framework. You have
the different cell type organized by
lineage and you have a dot plot. The
darker um the plot the bigger it is the
more it is expressed in a particular
program. So you can see it's expressed
everywhere. Program three as I show you
was mostly maloid. And then program two
is very specific to one subset we've
defined that had very inflammatory gene
program. And if you zoom in on program
2, which is, you know, here, it's this
particular subset. And it had a lot of
specific markers including TNF file six
al beta specifically expressed here just
to kind of show you the power of some of
these analyses. I may not have the
genotype of these patients, but I can
still tell you what could be uh relevant
here. Now I'm also interested to know if
there's enrichment that share across
multiple disease and I can do very
similar analysis here and in this case
um T-Rex comes up as being enriched for
these susceptibility variants across all
disease. I can you know here I'm showing
some of these different disease some of
these key genes that are up across let's
say lupus type 1 diabetes and RA and I
can find some of these genes driving
these analysis including some some of
these key ISGs interferons so many genes
and I can look at where they land in the
context of our embedding not only do
they land in the T-Rex they actually
land into a very particular subset of
T-Rex that we didn't know about and so
it helps us hone in on to know what's
that subset we should be doing some
follow-up studies on. So I'm showing you
some of the key genes here. As I
mentioned, none of this is published,
but we're sharing this so that we're
hoping to motivate the community to
embrace on these tools. And finally,
I'll skip TCR for sake of time, but gene
program very quickly. So many different
ways of looking at gene programs. I'm
going to show you one vignette using
consensus non- negative metrics
factorization or CNMF here where we're
going we're trying to define gene
modules that are tied to both cellar
identity and factor activities. I'm I'm
using the maloid cell as my example
here. And so, you know, as we try to map
the activities across different cell
type, it's I'm oversimplifying it, but a
combination between these programs that
are going to be tied to it the true cell
identity. Yeah.
And those that are tied to its activity
and and so in terms of this true
identity, um I'm showing you these
different programs. These are micro
genes that define these cell types. not
shocking but we are interested in the
gene programs that are tied to function
that across many many subsets and so for
example we find these IHG program in IG4
disease lupus lupus pediatric which is
known but you know how I told you about
these I1 beta monocytes when they
actually come up as a gene program and
you can actually find them specifically
in IG4 litis and other disease so that's
another way of kind of coming together
so to summarize
uh I showed you some generalized
strategies ies to define share and
distinct programs. We finalized
integration of these 20 million cells
and we're actually using the other 20 20
million cells we have to see how
generalizable our findings are. We've
developed the cell annotation platform.
I've mostly went uh over it but if you
want to hear more about it do reach out
to me. I've shown you that with our
framework we can find shift and
abundance that are sharing across
disease. We can find sort of context
with susceptibility genes. I didn't
cover the TCR, but we can also find TCR
share cross disease along with share
programs and so you can imagine what
we're going to be doing next. If you're
interested about the annotation jam, do
reach out and we're going to be
releasing all our code on GitHub. So if
some of it is useful to you, I'll be
delighted to team up. Um, and finally, I
tried to show pictures of the amazing
team that has been involved. This is my
partner in crime, Gary Reynolds, for
doing this, the Salation Platform team.
uh the whole lab actually more than half
the lab is working on this the funders
and more importantly the patients and
their family none of which would be
possible it wouldn't be possible to do
this work without their partnerships
thank you for your attention
Is this this?
>> Yeah, this is working.
>> Okay, good. Um, I'm I'm interested in
how you in the you started out by saying
you are your assumption is there's a
finite number of cell programs. So I
wonder with the current atlas you have
with with about 30 million cells how
close are you to being able to estimate
sort of the number of potential find
um that fined number and how does it
change in terms of look when you compare
it across ances if you look across
ancestries
>> yeah that's
>> and perturbations and stuff
>> that is a good uh question so I should
say um south subset I don't know about
the sal programs until we model
And so we wanted to know after how many
disease do we stop seeing new cell
subset emerge because we you know if you
start grouping other types of disease at
some point there's only so many cell
subset you can identify and we can
downsample our data sets to see when we
start saturating and only in the context
of of course what I presented which is
infectious autoimmune disease normal
pediatric and adult I didn't mention
this we have pediatric and adult that
are all non-treated
then we don't see more signal of course
once you prepost treatment is a
different story. You're completely
correct in terms of ancestry. Uh as we
add more ancestry, we may see a bit more
diversity. I didn't cover this, but we
actually have representative samples
from uh almost everywhere in the world,
but we definitely are skewed towards
Caucasian. So, the next iteration will
actually add another 3,000 samples from
South America and 2,000 samples from um
Africa. That will help with this. And
then we'll be able to estimate Great.
Thank you, Ben.
>> Lovely talk, Chloe. Um, my questions on
the cell annotation and particularly how
you're dealing with the sort of uh
subset of transcripts that you're
actually sampling in the single cell
technologies because as I understand it,
we're getting maybe 15 to 25% of the
transcripts per cell. And I noticed in
your sort of flowcharts there were
required genes for cell identity. But
given the amount of missing data, do you
worry about annotation problems cropping
up there or is the kind of overwhelming
bulk of the data sufficient to still get
you to the right place?
>> That's a good I love that question Neil.
So first I should mention that for
vessel annotation we also added over 200
surface protein because imologists love
surface protein and that's how you can
relate the gene signature to surface
protein and relate the legacy knowledge.
We've also included TR and BCR data
because it can help identify specific T
cell subsets. Now of course if you look
at one cell at a time in human data
you're right that we're capturing you
know 1500 to 2,000 genes. Some of it is
is dropout but some of it is also you're
looking at primary cells. So at any time
in point in time you don't express all
genes and so once we've defined you know
groups of cell with similar features
that you think have unique identity you
actually can do pseudob and that then
then you capture a lot more genes and so
like that's a that's a way around it and
then the single cell community is
already doing a lot of annotation. is
all over the place. And so there's a
there's a need to start like agreeing
like maybe you and I would call the same
cells two different ways, but it'd be
great to know that we're calling the
same cells to different ways. We can
build that catalog of synonyms and
that's kind of what this platform will
also help us get to. Yeah.
>> Great. We'll have one final question.
This
>> Oh, thank you. Um Chloe, this is
amazing. The what what you've built is s
such a service for the community. I
wanted to ask you about multiomics. So
some of these data sets also have
attack. How's the HCA thinking about
incorporating attack because it would be
incredibly useful to build a similar
resource and leverage your cell type
annotation platforms for for attack.
>> Yeah. So uh the the CAP can be adapted
to any species and any modality. And
then in terms of HG and multiomics,
we're all for it. You know we the reason
you saw so many single cell is that we
had to start with the modality that was
most out there and most scalable and
cost effective and you know a lot of it
was single cell with with protein which
I didn't disclose in TCR there's not
that many multimodel data set out there
and I think it's also tied to the cost
of generating such data at scale uh we
are actually integrating such data set
but to be completely honest it's a very
small percentage of the of the data and
as part of HT 2.0 I know that's now
being launched. One of the pillar is to
push for multiomics and trying to find
partnerships with industries so we can
drop the cost but it may make more sense
to kind of push such effort on very
specific contexts or disease or cell
subsets where we actually need to map
the regulatory landscape and this is
where partnership with this community
could kind of help synergize such
effort. Thank you for welcoming me.
Thank you for your time.
>> Thanks Chloe.
[Applause]