so before I introduce um today's lecture
I want to just mention that this is this
lecture um which is being presented in
conjunction with the broad MIT seminar
series is really um the MIT chemical
biology group lecture and so um it was a
longstanding lecture at MIT that was
first first held in
1979 and this lecture was in endowed by
um Ty Shen so Ty Shen was uh postto with
Arthur cop at
MIT in the
1950s and he worked on conversion of
carbohydrates to synthetic intermediates
so of course he was super ahead of his
time in recognizing some of the most
important
biomolecules he then joined Merc and um
there he was an execu he became an
executive uh director and he in he uh
developed the drug in Dano
methes um a leading uh
NAD so he had an illustrious career at
MC and then he really thought that one
thing that is important at universities
is to have amazing external speakers
come because they can really change the
landscape and give people new ideas and
um and so he endowed this lectureship to
provide MIT with the opportunity to have
incredible outstanding scientists come
and many of the people who have come um
have gone on to win Nobel Prize and so
um it's an incredible group of people
that have come through this lecture ship
I can just mention a few that are in
that category um Carolyn
bertoy uh let's see I got to scan
through this
list
um well I'll just mention um we've had a
couple of people who have won the the
um uh a number of important Awards you
can you can hopefully tomorrow pick up a
copy of this brochure so this is a two
lecture series there's a lecture today
and then tomorrow we'll have a lecture
in a hopefully little bigger room so
that everyone can
fit um so just to mention this um is
being conducted in uh along with the
broad MIT lecture series and you can see
um also that we have a great lineup for
that lecture series as well and we want
to um again thank the sponsors of that
lecture series which is up on the board
so really MIT and then these units are
the major sponsors of this so um let me
go ahead and do the more important thing
um for me to focus on now um in addition
to the great
acknowledgements um let me just
introduced Jim and I'm have my little
cheat sheet here so I make sure that I
get things right so um today's lecture
Jim Wells is really in the spirit of the
amazing people that have held this
lectureship previously um Jim started
his career at Genentech where he was a
founding member of the protein um
engineering department and in at
Genentech he did a number of things he
really uh showed
how enzymes can be engineered to have
new
properties and his his lab engineered uh
sisin to have a number of properties
that the enzyme didn't intrinsically
have he then went on to think about um
not only how enzymes work but how
protein protein interactions are
involved in signaling and he was a
Pioneer in understanding and unraveling
how how human growth hormone works a
paradigmatic signaling
pathway he and in the course of this he
always uses his knowledge his deep
knowledge of chemistry enzymes protein
chemistry to design new and think about
new therapeutic strategies that can
teach us new biology and um Advanced
medicine so he not only um figured out
these signaling Pathways he also
introduced common strategies that we use
today like alanine scanning
mutagenesis so in 1998 he left genitech
to start a new company
sunis and there he was the founder and
the head and that that uh company really
pioneered the method of tethering using
uh coent linkages to identify uh lead
compounds that might occupy protein
binding sites so again a very clever use
of chemistry to find new uh lians so in
2005 he uh went to
UCSF and there he continued to on this
strategy so he's developed um he studied
protease signaling Cascades he showed
how proteases could be co-opted to to
investigate uh pathways on a global
scale he um he developed many many new
methods and you you will see that in his
talk every time I read a Wells paper I'm
like oh that is so cool that's a really
neat new way to think about the problem
and so Jim just keeps doing this over
and over and over and probably many of
you have seen some of his recent work
studying the surface home and also
really exciting work um developing new
strategies for proximity labeling so
again and again just new and exciting
things so Jim we are so happy to have
you here and we're really looking
forward to your lecture which is
entitled I don't
[Applause]
know okay can can you hear me
okay okay great um wow Laura that was a
great uh intro and I have to say you
have to love the spontaneity of this
woman just had to deal with it something
that collapsed downstairs now up here
everybody's here seated it's just
awesome to see everybody here I'm so
honored to be here today uh whenever I
come and and I wish I have I'll probably
take a screenshot of this and send it
back home to my to my family uh it's
like the Hollywood of science you know
it's like everybody it compacted into a
very small area with the scientific
intensity that's it's it's uh just
really hard to beat it's just an amazing
place so I appreciate that and if you
don't mind I am going to take a
picture let's see get you guys to say
hello wave or how about K La
Harris there we go all right I got
it all right right well so thank you so
much Laura for this invitation and to
give this I'm honored to be part of this
group um just a uh uh want to start here
um so that ball there with a bunch of
fingers on it is meant to be a cell
member and a cartoon of a cell memberane
and and what my lab is focused on is how
the cell surfaceome changes from a
healthy state to a disease State and
then build modulators to modulate this
set of proteins membrane proteins
there's about 5,000 genes that encode
the uh membrane surfaceome and secreted
protein uh set so quarter of nearly a
quarter of the genome is devoted to it
um and it's an incredible compartment
for drug Discovery half the drugs small
molecule drugs engage this compartment
and virtually all of the biologics drugs
do and then you may wonder why there's a
pirate ship sitting on top of that cell
that's meant to be my lab I consider
them Pirates
we we behave like Pirates we break
things and then we put them back
together we hunt for Treasure Etc um and
the other aspect of this is I call
pirating proteins to attack the C cancer
surface Zone because unlike the great
minds of David Baker or Bill deg gr who
would buil build things from scratch um
my lab focuses just on taking parts from
nature fashioning them in a way that can
be utilized to do these uh these
activities so um my uh inspiration for
the surfaceome came from the simple
micrograph uh from a colleague of uh uh
UCSF colleague sarra bapi who is
studying how kras and other enogen alter
the the alter cells when I saw this
micrograph of going from a um from a
what I call a fried egg to a Quant all
due to the trans transformation by kras
I was just going what the hell what's
going on in the cell surface here and so
we got really intrigued that's was sort
of our our ENT entry into this about 10
years ago when we started this work and
so we wondered can we find kasas induced
surface targets and if we did even in
these isogenic comparisons we might been
be able to identify new service targets
that we could attack uh right which then
was
undruggable thanks now to Kon shokat and
his his work it's now is druggable but
then it wasn't we could attack kras from
the outside with the uh you know the
consequence of kras uh transformation so
that was our rationale and it started
here with with h a postto in my lab
Kevin Le young and a really talented
graduate student Alex martinko that
utilized a self-surface uh capture
method that was developed in Rudy aol's
lab where you can take um you know there
are carbohydrates on the surface of
cells right
Laura and you can take those
carbohydrates and mildly priate oxidize
their cyc acids for instance to alahh
that alahh creates a handle for biotin
hydrazide a hydrazide with biotin on it
to label those membrane proteins and
carbohydrates are are very unique to the
cell surface especially complex ones and
we that way we could enrich the cell
surfaceome because as I mentioned it's
only uh you know a quarter of the genome
is encoded there but the concentration
of membrane proteins is about 1% the
concentration of so cytosolic proteins
so yes you could do this by mass
spectrometry just lysate mass
spectrometry and people do um but uh we
prefer these enrichment methods because
it gives us a much deeper dive into
what's there um so using a KAC approach
where we take the the Kos transform
cells or or the um uh the vector control
we can compare what was there and you
get these volcano plots where you see
here uh from0 to six in log two units
the induction of proteins from kayas and
it's a bidirectional remodeling event
some things go up like these proteins
here some things go down like these
proteins here and so it's not just that
the enco Gen induces all of this new
protein expression no it's remodeling
because the cell is learning to do
something new it's learning to be
transformed and it's learning to
metastasize and in fact when we map
these onto the sort of Hallmarks of
cancer you would see that most of these
things are involved in tumor
metastases uh immune Invasion uh other
other forms that are well known to to
induce uh uh uh transformation knowing
these Ecto domains we chose the single
pass ones uh which have just a single
Ecto domain a transmembrane domain an
intracellular domain we clipped off the
EO Ecto domains expressed those and then
generated antibodies to these targets to
then follow them in different uh uh in
different cancer settings and from there
some really interesting things came out
of that this one protein cdcp1 Cub
domain containing protein one which is
an anti- anous protein uh we' made some
antibodies to that and those have been
licensed out several of these others
have been as well and so we use that as
a sort of as our launch pad for getting
into the surfaceome and what it what it
does find out what's upregulated in the
surfaceome but there are many other
things that happen on the surfaceome and
cancer and one of them most important is
proteolysis so it's well known that this
the the business of metastasis happens
with uh remodeling the tme and that's
the induction of of protasis for
instance
as are many other things so proteases
can are involved in a number of things
on the outside of cells they're involved
in protein shedding many of the growth
factors that are produced in cyto kindes
are produced as membrane bound things
they're shed by proteases and then that
goes off and then activates neighboring
milu and or autocrine uh activation of
them uh themselves they receptor
activation events in fact most of the
proteolytic events that happen on the
surface of cells that are well annotated
are activation events shedding is that
way okay um and these these protolytic
events uh are associated with all of
these different phenotypes here growth
survival death angiogenesis Invasion
metastasis inflammation immune Invasion
and through knockout studies many of the
proteases that that are doing this work
are shown down
below so it's interesting because um of
the post transational modifications that
occur on the surface of a cell and
there's not that many only about a
handful compared to inside the cell
where there's many and they uh
phosphorilation def phosphorilation
ubiqutination de ubiquit all of these
they're all reversible inside so there's
the writers and erasers inside but
outside the cell there's only the
writers the all these things are
irreversible and proteolysis is an
obvious one and it's the most highly
regulated one too so even though there's
glycosilation out there which is super
important the the the regulatory
features of that are not what they are
certainly in cancer with proteolysis so
we wanted to understand this uh um the
proteases involved and especially what's
being cleaved on the cell surface so we
could identify some of the things that
we don't know about that we would that
we would find out about so that was the
question we asked can we discover the
proteic cleavage sites on the surface of
cells because while we know a lot about
the proteases very little was known
about this in fact when we started this
work there were only about three dozen
annotated proteolytic events which had
been characterized to occur on the
outside of the cell I told you there's
5,000 proteins there's got to be more
than just three dozen so um to study
what was actually being uh what was
being cleaved on the surface of cells we
hearkened back to A protein that uh
Laura mentioned uh that we were working
on a Genentech s liin and we had
fashioned that to be like resistant to
oxidants which then turned into
detergent and we fashioned it to have a
better specificity we also with two
mutations and these were rational
mutations these were these were not
quote directed Evolution mutations these
were based on structural inspection and
mechanistic insight some of which came
from Tom Kaiser's group with two
mutations we were able to take sisin
which is a ferocious protease found here
in
tide this was actually I think that that
suyon may have been the first engineered
protein that was sold but protein
engineered protein and it was sold here
for the work uh for uh use in in tide
okay so we with two mutations you could
convert This ferocious protease this
sering uh 221 cysteine because it's a
cysteine class protease and making more
room for the Cy this allows it to to
form an ACL tho ACL enzyme intermediate
so this um because cystines are much
more prone to amiz than than hydroly it
we could then use it as a peptid ligase
where uh the alpha amine of a second
peptide would come in displace that and
create an uh a new peptide bond so we
could use this for synthesis it didn't
work so well at first but with this
additional mutation here proling 225
alanine allows this more room so it
actually carries out this almost as
efficiently as it will carry out
proteolysis this enzyme then has been
used in a lot of different uh uh
applications for instance blockwise
peptide synthesis um yeah great to talk
to the uh uh uh the group today who's
making uh synthetic proteins here this
might be helpful there um cyclic
peptides bio conjugation but the use
that we were going to apply it to is
this one here which we call n
terminomics where we can tag the newly
formed uh uh proteolytic events with
satell liase plus a peptide Esther tag
so the way that works is that we take um
satellite we take our uh extract this
was first applied to study apoptosis in
in cells we took lates from cells which
which would undergo apoptosis namely
caspase cleavage that would generate new
ENT termin if we had sellig gaze in this
tevest peptide which has a a biotin on
one end a tev proteas cite in the middle
and a and a a mass tag which would stay
Remnant once tagged we could generate
this ACL enzyme intermediate with s
liase and then the new ENT Terminus from
A protein that had been cleaved or
resident uh uh uh already cleaved would
come in displace that now it's
biotinated we can pull that out and
sequence then the thing the uh the
protein that was now uh contained this
Mass tag and that gives us exactly the
Precision of where it was cleav because
it's sitting there right on the alpha
amine the enzyme will not tag will not
use Epsilon Amino groups of Lysine it
will only use uh the uh the Alpha amines
from uh from peptides so we fashioned
this to um to then be for apoptosis
we've been uh studying that that aspect
but we wanted to use it on the on the uh
cell surface so enter um Amy weeks a
postto who's now at University of
Wisconsin Amy then engineered additional
variants of SLE lias to make it uh even
broader specificity and showed that we
could take um uh uh tried to apply
subtle lias to the cell surface but
unfortunately when we did we got very
few peptide IDs when we just added
soluble sellig gaze with the tag very
few IDs and Amy came up with the idea
that hey maybe the thing to do is to
tether it onto the cell surface and that
way rather than trying to tag thing from
from the outside we tag them on the lawn
of the cell so like rather than mowing
the lawn with a helicopter you mow it
with a lawn mower on the ground okay so
so using this we showed that we were
getting now many many many more IDs the
the liation occurs very quickly within
10 minutes we basically saturate the
cell surfaceome with uh of the intermed
that we could uh access you inactivate
the active site cysteine now with an
allinine it's dead so there's no so we
knew it was coming from there then enter
uh Katie Schaefer and Irene Louie um a
postto and graduate student in the lab
and they were able to make another
variant of this that did not require
genetic uh engineering to get it into
the membrane but rather just simple uh
um attachment because what we did was we
put a uh an oxim on the end Terminus of
sleaze and then with mild priet
oxidation we could then jump on the
sugars that were there so this allows us
to label not just through genetic
engineering of the cell but through any
cell primary cells uh uh tumor cells Etc
we could simply add this agent it'll
stick on the cell surface and allow
labeling and doing that we could show
robust labeling on the cell surface with
sub liase when it's fluorescently tagged
and very robust um bation now of cell
surface uh proteins um this allowed us
to pick this
aminooxy uh uh attachment uh liant
because we got more robust labeling with
that so then we started labeling the
cell surface on first of just um uh some
uh primary cells nkt cells CDH cd4s or
some tumor cell lines adherent cells and
what we found was that uh we identified
for each of these different cell lines
we identified about 300 different
proteolytic events so imagine we were at
36 and now we're over 300 per cell line
so we in total we identified something
like in these six cell uh cell lines we
identified almost 500 proteins the
interus of them um uh uh and about and
we of course we see signal peptide
cleavage this is about 11% of our uh
cuts are that we also see then um other
cleavages and especially those in the
extracellular region of the of the of
the protein so remember these proteins
have in some cases very large
extracellular domains most most of the
cuts we see are are in those domains um
now most of them we don't know their
their functions we don't know what they
do but um it it provides a lot of Gris
for study since the annotated literature
would suggest many of these perhaps most
of these are going to be gain a function
in their uh uh in their character uh
interestingly we get uh both type one
and type two remember type two is turned
around backwards so the C Terminus is
out the you think about that if you've
cut it there is no Alpha amine that's
present on the thing that might be shed
so what that means is for this class
these are proteins for which the the
cleave fragment remains attached to its
it its parent um we also there's a whole
bunch of multipass cleavages that happen
now um some of those uh are known to be
um activating uh like the uh par for
instance which is a trans it's a 7tm
receptor that gets activated that's the
only one that's annotated but there's
many more that that are here that we
don't yet know
about so then we wondered do these
enogen induce differences and to study
that we then compared uh for instance um
different uh enogen
transformed uh uh isogenic cell lines
and here what I'm showing is uh kras
versus the empty Vector this is showing
the uh cell surface proteolysis
enrichment that we got again we get
bidirectional effects on proteolysis
some events go up some events go down
and along the Y AIS what we're showing
is the expression differences so using
cell surface capture we can determine
how much of each protein is there and so
in each case you can see that there's uh
some proteins go up in expression some
go down I showed you that earlier um
this is also showing that there's really
only a mild correlation between the
extent of proteolysis and the expression
levels now that that's actually really
good news if you want to look at these
as potential drug targets especially the
cleave form because it provides you an
and gate for um specificity and I'm
going to tell you a story about that uh
in in just a minute um so we saw as I
mentioned a number uh about three dozen
have been annotated some are shown here
in in uh uh red dots we find these
cleavage sites in precisely the same
cleavage site that has been annotated in
in the literature so that gives you a
sense of the resolution of the method
the accuracy um and one of our favorites
is this one
cdcp1 I'll come back to that um you see
here if we compare an isogenic cell line
that's her two versus kras transformed
generally you you'll see a similarities
between these two they're both very
powerful uh uh proliferative enogen
you can see that we get um most pink on
the right side of this and most mostly
blue on the down on the left side of
this um but there's a lot of differences
between these two so there's customized
proteases that are being built here
which are um specific at least in
aggregate for what they can be uh what
they will cut so um enter this group of
posts uh giia Joe and Shian Lim uh who's
uh
G is currently at uh University of
Chicago and Shan's at jentech they
studied one of the proteins that we
found cleaved and that's this protein
cdcp1 cdcp1 is a uh has two large
domains on the outside transmembrane
domain and an intracellular domain and
it's involved in this process of aus so
when a cell dissociates from the cell
its Brethren sister its tribe and it's
it's out there in free floating normally
cells will undergo
apoptosis um they know they're doing
something wrong illegal maybe um and and
so uh uh but this protein if induced it
will induce survival from uh anoas and
in fact we saw that here this is a a an
immortalized pancreatic cell which has
very low expression of cdcp1 but as soon
as you add Kass you get a lot of
expression of cdcp1 and in most of these
pancreatic cell lines which have Kass
you see this cleave form um cdcp1 is
really interesting we found that after
it's cut in one of three places in this
this is an alpha fold model we do not
yet have a structure of it but um right
here in this region cut one cut two cut
three are is a nested set of three
different cut sites all dibasic in their
character um that can leave uh give rise
to this band that's uh shown here that
would be the the C terminal fragment but
these two these two stay together in the
membrane once it's cut it does not leave
so we could express them as uh coexpress
them and these two domains cut here and
there would actually assemble as a
single antigen
um so it uh we imagine that it looks
like this um we wondered could we make
an antibody that would see this cleave
form because if we did we'd be able to
get something would be much more
selective for cancer cells than normal
cells um and to do that we we used uh
our phase display Library um Fab phase
display Library where we have um the uh
fulllength cdcp1 as an FC Fusion antigen
this is a Decoy for us so we take our
Fage Library we we uh um take we the
Fades that would bind the full length
and then positively select for Fades
that have the cleave form on them
because we can coexpress the Ecto uh the
N Terminus and C terminal domain and
this way we could positively select for
Fage that would bind to the cleave form
and negatively select for things that
bind to the full
length and indeed we found such uh such
molecules such antibodies this cl3 a two
nanomolar binder you can see here by B
binds to the cut form 3 it actually
binds to all three of the cut forms so
it's probably not binding right over the
proteolytic site but it's binding nearby
and sees that confirmational difference
and it does not bind to the full length
now if we take these these antibodies
and we fashion them with uh an ADC a
drug we put a poisonous drug like an Ora
Statin analog on them
mmaf um you can see if we put them Just
into a mou
um wild type Mouse not engineered at all
just looking at safety here you can see
these three curves at the top are
different dose ranges of the antibody to
the cleave form of uh
cdcp1 and these others which show some
dramatically uh toxic effects are the
ones which have which are directed to
the fulllength
cdcp1 so in other words making something
to the CLE form had much greater safety
profile than ones to the full length and
then we uh with our colleague Mike Evans
at UCSF we then went and um uh uh built
an rlt version of this with litium uh
177 on the uh on the antibody and you
can see here unabated the tumor will
grow uh wildly um and then it two
different doses uh higher um low dose in
a higher dose you could see what could
dramatically Abate the tumor growth so
this is an example where you have an
antigen you know it's functional because
it's uh important for the the the tumor
itself and in fact it's synthetically
lethal for Ras if you knock it out and
but you do have it in other tissues some
other tissues and you don't want to go
there you want to be only on the cancer
then Target the thing that's the the
consequence of uh a proteolysis and we
can get there um Gia then went on to do
some other really interesting uh uh
selections we wondered well we can build
things to the cleave form but what about
protecting these cleavage events so she
developed a similar kind of approach we
call them bandab bodies like
Band-Aids and uh in in so that the idea
was can we block proteolysis by building
an antibody that will sit right over the
site of prot proteolysis and prevent the
cleavage at all and uh and there's other
consequences not just proteins like
cdcp1 or fa2 that undergo this
activating cutting events but also uh
proteases themselves they are all built
as pro-enzymes that propiece has to be
cleaved to make them active could we
find uh bandab bodies that would protect
against that cleavage and and therefore
inhibit that uh
MMP okay so what we did in this case was
to the trick was we we're going to use
again differential
selection uh but we we're going to do it
where we select against the um uh
binding to the the cleavage site to
begin with and only and and bind
everywhere outside and then select four
directly for that that uh that cut site
and so what we did was we here's the POI
this would be the cleav protein of
Interest this is be the uh where the
cleavage site is we built a mutant poy
which mutated this cleavage site now
what we do is we use this as a negative
selection to to scrub away Fage that
would bind to everywhere outside of that
cleavage site in a negative selection
mode and then uh then use this antigen
which is basically just a wild type
protein with an intact cleavage site to
collect those Fades that would bind to
that and and indeed that that worked we
could get we call this epitope directed
antibody selection it's actually way
easier than directed design I I'll show
you a couple examples of this we did
this in uh uh six different six
different examples of this and every
time we were able to find an antibody
that would block the proteolytic uh
cleavage um so we showed that for
instance on uh in in the case of uh um
oh uh I was going to skip this because
uh this case here where we have cdcp1
again we wanted to find an antibody that
would sit over there so we built that
the the poy that had poisoned these cut
sites and then selected on the wild type
and indeed if you add uh
cdcp1 with a um uh uh without the
blocking antibody in plasma plasman
which can cleave it um you can see that
you can protect against thatle cleavage
with any of these antibodies here um we
can also use um uh uh have been able to
show that this processing of
cdcp1 is going on inside the cell
because if we take those antibodies
which we've shown can block the
processing they don't prevent the
surface processing that we see in fact
we showed that by uh taking the gene for
the CLE for the CLE form antibody
expressing it in coexpressing it with
cdcp1 and in that case we can prevent
shown here the cleavage of cdcp1 in
other words if they're expressed
together as they traffic through the ER
they you can block the the cleavage but
if you just add the Fab the purified Fab
outside it doesn't prevent it so the
proteases can be active in the ER and on
the surface of the cell this is an
experiment that shows us that the
processing is happening in the ER okay
we've also applied it to uh uh mmp9
which blocks uh uh uh by blocking the
pro-sequence uh cleavage we're able to
find antibodies that prevent the um uh
the activation of the pro uh MMP because
it will autoactivate itself and you can
see some antibodies don't work like
these still gets activated but these
here prevent the processing and those
that are most effective at preventing
processing also suppress migration of
cells in a Cell migration assay so these
kinds of approaches I think are going to
be very important we've also done it
with mmp1 and mmp3 you can get highly
selective Inhibitors this way and I just
have to say it is so freaking easy to do
this this is not a rocket science design
project to direct things there all you
need is the differential selection of
what you want against what you don't
want and you can uh you can get there so
it's very effective um so I may have
time to tell you a bit about what we've
been doing in the protein degradation
area which is another area we've been
modulating uh uh the cell surfaceome um
as you know antibodies are super
important modalities about half the
Pharma big Blockbuster drugs are
biologics these days most of them are
antibodies um and uh there's one of the
things is so cool about them is that you
have five shots on goal you can bake a a
functional inhibitor you can also bake a
uh antibody drug conjugate or get the
immune cell involved with adc's antibody
directed cellular cytotoxicity or bites
or carte cells um so there's a lot of
different things you can do there's
another modality uh we were inspired to
uh to investigate which is can these
these antibodies be harnessed for
extracellular targeted protein
degradation
and uh this is inspired by the work on
protax and glues all intracellular so we
call this uh extracellular targeted
protein degradation the the sort of the
pioneer of this was this work done by
Tom aawa at Shou guy who developed these
sweeping antibodies that will bind a
soluble protein take it into the uh get
taken up by the
fcrn uh and so soluble protein shown
here in these little green things and
then bind antibody binds it'll get uh
moved into the endosome uh where it gets
acidified they've engineered it so you
can get losal release in the endosome
and then it will leave the the Target in
to go to the lome and then finally uh
reappear so it can do work this
catalytically the the first uh uh second
example of this was work from Carolyn
berto's lab using what they call LX
which which are these um antibodies that
use a glycan recycling receptor the uh
the Manos chloride independent mano6
phosphate receptor so this binds uh uh
gly uh poly uh glycans um and by
fashioning uh he had to sort of uh
attach a dozen or so of these glycans
chains to the antibody that would then
if the antibody binds a cellular
membrane Target then it will traffic it
in into the lome for degradation or you
could also use it for soluble um
degradation of proteins um as well if
the antibodies directed to a a soluble
protein um so that's that that those
were Inspirations for us and um of
course the the the protac or and
molecular glue area is one where you
have protein of interest uh E3 liay are
brought together with a small molecule
that binds each independently um a glue
would be where it's one combine both um
but in any case once you put them next
to each other you'll get the degradation
ubiqutination of the poy and uh in
subsequent
degradation so we were inspired because
there are some E3 liases which are known
which are transmembrane E3 liases this
family over here one in particular rnf43
that's involved in Wind signaling has an
E3 liaye domain we wondered could we
bind build an antibody that binds the
Ecto domain of barn f43 and have this
bind a protein of interest is in a
bispecific format namely uh we did it
with first with pdl1 would we get
degradation of the product and in fact
this did work we're able to degrade
pdl1 uh egfr cdcp1 and actually now a
number of other Targets in a company
that's been formed called Epi
biologics um and uh uh that uh
degradation is uh specific to the uh
sorry um that degradation requires both
arms to work single arm uh uh antibodies
do not degrade pdl1 only the bispecific
does um It's Time dependent uh it's
actually slower than a protac protacs
are tend to be uh faster um if you knock
down rnf43 it protects if you have more
or less of the rnf43 on cells it uh
there's a dose response for the amount
that's there generally you have to be
within about tfold POI and uh degrader
so it can work in a um uh with less uh
degrader there than than than po um it
requires the lome based on inhibitor
studies and um they there's uh a lot of
uh uh cool s about this along with uh
additional um uh antibodies that can be
brought to bear so um we've also and I
know I'm running out of time so I'm kind
of speeding up here but I also wanted to
tell you about another variant of this
which doesn't use a a transmembrane e3
lies like a Protek or or a um uh or a
glue but rather uses just natural
recycling characteristics especially
prevalent in cyto kindes that's the way
they're turned off so we said well
rather than having antibody that binds
to the uh to the degrader let's just use
a natural ligan that binds to the
degrader the cyto receptor fashion
something on the other side that binds
the POI and can we get those degraded
and this is the work of Katarina pants
uh from couple of years ago and uh yes
we were able to for instance using a
degrader to um uh that would uh that
would uh uh bind to the cxcr7 receptor
which binds C
cxcl12 uh we were able to degrade both a
membrane proteins egfr as well as uh
soluble
proteins so um we're really excited
about this and uh this is just showing
the degradation of egfr you can see
before treatment and after treatment
egfr just takes a major hit and it's
very specific if you look at the if you
do surface omics as I described earlier
you ask what's being hit in this example
here it was very specific for egfr
versus other things that could be there
um and it kills better than just the
normal antibody wood and uh so we're
also interested in using it for soluble
proteins for instance we showed this in
VF it can take up vef effectively from
outside so all of the soluble proteins
that you can think about could also be
amenable here um so uh we're excited
about that this uh company epi biologics
is formed is actually has three
different Mo modalities we call them all
epacs depending on the degradation
mechanism that they employ and they've
been very effective in degrading egfr as
an example shown here but a number of
other targets and they promote the the
life of of of animals when given to
those that have tumors um so when you
think about this field it's I I'm it's a
very exciting area this uh extracellular
targeted protein degradation it sort of
reminds me of like the early days of
flying because there's many different
variants of this in fact uh at Epi they
now have 230 different degrader systems
that they've identified in screens and
whatnot um and it's uh so it's on its
way I would say it's it's kind of in
this stage here maybe the Spitfire stage
you know we haven't seen the first
clinical trial with these but I think
they're soon to come I should mention
that that the sweeping antibody uh area
uh Tom agawa has an approved antibody
for the il6 il6 receptor complex that
circulates so it's shown that
degradation of those soluble complexes
can have therapeutic benefit so um with
that I I just like to say I hope you get
the sense of sort of pirating proteins
for extracellular biology I think it's a
really exciting area um this is my lab
here and I'm totally indebted to with
I'm just can't believe I get to work
with these great people here two of my
former lab members are
here and excited to see them here and uh
so with that I'll stop and take any
[Applause]
questions oh there we go didn't take
long hi thank thank you um great talk
I'm I guess surprised that the
protolytic cleavage of CDC P1 happens
seemingly entirely inside the vesicle
and not in the surface do you think
there's potential to identify a
protolytic
surfome that you could split into a kind
of exclusively surface cleaved lineage
and a
pre-processing cleavage step
yeah that's a that's a great question um
I well it's well known that there are
very important proteolytic events that
do happen in the ER many of the hormone
activating events happen there that are
constitutive using the what are called
Pro uh protein
convertases uh or uh uh CX like or furin
like proteases um but most of the
proteases are not there most of them are
sitting on the cell membrane and they
get activated like the mmps ETC so I
think uh in our proteolytic in our
proteomics approach we can't distinguish
where the event happened it just appears
at the cell surface and then we know
it's there but when you get then
antibodies to it there is now a way that
you can actually dissect where it
happened based on adding the antibody
did you block it or expressing the
antibody did you block it yeah
maybe um I'll just follow up on that
question do you think that there's
something um different about like
proteostasis or something in the tumor
cells so you get that cleavage prior to
it coming onto the membrane you know is
there do you guys have any insight into
that yeah Laura I think of I think of
the cell is basically bristl in with
with um preformed signaling molecules
now many of them are in the latent form
and they're just waiting for a
protolytic event to come along and
launch them like a missile it happens as
soon as the you don't have to make it
you don't have to transport it's already
there and that's the way most many
growth factors are activated so I think
this is the tip of the iceberg here
which is why one of the areas that we're
really excited about is using some of
the proximity labeling methods I'll talk
about tomorrow to deorphanize these
cleave fragments to find out where they
go because there's so much we don't know
about that aspect of it and that's so
I'm really excited about
that any more trainee questions because
I okay here we
go hey thank you Jim so uh you mentioned
um that you we're picking these targets
based on for example overexpression of
certain enogen in isogenic settings but
um from the perspective of thinking
about Therapeutics in human would it be
necessary to do the profiling in many
tissues or how do you think about
therapeutic Windows yeah absolutely so
we get an idea of what might be there
and what candidates might be there from
those isogenic
experiments um and we can also test if
they are from those candidates we can
find out are they synthetically lethal
so we can get or look at them by dep map
for instance and look at that but you're
absolutely right this is not from that
data there to a therapeutic there's a
lot more validation that needs to be
done multiple cell lines I showed the
the pancreatic cell line panel that we
did for instance and then uh more and
more my lab is getting into whole tumor
proteomics to identify these events
there and that
although you know there's an upside and
downside to that the upside being it's
in the re it's in a real tumor and it's
you know somebody had that the downside
is it's not renewable you know so unless
you're in pdxs or you know xenographs so
great question there's these are just
early Discovery tools that get us into
candidates and mo molecules that can
bind to to them to probe them in more
depth in a real uh you know real t
setting
yeah I'm going to allow faculty to ask
questions
no
anybody you talk me through a little bit
about the extracellular tpd I'm thinking
the intracellular protein you're going
to get it ubiquinated and then the
proteome Chomps the intracellular part
what happens to the extracellular
stock well in a case where we're using
that
rnf43 um inhibitor studies suggests that
after ubiqutination they do ubiquitinate
their their target um they uh much of it
goes through the lome um there's not
there is some inhibition with proteosome
Inhibitors but most of it goes to the
lome and there you know it's you know it
would be chewed up to uh certainly the
Ecto domain would be chewed off and then
what happens to the rest of it I don't
know the intracellular domain Etc I
don't know maybe that's released but uh
the Ecto domain would certainly be a
Target and then we see it then degraded
when we look at the the the whole
protein you see degradation of any
Associated
proteins yeah yes yeah do you do you see
any degradation of the uh Associated
protein when you do the extracellular
and and the second question was that
what do you think the resistance
mechanism will be so suppose you you
have an egfr degrader and a classic
inhibitor versus the egfr degradation
mechanism that you are using what would
be the difference between the two
resistance
mechanism yeah if you if it were a small
molecule for instance in inhibiting the
kise domain of egfr then it's known that
you get resistance to the kise inhibitor
binding um in general uh the kind of
resistance you'd get here would be if
there's a trafficking mutation that
would uh affect getting to the lome so
maybe it would just recycle back um uh
Yosi yardin group has shown that uh
comparing kyes small molecule inhibitors
for her two to antibody resistance it's
harder to get them to the antibody
because you have to disrupt a protein
protein interface of the antibody but
you can get them um those are the kinds
of resistance that we would imagine
would would occur oh you asked about
what else gets sucked into the into the
wood chipper yeah so I was actually
surprised that more doesn't because we
now know I'll talk talk tomorrow about
about horizontal signaling in in
membrane complexes there's actually
around egfr there can be up to 30
different proteins that visit that in
the on versus off state of egfr so I was
a little surprised that it was as
selective as it as it is and it may not
be always that that way
yeah thanks
am well it it's getting late so if there
are no further questions let's thank Jim
again and please come tomorrow for the
second installation of the talk