okay so today we're just going to go
through some topics and um we stop me
when you when you are I want to um first
thing I'll do is just talk a little bit
about some of the things in my research
and some of them are connected with a
topic that's lingering in the back of
this class that um but that's not
explicit and that is this the second
adjacent field of statistical and pure
math um sort of computational or
musicology research that is not directly
computational so we'll do a little bit
with that um you'll find on the on the
canvas site there's a very cool uh I
think it's like nine page it's really
short it has lots of pictures uh article
that I'd like you to take some time to
read by Leon H uh hackford who um wrote
a whole book on mathematics and music
which is very cool but I find the most
cool thing about that is the Final
Chapter how not to mix math and music
and the ways people have mixed math and
music and got things really um wrong so
uh might bring that up a little bit more
so we'll do a little bit with some
statistical and math things uh that
relate to my own research too okay so I
um I'm trained as a um actually let me
turn off this light somehow yep is that
good I'm trained as a medieval music
historian so uh I really really got into
Medieval music you'll hear little clips
of it here and there and
um and that was you know really what I
wanted to do when I programmed on the
side uh to make some spending money and
things like that when I got into
Medieval music I thought I'd be looking
at things that are really beautiful like
this all the time these are uh people
playing a little crank or her Gertie
type thing and stuff and there are these
beautiful beautiful music manuscripts
this is from the early 14th C Century
called the um the novel of Fel the horse
named Fel the Randa Fel and you know
they're all really really gorgeous or
there's the the original Carmin Brana
that um that Carl ORF based his uh music
off of yes this is what music notation
once looked like um and then you know
gorgeous books in the shape of a heart
or um so I started focusing on the 14th
century in Italy where we have this one
really amazing book this called the
squatchy aupi codex has these beautiful
pictures of all the musicians who are um
who are in there and it's great I think
it's valued around $35 million or
something like that so I thought I'd be
working on this well it turns out people
have been doing Medieval music research
for I know hundreds of years and guess
what they've all studied the really
pretty books so if you wanted to go into
this in the you know around 1998 2000
whenever I really got it started about
25 years ago uh here's what's left for
us to
study little things like that you can
kind of see the the music here here and
stuff like that or um this is one of the
ones I've been looking at uh worms eat
them ravages of time or other little
indignities um that the music is wrapped
up to keep people's um sewage payment
records you have to pay somebody to
clean out your chamber pots and you want
to make sure that somebody's paid their
bill and so you know you wrap it in a
piece of worthless music and you do that
um well when you're wrapping music on
top of other documents sometimes the
document smaller than the music so no
problem you trim the music and uh then
it fits there and some people um you
know there's there's nothing important
on the left side of a score right I mean
just clefts time signatures key
signatures you know you know nothing
like that they used a lot of cffs back
then um and then sometimes you wanted
things to look really nice so you would
uh wipe off wash off or scrape off all
the music that was there so that you
know your cover looked a little nicer
and then once you've scraped everything
off it's all parchment and Vellum and
stuff uh then you can reuse it for in
this case Church landold Holdings in
Florence
um and then there's these little streps
that you find sometimes that you weren't
even sure are music but oh th those kind
of look like quarter note stems quarter
note stems and stuff like that so uh and
this is what was left for me so I became
sort of a music fragment scholar and um
my things are all on fragments of
polyphonic music from The 14th Century
so I wanted to look at these things and
you know how to move forward uh one of
the things back then you with no
computers is just spend a lot of time so
one of the things they were really good
about then is that they like who was
told that in a music class when you
write a quarter
note that's a very bad one when you
write a quarter note its stem should be
exactly an octave long and so therefore
it's kind of exactly like this I don't
know if people are still taught that
well they were very good at that so you
can kind of figure out based on the
heights the stems What notes must have
been cut off there and where they are
and you just stare for hours and hours
and hours of other books until
eventually you find one where every one
of the stems lines up I had to squish
this by about 10% to get it but things
like that or for something like this you
just uh there's three parts they wrote
the parts separately back then kind of
like I don't know iterating through the
recurse method and not the flatten
method and so um part one part two part
three and so you TR try every
combination of clef and time signature
and key signature until you finally find
where things um line up then use your
knowledge of Music Theory from The 14th
Century to fill in the missing parts and
eventually your friends record the piece
for you
[Music]
um then when the notes get big it's what
we actually know
so anyhow those was some of the things
and and um then first place where
computers really started coming in uh
was about when we started getting nice
color photographs before everything was
black and white photoc copies and stuff
and um I with some other people and some
other people independent of me all came
up about the same time with a technique
that um that if you measured the colors
of the overwriting and the colors of the
under writing the ink would probably be
different so you could remove one and
bring the other up and so we had these
various computer uh techniques for
getting rid of the overwriting and
getting to the music
underneath but um everything after this
was still going to be done by hand so I
started thinking about ways to use
statistics and computers to do various
things so about this time started
creating music 21 and if you ever wonder
why there's some things that are obscure
music 21's sole purpose was to try to
identify music fragments like that and
everything else that this class has uh
sort of come about has just been sort of
a side uh side project um
so while I was building that I switched
into sort of a statistical mode so we'll
get back to music 21 in a bit but first
want to think about some of the things
that that were coming up with all these
fragments and I was trying trying to
figure out what they were and that meant
I would need to find another piece that
was like that but the odds that another
piece would exist that matched up with
the music I was told were really really
low uh in fact uh a very famous uh
article by uh somebody who's very famous
in my field Nino Pera um the oral and
written traditions of Music said that um
the surviving music from the Middle Ages
is the tip of the iceberg and that
metaphor ended up being uh quoted and
reused in whole bunch of other articles
that you don't need to see here but um
so th this became sort of what everybody
knew so if you're thinking about music
from you know 600 years ago and you
think about all the things you've lost
in your 20 years of life for however
long um what percentage of things would
have survived from 600 years
ago or would be lost would be lost about
90%
99%
99.9% these are all numbers that I found
people said and then somebody said
basically everything so I I have to
convert everything to a number that's
pretty close to basically everything for
me
um I'm going to skip over that we don't
have all the time in the world um so I
started to think about some statistical
methodologies that could um that could
help in this and one of the things that
we have in some cases is uh this is a
table of contents for a book of music
from The 14th Century where the book
doesn't exist but the table of contents
does so I started looking at okay here's
all the pieces that do not
exist and then here's all the pieces
that do
exist and stting to look at the
ratios and in this particular manuscript
it looks like about 68% of them survive
so that was that was the first thing
that maybe the
99.9999 number didn't exist and then I
looked at there's a poet bunch of poetry
manuscripts so this is um one from about
the time of Dante or chasser um by a not
very good poet named kenani but one of
the things that makes him a bad poet
that's really good is that when he gets
into something when he's talking about a
feast he will list for the next 50 lines
everything they possibly ate and when it
gets to a concert he lists um with the
viola
we played our Mayday songs we just had
Mayday uh so these are the MayDay songs
like the rose that never changes its
color sweet um sweet taste and so on and
these all look like names of songs and
so we can look at for each one of them
do we have a song by that name or do we
not and so we have how many are known
how many are unknown and we
eventually get to a number that looks a
little bit similar to the last one about
71%
survive so I was kind of going through
this the chronology is a little bit
wrong I had to justify this later but
first I was thinking about how animal
biologist uh ecologists count animals um
has anyone taken a biology class or
something where you do population
estimates yeah what so one of the ways
that you can do it is you um C you want
to know how many deer are in the forest
right so you go and you capture as many
deer as you can in a month and a half
you you come back smelling pretty bad
and stuff but every time you find a deer
you tag its uh ear or some way in some
way that you can identify this is a deer
that I saw and you come back several
months later or whatever and then you
count deer again and the percentage of
deer that um that we're tagging the
first time give you some sense of or the
inverse of it gives you some sense sense
of how big the population is if you
tagged 100 deer the first time and you
come back later and you only find then
you capture 100 more deer and you only
Capt see two of them are tagged you know
there's a huge population of deer out
there similarly if you captured 100 deer
and next time you capture 100 deer 98 of
them are tagged you probably saw most of
them so started thinking about well if a
piece appears in one manuscript we'll
tag that piece and then we'll see how
often it appears in another
manuscript so I started coming up with
formulas uh to do this type of thing and
I realized that that there's an equation
that tells us the number of missing
pieces all you have to do is you take
the number of pieces you originally had
and you multiply by the probability that
any piece would be missing tell me if
I'm wrong you're the MIT students uh it
equals the total number of missing
pieces and it's a super great super
simple formula except that it's a
formula with three unknowns we don't
know any of these three numbers
but we can kind of figure out um some of
these things so we can look at um well
what's the probability that a given
piece would be in a manuscript now we'll
start with the assumption that every
piece is sort of selected randomly so we
start with how many pieces are there in
a manuscript is just like a collection
you know like a box set of of lots of
tunes how many pieces are there in that
manuscript we'll call that R subi and
you divide it by the total number of
pieces that were originally copied so we
know how many pieces are in a manuscript
because we can count that that survives
but we don't know that so we just move
our unknown to another
place so we can also figure out what's
the probability a piece is not in a
given manuscript what's the what's the
formula just see if you're awake if this
is the F Formula it's in the manuscript
what do we do one minus good good we're
all on same page there great so what's
the probability that it's not in too
many
scripts you just take the first
probability and you multiply by the
second one in the assumption that these
are independent and so try to keep ones
from different places whatever so
then what's the probability that any
given piece is not in any of there were
at that point 85 surviving
manuscripts well you just have something
like
this and that gives us takes uh but are
two unknowns that gives us the
probability that a piece is
missing so we can go back to our
original
equation
and plug that
in and all of these have n as a
denominator so now we've at least
reduced our U giant we've reduced our of
our Master our main equation into two
unknowns so we're getting a little bit
better then we
thought what how many pieces were
missing well the number of pieces that
were missing is the number of pieces
that originally were minus the number of
pieces that
survive
so we can count the number of pieces
that survive it takes a long time
actually to to figure out every single
thing because people count differently
but we can kind of reduce this entire
equation
to one equation one unknown and at this
point I was thinking I must have screwed
up something really really bad I have a
music degree I don't have a stats degree
this seems like a pretty fundamental
equation to have and it turns out people
had been talking about equations like
this a lot in the 60s or so but um back
then it was all about what's the way
that you solve an equation like this
with 85 you know it's a what it's a 85th
power equation or something like that um
you know and so all of it was on the
high math that I don't understand that
can get you um something to this this
answer but um this is my first uh
computational thing it's in a language
called Pearl where if you know it you're
lying about your age uh it was the the
big uh it was the language that built
the internet in the 9s um things and the
one of the things you can do is you can
look at at um guess various numbers and
look at the error between the left side
of the equation and the right side of
the equation until you find the number
that comes closest to balancing it so
you just kind of try everything and you
multiply everything
out and since this isn't really a class
about that but it turned into um saying
that the percentage of missing pieces
varied by genre by type of piece it was
interesting part is that the ma the mass
the music written for sacred Services
survives uh has more missing than the
ones for everyday sort of dancing and
love making and all that stuff and I
think that's because uh over time nobody
could read this music um so the only
reason somebody would keep it around is
for the text and you if you're um
running a church you already have lots
of copies of the text of the mass but
the song about you know we all went off
into the woods uh each one is a pair and
we all came back as three um they you
know that that's people still keep
around so those sort of body songs uh
have the least
missing so it turns out that our best
estimates now are that about
25% of the pieces maybe 50% I don't know
maybe 60 maybe I'm off by a little bit
you know by a logarithm order of
magnitude or something but we can
actually really say something about
Medieval music based on the fact that
much of it
survives and I was very very scared that
somehow I had made a math error and
stuff until there was just a math
disertation at Yale that uh verified all
the work and stuff so I'm finally
finally not worried I'm going to have to
do a retraction of one of my biggest
papers okay so now we're going to get
back to these
little uh scores and once I had sort of
convinced myself that a good chunk of
the time three4 of the time was saying
we're going to be able to figure out
what music is on here because it's going
to be in some other piece we already
have so there's this collection that I
mostly use it's called polyic music The
14th Century we have it over in the
Lewis music library it's beautiful it's
expensive and things comes in these
gorgeous green volumes and there's a lot
of them all the music from The 14th
Century uh it's about 20 it's 25 volumes
in this series and then there's been
some others since there so this gives
you a sense of uh what it is and
um now MIT was able I'm going to skip
some of these MIT was able to help me um
get some of this into um into a computer
so we'll get on to that in a little bit
but what what if you want to do if if
you want to find if any of these pieces
has a match in another thing because
somebody's written down a lot of these
little fragments or they've put all the
pieces in and I wanted to see not just
were any of these little fragments there
but at this point are any pieces quoting
or copying from or plagiarizing from
anybody else's music so what you have to
do is you take all the songs and you
compare each one of them n by n right um
sorry that's not enough we got to zoom
out a little bit
and there we go yeah so it's something
like that that's actually just comparing
each of the volumes we actually want to
compare each of these volumes has about
150 pieces so you have to do the square
of the number of pieces divide by two
because it's symmetrical and so you have
about 3.1 million comparisons and that's
the reason why nobody had done this
before um I'm actually really lucky our
best estimates which I don't know is
that 14th century music is about
10% of the size of 15th century music
and every successive century is about
tenfold more music so I have algorithms
that I've devised that I think will also
work for the 15th century and maybe if I
ever had a huge research budget I could
do the 16th but it's going to be up to
you all to figure out what's the
algorithm that can compare every piece
of known music to every other piece and
get that and that's why I care a lot
about simil similar it so sorry I got
ahead of myself so with um with great
scholar Anna Katherine grow uh created
the electronic Medieval music score
archive project or msap uh which slides
a little bit out of date but back then
it had about 1.3 million notes now we're
close to like 1.8 million and of course
you know this this one right so what you
do is you take all the take all the
music and you take music 21 and then it
does something like this and you know
that's how that's how it looks when you
do run the
matches now you all know that this is
what you do to uh to get funding for
your project and that's not actually how
it works right only in CSI uh no the way
it actually works is you go and you take
your scans that you've done and how do
you get them scanned you spend all day
putting them on a scanner um and
then enter every one of these pieces
into um mostly Muse Corell finale
whatever it is and then we exported
everything as music XML some people uh
like there's a specific output for music
uh musicology called Mei which is pretty
similar uh but I use Music XML and so
then we have here's the music XML for
the first three first four notes of this
one piece called sorry I'll just jump
back called an Neu which is um
completely only one copy of it in the
world then uh wrote some programs python
music 21 um things just to take every 31
note little segment I don't know why I
ended up with 31 um and just
automatically chop it up so that there's
these um little segments things and
ideally you would chop it up you would
slide your window over one note at a
time but there's a trade-off between
getting the best um similarity and then
um and also not having your database EXP
explode with internal quotations so we
did this and had it go through
everything here and then once we had
chopped up the pieces into these little
31 note segments uh then we did uh what
keep was talking about a a Viewpoint or
a hash or an encoding system to try to
reduce the complexity of it so the
complexity the system that I used you're
going to kind of laugh at um if a note
was the same duration as the previous it
got the asky letter A B CDE e f g I
dropped Sharps and flats because
different copies of the same piece in
the middle ages sometimes write it as B
flat sometimes they don't write a flat
you're just supposed to hear that well
obviously there was a augmented fourth
I'm going to sing that flat so they
don't always put that in so we get rid
of accidentals and then if the note's
longer than the previous note um then we
use H through n and if it's shorter then
it's O through U so um p is a b that is
shorter than the previous note you just
go through and put everything in like
that and the first note I always just
assume it's the same so we take all of
these things and put it into a giant
database um it's not that big it's about
188,000 of these little segments at that
time and so this is the segment for the
opening of Ana it's kind of I always
think it's kind of unceremoniously
stored there like the arc at the end of
the Indiana Jones film if you've ever
seen it just can't really tell where it
is so then we have to compare every one
of these
188,000 sequences against every other
one so we take the first one the Anan
Neu Melody and just some random other
one and we can figure out what are all
the things we have to do in um earth
mover leein or some other distance thing
in order to transform the first one to
the second one so you have to well you
insert a whole bunch of things and then
some things the same delete whatever and
the end you get a ratio from 0o to one
of how similar they are I always like to
store float uh store integers um in
databases it saves a lot of space so I
just multiply by 10,000 so I get a
number between 0 and 10,000 to store
these ones are 177% similar these are
actually a
surprisingly bad amount of similarity
random pieces tend to be uh more similar
but so this this is not a match right
nobody's going to say that those that
those two lines are the same piece
slightly different
no um but that's okay because we do it
188,000 by 188,000 times or 35 billion
divide by two since it's symmetrical 16
billion 18 billion right um
yeah but then I went through and stored
every single time there was something
that was more than 50% similar so
there's two IDs and the ratio of how
similar they are and over 50% similar
ended up with 814,000 things I'm never
going to look at those that's just way
too many so I started going to at around
65% similar I started to suspect these
tended to be pieces um by the same
composer or uh quite often if we knew or
I suspected they would be or something
like that at 70% similar you're like wow
these aren't the same piece but they're
they're a lot like it but at definitely
at over 80% similar um they're always
the same piece and how can something be
the same piece and be 20% off it could
just be that they were sliced at
different points so they're the exact
same thing but the but the first third
of one segment is in some other one okay
okay so this is what the actual um
workflow looks like I used to use
Eclipse um and just running through all
these pieces and occasionally it finds a
match and it puts it up and I get to see
okay does that look like that or yeah
that one kind of looks like that one um
and sometimes we already knew them the
computer does not read uh what pieces we
already knew were quoted but we ended up
with some interesting things this is a
piece by a guy named johanes this is
unpublished yet don't don't put it all
over everywhere um a guy the name of um
johanes jonia one of the most important
composes around 1400 and one of his
pieces it's a part of the mass p poent
and it turns out that a big chunk of it
was taken from an unknown uh sort of uh
an anonymous never recorded by anybody
German
[Music]
song Let me see if I can do the
here we are if you've never
read so we can find that there was a lot
more copying than we ever expected um
this one of my favorites here's a a
French piece and Italian piece nobody
ever suspected they had anything in
common because whoever and I don't know
which direction the coping happened
whoever did the coping did a good chance
of covering their tracks the colored
Parts represent the same music okay and
then down here stole something from up
there and then up here we stole
something from over there and so on so
it's just two that are pastiches of each
other and then if this were a musicology
class people would actually care about
which one this um what all these other
things but eventually we got to start
reading these erased pieces and figuring
out where they came from
so that's the big reason why I created
Music 21 and why you will find that
there are lots of weird little things uh
that are only useful for music uh for
Medieval music hidden around deep inside
the various um libraries and stuff so
that's what I do when I'm not um
enjoying in being in your company any
questions or anything you want to see
again there are by the way U lots of
places do want um historians who can do
this type of work so if you're all
interested Humanities in general but
you're like but you know I also want to
program and stuff people are are dying
for things like that yeah question so
like what made you want to expand
music uh you all uh your predecessors
people for about 10 15 years before you
from here at MIT it just felt like you
know people wanted to uh do interesting
things with composition with analysis uh
everybody wanted to uh solve their first
year Theory uh homework by computer um
and why not if you can program the
computer to do it and it's not uh you
know complete Black AI you're probably
teaching yourself how to do it better
also so it was it was things things like
that and of over time I've taken out a
lot of the most egregious that only a
person working on 14th century Italy
would um would want to do this and put
this in a separate project so there's no
longer an automatic U change medieval
notation into modern notation tool you
have to install that separately but yeah
um I just just felt like I was having
too much fun and other people wanted to
share in it and that meant eventually
docs would have to happen and uh then a
very generous uh funding organization
called The sver Institute selected music
21 to be uh one of MIT mit's
representative project for their funding
Organization for three years and that
allowed me to do a little bit more than
one person can do at their desk and now
the thing that helps me do more than one
person can do at the desk is community
of a lot of people who keep adding to it
um and doing cool things with it so
thanks other
cues why is it called music 21 uh course
21 M I wanted something that um that
would connected itself to MIT in some
way but wasn't uh MIT music because your
trademark office would probably uh get
against me and also I was a second-year
professor without tenure so I might have
been denied tenure and needed to able to
take it with me if I went someplace else
but yeah so and then somebody later was
like oh it's the thing for the 21st
century I said I I actually never
thought of that connotation if I had
there's no way I would have called it 21
because that sounds very a arrogant and
be um a little obsolete in 2006 when
you're already in the 21st century it's
perfect for 1980 or something
yeah what was it called before music uh
it was called um uh P music first for
Pearl music when I was writing it in
Pearl and then uh the fact then as soon
as um the intro to CS class switched
from your older language scheme to
python I was like well if if all of MIT
is going to move to a new language at
the same time then um you know it it'll
be easier for me to learn a new language
than to have uh the rest of my life
teach my students how to program in
Pearl and I'm very glad I
did uh the other thing is the work on it
I sort of began in 2004 but work really
began around
2006 and at the time I predicted that it
would have a 20year lifespan that it
would be sort
of five or six years of um of getting
people to notice it and start using it
seven or eight years of it being the
main thing out there and um five to
seven years of you know the decline
while something else better came out and
I'm still looking for that say better
you guys can do that it's about there's
there are things we've learned from
using it that um I think are have have
made realize that there's some pretty
poor design decisions such as having to
copy everything all the time and things
like that and so um I would you know I'd
really love it if somebody else would um
would create something new and better so
whoever's here or watching it uh you
have my blessing to try to try to knock
this off its shelf and maybe the new
thing will have a lot of uh machine
learning built in or something to be
able to do better analysis yeah but
Python's been enduring a lot longer than
I thought it would be I mean it's sort
of been 15 years as as a major language
and it seems to be still growing so that
probably will stop Julia's next Julia's
next that's people have been saying that
about Julia and R for there is a Julia
Port of Music 21 if you like that I
don't know how how good it works so
that's a perfect transition oh we can we
uh we can keep going more to a second
topic so for this one get out your
laptops we're going to have um because I
couldn't have scripted a better
transition to um okay so now more grab
bag and these are more requested from
previous years than anything sorry I
can't stand all that dust
um oops did pushing all this shut it
down no here we
go okay so here are some of the things
go ahead and um go to this website M21
sand 2 if you leave off the two you get
to use uh a three-year-old version of
this you should be seeing something that
looks a bit like this when you get
there 21m
21 M21 sand 2
M21
sand 2 sandbox the place where you play
around so the thing I've always hated
most about music 21 is that um you can't
see anything uh that's two things you
can't see anything you can't hear
anything unless you you know we didn't
even even have uh Jupiter notebooks or
something back then so we didn't have
that and number three it's so hard to
install um that's getting easier but
still so I thought that something where
people can start playing with it
immediately online would work and so
I've been working on um sort of in
parallel for the past six years um
there's a typescript or JavaScript Port
who who has done JavaScript here in some
ways about about okay a little bit more
than half things so the big difference
in uh if you're new to JavaScript is
that you're going to put new in front of
anytime you want to instantiate
something and I've imported music 21
without importing all of the things so
you're going to have to type that quite
a bit um but what's kind of nice is you
can go through and change a note and
immediately see the stream there or um
octave things like that or put
everything down what happens if we put
everything down here doesn't it
automatically giv me a good cluff no
it's did I put it in okay well we can
put in a proper cluff s so we'll pend to
the stream a new music21 docf dobas
cff and now we can see our notes again
and uh by default if you click the
thing by default
there we go okay well I've lost all my
changes but you can kind of see and so
um some of the things you can do create
interactive little systems where you're
scrolling things up and down where
you're hearing um everything but it's
still a absolutely a work in progress so
if you do
analyze key you get analyze is not a
function so there's still a lot of
things um missing there but there's
something really nice to being able to
manipulate with scores in a browser
stuff the Alternatives that people are
doing right now um tend to be about
actually uh using HTML elements to
represent notes now that you have custom
elements and that lets you use your
browsers builtin um get Elements by
class and all these things to move
around a score and in theory it should
be uh substantially faster than this or
at least more
powerful I know if anybody wants to you
can play around with with any of this
for a little bit you can make this a
dotted
quarter what I hate is uh duration dot
dots equals one and nothing's going to
happen until I get rid of this analyze
thing here yep play the round give it a
78 78 time signature and then um here
let's let's do this let's create P
equals stream dot part oops I'm totally
in yeah like just being in this class
with you all I can't not be in Python
mode so I'm just going to keep typing
Python and then correcting it to
JavaScript until it runs but uh we can
do something like
for uh let I equals
z i is less than four i++ and then oh
this pains me as a python
um uh as a python person to not have
indented code but
um actually do we have to call that um
we have to call that a measure music 21j
is a lot more strict about such things
to
I H what did I do
wrong so hard to tell without
indentations but there's this edit
doesn't allow me to hit tab to indent
things here always make your life easier
get rid of that so you can see
everything on one
page anybody know what I'm M typing here
I have a fully baked version over here
somewhere on another
tab here we'll go over to the the fully
baked one that already works so you can
kind
of play around with it just saying first
note of each of each measure will be a
random number and as we go through we'll
just change them and if I make any
changes here it will automatically give
me a new random number I thought I had
it oh
this here I think I have to copy and
paste
what I think happens is
um there we
go and you can do overlapping
things anyhow so it be kind of fun for a
live coding environment if you don't
care about the quality of the music um
coming if you don't care about the
quality of the sound cuz it's not really
optimized for sound quality uh but you
could put it out through other
things uh let grab bag topic number one
how to do interactive um how to do
interactive programming stuff you can do
everything uh sorry John you just came
back in and I'm going just just say look
you're the only one has anyone else
taken interactive music
systems oh you are okay so you have yeah
so you can put everything into uh a you
guys mostly use Ki right as your as your
toolkit so you there are things you can
do on the on the python side they
connect up music 21 to things to uh get
better sounding interactive um things
but I often find sometimes just the
easiest little thing U can be all you
need okay close these things because
otherwise it will eventually just start
playing again and we have just enough
time for I think for one more topic and
then uh I might finally keep my promise
and let you all go a little bit earlier
um okay so the last thing I want to talk
about a little bit is music
visualization and uh we're going to
listen to a piece of music by a
contemporary Estonian composer arvo
parot and I'm going to ask you
afterwards to say something about the
structure or the form of this piece and
how it works musically first it's a a
piece for choir and so it has a text
it's a actually high high medieval today
uh it's based on a Gregorian chant of
it's sung in German translation uh o
Immanuel
and uh the German text is going to be
slightly important for that so it's
about a TW minute piece um and long time
of the year for doing it but get
that here we go
[Music]
1988 I think was um one of my favorites
um anybody catch anything about the
structure you have seen the entire score
every single note so we can get
something yeah measures always switch
between 1 two and 32 measures always
switch between one two and 32 one two
and
32 how many sections did the piece have
yeah tell like three seconds nice that's
actually correct how many people knew
that and how many people were like me
when they heard this like once twice
three times and didn't fully catch the
structure I was yeah yeah
so fantastic fantastic usually uh so
yeah there some things in and what voice
is most Mel what two voices were most
melodically active
yeah middle two I think good ear good
ear this this yall are are really
getting you we should have been doing
more music analysis in class because
you're getting a lot of things I thought
were going to be extremely hard and some
at least throughout the room we've had
correct answers but I want to uh spend a
little bit of time on music um visual by
the way there are a few uh ad almost
exactly there's one measure of 52
but yeah there's a couple other things
but yep so um are we up there yeah go
ahead and download um there is the MXL
the XML file music XML file of this
piece on canvas and uh take a minute
it's it's under copyright but I'm going
to assert a claim of fair use for us to
be able to uh analyze with it show
should show you the just the first page
if you're in Jupiter and
more than that if you're
not so this might uh some of these
things might be helpful for
um or what we're doing so a little bit
more we're going to be going through the
various
um ways of visualizing
I don't think we've maybe I've done a
tiny bit of visualization but mostly
just on slides I don't think I've
shown we feeling in a good place to move
on now okay so um you know we can do all
the things that um that we normally
would do we can get the key of the piece
which I believe
changes quite a bit I think if we do U
measures 1 through 20. analyze key we
get something very different no we
don't still get interesting just the key
signature changes um okay but now we'll
get into some visualization things so
the easiest thing you can do with a
stream um is to do something called plot
and plot just gives you um any whatever
you uh sort of a standard
readymade um
oops that's why I never do this here uh
sort of
readymade image sorry it doesn't Zoom
the image in but you on here but you
might be able to see something like that
and so you can see a
relationship of the um various parts
colored in different colors and which
ones are singing
what so here the three-part the
three-fold relationship sorry I'm going
to have to zoom this out tiny bit so we
can see this again
um the three-part relation three section
relationship of the piece becomes very
clear right you can see that something
happens at the
beginning this increase up here up until
a certain point and then a lot of things
change so what
measure does the third section begin
on yeah somewhere around there so you
can uh 45 I think some 46 44 45 so you
can kind of see something substantial
changes and um here's what Jason pointed
out right that um that the inner voices
in the second and third sections are the
ones that are
very um very
active right so where does second
section begin measure
13 to
measure 45 so let's let's get this SEC 2
equals arvo do measures let say 14 to 45
44 we'll say SEC 2. plot I think I think
the default is piano roll because that's
what most people want so we can look at
section
two and we'll say section three was
measures what 45 to
76 Section 3 equals arvo
dot
measures 45 to
76 we can plot
that there's a lot of similarities here
between section
two and section
3 what's what's the biggest difference
musically that you can tell from these
charts between section two and section
three you'll probably want to go all the
way back up to your bigger
role over here this side's been mostly
quiet yeah section two section almost
identical but section two is up section
two and section 3 are almost identical
but section two is up good can we figure
out about how much up it
is look at the key on the
side yeah the e to the A and the E to an
A so it's about about a fifth off in a
lot of things except for on the extremes
but what about the notes in
between these moving parts
where are they off what's the
relationship
there OCT yeah about yeah an OCT exactly
an octave up so we have things moving
now go I'll open up the score one more
time I know I why I wanted the score
open so I could keep going to back to
this um let me get a no here we go um so
I'll put this in front for a second
and sorry now i' now I've lost my my
train train of thought
um how easy is it to see which parts are
static and which parts are Mo in Motion
in
this quite a bit harder so what it what
kind of motion is happening we've
identified that it's the inner voices
that are in motion
um what's the
pattern now go back to your
visualization and see if you can figure
it
out in any of the inner
voices maybe it's easier if you just
look at one of the sections so you can
zoom in a little bit
more John do you want
to move in
parall they move in parallel first yeah
and looks good and within any given
voice what's the what's it
doing is it playing Mary had a little
lamp is it jumping around a huge uh
octave and then coming back down
Adam they're just playing the same note
uh not all of them are playing the same
note these ones are playing the same
note right but what what's what are the
other voices doing these inner
voices do it go all the way up and then
all the way yeah I you s repeating right
they're repeating what what do they do
what what's the pattern yeah stepwise
stepwise good it's all stepwise which is
the hard part about piano roll right you
would want a dionic piano roll at some
point um I think we have that somewhere
um and it's all step wise and it's even
more than that yeah go Vin it nebor
tones around a certain page top around
they're all neighbor tones around a
certain pitch yeah so you can kind of
top one I can't reach so we'll do the
middle one is I guess around e and is it
is there a pattern that you do three ups
and then a down and then what is
it up then down up then down up then
down so you could almost have a formula
um with this in fact uh the the one of
the um other python based music um
packages which is more about creating
algorithmically generable music is
called arvo based on arvo parr's um
ability to do this so you can you can
download install arvo and um it makes it
much easier than music 21 does to
generate uh here's a motive now spin it
out over a certain amount of time while
doing something else so yeah so we have
this thing going up and down and up and
down and things like that um by the way
some of the other interesting things
about the piece that we're not going to
visualize music 21 uh are um when does
it uh change notes on on any multi-
syllable accented German word which I
think uh sort of interesting here so the
accent always gets the gets the whole
note and it's always the opposite of
whatever it was
before and then you can kind of see well
in section two all of the voices kind of
play at once and they all rest at once
but in section three the top and the
bottom ones only coming in certain times
the visualization of this helped me in
figuring out well when are those times
and it turns out also very strictly
generated um that it is
just every other word
do they do that's two
words we don't
sing next two words derer we sing Oh
Come we
don't and there's one exception to it uh
no sorry there isn't an exception on
this one there's some someplace else is
an exception on things but I think
probably set up so that just the number
of words makes it so that God stands
alone at the end without accompanyment
so interesting piece now let's do a tiny
bit more analysis on it
um there's a plot that um I could call
this a cook plot cook because I saw this
in now in the reading for Nicholas cook
um article on computational and
comparative
music computational and comparative
musicology I first saw this in a book by
em uh somebody named Emily Dolan so I
call it a Dolan graph um even though um
and it shows you who is singing where at
what point which parts are performing
and do you remember this from the cook
it's slightly different graph that he
had a slightly different shape size but
same type of thing what's being uh
depicted
here take a guess what's that Dynamic
Dynamics yeah so it's a sort of who's
playing when and what are the Dynamics
and if you zoom in really closely you
can see that soprano is always singing a
tiny bit before the other parts but yeah
so the piece just sort of builds up to
about two3 point then drops off and just
very quiet everything after after that
um so there's quite often I think for
people who can read music notation uh
graphs and plotting visualization isn't
too much of a help but for getting a
sense of the form of a large piece very
quickly these um these tools can be very
very helpful uh we can kind of see what
what notes does he use the most well
obviously those that are going to be um
that that the sustained notes are going
to come quite a bit but we can
see that of the various pitch classes
basically there's a reason why it was
coming out as a
major as our
analysis as a definitely winning e
c but almost I guess every surprisingly
for a piece that sounds so um consonant
in many ways every pitch class is
represented at least once there
um let me see which I have a whole bunch
of ones that are maybe a little bit less
interesting but um we can look at the um
certain pitches use different uh quarter
different notes more so we can plot a
scatter plot and then what we haven't
seen yet is the second and third element
uh here um is quarter
length versus
pitch I think there's other things you
can do you can plot around with octave
and stuff so these are plot gives you a
ready made take in a score and get get
some kind of analysis there's two
slightly lower level things if you want
to if you're thinking of doing
visualization in there one call it the
graph which is underlying the plot which
is the um what you're trying to do and
what data you want to extract so it's
sort of a feature extraction again and
what do you want to put on each axis so
there's axes that are defined that you
can I don't know we can do let's plot um
Pitch against
Dynamic you know what I yeah
Dynamics does that
work you know what who puts pitch on the
xaxis we'll put Pitch on the Y AIS
versus Dynamics swap that
around that's why it's having so
trouble so you can see that the oops
that the lowest notes in the pieces only
appear on um on the quietest things and
kind of also look at this terrorist um
initial motion of the piece as the notes
were going up and um and both going up
in pitch and getting higher in volume
and then the very highest um volumes are
scattered all all throughout but every
everything down here shifted up a little
bit um just as we
saw think the best thing to do would be
now that we've thought about the piece
thought about its structure listen to it
one more time um maybe with the we'll
listen to it with the um piano roll and
see if
um see if we
can oops not that one the the big one
and see if we can hear the various parts
of the piece just as well as we could on
um with the
score words are harder to tell there's
no plot for
that you're mostly color blind Professor
just realized that I used a version of
the plot that does colors not based on
the part but just um as a way of being
able to see which pitches are which so I
apologize I made a mistake and said you
could can tell the lines by color but uh
I have to strain to see color so so
sorry about U about that but I did just
while listening to it make one
observation this interesting line that
the E is the very first thing that you
hear and it just after a little absence
comes back and it's one of the few lines
that's so preminent prominent throughout
there so maybe maybe e is the true sort
of root point of this piece
well thanks everybody um for going
through grab bag if you I have more
topics that are interest to me but
anything that's interest to you let me
know