It's great honor for me to introduce
professor Shiva Shanka for our next
talk. Uh P Shiva's research investigates
the role of cell mechanics and nuclear
mechanics uh in chromatin organization
and transcription regulations. His lab's
research identified novel approach to
induce cellular rejuvenation and
reprogramming. In recent several years,
uh his lab developed a chromatin
fingerprint based approach for the
disease diagnostic and the uh drug
discovery. Shiva received his uh PhD
from Rockefeller University and after
that he become faculty in National
Center of Biological Science and in 2011
he joined National University of
Singapore and co-direct mechano biology
institute. In 20 uh 21 he joined ETS
Zurich and lead a laboratory of
multiscale
uh biology uh there. Let's welcome our
next speaker professor
[Applause]
Shiva. Great. I
hope so. Let me thank the organizers for
having me here. Also, it's always a
pleasure to have your former PhD student
introduce you. Luchen was a former PhD
student. Good. With that, uh since it's
a very broad audience, what I'm going to
do is
um give you a flavor for the kind of
questions we ask uh and how we approach
them and most of the work that I we do
is in joint collaboration with Caroline
Wooler's lab
here. So, it's wonderful morning
session. So I don't have to go introduce
too much uh many things that many of you
have already talked about.
Uh nevertheless um so as all of us know
I don't have to belabor this we have
about uh 36 trillions of cells in our
body is the same DNA. So it has to pack
in different tissues in a tissue
specific manner. Uh also as all of you
know different tissues have different
stiffness. bone tissues are very stiff
whereas uh brain tissues are very soft.
So one is to try and understand genome
regulation in the context of the
stiffness. So what I'm going to do in
the first half of the talk is to give
you some basic principles that we have
discovered of how cells
operate. We'll then go forward and how
we can embrace uh AI to learn about cell
states and cell state transitions.
One other thing that we discovered we
and others of course uh identified was
um that
chromosomes while you pack the DNA into
the nucleus the interfaces between
chromosomes have been have been not uh
well appreciated right the intermingling
regions between the chromosomes which
can have trans interaction seems to have
a bearing on how transcriptional control
come about in a cell type specific
manner or tissue type specific manner.
Once you think of uh chromosome
interfaces, mechanics becomes important
because it's like a box in which you
pack chromosomes. If I change the nature
of the box in terms of the mechanics,
then you have altered genome regulation
which is what I'll show you in the first
part of the talk.
So over the years we and others have
laid out some of the principles that how
cells send signals from the
extracellular environment because cells
sense both chemical as well as
mechanical signals and these cells then
integrate into different parts of the
genome when you activate specific
transcription factors. So these
transcription factors then bring about
groups of genes which are collocicalized
for
co-regulation. And so this kind of an
idea already suggests that there are
really two spaces that we need to worry
about. The first space is really an
architectural space which you can probe
by imaging. Jennifer talked about quite
a bit of the imaging modalities.
And of course this physical space
intimately linked with the biochemical
space. The biochemical space of cells
are highly
multi-dimensional. Lots of biochemical
networks. One wants to understand causal
relationship between this physical and
biochemical
space. If such a thing exists, we should
be able to test it in very simple
models. Right? So one of the things that
we tried out early on was take a cell.
These are general principles. You can
work with any cells of your choice. Take
a cell, change its mechanics or change
its geometry. As you see here, there are
many methods in cell biology where you
can have micropatent surfaces where you
can change the shape of a cell. So when
you change the shape is the same cell,
right? When you change the shape of the
cell and take its transcriptto, the
transcriptto is very different, right?
All I've done is taken a cell change it
shape right and the DNA is packed but
what it produces is very different
proteins. Somehow the cells adapt to
what they see, trigger biochemical
circuitry in the signaling pathways and
trigger remodeling of the chromosome
interfaces because I'm changing the
shape of the cell and the shape of the
nucleus and I produce different
proteins. Right? This is very generic of
all cell types that you work with.
Right? The second important principle is
if you now stimulate these cells with
some signals, it could be mechanical, it
could be chemical signals, the cell
state, the cell mechanical state
dictates what the output is. Right? So
here is an example that I take the same
cells put them in a tissue organoid or
an engineered tissue or look at the same
cells in tissues.
What you find is that every cell has its
own local state you know in in in in in
culture or in tissues and now when you
stimulate these cells every cell has its
own program. So that's why
fingerprinting every cell's transcriptto
in a tissue is so important to
understand the biology of how cells
work, how cells transition to different
states, how cells transition to disease
states. Right? in the same
cells, same signals, either mechanical
or chemical or both, but they turn on
very different
um expression patterns, protein
production. So, what this led us to
believe is that there must be cell
autonomous properties that cells could
actually switch states here. They're not
still switching their states. Maybe
cells could actually switch the cell
states. And so we came up with a very
simple hypothesis. If a cell has to
maintain a memory because all of us as
we know we don't have billions of cell
types. We have about few hundreds or few
thousands of cell types depending on who
you talk to. Now cells have to maintain
memory right when the cells maintain
memory they maintain memory through
their transcriptional program because
they produce the same proteins after
division.
But they also have to maintain this
mechanical geometric memory, right? And
that's critical. As I said, the physical
space and the biochemical space are
intimately linked. So they really need
to remember their mechanical constraint
as well. So when you look at cells in
culture or in tissues when they divide,
they remember the mechanical memory, but
then they also remember the
transcription memory because they're
interlin, right? So we came with a
simple hypothesis that let's break one
of this memory element maybe break the
mechanical memory of a cell as they
divide maybe then they should really
forget their transcriptional memory. So
we impose this confinement so that cells
cannot stick outside and when the cell
divides one cell was sitting in a good
real estate a piece and now the cell
divides two cells four cells then there
is no space to sit whereas if the cells
divide in a tissue or a culture they
remember both the memories and here as
they divide they start piling up on
themsel because a mechanical state is
changing. One cell was having a tight
geometric constraint. When the cell
divided, two cells, four cells, they're
losing their geometrical constraints,
right? And we wondered that this
property could induce alterations in
chromatin ST signaling transcriptional
programs. And we had a lot of luck with
this simple
idea. The starting from one cell. This
is again true for it's a it's a very
generic property of
cells that imposing geometric
constraints and dividing them. What
these cells ended up doing is you
started with some cell type. This is a
messen camel fiber. As they divided they
switch their cell state from a messen
camel to epithelium. They continue to
divide and then they become stemlike.
All I've done is there is no exogenous
factors. I've taken a
cell. I've worked around the phase space
for cells with a simple hypothesis that
if you break the mechanical symmetry or
geometric symmetry, these cells end up a
system-like state. Right? This with very
high efficiency. That means that this is
a very default natural cell state
transition that our cells have in our
tissues. Of course, they have to
maintain homeostasis because you don't
want to become have diseases all the
time. If cells fit their states, we're
all unstable, right? Cells have to have
some stable solutions. But loss of this
mechanogenomic homeostasis then can
actually induce partial reprogramming.
Now, we have shown that we can actually
take eight cells, take them into more
younger cells by rejuvenation. And I'm
not going to talk about that. But this
idea suggests that this could be a
precursor for generating a disease state
because diseases start from single
cells, right? So how do we understand
then at a cellular level? How do
diseases start? And our claim is that
maybe this kind of a mechanochemical
constraint the cells have in our tissues
with alterations in the mechanogenomic
homeostasis could have this propensity
for a cell state switch. Right? So we're
now searching for such cell state
switches in real tissues. I'll talk
about one
example and as you know these are early
drawings from kahal almost 100 years ago
where he noticed simple microscopes that
cells do switch in the in the micro
environment without any exogenous
factors that means that the micro
environment has adequate information for
cell state transitions.
So it's been long appreciated that in
diseases like aging related diseases
like cancer or
neurodeeneration you don't switch
overnight. Cell state transitions happen
over a long period of timing. So this is
for example in different types of
cancers as a function of aging different
years that it takes for a single cell in
a stromal environment in a tissue
switches its state and start uh you know
abnormal loss of homeostasis leads to
growth of a disease right over a long
period of
time. So this is what we want to try and
understand. So one of the things uh that
we the main thing that our group does is
to use the lens of how the DNA is packed
in each of these cells and see how
alterations in this genome uh could lead
to these cell state transitions. So as I
said as we age as cells age in our
tissues there are very subtle
alterations in the in the chromatin
state how genes genomes are packed and
so we are very keen on reverting it back
or use this changes as biomarkers for
health and disease what I'm going to
talk today more is a little more of our
efforts to think about the way DNA is
packed as a exquisite biomarker for
cell's health or disease Right. So
towards that um to go with Caroline's
group uh over the years I'm not going to
go into all the details. Over the years
we've developed a number of uh uh
machine learning models to learn how DNA
is packed, how the hierarchical nature
of folding is set up in living cells. uh
by staining various markers of DNA, DNA
associated proteins, modifications in
the histone that pack the DNA and
various other uh you know uh regulatory
molecules that are within the within the
nucleus. Through this uh set of learning
and u either supervised or unsupervised
learning methods we have developed what
are called chromatin fingerprints for
cells state cell's health or disease and
these fingerprints are large it's like
taking a cell looking at how the DNA is
packed in the same uh you know idea as
taking your cell and taking a single
cell transcriptto a single cell
transcriptto will give you a whole bunch
of gene gene expression changes uh that
h that that are associated with the
cell. Likewise, what we have is a
highdimensional information of how the
DNA is packed because as I said, these
two spaces are intimately linked with
each other. Right? And so through this
uh we can now look at cell states very
easily now, right? So one
example that we tried early on was take
cells of different cancer states. uh
these are cell lines derived from
various stages of breast tumor
progression and look at the how the DNA
is packed in these images and what you
already see is that you have distinct
states of chromatin in these cell types
right you can actually see that there
are very distinct types of each dot is a
nuclei is a high dimensional information
of the DNA packing and now you construct
um a low dimensional map of how the
chromatin structure is set up And now
through a number of methods that I'm not
going to go into the details um because
diseases don't happen overnight or cell
state transitions don't happen
overnight. They happen over a long
period of time. It's so hard to record
image the cell states transition real
time in a tissue context for a disease
progression. So we have developed
methods where if we
had pieces of information during the
progression of a disease uh what we can
then construct is transport models uh
reduce take these uh information into a
latent space and transport the
distributions of how chromatin state is
set up in one cell state and how they
change over time. And if you did that,
you can then develop the envelope of how
the chromatin state transitions uh
change uh in a disease context. So these
kind of things can be very useful when
you really look at um uh you know
complex diseases. Here is an example
of breast tumor progression. This is a
uh ductal carcinoma that becomes
invasive car carcinoma. is the human
breast tissues tissue microarrays and we
emate the entire tissue microarray of
different stages of the disease and
fingerprint every nuclei for its state
of
chromatin. So we developed a scoring
system that we can then annotate a score
for this nuclei whether health or
disease state and the degree of disease
state. So using such a scoring system as
the disease sets in what you can see is
the cell state transition that happen
through the lens of how the chromatin is
changing in this context right from a
ductal carcinoma to invasive carcinoma.
So you get highdimensional readout of
the chromatin packing
states and how these packing states can
teach us about the biology of cell state
transitions. now right and using such uh
such methods um uh in collaboration with
um Caroline's lab and in particular
Shini she'll talk about some of this I
think in her talk what we developed is a
way of taking all the cell state that
exists in these tissues and cluster them
cluster them from healthy to disease
states and what you see is that uh this
kind of a clustering method can annotate
fraction of cells cells that are in the
healthy state, how the fractions of
these cells change from the health state
to the disease state as the disease
progresses. And one of the surprising
thing to me at
least that came out of this effort was
that if you fingerprinted the chromatin
states of the cells in different disease
states, different stages of the breast
tumor, you start seeing that even in the
healthy tissue, there are residual cells
which have the chromatin fingerprints of
a disease state, right? Although they're
not diseased state, they're annotated by
a pathologist as normal, but there are
residual cells. And it seems then that
as the disease progresses, your spatial
temporal
reorganization of these fraction of
cells that make this ducts into very
highly metastatic um duct. So this
allows us to trace uh cell state
transitions through the process of how
uh breast tumor progression happens. In
fact, there's a big unmet medical
challenge even today around the world
that we cannot predict which tumor
becomes aggressive and which tumor
doesn't become aggressive. There's a
over treatment as soon as a as a as a
individual is detected of ductal
carcinoma only 30% of them go on to
become invasive ductal carcinoma but we
cannot predict which one will become
invasive and which one will not become
invasive. So there's an ongoing project
in the lab to try and figure that out.
Now can we really figure out through the
lens of chromatin states which states
are aggressive and which states are um
non-aggressive. So with this uh what it
suggests is that if imaging modality can
give us so much about the
biochemistry there must be really good
ways to translate information from one
domain of the data to the other domain
of the data. Again here I'm not going to
go into all the details. We wondered
about this because I think these are
some of the work done in Caroline's
group was actually initiated this
multi-dommain data translation methods
in the field early on and what you see
is a picture of cells and the nuclear
and the DNA because the DNA is folded in
a very hierarchical m manner. This
should be able to tell us maybe to
predict what could be the transcriptto
of this
cell or what could be the genomic
architecture of this cell that are very
hard to measure. Right? These types of
uh you know data inensive measurements
in terms of omix technologies are pretty
expensive if you want to do it on a
whole body scale, whole tissue scale.
But what is a cheap data modality is in
imaging is a cheap data modality. I mean
depending on who you talk to. If you
talk to Jennifer she uses very high-end
machines that might be expense little
expensive but still it's much cheaper
than taking OMIX data of of cells. So
through this number of um you know
iterations what we are now shown is by
taking pictures single cell pictures and
learning how the single cell sequencing
could be in those cells even with
unpaired data we can now start uh
annotating what could be the
transcriptto of cells from an imaging
data modality. uh also these are
challenging uh multi-dommain data
translation because imaging pixels
whereas sequencing is numbers. So there
are many methods now that allow you to
go from this space to to various spaces.
So now in recent
work we have also shown that not only
you can go to transcryto or the taxic or
the high sea of that cell from an image
but we can also go to more biochemical
circuitry of the cell because ultimately
you want to understand the regulatory
mod uh so we can convert that into gene
regulatory network that's going to come
out or shiny will talk about how you can
predict protein localization from
imaging space where do the proteins go
and sit and so on and so forth.
And this is a very powerful enterprise
now around the world that because a cell
is complex has many many different
dimensions of how the data is
represented in a cell and you want to if
you want to understand the cell you need
to be able to annotate most of these
different data domains but it's hard to
acquire all the data domains of a single
cell. So these kind of translation
methods, data integration methods would
be valuable particularly if you can take
a simple picture. So we got excited
about this because if there is so much
information in a
picture, we should be able to enable
early diagnostics because it's so hard
to know where the diseases start in the
body. But maybe if we come up with a
simple hypothesis, we might be able to
succeed in early diagnostics. So that's
what we did. uh is based on an idea that
as all of you know any diseases that
start in the body secrete signals
whether it's tumor whether there's
neurodeeneration whether it's metabolic
disorders they all secrete signals to
the local environment and these signals
which are chemical signals end up in the
blood uh eventually and our blood cells
the immune system is the most sensitive
system in a body to detect any subtle
changes in the secret signals in the
body. So our hypothesis was that let's
image the blood cell chromatin state the
peripheral blood cell white blood cell
chromatin state and ask could that be a
detector of the physiology right so if
we can actually demonstrate this
hypothesis what that tells you is that
not only tells you about immune function
we can annotate that but also tells you
about early diagnostic meth approaches.
So here is an example of taking from a
tumor healthy donors and a tumor
patients. Um I think this was head and
neck cancer. We take the peripheral
blood cells collect the blood from the
body. It's very easy to
collect take pictures of the of the
blood cell chromatin state right and
through these we could already show that
with very high precision very high
sensitivity we can actually distinguish
between cancer p cohort and healthy
cohort right so that means that because
the immune cells are so sensitive uh we
could actually detect very early on
signals that are starting from the
disease right So this has led into two
successful finishing trials now clinical
trials in Switzerland where we can
actually now
ask can we then use this not only for
early diagnostics but efficacy of
treatments because there's hardly any
good method in the world today once
you're treated for a disease about the
relapse because the imaging method that
we have has a resolution of 1 million 1
millm when you take different imaging
modalities. But as you know diseases
start from cells. If you delete the
disease, you want to ask how much have
you deleted. So this is an effort to
look at proton therapy for advanced
tumors. This is a finish the trial is
finished. Uh uh and actually we're now
putting out the data on the paper
together with Caroline and her student
Hannah.
And what this trial suggested to us is
that uh as the it's a very systematic
trial. You collect the blood before
therapy, during therapy, after therapy
and post therapy to see how the immune
cell chromatin state is changing. Is it
coming towards the healthy cohort or is
staying as the disease cohort, right? So
we can actually now with this method
annotate every patient level
trajectories um of how the disease
progression and disease um therapeutic
efficacy can be annotated. Likewise we
have another trial that got finished.
Can we detect metabolic disorders using
this um chromatin states of blood cells
because metabolic disorders are a big
disorder in the field and is it possible
to use cost effective methods as this
simple images to give you uh insights on
metabolic disorders. Again um one of a
colleague who did this is in the
audience somewhere uh in the lab. So
this has motivated us to
ask move towards a large public health
project where we would seek all of your
help uh both in terms of uh funding but
also participation in the public health
project. What we're now trying to do is
can we then fingerprint blood cell
chromatin states of individuals. Uh if
we have a map of that of healthy
individuals then that's a reference map
that we can create. So this is what I'll
end with that we have started this
project in in partnership with the Swiss
Red Cross because how do you define who
is healthy and who is not healthy
because every clinician will not agree
to their own interpretation. So what we
decided to do was to partner with Swiss
Red Cross where they have a series of
checklist to make sure that a person who
donates blood is healthy with some some
boundary conditions and this blood is uh
implanted in the other individuals. So
we we're having that checklist as uh a a
measure of healthy individuals. And so
we are now uh you know taking uh blood
from a large uh cohort of Swiss citizens
across different age groups and male and
female. The idea is to create like a
like a chromatin imaging atlas of blood
cells, peripheral white blood cells
which is so informative of the
physiology in the body as a map that
will give us uh ability to do early
diagnostics because then any outlier of
the chromatin state outside this would
be an annotation for a disease. So we
are now large clinical trials starting
with uh uh you know with a one of the
biggest hospitals in Switzerland uh to
really fingerprint uh patients who come
for early diagnostics through PET
scanning
uh to collect the blood before the PET
scan and look at the blood chromatin
state and fingerprint and we have all
the metadata of the patients um to
fingerprint how their chromatin states
or blood cells look like um in the
context of various diseases and use a
healthy chromatin state as a reference
map, right? Because you need a good
reference benchmark to say and the
hetrogenity within because every one of
us is very different. Even though we are
healthy, you may look at the blood from
each one of you. The chromatin state is
very different depending on what you've
eaten, what is your metabolic activity,
whether you have small small cough,
cold, so on so forth. So we need to map
that envelope of the hetrogenity which
is a fingerprint which is an atlas that
we need to create and this is a large
project um and then we're also taking it
towards uh you know precision or simple
uh optical methods that are that can be
uh that these blood cell chromatin
states could be visualized on a small
microchip that's connected to a very
highly sensitive camera that microscope
that we have built.
and we're now prototyping the second
version that can connect to a simple
mobile phone so that then we can
actually take it to scale up the process
because then we can actually fingerprint
a lot more volunteers around the around
the globe. So right now this is a
Swissbased program and we'll sign we'll
eventually make it into a larger scale
program and we are of course writing to
a lot lot of foundations to fund this.
uh with that let me
end. So what I took you through today is
very simple ideas of a cell that sits in
a tissue micro
environment senses both mechanical and
physical
signals mechanical and biochemical
signals. We're used to thinking of
biochemistry more, but it's important to
realize that mechanochemistry is what
cells see in our tissues, right? And
that in that signals integrate to cells
and that with a loss of homeostasis, you
can induce a cell state transition. So
what I showed you today is how general
principles exist in our cells to
integrate mechano chemistry, transduce
them through canonical signaling
pathways, remodel the way chromatin
structure is set up in these cells
depending on the micro environmental
cues and that gave you outputs
differential outputs for the same cell,
same signals but very different outputs
because of the mechanics,
And based on this uh what I showed you
also is that we can
induce cell state transition because
that could be the precursor for
understanding cells how they switch into
diseases in
tissues. And that's that's what we're
now looking at with lots of these um
tissue based analysis that we're doing.
And on the other side, what I showed you
is the way that our genomes are
packed and its intimate link with
biochemistry, complex multi-dimensional
biochemical networks. The images of
chromatin gives you a fingerprint for
that cell state. And that fingerprint is
very, you know, resourceful, valuable
because then we can say the health of
the cell or disease in any complex uh
environment, right? whether it's
neurodeenerative
uh tissues, early developmental
programs, differentation programs or
disease disease programs, we can then
fingerprint cell state transitions with
that. So with that, let me end. I think
my time is up. Um let me thank a
wonderful set of colleagues uh who come
from very different areas. computer
science, cell biology, molecular biology
and engineering and physics and a number
of scientists that uh that are part of
this program and this work that we do is
uh in close collaboration with
Caroline's lab here with the broad a
number of very talented colleagues in
our lab contribute to our ongoing
programs as we move forward and I think
Shini one of the very talented
colleagues of us she will present in
this session I think yeah Okay, with
that, thank you so
[Applause]
much. So, I find the idea of actually
trying to predict things from blood very
powerful because it's very non-invasive
and and and it's sort of grail and I can
see how metabolic diseases have a very
strong signature because the high
metabolic state highly impacts chromatin
regulation. But a lot of diseases result
in like this massive inflammatory signal
that sometimes is, you know, at least I
I play with gene expression and single
cell expression. It's hard to sort of
dissect the different inflammatory
diseases, the inflammation signal is
just so overwhelming. So I'm wondering
if you begin to see differences or how
you would like dissect the different
like onslaught of causes of uh
inflammatory signals in in your
approach. No, that's a great question.
you know, so one of the things that we
we wanted to first identify is can we
distinguish between um a cancer versus
non-cancer another disease right so the
reason I say it is that you know uh you
get a disease specific secret in the
blood right and so the chromatin states
alter depending on the signals right so
if it is a cancer signal the chromatin
state remodel in one particular way
versus if it's the neurodeenerative
signal that we're now looking for uh
chromatin reorganized in a completely
different way in a metabolic disorder.
Of course, the output is single cell
transparing in immune
cells. the the idea that images of
chromatin has a powerful fingerprint in
the way that chromatin can alter because
you can't alter chromatin in many
different ways because you know we only
have a finite type of cell states in the
body. So there only allowed
configuration that chromatin can switch.
This what we are now testing that's why
this um large scale project is to
fingerprint what are the alert states of
chromatin that it can go
to how can we distinguish between just
inflammation inflammatory response
versus disease specific responses right
and this is an ongoing program any ideas
happy to uh get from you but what we can
already distinguish is that given that
different secret gives you different
chromatin states
And it's easy for us to scale up. We can
then good get very good stat statistical
insights on the chromatin state allowed
chromatin states in different context.
Right? Whether how early we can detect I
don't know at the
moment right these are late stage
detection that we have shown but we are
hopeful that we should if we get this uh
you know healthy donor atlas as a
reference map we should be able to
detect outliers much more easily because
a healthy donor atlas will tell us about
the variability that can exist in the
chromatin state of blood cells depending
on all the individuals even 10,000 we
are now trying to do for 10,000 um uh
donors I don't think that's enough we
need to scale that up more uh so we're
in the process
of yeah one quick question
u just very practical you know there
might be others uh
competitive you know about marker you
know for the early detection of the
breast cancer and I just cross the path
from the you
clinical research book and my quick
question is that did you find the
positive predictive value of your
studies and how does it compare to other
biomarker whether I should pick your you
know uh chromatin structure as a
initiate for public health or some other
yeah yeah that's a that's a fair enough
question you know the the space is too
large right because early diagnosis is a
big field in the it's billions of
dollars because so important there are
very competing technology the most
mature technology is this ctna you know
disease cells secrete DNA pieces into
the blood and the modifications of the
DNA pieces in the blood is a powerful
biioarker for disease right there other
competing technology exoomes disease
cells release small vesicles and
proteins inside them there's a lot of
mass spec proteomic approaches for
detecting exosomes in the in the blood
and circulating disease cells,
circulating tumor cells, circulating
disease cells. The other technology is
that what we are suggesting is a
completely orthogonal approach because
by the biology of the immune system how
sensitive they are we think that the
chromatin alterations could be yet
another modality and a cheap modality
because in the field if you want to
detect early I can't take a sequencing
machine or a mass spectrometry machine
but I can take my mobile phone if we if
we succeed. So now the benchmarking is
what we are doing with that class that
we are doing. Give us a year or two and
I'll tell you how it competes with other
technologies. Yeah. Thank you. Yeah.
Thank you. Thank you Shiva for this
wonderful talk. I will hand over to
Dora.
[Music]