BTO, representative of Moon Vision
Company.
Vamos.
Uh, hello everyone. My name is Tankto.
I'm the CEO and co-founder of M Vision.
In this presentation, I will primarily
focus on heat leaching and mineral
processing. We all know, we all heard
the world needs a lot more copper and
other metals than is currently
producing. But most of it if not all of
it is expected to be coming from
lowgrade or heat bleaching is ideally
suited for processing lowgrade or as it
is less energy and water intensive than
conventional mineral processing on a per
ton of produced metal basis. Today
leeching is already a hundred billion
dollar industry producing more than 20%
of worldwide copper. As many of you know
very well, the leeching process is
deceptively simple because after all in
leeching the or is mined sometimes it is
crushed and then stacked onto huge
piles. These are then irrigated from
above with a solution that ideally uh
will permeate through the whole stack
wetting it uniformly dissolving the
metal contained in the mineral grains in
the or itself. However, there are many
reasons why this actually does not
happen in practice and the fluid does
not distribute uniformly across a full
scale heap. And this creates a classic
Goldilocks problem. Too little fluid
content is the leading cause for poor
recovery. But too much poses the risk of
mass massive potentially catastrophic
landslides. And the two often are
related, meaning that if some portion of
the leeching heap is too dry and
unproductive, it is likely that some
other portion is too wet and potentially
dangerous. But how do you go about
solving this problem? Not only the pile
is thick and opaque, which doesn't allow
you to see inside, it's also huge, which
means that any sampling campaign is
going to be costly, slow, and by
definition incomplete. Well, today we
think we can thanks to a special kind of
natural occurring X-ray,
which
>> in the last few decades, scientists have
finally been able to look inside ancient
pyramids and volcanoes. Muon Vision is
now using that same technology to
revolutionize mining. The breakthrough
behind this revolution, muon
radiographic imaging, also known as
murography. Muons are subatomic
particles naturally formed when
radiation from distant supernova
explosions collide with the Earth's
atmosphere. Muons constantly penetrate
every square meter on the surface of the
Earth. At Muon Vision, we've developed a
subterranean technology capable of
detecting and recording muons as they
travel deep underground. We then use
that data to create 3D density maps of
large above ground structures like
tailings dams and leech piles. In a
mineral leech pile, for example, Muon
Vision's technology can identify dry low
density areas where leeching fluid isn't
reaching. When operators can see this
issue, they have the chance to adjust
their processing and prevent billions of
dollars in assets from being left
behind. In tailings dams, the same
technology can precisely determine the
static stresses on the material as well
as friatic levels, thus validating the
dam design and helping increase its
performance. When you see deeper, you
can work smarter. Muon detection
empowers you to look inside mining's
largest structures and optimize for
efficiency, profitability and safety.
See deeper with Neuon vision.
So what we offer is a service is a
radiographic imaging service that for
the first time allows operators to scan
map quantify critical fluid content as
well as uh air concentration in sichu in
near real time with very high precision
and continuously while operating
entirely remotely together. This has
never been done before. We think that
this represents a disruptive step change
and allows us to build that digital twin
that will finally identify, locate and
quantify the remedial actions that we
need to take place in order to maximize
the productivity and the safety of the
asset. In other words, instead of
proceeding blindly, which forces you to
process the material in just a single
pass even it is known that the material
is not homogeneous, with this service,
we can unlock additional value. This
includes maximizing yields from ongoing
operations, identifying secondary
leeching opportunities, reducing or
optimizing the consumptions of water and
exceivate
risks, costs and delays associated with
human interventions or routine sampling
were warranted. But senator three also
reducing and better managing the risk
for REI failure which as you can see
here can be a truly catastrophic event
for the asset the company and the
community all the way to potentially
extending the life of assets to defer
closure cost or to better time or
removal in highly mechanized operations
like on and off leeching. So here is an
example of what our service actually
sees. This was a small leeching
operations outside of La Ligua. The
customers you can see here started
irrigation and slowly the fluid start
partially filling the pore space in the
material. The density of the material
should therefore increase increase and
for the first 100 hours that is exactly
what we see. Higher density in the heat
means more attenuation and therefore
less muons and that's what we are
showing. But we also see the right
amount of densification.
The observed 3% drop that you see on the
muon flux is actually equivalent to a 5%
density increase in the heap material
itself which under reasonable
assumptions corresponds to having added
20% of fluid into the pore space which
is the operating point for a leeching
heap like this of a gomerated or but
this is not the end of the story
although the customer would have
expected that from here on the density
of the hippo staying constant it doesn't
in fact as the operation progresses now
we see that the number of muons is going
back up and the heap is getting lighter
even though the irrigation rate has not
changed. What could be happening here?
The most probable conclusion is that the
heap is actually losing its fluid likely
because of a preferential channeling
effect. And as you can see the
difference between
where you would like to be and where you
actually are is actually significant.
And no wonder this heat may actually be
producing a lot less at the end of the
cycle. This is not something you could
tell just by looking at the fluid coming
out of the leeching heap itself. and
he's an example of a problem that you
cannot diagnose reliably without
munioraphic imaging.
A little bit about our story and our
path. We started a few years ago in
Chile actually and while still small, we
have been steadily growing. We are now
capable of offering our patented
solutions and services across a range of
tool sizes and uh operate while
operating off the grid. We are
remotizing actually the last aspect of
our scanning service that is the
movement of the sensor themselves at
which point we will be able to fully run
in the background of mining operations
with minimal interference. At the same
time we are building advanced control
panel and visualization interfaces where
you can access your data seamlessly in
the cloud. And yes of course we built
and test our detectors in Chile. Today
we can also leverage our brand new uh
underground facility for murography
located about 40 minutes outside of
Santiago. Here we can show to cast
interested parties how our service works
but also we can validate it against
known density standards under control
conditions. This one-of-a-kind facility
was designed with a goal of uniquely
improving our readiness and decreasing
the risk around the adoption of our
technology. We have put together a
startup team which is a mix of young
talent, experienced professionals and
industry leader with more than 100 year
100 years of industry experience. As you
can see, most of the team is actually
here in Providentialia Santiago and we
actually importing scientists to Chile
like Adrian who was up to a few months
ago a postto at MIT.
Before I conclude, I would like to
clearly state that what MU vision does
and is capable of doing is not only
leeching. After all, m radiography is a
general purpose non-destructive uh
platform for non-destructive evaluation.
And indeed, we have identified multiple
opportunities across the mining value
chain from exploration to mining plans
and of course critical slope stability.
What we offer today is a digit
digitalization service which I hope you
can appreciate as being unique. Tomorrow
however, our ambition is to offer much
more and we hope to walk some of that
path together. Finally, as preparing
this presentation, I was also asked to
justify why why Chile. Well, that's
actually the easy part. We can say for
as you heard, you know, as we know,
Chile copper production and reserves are
more relevant than Saudi Arabia to oil
and gas to make an example. But we also
find that Chile is a very friendly
environment and most importantly to us,
we can access excellent human excellent
human resources and we mean it. You saw
that in the previous slide. We are
committed to hiring Chileenos and keep
growing in this country. There are also
technical reasons for doing coming to
Chile after all is the country of one
and a half leeching heaps which is one
of the most promising use cases of our
technology and also finally Chile has
very high elevation mines and for us uh
that is actually a a gift because the
best location for any midography
application is at higher elevation as
possible which means more muons and
therefore faster measurements.
What are we asking? Our mission is
really to help you do more and better,
but we still sit outside of the fence
and we don't really see what you see. So
what we're really asking is a continued
engagement so we can together define and
quantify the best opportunities ahead.
The old model of producing more just by
digging more. We think it's changing and
today mining is industry has a clear
desire to innovate. Our X-ray powers,
unique X-ray powers are ready to
transform it with your help and deliver
a step change to this critical essential
industry. Thank you very much.
[Applause]