Well, welcome to the final session here
um today and I hope you've enjoyed it so
far. This is going to be the highlight
because we're going to be hearing from
from eight different students. But the
the motivation for this, we're going to
call this Pico Talks um came from um a
question that people ask us. So, my name
is York Shivine. I'm the associate
director for fab.no together with an
arrhof associate director for
characterization. We're going to be the
chairs of this next session. And often
people come to us and ask what do people
do at MIT nano and and this is actually
a very difficult question. It's a
difficult question because we have 1500
users. So in principle I have to give
you 1500 answers. Um and of course 21%
of all MIT faculty use MIT Nano. So I'd
have to describe a large chunk of MIT
and more than 50 different department
labs and centers come through the
building in one form or another. Right?
So it's really really difficult to pin
that down into one particular thing. And
so what we're going to try to do instead
is to combine that give you a glimpse of
eight different areas that we found
found interesting and then hopefully in
doing so show you some curious
commonalities that you may find
throughout these talks of different
research areas that are completely
unrelated yet have a lot of things in
common like scaling up quantum effects
all kinds of things nano. So hopefully
you'll enjoy that.
Um I'll just add a few things. Uh nano
is about people. Uh it's not about tools
right and here we are showing you a very
diverse group of people in terms of
their interests and their research but
as you will see there are no boundaries
between their talks on the pico scales.
There are not really boundaries because
you cannot see them right all the
boundaries are are on the pico scale. So
um we will see the flow from one to
another and you will see like your said
the commonalities of a scale up and
commonalities of a quantum and
commonalities of mechanical testing that
go from one technology to another and
together we kind of going to transition
all of this and make a better world. I
think this is uh aligns with our
mission. So I will call.
>> Okay. So uh hello everyone. Uh my name
is Yanja and I'm currently a postto
working with professor Jiz Dalamo group
and uh our group's name is extreme
transistor research group. So I'm going
to show you how we can build one of the
most extremely skilled transistors in
the world um right atano.
So transistors are
oh
It's okay. Okay. Oh, so transi trans
transistors are the smallest building
blocks of uh modern microronic chips.
And so if you talk about microronics, we
can see it in our data life and it's
really ubiquitous. And I'm just showing
you on the left eight examples.
And probably one of the most popular
example nowadays is this AI hardwares as
I'm showing here. And in fact this is a
figure generated by AI and I really took
took me a lot of time to to train. I
like to let it generate in this fancy
way. But anyway um and uh these AI
models are really powered by these
microchips and these chips are inside
all these mainframes and in the clock
cloud. And these are the magics that we
can really get to the AI and already we
we have seen the superpowers of AI and
it is cool but it comes at a cost which
is the energy.
In fact about uh four years ago at 2020
people have been aware of how much
energy the AI could burn to support that
explosive growth. And just after four
years at 2024, a few uh maybe last year,
major tech companies have already turned
to these small nuclear uh module
reactors to power their data centers.
And apparently this is not a sustainable
trend. So how to solve this? Well, we
really have to go down to the bottom and
to see if we can get extremely energy
efficient microronic systems. And so
that's where our research comes in. But
in fact people have been trying to do
that for the uh micronics in the past 55
years and that can be seen from this
moral scaling in which I'm showing you
here that the number of transistors on a
microchip is doubling every two years or
um in microchip u microprocessor
including this microprocessors and GPUs.
So the size of these microchips are not
getting larger and larger. So the only
way to make this happen is to make
transistor footprint smaller and smaller
and in that way you can get much better
energy efficiency um as as well as um
higher performance.
So I will not go into too much details
here but that really comes to how we can
make this transistor smaller and that is
uh what we are uh researching about and
the the first um invention of the
transistor was in this planner structure
um in which you have this source gate
and drain terminals and so you can use
the gate to control the electron flowing
from the source to drain or so you can
turn on or turn off that electron flow
and there is a already a key design
parameter the gate lines. I will talk
about that later. Um and in about 2012,
people realized that well these
transistors are no longer able to
support further performance improvement
or energy efficiency improvement. So we
have to turn to three-dimensional
transistors. And as I'm showing on the
right, this is the so-called
three-dimensional fin field fuel
transistors or finite. uh you see this
silicon uh sheet is extruding out of the
planner substrate and then the gate is
wrapping around uh the channel. So in
that way you can get better performance
and also better energy efficiency. But
again this electrons still flowing from
the source to drain in the planner
direction.
And uh so if you look at the evolution
of these fins from this 22nometer node
when Intel first uh introduced this in
the manufacturing all the way to this 10
nometer node which is the state of art
for fin fats the evolution shows us that
the fins are getting higher higher and
higher also the weights of the fins are
getting smaller. So the cowars you can
see here I'm labeling the the weights at
the half height of the fins is about
seven nanometer and the height of the
fins is about 53 nanometer. So that
gives you a aspect ratio of 7.5
and uh there is also fundamental
limitations in how much you can scale
the gate lens. So um from uh many uh
physical barriers the minimum scale is
about 20 nometer below which these
transistors are no longer functional
anymore.
So how can we even get to smaller and
small transistors if we have some
fundamental limitations on one of the
directions right and our solution is
that we instead of flowing the electrons
in the horizontal direction we can
really flowing these electrons in the
vertical direction and in that way we
can minimize the footprint while still
we can have controllable device parame
uh device performance
and so in the right uh sorry in the
middle I'm showing you probably the most
uh skilled threedimensional transistor
till date. Um, and so it features these
6 nanometer diameter vertical nanowires
at a half height with 135 nanometer
height. So that gives you more than 20
aspect ratio which is quite impressive.
And we also introduced a new physical
magnum that I will not go into details
and it is basically the quantum
mechanical tunneling um between these uh
two material interface. And so in that
way you can further boost the
performance and as I showed as I
mentioned before um these transistors
are electrically controlled switches. So
that means you can use the gate voltage
to control the flow of the current. And
so this uh on on the right figure I'm
showing you that if we compare the um
the so-called transfer curves um of our
transistors to the state of the art 10
nanometer node from Intel then we see at
just.3 volt VGS or supply voltage which
is quite small compared to the nowadays
uh 7 volt uh supply voltage we get over
30% performance boost and uh so that
shows you it is a promising technology
although there are a lot of
manufacturing challenges and so it is
still not yet the the on the road map
but we hope that we provide a new
solution. Um so looking ahead for the
future uh in our opinion the
threedimensional transistors is a very
important building block and still we
need to sky stack multiple layers of
functional devices right on top of each
other in a monolithic 3D integration way
and so we call this 3D transistors into
3D system scheme and we think this will
give us much more energy efficiency and
so we can solve this energy consumption
problem and can power more AI
development in the future. And with
that, I'd like to acknowledge uh my
adviserss and mentors, professor Jizut
Almo, professor Dimitri Antonedis and uh
many many of our uh groups uh uh current
and previous members as well as our
sponsors Intel SRC MIT hardware and but
uh very important MIT nano for uh
providing us with these state-of-the-art
uh tools that we can make these
transistors into reality as well as MTLE
and ECS committee. Thank you.
And by the way, we'll take questions at
the end. You can also type them online,
but we have a microphone at the end. So,
we'll go to the next uh next speaker.
>> All right. Thank you, York. Um, I'm
Karen Young. I'm a fourth year PhD
student here in the electrical
engineering department at MIT and I'll
be discussing a little bit about the
future of solar specifically how do we
go from this which is a you know 1 in x
1 in device level solar cell to this
flexible 4 in x 4 in module um and
thinking about why we're even going the
route of flexible lightweight solutions
so I guess the case for lightweight here
um we think that lightweight really is
the future of solar because we have this
huge dichotomy between what is required
to completely power the entirety of
America's energy needs and what is
actually being produced by solar in
America. Um so essentially all you need
is a solar array about the size of Lake
Michigan and you can completely power
all of America's energy needs. But we're
only using about 10% of the uh total
electricity generated is from solar. Uh
so technologically what can we do about
that? Well, we in envision a network of
distributed solar arrays which place the
power of solar installation into the
hands of individual homeowners and
businesses. Um, so this allows us to
open up a lot more uh markets where
traditional solar cannot be deployed in.
Uh, so currently a lot of the solar
insulation in America takes the form of
utility scale solar. So essentially, you
have these huge insolar insulations, you
know, out in remote areas, you know, in
very sunny areas, Nevada, New Mexico, as
well as out in like farms in Illinois
and stuff. Um, and then you pipe all of
that electricity from the source all the
way to your house or to a, you know,
commercial business, you'll have
transmission losses along that line, and
that really limits the amount of areas
you can uh electrify with solar. Um
however, if we completely rein uh
reimagine how solar deployment looks
like, we can imagine um we can put down
a solar panel on top of your own house,
on top of your own roof, on top of a
commercial business's roof, and that
really expands the amount of places we
are able to deploy solar in. So, how do
we do that? Well, right now, 99% of the
solar panels that you see out there is
made out of silicon. Um, and that's
because it's, you know, quite efficient,
high stability, and also it's a very
wellestablished technology. It's been
around for, you know, 50, 60 years. We
know how to make these things. We know
how to manufacture them, and we know
where to put these. However, because
silicon is so fragile, you need a
sandwich in between two quite thick
pieces of glass, and that makes it quite
heavy. Um so you are unable to mount it
on low loadbearing rooftops such as
older residential homes, commercial
warehouses, uh commercial factories and
also these are completely you know
useless for disaster relief as well as
access to remote areas such as remote
villages. Uh so how do we rethink solar?
Well, in comes perovskite which is the
area of research that I work on. Um we
can see here that you know they're
pretty high efficiency. We've gotten
them up to about where silicon is at. Um
they're pretty they're pretty stable.
You know, the record-breaking is about
T80 80% of its initial efficiency for
about 9 9,000 hours. Um more
importantly, however, you can
manufacture these things really simply.
Um they don't rely on a silicon supply
chain. So you're not relying on, you
know, silicon wafers coming in from
China. You can completely manufacture
these things inhouse. Um so that really
um is really powerful for indep for your
own independent supply chain and kind of
deconvoluting your process from
geopolitical factors. Most interestingly
to me um you can coat these things
because they are solution processible
onto pretty much any substrate you want
including plastic which is the substrate
of choice that we'll be discussing
today. Um and that makes it a really
good solution for thin lightweight
flexible solutions.
So we want to do go with perovskites. Um
and how do we do that? Well um we use
something called slot deck coding. So
all of those really nice, you know, 26
27% high stability, high efficiency. All
of those devices are made with spin
coating. So it's the same spin coating
that you would use to spin on photo
resist um before you know development
and etching. Um, essentially how that
works is you have your substrate on a
chuck, the chuck spins, it makes a very
nice uniform film. Very nice for making
these high efficiency devices. Not so
scalable. So, how do we scale these? We
use something called slot decoding. Um,
and this is the slot decoder that you'll
find inside of the nanomat area inside
of Fab. Nano. It's enclosed within these
two glove boxes which are continuously
purged with compressed dry air. So, you
can get it down to about 2 3% very
controllable. Um, and then the actual
slot decoder is this thing right here.
Um, so how it works, I have a video of
an actual film being produced over
there. Um, but essentially how it works,
you have this syringe pump. It's pumping
solution through this I'll stand on this
side. Um, it's pumping solution through
this tube into this dye thing. And then
as the bed is moving, your solution is
coming out and that's what's creating
this film. So hopefully my video works.
There it goes. Okay. So we saw the dye
come down. The solution is getting piped
into the dye. It's flowing out of the
dye, creating this little thing right
here called a meniscus. And then you see
the bed move. And you see this nice
little yellow film here.
Uh so that's really good for making thin
films down to you know 10 20 nmters. Um
so
some struggles however of this it's not
you know as cut and dry as I explained
it to be on the previous slide. Uh so
first of all you need to make a
goodlooking film. So you need to make a
film that has doesn't have pin holes.
It's um defect free. Uh so a little bit
about the idea behind slot decoding. We
have this figure right here. On the
x-axis we have how fast the bed is
moving. On the y ais we have how much
solution you're pumping through the die.
And you want to be in this red area
right here. Um and we can see when we're
in this red area, you have a nice smooth
coating. However, if you step out of
this area, you can have uh some of these
examples are some of the defects that
you can experience. Um, but these
defects aren't always apparent in the
end film. So, how do we make sure that
we're actually in the red area? Well,
we've elected to implement some insitue
monitoring. So, this is kind of the
dream setup here. Um, we right now only
have cameras A and C. So, the camera C
is looking at the side profile of this
miniscus, which this is another video
I'll play in a second. And then the
leading meniscus camera is looking
basically from this side of it. Um so we
want to be able to see is the miniscus
behaving from the side as well as the
uniformity across the miniscus miniscus
itself. Okay,
there's the video. Okay, so we see you
know bed is moving the film is being
coated and then about halfway in you'll
see some bubbles right here. Yeah, right
there you see some little bubbles start
to form. Uh so without this side profile
monitoring this end film looks great
like to the eye it looks like something
that should work and then you complete
it into a device and it doesn't work. Um
so what happened here? Well we can you
know go back to our camera and see that
the meniscus and the coating wasn't
actually as stable as we thought it
would be. Um so once we fix this once we
get a good-looking film now we need to
control things like the drying and
crystallization. So I'll come back on
the other side. Um so we have an example
here of the drying crystallization. We
have three different solvents.
Essentially all you need to get from
this is that we can push the uh
stability of the wet film further and
further for longer times with this uh
mixture of solvents here. And that
allows us a bigger window to control the
drying and crystallization patterns. Um
that's all well and good. Doesn't matter
if it doesn't work. Um but it does work
as the title says proof is in the
perkite pudding. Um and we so we have
structurally made a good perovsky with
this XRD plot. We can see that all these
peaks are accounted for. This FAPBI3 is
perovsky. Um lead there's a little peak
there. Not too worried about that. Um so
structurally we made a good film.
Visually with SEM we've made a pretty
good crystal. You see that the grains
are you know about 750 nanometers a
micron wide. uh they're pretty pretty
compact, nice and dense. There's not a
lot of stuff at the grain boundaries. Um
so we've been able to make structurally
a good film and visually a good film. Um
and then we can go to the JV tester and
actually test if it is a good film. So
this 16 1.5% number here is when you
finish up this 50 mm by 50 miller
substrate here into a device. So the
next step here is to basically translate
this which is completely sauté coated um
into something like this which is a 4 in
x 4 in module um made on a flexible
plastic substrate.
So with that I just want to thank the
facilities at MIT Nano. This XRD plot
was collected on the you know fourth
floor building 13. This was collected
inside of characterization.no and then
all the fab was done inside of fab.no.
Um so again I just want to thank the
staff and facilities at MIT Nano as well
as my many colleagues in the one lab
including professor Vladimir Bovich um
Dr. Rahul Pachadar and Dr. Tamar Kadosh
um as well as our sponsors at the CEDO
office in the department of energy as
well as Petronis. So yeah thank you.
>> Hello everyone. Uh I am Alex. I have
done a variety of things around nano and
mtl for those of you who are familiar
with it. Uh and I'm going to tell you
about one of the more interesting
translational projects that I've done
that takes in as inspiration a lot of
principles we have as nano applies a few
of them and has resulted in something
pretty cool. Uh and that is art
restoration. Um art restoration not a
conventional nano subject. Um it is one
of the more bespoke uh areas of
expertise for people working in art
conservation. It involves a lot of
manual labor. Uh and basically I thought
around four years ago, what if we tried
to do something that involved any amount
of technology and wasn't just someone
sitting with a brush and in
a lot of the work that I've done here
has nothing to do with art restoration.
I've worked on things spanning medical
diagnostics, the growth of nanowires for
improving ionization efficiency, new
forms of electron lithography. Um, and
working on all of those has taught me
about precision. And I think nano really
is a lot about precision and working at
small scales and knowing what's
happening chemically, physically,
structurally in the design of new
devices and technologies. So, what I've
done to improve art restoration is to
take a damaged painting, apply a variety
of AI models to identify damages within
it, and then create a multi-layer mask
that goes over it to physically restore
it. And this is an exercise in
precision. Over 5,000 areas are restored
this way in under three hours. This is
almost two orders of magnitude quicker
than it could be done by hand. And this
involves quite a few interesting
structural aspects. So firstly, one of
the cool things that we can do is apply
some of the AI tools. So people here are
working on designing chips to create AI
models. We can use those to do digital
inpainting of damaged images of artworks
and result in digitally restored ones.
And then as many of you are familiar
with masks being used in nano and
fabrication, we can derive a mask of all
the areas that actually need to be
inpainted on a particular artwork. So
that mask comprises a series of color
accurate layers that are bound together
with a variety of membranes and
conservation grade varnishes. This mask
is truly quite thin. It is around 30
micrometers at its thickest. Um, it's
really difficult to handle. It is at the
limit of what humids could actually
interact with pretty reasonably. Um,
there's a cross-section of it. And once
it's applied over an artwork, it
physically masks damages to result in a
digitally restored version of an
artwork, but actually physically
manifested. Now, the cool thing about
this membrane, it's made of shortchain
hydrocarbons that are bound together
with varnishes that contain UV
absorbers. So, this mask is expected to
be able to work to preserve artworks for
around a century. And it's also very
easy to remove. It's bound to artworks
with a partly oxidized layer of varnish
so that it can be pretty simply peeled
off without damaging an underlying
artwork. So, that's just a taste of some
of the cool things that go into that.
Um, this is an incredibly quick process.
It restores thousands of damages in a
way that's parallelized and can rely on
some of the precision that's possible
with digital tools. Um, this has been
described by conservators across the
world as phenomenally cool, making their
lives easier, better, faster, and
cheaper. And I think that's kind of a
description of nano more broadly. I
think Nano is phenomenally cool. And it
makes a lot of people's lives easier,
better, faster, cheaper. And I hope you
appreciate some of the really cool
projects that emerge out of the space
and the labs that use it. So if you want
to learn more about this, I published
this in Nature. You can go read that. We
are raising money, so tell your rich art
friends to give their money to me. Thank
you so much.
Unfortunately, I have to bring the topic
back to the boring nanop fabrication. Uh
I'm Ishwan from Palasio's group at MIT
and I'll be telling you guys about our
work on the 2D transition metal
decoides. It's uh synthetis and uh from
system and integration applications.
So as all of you probably heard multiple
times today uh the mors law is chasing
us and as we're approaching the scaling
limit of the silicon devices we have to
look for new materials that as potential
channel material uh candidates for for
beyond uh the current technology
scalings. So one strong candidate would
be for the 2D materials and the 2D
materials not only can be a great
candidate for the front end of line uh
transistor devices and it also have um
capabilities to be added as the back and
line integration uh devices such as the
the quantum uh technologies and for
neuromorphic computing devices and
photonic integrated circuits and to uh
integrate 2D materials into the system
of the current mechanic
uh road map. We have several challenges
to overcome. Uh first we'll have the
materials because it's a relatively new
material uh compared to silicon which
has been around for decades. uh we have
to uh take care of the synthesis and the
characterization of the materials and
beyond that we have to look into device
engineering which is the scaling of the
uh 2D material based MOSFET devices and
maybe come up with some new design
because it's a new material and the next
step would be to integrate those into a
system uh that's like commercially
available and to do that we have to
consider the design technological co-op
optimization and system technological
co-op optimization.
So first of all we look at the synthesis
the part of work we do is to synthesize
the high performance 2D materials both n
type and ptype. Uh so for N type we'll
have Malibin dulfide and for Pype we'll
have tonselonide from the SEM images and
the OMA images here um well mostly
oh the OM image doesn't really tell much
from the SEM images here you can see the
uh we have deposited like quite uniform
model layer across the surface and from
the sharp peaks of the ramen and
photooluminescence uh spectrums you can
see the the optical quality of these
materials are pretty
And after we make them into MOSFET
devices, uh their performance in terms
of the current density and the uh the
opto uh the output characteristics are
pretty excellent. And but these are
small scale fabrications to make these
um compatible for foundaries for
industries. We have to scale up. So to
to scale up the the deposition of the um
2D materials, we have uh built this
customized the MLCVD system that is
capable of depositing MOS2 at um on the
8 in platforms and is also capable of
doing so at a back end of line cap
silicon compatible temperature 400° C.
And from these
I went over. So from these uh um device
statistics and the mobility and
threshold voltage maps, we can see the
material is quite uniform for in terms
of the uh 8 inch wafer scale.
And now that we have the materials,
we're looking at some uh device
engineering part. So with the uh FAB
capability at MIT Nano and materials
that we grow, we were able to make some
of the world's smallest transistors uh
with the physical channel length of 2.8
8 nometers and they performed
exceptionally well uh in terms of their
uh scale and to increase the performance
as well as the uh response time um we
also looking into building these uh
multi- channelannel MOS transistor which
means instead of one channels we have
now have two channels of MOS2 as well as
three gates to improve the control and
current density as you can see from here
and you know these new materials like
people always people from The industry
always ask uh what good are they if
they're not reliable. So we also perform
these reli reliability study for MOS2
transistors and from the uh the positive
bias temperature instability test and
the healthcare injection test we can see
these MOS transistors in terms of
stability are comparable to the current
silicon uh NOS devices
and step up from the front end line
devices. Now we look at the back end of
line integration uh functionalities
which ah it's animation. So uh first we
have the graphing based bio sensor. Um
it is a um functionalized by uh
functionalized the graphing based sensor
and can be made into a rate and
integrated into uh with the with the PCB
system into a complete uh system that
can analyze say your breath to tell uh
very health conditions which has um a
lot of interest from the health
industries and also we're making these
MOS2 based hydrogen sensor which can
tell uh which is functionalized by
palladium palladium uh pad platium And
it can uh increase in current in
response to the presence of hydrogen uh
which is uh brings uh you know hydrogen
sensing capability to to your micro
electronic systems. So all of these
works that we've done in the past uh are
uh quite terrific if I can say that and
uh we're keep exploring new
opportunities for the 2D material
applications and obviously not none of
this can be done without the uh the help
of MIT nano and our sponsors and uh my
lovely group and collaborators professor
Jin Khan and Jetty. Thanks. And if
you're interested in my research, uh you
can ask about them in the Q&A session or
we can connect afterwards. Thank you.
>> Um good afternoon. I'm Sen. I'm a postto
at uh the Roland Institute at Harvard.
And today I'm going to talk about how we
use a advanced electron microscopy
techniques um like the one you have in
MIT nano to study a tiny tiny scale
distortions a peer scale distortion in
quantum materials like the one you're
seeing here in uranium oxyelide with
this uh beautiful super modulated
structures.
So to back up, so quantum materials. So
these are things these are the materials
where the electrons in their crystals
like to interact strongly with
themselves as as well as the crystal
itself and in doing so uh shows
unexpected and often a super material
properties. These include things like
superc conductivity, metal to insulate
transitions and a lot more. And they
have they hold a tremendous perspective
for being ne uh foundation for the next
generation electronics, quantum
computing, advanced sensing and
detections and more.
One of the key feature of these material
is that these electrons likes to
interact strongly with the lattice that
they reside in. So for instance one
titanium dulfide is a classic quantum 2D
material where at high temperature at
room temperature it it conducts
electricity quite well. But once you
cool down below 100 Kelvin or so they
suddenly becomes insulator. So it shows
a metal to insulator transition. And
when that happens these atoms actually
moves a tiny amount uh from their
original uh lattice position. So they
distort about few pometers that is
1,000th of nanometer. So as a electron
microscopist what we aim to do is we aim
to look at the atomic positions atom by
atom and map those distortions pometer
scale distortions using the microscopes.
So the microscope technique that we use
is called scanning transmission electron
microscopy.
Uh in essentially what we do is we boil
off electrons from hot metal and we
accelerate them to high voltage here
300,000 volt and at that energy the
electrons are now moving at half of the
speed of the light and then we use a
highly um engineered set of
electromagnetic lenses to focus them
down to single point smaller than
one/10enth of nanometer and then we use
those electron beam to probe our
materials.
Sounds science fictiony, but if you go
down to the basement of MIT nano, they
actually have multiple of those
microscopes and we can use those
microscope to form image like this. So
here the each one of those fuzzy little
white spheres are columns of atoms. The
brighter ones are heavy tentum atoms and
the lighter ones are sulfur atoms. So we
have tools where we can see atoms uh
column by column.
So uranium oxyloride these are newly
rediscovered quantum 2D materials and if
you look at uh the lattice structure uh
you see the atoms are arranged in in
square lattice pattern.
If you were to look at it from the side
view, you will note that the yellow
tarium atoms here are separated with uh
has big separations
and um in fact these are so weakly
bonded that you can use literally scotch
tape to exfoliate uh mono mono or few
layers and you can in fact transfer onto
a flat surfaces and even do nanop
fabrication onto them.
So my collaborators at Harvard uh
measured the electronic properties of
this crystal along the horizontal axis
and they found that it was quite
insulating and because your crystal here
is forming a square pattern you'd expect
that you should be insulating both in
the horizontal axis as well as vertical
axis. But to our surprise we found out
that along the vertical axis it was
actually quite conductive and was uh
quite metallic.
So this is quite contradictory of itself
because if I'm sitting here in the
crystal and looking at these atoms, it
should be same vertical versus
horizontal. But if I'm electron here
sitting in this crystal, now the
vertical is quite different than the
horizontal. So that's where I come in as
electron microscopist. So I grab the
sample from Cambridge, the west side of
Cambridge, and take the T, go to MIT
nano and put the sample into one of
these microscopes. And this is what we
get.
So once again these fuzzy dots are
columns of atoms and we are seeing these
square lattice patterns as we were
expecting.
But if you have good eyes for these kind
of things and if you actually squint a
little bit to make all the uh to to make
your vision a little blurriier you might
able to see there is a faint modulations
of intensities.
Okay. So this immediately answers some
questions. the the reason why electrons
were flowing one way but not the other
way is because the lattice is not
actually square. There's something going
on horizontally versus vertically. Of
course, we wanted to really understand
what was going on. So, we decided to uh
take the sample out, prepare another
sample along the cross-sectional axis
and take a look at what it looks like.
And to our pleasant surprise,
this is what it looks like.
So the most striking feature here uh it
would be this black dark intensities
arranged everywhere and if we zoom in a
little bit you will see that those dark
intensities are voids. So what's
happening is instead of these layers
being completely flat they form a wiggly
set of layers. So we have a supervised
modulation of the crystallin structure
where it becomes this uh corrugated
layers instead of a flat layers. So we
have something like this where electrons
like to flow along the valleys and
troughs but not not across them. So now
that we have some understanding of
what's going on you know the obvious
next question is what can we do with
this? So it turns out that this
displacements these modulations are not
pure sinosoidal and it has a lot of
higher harmonic components to it and and
in combination of all of that they
actually break a specific set of crystal
symmetry. uh here it breaks inversion
symmetry as well as the time reversal
symmetry and then because uranium atoms
are uh magnetic uh we can actually use
them to generate spin current out of
this crystal and maybe use it as a spin
current source for um spintronics
devices.
Okay, to wrap up, uh we imaged a a piece
of uranium oxyoride crystal using MIT
nanos microscope and we discovered this
beautiful super modulation pattern that
was hiding within. Um I want to thank
all of my collaborators as well as Dr.
Aubrey Pen who babysits the microscope
every single day to its best of
capabilities. Thank you.
Okay. Um, hi everyone. Thanks for
coming. Thanks to the organizers for
organizing this summit. Uh, my name is
Ahmed. I'm a grad student in physics in
the group of uh, Professor Kum at MIT.
And today's talk is going to be based on
our recent work on photonics with a two
dimensional magnet.
Okay.
So, light is the fastest and the
cleanest information carrier we know and
photonics is the science and technology
of it. It underpins uh modern life from
the global internet to advanced
manufacturing.
Part of the reason why it's so
successful is because we know how to
solve. We know how to solve Maxwell's
equations
and the materials that are used in
photonics are mature. They're very
wellstied. They're reliable.
Unfortunately, they don't give us many
new surprises anymore and not a lot of
knobs to turn.
It's also fair to characterize photonics
as an engineer's field as much as a
physicist because you can design
something, simulate, fabricate, and in
the end what you get is usually what you
expected.
Quantum materials on the other hand are
solids where the collective behavior of
electrons gives rise to entirely new
states of matter. Superconductors,
unconventional magnets, you name it.
Unfortunately, um, oh, I forgot. Um,
these properties because they're so
special, they can go far beyond what the
ordinary materials can offer.
Unfortunately, it's very hard to predict
their properties because we don't really
have a Maxwell's equation uh equivalent
to guide us.
Um they have rich degree they offer a
very rich um they offer a very u rich
landscape of degrees of freedom. Spins,
charges, lattice, they're all
intertwined. And if you tune one knob,
several others are pulled on at once.
And lastly, it's firmly a physicist
field because we do the experiments, we
uncover often unexpected things and
theory struggles to catch up.
Um, it's this uh middle part, it's the
apparent orthogonality of these fields
that's interesting to us both from a
basic fundamental perspective but also a
technological one. We work in the middle
where the intersection promises bringing
best of both worlds together. And this
is what what I'm going to be uh talking
about today especially uh when it comes
to using the rich degrees of freedom
freedoms of quantum materials and how
they're intertwined.
Uh we recently became interested in this
uh two-dimensional material called
chromospher bromine. Um this is a two
dimensional material. It's an
antiaromagnetic uh insulator
semiconductor and uh once you cool it
down interestingly the chromium atoms in
plane point in the same direction it's
an inplane uh in the in plane it's a
ferroagnet but if you look at out of
plane the chromium atoms are pointing in
opposite directions the spins are
pointing in opposite directions so it
goes right left right left and also
quite interestingly the material has
very strong optical exitations called
exatons that determine its optical
response in the near infrared and the
visible.
Uh what's very surprising
uh and highlighting the rich degrees of
freedom of quantum materials is that
these two seemingly unrelated degrees of
freedom are very strongly intertwined.
If you apply a little bit of magnetic
field to change the uh relative
orientation between the spins of two
layers, it turns out this changes the
resonance energy of these exitations,
these exatons. What this translates into
is that you can tune the magnetic you
can tune the optical response of this
material by applying magnetic fields.
One can think of this as a strongly
tunable continuously tunable color. Here
we extracted the permitivities
uh corresponding to two different
magnetic configurations.
And if you look at the y-axis here, the
relative permitivity, real relative
permitivity goes up to 800. And if you
want to compare this to silicon or
silicon nitride that are uh very common
materials for more common photonics uh
for silicon the relative permitivity is
13 and for silicon nitrite it's four. So
you wouldn't even be able to see them if
I pull out it here.
Okay. So we have something quite
interesting at hand and we want to do
something interesting with it. So we
want to nanopattern this material. Um,
I'm not going to go into details of the
nanop fabrication too much, but we use a
quite unconventional method of
nanopatterning. If you ask me questions,
I'd be happy to answer them. Uh, we
bring Oops. We bring uh silicon nit
membranes to MIT nano. We mill them with
the focused ion beams at the basement.
We bring them back to our lab. We
transfer these silicon nit membranes on
top of the material of interest,
chromium sulfur bromide in this case,
and then we edge through. And in the
end, oops, we have what's called a
photonic crystal. So a photonic crystal
is an artificial structure that is
designed to control the flow of light.
And some of these photonic crystals have
traps, some resonant modes that can, you
know, trap light. And the quantifying
measure of this trapping as to how many
times the light is going to be bouncing
back and forth within the material until
it leaks out is called the quality
factor or the Q factor.
Um, we made these photonic crystals and
if you look at what the photonic crystal
looks like, it's almost boring. There's
nothing special about the photonic
crystal itself, but the material itself
is very interesting. Um,
yeah. So we pattern these materials. We
send light. We collect it back. We look
at the reflectivity. And if this was not
patterned, if this was just a simple
slab, you would see a smooth curve here.
But instead, we start seeing these dips,
these traps, so to say. And these traps,
if you calculate the quality factor, it
turns out they're over a thou uh the
quality factors of these resonances are
over a thousand. This is already a very
large number for the kind of mode that
this is and I'm not I'm going to skip
the details but feel free to ask me that
later. What's really remarkable is these
traps
can exist when the this photonic crystal
is as thin as about 2% of the wavelength
of light in air.
We did we did we carried out other
measurements. we carried out other nanop
fabrication u designs and we see very
similar things. What's even more
interesting is because of this
interconnectedness between these two
degrees of freedom, the optics and the
magnetic order, if we apply a little bit
of magnetic field, we can tune these
modes from one wavelength to the other
continuously if we don't like where the
motor is sitting. And this uh this
happens because whenever we change the
magnetic ground state of the material,
the permitivity changes up to about 100
uh sorry 800 which is one to two orders
of magnitude larger than most uh tunable
materials.
Um just to conclude, we uh
we fabricated ultra thin uh photonic
crystals made out of this quantum
material chromium sulfur bromine. And we
demonstrated continuous tunability of
these modes. And um next steps are
making photonics more interesting by
incorporating quantum materials within
this structure or vice versa making
quantum materials more interesting and
functional by using them in already
established nanopotonic architectures.
Um thanks for listening and I'd like to
quickly flash uh my collaborators and
the funding agencies.
Hi everyone. I am uh Somu. I'm currently
a PhD student uh in mechanical
engineering working with professor
Carlos Portella. Uh this talk is going
to be a little different from the themes
that you've seen before but I'm going to
talk about uh shellbased porous meta
materials, how you can scalably
fabricate them and a little bit about
their mechanics. So when we
traditionally think about materials we
think about making changes at the atomic
or molecular scale and when you by doing
this we've uncovered several different
classes of materials like metals,
ceramics, polymers etc. Uh and here's a
plot of uh the compressive strength
versus density for all of these
different classes of materials. Now if
you want to think about lightweight
materials, one way to do that is to sort
of make voids at the micron or
millimeter scale. And by doing that you
have a new class of materials called
foams. Uh but if you look at this plot
there is this large area in the middle
which is just an unexplored design space
which is below the theoretical limit.
And it's particularly useful because
those are lightweight high strength
materials. And you can think of
applications for this in uh one possible
application could be space technology
where every gram of weight saved is is
thousands of dollars saved in in payload
costs. So the question then is how can
we reach that design space? With
advances in additive manufacturing
technology, specifically techniques like
two photon lithography, we can shine a
laser onto a resin and and print
structures at the micro scale. The
structure that you see here is a
structure that was printed at MIT nano
using the two photon lithography tool
there. And with that we are now able to
move away from these aperiodic foam like
materials to more periodic truss and
beam based materials and start pushing
closer and closer to that theoretical
limit. And not just that we can use
other structural elements like plates
and shells and really push the limit on
what is possible. Um, but if you'll take
a closer look at these different studies
that you have here and you look at what
length scales these materials operate
at, you will see that the smallest
feature size is usually in the order of
hundreds of nanometers and the total
sample volume that was tested for
mechanical properties is usually like
hundreds of microns. So then the
question is is there a way to scale it
up? If you look at nature for example,
bone is an amazing meta material where
the smallest feature size is just tens
of nanometers, but the actual sample
size is basically the size of a human
being. Right? So the these periodic
latises that we're able to make offer a
lot of mechanical efficiency and
tunability, but then nature has figured
out the scalability part of things. So
the question is can we combine these
two? And that's where my research comes
in. It's to look see how we can scalably
manufacture metamaterials and how we can
individually tune the knobs at different
length scales. So to answer the first
question, we take inspiration from
nature where we use a process called
spinodal decomposition where you have a
polymer and a solvent and when you heat
it up, the polymer phase separates and
freezes in in in its place and from that
you can get this epoxy template and you
can make large volumes of this material.
You can then use coating techniques uh
such as metal and ceramic coatings that
you have at MIT Nano to coat these
materials and then burn away the
polymer, ash it away to get these
bicontinuous pinal shells uh with shell
thicknesses in the orders of tens of
nanometers and you can make hundreds of
cubic cm of this sample in a matter of
minutes. But before I go on talking
about how we can actually achieve this
in lab, uh one question that might come
up is are these structures mechanically
efficient? To do that here I have a
computational simulation of the process
and I can extract a 3D geomet 3D
structure of the polymer. I can then go
ahead and actually print this using two
photon lithography techniques at nano
and coat them using atomic layer
deposition and then ash away the polymer
and I get this very interesting thin
ceramic shell which is a spodal
structure and the shell thickness is
only 10 nanome and you'll see something
amazing. This is a ceramic a glass-like
material and I can put this under the
SEM and couple it with our nano and
enter and you'll see what happens when I
compress it. It behaves like rubber, an
elastic material. And I can compress
this multiple times and you'll see that
it is able to completely restore each
and every single time. And this shell is
again just 10 nanometers thick. Um, and
the whole unit cell itself is about 100
microns.
So if you actually go ahead and measure
the strength and stiffness and try to
sort of look at where it falls in the
context of the materials that I
presented previously, you will see that
it it performs much better than foams.
It's much lighter and has pretty good
mechanical properties as well. So now to
answer the second question which is how
can we actually make this in lab and how
can we tune the different knobs. Uh the
so the uh to answer that question at the
macro scale what we can do is that we
can we have this interesting mold that
we made where you can fill it up with
this polymer blend and then heat it up
and you can make these epoxy templates
of different shapes and sizes at the
macro scale and if you zoom in you'll
have this interesting spinodal
morphology at the micros scale. You can
also tune the structure at the micro
scale by changing the temperature and
composition of the process and you can
get more smaller pores or you can get
much larger pores. So you can you have
some control on the microscopic um
properties as well. And finally at the
nanocale you can coat this using
aluminina uh using atomic layer
deposition with aluminina and
essentially get nanome thick aluminina
shells. And so sort of going back to
where I started which is this idea that
can we combine the mechanical efficiency
of these periodic metamaterials with the
scalability of a periodic metamaterials.
We now have a system which we we call
selfarchchitected metamaterials which
span nine orders of magnitudes in length
scales from the smallest feature size
that's only a few nanometers to actual
sample size that are a few centimeters.
and we're closer to realizing this dream
of combining nature scalability with the
mechanical efficiency of man-made
structures. With that, I would like to
acknowledge uh the group this portella
research group. Uh also uh this work was
possible due to support from NSF math
works and a lot of technical support and
mentorship from MIT nano. Uh thank you
so much
Hello. Hello.
All right. So, u last talk of the
session. Um thanks for staying around.
My name is Skyome and I'm a postto here
at MIT. So, I will be talking about sort
of our work on developing a high yield
200 millimeter wafer scale processes for
quantum hardware at MIT.no. Nano.
So computing has really transformed our
way of living and we believe the next
leap is quantum computing. But um there
still faces two major hurdles which are
the scale and the accuracy of quantum
hardware. So if we um if we want to
solve impactful problems that um even
the best supercomputers today cannot
solve like drug design or u material
discovery or energy efficient
fertilizers for crops. uh we really uh
need these quantum computers with
millions of cubits. But even if you just
look at this um 72 cubit only u quantum
computer from Google, you already see
like uh such a tangle of wires over
here. So these electrical wires are used
to uh control and read out the
information from the quantum computers.
But as you can see, it's sort of a
wiring nightmare already and probably
won't work at scale with millions of
cubits in there. Um and to make matters
worse um unlike the transistors today
the error rate of these cubits are
inherently much noisier and with an
error rate about 10 to the minus4 it
means that all useful quantum algorithms
will fail due to a hardware error error
before they even finish.
So here um at MIT u we build these uh
high precision and scalable quantum
hardware that help solve both these
problems. So specifically uh we work on
something called quantum amplifiers
which is a critical component of quantum
computers and what it does is really
just the speaker and a microphone system
like we're using now such that you can
actually hear the useful information um
against a noisy background. Um so
compared to the existing solutions our
quantum amplifiers can address 10 to
100x more uh cubits per unit using a
single output line and therefore can
drastically reduce the system hardware
um overhead footprint energy consumption
and yada yada yada um and then help
scale quantum computing further. And
then at the same time because these
quantum amplifiers are really accurate
and fast what it can do is it enables
real time fast feedback and this allows
something called quantum error
correction to happen which essentially
is a way to self-correct and therefore
allows us to run these um comp long
longer and complex real world problems.
So for a while um these quantum
amplifier sounds great but they're
actually quite a feat to actually
fabricate them and um um just for a
while um only our collaborators at MIT
Lincoln Lab was able to do it in the
entire world and today we're very happy
to say that we can also now make these
quantum hardware um on campus ourselves
at MIT. nano and this is actually a uh
200 millm wafer that we fabricated these
quantum amplifier and processor chips on
with the reflection of the MIT dome of
course. Um and so what are really inside
these quantum amplifiers and quantum
processors. So one things are called the
Joseph's and junctions which are really
the building fundamental building blocks
of these quantum hardware. So what they
are really are really just um these tiny
metal insulator metal sandwiches with a
very thin layer of uh insulator filling
uh that's only about a nanometer thick
such that you can utilize useful quantum
tunneling effects from it. And uh making
one junction is not the easiest job in
the world. But and yet we have over
thousands of these junctions on a single
quantum amplifier chip. And um even even
if just there's one junction failure, it
will ruin the entire device. So um this
is why yield really really matters. And
to just to put a number into
perspective, if you have a 99% of
junction yield, that sounds pretty
great, but it leads to a horrible uh
near zero um device yield. And when
you're at 99.9% you're really just only
having about 30% of the device yield.
And only when you get to four nights of
yield do you actually would expect an
over 90% of device yield. So really uh
to see u to try to meet this bar. We
routinely fab and test over 85,000 of
these junctions per wafer. And through
many optimiz optimizations on the
process, we're now able to achieve near
100% yield and a very good uniformity
with less than 2% of variation across
the entire 200 millimeter wafer and over
a pretty large uh process window. And
then the other uh um sort of uh
interesting component are these things
called air bridges which are really just
these tiny metal overpasses that um can
cross and uh hop over um different
superconductors without touching each
other. So this helps uh enhance the
onrip connectivities
and um just like the junctions we have
actually thousands and thousands of
these bridges on a single quantum
amplifiers as well and um be and again
if you can kind of imagine if a single
of these arches uh collapses will
actually short out the device. So we're
kind of maniac so we want to make sure
that our process actually up to the
game. So we test over about 08 million
of these little tiny 3D arches on a
single wafer and using these um
electrical test structures. So if you
probe from here to here, it uh goes
through 15 bridges in series for
connectivity or if you probe from the
blue here to the green here, it can tell
you if there's any collapse bridges or
shorts. So using automated um electrical
probing testing we achieved and
demonstrated a 99.98%
um across the entire wafer and this is
sufficient enough for making the quantum
hardware that we uh wanted to achieve
and um just very quickly since we don't
have a lot of time left so even for
academics there's a lot of reason to
actually go with large 200 millimeter
wafers instead of small samples. First
of all our samples are huge because we
really really want to put uh push the
device performance to extreme. So each
sample is about five foot by 40
millimeter. So even for a 200 millimeter
wafer I could only fit about 100
devices. So it it's kind of a natural
choice because on small samples it's
kind of impossible to do u design
splitting. And then um also we kind of
want to have these um operational
discipline and while encouraging um
exploratory ideas. So just like
industry, we really want these rigorous
process control and these standardized
test structures across many different
wafers. And shown here is an example of
a group of electrical test structures
that we run on every single device wafer
across the uh wafer everywhere as well
like these uh dark little dots. So um
and besides that um the wafer real
estate really allows us to try these
exploratory even sometimes wild design
ideas without having to c cannibalizing
uh slots for you know safe baseline
devices and um and then actually the the
this creates sort of a low-risk
environment for information is actually
being quite powerful and effective for
us. So, one of my best designs actually
comes from a quick made design that I
just kind of tossed onto a existing
wafer that I run for some other stuff
and it turns out to be a huge winner
actually. And um lastly um working with
200 millimeter wafers allows us to
access a lot of these advanced
semiconductor wafer tools that um really
brings these automation reproducibility
safety control to a next level. And I
can't stress it enough is that it really
saved me a lot of huge times uh a lot of
huge time savings as compared to
thinking about that oh a big wafer takes
more time. This is because as an
example, if I want to pattern uh some
features on a wafer, it takes manually
about 20 more u or so minutes to do so.
But these tools auto this tool is
actually in nano. It takes about well
within five minutes. And I can uh
streamline a couple more wafers while
unattended. And this efficiency is
really a gamecher for uh this kind of
research requiring very very good
uniformity and yield.
And um if we put together the components
that we talk about, we actually get
these functional high performing quantum
amplifiers. And um if we zoom in, we
kind of see these um arrays of error
bridges and Joseph's injunctions that we
talked about. And um they not only work,
but they also we use that to demonstrate
sort of the record-breaking quantum
efficiency or accuracy measure um in
when used for a quantum computing uh
quantum computer. Um, with that I think
that's my time. Um, and I just want to
shout out to my uh labmates uh in the QC
group at MIT and our collaborators for
helping bringing this vision to reality.
Thank you.
>> Okay, thank you everyone. Uh, thank you
for the wonderful speakers and I would
like to use the stage and thanks MIT
nano staff. Uh, like professor Strano
mentioned in the previous session, the
gatekeepers of the knowledge. uh we are
lucky to have gatekeepers of knowledge
some of them with us for decades. So I
would like everyone to thank the staff
for helping the students and uh um
we we showed you half a percent of
what's going on in MIT Nano 1500 users
eight people representing uh the
project. So if you want more reach out
to me and we'll happily connect you with
more people. Thank you.
And and in fact to my my earlier
question in the beginning, what do
people actually do at nano? You can see
the answer is anything and everything.
Um I think we have time for one yes no
question but no more than that. Um so
maybe we'll go on to the next session.
Thank you.