hi I'm here to talk to you about
becoming a superhuman that needs less or
little oxygen our cells in our body use
oxygen to produce energy they burn sugar
glucose with oxygen and produce all the
energy that your cell needs and in the
end it produces water and CO2 in this
process so you wouldn't be able to burn
glucose and sugar effectively if you
switched out oxygen for anything else
however it might be possible to get rid
of our need for so much oxygen there's
this amazing protein in your blood
called hemoglobin hemoglobin picks up
oxygen in your lungs and carries it
through your bloodstream to your cells
uh and drops it off scientists have
already observed different forms of of
hemoglobin that bind oxygen differently
in different environments and so we
could probably figure out ways of
changing hemoglobin to bind oxygen more
strongly so maybe if you're on a newly
terraformed Planet maybe you'd want
hemoglobin that could bind oxygen more
strongly and really make do with the
oxygen that you have available in your
lungs for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow