The modern world is in transition to
intensive electrification. In the area
of stationary storage, there's the
liquid metal battery which I invented
here at MIT. The liquid metal battery
consists of two electrodes and an
electrolyte. In this case, the
electrodes are liquid metals. One is a
low density liquid metal, something like
calcium, and a high density liquid
metal, something like anamony, could be
lead, could be zinc. And the electrolyte
is calcium chloride, which is road salt.
As the battery discharges, it generates
heat. And we trap that heat to keep the
battery at operating temperature. So
after that we don't put any energy in.
Battery discharges, generates heat,
charges, generates heat. So let's say
you have an intermittent power source
like solar. You put the storage at the
load center. It enables intermittent
generation and it would even make the
existing grid more resilient.
For more MIT moments from MIT Open
Learning, like, subscribe or follow.