Last time we talked about so one of the
things we talked about last time was
series. So we'll continue on that today.
So series is that you have a sequence.
You're starting with a sequence. So a n
is a sequence
and then you form a new sequence. So you
form a new sequence
a new sequence
from
a uh as follows
that. So the new sequence uh let's call
that SN
and S1 is just A1.
S2 is A1 + A2.
S3 is A1 + A2
plus A3
and uh and so on.
So this is the first
sum of the first n elements, right?
And and you typically write you
typically write uh sn
you write sn as the sum here from and
then in this case I'm starting at one
but you could start as something else. I
= to 1 to N of A I I
and so to say that the at so and you
write the series you also write so this
is slight beauty of notation that you
write
this
infinite sum sorry um as a series. So
you think about this as you think about
this thing here. When you write this
thing here, you're really thinking about
the sequence sn
and so uh so the series here the series
converge
This uh means that the sequence
means
that the sequence
as inn converges
right and so the most uh right so
remember that a sequence converts so we
by the cush convergence.
[Applause]
So recall
by the kushi convergence
that uh that Sn
converge
If and only if
in this accuracy sequence,
right? And it's a C sequence just means
that if you go sufficiently far out and
you're looking at this difference here,
then this here is small provided
that M and N are larger than some
capital N where this here is chosen
depending on epsilon. Right? That's what
it means to be a cushy sequence. So like
in particular of course if you take so
in particular
if you take m
uh m to be n + one
sorry let me take m to be
um uh n minus one doesn't matter but so
if I take it like this then s n min -
sm. Well, this here is a sum of the
first
n element and from that we have to
subtract the sum of the first
n minus one element. So this here just
leave this here cancel out all of these
and so you're just left with a n.
So,
so this means that if it is converging
right then in particular a n here has to
go to zero
as n goes to infinity
right because in fact this whole
difference here as long as m and n are
sufficiently large have to be as small
as you want right and so in particular
special case where where this here is
the one prior to that then you see that
the a end will have to go to zero right
so again if you see a series the first
thing you don't apply any test the first
thing that you check is that this
element here goes to zero
okay now
what are the most important series
so the most important is the geometric
series
and the reason it's the most important
is that it can be used to determine it's
easy to determine whether it's
converging or not and it can be used to
determine
using the test whether other series
converge. And so the geometric series is
that you take a sum typically here you
start at zero. You don't have to start
at zero. But of course the limit right
the limit if you take a series then to
say that it's converging mean that the
sequence doesn't converge
and the limit of these here this here is
also and that's where there's this abuse
of notation it's denoted by the same
thing. So this thing here is is uh
playing the role of the sequence but
it's also denoting the limits. Okay,
that's just a standard thing.
So in this case I was starting from one.
Okay. So now the geometric series is
where you take some number C and then
you multiply it by itself. This is some
real number and you multiply it by
itself with itself I times and where i
runs from zero to infinity right and
when i is zero this is meant to be one
okay
and the reason why I want to do it here
at zero is that
that it's probably worth remembering
that this here it's easy to deduce But
it's such a standard fact that it's that
this here is this here is converging. So
it's converge.
So the geometric series converges
provided that the absolute value of C is
less than one. And when it is this here
is a limit. Okay. If so then you can ask
if C here is equal to
is one
right so if C is actually equal to one
not just the absolute value but if C is
actually equal to one then it's just one
times itself a number of times but that
does not go to zero right so that's
clearly this diverging and if it's minus
one multiply itself by number of time
then it's just alternate between one and
minus one so it doesn't go to zero. So
it's divergent here.
And in fact, if as long as C here is
bigger equal to the absolute value is
bigger equal to one because you take
this number and multiply it by itself a
number of times. If C the absolute value
of C is bigger than one, then it
actually is even blowing up. It becomes
larger and larger, right? In absolute
value, right? So it's it's divergent
here and it's converging. So that was
kind of easy, right? And it was easy to
determine why we did there was this
little trick will determine what this
limit was, right?
And this is like a trick that go back I
think certainly to the ancient Greeks. I
mean this idea and you can do this with
various other thing this things about
adding things in different order kind of
stuff or multiplying by something.
Okay. So that was the most important and
again we'll come back to why it is the
most important but it's because it can
be used to determine whether other
series converge or not. another
classical but that sits inside a family
of uh of um of series is the harmonic
series.
So this is an example of of a series
it's it's one
uh series that sits inside a larger
family of series.
And so the harmonic series is when you
take one / n and you're summing here
right like that right this series here
and we we saw that last time is
divergent
and in fact the larger series that is
sitting inside is so sits inside
a larger family
and that larger family is where you're
summing from 1 to infinity of 1 / n to
the alpha and here alpha is taken to be
bigger equal to one
and so in a case where alpha is equal to
one that's a harmonic series this one's
diverge but if alpha and so this here is
for alpha equal to one it's diverg
because it's the harmonic series
and when alpha is strictly bigger than
one. Well, we just last time we just saw
one example of this when alpha was equal
to two and we saw that that converge.
But in fact you can prove that for any
alpha strictly bigger than one it does
converge.
And the typical thing to use there is is
and we'll talk about that at some later
lecture is the what's called the
integral test.
Okay.
Now,
now there's
uh when you have a series
then most but not all
most test
but but again not all uh determine
really whether the series is what's
called absolutely convergent.
So what is absolute convergent? We
talked about that last time, but let me
remind you
absolute
convergence.
So if you take a series here
then here is absolutely convergent is
absolutely converging.
This just means it means
that uh the series where you're slapping
on absolute value. So this thing here
means that this series here is converted
and so it's easy to see. So, so easy
to see and we saw this last time
and it was just from the Kushi
convergence.
So, it's easy to see that uh absolute
convergence
implies convergence
but not the other way around. So Kushi
convergence theorem gives you this
implication
why it's not the case that you have the
other way around
and that is because
what's called the alternating series.
So
so the alternating series alternating
And there's something called the
alternating uh series tests. And but let
me just explain to you in words why the
alternating series converge. So
alternating harmonic series.
So if you take the series here minus1 to
the n times uh over n and you're summing
here from zero to sorry not to zero
because you're dividing by zero from one
to infinity this here is called the
alternating series
alternating harmonic series right if you
were slapping absolute value sign on it.
So, so this means that a n here is -1 to
the^ n / n, right? So, if you take the
absolute value sign, the absolute value
sorry of a n, then this here is just
one. So, this is 1 / n. So, this here is
the corresponding series when you're
slapping absolute value and this is the
harmonic series.
And this is divergent,
right? That was what we just discussed.
Now, why is this series here convergent?
We'll probably come back to that in a
later lecture in a more general setting,
but let me just explain this.
And so the idea is
that before you're starting summing,
so imagine that you have here before you
start your sum, then you're sort of in a
neutral position, which is one zero,
sorry. And then you do the first then
you do the first thing this you're
looking at S1,
right? But s1 would bring you down,
right? Because s1 is just equal to min
-1 to the^ 1. But that's minus one. So
it's minus1 / n. This is the first
element.
So that's going to bring you down. Let
me just kind of exaggerate the picture
and bring you down here to minus one / n
at minus one over. This is n is equal to
one. So this is minus one.
This is how the series starts, right?
And so the next element is s_2 but
s_ub_2 is -1. That was the first element
and then plus and then min -1
squared
over two. So this is and you would be
tempted but it's not. Don't add them at
this stage but just looking at it like
this.
Right?
So the next so this here is this here is
S1.
Let me just write it down here. This is
When you're looking at S2, then you're
coming back towards zero, but you don't
go as far up as you went down, right?
because it's one over uh two right so
this here is s2
and then you see the next one is the
next one if you start here then you are
supposed to so for s3 it's really s2
+ -1 to ^ 3 over 3 so this is s2
minus right because -1 to the^ 3 is a
negative sign like that. Right? So the
next one here
so you're starting here before you have
done any summation you're starting at
zero you brought down here you come up
here and then but then in S3 you're
going down but you don't go as far down
as the previous one. So you're going
down here and so you're really
continuing this process and you see that
these interval get smaller and smaller
and it just go down and then it come up
but it doesn't go up as far up as you
were before and then so on so forth and
so you can make this more precise. It's
it's quite easy and this show you that
this series is converging and in fact
this is like the basis for this
alternating series test and it works as
long as you have alternating where the
sign of the a ends are alternating and
the absolute value goes to zero in this
here that's alternating series test case
I'll probably come back to that at some
later stage but this just show you that
if you take a series
you know then um so the absolute
convergence means that if you slap
absolute value sign then that new series
also converge absolute convergence imply
convergence but not the other way
around.
Okay. So now the next thing
um is that so the next thing is like if
you take a series
Suppose you take a series and suppose
that you knew
that. So suppose you have a series like
this
and you knew that a end here all of the
a were non- negative fall in
then convergence here convergence
just imply right so convergence is
because the sn is now the sum sum here
of these guys here,
right? That's SN.
And you see that this is of course less
or equal to because all of these guys
are non negative. It's less or equal to
where you're summing
not just up to n but one more right
because this here is non- negative and
so this here is SN + one. So you see
that if the elements are non- negative
then the sequence
sn is so sn is monotum
nondereasing the sequence and so to say
by the monot convergence theorem to say
that this sequence sn is convergent is
equivalent to saying that so sn converge
if and only If
SN is bounded from above,
right?
Okay. So now
when you have a series and you have
already checked that a n goes to zero
and you are then asked to determine
whether the series is converging or not
right then there are these number of
tests right and so there's a bunch of
tests so test
for convergence
And so there's a bunch of them and and
let me talk about uh in this lecture
I'll just talk about the comparison test
and I mentioned them very briefly but
uh last time but I'll talk a little bit
more about them and then there's a ratio
test
uh and then there is the root test. So
I'll talk about those three but there
are other tests. So root test.
Okay. Now
um
Okay. So now let's start with the with
the comparison test and there are like
two versions of this.
One version is the following
that suppose that you have so uh
comparison test
uh version one.
And so the first version of the
comparison test is the following that
imagine that you have two series here a
and again we talked about this last time
but but let me just say a few more words
that you have this series and you have
that series and I'm assuming here that
the a and the bn
are non- negative numbers and in fact
I'm assuming that bn is larger equal to
a n.
Then the comparison test this version
the simple version of the comparison
test is that if
this here
if
the series based on the BN is convergent
then the series
of the ends is also converted.
And so this is so the this version of
the comparison test is used both in this
way but it's also used sometimes where
you know that this series is divergent
and from that you conclude that this one
right that's just a negation of the
statement right
so um
okay so let's See it's this it's so that
prove here is of that is is is actually
easy and so why is this the case?
Well, the thing is
that you know so that by the Kushi
convergence
by the Kushik convergence.
Um we just we know that to determine
whether all we need to check to to
determine whether this sequence here is
convergent. All we need to figure out is
if the
if the if it is a cushy sequence, right?
So this means that you want to say that
so so suppose you're looking at
at the series the the sequence sorry um
defined from a and so this is just where
I'm now summing the first n elements
in a and I just want to
write some using the
superscript a just to to say to to to
denote that it's coming from the
sequence a n. So if you're looking at
this and so likewise I
we look at this thing here.
Now of course you have that suppose
you're looking at S N A minus S M A. You
want to show that this here you want to
show that this here is a C sequence. So
you're looking at this difference here,
right? But this thing here is just this
here difference. I'm assuming that m is
less than n straight strictly less than
m n sorry this here just means that this
difference here is just when you're
summing where you're summing from m +
one. So this is just the a m + one
up to a n this is just this
>> fine. Yeah,
>> when we're proving to learn this like
this now um just like to get some
motivation like the reason that we're
using sequences
>> I you could either use at this stage you
could either use cushy sequence that's
what I started you could also have used
the mono convergence here maybe that was
>> okay because I was just going to say
like back to the definition of
convergence that we just had where we
had like yeah absolute value of
>> yeah that's right
>> is that is it just like
>> so so if you if you went all the way
back to the definition, right? Then you
would have to determine what the limit
was,
>> right? Which we don't want
>> and we don't want because we don't know,
right? Just because we may know what the
limit of B of the sequence based on B
is, but we don't. But this doesn't mean
that you can figure out what the limit
of the A.
>> So does that motivate why like sequences
are like more useful in general?
>> Yeah, that's right. That's right. That's
right. Exactly. That's right. That's
right. So the advantage with cushi
sequence is that you don't have to
figure out what the limit is and and
it's often I mean like in this case you
have no idea I mean you know it's not
it's not in terms of anything from the
bees right and and I should but let me
just continue doing it like this but
just now when you ask I should probably
have done it using the monotone
convergence theorem but you can do that
as an exercise but it doesn't matter I
mean So
the difference here is
this is what the difference is the
absolute value signs are really
irrelevant because these are all non-
negative numbers. So I don't have to
have the absolute value sign
and now this thing here is of course
less than but this here is less than the
corresponding B's
and this is like less than the
corresponding
B here like that.
But this here is exactly S N
the one based on B S M based on B and
this here as long as N and M are
sufficiently large we can make this as
small as we want. So therefore this here
was as small as we want. Right?
You could also have done it maybe let's
just say that that you could also have
done it using the mono convergence
right because now of course you have
that again the same sort of thing say
that if you take the sn based on the a
so that's a1 up to a n sum of these guys
but these individually is less than the
corresponding b's
And this here is just the s the sequence
sn based on the piece right but these
here if this se these here converge this
is equivalent to saying that they are
bounded they're less than some c some
real number c and this here is for all a
for all in sorry right but this means of
course that Those things here are bound
fall in right. So, so then you know and
this here is a mono also a monotom
sequence mono increasing sequence that
is now bounded from above. So therefore
it converts.
So you can do it either of those two
ways but so that's really easy to check.
Let's see an example where we are using
this test here.
Um
and so
so this could be that you're looking at
something like
um you're looking at so here's an
example.
Um
uh you're looking at a series that is 2
to the minus n / n
n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n
=
1 to infinity.
Uh this is your this is and and you you
want so you you you're being asked is
this
is this uh series
convergent?
Okay, so this is like typically how it
works.
And so of course in this case you should
think about the the that this here is a
sequence a n right and so you have to
find the bn right but in this case we
just say so we're setting a so set so
answer
set
a n = 2 to the minus n / 2 and bn
= to 2 - n.
Then
[Applause]
then uh then you have that a n is bigger
equal to zero is smaller than bn
and
and this sequence here based on the bn
oops
is a convergent
geometric series.
It's convergent between because because
c here in this case is 1 /2, right? It's
1 / two. So it's just, you know, 1 / two
1 a half is the same as 2 to the minus
one, right?
And so this is convergent.
Okay.
So this is just so so you know so
typically you know this could be used to
that you're given a sequence and you are
being asked is it convergent or not and
so you have to find the se sorry and you
being asked whether it's convergent or
not and you have to find the comparison
series
and then uh and then in this case right
say that this thing here right is is uh
is a convergent and uh and so therefore
the sequence a n that was squeezed
between that and zero was also
convergent.
Okay, so this was the first version of
the comparison test.
Here is another
more fancy version of comparing where
you're comparing two series.
In fact, it's pretty much like that
except for for this stuff we talked
about.
I mean, typically um typically the tests
are where you comparing it with some
other series.
So here is version two.
So comparison
uh version two.
Okay.
And so you have again two series and
and and again it doesn't matter this
what the sum is matters where you
starting but whether or not it converges
doesn't matter where you start.
So suppose that you have the series and
you have this series
and suppose that you know
that uh the the bn
none of the bns are zero.
uh and you know that the a n divided by
bn
that this ratio here as n goes to
infinity converts to some l and l here
is um l here is um is not zero and it's
not infinity
meaning that it really is a limit
like that.
So if that's the case then the serious
[Applause]
um
then
right let's
[Applause]
right then uh let's have these as non-
negative numbers
uh then uh Um
then uh then the series uh a
converge
uh if and only if
the series and converge.
Okay.
Um and so a an example of this, a
typical example like of this is where
you're looking at the series
uh 1 / n squar minus one. Suppose you're
looking at this and now just to make it
so that make sure that it makes sense
that you're not dividing by zero. You're
looking at this thing here.
Suppose that this is the series that
you're given.
Well, this here is so you wouldn't use
the first compar although you could have
used the first but then it would be a
little bit more uh complicated. Not
super complicated but a little bit more
complicated because this thing here is
you know this is right. So the first
thing you observe is that this of course
goes to zero. this here goes to zero.
But the second thing is that it's very
close to a series that you know
something about. It's very close to this
series here.
But again, it doesn't matter where I'm
starting in order when you're asking
whether it's convergent or not. So it's
very close to this series. But of
course, this thing here,
this thing here is a smaller number. So
this is actually bigger than 1 / n^2,
right? This here is a convergence
sequence series, right? So this does not
help you. This is not great for using
the first test. You could have done it,
but then you know you could use still
use the first test, but then you have to
be slightly more clever. So
instead of that, you can use this second
test. And so in the second test you set
a n equal to 1 / n^2 minus one and you
set bn = to 1 / n^2.
And then you have that a n / bn. But
this is just 1 / n^2 - 1
over um n^2
1 / n^2. Sorry.
And so this here is the same right as
n^2
n^2 minus one right like that. And now
you can divide by n^2 in both
denominator and denominator. So you're
getting 1
uh 1 - 1 / n^2. And now you just use the
usual algebraic rules for limits. This
here converts to zero. So it means that
the denominator converts to one. So this
means that this ratio here converts to
to one, right? And so you see that it's
converging the ratio is converging to
something that is neither zero nor
infinity.
And this means that this series here is
convergent if and only if this is
convergent. You already know that this
here is convergent. So we conclude that
this is convergent. So that's like how
it's typically used.
So um
right so now the next s uh the next test
um I I want to talk about is the ratio
test. And so this is a this is I mean
like the comparison test are typically
like almost the easiest test.
Uh but this one here is extremely
useful.
And so the the next two tests,
the ratio test, both
both a ratio test
and root test
are based on
are based on comparison.
with
the geometric series.
And so this is explaining why
uh the geometric series is so crucial.
Okay. So what is the ratio test? Well,
the ratio test is simply the test that
if you're looking at
so if you have a series, you don't have
to look at any other series like in the
comparison test, you have to find
another series.
But in the ratio test, so this is a
ratio test.
So you're looking at a series
like this
and the ratio test is that you're
looking at uh a n
+ one
over a n. So you are looking at the
ratio between two consecutive elements
elements of the a right. So you're
looking at this
and you're looking at the absolute value
of this
and you're asking
if the limit here as n goes to infinity
suppose that the limit exist and let's
say that the limit is a
so so it it's ask is you know it's
asking you if this you know it's somehow
the test here at this form of the ratio
test it require
that the ratio here has a limit.
So the ratio test then say that if a
here
is um
if a here is
um
is uh by sorry yeah if if if a here is
uh less than one
then the series is so let me let me
write it like this.
So a
less than one this here means that the
series is convergent.
Uh true if this a here is bigger than
one this implies that the series
is divergence.
And three is that if this a here is one
then the test is so test is inconclusive
but so it's important to remember that
it is possible that you don't get
anything out of the test okay if you are
in the unlucky case where this limit is
one right
and it is I should also emphasize that
it is crucial to have a limit right so
you the test here in this form it's
crucial to have a limit
okay
and and we'll talk a little bit we'll
come back to that because we'll come
back to this
Okay. So now
let me try to explain
uh why uh why you have well in
conclusive I don't really need to
explain anything right but but why why
in the case so proof of case one
so this means that I have to show so so
so need to True.
That if this limit here, if this limit
here, if this limit
of a n + one over a n, if this here is
less than one, then the series is
converging.
And I'll just sketch the proof because
we're going to prove we're going to do
Yeah, I I I will just sketch the proof.
We sort of come back in a way to the
proof because it's very close to the
same proof that is used in the case of
the root test.
So,
so that's what I need. So I have that
there exist. So given
um
so given
uh a zero less than one. So given a z
with
a z with a z bigger than this a and less
than one.
Right? So true. So if you pick a a zero
that is strictly bigger than a and still
less than one, then we know that there
exist there exist
uh n such that
if little n is bigger than this capital
n then uh a n + one
over uh a n
and really I should have absolute value
here on this
then we have that this thing here is
less than
um it's less than a z right because uh
if you're very far out then this here is
this ratio is going to be very close to
this but this is strictly less than that
Right? So we have this, right? Okay. So
this means that maybe I shouldn't call
it a zero because there's too many A's.
Now let's call it something else. Let's
call it alpha to make it just look much
more distinct.
Uh okay.
So uh so this means that so you see that
if so in other words if
um if n here is bigger than this capital
n then you have just multiplying over
you have that a n + one is less than
alpha * a n like that right
in the ratio test I should have said
that but obviously you are assuming that
these a ends I'm not sure. So you can
divide by them. Right?
So you have this if you're far out you
have this that the next one is a
fraction of the previous one.
Right? But this means of course that if
you take if you take if you're looking
at n is bigger equal to this capital n.
Well, you have that
you have that a capital n + one, right?
If you're using this
a capital n as little n then you have
that this thing here this is now the um
this here is now sorry if you're using
if you if you first pick n equal to
capital n
then what does this inequality tell you?
tell you that a capital n + one is less
or equal to alpha a capital n.
Now apply this inequality here for n +
capital n + 1. So then you have that a
capital n + 2 absolute value is less or
equal to alpha a n + one like that.
Right?
But you already proven that this thing
here, forget about the alpha here, but
you proven this inequality. So filling
in that inequality, I have this alpha
here, but then I have another alpha that
is this.
And then like this,
right? And so now you can continue this
way. So this here is like alpha squared
time a capital. And so now you see that
you can continue. So if you're looking
at so
[Applause]
if you continue like this then you see
that a capital n plus some little m
is lesser equal to alpha to the power m
* a to absolute value of a n. Right?
This here the previous line was just
where m was equal to two but you really
get it for all integers right
and so this say that at least the tail
of this sequence here the tail of the a
sequence is this is just some fixed
constant this here is a convergent
geometric series so the tail is bounded
by a convergent geometric series so you
can just apply the first uh the first
comparison test to prove that the
sequence a that the series a n is
actually convergent. Okay. So, so this
so so the the the
ratio test again was to compare it use
the first comparison test where the
comparison was the geometric series.
Okay.
Um and so of course if the so this prove
this prove one two here but two is kind
of really the same because if this alpha
here
so to show the second part
again the third one to prove it's
inconclusive there's nothing to prove
because it leaves open any possibility
Uh but but you want to show that if this
limit here so if this limit so proof of
two
so you want so you'll be assuming that a
here is bigger than than one but this
means that there exist so if you take
alpha
so this time
choose
alpha such that
uh alpha is bigger than one but it's
smaller than a
but then you have that for right since
this this ratio is converging for for
little n bigger than there exist some
capital n so that if this little n is
bigger than a capital n then you have
that a n + one over a in that this thing
here
if it's far out out is going to convert
here but at least far enough out it's
going to be bigger than alpha right
multiplying over again
means that a n + one is bigger than
alpha * a n
this here is now bigger than on. And so
in the same way as before, you see that
if you're far enough out, then the next
element is some
multiple some some big number some at
least bigger than one times the previous
one, right? But this means that they're
getting larger and larger as you you
know from some fixed stage on and
outwards, the a ends are getting larger
and larger. So they don't converge to
zero as they were supposed to. Right? So
this is proving true, right? And three
again does nothing to prove because it
leaves open both possibilities.
>> Um okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Does that assume that the series is
increasing?
>> Uh
Like I guess just looking at it
>> like from a high level we're saying that
wait so you you're asking uh what what
are you asking? So for part one we say
that less than
that only work
>> no no so there's no assumption here on
whether the sequence is
uh right I mean so so one one yeah so
one implies that the absolute value is
going down as you say right yeah but it
could alternate signs and things like
that yeah but It's uh but it is yeah and
so it's just because you're comparing it
with you're going to compare it with a
convergent geometric series and in
convergent geometric series the next
element is some fixed fraction of the
previous one.
Yeah.
So, so you you're right that in order
for the ratio test to give you
convergence, then it then it's it's
going to require that sufficiently far
out the absolute value of the a element
is is going down. Yep. So,
so the other
the other uh the other and this is like
and this in a way addresses that point
you're making there. So the other test
that's that is also based on on
comparing it with the geometric series
but this does not compare consecutive
elements. So it's leaving the
possibility that the next element could
be larger than the previous
um
and so this is the root test. But of
course you know it it cannot be that you
it cannot you know you cannot have keep
having the next element larger than
previous but you could have you know
there could be somewhere where you know
the next one actually went up but then
presumably they're going after that
they're going down at least for a long
time and then maybe there's another one
that jumps up but not very much etc.
Right. And the root test is is is is
okay with that. Whereas that test wasn't
okay with that. So the root test so this
is so you have a series again like this
and the root test is
that you're looking at you're taking the
absolute value of this
and then you're taking the nth root. So
this means this is the same as saying a
n absolute value. If you want to write
it like this one,
right? So it's it's it's a dealing with
this and the root test is saying that
suppose
that this
that this when you form this here that
this has a limit.
Suppose that this nth root
suppose that this here has a limit and
let's call this limit C.
Suppose that you have this
then it has the same three parts here
as in the previous.
Um
and so this is um so this is so so
there's three possibilities where C here
is less than one h then this implies
that the series is convergent.
Uh two
C is bigger than one implies that the
series is divergent.
And again the case where C here is equal
to one in conclusion
test this in conclusion
and again we're going to compare with
the geometric series. So let's see how
the proof works.
So
okay. So now let's prove uh one
proof of one.
So again we are in a situation where we
have uh that the nth root of the
absolute value here
as n goes to infinity
is equal to some c and we're assuming
that the c is less than one right so now
um I'm I'm again choosing something that
is between
c and one. So, choose
uh C.
Let's call it C 0. Um uh will
uh C less than C 0 less than one. Okay.
And now we know that because we have
this limit, we know that there exist
there exist
capital n such that if little n is
bigger than capital n
then uh then this
then the nth root of this absolute value
sign is actually less or equal to C
right this is just because C was
strictly bigger than C right so we have
that so now we just take the nth power
on both sides so this implies by taking
n power
the nth power
we get that a absolute value of a n
sorry
is less or equal to c 0 to the power n
okay
right so but that's already great right
because this means that you have
compared at least from a certain stage
and and outward you have compared the a
with if you're thinking about that this
thing here is like the b Right? Then
it's you have compared this guys here
with this series here based on these at
least from this capital n and outwards
and this is a geometric series because
it's just some number small strictly
smaller than one multiplied by itself n
times. So, so again by the first
comparison test.
So by the first comparison test
um um the a
is convergent.
Right. So, and and and note here that
what you're proving is you're actually
proving that this series here is
convergent. Right. Right. Because you're
comparing this series here with the
geometric series. But this here is just
and this just means
sorry means that that the original
series here was absolutely convertible.
But absolute convergence means implies
convergence. Right? So, so you are
actually proving absolute convergence.
Okay.
Now let's try to again you know there's
these three parts to it but the last one
uh leaves open any possibility. So
there's nothing to prove. So let's just
prove the second part here and that's
just goes similarly
and again the this it fails dramatically
to be convergence because the
a n as we'll see does not actually goes
to zero. So so proof of of two.
So we have that this so we're assuming
that this in here
this converge
to some C here which is now bigger than
one.
So this means that there exist So this
means that there exist
capital n such that
if little n is bigger than this capital
n. Sorry. Right. So so we have this in
here
and what I should before I do this I
should choose my just like before I
should choose my C zero. So choose
C 0 such that
C 0 is bigger than one strictly bigger
than one but yet is strictly smaller
than C. Right?
So you choose this and now using this we
have because we have that this limit
here converts to C. So it converts to
something that is strictly above this
C0. This means that there exist
capital n such that if little n is
bigger than capital n then uh then this
the nth root
here is um is is bigger than c. Right?
But now again taking the n power on both
sides then you have that a n
to a n is bigger than strictly bigger
than in fact c 0 to the n power.
But you see these guys here right c 0 is
strictly bigger than one. So this this
here actually even goes to infinity
right. So this does not go to zero.
Okay.
So this pro prove again that it's
divergent.
So this proof two.
Okay. Now the next thing the next thing
I want to talk about is power series.
So power is
so remember that so the first example of
a power series
is something we already looked at more
or less. So suppose you take suppose
that you've looking at the series some
number I call it x now instead of c to
the power n and n= to zero to infinity
right. Yep.
So, so what we proved so in the root
test here we proved that the series is
absolutely convergent
convert here we proved it's divergent
and what we actually proved we proved
that a in fact this here a in
that Yeah,
allow me to write that goes to infinity
like this that they they were supposed
to go to zero but we actually right if
it's if the series was converging the
most elementary thing is the most basic
thing is that the a has to go to zero
otherwise it's not going to converge but
in fact not only do they not go to zero
they actually in absolute value goes to
infinity So it's it's very very far from
being convergent,
right?
Okay. So now uh so suppose so we looked
at the geometric series, right? If you
think about x is just representing any
number, you can look at this series
here. This is the geometric series
and we know that it's convergent. So we
know that this here is convergent.
It's convergent if if the absolute value
of height is less than one and in that
case this here is sum here is just this
familiar function
but in general so in general
you may have a sequence so a if if a
general if a is a sequence
then you can form a power series and the
power series is is like that where this
is the coefficient the a is now the
coefficient to the x to the power n
right so this is if you will this is
sort of like a infinite polinomial a
polomium of interderee right because the
sum of all these polomials, right? Okay.
And this is called a power s. So this is
a power s. This is a power s.
And the question is then
the question which turned out to be
quite subtle is um so a lot of the basic
functions can be represented by power
series. This here was one example.
Another example is um is so another
example of if you're looking at the
exponential function and we'll come back
and discuss this more but the
exponential function has a nice power
series representation
and this is the exponential function the
power series representation of the
exponential function
and also the s and cosine. So cosine x
this also have a power series
representation
and the power series is -1 to ^ n x ^ 2n
divided by 2 n factorial where you're
summing from 0 to infinity
and sign have a similar one.
So sine uh x has a similar one where
summing from zero to infinity and then
it's -1
^ n x ^ 2 n + 1 / 2 n + one factorial
right and so and lots of functions has
um power series representation
but it's not every function. If I write
down a function uh then so in fact I
it's easy to write down a function that
doesn't have so if you have but I'm not
going to prove to you that it doesn't so
if I take the function that starts off
being dead zero and now it's it's it's
it's becoming interesting so this
function here this one does not have a
power shares even locally does not have
a power shares okay and the thing is
that that uh power series is an example
of something that's called analytic
function and this here is not an
analytic function. So that's why I know
that it definitely doesn't have a power
series. But anyway, so
um okay. So now
uh
right so so the question is that if you
take a power series
so suppose you take a sequence a n
and you write it down. Suppose you take
a sequence a n
and then you write down a power series
based on it.
Then the first question that comes to
mind is
when does this for which x does this
series converge? Right? So for which x
does the series converge?
So this is like the most basic thing
and uh let's look at some example.
Of course if you
if you look at uh so the first example
let me just that is what we already
talked about suppose I'm looking at this
thing here
well this here is you know x if you
think about x's being fixed this is a
geometric series and we already know so
this is for each x for each fixed X.
This is the geometric series.
So we already know that this thing here
converge. So converge
for as long as the absolute value sign
absolute of x is less than one and we
also know that it and diverge
otherwise
because we've already determined that
right
okay
uh now you see uh like the next example
I want to look at is the one power
series that represents
the and but we haven't proven that yet
but we'll see talk about that next time
is the exponential function. If I'm
looking at this power series here, then
I have
then I I'm interested in for what x
for
what x
does this converge?
And so it's natural here to try to apply
one of the tests. So you just think
about X as being fixed and you just
apply one of the tests. And the natural
one is either the root test or the ratio
test. Let's do the ratio test.
So X is fixed and I'm not interested in
X equal to zero. I'm assuming that x is
not equal z because when x is zero right
this here is just right it's only for x
to the power zero is by definition one
uh and all the other things
uh all the other terms are zero right so
this here is it's definitely convergent
when x is equal to zero right so let's
not look at that
and then because if you don't look at
that you can look at you can think about
a n you can now think about sorry as the
as the series where bn is x to the power
n over n factorial.
If you think about this thing here and
you think about the series as BN, then
the ratio test tells you that if you're
looking at the ratio of BN + one
over BN.
So if you're looking at BN + 1 over BN,
take the absolute value of this here.
Well, this is just x
to the^ n + 1 over n + 1 factorial. And
then you have to divide it
by x ^ n / n factorial.
Right? If you do that, this here why it
turns up, flips upside down, and you're
getting x to ^ n + 1 uh * n factorial.
And then you're getting x to the n * n +
one factorial. So this is what it's
equal to.
And now of course here there are x *
itself n + one times the n of those is
canceling out with this. Right? So this
is x
and here you have you see here the n +
one factorial. You can write as n +1 and
then times n * n minus one etc. But
that's just n factorial. So you can
write like that. And so you see that
this here cancel that. So you left with
n + one. Remember x is fixed. If x is
fixed as n goes to infinity this here
for each fixed x this here just goes to
zero. So this so now you have from the
ratio test if that limit if it has a
limit it does have a limit if that limit
is strictly less than one but it's
actually zero right so it's it's
definitely fall into under one so it's
convergent right so the ratio test tells
you so by the ratio test so by the ratio
test
this is converted.
Okay.
And so we finish here. There's a little
bit more posted already that my lecture
notes. There's a little bit more uh and
I'll probably talk about that uh next
time. I'll just start with just talking
about the stuff I didn't get to. stuff I
didn't get to was and we we touched upon
that earlier is lem soup and lem mint h
and um and the reason why we're covering
it here is that what if the ratio what
if these things what if the nth root so
you're asking for either the ratio or
the nth root of something to have a
limit but what if it doesn't have a
limit right and so it's dealing with
that case. Okay.
All right. Any questions?
>> That means for all X, right?
>> This is for all X, but think about X as
being fixed, right? Think about X, you
know, you're just for you're just asking
for one particular X, but it holds for
all X, but but don't think about X also
as being variable, right? Because X, you
think about X as being fixed, and then
you let N go to infinity,
>> right? And then Yeah. Yeah, that's
right. And so you have for all X this
makes sense. And then you can ask how
does it vary in X? But that's a
different story.