So welcome to this edition of the broad
MIT uh seminar series. Um I wish to
thank our sponsors and uh also professor
Ed Sknick for endowing this seminar
series. Um so thank you Ed for your
continued support and leadership. And so
today it's a privilege to introduce
professor Nathaniel Gray who doesn't
really need an introduction to this
community. Um Nat is a Krishnan Sha
professor family professor at uh of
chemical and systems biology at Stanford
and he's also a member of the chem
there. Um Nat received his bachelor's
and doctoral degrees from University of
uh California at Berkeley and there he
developed these combinatorial um uh
platforms and functional genomics
approaches and that yielded uh pervenol
that's one of the uh one of the early
selective inhibitors of um cycl
dependent cycl dependent kynases and
then following his PhD Nat went on to
work at Novartis and there he his team
developed the um allesteric the first
alleic inhibitors of BCR aable that you
know resulted in the drug aim and then
also uh the alk inhibitor that resulted
in a drug
serotonin nat started his lab at Dana
Farber in 2006 and there also he has
developed a lot of firstin-class
pharmacological agents
uh just to name a few uh his work
particularly on targeting these
gatekeeper mutations in kynases has elia
drugs like osmortnib
and punat and and and then today Nat is
going to talk about a completely
different u space about molecular glues
and transcriptional
reprogramming. Um so NAT has received a
lot of awards uh including NSF's career
award, Damon Rener Damon Renan's uh
foundation's innovator award and more
recently the Paul Mars prize. Uh please
join me in welcoming
Nat. Thank you so much for that uh kind
introduction. Thanks for coming to spend
your afternoon uh here to listen to our
science. So yeah, I'm going to talk a
little bit about uh chemically induced
proximity. I'll start off with a
introduction regarding um degradation
and then sort of show how we evolved it
to transcription factor uh
reprogramming. Uh these are my uh
disclosures. The ones in in red are the
most relevant to uh today.
So I think if you look across the
therapeutic uh landscape, you know, one
observation I've made is that uh as you
evolve sort of fundamentally new uh ways
to tweak uh nature, you fundamentally
get different uh mechanisms at play. And
I think one of the things we can do uh
best in in academia is to try to
increase, you know, what's on the menu
here for uh different uh approaches. And
I think we're we're gradually seeing
more and more intricate ways that we can
uh manipulate uh nature to affect uh
therapeutic uh ends. So what I'm going
to talk mostly today about is this uh
final box. So proximity therapeutics. So
what is what is proximity therapeutics?
It's therapeutics where you get the
pharmacological effect not by inhibition
of A or B but through a new function
created by the unnatural uh union of two
uh proteins. And one of the major
advantages of proximity therapeutics is
that new function that you can get may
not be predicated on either the function
of A or function of B. It really can be
a denovo uh function. A second advantage
is even though I've drawn the sort of
equal binding to each side often times
these molecular glues will primarily
bind to one protein and then induce a
protein protein interaction with a
second protein. That means that the
second protein doesn't need to be
naturally druggable. May not have a
drug-like uh binding pocket. And of
course, this goes back to um mother
nature that's already taught us that
this is a very powerful way of inducing
uh new protein function. So many natural
products will act as molecular glues and
often targeting things that historically
been very difficult to target. So for
example, seminal work targeting
calcinurine which remains a very
challenging target for small molecules
but very well uh targeted via this
molecular gluing approach. So what we're
trying to achieve is a molecular glue
that will lead to a gain of function of
the target gain of function of perhaps
the other protein uh and fundamentally
new pharmarmacology. So the first system
where this was sort of discovered was in
the molecular uh glue uh degrader either
with bveillance or monovalent glues
where the idea is to induce a new
substrate interaction with an E3 ligase
to get ubiquitation and protein uh
degradation. So um about 10 years ago
when we started this work in
collaboration with uh Jay's lab we
started thinking about uh what are the
the key features of these molecules that
are going to be fundamentally uh
different from a traditional occupancy
driven inhibitor right where you're
looking at resonance time you're
primarily looking at inhibition of an
enzyatic activity you often have to
maintain high drug levels to maintain
full occupancy in contrast these
proximity based methods are event driven
so you're simply trying to have a
molecule induce a productive interaction
and then if the function comes from the
enzyatic activity of one partner you can
have turnover. So in this case uh
degradation of B84 induced by
recruitment of a cereblon liase and then
the pharmarmacology is controlled by uh
how the system responds to loss of
protein function and then the only way
the system can restore function is
through protein reynthesis. So in the
case of degraders, how quickly the
protein comes back really can predicate
uh how quickly uh the system will
restore itself. And so the index case
for this was uh an initial degrader made
by Jeanji JQ1 uh then elaborated by
Dennis Buckley into this compound, a
very efficient degrader of uh BRD4. And
this was really uh impressive because
before this uh discovery people had
proposed this type of molecule um but
they were typically active at very high
concentration. So people really thought
about this as sort of a chemical biology
ploy. But here you can see even this
initial molecule at 100 nanomolar uh
leading to very potent uh degradation
and this gave a lot of credence to the
idea that maybe therapeutically relevant
degraders uh could be synthesized. So I
think um for those of you who are not so
familiar with degraders here are uh five
things that are really uh unique about
degraders that have uh garnered you know
huge interest in this modality. So one
is you can get really high target
selectivity. So why is that? That's
because you combine not only the usual
features of small molecule protein
recognition but you're inducing a new
protein protein interaction. And so if
there's differences between the protein
interface between protein A and protein
B that can be exploited by the small
molecule. So you're combining both the
the protein level selectivity and the
lian level selectivity uh to get
targeted degradation. Furthermore,
because the inhibitors are uh not
occupancy based, they actually can
overcome many point mutationbased
resistance mechanisms where the point
mutation might induce a 10% or 10-fold
decrease in in um occupancy, but you can
still get enough turnary complex
formation to get uh degradation. You're
also eliminating the scaffolding
function uh of the uh protein uh which
can lead to unique and interesting
polypharmacological effects.
Many times the recruited protein may not
have a binding pocket as itself.
Therefore, you can go after undruggable
targets. There are several examples of
that in the literature. And then just
like a coalent inhibitor because it's an
event driven pharmarmacology, you can
also have a very different PK profile
PKPD profile relative to an occupancy
based um you know inhibitor. So right
now in the field there sort of two
general flavors of compounds. are what
are called heterobivalent or or protac
type compounds where primarily the
difference is these are created by you
know by chemists by uh linking a
targeting liant via linker to an E3
recruiting moyad. These molecules will
often show a hook-like uh behavior in
their pharmacology where a single small
molecule binds separately to the two
targets. This is in contrast to a
molecular glue where the biochemical
definition is that the glue has higher
affinity in the turnary complex. And the
advantage of course with these molecules
is they're often smaller uh more
drug-like and easier to develop. Despite
that, many people have successfully
developed uh compounds with suitable uh
properties for clinical development from
heterobiovalence as well. So our first
foray uh into this area uh was
developing uh kynise degraders. And so
initially we tried to degrade some of
our favorite uh kynise targets and we
ran into trouble. So we decided to try a
sort of promiscuous pathf finding
approach where we made intentionally uh
promiscuous degraders. We took very
generic uh kinase binders. We linked
them via linkers to E3 recruiters. And
then in collaboration with Katherine
Donovan and Eric Fischer at the Farber
who are our lab neighbors, we use
chemoproteics to figure out which
kinases were um uh degraded. And one of
the seminal findings from this study
where we profiled several hundred uh
kynise degraders was that many of the
best kynise degraders didn't actually
start from the cognate lian uh for that
kynise. So you know up until this point
sort of the favorite way of making a
protag was you know take your best
inhibitor of the kynise then make a
degrader from that. But what we
discovered from this schemopomics
approach is oftentimes things that were
well degraded were actually very weak
affinity targets of the initial
targeting lian. So for example the
satinib a very potent sarkc family and
able family kinus inhibitor as a
degrader is very selective and potent
for c terminal sarcinace. So this lookup
table became a very powerful way of
finding good starting points for making
degraders of uh favorite kynise targets
and and and our lab together with many
people in the field have now made a
whole inventory of compounds that can
degrade all sorts of different kinases
either selectively or in a um polyynise
fashion of degrading two three four or
five uh kinases and this has sort of
sparked a big interest now uh in the
field several biotech companies got
started uh and many pharma companies
also invested heavily in this
technology. Uh this is actually from an
old review article, but there's at least
15 different uh compounds now in
clinical trials and hopefully uh we're
going to see um some of these be uh FDA
approved. So here are some of the key
milestones I think in the field that
we're we're waiting on is you know
regulatory approval of the first
rationally uh developed the
greater um there's been some
conservatism. so far in the targets that
have been degraded. So there's been a
lot of work on targets like ER and AR
that we already know are good targets.
But to me the most exciting thing is to
be able to derug things that were
previously undruggable. There's some
examples of that now in the clinic. One
of the promises of the technology is to
be able to achieve tissue specific
pharmarmacology by uh recruiting liases
that are tissue specific in their
expression. There's also quite a bit of
work to expand to non-oncology
indications and then there's work to
generate targeting agents where you for
example conjugate a degraater molecule
onto an antibbody. So you use the
antibbody to target to a cell surface
receptor and then you have the uh
antibbody get internalized to deliver a
degrader to make a sort of a
polypharmacological
uh uh agent that can achieve tissue
selectivity.
So uh really one of the the limitations
of that protac uh approach is that
you're often looking for your keys under
the lampost because it often starts with
a binder uh first approach and so people
are starting from uh targets where
there's already uh ligans. So we started
thinking is there another way of of
discovering um novel degraders and so
several folks uh in our lab decided that
maybe we can sort of take what we
calling a a degon display approach. So
if we start uh from a protein uh binder
but we simply want to go fishing for
appropriate liases. So in our genomes
there's over 500 different liases and
for most of the liases we don't actually
know what their endogenous degron is. we
don't actually know what they recognize
as being messed up. So we we know some
deg are are phosphorilation sites or
proline hydroxilation but in many cases
we don't actually know what that
deg could we simply go fishing uh for
targets that would be um uh
degraded. And so one of the fish hooks
that we looked at initially were uh
simply trying to expose a heterosyclic
system at the protein surface or expose
an electrophile. And so we know that
electrophiles can get generated on
protein surfaces from you know
tyrrosines or tryptophans through
oxidative processes. So we hypothesized
that there might be liases that would
have evolved to recognize uh
electrophiles to eliminate uh that
protein function. And I'll show you now
three quick uh vignettes for um degrons
that we discovered that were either
covealent electrostatic or involved pi
uh cation uh interactions. So Z in the
lab initially started um looking at a
pending deg
uh JQ1. So JQ1 is a binder of BRD4 and
BRD4 is a very easy protein uh to
degrade. It has a lot of lysines and
once ubiquitated it's very efficiently
eliminated and so we built a library of
these fish hooks either these
heterosycles or these types of
electroiles. So this is an electrophile
that will form a shift base with a
lysine. Here's one that'll undergo an SN
aerial uh type reaction or an isolation
reaction uh and looked for compounds
that could efficiently degrade uh
BRD4. And so one compound to emerge from
this uh screen is this ZZ9 compound. So
this compound has a highly electron
deficient aerial system will react with
a thol. And so we initially screen this
library using a B-4 hybrid assay and
then we can confirmed uh by uh western
blotting. We got some incredibly potent
brood domain degraders. You can see here
down to subnanomar um
potency. And then we confirm once we see
that degradation how selective is it at
a proteomewide level. You can see this
is a very selective degrader of uh bromo
domains. Then um the system that we
typically use to look at degradation is
what's called a hybrid assay. I
mentioned this earlier. Uh so we fuse
BRD4 to a split luciferase system and
then this can be reconstituted to form a
luciferase. And we can see that this
compound was incredibly uh potent. So
this is a 15 picolar degrader of BRD4
much more potent than these
hetererovalent compounds here at about
21 um nanomer and again completely sort
of serendipitously discovered through
this electrophile uh library
approach. So one of the key features of
these degrader molecules is you know
figuring out you know how they're
binding and what's the selectivity and
so one of the things we often do is
we'll make a negative control. Also here
we invert the stereochemistry of the
benzoazipene type system. Turns out that
completely uh rescues uh the degradation
activity showing that only the the
correct uh binding isomer uh is
active. We then uh teamed up with
Benit's lab um together with Susanna and
Mikoloi to try to figure out um what
liases could be responsible for this
degradation. And so what you do here is
you uh look by crisper cast 9 screening
specifically at which liases can rescue
BRD4 from being degraded and using this
screen we'd identified decaf um 16 as
the relevant liase. So decaf 16 is the
substrate adapter of this cull based
ligase just like cereablon is. Uh so
here it binds
here we're able to show uh that the
relevant lysine that's reacted in decaf
16 is cyine um 58 and although we didn't
get a crystal structure of this compound
we had an earlier acryumide compound we
got a crystal structure of called mmh2
that forms a covealent bond so it's very
interesting the protein forms a complex
with the liase then the li the ligan
reaches across this interface to form a
coalent bond to 1658 and this is not a
normal sort of electrophile labeling.
It's actually a templated labeling and
you can see this from this incubation
experiment. So only when you incubate
decaf 16 B4 together with a lian do you
get efficient uh labeling. So just like
a kinase you know will take ATP and then
transfer the phosphate to another
protein. The same thing happens here. uh
the the ligase is receiving the
electrophile in the context of that PPI
uh interaction and that's one of the
reasons I think that ends up being such
a potent degrader is you have a
templating effect uh to get that
efficient uh modification of the uh the
thol. So here's sort of a cartoon of
what we think is happening. The
molecular glue binds to BD4. You get
this induced protein protein
interaction. you get the uh isolation or
the alkalation of the thol the
modification and then the subsequent um
proteisome mediated degradation of
BRD4. So that was the example of of a
covealent deg. What about uh this
potential? So for this one was the same
library uh and so here we were trying to
actually target a different residue.
This is some very nice chemistry um very
old chemistry but recently popularized
by Barry Sharpless's lab for reacting
with either lysines, tyrrosines or seren
where you can basically get uh
sulfanomids or sulfanate ers. And so we
thought maybe there's liases that will
react specifically uh with this
electrophile. And so we found this
second compound ZZ1 again it's a BRD4
degrader. That's our sentinel protein
for uh degradation. And then again in
collaboration with Zuzanna we discovered
another uh ligase that's a component of
the C terminal LSH liase CTLH ligase and
this component uh WDR 26. So it turns
out this is a very complicated ligase
and if Brenda Schulman's lab hadn't
already been working on this we would
have been completely lost in trying to
figure out uh this uh this biology.
Luckily, Yakab Critzoot in her lab had
actually just solved the uh cryomm
structure of this very complicated
ligase. So, um the chemist description
of this is a as a giant donut. Uh and so
you basically have this donut composed
of all these different uh protein
factors and the factor that we thought
we were labeling and was identified from
this crisper screen was this Yel 5
component.
uh and Yakob in Brenda's lab was able to
reconstitute this system and basically
show that with the addition of the
molecular glue only when you combine all
these other um factors uh over here can
you get efficient ubiquitation and then
degradation of the of the
protein. We're able to confirm that if
you delete either Yel 5 or
WDR26 that completely rescues uh the
degradation. So those factors are
essential uh for the degradation. And
then we looked across the dependency map
developed by the broad institute for
cells that were either high or low in
Yel5. And as you can see cells that have
high levels of Yel 5 very efficiently
can degrade Brd4 whereas whether you
have a low expressor then you get kind
of a wimpy uh degradation of
BRD4. Then Yaka went on to be able to
solve the cryomm structure of ZZ1
induced neo substrate recognition. And
so essentially what happens is um the
BRD4 neo substrate gets glued by the
small molecule inside the hole of the
donut. Here's a closeup of that
structure. So here's the the molecular
glue ZZ1 sitting there at the interface
gluing BRD4 uh to Yel 5. And then one of
the conundrums was that when we looked
at this cryom structure, we actually
didn't see any bond formation with the
nucleophiles uh here that we had
anticipated. So remember the initial
idea here was to get a nucleophilic
attack onto this electrophile here. And
certainly there's a whole bunch of
electroiles. There's a tyrrosine,
there's a lysine, there's a histadine,
but we didn't see that bond formation.
And furthermore, when we mutated each of
these residues, none of them uh
prevented the ubiquitation of the uh of
the target. So this was very uh
confusing. And furthermore, we then
incubated BRD4 with the uh ligase and we
actually didn't see any modification, no
covealent uh modification. And then we
noticed actually that this binding
pocket was actually very um uh basic.
And so we began to hypothesize that
maybe we weren't getting coalent bond
formation. Maybe there was some kind of
an electrostatic interaction but our
electrophile is not charged. So so why
would that be? We then figured out that
actually this kind of a sulfan fluoride
will react with theols. First we tested
dio that will actually react with a
theol to generate a sulfinic acid.
And in fact the biologically active
compound was actually not the sulfan
fluoride. It was actually the sulfinic
acid. So we had inadvertently made a
prod drug that in cells gets metabolized
to this negatively charged muy that
interacts now with this uh basic
pocket. Then to corroborate that we
synthesize both the sulfinic acid and
the fully oxidized sulfonic acid. Lo and
behold, those two compounds are actually
more potent um uh degraders uh and also
uh work in the um oops in the um
interaction uh assay.
Oops. So here is the chemistry that
takes place. So you basically get an
additional uh thol attack to get this
oxidized dulfide. Then a further thol
attack comes removes that and that's
what gives you the the sulfinic esther.
And this was interesting because
normally chemists are judiciously not
putting negatively charged on their
molecules because you block good cell
penetration. So this was actually an
interesting way of getting a negatively
charged egron into cells. And you can
imagine there's probably a lot of liases
that recognize negative degrons because
for example phosphorilation is very
common very commonly used as a PTM and
there's many proteins that possibly
could recognize phosphorilation and
induce um degradation. So that's sort of
the second uh vignette of a negatively
charged molecular glue. And then for the
pyatine interactions, this is a very uh
common interaction between ligans and
also between uh proteins but is not
often exploited by medicinal chemists
because it's often not as uh directional
and easy to uh predict or to design into
molecules. And for this we were inspired
by this prior um work from Miko and from
Ben and from others um where they
discovered that this CDK inhibitor this
elaborated CDK inhibitor which binds to
a variety of CDKs in including CDK12
actually ends up being a degrader of
cycl K. Okay. And so the way this
molecule works is it reaches across this
protein protein interface and then this
purodal group interacts with an arginine
on DDB1 and then instead of ubiquitating
CDK12 you get ubiquitination of cycl K
and then subsequent degra degradation of
cycl K. So this is what led us to be
inspired that this type of functionality
might be able to serve as a deg. And so
we we elaborated a variety of kynise
scaffolds and we've been working with
this primital system as a CDK binder. So
again Z built a library of uh
electrophile of um modifications at this
position uh making you know both R and S
and antimer compounds and then lo and
behold we found a compound that was a
very good um uh glue between CDK12 and
uh
DDB1. So you can here you can see very
good uh degradation. So in contrast to
the first example which only degrades
Cycl K, this compound will degrade Cycl
K, CDK12 and
CDK13 and it's completely dependent on
DDB1. If you knock out DDB1, then you
rescue that degradation uh activity. And
we've been able to take that um degron
and actually adapt it to quite a few
different compounds to get interactions
with liases that have this type of an
arginine, not only DB1 but others as a
way of getting a a molecular glue. So
the advantage of this um sort of fish
hook approach is that you actually find
uh novel liases um as opposed to
continual use of cereablon and DHL. And
so we hope that has uh further
advantages as we elaborate uh the
approach. So in the next segment I want
to switch from uh making degraders to
how do we make molecular glues that do
other uh things. And so this was a
project initiated when we started at
Stanford about three years ago in
collaboration with Jerry Crabtree. And
so here the idea was a little bit
different. We wanted to see could we
make a molecular glue that will restore
communication from cancer driving
pathways to the apoptoic pathway. And so
we know cancer cells judiciously
downregulate communication with
apoptosis to prevent uh cell death. And
so what would happen if we made a
molecular glue that could essentially
glue an ankcoenic transcription factor
into the cell death uh program? And so
the idea was actually quite simple.
We're going to now make a a molecular
glue between a death regulator and a
cancer driving um uh transcription
factor. And the transcription factor we
decided to target was BCL6. So BCL6 is a
well well credentialed anka gene in
lymphoma. and it gets upregulated in
lymphoma through um promoter mutations
that simply uh increase its expression
level and it's a very powerful repressor
of proapoptoic uh genes through um uh
repression of p-53 noxa and other
proteins. The other reason we chose
BCL6, there's there had been a lot of
beautiful prior med efforts from other
groups to try to target BCL6. And what
prior groups had tried to do was drug
this BTB domain. This is a professional
protein protein interaction domain that
normally recruits co-opressor proteins
to BCL6. And so the idea previously had
been let's block the BTB domain, release
these uh co-opressor proteins to then uh
derpress um BCL6. Unfortunately, these
molecules were not that active in
cellular assays and not in vivo. And
people have also, for example, made
degraders using this liant, again, you
only get a partial um uh activation of
Bcl6. So the idea here was instead of
just um knocking off the core, let's add
now an additional step where we make a
bvealent that will also recruit an
activator. And you might have guessed
the theme of of BRD4 which we we can't
seem to get away from this protein uh
because BRD4 is generically activated
you know downstream of many an encogenic
uh signaling pathways. So we thought in
addition to removing uh the repressors
more efficiently by this blocking
interaction, if we can also bring the
transcriptional activation activity of
BR4, we might further induce the BCL6
dependent gene expression program to
activate the expression of proapoptoic
uh
genes. So the first um molecule that we
made kind of looks like a protac, but
it's not a protac. So it's JQ1 linked
via linker to this BCL6 um liant. And
then a second story I I'll tell you
about in a moment is we did the same
thing uh but instead of using uh BRD4 we
recruited uh CDK9 which is another very
potent uh transcriptional activator uh
protein.
So the reason that we chose uh BR4 not
only is because of the the well-known
pharmacology and our experience in
developing biovalence but also in
lymphoma it's a very powerful
co-activator of Mick uh and Mick is a
driving anka gene uh in
lymphoma. So here's what the the
workflow of this project looks like. We
build a library of these molecules where
we do many of the things that you do
with the protag molecule. we explore the
targeting lian uh the linker and then
Saigore Sankar a really talented student
in Jerry's lab uh developed a whole
series of assays that would allow us to
guide the the medicinal chemistry. So
the first assay is a gene activation
assay where we ask how well can these
molecules derpress BCL6 gene expression.
We then measure the ability to form
turnary complex formation. How how good
of a glue is it? And then we measure
Bcl6 dependent cell killing in a
proliferation assay. Whenever we do
this, we make two negative controls
where we either disable binding to BRD4
through making an anantimer on this side
or we modulate the ability to bind BCL6
through a very subtle mutation or
modification on on this side. So the
first molecule that we started
characterizing we called TIP 1 for
transcription chemical induced proximity
one and we got a very nice induction of
gene expression and it shows this
canonical hook behavior uh diagnostic of
um biomolecular molecules like this
where a critical concentration is used
to induce turnary complex formation. But
as you jack up the concentration too
high, then eventually you break up that
turnary complex and the gene expression
is induced not as
strongly. So we were very heartened to
see that these compounds were incredibly
efficient killers of lymphoma cells that
had high BCL6 expression. So here this
TIP 1 inhibiting cell proliferation at
about 1.3 nanomar. In contrast, the two
negative control molecules that either
inhibit because of BRD4 inhibition or
because of BCL6 inhibition are over a
hundfold uh less potent. We saw a very
good correlation in cytotoxicity between
cells that were high and dependent on
BCL6 uh and and well where there was
good killing by the T-IP uh molecule. We
then were able to take TIP 1 into invivo
studies in collaboration um first with
Mike Cameron at scripts uh and we could
show that the primary um uh organ type
where you saw dramatic effects on gene
expression were in in the spleen where B
cell reside but in in tissue types that
don't depend on BCL6 you see very modest
effects on uh on gene expression. Then
we looked at efficacy and here we
collaborated with Michael Green at MD
Anderson. So he is able to get uh
lymphas uh from uh folks that have
failed many lines of therapy. So
typically if you have lymphoma you get
chemotherapy and then you get salvage
therapy with uh other targeted agents
like BTK or with um archop or with bicep
specific antibodies. So even when we got
patients that had failed three to five
lines of therapy, uh their tumors when
implanted in mice responded very nicely
to these T-IP molecules. But this was
not any kind of sort of non- selective
activity because if we got lymphas that
were BCL6 negative, they didn't care
about the T-IP at all. They they grew uh
they grew very nicely. So this is really
a a mechanism that depends on the tumors
being driven by um
BCL6. then cited this really uh
insightful experiment to prove that
turnary complex formation is required
for cell death. And so what he did was
he titrated in the one-sided molecule in
the presence of the biovalent. So if you
first put in the biovalent compounds,
you kill cells very effectively. But
then if you titrate in one half of the
molecule, you actually rescue the
cytotoxicity. So even though there's
more drug there because you're breaking
up the turnary complex you rescue the
cytotoxicity and then once you get high
enough then the curves start coming down
again and you can do that both by
increasing the concentration of the BCL6
inhibitor you can also do it with a BRD4
inhibitor although that's harder because
the BRD4 inhibitor is cytotoxic um by
itself. So what happens at the chromatin
level? So what's happening at the
chromatin level is the T-IP is
relocizing BD4 from where it normally
exists at superenhancers to uh BCL6
binding sites. So fundamentally the
molecule moves BRD4 from where it's
normally bound and accumulates where
Bcl6 is bound and then those Bcl6
repressed genes are then turned on uh by
the molecule. And so here you're looking
at phosphorilation of RNA Paul 2. So
this is the enzyme that makes mRNA. So
as you look at increasing time you get
increased uh phosphorilation of serene 2
and turn on of RNA plyase 2. And the the
effect is so powerful because when
you're modulating this transcription
factor you're not just getting the
effect on one gene, you're getting the
effect on the entire Bcl6 gene
expression program. Right? So
transcription factors are so powerful to
get on your side because they regulate
many proteins
simultaneously. So one of the proteins
that it regulates is Mick. So actually
this compound is one of the most potent
indirect MC inhibitors uh that we've
ever seen. You're actually depleting
Mick at about one nanomolar of this T-IP
molecule. And then once you downregulate
Mick, all the Mick uh target genes are
also uh deregulated. This effect is
actually much more powerful than a
degrader. So we compared the effect of
degraders of either BRD4 or BCL6. The
T-IP is considerably uh uh more potent
even though it doesn't degrade the same
way that the other uh compounds do. So
that was you know recruitment of of
BRD4. We wanted to know is this a unique
feature to BRD4. So inspired in part
from our prior work on CDK9 as well as
Amitz's work recruiting uh kynases we
thought maybe we could try recruiting um
T-IPS with a CDK uh binder. So Basok
took this on uh in the lab and so here
the idea was can we bring CDK9 activity
to the sites of BCL6 to induce
phosphorilation of RNA Paul 2. And
again, we were partly inspired to do
this because there's a beautiful
pharmacopia of uh CDK9 inhibitors made
by uh many of the people uh uh some of
which are in this room. So these
compounds have varying affinity uh for
CDK9, but all of them bind in the ATP uh
binding site of uh
CDK9. And so again, the idea is making a
molecular glue to CDK9, pulling it to
chromatin via BCL6, and then hopefully
releasing CDK9 to phosphorolate RNA
polymerase 2. And so the initial
molecule that Basel made was uh shown
here, CDK TIP. Again, we make a negative
control on the BCL6 side or we methylate
the hinge binder of that site. only the
parental molecule again induces nice
hookshaped behavior in the gene
expression of GFP you get a nice
molecular uh gluing
interaction and then here's what was
really uh interesting when we look at
the anti-prololiferative uh
pharmarmacology so there's a bunch of
curves here let me just uh walk through
them so here is the t- molecule inhibits
cell proliferation at 9 n n n n n n n n
n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n
n n n n n n n n n n n nanomolar. Here's
the the parental liant the SNSO32
originally made by chemist at Bristol
Meyer Squib uh inhibiting here in the
high nanomolar range. Here's a degrader
of CDK9 that we published previously,
thal sns2. And then here's a very nice
compound made by Novartis NVP2 version
2.0 that has a very comparable potency
to the T-IP. So you can say, okay, well
that's not so impressive. You know, your
T-IP is just killing cells at the same
nominal concentration. Of course, this
compound is a normal low molecular
weight compound intracellular
concentration probably a thousandfold
higher than the T-I but at you know
similar concentrations here nominally
killing cells but the real surprise
comes when you don't look at cancer
cells but where you look at normal cells
so here the selectivity is completely
inverted so here the CDK9 inhibitor is
quite toxic to the normal tonsular cells
because they highly depend on CDK
activity. In contrast, the degrader uh
the the T-IP is only active at two
microar. Okay, so this is fundamentally
the difference between an occupancy
based inhibitor and in an event- driven
inhibitor. So this compound is working
because of transcriptional shutdown of
CDK9. This compound is working because
of BCL6 dependent recruitment of CDK9.
So you've completely changed the
therapeutic window by making this
bvealent compound. So to extend on that
finding, we collaborated with the the
prism group here at the broad institute
and we're able to show that this uh CDK
tip was extremely selective for lymphoma
cells that have high levels of BCL6. Uh
you know in contrast, I didn't show it
here, but the CDK9 inhibitor will target
you know many cells that are addicted to
continual uh
transcription. So then Basa was inspired
to make further compounds or that
initial CDKTIP didn't have good PK
properties and so he took a play out of
the protag book of making uh rigidified
uh linkers and was able to make a second
compound uh that was even more potent
CDK TIP 2 activated about CDK at about
um 900 picolar with this spyro uh
linker. uh this compound had much more
reasonable uh pharmacology a halflife of
about three
hours and then we looked at the efficacy
of this molecule here not in cancer
models we actually looked at a germanal
center uh bell reaction so what bcl6 um
normally does is it gets upregulated
when cells are undergoing VDJ
recombination to make new uh antibodies
and so the ontarget pharmacology of
inhibiting uh BCL6 is to block germinal
center formation. That's exactly what we
see. So as we titrate in uh the
compound, we get a dose dependent
formation uh inhibition of germinal
center formation. In contrast, there's
almost no effect on naive cells or on
memory B cells. So we anticipate this is
going to be a much more targeted
approach for activated uh B cell
therapy. So as if you deplete B cells
you know with a antibbody then you're
going to kill you know both germinal B
centers as well as naive B cells and
memory B cells but Bcl6 is only
important when you're changing the gears
on gene expression uh and that's where
this T- molecule uh selectively uh
works. So again the model of what we see
happening here is we see CDK9 being
recruited away from superenhancers
towards the sites of BCL6. Uh that then
activates gene expression. You can see a
massive increase by chipsseek of
phosphorolated serene 2 um and then
release of CDK9 and phosphorilation of
RNA Paul 2.
To corroborate this finding by an
independent uh method, we instead
recruited CDK9 not with the ATP
competitive inhibitor. We instead made a
tagged version of CDK9 and we could
actually achieve uh the same thing. So
if we link the BTB domain of BCL6 via
the tag, we can also get a inducer of
BCL6 dependent expression. again that
corroborates that we're really
recruiting the kynise activity of uh of
CDK9. So I think this is going to be
generally a a very powerful approach to
link encoenic uh transcription factors
to a uh a death regulator. And of course
if the death regulator is a
transcription factor you get the entire
expression program of that death
regulator uh and that induces many
changes uh to the gene expression uh
program. So beyond trying to kill uh
cancer cells you can imagine uh
modulating many other effects in uh gene
expression. So for example, you could
use a T-IP to try to turn on a uh a
therapeutic uh gene by inducing a new
interaction with a factor that drives uh
that gene or you could induce for
example other cell fates uh like
differentiation if you affect the
appropriate um uh
factor. So I really think these um
proximity based therapeutics due to
their novel you know gain of function
pharmarmacology can really uh reprogram
cellular function in unanticipated ways
and we have to be creative enough to
figure out what pairings of targets will
give you that that effect and so I think
there's going to be an emerging field of
of what I'm calling um functional
genomics for glues. uh you can't just
you know necessarily predict it based on
the known function of the driver and the
apotic protein. You may need to develop
a functional genomic screen to ask
what's the the new pharmacology that
you're going to see through that
unnatural um uh
interaction. So let me uh stop and and
thank some really incredible people that
did uh all of this work. So the uh
chemistry efforts in my lab are led by
Tinguang and then all the degrader and
proteomics work we've done uh in a
long-standing uh collaboration with Eric
Fischer's lab and Katherine Donovan. We
then had a great collaboration with uh
Brenda Schulman and Yakob that helped us
figure out the whole white pel uh story.
Ben Eert's lab and Zuzanna and Micholi.
Um we've had tremendous collaboration
with Michael um um green doing the
pharmarmacology on lymphoma. Uh the
whole tip uh concept we developed
jointly with Jerry Crabtree's lab really
spearheaded by Sai Gorsanker Basil Roman
who has his own lab now in Germany uh
WZY and I didn't get to talk about the
work of Meredith who've been able to
also do things with
P300 and I'll stop there and take any
questions.
[Applause]
Okay, questions starting with the
graduate students and postocs. Let's
see. I will just stand here until one of
you ask a question.
Oh,
um, thank you so much for your talk. So,
this might be like a little bit more
basic question, but um in the second
part where you were talking about the
molecular glues that you developed, you
said specifically they're not Protax. Um
but it seemed like you know you saw the
hook effect and the way that you kind of
developed them was like through kind of
Protac ways that you would develop
Protax. So how do you know that they're
molecular glues and not Protax?
Yeah. So I think people get a little bit
confused. So in my mind a a a a glue has
a you know a biochemical definition in
that you you know get heightened
affinity in the in the turnary complex.
So a a protac uh can be a molecular glue
if there is cooperivity in the binding
and and so actually some some protaxs uh
don't show a hook effect because of that
enhanced uh affinity.
So I think uh the distinction is
actually sort of more important for the
chemists you know are the chemists
creating the molecule by you know making
a hetereroyal linking two things
together or are they making things by
elaborating sort of a single uh compound
but the the definition of the glue is
really in the in the bioysics of that of
that interaction. Um so the T-IP
molecules that I I talked about some of
them actually have molecular glue
properties in that they have higher
affinity in the glued uh turnary
complex.
Thank you very much for your nice talk.
I'm not experienc so I got interesting
questions from the talk. I heard this is
very powerful useful and interesting
interest techniques. But my general
question is from the disadvantage or
challenges what do you what do we see I
mean in the future for the glue based
therapeutics.
Yeah. No sorry I I think there's there's
a huge interest right now in um uh in
glues and you know chemists are are
getting better at how to design them
rationally you know how to find them by
um uh by screening. So I think some of
the things that would be really useful
you know to work on right now is you
know what I call uh direct to glue uh
discovery because you know many many
glues are actually really wimpy binders.
So if you start from the binder first
approach then you're going to miss all
the glues that are wimpy binders but but
good glues. So you need strategies to go
you know directly to glues but you know
chemists you know need to have some idea
of what to make. So you know what's the
chemical space for you know for a good
glue. So obviously one approach is you
know working off of glues like you know
the theomide scaffold and there's been
huge amounts of effort making glutamid
uh derivatives and that that I think is
exciting but I think we need uh ways of
going uh directly to glues from uh low
affinity binders. Uh and then I think
the other you know major challenge is uh
you know choosing you know what what
what to glue together. You know we're
still very much uh affected you know by
the the human genome sequencing and the
dependency map and looking for cancer
dependencies and that's all uh well and
good. But when you reprogram cells um
what you're getting is is not just the
the modulation of that single uh protein
function. you're getting something
completely denovo uh you know I don't
know if you want to call it systems
pharmarmacology or or what you want to
call it but uh we need ways of um
predicting what's going to happen and so
some of the nice work I've seen coming
out of Miko Taipal's lab so you know
they're trying to do you know artificial
gluing of two proteins together and then
asking you know what what's the cellular
effect of that so you know chemists need
that information to know you know what
what factors to bring together.
Lovely talk. I'll probably squeeze in
two small questions. The first one is in
the case of your decaf
16. Does the coalent attachment does
anything to the endogenous targets? Does
it degrade? And the second one is more
of a philosophical question. Normally
when you think about optimizing a small
molecule, you look for potency, binding
affinity. In terms of degradability, do
you need a tight binder? Because you
need the thing to go out. If you have a
a pomola binder, your off rate is pretty
low. You want the ubiconated molecule to
go out and re-engage. So, could you
comment on these two, please? Yeah. So,
yeah. So, for first question, yeah, no,
it's it's, you know, um coalent
modification of the indogenous protein.
There's nothing um uh tagged in there.
Uh and then, you know, the protein
that's getting tagged is the liase. So
once tagged that ligase then is a uh
catalyst for degradation of everything
that that modified ligase binds to. So
there's still turnover uh in in that you
know in that scenario. So yeah there's
been some nice work from uh Fur
Ferguson's lab where they've sort of
characterized the the regimes that
different degraders operate in. Right?
So there's what we sort of call the kiss
of death compounds where it's a very
wimpy interaction but it's a perfect
geometry setup for ubiquitation and so
transient interaction is enough to get
ubiquitation and degradation and then
there's some where um it's a slow
ubiquitation and you need a stable
turnary complex and so in that case you
need you know higher affinity binding
you need more gluing because the
ubiquitation is sluggish sometimes it's
because of the biohysics of that
interaction sometimes it's because Some
substrates for example have associated
deubiquitating enzyme that's constantly
taking off the ubiquitin and that can be
very hard to uh you know to counteract.
So I think you know like any good
medicinal chemistry campaign uh you know
the the closer you can be on the SR with
the functionally relevant assay you know
the better and so you know a lot of
companies that are efficient making
degraders you know they're directly
measuring that efficiency of of
degradation of course you know binding
might be necessary but sometimes uh you
know the binding is is really weak and
it's still a very very good uh you know
degrader I think one challenge we have
in the field is that we're not so good
at picking which targets that we're
going to see a big benefit from from
degradation. So we know we can degrade
it but you know where are we going to
get a a big shot in the arm because of
uh you know
degradation beautiful talk could you
speculate a little bit about monovalent
tips and which methods do you think we
should think about in order to search
for them whether any type of modeling of
phenotypic screening or or Yeah. How
difficult do you think we'll we'll have
to try to to find those?
Yeah. So I think you know we could
certainly you know do this kind of fish
hook approach with all the epigenetic
modifiers right. So there's you know
beautiful chemistry now done by the
epigenetics field for all the readers
writers and erasers of chromatin. So you
could you know you could elaborate some
of those uh scaffolds. Personally I'm
I'm satisfied to be in hetererovalent
land initially to you know figure out
the matching and pairings you know that
that work uh and then you know if if you
know the hetererovalent is too clunky to
be uh developed you know then then try
to get you know a smaller interaction.
Of course you know the the problem with
hetererovalence is you know it's usually
like linking the two crocodiles you know
by the mouth. Uh, and that's maybe not
what you want to do, right? You might
want to have the two crocodiles come
together by their bellies. Uh, and that
and that could be better, you know, with
a with a glue type compound, but we're
still at a very early state of of
finding uh, you know, gluing
interactions. Of course, biology has
been doing gluing act interactions, you
know, forever. You know, phosphorilation
is a covealent glue, right? It's a
phosphate and then it induces a protein
protein interaction. So, it's coalent
and and it's a glue. And often you know
the the amount of affinity that you need
there is you know can be can be quite
small. So I think that's a a very
exciting area.
Hey uh thanks for your talk. I had a
question about maybe about the the issue
that you said about targeting for the
last part because you targeted you know
the death
uh sequences and I was just curious um
as to whether you think there's an
immune component to that. That seems
like a clever target because you would
get potentially then an immune component
in the animals and so I wondered if
you'd actually looked for that. Yeah.
No. So, so, so definitely, you know, you
you affect uh expression of markers that
will affect the the the immune uh
effects because BCL6 regulates all sorts
of uh cell surface uh proteins. But you
can imagine you know other systems where
you know you'd want to increase MHC you
know presentation. Uh so no definitely I
think that's a viable target. There's a
beautiful talk you know and we've also
been working on on on p-53 you can try.
So there's the field of corrector
molecules and corrector molecules have
typically just you know stabilized an
unstable protein but you can also
correct by gluing in another you know
scaffolding uh function. So there's, you
know, not now good examples of glues for
uh p-53 to to rescue, you know, weakened
alals of that. So I think that that's a
potential uh, you know, as well.
All right. Good. Um so you talked about
this approach where you search in a very
focused uh place in chemical space by
creating a binder and then decorating it
to find degraders but I'm curious like
what your intuitions are on neopppis
that are not just finding ubiquitin
liases are we going to see a lot of
fruitful stuff there no absolutely so
yeah I mean there's a beautiful paper
from from Katherine and Eric you know
doing uh IPMS you know with glut blue
tyramid uh libraries and and certainly
you find some of the things that are
degraded but you also find a lot of
other uh weak interactions. I didn't
show the data but we've done IPMS with
all of our uh T-IPS and amazingly we
could have done target ID if we had not
known the the two lians by that IPMS
data. So you can really pull down the
relevant um uh targets but you also find
uh you know some other things. So you
know one approach may be yeah you know
you find uh weak glues by IPMS and then
you elaborate weak glues into you know
functional aectors of of those targets.
So I think that that is a possible uh
work plan for um uh you know for that um
and then I think there will be you know
like there are for active site binders I
do think there will be privileged uh
scaffolds for canonical interaction. So,
you know, for a helix groove
interaction, uh, there may be a scaffold
that helps, you know, mimic that and
serves as a as a molecular
glue. Great talk. Thank you, uh, for the
nice overview on the T-zip. So, the I'm
still got something like swirling in my
head. So, you have a CDK9 inhibitor,
right? The BMS molecule, and now it's
fused to BCL6. So, what do you think's
going on molecularly in there? because
you have a CDK9 inhibitor and then
you're relying on it to be a
transcriptional
elongation kynise, right? But you've
blocked up the active site with your
drug. So what do you think's actually
going on physically? Yeah, sorry I I I
went through that too quickly. Um so we
we think it's a catch and release uh
mechanism and we sort of have two lines
of evidence to to corroborate that. When
we tried to do a T-IP with NVP2, which
is much higher affinity, it doesn't work
at all. it does it doesn't release uh
and then we also recruited CDK9 uh you
know via this FKBP tag uh you know and
that also worked and then when we do
that and we throw in the kynis inhibitor
then it then it stops working so it's a
you know recruitment dependent you know
kindness activity recruitment dependent
process and then we see you know
upregulation of uh RNA Paul 2
phosphorilation so we we see the
canonical mark so we think it's really a
you So it's like uh you know pulling a
dog by the muzzle, the muzzle comes off
and then the dog you know starts biting
things. So yeah. So your drug is
collocicalize these things. Do you think
that there's any sort of like a
condensate that keeps it doesn't just
diffuse away quickly? Yeah. So so so I I
do think there's a local environment
effect. So I I you know I don't know how
how general that is. You know Amit's
nice work with the uh thick approach uh
I think is beginning to address that. So
part of it is localization but you know
kinases do have uh you know substrate
specificity right so you need a a good
you know consensus phosphorilation site
and yeah you need it not to diffuse away
too quickly and then of course it also
depends on how um efficient that that
kinace is at at phosphorilation and then
of course the geometry for for setting
up that phosphorilation reaction but I
do think there will be a lot of uh
kynases where you know you're
essentially you know getting a gain of
function through induced
phosphorilation. Awesome. Thanks.
It's like know the condensate formation
like you know catch and release. So the
release requires that well you know the
Kanye should not move away too far from
the side right so there is a
diffusibility question and so do you
think it's only in the condensate
context that's where these uh we can use
an inhibitor of a kind so if I want to
do it in a cytool where or in a highly
dynamic system where proteins can move
far apart really quickly where can can
we really use an inhibitor in those
context?
Yeah, I mean we we we have one one data
point here. So I I I wouldn't venture a
speculation, but I I I'm sure there'll
be situations like you describe where
it'll it could diffuse away uh you know
too quickly.
Um thanks. So So the death spiral for
cancer therapeutics is resistance is
chemical resistance. So are glues going
to be better or worse? Yeah, great great
question. So we've looked at this a
little bit. So the Achilles heel so far
we've seen, you know, both for some
Protax and for uh T-IPS is is one, you
know, they're hetererovalent. So you
know, e-lux pumps and other things can,
you know, elux the compound. They're
also, you know, highly dependent in the
case of the T-IPS, you know, on BCL6
expression. So if the tumors can evolve
to to low Bcl6 expression uh then they
become resistant. However,
um these compounds kill incredibly uh
you know rapidly and they're active
killers that depend on the anka gene and
they don't care about bypass signaling
because they're basically taking the
cancer driver and inducing death. So you
know one common thing for kindness
inhibitors like with EGFR they can
upregulate MET and then they don't care
about EGFR anymore because they have CMT
but in this case it's fine if CET comes
on because the EGFR signaling is going
to drive the the cell death sort of an
active killing uh mechanism. So I think
the the the resistance mechanism are
likely to be orthogonal to occupancy
based inhibitors which suggest you know
maybe they can be used um you know
together. But the big advantage of these
T-IPS is because they're
contextual, they require A and B to be
there. You immediately have more of an
andgate in their in their activity. So
as I showed for the CDK9 TIP, you know,
we get, you know, much more selective
killing of um, you know, BCL6 dependent
lymphas than we would with a, you know,
CDK9 or other, you know, inhibitor.
Any any other questions?
Okay, this one from a traininee. So the
last
one it's a small question for first
part. So uh you observe in a deg
development you observe the um the
suffix region ended up surfic acid. Does
it happen uh every time for kind of
suffix regent or is that the general
metabolic pathway for that kind of
region? Yeah. So, so that you know
highly reactive sulfanyl fluoride you
know gets metabolized by intracellular
glutathione. So it does happen pretty uh
pretty generically but I'm not proposing
that you know sulfanyl fluorides are
going to be you know good uh prod drugs
for for drugs because you know they're
too reactive and they're going to
probably be taken out you know through
through liver metabolism but there's
other ways you know we can get a a
negatively charged group you know and
probably a better prod drug would be a
you know hydraytic reaction from a
sulfonate you know type esester uh and
so you can explore that kind of
chemistry too.
Okay, thanks a lot.
[Applause]