okay good afternoon
so what have we done so
far what is thermodynamics about
remember you told us that uh it's about
heat and
work but uh to date we haven't def find
heat yet nor we spoke about work
although indirectly with the wave
processes but
uh we we have done four hours and we'll
do another two
today without talking about heat
not saying that thermodynamics is not
about heat it is also about
heat but you can go a long way without
and before
defining uh the heat interaction which
will be um the topic of next uh lecture
on
Friday so how could we go that long all
right we just review briefly what we've
done we Define few words like system
property State uh what we mean by law uh
or principle uh which is in fact a
theorem of uh the equation of motion on
your
model
um then we introduced the first law
which is a statement of
existence or actually the first
assertion is a statement of existence of
certain class of processes namely those
that allow you to interconnect any two
states of any system and remember we
mean the well- defined system separable
in the sense that we have made very
explicit
the second
assertion allows you allows us to
introduce a a property a general
property for any of these systems um and
for any of its state by uh supporting
the measurement
procedure that implies uh finding a
weight
process that goes
uh that
interconnects two states that way you uh
can
measure the energy difference between
those two states and uh that is um what
uh defines the property
energy and then this property can be
proved to be uh
additive to
be transferable between systems as a
result of
interactions and
uh also to be
conserned which takes us to the idea of
making a balance of this property
checking in a given
process uh that the change in the value
of the of the energy uh so the
difference between the final and the
initial energy that's to change in
energy
be equal to the uh energy that has been
exchanged during this uh
process with uh between the system and
the
environment positive if
receive okay and this is of course the
hinge of uh the solution of many
problems uh that you have certainly seen
in the undergraduate or previous
graduate courses on thermodynamics so I
rely upon your experience here uh
because this is as you know it's not of
course about application or problem
solving I assume that that you have some
experience on that because the more
experience you have uh the more you will
your intuition and your um uh sense of
um of of things will allow you to
uh pick up the meaning of the underlying
uh uh Theory and assumptions that you
were actually making when you perform
for example an energy
balance then we move on to the second
law also the second law is done uh
is is made up of two assertions one is a
statement of existence again but now
this time it's the existence of the
stable equilibrium states of a
system and
um
that um by itself together with
the definition of stable equilibrium
State remember it's a state that cannot
be changed without leaving
some external effect to your uh so in in
the environment of your system so if you
if your system is in a stable
equilibrium state in order to change it
to another state you have to spend
something you have to uh leave some net
uh effect in the
environment otherwise it is impossible
and this
impossibility U is what uh
we allows us to prove the um
impossibility of Perpetual MO machine of
the second kind which is the Kelvin
plank statement of the second
law the second
assertion supports the
definition of a property that now we
know because we defined it the last time
is H
entropy so it uh shes uh that uh it it
says well you you can all
always
um make a weight a reversable weight
process which takes your system from any
state it is to a stable equilibrium
state but not only stable equilibrium
State a stable equilibrium
State um that for example could be in
mutual equilibrium with your Reservoir
so in this picture I jumped to this uh
conclusion
uh that we have used and proved
um as a consequence ofer two of the
second law and that we used as a means
to define the measurement
procedures
for a property that we call temperature
of a
reservoir I'm not going to repeat that
but as you have seen in the first
homework set I am asking you to repeat
it uh in a short uh
video and uh we used that same um
process reversible weight
process uh between the system and the
reservoir in order to
measure the property
entropy which is
defined by this ratio it's the the ratio
between the change in energy of the
reservoir that occurs when you manage to
make this reversible weight
process that
interconnects in which your system goes
between the two states for which you
want to measure the enthropy
difference divided by
the temperature of the reservoir which
was defined by the previous uh
measurement procedure this
ratio turns out to
me
independent on the reservoir that you
have Cho that you have chosen and used
as therefore just an auxiliary system
uh auxiliary to this measurement
procedure but the result is independent
of that system
therefore it is a property of just
system a something that depends on your
system
a that we call the
an we
also in Define uh a property called
available
energy with
respect to a reservoir it is an addicted
property it can be expressed in terms of
energy and
entropy and it allows us to give an
engineering interpretation of entropy as
being um apart from a constant value
which is this group here is
proportional through the inverse of
temperature of the reservoir to the
energy that is not
available uh so it's not transer able to
a weight in a weight process for the
system when in combination with the
Reser that
temperature so
entropy has the non available uh
energy and it is additive the additivity
remember we also had another property
which is adiabatic
availability which contain much of the
information much of the value in terms
of um what's the best I can do with a
given system in a given State um in a if
if I constrain myself on just wave
processes but
uh the disadvantage of that tic
availability is the fact that it is not
uh
additive whereas entropy
allows to compute the same things and it
is add it which is much more convenient
and
uh um and then we moved we also proved
or said that we can prove um this uh
theorems
about
criteria to determine whether a process
a weight process is
reversible and remember the definition
of reversibility
uh process is reversible if we can
undo not
only what happens to the system but also
what happens to the environment so we
have to be able to find some other
process not necessarily tracing back
backwards the original process but one
in which you can
um
um bring your system back to your to its
initial state while also you bring the
Environ environment back to its initial
state that definition is very is very
solid and uh conceptually valid but it
is also very abstract it doesn't
correspond to a a practicable um
measurement I mean procedure to
determine whether a process is
reversible or not because if you go by
that definition you're supposed to try
all possible processes until you are
really sure that uh uh you stke them all
and uh is impossible to or possible to
um bring back those states to their
Originals uh and so that's clearly
impracticable instead uh
property diabetic Avail availability or
uh entropy or also available energy
um are allow you to one is if you know
how to know how to measure it them and
we know because now we have the
measurement
procedures it uh they allow you to have
a quantitative Criterion to decide on
the
reversibility uh on the reversibility
and actually you can also quantify the
irreversibility um in terms of how much
these properties uh that um appear the
criteria
uh change so in a reversible process and
remember here we're talking about weight
process just weight process in a
reversible weight process the entropy
remains
constant in a in an irreversible weight
process the entropy increases
that the together with the fact that
entropy is ative that entropy can be
exchanged via
interactions see you can transfer
entropy from one system to the other is
something that you do remember the
example of the can of Coke in the
refrigerator well uh when it cools down
uh there is not only energy that goes
out of the can into the air refrigerator
but also uh an tropy flows and we will
get to that
uh um and together with that and with
the with the principle of entropy non
decrease which is in weight processes
which is just what we um said about
criteria for reversibility or
irreversibility you can write the
entropy balance
equation which contains three concepts
on the left hand side
the change in entropy during the given
process for your system a so the
difference between the final and the
initial entropy on the right hand side
you have two contributions that must
balance the left hand
side the first
contribution is how much entropy you
have
exchanged between your system and the
envir its environment during the process
and that is positive if
receive so you have to put it positive
if receive that's the meaning of the SLE
the arrow on the symbol on the energy
transer and the second term is the
entropy that has been
generated by um reversibility so it's
the contribution to of of
uh of the irreversibility so if the
process is reversible that turn is equal
to
zero
but of course we will return to energen
entropy
balances and as you know if you have
done in previous courses or maybe in
energy conservation or Energy
Technologies uh
courses uh if you done exit G you know
that the combination of the energy and
entropy
balance exergy exergy mean mean
meaning the
maximum uh useful effect that you can um
obtain uh in a for under given
conditions from a system in a given
state or vice versa it's
also so by the combined energy and
entropy you can compute what is the
minimum amount of energy so valuable
resources that you have to spend in
order to obtain a given effect so a
given change for example to produce or
to heat up uh something uh water
steel all right and again we'll we'll
come back when we talk about um
in a couple of lectures we will have one
uh review of this exergic
Concepts then we moved
on
to um focus on the equilibrium stat but
not only the equilibrium States because
uh here we have uh in the maximum
entropy
principle that says that if you have um
your
system and you fix the values of the
amounts of
constituents of the parameters of the
external
forces such as the volume but not only
not necessarily only the volume and uh
you also fix the value of the energy
that fixes only a short part of the long
list of values of properties that uh all
together form what we call the state of
the
system so by
fixing this short short partial part of
the list you're leaving free uh the rest
of the properties so there are many
states that belong to that uh
subset so that share the same values of
the amounts the parameters and the
energy
and
among all this uh in in this
subset there is one and only one stable
equilibrium state that is a consequence
of of of the second
law but
uh another theorem is also that that's
stable equilibrium
State as the highest value of the energy
no other state has the same value it has
the strictly uh uh highest value within
that
subset and
finally we introduced the uh the state
principle saying that well
if it is true like the second law says
that if I fix the values of amounts
parameters and
energy and these
values point to a
unique stable equilibrium
state it means that these values fix all
the properties of that
state because fixing the state means
fixing the values of all the properties
so it means that
for the category for this for the very
particular class of states which are the
stable equilibrium
States the properties are all
functions of these three groups amounts
parameters and
energy of these three properties or or
um it's actually uh R if you have R
constituent is R values um you it's like
as many parameters as you need plus the
energy so R plus s+
one values fix the value of any other
property of the stable equilibrium
State H including the
entropy so that gives them a proof of
the existence for stable equilibrium
states of this
function which we call the fundamental
relation
and which if it is uh sufficiently
regular or well behaved so that you can
take um
derivatives and these derivatives are
not zero infinite you can
um invert this function so instead of
writing S as a function of e and and
beta you can write it as e is a function
of s and
beta whereas the fundamental relation in
entropy form this
one is always there for all
systems
uh
the E versus S so the energy form is
there only for systems for which the
these derivatives don't go to uh to zero
and therefore um we will see in a moment
that there are some exceptions
particular systems that are important in
the uh Quantum world for which there is
an upper
Bound in the edge
okay now about taking
derivatives when I have a
function I can write a differential of
the function we just do it uh just for a
uh one variable or say two variables
so Z is a function of X and
Y and therefore the
differential is the partial of f with
respect to X time DX plus the partial of
f with respect to Y in d y
okay now we apply
here the that
idea to the function to the entropy form
of the fundamental relation and
um so written in this way uh really here
what I have is the partial derivative of
s with respect to e that multiplies the
E plus the partial derivative of s with
respect to uh V the second variable time
d V plus the partial derivative of s
with respect to n or n i
uh times DN
I and so on for all the other
vales we have defined those partial
derivatives look at this one the partial
of s with respect to B we called it one
/ t
because we will
identify so the inverse of that uh
partial derivative as the
temperature of the stable equilibrium
stage this
property notice that is defined based on
the fundamental relation and the
fundamental relation is defined only for
the stable equilibrium state
so
temperature is defined only for the
stable equilibrium
States even for the
reservoir we Define
temperature in that particular
way
and it's the temperature of the stable
equilibrium states of the
res then we give also names for example
the uh partial derivative of s for
respect to the
volume we call it p/
t where P will be
identified as the
pressure and the
pressure uh I think I will not go into
this uh proof but you can uh prove it
and again find the proof all details in
in the book it's maybe if you haven't
seen it it's useful to go and look it
up the
pressure when a system is uh is first of
all is defined only for stable
equilibrium
States and you say
well look if I have a wall and I put a a
pressure sensor on the wall uh I can
always measure the pressure even if my
system is not in a stable State well no
what you're measuring then it's the
force per unit area on that
location okay so the force per unit area
you can always measure with with this
with the sensor that we shouldn't call
it pressure sensor it's called Force per
unit area
sensor it turns
out that when the system is in stable
equilibrium
state that Force per unit area
corresponds
to the pressure we find this
way but for example in a known
equilibrium
State when you measure force per unit
area in different locations of your uh
system you may find different
values whereas if your system is in a
stable equum States
state wherever on the surface of the
confining surface of your system you
measure force per unit area you find
always the same
value and that's which corresponds to
the pressure so to give a to fix ideas
suppose I have a
box and in my box I got
uh some particles and suppose that the
particles are
all uh initially
all very regularly distributed
only in this central part of the box and
they all move in One Direction uh
initially so they they're going to
bounce on this wall and then go back and
so on U but of
course due to some Randomness that uh uh
results from the Collision
their collisions with the wall
eventually they will um scatter around
and fill the entire box
right but initially if you measure force
per unit area
here when the particles are hitting this
wall all all all here you're going to
find a very different uh value from what
you do if you measure um if you measure
uh uh your pressure there and by the way
by what do you mean by uh measuring
pressure the pressure measurement is
simply that you
conceptually um breaking the wall
substituting it with a movable piston
and then uh find what force you need on
that little piston of area a small a a
small
area in order to keep fit in the same
place where the wall
is once you find this value of of force
that uh then the force per unit area is
a s over
a and that's the result of
your uh Force per unit area uh gauge or
measurement
device but if you do that
here well there are no particles think
there you find zero uh zero Force per
unit area and as the the particles
scatter around and distribute and become
all randomly um directed then
eventually you will reach an equilibrium
the stable equilibrium State and in a
stable equilibrium State you will find
the same values no matter where on the
wall of your system you're going to
measure the force per un unit area and
in that limit so for the stable
equilibrium State you will find that f/
a at stable
equilibrium is equal
to this
P the thing that we call pressure of the
stable equum
State and this other derivatives partial
derivatives of a fundamental relation
partial of s with respect to the amounts
of
constituents
are if you change sign sign and divide
by T that's the chemical uh
potential of uh that particular con
constituent we'll return to that and
also to a a measurement
device uh that is based again on
measuring Force per unit area
but uh
not directly like this but
indirectly by putting
a a semi permeable substituting the wall
with a semi-permeable membrane and
then
measuring the
force per unit
area uh here
where just particles of one type can
cross the semi-perm membrane that will
be a measurement of what we will call
but defines the partial pressure of
constituent
I and U you measure it again by using
this uh pressure uh or Force per unit
area uh
gauge all right so back to the
differential of the fundamental relation
so essentially it's this formula except
that for the partial derivatives we've
given names and we'll see um at the end
of today why we give names to this
partial derivatives because they enter
into the uh necessary
conditions that must be satisfied in
order for two when two systems are in
Mutual
equilibrium and these conditions will
involve this partial uh derivatives and
these conditions will
be um
consequences of the principle of Maximum
enthropy that we just uh
reviewed
okay now if you
do the same
um development so you write the
differential of the fundamental relation
not in entropy form but in energy form
so the the
same expression that used sort of um
invert then you write the differential
in this way and you can
uh
see and you can see it directly by uh
solving the above
equation uh for
de so you take de on the left hand
side and U and put the rest
on on the on the right hand side and uh
you uh you can um you can obtain this
equation so it's just
algebra um in this particular form which
is called the gives a relation H you see
that
temperature
pressure the negative of the pressure
and
the chemical
potentials are the partial
derivatives why why do I say
that okay that's because you know
the the expression for the differential
geometrically related to if I have a
surface and I focus on one point so
suppose this is a an equilibrium State
and I'm I'm talking about the surface so
this is X
Y and Z and this
surface has a function f of x y = z
okay so now I'm at a particular Point
let's
say with position I mean with
X TI for variable X and Y TI for
variable Y and therefore that would
be
Z so that particular stable equilibrium
State now I
uh writing the differential means
writing the equation of the plane which
is tangent to the surface at that
point these um partial
derivatives are the slopes of that plane
in the directions of X and
Y right
now if I rewrite this function uh as a
function so if I solve it so I rewrite
in terms of uh change the independent
variables so I solve it make X explicit
so it becomes X going to be a function
say of G and Z I'm sorry of of a
function G of z and y so y remains an
independent uh property
and now Z
becomes so it's a different function of
course that's why I write f and
g but it's the same surface so we can
represent the same surface either in
this way or in that way and the tangent
playe therefore it's hasn't changed
doesn't depend on how I decide uh to
consider X Y or z uh a pair of them
independent and the other dependent
okay so the
uh so the expression for the
differentials should
be uh the
same in the sense geometrically in the
sense that they should
represent the same the same
uh therefore if I
write um
the differential of this function here
DX is the partial of G will respect to
Z in d z plus the partial of G with
respect to Y in d y okay
but I can solve this
equation and write it as
DZ equals 1 / by the part of G with
respect to Z time
DX
plus actually
minus um the partial of G with respect
to Y divided by the partial of G with
respect to Z times
V1 okay so I
found either this or that
represent this tangent
play but
also this other form represents the same
tangent
plane therefore I can
conclude
that this coefficient of the X in this
in the expression of this you compare
this and that these coefficients are
equal so this is equal to the partial of
f
oops uh the partial of f with respect to
uh
X and
this is equal to
this same plane means same slopes same
coefficients therefore this is the
partial of f with respect to Y of
course this is true only when f and g as
are related by the fact that one is the
inverse of the other
okay and
that's why that's what I have applied
here to show that uh
if if that relation is 1 / t
it's
inverse is the derivative it's
yeah it it is equal to the inverse of of
the derivative of G which is the energy
form with respect to uh
enter so you go from here to there using
that uh
for
okay now it
immediately St stands out the fact
that if you deal with AUM States stable
equilibrium States and there is an
entire uh long chapter about relations
that you can prove between properties of
stable St we we just touch on this and
it's not our main uh concern but you you
may find lots of papers lots of formulas
and we will use them only when we need
them but one thing I need to to use
because that would introduce and to uh
therefore
Define uh it's the symbol that we use we
use here a symbol we just don't write
only the partial derivative but we write
also parentheses and some substates why
do we do that
uh we do that
because it could happen that
uh for
example uh all right we
have the fundamental relation
in
uh in energy form written this
way but
for
example later we will um give a brief uh
we touch on the subject of changing
variables for example because maybe
entropy is not that uh easily measurable
in the lab in the sense that uh uh we
don't have an entropy meter
but we have a
thermometer
so we measure
entropy
indirectly using the instruments that
are simpler like the thermometer and the
thermometer we will see
measures the
property uh
uh
temperature which is the partial
of this
function with respect to the first
variable as written here so why do I put
the n and V there okay because you see
the next thing I do I can
do is for example to uh write an
expression of uh how the energy changes
let me call it e till
then as a function of t v
and
then
see okay so now I look at these two
expressions there are different
functions but for example suppose I'm
interested in the pressure I take the
pressure it's minus the E the partial of
e will resp ECT to V of the fundamental
relation of this formula but now that I
have another function that expresses the
energy in terms of other variables in
which I also have volume I may be
curious to see well how about doing
minus the partial of e TI with respect
to
V is that the
pressure well not necessar actually
enough
and sometimes if I'm
sloppy and maybe I say all right this is
the function I'm interested in I don't
want to carry around till there so I
just write it as e
well then I may get
confused because when I look at this one
or look at that one which which is which
okay so the idea
is if you want to be
careful is to carry with uh your partial
derivatives also a precise memory or
indication of what the other independent
variables of your function are so if I
write here the other variables so I
write s and
n and here I write the other
variables which are t and n
there is no way I can get confused
because by just looking at the formula
for the partial derivative I know also
what what were the original functions I
mean variables of the function of which
I'm taking the deriv so this is a
notation to to
avoid to get lost uh and Confused
and this kind of confusion is very uh
common if
you if you don't uh because in many many
times maybe you don't need uh this kind
of pedantic way of proceeding
because the context may be enough if
below if just below that partial writing
that partial derivative you have a
paragraph that says well this is the
equation of which I'm taking the
derivative then you're okay the context
tells you what is the derivative of
what
uh but if in in more complex situations
where you keep changing variables then
uh this is really uh essential and
that's why in the business of the
Dynamics it has been introduced and it
is
standard so
also to be sympathetic with ma
mathematicians this I am you should not
read this symbol AS
saying the derivative of energy with
respect to volume at constant entropy
and amounts of
constituents
but yeah you can say it many people say
it sometimes I even say
uh but I don't mean
it yeah uh the real meaning of this is
that uh these are the independent
variables so I'm taking the partial
derivative of a function uh the partial
derivative of with respect to volume of
a function of energy volume uh entropy
and amounts of constituents that the um
that's the proper
language
okay
so why do we give names to temperature
pressure and then chemical potentials
because they enter and we will see it um
hopefully later
today not sure uh any in any way uh
because they enter in the conditions for
Mutual equilibrium between
systems so we'll return to this to make
some proofs but just to
anticipate
um when two systems A and
B are in mutual equilibrium it means
that the uh overall system is in a
stable equilibrium State that's the
definition of mutual equilibrium
remember
so we will prove and we will actually uh
I want to go over this proofs because
they're uh
useful uh also for other uh
reasons it turns out that if the two
systems A and
B can
exchange
energy then
they must if if they are a mutual
equilibrium they must have the same
temperature so the temperature of system
a of theable equilibrium state in which
system a
is must be equal to the
temperature of the stable equilibrium
state in which system B is when they are
in neutral
equilibrium they can also exchange
volume for example
by means of a move movable piston or
partition uh there's a system as the
Piston moves you see that for example it
moves to the right uh the volume of a
increases that of B decreases by the
same amount so you can say you can say
that the Piston you can interpret it as
the Piston has allowed the systems to
exchange volume one gains volume uh by
subtracting it from the so it's like a
transfer of volume all right in that
situation in order for the two systems
to be in mutual equilibrium you need
also pressure
equality If
instead you have a porous wall or a semi
THM membrane that allows the
exchange of one of the constituents from
system between system a system
b h
well the necessary condition for Mutual
equilibrium is equality of the chemical
potentials of that constituent so the
chemical potential of constituent
I measured in system a must be equal to
the chemical potential of system B
measured in system
B so we will prove this because are very
important and actually regarding quality
of chemical potentials we will uh go a
long way in finding a very uh
interesting results and important
results for
applications but before we go and prove
uh these uh conditions for Mutual
equilibrium I promise that I would uh
review what we have done so
far you may call it thody without
heat so far and by means by using by
introducing this um energy versus uh
entropy uh
diagram representation of
states which is uh so important that we
put it in the cover of uh uh our
book okay this is a
the surface this is a fundamental
relation for
water all right so how do we get to
construct these energy uh energy versus
entropy
diagrams again we start from the idea of
State a state is a long list of numbers
usually very long
we Define a few of uh now these numbers
are the properties are the amounts of
constituents the values of the
parameters but also all the
properties of our uh
system at the given instance of time
among these properties we have energy
and entropy but we have also many
others so in order to have a complete
representation geometrical
representation
for a for a state of a system you would
need
um um
an A multi-dimensional Space in each
where you have one
axis for each of the independent
properties of your
system and since independent properties
of a system are generally very large or
even uh most of the times
infinite and you
need to simplify so what we do
is
to
uh
project onto a plane but first what we
do is to uh make a cut of this
multi-dimensional space a cut at fixed
values of the the amount of constituents
and the
parameters when I say parameters think
of the volume and that's the most
common uh at least when you study
properties of
substances
and okay so if I fix the values of the
the amounts and
parameters I still have a large
subset I I still uh need um a
multi-dimensional
space only it's the dimensions
is uh the full thing minus the the
amount the number of constituents and
the number of
parameters still very large then you
project onto all the states onto the
plane made of the two variables that we
must uh uh light energy and it
okay and then you get a two
representation and it it's going to look
like
this energy
the you
project so let's look at the generic
Point
here the generic Point here remember is
the
projection onto that
plan many states will project onto that
plane
because many states will share those
same values of energy and entropy but
differ in the
values of other properties so they are
different states which nevertheless are
represented by his saying Point as a
result of the
projection
okay now that we have understood the
geometry let's see what the theorems
that we have seen so
far uh tell
us about where these States can be in
this diagram so for
example let's start with the statement
of the first assertion of the statement
of the second
law it says well consider all the states
of a system with a given value of the
energ all right so fix the value of the
energy all the states will collapse or
will project onto this um uh dashed line
horizontal
and you see we
have the max entropy principle that we
just mentioned that says that among all
these
states there is a stable equum
state which
is the one that has the highest value
of there are no other
states with that value or even higher
values of ENT so that means that there
is a maximum for the entropy for that
given value for the energy and uh
corresponding to that maximum there is
one
state notice it's only one state so this
particular Point
here is the projection of only one state
whereas here it's a projection of many
states when you go to equilibrium there
is only one
state well that's to say that
geometrically this curve which is the
locus of all the stable equum
States is a
sort of a wire curve in that
multi-dimensional
space all
right so there are no states with higher
entropy so all the possible states are
to the left or with the with a lesser
entropy then stable uh the stable equum
State I do the same uh for another value
of
energy and I get another stum
State I do it
for the minimum value of
energy
compatible with
the fixed values of amouse of
constituents and parameters that we have
chosen in order to make our cut of the
multi-dimensional
space and we still have a stable
equilibrium
State and that's the minimum energy
stable equilibrium
State we'll come back to this in a
moment
uh
okay the
slope of this
terve you
see this curve
represents this table equilibrium State
the fundamental relation in um energy
form because it's e is the in the Orin
and the s in
the uh the Oba and so
um this is the this curve is the
representation of E versus
S at fixed the values of n
andv okay so the partial derivative of
this
function
corresponds
to that's this thing it's the
temperature
or actually partial
derivative
is slope of the tangent to the curve at
a given State equilibrium
state so the
temperature is the angular coefficient
of the tangent
line the
slope the
so I can read the
temperature and
uh I have buil in this
um uh diagram also result that we
haven't proved
yet
namely uh the concavity of this
fundamental relation implying that as
you go um high in energy so you go
stable equilibrium states with higher
energy the slope goes up they also have
higher temperature so temperature is an
increasing function of
energy but
remember temperature is defined
only as being the slope of this curve
only for the stable equilibrium stage
for which there is a curve
you are inside here there is no
fundamental relation there is no uh
function to take derivatives there is no
temperature
okay yeah maybe you can compute things
like the average kinetic energy of the
particles
but uh
whereas the this is related to
temperature at stable
equilibrium it is
not temperature if you're off
equilibrium of course for stable
States
um all right said yes as I as I go um
down in energy I reach the
uh minimum energy stable equilibrium
State and this here another buil in
another feature that goes by the name of
the third law of thermodynamics it says
that the lowest energy stable
equilibrium state has zero
temperature we will not prove that as
this comes more from the model from the
models uh um of the statistical
mechanics or quantum
mechanics
so we don't we have nothing to add to uh
to the uh important but uh uh very very
well known
result it comes from
physics uh in a moment we will we will
also see but I can anticipate that uh um
the
entropy takes a minimum
value and the minimum value is for those
[Music]
particular
uh non equilibrium
States for
which the adiabatic
availability is equal to the energy or
better to the difference between energy
and the minimum energy uh for allows for
that given combination of amounts of
constituents and
volume so if I have a a state uh
here this state from this
state you can transfer in a weight
process to the weight you can extract
out of your system in a weight process
all the energy of the
system meaning that you can take that uh
State uh and bring the system down to
this state the minimum
energy you can do this this here and you
extract this much
energy uh whereas in in a moment you see
that if you do that uh in
a uh no equum State the Artic
availability corresponds to this much
you can go at most down to this stable
equilibrium State and if you start from
a stable equilibrium State remember what
the impossibility the theorem about the
impossibility of perpetual motion
machine of the second
kind says there's no way you can start
from an equilibrium from a stable
equilibrium State and extract energy in
a weight
process and here it
is you cannot go
down in a weight
process you see in a weight process the
the feature is that if you want to go
down to being energy here you need to
also reduce the entropy but you cannot
ruce the entropy in a weight
process let's will return of course in
to these
ideas here I just wanted to say that
there are some special systems for
which there is an upper bound to the
energy these systems are those that do
not have translational or rotational uh
uh or vibrational uh inrease of
freedom and because if you have a
translational degree of Freedom a
particle uh can
move if it can
move uh you can accelerate it to do as
much velocity As You
Wish yeah there is the limit of the
speed of light so on uh maybe that is an
upper bound I've never really thought
about that
uh but here we're talking about systems
like um the spin of an
electron okay so if you want to
concentrate on just the
spin feature of an
electron without all the other details
so that the electron must not be bound
in a in an atom and so on but if you can
define a system in which the only aspect
that you are interested in is the spin
or if you like the spin it could be like
the polarization of
photons these are very um typical of
phantom
Optics because you can with lasers and
so on you can produce beans or very
diluted beans with the with photons like
you can treat one Photon one at a time
and uh you can uh using using particular
filters when you produce these poons you
can have them polarized in various ways
okay but these various
ways um are
Finance so if you like the spin or maybe
even an atom can be modeled with a
finite um number of energy
levels and if it's finite it
means that the energy cannot go above a
certain the the upper energy
level okay well in that in this
situation the sa equilibrium State
fundamental relation looks like this
when you project on eus S diagram
um this is what this is the ersus say
this is the fundamental relation that
you
obtain
okay that function that you're
representing it
there let me write it uh as s is a
function of
e so this is e
minimum this is e
maximum and the fundamental relation
s is a function of
e plus whatever other uh parameters and
amounts
are looks like
that all right so yeah no nothing more
uh for systems with translational
degrees of freedom as versus e
instead there is a
minimum particles are not moving so
there's no kinetic energy and therefore
you have you they are
minimum and this corresponds to the zero
temperature uh stable equilibrium State
and then uh this is
uh well the fundamental relation
the one that we have seen
uh just in the previous dier but if
there is an upper
bound you reach this value here and you
go
down so look at what happens to the
slopes here the slope is infinite
and remember that the uh partial of s
with respect to e is the inverse of the
temperature 1 /
T so if the SL if 1 / T is infinite the
temperature here is
zero then it reaches a maximum the
entropy reaches a maximum for a value of
the
energy so we are we are moving this is
zero temperature it reaches a maximum
here here the inverse of the temperature
is equal to zero because the slope is
equal to zero so that means the
temperature here is
infinite and then you go on the other
side here and the entropy goes down
so you get another state with zero
entropy another stable equilibrium state
with zero entropy corresponding to the
maximum energy the second law is still
satisfied for every value of the
energy there is one and only one stable
equum
State you cannot do it the other way
around in other words if I fix the value
of the
entropy so the
minimum energy principle instead doesn't
apply in this case in this case it does
I fix the value of the
entropy and the stable equilibrium State
corresponds to the minimum
energy because the state the possible
states are only in this area here and
that's the minimum energy but for a
special system like the one that we
talking about I fix the value of the
entropy and there are two stable
equilibrium States one with minimum
energy and one with maximum
energy except
here I fix the value of the entropy
there is only one stable equilibrium
State and
uh if I fix it a higher value of entropy
than this one there are no
States so also this last state so like
the third law says that there is um zero
uh temperature for the minimum entropy
energy stable equilibrium State It also
says that implies I mean I mean that uh
the temperature of the highest
energy stable equilibrium state is
zero however here you have a little
problem somehow of discontinuity because
you
go yeah I forgot to say one important
thing the slope on this side of the of
the
curve is
positive okay whereas on this other side
of the curve the slope is
negative so
all
these uh part of the uh all these stable
equilibrium states have negative
temperatures negative
temperatures are not so exoteric they
were discovered in uh I think it was
1956 that's when I was born by uh Ramsey
at Harvard
just next
door and actually his daughter was the
wife of Professor
kek who was
downstairs and uh with whom I have done
my Master's
physic okay all right so negative
temperatures
we will see that the idea of negative
temperature is I mean the
the uh the name is not really uh very
good because you say negative it's below
zero well really actually if temperature
measures uh the tendency of a system as
we will see to uh yield energy to give
out energy
um these negative St temperature
states have a have more uh
tendency uh to give out energy than uh
the positive temperature equilibrium
States uh they're hard to
keep also because uh we
we I don't know if we can make in a lab
a something that has a properties of
that we could call Reservoir although
I'm not sure but uh uh that we could
call uh Reservoir with a negative
temperature I'm not sure it can be done
in the lab
uh simply because most of the times
reservoirs have been constructed uh uh
by using systems that have translational
degrees of freedom and therefore they
have no negative temperatures but
maybe uh it is
possible also to do a a reservoir with
negative temp
anyway so we have a problem here that uh
the temperature goes from
zero positive values to plus infinity
here then immediately after it switches
to minus infinity and it goes down to
zero again so it's some there is some
sort of dis continuity if we uh insist
in talking of temperature but if instead
we look at a scale in which we uh
instead of temperature we do minus one
over
temperature uh
this which can be interpreted uh again
as the tenden and escaping tendenc for
energy so the still measures the energy
the the the tendency of a system to in a
stable equum state to give up uh um
energy and
um you see then this property here for
this curve would go from minus infinity
in
the minimum
energy minus infinity it goes to zero
and from zero without this continuities
it goes to plus
infinity so that is also a better scale
so this is the uh it also shows you that
U um this property is continuously
increasing from minus infinity through
zero to plus infinity and these ones
that have a high value for this property
are the
hotter uh
if we understand as hot something that
has a strong tendency to give out
energy okay so this much for
um special
systems now let's go back to our sucess
diagram and try to visualize the idea of
adiabatic availability remember
adiabatic availability is
a property that measures the maximum
amount of energy that you can extract
out of a system in a given state in a
wave
process and you manage to extract it
when you manage to take your
system yeah there is a y there that's a
wrong spelling that's uh
Italian it's also wrong in Italian
anyway I'll correct it uh it has to
finish to end up in
a stable equilibrium
State and that uh process must be
reversed okay so what do we know of the
reversible process or reversible weight
process in terms of enthropy what did we
learn we call in the principle of
entropy non
decrease but we called it also Criterion
for reversibility of processes if a
process a weight process is reversible
the entropy stays constant okay so let's
do this in a plot I start from my
system in some State
here generic State
E I make a process in which I want to
take an energy out of the system so the
energy goes down because I'm taking out
of the system it goes down because I
want to give it to the
weight I want the process to
be not only weight process but
reversible so in a reversible weight
process the entropy doesn't change so I
go
down this
way I go down and until there are
states uh eventually I reach the
minimum uh energy stable equilibrium
state with that
entropy and there are no more States
below that so that's all I can do in a
reversible weight process this is is as
much as I can go
down so the difference between the
original energy and the energy of the
lowest uh
energy stable equilibrium state with the
initial
entropy is thetic availability so this
is the visualization of thetic
availability it's the distance in that
diagram uh between your state and the
stable equilibrium uh
curve
vertically so for example if I consider
if my initial state were
here at zero
entropy you see I can go
down and
meet the zero
entropy uh stable equili
state which is the minimum
energy state stal state of uh of mcats
or
actually regarding this area it's uh us
this it's discussed in the book I don't
want to go to the details but uh somehow
there is
a this is not necess this stum St is not
necessarily zero
entropy it's zero temperature by the
third law but it could have a
finite
entropy equal to the logarithm of the
degeneracy of the uh of of of that
lowest energy your ground
step
uh okay nevertheless the amount of the
diotic availability for a for the S
Forest state with zero um entropy is
equal to the difference between its
energy and the lowest
energy for those value of amounts and
Par so this is the visualization of
thetic availability if I go the more for
a given energy the more I go to states
that have higher
entropy the less adiabatic
availability they have until I reach the
stable equilibrium state that has zero
diabetic
availability I'm already there I cannot
go down vertically because there are no
States available
there okay we talked about
resir remember Reservoir have a
constant temperature they're stable
equilibrium
State and all the same temperature
TR for as long as the system behaves as
a as a res because as we said if I make
Reservoir with uh make um yeah if it's
done like water at a triple point H as
long as I have all the three phases
coexisting that is behaves as a
Reservoir in St equum
States but if I put too much energy for
example and one of the phases
disappears uh then that does that system
doesn't behave as a res anymore so it's
it's in a limited range of states the
system can be headed as a thermal
resware or can approximate because that
is an an approximation
practice because rigorously rigorously
uh speaking
uh
uh true resare doesn't really uh exist I
know confusing new but some sometimes
it's good to be confused uh because the
reservoir is a very limiting uh
uh
system and uh in fact if you think
deeply enough you find also this
discussed in the book uh you you see
that strictly
speaking uh if a wrestle were satisfied
it's defining features it would be
violating the second
law all right so we are using that as a
limiting system and this in
fact allowed me to say that uh
in in the years after publishing that
book we've been uh
uh together with Professor Z of
University of bologa in Italy
uh who contributed also in some of the
proofs of the book uh
uh we went on and tried to find an
alternative way of defining entropy
without not without the
reservoir without uh because the
reservoir is some some sort of a
macroscopic
object and we want to to do it more
generally so that it our definition of
we could extend also uh to microscopic
situations but also in an operational uh
therefore
laboratory
uh applicable measurement uh
procedure we so we did we have some
papers around uh around that concept
and uh also some also a famous
mathematicians s l uh
in later on I mean after our book has uh
published U alternative definitions of
any for non States and
initially uh they didn't do it for non
equum States but then they realized that
um they could do it that uh we were sort
of doing the same
thing so what I'm saying is
that I'm telling you this definition of
entropy uh as it were an easy uh stuff
but it's not really very easy because
conceptually uh entropy has
always uh been a a a difficult uh
um topic uh to understand there's so
many facets one is the laboratory the
other is the statistical and now we have
also the
quantum uh so it has so many facets that
uh you shouldn't
say yes I understand what entropy is on
the other
hand you should say that you understand
what entropy is you know like
contradicting a bit because if you want
to go home now and say well what's what
what did you learn in thermodynamics
course so
far well I learned you could say that uh
yeah there is energy everybody knows
about
energy with energy you can do useful
things but not all the
energy
is convertible into useful
effects uh in
fact
entropy is a measurement of that part of
the energy that cannot be converted into
useful effects so from an engineer point
of
view that's a very clear statement and
it's true that's not controversy about
this
okay all right so let's move on um
because we're running out of time and
um so the
reservoir has stable equilibrium
states that all have the same
temperature so since temperature is the
slope of the fundamental relation of the
curve that represents the fundamental
relation the fundamental relation for a
resing work is a straight
line so the equation for a straight line
is this
one changes in
energy are related to changes in entropy
between two if the system goes from one
stable equilibrium state to another
stable equilibrium State and therefore
it moves along this
curve then
the ratio of the energy change to the
enthropy change is equal to the
temperature of the
res
why uh we use the the reservoir remember
we used it so that we could
uh make that property additive uh so we
build we built additivity
into uh the concept of diabatic
availability and in fact if we consider
the adamatic availability of a composite
system composite of a system like a
normal
system and the
reservoir then thetic availability of
this
situation is what we call available
energy it is a it turns out to be a
property of system a for given uh with
respect to a given vers it's called
available energy of a system with
respect to a given energ and resir and
we have
given the formal expression in terms of
energy and entropy so you can
compute
uh the available energy the maximum work
that you can extract from your system A1
it has available the possibility to
inter
with a res and exchange with
it so let's see how we can could
construct see this is the formula for
available
energy and how can we construct uh uh
that
formula so here
is
the eus diag for our system
a fixed values of n
andv stable equilibrium State
curve let me consider
Again State
A1 if for State A1 I make
a um reversible weight
process I can go uh the entropy remains
constant and I can go down this much and
that's how I extract thetic I mean
thetic when I want to extract the
available energy here remember in the in
the end in the final
State the composite system must be in a
stable equilibrium State it's only then
and only when I reach the stable
equilibrium state that I cannot extract
anymore in a weight
process so stable equum state for a
combination means Mutual equilibrium so
the final state of system a is in mutual
equilibrium with the
reservoir all right if the reservoir is
a temperature
TR when the system a is in usual
equilibrium with the reservoir we said
that we will prove that uh
the two systems in mutual equilibrium
must have the same temperature so system
a must end up in the stable equilibrium
state that has a slope that has
temperature equal to the temperature of
the
Vel so if this is temperature resare I
go and look for the point here on on
this curve where the slope is equal to
tr that is the state in which system a
will be in mutual equilibrium with the
res and that is going to be the final
state of system
a you
see uh in order to go from the initial
state of system a to this final
State I need to change the
entropy
system in this case since State a r is
to the right in the diagram of State
A1 the entropy Sr is greater than S1 and
one
possibility is
to let entropy
increase by means of some spontaneous
process let make a weight process an
irreversible weight process in an
irreversible weight process I can
increase the an and so I can go from
here to to there in the weight
process and the amount of energy I would
extract in that wave process would be
only the difference between the
initial final energy that's the energy
balance so it would distract only this
much
but in another way
is
to since I need this entropy in order
for to go from here to there I can ask
it to the reservoir the reservoir is
there and
uh interacts with my
system in whatever way is uh uh allowed
so they can also Exchange
uh
entropy so if I if I ask the resw to
give me this much entropy so that I can
go from here to here in the entropy uh
axis the reservoir let's go back to the
so if if the reservoir has to give me
some entropy it means that it must go
from here to the left
in order to give me some
entropy
it it can give me also some
energy So I says all right
R while you're giving me this much
entropy and going from here to here you
can give me also that energy go from
this stable to the new stage to this
lower energy stable equum State and that
energy becomes
available to
go to the
weight so the P the reservoir you take
energy out of the
resir and give the energy to the weight
and give the entropy to the
system yes
and
therefore uh you can see this uh um
inclined line you can view it also as
the stable State C for the residir so
this much
energy reduction of
uh uh
of the for the reservoir implies this
much energy so this are much entropy
reduction inlies as much energy
reduction
so in addition to the energy that you
can extract directly from system a going
from here to
here so difference between final initial
and final energy of system a you can add
also this
much as energy
that is extracted from the Reser and
therefore
geometrically geometrically the
available energy is the sum of these two
contributions which is also the
geometric representation of this
formula
okay all right well
I think we will take it from here but I
want to skip this for the moment and uh
uh so the next time I still have to do
what I I didn't manage to do today it's
the the necessary conditions for Mutual
uh uh
Equity so I
think yes time is up for today so I'll
see
you on Friday