I'll be talking about
colocalization which is predominantly a
method used to find overlaps between
gwas and eqtls start off with something
that a lot of people are probably
familiar with but which is foundational
to the whole topic which is linkage
disequilibrium and that's basically the
fact that variants that are near one
another on a chromosome tend to be
inherited together uh and because they
tend to be inherited together if one of
the variants creates a change in some
kind of TR we're measuring like height
or cholesterol the other variants that
are inherited with it tend to also be
statistically associated with the trait
so when you have a gwos Locus it looks
something like this where there might
only be one variant in this Locus that
actually Alters the trait in humans but
you have many many variants that the
gwos identifies as statistically
associated with
it and this is a problem if we want to
compare two gws right here we have the
same
Locus and we're looking at two different
traits which I'll get into in a bit uh
and it might be the case that when you
have these two trades you have a variant
that's genomewide significant in both of
them it's statistically associated with
the trade on the left and the trade on
the right but that doesn't mean that
that variant or any variant is
necessarily causitive for the changes in
both traits in fact you could have
variants that are different from that
original variant in fact also different
from one another that are responsible
for the two traits and that could mean
something very different biologically
than if the same variant is causing
both or alternatively to have a
more oh well so yeah as I said a gene
that's significant for both traits is
not enough and to get around that we
have to look at the entire locus of the
association we have to look at the
entire Locus in a way that considers
linkage
disequilibrium uh and a positive example
uh would consider linkage in this kind
of way so here we have the most
significant variant for the trade on the
right and we can see that uh even though
this variant is technically significant
in this other trade notice that this uh
P value scale is very high uh it's
clearly not the most significant variant
and these variants that are in linkage
disequilibrium with the variant in the
trade on the right are not in linkage
disequilibrium
on the left and that's evidence that
even if you do have a shared significant
variant it's not a shared causitive
variant uh and in this uh alternative
example you have two very similar
looking
chws uh and in the locus on the right
the most significant variant is also
significant for the trade on the left
and even though it's not the most
significant variant in the trade on the
left the linkage pattern where we see
these variance in tight linkage with
this purple variant is pretty similar
and that's evidence that in this case
you do have shared significant variants
and that those shared significant
variants are likely due to a shared
positive variant and the reason we care
so much about this is that we often want
to compare gws and
eqtl and the reason for this is most gws
are
non-coding and because they fall in
non-coding regions the mechanism isn't
as immediately clear as if they fell in
the coding region of a protein one idea
is that they may often affect Gene
regulation and so the question we want
to ask is does this same variant that's
responsible for the gas trate also alter
the expression of a gene variants that
alter the expression of genes are called
eqtl or expression quantitative trait
Losi and mapping them works very very
similar to GW and so because of that we
can do use this method of comparing to
gws Losi to link eqtls and gws so here
actually the trait on the the left is
LDL
cholesterol and the trait on the right
is the expression of the
CP Gene which is known to be linked to
LDL cholesterol and so this VAR whatever
variant is altering the expression of
this Gene also seems to be altering the
expression of the level of cholesterol
in humans and that's not proof that
changing the expression of this Gene
changes the level of cholesterol but
it's pretty strong
evidence so I'm going to be talking
about two families of methods uh the
first method is transcripton wide
Association studies or
TS and there are quite a few pretty Sim
versions of this the second set of
methods are colocalization methods both
of these answer a pretty similar
question probably some very strict
people would say that TS aren't
colocalization methods uh but I'm going
to give some time to about and so PW
methods basically correlate gene
expression between a
gwas uh sorry
correlate the genetics of a g was and a
gene expression trait
so this would be pretty straightforward
if you just had gene expression measured
in the same individuals you had the GW
was tra and you wouldn't even need
genetics in fact you could just look at
whether the expression of this trait of
this Gene was correlated with the trait
but it's pretty rare that we have both
of these sets of data in the same
individuals so originally how TS worked
is they looked at the genetic
Association ations that affected
expression and then they looked at which
variants were present in the
individuals uh that the gws was run on
and you can impute to a certain level
you can infer what the likely level of
expression in these individuals is and
then with this estimated expression you
can compare that to the GW was
tray um so you start off with the the
Snips for expression
which you identify in some expression
data set such as gex then in other
individuals you use their genomes to
predict the expression and you can
compare that to the trait and then later
versions uh simplified this so that you
can actually do it just with summary
statistics you don't need the genomes of
the individuals in either case and at
this point it's essentially a genetic
correlation test but because it's a
genetic correlation test for uh
expression in some other trait it is
looking at that relationship between
gene expression and say LDL
cholesterol uh TOS is very powerful but
it's imprecise now I've only talked
about one method essentially but the
different methods of ts are very very
similar uh and it
works very well
when the positive variant is actually
missing from one of the data sets which
can be a huge problem for other methods
but because it's just relying on the
correlation TS isn't that thrown by
that uh however we also know that many
genes in a Locus have correlated
expression that uh genes tend to go up
or down together and in that case TS
can't really distinguish between them
and you often have multiple hits in a
Locus when you have these multiple hits
you know you end up with a lot of
positive findings so I think TS is very
good uh when you're you know doing some
sort of exploratory analysis but tends
not to have the specificity that you'd
want to really consider it confirmation
of some
idea so going to go on to colocalization
methods please do feel free to to
interrupt with questions I can still get
everyone to the next talk on
time uh cocalis ation
methods ask a slightly different
question if T asked are the genetics of
gene expression and the GW trait
correlated colocalization asks is there
a variant that is responsible for
altering gene expression and altering
the GW was trait so the statistical
methodology of all of these methods
looks something like this what is the
probability that a variant is
in in a Locus is causal for a change in
expression and also for a change in the
GW
trait and how can we measure that
conditional on the data we've observed
in our gws and our eqtl
mapping and essentially this is fine
mapping right because if there was no
linkage disequilibrium this would be an
easy question if there was only one
positive variant in a Locus
that would be the only variant you would
find because there tend to be these
correlated Association statistics we try
to narrow those down with fine mapping
and when we narrow those down
together uh you have this joint fine
mapping that is essentially what most
colocalization
is uh part of the reason colocalization
is powerful is because as a basian
method it kind of lets us flip this
question around so instead of asking
just what is the probability that this
variant is linked to expression and to
the gwos trait given the data we
observe we can ask
well what is the probability that these
data would occur
if we assumed that the variant is truly
an eqtl and truly a xwas
Association and then what we have over
here on the right is we have our our
prior because this is a basian method it
includes our estimation before looking
at any of the data that the gwas hit and
the eqtl are the same variant and the
prior is actually one of the areas in
which different calization methods tend
to
differ so one important way in which
colocalization methods can gain power is
by not just looking at individual
variants because sometimes you don't
care which variant is an eqtl and which
variant is responsible for the change in
the GW was trait you just care whether
it's the same variant and in those cases
you can do this joint fine mapping and
then you can actually sum it up over a
region so you can take the probability
that you know this first snip is
responsible for both the expression
change in the gws trait change combine
it with the probability that this next
snip is and this next snip and so on and
so
on uh so some important things to
remember about colocalization
again it's not actually testing
causality if we find a calized Locus we
tend to assume that the change in
expression is contributing to the change
in the GW trait but we don't know that
this is the case it could be that uh the
change in the gas trait actually somehow
leads to a change in the gene expression
or it could be and this is probably more
like likely that they both share some
third cause that the expression of some
other Gene affects the expression of
this Gene and also affects the gwas
trait and this was sort of like the the
challenge Tas faces where you have these
correlated expressions of genes in
nearby
Loi and should also remember that
because it's a basian a set of basian
methods the output of colocalization
analysis is typically a probability this
probability can have a lot of different
names posterior probability Regional
colocalization probability uh etc etc
but it all kind of means the same thing
it's the probability that after doing
this analysis in this Locus the same
variant is responsible for the changes
in expression in gwas trait so a
posterior probability of 0.9 in this
case would mean that we're 90% sure that
the same variant is responsible for both
changes this of course given our
assumptions given our methodology and
given the data that we've
observed so there are a lot of
colocalization
methods uh and in fact I haven't updated
this slide from previous times I've used
it so there's actually additional ones I
could have added since then uh some of
the most common ones are collo EAP and
inl which has since become fast
Ino uh so I'll talk a little bit about
the differences that tend to occur
between them because they they all have
that same basic premise at this point
which is jointly fine mapping expression
in the gws trait but one of the things
they differ in is how they handle alic
heterogeneity it's possible that the
association in a Locus isn't just due to
one variant that affects the GW trait or
one variant that affects the expression
of the gene there could be multiple
variant that are affecting the ex uh the
expression and in that case because
these variants are in linkage
disequilibrium you end up with a very
different set of summary
statistics and it becomes even harder if
you have say multiple variants that
affect a trait but only in but only one
variant that affects expression in the
locus then you'd still probably want to
return a positive colocalization result
because after all there is a shared
variant affecting both the gws trait and
the expression but it might be more
difficult to detect so some methods uh
are really designed around allowing alic
heterogen
heterogenity uh to
exist additionally because it's
essentially a fine mapping method there
are lots of different fine mapping
algorithms lots of different fine
mapping methods that you can use as the
basis for
colocalization and as other fine mapping
methods improve you tend to get improved
performance of
colocalization
additionally
uh pardon me these methods differ in
their prior probability so remember we
have that assumption up front of How
likely it is that the eqtl and the GW
are the same Sniff and there are
different things you could consider here
you could for example just say it's
totally random that there's some
probability that a snip is an eqtl some
probability that it's a Jos Associated
variant uh and those two probabilities
are entirely
independent you could also just have
something built in where you could say
well based on our understanding of the
biology of Gene regulation we think that
if a variant is an eqtl
it's you know say three times as likely
to also be a Goos
Association or you can look at the
summary statistics from the eqtl
analysis and from the gwas and try to
estimate the enrichment so you look at
how much overlap there is how large that
overlap is compared to what you'd expect
by chance and then you use that is your
prior in all the individual low sign and
uh addition Al and this is I think
perhaps the most important thing if you
just want to use results from cooll
localization there are very different
prior prob uh sorry posterior
probability cut
offs in frequenti statistics there's
kind of the accepted P less than 0.05
cut off which you know you'll have to
scale for multiple testing but which we'
have all sort of agreed on and I don't
think there's a threshold everyone's
really agreed on with B
statistics so depending on the method
and who's running the method I've seen
for these calization studies posterior
probability cut offs of 90% or greater
50% or greater 20% or greater 10% or
greater or even in one case 5% or
greater so that would mean that you
could have a Locus where you think that
there is only a 5% chance that the same
variant is responsible for both the eqtl
and the gwos association and you're
still returning as a hit so if you want
to use these data please please please
please check what the cut off
is generally what I use is fast inl uh
this isn't necessarily the best method
though it's the best for the things I
tend to be doing with colocalization it
allows a Le look heterogenity so it
still works pretty well if there's more
than one causitive variant in a Locus uh
additionally it estimates the prior
probability using the enrichment in the
data so it isn't just based on our
biological understanding it isn't just
assuming these things are independent
which we know is untrue it's looking at
the data across the entire genome
estimating How likely they are to
overlap and trying to use that in any
individual
Locus so how well does Co I have a quick
question oh absolutely um how we or do
we at all think about multiple testing I
know you talked about it with the
frequentist way but Invasion do we
adjust that pip threshold for when we
have more tests or how should we think
about that yeah you can't uh in basian
statistics you can't do uh just the same
sort of say Bon frony correction that
you can do with P values
uh it also just
depends how you want to use these data
if you want to test a specific Locus
right obviously you have to do don't
have to do any multiple testing
correction if you're looking across the
genome often in basing statistics we
don't have that kind of correction we
just have say the 90% cut
off um I have two questions the first
question is so it sounds like calization
is like stronger than T was or like more
strict is that right and then the second
question is what happens if you're
colocalizing a Locus that truthfully has
has multiple causal variants but you're
only using a single causal variant
assumption does that result in t result
in false positives false negatives or
hard to say yeah so to the first
question I think colocalization methods
tend to be more conservative than TS uh
as a result they also have weaker power
uh and I think this this weaker power is
also why the posterior probability
threshold often
gets lowered to pretty generous levels
and then as to the second question what
the effects of having multiple positive
variant while assuming that only one
exists generally this will lead to false
negatives uh if the two variants are say
roughly similar in their effects
then the fine mapping will just sort of
divide the effect up between them and if
say only one of those variants is
actually causitive for the expression of
the gene it'll try to put as much of
that fine mapping probability in that
one variant and will thus weaken the
amount of overlap you're
getting if you have uh the same two or
more positive variants that both affect
the gws trait and the eql trait I
think in in theory you should get better
per um better performance
then you would with partial overlap even
with these methods that assume one
causitive variant but in practice this
actually magnifies LD differences
between populations so you're still
going to take a hit to your power thank
you
welcome so we've been talking about
power which is perfect and how often you
find things because the answer to how
well colocalization works is not great
uh most methods have found somewhere in
the range of 20 to
35% of gwos lowai are explained by eqtls
so this means if say you have uh an LDL
gws and you think you have uh an
independent Locus in a region there's
maybe a quarter to a third chance that
when you look at this Locus you're going
to find an eqtl that seems to explain
it if it's not clear why this is this is
actually a something that people are
still arguing about a lot uh there's a
lot of possibilities and this is despite
the fact that as I've complained about
the posterior probability cutoffs are
often pretty
generous so you know as I said it's a
matter of debate people are arguing
about this a lot this is one of my
favorite paper titles of all time where
are the disease Associated
eqtls and a lot of the the possible
answers uh include just problems with
with power or it could be that there is
an eqtl that explains the Goos variant
and it's in a specific cell type or
there's a gene by environment
interaction that makes us struggle to
find it it could matter only early in
development there could be essentially
any
context that is required for the eqtl to
matter that we're not finding in our
eqtl mapping studies and one uh very
very specific point that I want to make
is there's a commonly cited number
you've seen I've seen it cited over and
over and over again that
colocalization explains 43% of jws lowai
in fact it's probably the most common
number I see
cited and part of the reason I even
wanted to do a primer is just to specify
that this is a misreading of the paper
people get it from it is from the gex
paper which uses an unusual Co
localization method I don't think they
do it incorrectly but they divide the
genome into independent linkage blocks
and then look at whether there's any
overlap in the block an independent LD
block can of course have multiple gwas
Losi and if you have a highly polygenic
trait like say height you're actually
almost guaranteed to have multiple
independent associations in a gws Locus
so in that case When you're counting
whether that Locus is a hit or not you
have multiple probabilities for it to be
a hit and if you say have four Jos hits
in one of these blocks and one of them
colocalizes in this statistic that's
getting reported as one out of one
colocalizations again I don't think this
statistic is incorrect it's a
computationally simpler thing to do this
wasn't the main point of the gex
paper however when this number is cited
it's usually presented as the fraction
of gwas Losi that are explained and this
is actually giving a pretty artificially
High estimate of how well this method
works so I'm going to have a summary and
then talk a little bit about how to use
these methods so eqtls may explain the
mechanisms of non-coding Goos
associations there are statistical
methods that we used to see whether
eqtls explain these associ a and the two
big families of these are transcription
wide Association studies and calization
methods uh these methods often say more
about a region or a locust than they do
about individual variance because we
often care more about the locus than we
do about any of the individual variants
however most OS associations are not
explained by these methods yeah so uh I
had a question kind of related to uh I
guess when you run T and Colo with
exactly the same gws and eqtl data is
there are there cases where you may have
strong Tas signal but weak Colo signal
and vice versa and sort of do you have
any recommendations for how to reconcile
those differences I guess before you go
into the description of how each of
those kind of practically work yeah
that's a really good question if and in
fact if you run a colocalization method
and a TS method on the same data set you
will get uh very imperfect overlap and
in fact it's worse because if you then
run say another toos method and another
colocalization method on the exact same
data set the TS methods and the
colocalization methods will often not
even overlap that well uh and how I
would handle that again I think TS is is
good for for certain
exploratory
uh
examinations but it tends to to have a
lot of false positives and it tends to
report genes in sets because these genes
have correlated Expressions so if you
have a your Gene is a positive result in
t was you don't even necessarily know if
it's specifically that Gene or another
Gene in Locus so if
there's uh imperfect
overlap I think in that case it depends
what you're planning to do with this if
you know you just want maybe a large set
of genes that you're going to be
testing uh then TS might be the way to
go if testing these is more difficult or
you want to make more specific claims
then TS is probably a little too broad
and you're probably going to want to use
a co-localization method you might even
want to use multiple co-localization
methods uh the results won't perfectly
overlap and in fact imperfect overlap in
that case is not proof that the result
is false um but typically I you you can
have more confidence that positive
result is a true positive using the
colocalization methods that makes sense
thank you you're
welcome um so I understand here we are
talking about Jas and eqtls but I just
wanted to extend the question to other
qtls right there are pqtls and other
qtls being developed and people start
using colocalizations for pqtl and Jas
colocalization um results so how do you
see that U because eqtls are way more
denser but pqts we have only few
proteins for which we have these qtl
mapped so how do we look into
colocalization methods when we have to
apply it to pqtl or other qtls and the
other question is how do we even think
about these priors when we look into
these other kind of
data this this is something I I really
like thinking about and something about
which I have a lot of opinions that I'll
try to keep relatively brief but yes
basically any association that kind of
has the form of a gws or eqtl mapping
you can use colocalization with we tend
to do it a lot with
eqtls because we have relatively
abundant eqtl data compared to a lot of
molecular other molecular qtls and we
tend to not only have relatively
abundant data but we have it across a
fairly large number of tissues Which is
less likely to be the case with things
like
pqtls but people have done Co
localization analyses using
pqtls uh and it's hard to
compare the power there because one they
tend to be done in blood which is also
the eqtl tissue where we tend to have
the highest power uh and it tends not to
be on the same scale but there are
definitely
pqtls that colocalize with gwas hits
that no eqtl colocalizes with
somewhat more surprisingly there are
gwas hits that colocalize with an eqtl
and there's no pqtl that I'm not sure if
that makes as much conceptual sense so
it might just be something like power uh
or the fact that you can actually have
eqtls that are shared across tissues
even if the
pqtl uh that's associated is not shared
and then again you can do it with pretty
much any molecular qtl uh there was a a
paper fairly recently that did them with
chromatin accessibility qtls and that
actually had much much higher power than
we've been seeing with
eqtls uh and I asked rayun who wrote
that paper why he thought that was and
he he
said it probably has to do with the fact
that it's easier to measure chromatin
accessibility qtls it's a bit more of a
a binary measurement as opposed to the
the Contin
distribution of gene expression and it's
a measurement that or an observation
that might be more consistent across
cell types tissue types Etc so even if
there is say a very cell type specific
eqtl we might be able to detect
something like chromatin accessibility
utl so there is a trade-off between a
few of these different things right
between how accessible and how
well-powered the data are uh between how
good we are at measuring the data and
also just how relevant the data
are you're
welcome I was curious have you looked at
how many of the
eqtls had localized what GW was because
you said the other way around like
there's 20% of all gwas Loa or a little
bit more than that that had a eqtl that
Co localized but have you look at the
other way around like have all the eql
signals being claimed by any
yeah I I don't have a number I think
generally it's it's lower um because you
know you can
imagine
that there are many traits for which the
expression of most genes doesn't matter
at all even if a large portion of say
height is explained by the expression of
genes it won't rely on the expression of
every chain uh so it's possible that if
we did really get a fully
comprehensive list of human gws traits
we'd start finding associations with the
expression of nearly every Gene but even
then we wouldn't find associations with
every eqtl because in fact we
have observed eqtls for almost every
Gene in the gex project and so in most
of these situations where we have uh a
gws hit that we would expect to
colocalize with a nearby Gene say I've
been using LDL as an example a lot
there's a gws hit near ldlr the LDL
receptor Gene uh ldlr has an
eqtl you really might expect that that
eqtl explains the Goos association with
ldlr uh and it doesn't there might be
some ldlr eql that we haven't found yet
that does but that's specific eqtl seems
not to be
explanatory okay so I think I can get
through the rest of this and
probably under five minutes actually and
and then we can head over to the other
talk uh but these are just some
resources because in a lot of cases a
lot of these analyses have been run so
if you want to ask you know some
specific question you might have to do
it yourself but if you're just looking
for genes whose expression is associated
with the trait you're actually unlikely
to have to do the analysis yourself so a
large toos resource is toos Hub which
has uh hundreds of
traits and then models for the
expression of almost every Gene so you
can look for a trait or you can search
by a
gene uh and it'll tell you what the
associations are and you can see that
you know in for this significant LDL gas
Locus there are actually a lot of genes
that are reported together because uh
likely due to their correlated
expression it's difficult to distinguish
which gene or which genes is ultimately
responsible for
colocalization one of the most common
methods is Colo and it's also I think
one of the easier ones to use because
it's an r package so a lot of people are
already going to be comfortable with the
environment uh you can this is I I think
the the upto-date version some of these
methods have actually been converging a
bit and so now at this point collo and
fast and lo are very
similar but I have run this it is fairly
easy to run then fast and lo which is
what I tend to use is perhaps a little
trickier it's a command line tool but
one benefit is that they actually just
do have the eqtl side of it done if you
want to work with the gex data they've
already done the fine mapping uh and
that can go into estimating the
enrichment for the priors and that can
then go into the co- localization itself
true to the name it is pretty fast so
what you have to provide are just the F
mapped gws statistics and it's still
relatively straightforward to run there
also a variety of resources for
displaying potentially colocalizing
Loi uh so this is Locust plot this is
one packaged uh our package that can be
used you can tell really in my earlier
plots I just took the right side of
these uh meanwhile the left side is also
uh basically showing a QQ plot for the P
values of both both lowai and you can
see in our our positive control Locus
that the P values tend to be relatively
correlated which is
encouraging and then uh there's also eqt
plot uh which I tend to really like it
has a lot of information conveyed on it
which can make it a little harder to
read quickly but it manages to show you
the effect sizes the associations of
both both traits all in one plot and
both of these are are pretty easy to use
they're both our packages as well so I'd
like to acknowledge my postdoc mentors
as well as Shamil SV in whose lab I I
learned most of the things I've talked
about today as well as the mpg primer
series that's it that was great um I'll
start us off with a anonymous question
online they say eqtl studies tend to
have much smaller samp sizes than gws
studies this may lead to poorly
estimated LD and not so great fine
mapping in the eqtl data even before
attempting the
colocalization so are there any good
ways to improve your power for example
with the reference population LD or a
minimum study size for the eqtl that you
would
recommend yeah and I think that's that's
getting it a what I think is a pretty
important point which is that I think
typically we're
the jwas Losi we're pretty confident in
because we don't have to worry about
context we don't wor have to worry about
developmental timing we just measure
something about an individual and look
at their genome uh I don't have a
specific cut off for the power of an
eqtl study one thing to consider is that
even
though uh eqtl studies tend to have much
lower sample sizes eqtls often have much
larger effect sizes than gws low
you can have an eqtl that's changing the
expression of a gene by double digit
percent which you're unlikely to find uh
for for an association in say an LDL gws
so it also does depend on what eqtls
you're looking at uh as for the the fine
mapping that can be tricky depending on
whether you're working with summary
statistics or the actual genomes you
might want you might be forced to use uh
a reference population
LD uh but if you have the genomes you're
probably going to want to use the ins
sample LD because even if it is a
smaller set it is the set of individuals
you're working
with I'm gonna keep asking questions um
to follow up on the population LD a lot
of these large GW Ed multi-population
meta analyses and a lot of eqtls include
samples from all different ancestries
and population
so if you're stuck with summary
statistics how do you accurate how do
you best find the best reference LD
panel and how important is
that yeah I'm not sure how you would
find the
best uh LD reference now most of these
methods have simulations on how much of
undetected structure you can have in
your gws or eql population and still
work and in fact there
are uh applications of these methods in
agriculture where we can actually see
that in the very stratified distribution
of
breeds uh you actually still have pretty
high power
so even though I tend to think that
perhaps the papers are really optimistic
about how well they can handle
population structure it's actually not
uh a lost
cause uh and if you can basically get a
reference that allows fine mapping to
work well enough then you should be
pretty well positioned to use
colocalization was when you say 20 to 35
are you talking about line
mapped hits or just all GW Losi uh just
trying to think through yeah it does
depend how you measure it it's generally
people people are trying to report
independent uh gws hits so you you can
try to detect the independence through
fine mapping it should separate into
different clusters you know in theory
you could also use some kind of stepwise
approach to counting the number of Loi
but given that you're fine mapping
anyway I think most people are just
reporting the the number of 95 or 90%
credible sets in F among those only 20
to
35% williz is there any other hypothesis
out there for what biological mechanism
could be going on that yeah ISL pqtl oh
um it isn't an eqtl or pqtl are we are
we just missing it is it like the
missing heritability thing I we're gonna
get there we're gonna find the eqtl if
you ask me uh I think we are just
missing the correct eqtls that they are
more specific than the you know adult
bulk tissue postmortem samples that
we're typically working with have been
able to reveal uh and that as we refine
methods as we look in more specific cell
types across development Etc we're going
to increase the number of
colocalizations in fact I think we're
already seeing that in a lot of cases
it's largely a power game I guess could
you kind of refine your analysis say the
most you know with your Pips the highest
with the best eqtls we're you know we're
getting that number much higher like if
you stratify those gws hits you know
kind of according to levels of evidence
like you said in terms of we like these
eqtls it's a well-powered the right cell
type issue type and then we've got you
know strong fine mapping among that
subset that we're capturing most of it
among the rest is what I'm just trying
to kind of gauge the sense that you know
instead of a binary you know this is
what we're getting are we doing a lot
better at our most obvious or at least
well kind of characterized Lo yeah and
it's true typically you know the higher
end of these
estimates uh come from say blood eqtls
and relevant traits there just because
that's power is the highest um part of
the issue though seems to not simply be
that we're struggling to find map eqtls
or that we have the eqtls we're finding
have really weak
power it seems to be that we're finding
the wrong
eqtls
so it it may it's probably a power or a
context thing at least in my opinion but
it's a power or context thing that's
actually causing us to look in the wrong
place rather than just adding some noise
to the data