so now is the time for lightning talks
all right so Bowen
first okay so uh good morning everyone
I'm Bowen I'm a PhD student in computer
science here at MIT and in this work we
explore the idea of learning a j of
model of molecular Dynamics trajectories
to further expand the value that can be
extracted from simulation data sets so
the main idea is here at the top left
molecular Dynamics or MD is a very
common technique used for studying
various molecular phenomenon and it
gives us the trajectories which are time
series of molecular confirmations now
these uh these confirmations are
generated sequentially by integrating
the equations of motion in this work we
explore the idea of learning a surrogate
model of MD trajectories um by learning
a a joint generative model over the
confirmation at each time step so
inspired by generative models of videos
for example that can create a one minute
video from scratch um we train a model
to go from a uh a trajectory of Pure
Noise and progressively remove this
noise um to give us a trajectory now you
may ask why do you want to do this joint
modeling we know that the underlying
equations of motion are Marian there
should be no need to learn a joint
generative model like I described now
typically people learn surrogate models
of MD to accelerate the simulation or
the sampling in our case however we
argue that it is interesting to learn
this joint generative model because of
the new capabilities The Wider range of
capabilities that it unlocks by uh
controlling how you condition the model
so for example if you condition the
model by providing just the first frame
and ask to fill in the rest then you get
a standard forward simulator if you
however provide the first and the last
frame the model will try to give you a
sequence of confirmational states that
Bridges these two frames that is a
transition path if you provide say for
example every 10 or 100 or 1,000 frames
um the model will try to upsample your
trajectory to perhaps resolve faster
motions that you missed when saving your
md trajectory at two course of a time
interval and most ambitiously if you
mask out part of the molecule and
describe what the rest of the mo should
be doing then the model will try to impt
or design the system to accommodate or
induce those motions now I want to be
clear that we are far from being able to
do what I've just described for large
molecular systems like proteins uh for
one thing the data to train such a model
doesn't exist right there's no YouTube
of MD simulations that we can train on
uh but what we have done is provided a
proof of concept based on training such
a model for tetrapeptide systems so very
small peptides of four amino acids we've
created an extensive data set of Tet
peptide simulations train a model on
those uh on a subset of those
simulations and Sample trajectories for
uh unseen peptides and we've validated
that our model can accomplish to varying
degrees each of the tasks that I've just
described so here at the on the right
hand side on the top left we see that
our model when used as a forward
simulator can provide uh quite
reasonable and accurate free energy
Landscapes of unseen peptides and this
can be seen by comparing the MD free
energy Landscapes on the left and then
our models free energy land Landscapes
on the right our model can also resolve
to some extent the kinetics of the
system um by looking at the recovery of
the relaxation time of different
torsional Collective
variables uh in the middle here we have
an example of an interpolation path
between two macro States uh on the free
energy landscape of a particular
tetrapeptide uh we do have some more
quantitative assessments of this uh but
the explanation of those is a bit too
convoluted to put on one
slide uh and then on the bottom right
here we see that our model one used as
an upsampling model uh is able to
recover the autocorrelation function uh
of various Toral Collective variables
some of which have rather non-trivial
Behavior at these short time
scales as for the uh imp paintingdesign
uh we do have some results uh very
preliminary results there uh but not
quite exciting enough to put on a
highlight slide uh so in summary what we
want to do in this work is just to
introduce this idea and the promise of
this kind of framing of generative
modeling to the community um but also
motivate the development of
architectures that can accomplish kind
of modeling for larger systems such as
proteins and perhaps most uh importantly
help motivate the curation of such data
sets now one important caveat is that as
with any kind of generative modeling
there is the risk of
hallucinations however unlike people who
work on generative modeling in natural
language image or video we do actually
have access to the ground Truth uh
physical model of these systems in so
far as you trust the force field that
generated the simulations so one very
interesting line of work uh will be to
see how we can detect and steer away
from hallucinations by judiciously using
uh these physical stimulators in the
generative process uh so with that I I
thank you and happy to chat more at the
poster session