good morning everybody Welcome to the
mpg primer series um today we have the
pleasure of having R speaking Jordan is
a fifth year PhD student in Alex Price
research group in the department of
epidemiology at Harvard School of Public
Health Jordan's current research focuses
on methods development for caal variant
identification using
multi- before his PhD Jordan was an
associate computational biologist with a
data science group here at the Bro
Institute um with that he's talking
about population structure and AD
mixture today do we have some slides
up thank you oh um feel free to raise
your hand and ask questions throughout
the talk there's a microphone in the
middle and I could also bring you one if
you raise your hand so yeah I'm Jordan
uh and I used to be an associate
computational biologist here now would
come to this lecture and the other MPG
lecture pretty often and it kind of help
me like figure out what I want to do for
my PhD so it's uh exciting to come back
and give back um and today we'll be
talking about uh population structure
and AD
mixture and so this is the outline for
the presentation um we're probably not
going to get through it all like we'll
probably just get through the population
structure part and like feel free to ask
questions because I'd much rather have
us get through a little bit of this
lecture and uh have us all actually
understand what's going on and uh get
through all the floods first we'll talk
about population structure uh some
background and then go through three
different approaches towards inferring
population structure um and then if we
have time we'll get to population ad
mixture talk about an interesting
phenomenon that is caused by ad mixture
um and then talk about how to infer
local
ancestry and so without further Ado uh
population structure you can find it in
different ways uh but it can refer to GE
genetic differences due to Geographic
ancestry another definition is
differences in alal frequencies or hype
frequencies among different groups or
populations within a species and then
population ad mixture an admix
population is a population with recent
ancestry from two or more uh continents
or groups that were uh previously
isolated so why study population ad
mixture um the first reason is that
helps us understand human migratory uh
patterns and ancient history uh the
second reason is to improve our power to
identify and localize disease genes and
understand mutations that cause disease
um I won't really talk about gwos
because that's the subject of the primer
for next week but understanding
population structure and kind of
handling it appropriately is a
prerequisite for doing effective
Vios um okay so one of the definitions
for population to structure talked about
alal frequencies and so to kind of
understand what's going on here we
should just start with this object
that's called a genotype Matrix uh each
row of the genotype Matrix contains data
for an individual uh that we have
mutation calls for then each column of
the genotype Matrix corresponds to a
specific mutation that might occur in
each person person's genome one zero one
or two times and so this first entry
zero uh in the one one that has a zero
here uh that's saying that individual
one has zero copies of mutation one and
then if we go down one we can see that
individual two has two copies of
mutation one um and so we're going to
see a lot of this genotype Matrix today
but if we look at this we might start to
notice something and and it's that some
of the rows are colored red and some of
the rows are colored blue uh but really
what we're supposed to see is that like
the red rows tend to have a similar
pattern of genotypes and the blue rows
tend to have a similar pattern of
genotypes and so just going into a
little bit more detail we can see that
in the first two columns uh the red rows
tend to have zeros and maybe a couple
ones in the first two columns and the
blue rows tend to have twos and maybe a
couple of ones in the first two columns
this corresponds to us saying that
mutations one and two are pretty common
in the blue rows and mutations one and
two are pretty rare in the red rows then
it switches at mutation three um and so
now red has high Valu blue has values
and so if we want we can now just
directly compute simal frequencies um
and so to do that uh we can group all
the red individuals and then uh sum the
number of mut times we observe each
mutation and then divide it by the
number of chromosomes and so that's two
times the number of people so here we're
going to sum up this column we get one
and then we divide it by eight because
there's four times two people or
chromosomes and so that's how we get
this alal frequency and that just tells
us how common a mutation is in a
population um
and so what we can see here is that we
have these patterns where all the red
people seem similar all the blue people
seem similar one potential explanation
for this is that uh these two groups of
people have ancest have distinct
ancestries or uh have descendants that
from distinct continents and that's one
thing that could cause this pattern Neal
frequencies and this is exactly what
we're talking about when we talk about
population
structure and so to take uh make things
just kind of more concrete you can look
at a very specific mutation RS 10913
before then look at three populations
that have been sequenced in this uh hmap
project so we have Northern Europeans
from Utah uh uin individuals from
Nigeria and Han Chinese individuals from
Beijing we can see that this mutation
has different frequencies in these three
populations there's nothing particularly
interesting about this mutation but it's
like an example of how we might have
different alal frequencies but if
instead of looking at just one mutation
uh we choose to look across the genome
we can look at these three different
populations and kind of quantify the
degree of uh genc Divergence between
these three three populations and that's
what's happening um in this FST metric
where uh High values mean that two
populations have diverged uh have lots
of Divergence genetically low values
mean that there's very little Divergence
so we can do this and kind of do this
pairwise analysis across these three
populations but uh so if we want we can
pick any two populations and say what is
the genetic Divergence between these two
populations maybe that's interesting or
not but it's important to understand
that uh kind of the variation the
genetic variation that exists between
populations is much smaller than genetic
variation that exists within populations
and so Rosenberg at all 2002 science
takes a crack at estimating these
quantities and they say that 5 to s% of
worldwide human genetic variation is due
to genetic differences between
populations the remaining 93 to 95% of
human genetic variation due to genetic
variation within
populations um and so given that uh
maybe these population labels are are
unable to explain most of the genetic
Vari
why consider this at all and so in
genetic analyses individuals are often
classified based on their Continental
genetic ancestry this is this warer to
the continents or subcontinent from
which individuals distant ancestors have
historically resided and so this is
really based on oops
um where your genome has come from uh
and it's distinct from self-identified
race or ethnicity um and so however this
approach of kind of classifying
individuals based on their Continental
genetic ancestry glosses over lots of
within continent genetic heterogeneity
but it does capture some extremely
important historical migratory patterns
so this model like obviously loses lots
of detail and isn't objectively correct
but it captures some may still be useful
um and there exist alternative
approaches that allow us to understand
genetic structure on a much finer
scale and those are really important um
but to continue let's just look at an
example of kind of one approach towards
classifying or anal izing population
structure uh this is the output from a
modelbased clustering program such as uh
structure and so the way that we should
interpret this plot is that uh each
super skinny colored bar corresponds to
a single individual um and
uh I can't use this to move can I okay
um each super skinny uh colored bar
corresponds to a single individual and
then the colors of that of that bar
correspond to the ancestry contribution
from different groups so uh for example
in the European individuals we can see
that there's lots of blue that
corresponds to European ancestry however
we can see that in some group in the
middle uh there's a lot of sizable
proportion amount of orange contribution
so that corresponds to their these
individuals having a sizable uh amount
of uh African genetic ancestry in
addition to their European genetic
ancestry
[Music]
um
yeah and so I mean this is like a very
coarse grain approach where we've kind
of just said let's just Suppose there
are six ancestry groups in this
population that we're analyzing however
if we want we can be much more granular
about things so this is from a recent
bioarchive preprint who at all 2023 um
and in this paper they instead of uh
just classifying individuals based on
their Continental genetic ancestry they
take the UK biobank resource and try to
classify the individuals uh based on
much smaller regions they divide the UK
and Ireland into 23 different regions um
and then in each region they uh classify
the individuals or they they uh estimate
the genetic ancestry using these these
very small regions in addition to some
other Global regions and so we can see
here this plot is basically just all the
individuals that are from Cumbria and so
we can see kind of which color each
region is we have to match the color
from the region from the map to the
color in uh our ad mixture plot but here
we can see there's a lot of individuals
that have primarily auman ancestors
however there's a sizable portion of
individuals that have primarily
Northumberland ancestry which makes a
lot of sense because Northland is right
next to kumria and we can tell like a
similar story about North Yorkshire um
and so like that's that's pretty cool
but the point of this slide is just to
show that we don't have to use uh these
super large Continental ancestry groups
to understand our ancestry we can be
much more granular about things um so
that's kind of the background for
population structure uh feel free to ask
any kind of broad questions about our
understanding of it but if there aren't
any of those we're going to go into the
inference so we're going to talk about
three different approaches for uh
inferring population structure and uh so
we'll start with these tree based
approaches these are some of the
earliest approaches and
um they're kind of well we'll see
they're simpler than the other ones and
so what we see here is this is a big
tree um and all the leaf nodes at the
very end of the tree the the periphery
of the tree correspond to individuals
that we uh have genotyped and are
analyzing um and then we can interpret
this tree roughly as a a tree Will Group
individuals that have similar genetic
ancestry or or look similar genetically
um and we can roughly think of the
distance of the path between two leaves
of this tree so if I go up and then back
down we can think of the length of that
path as some approximation of uh the
genetic similarity or distance between
two individuals um and so now we'll talk
a bit about exactly how we get a tree
like this
so living in this certain region are
mixed have mixed ANW to
fromion does it mean we are referring to
a past where there was no mixture or was
there always a mixture and then they
start because it's looks like circular
the you say people from their areas but
when they all mix or when not mix yeah I
mean uh it's it's it's a very good point
kind of how you find
is of how far back we want to look or we
understand is like yeah these previously
isolated population so we get
some
uh information how make this fall based
on population that have been previously
isolated oh we think of European
individuals long
being uh
European so it's a tricky question to
answer um but and it requires some call
but it's kind
of it's true that if we go back far
enough all populations kind of have to
be ad mixed um but
these labels uh these kind of
Continental ancestry groups are still
useful for understanding population
structure because the populations have
been isolated for a long time as a
result there has been genetic Divergence
between them so taking that genetic
Divergence into account is important is
that is that that a decent answer yeah
thank you okay good cool
um cool so now we're back to our
genotype Matrix and so uh just to re re
interpret this again uh this one here
means that individual two has one copy
of mutation to um and so here we have
genotype Matrix for eight individuals
and 10 Snips just in our cartoon example
um and in order to turn this to turn
this genotype Matrix into uh some tree
structure that tells us about the
similarity between individuals uh the
first step is to compute differences
between genotypes and so kind of the
most straightforward approach to doing
this is to take one genotype subtract it
from the other genotype and then take
the absolute value of each of uh those
genotype terms so 0 minus one is
negative 1 and the absolute value of it
is one so we'll do that for every single
one of these columns then we'll sum up
the absolute difference and divide it by
the number of markers and so this just
tells us a kind of crude metric of
exactly how similar do these genotypes
look uh and then we'll do this for every
pair of individuals and so we'll end up
with like because they're eight
individuals in our data set we'll have
like an 8 by8 distance Matrix um and
then from here we just apply some
hierarchical clustering algorithm uh and
kind of like a hand wavy way the way to
think about these algorithms are uh
either we we start with all of our eight
individuals in one big cluster and then
we split it into two clusters and then
we the way that we decide that
partitioning of the individuals into two
clusters is we try to uh minimize some
like something like the sum of the
distance between individuals in the two
clusters so we kind of have two groups
that looks similar to each other then
we'll continue to divide those two
clusters until everybody has their own
cluster or alternatively we'll start
with uh everybody in their own cluster
then we'll kind of merge these clusters
based on the distances to each other um
and so I'm I'm kind of not doing a great
job like explaining this component of
the inference in detail but I'm doing
that because I think the rest of the
inference methods are more interesting
and so uh but it's it's uh definitely
like if you're interested in this read
more into it it's cool um but so now if
we do that for a larger data set than
our eight individuals we might end up
with the tree uh diagram like this and
so um in order to kind of let's look at
this tree diagram for a second we can
see here um it's kind of hard to see
here but uh the oh maybe I should go
back so like in this picture we can see
uh the legend for this figure uh tells
us kind of what geographic region these
individuals were sampled from and then
they code it based on the shape of these
uh nodes so we can see here that mostly
we have circles together over here and
mostly we have squares or diamonds
together over here that corresponds to
individuals that were sampled from the J
same geographic region having similar
genetic ancestries to each other um so
that's what we see here but there's a
few other interesting observations that
we can take from this tree structure uh
the first is that as I mentioned before
we can think of the distance of or the
length of the path between two
individuals as being an approximation of
the distance between those individuals
and so we can see here is that the
distance uh of the length of the path
between two individuals from the same
population is similar to uh is only a
little bit smaller than the length of
the path between to individuals from
different ancestries or different
populations and that's kind of
Illustrated in the cartoon and the right
like the distance between uh a to a is
only a little bit smaller than the
distance we from A to B this is kind of
consistent with that slide earlier where
I was claiming that uh Continental or
population labels are unable to explain
most of the human genetic variation um
feel there's one other thing that I
wanted to say about this
figure um oh and one other thing just to
notice is that we aren't able like the
output of this uh inference method
doesn't give us a number of like uh what
is the percent ancestry from this group
for this individual uh and so we can
kind of see it and kind of understand
what's going on in the data but uh
having an explicit estimate of this
quantity which is uh what portion of
your genome comes from a given ancestry
group will be really helpful in some
applications and we don't get it from
this type of method um so uh with that
motivation we can move on to uh a group
of methods which we'll refer to as
model-based population structure
inference and so uh one good thing about
these methods is that they will give us
that number of what portion of an
individual's ancestry came from a given
group um and so so this kind of group of
methods is a little bit uh the I think
the name is kind of deceptive because
like a lot of these approaches assume
some kind of model but here the model
what we mean by modelbased clustering or
uh population structure inference is
that uh we're going to propose an
explicit generative model for our
genetic data that's kind of based on our
understanding of genetics um and then
use that genetic model to do our
inference and so here uh let's just get
ourselves familiar with the uh data
objects that we're going to be working
with so G is our genotype Matrix and uh
that's the same object that we've
already interpreted a couple times g l
is the number of mutations of number of
times mutation L occurs in individual I
and then we have these other two objects
uh there's this P Matrix and so the
dimension of p is uh the number of
populations that we have contributing to
our individuals in G uh by the number of
snips and so each individual and or each
entry in L tells us how common snip uh L
is in population k sorry I think I said
something wrong there uh each entry in P
is uh tells us about how often mutation
L occurs in population k um and this is
just what we were Computing on that
first slide where we had the blue and
the red individuals um and then we have
this Q object and so uh the the the Q
object we can think of as our ancestry
proportion Matrix um and so each entry
in Q tells us what the proportion of
ancestry uh K is an individual I so uh
if this if if if
q11 is one then we're saying that
individual ones ancestry is all from
population one um and so for now just to
make things simple we're going to assume
that Q is binary and that each row has a
single one and uh all the rest of them
are zeros and so this corresponds the
assumption that all of our individuals
have ancestry from uh one group each so
there's no ad mixture this isn't a good
assumption uh but we'll relax it in a
second um and so just to really drive
home exactly what Q is this is like a a
sample 23 and me report and for Jamie it
says that they have 74% European
ancestry 17.5% subsaharan African
ancestry and so these are example values
that might go in Q like Jamie would just
be one row across this way and they
would it be four numbers in here um
except it wouldn't fit our current
structure because uh Q has only one one
right now and all the rest are zeros um
okay so now we're going to talk about
our infant strategy kind of at a very
high level uh this is kind of this is a
an outline for how to do uh comput a
maximum likelihood estimator which is
kind of a general statistical thing
you'll probably run into
um but the first step in doing this
inference is going to be propos a
generative model that relates our
observed data oh I I forgot to say
something um here there's a dash line in
the middle uh and so we're asking
ourselves what's up with this dashed
line and so the things on the left of
the dashed line are the object is the
data that we're assuming that we've
observed and have access to so we can
like load G and P directly into memory
in our computer and mess around with
them but Q is uh uh what we want to find
out this is our unobserved variable that
we want to under that we want to do
inference on um and so the first step in
our inference strategy is to propose a
generative model that relates our
observed data to are object of in
inference and so in words this is going
to be relate our genotype and alal
frequencies to uh the unobserved
ancestry proportions that we want to
infer um the Second Step will be to use
the generative model to write out the
probability of The observed data given
the unobserved data and so this is going
to be we're going to write out the
probability
of our observed genotypes given uh the
ancestry uh the ancestry proportion
Matrix q and then finally uh we're going
to find the values of q that maximize
the probability of our observed data and
those will be our favorite values of Q
so this is very not specific and we'll
go into this in in more detail so the
first step is to propose a generative
model that relates our genetic uh or
observed data to the unobserved data and
so here our generative model is going to
be that uh the genotype for individual I
at mutation L given that they're in
ancestry K is binomially distributed
with parameters p k l and 2 and so to
make that kind of less mathy uh we can
say that if individual I uh we're trying
to say what is the distribution of
mutations for an individual that is in
ancestry K we're basically going to flip
coin twice uh and then we'll take the
sum of the number of times that that
coin comes comes up heads and the coin
comes up heads
uh with a probability equal to the alal
frequency and so kind of intuitively
each individual has two chromosomes uh
if I tell you that both of those
chromosomes come from a given ancestry
then we would expect those chromosomes
to have a given mutation based on the
alal frequency of that uh mutation in
that population and so hopefully this
this first statement is is kind of clear
now um so the second step is going to be
write out the probability of our
observed data for individual eye so here
this equates to uh writing out the
probability of an individual ey's
genotype given that they're from
population or that they have ancestry K
and so here this GI corresponds to one
row of that genotype Matrix and we can
write out the full probability for GI as
the product of each of the probability
of the individual mutations and so we're
making some assumption here saying that
the mutations are like independently
distributed uh but we're not going to
worry about that for now but basically
yeah let's just go back to this so we're
looking at the probability of one row of
this G Matrix and we're going to say
what's the probability of GI i1 and
multiply it by probability of gi2 do
this for the entire row of this Matrix
this gives us the probability of
individual's observed genotype so now
we'll notice that g l given Qi K is
equal to one that's exactly what we have
up here and so uh uh we can just go to
Wikipedia and look up what is the
probability for a binomial distribution
like what's the equation for the
probability of a given outcome from a
binomial distribution and just plug that
in for p of G given Qi K is equal to one
and so that's exactly what we've done to
get to this next line is we've just
replaced this pgil with the Wikipedia
probabilities uh for a binomial
distribution so now the third step is we
just have to ask ourselves uh is this
quantity maximized when we have
individual coming from ancestry one or
ancestry 2 or ancestry 3 um and so now
we'll just go into a workout example of
this we're doing we're assuming that we
have two populations we're going to try
to figure out whether this individual
has ancestry from population one or
population two and so the end of the
first row of equations is just that
exact
um equation from the last slide and then
we just plugged in the numbers and so
like
G11 is this individual's genotype at
snip one P1 L is the population one a
Leo frequency at snip one um and that
those are all the things we have to plug
in here and so we'll just do that for
each snip and then we end up with some
uh equation which we can evaluate
numerically and we get
022 so that's the probability that
individual one's genotype would occur if
they're in population one and then we'll
do the exact same thing for population
two so now we're just plugging in these
alal frequencies from population two
instead of the IL frequencies from
population
one and uh then we just just compute
what that number actually is we get
068 and so uh we have these two numbers
and we can see that the probability of
indiv individual ones genotype is higher
if they're in population two and so our
estimate is that this individual is
probably from population to um okay so
this approach assumes that each
individual belongs to a single ancestry
we just compared the individual the
probability of individual ones genotype
if they're in population one the
if they're in population two however we
know that admx populations uh exist and
and have genetic ancestry from
populations that were previously
isolated so can we change our generative
model to uh no longer have this
assumption that individuals belong to a
single ancestry group and so here we
have the exact same data objects as
before G and P are on the Le hand side
indicating that these are observed
objects Q is on the right hand side but
now we're goingon to assume that each
row of Q has values between zero and one
that sum to one uh I guess there's an
extra this whatever um
and but so it's the same as I mean now
it's now we're actually in a case where
we can give Jam's 23m report where here
now we have contributions from multiple
different ancestry groups um and
so in our inference kind of at a high
level strategy is going to be exactly
the same Ros Model A generative model
that relates our observe data to the
object of inference use the generative
model to write the probability of the
probability of The observed data and
then to find the values of q that
maximize the probability of The observed
data and so first let's just I mean the
hard part of this is just going to be
kind of Transforming Our generative
model so before we assumed uh this
distribution for the genotypes of
individual L at mutation or individual I
mutation L um but then here this assumes
just that q i k is equal to one which is
saying individuals I only has the K
ancestry group uh but this doesn't isn't
going to work anymore so intuitively if
individual I has 25% ancestry 1 and 75%
ancestry two then you expect their
genotype to look like a weighted average
of the Leal frequencies from ancestries
1 and two with weights 25 for ancestry 1
and 75 for ancestry 2 so the weighted
average of the Le frequencies at snip L
is just going to be this thing so we've
taken this is the the Leal frequency at
snip L 25% of that and then this is the
Leal frequency at uh in population two
75% of that and so we just have to take
this number and plug it in for our our
old ilal frequen that's exactly what
we've done here so here we've just taken
the old binomial distribution that we're
using before changed the first parameter
to reflect individuals like indiv
individual eyes personal weighted alal
frequency based on their ancestry
proportions so now our strategy is going
to be basically the same all we have to
do is now uh change our generative model
up here that now has individual eyes
personal alal frequency based on their
uh weighted uh ancestry
proportions and then we're basically
going to do the exact same procedure
down here de like like right individual
eyes uh the probability of individual
eyes genotype as the product of all the
mutations and then we'll just plug in
our our Wikipedia binomial uh
probability equation down here um and so
here this Alpha parameter is what we're
doing what we're using to quantify the
proportion of individual eyes ancestry
from population one and then one minus
Alpha would just be uh the proportion of
individual eyes ancestry from population
to and then we just have to figure out
exactly what value of alpha maximizes
this equation for each individual and so
here uh we have a worked out example
um I've yeah here so we're just going to
figure out exactly we we we can uh plug
in our values for individual eyes
genotype and the different minor or the
different alal frequencies into that
equation from before and now we have uh
an and the only variable here is Alpha
and so this is just going to be the the
probability of individual eyes genotype
at different ad mixture proportions and
we can just graph this out and so here
this is the uh numerical value for that
last equation where we vary Alpha across
many values and we can see that
uh individual eyes genotype is uh much
higher sorry uh we maximize this
quantity when Alpha is equal to 0 22
which corresponds to individual
individual I having 22% ancestry from
population
one and so now
um up until now we've assumed that we
have access to some a Leo frequency
panel where we know the Leo frequency
for each individual or sorry we know the
Leal frequency for each mutation in each
population um that's this P Matrix
however um and so this is like there are
many resources that we can use to get
this alal frequency reference panel um
however there's maybe maybe that's not
so good if we don't really know exactly
what populations are contributing to
each individual um in our uh like maybe
there's some population that isn't
included in our reference panel that has
contributed ancestry to our genotype
Matrix G um and so now we're going to
try to do this exact same inference
problem but move p over to the right
hand side of the dash line and so that
means that now instead of assuming that
we have access to some alal frequency
reference panel um we're going to assume
we're going to infer our Alo frequencies
from the dat
um and so now our inference approach is
a little bit more complicated um because
we have to infer both Q the ancestry
proportions and P the alal frequencies
of each ancestry
um and so at a really high level our
approach is going to be just alternate
between estimating the alal frequency
Matrix assuming that we have the
ancestry proportions and then uh go on
to estimating the ancestry proportions
uh given that we have the Le frequency
Matrix and so this is uh similar to an
approach used by software uh such as
structure and AD mixture but it's it's a
simplified version of this but it kind
of gives you the intuition behind what's
going on um and so to do this approach
we're first going to take in each value
of Q basically just randomly assign
ancestry proportions so say individual
one is in is in population one
individual two is in population three
randomly assigned q and then we'll use
that randomly assigned Q to estimate a
frequencies um given our current
estimates of the ancestry proportions
and then proceed to estimating uh
individual ancestry proportions based on
the current estimates of ilal
frequencies uh and so like this P update
P given QEP is just taking the means of
all of the uh ancestry of the genotype
Matrix what's
up
yes thank you
um do you have to provide this approach
with the number of populations that you
think yeah okay that's and they're SL on
it in a second
oh
um yeah I mean here in all of these
mates you can
see one how that's a tricky question um
okay so here um we just take turns
estimating the frequencies given the
ancestry proportions then estim ancestry
proportions given the legal frequencies
this updating legal frequencies just
taking means of our genotype Matrix uh
and then
updating an portions even our new
frequencies is exactly the procedure
that we went over like three slides ago
so we're going to do like this thing a
bunch of times until we reach some
stable solution um and it's kind of
wacking that we can like find the true
anti just starting from random
assignments because like initially this
frequency Matrix isn't telling us very
much but it works out which is cool um
so yeah as as you just asked uh do we
have to provide this method with the
overall number and S population and the
answer yes um so here we run this
algorith on a big dat varing number of
populations and uh you can see that when
we set the number po
the method basically spits out ancestry
proportion that correspond to like
African like European ancestry vers
Asian plus American Oceanic an that's
kind of the main division that we get
from but then as we increase K all the
way you start to get much more granular
an definition and like you get the
smaller group of individual uh that have
their own kind of
end uh category and so it's not at all
obvious which of these answers is
actually right and that's a major
disadvantage of this kind of method so
maybe we have some ground truth about
how many intersections we expect to use
to see the data this will be good but
It's Tricky it's not obvious what the
cor K is here um so uh that's a good
motivation for moving on to PPA based
population
structure so uh phal component analysis
uh is a very general data analysis
technique you'll in all kinds of fields
kind just try to get intuition behind
what's going on we have a data set with
two features X1 and X2 um the first
principal component is going to be the
feature along which the data varies to
or we'll kind of try to consider all the
potential axes in our data and then find
the one that spread the the data out the
most along this active um so then on WE
computed component one proceed to
identify the a which explained uh the
max variation kind of taking into
account the first principal component
and so here I in this example with two
uh features it's kind of silly like
there only one compon but we can do this
with much larger uh dat here this is
what component analysis will look like
when we do it on gen we have I
individuals and L mut um and then
basically our first principal component
will try to capture as much of the
variation uh
in G is possible and so basically what
the first princial component will
capture corresponding to this well this
first Matrix uh going to be many
mutations that co- kind the maximal
combination of mutations that coar
together and if we think about it like
what group of mutations are veryy likely
to co together uh a reasonable guess is
something like because of individuals
have uh an from group one they're going
to have a bunch of special bu mutations
that aren't about high frequency in mut
in population two and similarly
individuals from population two have a
bunch mutations that aren't seen in
population one so we're going get lots
of shared mutations that are varing
together and uh that might be what you
expect and unfortunately it's exactly
what you and so this is uh PCA run on
one of the really early population um
SEC data sets called
um we have European Nigerian Chinese and
Japanese ancestry individuals and you
can see that when we do PCA on it pc1
captures primarily captures differen
between uh the African uh the Nigerian
and the non- Nigerian individuals and
then PC2 captur primarily captur between
the European and the non European
individuals IND kind of these uh
population structure uh maximally cap
lot of variation of the
Matrix um and so interestingly uhal
component analysis can also capture
continental adure and so here um in this
figure the authors have compated Native
American European AR data uh with
Hispanic genotype Hispanic Latino
individuals as well as africanamerican
individuals um and so what we can see
here is that uh many of these
populations kind of occupy these
distinct regions of this plot and also
see that like
uh but there's also lots of variation
Within These groups and so individuals
that identify as uh Dominican uh from
from being from the Dominican Republic
uh have kind of this unique ad mixture
profile so we can interpret the
intermediate values between these far
groups as uh these individuals having um
contributions from different continental
ancestries and uh so here it's probably
like it's important to say um a lot of
this ad mixture like for example in the
African-American individuals or between
the African and the European individuals
this reflects uh some Legacy of slavery
that
uh appears in our genetic data and so
it's probably good to not just treat
this uh with complete Detachment and
kind of acknowledge uh the historical
events that have led to this
um
so the next figure is uh
it's like everyone's favorite figure um
and so it's it's from November at all
2008 nature and what the authors do is
they take a bunch of different European
uh ancestry individuals and do PCA on it
and uh on the left they have PCA so this
is just uh basically the maximal axes of
variation in the genotype Matrix and if
you compare the figure on the left to a
real map of Europe on the right they
look kind of similar right so it's like
Portugal and Spain are like down here
like it is on a real map um you have
like Great Britain and SC Scotland up
here like in a real map and we go to the
East and like there's some France uh and
so like how crazy it's like we just have
the genotype Matrix and we remade a map
of where these individuals are from
based on it um so this like really uh
these last two examples have really
showing us some of the advantages of
principal component analysis where it's
like here we're able to like get
estimates for adure portions I guess we
could get that from the model based
framework too but here um we rather than
having like super distinct isolated
populations we have kind of alal
frequencies that vary with a gradient
over space and so it's like there's
probably small levels of migration a
long time ago between people that live
in France and Spain but not a lot and as
a result we kind of have these
continuous Clines of of of uh alal
frequency differences um and so PCA it
would be really hard to decide like what
are the correct populations or what's
the what's the right value of K to use
here uh but PCA uh makes it easier so
that we don't have to think about that
so much uh we're able to capture these
continu with differences in Le frequency
across Geographic
space um and so a pretty important
question oh there's a chat is this okay
um okay uh
so relevant question here is is
modelbased ancestry inference or PCA
better um and so uh model-based
inference approaches are motivated by
explicit genetic models uh with distinct
ancestry groups and as a result they
impose corresponding constraints so it's
like the uh the an C proportions are
guaranteed to sum to one they can't be
greater than zero or or or less than
zero or greater than one and the just
immediately spits out exact estimates
the quantities that we're interested in
so that's an advantage for model-based
inference approaches um and they also
allow us to impose like some prior
knowledge on the data like if we know
that there are three Source populations
we want to think about it that way we
can impose that understanding of the
data on our inference uh however PCA May
better capture situations where
population structures uh where structure
varies continuously if we don't want to
specify that number of populations then
we can we'll just compute a bunch of PCS
and kind of see like where they stop
capturing things that look like
population structure
um yeah so those are advantages of PCA
over mbased inference but really both
are useful uh and if you're doing this
kind of research you uh will find
instances where you want to use each of
them there's no these chats do I need to
worry cool no um so how much time do I
have left
that is a great question I think we are
it would be wonderful to have some Q&A
we're about four minutes before we have
to do the change over and we're kind of
at a natural stopping point definitely
um let me do one last like yes
oh there's like uh this slide um and so
this is GNA be my question to you great
um so I think if you want like this is
interesting and you want to learn more
about MPG like when I was a computation
biologist I didn't really know anything
about this and I got excited about it by
coming to these the first is you should
keep coming to the mpg primer and the
mpg seminar uh the next is that my pii
uh teaches this ep511 class at hsph in
the spring and he'll let you um probably
let you just uh audit it if you don't if
you can actually take a credit and I I
think it's an awesome class you go over
like lots of stuff like this in more
detail and he also shares his slides
online freely right yeah yeah and so
like a lot of the slides from his class
I stole for this and they're all free
online so you can go check those out and
like I use those as resource all the
time and then this book is uh pretty new
and like not actually finished but
there's like the first three chapters
from it and a lot of the slides I also
stole from that and this book is awesome
too so check sto with appropriate
credit but yeah uh are there any
questions about the subject matter for
presentation let's first give a a round
of applause for for Jordan
thanks Jordan that was such a good
primer um I was wondering do people like
combine PCA and model based so if you
say if you want to get the ancestry
proportions could you look at the
PCA like and identify how many KS you
want to specify and then put
that um five
that seem real and then sees that as k
um I know in some of the modelbased
clustering literature there is
discussion of how to choose K and it's
possible this is suggested as an
approach but I don't know if it is that
it's a cool idea I think it I like it
thanks
nice I've got a question um while other
people might want to come up to the mic
uh for the I had a question about the
Assumption about assuming Independence
between Snips for the generative models
and given that we know that assumption
is not true and um do these models still
perform well or when when do they
perform not as well yeah
so it's true that it's typically if we
just kind of use every snip in the
genome oftentimes Snips one and two will
be in linkage dise equilibrium which
means they co-occur or uh never co-occur
um and that violates our methodological
or our generative data assumption that
GI G G11 is independent from G2 g12 um
and so typically I think the advice is
to just prune your genotype data such
that you don't have adjacent Snips in LD
or or or close uh yeah yeah nearby Snips
in LD um but
I bet that kind of to what extent you do
that pruning how strict about it you are
um
and you can probably get away with not
being perfect about things and it'll
still come out mostly right because kind
of the dominating factors in uh your
genot type Matrix will be these ancestry
proportions not this kind of small
region of LD but it probably you
probably get better estimates if you
prune your Snips better and I think that
some of these methods also do relax this
assumption that there uh is Independence
between adjacent Snips uh but I'm
actually not that sure that about that
the approach might just be you have to
do some pruning based onage dis
equilibrium that sounds that sounds
great um we're almost at we basically
we're at time but we don't have to move
today the prime the seminar will be in
here so you guys can get your breakfast
um and then let's just thank Jordan one
more time for his wonderful primer