so I'm sitting between uh you and a very
exciting session with our uh startups uh
you're going to hear uh four exciting
startups uh present some their
Technologies and solutions that they've
been developing uh over the years uh but
before we do that I wanted to take some
time and uh talk about our Innovation
driven entrepreneurial ecosystem around
MIT and share with you a little bit how
it works and how we collaborate with uh
industry and others uh to to make this
work my name is Olivia Kad I'm a program
director at MIT uh in corporate
relations and um as you know MIT stands
as a hub for uh research and Innovation
and um it's only through Partnerships
that uh with industry and
entrepreneurial leaders like yourselves
that our Innovation ecosystem can create
meaningful impact and the word impact is
super important for us here at MIT you
see an aerial view
of the uh area of Cambridge we are
sitting in we are in Kendall Square so I
found out when I moved from uh Houston
to Boston that people at MIT get
offended when we say that MIT is in
Boston MIT is actually in Cambridge I
just want to point out uh right across
the Charles River from um from
Boston
um we we all know that Innovation often
happens where discipline disciplines uh
converge and disciplines meets and this
is very true in Kendall Square in what
you see around MIT and a few years ago
uh two of our faculties at the Salone
School of Management Professor Fiona
Murray and Dr Phil button uh did a study
to understand what makes that Innovation
ecosystem work and they identified five
key
stakeholders uh that are present around
Kendall Square uh that are extremely
close to one another and connect with
each other all the time back to what I
mentioned before about the collaboration
between all those stakeholders that's so
critical we have entrepreneurs up on top
these are probably the most critical
piece of the puzzle and you're going to
hear about four of them uh a little bit
later after my talk access to risk
Capital Liz touched on that this morning
what we do at MIT we do tough Tech we do
things that are uh Capital intensive
typically and so we do have we do need
access to risk capital and there's quite
a bit of it around in our ecosystem
corporate big companies and smaller
companies that are in our Innovation
sphere ecosystem they can be directly in
Cambridge in kenel square or connected
through the industrialism program uh
connected to that ecosystem government
plays a key role around MIT I'll share
with you some numbers in a minute but
more than 80% of our research um is
sponsored by uh uh the government and
then univ University or I would say even
universities because MIT collaborates
and you heard Kathleen talk about this
the work we do with community colleges
uh around and uh and more of these
initiatives so what's unique about
Kendall Square and the the ecosystem it
is in MIT is in is the proximity and the
density within that ecosystem of those
five key uh
stakeholders I want to share with you
some numbers and and a lot of you being
from industry these numbers will
resonate but MIT is a
nonprofit organizations organization
that's managed by a privately appointed
board of directors and we call that the
MIT Corporation if you look at MIT as a
look at it as a company our operating
budget every year or last year was $4.6
billion and it's quite a big number but
in that number what's more interesting
is how it split 46% of that budget is
dedicated to uh research sponsored
research 34% of that budget is dedicated
to uh teaching and instruction and right
there you see the two main drivers of
MIT that are part of the mission of Mi
is to teach and to do
research and I wanted to share with you
these numbers because when you look at
the two billion spent on R&D on research
on sponsored research it shows really
the power of the Institute the power of
MIT out of those two billion a big part
of it comes from uh activity on campus
about $800 million is spent on on campus
on sponsored research and we have about
1.2 billion spent in our MIT Lincoln lab
in Lexington that's a federally funded
research and development center ffrdc
that works for National Security so
typically DOD type of uh type of
activity historically MIT has been
involved in uh many discoveries and many
in Innovations if you look at the uh
picture on the bottom left part of the
screen you're going to see two
researchers working on development of
the radar technology during the second
world war this is really a time where
MIT pulled together about 4,000
researchers coming from all over the
world and all over the US from different
institutions and companies and they
developed the radar technology that
helped the Allies uh win the second
world war what you see on the uh bottom
right corner is the work that MIT did uh
during the Apollo Mission AP poo program
where MIT developed the guidance
navigation and control system this was
our our moonshop uh project and program
and uh still something that today is
very very difficult to do to navigate a
spacecraft uh uh hundreds and thousands
of miles away fast forward to today uh
we see sponsored we see research project
at MIT touching the Biotech Industry and
what you see the picture on the left
hand side up upper left corner is
Professor uh Bob Langer working with his
uh student then Bob Langer is at the uh
Foundation of uh
modna on the top right hand side you see
the work we do with plasma Fusion
commercial plasma fusion with a startup
company Commonwealth Fusion system that
came out of MIT came out of the plasma
science and fusion Center psfc Lab at
MIT raised
$1.8 billion dollar in series B 1.8
billion so when I talk about t Tech and
capital intensive industry that's a
great example of that and today is on
part to demonstrate commercial Fusion uh
in 2026 with um a plasma Fusion reactor
they're building in uh devans U an hour
away from campus so these are just some
illustrations of the history of MIT and
the the kind of um impact that we're
having uh today we love numbers at MIT
so I wanted to share with you a few
additional numbers we have over 177,000
employees a th000 professors and 12,000
students and an interesting
characteristics if you look at our
student body is 60% of them are at The
Graduate level 40% are undergrad so it
shows you also the the research capacity
that we have at MIT through our students
and oh by the way 91% of our undergrads
get involved in research projects that's
the the quality of students we um we
have at MIT there's a statistics we're
very proud of as well look at our
undergrad class our current class that
entered last August about a thousand um
people 49% women it's also an
illustration of the uh Testament of MIT
to push women in science and continue to
uh continue to do
that if we continue with a few uh
numbers um MIT launched back in 2013 an
initiative uh across a different schools
the five schools at the time um to
really enhance the uh institute's
culture of Innovation and
Entrepreneurship and at the time they
came up with an interesting definition
of innovation that's only one of the
many definitions you can you can think
of but we look at Innovation as a
process of taking ideas from inception
to impact what's interesting in that
definition the word technology is not
there and there's a reason for that
because we all understand that
Innovation goes well beyond technology
there's other components you need to
take into account and there's another
interesting aspect is when you when you
look at Innovation as a process you go
beyond the instant moment of invention
and you push towards the uh continuous
process sometimes highly nonlinear of
innovation and and this is this is a
definition that resonates well with our
researchers and scientists uh on campus
we have over 65 research Labs centers
and programs as I said we spent uh last
year about $800 uh million on sponsored
research 20% of that came from industry
and we have had uh 343 patents issued in
fiscal year 24 I realize this is only
one way of measuring the impact of MIT
what's a lot more um important for us is
the concept of technology transfer
that's really at the core of mit's
Mission to advance knowledge so Moving
Innovation from the from the lab into
the marketplace is really a driver that
you will see very strongly represented
within our researchers and faculty and
scientists at uh at MIT that's something
that really drives uh them and and also
is important for uh
students we we're very fortunate to um
have uh a very strong industrial yon
program at MIT this program was
established after the second world war
at a time where uh the United States uh
needed more collaboration between
universities and and uh in industry in
general and back in 1948 the industrial
Ison program was established lished
today we have uh over 200 member
companies a lot of them represented in
this uh in this room and our mission is
very simple in the ILP um we're here to
connect industry to MIT and how do we do
that we do that by enabling large
organizations strategically engage with
mit's Innovation ecosystem that I just
talked about it's a fairly complex
Innovation ecosystem um companies need
some guidance to make sure they tap into
the right lab the right researcher the
right faculty and this this is really
what we do in our
program um the uh through the ILP uh
program companies can do um quite a few
things uh at MIT one of the ways to
engage with us is to use the program to
develop uh your talents and your
employees and we just touched on that in
the previous panel session how important
it is to stay up to speed on different
Technologies like Ai and digital Etc so
using the ILP to have access to learning
Expeditions uh we do a lot of that for
companies access to our webinars
conferences like this one and others we
hold on campus uh this is something a
lot of Our member companies leverage and
use quite a bit the second piece is the
process of discovery and it's really
engaging with faculty and researchers on
campus talking about strategic problems
for your organization and and finding
Solutions together co-developing uh
Solutions together and then finally
networking that's what we're going to do
at lunch in a in in a few minutes uh
connecting with companies organizations
in the program but also connecting with
the more than 800 startups we have uh in
our startup exchange uh
program speaking of the MIT startup
exchange uh that program complements the
industrial isone program by connecting
companies with startups that our Prime
uh for collaboration this program was
created over N9 years ago um and
supports MIT connected startups in
growing expanding and solving the
world's greatest challenges and this is
what you're going to hear um in a few
minutes when we have those four startups
do doing their uh lightning
talks they they do that the startup
Exchange program does that through demo
days lightning talks at different
conferences the st25 program which is a
one-year program for uh handful uh of
startups that are selected and that
program really Fosters relationship
between industry and startups and and
these are sometimes difficult links to
establish these are almost two different
worlds that speak different languages
but the startup Exchange program really
brings those two together and that's uh
that creates meaningful impact and great
results so as you saw uh engaging with
MIT is isn't about accessing a single
resource or solving a single problem
it's really about becoming part of a
broader ecosystem that I just talked
about with the five key stakeholders
that I mentioned through programs that
the like the industrial isone program or
the startup Exchange program we aim aim
to contribute to those Partnerships by
offering early insights collaborative
opportunities and access to a community
of passionate and mission-driven
um researchers scientists and faculty to
solve tough problems and make an impact