So, good afternoon everyone. Hope you
had a an enjoyable lunch and some good
conversations. Um, so we got a a a kind
of panel for the next kind of three
quarter an hour or so. So what I was
hoping to do was to try to kind of pull
together some of the the disperate
threads from some of the talks you've
seen so far and some of the talks going
to come on this afternoon and try to get
like a a higher level view of where we
are with communications where some of
the big issues are what the actual
problems are where the system's working
for us where it's not working for us
where the big levers uh might be. So I
want to introduce my my panelists. So
David Shereé you already know from this
morning and I wanted to introduce Sanjay
at the end. Uh Sanjay is a senior
research fellow at Collins Aerospace. Uh
he's been a PI on various DARPA and AATO
projects. Um he has 29 granted patents I
believe.
>> Yeah. Right.
>> Close enough. Um and has been looking at
both kind of, you know, networking, AI,
machine learning in the aviation space
where you've got, you know, probably one
of the world's most denselyworked
objects at 30,000 ft moving around the
world. So I thought it was a good uh uh
good. So what we're going to do is kick
off by asking Sanjay to talk a little
bit about what's happening in aerospace
and communications, the applications
that sit on them, what we're learning as
an example of this really dense
environment. Um, and then I've got a
couple of questions I wanted to kind of
kick into the the group and then we'll
open the floor up for questions and uh
contentious questions and disagreements
and all that kind of stuff.
>> You have to keep people awake after
lunch.
>> Yeah. So we got sadly got the the
caffeinated end of the day. So So I'll
hand over to San do you want to tell us
a little bit about what's happening in
aerospace?
>> Sure. cases.
>> Um, so I'll focus more about the
aircraft itself, not in what's around
the aircraft or the IT side of things.
So there's there's perceived demand for
more and more applications on the on the
aircraft. Um, where the seats are going
to get modernized, galleys, labs and so
on. Um many of you may remember 3 four
years ago there was something called CO
and there was a perception that the
aircraft were distributing the viruses
of bacteria around the world. So the
perception developed some more and
people said well the lavatory that's the
problem child and so we set about adding
functionality to the lavatory which
hasn't been upgraded in uh several years
on trying to make things touchless so
you could wave your arms around the
faucet and the faucet turns on and so on
and so forth right um and here I was uh
I'm a telecom guy I came from AT&T Bell
Labs and I thought how a I knew how a
toy toilet work because I'd replaced one
in my house, right? An aircraft toilet
is a very different beast. Okay, so um I
learned a lot in that program. Uh but
it's it's basically it's to say that
things in aerospace work very
differently than they do on Earth. And
we have to be cognizant about the fact
that an aircraft may take off in
Johannesburg, land in Paris, go to Japan
next from there go to India and so on.
It's it's working on a global basis.
>> So anything that you need to do needs to
be certified in all these places um
needs to operate in all those places. Uh
and we can for us as system developers
it's hard to say where the aircraft is
going to be next. So we need to plan for
all those eventualities
>> more.
>> Oh no, that's fantastic. Yeah, that's
great. [laughter] Thank you.
>> I can go on.
>> And I think that's really a metaphor for
some of the things we've been been
talking talking about today. So um so
I'll kick off. So so you want to just
pull a little bit on one of the threads
that uh that David kind of started to
pick out which is this sense of which in
this whole space of communications and
networking and the applications that sit
on top of them and the the layering of
the networks and the social media and
the you know there are some areas where
we got I was like a two by two of some
places where there's a technical
question. Have we got is is the issue a
technical one and one way is it's a
money routing one um technical non non
technical non-technical versus
successful money routing non-successful
money routing. So something like the
data centers were a good example of
somewhere where we had a really serious
technical problem but a system that
could root money to to to make that
happen. Whereas in things like social
media, we have this difficult social
issue but no money routing problem that
allows us to um so I really want to ask
everybody so you know what's their sense
of where the action is in the
communication space all the layers and
across all the spaces where we have
either a money routing problem we need
to fix or we have a technical problem
that is really kind of pressing that we
really need to drill down on.
>> Let's talk with David. I' I' I'd
actually [clears throat] add a third
dimension to that which is
sort of the societal dimension to it and
and the interplay. So I you know I love
the talks this morning because as you
say in some sense they're dealing with
an extremely hard
extremely
interesting area but in some sense it's
single-dimensional. It's technology and
we can do the technology and MIT excels
at doing the technology
and the area that I find myself in is
this mushy one where there are technical
dimensions to it, there are financial
dimensions to it, there are
inexplicable societies dimensions and of
course
you know
my mind wandered off for a
There's a I am told which is to say I
might be wrong. I am told that in
certain Native American traditions when
there was a tribal conclave and they
were getting together to discuss some
weighty matter
one person might say who speaks for the
wolf
who speaks for that which has no voice
and who speaks for society and that's
not just the money. So, it's a it's a
it's a mushy multi-dimensional space and
that's very hard to get a discourse
going. It's hard to get it going in an
academic environment.
It's hard to get it going in a societal
environment and we that's problem of
civil society to try to figure out how
to discipline Facebook. I mean, it just
so
I that's not the only hard problem. It's
obviously the one that I'm attracted to
because I see what's happened to the
inter internet. But I I think living in
that multi-dimensional space is
something that takes a great deal of
thought,
multiple voices. We need a grand
conversation around some of these
things. How do you orchestrate that?
Who's in charge?
>> Very good. Um for me uh I think like the
physical layer is mostly ignored till
like it's broken like so that's that's
where I live uh all the sexy stuff is
above right everyone gets funded
>> above uh we need you
>> yeah yeah of course right like we I mean
we are seeing this happen across the
world now with all the warfare it's
actually testing
um that layer
Um,
so yeah, that's that's where I I think
the hype cycles and and software really
live up on the, you know, higher up in
the stack. Um,
that's really what all I have. I mean
defense, you know, defense funding now
with Andreal and Palunteer getting a lot
of funding and hardware becoming more
interesting. I think some could argue
it's like maybe a VC way of like exiting
at a different round. Um that could be
it. But you know um software enabled
hardware is becoming more more
interesting now. Well, that that sounds
good to ask you actually just to just
join that bit. So that we talked about
quantum this morning. We talked about
integrated phonics. Um we didn't talk
about some of the things like um
computing in the photonics which is
another area that's being worked. You're
doing work on the meta materials and the
software enabled materials. Uh you
what's your sense of like the u this the
scope of that innovation space in the
hardware that might bring through
breakthroughs that will just disrupt
everything above it. you guys like
>> yeah I think it was uh Watson Watt who
said like give me the give me the third
best technology right because the first
will never happen uh the second will
take too long and the third will be here
tomorrow you know so um yeah I do think
I do think like Ukraine is a great
example it is showing us like warfare
like you know all our drones that the US
makes they're not that good. Um, the
Ukrainians are the best drone
manufacturers in the world. Um, and you
know, they don't have like sophisticated
sensors. Uh, they won't have like
photonix chips. You know, precision
warfare was after World War II a big
thing. But now you don't need like you
you we're pretty good. Like now it's a
matter of going back to making those
weapons that or whatever. uh you know
scaling up which we we are we're still
focusing on the precision stuff. So
that's my my take.
>> Thank you. So so Sanjay you seem to be
in an industry that has it's on this
kind of um cusp of um both being
standards driven but also having to deal
with this complex um global governance u
and the need to innovate and the need to
change your systems. It's like you where
you where do you see the like the you
know the the major risks and levers in
those sort of systems? How how do you
deal with those?
>> How do I deal with this? I don't know.
I'm a [laughter] technologist. I don't
deal with that stuff. But uh but I think
maybe I want to touch a little bit on uh
what Chai said. An aircraft today, a
relatively modern aircraft like a trip 7
um has just about every networking
technology that we all know of on the
aircraft,
right? We have CAN buses, RS230 to
RS485R, airing 667, which is basically
uh time triggered Ethernet and so on so
forth, right?
Every single thing is there. Now you
want to bring something new on board.
How do you integrate it and go to the
higher level applications
and is it possible to do this with
wireless? All right, I'm wireless. Um
David reminded me this morning how old I
was when
>> [laughter]
>> u
>> damn
>> when he talked about cell phones and so
on. Uh but how do we do this? So
there's parts of the industry that's
trying to drive towards standards so
that once you get a standard done and
things are compliant with the standard
it'll be more easy. All right. So SAPE
society of automotive engineers people
are actually driving aircraft standards.
All right. So they uh there's a group
called uh NTAC that's trying to unify
all these networks into a single
physical network and single protocol.
Um, and they'll probably publish
sometime in 2026 an airing standard. On
the wireless side, uh, we also heard
this morning from several people that it
takes too long to get things done. Maybe
it is the third best technology. I don't
know. [laughter]
Uh, so there's something called wake and
this is what happens when you put
engineers in charge of acronyms. It's
called wake, right? So it actually is
wic. And it's a wireless spectrum that
was allocated by the World Radio Council
just for internet working on an
aircraft, not between aircraft, just on
the single aircraft.
>> Oh,
>> so in principle uh oh by the way, why
does it take so long? Wakes's been in
discussion since 2004.
So that's 22 years and we still no
nowhere closer to getting product on the
aircraft. All right, that's how log
gets. It's now right now the what's
known as a search document is being
rationalized by all the pnts across the
world to say yeah we agree with this
right so if we can get v basically
approved by all the pnts and if NTAC
gets to a certain point where the data
models and and so on would be consistent
then it wouldn't matter what the
underlying physical layer is it could be
wire it could be wireless it could be
anything else right So that would be one
way to address these things which again
us as technologists are trying to make
it happen but we come back to the money
trail. Who's going to pay for it?
>> Excellent. So um we were just sat in out
in the the room across the way having
chat lunch and one of the things that we
kind of chatting quite a bit about was
this kind of question about kind of
decentralized and and centralized
systems. uh which is an argument that
we've really been having in the telecoms
industry for you know kind of at least
40 years um but and one of the senses
you know it's like with things like the
you know TCP and the internet um very
much kind of decentralized architectures
but resulted in to actually execute at
scale you know a fairly centralized set
of industries as as you mentioned but
the generative power of those is kind of
continues to you know new layers of
activity which then centralize in some
ways that sometimes good sometimes not
had you know I don't have any any
thoughts about what that process is and
when we need a counterforce of people
are talking about blockchain enabled
whatever as a as a counterforce to this
is it you when do we need these things
when don't we need them when they're
useful for innovation when do they get
in the way of deployment you know I'll
kick that one into the crowd
I mean the internet has to be
decentralized almost by definition
because it's global in scope we got
75,000 ISPs occasionally they merge
occasionally we tell them not to merge
but it's sort of there.
The web I think was the last great
decentralized application and
it has a very by the way it has a very
simple money routing model. The
economists actually have a name for it.
It's called bill and keep. Okay. People
pay for stuff at the edge and there's
nothing in the middle. There's the
protocols connect servers who might be
on the edge with as soon as you put
something in the middle a relay an
arbiter a recommendation engine the
who's paying for that but if you look at
the way email works for example when I
send a message I send it to my server
which sends it to your server we have
two servers I pay for my server or maybe
my company pays for my server you pay
for yours build and keep and this is a
and you see that model by the way in
certain social networking
application like matrix. But
what computer scientists will tell you
if they've thought about this is if you
can imagine accomplishing the goal with
a centralized solution, the sol
centralized solution
will be the one that's roll that's the
rock rolling down the hill. Okay. Easier
to monetize, more nimble
decision-making, top down
decision-making. You know, if one
company had been in charge of that
standard, they might have dominated it,
but you probably would have taken 20 20
years to get it done. We have been
trying to fix the routing protocol in
the internet, which is border gateway
protocol. I like to remind people in the
beginning, the government told us that
we were not allowed to have security on
the internet because the intelligence
community wanted to spy on it. That's
not a surmise. They said it. And we
weren't allowed to use encryption until
the year 2000. We designed BGP in 1990.
So surprise, it's not secure. We
couldn't use encryption. We were told
not to. So, but since then, we've been
trying to secure. We we're still trying
to solve this problem. Why? Because you
go into the ITF, there's there's a
there's a method that I have described
as the dueling pundit method in which
two very smart testosterone loaded
people stand up and yell at each other.
And we watched a committee lock up for
five years before we blew it up and
started over. And uh well, you know, if
a company's in charge, they can just
say, "Let's do it this way."
>> You know, there's a there's an Israeli I
perhaps every military has this
expression, but but I was taught this by
Israeli. He said, "One bad general is
better than two good ones. Sometimes you
just need a decision and it could be the
third best decision."
But how do you in that space fight the
gravitational pull of the centralized
solution which of course creates a
powerful actor who then begins to
exploit the situation and that's sort of
every once in a while you get a benign
actor but
uh and by the way I'll give you a
wonderful example of a benign actor uh
there's a there's a there's a social
well it's not really social well signal
there's an application called signal
anybody here use signal
Yeah. Okay. The guy who designed it, who
has the quirky name of Marley, Moxy
Marlin Spike, um said decentralized
solutions will never succeed.
They take too long. There's too much
problem with convergence. The only way
to build something like this is a
centralized solution. And I declare
myself benign dictator. [laughter]
And in order to prove that I am benign
dictator, I make the following promises
to you. I will never profile you, which
would have been hard because it's all
encrypted. I will never show you ads and
I will never charge you money. Oops.
Money routing.
You know how Signal is paid for? Anybody
here know how Signal is paid for?
>> Donations.
>> Donations. It's a 501c3.
>> Give them money.
You know what it costs per month per
user to run Signal?
10 cents.
That's a dollar a year. But they have 50
million users. The president of Signal,
who's a woman named uh there goes my
brain. Sorry. Not like I don't know her
well, but uh I'll come back to you in 30
seconds. She has to raise $50 million a
year to keep signal going.
>> Is that stable?
Right. Meredith Whitaker. Thank you. I
just have to stop. Let my brain catch
up. Um so,
you know, that's that's the benign
dictator model. you know, just get
Meredith to raise $50 million a year,
make a donation to signal. I I I this
this is a really complicated space.
>> I always been amazed um at your when you
come to these conclusions and it's like
the amounts of money involved like
really small. So, I remember you talking
about how much money would it cost would
it cost each consumer to not have ads on
TV and social media and it was like was
it like eight bucks or something like
that for the industry to go away? it was
going to if you read Facebook's annual
report very carefully
and you try to guess what percent of
their expenses
relate to optimizing their ad business
as opposed to optimizing their
consumer-basing business and you just
stripped all that out.
I think Facebook would cost per user a
dollar a month. It's small enough they
don't know how to collect it, right?
Meanwhile, they're sucking 25% out of
the total ad revenue in in the in the
world and Google's getting another 25%
and it's remarkably unstable.
>> Excellent. Thank you. So, a long answer.
Sorry. General comments, but also I was
very interested in kind of your views on
um kind of centralized versus
decentralized innovation in
communications and where that's you know
given this you know the structure of the
industry and those sorts of things would
be interesting. Yeah, I think if you if
you bring the costs down and you kind of
see this with um Helium Helium Networks
was a is a company that was trying to
connect IoT devices and they were using
these things called Sense Caps that were
essentially Raspberry Pies and uh um you
could buy one. I bought one during
COVID. I made a bunch of Helium tokens
that you could sell um on the on on
Coinbase, I guess. or some other
exchange if you make them cheap enough
like yeah people would you'd get these
secondary markets and people would uh uh
see an opportunity there. So, you know,
going like
RAIS, if you think of RAIS's that people
could probably start putting RAIS's on
on their houses and route traffic
um for 5G in the future and then, you
know, charge the network that, you know,
it could be that. So, make it cheap
enough, you'll get these smaller
economies.
So it could be decentralized.
>> Go San any thoughts?
>> Maybe touch a little bit on a single
company versus um and I think if you
looked at Cisco's model from 30 years
ago or whatever
and all they cared about was driving
data on the internet,
they would enable any application so
long as it brought data on their
routers. So they drove a lot of the
standards by building the hardware out
and the software out and then
encouraging it e to make it into a
standard. Right? So maybe that's the
model we need to pursue. Excellent. So I
just want to open it up to the I've got
a load more questions but more fun to
open it up to everybody in the audience.
So, has anybody got any kind of
questions or points of view around, you
know, where communications is going,
what the challenges are, uh, anything
you'd like to ask the panel
or I'll continue down my list as a
threat.
>> We're in the after lunch slump.
[laughter]
>> Okay. So, let me looking at your
question. I don't know if I need a bike
for the audience. Um, I'll speak loud
enough. So if I think about
commonalities among the speakers, uh
standardization is one, but thinking
about how do you be aggressive with
regards to innovation yet trying to
standardize the
>> great question
because uh I participate on many
standards bodies whether it's RTCA or
SAPE and so on and the first thing you
need to sign off is saying that you will
not bring an innovation or invention
unless you're going to make it generally
available to everybody.
So any inventor who's solving a complex
problem is not likely to bring maybe
it's the third best again, right? So um
because the standards body is pretty
much
unless you're a benefactor of some sort
and uh
>> you wouldn't be in because many
inventors would want to monetize their
own invention. So they probably will not
bring their best to a standards body.
Um, on the other hand, um, some of us
know the progression. I think David
touched on it this morning on on modems
that started at 9600 board or even less
than that, 300 board, right? And
>> I had one.
>> Yeah. All right. The acoustic coupler.
So, um, and then finally it became
basically a soft modem and the cheapest
soft modem you could get was around $3.
I think it was basically an analog front
end, right?
And the reason for the $3 was all the IP
that they were paying to the different
patents that were included in that. All
right. So, if you can get your invention
into a standard and have a standard
price for it across the industry,
then you're sort of set for life because
it's going to pay for a very long time.
Um,
that's one way to do it.
The IETF requires that if you bring a
technology which is covered by a patent,
you must commit that it will be licensed
on what's called reasonable and
non-discriminatory terms, rand.
We don't absolutely exclude
uh ideas that are patented. You just
can't offer to use them in an
discriminatory way.
And you can make money that way.
>> Yeah.
>> I think just I think one of the things
that strikes me in this kind of space is
that these things like standards and
open source are tool sets for kind of
driving these industry structures. So I
very struck with things like the like
OpenStack and those sorts of things
where effectively you had uh series
industry players who are using open
source to take away each other's
competitive advantages and by the time
you sum that up you end up with two
completely alternative approaches that
consumers or companies can choose to
use.
>> Um and I think that you know I think
open source is a kind of a um often you
know not considered enough as a as a
tool for shaping some of these technical
things. And I'm really struck by the the
long-term competition between
um kind of telco mobile, for example,
and Wi-Fi. Um you know, one comes from
the IT industry, one comes from the
telco industry. Uh they actually play
well together in some senses. And the
fact that they're different from each
other, got different stakeholders and
not converge is actually probably a good
thing going forward. We don't we
probably don't want Wi-Fi 12 and 8G to
become the same thing because we want
that kind of creative tension in there
that allows them to um you know most
most data that's carried over people's
devices actually goes through their
Wi-Fi in their homes not through the
mobile but the mobile the Wi-Fi doesn't
work when they're traveling around but
that creative tension has given us an
infrastructure that's kind of um so this
kind of what you lock down what you do
in terms of structures that of agreement
where you have open source in there to
do I think it's a really which if we can
keep that healthy, I think we're we're
in a in a in a good position. So,
>> but it is problematic how long sometimes
those solutions take to mature. And the
gap from a vision to
something like the phone in my pocket. I
mean, you know, it's regrettably long,
but maybe it has to be. Maybe that's
just reality.
>> Yeah. So I was I shouldn't be
interfering as as the moderator but as
um David talked about David K
earlier on. Yeah.
>> Um and I was at an event yesterday where
he spoke. So he was um Xerox Park early
on involved in the early definitions of
what it would mean to have a personal
computer and hence the need to kind of
integrate those. And I think they were
saying or he was saying when they
started work on that um they accepted
the fact that the industry was building
mainframes and what they were doing was
15 to 20 years out from what could be
achieved at commercial scale and then he
was working with Nicholas Negroponte who
was then in the architect machine group
who was trying to say okay 15 20 years
out from that what will that mean for
the way we use it and these kind of like
as you say the societal implications
side of things. So at one end you've got
somebody going okay this is the raw
technology we've got can we design a a
pipeline to get us halfway there and
some of the other end saying what are
the social outcomes we want what are the
economic outcomes we want what literacy
outcomes we want and those intention
really gave this kind of really
fantastic but you're right it was a
40-year journey between what Nicholas
was saying at the for you know the early
stages of the art group up to these
things turning out in people's homes
>> in 196 60 I think eight
JCR Licklider and Bob Taylor wrote a
paper. Taylor went on to run Xarks Park
and Licklider was a psychologist but he
was at DARPA. Why did hire Why did DARPA
hire a psychologist? Duh.
And they wrote a paper talking about
what the online experience might be.
And they were techno optimists, but boy,
they nailed it. You know, it's not like
they were completely offtarget. They
they really saw it is possible to look
into the future and say, you know, it
might grow up like this. It might do
this. It might do this. Uh it's worth
finding that paper. It's fun.
>> So, so just follow that through then.
So, if you were to look out 40 years,
what would you want the worked society
to look like? And what technical or what
technical and money routing things do we
knew do we want to do that we you know
to get us there or has all the the
difficult heavy lifting been done and
now it's just about funding innovation
ecosystems that build the right apps to
solve these things you know is is there
a personal computer out there that we
need to move towards
I mean I don't think we'll be using
phones be probably talking you know with
a chip in your
directly.
>> It's a worrying concept.
>> And who controls that chip?
>> Who controls the chip?
>> Yeah.
>> Who's in charge?
>> So, I was going to throw another one.
What the question about? So, one of the
the big issues that's obviously always
in the background is security.
>> Um, you know, the security of networks,
the role of networks in security in
various forms in terms of kind of supply
chain security, in terms of cyber
security, etc. you know, I don't know if
any of you got any thoughts around, you
know, uh, where that's going. You know,
for example, with aviation, uh,
presuming that must be a kind of, you
know, a challenging security, uh,
environment with people plugging random
things into their USB ports and tweaking
their RS232s and all that kind of stuff.
>> Yeah. So, great question.
So, I I'll I'll stay clear of people
plugging things in on the Wi-Fi network
because we don't do that. Uh, our
company doesn't. Uh so uh some of our
competitors do um but security is a big
issue for aircraft especially as you're
building more and different types of
networks. So the industry has defined
four security assurance levels. I don't
know if many of you are familiar with
something called a design assurance
level uh which is very common in
aircraft. So you have a DA you know DAL
1, DAL 2, D three, D four and D five.
And the lowest design assurance level
basically doesn't need much in terms of
certification. Whereas the highest like
a cockpit system uh for the flight
management is typically a DA one. Okay.
So similarly the security industry and
the regulators have defined four
security assurance levels. So it goes
from SL 0 to S 3 and depending on which
application it is and and so on you need
to pick a S and justify that you need to
be in that cell because many of us will
probably go towards S zero and somebody
in the cyber security office is going to
say no no that's a S 3 right so there's
going there's there's tension between u
different groups But so
in short so we've started addressing
that uh from a standardization and a
product perspective to say that if
you're bringing a new system on board
then you need to do this um within our
company itself we have to go through um
security readiness check whenever we are
defining new products or when we are
redesigning an old product because of
whatever reason um and we have to go
through the security it's it's a risk
analysis basically before we move
forward with it.
>> Excellent. So Sh you you you're like on
the hardware side of security to intent
purposes you're building hardware that's
intrinsically
>> Yeah. more secure.
>> Yes. The security on the hardware side
is like well a high power microwave can
blow out all your uh your front end. You
know you can get jammed and spoofed and
your vehicle can be captured and then
all everything that you know everything
that is secret is now exposed to your
enemy. Um so there are different levels
on on the pure hardware side uh that you
have to be concerned about with virus.
So Dave, what's the security assurance
level of the internet? I don't even
think about that. What's the security
level for the for social media?
Z minus three or something.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
Yeah. I mean
again
the question is who accepts the
responsibility for what
>> and
it's in if it's in some if it's a
centralized solution and it's in
somebody's business interest or they're
being regulated then then you know
they'll at least sort of like maybe on
Tuesdays try um
but
Security is the enemy of moving fast
and certainly in avionics I mean the
rate at which you or and and medical
systems the rate at which you can roll
out new systems because of the
requirements for testing and so forth
and somebody who's in a competitive
marketplace and wants to get a product
out there. The thing they know is
slowing down to make it secure means you
fail. It's just a horrible dynamic. So
they'll come around and try to put the
security in later and well that doesn't
work. So it's a nasty dynamic. So were
the were you know the the security
problems that mattered in the the
internet at large the ones you thought
were there early on or are they are they
emergent properties as people layer
these applications on top of this really
generative infrastructure that's enabled
by the the internet and then the web on
top of it and then the
so you can't predict them in advance in
some sense.
>> Well as I said I'm frustrated by the
insecurity of the global routing
protocol and it's insecure for a good
reason.
We understood
that it was possible to build a secure
routing protocol. Woman named Radio
Pearlman wrote a thesis in 1988 that
showed how to do it, but it used public
key crypto. We weren't allowed. Um,
but obviously if you listen to the news
today, most of the things that get
people's attention are the internet as a
vector for the penetration of an end
node. And uh we actually debated that in
the early days of the internet.
It was a very interesting conversation
because you know people say bunch of
academics designing the internet didn't
care about security. [snorts]
We had a guy from NSA on all our design
committees. Okay. He just made sure we
didn't make it secure. But
>> I'm not joking.
>> Anybody's listening? Yeah. But
we talked to NSA about whether the
network in their view whether the
network should have a responsibility for
protecting the host and they say we
don't trust the network and because we
don't trust the network we can't trust
the network to protect itself. So the
net protects the net and the host
protects the host design it on that
basis.
Well, we did. And I I'll tell a quick
story, but I don't want to take up too
much time, but the day the Robert
Morris's worm or virus got loose on the
internet and it sort of got into a whole
bunch of machines. I was funded by DARPA
and uh my phone rang and I picked up the
phone and it was my it was the guy at
DARPA that was funding my research.
That's a military guy. Um this is a
test. Who lives in the real world? What
question did he ask me?
Nobody has an answer.
>> What?
>> Oh, no, no, no. His question was, "What
am I supposed to tell my commanding
officer?" [laughter]
>> And I told him, "The internet performed
a card to the degree specification. It
delivered the virus to [laughter] as
many machines as it could, as fast as
possible. Thank you."
And there was a long pause, but you
know, that was the division of that was
what we agreed on. And NSA very quickly
figured out that that didn't work. So
they created secure enclaves in which
they all trusted each other and then
they had encrypted channels between
them. And so parts of the net were
trusted and part weren't. But they
we had to
we did not have in the early days a
threat model. We didn't have a sense of
how to modularize the solution. We were
really feeling around in the mud. It was
a but we knew it was a real issue. Um,
we just didn't we just had to learn how
to think about it and they didn't know
how to think about it either.
It was too young. It's just confusing.
>> So, do you think we really have a a good
threat model for the worked world or is
it still too turbulent and too much a
kind of, you know, new actors actors
coming in that it's a
>> I don't want to be the only one to
answer here. The more complicated the
thing you build, the more modalities for
hacking it has.
>> Yeah, that's right. You want to chip in
on that.
>> What?
>> Anybody want to chip in on that?
>> No, totally. That's um
>> unonymity.
>> Sorry.
>> Unonymity.
>> Yeah, I mean like you know any any Yeah.
I mean anywhere you can as you know as
you build um more functionality anywhere
you can get in that's that's that's the
way to do it.
>> I think one one thing I would add to
that is that talking to some of the
people that kind of built some of the
social networking systems and those
sorts of things. I don't think anybody
who was building those really thought
that they would become the um the
playing field for nation state
information warfare in the way that they
did. I think we we built things like
Wikipedia and things. I think we really
did think that the best arguments would
rise to the top. And I don't think we
really understood that by opening these
things up and making them globally
important, we would invite actors in uh
that would behave at nation state levels
in ways that we didn't expect. I think
we we we honestly thought that would
happen at a lower level. And that came
as a bit of a surprise.
>> Absolutely did not understand that. I
mean Facebook thought the early days
they thought the whole world would put
their stuff online and share everything
and then you know
>> and it would all be fun
>> and became a vector for like controlling
you know uh elections
>> and I think that's so just one one
question as we finish up then so is that
is this so if we do have these emergent
properties of these systems as we build
them that are um destabilizing at a
large scale either or at a personal
scale in families is or you know how do
we think about that kind of managing
this relationship between technology
norms laws and economics in ways that
gives us some kind of sense of getting
to the social outcomes that we want and
the economic outcomes we want from these
very very powerful generative
technologies.
I mean, I think I see at least in the
government side, I see uh they're going
backwards to older systems because now
no one has them. So, [snorts] they can
use them and not be um
>> coals backed.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, you got RS232 lurking around. So,
that's a good sign.
>> You have canvas.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> I think I think it would be interesting.
I think there's an interesting exercise
to go through. There are two,
if I avoid saying the word AI.
There are two scenarios for a new social
experience that we could talk about. One
is pure multi-person virtual reality.
That's the metaverse, which Meta tried
out briefly and then decided was not a
good idea. And I like to remind people
it was invented by a science fiction
writer,
>> William Gibson.
And the other is augmented reality where
you look at the world and you're looking
through some sort of glasses and so you
see some sort of overlay on the real
world. And and I think you could examine
both of those through the lens of who
would control it, who can manipulate it.
Um when I look at the world through my
augmented reality glasses, am I going to
see the world plastered with ads?
You know, um and who gets to put the ads
there? What am I seeing when I look at
the world and who controls it? And I I
think you could at this point we
understand enough about abusive behavior
that you could you could you could
probably get a bunch of scenario
planners together and say how would
those how would those play out as they
grow up and and ignore the fact that
meta, you know, but that's all right. Um
I I
this idea of seeing this is a very small
digression, but it really just sort of
oh my god that's the future. I don't
know how many people like to watch
hockey here, but if you if you watch a
hockey game, you will notice two things.
And one of them is the boards, which
used to be white, you know, they have
ads on them, right?
The ads are now being digitally
overlaid. Okay. Um, from one camera, the
other cameras show the original boards
which have ads on it. And then on the
glass, that's what, you know, the puck
stopping glass, you see ads. Those
[snorts] are being digitally put there.
Obviously, we're on the glass. There
would be people behind the ads that
would be pissed off because they
couldn't see anything. So, they are
overlaying ads
on to the surfaces of the rink.
And they said, "Oh yeah, we make a lot
more money." I asked about this because
even though I was watching a game last,
my son is a total hockey freak. We were
watching a game that was in Ottawa, but
the ads that were on the boards were
Boston ads. Boston was injecting had
bought the rights to inject the ads onto
the digital version for the Boston
audience. And I said, "Okay, that's
augmented reality. That's what it's
going to look like. [sighs]
It's all over. It's going to look like
ads. It's nothing but ads placed on and
everything. Stop. Take the glasses off.
Throw them away."
So I don't know with any last questions
or with that I'll ask for any final
comments from the the audience about you
know kind of whe you think it's that
optimistic future for communications
network and its implications or whether
we're going down David's dystopian view
of advertising kind of everywhere. So I
think um Sanjay you want to just wrap us
up first.
>> Oh I'm optimistic. I think uh the things
that are yet to be invented and
innovated and so on and u the future
is a lot brighter than a pessimist would
like to define it and I am at times
pessim pessimistic because like oh you
know saying that the light at the end of
the tunnel's been turned off kind of
thing. No I think there's there's more
to it.
>> Some days I'm optimistic. Um, I think I
think um
I'm optimistic about technology, but I
don't know about the the combination of
everything put together whether it's
it's optimistic.
>> David,
>> did you want me to vote on the
optimistic spectrum? [laughter]
>> No, in some respects I'm very
optimistic. You know, I think the
internet's been a tremendous force for
good. And um
you know, I don't know whether you could
find somebody who said,
"Yeah, if I had to do it again, I
wouldn't.
I don't think so. We just need to figure
out how to rein in some of this
stuff." That's going to be hard because
they're powerful actors.
And I I just add this like um to my
sense when when I go around campus
meeting with the various researchers
pretty much everything we touch on there
seem to be several orders of magnitude
of improvement to come. And when we've
been talking about things like um AI
everyone say it's going to melt the
world but you talk to different
researchers there's hardware that's
going to be a thousand times more uh
energy efficient. There's software that
could be a thousand times more
efficient. There's systems that can be
built that are a thousand times bigger.
So we we're really still only partway
through this kind of explosion of these
very very large scaleworked
intelligent computationally rich systems
and so these kind of questions about how
we think these things through um and get
some at least some of the outcomes we
want I think are becoming are going to
remain really pressing for us. So with
that I wanted to thank the panel um and
for everybody for for joining us for the
session. So thank you.
[applause]