Good morning everyone. My name is Siang
Cha from Soul National University in
Korea and working under the supervision
of professor Martin Siner and it's a
pleasure to be here today to give this
primer. Um before professor Steiner's
talk on exploring the predictive prod
universe using computational methods. I
would like to briefly introduce some
concepts of product sequence and
structure analysis which is which will
provide a foundation for today's
discussion.
Let me first introduce our lab. Our
group's goal is to accelerate biological
science by developing fast and easy to
use open source computational tools. And
we believe that by lowering the
technical barriers to powerful analysis,
um researchers around the world can ask
and answer bigger questions in biology
more efficiently.
In short, we develop tools for biology.
Now, let me start with a question. Um
why do we compare proteins? If you open
a protein database, you will often see
entries labeled as hypothetical protein,
uncharacterized protein or unknown
function. And in fact, a huge fraction
of protein sequences fall into this
category. In uniro, more than 30% of
entries are annotated as hypothetical
proteins. And in some metagenomic data
sets, the proportion can be even higher,
reaching up to 50%. And this highlights
how little we know about the functional
landscape of proteins. But science is
driven by curiosity. Um what are these
proteins and what do they do? The most
straightforward way to answer that is
through comparison. If these unknown
proteins resemble other proteins whose
function we already know then we can
gain a clue about their function. For
example, if you find that a lizooal
asperic proteosis looks very similar to
an orange colored hypothetical protein,
we can assume that the hypothetical
protein may also share a similar
function. So protein comparism forms the
basis of function prediction and
understanding evolutionary
relationships.
So um and let's begin with the basics.
What exactly is a protein? And you all
might know but proteins are polymers of
amino acids linked together through
peptide bones. And proteins can be very
long with hundreds or even thousands of
amino acids and their corresponding
nucleotide sequences are even longer. So
given this long change the question
becomes how can we compare two protein
sequences or even how can we compare two
protein structures
I'll start with sequence alignments
sequence searches form the basis of most
of protein binformatics task tasks such
as identifying disease associated
phenotypes or predicting protein protein
interaction or performing denovo
structural prediction and studying
evolutionary relationships all begin
with sequence comparison
and broadly speaking There are two main
categories of sequence alignments,
global and local. Global alignment
compares entire sequences end to end
while local alignment fi focuses on
finding the best matching regions within
the sequences.
Um local alignment is particularly
important in biology because proteins
often share only a single domain or a
short motive. For instance, um these
structures share conserved regions shown
here in green. It can be critical for
function or can simply reflect
evolutionary history. And therefore when
we are interested in functional
similarity or evolutionary
relationships, local alignment methods
could be more appropriate than global
alignment.
Um one of the earliest and most
classical approaches is the Smith
Waterman algorithm. It finds the optimal
local alignment between two sequences
based on the dynamic programming and it
captalates
all possible local alignments by fing a
scoring matrix and the algorithm begins
by initializing the metric mat with
zeros and then filled it according to a
substitution matrix and gap penalties.
Um for example to calculate the score
for the yellow cell we consider three
candidate
um scores derived from the three green
cells from the diagonal green cell since
the letters in both sequence match as t.
The sufficitution matrix gives a score
of four which is 1 + 3 and from the top
green cell a vertical move indicates a
gap. So applying a gap penalty of minus2
it's minus2 and from the left green cell
applying the gap penalty of minus2 gives
6 - 2 equals 4 and the value for the
yellow cell is the maximum of these
three candidates four zero and four. So
it becomes four because this maximum can
be obtained in two ways from the
diagonal and the and from the left two
red arrows are drawn to indicate both
trace back options. So there are arrows
from 1 to 4 and 6 to 4. After filling
the scoring matrix, the algorithm finds
the highest value. So here 13 and it it
traces back from that cell until it
reaches a cell with value zero. The
trace path is the optimal local
alignment.
Computing all possible alignments makes
Smith Woman extremely sensitive.
However, it is also very slow with time
complexity proportional to the product
of the sequence length. As a result,
searching against large databases using
Smith Waterman alone is invisible. So,
in summary, Smith Waterman provides the
gold standard for local sequence
alignment in terms of sensitivity and
accuracy, but its computational cost
makes it impractical for large scale
database searches.
So, the field needed something faster
and that's why blast was developed. Last
makes it possible to search a sequence
against a large database such as refig
gem bank or Swiss proud and pdbid
uses short words or cers to see the
alignments
and [clears throat] then extends them.
These initial matches shown as dots in a
dot plot serve as seas that are extended
into alignments. So if the sequences are
homologous you will see a diagonal line
of dots as in the figure on the left and
if not only a few scatter dots appear as
in the figure on the right. And this
heristic approach is much faster and it
revolutionized sequence searching but as
databases grew from thousands to
millions of sequences even blast began
to feel slow. So to overcome this
limitation MF6 was introduced. Um the
main idea is to filter sequences
as quickly as possible so that more
computation time can be spent on
meaningful true positives. For this it
needs a pref filter which is fast and
sensitive. The mm6 process work like
this. First it finds the double kr
matches on the diagonal then runs
ungapped alignment and if the score is
high enough it runs gapped alignment.
the the data size is reduced
dramatically at each stage from 10 to
the^ of 8 to 10 to the^ of five and then
three and so on so that the algorithm
can focus only for the subset of the
targets and the final gap alignments.
Um aides from being optimized for modern
hardware also incorporates al
algorithmmetrics that make it both
sensitive and fast. It combines space
cam indexing and optimize Smith waterman
extensions.
It uses space cameras for the curry
sequences which makes it less strict and
allows it to catch alignments with
subtle mutations. For example, from this
curry sequence, it doesn't use
sequential sequential amino acids as
cameras but it uses space. And moreover,
while searching the speech camer against
the target database, it considers not
only the exact cam but also the similar
gamers for the same reason.
And as a result, MM6 is hundreds of
times faster than blast enabling
practical large scale large scale
searches across today's massive sequence
databases.
But sequence similarity has its limits.
Um sometimes two proteins have very
different sequences yet they fold into
nearly identical 3D structures and
perform the same function. Consider
these two proteins. Both remove
miscellated amino acids from tRNA and
thus share functional similarity and
also the structural similarity. But
their sequences are so different. Um
each sequence is longer than 130 amino
acids. But when aligned with Smith
Waterman um only 16 amino acid was
aligned with eight matches and eight
mismatches. So when aligned with blast P
the protein version of blast no
alignment is detected at all. Proteins
with similar structures can often carry
out similar functions even if their
sequences have diverged beyond
recognition. So recognizing such cases
provides evolutionary insights and
informs protein structure prediction
um um protein structure prediction and
um function prediction and even
pathogenic city studies. This brings us
to structure alignment. The idea here is
that structure is more conserved during
evolution and as with sequences there
are both global and local alignment
methods. Um, global alignment finds the
best end to end match while local
alignment identifies similar
substructures.
And because sequences are
one-dimensional and structures are
three-dimensional, there are several
ways to present the um represent
structural similarity. First as 30
structure and second as 2D distance
matrix and third as um 1D secondary
structure strings.
For example, in the 2D distance matrix
approach for a protein of length N, you
can build an N byN distance matrix where
entry J is the distance between C alpha
atoms of the residue Y and residue J.
Um, so today I'll talk about three
methods, one for each category. First,
TML is a state-of-the-art global
alignment tool that works directly in
3D. Its goal is to produce a global
alignments and an optimal superposition
that maximize the structural similarity.
First, it introduced its own similarity
score called TM score. And unlike RMSD,
which is very sensitive to outliers, the
TM score is a length normalized measure
that rewards many close residue pairs
while discounting far apart mismatches.
um the TM score ranges from 0 to one and
generally a TM score higher than 0.5
indicates the two proteins adopt a
similar fold. So it begins with an
initial rough alignment and given a set
of aligned residue pairs it computes an
optimal rigid body superposition
and by using dynamic programming it's um
update the align updates the alignments
under the current transformation. So the
cycle of superposition and scoring and
realignment repeats until the
convergence
and because of its iterative refinement
CML is both robust and efficient. It
avoids getting trapped by local
mismatches
um but and and instead it converges on
the best overall structural alignment
but um it's less suited for identifying
small local similarities.
Dali on the other hand is a local
alignment algorithm based on distance
matrices. Instead of directly
superimposing the coordinates, Dolly
compares the internal distance patterns
of products. Um here's a general
workflow. Darly first computes the
distance map for each structure and
these large matrices are then split into
smaller submatrices.
The algorithm then scans for similar
submatrices between the curry and the
target proteins here A and B. And if a
sub matrices from protein A matches one
from protein B, it this indicates that
the two regions may share a conserved
structural motive. Next um the matches
are concatenated into longer alignments
often using Monte Carlo optimization
procedure and it's it does it like
iteratively until it reaches convergence
because Dolly operates at the level of
distance patterns not absolute not the
absolute coordinates. It is very good at
detecting recurrent local motives even
if the proteins are proteins defer
globally.
In short, while TML excels at
recognizing entire fold similarities,
Dolly shines at finding local structural
motives and conserved domains of
proteins.
With such structural alignment methods,
we can detect proteins with very low
sequence identity but strikingly similar
folds. For example, these are the
structures I showed a few slides ago.
And TM line can give this proteins a TM
score higher than 0.7.
Since a TM score above 0.5 generally
indicates structural similarity, this
reveals relationships missed by sequence
alone.
Both tools are powerful, but how long
would it take to search one sequence
against Alpha Flow DB? Powered by Alpha
2, AFDB contains nearly every predicted
uniroin with over 200 million entries.
So um but even for smaller databases
like Swiss prod which has about 800,000
entries deli may take a week and TMLI
may take more than a day and for the
whole alpha DB tali would need about a
year to search a single sequence against
the entire database and Dolly would need
about seven years. If searching a single
sequence takes this amount of time it is
nearly impossible to conduct meaningful
research on such large databases.
Thus, despite their accuracy, these
tools face a scalability problem. And to
overcome this bottleneck, our lab
developed full
transforms protein structure into
one-dimensional sequences and then
applies MM62 and it combines the speed
of sequence alignment with the depths of
structural information. As a result,
tasks that would take days or weeks with
traditional tools can be performed in
seconds with full. The key idea of old
sig is reducing the dimensionality from
3D to 1d. And here is how it works.
Assuming found the nearest blue residue
for the given red residue by also
considering the preceding and the
following residues. Fig extracts
geometric features such as angles and
distances. So how does full stick
retrieve the nearest neighboring
residue? It uses virtual centers defined
by C alpha, C beta and N and C atoms. So
each residue thus has one virtual
center. For example, from these
structures, this structure, it retrieves
a virtual center for every residue and
then finds the nearest residue for each
one using those virtual centers. Um
for this red virtual center, um the
nearest neighbor would be this green
one. To sum up, it finds neighboring
residues using virtual centers and
extract the 30 descriptors and then
encodes this features using a VQV model.
Finally, a single letter is assigned to
each residue and as a result, similar
structures are encoded into similar
letter sequences as you can see in the
figures on the right and these letters
are called 30i letters. Because the
resulted alphabet consists of 20 letters
the same as the number of amino acid
types. The encoded structures can be
directly input into MM62 which is
sequence alignment software.
And for example consider two structures
that diverged more than a billion years
ago. Their sequence identity is only 16%
but after converting them into 3DI
sequences their identity rises to 54%.
And this makes it possible to capture
their similarity using sequence
alignment methods.
In summary, unfolic bridges the gap
between accuracy and scalability. It
achieves structural sensitivity
comparable to classical tools like Dali
and TM online while maintaining the
speed of sequence-based methods. Then
what is the next bottleneck? Even with
full sick databases continue to grow.
The ESM metagenomic database contains
more than 600 million entries. And in
the future, if metagenomic resources
such as login or magnify structures are
predicted, there could be billions of
prod entries waiting to be analyzed. And
conducting meaningful searches at these
scale will be extremely challenging.
So how can we make a meaningful but
smaller database? Imagine we have 12
structures and by clustering them by
similarity, we can reduce them to three
clusters. So we can reduce the size of
the database with little information
loss. In practice, clustering can be
framed as great graph clustering. Each
sequence is a node and significant
alignments form edges. There are several
approaches and I'll um the first one is
the set cover algorithm and set cover
picks representative node and form a
cluster with all its neighbors and
removes those nodes. And then it picks
another representative and forms a
cluster and remove and it repeats until
this until every node is assigned.
Second connected component algorithm
form clusters by taking connected
components of one of the graph. So every
node in a connected component belongs to
the same cluster. This often produces a
small number of clusters but can include
noisy members. And for example that
these two yellow sequences may not have
sequence similarity at all. Third grid
incremental algorithm sorts sequences by
length. It picks the longest remaining
sequence and as a cluster center and
assigns all neighbors to it and remove
the assigned sequences and repeats it.
This helps keep full length sequences
and their fragments clustered together.
And how long would cluster take? A knife
clustering method has quadratic
quadratic time complexity. Imagine dots
representing sequences or structures and
k clusters initially empty. You take the
first blue dot and then assign it to the
first cluster. For each subsequent dot,
you compare it to existing cluster
representatives and if it is similar
enough, it joins that cluster and
otherwise it becomes a new cluster. For
example, the second dot may not match
the first and so starts the new cluster
and the third dot may match the second
cluster. So join that cluster and
repeating this process yields K
clusters. But if K grows up to N, the
algorithm requires quadratic runtime.
Most clustering algorithms scale near
quadratically because assigning it new
new sequence can require many
comparisons. So clustering a billion
sequences requires almost 10 to 18
comparisons.
Linklas was developed to achieve linear
scaling. Clustering only requires 20
times of the number of the sequences.
And how does it do that? It uses
cameras. Linklas first selects 20
cameras per sequence and group sequences
to share a cam. Um for each camera group
the longest sequence is chosen as a
center and each other sequence in the
group is aligned to that center because
link avoids this kind of all VSSL
comparison within groups it dramatically
reduces runtime. If the alignment meets
the clustering criteria an is thrown and
they are clustered based on grid
incremental algorithm.
When we clustered alpha 4 DB sequences
with MM6 by sequence identity 50% the
size was reduced from 214 million to 53
million and it makes a large scale
analysis much more manageable.
And in summary, we have seen how
sequence and structure structure
alignment methods allow us to explore
protein similarities at different scales
and sensitivities from Smith waterman to
blast mm style tmine and fseek. Each
tool addresses the specific need and
bottleneck together with clustering
strategies especially with link clust
methods make it possible to work with
unprecedentedly large biological
databases.
So we started with the fact that
sequence searches form the basis of most
of bioinformatics. Now with structures
we can supercharge the analysis tools
enables enable us to ask new questions
and make discoveries that would have
been impossible just a few years ago and
they set the stage for professor
Steiner's talk where you will see how
these methods are applied to truly
massive databases in practice. Thank you
very much for your attention. So before
we continue with the seminar with Martin
Steiner, are there any questions you
want to ask in um regards to the first
session?
field question is um whether uh whether
you're using you know the 214 million
alpha fold sequences somebody must have
gone back and compared those 214 million
sequences to properties of the the
actual PTB database to understand
whether there's biases in that in the
alphafold uh database that would impact
your results and our you know what we
look at.
>> Yeah. So you you're you're asking the
quality of the models in some way. So
can we really trust the models on the
alpha fold structure?
>> Subtle flaws in AlphaFold by direct
comparison between AlphaFold and the
PDB.
>> Yeah, I mean the Yeah, that's a good
question. I mean PDB has 200,000 entries
and we have now 214 million entries in
the Alphaold database. So I guess there
will be quite a big disconnect where
many will not align very well or at all
to the PDB.
>> Oh, I was thinking more even even local
properties. Yeah,
>> too many too many alpha helyses, uh,
patterns, etc.
>> Yeah, I'm not aware that somebody has
done this like systematically at that at
the scale of like really trying to
figure out if there is something
completely odd about some of these
structures or like property wise. It's a
very interesting um um idea. I think
many of the faults should be pretty much
conserved, right? We should find similar
domains and so on and they are also in
the PDB. So, we can check their quality
and there is a work from TED um um
Christine Orango's group and um David
Jones's group. Um so that gives you can
see how much coverage you have through
that. I think that gives some kind of
level of of of um um um guarantees. Um
but for the other ones where we do not
where we cannot map them back I don't
think we have really systematically look
into this and understand what that
really is. Yeah.
>> I think Christine has also looked at how
many folds how many new folds are in yes
>> alpha fault database compared to BDB
>> right? But then there's many things that
do not have something that are not
annotated as a folder as a domain. And
then the question is what are these
pieces right? Like what are all of the
missing pieces where we actually don't
know what that is right? Yeah.
>> Any other question?
Great. Then we can just continue. Thank
you Martin.
>> Okay. Um thank you so much for the
introduction and also um giving me the
chance to present here and it's a very
interesting format. It's the first time
I have this like precursor and um thank
you Suang really to set up so many
things up for me so I can skip many
topics um and can get over them very
very fast. Um so before getting started
um the most important things we have
stickers with me with us. Um so if you
if you like our software and you you you
want some stickers please come to us um
um get them because like we really don't
want to bring them back to South Korea.
Um so it would be nice if you can just
come up and um yeah uh pick them up.
Okay. So I'm pretty much interested in
exploring the global proteomic diversity
already started from my from my PhD like
an analyzing really big protein sets and
I think this really it motivates me
because I feel like there are many
pressing problems that we have these
days you know like plastic pollution for
example but then if you go out there you
can find peptases you can find enzymes
that can break them apart we have
carbonization of the planet we have
organisms that capture and put them down
to the the oceans right um we have
antibiotic resistance but then we have
medicine out that is just developed by
in nature from bacteria to attack other
bacteria. And one project that we do
together with the Novon Nordisk
Foundation um funded by No Foundation
and researchers in Copenhagen is the
idea to go back to ancient proteomic
diversity and drill into the into the
core and like sequence it to revive
ancient mutation of plants to make
plants growable under changed climate.
You know we the planet is getting
hotter. So what mutations do we have to
put into plants in order to make them
growable um under these conditions? So
learning from ancient data I think
that's really all yeah just like a small
glimpse of what is possible but really
the technique how to do that is using
metagenomics right so you go out there
you sequence oceans you sequence um um
soil whatever you want to sequence and
you do it by sampling that and put into
sequencing machine and what you get out
is like these short reads like terabytes
of reads and then once you have these
reads you can start asking questions
right so you can take these reads and
you can search them against reference
genomic databases right and then you
know that This read is for example from
an E.coli and therefore that's an E.oli
and so you can kind of assign
taxonomical labels. You can also take
these reads take the six frame
translated version of it and search it
back against protein databases and then
you can figure out what are these
functions and I think that's really
critical to understand what these
microbes can do or you can take the
whole bag of reads and try to
reconstruct metabolic pathways. So what
kind of communication patterns might be
existing in these microbes? Um and I
think all of these is really dependent
on search right. So your initial search
is important. The problem is that 50 to
90% of these proteins remains
unanotated. Especially if you work on
soil or like environmental samples, many
of these things you cannot map to
anything. We don't know. That means we
don't even use these data. We often
throw it away. We discard it and we work
on the 10% that we can annotate and can
um make statements about it. I think
this is a really big problem. Um before
going into into um into how to solve
this problem, I want to just show an
example where we use proteomic diversity
for finding enzymes for imunotherapy in
huge protein databases. Um and so here
what you have you have a cellular
system, you have a cancer cell and you
have a T- cell. So cancer cells try to
somehow evade the immune system, right?
So they try to get around it. Um so what
they do is one mechanism that they use
is this like alkine mechanism the small
molecule they um secrete and they block
tea cells so tea cells are not
functioning in these environments big
problem so in humans we do have um
solutions for that we have these
curinases these are enzyme that breaks
these small molecules apart and
therefore then have a chance to
reactivate the tea cells and from
working against this cancer again and
there's a study by triplet all in 2018
where they asked a question could we
somehow find an efficant curing
a more efficient enzyme and um combine
it with a cancer vaccine and see if you
could increase the survivability in
mice. And they did go and find um some
bacteria um by doing um like very old
brow tricks um to find something that
seemed to be efficant um to to um um and
increase the the lifespan of mice. So I
thought that was a very interesting
study and I thought somehow can we do
that now in a different way in a more
maybe systematic way with the techniques
that we have at hand at these days. Um
so
um so here that's example right we have
the control we have the mouse with um
this PFK enzyme and the cancer shrink so
the question is can we find an enzyme
that shrinks it even further um can we
find a more efficient enzyme in
databases so my question to you how
would you do it somebody would ask you
how would you go for that um so you have
heard from Suyong some tricks and one
trick that we use is MM6 so just take
the best the PFK um enzyme and search it
against a protein database so you take
the protein with the highest efficacy.
You search it against a protein
database. Now you find around 10,000
candidates. Um and um now my problem is
solved as a bathematician. I'm done. Now
I'm handing it over to the vet lab and
the vet lab can just do all of these
experiments. Um wouldn't you would tell
me you're crazy. Um she wouldn't because
she's very polite. But so would you tell
me we can maybe do three, right? So that
means we have to be somehow reranking
these things in order to increase the
chances of success. Um so this order is
mostly defined by similarity, right? the
most similar ones are on top and the
most dissimilar ones are at the bottom.
But maybe an enzyme the most similar one
doesn't need to be necessarily the best
one. Okay, so how do we go with that?
The good thing is that we had some data
points. So we have 159 measurements from
this triplet at all study. They have
tried quite a lot um of of proteins and
they did get KMK CAT measures and we
have associations with protein sequences
for that. So okay, now it becomes a
machine learning problem, right? So now
we can somehow learn something on top of
this to um to yeah learn something from
this 159 data points. I think the
problem here is that with 159 data
points you can't really train deep
neural networks. You need way more data,
right? Like you can't have billions of
parameters. But here's really where
language the power of language models
comes in. Similar to like a GPT like
system, we have um language models like
ESM1B for example for proteins. And what
they can do is you can take protein
sequences and you can embed them. And
the embedding is at the end you can get
generate um a floatingoint vector, a
vector of like numbers and that
describes that protein somehow. And you
can associate these vectors with um
these experimental measures and then on
top of that you train something fairly
simple like a random forest for that is
very data efficient doesn't need too
much um data to be trained on and by
doing so you can get a regressor that
has an 0.81 spear correlation. So it's a
quite decent um regressor to somehow
rerank these hits. So with this together
we have now a pipeline right we are
somehow ready to to put that together.
So we search these proteins we find this
10,000 hits and we have our regressor
model that we have pre-trained on this
159 data points and then we rerank these
hits and the ranking changed quite a
lot. This is actually a ranking that
really happened for for what we have
seen in the paper or for this Q&A. Um so
something that was before at position
143 is now at position one. So it has
shuffled the list quite a lot. And for
the top three then we we we started to
do experiments right? So we wanted to
see is one of them more efficient. So
would you help with this? And um we did
find out that majority of them are very
similar to the best previously
performing one while the third one um is
substantially better in the catalytic
efficacy
and with this um mongle group went into
the mouse models and actually showed
that if you would administer this enzyme
you could shrink cancer. code um even
further. So meaning this afficant enzyme
also helps for this for this kind of
therapy. And this works not just with
KMK cut, it also work for luminescence
stability. So you can assign all kinds
of properties and and and and use them
to make predictors on it. So we make a a
kind of notebook where you go to um um
seek rank.ab.com
where you can upload a faster file with
measurements. So experimental
measurements that you associate with a
sequence. we on the fly will generate a
regressor for you um search through a
protein database and then um rerank
these hits for you and you get you a
reranked list that you might be able to
use for doing experiments on them okay
so what if you don't find any homologus
sequences um I think um Su answered that
question already um but I like this
question here to show you a pair wise
alignment now you have learned what a
pair wise alignment is right now we can
all judge it so there's a pair wise
alignment do you think this is a
homologous pair and raise Raise your
hand if it's a homologous pair.
Raise your hands if it's not a
homologous pair.
Raise your hand if it's maybe.
Okay.
So maybe is right. We often cannot see
it from the amino acids alone, right? Um
but then now we can use structures,
right? That's really what we have seen
in in the precursor. And structurally
this is very similar. So I could you ask
the same question. Does it look similar?
And now this looks fairly similar
hopefully. And yeah and through the
emergence of alpha fold right we have
now a tool that can um with high
accuracy actually predict these
structures um and so we can somehow
really generate models and as suing
mentioned we already have done that for
many of these big databases um so just a
basic question um who knows how
alphafold works if yes I can skip that
do you know how alphafold works
1 2 3 4 5
who wants to hear how alphafold works
okay more people want to hear it. Okay.
Um so this is a um an an um slide I took
from from Sergio Hinikov um here at MIT.
Um he has a very simplified version or
like a view on alpha fold um which I
really like. You start off with a
sequence and you search a sequence
against a database and what you generate
is a multiple sequence alignment and
from that multiple sequence alignment
you make a prediction that is actually
given to that neural network that um
that first an EV former block or an MSA
module that extracts evolutionary
information and then it's given to the
structural module which turns it into
coordinates or something that looks like
a structure in the end and then you
recycle this information back into the
network and you can over time improve
the prediction. So initially you have an
initial guess and then that guess
becomes better and better over time with
more recycles.
So how how does that work? How can a
network do that? Um because it's kind of
cheating, right? It's not really um
playing the game really fair. It doesn't
use just a single sequence, but rather
use a multiple sequence alignment. And
that mult multiple sequence alignment
actually tells you a lot about
evolution. So you have these columns
that are for example this like a green
column here um on the left. That's a
column where you do want to change the
amino acid. If you change it, you might
change a functional site. it might be
really bad for for for this for this um
protein. Then you have these regions
where you have like um yellow, red and
green. These seem to be like a a column
where you can change the amides amino
acids fairly easily. And so meaning that
might be a disordered region or
something that might be not very
structured. And then you have this like
blue yellow blue pattern that you see
here in the middle that are like somehow
alternating and it's like co-evolving
residues. Co-evolving residues means to
have somehow often physical contact in
the structure. If you find enough of
these co-evolving residues, you actually
the the folding problem becomes kind of
constrained and then you get an initial
guess in the energy landscape of the
protein and then with the structural
model you can take that guess and refine
it and turn it more into what a
structure actually looks like. Just a
gut feeling how that how that model
works if how it's exactly work we don't
know um but um just an intuition.
So but the MSA is important. So if you
don't have a proper MSA, you don't get a
proper structure prediction. And so uh
yeah, the DeepMind team put a lot of
effort into making these um um MSAs
really really well um using a lot of
these big protein databases that are out
there and searching through them to
generate like a really really diverse
multiple sequence alignment. The problem
is that these searches become actually
fairly slow. So it can take 20 to 30
minutes sometimes to generate one of
these MSAs and that is um really like
much slower than actually doing the
prediction in the end with the neural
network. So generating the MSAs is a
hard task. But we have heard something
there's mms. So we thought okay why
don't we replace these methods
jackhammer and hex blitz that are used
in the alpha system and just use mms to
do fast searches and because it's um
it's fairly efficient. So um we did that
and we can can generate um MSAs much
faster and we can generate it so fast
that we were able to set up server um a
small server that is just one server
that is currently providing these MSAs
to the community. So you don't actually
need to generate MSAs on your own. You
just send a request to our server and we
generate an MSA back for you. Um and
yeah, you can do that through web
interface. You can use that or you can
use it through terminal. You can somehow
access our server and we generate a
multiple sequence alignment for you for
monomer prediction or multiple sequence
alignments for complex prediction where
we actually pair up the sequences based
on um trying to maximize the orthology
in the in these pairs. And um we worked
um with with Nvidia and um you know
their minds um to make that even faster
making MM6 ported to the GPU. So you can
actually now generate MSAs in the ranges
of seconds. Um um just using the GPUs
you have around even gaming GPUs you can
use for this kind of purpose. Um yeah
and one of the persons here Chris um so
I'm very happy that you come to the
talk.
Okay, with this this is what then like
we have that server. We wanted to
initially wanted to make somehow alpha
fold accessible to the community. One
way of us to do it was to have that
server but then also together with
Sergey and and Milo and Yoshitaka Lim
and Constantine we started to build like
a call-up notebook that people could use
to just make these predictions somehow
um um in the web.
Okay. Um and you just run all and you
can make a prediction which is really
great. But this thing has grown quite a
lot. Now this server is not just just
alpha fold and the back end for color
fold but it becomes like the backbone
for all of these methods um bolts one
chai bio emo and so on. They all are
pretty much using the server to try to
generate MSAs or using um mmcs to
somehow do it. So this is obviously like
a big responsibility for us to not
really um um ruin their services um uh
which we try and sometimes fail but we
try our best and um yeah we have not
just call but you can also run these
things in Linux and Mac OS. So we can
install our call-up fold locally and run
it there. And this thing here is like
really like an I would say an overnight
success that was built on a Sunday on a
Sunday on a couch and um it ended up
being released at midnight or so. So
this is what we have done as a first
system and we had thousands of users
from the first day and I measured the
success because I'm from Korea. Um I
measured the success in in K-pop views,
K-pop video views, right? So you can say
how many million views would you need to
have a successful K-pop video? So,
Colorfold has generated over 80 million
um MSAs, I would say it's a medium
successful K-pop video. So, but for but
but for um for a bionatics resource is
pretty good, I think. Um it's it's not
often that you see these big numbers for
bionformatics.
Okay. So with Alphaold um um emergence
also the the database came as Suing
mentioned and we have 214 million models
right out there that we can um um use
for um yeah to to explore really models
of structures for nearly every um
sequence in the uniro but no viruses
viruses were excluded from the uniro. So
if you want to find them, you don't find
them. You might find proofages because
they might be incredib
and they're just labeled as bacteria,
but you do not find like RNA viruses and
so on. So we thought that's a great
opportunity. So why don't we generate
that? Um it's a is a easy publication,
right? You just take 347,000
um um um proteins and then you put them
into color fold and colorful gives you
structures and you have a paper. So
that's great. Um so we we did that and
um started with this. But the problem is
we realized very fast that many of these
predictions are pretty bad. So and the
reason for that is that multiple
sequence alignments of many of these
viral proteins become very shallow and
so you don't really do good structure
predictions. So you have to do better
here, right? Um otherwise um you're just
delivering a database that hasn't much
quality in the end.
So one thing that we have done before
that um Simon and Yuri in my lab started
it is to just show how much power is in
the MSAs for for structure prediction.
So we went to cusp 15 and we searched
the cusp 15 targets. This is like
structure prediction um um challenge
that happens every two year two years
and we we took these cusp 15 targets and
we searched against 22 pabytes of
sequence reads. Um it's just as a
sentence on a slide that is a lot of
work that is not easy. Um, so it's not
easy to search against 22 pabytes of of
of data. But that's where really Ryan
cheeky at all helped us with having set
up an AWS pipeline that can really
parallel go through all of these samples
and search. And by doing so, you go from
a very shallow MSA to a deep MSA
and from a ranking perspective in a
competition going from rank 11 to rank
three and by effectively just changing
the MSA and do not not much more. Okay,
we thought okay, why don't we do the
same thing for viruses, right? we just
have seen that works for cusp. Maybe we
can also do better in viruses. So we
start off with about 50% of the
prediction being about um um high
quality and the rest are low quality or
very low quality. Just to show you what
a very low quality structure look like.
You can see here in white this is the
experimental structure. In orange you
can see the yeah lowquality prediction
on top is pretty useless. There you
can't really find much similarities but
by searching it against a resource
called Logan which is an assembled
version of the SR. Orion cheeky at all
went on and they just didn't want to
make the SR searchable but rather wanted
to assemble it into context. So you
cannot now search through these
contexts. Now you'd have one pabytes
instead of like 22 pabytes. Um you can
still increase your MSA quite a lot with
this and and you can um improve the
predictions um also by by a big big
fraction. And then you can also use the
tricks of recycles right I've mentioned
the alpha fold system has recycles. you
can just increase the recycles to 12 and
then you can even rescue a few more
predictions and then if you take the
best out of it you can um get over 60%
of these structures to um a high quality
level and meaning now you have a quite
good viral structural database. So
normally this is the point where I will
talk about foldsek but I don't have to
because su has explained to you what
fseek is and so I can save a lot of time
here so I can go directly into the
applications of it. Um there is this
work by Greg Lor's group at um Western
UN University in Canada. They did
metagenomics on um on on on wastewater
and they were pretty much interested in
the phages wastewater phages that are
that are that are there. Um and they
wanted to annotate these wastewater
phages. So they did the or calls and so
on and then at the end they use a
software called Baka which uses amino
acid alignments and HMMs to map back
against the protein databases and by
doing so about 15% of these open reading
frames could be mapped back. But by
using colup fold and predicting the
structure of these um using obviously
also environmental data to build an MSA
um you get like a good structural model.
You can then map these structural models
back to the alpha database and you reach
now 60% or so that you can map from
these open reading frames to the to the
alpha database. So significantly more.
Um and another great study that I wanted
to highlight is by the Benfield group
that looks at these like giant ors with
80,000 amino acids. Um um really big
machines that are out there. The
question is why why does bacteria need
something that is bigger than Titan? Um
and so what they have done is they
thought okay maybe there are many non
many non-cononical function in this one.
So they wanted to slice up these huge
open reading frame into small pieces and
map them back to databases to see what
these regions are. And for many you can
just use classical amino acids works
pretty well. Um amino acid searches. Um
but whenever you see this donut here
there's a points where you need colorful
fold and full signal conjunction to
actually map it back to the database.
Okay. So I think there's a lot of
opportunity for using structures in
metagenomics. But there's a big
roadblock. If you if you want to predict
1,700 structures um with alpha 2 you
need about 4,200 hours um prediction
time. Right? In metagenomes, we work in
a million or billion scales. So that
doesn't really work. With Colop fold, we
bring that down by a factor of 100
approximately. Um, so you need 48 hours,
but that's still not fast enough to to
do it. Um, you have now MMC uh GPU that
brings it down a little bit more, but
it's still not in the same range where
you have to be to be really in a
metagenomic level.
But this is where Michel Heing and
Booker Rust helped us out. So together
with them we trained a translation
system a translation system very similar
to like German to English um or um
English to Korean. Um you can train
between amino acids and 3DI right these
are two different languages. One is the
language of of of the protein itself and
3DI is our alphabet that describes the
structure and if you would get these 3DI
strings and they would be high quality
enough then we would actually not need
the structure for search. We could just
use the string in itself.
And it seems to be the case that um we
actually can um um shortcut this quite a
lot with this with this prost 5 language
model um this transformer and the
performance of the search is comparable
to actually using reals real structures
in the end.
And so from a practical application you
can just now easily download these prost
5 weights. you can download a PDB
database or an alpha fold database or
fold system and now you can give it a
faster file like just a normal faster
file um and you can search against these
structures without needing structures
right um but still maintaining the
sensitivity that you could get with um
regular structural searches
okay and that is faster that is about
300,000 times faster than the alpha fold
base system and about um 3,500 times
faster than colup fold so now we're
getting into a range where it is faster
fast enough that you can do like a few
million proteins or maybe tens of
millions of proteins. Maybe billions are
still very expensive, but you can at
least do it at a larger scale, right? So
for some things that you cannot map
back, you can go and using this approach
now to to see what the thing might be
from the metagenoms that you um looking
that you're looking at. And we're trying
to make these things even faster. And
recently we have more and more of this
realization and also more data that
confirms it that these language models
that are really really big. They often
have like billions of parameters don't
need to be that big necessarily for the
tasks. So we saw already that you get
quite decent performance for the prost 5
model using only 20 million weights
instead of like 1.5 billion weights. And
that makes obviously the the the the the
inference much much faster and and
hopefully makes it then even easier to
do larger scale metagenomic analysis
with fault.
Okay. Um once we had fault we wanted to
use it to somehow organize the alphault
database. Um and this really goes into
this problem of clustering. Um so and
you have heard from from Suong that
clustering in a default is actually
something that is quadratic right and if
you have a quadratic of 214 million
that's a really big number um and even
full isn't fast enough to search 214
million against 214 million but since we
we um somehow have now a structural
representation that is a string right um
we can use every kind of algorithm that
we have developed before for for
clustering or for biogeimemetics in
general and [snorts] so we can cluster
in linear time using lintclass. So why
do we actually want to cluster the the
alpha database? Why would it be
interesting to cluster it? Um I find it
just interesting to know how much you
can compress the database without
actually losing too much information,
right? Like how much redundancy is
there? I mean you can imagine redundancy
being like the same multi-dommain
composition like a globally alignable um
sequence um or structure in that point
and you want to put them together and
ask the question how many bins would I
need to to to cover the whole alpha
database.
So we went on and we take this 214
million proteins and we clustered them
first with MM6 um on amino acid level at
50% sequence identity at a 90% sequence
overlap meaning that they are nearly
full length alignable at 50% sequence
identity and we end up with 52 million
about 52 million clusters per clusters
we pick the best predicted
representative where alphafold has
generated the best um structural model
and we use falsy clusters to cluster um
um down by structural similarity at a
90% overlap meaning again you want them
to be um end to end nearly alignable and
what you end up with once you remove
singletons and fragments with you end up
with 2.3 million clusters so that number
in itself is already interesting so you
get from 214 million to 2.3 million
right um so it's near 100 um um fold
reduction in in in size right so um that
already means something about how
redundant is the protein structure
universe
And then with um with Petro's group at
the ETH, we went on and we we analyzed
this this clusters more in detail. I
want to I don't want to go too much into
it. Um if you're interested, we looked
at the dark clusters like how many of
these clusters are dark. A summary 35%
of them are dark, meaning we have no
experimental um information about them.
We cannot structurally map them back to
the PDB. We can really not gain much
information about them. Also with
computational tools to predict the
functions, we kind of fail. And we
looked at these um clusters from the
perspective of evolution. Like how do
these clusters distribute in in in the
tree of life? Like how many of these
clusters are essential to all life? Like
how many machinery are essential? And
how many machineries are for example
essential to only bacteria or ukariots?
And we tried to find um new domains.
Okay. Um we wanted to scale this
analysis up you know um we wanted to um
include more metagenomic structures to
this kind of analysis to cluster not
just the alphaold database but also go
to this uncultured world right
unculturable world um there's this ESM
Atlas which is predicted by ESM fold
it's not alpha fold it's a language
model based structure pred predictor but
they have predicted um 617 million um
structures and so we have done against
these 214 million of the uniro. So we
wanted to combine the set and somehow
learn something from this you know like
how many structures are environmental
specific and um how many are shared with
the with the uni pro what can you what
can you just see from from um um looking
at these environmental data. So
understand the whole metagenomic
structural universe in some way
and we use the same pipeline um slightly
tweaked. So um since we talk about
clustering here we clustered a bit
differently. So we combined the alpha
database with the ESM artas and we also
used MMC the first step to cluster but
we cluster at 30% sequence identity
means lower than before and before we
had 50 and we cluster using the
clustering mode that Zong explains where
you keep the longer ones um and we merge
fragments into this. So why do we do
this? Why? Because many of these
metagenomic sequences when you look at
them in the ESM atlas are fragments.
they're not just complete open reading
frames and they are really a pain for
the analysis in general. So we wanted to
somehow keep the longest the longest one
as a representative. So that's what we
did. We end up with um 187 million um um
clusters and then we use our full seek
clustering um same criteria as before um
and we end up with like 5.2 million
non-zingleton clusters. So it's like a
about 2x bit more than 2x um um increase
in clusters over the alpha fold
database. Um but we have more than 4x
more um structures or sequences in the
beginning. Right? So that's already also
tells you it's compresses still fairly
well. Um but you have 3 um 5 million ESM
only clusters. These are clusters that
only contains members from the ESM but
nothing from the from the um uniro at
all. So we wanted to kind of understand
what is there. Um one big obvious
question is the question is how many
more novel folds do you have right? Do
these actually fold in something very
very unique and um and if it does um how
many units out there so we we teamed up
with Christine Orango and David Jones um
which in this um have recently processed
the whole Alphault database and cut them
into domains this resource and they
search for novel folds in this one. I
said okay let's just do the same
analysis but do it on this like um 3.5
million clusters here okay
the pipeline is like um there's a lot of
filtering steps in it but effectively it
is t pipeline so you start off with this
ESM only clusters um then you have that
many um domains that you can actually
extract from it so 5 million domains um
you check if they're in cast um so many
of them are not in cast you check if
them are high quality so many of them
fall out because they do not fulfill
their quality criteria of the t
pipeline. And then my big question is
how many novel domains did we find?
Never folds. Do you have a guess? More
than 10,000.
More than a thousand.
Okay. More than 100.
Okay. Um the answer is we found
initially zero.
Um so that's a surprisingly low number.
[laughter]
Um so we thought okay maybe it's quality
right so this database was generated
using ESM fold and we know that ESM fold
might have some shortcomings especially
if you go out of distribution and many
of these metagenomic proteins might be
out of distribution so we thought um
let's see if we could repredict some of
them so we took 25% of these ESM only
clusters and repredicted them with alpha
fold um to be precise colup fold um and
then asked the question how many noble
folds can find um so how many did we
find I think I already okay that was not
smart it's already in the title um we
found exactly one um and so what is
great I can show you all the folds this
is how the novel fold looks like um and
so it's a bit surprising I think so even
after repredicting and and so on I would
expected to find more right um but it is
somehow limiting so maybe one hypothesis
is that there is some in inherent bias
in the in the prediction methods in
itself or it It could be really that we
are we are narrowing like the fold space
and pretty much in comparison in the TAD
they found around 7,600 novel folds just
that means in the up database so
substantially more than we have found in
these metagenomes but um if we wouldn't
have t we would found way more novel
folds in the set but since we had TAD
and we mapped against TED many of them
fall out
but there is a lot of variability in
these environments we're curious what
could be another reason for this
variability and we looked at the domain
composition asked the question can we
find Cath combination like domain
combinations that we do not find in the
alpha database like completely unseen um
um combinations of of of domains and
there is quite a lot of novelty in
multi-dommains combinations so it seems
like a lot of combinations driving the
diversity and we see that especially
enriched in transporters so we see in
more and more functions that are somehow
fused onto a transporter um that are out
there in the metagenomes but they are
not in the alpha database.
Okay, with this I want to go to the next
thing that I believe is probably the
next biggest modality of structures that
we will have in the in the in the near
future and these are complexes um
structural complexes.
So with the emergence of alpha 2 people
realized you can do monomers but then
also very fast with some tricks people
realized you can do complexes. You can
actually see how how how these um
quartinary states are are built and and
we thought we just somehow need a tool
that can compare um these quartinary
databases efficiently. This is false
multimeir.
Okay. So what does it mean to compare
complexes? So here you have a complex on
the left and on the right. The one is
left is on the query and the other one
is the target. And the one on left has
three chains A, B and C and the other
one is X, Y and Z. And the problem of a
complex alignment is you want to find
like a good match between these between
these two um units. So a good answer is
you match a tox b to y and c to set
right and if you do so then you have a
perfect overlap between these two units.
Um so now computationally how long does
how long would it take you to do that?
So you say you have n chains here right
um on each each side. Do you have an
idea how long it would take to do that
to find an optimal matching between
these two um um complexes?
Yeah, just your thoughts I guess. Um
it's n factorial. So it is actually
quite quite quite complicated because
you you match A, right? And you have the
chance to match B or C, but they can be
matched in either way. And then you
could move that and you can check match
again. So you end up with an n factorial
comparisons to really find the best
possible way to superpose these two
complexes. And this is obviously not
great. That doesn't scale really well,
especially for big complexes and make
things um um quite inefficient. So we
thought about how can you make that
faster. Um so what does it mean to um do
a complex to complex alignment? What you
actually want to find is you want to
find a translation and you want to find
a rotation that matches these two chains
together. Right? Um so this is then if
you would have the translation and the
rotation then you would find your your
chain matching in some way. And one
observation is that you could take each
chain one by one and you can apply the
translation rotation completely
independent um of the other chains onto
it and you would still end up in the
same solution. So what does that mean?
That means we don't need to care about
the complex in the beginning. We can
just care about single chains and find
superpositions and then somehow cluster
them. So how does it work? You just
compute the superp positions from all
the chains in the query against the
target. So then you get your rotation
and translations and you see there's one
solution that emerges, right? And this
is the solution that will actually tell
you what the chain matching is at the
end and this is you can do an n square.
So now you don't need n factorial to do
that anymore. So that's substantially
faster.
So we wanted to somehow yeah use that
and so there is this work here um from
fangs group um from ultra at all where
they look at this um crisper systems we
wanted to somehow take this gene
neighborhood that they have discovered
like a crisper a new type of crystal
system and predicted this alphafold
multimeir because I think there will be
more and more discovery in these like
neighborhoods based on like complex
predictions because often this like
operons right so there is a lot of like
protein protein actions within them and
if you give these chains to um a fold
multimeter. You get this prediction here
on the left. It has a PTM score of 0.5.
That means the prediction is so so it's
not amazing, but it's also not bad. But
you would like to have the tool now to
search against this um the PDB for
example to see if you find similar
complexes in the databases. And with um
full multime, you can align this in less
than a minute. So you can take this
complex and search through the whole PDB
and identify um complexes that have a
similar chain um confirmation. And you
can even find [clears throat] hits that
are lower than 20% sequence identity,
you know, really really distant things.
Um, so we can do in less than a minute.
There's a software called us align which
does it pairwise. It would take 13 uh 13
days um to to really complete this task.
So this searchfor.com is a web server
where you can just put in a complex. You
can push search. It will now search this
complex against um the PDB. And now you
see all of these things that it matches
the chain matching as well. And this
takes a bit to load because they're
quite big complex. And you can see um
yeah, you can see how these chains are
are similar to the experimentally
determined structure. And you can
highlight regions. You can see um where
they are in the complex and you can see
the yeah thing in full screen can take
pictures and so on and put them into
your publications.
Okay. Um next is the idea of fully
interfaces. Um so this is unpublished
work that we do together with um Katya
look at the IMB um it's the idea to
somehow compare interfaces um instead of
whole chains full seek multime
effectively just take chains and find
these chain matchings but we often
interested not in the chains but rather
in the interface that describes the
interactions on like a smaller level. So
I think from an alpha fold kind of
perspective just imagine you do alpha
fold predictions of multimemerse you
it's actually hard to know currently if
you have really done like a a novel
prediction or not so if it's a novel
interface or not we have no tool that
actually tells us okay for that
interface that I've just predicted how
novel is that is it something that we
have observed before or is it something
that is really really really new and for
that we wanted to build this tool
so
the idea is actually fairly similar to
what we just do in in in in fals. We
just extract effectively the region
where between two chains like in was it
in a 10 amstrong distance from the C
alphas and just take that neighborhood
and for this neighborhood we convert it
into 3DI string. So we will have two
strings for the interface of the chain A
and for the interface of the chain B and
then we try we do that for the database
as well. We do it for like the PDB,
extract all of the interfaces from from
the PDB
and then we can do an alignment task. We
just align the chains independently and
we use full seek multimeter in the end
to do the chain matching. Um and with
this we then can figure out what
interfaces are similar to each other
and there is software that can already
do it. Um there's a software called iine
and we benchmarked um fseek interface
against iine on a domain domain
interface benchmark um based on proc cid
um and on this benchmark fse slightly
outperforms iline while they were
comparable in performance. However, um
FIC is substantially faster. Um I do not
have the exact number. I think we in a
range of like a few seconds to do this
comparison and benchmark while if you do
it with line it takes um um a few hours
in general.
Okay. Having now like a really fast tool
to compare interfaces, we're curious to
cluster these interfaces.
um starting off from the P PDB take
these biological assemblies um extract
um just interfaces but only the ones
that have at least four residues. Then
we have about 3 million DR like dmer
interfaces and we use um full seek
interface clustering to to somehow
cluster these groups together
and what we ended up with is about
43,000 clusters while um 11,000 of them
are singletons. So it's a big reduction.
So means like um interface space is much
much much smaller than um the the the
dimemer space in general. Um and now
with this we really have a lot of
questions in mind. We have not done so
much analysis. This is really work in
progress heavily. But we were curious to
annotate these. We want to figure out
how ancient are these interfaces like
are they um specific to certain
organisms um and and and really
understand what these clusters are. In
addition of this, we were pretty
interested in predicted alpha fold
complexes and asked the question in
these alpha fold complexes. How many of
the interfaces in the PDB are actually
covered um through alpha predictions?
Are they all covered? Do we have some
problems for some of them or not? Um we
started off with some analysis. Um this
is our flying spaghetti monster. And
this is the biggest non-coil coil BFMD
which is a a database of predicted um um
uh complexes from AlphaFold. Um, and we
compared the interfaces like of this
BFMD against the PDB. And this one is
the one that has nothing in the PDB, but
it's like a big cluster that is somehow
occurred in the in the um in the alpha
fold one. So, it might be a novel
interface. Um, novel interface or wrong
prediction. We are not sure and we have
to now kind of understand if this is
really like a novel interface that Alpha
was able to predict or if this is
something um where something really went
terribly wrong. Okay, the last thing
just I want to talk very briefly about
um is 3D motives. So we we method
developers we put out fullse seek and
then you know a few days later when you
put out full you're very proud of
yourself you think you have generated a
good software but then the community
asked the question how can I find
binding pockets um and then how can I
find these custom motives and your
answer is you cannot and that is really
frustrating as a method developer um uh
and so we wanted to have a solution for
this so why are these things really
important you know these ensematic sites
are very conserved you have these like
these ensematic triads that really
causes the enzyatic reaction and you
want to be able to somehow find that. So
why is it hard to find it? And Su
introduced dynamic programming to you.
Dynamic programming actually means that
you can align from left to right because
you fill up the cells from left to right
and you have always the property that
you look back to what was previously
aligned and you compute the score to
what is previously aligned. And this is
what fseek and mm sensor can do. They
can find really like a stretch that you
can align really well from left to
right. But these motive like the sync
finger for example here doesn't need to
be following this rule. So it can
completely shuffle the order of the
letters. Right? And that makes the
problem much much harder. So it's much
harder to find something that you cannot
align from left to right.
So how can you find that? So we have
developed a f full disco um especially
for this purpose. So if you have a
structural motive for example um so here
a sync finger with this like four
residues the way how you would find it
is actually very tedious and what you
have to do is you have to compare all
pair wise interactions. So you have to
cut cut this piece into into pair wise
interactions. You have to ask the
question is this pair wise interaction
somehow compatible to something in your
structure in the end and you have to do
it for all. So you're checking all of
these pair wise interactions. Um and in
order to be fast and we want to be fast
we have to actually store all of these
pair wise interactions. So for the
upfold database we have to store um a
big set of these paractions and this is
really a big problem. So there is a
software that called um RCSB. They use
this pair feature representation where
they take the C alpha distances, C beta
distances and an insect intersecting
angle between two amino acids
and um then they store the identifier
for the structure where this um pair is
from as well as the position of where
where does the pair is anchored in the
structure. And if you would store that
it for 214 million structures you would
like need 73 terabytes of of disk space
which is not really handable for many of
the groups and many people do not have
that much space and also obviously it
makes search slower because you have to
go through this big big data set in the
end. Um so we thought about in disco how
can we make that smaller and um also
maybe include some more features that
might be important to identify um these
these motives um a bit more sensitive.
So we take the same features as the RCSB
um um idea but we add the side chains
you know the side chain orientations and
I think that's very important for
ensematic pockets because the side chain
orientation really contributes a lot in
the end to the geometric pattern right
and we also decided to not store the
position but we only store the
identifier. So now our algorithm what it
does is it takes a motive it breaks it
up into this pair wise interactions and
it searches them in in an index that is
10 terabytes big um through an inverse
lookup table and it finds where in what
identifier can I find all of these pair
wise features and if I found it I can
take a slower algorithm afterwards to
find more precisely where are the
positions of this one. So you can see
that like as a fast pre-f filter, you
know, similar to the pre-f filter you
have seen in MM62. This is a pre-f
filter that somehow narrow down the
space of structures. And when you found
the set of structures that have a chance
to have that motive, use something more
thoroughly to find really where does the
um where is the motive really occurring
in it. And yeah, full disco
substantially faster than pi score
motive which is ani python
implementation of the RCSB. um you can
search a motive without pre-f filter
alone in in seconds. When you really
want to need to know the position where
it occurs, you need about a minute or so
um to search a motive against the A4
database. So why is it useful? So for
example, you can take a sync finger
and you can search the sync finger
against the database. So what you find
if you search a sync finger against the
alpha database is this uncharacterized
protein here on the right side which is
a Pacific oyster. Um we don't know what
it is but it seemed to have the sync
fingers quite a lot. And you can also
find sync fingers in unanotated
metagenomic sequences. So you can kind
of get an idea of what the thing might
be able to do.
Or something to play with with your
imagination is you can actually start
looking at states. So you can take a
here's a GPCR in an active and an
inactive state. And you see highlighted
are certain hinge points that describe
the state um um of this of this GPCRs.
So you now you can take the left motive
and search it against the alpha database
and the right motive and search against
the alpha alpha database. The left one
should find everything that is in an
active state and the other one should
find everything that is in an inactive
state. So now my question is how often
do you believe in the alpha database
that you have an active versus an
inactive state? When you make a
prediction alpha for would you always
believe it always generates everything
as an active one or everything always as
an inactive one.
So what we have seen is when you search
against the PDB you find 50% active and
50% inactive. If you do the same search
in the alpha database you find 50%
active and 50% inactive. So maybe alpha
is kind of sampling you know what it has
seen. So you I think there's a lot of
structural diversity probably in the
alpha falls um DB um um out there
already and you can probably explore
different states. So you can easily use
full disco um through our web server
upload um a structure then define your
motive that you want to um search
you can click search and then after some
time you will see the hits in the um in
in all of these databases alpha database
included um and then yeah this is how
the motive looks like this is how it's
in the query look how how it look in the
query and this is how it looks like in
the target
and so yeah we keep on developing this
um so if you try that out and you have
any problems please let us know um we
happy to to help and and fix things. In
conclusion, um Su has taken my
conclusion. Um so I had to have a
different conclusion and and this
conclusion is that I I I see so there's
this um um tweet by um Seaming Lin that
sees us somehow as this like small stone
here um that holds up that that big
thing on top which is like protein
design I would say like um AI bio in
some way. Um so I I see we are building
these like fundamental units right
somehow that helps others um to to make
their work and life um easier is really
nice was really really motivating and I
also see our work like this but I want
to at this point really thank everybody
that contributes open source software
right because our software would be
possible because we are standing also on
somebody's stone right so um many many
of you have contributed code have
contributed ideas um and put them out
there and let other people use it for
free I think that's really the great
thing about academia here we can do that
right we can really live idealistic give
our code for free and let other people
use it and so um if your face is not on
here but you have contributed then
anyway thank you so much for for doing
this this is really really critical and
with this I want to thank everybody that
helped make this work possible and yeah
thank you for listening
let's see if it's working now yes it is
any questions
A wonderful talk. I really love seeing
all the tools your lab's creating and um
it's become apparent to me that you know
so many of these tools are depending on
the fold seek 3DI alphabet. And I think
from the primer we we sort of got a um
an understanding of why it's 20 because
it it feeds directly into MMX 2. Um, so
that was sort of a logical choice I
think technically. Um, I'm just curious
to know if you and others are thinking
about that choice and how that's
impacting all these future tools that we
sort of kept it at uh 20 for the
alphabet size. Is that a problem with
the coarseness of those um of that
alphabet or you know should we go for um
a more descriptive alphabet?
>> I think it really depends on the use
case. So if you want to use an alphabet
to reconstruct a structure from it, you
know, you want to really have something
that contains a lot of information, then
our alphabet isn't great. So you would
not be able to use the 3D string and
then go back to cartisians and you would
lose quite a lot. For us, this
representation um was useful in that
coarse crane level because in the end it
it captures enough for the alignments to
find the folds that we want to find. And
and yeah, as you mentioned, 20 is nice
for MM6. And in the evalation studies,
we showed that with 24, you're a bit
better. If you go higher, you don't you
don't gain very much anymore. Um but
there is more to gain. So you can
probably do a better alignment if you
would not just have one structural
alphabet, but multiple structural
alphabets. And we also have um
Johannes's group has work on a
complimentary 3DI alphabet that takes
this virtual center and just places it
in the other direction kind of and um
optimize it to be maximally
complimentary and you can just stack
these two alphabets together and you
would get a better alignment out. Um so
yeah there is a lot you can consider for
these alphabets. Um but I think yeah
for us for the alignment purpose you can
just not really use a really high
dimensional one right that's definitely
a problem. Um, so we need to be somehow
low dimensional otherwise our
substitution matrix would not be
trainable and so on. So yeah, I think
that trade-off that we have made is a
good technical trade-off, right? It's
not obviously the best solution and it's
probably like best from the perspective
of like finding more um um structures,
but um it was good enough or I think it
is good enough to find the majority that
you care about. Yeah. And I just wanted
to ask a question about your uh your
clustering. Whether you think whether
you think you could infer whether
something was a product of convergent or
divergent evolution and whether your own
system biases toward divergent
evolution.
>> Yeah, it's I get this question a lot and
I never have like an amazing answer um
because I don't even know how to really
know if it's convergent or not. It's um
how would you measure that? It's a bit
hard. There is one database um from from
Nick Gishian's group um I think it's
called Mali Malisam Mali um I forgot the
exact name but they um handcreated some
cases where they really believe these
are convergent evolution cases. You can
actually look at the structures you can
see they are somehow super poseable. So
if you put them over each other you
would probably see that they look
somehow similar but the sheets are
shifted you know and and and sometimes
the other direction and and so on. So
it's there are differences and if we
cluster that with our clustering
algorithm we cluster zero. So we don't
cluster them together at all. So I would
rather indicate that I would this would
indicate that we have probably more
non-convergent cases in these clusters
than we have convergent cases in the
cluster. Yeah.
>> So there might be a bias.
>> Yeah. Yeah. There might be a bias there.
Yeah. You need probably to find these
convergent cases, you probably probably
want something that is like superposing
really strongly, right? because the it's
hard to align because the 3DI alphabet
will be quite screwed if you start
turning the sheets completely around or
do something quite um aggressive to the
to the structure somehow. And so you
would probably need a different type of
algorithm to really um align these um
cases. Then yeah
>> subcluster the cluster
>> subclusters to clusters. Um yeah
something like that I guess you could do
with some other method for example then
and see if you can do it. Also in Fzig
we have TML line as a module in it
right? So you could say you just first
try find somehow some similarities in a
fast way and use TML line to try to find
some convergent cases but then once you
have it how do you really show that it
is that's another problem and I don't
know I have no no strong feeling how to
make like a really objective measure of
this is really convergent or this isn't
really convergent. Yeah,
>> maybe one last question from the chat.
Um, Anthony asked, "Alpha 3 seems to
reduce the importance of the
multisequence alignment as there is no
dedicated specific attention block for
the alignments. Do you think this
changes the cases when collab fold is
beneficial?
>> Alphault 3 has still has the MSA block."
So they it still has it. So what they
have done is the the alpha 2 model has
uh an MSA block then a performer block
an MSA block a parapformer block and
they're somehow talking to each other.
So that's how the network architecture
of alpha 2 is. Alpha 3 took these MSA
blocks and it moves it in the beginning.
So you have four blocks for extracting
MSA information and then you have 48
blocks of pair pair representation. So
they still extracting knowledge from the
MSA. So I don't think you lose the
dependency on the MSA um completely.
they changed even the MSA block to allow
more sequences to be in the to be
considered in the MSA block. So they
they want to actually extract more
knowledge from bigger MSA. So I don't
think it makes MSAs obsolete in any way.
>> Thank you so much Martin and Suang. This
was fantastic, very instructive and
thank you all for joining today.