(upbeat music)
- MIT teaches 11,000 students.
It's about one in a million
people in the world.
The aspirations of open learning
is to reach a billion
learners of all geographies,
of all backgrounds, of all ages.
- The vision behind MIT Learn
is to create a whole new
front door to the institute,
to give people one place
to go with their curiosity
and find the learning
opportunities they want
that meet their personal or career goals.
You can find what you want to learn
the way you want to learn it,
from short one hour video introductions
to complex technical topics,
it's all here in one place.
- [Speaker] AI is very central
to the way Learn works,
personalized instruction, the tutor,
the conversational TA and the syllabus.
- Our research shows that
learners evaluate carefully
a course before they commit.
For this reason, we have
designed Syllabus AI,
an AI chatbot that helps
learners make the decision
whether course is appropriate for them.
- For example, I'm a biology major.
I have taken the secret of
life, what is the next class?
And out of the entire catalog
of open learning, it selects
the appropriate classes
for that learner, a system
that really personalizes
to the understanding of the student.
- Great, it's told me
about a specific course
that is a prerequisite,
and I'm also curious,
I'm going to ask the Syllabus AI
what the main takeaways
are from this course.
- [Speaker] We have designed some AI tools
that will help learners deeply
engage with the content.
Learners can ask question
about video content,
generate video summary,
generate flash card from the
key ideas from the videos.
Tutor AI also help learners
as they work with the problem sets.
- Our Tutor AI will help you
as you're working through the solution,
but not provide an immediate answer.
- With the advancement of AI
and the AI infrastructure
we have built in MIT Learn,
we'll continue to innovate,
to use AI to improve MIT Learn
and offer personalized education
for anyone, anywhere in the world.
(upbeat music)