okay hello everyone thank you all for
joining the last seminar of spring term
uh it's a great pleasure to have
Professor Peter MCM here with us today
uh Peter is an assistant professor in
the department of applied and
Engineering physics at Cornell
University and he's been there since
2019 prior to that he completed his PhD
and post-doctoral training at Stanford
University uh his research is focused on
Computing with physical systems both in
classical and Quantum domain and uh he
has been recipient of many awards
including the Packard and Sloan
fellowships Office of Naval Research
young investigator program award Google
Quantum research award he's also a sear
Israeli Global scholar in Quantum
information science uh so it's a great
pleasure to have you here Peter today
very excited to learn more about your
work before that I just wanted to remind
everyone if you're in the room feel free
to ask your questions throughout the
talk that's what Peter prefers H for
whoever is listening to us on Zoom
please type your questions and at the
end of the talk I'm going to help
moderate the questions for you so with
that thank you for joining and we're
excited to hear your talk awesome thank
you uh so thank you very much for the
kind introduction and thank you for the
invitation to speak it's a it's a great
pleasure to be here and it's been a
while since I gave a talk uh and it's
always wonderful to uh to come
visit so uh let me let me start my timer
to make sure that we uh end this on time
so uh my grand plan is to tell you today
about Computing with physical systems um
so I'm going to start off by describing
uh some challenges in modern Computing
that I think could be addressed by
building what we think of as Computing
with physical systems or physics based
or physics inspired Computing and I'll
describe a bit about how that what we
mean by that differs from conventional
Computing and how we could benefit from
uh Computing in this new way uh I'll
then talk about what we call physical
neural networks or how we can use almost
arbitrary physical systems to perform
neural network processing for us
and uh then I will describe an onip
photonic neural network platform that
we've recently
developed uh that is an example of a
physical neural network and uh this will
be towards sort of how can we scale uh
these physics based machines to larger
and larger neural network sizes and then
finally I'll end with some commentary on
uh prospects or speculations about uh
where physics Computing might go um and
especially since this was a nano seminar
I felt almost obliged to include some
Nano Electronics in this so we we
haven't actually don't have any results
to talk about in Nano Electronics but I
thought I'd uh end with some description
of sort of how some of the things I
talked about might be applied in uh in
the sort of either CS or other
conventional Nano electronic
Realms so first of all let's begin with
uh why do we even want to build
computers that are faster or more energy
efficient uh maybe to this audience
that's completely obvious so I'll I'll
go relatively quickly through this but a
large motivation for us has been the the
growth in deep learning in neural
networks you can see in this uh this
chart here uh the size of uh uh or the
compute cost required to train various
machine learning models spanning the
last several decades and kind of if you
look in the last decade you can see this
really massive increase over many orders
of magnitude um and part of the the
reason that this has happened is this
discovery that as you scale uh certain
neural network architectures the more
parameters you the more compute you add
the more capable these models become so
there's a strong sort of desire to make
the models bigger and
bigger uh but it creates an a pretty
obvious problem which is if we sort of
zoom into the last decade and we look at
this nice plot of in Blue uh these
neural network models and how they've
been their compute demands have been
increasing with time versus the Moes law
scaling in Orange of uh standard
conventional
processes uh there's clearly a major
issue uh that the models are growing or
the compute demands are growing much
more rapidly than our computers have
been growing and you can make
specialized chips that are designed
purely for neural network processing and
get some benefit from doing that uh this
essentially jumps the line up by a bit
but it doesn't really change the
fundamental Mo La scaling underneath it
uh so that is good to have it's good to
do uh but it's not
sufficient another strong motivation for
us has been uh thinking about sensing
that there are sensors all around us and
sensor bandwidths keep increasing um so
we have even Now consumer electronic
devices with 200 megapixel cameras um
and in this uh this example shown on the
on the left here if you think about uh
some kind of Medi pixel sensor that is
digitizing data at sort of maybe 50
gigas samples a second uh in some
defense application even if you already
have 512 pixels of this the amount of
data that's coming out of this kind of
sensor is enormous 500 terabits a second
uh so storing that data is clearly a
challenge and not a great solution to
the the Deluge problem uh but also
processing it in real time is also
really
challenging and something that appeared
in a relatively recent SRC report is
this notion that maybe one of the ways
to solve the sensing challenge will be
to perform analog pre-processing so
before we digitize
this really high bandwidth signal that's
coming into our sensor uh maybe we
should perform some analog
pre-processing that extracts the
relevant features for us this is
something that's really inspired by uh
by Neuroscience and even the human
visual system where there's really high
bandwidth data coming into my eyes but
in order for me to know that uh the sort
of the remote control is here and my
mouse is here and so on I don't need the
full sort of super high megapixel
resolution image uh and so our brains
actually do a a whole bunch of
processing before the information
ultimately gets to the part where we
make
decisions so okay we would like uh more
speed or Energy Efficiency for both
these reasons uh what are some options
we have to achieve that so very
generically there's essentially four
strategies that I'll talk about that you
can try to use to make computers more uh
have higher throughput or greater Energy
Efficiency so the first is that you can
elim abstractions so Computing is built
on a a great system of abstractions uh
which is something we all learn about in
undergraduate electrical and computer
engineering degree um but it has a major
challenge that now there's uh so sort of
so many layers of this that you've
introduced inefficiency at each layer so
now you could imagine stripping some of
these away for example we rely an
abstraction of digital logic even though
it's built fundamentally on physical
devices that are analog U we assume that
signals are deterministic and always
correct uh you could imagine going
towards analog or probabilistic
computation and really part of this
philosophy is going to be designing
behavior from the bottom up so you start
with your physical substrate and what it
naturally does and build up from there
rather than the conventional approach of
going from the top down and I'll have
another slide on this later to give a
sort of even crisper picture of what uh
what this is really all about a second
category is that a major challenge in
compute systems is that your your memory
is often separated from your processor
and there's a bottleneck and bandwidth
between the two of them sometimes called
the vyan bottleneck and that you can try
to address this by uh Computing in
memory so merging the memory and compute
this is something that people of course
are ready do a lot of in conventional
digital and analog electronic Computing
uh but it's a general I think principle
that you can also apply in uh in physics
based Computing uh the third option you
have is something that I think
especially in the the DAT seminar series
uh many people in the audience are very
well familiar with is that you could try
to go beyond seos you could use
alternative Hardware Hardware physical
substrates or even modalities for
example Quantum Computing is something
that you could try to apply in at least
very specific
applications then finally a fourth
pillar which is has for a long time been
something that sort of people have been
really resistant to but is now maybe
something we were forced to to think
about taking seriously and whether we
should really do it is being tolerant to
VAR ations instead of insisting that
every copy that comes out of our Fab
Works in exactly the same way for the
level of works the same way we mean in
our abstraction hierarchy uh maybe we
shouldn't insist on that anymore
certainly it's an option you have if you
would like to get the most out of the
physical device you have if you allow
each copy to vary uh you can uh you can
push the performance and so this may
require some tolerating some amount of
train retraining or reconfiguration of
the device after its fabric a and many
people have been thinking about this uh
Jeff Hinton had a a a talk at a Europe a
year at a bit ago where he described
this as mortal Computing that each piece
of Hardware will sort of fundamentally
live its own life as you have to as you
have to retrain it U so those are those
are some options you have let's now talk
a little bit about this uh business of
eliminating
abstractions um so on the left here we
see this uh standard stack of
abstractions that you learn about
throughout an e
degree uh starting from uh depending on
where you like the camos transistors
building all the way up through
insisting that they output digital logic
digital signals you have logic gates you
can construct adders and multipliers and
so on from that building all the way up
through to user
applications and a beautiful thing about
this abstraction hierarchy is that if
you're working at any one of these
levels you don't need to know in great
detail exactly what's happening above or
you below you but the price you pay for
this is that now each of these
abstractions is assumed to be extremely
tight and you can't just decide oh well
I'll make my my add only sort of add or
add some of the time uh that's that's
not an acceptable thing to do in this
framework where people are are relying
on you to do the thing you said
according to the
specification a completely uh different
way of going about things is to do what
one by term physics based Computing
where we start with some physical
Hardware it could be uh unconventional
it could just be camos Hardware
uh and we we treat it as a complex
system that is naturally performing
computations for us and we program it by
deciding on the connectivity between the
components of the hardware or the
parameters of the physical system that
we can
change and so in this setting the
hardware connectivity and the parameters
induce certain dynamics of the hardware
which in turn induce an algorithm so you
don't start at the pop top and say I
want this algorithm and compile down you
start with what the hardware naturally
does and you tweak it until it does the
thing you desire and so programming in
this kind of model is analogous or is
done by really adjusting the tunable
parameters of the system and so here
there's no real separation between the
notion of the program that you run and
the hardware that it's running on and uh
this makes programming more difficult
but what you get in an exchange is that
all the sort of inefficiencies that you
had uh that you were by imposing
constraints at each layer and an
abstraction hierarchy are now all
gone so I wanted to give one example uh
of this kind of physics based Computing
modality that's been explored over the
last decade and that uh including by
people uh at MIT so uh maybe some of you
will have seen this before if you have
great if you haven't you can ignore it
we're not going to use it later in the
talk but I wanted to give at least one
example uh for those of you who have
familiar with things called icing
machines so icing machines are special
purpose pieces of physical Hardware that
have been designed to through their
natural Dynamics heris optim perform uh
combinatorial optimization and an
example of this is something called
oscillator icing machines where people
have proposed connecting nonlinear
oscillators for example could be couple
like a nonlinear capacitor and an
inductor that are coupled for example
resistively shown in this example to
another spin uh and the idea is that you
would design these through their natural
Dynamics will uh will naturally minimize
the over an overall cost function given
by an iing hamiltonian and this is
something that's now been sort of even
scaled up relatively large this is an
example of 2,000 oscillators in a in a
seos uh seos device and in this uh kind
of setting you have essentially a
network of coupled oscillators they have
some Dynamics this is describing the
evolution of the phase of each
oscillator and really the thing that
gets programmed here there's no program
the thing that gets programmed is how is
each oscillator coupled to each other
one which is this ji J and the in this
formula
here another example of this is uh
probabilistic bit machines where people
have taken stochastic magnetic tunnel
Junctions uh which behave as essentially
probabilistic bits that you can bias
connected them together in networks they
have a slightly different Dynamics than
than these oscillator versions but a
very similar concept holds you
essentially the M the system is doing
what it naturally does these these These
smjs are sort of flipping back and forth
and the thing you control is how they
are connect conected and there's been
work at in MIT and and Durk and M's
group and also luch child's group on
this kind of thing so some of you might
have seen this before so this is an
example of what I mean of getting rid of
the abstractions and really just working
at the base level of the
physics son now I want the first story I
want to tell you about is work in our
group on constructing neural networks in
this kind of way of taking physical
systems and operating at the level of
the physics to construct uh or perform
neural network inference
so uh some sort of quick preliminaries
and mostly so I can show you some
diagrams uh so that you can sort of
match them uh to diagrams later on uh is
if we think about a a deep neural
network really what we mean by deep is
that there are multiple layers so here
is an example where we have some image
encoded in a vector let's say this dog
here and this this data gets or this
information gets propagated through
multiple layers of a neural network
where we can think of each of these sort
of boxes here there's supposed to be a
gray box around it but it's okay okay uh
or uh or a single layer of the neural
network that performs some function on
the input vector and outputs another
vector and this gets propagated through
until uh out poops the answer that okay
this thing that you sent in was an image
of a
dog really the way we like to think
about this is that it's a network or a
composition of functions you're you're
taking an input of a dog and some
parameters that control what function is
implemented here uh you compute it and
then you're passing it to the next one
so you're now
sending that as an input to the next
function and so on and so on so really
these uh this is a specific onsets for a
function that takes a an input and a set
of parameters and produces an
output and of course okay if you put a
put a cat in you should if your network
is trained correctly and these
parameters are set right it should
predict that you have a that it's a cat
soort of how does this training happen
well if we start with a network where
the parameters are just set randomly or
untrained in some way then uh you'll
just get a random answer out and
training proceeds by updating the
parameters uh so that when you when you
uh when you put a dog in and it gives
the wrong answer you maybe prod the
parameters and move them in a different
direction and then once you've uh once
you fixed these parameters for all of
these layers here now you can perform
inference where you can put in a new
image of unseen data and have it
correctly make a prediction and so
everything I'm going to tell you about
uh in this talk today is really going to
be about making Hardware that could
potentially be more energy efficient or
faster for the inference task but by
necessity we have to have done training
to get there so I'm not going to give
you a method to improve the speed or
Energy Efficiency of training but I have
to cover it in some way because
otherwise I couldn't have got to the
inference
phase and uh this is uh sort of not not
a silly thing to be doing even if you
only solve the inference problem already
that's a very large fraction of cloud
compute for machine learning because you
you train a model once and then sort of
at this point literally hundreds of
millions of people may use that model in
inference
mode so how are neural networks
implemented in conventional Hardware
well if we think about a typical layer
sort of most simple form of this will be
this layer of a neural network will be
performed by matrix Vector
multiplication so we have a vector in we
get a vector out and they're related by
a matrix Vector multiplication of the
what's often called the weight Matrix W
describing the connections between the
neurons and the input vector and then at
each point or each neuron each element
of the vector and element wise
nonlinearity is typically applied
something like this REO function and
this has been uh has been implemented in
Hardware accelerators and digital
electronics where you have things like
systolic arrays where you uh where you
almost have you can almost see like the
spatial structure of the Matrix in the
hardware itself uh if you squint uh and
people have also been working on analog
processes in electronics for example
this cross bar array here where you send
in the vector as voltages on these blue
lines and then they are connected to uh
the red lines via uh programmable
resistors uh so memoris of devices or
resistive memory devices so the the
weight Matrix is encoded in these
elements that connect the the wires of
the crossbar and then you read out your
answer as currents on the on the on the
red lines and this here you can really
see that like uh the the hardware has
been designed to perform Matrix Vector
multiplication um and people work really
hard at getting these kind of devices to
exactly perform a matrix Vector
multiplication so we we asked the
question of does do you really need to
do this do you really need to make
Matrix Vector multipliers to do neural
network processing uh I mean intuitively
the answer should be no like I don't
think what's going on inside here is a a
high Precision metric Vector multiplier
um
but uh can we can we try show this with
a sort of less exotic Hardware than the
human
brain so what we're really going to do
is say okay currently the the mode
people work in is they run some python
where they call reu on a matrix Vector
multiplication and that gets compiled
all the way down we're going to see if
we can instead start with some hardware
and build up to it performing uh neural
network
inference and let's not take something
that like almost does a matrix Vector
multiplication just a little bit off
let's really see if we sort of make no
effort at all to make the physical
Hardware perform something that we we
recognize as being like a neural network
computation and see if we can
succeed so uh the the the training in uh
in deep learning or deep learning is
really just about training these
controllable functions so if I'm trying
to classify this mless handr digit 8
here we're really just about trying to
pick parameter values uh Theta 1 Theta 2
theta 3 where each of these are vectors
uh that such that when you put it at
eight you get out the classification so
it's just about tuning the tuning the
parameters so that it makes the correct
prediction another observation you can
make is that every physical system or
almost every physical system uh really
is you can also think about as
performing a controllable function so
the quantum.tv is broken and over here
there should be a gray box for those of
you on Zoom you will see it but for
those of you in the room the the gray
box is invisible but imagine there's a
gray box here that represents a physical
system and if you have some control over
what the how the physical system behaves
you have some things you can control
about it and then you can there's things
you can measure about the system you can
think about this the undergoing time
dynamics of some physical system is just
having the physical system perform a
function computer function Fe you it
takes in some input and it performs some
function according to its Dynamics you
can kind of arbitrarily split the things
you can control about the system into
what we might call the data input data
and what we might call parameters this
is a sort of arbitrary distinction that
you're allowed to make uh and so you can
then think about any physical system is
really performing controllable or
trainable functions for
you so what's an example of a physical
system that performs some uh some
physical function for us and then
controllable function well this is a
somewhat exotic example uh constructed
in Optics but maybe uh a strong benefit
of it is it clearly doesn't look like
sort of conventional neural network
Hardware we have at the heart a
nonlinear Crystal that will perform some
frequency generation and since this
isn't an optic seminar uh I won't go
into great detail about the optical
physics that happens here but suffice to
say essentially you can think about this
box as uh being able to take sort of two
photons and add their wavelength and you
get out a photon of a of a of a higher
energy oh sorry add their energies and
you get out a photon of a higher energy
and we we're using this in the uh a
setting where we we shape the spectrum
of the pulse that that gets sent into
this uh nonlinear Crystal with a pulse
shaper and then we measure the Spectrum
out with a a
spectrometer so if I feed
in uh a light with uh frequency Omega 1
what comes out is light at two at two
times Omega
1 if I send in light at Omega 2 then we
get light out at two Omega 2 because you
just added two Omega 2 photons together
and if you put in light of two different
wavelengths you get this sum coming out
of Omega 1 plus Omega
2 now we can imagine uh putting in an
input Spectrum that's a bit more
complicated than just one or two single
frequencies that it has this spectrum
here and we can look at what we get
out and uh you can see that what you get
out is actually at least a non-trivial
by ey mapping of the
input and you could think about dividing
some part of this this spectrum on the
left that you input and being you can
denote some part of it like this part
that's stepping that's increasing in the
animation as the part that's going to
control what function this thing
realizes uh so you could now really
think about this Optical system as
realizing a controllable function of
your uh your input your input
light so the next uh or the the kind of
the key idea then is given that physical
systems realize uh controllable function
fun for you is you can then take uh your
standard sort of neural network diagram
and think well what happens if you take
this block this layer of the neural
network and replace it with a physical
system that performs a that computes a
physical function for
you and in fact you could do the same
thing or on a deep Network you could
take sort of each layer and replace it
with imagine there are gray boxes where
there are holes here um with copies of
this physical
system uh and each one can have
different uh trainable parameters and
this thing will then realize some
complex trainable physical
calculation so we did this with a with
this nonlinear Optical setup that I
showed you in a few slides ago where
well we didn't copy the entire setup
five times but we used it five times in
a in a in a sort of a Time multiplexing
fashion where again the the gray boxes
here are missing but imagine each of
these gray boxes is a Cy of this
conceptually a copy of this frequency
conversion
setup and then each layer is going to
have different set of parameters and
what we chose to be the parameters was
the left hand part of the spectrum so we
just declared we can arbitrarily do it
declared that the left hand part of the
spectrum those are going to be the
tunable parameters and then the right
hand part of the spectrum is going to be
uh the the input data that of what we're
trying to classify and we did a a
demonstration of this for classifying
spoken vowels that have been then
encoded in what the people in this
community called forant
frequencies and the idea is that at the
end of sending this uh this signal
through the network if we look at the
Spectrum the the part of the spectrum
that is the highest intensity will that
will encode which vow uh it's been
classified
as so the key part of this then is how
do we train this how do we figure out
what uh parameters so what Val values of
the spectrum we should put in at each
layer of the
network and uh the sort of key two key
ideas for how to do this was first let's
use a differentiable digital model of
the system in training so a laptop is
going to be involved in training not an
inference but in training uh so that you
can perform gradient descent using
backprop which is sort of a great
algorithm for training these things for
uh kind of we know all reasons we know
in love especially the fact that in a
single pass you get back a gradient so
get back all of the the derivative with
respect to every parameter in a single
pass and where the the second key idea
to make this work is really you don't
want to do everything in the laptop you
only want to do half the work in the
laptop you want to do backward passes in
uh the laptop and you want to actually
use your physical Hardware to make uh
predictions that are going to be used to
compute your loss function so let's see
if I can get out of the pointer mode and
play a little video um
and
then move this where's my
pointer there we go
and so we'll see this now we have some
choice of parameters and data we send it
through the physical system we get an
answer that's not quite correct so we
were supposed to be classifying this as
an eight and it was it was not uh we get
an we compute an error so how far off
was the prediction you send that error
through the Digital model on your laptop
and it computes gradient and now you can
update your parameters and then sort of
repeat this in a
cycle all
right so when we do this uh sorry let me
get my get my mouse pointed
back so when we do this uh as a function
of epoch so how many times we've been
through the training data set uh we can
look at the accuracy of classifying the
vowels which was the task we were trying
to do and we can see in the blue line
that as you as you go through the
training St you manage to get up to 93%
accuracy doing it in this way so this
works uh the black line is what we got
the first time we tried this uh when we
didn't do it in this uh sort of hybrid
manner of forward pass through physical
system backward pass through Digital
model where we only did the training in
a laptop so forward pass and backward
pass both through a digital model uh and
it doesn't work well at all uh and the
reason for this is that our physical our
model of the dynamics of the physical
Hardware is a little bit inaccurate
because modeling analog systems with qu
like great quantitative accuracy is
really difficult uh so that that doesn't
work well but once you once you
introduce the sort of hybrid scheme then
it works really well and the intuition
there is so long as your differentiable
Digital model is accurate enough that it
gives you the sides of the gradient
correctly then you at least make
progress and you move in the correct
direction so we also did this uh we also
tested this algorithm for for training
on a few different physical systems and
with a the task of handwritten digit
recognition which is a little bit more
difficult than vowels um we managed to
do it with a a mechanical setup of a a
piece of metal that was shaken which is
also kind of a weird physical setting
question so I assume that uh going from
the air to actually updating the
parameters is not trivial is that
correct um it's it wouldn't be trivial
if somebody hadn't already written pie
torch for us but uh we are literally
building building or standing on the
shoulders of giants and so we can
literally uh use all the Machinery of
back propop in something like P torch uh
to do that for us so we compute the loss
function so this error and then uh and
then we need this different the thing
that's not in P torch by default is what
is the differentiable Digital model of
our physical system that we had to come
up with ourselves but once we have that
uh then we can sort of chug through and
I think this would indeed have been like
a couple of years effort in the I don't
know maybe early 90s but uh now it's now
it's easy
question the input
parameters input parameters are they one
for one looks like half of your spectrum
or what it is is your weights and the
other half of is your input parameters
are you able to just set the input
parameters one to one once you've
completed the training or do they also
need like a slight
mapping right um essentially the answer
is they map one to one I mean there's a
there's like an implicit thing going on
though of like how do we set that part
of the spectrum it's like well we get to
update uh values in a lookup table for a
spatial light modulator and those are
really the things we're changing and so
it's like we're not directly changing
the Spectrum we're we're we're changing
the the thing we can control of the
electronic device that changes the
Spectrum uh but yeah there's no like
extra trained thing to go from trained
param the inference
parameters thank
you thank you uh do you also have uh
many many different layers and each
layer is the same crystal but with the
different shaper and output ah great
question yes so the short answer is yes
we have many many layers both in
inference and in training and in
training just so that I didn't have to
draw this thing with many layers uh I
already showed one but it extends
naturally uh also great great thanks to
pytorch um so yeah we're do this uh this
vows example we're doing with five
layers and then some of the other
examples I show we had slightly
different architectures with varying
numbers of layers but uh all of them
with more than one I see so for each
reference or inference then um for each
layer when it propagates to the next
layer um how do you I guess how do you
implement it so that it's not blocked by
you know the manual tuning speed of a
grad student ah right so it's uh it's
not locked by the manual tuning speed of
a grad student but it is currently
bottom neck by something else which is
also not desirable we'd like to get
Beyond it which is uh in this Optical
setup for example we we measure at the
spectrometer but then how does that get
fed to the next layer it's like well
it's now an Electronics it's in some
laptop and then we feeded into the sort
of data for the pulse shaper for the
next round so there's some limit on the
througho of the system of like how
quickly can we take the output of a
spectrometer and feed it into the pulse
shape before encoding the data for the
next Set uh which we'd like to get rid
of but uh it's a yeah limitation of the
current sort of Paradigm so I think as
we we think about sort of incidentally
none of the examples I'm going to show
you what I'm saying you should build
Ural Network like these were more sort
of chosen as extreme examples of like
you can do it this way um we we' like to
think about sort of how do we get rid of
these bottlenecks but fortunately it was
not limited by how quickly somebody can
type on a laptop or anything like
that uh so the function fop M uh needs
to have certain mathematical properties
I'm not sure I you know they need to be
they need to they need to do some kind
of integration um and it looks like you
do that here because you're converting
things to
Spectra um but can you perhaps go into
just um have you characterized the kinds
of functions that are even that that
that are possible by some of the
physical means because I I don't see how
you know not everything's going to do
this right not every every physical
system is going to nicely behave like
this right right yeah it's a great
question so sort of P the answer is uh I
told you that pretty much every
controllable physical system can be used
to do neural network inference I didn't
promise you that it would be good uh or
good at it so which is maybe a little
glib but it's actually pretty close to
the truth uh it's just like pretty much
any neural network architecture you
could come up with in a neural Network's
101 class as a homework exercise will
act as a neural network to some extent
but whether it's good or not well that's
that's an art um so that's part of it is
figuring out what and it's and it's task
dependent some some architectures are
good for some tasks and not for others
uh so that's part of the story is
finding physical Hardware that matches
the task well and does have the
sufficient sort of complexity but I
think there's a really sort of even
deeper thing that's really interesting
there which is physical systems we can
think about what mathematical function
they Implement just from sort of
analyzing from a physics perspective and
often when you're doing things you'll
naturally see a convolution arises in
how the inputs and outputs are connected
um and you can have some intuition from
the computer sign side that well
convolutions get used in for example
image processing in the earlier layers
so A system that naturally performs
convolutions might be good for that um
but we also know that sort of Highly
connected systems are good so if you
give me some system that are very
sparsely connected components that's
probably not going to be very good for
most tasks you want something that with
with sort of all of the internal
elements then neurons if you will sort
of speak with each other a lot but also
that that that Pro that connectivity is
programmable and we're still just
beginning to learn sort of what
intuitions can we take and then how do
we realize them in different physical
systems
all right great so uh I wanted to give
another couple of examples of uh demos
we did with this but I I also want to
move on to talking about things that are
sort of less toy examples than these
ones so just going through relatively
quickly we did an example with mechanics
which was also picked not because I
think you should make your neural
networks and replace gpus with with
mechanics but because it's an example of
something that you would niely maybe not
expect to able to do handwritten digit
recognition and yet is able to succeed
at least to the level of about 90%
accuracy so this is literally we have a
a piece of metal that we shake with an
audio speaker we listen to it with a
microphone that's sitting up there uh we
also did one with the the world's
simplest analog electronic neural
network it's an RLC oscillator we added
one transistor again for the intuition
from CS that neural nonlinearity is very
important in giving sort of power to
neural networks U and this does a little
bit better and then we also did a demo
with the Optics setup that I already
showed
you so uh something that uh sort of
naturally comes up with this is like
well okay you first of all you did some
toy demos uh can you do better than you
did if you get more sophisticated
hardware and then how tolerant is this
whole thing to sort of variations from
hardware and and mismatch between the
model you use in the in the in the
training and the actual the actual
inference so we we did some simulations
with a a prototypical model of coupled
oscillators with a thousand oscillators
which is larger than the hardware we had
but it's something that sort of shows
how does the scale and for an easy task
of IM 10 digit classification we can
then get to state-of-the-art accuracy
with a a network of a thousand
oscillators this is now solving the the
the memus task a completely different
way than a sort of neural networks 101
would do it but it's also possible in
this sort of weird Paradigm of like
connected coupled oscillators
um we also uh tried a more difficult
task which by ml standards is not
actually hard it's just hard for us in
this this sort of nent community uh of
fashion imess which is a variation of
image recognition of of garments like is
it a t-shirt or is it trousers or
whatever um and we were able to show
that we can train these uh network of
thousand oscillators or thousand is
oscillators to perform mest handwritten
mest fashion uh recognition uh accurate
L but then we can also sort of see how
do we if we make our model and our
simulated Hardware mismatch how much can
we tolerate and it turns out that with
this sort of physics aware training type
approach you can tolerate a mismatch of
up to 70% difference in the parameters
of the model versus the actual hardware
and it's still have it perform inference
at a almost state-of-the-art level U and
similarly you can train it to be a in a
way that it's resilient to variations
from device to device so you get a new
device off the production line it's up
to let's say the parameters of the
components are 10% different from the
ones you trained on uh so long as you've
trained it in this style uh if you just
transfer the parameters to the new
device you'll get almost the same
accuracy so 87.5 versus
88.9 so the main kind of things we take
away from all this this work so far is
that we can make functioning neural
networks out of physical Hardware
without forcing the hardware to do sort
of very specific mathematical operations
we've given a training procedure I want
say that it's only training procedure or
the best training procedure but it's a
way uh that we were able to train these
things and the system doesn't need to be
Noise free to work well given that I
showed you experimental results that
took place in a real lab uh that's
hopefully convincing and we of course
also have the simulations that sort of
back up about how that works as it
scales U and yeah you can work with
pretty imperfectly calibrated hardware
and uh this transfer is possible so this
sort of covers well it's feasible to do
this it's General across a a fairly wide
variety of devices the training is
efficient because we use backr and uh
these things look like they could be
then manufacturable because you can
tolerate these
variations so now I want to tell you
about some work we've done over the last
year or two uh that recently came out as
a pre-print that is on a specific
photonic realization um where we look to
scale up uh photonic neural network
onchip photonic neural networks using
this sort of style of of thinking about
things
so uh many of you may know already uh
there's a large effort at onchip phonic
neural networks that was really
pioneered here this is this paper is
from Durk England and Marine solutes
groups uh from seven years ago now where
they performed a matrix Vector
multiplication on an in input Vector
with of Dimension four to an output D
Vector of Dimension four using an array
of Max Ender
interferometers and in the sort of
intervening seven years people have been
pushing the scale of this but they found
it really really difficult uh so if we
look at the state-ofthe-art and input
Vector Dimension and output Vector
Dimension this original work was there
and sort of some people have managed to
push up a little bit and push a little
bit on the side um but it's nowhere near
as big as we would like and no one ever
shows you a plot like that without you
know sooner or later in the presentation
we're going to fill up we're going to
fill in a new point in this in this
plane
somewhere uh and we really tried to be
fair in this plot though this is
including many of the sort of most or as
far as we know all of the M the main
recent results in this
field so we'd like to scale these but
it's proven really difficult and part of
part of there's many reasons for it part
of something to notice here is the scale
bar that the these these mzi devices are
not that small 60 microns in the scale
by there so a really interesting idea
was proposed in 2019 uh from sham FS
group at Stanford and one of his former
students Z for you at at Wisconsin they
both simultaneously proposed this idea
of If instead of we make a mesh of mzis
or a crossb phase change memories or one
of the many other approaches people have
taken to building onchip neural networks
what happens if you give me a slab of
material and you just let me program the
refractive index of it arbitrarily uh
you'll get these sort of very weird
patterns that control the light in weird
ways but you can train it to do
inference it was a really fascinating
idea but they left open a major question
which is they showed that in simulation
this will work but they didn't say how
you you could make it device who
refective in you can control is a
function of
space um so how can you do that how can
you make a device that's like a slab
wave guide shown here where you can
control uh this uh this map of
refractive index and that's what we said
out to do so uh we we recently yeah
worked on this and did an experimental
demonstration where we we at least
provide our solution to this problem
there are other people working on it as
well but our solution is as following so
we start with the Silicon substrate and
we add a slab wave guide oh we're going
to go back to like having missing boxes
again which should be interesting but
the most important part here is the red
bit uh which is a slab lithium Nate wave
guide surrounded by cladding so that's
where the light is going to that we're
we're trying to do computation on is
going to propagate and then we're going
to add a big chunk of photoconductor on
top of that and then an electrode and
we're want the electrode because we're
going to bias this with the
voltage and why does this let us control
refractive index of this red wave guide
as a function of
space uh essentially the answer is we're
going to use the electrooptic effect in
the lithium nabate but in a slightly
weird way that if we look at a patch of
this uh uh of this device and we sort of
yeah go down taking a cross-section of
it what we see is that effectively we
have a circuit model where we have some
uh resistance or really it's impedance
but you can think about it resistance of
the photoconductor and the resistance of
the uh the wave guide and so this a
resistive divider effect for this bias
voltage that's put on about half the
voltage is going to drop over the
photoconductor and half of it is going
to drop over the over the uh the lithium
dibate wave guide which we will Define
as that having no refractive index
contrast now you just sort of get this
extra phase shift everywhere in the in
the wave
guide now imagine you shine light onto
this wave guide from above with a
pattern and this pattern is going to be
directly transduced into a refractive
index pattern in the way it works is
that wherever you have like for example
this region here that we've sort of done
this inset to we wherever you have light
the photoconductor will absorb the light
by definition it will increase its
conductance or reduce its
resistance and now your resistive
divider will have a smaller resistor for
the photoconductor part and so you'll
drop more of the voltage over the uh the
wave guide and through the electrooptic
effect you will now induce a phase shift
at that part of the the wave guide um
in the in the work that we're presenting
we've achieved a refractive index
contrast of 10 Theus 3 we think it
should be possible to push this to 10us
2 this is enough that we can do an
experiment like this where we shine the
Pat this is literally a pattern that we
shine like an image onto the top of our
chip uh and we pattern we pattern this
sort of pattern of this Fork shape and
we send in a beam in the middle and what
we see comes out we come out this is
experimental data uh we see two beams
coming out so this is showing that you
can effectively make like a beam
splitter device uh in this way so this
is showing that the the the physical
mechanism is working uh this shows a a
picture of our our chip and we're
shining this pattern from above you can
see sort of the pattern here it's like
below ey resolution but you can see the
green light at least so the green the
green light is what we're sending under
the photoconductor then we have infrared
light coming in and out is the light
that the computation is being performed
on you can imagine using this platform
not just to make beam split
or other programmable circuits which is
indeed something you could do but you
could use it to perform machine learning
in the same sort of sense as the mzi
array chips where uh we're now going to
have this pattern that is going to
encode our parameters of our neural
network and we're going to perform a
gradient descent update of those
parameters using the physics aware
training sort of hybrid Loop that I
showed you in the last section uh so you
could imagine encoding an image into the
input Vector you have to do some sort of
unfolding to get it into one D and then
uh trade it so that when you look get it
get the output that it's sort of peaked
at uh at two because you put in an image
of two uh and this is really happening
through this physics of wave propagation
through the wave guide uh where the the
uh the the sort of refractive index
modulations are the things that are
changing how the the waves from
different uh input digits are being
changed uh so if you put in a different
digit you should get a different pattern
of of wave propagation coming out
so we we tested this on amest hand and
digits uh with a variation so not the
full size images but 7 by seven down
samplings which makes the task harder
it's more difficult to identify the
image when you when you shrink it um and
we feed it into the system by just sort
of reshaping this array to 1D so it's a
49 dimensional input and a 10
dimensional output because we're just
trying to classify a single layer uh
what we what image we we had and we
achieved an accuracy in experiment of
86% and that puts us over here so we're
not anywhere near what a GPU could do
not by many many orders of magnitude um
but we've really managed to push uh
where these how big the the computation
is that the onip platform can do in
these spatially multiplexed examples U
and this is really in large part enabled
by the fact that we sort of got rid of
the abstraction of these disc components
and just directly program the
physics so yeah so what what sort of
principles are this that we did we use
in this example well we didn't insist on
exactly performing a very specific
Matrix Vector multiplication we just
sort of trained on the parameters that
we could control um we are doing
inmemory compute the the parameters are
sort of sitting in the wave guide so to
speak um and it's it's using an
alternative hydrid it's using photonics
and we trained on a specific device so
uh we're tolerant to the fact that the
devices that come out of our key room
that the the student in postto who built
this make is a little different each
time but that's okay we have a training
procedure that can that can handle
that so now in the last let's say five
minutes or so I'd like to talk about
some prospects for where I see this uh
General field so to speak going um the
main things I'd like to touch on are uh
a near-term applications so clearly
Building A system that can beat a GP pu
at doing running chat GPT is extremely
difficult and we're not going to do that
anytime soon uh so what can we do in the
inters I think smart senses are a really
good answer to that I'll also talk a
little bit about uh how we might imagine
building large scale neural network
accelerators that uh connects with the
the Nano theme of this this seminar and
then I'll say a couple of words about
possible extensions to to Quantum neural
networks so smart sensors of this notion
of you can have a sensor that is
integrated with the neural nwor that
sort of pre-processes the data and this
kind of physics based or physical
Computing Paradigm is very well suited
to this because you may have many
different things that you're trying to
sense that are not electronic they could
be photons I.E Optics they could be sort
of acoustic waves or mechanical forces
Etc and a natural Paradigm for
pre-processing this is first make an
invisible gray box that has a physical
system that is the same like modality as
this so if it's photons and you should
have some Optical system that
pre-processes to extract the relevant
information before you transduce
digitize and then do further
processing and as one example of this we
recently well not recently I guess the
paper came out about a year ago now uh
did an example where we uh used a two-
layer Optical neural network to extract
the relevant features of a 3D printed
scene where we have a traffic sign and
we're trying to extract what is the
speed limit on that sign you don't care
about all the sort of great details of
this image you just care about what are
the numbers on this side and we were
able to achieve a compression RTI of 400
to1 where you can digitize just four
pixels and are then able to accurately
classify what the speed limit is uh so
this is an example of sort of doing this
pre-processing you're not doing the full
thing in the physical system but you're
greatly reducing the bandwidth that you
have to digitize uh and and postprocess
uh by doing this sort of pre-processing
in the analog
domain you could imagine playing the
same game with u with microwaves it's
not specific to Optics and that's
something we're we're working on with a
mixed signal CS group where sort of
heris you can think about like wideband
radar having 100 gz of bandwidth it's a
little bit weird that you have to
digitize 200 gigas samples a second in
order to tell a very few number of bits
so like What airplane is it and how fast
is it moving um it feels like a natural
place where you can sort of benefit from
from trying to pre-process in the analog
domain we're also really interested in
even though it's really difficult how
you can make uh analog electronic neural
network processes that might ultimately
actually be able to beat gpus at at at
running chat GPT it's really really
challenging but we're inspired by the
fact that the human brain has a vastly
larger number of neurons and parameters
parameters synapses than artificial
neural networks and yet only uses 12
wats of power so it feels like in
principle
there's we should be able to do much
better than we're currently doing now
and so there's a bunch of strategies you
can take um many of which are not kind
of unique to us people have been
thinking about these for for a long time
of like lower the voltage operated
analog U you can think about tolerating
noisy components maybe using exotic
Hardware Etc something that I think is
actually an idea that uh that is really
interesting uh but that is something
that people have kind of uh ignored
until ignored for a long time is the
notion that you can you don't need
updatable memory anymore and this is
something that's a bit new in The Last 5
Years uh five years ago if you wanted
neural network accelerator is almost by
definition that you must be able to
change what neural network it
runs um because you want your your chip
to be able to do many different things
but uh this has changed now that we have
what people are often calling Foundation
models things like GPT where it's
trained on the entirety of the internet
and open AI brings out a new GPT model
only every one to two years and that
model can do many different tasks and
you can sort of post tweak to do many
different tasks it's maybe not so stupid
to think about can you or should you
make a neural network accelerator that's
sort of printed it's like a CD R you
print it that has the latest model on it
and you use it for a year or two and
then you throw it out and you buy a new
one uh the next model comes out and if
you do that uh if you don't need uh
programmable memory anymore that is
greatly reducing a constraint on your
engineering so you can maybe uh get
large factors of of of benefited both
speeded energy by by having sort of
printed prefabricated neural networks so
a couple of ideas for sort of just
concepts of how one might benefit from
this idea one is people have built these
crossbar arrays where they use memorist
of devices uh but the transistors that
you use to drive the currents to uh to
update the weights are actually pretty
large and so the unit cell sizes are
pretty large and people are also
insisting that this thing do exactly a
matrix Vector
multiplication you can maybe relax both
those assumptions and then shrink the
unit cell size and uh there's probably
potential for sort of a few orders of
magnitude win from doing that another
kind of even more exotic idea is to
maybe try and make some uh some Nano
electronic material where you patn the
the material uh in in 3D or 2D space uh
and if you just sort of do a counting
argument of like if how many voxels you
have when you patent the conductivity of
a 2d 3D material versus some sort of
reasonable size of it um you can imagine
really getting a very very large number
of parameters uh embedded in your your
system but they're fixed uh but that may
be okay uh so one uh one concrete idea
for how to maybe try something like this
in the near term is Imagine taking a
slab of silicon and then patterning the
the P andn type dopet uh in a completely
programmable way and if this diagram
looks a little bit familiar
we were inspired to do this by the work
at the photonic side like can we take
the photonic reprogrammable refractive
index idea and do the same kind of thing
in Nano Electronics I think the answer
is yes I'm a new postto who will be
starting working on this in a couple of
months and uh so sort of check back in
this space in a couple of years and
we'll see if we see if we succeed it but
I'm really really excited about this
direction I think there's lots of
different ways you could try Do
It um I will say epsilon about Quantum
neural networks which is a very natural
thought for at least someone from my
background or I came from the quantum
Optics background is or Quantum
information background is can you play
the same game with Quantum physical
systems I've everything I've told you
about so far are classical but uh we
have the same story in quantumness of
people are thinking about sort of many
layers of abstraction to build up fa
tolerance and Universal Quantum
Computing but if you want to get sort of
wins in the near term maybe it makes
sense to uh play this game of try to do
the same thing we've done tastico like
replace the physical system with maybe
some dissipative maybe poorly calibrated
Quantum system and then uh and then try
train it in this way and maybe there's
an interesting question of like well
what should the equivalent of the laptop
be for training a Quantum system in this
way maybe it should be a standard
circuit model quantum computer uh maybe
it can be some sort of like
approximation of the Dynamics with like
some tenso Network approximation uh
we're still busy figuring this out this
is something we're actively working on
primarily in the super conducting
circuits domain
so that uh I should acknowledge the the
group and everybody who did the work as
well as the people who are funding uh
funding this work and I will leave you
with uh some thoughts of uh yeah we've
we've shown that you can make physical
neural networks and harness the natural
dynamics of many systems uh in our
onchip photonic neural network scheme
we've sort of proposed this new way to
make a programmable refractive index is
a function of space and this is seems to
be an interesting way to sort of push
the scaling of these uh onchip deves and
then uh sort of thinking towards the
future I think in sensor or smart sensor
processing is a really promising
near-term application but uh photonic
neural networks and Nano electronic
neural networks should be competitive if
you can make them large enough and so
big challeng is how are we going to
really be able to scale this um and uh
that's something I'm looking forward to
working on in the for the next the next
few years I think it should keep us busy
so thank you all so much for your
attention thank you for the questions
that we've already had and I look
forward to more questions and more
discussion after the uh uh after the
formal end of the
[Applause]
talk okay we'll take a few questions but
just a reminder there is going to be a
reception right after so uh for now
we'll take a couple questions hey Peter
thanks for the great talk so I I find
the need for the differential Digital
model to be like I don't know it's just
kind of unsatisfying so I'm wondering if
there's a way you can use the physics of
the system to get that differentiability
like using Loren's reciprocity in the
response to perturbation I don't know
just be interested in that it it
disturbs us too we would really like to
get rid of the laptop because for one
thing it means that we have no chance of
getting a like a speed or energy boost
in training and we would like to be able
to do that
um so there's a bunch of people thinking
about a bunch of different ways and in
in the Optics case Alex lovi's group at
Oxford for example has this interesting
proposal of for a very specific setting
if they send the light through in one
way it does the forward pass then they
can compute the eror and if they
literally send it backwards they can
engine excuse me they can engineer it so
that you get gradients but it's a very
specific setting and like the largest
demo they've managed to do is I think
like something like with three two
layers of three neurons or something
like this so it's really yeah it's
really hard the engineer is difficult
but it would be really nice if you could
make something like that but
generalizable and tolerant to to
variations uh Flor and marads had a few
really interesting ideas in this this
space as well uh yosu beno's group
brought out this notion of something
called equilibrium propagation for any
system that equilibri their their Theory
roughly holds um and that's also sort of
a local rule where you don't have to run
backrop on a laptop so there's a bunch
of ideas but nobody's yet sort of
stumbled upon like the one thing that's
clearly going to be the winner uh our P
method I I literally described it as
like it's a way to do it I'm certainly
wouldn't say it's the best or the end I
hope it's not the end great thank you
you thanks for the talk P um it's hard
not to listen and wonder about
applications in control so maybe you
could comment a little bit on that right
yeah uh I think uh there's this sort of
nice merger of uh sort of control
traditional control community and
reinforcement learning community and
this kind of stuff naturally plays in
with that because okay once you allow
yourself to do reinforcement learning
you can naturally imagine a physical
controller doing the reinforcement
learning um and this feels really
interesting for sort of very small scale
systems where you're very constrained in
the amount of power you have that said I
I dug into it a little bit in the case
of sort of micro robots because I had
the same thought I was like ah maybe
these people who are building sort of
really tiny robots could use this but it
seems really challenging because they
can already get the Coss processes that
do the control
down to like an amazingly small size and
power budget and so after speaking to a
few of them for a little bit I I I
became a little bit less optimistic that
there's like an easy win there but it
really does feel like ultimately you
should be able to benefit um it's just
yeah already the seos has already gone
there once that's happened it gets
really difficult to
win yeah and again very nice talk um
sort of coming from a similar space uh
with the sort of precompression
algorithms that you guys are
implementing
physically uh do you guys foresee those
needing to be reprogrammable I mean how
do you decide and especially like an
autonomous system if you're if you're
trying to pre-c compress sensor data uh
along which Dimensions to compress and
when those scenarios are appropriate and
then how do you then in turn you know
keep your system from being too
generalized you know how does this sort
of adaptability between very compressed
and not compressed at all come in right
right yeah so I think the the way we
think about it is largely like take any
like for example Machine Vision system
that is already using deep learning to
make inferences from the images this is
a natural setting to immediately do that
how generalized it should be it's like
well how how generalized are they
currently doing it what is they how wide
is their training data set so so to
speak you can just do literally exactly
the same thing but now you're going to
reduce a bottleneck in the middle if you
want to go to new applications where
people aren't already doing Machine
Vision with deep neural networks then
you have much more thinking to do but
it's not really thinking that's specific
to our way of doing stuff it's the same
questions you always ask when you say is
it okay to use machine learning to do x
uh and when should how like how much
training data you need how much do you
need to update it how like how often you
need to refresh it it's that's true of
anyone even doing it the conventional
way a just gets rid of the
bottleneck uh thanks for a nice talk um
so uh for restricted baltim machines
there is this kind of uh uh bipar type
connectivity that my understanding is
they use to be able to use back
propagation uh and kind of training do
you have similar restrictions on both
kind of the physical systems again I
guess this is another way of asking the
same question that's been asked a couple
times already or uh uh kind of uh yeah
physical systems or training um
mechanisms that you would use to uh to
enable this back propagation training
for your system like are classes of
systems that work better or worse than
others the key thing for us for
trainability is really how good is our
differentiable Digital model so you
don't need to like necessarily restrict
the system to be in yeah like taking on
some bipar at graph like an RB M but
uh you it's a pretty general statement
that like you want your model to be good
enough that the gradients have the
correct sign and certainly you can
imagine some constraints on the hardware
to let it not go into regimes that are
too hard to model so that's one
constraint like for example I'll sort of
thumb suck exam thumb suck an example
it's not like a real example but like
imagine in our 2D wave guide stuff that
if we pumped so hard that the lithium
nabate started doing frequency
conversion now our model of the wave
propagation if we didn't model that part
would would be off and so things
wouldn't work well so You' be like well
you should restrict yourself to lower
enough powers that that doesn't happen
um is yeah an example but uh it's
there's many settings in which it helps
you at least to be a little bit
constrained so that your model is good
thank
you thanks for the talk um I I had a
question about um kind of how many
layers you can embed Within These
physical systems I think most of the
examples you showed there's kind of only
one set of weights and one physical
system that you're tuning have you tried
sending
um uh your model through like multiple
sets of physical systems and do you see
any change to your output there right
right so this one the first set of
examples I showed of uh vowel
classification was actually with I think
a five layer neural network um so we had
five conceptually copies of the
nonlinear Optical Crystal like in
practice we actually the lasers are
expensive so we only had one and we send
it through we measure the data then we
send through another and another we like
Multiplex it in time but uh certainly
what's happening from a computation
perspective is a deep a deep computation
as you go through these five
layers um and yeah in some it depends on
the example like in the sensing example
that I I mean I told you only for about
30 seconds but there were two uh there
were two layers uh in the uh
reprogrammable wave gu we actually only
did one layer not because we couldn't do
two or five or more layers um but uh
because we wanted to demonstrate that
even with just one layer we can actually
get close to the sort of theoretical
maximum for a for a linear a linear
classification thank
maybe one last question and then we'll
open it to the
reception hi thank you for the
interesting talk um I'm curious in the
physical neural network examples you
give uh you still kind of keep this
layerwise structure whereas I guess if
you have some parameterizable physical
system um you should be able to just
tune those parameters themselves without
the use for layers like layers doesn't
feel like a fundamental design Choice uh
I'm curious what are your thoughts on I
guess maybe that's like an optimization
problem or generally like how learning
could or should work alternatives to
back propop that sort of thing right
right yeah that's a great question so
uh one sufficiently complex physical
system should be able to realize
something that is effectively a deep
computation so in principle I should
have been able to give all my examples
with just one physical system I
shouldn't need
multiple but uh
it it yeah engineering one system that
does the sort of the whole thing you
want is actually kind of challenging it
goes back to the question that we were
talking about a little earlier of like
how what does the physical system need
to be able to do if you want it to do I
don't know maybe it's a getting a little
too close to like following exactly what
CS people do but uh like a convolutional
neural lay with convolutional layers
followed by fully connected layers if
you want if you want one system that
does sort of everything you can imagine
that it's pretty natural to actually
have two different ones that each sort
of do the different part better rather
than trying to engineer this one that in
principle you could make but what
physical system is that uh that said
this uh this kind of idea uh here I'm
kind of optimistic that actually if you
give me a big enough piece of silicon
like you can actually get this thing to
learn the whole thing all at once it's
probably going to be a really hot
trading problem though
okay great so let's thank Peter again
for a great talk thank you
very and thank you all for joining
there's going to be a reception so
please stay back Peter will also be here
so you can chat