Thank you. Um, and again, I'd like to
express a heartfelt thanks to all of
today's speakers, and to all of you who
joined us for a thoughtful and
energizing discussion today. We heard
from researchers, an entrepreneur, an
industry leader, all of whom are
tackling the challenges of employee
wellness and resilience from different
angles, but with a shared goal, helping
people thrive in a world that's changing
fast. If you'd like to learn more about
the work happening at the MIT Health
Systems Initiative or explore ways to
collaborate, they'd be glad to hear from
you.
You can look them up at hsi.mmit.edu.
And if your company isn't yet a member
of the MIT industrial liaison program,
we encourage you to check us out at
illep.mmit.edu.
ILP members get curated access to MIT's
faculty research and startup ecosystem,
plus invitations to in events like this
one. Feel free to contact us at
asky-enilpit.edu.
We'd love to continue the conversation.
This concludes our webinar. Thanks again
for joining us today and we look forward
to seeing you at future sessions.