[Music]
Um, I also want to hide the Morisae, but the
stained taxes, I
want to hide, but it looks bright, my clouds, the night I want to avoid,
tomorrow, my
friend, sitting in an empty room, with the
TV
on, I can't see, I'm old
[Music]
That day, your song, a night that doesn't make you happy, I
turn off the music in an empty room [Music] My heart that has been sitting, my heart that has been expended, oh, my cute, can't be built, I keep flowing inside my person, only I know, someone wants to hang a bow, but there's no hanger, and on a night when there's no hanger, sitting in an empty room, am I all messed up? I can't
feel anything,
what's the point?
My
heart that I couldn't find, my abandoned heart, my
broken
heart, oh,
long hair
[Applause]
guys
[Music]