my name is Patty mass and I'm a faculty
member at the MIT media laboratory and
my work lies at the intersection of
artificial intelligence human computer
interaction and um basically psychology
so I studied um artificial intelligence
and computer science over 30 years ago
back in Brussels Belgium and of course
um the uh MIT AI lab as it was called
back then was really the mecca where
people uh would want to be if you did uh
AI research so soon after getting my PhD
I uh went to the AI lab to become a
postto there and then after that I
became a visiting Professor actually for
a year and yeah was just super excited
to be working with all these uh Founders
in the field field and really these
seminal figures people like Marvin
Minsky Pat Winston uh Rodney Brooks and
others so after being at MIT for 2 years
at uh the AI lab again uh right now it's
called seale actually um I decided to
move to the media laboratory because I
uh was more interested in helping people
with uh being smarter and being better
off rather than trying to um model
intelligence in machines uh the media
lab is a lot more focused on sort of um
uh the human impact of emerging
Technologies and really and societal
impact and we really try to think hard
about how um emerging Technologies or
Cutting Edge Technologies like
artificial intelligence but also
wearables things like that how they
might improve uh people's lives the
reason why I uh do the work uh that I do
is that um technology plays such a huge
role in our lives um kids as young as to
start using iPads and and uh they start
learning from or via computers with
things like KH Academy scratch Etc um as
early as age 11 or 12 a lot of kids get
smartphones and before that they already
start using laptops Etc so from that
very early age on we are um surrounded
by technology and it plays such a huge
role in our lives but unfortunately a
lot of that technology that we use
smartphones apps and all of that have
not necessarily always been created with
the best interests of people in mind um
ultimately the companies that create all
of these products have a bottom line
that they have to think about and uh
right now the the whole uh business
model of advertising is still what
drives a lot of Technology development
and what um ends up uh deciding really
what types of Technologies we do
surround ourselves with so we try to ask
the opposite question what if uh these
technologies that are so present in our
lives
24x7 what if they were designed with uh
the best interests of people in mind
could technology help people uh learn
take care of their health um um develop
into the person that they ultimately
want to be can it help uh the elderly
when some of their um abilities uh
decline such as memory and so on um so
we we try to look at how these systems
could help with all of these aspects of
life