and now I am going to uh you know put
myself in the game here
proverbially and uh share a little bit
of of research that you know this is I
would say a mashup of of several
different research projects but the goal
here is to zoom out from some of uh
John's focus on Workforce challenges in
the US and then like I mentioned earlier
present a bridge between these Workforce
challenges and then some of the
technology and Innovation topics that
we're going to talk about in a moment
and I know a a global audience here so
feel free to uh offer questions and and
uh comments in the chat on any
disagreements or bones to pick with um
my characterization of of global
manufacturing many of you who live it
every day uh might see the data that I
present quite differently so um here we
go so this I want to
start by uh introducing a kind of
metaphor with manufacturing so I I think
about uh Manu ufacturing as one of the
purest forms of economic competition and
when we talk about uh tradable
Industries Industries where uh we're
producing value that is consumed
elsewhere that these are the industries
that have the biggest impact on any
Regional or even National economy these
are export driven Industries in large
part um they're they're competitive and
and I think the metaphor of a game in
which uh both employers but also nations
are competing with one another um to to
outdo and and essentially out earn the
other um we we need to kind of Define
the rules kind what is what is really
driving this competition and for a long
time the the rules of the game um
centered on people like Sam Seer and
this is this is Sam Seer he's from New
Hampshire he works at a company called
hypertherm um and and he's actually I
think a great Target for for a program
like John's where he previously had
never really seen a robot on the factory
floor a few years ago he moved into this
company that's investing a lot in
Automation and also investing a lot
internally in their training and then he
was able to get um training to to
maintain uh robots and and automated
cells and now he's a a support
technician earning more in that job and
and I think I think Sam is kind of a
nice backdrop for this discussion
because for a long time we thought the
game was a race to the bottom in terms
of of wages and labor costs that the
winners of the game would be the ones
that could offer mostly commodity
products Goods at the lowest price and I
think over time we've realized that for
some items there there might indeed be a
race to the bottom where the lowest cost
producer wins but that this isn't all of
the story that actually um some uh
countries and some employers can offer
far higher wages and offer a higher
quality product even if they can't
compete on price they can still um
compete and develop a profitable Factory
so race to the bottom isn't quite it in
in the United States given that in many
conts we we can't compete in the race to
the bottom and nor um do many American
employers want to compete we we've
pivoted to think about the game as
inventing the future as the goal of a
manufacturing economy should be to
support um new inventions and new
Innovations where the R&D side of a
business really takes the lead and the
production follows and is really in
support of new technology and
Innovations now what I think has been
challenging about this it Chris love
will talk a little bit about this in the
biospace moment is that to try to
separate invention from production or
try to uh I would say let's say
subjugate production in in The Pursuit
Of Invention this is a lot of what was
happening with the manufacturing
Innovation institutes which were focused
mostly on developing new technologies
not necessarily on improving production
techniques and and and productivity um
that you really see um Innovation suffer
if if productivity is there so a lot of
um I think really striking examples of
companies that tried to innovate in the
US and produced in China and eventually
they found more and more of their
engineering Talent going to Asia to
locate near production so it turns out
that I think invention and production go
more hand inand um s such that a game
that's really just defined by who
invents the most is an incomplete story
as well now what I found in in going
around to factories um in in the years
after covid um was this re-evaluation of
of that rule of inventing and uh an
understanding that in order to sustain a
domestic economy in order to support
needs like National Security that
countries in in many cases might need to
play their own game that they might need
to support their own needs even if it's
not cost competitive and a lot of the uh
market for defense Contracting and I'll
focus on the United States for a moment
is is motivated by that um by that where
where companies aren't interested in
competing in commercial markets and
instead are producing based on very
lucrative defense contracts and and
these companies I think are part of the
reason why John showed that we've
actually in the United States declined
in our overall productivity over the
last 10 years because there's a
motivation to produce something to spec
and often times is something very hard
to produce but not necessarily to
produce it more competitively there's
some of the same motivations in in
medical devices and and farm as well so
um so I think this playing your own game
is is okay to some degree but what the
result is is that in places like New
England where I live or in Ohio uh over
40% of uh small and medium manufacturers
have at least one defense contract so
there's a lot of Reliance on uh public
markets that are kind of insulated from
commercial pressures and not as much of
this more traditional competing to
export goods and competing to um produce
the the highest quality good at a
competitive price so what I think we've
seen in the past couple years and what I
want to focus on is is a a game that
kind of that that synthesizes some of
the um elements of each of these
previous three and I'm just going to try
to summarize it as as winning the
frontier and and what that means is that
as new technologies come about as
they're introduced so we could talk
about new nuclear technologies at MIT we
have a company that's trying to design a
new version of a a nuclear reactor um as
new Computing Technologies come out as
new battery technologies coming out
where are going to be the places that
are a developing the most advanced
versions of these Technologies and able
to produce them and that what that's
what I think winning the frontier means
is that you're able to produce these
Technologies and scale them up um in a
sort of complimentary ecosystem and and
I think why that's so important and why
it's not necessarily uh a global effort
to Wi the frontier but oftentimes a more
localized one is that we just see
clusters of manufacturing Excellence
happen when when it comes to different
products and it's very difficult to
maintain with maybe the exception of the
semiconductor supply chain to maintain a
very globally distributed uh value chain
that continues to innovate at a very
fast pace okay so so what does the
winning winning the frontier look like
what does it mean I want to give kind of
a recipe of what this means so I think
the recipe needs to start with invention
that that we we still care about the
development of new of new products of
new technologies and that's kind of the
invention outcome what are the
ingredients that go into invention you
know Don talked about um Talent that's
certainly important there's also a lot
of Technology development effort that
relies on and then there's certainly
risks so there's kind of the um the
technology Capital the risk capital and
then the human capital that all are
ingredients in this in this recipe but
as I mentioned before invention isn't
sufficient uh so let me just go into the
kind of the global Dimension here so I'm
going to focus on four different
countries and how they have been
competing in these along these different
ingredients one the United States um two
is Germany three is Japan and four is
China and then I'll I'll I'll show some
data on how um they've competed so I
imagine each of you have uh in the
audience have a sense of how these
different countries have competed but I
I'm going to um propose that that this
is the the breakdown of of competition
here is that when it comes to invention
the United States still according to
traditional data points excels at each
of these categories we have a lot of uh
risk capital in the private markets we
have pretty strong technology devel
vment coming out of um you know Advanced
Innovative companies as well as
universities we have excellent
engineering institutions in a um an
engineering Workforce and then finally
we're pretty darn good at at inventing
um new new types of Technologies as well
and then other leading manufacturing
markets typically excel in one or the
other of these Dimensions you see the
German engineering Workforce is really
uh excellent in terms of Technology
development and uh adoption Additionally
you see Japan in in South Korea is is
really excellent and then uh in terms of
risk Capital um the this the Chinese
Communist Party in the Chinese
government has offered a ton of risk
Capital to to subsidize the growth of
manufacturing firms um that's allowed
them to support some Innovative
Industries so a different type of risk
Capital but certainly um very effective
um in the short term so I'm I'm going to
start with this and I'm going to add a
few elements to the recipe here that I
think fill it out and get Beyond just
invention so if we look at at how this
invention story has evolved over time
you'll see this is just a um a plot of
manufacturing related patents so you
could think about patents that relate to
inventions that relate to the factory
floor if you were to expand this to
Computing patents or patents of of new
products in uh biologics the United
States the the pink line which is the US
would would be uh far higher but just
looking at manufacturing Investments
over time you see that the the US began
in the 1980s um as the the leader in
this type of invention a lot of R&D
Talent has begun to focus on different
problems but Japan and and and later
just in the last 10 years China have
really accelerated their investments in
these areas and and and I would say this
is turned them into um you know
inventive
powerhouses Germany um is much more on
par with the United States these days
despite being um significant smaller
economy so I think that's significant to
call out as well okay so now we get from
invention and and like I talked about
that inventing the future is this
insufficient idea we also need to think
about how would you produce the things
that you invent because there's this
positive feedback loop between inventing
um new Goods producing them learning
from production and then improving the
inventions and and what we see in in the
production numbers is really that the
United States over the last uh 45 years
has has depleted its production capacity
that no longer um Can it
produce um you know produce at the level
of other countries and a lot of the the
challenge is not just that uh there
aren't uh incredibly productive and
effective American factories there still
are but because American manufacturing
has been in Decline it's had difficulty
recruiting new workers it's had
difficulty um encouraging you know um
recruiting New Capital to subsidize risk
um in production not necessarily in
invention so that it's fallen behind
these other countries so so what do I
mean by that in in practice here's just
a a plot and ites doesn't come up to the
present I can explain a little bit why
on how uh you know we get missing data
after the Trump Administration um but
this is looking at manufacturing exports
and what I think the story is here is
that we have really three equilibria of
manufacturing economies um that are
exporting to the rest of the world one
equil one equilibrium is kind of uh I
would say Korea Taiwan and China which
are heavy exporters we don't have
Chinese data here but exporting at
upwards of 20% of their GDP are come
from manufacturing exports so these are
very much manufacturing driven economies
where production you know is is
dominating the market the the second
excuse me there um you know the second
equilibrium it comes from comp countries
like uh you know Germany um in in some
cases you know Mexico even though the
Mexican manufacturing economy has been
hit pretty hard over the last uh over
the last decade but but really we could
think about that as Germany and Japan um
being in this this lower equilibrium
still significant chunk of the
manufacturing economy about 20% of GDP
in Germany comes from manufacturing um
and that's been stable even as precious
for the industrialization have come in
um and that would I would say is a
middle tier um equilibrium manufacturing
is still very important but it's it's a
diversified economy and then finally at
at the lower level where only you know
less than 5% of GDP come from
manufacturing exports and only about 10%
of of overall employment comes from
manufacturing is is the United States um
and it's it's on par with with France
which has suffered from similar
de-industrialization so so what does
that mean for the us to have
manufacturing as more of a marginal play
more of a marginal role in the economy
it's that while there are all sorts of
res economic resources focused on on
invention of new technologies there
aren't the same resources focused on how
to produce them well so you get this
Detachment between invention and
production which I imagine many of you
are are very familiar with so so why
this kind of long-winded context is
because part of the the Trends today of
bringing invention back closer to
production depend on the you know the
bending of the curve for the United
States and the United States to play
catchup which is what I'll I'll focus on
a bit in a moment um okay so what are
the ingredients for for doing production
well that are that are different and and
what are kind of missing in the United
States but present in other countries so
there's mechanical Talent on on the left
which John uh Lou is talking about where
um the US manufacturing Workforce and
and the the production Workforce in
particular um has just you know uh the
investment in that Workforce has
declined dramatically the second is is
technology adoption which is actually
related to Mechanical Talent the more
talent you have on the factory floor the
better able you are to adopt new
technology so you see in John's numbers
and I'll show you more numbers in a
moment that technology adoption in other
countries has accelerated um and and
reached far higher levels than in the
United States where only um you know 12%
of uh of us manufacturers have any
robotic automation at all less than a
third in many cases have soft any type
of advanced software on the factory
floor and then finally I I want to talk
a little bit about Capital markets so we
have um a lot of investment in
traditional risk Capital supporting new
higher growth businesses that are
focused on invention in the United
States but we don't have Capital to
support operational risks for example so
any asset intensive investment in
manufacturing the United States isn't
hasn't been supported in public public
markets um really since the 1980s which
which marked kind of the transition to
focus on asset light companies and
supporting um you know companies that
might have a small manufacturing
footprint in the United States but
really are just system integrators and
relying on on the real production the
industrial base coming from abroad and
that that shift in um your support for
operational risk um essentially
disinvestment in operational risk I
think limited what manufacturers could
do even if they wanted to uh produce
things Dom ially so that's a missing
piece in in US manufacturing currently
and just to give you some data points on
this um one is you John showed you the
Manu robot adoption as a as a proportion
of overall manufacturing I want to show
you just robot adoption overall and over
time to show that in in China um largely
subsidized by the central government
robot adoption has has grown pretty
dramatically you've seen some growth um
in in Japan as well but in the United
States has actually been been pretty
flat over the over the last 10 years and
at a pretty low level as a share of the
manufacturing economy um okay so finally
I think one of the missing pieces and
one of the things that even in uh places
like the Department of Defense they
don't like to really you know consider
and talk about is the industrial Base by
which I mean real commodity production
of components that everyone relies on
but no one really thinks are um you know
are you know High added value no one
really wants to produce in um High wage
markets and I I think it's it's
important not to ignore that the
industrial base has really Consolidated
in um in one place uh particularly for
Advanced Technologies still that rely on
commodity components those components
are primarily um coming from China and
and there hasn't been much
diversification Beyond maybe Taiwan
taking some of that market share okay so
I I'm then going to shift from this kind
of uh very broad overview of uh kind of
the global manufacturing Dynamic of just
four countries to look at what went
wrong in in the US context
so the United States if if we look at
this kind of breakdown the United States
actually used to be in in the late 1800s
and early 1900s um very good at
operational Risk Technology adoption and
mechanical talent and you can see in
this plot that between about 1950 and
1980 you have all of these indicators of
manufacturing performance investments in
new technology the red line um
employment the yellow line productivity
value added wages all going up and to
the right it's a very positive
equilibrium and then in the 1980s some
something happens that that's pretty
dramatic this is the onset of
competition from Japan and really a
conscious effort at the federal
government level frankly to disinvest
from manufacturing and shift Capital to
other sectors and in sectors that are
more focused on invention and less on
production a you know uh essentially
pulling capital and in the the failure
of of companies in the public markets
that were more asset intensive um and
then in the 2000s really a move a pretty
intensive mood to toward globalization
and and the consequence that I think is
is easy to ignore is that not only was
this a reduction in employment and a
flattening of wages which you might
think you know the flattening of wages
is because of pressures to race to the
bottom but it's also a flattening of
investment in new technology of taking
those operational risks so the red line
there's this blip with the early in
about 1998 with early investments in
computers but then since since that time
uh investments in new technology have
been pretty flat just like we see with
robot adoption numbers so this is not
really recipe to to compete or to to win
the frontier in both invention and
production and and how I've begun to
think about this is that one of the
consequences of of this disinvestment
over the last 40 years is that we have a
Lost Generation of manufacturing
innovators and Manufacturing workers so
here's just a plot of the age
distribution
in manufacturing um in you know the last
couple years is the blue distribution
and then in 2000 is the the red
distribution now the red distribution
where the majority of workers are in
their uh 30s and 40s and then you have
kind of equal tails on either side
that's a pretty normal distribution for
for any industry but the blue
distribution is is abnormal you know in
a problem where you have the um the the
highest frequency of workers in their
60s and in some cases their 70s
um and you have this huge gap of workers
in their 30s and 40s and then you you've
seen manufacturers try to catch up with
this bump of workers in their um in more
entry-level positions so this is this is
a gap not just um because of the
impending retirements of the the the
bulk of manufacturing workers but it's
also a gap in in knowledge and talent
that you think about a lot of the Future
Leaders of manufacturing should be in
that middle but there there was really a
Lost Generation of manufacturing workers
you know this is also reflected in in
wages I think John referenced some of
this but um the idea that the
manufacturing worker used to make 40%
more in manufacturing than they could in
other sectors and today they only make
about 2% more so the there used to be
this big wage premium manufacturing that
was attracting droves and droves of
workers no longer is that the case and
then finally I I think I want to Pivot
to some more encouraging news that in
manufacturing this isn't a general story
I imagine some of you in the audience
who are in certain industries being yeah
like hey I I see this data but this
isn't my experience with manufacturing
my manufacturing is much higher wage for
example we have much advanced technology
we're thinking about introducing um we
have lots of robots we're thinking about
introducing an AI layer on top of maybe
the software that you use to interact
with the robots I think that's great and
I what I want to recognize is that there
is a lot of variation even within us
manufacturing so if I break it down um
in this kind of you know Cardiac Arrest
chart here you'll see that and I'm
plotting productivity on the left panel
and wages on the right panel a what I
want you to note is that there's a
relationship between an industry's
productivity as wages as you might
expect and B to note how high the
variation is um in terms of value added
employee by manufacturing industry right
so that the top industries are 3x more
productive than the bottom Industries
and pay more than double the bottom
Industries right so this is a huge
spread in terms of the variation in
productivity of these industries part of
that is just industry Dynamics and and
how they compete but part of it is
investments in technology so if you look
at chemicals and steel there's been real
transformation and also just you know
differences in volume and and the
character of production in these
industries but that translates in into
wages um and in some cases into to
Global
competitiveness so what I want to um do
and I think this transitions to to Bruce
because uh I think Bruce's efforts in
Industry take off from um some of these
inspirations
is that we've seen beginning a little
bit uh before 2020 but really taking off
since 2020 a shift in how entrepreneurs
and investors have begun to think about
manufacturing and I think there have
been two Inspirations that have allowed
um American uh manufacturing operators
in particular to see new possibilities
of how uh they can compete in a a very
competitive Global manufacturing
environment on the left you know I think
SpaceX um and and to to some extent and
Tesla have been real Pioneers uh not
always successful in their manufacturing
efforts but certainly Pioneers in
showing that taking big risks in
adopting new approaches to manufacturing
can pay off and and can pay off and
actually really high wage markets in the
United States so to to hire intensively
um in in places like California um has I
think changed the calculation for others
that have looked at well if if Tesla's
able to do that or SpaceX is able to do
that we must be able to to um adopt
experiments in a similar way or adopt
new approaches to manufacturing that
would allow us to compete in our
industry so we've seen this um not only
from the uh from folks who have worked
at SpaceX or Tesla and left to start
their own companies so now there are
kind of these these cousin companies of
SpaceX and Tesla that have been inspired
by their more experimental approach to
production but also um for example the
the automotive companies that are
competitors to Tesla starting to adopt
some of their approaches to using uh
software as kind of a key approach not
just to you know software in the vehicle
but also software as a um you know a key
component of the manufacturing process
and that that software and and good data
science should be a a central part of
the factory floor so I think that these
these models um of start more startup
companies that are inspired by high
growth software startups um are now
we're seeing more of this in uh
manufacturing companies more traditional
sectors then the second model that I
think is is really interesting but takes
a more you know traditional
manufacturing approach that includes
statistical process control you know
Theory constraints is Amazon that Amazon
has experienced you extraordinary scale
up and extraordinary growth um using
many manufacturing principles and
applying them to Logistics and
warehousing um in their fulfillment
centers so uh in in transitioning to
Bruce I think you know Bruce's Uh
current efforts in Industry which I
think he might talk about a little bit
are um partly inspired by applying these
princi so Jeff Wilkey who was formerly
CEO of Amazon um consumer um was a
co-founder of rebuild manufacturing
which Bruce is a part of um and it's all
you MIT uh leaders for manufacturing
alumni who come now from various
experiences over the last 30 years and
are applying these experiences to
traditional manufacturing Industries as
part of the industrial base so I think
there's a lot of exciting potential and
um skill and scaleup that that are being
used um there and and at other companies
um that have taken the Amazon
inspiration as well so um the final
thing and I know that we have a global
audience here so to Pivot back to the
global Dimension a bit is to think about
what uh American manufacturers are
learning from foreign companies so I
mentioned in the conversation with John
the the RO of BMW is I think a real uh
Pioneer in American manufacturing over
the last 30 years it's actually the
largest American exporter right now is
is BMW South Carolina facility um so and
it's not alone it's representative of
this much larger Trend so if you look at
this plot we recently uh published a
couple papers on the role of FDI in
reshaping the foreign direct investment
reshaping us manufacturing and you can
see that foreign direct investment has
more than doubled in the last um in the
last several decades whereas overall
capital investment us manufacturing has
been relatively flat so foreign firms
foreign owned firms have taken a larger
and larger share of of us Manufacturing
investment you know the motivations are
are multiple part of it's access to
Talent part of it's access to a consumer
Market why there's so much FDI but I
think aside from those motivations one
of the key uh takeaways that we have
looking at the data is that these
foreign owned firms are more like
they're more productive than their
American counterparts they're more
Capital intensive and they pay higher
wages so they're really raising the bar
in in manufacturing in a lot of
Dimensions um and and I think one of the
open questions is are American firms
going to learn sufficiently from their
new foreign own neighbors such that
they'll be able to reap benefits from
knowledge spillovers and really um grow
based on the you know the positive
inputs from companies that have uh kind
of that started elsewhere so so this I
think is an interesting Trend to follow
some of you might have experiences i'
love to hear your input in in the chat
um and and one that that I think we're
um going to continue to to look into so
with that I'm going to
um look to see if there are any question
questions I can't currently see any of
the questions if anyone wants to help me
out um in case anyone had any responses
the
presentation Steve did you see any
questions in the
chat oh I see two
now okay so uh I'll just read the
question for everyone do you think the
decline in US manufacturing begin to
shift upwards is the Federal grant
funding requirements for us
manufacturing me to take effect the
Technologies developed in University
Labs with Federal grant funding are
commercialized um so I I'll I'll take
this question a little bit broader is is
kind of is US industrial policy working
and I should note that us industrial
policy is playing catchup with uh
longstanding industrial policies in
other countries that have been very
successful at stimulating new Industries
um and I think there there's been a lot
written about Japan and Korea and and
those industrial policies as models for
other countries a lot of Latin American
countries have tried to look learn from
the Japanese and Korean models but the
question of us industrial policy right
now is that there are certainly
short-term benefits that we're seeing so
there's been I think 170% increase in
new Factory investment so it's pretty
clear given the the current state of
factories that are are half half built
that there's going to be a spike in US
manufacturing employment and US
manufacturing capacity um by 2030 right
that's that's pretty clear given where
new Greenfield facilities are um the
question is
um and I think this is a question that's
interesting to John and and me and
others is that you know will those
factories operate any differently than
other factories over the last 20 years
will they continue to decline in their
overall productivity or will they really
learn lessons from their peers abroad
learn lessons from higher growth uh
factories and the like so so I think
that's the the the open question but
there's certainly going to be a
shortterm kind of Sugar High um from
industrial policy incentives the second
uh the conductor upwards trend is do
more reflection of the shortage due to
covid or more steady rise in the
productivity of this industry um I mean
I think there are a few motivators for
um investments in semiconductors in the
US I think one is the kind of fragile
geopolitical nature of where Advanced
node semiconductors are currently
produced you know namely Taiwan um and I
think there was also a pretty Stark
recognition during covid motivated some
by the automakers but some just in
general um
by uh you know um you know consumer
electronics that the the semiconductor
supply chain that used to be really
strong in the US was just totally
atrophied and that we had you know
design capabilities in the US and still
in many ways are are highly competitive
in design but we don't really produce uh
equipment we don't have um you know
testing and uh assembly capabilities and
our Fabs are are falling way behind we
don't Pro we you know in as of you know
2021 2022 we didn't really have any
advanced node capacity in the US at all
so I think there was a w certainly a
wakeup call around 2020 but the the lack
of capacity um had been a problem for a
long time and really and I I I talked to
the people in semiconductor industry
about this that a lot of people in the
semiconductor industry didn't think this
is a problem right they're totally okay
with the global nature of the
semiconductor value chain like it's okay
that asml is producing things C certain
you know their their products in the
asml in Europe and we have um tsmc in
Asia and we have kind of analog in the
US you know that that's all fine um and
they didn't see a real problem with it
whereas now the US I think driven by
mostly National Security concerns is
saying well that is a problem and we
want to have more capacity domestically
um I'm going to go to the last two and
then I see Bruce so then I'm going to
introduce you Bruce um what
opportunities do you see for technical
leadership and Manufacturing to connect
with manufacturing leaders um to get
involved with these programs well I
think it's going to depend on the case
you know I in some cases what we might
do well and this is I think a broader
question of how might companies that are
that do manufacturing engage with folks
who work on an MIT you know what we do
with some companies is we'll just have a
group from the company visit and we'll
bring in relevant uh researchers or
teachers and we'll do workshops with the
company based on their challenges we're
going to do one of those um uh in in a
few weeks with with a large
multinational and and those I think can
be really fun and and we learn a lot
from from companies and and that's how
you know that fuels our research um and
hopefully companies find that valuable
um the another path is if companies have
particular either technical questions or
or research questions that they don't
quite have people on their R&D team to
pursue um that there are there are teams
that that work on those sponsored
projects here where you could sponsor an
MIT graduate student or postto for
example to take on that technical
challenge they'd have to be able to
publish it as part of their research but
it also could be beneficial for industry
so we've had various of those
Partnerships in the past as well um
final question how can American
manufacturers handle High labor costs
can we only manufacture expensive
products great question so that that I
think was the big point about this this
idea that race to the bottom you know
doesn't really work and it's not really
the game that we're playing anymore um
I'll give you you know the initial
picture I had of samser at at hyperm I
think is a good example so hypertherm is
in new rural New Hampshire they try to
hire uh you know they they they have a
tough time hiring because it's a rural
you know relatively sparse Community uh
they pay really well they pay their
workers well above they're still a
manufacturing premium at hypertherm it's
an employee owned company so they do
profit sharing with their employees so
this is like distinctly High wage
they're not trying to compete on wages
and what what they've done is just and
they still are competing with um cutting
tool manufacturers from China right so
they're Mach Machine Tool manufacturer
and they compete on quality and price um
but really where where they're bread and
butter is is productivity so they say
yeah our our workers might make 4X 5x
what our competitors's workers might
make but we're also we're going to try
to be 8 9x more productive and that I
think is is the recipe to competing on
um to competing with high costs and
particular High Cost of Labor and I
think of uh some of Bruce's colleagues
who are producing commodity Parts like
um you know bicycle composite bicycle
wheels or backpack frames less
expensively than their Chinese
counterparts and and with with higher
quality so it can be done even in high
wage markets like Colorado as well so I
think that's those cases are really
exciting now I think what many of you
probably gathered from the data is that
those cases in the US are are an extreme
minority they're they're the exceptions
rather than the rule and I think you
know the the other exciting piece is
that the exceptions in the US where
high- wage manufacturers Thrive look
differently than how German High wage
manufacturers Thrive so it's like
they're playing the same game but
they're using a different Playbook which
which I find very interesting and I
think that we have a lot to learn from
uh from one another so I'm going to pass
it over to um to Bruce but would love to
talk with anyone else um about this if
you're interested uh my email is
accessible on our website so feel free
to drop me a note or we can talk more
about in the panel