So, one thing is this diagnostic toolkit
for bipolar disorder
um that I sort of mentioned. Um I think
that's a really important project in the
lab. Um, I think that
I love this ability that we can
constantly push our tools um into new
areas because it means that we always
get the first look and um and I I think
that
uh it's also been a very very powerful.
So, you know, I I have people who come
to my lab and what they want to train in
is on the using these imaging tools and
then they go get jobs and basically they
say, "Oh, I'm I did this on a not on a
knockout for a certain gene, but I could
do this on any Alzheimer's model." You
know, they get the job, right? Because
it's such a powerful tool
and you get to use it in a disease
model.
Um, so, so I think that that's I I think
it's a powerful tool because it's a
discovery tool and it gives us insight
into how things work normally, but it's
also a very powerful tool to probe um
dysfunction. Well, you know, the cancer
field has really been revolutionized by
this ability to do um kind of
personalized genetics where you could
actually take a sample of the tumor,
find out exactly what the mutation is,
and predict whether a certain treatment
will work or not. And that has been
really um very uh kind of heavily
commercialized at this point.
Um but nobody's really done that for
neuroscsychiatric disorders
and if you compare the number of people
that are affected the numbers are huge
right so for example the prevalence of
bipolar disorder which is actually the
most genetically penetrant of all uh um
neuroscychiatric disorders it's 1 to 2%
of the population
Um, but when people have cancer, not all
cancers are the same. So each specific
cancer has a different diagnostic,
right? So that's a much smaller fraction
in comparison to the fraction of the
population that has bipolar disorder.
And if you ask a clinician, well, if I
gave you a test for bipolar disorder,
who would you test? and he said, "First
of all, any adolescent that's beginning
to show behavioral symptoms, obviously
you would test. If there's anybody in
the family that has a history, I would
test the entire family, including all
the kids. I would test anyone who comes
into my office that has depression
because it could be that it's just the
first symptom of bipolar disorder. So in
terms of the fraction of the population
where a test like this could be useful,
it's just
orders of magnitude higher than any
diagnostic test that exists today. And
those only exist actually there there
it's not true. It's the cancer field is
an area where that's been very um
successfully implemented. There are some
diagnostic related to um um
transplantation to ability to uh um
accept transplants and which ones but uh
but that's kind of it. Um, so I think
that the potential is really huge. And
and you know, also if you know anyone
who has bipolar disorder, you you can
see how debilitating it is. And um, you
know, and many of these people are
brilliant, right? And this totally
derails their life and it derails the
life of their entire family, right? It's
it's a huge huge um
kind of unmet need to be able to even
diagnose it. And the diagnosis is really
the first step towards appropriate
treatment.