All right, welcome back everyone. Uh,
I'm Ben Neil. I'm here to chair the the
last scientific session before our
plenary speaker, Robert Pinch, takes the
stage. And, uh, I think we're going to
move slightly more translationally
oriented at the end of the V2F
symposium. And I think that's nice to go
from variance to, you know, functions
and mechanisms with the idea of getting
to therapeutics. So I'll uh invite our
first speaker up here uh VJ Sankarin a
colleague of mine at Boston Children's
Howard Hughes investigator and and
really
demonstrates I think how basic science
can have such clear impact on drug
development when you understand the
biology. So teach us some biology.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much Ben. Um
and huge thanks to the organizers for um
the opportunity to come and participate
in this amazing symposium. Now before I
get started, I just want to give a
little bit of my own perspective because
I've been here all day and I've had a
for you know I've been fortunate to hear
a variety of the talks and I think we
started off with Ruth telling us that
there are now 9,000 associations with
BMI. We know in blood cell phenotypes or
height we have thousands if not tens of
thousands of associations. So in many
ways we should be motivated to try to
develop these scalable approaches that
you've heard about throughout throughout
the the the day and certainly we're
excited and interested in trying to do
that. But my goal in the next 25 minutes
or so is going to be to give you a
perspective of maybe there's a
complimentary
benefit to really trying to wrestle a
single association down to the ground.
And so I'm going to try to tell you
about one locus and one association that
we really want to try to mechanistically
and hopefully um therapeutically try to
try to really understand. But before I
get there, I want to contextualize a
little bit of why we do what we do. So
each of us is thought to have
approximately 100,000 blood or
hematoportic stem cells that reside
within our bone marrow and that are
responsible for maintaining and
replenishing our blood and immune
systems throughout our lifetime.
Each of these stem cells needs to be
able to produce millions of platelets,
red blood cells, and a variety of white
blood cells throughout our lifetime in
order to maintain our health and and
immune function. Now, we understand a
great deal about how this process of
blood and immune cell production occurs.
And yet, most of our understanding of
this comes from really elegant and
informative studies in model systems,
including mice and zebra fish, which
have and continue to teach us a great
deal about this process. And yet often
when we make observations in our
patients or from interindividual
variation in humans, we have challenges
in trying to map that directly onto our
understanding of this process of blood
cell production or hematopoesis. And so
we view this not as a limitation but
rather as an opportunity to take
advantage of observations that we make
in humans to better understand this
process. And our interest in this really
started now about 22 or 23 years ago.
And at the time we were interested in
trying to understand why the most common
monogenic disorders in the world
including cickle cell disease is
depicted in this electron microraph as
well as betathalmia had such incredible
clinical variability. We knew that
patients with this diagnosis could
actually be completely asymptomatic or
largely asymptomatic and yet we knew
that many patients could often be
severely affected requiring weekly or or
more frequent um hospitalizations.
And at the time we knew from decades of
work that one key factor mediating
interindividual variability in the
clinical severity of the disease was the
level of fetal hemoglobin that these
patients expressed. So typically during
human development there's predominant
expression in uterero of this fetal form
of hemoglobin or gammoglobin is shown in
the green and shortly after birth this
switches off and there's upregulation of
the adult beta heemoglobin molecule is
shown in the purple and this is what is
mutated in both cickle cell disease as
well as in betthalmia
and so continued persistent production
of this gammoglobin molecule can
ameliate the severity of of these beta
hemoglobin disorders and that had been
known for decades decades. Yet the
precise molecular regulation of this
process was not well understood. And so
after years of failing to try to
understand this process through a
variety of systems, we were fortunate
because we were able to be involved with
some of the earliest genomewide
association studies initially in
non-anmic individuals and then working
with Joel Hershorn, we were able to
replicate these associations initially
in individuals with cickle cell disease.
And these studies collectively reveal
three major regions of the genome
associated with interindividual
variation in fetal hemoglobin including
this association on chromosome 2. And
these this in these initial observations
really led us to go on to functionally
show that BCLNA serves as a key and
direct repressor of the gamoglobin gene
such that when it's well expressed which
is happening in all of your bone marrow
cells right now there's repression of
gammoglobin and predominant expression
of the adult form of hemoglobin and at
the earlier stages of development
there's lower BL1A expressed at the
protein level and this then deresses the
gammoglobin gene and favors production
of fetal hemoglobin.
But as Molina mentioned earlier today,
this of course did not just teach us
about a fundamental developmental
process, but thanks to an extensive
amount of subsequent translational and
uh clinical work. This has now led to
the development of now FDA approved
therapies that target this axis
particularly uh exel or cast jevy which
um is from vertex and and um crisper
therapeutics. And this drug acts by
actually taking this repressor of the
gamoglobin genes BCL1a and targeting an
arythroidid specific enhancer of this
gene to thereby downregulate BC1a as
Jesse was mentioning and this thereby
derpresses the fetal hemoglobin genes
allowing their robust expression and
thereby ameliating clinical symptoms in
patients as has been borne out. And so
this early success really for us has
served as a motivation to not only think
about diseases like cickle cell disease
that affect the red cell lineage but
more broadly think about how we could
take advantage of human genetic
variation across the alyic spectrum to
better understand this process. Now much
of our focus has really been on how
blood cell production occurs in
non-malignant states or how this process
might be uh impacting rare blood
disorders. But over the past decade,
thanks to a lot of work, including work
from this community, particularly from
Steve McCarol, Ben Eert, and others,
we've learned about the fact that
sematic mosaicism we know is widespread
in all of our tissues as we age. And
this has particularly been notable and
well worked out in the context of the
blood system where there can be cancer
driver mutations acquired in blood stem
cells that then result in clonal
expansion of the stem cells. even the
absence of an overt malignancy, a
condition that's been termed clonal
hematopois of indeterminant potential.
And approximately 10 years ago or so
when this condition was first um
described, it was thought to be a
invariable precursor to the development
of a variety of blood cancers including
myotus plastic syndrome and acute myoid
leukemia. It was also known that this
condition could predispose people to a
variety of other comorbidities including
cardiovascular disease and other
conditions. But this progression of
course as shown here was thought to just
be an inevitable evolutionary process.
And yet over the past several years
we've learned that actually it's very
hard to predict even if one individual
has such a mutation what is the
likelihood of going on to either see a
clone with one of these drivers such as
DNM T3A TET 2 um so and so forth is that
clone going to expand? And we know that
even for individuals with the same exact
driver mutation, there can be no
expansion over time, regression of the
clone in some instances, or there can be
some growth at variable rates. Moreover,
as shown in the y-axis here from this
study in in in the UK, we know that
individuals have variable rates of
progression to blood cancer such as
acute myoid leukemia with some
individuals having no increased risk
even if they have one of these driver
mutations compared to the general
population. and yet other individuals
even with the same driver mutation
having some increased rate.
So what underlies this variation? Well,
we know of a variety of factors. So we
know from both observational and
interventional studies in humans as well
as studies in model systems that chronic
inflammation and some infectious
exposures can actually have a role in
enabling some clones to expand in in
circumstances. And so certainly this has
been and continues to be well studied
and is really the subject of a variety
of of of um studies in in model systems.
We know that exposure to some types of
chemicals and radiation can actually
allow some types of clones to expand
particularly in the context of treatment
with chemotherapy for solid tumors. We
know that clones with mutations in TP53,
PPM1D and Czech 2 can often be seen to
expand in those settings. But what about
the role of germline genetic variation?
And could there be either genetic
variants within that are inherited that
either affect the likelihood of a clone
expanding or that protect an individual
from that expansion. And so we thought
perhaps we could try to identify such
varants. And this was the work of a
medical fellow in our laboratory
Goraval. Gorov got interested in this
problem and really wanted to try to
understand not just what were the
variants that were there because there
had been other efforts to try to
identify those but really what were the
variants that were most either
protective or put individuals at the
greatest risk of progression or clonal
expansion with with clonal hematopoesis.
And so, Gorov took studies that had been
both um previously done from a variety
of bio banks as well as um other studies
that we and and and other colleagues
could do in a variety of large bio banks
and could from a population of about
700,000 or more individuals look at
individuals with detectable clonal
hematopoesis across these various
studies. And then it just asked what
variants were either putting individuals
at risk of having clonal hematopois or
what were protecting individuals. And
this really allowed him to look at a
variety of variants, many of which were
increasing the risk subtly but
significantly for for acquiring um
colonal hematopois. But Gorov got
particularly interested in this variant
on chromosome 17 that actually had a
pretty had the most substantial
protective effect against clonal
hematopois.
Now looking at this hllet type this had
a alil dose dependent protection against
clonal hematopois with individuals
having two copies of this haplletype
having about a 30% reduction in
acquiring clonal hematopois.
This was protective in contrast to some
of the other variants that have been
described as protecting against specific
types of clonal hematopoesis. This was
protective against all the major forms
of clonal hematopoises we could see
including DNMT3A TE 2 mutant clonal
hematopouis ASX1 and Jack 2 and
importantly and in contrast to what had
been seen for other variants. This
protected individuals from acquiring a
variety of blood cancers including from
um acute myoid leukemia and the myo
proliferative neoplasms as well as all
forms of myoid malignancies as far as we
could um see from from these large bio
banks. In addition, there was a subtle
but significant decrease in all blood
counts where we could see that there was
a reduction in platelet counts, a
variety of white blood cell counts as
well as red cell counts. But even in
individuals with two copies of this
hletype, the counts still remained in
the normal range that's typically seen
in this setting. If we then looked
across a variety of other phenotypes,
other than the impact on clonal
hematopoesis, the impact on blood counts
that I mentioned as well as the
protection from blood cancers, we did
not see any other phenotypic
associations with this particular
variant. Really suggesting that it was
relatively selective for its effect in
hematopois.
So how was this variant acting? And
finally I just mention one other thing
which is this variant was actually found
across almost all global populations.
But I would just note that this has been
maintained at relatively low frequencies
with the highest frequencies seen in uh
a number of European populations
typically in the four to 6% range with
other populations having this variant
suggesting an ancient origin but
suggesting it was maintained at
relatively low frequencies. So how is
this variant acting? Well, if we looked
within the hletype, there was only a few
variants within that hllet type and only
a single variant we found that was
actually overlapping any kind of
functional annotated region. And in this
particular case, it was a region that
was actually accessible within
hematopoic stem cells. This was also a
region that was bound by gata 2 and a
variety of co-actors that are known to
be important for transcriptional
regulation within blood stem cells. We
could also see that this region of
chromatin accessibility was selective
for early blood stem cells and very
primitive progenitors. But then this
region became inaccessible as blood stem
cells underwent further differentiation
really suggesting that this was
selectively accessible within that
compartment. And in addition, if we used
either correlations between attack
sequencing and RNA sequencing or looked
at long range chromatin looping data, we
could see that this regulatory region
had interactions with the promoter of
MSI2.
Looking broadly within the region and
over several megabases that surrounds
this particular variant, what we could
see was that MSI2 was the only gene
expressed within blood stem cells and
none of the other genes in that local
region were expressed um in in this
context. If we looked at correlations
between the degree of chromatin
accessibility in single cells in that
region and the expression of MSI2, we
saw a nice correlation between those
really suggesting that this was a
regulatory element affecting MSI2. But
to directly get at that, we could take
blood stem cells from healthy human
donors, introduce crisper eye constructs
that allow us to transiently suppress
gene expression from a regulatory
element within these primary um stem
cells. And we can see across a variety
of guide RNAs targeting this regulatory
element that we could selectively
suppress MSI2 expression. But we did not
see changes in any other gene expression
locally. Now MSI2 has been really well
studied by a number of labs, some of
which I'm describing here as being
critical for progression in a variety of
blood cancers and other cancers and has
been known to be important in in some
stem cell populations. But our goal is
really to understand how is this variant
acting to protect individuals from both
acquiring clonal hematopois and from um
going on to develop blood cancers. And
so to start to get at that we really
wanted to try to delineate what are some
of the variant effects. So at first we
took this regulatory element with both
the um reference and and the
non-reference alil. We could put it
upstream of the endogenous MSI2 promoter
and then put this into blood um stem
cells from from healthy human donors and
then actually examine what is the
activity of this regulatory element
within a context that's relevant the
these primary hematopro stem and
progenitor cells. And critically what we
saw was that this enhancer element did
act as a typical enhancer in this
exogenous assay where we could see an
increase in in in in um regulatory
element activity. But this was partially
suppressed by by twofold by um simply
introducing this this variant associated
with resilience in individuals and that
protects individuals from acquiring
either colonal hematopaths or these
blood cancers.
We when we looked at the variant effect
we could see that this actually
disrupted a canonical GATA motif that is
bound by gata 2 and this is the typical
motif for this. And indeed if we took
hetererozygous donor stem cells pull
down gata 2 we could actually see
reduced occupancy of gata 2 in the alil
associated with resilience from clonal
hematopoesis as well as protection from
blood cancers. And similarly, if we took
accessible chromatin reads from
individuals who are hetererozygous for
this variant, once again we can see that
there was reduced chromatin
accessibility at this element. Really
suggesting that this was disrupting a
canonical gata 2 motif that was critical
for binding of gata 2 and thereby
resulted in reduced both enhancer
activity as well as reduced gata 2
occupancy. Now, unfortunately, we did
not have a direct way to precisely edit
this particular variant in, but we could
show using our reporter systems that
introducing small micro deletions into
this element to actually mimic the
effect of the um the variant. So, we
could create these small microdeions
with paired guides within the enhancer.
And we could also target MSI 2 directly.
And when we do this, we see that there's
about a 20 to 30% reduction in MSI2
expression within the stem cell
compartment at the mRNA level. And we
can also see by intracellular staining
for MSI2 protein that within this stem
cell compartment there's a reduction in
protein levels either subtly by the
enhancer or more profoundly by directly
targeting MSI2 itself. So what were the
phenotypic consequences of this on the
stem blood stem cells? Well, if we
initially look and perturb either in in
um in this case adult or cord blood
derived um stem and progenitor cells
from the blood system, we can see in
this case in the context of adult stem
cells that there's a reduction both in
the fraction of cells that are um these
long-term um stem cells. This is using
phenotypic markers and we can see a more
profound reduction by directly targeting
MSI 2 and this was also true if we look
at the number of stem cells that's
present. Um, we could also see similar
results which I'm not showing you here
from cord blood. And so this occurred
across a variety of stem cell sources.
However, ultimately our gold standard in
the field of stem cell biology is to
take these cells from healthy human
donors or that are manipulated and
transplant them into immuno deficient
and kit mutant mouse recipients and then
wait four months for long-term
engraftment. And so if we introduce an
equivalent number of cells either with
the edit at a benign safe harbor locus
AVS1 or in this setting with a
microdeion of an enhancer or targeting
the knockout we actually see that if we
wait four months there's a reduction in
human engraftment in a dose dependent
manner depending on the degree of
reduction of MSI2 as shown here. This
was true across all lineages. So the we
had reduced engraftment across the stem
and progenitor cell compartment as
marked by CD34. The B cell compartment
is marked by CD19 as well as the myoid
cell compartment is marked by CD33 as
shown here. But interestingly, if we
took the marrow of the primary donors
and then actually replated them for
colonies, we actually saw an expansion
of the myoid cell colonies. And
importantly, we did see that there was
actually a skew towards myoid
differentiation. And this was consistent
with what we've known from studies in
mouse systems where it's been shown that
MSI2 is critical for the balance between
self renewal of stem cells uh producing
more of themselves and their ability to
undergo differentiation towards the
myoid lineages. And so this resilience
variant seems to actually be reducing
the likelihood of a stem cell undergoing
symmetric self renewal and uh make it
more likely that that stem cell will
undergo differentiation.
So what were the underlying mechanisms
by which this was acting? And to start
to get at that, we could conduct single
cell RNA sequencing in a sorted
compartment of the stem and progentor
cells enriched for stem cells. And then
we could examine differential gene
expression within molecularly defined
stem cells in that compartment. And this
allowed us to find a number of genes
that were differentially expressed
including most notably the most uh
downregulated gene was reassuringly MSI
2. And so this allowed us to look at
gene expression changes by modeling
variant effects in this setting in
primary human hematopro stem progentor
cells. But we also wanted to understand
since MSI2 was a well-known RNA binding
protein, what were its targets in this
setting? And so teaming up with Michael
Caras and his lab at Memorial Stone
Kettering, we could use this approach
called hypertribe where we could hook
MSI2 to an ADAR editing enzyme. And this
allowed us to look at endogenous targets
of MSI2 by turning this RNA binding
assay into essentially a sequencing
problem. And by deeply sequencing
primary human hematoproxim cells with
this construct present, we could
identify about 3,000 mrnas or so that
were bound by MSI2 or putitutively bound
by MSI2 based upon the edits. And
critically, we could find many more
targets that have been identified
before, but these targets match the
known binding sites from other
orthogonal approaches like clips seek or
and so forth that have identified the
targets and critically these were
enriched in the threep prime UTR of
these mRNAs as well.
We found that by looking at the
putitively edited targets, if we looked
at differential gene expression, there
was a down reggulation on average of
this gene expression. So this allowed us
to really focus in on a group of genes
that we could show was both
downregulated upon perturbation of the
MSI2 enhancer but that was also edited
uh upon introduction of this hypertribe
construct. And this identified both
known targets of MSI2 as well as some
novel targets including some key factors
important for stem cell self renewal and
factors that were important for um for
uh the the the regulation of stem cells.
And so this of course made us wonder if
we have this set of about 200 mrnas that
are down reggulated and bound by MSI2
could we learn something about how
they're playing a role potentially in
enabling um you know the activity of of
this particular context and so we could
examine ribosome profiling data that we
performed within primary human hematopro
stem and progenitor cells. This allowed
us to show that this set of about 200
mrnas was actually amongst the most
highly translated mRNAs within the
hematopic stem cells of human donors.
But moreover, we could also show that
this particular set of mRNAs if one
looks at mutant cells versus non-mutant
cells for example in TE 2 clonal
hematopouesis was actually upregulated
and we could see this across other
drivers such as DNMT3A as1 and so forth.
Moreover, if we looked at a variety of
AML survival data akin to what's seen
with MSI2 expression itself, the set of
genes was also associated with um worse
survival with increased expression
associated with that. But what about the
cooperivity between this particular
resilience variant and the acquired
sematic mutations that acquire that
occur in individuals? And so we teamed
up with Alex Bick at Vanderbilt
University and Yash Prashad in this lab.
And as you can see from the data I
showed initially from from George
Vicilio's lab, you can see that
individuals with clonal hematopois have
a variety of annual growth rates. And
here we're following individuals for a
median of six years in the bio view
cohort. But individuals with even one
copy of this variant actually had
decreased growth rates of these clones
in the setting of having pre-existing
clonal hematopesis at time one and then
following them to the second time point.
In addition, where individuals had
detectable clonal hematopesis at time
point.1 but then had disappearance of
that clone, we found that this
disappearance was much more likely
1.8fold more likely in the setting of
having this resilience variant. So not
only is it protecting individuals from
acquiring clonal hematopois, but
actually makes it more likely that that
clone will disappear. So could we model
this? Well, we could go on and edit ASX1
just as a typical driver mutation. If we
do that and we co-edit this benign safe
harbor locus a AVs1, we see that the
stem cells expand with this driver
mutation, we could suppress that
expansion in part by editing the uh
enhancer that I'd shown you before and
almost completely suppress that by
editing MSI2. We could see in this
setting moreover that um that uh we
could um see colony replating if we
introduce secondary colonies really a
feature of self-renewal that we're
seeing and this could be at least in
part suppressed by editing the enhancer.
And moreover, if we performed long-term
engraftment of these cells um into
xenotransplant recipients and just
waited, we could see an expansion of the
primitive stem cell compartment and this
could be at least in part suppressed by
um editing the enhancer. Moreover, we
could also use um
uh the reciprocal approach in
collaboration with Michael Carus' lab
where we could take an ASXL1 mutant
mouse recipient.
Maybe I'm not pointing this in the right
place.
Just go forward somehow.
Doesn't seem to be
Well, it'll maybe let me go forward. Um,
but using this approach, we could
actually Oh,
I didn't do anything bad. Oh, there we
go. Seems to be doing something perfect.
So, we could see that um by Thank you.
Um so we could see that by introducing
an ASXL1 mutant mouse and then
increasing the expression of MSI2 that
these mice actually have an expansion of
the stem cell compartment whereas
ordinarily these mice do not have any
phenotype. And at about eight months, we
see that there's a reduction in a
variety of blood counts and a variety of
signs of the fact that um these mice
then go on to uh
>> Oh, perfect.
>> Um these mice go on to have features
consistent with my plastic syndrome
including dis um disarotic
changes and and pelra huic type uh
nuclei and the neutrfils. And so what
I've shown you really is how by really
deeply diving into a single variant, we
can start to learn about mechanisms that
might actually both protect individuals
from acquiring sematic driver mutations
in a condition that we know as clonal
hematopoesis as well as that prevent
progression of those clones even once
acquired as shown both based upon our
longitudinal profiling data of
individuals as well as what we could
model. And I think what it really
suggests for us is of course this is not
the only protective variant but
certainly I think it suggests that by
really deeply understanding this maybe
we could identify strategies that not
only allow us to target cancers but
actually potentially prevent cancers in
the future as suggested in this uh
diagram and this poster from 1932 from
from Paris. And so our hope is really by
understanding some of these variant
mechanisms, what occurs in individuals
and what heritably allows individuals to
be protected from cancers and and
pre-malignant conditions that we could
understand more about this process. And
so with that um I just wanted to finish
up by acknowledging the people who've
really contributed to this work
particularly Gorov Agurwal uh a number
of of uh other lab members and our
collaborators as well as our funding
sources. And I want to thank you all
very much and I'm happy to take any
questions. Thank you.
remarkable talk and grace under fire.
So, even better. Uh, any questions for
VJ? Yeah, go ahead, Brad.
>> Yeah, that was awesome. So, the variant
I'm just it's maybe just a a random uh
un unfortunate or I guess in some cases
fortunate event for individuals. Are
there other selection pressures? Like do
you do you see this as just a random
mutation? Do you have a phenotype in
other tissues?
>> Yeah.
>> If it's protective of leukemias and
stuff, would it ever be selected for? Is
there not enough, you know?
>> Yeah. So, um, so this this her I mean
this is an inherited variant that's
clearly occurred like early in in
history. It's interesting that it's been
maintained at low, you know, low al
frequencies. As far as we could tell
though, like I mentioned with the
phenomewide association studies, there's
no other major phenotypes that it's
associated with. But we just have to
remember that, you know, we're all
related probably, you know, we have
common relatives about 3,000 years ago.
And, you know, probably some of those
pressures that our relatives had to go
through, you know, exposure to a variety
of infectious ages, this might not have
been a beneficial, you know, variant in
this setting. But in the modern era
where we're worried it where we live,
you know, nice hopefully long lives, you
know, and and and are relatively
protected from some of those issues.
Hopefully this by mimicking this,
especially if there's, you know, there's
lots of drug developers, you know, I
this is out of my, you know, area of
expertise, but certainly this could be a
potential good target by mimicking this
effect. And so I think that that's
really our hope.
population.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, so Brad was asking are
there populations at altitude or other
places? As far as we could tell, this
has been maintained at relatively low
frequencies across all populations, but
it's found across all populations.
>> Any other questions for VJ?
>> All right. Well, excellent talk. Lovely
biology as promised. Thanks for
listening.