Hi, I'm Dr. Christopher Dennis Cole,
founder and CEO of Da Vinciables. I
created this company after leading
sensing and systems teams at Whimo and
Apple and completing my MBA at MIT. Our
mission is to transform female health
through AI powered insights personalized
for the female body. We're an MIT Delta
V Techar Sports and Harvard V partner
venture. And our team essentially brings
together deep expertise in AI,
wearables, women's health, and go to
market strategy. We've secured four
patents and completed top tier
accelerators at MIT and techars. We work
closely with Harvard, Bringham, and
other medical experts to ensure our
platform is both clinically aligned and
user centric. We're essentially
empowering personalized female health
through wearable AI. And this is because
women's health has been underserved for
far too long. Existing wearables are
generic and don't address the unique
female physiology such as menstrual
cycles, hormone fluctuations, and
uterine health. This gap, as you might
imagine, leaves female athletes and
professionals without tools to manage
energy, mood, injury risk, and chronic
conditions. In fact, half of the
population aged 18 to 34 already live
with a chronic condition. And the lack
of tailored tools exacerbates outcomes
across life stages. Major brands like
Nike acknowledge that 45% of teenage
girls drop out of sports due to these
challenges and corporate wellness
offerings today simply aren't
personalized for women. Which is why Da
Vinci has a patented AI platform
delivering personalized insights for the
female body. We integrate biomarker data
from wearables such as watches, rings,
and our own smart active wear with
proprietary algorithms to generate
real-time adaptive recommendations.
Essentially, when to train, what to eat,
how to optimize performance across
hormonal phases. Think of it as an AI
coach for every woman's physiology. For
corporates, Da Vinci provides a plug-in
wellness solution that addresses the
massive blind spot in women's health
offerings, enhancing employee wellness,
reducing chronic condition risks, and
driving better health outcomes across
the female workforce.
Our platform delivers insights through a
simple mobile app interface. For
example, women receive phase-based
guidance. Again, how to train smarter,
which foods to prioritize to manage
fatigue, how to adjust sleep routines,
and how to understand mood and energy
across your hormonal cycles. This will
help women optimize both their
professional and personal wellness,
bringing true personalization to
corporate health programs.
We also have a body API married to a
female bio intelligence large language
model agent. And what that's doing is
it's analyzing biioarker and wellness
data to assess health injury risk and
optimize performance. So let me walk you
through the flow. User data is retrieved
and contextualized. Our LLM with rag
generates personalized insights. And
three, the system integrates external
data sets and models for continuous
learning and adaptive recommendations.
Essentially, it's personalized and
adapted to you as the individual instead
of operating on the law of averages like
many systems. So, this allows us to
deliver precise and actionable guidance
helping women manage their health
performance both in sport and in daily
life.
We've validated Da Vinci with over a
thousand user interviews and pilots
across three universities. Athletes use
Da Vinci to optimize training among
menstrual around menstrual phases,
reducing injury risk, and improving
performance. And we're also launching
with corporate partners to enhance
employee wellness programs, providing
actionable insights for women balancing
work, health, and family life. Our
champions network of pro and collegiic
athletes helps to drive grassroots
adoption and awareness as well.
So, what are we seeking? We would love
to partner with corporate health and
wellness individuals and organizations,
Fortune 500s, health ecosystems,
valuebased care providers who want to
offer groundbreaking female first
wellness tools to their employees. We
currently also partner with sports and
athleisure and wearable brands to
license our technology and expand our
reach. Our ideal partners would span US,
Europe, and Asia. Would love to explore
pilots, co-development, and integration
opportunities. So, please feel free to
reach out so we can close uh the gender
health gap together. Thank you so much
for having us.