so I am Tom uh I'm a postto here at MIT
uh and today I'm going to be talking to
you about scaling AI enabled protein
engineering um and for this I think it's
important to uh focus on the context
I've been working in and particularly
the application spaces so if you join me
uh here in the middle of this design
build test learn cycle um I've been
working lots on neglected tropical
disease and particularly developing
recombinant snake antivenom um and also
in bioindustry and sustainability so
discovering binding proteins that would
modulate the activity of industrially or
agriculturally relevant enzymes now
these seem like two fairly disparate
Fields but I do believe they are united
by a commonality which is that lots and
lots of our um extremely powerful modern
biotechnological tools could be applied
to solve a vast range of problems in
these spaces but we are limited by the
costs associated with implementing those
tools um so my thesis is essentially
that by reducing costs we can increase
the number of people that are working on
relevant problems and thus increase the
number of solutions that are found um to
reduce costs I believe we can uh kind of
combine lots of advances we've had in
these uh three themes and particularly
um relevant to today is in the design
space so using phenotype enriched
Library design and this can either be uh
kind of Taken um notice of Nature's
ability to design things so looking at
metagenomic databases using AI guided
directed Evolution or um one of my
favorite things now is just entirely
denovo protein Generation Um and by
combining these things uh I think it
becomes possible to say that we can
achieve things like this where we can
get one to 10 binding proteins against a
specified epitope on a Target protein
with inv vitro validation and in silic
structural um prediction for less than
$100 and hopefully you agree with me
that that is a very impactful price
point if we want to actually go out and
develop um Solutions in some of these
spaces so to talk you through why I
believe that this is a reasonable
statement to make it can start with um
our work in the design space which was a
through a collaboration with the baker
lab using RF diffusion to denovo design
um mini binders against snake
three-finger neurotoxins um with this we
achieved a 2% hit rate uh with pamola to
nanomolar affinities and most
importantly achieved functional invivo
neutralization of these toxins and this
was massively aided um by the ability to
pre-specify the epitope on the Target
that we wanted to bind to so we could
block the known toxin receptor
interaction in Vivo if you want to learn
more about that you can follow this QR
code in the bottom left to the preprint
um so what so after that work um what
quickly became uh abundantly clear to me
was that design was no longer a
particularly rate limiting step in our
ability to implement Solutions uh and
instead that fall Fells more on our
ability to build build designs and
actually test them in the lab and this
is something touched upon already the
ability to generate data or
experimentally validate um our insoo
predictions so for this just as an
example um I've shown here how much it
costs to actually assemble uh different
numbers of 400 base pair mini binder
genes depending on the vendor and this
is going from ordering the DNA to having
an entirely sequence validated clone um
this I think is best uh showcased with
this example scaling it up to test for
instance 3,000 uh designs if you ordered
this as E blocks from IDT it costs over
$80,000 from twist as Multiplex Gene
fragments it's about
$25,000 but you can use alternative
sources of DNA so for instance oligo
pools where you can get the cost down to
about $3 to $4,000 for this or about $1
per design um now to actually achieve
this you need to assemble the oligo
pools into full length genes yourself
which um I've built a pipeline to do in
the and this I can chat about more at my
posto if you want to come and talk about
it but just to briefly show that we''re
already just on our first pass of this
achieving 76% of assemblies being
entirely error error free without any uh
required error correction
processes um obviously all of our
building means nothing if we can't also
test uh so for this we've been
establishing um the use of split
luciferase uh in particularly in a kind
of automated setup where it costs about
six cents um per assay to test each
design and with this we can get the
expression level of a protein of
interest and also the bind in affinity
and specificity um and what's very nice
about this is that it's an entirely no
wash homogeneous assay it works in cell
liate um so it's very simple to
implement we're now using that to test
more um designs against uh snake three
finger neurotoxins and in particularly
using the scalability of this pipeline
to look for cross reactivity which we
believe is going to be a fundamental
phenotype for achieving an actually
cheap and effective uh snake antivenom
product so hopefully today I've uh
interested you in maybe some new
application spaces of lots of the tools
that we're developing uh and also convey
to you the importance of building more
efficient build and test Cycles thank
you