okay here we are good
afternoon so we have done chemical uh
kinetics and
U today again with with chemical kinetic
we are going
to uh approach
uh
the truly non equilibrium thermodynamics
topics including on Sager relations that
will we will introduce uh
today from the chemical kinetics point
of view so let
me remind you of where we
were and also it will allow us to
introduce uh some new
ideas on things that we already
know so consider a a a single chemical
reaction
mechanism which we have learned
to represent by this equation here
stochiometric coefficients and symbols
so the chemical compounds
and this is the way we have
written the reaction
rates or more precisely the rates of
change of the reaction
coordinates and just as a
reminder these are the concentrations
stochiometric coefficients of the
forward and backward half
reactions these are the reaction
constants and the reactant for the
reaction constants we
have uh
developed two equivalent ways of writing
them one in terms of the arous
activation
energy and the other in terms of these
um equilibrium constants of the uh
forward than backward
reactions half
reactions
okay and of course the the net reaction
rate is the difference between the
forward and the backward we
Define uh this ratio and the logarithm
of this ratio we call the degree of this
equilibrium and we have seen examples in
which this degree of dis equilibrium
builds up as the uh chemical
uh Dynamics doesn't isn't fast enough to
catch up and maintain equilibrium for
example in the nozal expansions that we
have
seen now we can write this difference uh
also by using this
ratio in this
way we
Factor Epsilon plus out and inside
remains Epsilon minus over Epsilon plus
which is e to Theus the
Affinity or we can Factor also Epsilon
Min do minus and then this is the
equivalent
expression
clearly this shows that the reaction
rates are
functions of the
um um
the affinities of of of each reaction is
is a function of its own Affinity
through this
exponential but it is also a
function of a bunch of other stuff which
is included in here and in these
concentrations so it is it is not
correct to say that the uh reaction
rates are functions of the Affinity
period they're also function of the
affinities this is important
because in a moment we will see that you
may want to uh construct
other relations between rates and
affinities you can also do uh the
following you can uh
divide the rate reaction rate by the
Affinity of that
reaction and
therefore it would uh this would look
like uh and if I write
Epsilon dot J equals
L JJ y
j it
looks like uh a linear relation that it
is not linear because the LJ JS depend
on the affinity
and depend on bunch of other
stuff nevertheless
this uh ratio this
L proportionality constant
between which constant is not between
rate and Affinity can also be viewed as
if you do the substitutions as except
for the gas constant the denominator is
this is the logarithmic
mean of the forward and the backward
reactions
okay now we are interested in seeing
what happens if we are near equilibrium
you know that at equilibrium the
Affinity is equal to zero so if we
approach
equilibrium uh so the
Affinity uh is small positive or
negative but
small then
we can linearize these Expressions here
e to the e to the minus
X the first linear approximation is 1 -
x or e to the x is uh 1+ X in either
case this linearizes becomes just the
affinity and so we get an expression
like this
one but
with the coefficient now being the value
at y equal Zer in the taor series
expansion you have to take the constant
terms and evaluate
it evaluate them where do you do the
expansion about in this in this case
it's when the Affinity is equal to zero
and when the Affinity is equal to zero
the Epsilon plus and minus 10 to the
same value which is epsilon0 the
equilibrium
value which is also so since they are
equal also their mean even even the
logarithmic mean are is
equal and you can Al also Express that
if you use
this definition down here and what we
have done in the previous lecture uh
lectures you can also connect it to the
um concentration at equilibrium of the
activated con uh
complex
Okay so we've
linearized now we have a linear
relation and if we substitute this
linear relation the expression for the
entropy rate of change of the entropy
which for a closed um
system is also is also the entrop
entropy produced by reversibility so it
has to be greater than
zero you see
that uh it becomes the
square it's a constant this L uh times
um the Affinity Square I mean yes the
Affinity
um uh squared or the inverse of L
times the rate squar this is why we can
identify the inverse of
this ratio L as a sort of a chemical
resistance uh to
um going back to
equilibrium the the
higher this it means the lower the L and
therefore for a given dise equilibrium
because the Affinity is dise equilibrium
for a given dise
equilibrium you have uh lesser rate
towards
equilibrium
okay now in practice we have
seen like in this example that we've
discussed few
times
hydrogen the detailed kinetic mechanism
contains a lot of chemical
reactions and you need them in order to
describe the the
Dynamics however you may notice that uh
these reactions are not all independent
of one another just for an
example uh here if you take uh the 11
and the 14 reaction and subtract them
it gives you the same result as if you
take the first and the third reaction
and you subtract
them so they are lineally combined
they're not
independent and there may be uh there
are many
other U linear dependencies
here so let's go back so up to here is
the same slide that we were on uh a
minute ago this is the new part so in
the idea is that now we have a complex
chemical uh detailed
scheme or a reaction
Network and
uh it contains a lot of linearly
dependent
reactions that means that we can
identify a subset
of linearly independent
ones with respect to which you
can um write all the
others so let's suppose that the
stochiometric
coefficients now here I'm running out of
symbol so instead of new I'm using this
other uh letter that I wish uh your
Greek colleague was here today because I
forget what the name
is in any case it's
a this is the doomric coefficients of
the linearly independent mechanism with
respect to which I can write all the
other ones so all the other uh schemes
for example in the 24 for hydrogen are
linear combinations so these X are the
linear combination coefficients of the
independent ones
and due to the uh
linearity of the
way
uh uh
the the affinities
are
defined also the Affinity of the J
reaction is the same combination of with
the same linear coefficients of the
affinities of the independent
ones and so when you substitute this
into the expression for
the rate of entropy
change which for many reactions is the
sum of the products of of the rate times
the affinity for each
reaction that substitution plus plus a a
change
of switch of summation symbols and
uh and recognizing that this
one I'm sorry that this uh that this
linear combination of the rates is also
uh the rate of the independent reaction
turns out that this summation which
before had the 24 terms now as the
minimum number of terms which is the
number of independent reactions their
rates and their affinities it's the same
product of rate and an affinity
that's what we just
got and above is just a reminder what
was the
essential of in the previous slide so if
we keep
U uh going and
substitute um
uh again the the expression for
the for
the affinities of the J reaction in
terms of the of these
other
Upsilon Affinity of the independent ons
you come up with
this and
therefore you have a a a
quadratic form in
the uh coefficients of the linear
combination that couple and
combine uh the L's so the ratio rate to
Affinity of the single non indpendent
reactions okay so this linear
combination if you notice
uh not linear this is a quadratic
combination of the L's if you notice uh
is symmetric because if you change K and
L it doesn't it doesn't
change all
right so we come up with the fact that
the entropy production is a quadratic
form in the affinities of the
independent uh
reactions and the Matrix of the U
quadratic form is non- negative that's
required by the fact that you need that
to be non negative to satisfy the
principle of entropy non
decrease and it is also
symmetric if you take this Matrix and
take the its
inverse you
can uh re
right uh this double summation in
instead of in Terms of the quadratic
form in the affinities it's a quadratic
form in the rates of the independent
reactions where the coefficients are
these and these RS are some sort of
generalized uh resistance
now these independent mechanisms are
coupled via these um linear
combinations so if you try to write the
rate of uh each one it is uh not any
longer just uh dependent on its
Affinity it depends also on the others
and this
coupling
uh is important and is typical of uh of
non equilibrium
behavior and we will see more about this
because that's a a good introduction to
what happens in in many other phenomena
for non
equilibrium of course I mean so far we
didn't believe linearize yet but of
course we can linearize again we can
assume that we go near equilibrium where
all the affinities are go to
zero so that's the linearization that we
did
before and this is the linear
combination of the rates so the rate of
the independent reactions becomes
summation like this and if you keep
going in the end you find that it is a
um a
summation of
the those affinities times these um sort
of generalized inverse resistance so
let's call it the generalized
conductivity
Matrix
symmetric and
again the rate of entropy production is
a quadratic form either in the
affinities or in the Rays this time it
is a real quadratic form up
here I sort of were a bit sloppy in
saying it's quadratic form but
um these coefficients uh may also depend
on the affinities when you're far from
equilibrium so it's not really a
quadratic dependence when you're off
equilibrium whereas when you linearize
then it becomes a a a quadratic
form and these properties here since
they are evaluated at
equilibrium they are equilibrium
properties so if you want to measure
them for example in a molecular Dynamic
simulation you would have to wait uh uh
you you have to to to go and wait for
[Music]
uh identify an equilibrium state in
order to evaluate
this which makes it easy because
equilibrium is is is reached quickly
because of
collisions and uh uh and so these
are easily
measurable Properties
or since we know if we have the full
reaction mechanism like the 25 24
reactions for hydrogen then you you can
infer these values from those uh
rates
okay so now let's step back one moment
and assume we don't
have uh developed
a a
theory
for uh reaction
rates and all we know is from the
entropy
balance this expression which is one of
the first that we derived on indeed
chemical reactions because remember the
Affinity is the derivative of s with
respect to
Epsilon so this is simply the rate of
change the derivative of s with respect
to T which here
is taken to be the entropy produced by
reversibility because we are consider
considering the isolated
system okay so that is our
constraint it's part of our model with
which we like to describe properties uh
even far from equilibrium from chemical
equilibrium but assuming a sort of a
pseudo equilibrium
okay we also know that at maximum
entropy which is stable equilibrium
chemical equilibrium the affinities must
be equal to zero and now suppose that
our Theory we want to develop a theory
in which the rates are functions of the
affinities and nothing
else or maybe some other parameters that
can be kept constant while you change
the
affinities clearly when you are at
equilibrium the net rate must be zero so
you want this function to be zero when
the argument is
zero and this this argument is a is a is
a vector so that's why it's bold phase
so this zero this is a list of
conditions
so that you can substitute that into the
expression for the entropy and you get
that the
entropy uh rate of change is also a
function of the
Affinity
now you linearize linearize around
equilibrium this
postulated
constitutive equation which presumably
should represent uh our rat
so we
do the
linear uh tailor
series and we will stop at the first
term that is non
zero okay so the first term is zero this
should be a bold phase zero okay then we
have plus the first derivative evaluated
at zero this is also another bold uh and
that
multiplied by y so this is the linear
term plus dot dot dot dot because in
fact this is already um different from
zero I'm going to call
this partial
derivative H is L our generalized
conductivity the inverse of the
resistance matrix it's a matrix
and it's a matrix that we can also write
as the
Jacobian
matrix uh of the various uh rates as
functions of the
various
affinities big Matrix to be evaluated at
Y is equal to
Zer then you take these expression
substitute it into the expression for
the entropy production and get
that the entropy production is a
quadratic form in the affinities with
the metrix of the generalized
conductivity set to serve as
coefficients of that
form that
requires that being this the dominating
term in the our expansion these Matrix
must be non- negative in order to
satisfy the principle of entropy non
decre non
decrease you may also do uh the linear
expansion of this expression here for
the entropy with respect to again to Y
around
equilibrium if if you do
that you get the the term at equilibrium
is zero because the affinities are zero
you put zero here you get
zero the first derivative of s uh dot
with respect to
Y uh at equilibrium is also
zero when you evaluate it you here is
the
evaluation so you you have to take
derivative properly of this expression
here with respect to the Y's and it's
better to do them with the indexes
otherwise you sort of Miss uh some
details so it
the S with respect to y
j it picks up from this summation the
Epsilon J
plus the summation of the Yi times the
derivative of Epsilon I with respect to
YJ
and at equilibrium the epsilons are zero
the Y are zero so this is zero that is
why this first term that the linear term
in the entropy
disappears showing that indeed indeed uh
we are at at a
maximum or a
minimum the derivative is
zero and then we go to the second uh
term in the tailor
expansion so this is the general one but
then you remember that the coefficient
has to be evaluated at zero
so you have to evaluate this hestian of
this Matrix of the second order
coefficients second order
derivatives
uh and so you take uh it's the
derivative with respect to YK of this
first derivative so you get derivative
of Epsilon J with respect to
YK then from the summation
uh corresponding to the YK you pick up
the cor coefficient that multiplies y k
is partial of Epsilon K respect to
YJ and then the summation also has some
leftovers which are the second
derivatives of the
epsilons however when you evaluate them
at equilibrium these are zero so the
summation disappears but these ones do
not
and
notice that the these is not equal to
that because one is derivative of J
respect to K the other is derivative of
K with respect to
J so essentially you
left
with these Matrix here plus it's
transpose when you switch the uh i j
with K you get the transpose
so
clearly the sum of the Matrix plus it's
transposed is a symmetric
Matrix which satisfies the fact that we
know like Schwarz theorem of second
derivatives that they're symmetric it
doesn't depend on the order so that that
is
okay so we get the same expression here
however in addition
to uh non-
negativity there is an additional
constraint that U was U proved and we
will try to see how we get there U as we
go on was proved by on Sager in 1931 for
which he got Nobel Prize in 68 and uh
which he used the statistical uh U
considerations to show that this
Matrix needs to be
symmetric and this
symmetry is not a trivial result it's
actually the basis for a number of
rationalizations of uh coupled non
equilibrium
phenomena that are used in variety of
applications of which we will touch a
few
as we go on and until the end of of the
course few lectures that we are left are
going to be all
around uh seeing the consequences of
this important uh result in addition to
seeing how you could
uh prove
it now this is just
a reminder of a
simple mathematics of when you have a
system like for a two for a 2X two uh
Matrix
L what is the consequence if the Matrix
is symmetric and positive and positive
semide definite or non-
negative and also by by seeing that uh
seeing this um more
explicitly
uh these relations will uh we will
return to these relations Al not only
for chemistry like here but later on
also we will have couple defects and we
will typically take them two by two
because uh it's already complicated with
two and uh going with more um you have
to first have understood the two and
then go to more complicated
so that's the linear
relation so it says that the Affinity
that the the rate of reaction
One H is proportional to the uh as a is
partly due to the to the fact that
reaction one is in dise equilibrium
absolute
one but also it's coupled with the
disequilibrium of reaction
to so in some extreme cases you might
have
a a reaction one that
advances not due to its own degree of
dise equilibrium but due to the degree
of dise equilibrium of another
reaction and you may rewrite this system
of equations in various ways you can
solve solve it so you can write the
affinities as functions of the rates or
you can do something in between in which
say the the rate of
one is U given by its own coefficient
times its own Affinity Plus something
that relates it to the rate of the other
equation the other
reaction okay now when a a matrix is
positive semide
definite it
means
that the elements of on the diagonal are
are non negative it means that the igen
values are non-
negative therefore also the product of
the igen values which is the determinant
is not
negative the
sum which is the trace of the Matrix is
not negative and so on
and the rate of entropy production is a
quadratic form of this
Matrix and a quadratic form is
written uh General this
way uh however if you write it in this
way you notice that this um um double
product in in the middle may not have a
a definite sign because the affinities
can be positive and negative so because
y1 is positive and Y2 is negative this
is negative and so you have a negative
term so there are ways like we did also
for the
brown theorem to write quadratic form in
canonical
forms either in terms of the affinities
or in terms of the rates so that it's
essentially a sum of squares
multiply it by positive
coefficients and so you make sure that
uh you I mean if you can manage to write
it this way you have
proved that you are in in shape in in
terms of non- negativity of the entropy
production sorry so the proof uh that
onager
gave is a requires some statistical
mechanics and I might be able to give
some hints about it later on but
um hopefully it will be given in some U
later versions of this course when
Professor Constantino will will join
in uh
but for the
moment let us uh prove it
from uh this principle of Maximum
entropy production rate proposed by
Ziggler around
58 which is simple
enough and uh doesn't contain any uh any
a lot of
uh physics accept the
idea that um when a system is in
a non equilibrium
State we already know that it tends to
reach
equilibrium developing
entropy uh until it gets this entropy
gets to the maximum allowed by the
constraints for example
the energy if the system is
isolated
uh but this is not about uh the fact
that the entropy increases it's the fact
that the system when it is in non
equilibrium uh searches for the path of
U steepest Ascent in the entropy Allowed
by the
constraints so it's like you need to
climb a mountain and go to the maximum
of the
entropy there are many path that you can
choose in order to climb that
mountain okay uh it turns out the
systems like to go there in the most
direct way as possible of course there
are constraints like the internal
structure of your
system the molecules the collisions and
all
that uh
so here the idea is is the following
what are the constraints for a chemical
chemical reacting system they we take as
a constraint this equation which comes
from the entropy balance plus our model
for the
properties and
then we we we make an assumption
like we did before where okay we want a
theory in
which the rates are uh linearly related
to the
affinities so I want a linear
theory that means that the entropy
production is given by
this quadratic
form and when we take the derivative
respect to Affinity we have this
expression
here okay H notice l i j and
lji uh I am not I do not know uh if they
are equal or not I'm not assuming I want
to prove that if you assume that this
rate of entropy production is maximal
subject to that constraint
then we prove the
Symmetry
okay now the method for uh maximizing is
simple we know it it's the lrange
multipliers method we have only one
constraint which is this
one so you Maxim you in order to take
the constrained maximum you take the
maximum the unconstrained maximum of
your function
minus the undetermined lrange
multiplier multiplied by uh the
constraint written in in the form
something is equal to zero so this is
equivalent to that equation set equal to
zero so it's the left hand side of that
equation okay and then all you do is to
take the derivative of this with respect
to the affinities and the set it equal
to
zero and so the affinities are in
here in here and in here so we get three
terms one is multiplied by one and one
by minus Lambda so one minus Lambda of
the derivative of s with respect to y s
dot with respect to Y plus this last
term uh which uh contributes an Epsilon
Dot time
Lambda okay so you set that equal to
zero you get this relation which says
Okay then if you want to do that
maximization your rates must be equal to
Lambda minus one / Lambda times this
derivative this is called Ziggler
orthogonality principle and
we'll try to interpret that
in in a while
for for the moment uh this is the result
in terms of the lrange multiplier and
then as typical in the in the method you
substitute this back into the
constraint in order to find the value
for the LR multiplier so you take this
one substitute it back into the
constraint which is
here and do the
things carefully so when this derivative
is written up
here and it has the
L's plus the transpose of
L but now these are multiplied by ep y y
i and YJ under a double
summation if you
switch the I and JS here things don't
change because of the double
summation there therefore for
this is
twice this double summation here with of
just one
L but this double
summation written this way is the
entropy production
rate okay so we got entropy production
rate is equal Lambda minus 1 / Lambda *
T ice the right all right so that
imposes that this combination must be
equ Al to one and therefore Lambda you
get it when Lambda is equal to two so we
found the lrange multiplier Lambda is
equal to
two and we can substitute it substitute
it into result and so the result of the
maximization is that is this expression
here the
orthogonality um coefficient
is2 finally
uh we can substitute into
here our assumption for Epsilon dot so
this is for the left hand
side and this is for the right hand
side and you get this expression
here then you move things left and right
so to keep uh the this the summation of
the ljs together and and leave the lji
on the other side and here is the final
result that this summation must be equal
to
zero and it has to be equal to
zero wherever your
theory applies that
means uh in any of the non-e equilibrium
States so for our arbitrary choices of
the affinities and remember here the
affinities are many because you have
several
reactions that are coupled like uh like
the like we've seen in the example
so among the various choices you can
select one for example in which only one
of the
reactions is that um is off equilibrium
and the others are at
equilibrium that therefore picks up only
one term in this summation and imposes
that the uh
coefficients uh must be zero and so that
proves uh the symmetry of the
Matrix
so uh so we prove that at least you get
you get on
sag
symmetry if you accept the principle of
Maximum entry production
rate it's
uh not sure you can do it also in the
reverse in other words is is this and if
and only if theorem uh not so sure in
other words does uh on Sager
reciprocity reciprocity prove the
principle of Maximum ENT production rate
well I think it probably need a little
more this is
Ziggler and this is the pictorial
um representation of its of his
orthogonality relation
so suppose we have two
reactions and this
plot wants to uh
represent on a
plane um the uh
affinities so for example suppose you
are in this point here it represents a a
non equilibrium state
in which the Affinity of reaction one is
this
much the center is zero and that's
equilibrium and the Affinity of the
second reaction is is this
much
okay here the rate of entropy uh
production so the quadratic
form has a certain
value different than
zero and these Contour plots represent
all other
non equilibrium states that have that
same value of the
entropy As you move further from
equilibrium the entropy goes
up as you go towards equilibrium the
entropy goes down so you may think of
those U uh contour lines as those of an
ellipsoid that is touching zero at
equilibrium the red curves
represent uh the gradients of these
Contours so these are these curves are
everywhere
orthogonal
to uh the constant entropy Contour
uh
lines
okay all
right the expression for the
gradient is the gradient is like a
generalized derivative so uh the
derivative of s dot with respect to Y
Vector this is the
gradient and if I plot the gradient
uh it has it is a
vector which is
orthogonal I plot it here so it's
orthogonal to uh the curve for which it
is the
gradient
okay now what the Ziggler principle
orthogonality relation says is that I
take this Vector which is the gr take
half of it and that gives me the uh
right
the right
Vector the Epsilon dot is the right
Vector is just a half of the the red is
the half of the of the
black and this Vector
here uh let me now last step move it
back to uh the to to here to the
zero so then on the same plot I am now
reading on this axis the
one component so that is the rate of the
first reaction and on this other axis
the second component so that's the rate
of the second
reaction and what this shows is that uh
yeah you know if uh if you didn't if you
had only one reaction and one
Affinity uh the proportionality is
typically that uh
the rate and the Affinity have the same
sign so if uh uh if Y is is neg is
positive um Epsilon one is
positive and the their relation is uh
like take instead of this system here
instead of having 2 by two just one by
one it's simply the proportionality l11
is the direct proportionality and it
says that the rate of one is is
proportional to and also if you had only
two reaction two the rate of reaction
two is proportional to its degree of
dise equilibrium same sign because we
said that these L's are
positive but here you see the
coupling makes it
so so the cross the off diagonal ter
makes it so in this particular region of
of
states that look at reaction two it has
a positive Affinity but as a result of
the cap gets a negative reaction rate so
these off diagonal
terms may actually uh Drive the system
in uh somewhat unexpected
Direction something that if it were by
itself would
violate the uh the
entropy non decrease
principle because if I didn't
have also the other terms and only this
one uh it's so if I have only one
reaction it is impossible that the rate
be in the opposite sign of the
Affinity okay so that is
the at least in the business of
reactions chemical
reactions uh the importance of these
coupling
terms and it is
actually for things like these for many
aspects of this chemistry
of equilibrium that
uh also IIA pin
has gotten Nobel Prize forget now what
year um but I want to just that I
mention him I want to also mention that
if you're doing your PhD thesis in the
field of thermodynamics whatever field
of
thermodynamics uh make sure you apply
for theia PR Goin prize
for
thermodynamics which is held every two
years and uh it's um it's a prestigious
thing doesn't bring a lot of money but
it's it gives you some Prestige and you
may look up uh the website of the of the
prize and see what the previous winners
are uh very diverse and very um high
level set of uh of guys who most of
which are now uh renowned
professors World worldwide because it's
like an international
PR
okay so let's do a little uh
switch first of all it sound like like
sounds like a switch back and then it
will be a switch forward so let's go
back to heat
transfer and this is a a slide that more
or less we have already seen maybe not
exactly in this
fashion you take a a onedimensional
fluid
element subject to a gradient of
temperature so it's it's fluid element
on one side as one temperature so
there's a heat interaction at one
temperature with the fluid element on
its left and another heat
interaction at a different temperature
slightly different temperature with the
element on the
right and for the moment let's assume
that this is in a steady
state so let's do the energy
balance and we do the energy balance per
unit of area of the surface of of um
interaction between these adjacent
elements so zero because we are at
steady state so there is no accumulation
of energy
um otherwise here it would be the
derivative of uh of the energy per unit
volume
divided with respect to time but it's
zero because we are assuming steady
state
is equal
to the heat flux I'm going I'm using
here the notation of heat transfer so
qou Prime is the typical notation for
heat transfer
uh and then we have a heat flux at X
Plus
DX so you may recognize this is the
incremental
uh the increment of of the function Q
Prime is a function of X so this is the
partial of Q Prime with respect to X
time DX and it is equal to
zero and then we do the entropy
balance remember we're doing the balance
for this element in the
center so here we have to account for
here I multiplied by a okay so we have
to account for the entropy coming in
from the
left which is Q dot over
t
uh and qou Prime is Q do over a is the
flux so this is the heat rate per unit
area minus the uh entropy that goes uh
out on the other
side and this is Q Prime divided by the
temperature which prevails there which
is different slightly but different
different and then plus the entropy
produced by
irreversibility so here I'm going
denoting this lower case s with the
triple prime is entropy generated by
reversibility per unit
volume and the dot is the right so
that's soon we will go actually already
here we give a a a special symbol for
that so we use from one from now on when
we you see Sigma it's not it's not the
stress tensor it's not the surface
tension it's the rate of entropy
production per
unit sometimes different fields uh use
the same symbol for different purposes
but uh there is only one Greek alphabet
okay so from this
one if you do properly this
uh use this
and recognize the
incremental TX plus DX minus TX ided by
DX that's the derivative of t with
respect to
X and the
denominator um
here you can neglect the
difference
of and so this denominator you can
simply call it t^ s that's why the
approximate
symbol
okay okay so we like uh to write this as
a so the entropy production
rate you we write to write it as the as
the flux heat flux times this gradient
of the inverse
temperature this will is analogous and
this is why we we are doing it now it's
analogous to the chemical um um idea
that right entropy production rates are
given by a product
of reaction rate times an affinity if
you interpret this gradient of uh the
inverse temperature as the
Affinity or the degree of this
equilibrium
in with respect to heat
transfer then you have a similar
concept and we have already discussed
this in a previous lecture so I will not
do it now but I simply remind you that
this part of the slide was to
um uh show
that
um you cannot be at
equilibrium if this is different from
zero and
therefore when we actually
adopt an
equilibrium local equilibrium model for
our fluid element we are neglecting this
difference and you will see uh hopefully
uh today uh we will see what that uh
what accounting for that
difference uh
makes uh and how things change if you do
account for that but for the
moment if you want you just go back to
that previous lecture to
find more discussion about this this
graph what we may uh
also add is the following
now this fluid element in the middle of
two things that are at different
temperatures although minute
differences uh could be in
principle see that was a that was that
heat transfer uh direct with with no
useful effect is dissipative and in fact
you have entropy produced by
reversibility and we have learned that
whenever you have entropy produced by
reversibility you could if you have if
you can avoid that entropy production
you can do something useful with it so
here what you would uh what what you
would need to do is to replace your
fluid element
by a small heat engine a
local uh
something maybe bacteria maybe um
because here it maybe a small small
system in any case a heat engine
that while uh uh exploiting this
temperature difference extracts some
work like a Carno
engine uh we have learned that in order
to compute this the maximum work you
have to do energy balance and entropy
balance and you have to assume that the
entropy produced by irreversibility is
equal to zero if you do that so you
start from the entropy balance and
impose that this the
derivative that the entropy that goes
out here is equal to the entropy that
comes
in
uh that gives
you one relation then if you substitute
it back into the energy balance it gives
you uh that maximum work
and of course the answer we could have
done it even without redoing the energy
and entropy balances it the answer is
that the maximum work you extract there
is equal to the to the
temperature that prevails around there
more or less is the
same so T times the entropy times Sigma
times the entropy that you uh you would
have produced by IR ibility if you
didn't do that
work okay so you get this relation
here
um if your fluid element is in is a is
is three dimensional instead of of if
you okay here we've
discussed uh a onedimensional
case but if you
you can make it also
three-dimensional so you you have a nice
uh a nice uh fluid elements of the kind
that you consider in in 3D heat transfer
then of course you have to account for
exchanges uh
of heat the heat flux is a vector that
has the three components
and the equivalent of the energy balance
here this derivative of Q respect to X
is equal to zero becomes the the
Divergence of the vector Q Prime is
equal to zero or in this other problem
it becomes the Divergence of Q overt of
the vector Q overt which is the entropy
flux uh is equal to zero
and uh this expression for the entropy
production rate per unit
volume if from this uh which is just the
X component of the heat flux times the X
component of the gradient in one / T it
becomes the dot product the scalar
product of the heat flux into the
gradient of 1/ T which is a
vector so I like this is why I like to
put the underline uh into under the
nabla symbol because nabla is a vector
operator like Q okay I'm sure you are
familiar with
that so
nabla is this operator here
it's a vector which has as components
the partial derivative
symbols all right so we have seen the
analogy in the
structure for the rate of entropy
production
with the chemical
U
formalism Affinity times rate Affinity
times rate rate of heat rate of heat
exchange and so the Affinity is the
gradient in the
temperature so if we do let's do the
same
procedure let us
assume like we did that the Epsilon dot
is a fun function of the Infinity with
the function being zero at equilibrium
let's assume the same here so let's
assume that the
heat flux Vector is a function of the
gradient of the inverse
temperature and it is equal to zero if
there is no
gradient because we know that if the
temperature profile is flat there's no
gradient there is no heat flux okay and
we linearize this expression here like
we did
here so you take this
derivative and so the derivative of
vector respect to another Vector becomes
tensor we call it
l double underline it's for a
tensor and the first term in the and so
you're linearizing in in gradient of one
/ T so that multiplies gradient of one
over T and of course this tensor is to
be evaluated at equilibrium so this is
an equilibrium
property you would evaluate this when
there is no gradient when the
temperature is
flat well if you call that
L uh
K tensor times t^ s you obtain the for
of thermal uh
conduction
okay on which most of the heat transfer
is
based so this is a fundamental step then
from this you construct all the
applications
notice that uh K is is a tensor first of
all and
only in some special
cases uh that tensor is isotropic so you
need only one one variable to represent
it so for an isotropic material then you
can write uh
that you Q Prime I'm sorry Q Prime is
equal to minus
K the gradient of of
T that's because of course the gradient
of uh 1 / T is equal to minus 1 / T ^ 2
* the gradient of T okay
so that is the uh standard the forier
law of proportionality heat and so that
it says that the heat flux is in the in
the direction of of
the the
gradient
right and that's true for an isotropic
material but for an an anisotropic
material you may have
that the gradient is in One Direction
and The U heat flux is in another
direction for example here suppose you
have a
two-dimensional problem in which you
have a two-dimensional anisotropic
material um and so the two- dimensional
means that uh
whatever uh nothing changes with the Z
Direction neither the temperature nor
the heat flux nor the boundary
conditions in that case every everything
that every partial derivative with
respect to Z is equal to zero that's
condition for 2D symmetri of
things so for example the temperature
field depends only on X and Y that's to
simplify and here so this is this
expression
the for La
becomes this linear expression
here and how do you build nonisotropic
materials for example by sandwiching uh
layers of different materials for
example you could have a a highly
conductive layer of material like carbon
sheet uh
in sandwiched
between an epoxy or some other material
with low
conductivity that makes an
isotropy okay so these are the equations
let's see how you would
uh so in order to characterize this
material
uh don't just have one thermal
conductivity you need to measure three
parameters or actually there are four
entries in The
Matrix but thanks to onager
principle the off diagonal ones must be
equal because of it his reciprocity
General reciprocity theorem which
applies all also in this
business and therefore you need only to
measure three and here are the three
measurements that you could
make you cut the sample of your
material thin in the X
Direction and assume that uh things in
the y direction do not change or set up
in EXP expent in which they don't
change and then so that you are set up
to use the first equation here with no
component of the gradient in temperature
in the y direction this is zero and you
have only the this direct relation so
you measure the heat flux you measure
the gradient in temperature the across
the small thickness of your sample and
you take that ratio uh and uh so this
ratio gives you the conductivity the
XX component of the conductivity tensor
that must be
positive because uh this
tensor is is a onager matrix so it is to
be positive semide
definite do the same for the y direction
and and and and you measure kou y
uh now to measure the off diagonal terms
one way is to put your
sample you squeeze
it uh between
insulating um
materials in the uh two faces on the
with the direction in the Y Direction
with the normal in the y direction okay
so this is a an insulation this is an
insulation and you subject your sample
to a gradient in temperature in the uh X
Direction
okay now since the insulating material
uh since this um wall is insulated the
Heat
component in the Y the y direction here
is zero and also here is zero so you can
assume that it is zero
also uh not really precise but that it
is zero also in in between because this
is supposed to be a small thickness of
your
sample
however in spite of that so there is no
heat flux in the vertical Direction
Direction yet you're going to build up a
gradient in temperature in that
direction
because of uh this equation here which
is Rewritten
here the insulation sets this equal to
zero and therefore makes these two terms
equal to one
another I mean equal and opposite to one
another
so by measuring the gradient in
temperature that that builds up in the y
direction and dividing by dividing it by
the imposed gradient in temperature in
the X Direction you get this ratio of
the off diagonal
coefficient versus the direct
coefficient okay
and in fact you notice that u in this
case the X Direction component of the
heat
flux Q Prime
X is
less than it was in this other example
in this other situation because you see
the the the there is still
proportionality between the flux
and the imposed gradient in the X
Direction but the coefficient of
proportionality is
smaller physically you can you can
realize that uh this sandwich makes it
so that the heat
flux finds it easier to run through the
high conductivity uh
layers and since those layers are
inclined as hinted by these inclined
lines here uh the heat flux enters here
but it it likes to go up in following
the
um the high conductivity
materials that's why you build up
temperature gradient in the direction uh
where there is no heat uh net heat flux
all right
so this uh is also called riluk
effect which was discovered before on
Sager theorem many of the uh things that
are rationalized by the onager
reciprocity theorem were actually
discovered independently and not uh
sometimes not even connected to one
another
uh by uh various researchers in the 19th
century and
U it's only later on that you could
connect them and so it's somehow you had
four different effects that thanks to on
Sager were related and become only three
independent
ones notice also that for example using
this uh idea
you can construct a sensor a
non-disturbing heat heat flux
sensor
uh
because in here by putting the
thermocouples across the
sample which are off the way the where
the heat flux
goes by measuring this temperature
different difference you measure you
measure the heat
flux and
therefore uh you don't have to put
thermocouples in the way of a small
sample because the typically if you put
the thermocouple that will disturb the
measurement because the thermocouple has
it own size and therefore it uh it
Alters the actual
situation okay
of course
in the Fier uh equation
of so the the complete energy
balance for
a for a for a
uh with with no uh no motion no velocity
so not not a gas or a fluid but say
solid or maybe a static
fluid this is the
U equation and if you have for example a
gas uh okay this
U uh row U is the okay let's say that uh
rou is the energy per unit
volume okay so you could write it as
as M over V * U over
M and so by seeing that you see this is
wrw and this is U so here I'm using U
without the star the asteris
but that's the uh energy per unit
Mass so specific energy per unit
mass and for example for a gas that
would be row
uh CV times
t or at least the
derivative with respect to time of r u
can be written as uh this derivative
here and if the density is constant and
the specific heat is constant it goes
out of the derivative and you get only
uh uh row
CV DT
oft minus the
gradient
of uh Q okay Q is
uh for your equation if you have an
isotropic
material if it is a okay let's keep it
as a Tropic just simplicity so I have to
M to substitute here minus K times the
gradient in t Okay so that makes
it if K this requires that K be
independent of of space of temperature
so if K is a constant it goes out of
this otherwise you have to keep it
inside so if K is constant because con
because uh the conductivity of materials
does change with temperature so this
step may not be always allowed but if
you do that this
becomes um the laash of the temperature
because you know that the gradient
dotted into the gradient gives the laian
operation
if you dot this Vector into another
Vector equal to
itself the dot product gives you uh the
products of the components of the
vectors and so here you have the partial
of x times another partial of X so
that's the second derivative with
respect to X twice and those are uh the
various ingredients the three uh of that
represent uh the LA
okay all right so in any case this is
the equation of
Fier the for energy energy
balance and
um yeah um there is a if you have
nonisotropic
material
material there is an interesting change
of coordinates if we have seen
that the the heat flux and the gradient
temperature are not in the
same
direction and there is
a a change of
coordinates that you can do
uh so Define nonorthogonal coordinates
instead of the usual orthogonal X and Y
small X and Y you can define capital X
and Y here
actually this is wrong it's not there is
no equal sign here this is just the
multiplication so that's the linear
combination of the original coordinates
to give these
um coordinates with are at a certain
angle between one another and if you
write it that way then
the
equation um the the laion in terms of
the new coordinates becomes like that
for
a uniform
material and um where K is equal the
effective
conductivity uniform conductivity is
equal to this linear combination of the
various
uh term so this is the it's like the the
gradient I mean the the square root of
the of the determinant of the
tensor conductivity tensor and also the
heat
flux a vector in the original
coordinates it becomes a linear
combination also here there is should be
I have to correct this it shouldn't be
an equal sign it's just a multiplication
sign and it gives the um
the the
flux component in this new nonorthogonal
coordinates and they are related through
that uh
conductivity directly so there are no
off diagonal terms okay so this is just
a useful change of coordinates but there
is one last uh item that I wanted I
promise I would
discuss which has to do with this
problem that if you
are dealing with the heat
transfer there is this
conundrum of the fact that
um the
entropy that you cannot be at
equilibrium uh and in fact the so the
entropy of
your sample or your
material is off the equilibrium so
assigning it the equilibrium entropy
introduces an error and it's interesting
to see how you now solve that problem uh
by assuming uh instead assigning to the
fluid element or continum element not
the equilibrium entropy but an entropy
Which is less than equilibrium and it
is departs from equilibrium more the
higher the heat transfer so we make it
through a proportionality constant which
I for convenience called B over2 uh
proportional to the modulus of the
square of the heat transfer so clearly
if you're at equilibrium there is no
heat transfer and this
difference so the entropy is that over
equ but the higher the heat transfer the
farther you are from
equilibrium so if I take the
differential of this one uh it gives me
the differential of the equilibrium
State plus the differential of that
which
is so the two goes away it's B Q doq
Plus q. DQ plus DQ doq so it's twice Q
do
DQ
okay now
the this is important because if we do
the um the entropy
balance like we wrote the energy balance
here we should write also the entropy
balance and that is given by the
Divergence of the heat of the entropy
flux uh which is Q over
t plus uh the rate of entropy production
uh per unit
volume which is
Sigma now usually these
two are related through the Gibs the
Gibs relation the Gibs relation is you
can write it as
the S = 1 / t d of row
U and uh there is
I like to write it in terms of entropy
per unit volume is that in this way from
the Gibbs relation we'll see more later
about this uh the pressure disappears
the pressure is always a bit problematic
to treat so if you find a way that it it
disappears uh it's better okay so if
this is true for the differential
differential it means all possible
changes in all directions it's true also
if you take the derivative with respect
to time so just move uh only with
respect to time so this can also be
written as partial with respect to
T and is 1 / T * the partial with
respect to T overall
U okay and yeah this is short end for
the partial with respect to time and so
this the Gibs relation couples the
energy uh and the entropy balance and so
in that
way and this is
actually what I just uh
wrote yes I should no this is true
because the GS relation is valid for
equilibrium so this is true for the E
for the equilibrium entropy s SA
or S Sub s stable equilibrium
State yeah here I should just unify the
notation
anyway so if you do this
substitution and you can obtain the
expression for the entropy production
which is the product of the heat flux
times this thing so this not only the
gradient in one / t uh but there is also
B uh a q dot b times derivative with
respect to T of Q which comes from
here so this term in in in square
brackets is now the
Affinity so the Affinity change the
expression for the Affinity has
changed and if we assume a linear
relation between flux and
Affinity
through positive constant
L what we obtain is a
correction to the F law of conduction
which
was proposed by
katano which gives rise to the katano
heat equation
1948 katano didn't uh start
from these premises he wanted to fix
another problem that I'm describing in a
second but so uh let's let's take this
one and then substitute back into the
energy balance equation so we have an
expression for qou Prime you can take uh
the the Divergence of that and that
gives you this term
which is like typical for but also it
takes it's the gradient I mean the the
the Divergence of the partial derivative
with respect to
T diverence of this
contribution you can
switch
different partial derivative with
respect to time with have the partial
derivatives with respect to
space and uh and so this also appears
and again using the energy balance is is
the partial with respect to time of r u
so you have the double partial with
respect to time which if you then
substitute
um this expression for the for the
specific Heats and the
density uh then can be Rewritten in this
way so in other words you will
obtain an equation with double second
derivative uh with respect to time of
the temperature first derivative respect
to time and then the usual if you didn't
have that term you would have the
standard
for
equation but with that term things
change and it becomes a dumped wave
equation and it actually
fixes a a problem the probably I'm sure
you're familiar with uh this problem
from heat transfer in which you have
semi infinite uh solid which is
initially at a certain temperature T
t0 and at time equal zero you um
suddenly change and keep from from then
on the temperature temperature here on
the
surface uh as a result you obtain Pro
temperature profiles that look like that
given by the error function uh
distribution uh with SP
with and as time goes on the
distribution goes like that so as time
proceeds but what is the problem the non
physical problem is that already start
starting from time0 plus when the error
function uh
sets
on it turns out that since the error
function
is is non zero everywhere it turns out
that maybe minute but you still have a
an infinite prop propagation rate of
what you have done uh here which is UN
physical uh because there is no
infinite if you you do something here
now it it is unphysical to think that it
is felt immediately at infinite
distance uh so the katano equation
solves this uh
problem and in fact uh this Pro so this
equation has been used to represent the
Early times of this sharp change of
temperature problem or
uh situations in which
you change the uh boundary conditions
very quickly and therefore
uh you need to to to account for a a
propagation speed which is this
coefficient here becomes now the wave
celarity and the
gamma becomes The Dumping coefficient
okay
and okay so yeah yeah um so time is up
and uh I think we should stop uh here
for today