and you know you heard Bruce talk about
the manufacturing at MIT initiative uh
our next speaker Chris love is not only
a professor of of chemical engineering
at MIT but he's also one of the leaders
of manufacturing at MIT and you know I
think there's some similarities and some
differences with with Bruce Becker
whereas you know Chris has an academic
appointment and he's um an entrepreneur
um and I think in contrast to what Bruce
was talking about is applying new
technologies in in many Legacy sectors
Chris has experience applying new
manufacturing techniques and thinking
about new ways of manufacturing in an
emerging sector of uh biotechnology and
biomanufacturing so uh Chris so glad to
have you here and I'm really excited for
your
talk thanks Ben really appreciate the
opportunity here to share a little bit
about the bioeconomy uh I'll start with
a quote you know a new era is beginning
uh this was a quote that Steve Jobs gave
not about the Silicon Valley
Technologies but rather about about the
impact that biology would have in the
21st century uh so what I'd like to do
here is with the next 25 minutes we have
uh including your questions is to talk a
little bit about what is the bioeconomy
going to look like going forward what
does this really mean and where are the
opportunities in manufacturing to kind
of really fully participate and enable
that economy uh which stands to be you
know quite an important one in terms of
both uh how we deliver materials but
also things that we appreciate like
medicines as well
so the bioeconomy depending on how you
consider it what you uh you know how you
measure it it really can touch
everything that we have going forward in
fact some estimates have put this at you
know approximately $4 trillion dollar of
Economic Development over the next 10
years uh with about a trillion of that
attributed to the United States and this
really cuts across really every sector
that uh is a key part of our economy
biology is going to have a role in
contributing to production in each of
these different spaces and some of you
might already have some experience in uh
materials and products that are already
enabled by biology picked a few examples
here there's many more I'm sure but if
you've had an impossible Burger
somewhere uh you have had a bioeconomy
type product Stella McCartney and many
other designers are really thinking
deeply about how to use materials that
are made from biological sources uh as
part of their fashion uh wees and we see
a number of different chemicals now
especially fine chemic chical fragrances
and intermediate ingredients starting to
be made by biological methods and so in
all of these different areas you know
there's some estimates that as much as
60% of raw materials around the world
could be produced by biology in the next
10 to 15
years what's really powerful in thinking
about the bioeconomy is that it is
something that offers a completely
circular approach uh the the the source
of energy in biology to generate plants
and such of course is the Sun these
plants can be broken down or different
kinds of materials can be broken down
and processed into other raw ingredients
and materials that can be used then to
create what I would call Value ad
products uh Fine Chemicals specific uh
proteins uh cells that we need for
different kinds of uh other products and
if done in the right way these are uh
circular types of processes and what's
really interesting about this is an
economic style is that this can occur at
a very macro scale level right across
the globe but it could also be done at a
very local level and so there's
opportunities as we think about what the
bioeconomy is going to look like uh to
think both locally and globally in terms
of how these systems might uh
interact and just to put it in
perspective I I really like this
analysis which looks specifically at
growing plant-based Pro proteins you
know through a variety of different
mechanisms but you can see the sort of
impact that uh investing in this
particular space of ology can have on
things like uh sustainability uh this is
just looking across several different
sectors as to money invested in what's
the the largest impact on reducing
carbon uh emission equivalents and the
bioeconomy because it's natural you know
using water and and uh natural energy
sources is intrinsically a more
sustainable type of approach and so a
place where you get a lot of of benefit
from it and so I think intrinsically
linked into
the creation of the bioeconomy that's
emerging is this need to think about how
do we do this in a in a more sustainable
way as
well and just to put it in perspective
you know just to put some numbers around
it this effectively like for for
plant-based uh materials if we reached
kind of 11% penetrance of the of the
proteins into the overall market for
ingredients and Foods you could save
roughly a gigaton of CO2 emitted a year
this is roughly you know one year of
carbon neutral Japan or enough water for
London for 40 years so I think kind of
starts to put into perspective the
potential impact that even just a small
amount of this economy can have uh more
globally in total but the question of
course becomes like how do we think
about starting to unlock this potential
right this all sounds great and there's
a number of different elements that are
starting to emerge here uh we're seeing
the first wave of these kinds of
companies moving into the
space the nature of all products right
at the heart of it is
manufacturing we are as a as a nation
very uh good at Ting lots of new ideas
in fact the tools in synthetic biology
and metabolic engineering some of these
uh disciplines that have emerged to
reshape biology and to build things new
that weren't possible before are vastly
exploded right we have a number of
different research centers and labs
around the country startup companies
that are creating new ideas in this
space uh but as we can kind of see from
this uh pcast report uh presidential
advisory Council report uh from a couple
years ago now biomanufacturing is that
critical link it links that product idea
and the research that we're doing in
that space to the marketplace and so the
question becomes given all of the
potential of the bioeconomy what's going
to be necessary to really truly
transform the biom manufacturing base
that we have in order to be able to
realize this economy at
scale and so I appreciate that not
everyone maybe is is fully firsts in
what goes into biomanufacturing and this
term I I find gets thrown around in a
lot of different ways right now uh in in
the the broader uh community
when we think about biomanufacturing
this is really about establishing
reliable processes to make and package
products that use biology at the core of
it uh and so this is at scale these are
you know tools that are being used to
produce uh the the material to purify it
and then the example that I've given
here is in formulation for a medicine
but some type of packaging that is you
know could be for a food product or a
fragrance for example um what what this
typically involves is cells and cells
are messy cells are biology they grow
and they're not perfectly understood but
what's amazing is that the tools for
uncovering that biology are starting to
change quite drastically and so we're
starting to be much more precise in our
ability to Define and understand these
and so what I want to do in the time
that we have here left together is kind
of unpack a little bit about what
biomanufacturing looks like today and
where it might be headed next uh based
on some of these uh convergences of
better understanding of the biology
Automation and the advances that are now
possible at the interfaces between these
two spaces we heard in the last session
about AI that certainly has a component
in this as well uh and something that we
can we can think more about perhaps in
the panel
discussion all right so let's start with
what biomanufacturing looks like today
it's complicated it looks like you went
into your lab and you have a a little
flask that you grow some cells in and
then you you purify them through some
type of filter and you do something a bi
Manu facturing facility today largely
looks like that benchtop experiment
expanded at a much larger scale it's
very manual it's very complex and it has
a lot of touch points and so this means
that quality assurance and other types
of processes that we consider when we
think about manufacturing to ensure you
know reproducibility and reliability of
the products that are being produced has
a very different connotation we have to
be able to look at different
intermediate points to make sure that
things didn't get changed when somebody
took the VAP of material from one room
to the other one to start something new
and so this kind of lends itself not so
well right to thinking about this this
other vision of of a transformed
bioeconomy in which making products with
Biology becomes much more fasile and so
it's at this interface that we have to
think about what could be possible
next today to build one of these types
of facilities like the one that I've
shown you uh it depends a little bit on
the industry and the specifics that
you're interested in but you know
anywhere between 30 million and up to 2
billion
to build and it could take as long as 2
to 5 years to actually get all of the
physical equipment into a building
qualified validated and ready for
production uh so the lead times to build
this very large capital expenditure is
long uh and one of these facilities
typically only operates maybe 20 to 40
campaigns per year of operations and of
any kind and so as a result right that
you know building one facility is only
linearly scaling the Capac capacity that
we have access to in addition we need a
really large and expert trained
Workforce many of the folks that work in
this industry have advanced degrees or
uh you have trained with very specific
skill sets to be able to uh to operate
these types of protocols and to make
sure that the quality management is
there and so you know from an economics
standpoint right we really need to do
more with less how do we get to smaller
facilities that are faster to stand up
that cost less capex and perhaps use a
different kind of skilled labor in order
to actually operate these and so it's at
this intersection that we've been
thinking a lot over the last couple of
years uh and we'll talk about that a
little bit more
here the other challenge in
manufacturing that we have to think
about how to overcome is the complexity
and diversity of products I've shown
here sort of one one way to Envision
this this sort of paramal scheme where
at the base of this are the core
elements that we need to make anything
in biology this is salts and sugar
sugars and uh amino acids you might need
some plastic so the chemicals these are
used to produce things like DNA or
proteins which are then used to make
more complex products like mRNA vaccines
or uh alternative food products or
microbiome type uh Solutions and then
these might even be integrated a step
further into artificial tissues the
challenge is kind of the one that's
shown on the left that as we start to
scale the the biology into more and more
complex Solutions the cost of manufa
facturing those is
increasing there's also a challenge in
that as we want to introduce new
products into the marketplace we have to
have access to capacity I've mentioned
how expensive the capacity is to build
out if we think about where that
capacity lies a very large amount of it
lies in other parts of the world so in
Europe and and and Asia these are not
facilities that are available in the
United States for manufacturing and so
there's a kind of crunch overall in the
capacity that's available in thinking
about bringing those Innovative new
ideas and new products that could be
really important for the economy overall
into the marketplace in a timely and
efficient
manner the other challenge of course I'm
sure as you appreciate is the capital
expenses and the Returns on investment
are best suited at the more complex
biological products which means that we
are also at a point where we need to
think carefully about what it looks like
to to assure supply chain of some of the
basic building blocks of the bioeconomy
chemicals and and uh bi biological
components plasmas and and proteins
lipids that can power some of these more
advanced and exciting ideas that are uh
you know really at the heart of what's
in a number of different startup
companies and academic institutions
these
days so when we think about like how do
we transform this underlying Base today
we're sitting at this this standpoint
where we have you know very complex
largely manual uh and centralized
facilities that cost a lot to build out
and you know I think as we kind of
appreciate in order to scale up
production we really want to scale up
certain aspects that you know for
certain types of products it's going to
be necessary to go to very very large
scales in order to drop that denominator
in the economies of scale and so for
certain products like you commercial
scale you know Global Supply of certain
foods or materials this is going to be
very very important uh to be able to do
but the question is how do we innovate
fast in this this realm these are very
expensive facilities to build they take
a long time and they will take you know
they will basically be fit for purpose
for one use and so what we've kind of
been thinking a bit about and seeing uh
happen as a result of kind of movement
in other Industries we might look at
like additive manufacturing or even
inkjet printers as other examples of
distributed production small footprint
manufacturing that complements this kind
of very large scale uh represents a
really unique opportunity in the
biomanufacturing landscape to bring low
Capital expense uh entry points in for
small and medium Enterprises that are
trying to get started and to allow for
from vertical integration in this uh
particular uh sector these are going to
be absolutely dependent on a high degree
of automation uh but would enable kind
of pilot and entry new product
introductions uh and allow for you know
special use complex products things like
cell and Gene therapies that are you
know sort of a unique and special uh use
case so what would what would physically
technology-wise be necessary to
transform this uh you I've mentioned
doing more for Less we need the
processes to be continuous today as I
kind of showed you Manufacturing in this
industry is largely done in batch so
these are staged operations where you
transform from one to the other that
demands very large volumes by going to
continuous I can reduce my overall
footprint I can reduce the amount of
materials that I'm using there's also an
opportunity to switch to single use
these are disposable elements as opposed
to the stainless steel type tanks that I
showed you seems counterintuitive at
first but when you start to consider the
energy cost the chemical cost and the
water costs of actually cleaning those
stainless steel facilities in order to
uh remove any residuals from one product
to another one single use materials
become much more interesting and if you
combine that with as we're seeing across
some of the vendors now thinking about
bioplastics that are degradable suddenly
the footprint of being able to
manufacture by the biology even though
it's using a plastic base as opposed to
a chemical stainless steel base uh is
quite
compelling all of this means
intensification
uh reducing the total volume of the
facility itself the energy costs for the
HVAC in many of these facilities is 50%
of the carbon footprint so getting to
smaller and smaller facilities
facilitates that but the only way to get
to smaller of course is going to be to
automate some of those steps and to
remove barriers between
steps and we're already starting to see
this transition occur in a in a high
value industry this is occurring in the
biopharmaceutical space where they've
made the conscious decision over the
last 10 years to really move from fed
batch operations into single use
intensified continuous processing for
very specific applications like
monoclonal antibodies used in in uh
biopharmaceuticals but this chart kind
of gives you a sense of between the blue
arrow and yellow arrow the the real
saving and that present cost of being
able to stand up a new facility based on
these newer principles compared to more
traditional ones there's an opportunity
now for the other Industries in the
sector to really think deeply about how
they can also so achieve these economies
uh in in production uh cost but also uh
in in improving their
sustainability to kind of put all of
this in perspective and to show you kind
of technologically what a process like
this might look like today this is a
state-of-the-art continuous monoclonal
antibody production process there's a
bunch of blocks on here but effectively
you know you have cells in the top left
they produce the monoclonal antibody
that flows through all of the the green
lines through a number of different
steps into the bottom left where it says
bulk these are uh the individual steps
that are required to assure the safety
and sterility of the material that's
produced as well as to to to make it
efficacious but what's interesting is
this is where there's now an
intersection and convergence between the
biology and what we're learning on that
front and the engineering that I just
showed you the mechanical steps of
moving fluids around hosts the biology
for making things like proteins is
becoming a lot like software and we can
think about this a lot in the same uh
mindset I can have a a host maybe it's a
simple host a yeast that I can reprogram
based on reading its genome and writing
its genome to be able to do tasks that I
want make that monoclonal antibody make
a food protein make a fragrance uh make
a single cell protein for cattle feed
stocks these are all different tasks
that I might accomplish I can read and
write them now in very efficient ways uh
We've started a Consortium here at MIT
that is building some of these basic
building blocks uh we have a very
diverse membership as you can see from
biopharmaceutical companies to vendors
to uh companies that are interested in
very large scale uh protein production
and really trying to understand like
what are the key levers and how do we
start to build an open source platform
for advancing these types of biologies
in a new new
light and if you have these new
biologies as we're advancing in this
this particular area it allows you to
revisit some of that engineering mindset
I've shown here what you could do if you
used an alternative biology to power
that same platform for protein
production I've cut out three or four
distinct key steps that are key cost
drivers reduce the complex ability
reduce the interfaces between it and
based on some modeling work that we've
done uh with a couple of our
biopharmaceutical company Partners we've
shown that actually getting to uh
similar cost targets is possible with
even less physical output from the
facility just because of the speed with
which some of these other Al biologies
operate and so you can start to really
shrink this thing down into a different
type of form factor and so our idea you
know one idea that we're we're exploring
is you could you build this to be
something that's easy as agile as
printing this is not to replace
centralized facilities but we all have
the experience of having a desktop
printer I have one here sitting next to
me it costs like 80 bucks and I can
print anything I want and when I'm done
printing something I can take that same
file and take it to the commercial
printer and print that exact same thing
how do we enable the bioeconomy by
building these this kind of uh simple
Technologies to facilitate that we had
an opportunity in MIT to build one such
system as a prototype system we built
and demonstrated a few years ago we
showed that we could use the same
physical system using that yeast toast
that I described a moment ago to produce
three different FDA approved
biopharmaceutical products all with
phase appropriate clinical grade quality
uh all in a fully automated and fully
hands-free manner we've now gone on and
made a number of different proteins on
this particular platform
uh and we're we moved this into a
company that's now starting to
commercialize this uh this is an example
of one of their systems here shown in
the picture at sunflower Therapeutics
where they're building you know GMP
grade versions of these kinds of
facilities they can fit in a small room
like an office space or seminar uh kind
of facility and what's cool is that each
one has the capability of making a set
of different products they showed during
the the pandemic that they could
actually produce a couple of different U
materials gcsf used a number of cancer
treatments and a covid-19 vaccine
subunit they were able to do all of this
with one of those systems like I showed
you in a warehouse that was not GMP
grade that was not you know something
that you would typically see in a biom
manufacturing space but uh met all of
the requirements to be clinical great
because it's fully closed and fully uh
you know automated in the way that it
operates so I think these are some of
the directions that are going to be
possible with these types of
Technologies and what you can now
imagine is as we think about Regional
innovation hubs how do we start to
enable a wide range of different
innovators to be able to plug into the
manufacturing uh to be able to
facilitate their ideas for the
bioeconomy uh these types of low
footprint uh small footprint
manufacturing Solutions are now
available for a wide different range of
different um types of products I've
showed you one for proteins but there's
ones for small molecules mRNA and cells
and so we think that not only does this
address sort of the robustness but it
also adds a strong complement to the
base in thinking about how do we enable
more products into the
bioeconomy there is still work to be
done and I'll just highlight here the
last couple of slides here that that the
science of the biomanufacturing itself
still needs a lot of work we as a nation
have spent a lot of time thinking about
the front end of biotechnology how do we
build new drugs how do we build new
products uh how do we engineer the
organisms we spend less time thinking
about the scaling of that particular
question and outline here a few
different topics that I think are
critical in being able to build those
Next Generation facilities that are
going to be able to meet the cost
targets and such uh but what's
encouraging is even those models that I
showed you for small footprint the costs
per gram because they're highly
automated and use very little labor can
be very equivalent to large volume
manufacturing uh at certain inflection
points this certainly works in the
biopharmaceutical space and now the
opportunity is to bring some of those
ideas into some of these other ones
where we have to drive the cost of
production down even further so I'll
stop here and I'll just you know I just
encourage you I think as we think about
what the bioeconomy means it really is
going to mean Transforming Our biom
manufacturing approach and if we can
make it more accessible we can really
Empower circular bioeconomies to occur
at really any scale of our economy and
ultimately lead to larger uh more
sustainable uh infrastructure thanks for
the time Ben and look forward to uh to
the panel discussion
later great thanks so much Chris and and
we'll be sure if you have any questions
for for Chris please put them in the
chat we can revisit in the panel