now we are back to the second segment of
the next generation of MTL leaders and
innovators and this is the final session
and we will feature four extraordinary
colleagues as speakers who are really
shaping the future of
MTL and these four colleagues are Sam
Cod so will there be a slide with the
names or not at least okay yeah so first
we will have Sam Cod who is an assistant
professor in electrical engineering and
computer science and he's working on
advancing computational design our
second speaker is cishan Yu she is an
assistant professor in electrical
engineering and computer science and
working on impactful Research in
biomedical Imaging our third speaker is
deblina sarar assistant professor in
Media Arts and Sciences bridging
nanoscale devices and AI with neuros
science and lastly we will have yena
notos also assistant professor in
electrical engineering and computer
science working on advancing
revolutionizing photonics and
computational Optics so we will go in
this order and have Sam here
first okay while we wait uh hi I'm Sam
I'm so excited to be here I'm a new
faculty here at MIT my research focus is
in power Electronics so how to take one
type of electrical energy and turn it
into another type of electrical energy
and so uh I mainly work in discreet oh
there we go uh discret circuits uh but
it's really exciting to be a part of MTL
and have that connection uh with folks
who are working on devices and materials
as well now I'm going to argue today
that future electrification requires
improved power conversion what we have
right now is not good enough if we look
at applications of electrification uh
electrified transportation is one of the
most common ones uh we have electric
vehicles readily available they're not
being adopted we still have less than 1%
of evv adoption in the US so we need to
make charging more accessible and more
affordable if we look at Power
Electronics on board your electric
vehicle it starts with the charger
whether that's DC fast or onboard
charger the motor drive and then
everything else in your car has to go
through a power converter I do a lot of
work on electrified aircraft and
similarly we have the same type of power
drivetrain right we have a battery or a
fuel cell or maybe some parallel hybrid
structure we have a distribution system
and we have Power
Electronics there's been a lot of
discussion today about Computing the way
we deliver power to our gpus and our
CPUs matters a lot right we saw that
we're hitting this limit of how much
energy we have available on earth now
imagine if you're losing 10% of that
every time you go to a GPU or a CPU so
this building block is absolutely vital
and then we have Renewables which we
already have solar and wind but now
we're going to have close to hopefully
100% Renewables on the grid which means
our power converters also now need to
offer support and provide inertia to our
grid as we move towards more
Renewables and then there's more uh
Niche applications such as building a
future lunar microgrid right eventually
we're going to house uh astronauts on
the moon and we need power converters
that are going to be ble to handle
radiation
effects and then we also have high
voltage DC transmission so how are we
going to deal with all of these
Renewables on the grid and how are we
going to get that power from one place
to another uh and we need high voltage
converters that can handle reliability
and resilience and unfortunately what we
have right now isn't good enough to meet
these needs and when I what I say uh
meet those needs what I mean is we need
better power converters and we measure
this in a few different metrics when I
talk about high performance power
converters it's not just one place that
we need better power converters it's in
a lot of different
metrics the biggest one is efficiency
right we've already talked about that in
Computing it also matters for power
delivery how much power I deliver to my
source from my source to my load is the
most important question I need to answer
we also care about cost the size both in
volume and weight and also the
reliability now what makes my job fun is
that there is is no one size fits all
right if I'm designing a solar micro
inverter I really care about cost but
when I'm putting something on the moon
cost doesn't matter and so this means
that we have to do this optimization in
different ways for different power
converters and different
applications so today I'm going to talk
a little bit about some general Trends
in power conversion uh but like I said
there's really no one size fits all so
my job is to take different circuit
elements and piece them together as
building blocks
in power converters and we have passive
components which allow us to store and
process energy and then Active
Components and so you can tell uh that
we are circuits people because we like
to use this ideal switch
model but our passive components this is
the first question I want to answer is
how to best utilize these passive
components historically for the past 60
years we've used inductors to store and
process energy but that's not good
enough anymore and so now we're looking
at different building blocks that allow
us to better utilize energy processing
so here I'm showing a survey of all of
the commercially available capacitors
and inductors uh this is data scraped
from octo part and for each of these
components we're Computing the energy
density so the amount of energy per unit
volume we can store and what we find is
capacitors have over a thousand times
higher energy density potential than
inductors so this begs the question why
can't we use capacitors to store and
process energy now unfortunately I can't
just take where I have an inductor in a
circuit and pop in a capacitor and it
will not work the same o that messed up
but we can use hybrid switch capacitor
converters now if you look at the
Blurred squiggles you might be able to
tell some of those are
capacitors uh and the idea here is that
we primarily use capacitors to store and
process energy and this is my main area
of research now again we work in discret
power electronics and so so typically
when I show these types of converters
one of the first questions I get is
that's too many switches uh and we use a
lot of switches in these converters and
we're in the hundreds of volts region so
it is very difficult to manage these
switching losses but people are
primarily concerned from a reliability
aspect uh they worry that these are too
many switches and too many components
and in fact some of these topologies
have been around since the 60s but they
haven't been utilized because of this
concern of
reliability but because of advances in
switch technology better gallium nitride
and silicon carbide devices I can now
have 20 devices they're all switching
650 volts and I can do it efficiently
and in a small package and this is
really vital to our future now as far as
the question of reliability goes let me
show you one application so as I
mentioned I work a lot in hybrid
electric and fully electric aircraft
space uh it's an exciting space to work
in even if you don't think we're going
to get to fully electric aircraft even
just just moving to partially hybrid has
huge impact on emissions fuel
consumption noise maintenance and cost
so it can very directly and immediately
impact people's lives here we've
collaborated with a company called
ampair they're a hybrid electric
Aircraft company located in Southern
California and we built a type of hybrid
switch capacitor converter so one of
these lots of switches lots of
capacitors converters uh to interface
with their electric drivetrain on the
aircraft so this goes between the
battery and the distribution bus so it's
a DCd regulating converter it has a
really nice uh efficiency of 99.52%
including Gate Drive losses and a
specific power density so how much power
per unit weight we can process that's
about five times higher than what you
can get off the shelf but what's really
exciting about this project is we took
this system and we went through full low
altitude flight qualification testing so
we did vibration shock thermal Emi
failure Hazard analysis lots of control
to prove that these types of topology
that people were resilient were
concerned about the resiliency for can
be designed in a robust way we still
have a lot of things to tackle before we
can Implement these types of structures
and all of the applications I talked
about uh and that's what my research
group focuses on but uh it's a first
step towards showing this kind of
demonstration and in fact a few months
ago uh this actually flew on that
aircraft shown below as part of this
demonstration now let me zoom out a
little bit more like I said I primarily
work on capacitor-based
conversion but there's another question
of are there other passive components we
can use to store and process energy uh
and one of them is pasos so instead of
storing energy uh through electric
fields or magnetic fields we can store
it through mechanical energy and so Dave
peralt who's a wonderful faculty here at
MIT does a lot of work in pazos as well
as some folks at Stanford and Berkeley
uh and what they have demonstrated is
really impressive power density and even
up to 3 kilowatt which was uh previously
unheard of for pasos and so this is a
place we're really excited about in the
future uh is how these new devices can
move us
forward so I've talked about passive
components let me talk about Active
Components I mentioned briefly that
gallium nitride and silicon carbide have
completely changed the field of Power
Electronics our goal is to switch as
fast as possible uh in my types of
converters we're Limited in the hundreds
of kerz because we have so many Swit
but Dave peralt uh works in the
megahertz region and many people are
moving towards that and so are we
because the faster we switch the smaller
our passive components and this is
really one of the big bottlenecks
towards small and efficient power
conversion and so these new devices
really moves us forward and that's why
it's so exciting to be a part of MTL and
be surrounded by researchers who are
working on these new
devices now I'll mention just briefly uh
some of the active devices that we're
excited about um so currently mosfets
can only block voltage in One Direction
uh but there's monolithic bidirectional
switches being developed by a lot of
different companies these are also
called four quadrant or AC switches uh
when I talk to device manufacturers
they're not as excited about these
devices but in power Electronics we are
so excited because that means I can have
one device that replaces four and from a
complexity standpoint that is huge and
so in our world of Power Electronics uh
this is really kind of the thing people
are watching right now and because uh it
enables what's called current Source
inverters and Matrix converters so you
can directly turn AC into AC right now
you have to go AC DC DC AC which is a
little cumbersome uh and so this is a
really exciting place to be working in
there's a number of companies that have
preliminary devices uh that we've been
able to test and we're excited about uh
the future here here we're looking at
combining these devices with
capacitor-based topologies that enable
us to have buck and boost operation in a
single stage converter uh this is really
nice it's about a 10 times reduction in
passive component weight compared to a
conventional uh approach so 10 times is
a big deal in our field um
so with that let me end on this slide
because really in Power Electronics we
are pulled forward by new devices right
hopefully I've made that clear that new
passive components new switches mean
that we have new topologies and we can
create better power conversion but
really what matters to us is the
applications of electrification if we
want to tackle these challenges and make
Computing available to everybody we need
better and more efficient power
conversion so that's all thank
you thank you so much Sam for this very
interesting talk on your work and do we
have questions either from the audience
or from the
pig no black says
no they say no and we are a little bit
tight in time so thanks a lot
again so San is our second speaker and I
know she was here yes she is here okay
great I'm very happy to be here for the
4th uh 40th anniversary of MTL so my
name is sishan my lab works on about
Imaging Technologies uh so the hope for
my lab or the dream of my lab is to have
better understanding and diagnosis of
diseases with non-invasive Imaging and
intrinsic contrast so this is probably a
very different flavor from the other
talks because we have not been able to
do this in chips yet but maybe in 10
years we will be able to move this to
chips so now this is mostly like bulk
Optics and devices and we want to bring
it into the hospitals for interoptic
Imaging and surgical
assessment uh should I use this
okay so uh just a brief introduction or
background on image and microsopy so for
the last 100 years a wide variety of
tools have been invented in the field of
biomedical Imaging that has transformed
biom medicine and people are probably
familiar with x-ray MRI pads which can
penetrate through the entire body and
gives you this visualization of internal
structures and functions of the body so
that doctors don't have to cut US Open
and see what's happening within us for a
diagnosis and so on the other spectrum
of this image modalities we have Optical
microsopy which gives us the unique
submicron resolution without destroying
the tissue so what it means that is that
we although we can only see maybe 10
microns 100 microns deep into the tissue
but the unque unque sub Cellar
resolution it gives us can help us
understand what individual cells are
doing in living
tissues but if you have uh dealt with
certain types of microscopes before most
microsopy has been limited to dead and
slice tissue and cells why is that what
is challenging about image and living
tissues so we could take a look at just
a tumor tissue for example so there are
two fundamental challenges is first
there is a lack of contrast the second
one is lack of uh contrast so if we look
at this
one let's see yeah so this is a piece of
tumor tissue if we just use natural
light to look at it it's very hard to
see through right that's the same thing
why we cannot see through the my skin
unless we use X-ray and the second thing
is unless we use stain the tumor
contrast won't stand out so uh in the
recent decades including two Nobel
prizes there has been a lot of efforts
on engineering the tissue so that we can
see through to an extent and have the
contrast and this includes the efforts
of how to section tissue so that we can
actually see what is within each tissue
at different Z slices this includes
efforts in clearing staining so that you
can actually see that is a tumor cell
that is normal cell and we can use
morphology of each cell to give the
tumor a grading so this has been very
effective and highly used in hospital
and clinical settings and also in
biological research Labs but as you can
imagine we would not want to do this to
ourselves while we're alive it perturbs
a living system with a very high degree
right so instead of engineering the
tissue uh we want to engineer the light
so that we can get intrinsic contrast
with non-invasive Imaging and we can
directly see what is happening within
the living tissue with minimal peration
possible and that's our mission so first
challenge how to generate molecular
contrast without staining so we've all
seen this before uh in Natural History
Museum this is a Utah Museum of Natural
History where you see this kind of a uh
display of rocks if you don't turn
lasers on if you just have natural light
it looks very medal core and regular
right but if we use different laser
colors to shine the lights onto the
rocks what will you see you will see
false fluoresence fluoresence of
different colors so the combination of
different lasers and then different
combinations of the camera colors can
give you indication what kind of
chemicals are there and that's what
gives the color it's the same idea for
label-free Imaging of biological tissues
so the contrast is a little bit weaker
because we have very bright light here
but you can probably see the Hues of the
white the yellow light so here we shine
the lights of ftoc and near infrared if
you detect yellow lights the there will
be Auto fluoresence from this thing
called fad which is a metabolic product
that everyone has every animal has every
cell has for indicating their
oxygenation status and just like the
Rocks if we switch the laser color from
let's say 900 NM to 1200 NM if we detect
blue light now we are detecting an ADH
which is another important important
metabolic byproducts and by combining
the concentration or the intensity from
the yellow color fad blue color and ADH
we could have educated gas on the
glycolysis TCA cycle and oxidative
phosphation of the cells and tissue
which is a huge importantly uh indicator
for cancer immune responses and embryo
development besides Auto florescence so
a lot of our tissues are highly
organized you can think of them almost
as like a nonlinear Crystal so if
they're organized enough they are Quasi
phas match that they can generate second
Harmon generation and third Harmon
generation what doesn't mean is that it
will convert the near infrared light to
half or the third of wavelength that
makes it visible to the detectors again
so the green color here shows collagen
fibers that is affected by aging that is
affected by by uh different
endometriosis different disease status
and then the third hormone generation
which gives us this purple color can
give you the interfaces of lipid protein
collagen fibers which gives you this
very very versatile contrast of lipid
dropless immune cells and the neuron
fibers and when we put this together we
what we did is really like the Rocks so
we switch the laser colors and we switch
the colors of the photo detectors and by
combining the contrast we can have a
much more comprehensive view what of
what is happening in the tissue so what
we are looking at is a leaving rat with
memory cancer and with this deep
metabolic Imaging we could see the
cancer cells are forming clusters and
they're going everywhere to meses to
other sides and they're forming vessels
to provide oxygen to provide nutrition
to their further growth which is very
scary but which is very important to
capture if we want to do real pathol
realtime pathology image guided therapy
and rare disease biodiscovery
and so that is one challenge right
generation of intrinsic molecular
contrast without staining or changing
the tissue the other contrast the other
challenge is how to generate the depth
penetration without physically cutting
through so there has been very
groundbreaking breakthroughs in are
filled with invivo optic clearing where
they use Dorito dieses to clear the
tissue to make it clear which is very
exciting on the other side besides
chemicals we can use also use clever
Optics to get deeper so by using the Las
Laser Source that's developed by our lab
we could push the depth from 50 microm
uh 200 microm all the way to 500 microm
to even 1.5 mm it sounds very small but
if we think about the the half Micron
resolution so the ratio of depth and
resolution is significant in this case
and by doing this we could finally
penetrate through the de cell layers of
the skin we could actually see the
subdermal layers and for brain organoid
we could finally go through the service
and see what is actually happening in
the center if the drug penetrates
through there if there is drug efficacy
in a more realistic model so that's the
deep tissue Imaging so what our lab does
is we want to leverage the risk vces in
Optics and algorithms to advance the
understanding and treatment diseases so
we work on light shaping Technologies so
that we don't have to engineer tissue
but we can engineer the colors of light
so this is a fiber shaper device that we
recently developed in the lab but just
this is very simple device but works
effectively by just shaping the lights
we can control the nonlinear conversion
processes within this mod mode fiber and
by control this adaptively with the
Imaging process we can control what
contrast we want to maximize in the
tissue without engineering the tissue
and then we also realize there is always
a limit to the physics instrumentation
no matter how hard working we're at in
the lab so we use ai physics-based ai to
overcome this physics limitation with
trustworthy prediction so this is an
example how we use physic basic AI to
overcome scattering and defraction to
achieve sub defraction limited
resolution deep within the tissue so
this was the first demonstration of deep
thick 3D isotropic imaging and then on
the third one we really don't want to
develop technology just for the sake of
technology and thankfully we're in
Boston so we have the best technicians
and uh uh hospitals and biologists that
have the most Frontier questions so we
closely collaborate with them to use our
technology to help them answer their
important questions in biom medicine so
I think I'm running out of time but I
want to highlight three examples in this
collaboration between the biomatic
questions and the Deep metabolic imaging
technology that's developed by our lab
so the first one is invivo Imaging of
cancer so the goal is that if we don't
use St if we don't use sectioning the
dream is that we can just shine this
light onto the patient and evaluate the
efficacy of drug responses or immuno
therapies or just real time diagnosis
for better surgical margin assessment so
this is a proof of concept experiment in
the rat this leaving rat what you're
seeing is their vessels are flowing and
the purple cells you're seeing are the
neutral fils that are coming in and out
of the uh vessels to fight or
collaborate with the uh tumor cells so
this capability of non-invasive
monitoring of immune responses can
Empower realtime pathology and image
guided cancer therapy in human clinical
trans translation the second example I
want to highlight is uh Imaging of brain
Organo so we have uh an expert Professor
Roger Kim in biological engineering
mechanical engineering at MIT who is an
expert on creating brain Organo
mimicking neurodegenerative diseases
like ALS but the organ noise unlike
their president which is 2D cell culture
this 3D cell culture are really thick
hard to see through so use the Deep
metabolic Imaging you can see through
the entire thing and using the AI based
fist based AI you can reconstruct the
highly resolved cells with individual
metabolic status so now we can have a
more accurate assessment of the disease
progression and we can finally see if
the drug actually penetrates to the
center of the brain organoid the final
example I want to highlight is a recent
collaboration with a Dr Mickey so McKey
is an expert on line disease so Lyme
disease is prevalent on the east coast
and Europe so when we when some people
get the tick bites they're fine but
other people get stic bites they would
develop really severe connective tissue
disorder and so there is a huge
heterogenity in this immune response and
also treatment response and this deep
metabolic Imaging uh that's conducted
between the two laps allows us to see so
if you can see here these like warm like
structures are the bacteria and this was
the first visualization of this bacteria
they are freely swarming in the patients
in the mouse patients that are
susceptible to Lyme disease what's more
interesting is that when we compare so
this mice is mimicking this mouse is
mimicking human conditions that are
susceptible to Lyme disease and this
mouse on the right is mimicking um human
patients that are more resistant to Lyme
disease so they have very different
immune responses and we are now
characterizing the bacteria distribution
and also the immune responses to see if
they can serve as biomarkers for
personalized diagnosis and treatment so
this is the last slide um so given the
recent breakthroughs in about Imaging uh
we really hope that with the Optics and
ACR venes we can make Optical by Optical
microscopy a go standard for invivo
pathology and personalized medicine
thank you
[Applause]
excellent yeah fascinating so do we have
questions yes there is
one uh the question is the longest
wavelength is 1100
NM yes so for for ACT 1100 nomers is so
far our favorite wavelength because
because it supports all the way uh all
the modalities in a single shot is is
there any benefit to going to longer
wavelengths that's actually a great
question so it's a hard debate in our
field because the longer you go it's the
similar like why you see the red sunset
while you see the Blue Sky it scatters
less so you would want to go to longer
wavelengths right uh so there is
trade-off because longer wavelength also
has higher water absorption so if you
have samples or diseases that has less
water it might be beneficial to go uh to
go rder however it's complicated because
it's engineering trade-off issue because
if you go rder the so the wavelength of
the light has to match the energy gap of
the fluorophor so you kind of have to um
yeah do this trade-off of quantum
efficiency and uh signal yield yeah but
we are actively going from 1100 to 1300
to 1700 just to see if we can push that
depth even bigger great question does
that help with the penetration depth
also or uh yeah because uh because for
example if we do 1300 nomers what we see
this really varies on different tissues
so brain organoid although everybody
claims they're highly scattering they're
semi-transparent in our image modality
but the skin is super super thick like
for skin if we use this thing uh the
same modality it just disappear the
signal disappears after 100 microm uh so
which we need to use longer wavelengths
to C it down yeah so other questions we
will take in the after session during
the reception thank you so
much thank you and as I introduced at
the beginning our third speaker is deina
sarar
so okay hello everyone it's a great
pleasure to be here today uh my name is
deblina sarar I'm an assistant professor
at MIT media lab and today I'm going to
talk to you about our lab's work in life
nanom machine
symbis so just to give you a little bit
background about myself I actually
started my research Adventure in Nano
electronics and applied physics and
specifically in developing energy
efficient Nano Electronics so we
developed a transistor which channel is
only six atoms in thickness and showed
that it can overcome the fundamental
limits of power of existing devices and
and then while working on energy
efficient low power electronic devices
for electronic computation I realized
that brain is the lowest power computer
ever so I did a very steep transition
from the field of Nano electronics and
applied physics to the field of
neurotechnology and Neuroscience to
learn more about the brain and there we
developed a technology which helps us to
look at previously unseen biomolecular
building blocks of the brain and how
that leads to brain computation
and in my own Lab at MIT which I call
the nanoc cybernetic botre we fuse these
fields together we fuse Nano Electronics
Applied Physics with Biology so we
continue to innovate in the space of
energy efficient uh Nano electronic uh
devices specifically for creating energy
efficient Ai and there we are very glad
and happy to be a part of MIT and mtl's
uh AI Hardware program and then we also
fuse these Nano electronic devices with
Biology and the idea is to create a new
paradigm for Life machine symbiosis and
in this regime we have created the first
autonomous and non-surgical brain
implant we have created bioelectronic
devices which we have shown can treat
brain cancer which is even resistant to
drugs and radiation we have also created
a novel bi electronic therapy for
disease dises of aging and
neurogenerative
diseases so why do you want to fuse
nanoelectronics with Biology so the
versatility of Nano Electronics is that
they can be designed from scratch and
according to an ingenious dream to
create functionalities which are beyond
the capabilities of biology and
specifically in our lab we create
subcellular sized wireless Nano
electronic devices so these are
subcellular sized sized much smaller
than size of even a single cell so they
are wireless and Battery free so you do
not need a battery or you do not need
wire coming out of open wound or wires
uh going through the body so these
devices can be seamlessly integrated uh
with Biology and they can c-li and
coexist with the biological structures
without destroying them specifically we
are creating devices which can form
unique hybrid with our biological living
cells we have built electronic devices
uh which can sit on top of cells or wrap
around living cells like variable
devices we have created devices which
can even work from inside a living cell
we have created an antenna which is
called cell Rover which can be
wirelessly actuated from inside a living
cell and you have also created devices
which are not completely inside the cell
or completely outside they just sit at
the transmembrane space so they can
communicate with both extracellular and
intracellular environment so with the
limited time here I'm just going to talk
about uh two of these Technologies today
so the First Technology I'm going to
talk about is what we called the
variable for
cells so just like we human body we have
our head we have our hands our legs
cells such as neurons also have uh such
specific parts so they have the Soma
which is like the head they have the
exons and dendr which are like the hands
and the legs so just like we have
variable devices for our body can we
also have variable devices for cells
inside our body and indeed we show that
that is possible so this kind of
Technology uh where it would be useful
is that it can create a potential
treatment for intractable and deadly
diseases such such as multiple sclerosis
which currently has no cure so multiple
sclerosis is a disease where uh the
neurons they lose their natural myeline
sheets so myeline sheets wrap around
axones and create a protective layer but
in this disease multiple sclerosis the
neurons lose their natural mine sheets
and currently there is no biological way
of recreating these malins and with such
a technology of variable for sell we can
actually completely forego this
biological mechanism and create
synthetic artificial milein sheets so
which could lead to a potential
treatment for this deadly brain disease
so we have developed such variable for
cell devices in our lab and using MTL
facilities and you have shown that these
devices can be wirelessly actuated to
create devices which can roll over with
ultra low radi of curvature we have
shown that these devices can wrap around
cells and then without causing any Toxic
effect or without affecting the
functionality of living cells we have
further showed that these devices we can
further uh uh integrate different kinds
of electronic materials like
semiconductors metals or insulators so
they can also Roll Along with these
devices without f failure or
functionality so this can lead to
further Advanced functionalities to
these
devices so that means it is possible
right uh that apart from having variable
devices for our body we can have even
variable devices for cells within our
body so what you see in the middle image
is basically ai's rendition of variable
for cell devices while in the right are
actual scanning electron microscopy
images of the variable for cell devices
that we have built again using MTL and
MIT Nanos facilities these images are
also taken at MIT Nano so in blue here
these are the actual cells and cellular
parts of neurons and in red here are our
uh
devices so the second technology that uh
I'm going to discuss is the first
autonomous and non-surgical brain
implant so I apologize from in the very
beginning because this work work is not
published yet so I'm not going to be
able to show a lot of data but happy to
talk to you uh in person to discuss more
details but I would uh give you an
overview and why we are so much excited
about this technology and what it can do
so why do we need a brain implant um So
currently more than three billion people
around the world suffer from different
brain diseases and mental illnesses
currently no brain disease have any cure
and according to World Health
Organization neurological disorders are
the number one cause of ill health and
disability and drugs have mostly been
known to be ineffective in uh curing or
treating uh neural
diseases however electrical stimulation
of neurons have been shown to treat even
neural diseases which are resistant to
drugs however existing techologies for
brain stimulation have severe
limitations right now the only way to
stimulate a region focally deep inside
the brain is to create a hole in the
skull and putting a centimeter scale
probe in that's highly highly invasive
in nature uh any kind of such surgical
technology is associated universally
with pain but also risk of infection
morbidity mortality and psychological
adverse effects moreover such kind of
intracranial brain implant is only
limited to less than 1% of the patients
so currently only one% of the patients
can undergo such kind of
procedure now imagine a new paradigm
where you can have extremely small Nano
electronic devices which can be
introduced to the bloodstream or
cerebral spinal fluid they can travel
through uh the body fluids and have the
capability of autonomous ly recognizing
a particular disease region in the brain
and they can self- implant in that
disease targeted region without the need
for any surgery so this is not a science
fiction anymore we have developed uh
such a technology in our lab and also
this non electronic devices have been
built using MIT Nano's uh facilities and
this is the first demonstration of
electronic devices which can cross the
bloodb brain barrier and after the
devices are self- implanted in the brain
so we call it self implantation because
this procedure does not require any
external Imaging or guidance procedure
for the implantation and after they get
self- implanted we wirelessly actuate
them to electrically stimulate uh the
brain so this indeed creates a new
paradigm a paradigm from invasive brain
surgery creating a hole in the skull and
putting things in to the Paradigm of a
simple injection but it's also important
to distin distinguish it that this is
not just injectable Electronics because
if you had to inject Electronics
directly into the target region of the
brain that will still be invasive and
you still have to create a hole in the
skull and inject Electronics in but this
creates autonomous targeting so we are
actually injecting the devices for from
through the periphery through the
peripheral uh blood vessels or cerebral
spinal fluid and these devices can
autonomously Target and recognize uh the
particular diseased uh
region and it it can create
accessibility great accessibility so
compared to as a mention only 1% of the
patient can go through this uh highly
invasive uh intracranial surgery so a
simple injection in the peripheral you
know blood vessels could make it
accessible to most and this can be
accessible to different age groups uh
also people who cannot undergo surgery
also by completely eliminating Surgical
cost uh this basically is accessible to
people across diverse uh socioeconomic
uh
spectrum and how does it compared to uh
what exists today so I think everyone
knows about um neurolink and other
companies like metronic who actually
make wired implants for the brain again
they are highly invasive in nature
requires creating a hole in the skull
neuralink device requires creating a
1-in hole in the skull to put things in
so these are highly highly invasive
invasive electrons cannot reach eloquent
structures in the brain there are
structures in the brain very very
sensitive so you cannot put invasive
electrod there there's a region in the
brain called brain stem that's called
touch notot region so if something
happens there the surgeons just leave it
as it is and the patient is left to die
because if you want to surgically reach
there it will make things even worse and
there regions in the brain if you want
to do surgery a person will look lose
their Consciousness or will they will
lose their uh other abilities such as
picking or normal uh locomotive uh
functions so uh surgery surgical
procedures are not possible in many
regions of the brain there are also
endovascular electrodes where people try
to put electrodes to the catheter but
that also requires surgical uh
procedures and again is only access
accessible to less than 8% of the brain
there are procedures such as
transcranial a magnetic stimulation that
does not include a implant inside the
brain those are uh magnets which are
placed outside the skull but they do not
have spao temporal resolution required
in many cases you know to treat brain
diseases and also they're only confined
to the brain surface uh they cannot go
deep inside the brain so right now
treating anything deep inside the brain
the only way is to again creating a hole
in the skull and putting this uh
centimeter scale probin our technology
does overcome uh these challenges
moreover none of these Technologies can
do autonomous targeting so autonomous
recognition of targeting and that's very
important because there are microscopic
pathological sites in the brain which
may not be even recognizable by uh for
example Imaging such as MRI so our
autonomous targeting can uh overcome uh
those
challenges I'm very happy to share that
we received the highest recognition from
National Institute of Health for this
work uh we received the ni director's
new innovator award and actually got the
highest and rarely achieved uh impact
score uh we received actually the
perfect uh impact score of uh 10 for
this work and Co from Ni statement
mention that this technology has the
potential to create a Herald a new era
um yeah thank you very much
yeah we also have uh other awards that
we got including the Mind prize
distinguished scientist award and the um
you know deg new innovator award and
again I'm very thankful and happy to be
a part of MIT Nano facilities our
wireless devices Nano electronic devices
are built in MIT Nano this is our second
home and very thankful to my students
and posts uh who make this work possible
a final last slide happy to also share
that we recently Incorporated a Dela SE
Corp to translate this technology to
humans we have demonstrated this um very
very robustly in animals and right now
we are you know ready to go forward to
the next step and translate to humans so
we call this uh company kahira
Technologies kahira in Irish actually
means a warrior it's a Female warrior
and the idea is really to set a war
against currently intractable and deadly
brain diseases and again we are part of
MIT start Nano program very very
Greatful full and uh this uh companies
uh very soon will be uh there will be
opportunities for investment so if you
interested happy to talk to you further
and I didn't show much data but happy to
you know show the data and details when
you talk in person yeah thank you very
much excellent thank you thank you for
the fascinating work Kina but given the
time I think questions will wait until
after the session okay so and we have
our last speaker Elena notos so
introduction as mentioned my name is
Yelena natos I'm an assistant professor
here in the department of electrical
engineering and computer science um and
today I'll be talking to you about the
work done in our group The photonics and
Electronics Research group um on Silicon
photonics I'm really grateful for the
MTL leadership um for giving us the
opportunity to introduce some of this
this work to you so before we get
started on the work being done by our
group I thought maybe let's do a show of
hands who here is familiar with silicon
photonics
okay good I see about like half the
hands went up so this is a a good slide
to show then to start us off um an
introduction to Silicon photonics so the
idea behind silicon photonics is that we
want to repurpose standard seos
fabrication and tools to create uh
chip-based optical devices and systems
so on the bottom uh panel here we have a
cross-sectional view of a silicon
photonics platform that we've developed
on the past on the very far left hand
side you can see a bulk seos transistor
which probably everyone in the room is
pretty familiar with you have the
Silicon layers the dope silicon the
metal coming down into contact with the
dope silicon well what we can do for
silicon photonics is we can take all
these standard device layers and
components and we can repurpose them to
create Optics on chip so for example in
the center here we have our silicon
dialectric wave guide that's going to
look like a rectangle of silicon that's
patterned to create a long thin
rectangle that's going to confine and
guide the light down arches
we can then take that wave guide and you
see here this active device we can
stretch the wave guide out we can dope
regions of uh the side of this wave
guide and we can place metal that those
orange bars down into contact with the
dope regions to enable modulation
through electrooptic effects of the
light in our wave guide so we can
confine the light we can guide the light
we can modulate the light and then we
can create all kinds of different
interesting passive devices maybe we can
emit the light off the chip we can
create filters
um Splitters
combiners so by creating these silicon
photonics platforms we can take optical
devices that were once complex and bulky
maybe you know there was an optical
table filled with bulk Optics or Optical
fibers and we can take that entire
system and we can integrate it onto a
millimeter scale completely flat
photonic
chip also by taking advantage of wafer
scale fabrication processes you can see
an example of a photograph of one of
those Wafers uh fabricated for our group
by um aim photonics and Sunni and Albany
uh by taking advantage of these wafer
scale fabrication processes we can take
advantage of the high yield enabled by
silicon photonics in addition to um
having lowcost ways to fabricate these
photonic devices and also scaling up the
the production really to seos type of
scales also and I I think that this is a
little bit of a unique functionality
right we can take these um uh by
integrating down onto the chip scale we
can enable new functionality that was
never before possible with bulk Optics
or fiber optics and I'll talk uh to you
about some of these functionalities as
we keep
going so this field of silicon photonics
was really driven in the last couple of
decades by this primary motivator of uh
applications in Datacom or Telecom and
the idea was can we create these
photonic chips that can process light in
a very energy efficient and high-speed
way but all on the chip
and because of the the real promise that
silicon photonics has had on the Telecom
and Datacom industry there is a lot of
Financial Resources um and Innovation
that happened in our field especially
over I'd say the last five to to 10
years with a lot of semiconductor um
infrastructure being being brought up
and now we're seeing these silicon
photonic specific foundaries and
platforms that are now standard and
available to everyone in the world and
that brings us to today we can now start
thinking about can we create silicon
photonic systems that aren't just
limited to processing light on the chip
but can we create chips that are going
to emit light off of the Chip and
interact with the surroundings and
that's really what our group here at MIT
is focusing
on so in our group we're developing
these novel silicum photonics
fabrication Platforms in collaboration
with many different foundaries around
the world we then use these platforms to
enable novel devices using first
principle electromagnetics and device
physics and then we take these devices
and integrate them up on you know the
kind of 10,000 100,000 uh device scale
up into large scale systems to enable
enable uh new solutions for many
different applications you know just
listing off some of them here we have
lar sensors AR displays trapped iron
Quantum system biophotonics and Chip
based 3D
printing so for the sake of time here um
I'll just very quickly talk you through
some of our recent results um in many of
these these spaces so first we can think
about can we create chip scale solutions
for liar sensors if you take a look at a
standard autonomous vehicle you'll see a
large box sitting on the top of the car
that's the car's lar sensor that lar
sensor is sending out light pulses H
that bounce off the surroundings and
come back and then the entire box spins
around to create a full
three-dimensional uh map of the
surroundings of the car this allows you
to have very high resolution sensing but
the limitations are we have a box
sitting on top of the cart that's
mechanically spinning around right so
this is a a a a um cost prohibitive
solution it's not going to be very
robust over time right if we have a
mechanical object rotating around and
most importantly it's going to be
limited in the detection range so as a
solution we can enable these silicon
photonics based liar sensors what that
looks like is we're going to have a
silicon photonic chip that's going to
sit here it's going to emit light off
the chip we can then use
these structures called integrated
Optical phas drays that take these light
beams and scan them around non-
mechanically we can then receive the
light back on the chip and do all the
processing on our chip so this is some
nice work led by my students uh Daniel
and Ben which you can see in the top
there recently we showed the first
demonstration of a multi-beam system
that can track multiple targets and once
using the Silicon photonics uh lar
technology additionally we can think
about can we create solutions for for AR
displays so when you think about a
current AR display what that looks like
is you have um a little micro display
that sits on the side of the head and
you have a b a bunch of Optics that take
the information projected by that
display and put it out in front of the
user that's viewing it the limitation
here is that of course I think like uh
pre brought up earlier there's some
social limitations to um walking around
with these little Optics on the side of
our head so we're not seeing a lot of
adaptation just because of the form fact
Factor if you look at def the defense
industry they're very interested to have
a lower weight solution for AR displays
because if you're in a high G
environment in a fighter jet and you
have these Optics sitting on the side of
your head that's going to strain your
neck or maybe you're um a soldier or or
you know a more uh the the more discreet
side of the Department of Defense and
you want a solution for AR displays
that's that's not going to be able um to
be
detected so what we we've done is we've
velop this solution um for AR displays
that consists of a single silicon
photonic chip that sits in front of your
eye and actually projects three
dimensional holograms for the user to
see that's only uh only requires a
single transparent chip that could be
integrated in a pair of glasses and it's
actually going to project holographic
information for the
user now to enable this if you were to
take a standard silicon photonic chip
and put it in front of your eye you
wouldn't be able to see through it and
that's because silicon photonic chips
are based on a silic wafer handle so we
had to work with Foundry Partners to
actually develop the first uh 300 mm uh
platform for fabricating visible light
photonics but now on transparent Wafers
this is work L by my former student
mea and then if we think of these
applications where we're using visible
light as opposed to infrared light we
need to also develop new devices so here
uh we developed these liquor
crystal-based integrated modulators uh
that for the first time enable um
visible light modulation using liquor
Crystal on chip and this enables us to
take these uh modulators and Shrink them
down to orders of magnitude compared to
what you would normally use for visible
light integrated uh modulators again
work led by Mila and um Andre is
actually sitting in the back
here also we can think about using
silicon photonics and emitting light off
the chip to revolutionize how we think
about 3D printers so if you look at a
standard 3D printer
what that's going to look like is a
system a big box that sits in your lab
that's going to plop out little balls of
plastic and create a 3D object if you go
to higher resolution 3D printers they're
laser based and again what that looks
like is a box that sits in your lab but
now that scans mechanically scans laser
beams around to cure 3D objects well
what we're proposing here and what uh we
recently showed as a first step towards
this is can we take that entire 3D
printer and now integrate it onto a
photonic chip that's going to project
visible holographic images into a vat of
photocurable resin to enable a portable
completely um different form factor uh
chip scale solution for 3D printers I
think that this is the first proposal of
actually using a chip to do 3D printing
we're pretty excited to see where this
goes also we can use silicon photonics
to enable different biophotonic
solutions so we can have a chip that
emits light and focuses light above the
chip and then actually traps and
manipulates different types of
biological particles so here we're using
uh this chip to manipulate cancer cells
um this is the first uh demonstration of
a biological experiment using a single
beam integrated Optical tweezer a work
Le by my students tell with help from
Sabrina and
mea and then if we think about different
biological applications um maybe some
type of sensors or probes into the body
we can't have chips that are just going
to sit on top top of the body we need
something that's going to be more um
integrated with the body so again we
worked in collaboration with our Foundry
Partners to demonstrate the first uh 300
mimet flexible silicon photonics
platform work L by Mila with help from
Andre and Ashton and then finally we can
also create chips that emit light off
the chip to interface with different
types of quantum bits cubits and our
Cubit of choice at the moment is the
trapped ion um ions need different
Optical uh wavelengths and polarizations
to enable State preparation Cooling
excitation and readout uh so here we're
working in collaboration with Lincoln
lab to enable integrated photonic chips
that emit light off the chips to
interface with these ions to create a
scalable and stable way uh to move these
trapped ion quantum computers from the
lab to more large scale systems and
specifically we demonstrated the first
um integrated photonic devices that
enable polarization diversity down at
visible wavelengths and then use those
devices to show polarization gradient
cooling uh to four times below the
Doppler limit using an integrated fonic
system for the first time this is work L
by Sabrina also in the back here with
help from Ashton tal and
mitaa so I hope this gives you a flavor
for the type of work that our group does
and different directions that the field
of silicum photonics can go um I could
never talk about our work without giving
a huge shout out to my wonderful
students uh if you have any questions
you're very welcome to go talk to them
um you'll notice we're all wearing our
perg polos if you um look at the
students sitting back there they're all
wearing the red poos too so during
dinner if you can seek them out and ask
them some questions and of course we'll
give a shout out to our collaborators as
well thank
you thank you fascinating so do we have
a quick question for
yes for the work on other topics thein
consider any interfacing of Optics and
oh thank you for the talk and there was
a few themes about brain and Optics and
so with the ways that you're advancing
uh photonic circuits any thoughts about
um using it in some of the ways have
been discussed for brain interfaces yeah
that's a great question actually I think
if the IT team can pull back up the
slide we can pop that back up wonderful
thank you
um so yeah one of the the topics that we
are looking at is actually creating
these Optical chips that can trap and
manipulate cancer cells that's the work
um there on the bottom uh second from
the left that was showing a chip that
could actually sit outside of the body
and then probe into the body to actually
do some manipulation so for this initial
demonstration we were just um
manipulating cells in the lab uh not in
Vivo but there's actually some recent
work where people were showing this kind
of system with bulk Optics um doing
invivo manipulation of cells in a a
mouse model um so I think it would be
really exciting to explore some of that
and I think U some of the work that
we're we're working on with the flexible
Wafers I feel like if you're really
wanting to explore uh interfacing with
the body you need to think about the
form factor for these types of chips as
well another thing I'll mention is that
the majority of um silicon photonics
platforms really because of the Telecom
data com initial applications they were
really focused on infr wavelengths so
for a lot of these bio applications were
shifting to visible light or up into mid
infrared like cichon was mentioning
earlier um and that requires a lot of
this type of platform development so I
didn't even have a chance to pop it up
here but we're working in collaboration
with uh Sunni poly that's um houses a
photonics if you're familiar with that
um to actually develop a platform that
pushes down into visible wavelengths and
that's work that Andre and Henry are
really um pushing forward we're going to
be putting out a really nice big paper
on that soon
too thanks thank you so let's thank
Elena again and all our four Future
Leaders for sharing their extraordinary
research with us so thanks a lot for
your participation we are 20 minutes
past the schedule but this was very
interesting