Welcome everyone. Thank you for joining
us for our open conversation with
neurossychologist and lifelong learner
Beia Adams. Today we'll talk about the
ways in which curiosity and continuous
learning can transform personal growth
and mental well-being.
I'm Curt Newton, director of O MIT Open
Courseware. Open Courseware is a free
and open collection of materials from
thousands of MIT courses covering the
entire MIT curriculum. We create new
opportunities for millions of learners
and educators, share open education
resources from MIT, and help lead a glo
global revolution in free access to
knowledge.
This is the third event in the open
conversation series which focuses on how
open learning can empower people to
improve their lives, communities, and
the world. Our guest today is Beia
Adams. Beia has been on a fascinating
and inspiring journey from an initial
degree and work in clinical and
behavioral psychology to dance with the
London Contemporary Dance School and the
Royal Ballet and then back to psychology
extending into computational
neuroscience and related fields with MIT
open learning resources.
Thank you, Beia, for joining us today.
There's so much to get to explore and
share. Really looking forward to it. So
if we might begin um you know with your
wonderful accomplishments
academic and in personal pursuits
beia what would you please share with us
some of the themes and through lines in
your career and your personal growth and
how curiosity
has played a role in this journey.
>> Hi Kurt. Hi everyone. Um thank you for
having me. I'm so excited to finally be
here. Um yeah, a few things about
myself. Uh I'm a neurosychologist as you
said and I'm a former professional
dancer. Um I um I'm also a lifelong
learning. My career has been built
across diverse experiences, but I think
I've always retained an interest in
lifelong learning. Um I like to say that
if money and jobs were not concepts, I
would happily be a forever student. Um I
um started dancing when I was four, four
and a half. What I thought, my mom
thought would be just a few lessons of
of ballet turned into many years of
dancing. Um
I've spent most of my childhood and
teens dancing. Then I I've studied
psychology, clinical and and and
cognitive. I worked as a psychologist uh
for a few years. Then in my mid20ies I
um I I went on an extended sabbatical
because I wanted to explore dance um a
bit more and I wanted to perform a bit
more. So I um this time I studied
contemporary dance in London
contemporary dance school and I I
performed for a few years. I also
explored with other movement practices.
Um I managed to get a back a black belt
in Iikido. I started skateboarding,
longboarding which of course led to to
quite a few injuries and due to those
and also because I I'd really developed
an interest in the neuroscience part of
psychology. I went back to psychology
and I I resumed my studies and I
eventually specialized in medical
neuroscience and started working as a
psych as a neurosychologist which is
what I do uh now. Um I still dance
albeit not professionally but I do it
regularly and uh which with much joy. Um
I I discovered MIT um open courses in
2022 it was. Yes. And I completed um
several from from various fields. Um and
I'm planning to actually approach um
more uh in next year. Um I other than
that I'm I'm multilingual. I grew up
speaking several languages and then
acquired more. Uh my one of my project I
mean every five years I try to approach
a new language and I'm I'm doing that at
the moment. Um I find much um I'm I'm
drawn I'm curious about uh how new
languages work and how structure arises
out of them. Um, also this year I I
finished writing my first book of
fiction uh to be released next year.
It's called Humans After All and if you
if you watch my online spaces, you will
see excerpts from it already and
hopefully the final result next year.
Um,
yeah, you asked me about curiosity. I
think I think curiosity has been has
been there throughout my uh development.
Um I was um I've always been drawn by
movement and interested in movement, how
it arises, how our bodies move, why we
are able to do things and why we are not
able to do things. So I think when I
started doing uh doing ballet I was
drawn curiosity helped me dissect
movement uh understand technique
understand timing uh how movement
relates to music. Um another big
interest of mine um then also the the um
expression the possibilities of
expression that arise out of tney right
not just the series of steps. So what I
what I didn't know then but I appreciate
now um as a psychologist is that this
curiosity I had activated um the
dopamineergic system in the brain the
reward system that's something which
makes you you know go after after
things. It opens the door to learning
and it also makes you a bit more
cognitively flexible so that you can you
know adapt to learning and through you
know the connections that the
dopamineergic system has with the hypoc
campus to consolidate what you've
learned. So I didn't know then that um I
was actually priming my brain for deep
learning without even knowing what deep
learning was. Um later on when I
transitioned to uh to neuroscience, I
think
curiosity
curiosity served almost a protective
almost had a protective role
>> because instead of interpreting this
change as um a change in career in you
know almost in identity, I I looked at
the I looked at it as an opportunity to
explore something new, explore something
meaningful. Um, right. Um, and I think
that's important in in periods when uh
you know that we associate with
identity. U I was a dancer and then I
became a scientist. So um instead of
interpreting this this change as a
threat, I tried to look at it um through
the eyes of the explorer. What what
could come out of this? And I think um
that reframes uncertainty and it
refrains ambiguity which our brains are
not very good at uh to at tolerating. Um
that's that answer your question.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That uh that uh spirit of
exploration you know is so fundamental
to you know to what we can get up to and
uh it's I know thank you for sharing you
know that that sort of path. Yeah. Um I
mean I I would um I would share that you
know what we've learned about the people
who use open MIT open courseware more
broadly from around the world. You know
they're coming from a lot of different
you know positions. You know some of
them are enrolled students. Some of them
are educators trying to figure out how
to teach more effectively.
Many of them are just curious
independent learners. And what we've
heard, you know, from everyone kind of
across the board that the number one
reason why they're coming to these
resources because they have this
fundamental curiosity. It's, you know,
and there's often, you know, you know,
other other reasons beyond that. But
it's just really interesting that that
that force is out there so widely
reflected and uh and you've you've
definitely been living it. So, thank
you. Yeah.
Um well curiosity if we look at the way
curiosity arises in the brain um I think
that will probably you know just answer
your your curiosity and your question a
bit more. Um we become more curious when
our brains detect an information gap
right when we when we sense that there's
something we don't know but we could
know that there's something we don't
fully understand but we could
understand. And when the brain detects
this gap, it sets in motion the same uh
dopamineergic um system I mentioned
earlier u that in its in turn sets you
know prepares the neurochemical mill the
dopamine required to create the
motivation to go out there seek the
missing information and close the gap
and it's it it's exactly this
exploratory behavior that we uh
mentioned earlier. So most I I'm
I'm quite confident that a lot of uh uh
a lot of a lot of learners already have
some knowledge from certain fields but
there is that information gap there's
that that's something they wish they
would know more of and more from and um
that once they find the platform once
they find the source of knowledge they
just you know they seize it because
that's what the brain does right they
have the all the support the neurob
biological support to do that.
>> Yeah. And and it never stops, right? You
know, those those questions, that sense
of, oh, here's a here's a gap. Here's a
new thing. We we certainly feel that
when we're young all the time, but but
it also it it never stops, right? And so
to be able to support people at every
age of life continuing to explore that
stuff um as you've been doing uh feels
just really really important and uh uh
useful. Yeah,
>> it's self-relenishing I would say.
>> Uh like it's it never stops. Uh once you
you answer you know you find an answer
to one question that another one arises.
So, um I I totally agree. Uh and that's
actually an important thing to note.
Curiosity and motivation, they're not um
they're not personality traits. You're
not born of them and they stay rigid for
the rest of their life. They are they
are they are practice. They are tools
and facets of one's behavior that need
constant practice. And the more you
practice, the more will come out of
them. So, yeah, I agree.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
I wonder um if you if you have a
perspective on how living a life of of
curiosity
um
supports one's just sort of broader
sense of well-being and and connection
in the world, you know, through your own
your own experience or you know the the
work that you're doing with other
people. What have what have you seen
about that?
Well, curiosity per se, the act of you
know engaging curiosity and motivation
to engage in new pursuits and mind you
when I say learning curiosity to learn
something new and the motivation to
learn something new I don't mean just
abstract stuff actually it's preferred
from a neuroscient
uh for it to be multimodal right
cognitive motor social emotional because
it recruits more areas of the brain
uh going by the same principle of of
lose it or use it or use it or lose it.
>> Um so
maintaining a curious approach uh to
life, maintaining curiosity
um in and engaging with new learning
material with with lifelong learning um
has quite a few benefits and it why why
mainly why it is important? Um, it's
because it literally changes the brain.
It drives what we call neuroplasticity.
Neuroplasticity is the brain's ability
to change itself in response to
experience, in response to new learning.
So, um, curiosity, applied curiosity,
um, and new learning rewires the brain.
You form new new circuits. um you allow
for neurogenesis, the formation of u the
genesis of new neurons in some areas of
the brain, particularly the hippocampus.
It also acts as a protective buffer
against uh age related cognitive
decline. It slows down uh it slows the u
lowers the incidence of dementia.
Let us not forget the social benefits
that come with, you know, being curious
and engaging in in new pursuits with
others. Just the act of of of doing
something with others, of proving
oneself to be capable of being
competent, the feeling of self-efficacy
of of of mastery. they build confidence
and all these um all these things um are
proven to reduce symptoms of anxiety and
depression and isolation. Um also um you
know the um when you see a curiosity
um neuroscience shows us that um when
curiosity is high yeah our brains switch
from um networks that preferentially
process threat to networks u that allow
for exploration for the for you know for
curious approach for going out in
exploring one's territory that also goes
hand inhand with um let's call it
cognitive flexibility with the ability
to reappraise a situation not in terms
of threat but in terms of exploration so
maintaining this mindset of what else
you know how how else could I look at a
situation what else is there to find out
about this um um how can I look at this
from a different perspective perspective
like or then you know what else is there
that I you know I feel I could know but
I don't I don't yet understand but I
know I could the missing puzzle puzzle
how do I find it the brain loves puzzles
um
that that sense of of curiosity
it helps us like we said like I said
before reframe uncertainty but it also
um
you know it It also puts puts us in a in
a in a situation where we also become,
you know, more more resilient.
>> Uh we um we allow for for the brains
instances of of cognitive reappraisal
and um um
reframing of a situation to work so that
we have a better stress response, right?
we u more a less better decision making.
Um the impact of stress on emotional
circuits in the lyic system is is is
reduced. So um curiosity is not just you
know learning new material. It actually
impacts um mental health and resilience
long term.
>> Yeah. You know that that I I love
hearing that reflection. You know we at
open courseware at open learning we hear
from so many people around the world
that they've been able to make use of
our resources when they are living in
various sort of disrupted situations in
their lives. I mean lives are
complicated and having these materials
shared openly and freely with the world
you know you know clearly people's lives
have some stresses in them but they're
they're able to to tap into you know
some foundational I guess curiosities to
despite or working through with
resilience those disruptions continue to
keep learning and they you know they you
know we we love hearing the stories
reporting back about how you know they
you know continue to be able to keep
learning um you know um
you know people I'm remembering u
open course where we have this chalk
radio podcast and we just did a series
of hearing you know from learners around
the world specifically you know we heard
a story from a a person named Lafulla in
Afghanistan who you know
>> was living in a in a situation where you
know could not count on having internet
access from day to day from hour to or
um you know and all sorts of other
disruptions, but we're able to um make
use of the materials that we've shared
to keep learning and how just vitally
useful that that was. Um you know, we
hear those stories again and again, you
know, so it does it does seem to switch
something for people and uh really
really glad that we can can help support
that. Yeah.
>> Yeah. And it's it's um it's um the
occurrence of what you said is supported
by very you know clearly defined
structures in the brain. Um and again
it's the it's again the midbrain the
dopamineergic u subsystem in the
midbrain um mainly the vententral
tegmental area and the nuclear
circumbent which allow for this sense of
purpose right for this sense of of the
micro of maybe understanding it doesn't
have to be you know the big goal and the
big monster it can be the small gremlin
that you that you finally tame and you
learn how to deal with but it's those
micro wins those that that feeling of
process that you know I may not have
understood the full thing but at least
I've got this much you know I mastered
this much and maybe tomorrow I'll make
sense of the next bit and next week I'll
make this make sense of the next bit and
that gives a sense of of progress but
also of of purpose of goal directed
behavior which in times of hardship in
times of duress and distress is what
keeps you know keeps you going and It
could be it can be you know as little as
um you know like I said it doesn't have
to be abstract. It can be learning how
to play a new instrument or learning how
to that's not a small thing learning how
to code. I've actually approached
Annabelle's u um code AI and computer
science course so it reminds me of that.
Um, so yeah, maybe it has even a a
stronger impact on people who who who go
through through difficult times because
again it gives you that something to
look for to look forward to. That's
something to mobilize your resources
towards which is so important in um um
the staving of in in staunching symptoms
of of hopelessness which are very
closely linked with depression uh and
and crippling anxiety. So yeah, I
completely agree with you.
>> Yeah. Yeah. You're what I'm hearing in
your description is this this process of
building confidence bit by bit too. You
know, you start from a
>> from a place of
>> realizing, hey, there's something that I
don't know that I'm curious about and
building that confidence. That
confidence is can be really infectious
in a in a good way. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I No, you you're spot on. Now
that I'm I told you I'm I'm learning I'm
approaching foreign languages and I was
saying to my friend when I sit down to
relearn I call it relearning Hebrew
because I sort of knew something from
before and I'm drawn to it because it
forces my brain to do things
counterintuitively the same way I I I um
experienced with when I started Iikido.
It's against the way my brain would do
it. Right? Not only is it right to left,
but it's a whole different grammar
structure. So it you know puts me in a
in a situation of discomfort. So um I'm
you know go I'm sometimes overwhelmed.
Um I'm I don't know whether I'll be able
to make sense of it but I the micro you
know there are micro wins. If I manage
to understand this much then the next
day I'll sit down and see okay let's see
what happens. Let's see what happens
today. Let's see what I make sense of
today. So I become a bit more confident
because it's yet another small milestone
uh that I've um I've conquered. I'm this
much closer to something which I don't
even know where it is in in time and and
space but I become more confident and
that takes me back to when I retrained
um in neurosychology. I remember I had
to learn a lot of neuroanatomy,
neurohysiology, diagnostics and it was
uh you know often times it was quite
intimidating. It was overwhelming. Um
but even you know the small win of
understanding how cranial nerves work or
finding the acronym to remember
something or nailing a small
differential diagnosis that um not only
did it make me happy right through the
same reward circuitry uh but it um
boosted my motivation the big M word to
carry on. Yeah.
>> So, um it actually kept me on track. Um
otherwise perhaps I would have given up
if I looked at this whole chunk as oh
god here's the big monster. So I agree
with you. Building confidence slowly um
is definitely um something that we see
um with with with lifelong learners,
people who engage in lifelong learning.
>> Yeah. Yeah. This brings to mind, you
know, stories that we hear from so many
people, especially older learners. I
think there's there's a way in which
>> we're conditioned as older people to
think we're supposed to know stuff,
right?
>> And that moving into that space of not
knowing can be sort of uncomfortable.
But we hear from so many people,
>> you know, I studied this subject back in
school and I it didn't make sense to me.
And
>> suddenly, thank you open courseware for
instance for giving me this alternate
explanation. Suddenly now I understand.
I've kind of recovered that sense of of
yeah, I can I can I can come back to
this and and take another try at it. Um
and just how transformative that could
be for, you know, for people no matter
what stage in life they're at. You know,
got to keep doing
>> Absolutely. It also, you know, I like to
say this tongue and cheek that it it
stops you. It prevents one from taking
oneself too seriously, right? Keeping
humble. Uh a lot of us especially if
there's something we become good at
hopefully uh we tend to think that we
know the answers to all the questions or
what we know is enough but it's always
good to have this reality check that you
know there's something there we you
don't know or there may be another way
to look at it and that again takes us
back to cognitive flexibility right is
something that tends to because of how
how brain function declines
physiologically cognitive flexibility
um fluidity of of thinking and of
appraising reality and what's being
internalized as knowledge is a bit lost.
So um you know working on that wiring
through lifelong learning through
complex work through um um like you said
you know learning new things or
revisiting new things through mentally
stimulating hobbies. Um it it sort of
allows for for the looseness of of that
circuitry to to be maintained and also
for um you know the
the the distance from yourself that
sometimes is needed to just be able to
to learn new things and to look at the
world with different eyes. It's a it's a
it's a humble thing
>> uh to be able to do that later in life.
>> Yeah.
Do you ever have people who who have
learned about your story uh say
something like, "I just don't know how I
would have time to learn all of these
things. How do you how do you find the
time? How do you create that?"
>> I get that in the sauna. I get that uh
at work. I get that uh I get that. Um
and I my answer is how do you know I
actually get that question? My answer is
usually, well, I'm old, so I've had time
to do all those things. That's usually
my go-to get out of jail free card. I
usually say, well, you know, I'm old.
I've been around since forever. I've had
I've had time to do these things. But
then you know maybe the more complex um
less tongue and cheek answer would be
I've um
I've
I don't I I really enjoyed what I did. I
never even now people say oh why do you
swim 5 days a week? I'm actually enjoy
doing it. It's not something it's not an
ordeal. Most of the things I've done
I've done because I was really drawn to
them. So for me it's joy. This is joy.
Um I mean there are clearly things that
I would rather not do and there are
there just to maintain something you
know like you know having to do strength
in order to maintain flexibility. Um but
I actually like you said it's
self-relenishing it's self-perpetuating
like now I can't stop learning these
foreign languages. I actually I I wake
up and I think you know you know maybe I
want to make sense of that. Um so I
think it's just it's it's something that
um I was encouraged to do also. I had
good uh parental encouragement growing
up and luckily I had the uh you know the
context in the environment to pursue
some interests. Um
and
I maintained like I like I said it's
practice. I I I I maintained the the
curiosity and the motivation
and also the discipline which is
deserves another conversation all
together to to do these things and then
you know to complete the answer they've
brought me enough reward to keep me
going
um it was not something I did just for
the sake of doing I've I got a lot out
of it enough to to keep going.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um
curious to hear a little bit more maybe
about your sense of of the the social
aspects of being a lifelong learner. Um
in addition to all the things that we
individually are drawn into. Um um how
have how have you experienced in your
life um sharing it with other people or
bringing bringing other people into
these sort of journeys and uh things you
might want to share with share with our
viewers about that.
>> Um
well you you hit the nail on the head is
like you you read my mind. Um I actually
meant to bring this into a conversation
how um and and maybe you know part of it
I discuss is sort of a fiction context
in this book I've finished uh writing
how important the social dimension of
learning is in general and also how
important it's been for me and how
intrinsic it is to sometimes just stay
on track and to maintain the motivation
to keep going And it's something which
is perhaps um slightly waning in the
modern world. Um the act of learning
with others, the act of sharing
knowledge with others, uh you know,
we're in this together as hard as it
gets. Uh you know, we're learning this
together or we're learning from each
other to me has has been very important.
Although um in terms of personality
maybe I actually prefer especially when
it comes to abstract knowledge to to
learn alone but um then I like to uh I
like to share I like to um have somebody
to um have shared reflection with and it
also helps with accountability you know
um I I remember it could be it could be
a a discussion forum but um learning
with somebody else uh a study buddy
right preferably a human study buddy um
helps with um I've already mentioned
accountability and you know
comprehension and um sharing
understanding of material but what it
also does um I've noticed especially
when you know you study something which
is hard and um there are obstacles along
the way and and fatigue um
rears its ugly said having having a
study buddy um helps with eliminating or
reducing the sense of isolation that can
come out of you know months and months
of being engaged in in hard study and
it's sometimes it's that sense of
isolation that can halt progress. So to
me it it's been important to have
somebody to um when it came to academic
pursuits it was important to have
somebody to even meet and have a
conversation about you know tomorrow's
exam or what had to be studied. I was
lucky to have a good friend in
university and I'm forever grateful to
her for you know being my study buddy
human study buddy. Um and when when it
comes to other types of learning, of
course, um you know, just sharing the
fact that uh you know, let me show you
how I um learned to play guitar or you
show me this dance piece and I'll try to
copy you. It creates um a sense of
cohesion and also a sense of mastery. Um
like I've I've mentioned before, a sense
of efficacy. I'm showing you that I'm
good at this. I'm showing you that I'm,
you know, I'm I'm I'm competent enough
to do this. And then there's the, you
know, then there's the the
feedback that comes back to me and I
feel competent, right? Through the same
social reward and the circuitry that
supports it is back mirrored to me and
in turn I feel more competent and that's
extremely important and again it helps
with with resilience, you know, with
grit.
>> Yeah. So um social learning I I couldn't
encourage it more. Um and
the um the I think learning per se we've
already said you know all the we've
already outlined the benefits the
lifelong benefits that come with just
being engaged in in in learning but
there's also the aspect of you know if
we were to to visualize this in a sort
of visual vignette you have
this learning window or or door let's
call it and you of curiosity and
motivation which help you take the first
steps through good job I didn't say
window um so they tell you you take the
first step through the learning door
>> and then you have the discipline and the
rigor and the structure which keep you
on track but then I think you also need
a sense of community to to anchor you
into something which hopefully will
become larger than yourself
um so u I'm I couldn't stress more the
uh the the benefits of of social
learning and just you know doing it with
other humans.
>> Yeah. Thanks. Thanks. Yeah. It makes me
think of MIT's motto, you know, mind and
hand, you know. Yeah. Yes. There's the
there's the the learning part of it, the
intellectual part of it, but the hand
part, the doing
>> in particular, I think has this way of
just bringing other people into the
process. you know, we we demonstrate the
things that we're learning, you know,
through the through the hand, through
the activities out in the world. Um, you
know, we're creating opportunities to
engage with other people. Um, you know,
I know in my in my personal life, I've
been on a learning journey for over a
decade about um, climate change and how
how to respond to these, you know,
intersecting challenges and, you know,
the things that it calls me into, you
know, to to share my learnings have to
do with like how do how do how do we
show up for civic engagement, you know,
as a citizen, how to how to get engaged
there. Um, so there's this there's this
continuous feedback loop between
learning new things and showing up in
social spaces, you know, to uh both
demonstrate what I've learned, but also
ask those questions that are still
ringing that uh sort of lead me into
into the next thing. Um, I'll also note,
you know, yeah, it's not part of MIT's
official motto, but informally mind,
hand, and heart, you know, showing up
for all of this, you know, with our with
our full selves is a is a really
important part of it as well. Um, and I
I I think of uh of the heart part of it
as as very connected with um, you know,
that feeling of curiosity. What is it
that that spark or that that small flame
that that opens up as kind of the heart
piece? So, yeah, just enjoy riffing on
that for a moment. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I um No, I I I I totally agree and
I absolutely love um MIT's moto. Um
I like you know like maybe I mentioned
earlier this this aspect of of embodied
cognition and I touched on it briefly
earlier when I um and I when I mentioned
multimodal learning and you know just um
learning through all modalities which is
actually actually preferred and um the
brain likes that because it recruits
more areas it allocates more resources
is from various bits. Um and um
it's also a very it's quite it's been
quite the buzz word in the uh in the
last few years embodied condition and
how because you know there's both top
down regulation of of processes and
bottom up right it's not just the brain
dictating everything into the body. It
actually what happens in how how emotion
and behavior arises is both top down and
bottom up. What comes through the
senses, what comes from the outside
going all the way up into the higher
instances of the brain and top down as
well. So I'm I'm happy you touched on
that because it's linked with as I said
this buzz word.
>> Yeah.
>> In body cognition.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And if I may, um,
reflecting on the social aspect of this,
we're so grateful for all of the people
who are who are watching our live stream
right now and and, uh, who registered
and we got so many questions from
people, you know, right about the sort
of broader themes that we'd be talking
about today. Maybe maybe I'll turn some
of our attention to what we've what
we've heard from those questions here.
Um I think we got over a hundred
questions that were submitted and our
team has has uh done some valiant work
trying to group these into some themes
um you know that that people out in the
world are cur are wondering about you
know especially around curiosity. So
here's this.
>> Yeah, here's this first one.
>> Um, Beia, do you think curiosity is a
learnable skill?
>> And if so, what strategies might help
individuals and communities to develop
and reinforce and
uh carry it forward?
>> Uh, curiosity we've said, right? CU is,
let me think of other questions. So, is
curiosity learnable? um
>> or can it be developed? Maybe maybe
>> can it be enhanced? Right. So
>> straight straight off the bat there are
no chemical you know pharmacological
stimulants uh that could enhance or
create uh curiosity at least not in a
healthy way. But there are um there are
cognitive and emotional conditions that
we could create to enhance uh curiosity.
Well, that this question actually very
good one takes me back to what we
mentioned earlier, right? About
curiosity arising when the brain detects
this information gap, right? So, why do
we become curious? Because we know that
there's something we don't yet know or
we can't yet do or we don't yet
understand, but we could. So the brain
sets in motion uh it's you know tried
and tested ways to make us motivated to
go out there and you know find the
missing piece in the puzzle. So how you
know how could we how could we create
the context in which curiosity peaks?
Um
I've I've noticed both in dance and
neuroscience that but mainly
neuroscience has confirmed this that the
human brain likes and at the same time
hates um incomplete puzzles
>> and that's tied in with the information
gap. When the brain detects that there
is a missing puzzle, it will it will
increase motivation to go out there and
find it. Right? We like we like to find
the missing gap. So sometimes if we
frame the learning material and the
question in such a way that we sense
that there's something we don't yet
know, our brains will do what needs to
be done to put us in the situation where
we can go out and you know find the
missing p the missing piece. So um
that's usually a strategy. Then um you
know novelty novelty is you know
bringing new things into into our
reality into our um environment can can
um can can spike curiosity. Brain loves
novelty. Um new new perspectives, new
ways of looking at the world, new new
tools, new tools are great. Like how do
I use this? new angles into a into a a a
problem. Um that's that's what uh
novelty
spikes curiosity.
Um also um that gets me thinking about
something that a friend of mine
mentioned the other day. Um Tim he said
that um he you know he feels more
curious and more motivated to do things
and also performs better when he feels
free
or I would say I would say autonomous
>> um yeah and just to get my disclaimer in
early by autonomous I don't you know I
don't mean anarchy by autonomy I mean
the freedom to to explore to sometimes
choose the question rather than um
engaging in the type of learning that
where you you just have to to learn
given material all the time. The sense
of agency, the sense of, you know, I'm
the one who does the exploration and
sometimes if it we don't choose the
answer, we at least choose the question.
M
>> um also you know feeling you know the
sense of sometimes
feeling safe maybe that's the word and I
will explain the sense of um you know
that low stake not always engaging in
low in high stakes environment not that
their environments not that they're bad
and they're not uh conducive to progress
or or or mastery or competence but
because the constant involvement ment in
a high stake slightly threatening
environment dampens curiosity. As we've
said before, curiosity spikes when the
brain shifts from threat perception
networks to exploratory networks. So
sometimes feeling a bit looser, a bit
more comfortable in an environment with
lower stakes can set off exploratory
behavior. um if we're constantly engaged
in in in learning um activities that
titillate the brain's defense
mechanisms, we tend to become less
curious and then motivation goes down a
bit. So
to answer the question, you know, frame,
you know, look for puzzles, incomplete
puzzles, um novelty, autonomy to explore
and then, you know, find environments
where you feel looser, you know, not
constantly judged, not constantly
evaluated and stuck labels on. I think
that helps with long-term sustainment
and uh um
and you sustainment and enhancing of of
curiosity and the motivation to back.
>> Yeah. Good. Yeah. Um
it it leads me to another set of
questions we got from from some folks
which I will I will summarize is while
we've been singing curiosities praises
you know are there ways in which you
know one might be too curious are there
are there are there ways that we might
want to think about managing that
curiosity to particular ends versus just
welcoming it
with
Okay, that's an interesting question.
Becoming too curious as in dabbing into
>> an excessive number of interests.
>> Yeah. Well, I think we can interpret it.
You know, you you were talking about
novelty and how novelty is a is a the
brain loves novelty. Um I assume
>> No, you're right. The brain Yeah. No,
you're totally right. The brain loves
novelty. But if there's one thing that
the brain can't do, as much as we would
like to think that and as much as you
know uh biohackers promise us, uh the
brain can't process unlimited input.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. Um,
cognitive fatigue is a real thing and
it's mainly due to the prefrontal cortex
which is you know sits just here below
the forehead uh being metabolically
extremely costly and uh it fatigues
easily and performance uh performance
goes down. So,
um, if becoming too curious about too
many things at one specific time leads
to cognitive overload,
then you have a problem, right? Because
there's, you know, there's mental
clutter. You won't see clearly. You
won't see as clearly. the brains
analytical instances won't be as well
equipped to one comprehend and make
sense of what's being learned to also
evaluate evidence right if it's
something that you know requires you
know seeking truth or you know figuring
out whether you know trying to make
sense of things that mental clutter that
um prefrontal fatigue right prefrontal
fatigue actually it it the prefrontal
cortex
fatigues because of two for two reasons.
One uh when multitasking and two when
having to switch between uh sources of
information. So you know um being too
curious as in being a bit
>> uh you know jumpy and frivolous about
what you allow your attention to go
towards if that leads to cognitive
overwhelm that those analytical
instances of the bra of the brain won't
do their job.
>> Yeah. as well. Yeah. So you need to you
need to filter, you need to curate and
then to focus and concentrate just to
keep uh just to keep cognitive uh
fatigue and cognitive overload from
happening. So I would say that is that
is a caveat when when plus you just
don't have enough attentional power.
It's it's mainly an issue of um of of
computation
>> mainly it's just brain limitation
>> but um you know when one you know
maintains enough distance to become
their own filter and curator then
hopefully you know it will get distilled
to what actually deserves your attention
and what doesn't.
>> Yeah. it uh this this makes me think of
um of this interesting balance that we
have found ourselves in with open
courseware and our MITx you know free
online open courses um that there's a
way in which the sort of information
system online is now really good at
feeding that wish for dopamine hits
right and the novelty continuous
>> um
>> and on the other And there might be
things that that are out in the world
that are just like too big to take on,
right? You know, require too much
persistence. But by by sharing materials
like open courseware does, here's
materials framed within say a course in
which they were taught, but here's the
materials openly for you to sort of make
your way through. There's enough of a
container that that you can sort of
match your persistence at the moment to
track your way through.
Um it's it's it's like the best of both
worlds if you will. It's like yeah all I
completely agree all of this all of this
stuff to feed your curiosity but just
contain it enough to walk you through
it. That's
>> that's what
>> and that also restores a bit of agency
if you like you know you're the one who
who chooses what what you know what's
internalized instead of everything
coming towards you and being a bit
overwhelming. Um I had that issue. I
remember when I approached uh MIT
courses I was I want oh god what do I do
I want to do everything and then I had
that and I had the immunology course and
I had Patrick uh Winston's I had the AI
course and then I I had the mind and
machine course. So, but it had um I
noticed that the structure in which
they're they're presented and then the
individual structure of the individual
courses actually um helped me tone down
that initial anxiety and I was like,
"Okay, hang on. I can sort of find my
way through it." So, it wasn't that that
overwhelming.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's it's a it's a helpful feature
to not have a defined end date where you
have to finish it all by Right.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um, you know, we got some
other questions um about
the the the shifting information, you
know, content landscape [clears throat]
out in the world, you know, um, you
know, and between say all the all the
shows that we can stream online and, you
know, short form videos that social
media is pushing out. Um, what role do
you think on an ongoing basis platforms
like MIT Open Learning can play in
in fostering, supporting uh, stewarding
that sort of like ability for deeper
learning? This is kind of building on
what we've just been talking about, but
maybe anything more to think about there
with like
>> opportunities for open for for deep
learning, you know? Yeah. Deeper
learning, you know, beyond the, you
know, the the short form stuff or the
pure entertainment stuff. Yeah. [snorts]
>> Yeah.
>> Well, I think the crux [sighs]
is
maybe sounds a bit, you know, elitist,
the quality of it, right? the rigor, the
um the fact that it's not something you
can it's not I mean it is entertaining
and it's it's definitely rewarding but
it's not something you can just brush
the surface of right. It's not something
that can be you just take a look at and
you dab in and out of this course and
then you move on to another. It takes it
takes a certain amount of engagement
depth of engagement. Does this answer
your question? Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um I it's something that again takes me
back to what we were saying earlier
about the protective effects of of
lifelong learning and its implications
on you know mental health and wellbeing
and resilience. And there are you know
maybe two things to note. The benefits
we outlined are dose dependent and also
cumulative. Right? you don't um you
don't derive the same benefits if you
dab in and out of interests and you
don't do it in a sustained uh type of
rigorous engagement. And I think at
least the courses I've uh I've completed
and the ones I'm I'm looking at now
don't really allow for that type of
entertainment
involvement. You have to you have to
apply yourself and again without that
threat that can that can arise from you
know to too high stakes like you said
you pace yourself and there are micro
wins and it comes with sheets and you
can do you know you can do the exercises
and then you can do the you can read the
you do the assignments and
um it it sort of requires a certain
level of of depth
um from the learner in terms of
engagement that um underpins uh deep
learning and the benefits that come with
that.
>> That's what I think.
>> That's what I've noticed.
>> Yeah. Good. Yeah. In in conversations
with colleagues around here, you know,
we we we are talking increasingly about
how to how to complement that depth with
like the right forms of engagement. um
uh you know to have things be MIT good
without you know right off the bat
having them all be so hard [laughter]
academically
um uh colleagues over at the at the MIT
Museum who are talking about this
concept of depth on demand right where
you where you meet people with you know
really engaging things you know to sort
of peique their curiosity but then be
able to flow through and follow through
with that uh feels like a really
important
um uh set of things to be developing
over time and I look forward to uh us
being able to get into that more and
more.
I think I think you know hard you know
the the hardness difficulty is some
something that people go for at least
myself when I um when I looked at these
courses I was actually quite happy that
they're hard that I didn't understand
because and it's it's normal I think for
for periods of of of overwhelm and doubt
and fatigue to occur because the courses
are so so difficult and so rigorous but
again if we look at it from from a
neuroscient perspect perspective. It's
that level of challenge and that limbic
friction. We call it that friction, you
know, that that sense of I'm I'm a bit
overwhelmed and I'm a bit scared. But
it's exactly that that
sense of challenge that drives uh
neuroplasticity and then helps with the
motivation to stay on track. So I'm sure
that um other people will agree um the
reason why we approached these these
courses is that they were well excellent
right exquisite in terms of the quality
of the material and how they're taught
but also because they're just in that
goldilock zone of of difficulty right if
something is too easy the brain gets
bored if something is too hard then
those defense mechanisms we I mentioned
earlier are titillated and the desire
ire to keep going is is is dampened. But
I think they're um you know they they're
they're perfectly poised on that angle
of the Goldilock zone of just above that
level of competence and you know maybe a
bit higher for motivation to keep you
going. So I was happy that they're hard
and you know some of them were so hard
that I you I have chunks of them that I
don't I couldn't approach fully
>> uh professor ran Adams's uh quantum
mechanics one god I got to the harmonic
oscillator bit I still even now I have
shivers down my spine and it took me
quite a while to work my way out of that
jungle in murky waters
>> but uh I had a human study buddy and uh
I was I think disciplined enough to keep
going. Um, so yeah, I I kind of like uh
the fact that they're, you know, just
the, you know, they're a bit harder than
than my uh muscles uh can fight.
>> Okay. Well, that material is will always
be there for you, so you can keep coming
back to it. Yeah. So, I think we're uh
we're about to draw to a close. Maybe
I'll um pose this very briefly. One last
question from our audience about, you
know, any thoughts on sort of cultural
or organizational practices that might
help foster this sort of environment.
For for me, for instance, that raises,
you know, um something that we're very
committed to, which is this sense of
knowledge as a public good. That this
this knowledge being out there and
shared freely with the world and
supporting that is a really important
cultural practice that sets the stage
for people such as yourself to have
access to these materials. And if you
know if any brief thought on a cultural
practice that you would like to see
supported more to help foster this sort
of curiosity, I'd love to hear about it.
>> The first thing that comes to mind and
maybe not the most relevant one is
linked is connected to what I said
earlier, the the the sense of safety.
>> Yeah.
>> Um the sense of low stakes, right? the
sense of looseness and and autonomy, the
not always having to do something
um for some extrinsic good, right? the
sense of I'm doing this not because I'm
judged and not because there's always a
job down the line and I have to complete
this course otherwise I won't keep the
job and I have to complete this program
in order to uh you know exceed to you
know a better job and and whatn not to
to to sometimes keep it low stakes and
not with either a hatchet above one's
head or with an immediate
goal which is maybe not even related to
the to the main interest in the first
place. But to allow for for for
curiosity and and supporting motivation
to arise naturally to allow for more
looseness
um in people to to to move and and
choose their areas of interest and uh
then pursue it in a less judgmental
way. um you know just people feeling
more supported and and and lifted. I'm
using dance tones rather than constantly
you know evaluated and pushed u in a you
know do this so you can grab the other
type of way. Does that make sense?
>> Yes, it sure does. I think that's a
wonderful sort of way to to to wrap the
conversation. you know, may we all find
these safe uh inviting spaces to to to
engage in learning in just that sort of
way. Yeah, I really appreciate that.
>> Yeah. All right. Well, this has been a
wonderful conversation, Beia. So glad
that you've been able to share your
experiences and your perspectives and
insights with us. You know, your drive
to help others and yourself is is
inspirational. So, thank you to everyone
who's tuned in and joined this
conversation. We welcome you to keep
learning with MITx, with MIT Open
Courseware, and with MIT Open Learning.
We also welcome you to support our work
by sharing our resources with your
friends, colleagues, and families.
Sharing your experiences and your
stories of how you've used these free
resources with us. Share us share those
stories with us. And if you're in a
position to do so, please do consider
donating to support our efforts and the
thousands of people who use our free
resources every day. And until our next
open conversation, I wish you a fond
farewell. And uh thanks again, Beia, for
joining us today.