So, there's a lot of builtin support to
really make these engagements impactful.
It's not just we're going to match you,
you're going to travel for a week, and
then you're done. Um there's a entire
ecosystem to make this successful. And I
think um that's why our projects have
the lasting impact that they do.
Welcome everyone to Thursdays with
Terrell. I will have Becca introduce
herself, talk about how long she's been
at Sloan and what she's most excited
about in her role.
>> Thanks Terrell. Hi everyone. Thank you
for having me today. Um I've been at
Sloan for about 13 years and I started
admissions. So really excited that
Terrell asked me to speak today. Uh my
name is Becca Souza and I'm the director
of action learning here at MIT Sloan. So
for those of you who are not as familiar
with action learning, basically this is
a type of teaching that is well known at
MIT Sloan where students are taking
courses, they're being evaluated by
faculty members, but as part of those
courses, they're working with real life
host companies to solve real world
problems. And this is built into the
curriculum. This is not an internship um
but it's an aspect to really take what
you're learning and go and do. Um, so
what makes me excited for this role, um,
is one, I think we're always trying to
be cutting edge, so always having the
most updated courses that students
really want to learn from. And then
within the last year, I think we've
really taken more of an approach to
ensure that the companies that we have
as part of action learning are the
companies that students really want to
work for when they graduate or they're
in regions where students once they
graduate, they want to go to that part
of the country or part of the world. So,
we're trying to really align with um
student expectations and student
outcomes as part of action learning. Um,
so that's something that has been on my
mind within the last couple years and
really excites me.
>> Awesome. Thank you for sharing, Becca.
So, I do have a quick slide just kind of
as an overview of the experiential
learning aspect of MIT Sloan. Like Becca
touched on, action learning is a part of
our um curriculum and a way for you to
kind of get some hands-on experience.
Um, there's over 20 plus action learning
labs. We'll probably dive into um those
individual ones that you may have
questions about. um and they happen at
multiple points during the academic year
whether it's during the independent
activities period or during our Sloan
intensive period. So there's multiple
touch points for students to engage in
the action learning that we do have to
offer here. Um I do have my first
question for Becca um in terms of our
conversation today is could you kind of
kind of walk us through like what is
action learning and why is it important
to the Sloan um school's mission um that
we have here?
>> Great. Um so it's a really a simple
question. Um our motto is think act
reflect. So MIT also has a motto men's
monis mind in hand and MIT Sloan action
learning is a teaching method where
students take what they learn in the
classroom and they're able to apply it
to a real business challenge. So as I
mentioned before these are different
from internships. They're credit bearing
courses. So, you are registering for
these during the school year and you're
taking them just like any other class.
Typically, they're done in small groups,
anywhere from three to six students. So,
you're doing them with your classmates.
It's a great networking opportunity
because you're able to take these
classes with students from your
individual program, other programs at
MIT Sloan across MIT's campus. Um, and
then it's also an opportunity to learn
about leadership. um whether that's
leading within your team, leading with
the host company, um there's great ways
to practice that. And most importantly
is at the end of the term, you're
actually giving a result to a company.
So you're presenting um to the hosts
about um your recommendations with the
goal that they're going to implement
them immediately. And many students stay
in touch with their host companies to
see how that implementation process
goes. So really that's the definition of
action learning. Um we do have some
goals that we really want students to
come out of when they're taking action
learning. So as I mentioned, one is we
want you to apply classroom theories and
frameworks to real business challenges.
Um so take everything you've learned
throughout um the actual lab course, but
also throughout the curriculum at MIT
Sloan. We also want you to be able to
put some structure to problems. Um so uh
we have a faculty member Nelson Repening
and he always talks about a chief
marketing officer is not handed a
problem that just pertains to marketing.
It's going to impact the entire
business. And we want you to be able to
put structured to some unstructured
problems. And this is what happens in
action learning. um the scope of the
problem changes throughout the term and
students need to adapt. They need to
think on their feet. They need to
reflect and change course and so you're
able to really figure out um good um
project management skills. We want you
to be able to collaborate effectively in
teams as I mentioned have some open um
discourse. You're with a diverse team so
you need to be able to provide feedback
one to one another. You need to learn to
lead. And then lastly, action learning
is a great opportunity for reflection.
Uh many students take our courses
because they know they want to go into
that industry. So for example, the
professor who teaches healthcare lab,
she always recommends students who want
to stay in healthcare and who've had a
healthcare experience take her course.
Students who've never done healthcare
but you may want to take her course
because it's a great reflection point on
is this something that really interests
me? Is this something I see myself doing
in a future career? Um, how does this
fit into my career goals? You're able to
ask yourself a lot of questions um
during the action learning process.
>> Thank you for that answer, Becca. And I
do have a follow-up question as it
pertains to the companies that you
mentioned. Um, there may be some
questions here about like how do we get
companies on board and, you know, how do
we get them to engage with the Sloan
community before the action learning lab
even begins?
>> Great question. So typically how we get
um different companies involved in
Action Learning, one through our alumni.
That's our number one um resource.
students take action learning, they love
the experience, and then when they go um
into their career, they're like, one, I
want to give back to MIT Sloan, but also
this is such a unique um opportunity for
me to showcase my network and my MIT
Sloan strength with my company and get
some of these projects happening
immediately once they start. So, alumni
is our number one. We're also very happy
to say our second um source of projects
and companies through action learning is
repeat companies. So that's a twofold.
One companies do one project in
operations lab and then next year they
want to do it again because they loved
the work. They loved the results but
we're even seeing even more a company
does a project in operations lab but
then they say wait a minute we also want
to do a project in Gen AI lab. We also
want to do a project in enterprise
management lab. So we're able to share
companies across the portfolio again
because these companies are really
seeing the impact that MIT Sloan
students can deliver on. Um so those are
two and then third is mainly my team or
the faculty's outreach. So our faculty
have a big say in these companies
through their connections but they're
also looking at feedback from students.
A lot of the courses will survey the
students. What are the companies that
you're most interested in? What are the
countries you're most interested in? And
then they try to match based on that. My
team also does that. We use a lot of
different reports, mainly reports from
our career development office of where
are the companies that students are
landing jobs, where are the gaps, and
could we try to um you know focus in on
the companies that students are going to
work for or the companies that students
want to work for. um and to see those
numbers increase.
>> Awesome. Thank you for sharing that,
Becky. Rebecca, um I do have a question
that we pretty much get very frequently
when we're out recruiting students in
terms of how were student voices and
experiences integrated into the options
for action learning labs. So, if a
student has an idea about a potential
action learning lab, how can they go
about potentially launching that with
the action learning office?
>> Another great question. Um so I'll give
a story because I think this illustrates
how um pivotal student voice is at MIT
Sloan. So um in 2022 we had a course
Israel lab where students were taking a
um the lab and they were working with
Israeli startups typically tech startups
on new solutions. And then unfortunately
um some Middle East um fighting occurred
and we had a pivot. our students were
unable to travel to Israel that January
and so we pivoted and we connected with
a lot of alumni in Miami and they said
you should come and showcase Miami. A
lot of um South American work starts in
Miami when they want to expand to US but
we really have a large Israeli
contingency here and you can meet with a
lot of companies and talk about the
startup movement in Miami. So we did
just that. We pivoted and we took this
track and during it we met with some MIT
Sloan alumni who really managed large
real estate portfolios
and during that um the alumni and the
students were saying I would love to go
into real estate but during my time at
MIT Sloan there weren't many classes
focused on it. I feel like my resume is
not as well prepared when I'm trying to
apply for these projects. And so we
walked away from that saying why don't
we start a real estate lab. Um the next
year um we did so last year we um
introduced real estate lab into our
portfolio. Um again we wanted it to
really be unique and distinctive. So we
partnered with the center for real
estate on MIT's campus to offer this um
dual course that has MIT Sloan students
as well as um real estate students. So
they may have a focus in architecture,
they may have a focus in finance impact
impacting. And we really came together
to create this course so students could
have that hands-on experience when
they're going to apply for jobs for
internships and they can speak to their
real estate past. Um so that's a that's
a really highlevel example of how
students have made impact. But there's
also smaller examples. Uh my office, we
hold feedback sessions every term where
we ask students to come. This year I
actually asked my team instead of having
students sign up, can we reach out to
students who have not taken action
learning? And I want to find out why
have they not taken action learning? Has
it not been a priority for them? Are the
courses not fitting their needs? Do they
have any ideas? So once we hear this
feedback, we try to take action. Um, one
of our new deans priorities is really
interacting with the greater MIT and so
real estate lab is a great example of
that. Another great example um that
we've introduced within the last year is
engine lab. So um MIT has um something
called the engine. If you haven't worked
if you haven't looked into it, I highly
recommend just um you know googling
that. And what comes out of the engine
is tough tech startups. So Fiona Murray,
who's the dean of innovation at MIT
Sloan, she developed a course engine lab
where MIT Sloan students partner with
these tough tech startups that are
coming out of the engine at MIT. Um so
again trying to really integrate Sloan
with greater MIT resources and that also
came from the idea of um we wanted
something new and we want to make sure
this connects with what students want to
do upon graduation.
>> Awesome. You touched on the integration
aspect of action learning labs and I
know students may think this is a Sloan
exclusive kind of program but can you
talk about the crossover that we have
with the greater MIT and how students
can engage with different disciplines
here at MIT?
>> Yes. So action learning is such a great
resource if you want to integrate with
other programs within Sloan or other
departments within MIT. So I mentioned
real estate lab, our geni lab um that
began last year. They're hoping to
crosslist with course six at MIT Sloan.
So they have many undergrads taking that
course. Engine lab is a great example.
Our course entrepreneurship lab that
happens every fall and spring term
typically has over 10 different um
student bodies within it. So, they'll
have two-year MBAs, they'll have some
executive populations like our Sloan
fellows, they'll have students
cross-registered from Harvard, they'll
have mechanical engineering students.
Um, and once you're in these labs,
you're on a team and usually we try to
make the teams very diverse. So, um, you
kind of have this great mechanism that
introduces you to students outside of
your, um, individual network. Um so if
you know if I was a student I honestly
think action learning would probably be
a top priority if I really want to get
to know um students and um from other
parts of the institute and even beyond.
Uh entrepreneurship lab always has
students from Welssley. I mentioned
Harvard um many of our students from
Harvard Kennedy like to take action
learning because they want to see how
policy impacts some of these decision-
making. Um, so it's a great way really
to get to know um, different parts of
MIT.
>> Awesome. And I do have a question that
popped up in the chat that I was going
to ask next, so it's a great kind of
segue in terms of students in terms of
engaging with multiple action learning
labs. Is that's is that a possibility
for students to take part in?
>> Yes, we love when students take more
than one um, action learning course. So,
we typically say only one action
learning course per term. So um assuming
that ma mainly it's two-year MBAs on the
call you will have a core term in the
fall there is one action learning option
you can take your initial fall but then
after your core term you really are
starting to take a lot of different
electives and you have a lot of
different options and opportunity you
can take an action learning lab each
term there have been students who take
more than one each term but if there's
any travel associated with a lab you
can't just because the travel will
happen at the same time. Um, but we've
had many MBAs um, take up to three or
four labs and we love that because they
bring a different element. Again, all
those goals that I mentioned earlier,
they have already experienced that. So,
they can come in and say, "We really
need to focus on project management or
we need to really push back on our host
company. The scope is getting too large.
Let's um, really narrow it down." They
can offer some of that advice if they've
taken one before. Awesome.
And then I guess a follow-up question to
that in terms of students that are
coming from different programs as long
as we have some specialized masters, we
have the one-year MBA, we have the
two-year MBA, and then of course our
executive MBA. So what is the process
for enrolling um in an action learning
lab depending on which program you're in
because some of them may be here for a
shorter amount of time. So how do they
kind of navigate that process?
>> Great question. So, um, most of our
courses are on MIT's Sloan's bidding.
Um, and if you don't know bidding,
basically you will receive a,000 points
each term to bid for the courses that
you're most interested in. So, if
there's a course you really want to
take, you may decide, I want to bid all
my points or I may want to bid 500. Uh,
MIT provides you a lot of data and game
theory on how to do this. Um, I will say
most students do get into the courses
they want to. So don't um overthink that
process. But some of our courses also
have application because um the faculty
need to understand some of your um
unique skill sets. So for example um
product management we really want
students to have some form of experience
whether that's a class um a part past
role they've taken an internship in this
genai we need to understand what's your
coding ability what's your technical
ability. So some of our classes are
application and faculty will evaluate
and then some of our labs are
requirement for certain programs. So for
example, our masters in business
analytics needs to take analytics lab.
So you don't need to bid, you don't need
to apply, you're automatically going to
be enrolled in that. Our master of
finance has an action learning
requirement. So they have some options
that they can pick and choose from. Our
executive MBAs action learning is also a
requirement. So they automatically get
into the course the course options
there. So there's it the answer can
really vary per program per lab but most
the biggest message I want to get with I
want to um relay with this is don't
panic. Um a lot of our labs um have a
lot of seats because students are
interested and faculty are always
willing to work with students um to
figure out how to get you into classes.
So overall, it's not a stressful
situation. Um, we just want really
excited and engaged students.
>> Awesome. So I have one final question. I
know we're right at time. So I have one
final question before we transition to
the open Q&A. And there may be some uh I
guess concern or I guess addressing the
elephant in the room in terms of the
geopolitical landscape and how that may
be affecting some of our action learning
labs for some of our international
students. So, can you just kind of talk
about what we're doing um to be able to
accommodate students that still want to
have a travel aspect but may be a little
bit hesitant in terms of traveling to a
different location?
>> Great question. Um so, we want to make
sure that our offerings are equal to
all. So, a few things. One, we do have
international students in our fall
course, global entrepreneurship lab.
That is only international travel
typically to emerging uh countries. We
have 84 students enrolled in that and um
a good portion are international
students. We follow um we give any
recommendations from MIT's international
student office. So we're constantly
updating them, communicating with them,
giving them best practices. It's
ultimately up to the student to decide
if they want to travel. This year most
are willing to do that. However, if that
changes, we also have some
contingencies. Some of our labs have
US-based travel. So we have a course
called work lab that we're redesigning
for this year that's working with many
manufacturing companies that is only
within the United States. Real estate
lab will have international projects as
well as US-based projects. Operations
lab is mainly US-based projects. So, we
do have some flexibility that if travel
is something that you really want to do,
that is important to you, but you're an
international student and once you're
here, you don't want to take that risk,
we want to work with you. Um, and then
there's obviously some even further
contingencies where you sign up for an
international lab, but you're unable to
travel. You can still do some of that
work virtually. Sometimes even um for
example we've had a project um in Azon
lab that there was um Bostonbased
offices so students went and visited
there. So we want to make sure that if
this fits your learning objectives your
goals as a student but travel could
become in the way we want to make sure
you have options. And then the last
thing I will say is not all our labs
require travel. Um so we have um
healthcare labs. Sometimes you may visit
local Boston hospitals but no travel is
required. Uh we have enterprise
management lab no travel is required.
Genai no travel is required as of now.
PM usually no travel. So if you even if
you're like regardless of my status I
like Boston. I want to stay there. Um
there's still opportunities for you.
>> Awesome. Thank you for sharing that and
thank you for answering my moderated
questions. So we do have a lot of
questions in the Q&A. So I'll just those
now. Um I'll try to start in order and
I'll keep these anonymous so we can have
um some confidentiality in people's you
know questions. So the first question I
have here is in terms of the finance lab
or the proseminar in investment
management um do you have some projects
focused on fundamental equity research
as well?
>> So good question. Um a lot of our
projects are not necessarily
researchbased in the sense of like
you're just delivering a rapport. we're
solving problems. Um, so looking at this
question, I'm sure that we do have some
projects based on that problem, but
they're not research reportbased, if
that makes sense. Um, and just to give a
little bit clarification, we have our
um, finance lab. So that happens during
independent activities periods period in
January. And then we have two different
proseminars. Um, so those are one is in
the fall and one is in the spring. One
is focused on capital markets, one is
more focused on corporate finance. So
regardless of what your finance interest
is, we definitely can find a home for
you. Um, again based on student
feedback, we heard some feedback that
alternative investments is something
that students are really interested in.
So we've developed some alternative
investment projects within finance lab.
So if you have a specific idea in mind
whether if we can hopefully find that
within an existing lab or talk about
future but usually faculty are very good
at trying to find different products to
cater to um different student demands.
>> Awesome. And the next question I have
kind of has a two-way kind of um kind of
approach to it. Um, so for the
certificate programs that we offer at
MIT Sloan, um, so for someone that may
be specifically interested in one of
those, um, like the entrepreneurship
innovation certificate, would you
recommend taking multiple labs, um,
during their time here?
>> Yes. So the certificate, many of the
certificates um, coincide with the
action learning office and why that is
is because many of our certificates
require an action learning lab in order
to graduate. Um so for example um
product management uh certificate
requires that you take product
management lab. So yes if certificates
are of interest to you most likely you
will be taking a lab because it will be
a requirement. Even if the labs are not
a requirement for that certificate. A
lot of labs count as electives because
not only may the content be um
associated with the certificate, but the
actual project of the lab could be
associated and then it counts as an
elective. Um so action learning and
certificates do often go handinand.
>> Awesome. And the next question I have in
terms of potential restrictions. So are
there any kinds of companies or types of
companies like defense that would be
prohibited for foreign students um to
participate in action learning labs?
>> As of right now, no. Um however, when we
um find when we source our companies,
one of the questions we always ask them,
are there any conflicts of interest that
we need to be aware of students? So
whether you um have worked from for a
competitor or that maybe your our EMBAs
are currently employed so their company
may have an existing conflict. We will
then ask the students that. So um just
to get into a little bit more detail
once you're in a lab you will find out
all the projects and a lot of times
students have say in which projects they
rank their projects. During that
process, we will also say to you, are
there any companies that you feel like
you have a conflict of interest? Maybe
you have some financial tie to to
something or you've worked with a
competitor. And we make sure that it's
an equal match. So, if you say there's a
conflict, we won't match you. If they
say it's a conflict, we won't match you.
And we always have some contingency
plans for that. So, as of now, there's
no specific outliers of international
students can't work on certain projects.
However, I don't want to say an overall
no just because there could be a
conflict of interest based on each
individual student that could impact
project matching.
Awesome. Thank you for that
clarification. Um, and the next question
I have pertains to entrepreneurship lab,
which is actually one of our more
popular labs here. Um, do projects in
the entrepreneurship lab ever continue
beyond the semester? Um, for instance,
with our Martin Trust Center for
Entrepreneurship. Um so just trying to
figure out how do those particular
programs potentially lead to like
startup prototypes or seed funding those
type of things.
>> Great. So entrepreneurship lab is a
little bit different. You are not
working on your own idea. You're working
um on an existing startup's idea whether
that is to expand it to develop a new
product line um a new go to market
strategy a marketing strategy. So you're
not developing your own startup. There
are some courses um that are um hosted
by the Martin Trust Center like um I
think it's called entrepreneurial
ventures where you can really focus on
your own idea, your own prototype. Um
but to answer the question, do they ever
expand past terms? So from an action
learning standpoint, the answer is no.
We say once you give your final
deliverables the action learning
engagement is over. However, I can say
anecdotally from um speaking with many
students that is not always the case. Um
we have had examples where students get
hired from action learning companies,
they go to intern, they are asked to
consult um on future projects, they want
to volunteer and stay engaged. So there
are opportunities to stay involved but
specific to entrepreneurship lab um the
enga the engagement is done once you're
handing over your final deliverables.
>> Thank you for that. And I have another
question. This kind of talks about um I
guess student outcomes. So were there
any instances where students who took
the lab got professionally connected to
the host company and joined the company
after completing the program?
>> Yes. Um most recent we just posted on
LinkedIn. I think we have a couple
quotes if anyone wants to check out the
um MIT Sloan LinkedIn action learning
but um an EMBA student last year did a
project um with a company called
Manatech. Um they do a lot of different
things um a lot of innovation, a lot of
real estate and um he did the project he
was there in March for a week. He
wrapped it up in um end of April and
then the position of I believe it's
chief marketing officer became open.
They contacted him encouraging him to
apply and now he is there. Um so a great
story of one action learning engagement
really having an impact on career. Um we
have more of those stories anecdotally.
uh we don't do the best of like
quantifying it or showing impact um but
it definitely does happen in many
different ways and um not only full-time
offers but as I mentioned um internships
and even consulting opportunities.
>> Awesome. Few more questions in the chat
here. Um so we touched on the unique
aspect of the action learning labs here
at Sloan. Um but a lot of schools
nowadays have adopted a similar concept.
So, could we could you just kind of
touch on like what makes Sloan's action
learning labs different than some of our
peer schools?
>> Great question. So, um one thing that's
nice about working in higher ed is that
um a lot of times we meet with our with
different peer schools not as
competitors as really of sharing
knowledge across higher education. And
one thing that I always notice when I
meet with the different peers within
action learning is ours is set up much
more unique that ours is tied to an
actual academic course where students
are learning content. So for example
product management lab you are going to
be working and doing um work with a
company that's focused on that. However,
when you are taking class you're going
to learn about product management. A lot
of our peers it's quite different. Um,
so for example, Harvard does field where
all students get to work with a company,
but there's no associated class. You may
have a faculty mentor, but you don't
have a professor who's helping you
understand the concepts and the
frameworks needed to successfully
execute the project. Um, so I think ours
is much more academically linked and
tied to a bigger um, ecosystem of MIT. I
also think MIT within within MIT Sloan
we provide a lot of support to our
students. So many of our classes use a
faculty mentor. So when you take a class
you're going to have the actual faculty
teaching the course. They are going to
be a resource for you. Then you're going
to have the resource of a faculty
mentor. They're usually process experts.
They know these type of engagements.
They know how to make them successful.
But a lot of time times they're content
experts. they've worked in this
industry, they've worked in this region
and they can offer you advice on how to
um really meet the um demands of the
company. Then you have your team, then
you have the TA, then a lot of class
time is shared experiences. So as a
student, you can say we're running into
this concern. Has any other team done it
and how did you overcome this? Um, so
there's a lot of builtin support to
really make these engagements impactful.
It's not just we're going to match you,
you're going to travel for a week, and
then you're done. Um, there's a entire
ecosystem to make this successful. And I
think um that's why our projects have
the lasting impact that they do.
>> Awesome. So, seems like I'm kind of
bouncing around here, but I'm trying to
find the questions that are really
relevant to the conversation that we
touched on already. Um we touched on
this earlier in terms of um when the
labs are available. So for the formal
in-class semester, IEP and then it
intensive period. How do the action
learning labs differ across the
different periods of time that you may
be able to take them?
>> Yes. Okay. So at MIT Sloan, we have
three terms. We have a fall term, we
have IEP, and we have a spring term. So
some of our labs are specific to a term.
So you will take um I will give like
just specific examples of um analytics
lab is a fall course. It starts in
September, ends in December. So you are
um working with the company those
months. Then we have some courses that
overlap terms. So for example, global
entrepreneurship lab, that's one of our
flagship courses. It's taught by um
Nobel Prize winner Simon Johnson. That
is a fall course and then it extends
into AP. So the students are taking
class starting in September throughout
December. But then in January during IAP
they're going on site for 3 weeks to
their company typically to an emerging
market. Um so this year we have um
Kenya, Nigeria, Indonesia, Vietnam,
Spain, uh Chile, um we're real um
Kuwait, Dubai, we're really across the
globe. Um so that's an example of a
course that is spanning terms bu fall
and AP. Then some of our courses do the
opposite. They start in IP and then they
end in spring. Finance lab, you're
working with the company during IEP in
January, but then you're taking class
content in February and March. But then
we also have courses that are just
springterm. So our just springterm is
ASEON lab. You start in February, you
end in May. Um this last year we
introduced our first course that just
happens during AP. It's a one-week
course that works with nonprofits in the
local um Boston area and it's a mo it's
uh leading with impact. It's an
opportunity for students to really take
a multistakeholder model and apply it to
an organization in need. So a lot of
times students are like, you know,
probably in the future I'm not going to
want to work for a nonprofit. But what's
nice about leading with impact is you
have to take into account not only are
you working with a nonprofit, but most
likely you're working within the
government agency. A lot of times you're
working with university. A lot of times
funding comes from corporate. So it's
really that multistakeholder view. Um
and that's our first course that is just
one week specific in January. It doesn't
span any terms. Um so in short, it
really varies by lab. um when you are
here as a student, we give a lot of
presentations and we showcase visuals so
you can understand the layout. Um but we
make it we make it work based too on
what you need. So if you say to us, I
only can take a course in the spring,
we'll give you the offerings that just
um happen during that time.
>> Awesome. So I've identified three final
questions that'll get us to time but I
do apologize we don't get to all the
questions today but thank you all for
sharing. Um so they're very specific to
different um functionalities of action
learning labs. So the first ask is terms
of the funding aspect or financial
support for students that are
participating in action learning labs.
So can you just talk about that process
and how it works for students to gain
support financially for an action
learning lab?
>> Another great question. I apologize as I
should have brought that up on my own.
So uh forgive me. Amazing thing about
action learning it does not cost
students any additional. So the course I
mentioned global entrepreneurship lab or
known as Gab that has the most travel
that's 3 weeks. Most of our other travel
is one to two weeks. The host companies
pay for accommodations in airfare. So
students are not paying for that. Um we
really encourage the accommodations to
include breakfast have kitchens. So um
we don't pay for the food but typically
you know you are eating as a student
anyways um and we try to give you as
much resources for that. So any action
learning will not cost the student any
extra. The um school pays for any visa
fees that you may incur. Um we have a
lot of resources available. MIT
insurance. We have an emergency system
if anything happens on the ground and um
you need to um receive emergency
services. So, we help with that support.
Um so, the companies value what you're
bringing to the table and action
learning does not charge. So, we do not
charge the host companies to
participate. However, if they do
participate in a lab that requires
travel, the host companies pay for the
airfare and accommodations.
>> Awesome. Thank you for sharing that
response because I'm pretty sure that
was on the top of everybody's mind but
thank you to that person that that so
the next question I have is actually a
program specific question specifically
for those who were interested in a Sloan
Fellows MBA. Um is there any flexibility
at the start of the term to participate
in different labs before enrollment
during the full semester or is it only
during that 12 months that those
students are here?
>> Uh good question. Unfortunately, it is
only the 12 month months. MIT is very
strict until you're enrolled as a
student, we can't offer any of these
official um you know official offerings.
So, as a Sloan fellow, you take your
summer core um you there's no other
class, not many classes happening at
MIT, so you're really focused on core,
but then you're going to learn all about
bidding for the fall. So, we do have
Sloan Fellows students who take fall
labs as well as spring labs. So even
though it's that 12 months, um there's
really no missed opportunity. You still
have a full two terms to take action
learning.
>> Awesome. And then the next question I
have pertained to something you
mentioned earlier about business
analytics students and their requirement
of taking um the analytics lab. What's
the different focus between that action
learning lab and maybe their business
analytics capstone project?
>> Uh another great question. So a few
things. one analytics lab is not only
MBAN so you will get to have a network
of others and it's basically a shorter
engagement of your capstone so it it's a
good training exercise for capstone so
for those of you who are on the call and
um have never heard of the capstone that
is for uh our business analytic students
specifically it's a seven-month
engagement uh it begins in the spring
term and goes throughout the summer um
that is two students per company,
whereas our action learning is typically
a larger size, shorter engagement. Um,
and you, you know, less hours for the
action learning than the capstone
because the capstone is considered
full-time in the summer.
>> Awesome. I do have one bonus question
for you, but it's more light-hearted. In
terms of your experience working in
admissions, I definitely wanted to ask
this question. What advice would you
give to prospective students that are
navigating the application process,
regardless of which program they're
applying to?
Um, so one thing that I that I feel like
I really like about my background is as
Terrell mentioned, I started in
admissions. Then I actually worked more
closely with our EMBA and our Sloan
fellow students. I was um an adviser, so
I really helped them balance work, life,
school. And my biggest piece of advice
may not necessarily um help with like
the application um operations as I have
been a little bit removed. Well, one, be
authentic. Like, be yourself. Um, MIT
Sloan is a humble place. We love to get
to know everyone individually. So, be
authentic. Um, but my biggest piece of
advice when you're approaching
application process and just thinking
about the mindset of a student is MIT
Sloan has so much to offer. Um, and I
think our students who are really
successful by the time they graduate,
one thing they did throughout the
process is like write down your goals.
What are the outcomes you want um from
getting whichever degree? Um, and those
goals are going to change. The the point
isn't for you to graduate and say, "Let
me tick them all off." But just really
reflecting on why you're here, what's
the priority? Because by the time you're
a student, everything is going to be
thrown at you. and it it can become
overwhelming. But if you have that those
um specific things that you really want
to get out, you're going to be more
level-headed. You're going to um not be
trying to do everything. You're going to
be more um have more intent. And I
really encourage students to take some
time to reflect and um come in with some
form of plan. That plan will change. And
I I love when I see that. But a lot of
the foundation of the plan is most
important.
>> Great advice cuz we actually say share
the 8020 rule here. So being able to
come in with 80% of what you want to do,
but having that 20% to remain flexible
um during your two years here or your
one year here at Sloan. Um so great
advice for our prospective students in
the audience. Becca, I want to thank you
again for being here and sharing some um
insights into action learning because we
do get a lot of questions on the road.
um definitely happy to you know have a
colleague like you that kind of share
insight for our prospective students.
This is a valuable experience for you
all hopefully. Um, so Becca, thank you
again and thank you all for