hello and welcome to energy reads my
name is Kelly Travers I'm your host I'm
speaking to you from the MIT energy
initiative sometimes when we read these
articles to you on the podcast there's
just a bit more to the story that we're
dying to tell you and now we can today
is our first footnote edition of the
podcast where we will be digging a bit
deeper into some of our articles in our
last episode responding to Ukraine's
ocean of suffering we introduced you to
Ian Miller he's an MIT Alum as well as a
former colleague of mine at MIT well at
the energy initiative Ian researched
electric vehicles and also worked on a
modeling tool called the sustainable
energy system analysis modeling
environment or Sesame this tool allows
us to study the carbon footprint of the
energy system as a whole plus if that's
not enough Ian's also an expert on
photovoltaics and windpower as we
learned in the article within 72 hours
of the first Russian missiles striking
key Ukraine Ian was on a plane to Poland
he's been working tirelessly to Aid the
Ukrainian people ever since he
co-founded zeroline a nonprofit
dedicated to delivering Medical Aid
vehicles and equipment to ukrainians on
the front line today I'm joined by Ian
to talk more about his work his interest
and energy and how he got to where he is
today thank you for being here Ian and
for taking the time to share more about
your life with us thanks a lot for
having me it's an
honor well there is a lot to talk about
your story story is so interesting and
so inspiring so let's just Dive Right In
and I'm going to start with an obvious
question how did you get involved in
energy I first got interested in energy
in college I was majoring in government
at Georgetown and I took an energy
policy class which was focused on uh
policies to fight climate change and
that was very interesting to me but it
didn't really
go anywhere energy specific just yet but
it did start an interest a simmering
interest and then after college I became
a science teacher I started a after
school science program called young
scientists and I I taught that in Uganda
New York and Boston and a big part of
that curriculum was about energy it was
focused on energy now it was for little
kids some sometimes high schoolers um
but still um describing the science of
energy and of conversion of chemical
energy
into uh Fuel and electric energy for
middle schoolers and above that built my
interest further
gradually I realized that there was a
engineering desire in me and that I
wanted to work in energy technology
somehow and I looked at ways to do that
chemical engineering was a very uh
appealing way because there's so many
applications in energy within chemical
engineering uh whether it's designing
materials for better
photovoltaics or biofuels um or the the
software modeling World which is so
important to electric vehicle adoption
and many other areas of renewable energy
growth so I I looked at how to get into
chemical engineering and the the short
answer was graduate school I got some
coursework under my belt in chemical
engineering some of the prerequisites I
was missing I got myself into a couple
Laboratories at MIT as a lab assistant
to get some real wet lab experience with
uh professors Doyle and gleon and then I
applied and focused on energy in my
masters in chemical engineering at MIT
so do you think any of your early
experiences kind of also set you on this
path or do you think it was really that
energy policy class that kicked it off
for you it was a big part of it uh there
was a a more general interest right why
did I take the energy policy in the
class in the first place learning about
uh energy
challenges and climate change concerns
and and staying informed on those topics
and getting really excited about growing
electrification not just in
transportation but in other areas Like
Home Heating and be beyond that was a
motivator as well so when you started
working on your Masters in chemical
engineering you were pursuing studies in
solar and wind energy then your move
your research moved more into electric
vehicles and modeling greenhouse gas
emissions across the energy Spectrum can
you tell us a bit about your research
trajectory and how it's shifted over
time I started in wet Labs before the
Masters I was working on micro batteries
in Professor Karen Gleason's lab and
then in my Master's and then into my my
thesis research with Professor Bob
Armstrong I shifted more towards
modeling and they were surely related
because you know experiments um always
involve some amount of modeling whether
it's in the predictions or the
measurements or the analysis or a
combination and you know I had always
always been interested in
Renewables um and and Bob and mighty
more broadly are doing so much uh
exciting essential work in modeling of
Renewables I was immediately interested
in that so uh when Bob and uh Dr Frank O
Sullivan described to me the modeling
work they were doing and the Sesame work
that was just kind of nent it was just
starting with a Dr emry genser I was
really interested so they took me on and
the wind and photovoltaics Analysis
related really smoothly to the electric
vehicle work because as the Sesame group
grew and our research grew you know I
got to see the big picture of how
Renewables and electric vehicles can
interact so we've mentioned Sesame a
couple times now do you mind just kind
of running through what Sesame actually
is sure uh so Sesame above all is a fun
name for a software platform so that
people can say open sesame that's my bad
joke uh that that's good I like it great
so sustainable energy system and
modeling environment is the acronym
Sesame focuses on analyzing questions
like okay if electric vehicle share of
the fleet in a country say the US grows
to 50% by 2040 what does that mean for
electricity demand what does that mean
for the shape of electricity demand and
how does that affect the possibilities
for the power generation mix scenario
analysis is a really big focus of Sesame
right so look at that high EV future
with high renew Ables with no
manipulation of when people charge just
assume it matches when they charge today
and then compare that to a scenario
where where virtual power plants and
other in intermediary companies shift
when electric vehicles demand energy and
estimate which scenario has higher costs
which scenario has higher emissions and
those are the two most important outputs
of the Sesame model when it's analyzing
any future scenario the greenhouse gas
emissions associated with that scenario
and the costs associated with that
scenario I don't want to I don't want to
jump the the gun here I I can't resist
just a little it might not be widely
known how much the war in Ukraine has
generated interest in Renewables yeah no
I'm glad that you made the segue because
because I was actually just going to ask
you about your working Ukraine because
it really does seem like one energy is
such an underlying thread in this war
but also you are there doing great work
you know when the war in Ukraine broke
out you immediately flew to Poland to
see how you could help I think a lot of
people wish that they could help in
those moments but if you actually get on
the airplane and do it can you tell me
what it was like making that decision I
made the decision for three reasons
inspir Iration ease and impact the
inspiration part was watching the news
on February 26 the third day of the
invasion on my couch in
Boston I was horrified by what Russia's
Army was doing the attacks on civilians
the indiscriminate bombing was um a a
feature not a bug from day one and I was
inspired by zelinsky's calls for help
among others he was begging not just
governments but explicitly private
foreign citizens to to come help in any
way they could so I had the thought oh
maybe I could go try to help that light
bulb then became a more rigorous
analysis I I wrote it down and looked at
the pros and cons and that's where the
ease part kicked in right uh so I knew
that I could go to Poland and try to
help so it was in that sense somewhat
low stakes I I didn't need to know that
I'd be able to help or need to know what
the coming months held to try it out and
I figured if I failed to be helpful I'd
turn around visit my sister in France
where she lives and and come back and
call it a trip uh the third part right
the impact part was why I didn't turn
around and I stayed there and kept
working what was it like in those first
days because you are still working at
the energy initiative balancing that job
but then also I think what sitting in
lobbies of hotels kind of seeking out
opportunities you're exactly right I was
posting up in the cafe Lobby of my hotel
working my MIT job on my laptop and
hoping to overhere some of the hundreds
of volunteers and reporters who were
working out of the hotel and you know
surrounding the train station so I I
mentioned that I encountered thousands
of refugees I also encountered hundreds
of volunteers um some with pre-existing
NOS some not like myself one day I think
it was my second day there I overheard a
finish man interviewing with a reporter
about the aid work he had been doing you
know he he beat me by a couple days on
the first day of the invasion he was
working at Oracle in Finland in
logistics and he decided along with a
couple colleagues to drive a van down
full of bulletproof vests and
bulletproof helmets and the reporter was
asking him about that work so I
interrupted and we we verified
identities and then I asked if I could
uh maybe Shadow him uh and his
colleagues and he said absolutely and in
that shadowing uh quickly you know we
realized that I could help and began
doing so it started with helping uh
procure and fulfill delivery of some
observation drones that were going to
ke's Northern suburbs that week which at
the time were the front lines they were
under attack by that 40 mile Convoy of
Russian troops we kept on iterating and
growing and and I can say more about
that but that was the start and so since
then you've co-founded a nonprofit
called zeroline that's aiding ukrainians
on the front lines can you tell us about
zero line and the word that you're doing
yes zero line has a mission and a method
the mission is saving Ukrainian lives
and doing our small part to accelerate
the end of the war and our method is
helping ukrainians avoid Russian bombs
Russian Artillery is the number one
cause of Ukrainian deaths in this war
responsible for Approximately 80% of the
over 100,000 ukrainians who have been
killed since February 2022 we provide
that help partly through research so
through heavy Frontline research boots
on the ground interviews and
observations we try to identify
important gaps in government Aid and
government capacities and also homegrown
Ukrainian programs who are filling those
gaps but not getting the support they
deserve and then zeroline provides that
support injects private donations uh to
provide desperately needed uh equipment
and other Aid and also does what we call
partner coordination basically trying to
attract uh bigger more institutional
supporters for these really life saving
impactful programs we're the tiniest bit
like a venture capital firm or an
incubator in that there is this huge
need this Valley of Death Ukrainian
Civil Society is doing amazing work but
because of what Putin's doing because of
the industrial scale war crimes and
attacks the Ukrainian government can't
possibly do everything we have attracted
some in-kind donations from corporations
including a 300 large lithium battery
shipment from a finish company and some
others so that that Avenue is not a
closed door we absolutely want to engage
more companies maybe some more
technology focused ones maybe some
institutions like MIT honestly about
their uh used laptops right the aid that
zero provides we're a 501c3 right we're
not a military contractor so the the
physical items we're providing are
things like turn kits rugged laptops
communication equipment is a big Focus I
thought it was really gripping to read
about how you Quantified kind of Liv
save per dollar and so what you're
talking about is these things that you
need on the front line just $100 buys
for T gets $1,000 doll adds crude steel
armor to a Jeep it just really made an
impression big time big time yeah we try
to you know we try to make it concrete
both both in our analysis and in our
donor facing Communications right uh
people need and deserve to know how
their donations are actually going to
save lives what concretely they're going
to become yeah absolutely what has it
been like kind of living and working in
a combat zone it's a weird mix of uh
normal and New York City post 911 so I
lived in New York City when the Twin
Towers were struck and I'll never forget
being there and walking around the days
and weeks after everyone you know you
looked at the the feeling of having the
same thoughts was kind of insane and
intense and basically it it feels like
that every day in ke so yes millions of
people are going about their jobs but
almost all of them have a family member
on the front lines or in the m military
or who's been killed or wounded or who's
in Russian army occupied territory
living a nightmare or who was forced to
dig trenches for the Russian army you
know the majority of them are putting a
big chunk of the paychecks from those
jobs that they're walking to towards the
the defense so it's it's obviously very
different from from the normal that we
know in the US yeah I can't even imagine
it's incredible what you're doing so we
talked a little bit a moment ago about
energy and how it's you know kind of a
big theme in this war from Russia
cutting off energy supplies to Europe to
their targeting Ukraine's energy
infrastructure can you speak a little
bit more to this um from your
perspective as both an energy researcher
and as someone who's there in the thick
of it like you said this war is is
largely about energy energy was one of
the biggest factors that that caused the
War tragically and what I mean by that
is Putin invad
Crimea and the Eastern donbas in
2014 and the Free World and Germany's
government responded by increasing
energy imports from Russia Germany's
government was definitely hoping that
engaging with a
dictatorship was going to not only help
their own economy uh but also help that
dictatorship become less malevolent
and it's not a crazy idea many countries
including South Korea and Singapore and
others over decades after World War II
did go from more autocratic governments
to more democratic governments while
increasing trade with the Freer
world now it all ties back to Renewables
and nuclear as well because you know one
reason Germany was so desperate for
energy supplies and natural gas from
Russia was because they shut down their
nuclear power Fleet in the aftermath of
Fukushima it went from roughly 20% maybe
a little less of Germany's electricity
Supply to nearly zero and the the
replacement has to come from somewhere
and a lot of it has come from Renewables
growth but but not enough the last
energy component I would mention would
just go back to what we talked about a
little at the start
we're all about zero line's all about
filling these holes in in government
capacities so naturally we coordinate
with government and that includes
members of parliament who work in energy
including the chair of Ukraine's
parliament's energy committee these
people are really interested in
increased
Renewables not just for the
environmental benefits we talked about
before but for the resiliency
benefits well thank you so much for
telling us about that the work you're
doing in crane through Zer line is super
important and so I want to give you an
opportunity to tell any listeners who
might want to support your cause how
they can help donations to zerol line
really are like a turnkey way of saving
lives in Ukraine now there are other
ways of saving lives in Ukraine and
there are many good organizations but
for anyone listening if you're looking
for an effective way you don't have a
week to do research zero line is a very
effective way to help help Ukraine so
zerol line.org is our website it's fully
tax deductible if you care about that we
you know we're grateful for all the help
uh anyone can provide and we reciprocate
with operational updates that show
photos and media of the ways that your
donations become high impact Aid thank
you for sharing your story with us today
an thanks so much Kelly and to our
listeners thank you for joining I am
Kelly Travers and this is energy reads