thank you for introduction yeah Patrick
got sick so I'm replacing it but I can
do it well so my name is Hu I did my
master and PhD at MIT in mechanical
engineering and we spun out of MIT
around three years ago we are a
biomaterial based platform company uh
but today's problem we want to focus in
this event is a skin issue so skin is
the largest organ in the human body and
uh outermost barriers against many bad
things so therefore it experience a lots
of disease disas and conditions from
aema stasis to the scars and wounds and
sometimes chronic wounds if it is large
and a long-standing enough so our vision
is uh we are really want to make a kind
of synthetic extension of skin using our
Preparatory biomaterial thing that to
has a functional armor to protect
against those things those thing
including the dehydration pollution
infection UV and ederse mechanical
forces so it's basically we want to
replace something with a more neat and
nice and WAP around or bandages that is
out there already so our solution that
we have developed in MIT now we further
moved into the our company the more
commercial setup is a biod or sticky and
perceptible multi-functional armors
against all those aders factors we are
having a kit product with the patches
and a skin primers which is uh like a
moisturizer as well as a canic carrier
for therapeutic agents in it it is
adesive to the wet skin so it can be
actually applied on a whatever that
being applied on the skin it doesn't
need to be dry and clean it is soft and
elastic as the human skin and it's
transparent and it's having a physical
barrier as well as a mechanical
programmability so it actually can
contract in a programmed amount and
directions so how it works is we
developed this by inspired by some many
things including spider web glues and
you can see in this videos that is
really interesting in a way it looks
like a 3M tapes and dressings but it
actually can sticks to the skins that
are very wet or moisturized and it also
can contract in a desired directions and
amount is kind of programmable materials
so we have published in in a nice
journals because it's very interesting
Sciences but we are now looking into the
application of it because skin has a lot
of conditions uh this can be used in a
variety of different things including
the aema enclosur and scars and
chronicon and many of these application
we have done extensive preclinical
studies in academic and as well as
industrial setup after spinning out so
it is a large amount of opportunities
but one case that we really think it is
interesting is that we got approached by
uh the big cosmetic companies from South
Korea we did a contract R&D and it turns
out that our platform can actually
having an anti-aging applications by
having a mechanical modula ability uh by
adjusting a skin tension lines and all
those things you have anti- wrinkle
performances you know s ha per reduction
performances so we are trying to find
the way to commercialize in this
particular application with this partner
or some other partner in different
places but we also find out that this
can actually be really versatile
platform for various skin conditions and
diseases so what we are asking today is
essentially a partnership opportunities
uh we are a platform company that with
the many other programs but in
particular for this one we are looking
for both R&D level partnership for Coe
development into specific indications or
application area or also in commercial
state partnership such as licensing
mature product Supply we are both
looking for a potential Partners in know
medical such as Dermatology Advance
wound care area as well as consumer such
as Cosmetics we obviously interested in
a North American European market but
because especially for Cosmetics is very
big in Apec regions like China Korea
Japan we are also looking actively for
those areas as well so if you have any
question please ask us through either
either chat or in a breakout room thank
you thank you so much great great um so
um continuing on on that theme what um
where are you at as far as
commercialization and um the status of
santah Hill yeah so for this particular
platform we finished the R&D development
of the Technologies and we have a small
scale
manufacturability now we are at uh in
know finding a partner to actually
productizing this platform into specific
indications with the requirements and
specification and in parallel we are
working internally to make the
scalability of these manufacturing
processes because we understand that for
skin application generally volume and
the cost is a lot larger and the low
cost so that's where we are at and we
are the reason we are looking for
partner is many of these detailed
questions are quite geared to a specific
application areas that partner might be
interested fantastic and what is your
vision as you get these Partnerships
going where what's next yeah so because
we are more like R&D focused team and uh
because we have many different
applications we don't want to build
individual distribution and sales
channels and Etc so that's why we are
looking for a partnership for a product
development and also looking for a
specialized partner in specific intended
use cases that can take a chart take in
charge of the
commercialization uh instead of we are
been making a larg of distribution or
channels ourselves in various
applications okay fantastic thanks