Okay, congrats on turning in paper
number two. For those of you who've
turned in paper number two, and for
those who are wrapping things up, uh,
good luck. Um, your next assignment is
very, very open-ended. paper three, you
just get to pick what you want to do.
Um, if there's kind of the only
restriction on it is like you can't turn
in like this assignment in another
class, like you can't like the same
paper in two classes, but other than
that, there are very very few guidelines
on what you could do. I am particularly
enthusiastic about anyone who picks an
assignment that is connected to things
they're already working on. Um, so like
you know Kent should totally do
something about Mccclea. Like he what I
don't I don't know what that is but he
like probably no one has ever asked him
like you know write eight or 10 pages
about what it is you're trying to do
there or do some more research that
helps inform what you're doing or design
your next steps or whatever it is. But
that would be a great project for Kent.
Um and even if Kent is like even if it's
your is to like build Mccclea or
whatever it's totally fine to have
something that's very adjacent to that.
Um, I've had doctoral students who part
of their who like did part of the
literature review that they have to do
like for writing a chapter of their
dissertation or something that was
great. Um, so if there so any of I mean
you can also pick something that is
completely unrelated to what you're
working on just a thing that you're
interested in exploring further. Um,
anything is is fine. Um, but part of the
assignment is figuring out what it is
that you want to do. Okay. Um what we
want to try to do then today is talk
about um two of these as yet intractable
dilemmas that you've read about. So in
the first half of the book and in the
course we talked about these three
genres of learning and scale tried to
emphasize to you that these genres have
predictable characteristics. they have
semi-predictable impacts in school
settings. Um that uh and that their
impacts are almost never transformative.
They have the potential to be useful. Um
and to some extent there's a kind of
like ongoing disappointment. Um, you
know, think of all of the amazing things
that we've developed from radio, film
strips, television,
um, videos, personal computers, the
internet, instructional tutors, online
communities, all these different things.
And like none of them have really like
blown the walls off school. Like school
is still kind of school. Um, and in a
lot of cases like doesn't educate people
as well as we want to. So what like what
are some of the reasons why these
technologies don't have the
transformative impacts that we keep
hoping that they will? Um and that that
the four as yet intractable dilemmas the
the goal of this part of the book is to
say we know a bunch about why they don't
do all the things we want them to do.
Like we know some of the um challenges
that occur across these different
genres. Um, so you know, a thing like
Scratch, a MOO, an instructional tutor,
Khan Academy, there's a whole they they
might be really different in some
dimensions, but a lot of times they
still stumble across these same
problems. Um, some of this is me writing
like making an argument to the field.
Hey, if we if we want to do better in
the future, we're going to have to
figure out how we deal with these four
things. We're going to have to
understand these problems and how they
operate, and then we're going to have to
do better with them. Um, so today we'll
talk about the curse of the familiar and
the edtech Matthew effect and then we'll
talk about the trap of routine
assessment and the toxic power of data
and experiments. Um, why don't I give
you a minute to chat amongst yourselves.
Um, this was from a couple weeks ago,
but turn to the person next to you. talk
to this person about like what you
remember of what the curse of the
familiar is, why it would be a problem,
what kinds of things get stuck in the
curse of the familiar, and what kinds of
strategies seem to exist that might help
us get past that. Um, turn to the person
next to you and just externalize what
you remember about all this. Ready, go.
All right, come on back.
who want what what are what are some
what are some what are some things you
discussed that seemed core to the
definition if you were to quickly
summarize the curse of the familiar what
are some key ideas
like the idea of taking an old idea and
kind of repackaging it so that it
appears to be something new but really
isn't like I think we talked about the
idea of Quizlet versus flashcards it's
basically the same technological premise
but you're just digitizing it and and
What's the virtue of doing that?
I guess people will think it's new and
maybe won't be excited by that, but
there's no real change. Good. What do
people want to add to just that
particular idea?
I was going to say like it kind of stems
from this idea that um these new like
inventors um just have a lack of
knowledge of like what's come before
them. Um and like that's kind of like
where it can stem from. That can be a
problem. Yeah. Sabrina, what were you
going to say? And then Gloria, I was
going to say how they take like these
new technologies and instead of um
revolutionizing them, they just bend it
so that it fits the um how old
institutions still continues to be. I
like I like that we we take things and
we make them fit in existing
institutions. Yeah. I say that like
education and learning is very risk
averse. So people don't want their kids
or like to be the ones experimented on.
So when things are repackaged, it's
still like, oh, we know this works
because it's been done before, but it's
still new. Good. All right. So, I'm I'm
sensing a which might be appropriate
like a little bit of a negative vibe on
the on the people who are doing these
kinds of things. But if we wanted to
celebrate um folks who take technologies
that digitize existing practices, like
what's the virtue of that approach?
What's good about it?
I can carry like a million flash cards
in my pocket. Yeah. Yeah. Good. And
everyone knows what to do with them.
Like Quizlet has Quizlet might be the
most widely adopted piece of education
technology software used in American
secondary schools. That's awesome. Um
Zillian like if you want the thing that
people will use you there's some good
evidence that you have to give them
something they're familiar with. And
also like mentioned that you can have a
million different flash cards in your
pocket but you can also have a million
different flash cards from other people
like sharing ideas globally. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. So we can we can take this idea of
a flash card and we can like tweak a
little bit. We can do some of the things
that digital technologies are good at.
We can make it scaled. We can make it
shared. We make all this kind of stuff
though, you know, with always running
into the hard limitation of like how
much can you improve schooling by
improving flash cards like like flash
cards are like I mean the joke I tell
often is if like if you got all of the
world's experts together and we're like
what does education really need? Like
what do we really need to go to the next
level? No one would raise their hand and
be like, "There's a huge der of flash
cards." Like, "We need to dramatically
include improve flash card technology."
Like, there's plenty of index cards.
There's like there's plenty of pencils.
You know, flash cards are like it's not
an obvious thing to revolutionize. Um,
also you like like I mean, I think if
you talk to Andrew, he wouldn't be he
wouldn't tell you this was a thing to
revolutionize education. It's like this
was just like a useful thing for me to
study French that other people found
useful and that I could sell. Um and uh
you know but so so a hu you know the I
mean these kinds of technologies are
like the the sort of square boxes like
it fits in the school. That's a virtue
like we can like we can only benefit
from technologies that fit in our
institutions. Our institutions are
riskaverse and they're conservative and
they have a bunch of constraints. Um
yeah Mari I think one point also that
the chapter made is that It's just a
phase where people use it in way they're
familiar with and then after a while
they're able to use it in more like
revolutionary ways. So the benefit of
having something that they already know
how it works is that they can use it
long enough to get to that point where
they might feel comfortable using it in
a way that haven't been used before.
Great. That is that is one of the two
ideas that I've proposed with sort of
not great research evidence behind them
that might be a way of getting past the
curse of the familiar that you introduce
things in schools that have a kind of
familiar structure to them but open them
up in ways that go somewhere else. I
don't think there's a lot of evidence
that Quizlet has been able to do that.
Like Quizlet gives you flashcards.
Actually, I just took a screenshot of
their website right now. Um Quizlet is
more than flashards. Like if you have to
say that you're more than flash cards,
you're probably just flash cards like
you know your sort of sort of special
pleading there. Um all right, you all
have
described this part of the curse of the
familiar. What would be some key ideas
of the sort of flip side of the curse of
the familiar? Um what are the challenges
you run into if you make something
that's really new and novel?
I feel like just going back to what was
said earlier, like people don't want
their kids to be experimented on. Like
when something's new, it's not proven to
be successful yet. Um, and it's
obviously replacing something else that
maybe isn't the most successful, but in
some case it's there because it is
teaching someone something. Um, so
there's this idea that if you introduce
something new, you have no evidence to
back up whether or not it will actually
be beneficial. Good. So people are
riskaverse. you use the phrase was like
we know this thing in schools teaches
someone something. Um there might even
be sort of a lower threshold of
acceptability which is something like we
know this thing works in schools like
sometimes a thing works in schools
because people learn something.
Sometimes it works in schools because
like kids are quiet and well behaved and
busy and other things like that. like
not even really learning just you know
just like like like you know if you've
kept a bunch of adolescent like if
you've kept hundreds of adolescents in a
building safe and for a day like you've
kind of made school work um in at the
you know at at sort of the one of the
baseline levels of it. So there's
practices that we would consider sort of
sort of baseline not because they teach
but because they work to do the other
things that we ask schools to do. Um
yeah, Mari I think we also talked a
little bit about fear which I think it's
part of the risk averse aspect not only
from families but the student themselves
the professor the teachers as well um
and it was also an aspect I don't know I
would put it as credibility u because
even students if something is too
different they're going to feel like oh
this is not serious enough like I would
rather just have a lecture because this
is something I've seen being done before
so they don't and and you and you know
how to do it you know how to There's a
bunch of people who go into school that
are that sort of are like look there's a
deal here like you tell me to do things
that I know how to do and I will do
those things. Um you know sometimes in
lower performing schools that can be
expressed as like give me a set of tasks
that I understand how to do and like the
day will be quiet and function. um uh or
in in high performing schools it can be
something like give me a set of tasks
that I know how to get an A on I won't
have my parents call you um and and sort
of cause difficulties and things like
that but it's the same kind of deal um
new routines break up that arrangement
um and students can be some of the most
conservative stakeholders in these
systems you know people can come in
being like look at this new awesome
thing we might have us try and they'll
be like I don't know how to get I don't
know how to get an A doing that. Why
don't we go back to the thing that I
know how to get an A doing? What was the
um there were early on in the days of
MOOs, there were like a handful of
people that were trying different things
and there would always be learners that
would show up in these like, you know,
somewhat novel enterprise being like
this isn't real learning. This isn't
serious learning. Why don't we get back
to what we were supposed to be? It's
like my guy, it's optional. Like no one
is making you be here. Like go, you
know, um like if you want something
else, you know, there's zillions of
these courses being developed. There's I
think there's something in that um in uh
in the chapter on muks about that. Yeah,
I think teachers could also get
overwhelmed by introducing entirely new
novel idea
especially if that novel idea like what
if you have to change the curriculum?
What if you have to change the schedule?
What if you have to change your grading
arrangements? like a new technology
cannot like if it's actually changing
the way teaching happens, it's probably
trying to simultaneously change a whole
bunch of things that are going on. Um,
which can be like which can be
stressful, which can be difficult. Um,
so a lot of teachers have to prepare
students for a certain exam at the end
of the school year, whether it's like
the standardized assessments or AP
exams, and they can't really afford to
like go off trail. um and they need to
like stick with what they know because
they that's what gets the results which
which means that different parts of
school systems have different amounts of
flexibility to try really new things.
Like one of the fun things about being a
history teacher in Massachusetts is that
until this year when we just launched an
eighth grade civics assessment, there
was no standardized assessment, you
know, and I mean there has been some
like SAT2s in history, AP US history and
things like that, but they're usually
not like the centerpiece of people's
efforts. And so history, social studies,
electives for seniors off um and then
anything in the sort of co-curricular
domains, theater, arts, dance, physical
education, like a lot of times those are
places where you can do really different
kinds of things. Um the mathematics
sequence is often a place where you're
like, "Oh boy, like this really better
work." Um not only that, you know, not
only because people need to do well in
math, but like if you don't get eighth
grade math, nth grade math is really
hard. you know, if you like if you don't
get earth science, you might still be
okay in physics or something like that
because they're just sort of
sufficiently different and so forth. So,
the stakes in different parts of schools
are different. Um there's a there's an
old saw in any kind of education
development that um the elementary
school curriculum is pretty locked.
There's just some reading and math and a
handful of other things people need to
do. The high school curriculum is pretty
locked because these tracks and exams
and things like that. And middle school
is maybe the most open-ended space. So
quite a few new products for education
will find themselves in middle schools.
Not because like you know 12-year-olds
are a particularly great group to
embrace new ideas or something like
that. It's just like that curriculum is
more flexible in some ways than others
are.
Um so that we have this example of
Quizlet. You know, I feel like um uh the
the connectivist mukes that we talked
about before are sort of the
quintessential example of like here's
some really cool ideas, some really cool
technologies, potentially very different
solving some very meaningful problems
that that higher education had not
figured out good ways of solving and you
know were essentially rejected by the
higher education system. a sort of spark
of interest for a little while and then
people are like this is weird, this is
different, what we're doing is fine. Um,
and all this stuff kind of
died. So the question then is are there
strategies that would get you past the
curse of the familiar? Are there things
that you could do in developing products
and services that would let you use
technology to do really different kinds
of teaching and learning? Um, and I
think there are two strategies that have
some evidence behind them that they
might work. One of them Mario alluded to
before, which is build a technology that
starts somewhere familiar and goes to a
different place somehow. Um, like you
enter it and you're like, I know what
that is. And then you're like, whoa, I
could do these other kinds of things,
too. Um, the second sort of crucial idea
is something around cultivating
professional communities. The easy part
of scaling online technologies is like
getting people to download stuff. It
like it's not that difficult to get an
app on people's machines on schools
machines. It's not that difficult to
get, you know, millions of YouTube views
or other kinds of things like that.
What's really hard is not scaling
technology, but scaling community. How
do you get groups of educators to share
the ideas for new practices with other
people? But there are a couple of
organizations um that have done a a
demonstrabably good job of not only
scaling their product but scaling the
ideas, the pedagogies, the new ideas
underneath that. So um the two I like to
talk about are Scratch and Desmos. Um
they've probably made the most progress
on this.
Scratch maybe has never achieved like a
familiar place to start, but they have
thought a lot about entry points about
how you get people in for a while. You
know, Seymour Papard had this famous
line that you want technologies with low
floors and high ceilings. Yousef
referred to it a few times ago. You want
something that like is pretty easy to
get people into um and also things that
they can really do awesome stuff later
on. Um uh sometimes the Scratch people
have also talked about narrow entryways.
You want people to kind of get into the
software, like get into the platform,
have some more clear ideas about what to
do with a few things and then go other
places. Um for a while, uh Scratch was
experimenting with these micro worlds
where you would get a smaller set of
blocks, a smaller set of sprites, and
they would be connected to some um to
what they thought young people would be
interested in. So I think there was a
standup comedy micro world. There was a
fashion micro world. There was a dance
micro world. And it was like don't learn
everything about Scratch. Like just
learn enough to make there be a little
standup comedy routine or to make there
be a little dance or things like that.
So you have, you know, a set of sprites
that are relevant to that. You have a
set of blocks that are relevant to that.
And once you learn that smaller part, go
into more complex things. Um, a thing
that I think Scratch has done a very
good job of is scaling community. is
basically saying, you know, is
acknowledging that if educators just
download Scratch into their machines,
that is not enough to get over the curse
of the familiar. Like they know exactly
what happens when people who don't sort
of understand the pedagogy of Scratch
download Scratch. And you heard Yousef
talking about it, they just turn it into
like a recipe book. So instead of having
it be this place for computational
creativity, you see all the students in
lockep, you know, all building the same
greeting card or all building the same
roller coaster or whatever it is. Um, so
they have, you know, all kinds of
programs that are developed for
educators. They have a world scratch day
where people get together. They have
Scratch educator meetups. They had for a
while minutes with Mitch, um, which were
Mitch Resnik like giving short talks
about ideas and things and Natalie's
notes. They have other kinds of projects
and tools and things like that. Um, a
big part of them is meant to get Scratch
educators connected with each other. Um
if you and a few studies have done this.
If you interview teachers about how they
adopt new pedagogies, the number one
answer they will give you is from other
teachers. Um the main reason why a
teacher is willing to try a new practice
is because they see uh that practice
working in somebody else's classroom.
Ideally someone who teaches in a place
like them, in a grade like them, in a
subject like them that's near them. Um
what that means is that any of these
kinds of curriculum change, technology
change problems are really peer learning
problems. You have to figure out how do
you get teachers to share with one
another. That is just immensely more
complicated um than it is in to to get
software to be disseminated widely. Um
it's particularly difficult in most
places in the world in education
definitely in the United States in
education because there are there are
weak professional that like the
professional organization level of
education is really weak. Um if you were
like man I want all of the emergency
room doctors to do something different
and better you'd be like oh let's go to
whatever it's called the American
Academy of Emergency Physicians or
something like that. If you wanted all
the pediatricians to do something
different, you'd go to the American
Academy of Pediatricians and you would
convince some senior steering committee
of the American Academy of Pediatricians
that we're going to do this new practice
and they would be like, "Yes, this is a
good practice. Let's all do that." And
then that group has a journal pediatrics
and all the pediatricians read it and
you can and you can get people even
though there are, you know, thousands
and thousands of pediatricians in the
country, you can get them to be like,
"Okay, this is a new and better idea."
education does not have that
professional organization level. There's
there's no authoritative body that says
this is a good way to teach second
graders or this is a good way to teach
math or reading. Like we you know um we
have teachers unions which organize
teachers in a bunch of places in the US
but they and they sometimes have a
professional learning role but usually
not this kind of authoritative one. Um
sometime they're organizations like the
National Council of Teachers of
Mathematics or the National Councils of
Teachers of English and they sort of
have some things that are like this but
they're they're very weak compared to
other professions and other kinds of
things.
Um, how many of you use Desmos in
schools? So, we're just Okay, a lot more
now. This is way more than you would
have said five or six years ago. Um,
Desmos was originally developed as a
graphing calculator. Like its earliest
functions were just we're going to um
make a TI84 available on every machine
for free. Um and one of the brilliant
things they did was they got um instead
of consumers to pay for it, they got
testing companies and publishers to pay
for it. Um and what that meant was is
that I mean that was the way they could
make a high-quality project available
for free without ads, without
subscriptions, without um um costs to
the education system. And of course, you
know, for anybody who's used a TI84
before, you look at something like this
and you're like, "Yeah, I know what to
do there." Like, I'm going to start
teaching in equations and it's going to
start graphing them for me. Um, and you,
you know, I mean, for those of you who
grew up in affluent environments, like
replacing a TI84 might not be a big
deal. Um, but there are lots of
households and lots of families where
like an $80 cost, $120 cost, a big deal.
Um, like a real obstacle to kids
education schools, you know, where they
just have like TI84s in boxes and they
hand them out at the beginning of class
and put them back in the box at the end
of class and things like that. Um, but
you could give just this to lots of math
teachers and lots of students and they
would be like,"Great, I totally know
what to do with this." Um, and then on
top of that, there was all kinds of
other crazy things that you could do
with Desmos. You know, one of the things
they do every year is have an art, maybe
they still don't do it, but for a while
they would have art competitions, um,
where you have people who create
drawings using graphs and things like
that. I don't know what what were what
were the kinds of things that you did
with Desmos that were very different
from a graphing calculator in in for
those of you who raised your
hands. I think this is something you
could do on a graphing calculator, but
that was made so much easier was just
like um seeing just like different
versions of the same graph like
simultaneously or being able to like
slide the coefficients and the
variables. Yep. And so um modeling is a
term that a lot of math teachers might
use to describe that like you can look
at the same equation you know across a
range of parameters and things like
that. It was a sometimes we had like uh
TI was it
TI3 um so it was easy it's a lot easier
to input stuff into decimals when
compared to like traditional
calculators. Yeah. So some of it it just
made some efficiency gains like they
just figured out some ways of doing some
mathematical inputs that are like a
little bit easier if you learn them on a
keyboard than on you know a number pad
like finding intersections of uh two
polomials you just click on it as
opposed to like let's go through the
directions of how to find it on your
graphing calculator go left go right go
like it just like it's so much less
bandwidth and just to add on to that I
think I heard somewhere I don't remember
when but some technologies like chatb
are like extremely bad for beginners
because it distracts them. In this case,
I I literally made this analogy the
other day. Um I think it was just
yesterday. I was talking to some
somebody about this class and I said a
calculator sometimes if you don't know
how to use it, it'll be more distracting
and helpful to you. And for some people,
Desmos was easier in my classrooms than
a traditional graph. Yeah. get that if
you you sort of lower the barrier to to
like learning the interface like
learning the interface is not useful to
anyone. What's useful is doing math and
if you if the barrier to learning the
interface is high then you're spending a
bunch of your math time not doing math.
You're doing like you know user
interface on you know 1980s era
calculators. Um I mean yeah the
calculator calculators are a remarkable
piece of technology. They they cost like
50 cents to make or something like that
and they sell them for $100 because they
have a bunch because they have a like
regulatory lock in um because you know
they you get the testing companies to
agree to mandate them and then the
curriculum companies have to mandate
them and then Texas Instruments can
charge a hundred bucks. Um for something
that should be a lot less. Um all right.
So, what are some things that Desmos did
to try to get folks um excited about
some of the other capacities in
um in in Desmos um is in addition to
promoting the technology of Desmos um
their leadership promoted alternative
approaches to teaching mathematics. Um
so Dan Meyer who was the chief academic
officer of Desmos um he did a bunch of
teaching um in low-inccome schools and
in schools with a bunch of kids who
would have been pretty turned off to
math. Um thought a lot about like what
kinds of pedagogies really engaged
students and came up with this um
framework he called threeact math. Um it
was very mediabased. So um he would take
a picture of himself shooting a
basketball. Um, so you'd watch a video
of him shooting a free throw and about
halfway through the shot he would stop
it. Um, and that's all the video that
you would see. Actually, I'll give you
my favorite example of it. Like, do you
do you remember in geometry you are
always encountering like hexagonal fish
tanks and things like that? You're
always encountering like these shapes
that like would never exist. So, he like
found a hexagonal fish tank um and gets
a hose and holds the hose on top of the
fish tank and just makes a video of 30
seconds of just water filling up. Um and
usually when he shows this video at some
point some kid is like, "How long is
this going to take?" And he goes,
"Exactly." Um and then you sort of stop
the video there. Um but it kind of, you
know, these videos inspire like a
natural curiosity. How long does it take
the fish tank to fill up? Like will the
basketball go in? Um, and then what he
does, that's the first act, is sort of
setting up some kind of problem. The
second act is trying to figure out
what's going on in the setting. So,
students have a chance to ask a bunch of
questions. Um, how far away was this
person from the basket? How high is the
basket? How fast is the ball moving?
What is the ark? How big is the fish
tank? How wide is the fish tank? How
tall is the fish tank? What is the angle
on each side of the fish tank? How much
how wide is the hose? How much water is
coming out of the hose? All these kinds
of things. Um, some of some of these
details Dan or other teachers will give
to their students and some they won't.
Um, and then they sort of agree on a
question or the teacher kind of imposes
a question. Okay, the question is going
to be how long is this going to take to
fill up? And I'm going to give you these
pieces of information. Um, now because
it's a realworld environment, it's like
it's actually kind of mathematically
impossible to determine the exact answer
to these questions. um you know like the
the amount of water that's flowing
through the hose through a municipal
water system is not like a completely
predictable amount that's coming out
every time. Um you know he'll give some
measurements of the tank but the like
the tank probably wasn't measured to the
hundth of a millimeter or something like
that. Um so students start creating
models. Um they say all right well I
think it's going to be this you know
here's what I know and and sometimes
there's a little instruction there like
oh so to figure this out you're going to
have to calculate the area of a
hexagonal solid. Okay. um here is the
formula that you need to do that and
here's why it work and then you sort of
figure out these other things. So then
the third act um is Dan will show the
video again um and the water will be
pouring into the tank and the water will
be filling up. Usually he sort of
accelerates it so it goes a little bit
faster and he puts a clock in the corner
of the video. Now all of the students
have made some kind of prediction about
when they think the tank will fill up
but it's pretty much impossible to
predict exactly. Um, and he's got great
videos of kids watching these sort of
third act videos where you sort of see
like
h like their time they predict to go off
and then at some point in the middle
middle of the video like you know a
third of the class cheers. Yeah. Because
their time was like roughly right or
something like that. And it's just a
sort of great moment to be like like
typically when you get an answer right
in math class you don't like stand up
and cheer and stuff like that. Um but uh
you know there's a there's a few key
features of the pedagogy. First of all,
um, one things he talks about is it
dials up the math slowly. Um, so an
exercise like this starts at a level of
intuition and questioning that even if
you don't really understand polomial
functions or you know complex geometry
of solids, well, you can still ask basic
questions about it. You can still make
observations about what's important. And
then you sort of ratchet the mathematics
up slowly until you get to the point
where you're like working with
particular equations and functions and
numbers and those kinds of things. um
and that it's impossible to be right.
Like everyone in the room is just trying
to be the least wrong that they can um
and making a series of assumptions which
are which you know hopefully get more
and more reasonable as kids get more and
more proficient mathematically um but
will never be perfect. So um Desmos is a
to you know hopefully you can see how a
tool like the slider that Osel described
before might be quite useful in building
mathematical models of how long it takes
to fill up a tank with a hose and other
kinds of things like that. Um Dan Meyer
has given talks at math conferences in
all 50 states. Um he goes around to
places all the time. Not only Probably
even more important than Dan going to
all 50 states to give talks is you can
still go to math
conference in all 50 states and someone
will be giving a presentation on
three-act math tasks. Um because not
just Dan but other mathematics educators
have taken up the mantle of these ideas.
um probably in those talks they'll
explain how you can use Desmos for doing
these things. And so all of a sudden you
have not just a new technology to do
math, but you have a whole community of
people that are sharing new practices of
how to do it. Just like in Scratch has a
whole community of people who are trying
to say let's not just teach computer
programming as puzzle solving, let's
teach it as computational creativity and
things like that. I I want to emphasize
to you like I mean these are like
powerful powerful strategies for
changing teaching and learning and
they're super hard and time consuming
and energy consuming. They require
charismatic leaders. They require really
good ideas. They require technologies
that sort of fit with pedagogy. They
require convincing educators. You know
these riskaverse educators who you
described who are preparing their
students for math tests like here's a
better way of doing this. you know, nuke
a part of your geometry solids units and
try this new thing. So, there's a whole
lot that goes into it, but those I think
are sort of the two key strategies um
for for how we might get past the curse
of the familiar. Um start with the
familiar then go new places and think
about not just scaling technology but
scaling community, cultivating
professional communities. What
observations or thoughts or questions do
you have about those ideas?
Yeah, one more. Sort of like a spoiler
to my essay, but I I did I did mention
that um I'll be as vague as possible.
The target the target um that I was
recommending my technology to actually
had the infrastructure
implemented like five years before COVID
and they started doing a lot of
professional teaching within the entire
district. And so by the time CO came
around, they were ready for um distance
learning without necessarily preparing
for that. Um and they just happened to
have like the resources necessary
because everybody was involved. And I
remember like there would be teachers
like having separate meetings just to
talk about like what went well, what
didn't go well. Um, and then they like I
was one of the volunteers during the the
last accreditation self-study and I was
in there like listening to sort of what
happened during the pandemic like this
was
um at the end of like co um and then
they were recruiting for that self-study
but I was able to listen in on that and
it was really cool to see like the
community that built up. Yeah, it it is
it is impossible to change teaching
practice in schools without communities
of educators teaching and learning with
one another. Like every instructional
improvement problem in a school is in
some dimension a peer learning problem.
Um and you you know you could imagine
like how many education technology
startups have as one of their first five
hires someone who's really good at
facilitating peer learning amongst
educators. Like no one, right? like you
need someone who can like like you need
a front-end person and a backend person
and someone who knows pedagogy and a
marketing guy or finance guy or lady or
something like that like you're just
like there's just organizations that are
not intuitively equipped um for those
kinds of things you know when Andy is
starting Quizlet I mean he's a high
school he doesn't know anything he just
like knows how to like make flashc cards
online um and part of what their
organization needed to build over time
was was you know people who could
interface with schools not just to sell
to schools but to help help them think
about like what could different look
like here? What you know where do we fit
into practice? How do we train teachers
or have students become better at using
these things? Um I feel like um this
whole like talk is about how like
difficult this can be and like even with
these two ideas that you've brought up
like this still requires like a lot of
people buy in and just like other people
supporting it. makes me think like about
how difficult this can be for schools
that like aren't out of public schools
and like even like you have your charter
schools that then have their own set of
curricula and if you're trying to really
gain this type of support nationwide if
you have like this whole subset of
schools that are like avoiding your
technology like it can make things
really hard. Um, like thinking about
like like because I had written my paper
to like my high school which was like
like a Catholic high school in
Philadelphia and like those schools
don't do anything to try and improve
schools cuz like they are just
struggling to like keep kids in the
schools. Yeah. So like thinking about
trying to like improve a system that
like can't even look that far. is like
really interesting too of like those
teachers don't have time to like
cultivate that professional community
because they're just trying to cultivate
like a school community or I mean almost
every school has a certain amount of
time to do professional learning amongst
faculty like that's baked into most
schools but you have like there's only
one block of that um that is the that is
what you'll use to improve your
assessment practices to address chronic
absenteeism to deal with violence in
schools to take on a new state
initiative about sex education to do,
you know, a dozen different things that
might come along. Um, you know, I mean,
Omar described a school that 5 years
before co happened to decide that like
online learning, distance learning was
like a good thing for them to work on,
but it might have been equally
reasonable for them to work on phonics
instruction or executive functioning or
any one of a dozen other things that
helps improve schools. Um so yeah think
you know thinking about like what are
the what are the resources that
institutions have to make themselves
better and to make the kinds of changes
that are needed for new practices to
work. Um
we talked a lot about like cultivating
professional communities. Do you think
that the professional communities so
with teachers for example cultivating
that is enough or do we also need to
cultivate like the students communities
as well because I was surprised when
reading the chapter that students
themselves sometimes are also kind of
like afraid or concerned about using
this new technology. Yeah. I so I de I
mean it's exciting to hear like what
Omar talked about about bringing
students in on these kinds of change
initiatives. It would be you know
there's almost every edtech company has
some kind of ambassador program which is
hiring a group of teachers to be like
the folks who go to these conferences
and share what they're doing with other
people. I don't know of any technology
company that has a student ambassador
program. Um they're I mean they're you
know one reason is that the like the
teachers stay and the students leave
which is good. That's what the students
are supposed to do. Um like you probably
have to be a certain age to be kind of
useful doing like like a first grade
ambassador would probably do some
interesting things but like is not that
helpful for um for what they can
accomplish. Um but I you know but I do
think that generally
speaking school systems change agents
tend to underestimate students as
potential partners. Um because when you
you know when you get them really
engaged they can be they can be
transformative in institutions when
students get together and be like oh we
should do this sometimes that's when
faculty light bulbs go off and go yeah
you're interested in that like
absolutely like let's do it. I'm I'm
asking because I met a like this girl
she's doing her masters at um the
graduate school of education in Harvard
and in Brazil a few years back she was
supposed to start like giving an
entrepreneurship course to like middle
schoolers. She wanted to use Figma like
to do it very interactive you know
experiential and professor like teachers
were completely closed off to the idea
and then she simply bypassed them and
started reaching out to students and
they loved it and it worked so well that
like the excitement from the students
convinced teachers themselves to
actually give it a go because like if
there's one thing they have in common is
they're really concerned and like they
care about students, right? So she ended
up even giving like a TED talk about how
she believes this whole like
transformation is going to come from
students. Yep. Uh so that's why I was
interested in like you know we do that
less than we could. Yeah. the the exact
nature of the technology matters too.
The more the technology the more like
the business model of the technology has
some kind of like premium or
introduction kind of model like I don't
know if you wanted to implement
something like with robotics in a school
and the robotics kits are expensive.
It's pretty hard to be like hey kids
like go get your own robotics kits and
we'll like go around the system like
somebody needs to buy the robotics kits.
Um, you know, part of what makes like
the example you gave of Figma works is
that Figma has a kind of built-in
premium model as a consumer product that
educators can sort of piggy back on to
to try those things out. But yeah, I
mean, I would say anybody who has a
change strategy in schools, if your
students are part of that change
strategy, it's pretty likely to be
better than if they're not. Um, yeah,
related to that, I know that Wolfford
Technologies, which created Mathematica,
has a student ambassador program that I
did in high school. So you like present
at their conference and like I don't
know talk about it to all your friends
and host webinars and things. So yeah
that's one example of that. No that's I
I had I had not known that but that's a
that's you know and and again like yeah
Wolf's in a pretty competitive space
where of of different kinds of
mathematics software where where
absolutely cultivating student
preferences could totally make a
difference. Um, all right. Let's talk
about another
um uh let's let's do another one of
these challenges since I'm trying to
double up this week. Um, which is the
edtech Matthew effect.
Um, which is really supposed to be here
somewhere. Ah, this is what I used. Um,
okay.
Um, here
are here's sort of three variants
of of mythologies that people have about
technology in schools. Um, one is that
edtech will destroy the system. We've
talked about how that probably won't
happen. Um, and instead um, new
technologies domesticate education.
Actually, that article that Yousef
shared um, I thought it was Mimi and I
who came up with this metaphor,
particularly Mimi. Um, but that article
that uh, Yousef shared of Seymour Papert
responding to Taek and Cuban had a very
similar kind of framing of what schools
do. I don't think I don't know if they
exactly use the word domesticate, but
it's pretty close. Um, like new
technologies don't come in and blow up
schools. Um, instead schools take new
technologies and go, "Okay, you fit
here." Um, people are always hoping that
new technologies, a word they really
like is democratizing. Um, I think
people like the word democratizing
because you're not exactly sure what it
means, but it sounds pretty good. Like,
it would be better to have more
democracy, but it's like, is that
cheaper? Is that more equal? Is that
more just? Is that better? Um, I'll show
you in a bit. We really have pretty good
evidence that new technologies
disproportionately benefit the
advantage. They disproportionately
benefit people with the financial,
social, and technical capital to take
advantage of new innovations. So, people
are always hoping like, oh, this new
thing, it'll be distributed for free on
the internet. like the people who are
good at finding free stuff on the
internet are affluent people with good
internet access with discretionary
leisure time with parents who went to
college all of those kinds of things. um
uh and and you know so so this is a
figure that I that I used to describe
the edtech matthew effect about to say
it again um that in educational systems
especially highly unequ unequal ones
like the United States we assume that
folks from higher socioeconomic
backgrounds have better educational
outcomes you know generically than from
than folks from low socioeconomic
outcomes and the hope is that through
technology innovation like everyone will
learn but maybe we can build things that
particularly help this group. This this
is when people talk about democratizing
education this is basically like a graph
of what they mean. Um what actually
happens though is probably something
like this. Um which is that new
innovations disproportionately benefit
people who are already affluent. And
they you know a thing which is sort of
tricky about this is they probably help
everyone. Um there are not a lot of
education technologies that we build
that like really make things worse.
Maybe there are um but typically they
just help advantaged people more than
they help um disadvantaged folks. Here's
some um so so when we studied massive
open online courses the the
democratizing rhetoric was very active.
Um Udacity for a while like their
tagline was democratizing education or
something like that. That's pretty
unlikely to happen I think. So for
instance, so so we did these kind of
cool studies where um all these studies
were based on the fact that when edex
was founded and you had to register for
it, someone was like, "Let's get
people's addresses." So they would just
people would type free form their
addresses into edex. Why did anyone
collect their addresses? Like I've never
learned like were they going to mail
them something? I don't know. But we had
their addresses.
Um, uh, through the magic of residential
segregation, if you know someone's
address, you can make a pretty good
guess about how affluent they are, what
their education level is, or something
like that. Um, there are these units
that are called census block tracks,
which are something like the 1,200 homes
that are nearest yours. Um, and wherever
you live, like like the average median
income of your of the,200 homes around
you is like pretty close to your and we
might not be exactly right, but if you
do it over hundreds of thousands of
people, it works out pretty well. Um, so
this is a graph of people's average
median income at different ages. Um,
this is all of the people in the United
States and these are the people who sign
up for Harvard X and MITx. Um so for
sure there were people from every
possible income bracket that you
imagined who had signed up for Harvard
MITx courses. Um but at every age level
they were you know a typical Harvard X
or MITx participant is going to be
wealthier than a typical US residents.
Um this is a I for this is a kind of
study called a case control study and it
comes from epidemiology
um where you're comparing a particular
group to a whole population and it's
usually used for like people who get
viruses. So for folks who hated muks um
we were basically treating like MOO
participants as if they had a virus and
they thought that was pretty funny. Um
this is the amount of education that
their uh parents had. Um, and so clearly
the people who sign up for Harvard X and
Edex are more educated than the typical
population. What was the question you
asked? I was just saying I love how
there's someone who's under 20 with over
$90,000 in medium in their household in
their in their in the income of the
census block tract. Okay. So it's not an
individual. Yeah. Yeah. It's not like
it's not like they're a bunch of loaded
16y olds who are taking our courses. No,
but if you were 15 or 16 or 17 and you
were taking a Harvard X class, it was
very likely um that you were you were
much more likely to be from a census
block track with a much higher average
median income um than comparable um
Yeah. Yeah. you I mean you could also
figure like people leave like like it's
not that people become poorer they like
move to crummy college neighborhoods you
know and then their livelihood improves
over time until they get old. Um like
the subtitle the long boring subtitle.
It did have a long boring subtitle. It
meant something. Um what was this? This
was the odds ratio um of
uh these were these were the odds that
you
um were
um oh if you're if you had a parent who
graduated from college um this was the
odds that you were more likely to
complete a class. So for particularly
people who are the youngest. So actually
once once you for old learners um some
of their socioeconomic characteristics
seem to be less predictive of whether or
not they would be successful in a class
which you could might you might assume
to mean something like by the time
people are 40 years old or something
like that. Um you know your your initial
family upbringing maybe matters less for
the people who are signing up for this
class. Um but for really young folks um
if your parents graduated from college
you were way more likely um to complete
the class than if you signed up and your
parents had not graduated from college
pres you not presumably because you
lived in a household in which you both
had more support at the time that you
were taking the class and you had grown
up with many more academic and financial
supports than other kinds of people. Um
so you know it was I mean I mean you
know at like MOO organizations at this
time were telling stories like we
mentioned before like the boy genius of
Ulan Bar about all these people who are
you know far-flung places who were
taking courses and being successful and
all of that was true. Um there were
people from every walk of life from all
corners of the world who are really
successful. It was it was like mukes
opened a door and a handful of people
who definitely would have not have
accessed higher education before walked
through that door. But the vast majority
of people who walked through the door
were already educated, already um
affluent people. So, you know, maybe
there's a way that you could describe
that as democratizing, but it didn't
seem particularly democratizing to us.
Um what are some um this was my uh
doctoral research which I'll summarize
quickly. So you know just like in just
like today there's all these ideas like
man AI is going to transform education
and just like 10 years ago there was all
these man mukes are going to transform
education in 2007208 2009 it was social
media that was going to transform
education. It was blogs and wikis and
peer production. Yeah it sounds silly
now but believe me at the time people
thought. Um so we did this kind of cool
study where we like knocked on the door
of a company that um let you set up
wiks. At the time it was called PB
Works. Um, and we were like, maybe it
was called PB Wiki and then changed to
PB Works. And we're like, can we have a
list of all of your education related
wiks? And they're like, yeah, sure. Like
like in theory as something that we
could have scraped from their website,
but they just sort of handed it over.
Um, so that was pretty cool. Now we had
200,000 wiks that someone had labeled as
education related. And these weren't
wikis like Wikipedia that like everyone
would work on. They would be like a
class or a school or something like that
would foster these wiks. So we took 1%
of them. Um, and then I hired like a
small army of uh research assistants to
figure out what they all were. So we
like coded the car we like labeled the
characteristics of them. We did this
like private investigation work to
figure out like what school they were
from. And then if you if you know
something about a school, you know like
what neighborhood it's in and how many
of its students are eligible for free
and reduced price lunch and what its
racial divisions are. You can know all
kinds of sort of demographic
characteristics. Um, one of the things
that we focused on, um, was whether or
not they were title one schools where a
certain percentage of students were
eligible for free and reduced price
lunch and those who are not. Um, and we
basically sort of identified like four
different types of wikis that people
created. Um, things that just like
didn't work, things where there was like
like someone created it and then like
never updated it, threw it away,
whatever, that's fine. Um, things that
were teacher centered content delivery
devices. So things that were basically
just like simple websites. So in some
respects like definitely what you did
not want wikis to be like like um uh the
other one was sort of individual student
assignment or portfolio like something
an individual student made um and then a
sort of collaborative multimedia
assignment or workplace. So the first
thing that we figured out is that like
the vast majority of wiks either didn't
work or were teacher- centered content
delivery devices. Um this is a kind of
curse of the familiar example like you
can build if you if you give to people
this never before seen tool to do
collaborative writing. Um schools will
use it to just broadcast things to
students or to make students turn in
their assignments with it. Um they're
very unlikely to do the thing that wikis
were supposed to do. um but they were
more likely to fail um in title one
schools and they were a little bit more
likely to have some kind of student
component in it in the non-por more
affluent schools. Um so all of these
things were free, you know, they were
freely accessible on the internet, all
kinds of things like that. But you could
see from their like very beginning um
schools that had more resources were
going to be able to use them in more
interesting, more student- centered
kinds of ways. Um
uh we'll skip that one. Oh, this is one
of this is one of my sort of favorite
pieces of research. That's an example of
this. Um, so we make kids take this test
that we've discussed before, the
National Assessment of Education
Progress. And when we make them take the
test, we also make them take a survey.
Um, and in 2011, uh, kids took a math
test and we asked them questions like,
do you use a computer for drill and
practice in math? Um, do you use
computers for simulations and
applications? Then you can like ascribe
a few things from this. We're more
likely to have students do drill and
practice kinds of things than we are to
have them do simulations and
applications and things like that. You
know, I don't know, this would be like
Il and this would be like geometry,
sketchpad or Desmos. Um, we make black
students do drill and practice things
more than white students. We make poor
more than non-por students. Like when we
give people access to new technologies
um even if they have equitable access to
the technologies they often have
inequitable access to different kinds of
opportunities with them. So, one of the
papers that I um assigned to you um
which one of my very favorites is by a
guy named Paul Atwell um called the
first and second digital divide. Um and
his argument is that we the digital divi
divide was originally conceived as an
access divide like who has computers and
who doesn't, who has broadband and who
doesn't. But even if you could snap your
fingers and give everyone the exact same
access, there would still be a digital
divide of usage. There's evidence um
that uh uh people from low-inccome
backgrounds are more likely to use
technology for drill and practice kinds
of things rather than creative things
and they're more likely to use it with
less adult mentorship and support than
more affluent folks are. Um but the
funny thing when I read this 2011
summary was I was like man like it was
like it was like having the experience
of reading a plagiarized paper. You're
like I swear I've read this exact same
study before. Um, uh, this is what a
Apple MacBook looked like in 1996. This
is what it looked like in 2011. So like
like 15 years of like pretty good
technological proc progress. Um, but
these are the same findings from 1996.
Um, and as you can see like the numbers
are exactly the same. Like we asked
these kids these questions 15 years
apart. If you see any difference in the
numbers, they're probably statistically
insignificant. It's just like a little
bit of variation in the um in the
sampling. Um, but essentially like I
mean this was like 1996 to 2011 was like
a pretty big decade and a half for
technology and math. Um, and we made
almost no change in the fundamental ways
that young people were being able to
access and use technology. Does that
argument make sense to you? Um, totally
striking um, pair of findings there. Um,
but Olrich Boser did not um, did not
plagiarize from Wlinsky. They just had
the the same findings. Yeah. Out of
curiosity, is there a lot of difference
between public public schools and like
charter schools or like private schools
in the US on how those
things happen in real life? Here um I
let me here's here. Yeah. Um there there
are there can be like those things have
enormous different gradations in the
United States. Um so Dana was talking
about Catholic schools in Philadelphia.
those are like strictly speaking private
schools, but they might be serving some
of the most low-income neighborhoods and
families in Philadelphia. Um, where the,
you know, in, you know, a a a Catholic
school in inner city Philadelphia might
have more in common with its public
neighbor than it does um, you know, to
Sidwell Friends or something like that,
a super elite private school, which
might also be in Philadelphia, but might
as well be in a whole different world.
Um so so to some extent like it's sort
of like tax status or organizational
status can be related to those kinds of
things but not necessarily bec you know
because we have public schools that
serve you know that like public school
in extremely wealthy neighborhood might
have more in common with a private
school than it does with another public
school in inner city neighborhood. Um
this was kind of a cool study that was
done um looking at three schools that
had adopted a whole bunch of technology.
Um so they like they they had roughly
the same levels of access. They had
bought the same kind of stuff. Um there
was um they were all in the Bay Area.
These aren't real names. Heathcliffe
Academy which is a private mostly
wealthy mostly white school. Sheldon
Junior High which is a public mostly
middle- class and Asian-American school.
Caesar Chavez, middle school, public,
mostly working-class and Latino. And
again, they had all bought like roughly
the same amount of stuff. Like I think
like like each kid had a laptop, the
laptop was connected to broadband. Um,
of course, there are going to be
differences, you know, some access
differences in the really wealthy place
and the more working-class places, but
not but trying to find not striking
differences. Um, but what Matt found was
that the way people discussed technology
was quite different. Um, so at the
mostly white Heathcliffe Academy, um,
uh, playing around with technology was
viewed as essential. So if there were
kids who were like goofing around in
Minecraft and stuff like that was
encouraged. Um, oh, you're playing
around, you're hacking, you're doing all
these kind of neat things. Um, whereas
in the mostly middle class
Asian-American school, like sort of
goofy hacking applications of technology
were considered threatening. It's like,
oh, this is a risk to your education.
This is a risk to your progress. Um
whereas in the mostly working-class
Latino school, there wasn't like
encouragement or kind of discourage. It
was just sort of considered irrelevant,
like people weren't really paying
attention to what they were doing. So
again, the idea here being that like
here are three institutions that had
roughly similar levels of technology
access, but they had like the faculty
and community gave very different
cultural messages about what playing
around with that technology meant. Um,
and for the kids who are already
advantaged, they were encouraged to play
and hack and goof around and things like
that. But for the kids who were not
already advantaged, they got different
messages from their community about the
values of those technology. Um,
uh, and yeah, this is another sort of
myth pair. The idea that technical and
economic barriers are what keep people
out that like if we could just get
people the stuff, they would have, you
know, great education with technology.
whereas instead it's social and cultural
exclusions which can often be the
hardest. Um some of the we've talked in
the class before about um connected
learning. Um this some of these ideas
about like how do kids do informal
learning in their own communities and
other things like that. Some of the
things that the um that the connected
learning researchers are most worried
about right now is that like you know in
incre as America's polarization
um uh sort of increasingly
uh is expressed on social media. Um more
and more kids feel uncomfortable
communicating and expressing themselves
there. Um, and like white affluent dudes
are the least likely to feel threatened
in those spaces. And kids with all kinds
of different marginalized backgrounds
are are the ones who are more likely to
withdraw from posting their fanfiction
to sharing their art on Deviant Art on
other kinds of things like that. Like
basically what they saw was um you know
in recent years ac again across all
kinds of ages and racial groups and
backgrounds and things like that a sort
of withdrawing from public learning on
social media but a withdrawing which
seemed much more pronounced from people
from marginalized backgrounds um than
they did from people from more affluent
backgrounds. And all of those kids have
more access to technology than they've
ever had before. Um but there are social
and cultural exclusions that are keeping
them from learning experiences in ways
that are new. Um, okay. What can we do
about this? Um, this is one of the most
frustrating problems to talk about
because I feel like I feel like the
problem is extremely well understood.
Um, this is one in which I feel like the
evidence we can say for sure like if you
build a new edtech thing, it is very
likely to disproportionately benefit the
affluent. Um, especially if you're not
attentive to all to to how these issues
operate. like we should not, you know,
we should not assume that new generative
AI tools are going to democratize
education. They just are very unlikely
to do that. But then you might say,
well, all right, a there are some things
um you read some studies of things like
assistants and Carnegie learning that
seem to disproportionately benefit
people with low prior achievement in
mathematics. Like what are they doing
right? Like what are technologies that
disproportionately benefit the learners
who are furthest from opportunities? And
I would say that we don't know very
well. um the research on like how to fix
this problem is is more novel um is more
nent but here are a few things um that
maybe would be promising directions to
explore. So one think about technologies
that align home school and community um
if affluent kids automatically get kind
of an educational support infrastructure
from their homes and families from their
college educated parents and stuff like
that. How would you build technologies
or technology infrastructures that like
help all parents do more of this stuff?
Um, so family creative learning is a
super cool project by a woman named Rick
Rose wrote who got a PhD here who
basically was trying to figure out like
um how would you help boys and girls
clubs after schools support parents in
doing a better job helping their kids
use Scratch? like, "All right, so we
know like we know kids of software
engineers are the most likely folks to
use Scratch, but what if we just helped
all of the parents um support kids doing
Scratch?" So, she would do these like
multigenerational programs in after
school play YMCA's, Boys and Girls
Clubs, and stuff like that. You bring
parents and grandparents in, you feed
them dinner, you break the parents and
the kids up, you each teach them
something about computers, you put them
back together and share their projects
and stuff like that. Um, and that seemed
pretty cool.
um how do you make it so that the kinds
of things that you're working on with
technology align with young people's
interests? Um so this was a a photo from
a project um that was done at Georgia
Tech trying to um help more
African-American males in the Atlanta
area get involved in computer science,
computer programming. Um, and this was a
researcher who found um that uh a lot of
these kids were really interested in
video games and they were interested in
um the problems in the video games,
bugs, glitches, and things like that.
She was like, "Cool, let's make a little
QA testing company." Um, and so she got
a bunch of kids. She helped them um
interface with companies to do QA
testing. They were called the glitch
game testers because the language that
they used for bugs in that part of the
world was glitch. Um, and as kids got
more engaged in this program, she would
then help them like take AP computer
science and stuff like that and sort of
translate into academic programming. But
the idea was to like find out find out
what kids entry points look like into
these issues and try to build um up from
there.
Um, sort of similar I think to connect
this is this is like the heart of
connected learning like how do you
connect to the interests and identities
of young people? I mean, part of what
Scratch was doing with Micro Worlds is
being like, who is intuitively
interested in creative programming, um,
maybe not every kid, so, but like, what
kinds of kids could we get, um, with
hip-hop dance? What kinds of kids could
we get with fashion? What kinds of kids
could we get with standup comedy? Um,
how could we offer a broad array of
interests that could draw people in um,
to what we're doing?
Um, a a study that I would love to do
one day is to think
about how like what how do you how do ed
tech companies reduce cost in ways that
disproportionately benefit those who are
furthest from opportunities. Um, like a
funny thing to think about is like what
happens when you make something free.
Um, so MOOs for the most part were free.
Open courseware for the most part is
free. But those things probably
disproportionately benefit the affluent.
um like they're free things but they're
better for rich people. There's actually
a whole sociology of this like uh it
connects to like swag bags at the Oscars
and things like that. Like people are
always giving rich people free stuff. Um
which doesn't seem like it makes sense.
Um but there are certain kinds of
things. You know, Desmos is the bottom
example here. Um the TI8384 was a real
barrier to mathematics learning for
families. Um and Desmos reduced that
cost to zero. Now, a $120 calculator is
not a huge burden for an upper class
family, not a huge burden for a middle-
class family. It's a big burden for a
working-class family. And so, like,
you're saving money for the families for
whom that barrier is most relevant. Um,
another one of my favorite projects, has
anybody ever heard of Open Stacks? Um,
they did this cool thing where they
realized all like something like half of
all higher education enrollments are in
20 classes. Um, just about everybody
who's taking a college class this
semester across the entire United States
is taking sociology 101, pre-cal,
macroeconomics, micromatics, chemistry,
US history, psychology, economics,
algebra. Like, you know, I mean, there's
a long tale of zillions and zillions of
other classes that we offer in higher
education, but almost everyone is in
these 20 classes. They were like, let's
just pay really smart people a bunch of
money to write good textbooks and then
give them away for free. Um, so for
somebody who's coming to MIT and you're
paying $50,000 a semester, whatever it
is, you're paying like a $120 chemistry
book is not a big deal. If you go to a
community college and the entire
chemistry course costs you $120 to
register for a $120 textbook is a huge
deal. It's just doubled the cost of your
credit hours of education in that class.
Um, so taking that $120 and bringing
that to zero, that might really matter a
lot. that could save people, you know, a
meaningful amount of money that will
help them advance in their community
college education or other sorts of
things like that. So, this idea that you
could look across the education system
and be like, you know, what are specific
cost barriers to family that we use
technology to drive down those costs in
ways that like affluent people might
benefit from but probably won't notice,
um, but community college learners, you
know, lower income working-class
families might really benefit from. Um,
a thing that we experimented with a lot,
um, was trying to target the needs of
subgroups. Um, did I talk about these
experiments when we talk about MOOs? How
we put all these little uh,
interventions in at the beginning of MOO
courses to get people to some nodding
heads? It's in the books there. Um, we
designed a whole series of interventions
that were trying to increase the sense
of belonging or increase the sense of
well-being from people who might
perceive themselves being from minority
backgrounds. Um, and we thought they
worked for a while and then we weren't
sure that that our interventions was
working. But it's sort of an interesting
things to think about like what kind of,
you know, if you if you're trying to
serve people from a wide range of
backgrounds and you know that some
people from those backgrounds might not
have the same level of support at home
or might not have the same, you know,
might experience stereotype threat or
other kinds of things like that, like
what kinds of interventions could you
design to to address those needs? Um
uh another thing to think about is like
where could you target supports sort of
across someone's educational trajectory.
This is another sort of sad story of
things that we thought worked for a
little while and probably don't but
still the problem is real. Um Ben Castle
Ben Castleman worked at this school in
in Providence called MET. Um and they
were a charter school and they did a
pretty good job getting kids into
college. But one of the things they
observed which totally broke their heart
is that they would get kids into college
accepted to college and then they
wouldn't show up in the fall. Um like
like you like like you're in part of you
know four year 12ear educational system
which is trying to get kids into
post-secary education and you succeed.
They have an application letter and some
fraction of them don't arrive in the
fall. They ended up calling that summer
melt. um is the uh you know and part of
it is if you are the first person in
your family to go to college then
figuring out FAFSA, figuring out course
enrollment, figuring out moving on
campus like if you come from a family
where you're not first generation like
your mom and your dad just explain all
that stuff to you and figure it out and
you get through it. Um but each of those
obstacles, you know, and there are a few
of them to showing up at Campson's each
of those was enough. Um, so they
designed these technologies that
basically like sent little text message
nudges to kids all throughout the
summer, you know, have you figured out
your financial aid? Have you registered?
Have you other kinds of things like
that? Um, and for a little while it
looked like those nudges were working
and then people reproduced at larger
scales and this particular intervention
doesn't seem like it's it's actually
working. Um but it was at least this
sort of good idea of being like let's
think about people's educational
trajectory from you know for all the
transition points you have between
middle school and high school and
college and post-secary and lifelong
learning and things like that and where
might there might be transition points
that affluent folks just kind of breeze
through um but folks from working-class
families find more struggles with um and
pro probably the biggest challenge that
education technology has um is things
that really work in education often are
tailored to their particular context.
But usually what software developers are
trying to do is build a thing that works
anywhere. I mean that's that's a real
tension. That's a real problem. Um there
are some cool examples of this. You know
I think you you could think of like the
open edex platform is something kind of
working on that. So like there's one big
software platform and there are a couple
of you know there's like edex as a big
organization that offers mukes
everywhere but there are dozens of local
sort of MOO operators that offer in
their particular country in their
particular language in topics that they
think local folks will be interested in.
Um, one of them is Edrok, which is run
by the Queen Rana Foundation. Um, which,
uh, focuses on offering Arabic language
classes to folks in Jordan and areas
surrounding Jordan. And you could just
imagine, well, okay, like, so they can
take edex, they can make sure it
supports right to left reading in
Arabic, they can um, you know, do
whatever else you need to make the
Arabic interface work better, offer
courses in Arabic, find out what the
people in the Arabic world would want to
be able to do. um and they're using the
same kind of base software as everyone
else, but that software is kind of
customizable to serve particular um
notions and areas.
Um and and the idea is you might be able
to apply all of these different kinds of
thinking um all across a project's life
cycle. Um so as we were giving these
talks to people who fund technologies to
venture capitalists to philanthropists
to technologies developers to like you
know the big fang kind of companies that
have publishers who have a bunch of
things underneath them who are saying
like you know what are all the
strategies you might try when you're
funding a company um to get uh um to get
the right people at the table. You know,
lots of times when we when we fund
education technologies, the only people
who make those choices are like affluent
people who went to private school and
stuff like that. Like how would you make
more people from more diverse
backgrounds to be able to do that and so
forth and so on through all of the
different um uh programs. So in some
ways it's sort of uh disappointing that
there aren't better answers. Like it
would be nice to give a lecture like
this and be like we totally know what to
do to make education more equitable. Um
but we don't have that. But we have some
really clear I mean in my mind just
definitive evidence that when people
build education technologies if they
don't center the needs of marginalized
communities it will disproportionately
benefit the affluent like you can you
can pretty much guarantee that as an
outcome for almost anything that comes
along. Um and there's lots of
interesting work to be done and things
to explore to figure out like how could
we learn more about being more
intentional about building things that
serve a diverse range of folks. Um and
then I so I won't see you I will see you
each individually next week to talk
about your projects. Um and then the
following week we'll talk about the next
couple of um uh as yet intractable
dilemmas um the trap of routine
assessment and the toxic power of data
and experiments. So very nice to see you
this week and I look forward to seeing
you um individually next week and enjoy
your long weekend.