Hey everyone. Um, thank you all for
joining. This is so exciting. Um, I am
an MBA 2026. I graduate next next year.
Um, and yeah, uh, just a bit about me.
I'm originally from Atlanta, Georgia.
Um, I was working in New York at
Accenture before school, came back to
school, um, worked at Mackenzie Atlanta.
Um, this summer was nice to be back home
and I'm really excited to be one of the
BBSA co-presidents this upcoming year
and yeah, just happy to meet you all
virtually and um, yeah, and I'll be
helping moderate the panel today. We'll
start with you Dante.
>> Yeah, sure. So, happy to kick us off
everyone. Good to good to be here. Glad
to be back uh, engaged with the Sloan
community. It's always fun. Um, so I'm
Dante Montgomery. I was an LG leaders
for global operations graduate class of
2020. I before Sloan was um working in
oil and gas space at Exon Mobile doing
project management um and uh yeah came
to the LJGO program which is a dual
degree program with engineering. So I
did my masters in mechanical engineering
in addition to the NBA. uh did an
internship with private equity and since
graduating LJGL I joined Danahur's uh
general manager development program uh
spent about two years in uh product
management another two years in
um what we call uh global business
enablement uh it's more commercial
operations and now I'm the director of
global footprint and supply chain
strategy so I've had a breadth of
experiences in product management
commercial and now more operations
focused
Um, hey everybody. My name is Ellen
Baje. I'm also excited to be back
talking with the Sloan community and
hearing from all of y'all and hearing
your questions. Um, prior to Sloan, I
worked in IT consulting and did
accounting and finance. My background is
in accounting. Um, while at Sloan, I got
to focus on product management and also
entrepreneurship amongst other things.
Um, in post loan, um, I now I started my
own IT consulting business where I run
the company and I'm also an IT product
manager working on the workday product.
Pass on to Karen.
>> Hey guys, it's so so nice to be back
with fellow Sloanies. Um, I'm Karen. Uh,
before Sloan, I'm originally from
Boston. Uh, before Sloan, I was working
in like the tech uh, space. So, um, tech
and policy space, excuse me. Um, so I
was Harvard working at a think tank
before that, worked as a campaign
manager in New Hampshire. So definitely
maybe not your traditional MBA
candidate. Um, but definitely took a lot
of nuggets um, out of Sloan. Uh,
currently I'm a project manager at Meta
where I'm working on their content and
integrity operations team. So basically
what I do is making sure you all if you
use any meta apps so Facebook,
Instagram, threads um WhatsApp making
sure you don't see um certain types of
harmful content. So that's kind of what
my day today is about and I will pass it
to Acha.
>> Thank you Karen and um and good
afternoon and good good evening all. So
I'm a me I'm a recent Sloan graduate as
of um three months ago and it's good to
be back um with um Sloan and with people
who have interests of of Sloan. Prior to
Sloan, I was a I was a partner at a con
consulting firm doing work in the West
African space, specifically Nigeria.
And after Sloan, I've I've rejoined the
firm, but now have a more of um a
continentwide approach of moving the
energy se sector forward. And while at
Sloan, I focused on sustainability as
one of my um one of my um f focus areas.
And that's what I'm doing now going
forward. Back to you, Ariel.
>> Cool. Okay, thanks everyone. Um, and
yeah, feel free to use the chat and if
you have any like
person specific questions as well, throw
it in the chat. Um, okay. And just to
kick us off, I want to start with
community. So,
what ways were you involved in the
community and also like kind of what
were your favorite parts of the
community and what did that look like
for you in whatever way that means to
you?
I'm happy.
>> No order. No order. Whoever just wants
to jump in.
>> Yeah, I'm happy to share. Um, so when I
was at Sloan, I was um, so my first year
I was part of the uh, Sloan Energy Club.
I was a VP of community there. Um, which
also engaged in bringing together some
of the not just MITwide community, but
even collaborating with some of our our
peers, uh, specifically at Harvard. um
in their energy group as well. So that
was a lot of fun. Um and I was also uh
one of the um chairs within or one of
the panel chairs essentially for the
Africa Innovate Conference. Um so was my
first year and the second year I became
the co-president for BBSA, the Black
Business Student Association, as well as
one of the co-chairs for the Africa
Innovate Conference. So those were my
two kind of uh you know big community
leadership engagements. Um but of course
we led um you know had a number of ways
where we were engaging not just through
the clubs but just more socially and
interactive um you know on campus and
and around Boston. So it was always
something going on and way to connect
with uh fellow Sloan.
>> Yeah. Um I'll hop in there. um my
experience um at Sloan in terms of
community and kind of what I did um to
start like the club level um similar to
Dante um I was in several clubs I was in
the product management club
entrepreneurship club and um several
other things so that was one way to
interact with people um a fun way to
interact with people also was ours
groups uh we had like giant WhatsApp
groups and we had like a black WhatsApp
group called the friendly black hotties
where we would constantly just be in
communication with each other and plan
like events with Harvard it in with
people um at Sloan including game
nights, um movie nights, like just we
did a roller rink night where we like
all went out and to the roller rink. Um
and then you know also on top of that
just getting to know people with trips.
NBA the NBA experience is known for
taking trips and stuff and um I was I
took a lot of trips in business school.
I think I visited like 20some countries
while I was in business school and that
was a cool way to get to know people as
well. Um like I did like a boys trip
with like a lot of the like some of the
black men at Sloan. we went to um went
to London and then the following year we
went to Lisbon and where there I got to
really get to know people and and know
people a little deeper. My second year
at Sloan just to kind of loop it all
back around. I'm the VP of um
communications I guess for BBSA as well.
So we focused on like the social media
strategy and we also helped out with
like the sweater sales and stuff like
that. So um there's a lot of fun ways to
interact with people. It wasn't just in
the classroom. you really got to know
people deeply outside of the classroom
and and even now like some of the people
I got to hang out with are still my
friends today. We even took a trip in to
Phoenix earlier this year uh to
celebrate, you know, being friends for I
guess now four years. It's kind of
crazy.
>> When I met you, the first thing you or I
remember you said you helped create the
Kente sweatshirts.
[Music]
>> Yeah. Yeah. I was just gonna say Ellen
was integral in um the Kente sweatshirts
and so if you guys have seen that that
was all Ellen. Um okay so in terms of
community for me um I would say like I
kind of based community off a lot of the
my personal values and so like equity
and inclusion was something that was
really important to me. So I got
involved with BB BBSA um early on in my
first year and then my second year um I
served as co-president. Um mentorship
was something that was really important
to me. So um I my second year I served
as um gosh what do you call it? um like
a student like mentor, core mentor. Um
so basically like leading um orientation
and having a cohort of uh first year
students my second year that I kind of
shephered through their first year. Um
and then also I just like love having
fun and doing fun things. I'm from the
Boston area like I said. So, my first
year I was a CBC, which is called like
um a community building chair for my uh
cohort, my ocean. And so, that was
really fun, like planning random events
um from like Valentine's Day events to
Halloween events and parties and
whatnot. So, um that was like also a way
to to really get to know um my community
within BBSA, but also um just like the
broader Sloan community. Um, and then
lastly, I think to Ellen's point, it's I
think I met friends as well and like
built my community primarily outside of
the classroom actually. So, it was
through like involvement in, you know,
CBC, um, BBSA, but then also just like
randomly meeting people in a cafeteria
or like a trip. And I feel like your
random hangouts that you have like after
class in someone's apartment. Um I feel
like those relationships uh really last
and stand the test of time. And so I
have Sloan that have become really good
friends that have visited me now in my
new city. I'm going to a Sloan wedding
this weekend. So, um, our community runs
really deep and I think that's something
that's really, um, maybe unique of Sloan
than my other business schools is like
we just really value each other and like
each other for the most part and really
have fun with one another.
>> Yeah, just to add in there, I think for
me it was more um, first of all, the
Sloan Fellows program goes by really
fast. A year is a really short time. So
I think getting involved with the with
the clubs was something that a lot of us
struggled with just because of of
timing. But I was involved with the
energy club, the African business club.
But I think for for me I focused on it
from um informal point of view. So every
week my roommate and I had um Sloan's
over for dinner. So we would cook and
and like have chance to break break
break bread with classmates just talk
talk about things that you ordinarily
wouldn't talk about in class and also
just have a chance to reflect and get to
know each other. So I think for from
that perspective it gave me people that
I'm still f friends with now. I'm in
Dallas for for the weekend and in a few
hours I'll be meeting up with two two
other other Sloanies as a way to keep
that community going. So, it's it's a
very important value at Sloan.
>> I love that. I love all that. Um,
something you touched on, Karen. Yeah,
the Sloan cafeteria is notorious for
just meeting people all the time.
Um, and I love that. Okay, so this next
question is, what surprised you when you
got to Sloan? Um,
good, bad, all of it. What surprised
you? Um, yeah, in general or about the
culture at Sloan.
>> All right, I'll go first. Um, so I'll
start with the good and I think this
will answer a question someone had about
the stigma of not being team oriented
school which I have never heard and I'm
on like the subreddit all the time. But
anyway, like I think from my experience
for like the NBA subredder like I think
it was actually the helpfulness from
other people and the willingness for
people to help you not just when it came
to like in the classroom stuff like for
example your first semester you have to
take um a class called DMD and if you
don't know how to code anything it's
really difficult and I'm a person with
an accounting background and that never
touched that stuff but there was like
one of my good friends now Tyler he was
willing to just drop everything and
teach me and not only teach me but teach
other people how to do um how to code in
Python. on how to how to understand kind
of the work you were doing. And I think
that kind of spread um you know that was
kind of pervasive. I ultimately ended up
having allow or being able to help other
people with the accounting work. We had
to take accounting as a core class and I
was actually able to grab a classroom
and answer um the questions that people
had and teach them the basics and
foundations of accounting. On top of
that, you have your core teams and stuff
like that. Um, so I think the good was
really the Sloan helping Selonies wasn't
just like some corny mantra that's put
on, you know, things just to sell to to
sell a message. I think it was something
that was actually true and something
real. Um, I think one of the things that
was maybe difficult uh was the you're
going to you have this like kind of
choice paralysis, right? Like because
there's so many things going on at Salon
because you're some people are in the
NBA and they come in and know exactly
what they want to do. other people like
myself had a vision of what I wanted to
do, but after like learning more, I kind
of wanted to switch. And you do run into
this this um kind of scenario where
you're like trying to figure out the
best thing to do and and you ultimately
might end up trying several different
things. And even though the NBA
full-time program is only two years,
it's only two years. So like if you
don't focus on something like sooner
than later, then it might come back to
bite you in terms of like applying for
internships or getting whatever role you
want full-time. So I think that's
probably one of the tougher things for
business school. I know that's something
that's probably pervasive amongst all
business schools, but I think that was
just something that those are a few
things that kind of highlighted my
experience and the good and the bad.
>> Yeah, maybe one thing I'll add um to
that was a surprise for me was just how
like socially active and like really
personable the community was. Um and
it's not to say that I was expecting it
to to not be that way. I just think it
was so much further kind of on the far
end of the spectrum of being very
sociable, very personable, and in a very
good way where like your classmates are
really trying to get to know you for who
you are. They're not trying to oneup you
or anything like that. It's really um
you know, really trying to to build that
community at a very deeper level, not
just at a surface level. Um, I think
that was something that I was like very
pleasantly surprised by and and it
really I think really made my experience
there just one I'll never forget. Um,
maybe just to just to just to keep it
balanced of something that um uh was a
surprise that um wasn't so positive I
would say is is that so I I was very
engaged in like the broader MIT
community. Um, so it wasn't just at
Sloan, but there's a lot of schools that
are very good at what they do and
sometimes things are can be a bit
fragmented. But with that said, if the
people who excel at really pushing the
boundaries and, you know, have a
mission, have a goal of what they're
trying to achieve, you'll find that
there's more than enough resources, not
just at Sloan, but even at other
departments, uh, across MIT that may not
be well advertised or well known, but
it's those resource resources are there.
it's just not always, you know, front
and center for you to to grasp. Um, so
that was maybe one thing that's, you
know, has its pros and cons, but it was
a certainly a surprise when I got there.
>> All right. So, I'll um I'll start with
the bad for me. I think that that is
just matter of um the disconnectivity
with Sloan with parts of Sloan and the
rest of MIT
>> because you you take classes like for
instance I took a class in the
engineering bu building and I just felt
that the synergy amongst the the among
the two schools wasn't quite fused and
the Sloan time doesn't exist in normal
MIT. you you're running around trying to
get there on trying to be um be be a
proper student. And then I al also also
think that MIT is so broad that um a lot
of us at Sloan stay at Sloan. We don't
get a chance to really explore the
proper MIT um MIT community. So I think
that's also one thing that we we we've
got to do a better job of. Right. I
think the good is I was super surprised
the first um the first semester of just
the quality of the pro professors we
had. We had really fantastic professors
who who understood and who taught things
that quite complex in very easy to
understand language and also were
willing to help, willing for you to
email, stop by, grab a coffee and all
that. So I think for me I was very very
s surprised at that and then the fact
that they're so they're so qualified and
so smart they still had time to um help
you in some difficult topics. So that'll
be it for me.
>> Um
>> honest
>> Oh go ahead.
>> I would say my favorite thing about
Sloan is alone time.
>> Yes. I wish meetings at Meta started as
slone time.
Um, so I would say that I think for me
I think the bad was well it wasn't a bad
thing. I think just for me personally I
found it really to be intellectually
rigorous and challenging. Um, I didn't
come from like a science background or
accounting or engineering or whatnot.
Like I am a liberal arts girly through
and through. And so classes like DMD and
and some of the other classes were a
little bit challenging for me like
accounting and whatnot. But I think what
I really appreciated about the community
was that all my classmates were always
willing to like pull up their sleeves
and like just help me. Um whether it was
like prepping for an exam or like um an
assignment. And usually um in your
cohort or what do we call wow I'm
forgetting all the Sloan terms
>> oceans.
>> In our oceans but then what are our
little clusters of seven
>> core teams.
>> Core teams. Thank you.
>> Um in our core teams like usually
someone brings some level of expertise
um in your kind of core class topics.
And so those individuals were always
super willing to like sit down and like
mentor you um through uh the classes
which I really support which I really
appreciated. So I think everyone is just
it is like a truly collaborative
community and everyone genuinely wants
everyone to succeed and I don't think
you can always say that about all types
of communities but I always felt that at
Sloan and it wasn't just from my
classmates but it was also like your
professors as well who were willing to
schedule time outside of office hours
who if they knew you were interested in
something would like send you like
resources or articles or whatnot. not um
and so I just like pre appreciated um
the community and supporting me when
sometimes I felt like I was drowning.
>> Mhm.
Thanks guys. Um and a few people or
there's a couple questions that came up
and I'll kind of just combine them. Um
first part is how do you balance there's
a big thing about balancing with all the
clubs and everything. How do you balance
that with academics? And also in
general, are is there anything that you
had to do differently from your prior
studies um to now or to when you were in
um your MIT studies?
>> I think I can kick it off. Um I think
you just have to learn how to
prioritize, prioritize, prioritize. like
um there will be a million things like
it feels like you're drinking from a
fire hose sometimes. There are just so
many um assignments
um fun activities you want to do. You
want to go on all the trips, but you
just like have to prioritize like what's
really important to you and like have a
north star. And sometimes that might
change. Like I think I went into
business school thinking I was going to
be in consulting and that just like
didn't happen. But like being able to
pivot and like move from that I think is
really important. Um and as you're
pivoting um you know bringing people
along with you whether it's like your
colleagues or like switching what clubs
um you're potentially interested in. Um
so yeah I think prioritization was
something that was like really important
for me. Um, and your first year, first
semester, you'll try and do it all and
then you'll kind of get burnt out and
then you'll learn how to prioritize
second semester. Um, so yeah, stop
there.
>> And yeah, the second part to the
question was like just in general, is
there anything that you have to do
differently in previous studies versus
this versus MIT studies? Um, but I think
you touched on that too, Karen, just to
clarify.
>> Yeah, I think for me like I a lot of it
was new to be quite honest. So I had to
build up but that's why I applied to
business school and that's why I wanted
to come to business school was to learn
a lot of new skills. Um so I think for
me it was just like learning how to
think differently maybe tweaking like my
policy brain to a more business focus
and strategy lens. But that was
something that I really appreciated and
was able to learn and adapt from
learning from my um classmates and
professors as well.
>> Yeah. I was going to say one big change
is the internship aspect, right? Like if
you're doing a full-time MBA, um you're
going to have basically that first
semester, you've got to work on
prioritizing like Karen said, social not
just socializing and in your coursework
and your grades and stuff, but also
getting that internship that you want to
get if you want to go work at like a
Microsoft or Meta, wherever, like they
usually should recruit, right?
Basically, recruiting starts right when
you start school. So, it's a lot of
balancing. Um it's a lot of balancing.
It's also working with six or six or
seven new people you've never met before
who are from other parts of the world
who may have different working styles
and you've got to quickly learn how to
work with one another in your core team.
Um and then and and you really do get
this um experience of FOMO where you're
like, "Okay, I want to do all this stuff
plus I want to go on all these trips."
So, I would say like prioritizing and
making sure you get all those things
kind of um squared away right away and
and make sure that you focus on the
things that you're here to do at
business school, right? So if that means
you're there to pivot and get a new job
somewhere else then I would say focus on
getting your internship right when you
right from the jump from business school
and and you know there are other people
who are also everybody's also going
through the same thing for the most part
right so like um there's an
understanding that everyone has where
they know hey I'm going to go I'm going
to be recruiting for Nvidia right now so
I might be you know slacking on my
accounting work so can y'all pick up the
slack and then you know so forth and so
on it's a balancing act I forgot the
other part of the question but that's
like the difference in my studies
between what I did undergrad which is
accounting in in masters and undergrad
um in accounting and what I did in
business school but what was the other
part sorry
>> no I think that answers it was like one
part one question was about how do you
balance everything and one part is like
how was basically like your previous
studies different than this and it I
honestly a huge part of that is balance
so it's kind of just like
>> that was that helps thanks
>> can I say one last thing be don't be
afraid to say no to things like because
you want to do everything. Like you're
going to want to try to do everything.
Say no to some things. You won't miss
out on everything. I promise. Like it's
two-year program if you're doing
full-time. It's a one-year program if
you're doing like any other program,
right? Like or LJGO is like even longer.
Like you'll have time to do everything
or you'll you'll have time to do the
things that you really want to do if you
really focus on that. But don't try to
do it.
>> Yeah. I did want to add um maybe just
from like an LJGO perspective as well.
So LJGO's start the summer before the
Sloonies come on. So we kind of get a
little bit of a head start in in a sense
of you know adjusting to being back in
graduate school and that whole summer is
more kind of engineering and um like
math and statistics focused. So it's
typically more kind of academically
rigorous. So we kind of come into the
fall and already kind of in that frame
of mind. Additionally, one of the the so
LG's do typically take one extra class
and over what the MBAs take an extra
class, usually an engineering course
that um you know is with you know your
traditional engineering students, right?
Um so you do have a little bit of an
extra course load. On the flip side of
that, in the fall, um we're not
typically recruiting for an internship
because our internships are done through
the program itself. Um, if anybody wants
to talk more about how that all works,
I'm happy to have like separate
conversations. So, feel free to reach
out. But essentially, you know, we're
not recruiting for the the typical MBA
internships. It's all done through the
LJGO program. So, it's much low much
lower pressure in the fall for LGOS's to
again continue to find that balance and
get involved in a number of other things
because you're not recruiting as heavily
for those internships. But at the same
time there's like lots of like the
course coursework is pretty challenging
for LJGL particularly with the
engineering courses. Um but it's again
just finding the balance and being
intentional about your time um and how
you're spending it was one thing that I
had to learn through the that fall
semester um because I was definitely
trying to do everything and realized I'm
not Superman but it comes it comes
through trial and error. There's no
there's no kind of magic formula to it.
>> Yeah. And just to pick up piggy back on
that, Dante, I think um you can't do
everything, right? You it's just
practically impossible to. So, you have
to be very intentional and be very
strategic about what you can and can't
do. One of my mentors before business
school told me, "Figure out what you
want to do in business school. Write it
down and reflect on it almost on a
weekly basis to ensure you're chasing
your northstar because there's so many
options at Sloan. you show up and the
finance bros are talking about um
um ETAs um you got product management
people you've got consulting so the
there's so many options if you don't
have a northstar you'll end up with a
fancy degree from MIT great school right
but without a lot of um real substance
then you have to go back and relearn
some things and no one wants to do that
so really have a north star and stay
focused on Cool.
Thanks. Okay. And
now to move into kind of just like being
I guess a black person at MIT.
Um I guess one
one person asked if anyone has done
anything in terms of like
entrepreneurship and like kind of what
that's looked like if you ever faced and
maybe broaden it any face any situations
with less resources and maybe just in
general kind of like any reflections on
your time at being you know the black
experience um at Sloan and what that's
looked like for you.
So two parts, academic, how what that
looks like for you and just your own
personal experience in the Sloan
community.
>> Yeah, I can go first. I think for me uh
I walked into or orientation
and uh the Sloan fellow fellow's class
is about 103
people for my class. I walked in, sat
down, looked around, there were two
black people in the room. And in my
mind, I'm like, what is happening here?
like this is not not not not what what
it should be. Thankfully, a few people
showed up afterwards. It ended up being
six black people as opposed to two. So,
that's that's a huge improvement, but it
was still significantly less than the
rest of the of the class. Um, the good
thing about Sloan is
you'll have in my class, we had 44
countries represented. So there's so
many people from all over the world in
your class and it it the racial potent
potential racial stereotypes that the
typical Americans could have are not
there because you have people who
haven't lived those experiences and
you're able to meet people from day one
and really establish who you are and
being able to show up and um and and do
do the work and also be be caring is is
very important. important, but I but I
think um I didn't after the orientation
bit, I didn't feel that it was anything
negative being black at Stone. I felt I
felt pretty at home because all the
resources were were there in student
life and the admissions office, the
programs office. So, I think being black
wasn't a pro a problem. But I think when
I showed up, it was a bit of a of a
shock. But I once things started, it it
wasn't an an an issue that I I had to um
contend with.
>> Yeah, I'm happy to give some comments uh
about my experience. Um, so I've I mean
my whole life I was pretty much in a
very um diverse community um of multiple
you know how however any way you want to
think about that but it was always and
I'd say the black part of the like
population was never more than like 10%
of you know whatever environment I was
in. So, I it was kind of coming into
environment where I was already
comfortable and new, but the black
community is always, you know, very
close-knit and, you know, very
supportive of each other and always
finding ways to make sure we're
connecting with each other and
empowering each other and making sure
we're all moving forward in, you know,
the world that we live in, which, you
know, obviously doesn't look like us in
in our communities or in our, you know,
the black community. So, it was always a
positive experience for me and
especially at Sloan um with not just the
black community, but also being able to
share our experiences with our peers as
well and like what does it mean from our
perspectives to be, you know, black in
the business world, you know, the
challenges that we faced and really
having those open dialogues uh uh with
our peers. Um, so there's like plenty of
space to be able to have those
conversations which I found very
rewarding and very very uh empowering at
the same time. Um, and one of the things
that we did when I was uh on campus uh
we call them c functions u which is
basically an an opportunity for
different cultures to kind of share
their experiences through food, through
music, through dance through you know
whatever you know lens of culture you
want to look at it through. and we
started the um I think we call it the
black America C function. Um which was
like the either the first or second time
that it had been done at Sloan. Um and
it's actually shared across the whole
MIT community. So it's not just a Sloan
specific thing, but Sloan leads it, but
the rest of MIT is welcome to join. Um,
and so it was just great feeling
comfortable that we can kind of push
this out to to our peers and kind of
share what what our experiences are
like, what it's like to kind of have our
culture. Um, there's also an Africa C
function which I think had already been
established before as well. Um, so yeah,
just say all that to say that the
experience was never anything negative
uh from from what I experienced. It's
always kind of positive things as as I
reflect on my experience being black at
MIT.
Thanks, Dante.
I I'll know especially this year with
affirmative action and everything like
things have looked very different. In my
class specifically, I describe us as
small but mighty and I love everyone and
we had so many we went out to Martha's
Vineyard last year and we like we're
really close. And also to echo um your
point,
there's so many people over the world
like everyone feels a little bit new and
everyone has been extremely open to
getting to know one another and I don't
know if you guys feel the same, but like
that's been my experience.
Um and to your point, Jonathan, we've
had a few like ask me anything. We had
um um I guess a black at Sloan ask me
anything this past semester and a lot of
people came just to hear about what the
black experience was like and like just
things from our perspective and like
other affinity clubs have them as well.
So like things like that um are like
things that I really really
>> Okay, I think we heard you. Um, I 100%
agree um with your point, Arya. And I
think the thing I would add too is just
like I don't feel like being at Sloan I
was ever marginalized because of the
color of my skin, you know, like I don't
I think there was a question around like
resources or whatnot. Um, I personally
have never
um
personally that hasn't been my
experience. Um, I do think it's like
Sloan really tries hard to be like an
inclusive community. Um, and obviously
like everyone's their own individual
person. Everybody comes with their own
individual biases and whatnot, but I do
think like as a school community like
um, everyone really tries to show up um,
and support one another. Um, and so I
have found it to be like a really
inclusive community and I my friend
groups range from within the black
community to even outside of that. Um,
and so yeah, I I enjoyed being a black
person at Sloan, but um, I know that's
not everyone's experience, but for me, I
personally really enjoyed it.
>> Yeah. And and just to wrap it, I mean
like I would say the black experience
for us and like I already mentioned
obviously the affirmative action case
changed everything. Like our class had
31 black Sloonies. Um I know that
number's been cut significantly, right?
And and so I would say like the
experience that I had was wonderful in
the sense of you know not only did we as
a group you know get to know one another
at Sloan but then we also expanded that
right like the Harvard's right down the
road and like the black Harvard students
were like there too and we were we would
do like game nights and kickbacks with
them to like actually get to know one
another and we would you know hang on
campus. think when it came to, you know,
the black experience as loan, of course,
there were some like headscratching
moments where someone would ask a
question in class where you'd just be
like, "Okay." And you you'd have to kind
of correct them or like kind of call
that out, but it was never from a place
of like malice. It was just more like
they didn't know. And it's one of those
opportunities where like business school
is a place where you're supposed to get
to learn from other people, right? And
so in in a low stakes environment. And
so it was nice to be able to like have
that conversation with some people and
be like, "Okay, I I can see where you're
trying to go with this, but like
realistically that's not how like you
should you should see it from this
perspective as well, right? Like it
shouldn't just be from this lens that
you're seeing." And um to Cameron's
point, I don't think I ever felt like an
other like like there was never a point
where I was like I'm a black person at
Sloan and that was like like I never
felt that way. It was more just like I
am a I'm a person at Sloan who happens
to be black, right? I I really felt it
was an inclusive environment and a place
where you could not just you know feel
it from like the students but from the
faculty too like there would be cases
where like we would do case studies a
lot of how we learned at Sloan right and
there's there was some case studies
around race where we were like I think
it was u I can't remember the class the
the core semester class where we had to
like
>> OP thank you there's a OP case where
>> organizational processes sorry
>> yeah thank you there's a core case where
we're just like sitting there like,
"Okay, this is kind of nonsense." And
there'd be like chatter in the group
chat about all that stuff. And then we'd
also bring it up in class and like call
it out. So like I think there was
opportunities, you know, to expand your
horizons. A lot of the stuff like like I
said, I wanted to learn from other
cultures too. I got to learn more about
like a Saudi Arabian culture, Japanese
culture, amongst other things by, you
know, like getting to know our
classmates and stuff. So, I didn't ever
feel like I was like how I felt when I
worked in the business world sometimes
where it's like you're the only black
person and people realize you're the
only black person to treat you like
that. Like I didn't necessarily get that
feeling. So, I would say ultimately
overall it was positive. Of course,
there's some bumps in the road um on
certain aspects, but for the most part
it was working with me.
>> Yeah. And um let me know if let me know
if you can't hear me. But just to add on
to that, it is so nice having so many
schools in Boston because we have had
kind of just black students in Boston
meetups and that's been a lot of fun.
And I also feel like as Sloan and to um
Ellen's point, the corporate world can
sometimes be not be so pretty, but
everyone at Sloan, they approach things
with curiosity. And I think that's been
my favorite part of getting to meet a
subset of people who don't for the most
part aren't judging initially or are
truly just curious.
Um yeah.
And then Okay. And then next question.
Um to make it more fun, what's been what
is one of your favorite experiences at
Sloan?
I'll give one that is very uniquely
LJGO. Um,
as part of the LJGO program, we do a um
like a global not global, but a uh a
domestic plant tre. Sorry, I had to
remember what it was called. It's been
been a while. Um, so we do a domestic
plant track where we go visit a number
of different partner companies over the
course of a two-eek span. Um that's in
the the first January of so basically
halfway through the first semester or
sorry through your first year. Um, so
yeah, we're on planes and buses
literally almost every day for the for
two weeks visiting 12 or so different
partner companies as part of our kind of
immersion experience is getting to visit
different plants, different operations,
and also engaging with other LJGO alumni
who are typically leaders at these
facilities as well. Um, and so the
opportunity to kind of travel around
with kind of my LJGO peers during those
two weeks, like we really got really
close together, um, got to know each
other very well. Um, to the to this
point where I I still refer them as as
family at this point because we've had
so many very close experiences with each
other. And then one of the the nights
that we were there, I was actually one
of uh two people that decided we should
do essentially an LJGO ask me anything.
Uh because we actually had for once a
little bit of downtime in our evening
and didn't have to go to like a
networking event of sorts.
And that ask me anything session, I
think we held it like in the basement of
the hotel we were staying in and lasted
probably 3 hours long of us just kind of
just talking about anything and
everything under the sun. Um it was very
just eye opening kind of revealing some
of the the kind of deep experiences that
some of us uh had um that you know
others didn't really know about. So to
me that's like an experience that I I
I'll never forget is is kind of that
twoe trek and especially that night in
particular where we really got to open
up and and share you know who we really
are and what what makes us unique and
how we think about the world and all
that good stuff.
>> Yeah. Can I cheat and give you two? They
were they were back to back. So like I
think one experience one experience that
I really Okay. One experience I really
valued was actually the Saudi Arabia
trek. So this was like something that
one of our classmates happened to be
related to the crown prince. And so he
hooked so he hooked us up with like a
10-day trek where we got to go to Saudi.
We got to actually go to Riad, go to
Jedha, go to um Alula and then also
visit Saudi Aramco. I think it was one
of those things where like I had always
read about Saudi Arabia and this isn't
some plug for Saudi Arabia endorsement,
but like it was more just like an an
experience that I don't think I would
have ever gotten to have um if not for
Sloan. And then I think after that um
and also getting to know our classmates
like on a way deeper level while there
like the people who were there and just
like having like random conversations
with people who I'd seen in the
cafeteria but never really talked to got
to know their story and got to
understand kind of who they are and what
kind of makes them. And I'd say another
thing was um one of my favorite
experiences at Sloan was Gab which is uh
the global entrepreneurship lab and it's
a class where you get to in the during
the semester you get to work with a
company that's international. My company
was based actually out of Nigeria but
they operated in Ghana and were planning
on um um ext expanding to Togo and Benin
and so we got to work with them directly
on you know their strategy and their
expansion strategy and then not only
that but because Sloan is all about
experiential learning we actually got to
go to Ghana Togo and Benin and over like
a month it was I think it was like three
weeks we got to go and actually go on
the ground in Togo and Benine and speak
to people on the ground and understand
their stories and help like help this
company not only you know expand
globally but also to understand like how
their markets are different and I think
it was one of those things where it's
like I'll I'll never it's an experience
I'll never you know leave my mind
because not only was I working with four
other people who I got to know really
well but also you know getting to hear
the stories of people from Togo and
using Google translate because I don't
speak French and Togo and Ben are
French-speaking countries and like get
but still hearing their stories and
hearing the why behind the things that
they do I think that was just an
incredible experience and something that
really value and something I take with
me on a daily basis.
>> Yeah. So, um mine mine are are two
trips. I think as um Elon mentioned, MBA
is all about go going on trips and going
on track. So, I got a chance to take a
trip with the with my classmates just to
take them to the continent. So we went
to na Nigeria and we also went to Ghana.
And
that trip for me was was kind of a
lifecher for for me because it really
gave me a chance to see Nigeria from my
classmates eyes and Ghana as well. And
that really opened up my eyes to some of
the, you know, being from there, there's
a lot of things you take for granted,
but just having your classmates there
and the fact that they can literally ask
you anything was great because it now
got got us to get to know know each
other at a much much deeper level. I'm
so very in touch with with all all of my
classmates that we went on that track
with. That that was a really good
experience. And I think the other one
would be at the end of Sloan, you you
get to take a trip down to um the
British Virgin Islands, the B BBI trip.
That was an amazing ex experience
because you're done with school and
you're now about to face real life and
properly graduate. But it's kind of a
pause in that because you get a chance
to really just relax and really enjoy
yourself and and savor the moment of
being done with school, but also knowing
that you're connecting with people that
you're going to be friends with for the
rest of your life. So I think for me
that experience was really good at at
the end. Karen,
>> yeah, I would say Gab as well was one of
my favorite experiences. I lived in
Kenya with um four amazing classmates
that we are still like such good friends
and I don't know when else I'll get to
live in a country for a month and work
on a really unique project. Um and then
also I would just say like I know
there's a lot of emphasis on trips but
also just like the small like dinners
that I would have in my apartment or
like the kickbacks with the Harvard
community. Like I just feel like the
small things also were what was really
fun. And I don't think there are like
opportunities unless you're planning it
out like 3 months in advance with
friends now that you can just be like,
"Hey, come over and like let's have
dinner and like watch Love Island." Um I
wish I had that now to be able to like
chill with my Sloan friends and like
just do the little things. Um and so
like definitely like index on that as
well. Um because I know the trips get
really really expensive. Um but also do
the trips because I miss that as well.
But yeah, the little things matter as
well.
>> Can you guys hear me?
>> It like cut out and now I can hear.
>> Okay, really quick. We have about like 5
minutes left and we have two more
questions. First, um, whoever wants to
respond, but how has Sloan impacted your
leadership capabilities?
>> I can go. I would say now um I like
started at Meta a few months ago and I
work with um really like high performing
people and um I think something that
Sloan really helped me to do is that
like one being able to like communicate
really well thinking about like the
strategic picture of things and being
able to break that down. Um I think also
just like being confident um to like
speak in a meeting. um you don't realize
like sometimes um in like your strategy
classes with Donsol when you're cold
called you're like sweating in your seat
but those are like moments that really I
think prepare you for your professional
career um so I think those are like
skills that are like really important as
a leader and then I also think um like
most importantly is like being able to
work with people and so I work with like
a variety of different like crossf
functional stakeholders and I think
Sloan really set me up really well in
working with a variety of different
people from all cultures and usually um
most classes, you know, you're given a
problem to work on in in a small group.
Um and I feel like that's a simulation
to like what my real life is now on a
day-to-day basis is I'm working on
really complex problems with like
variety of people from all over the
world. Um, and so I feel like Sloan
really set me up um to really think
strategically about things. Even like
the little things of like how do you
like create documents and meeting notes
and whatnot. I think like those are all
like really important skills that you
don't realize you're building um in the
classroom but are really important for
your future work.
>> Thanks.
Yeah, I'm I'm in my current role um
which is like very much like operations
like global operations strategy like I
support um about 10 different
manufacturing sites and some of my key
stakeholders. There's like four
different general managers, four
different VPs of operations as well as
kind of in my function I have my own
management and their own priorities. So
there's lots of different stakeholders,
all of whom are much more well paid than
I am and have a much are much more
opinionated on what things should and
shouldn't be done.
>> Um, and oftentimes they don't see eye to
eye on different things. So, it's
organizational processes is one of the
classes that I'm like leveraging all the
time of
>> how do I navigate through all of these
big stakeholders, none of whom I have
any responsibility over to try and get
us all on the same page and
understanding who cares about what and
how can I get certain people to be on my
team so they can influence somebody
else. and all of those kind of chess
chess games is is something that I
really learned at Sloan um and I'm
leveraging literally every day um in in
my current role.
>> For sure. OP continues to be brought up.
>> Um with our last couple minutes,
um if people if any of you guys could
touch on any tips for black applicants
right now, how they should approach this
loan application.
and highlight sorry and highlight their
community, their involvement and and
just like who they
>> Yeah, I was going to say like first and
foremost be authentically you like I
think one thing that you know and maybe
Terrell can speak to this better than I
can because obviously I don't work for
Sloan but like you know in my
application I and in my video interview
the the video you have to do like be
yourself in the video like talk about
the things that you care about and
things that matter to you and don't be
afraid to hide any of that, right? Like
I know the current environments is what
it is, but like I still think you, you
know, Sloan is looking for people who
are really, you know, are themselves,
authentically themselves, and who have a
mission to, you know, impact the world
in a positive way. Um, I think another
thing when it comes to the application
process is don't only touch on, you
know, what you want to do at Sloan, but
like be get granular like talk about the
specifics you want to do at Sloan,
right? like do you want to if you want
to become a product manager, what does
that look like? Which classes do you
want to take? Who do which professors do
you want to hear from? What experiences
do you want to have in order to make
that happen? And marry how you are
today? What Sloan will give you? And
then and marry that to where you want to
go in the in the future. So, like I
said, be authentically you. If you're a
black person, don't be afraid to be a
black person in the application. You
don't have to fit some box that, you
know, checks every box that looks like
some other applicant. just be yourself
because ultimately I think that's what
salon's looking for and they want you
for you and I think that was something
that I kind of struggled with in the
application process but ultimately came
to realize that you know as uh after I
you know while I was there and after I
graduated so that' be the advice I'd
give blackies or black applicants.
>> Yeah. And I think for me it would be
around and ensuring that you tell your
full story. A lot of people kind of hold
things back because they don't want to
put it out there. It's not your that
makes your entire story makes who makes
you who you are. So go out there, put
things out there that could be
uncomfortable, but but go ahead and
explain how how everything kind of joins
up. And I think finally, you have to
kind of show why Sloan is important to
you and how it's going to bridge a gap
to where you're trying to get get to. So
if you say, "Hey, I want I I work in
finance and I want to get into
consulting, that's great, but why do you
want to get into consulting?" Paint that
picture and ensure that it that the
story ties together. A lot of the people
that I've talked to who want to go to
business school, they're not quite able
to tie the story together. And my advice
is wait and ensure the story ties
together because even if they let you
in, you don't know why you're there.
You're just going to go there and you
you'll be more frustrated than anything
else. So ensure that you you you have
that northstar and then also ensure that
you know that you in your application
you show why the Sloan degree is very
important to get into your northstar.