Hello, everyone, and welcome
to the 2024 Gardner lecture.
I'm Julie Shah.
I'm the department
head here at AeroAstro.
This Gardner lecture
is made possible
by the bequest of the
late major Lester D.
Gardner, a member of
the MIT class of 1898
to sponsor annual presentations
on aeronautical history.
An officer in World
War I, Major Gardner
was the recipient of
numerous aeronautical awards,
including the Daniel
Guggenheim Medal in 1947,
given for outstanding
achievement
in advancing aeronautics.
He had a long and storied career
establishing a publishing group
responsible for four
aeronautical trade
publications, including the
predecessor of Aviation Week.
He was also a founder
of the Institute
of aeronautical sciences,
which would eventually
evolve into today's AIAA.
Major Gardner's interest
in MIT and our department
continued throughout
his life and lives
on not only in the memory
of the Gardner lectureship,
but also the Hunsaker
professorship,
which he helped to establish.
Over the years, our
Gardner lecturers
have included Grover Loaning,
Igor Sikorsky, Yvonne Brill,
Neil Armstrong,
Robert Stevens, Jr.,
Gwen Shotwell, John Langford,
and Pam Melroy, to name a few.
This year, we are honored and
excited to welcome four speakers
to deliver the Gardner lecture.
These are four
core 16 alumni, who
have gone on to become leaders
and innovators in their field.
Together, they decided
to give a joint lecture
on a very specific topic,
which they are calling aviation
in the age of John Hansman.
Our John Hansman, Jr., is the
Wilson Professor of Aeronautics
and Astronautics.
He directs the International
Center for Air Transportation,
as well as the laboratory for
aviation and the environment.
Over the course of his
40-plus year career,
John has contributed to the
field of aviation in a myriad
of ways, through research and
technical papers, new patents,
and novel approaches.
But perhaps his greatest
contribution to the field
has been through his mentorship
of entire generations
of academic and
industry leaders.
Our Gardener lecturers
wanted to give us
a sense of John's tremendous
sphere of influence,
his impact on modern
aeronautical history
through their own expertise.
So a few words about
our speakers before I
turn it over to them.
Amy Pritchett is the Department
head of aerospace engineering
at Penn State University.
Her research focuses
on the interaction
of technology, humans,
and safety in dynamic time
critical and safety
critical environments,
including human-robot
interaction and space
exploration, human
autonomy, teeming
and aviation, novel flight deck
designs and manual control.
Craig Wenke is a chief engineer
for the Miter Corporation's
Center for Advanced
Aviation Systems Development
and editor-in-chief of the
Journal of Air Transportation.
Among his
accomplishments include
leading the development,
field testing, and technology
transfer of several
capabilities now deployed
as a part of the FAA's
operational traffic flow
management system.
He is an AIAA fellow.
John Paul Clark is a professor
of aerospace engineering
and engineering mechanics
at the University
of Texas at Austin, where
he holds the Ernest Cockrell
junior memorial
chair in engineering.
He's an expert in
the development
of the use of stochastic models
and optimization algorithms
to improve the efficiency and
robustness of complex systems
with a particular
focus on aviation.
And Brian Yutko is the
chief executive officer
of Wisk Aero, a leader in the
advanced air mobility market.
His focus is on electric
and autonomous aviation.
Prior to joining Wisk, Brian
served in numerous leadership
roles at Boeing and
Aurora Flight Sciences,
managing various rapid
prototyping and autonomous
technology development programs.
Thank you very much.
And with that, I'll
turn it over to Amy.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you, Julie, and thank you
to the Department of AeroAstro.
It is a pleasure to be
back and have a chance
to give this storied lecture.
Indeed, I have to
multitask, and I
have 15 minutes
to do it in that I
want to reflect the spirit
of the Gardner lecture
with a historical perspective.
I would like to stay technical,
as my former advisor taught
me to do, and focus on the
important technical aspects
in aviation safety.
And in doing so,
I think we'll see
that there is a common theme to
the presentation, a name that
keeps recurring in
what I will reflect on
as major achievements
in aviation safety.
So with this quick historical
perspective, looking back
to 1959, looking at the accident
record of jet air transport
aircraft, the numbers have now--
safety is hard to define.
We don't measure safety.
We measure the
opposite, accidents.
And the accident rate has
gone down to the point
that I think we can
argue the Civil Air
transportation in
the Western world
is the safest system ever,
definitely the safest
transportation system.
But right now, I'm ready to
take on nuclear power as well.
But to achieve this, to achieve
the level of safety that
is reflected with such a
profound reduction in accident
rates, requires several
different approaches.
And the historic approach was to
focus on single point failures,
make certain that you didn't
have some unwitting accident.
And looking back
through aviation safety,
we have those flashbulb
moments, those accidents
that we in the discipline
remember profoundly
and that the entire
industry used
to drive our new
insights as they
reflected what was going wrong.
For me, perhaps the first
snap bulb industry--
and one that's really important
to this more modern age--
was United flight
232 in July of 1989,
where the fan disk
in engine number two,
which was mounted in the tail,
right above where the three
hydraulic lines all joined
together, needed to power
the control surfaces.
Well, the fan disk blew.
And while there were many things
leading up to the fan disk
blowing apart and blowing
through the hydraulic lines,
it in the end highlighted
that at that instant,
in flight, given you
had a fan disk that
had design and maintenance
issues that in flight, we
had a single point failure.
Now, I particularly
recall this because I
was a freshman in what was then
called the MIT Aeronautical
Systems Lab.
We gathered around this
thing called the TV
and watched live
news to watch it.
And the McDonnell Douglas
engineer who was briefing CNN
was holding a schematic and
pointing everything out.
And his Brass Rat
was going up and down
in front of the national
news as he described
just how we had
gotten to the point
that one single failure could
make an airplane-- well,
at the time, they said it should
have been considered unflyable.
The second lesson that we
learned that day is that we,
in many cases, safety ends up
being a factor also of people
being able to come together
and work together in new ways,
for Denny Fitch to run back from
his passenger seat and be able
to work the throttles while the
crew already in the flight deck
flew around a while, learning
to fly the airplane only with
differential thrust and elevator
trim to the point that they had
something roughly approximating
a landing and something where we
would have expected
everyone to not survive,
to instead have 2/3
of the people survive.
And this accident, we look
back then on both lessons,
the single point
failure, but also
the role in the crew
on figuring things out.
Now we'll go forward
a little bit more--
1995, the Cali accident.
An American Airlines 757
was en route from Miami,
descending down
to land into Cali.
It's a tricky approach.
You can see on the
left the terrain
where you would have to
descend down into the valley
to line up on the final approach
to the land roughly to the south
here.
And unfortunately, the
autoflight system tried to--
apparently thought it
could fly through granite.
There was no terrain information
available to the pilots.
And as I will talk
about a bit more later,
there's also a
question of just what
was available to the
pilot for interpreting
where their autoflight system
was going to take them.
Now, this accident was in 1995,
and one of the principal things
that was called out was the lack
of terrain situational awareness
for the pilots--
1995 accident.
1993 study by
Koocher and Hansman
looking at terrain
situational awareness,
developing those
fundamental insights needed
for Don Boutwell at
Honeywell and others
to really develop the enhanced
ground proximity warning
system so that as the industry
recovered from this accident,
they were able to say, but
there is a technical solution
that we can implement.
So it was this
study in building 37
in a part task simulator cobbled
together with IRIX machines
that I view as one of those key
moments around the industry,
looking at what is
possible in 1993
and being positioned when we
actually had the accident in '95
to step in and to say
we have solutions.
And with this, here's the
data on jet aircraft accidents
for the period
1991 through 2000.
It's divided, each
bar representing
a different category
of the major descriptor
of the type of accident.
In this case, look at the
two big bars that we had
in the 1990s.
The leading types of accidents,
loss of control and next to it
CFIT, Controlled
Flight Into Terrain.
And the Cali accident
is a major part
of that big bar
of the fatalities
that we were seeing
because pilots
couldn't tell where the airplane
was going relative to terrain.
Let's skim forward to the most
recent set of data that I have,
2013 to 2022.
Can you find CFIT on there?
It's down there.
It's down in the noise.
It's one of those small bars.
And so we can see cases
where some of these advances,
we can point to as having
such profound impact,
like the enhanced ground
proximity warning system.
That's the good news.
The bad news is that how do you
make a system safer than this?
How do you address the more
complex and interrelated
accidents?
For this, I would
put out that you
have to do many things
all at the same time.
As engineers, we
normally start by looking
at the single point
failures, so the reliability
and redundancy, the fault tree.
And this is necessary
but is not sufficient.
Then we look at creating
multiple layers of defense,
robustness, and these
layers of defense
can include pilot training
and procedures and maintenance
and making certain that the
pilot doesn't have the fan disk
blow apart in the first place--
necessary, but again,
not sufficient.
And finally, we
find that we have
to also look at how we
control the situation.
And the levels of control again
are operational control, traffic
flow management, so you don't
have a pile up of airplanes
in the same sector.
Specifically
important is how do we
control the situation right
at the point of the incident,
of the problem--
the pointy end of the stick.
Now there's multiple
layers of control.
But hey, it's always fun to talk
about autonomy and autoflight
and to talk about how control
automation shaped the flight
deck.
So here is a picture
of an aircraft design
and first flown in 1969.
You can see that there's four
throttles, four stacks of engine
instruments, and there's even
a flight engineer over here,
a third pilot in the cockpit.
So I hope you can guess if
you're in this auditorium what
airplane this was.
And here was the redo, the
model 400 from the 1990s.
It still has the same
flight instruments,
but now they're shown
on a glass cockpit.
It still has the four engines,
but all the engine instruments
are shown again on
the glass screen.
And instead of having a flight
engineer, a third pilot,
we have reduced the pilots from
three being standard to two.
What the flight engineer used
to do is now start and stop.
The full authority
digital engine controller
is a full authority controller.
There are things that we
have successfully automated,
but there are other
things like where
do we want the airplane
to go that are very hard.
And for this, I will return
back to the Cali accident.
And with the Cali
accident, this is a picture
in the lower right here is
from the control display
unit recreated by the
NTSB from the NTSB report.
Why did the airplane try
to fly through a mountain?
Well, the airplane logic was
suggesting go to waypoint R
and then join the route
into land at Cali.
And the pilots had very
poor understanding.
What does this mean?
Should I have even gone to
point R in the first place?
And the answer is no.
And so here now,
we're also starting
to think not just about
the single technology,
but how do we get the
parts to work together?
How do we get--
particularly close
to my own heart--
how do we get the pilot
and the technology
actually working
together better?
And again, we can point to some
things in this time in the 1990s
where Eric Johnson and I met
each other by doing a class
project for Tom Sheridan
and John Hansman,
where we proved that in
the building 37 simulator,
it was pretty easy for me to put
the captains in what would be
an innocent mistake into a steep
descent into terrain and most
of them to not detect it until
it was too late to pull up.
And on the right, I'll show
the vertical profile display,
recognizing Sanjay Vakil,
Alan Midkiff, and John Hansman
here that emphasizes
not just where are you
in space and time in
a vertical profile,
but where is the autoflight
system going to take you
with the way it's programmed
right now, a display that I
think we can now
pretty much point to
in the A380 787 and other
subsequent aircraft?
So with this, we're working on
many new questions about how
human-machine interact.
We haven't answered them yet.
Aviation, I think of as
the leader in aviation
in human factors, and for this,
I point out that in 1951, it
was in a National Academy
study chaired by Paul Fitts
looking at effective
air navigation that
posted this model, a model
I wish that could be burned
at the stake and
tortured for its value
that it doesn't have called
"the men are better at.
Machines are better at."
And I mind not just
the gender language,
but the fact that it doesn't
understand that the two of them
need to interact and it
doesn't understand something
fundamental about who ultimately
controls the situation.
For that, I think we should go
back to the Federal Aviation
regulations.
Who controls the situation?
The pilot in command
of an aircraft
is directly
responsible for and is
the final authority as to the
operation of that aircraft.
And what does that mean?
It means that as
the captain, you
engage the autoflight system.
What do you do?
There's a 1996
Simpsons episode that
says once you engage
this navitron system,
all you have to do is sit
back and feel your ass grow.
We're not recording this.
I'm just quoting The Simpsons.
But no, as the pilot--
the pilot in command--
you now have to sit
there and monitor it.
How often do you
need to monitor it?
As fast as it can screw up.
For an autopilot,
that's pretty fast.
And then you need
to figure out when
to intervene and to intervene
before it is critical.
And this is not easy.
Now that I'm a
department head, I
can assure you monitoring and
supervising and intervening
is harder than just
doing the task yourself.
And yet this is the task that
we are putting pilots into.
Let's put them
into a tough spot.
We say that their role
is shifted to monitoring.
And yet there were
brilliant things said before
in that 1951 report.
The mamba mamba list was
embraced by the controls
and autonomy engineers.
Yeah, I can get my machines to
do these-- these new things.
And it's commonly cited.
Rarely cited is what's
on the next page.
In 1951, they took the
position that human operators
are poor monitors when
all they have to do
is watch the performance
of automatic equipment.
And so with this, we are at
a very interesting time where
we are seeing public-private
partnerships in aviation safety,
broad discussions throughout
the industry, talking about,
wow, what do we need
to do differently?
Not just focusing on one
system or one technology,
but looking at broad
operational principles.
And so now moving
forward to 2013,
the safety alert for
operators was actually
recommending that we have
pilots fly more often,
maintain not just the
manual control skills,
but we're now finding that you
need those same manual control
skills also to have the mental
skills, the knowledge, the task
ability to monitor
in the first place
and detect when something
is not going right.
Finally, bringing this
up to the very latest
stage, pointing out
some things again,
from the National Academies
that we're working on.
We find that the same
names keep popping up
in these national
level committees that
are coming together to look at
the current state of aviation
safety.
In our overall review of the
aviation industry's ability
to identify safety
issues, our summary
is that there are many ways that
we are monitoring air transport
safety right now as based on
the tube and wing aircraft that
are flying the
operational models that we
have at this point.
They span from
single organizations
to industry-wide teams, like the
commercial aviation safety team.
They span deep dives
on particular hazards
to things they're
monitoring systemwide.
And in this, we now have
the mechanisms in place
to be jumping on
any immediate issue.
And extrapolating
forward, what do we think
are the intermediate potential
near-term evolution issues?
But the predictive
is kind of hidden
a little on the Rubik's cube.
It's a little hidden
off on the right.
Predictive-- how do we predict
the safety of something
that's never flown?
Some new AAM vehicle
that's brought in
or V/STOL aircraft flying with
a very different business model,
very different traffic density,
and traffic operations.
For this, we need new
methods and new time frames.
And this is in the face of
all the amazing things that
are happening in
aviation right now.
Each of these things,
we can look at going,
wow, we can do new
business models.
We can have
transportation that gets
above the gridlock
of Mass Ave. We
can have new technologies that
are so much more efficient.
We can help with
sustainability and climate,
but at the same point
we also then say,
and how do we predict the safety
impact to maintain the safety
level for things
that we don't have
that same weight
of knowledge for?
An interesting time,
if I had an answer,
this would have been
a different talk.
But as it is, I'm
just saying this
is where we are now with big
questions left to be answered.
And so I thank you,
and I offer apologies
to similar important
technical advances
in addressing aviation
safety, including
icing, wind shear, collision
avoidance, and detection
and so forth.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
Hello, that was a great setup.
OK, I'm Craig Wenke, and I'm
going to talk about air traffic
systems.
There's a little
bit of obviously
the relationship
to safety is there.
I'm going to say a
little bit about myself
and that it's relevant
to this, which
is I was here at MIT for
10 years roughly, mostly
working with John
during that time.
I took that
experience to my work
at Miter, where
we operate what's
called a federally funded
research and Development
Center for the FAA,
which is where I've
spent all of the last 31 years.
And along that time, I spent a
lot of time working with AIAA as
well, as I'm sure
you do, and I'll
get to why that's
important later on.
I wanted to go back to when
I was preparing this talk.
I wanted to go back to
see some of the things
that we did in
graduate school, and I
had to go find a paper that
had a figure that would reflect
what we worked on.
That figure was glued together
with glue sticks and pasted up
to be photographed for a paper.
But one of the
accidents that Amie
didn't talk about that
were kind of in the news
when we were in
grad school, were
wind shear related accidents.
And there had been a couple
of them, notable one,
the Eastern accident,
where the airplane was
lost because it flew through a
downburst from a thunderstorm.
And so systems were being
developed to alleviate this.
And you see the terminal doppler
weather radar on the lower left
and other systems
like the low level
wind shear avoidance
system on the right.
And the question
was, how would we
use these systems to
stop these accidents?
You'll notice no accidents
have happened since then.
I can't tie it
directly to this work,
although the TDWR has
something to do with it.
But in the process of what
my work was around, how would
you design a system to detect,
synthesize data, and alert
the pilot of these things?
And in so doing, it
formed everything
I needed to go forth
in a career and looking
at human decision support
in the context of aviation.
And that's going to be
the theme of this talk.
So human-centered design
is one of those things.
Something else I
wanted to mention
for those of you who are in
this stage of your career.
The other thing that John taught
me that was super important
was that publishing is a
way to actually execute
on your entire plan because
you submit abstracts
for things you haven't done yet,
and then you have a deadline.
And you're not being
fearless enough
if you never withdraw a paper.
So it's OK to occasionally
withdraw a paper.
And finally, aviation is
all about weather, also
terrain, but also but
also all about weather.
And as I went on to
my career in working
in the national-- on the
National Airspace System,
I really began to appreciate all
the ways in which that is true.
Now, one of the things that
I found as soon as I left MIT
was that I was now
at a company that
was supporting the entire
development of the National
Airspace System.
And I lamented the
fact that the one
course I never took in aviation
at MIT was air traffic control.
So I had to learn all of that.
This is a diagram
of all the systems
that make up the US Air
Traffic Control system.
And it's an imposing system.
So you can see
the numbers there.
I'm not going to
go through them.
And it's run by a team of
14,000 air traffic controllers
and a number of other folks
that handle the other functions,
the traffic
management functions,
and so on and so forth.
And so anything that
is introduced to this
really needs to be
carefully considered.
Safety is the
number one priority.
And as Amy noted, the current
safety record is excellent.
And so everything that
needs to be introduced
has to be compared to that
record, which I'm sure Brian
will probably get into later.
So over the 31 years since
I graduated, a lot of things
have happened in this system.
There's something called
the Next Generation Air
Transportation
System was deployed.
And this revamped all of the
primary automation systems.
There's a lot of jokes
back in the day about
how the FAA ran systems
on vacuum tubes.
To my knowledge, there
are no more of those.
I'm not entirely sure.
There may be in Alaska
some weather systems that
have vacuum tubes in them,
but for the most part,
the system has been deployed.
And we move a lot more
people and freight today
than we did back
when I graduated.
And the delays are
generally not worse,
which tells you what's working.
So that's the state of the art
over the course of that time.
And where much of my work was is
that the science of air traffic
flow management has
changed radically.
Back in the day, 31 years ago,
the FAA controlled everything.
Now there's a collaborative
decision-making process
where the airlines and the
DOD and other operators
take part in the
management of the system.
And that's been a major advance.
Weather forecasts have improved.
Traffic management
tools have improved.
And so our ability
to do more than just
keep aircraft from
hitting each other,
but rather to make the
whole system more efficient
has improved.
And we've gone to
something called
trajectory-based operations.
And what this means
in practicality
is that when things get
incredibly dense at an airport,
we can manage the flow
by time of arrival.
And because of the deployment
of GPS and other precision
navigation systems,
aircraft are much better
at following those
things, provided
that the pilots are
interacting with the system
and not just watching it happen
and it was just talking about.
So just briefly, you guys
probably already know this,
but I didn't know it
when I left MIT, so I
figured I would put it in here.
Air traffic control
is what people
know is controllers
separating airplanes.
It's a fairly exact science.
It's well defined.
There are tools that have been
deployed over the past 31 years.
But fundamentally, it's not that
different than it was back then.
A traffic management
where you're
looking out, say, 30
minutes to 24 hours
to plan against things that
are probably going to happen
is something that has been
evolving quite radically
over that time.
And it involves many,
many stakeholders.
It's a bit of an art.
And honestly, there are a lot of
still unsolved problems in this.
And so that's where I'm
going to spend a good bit
of the time in this lecture.
So to get back to weather,
aviation weather forecasting
is challenging.
It's one thing to know if
you're going to hold a picnic,
that it's the 30% chance
of rain this afternoon.
You need much, much
more precise weather
to do anything with aviation.
You need to know whether
a particular routes will
be closed, whether
airports will be closed
or will be impacted
by low visibility.
This is an example
of the absolute state
of the art in long range
thunderstorm forecasting.
Each of those areas, which
are hundreds of miles long,
tell you that there's
maybe a certain likelihood
of thunderstorms happening and
what the likely tops of those
would be.
Planning to this is not
trivial, nor is it precise.
And so the essence of the
modern system is flexibility.
You have a lot of
tools to manage flows.
And so the challenge
is how do you
react to something like this?
Under 90 minutes, we can
watch thunderstorms move,
and we have a
pretty good chance.
So I'm going to talk about are
some of the tools that I've
been involved with developing
and applied my lessons that I
learned here at MIT to
help develop and deploy
and some things that
we haven't solved yet.
So one of the first
things I got involved
with when I left here
was in trying to support
this collaborative
decision-making process
by giving traffic managers
what you would think
would be a very simple thing.
There's weather.
We have a pretty good idea
of where it's going to be.
How do we know which airplanes
are going to encounter it,
and what do we do about it?
So again, simple problem.
They had no way to do this.
You were doing this
incredibly manually.
And so all of this--
all of this did.
We actually pulled a trailer
out at one of the centers
and put a bunch of
computers in it.
And we let traffic managers
come out and play with it,
looking at the real data and
do some tests to get back
to human-centered design
and come up with a system
where you could draw
a polygon or a line,
and you could add a
bunch of filters to it.
And it could move.
And what it would
fundamentally give you
in the middle of
the screen, there
is a list of which
flights were involved
and how many were encountering
it as a function of time.
And what we found was if you
give them something like this
and it was deployed in what was
then called the enhanced traffic
management system, they would
find a million ways to use it.
And so this tool actually is
the basis of a lot of the things
that caused your pilot to
say while you're sitting
on the runway in and
perfectly clear weather,
we can't leave because
of air traffic control.
That's actually a good
thing, believe it or not.
But there are things called
airspace flow programs that
keep us from overloading sector
controllers near these weather
areas and a whole host of other
what we call traffic management
initiatives that are planned
by the use of these things.
And one of the things
I learned from this
was that if you give
people a flexible tool,
they will find all
kinds of innovative ways
to use it that you probably
didn't even [INAUDIBLE].
But the most important thing
about giving any kind of tool
to people who have essentially
a full slate of work
on their plate, that the first
thing it has to do is save time.
And that's what
computers are good at.
Have the computer do the
things that are drudgery,
the things that are
difficult, and then
but have it be an interactive
part of the process.
And this was a great
example of that.
The next thing we tried
to do was say, OK,
let's say you take some action.
To move aircraft
around that weather.
What's the impact
of that going to be?
This proved to be
a much harder thing
to get designed appropriately
and for them to do so.
On the left there,
you see a case
where something called
a national playbook
play is being evaluated.
That's a predefined
set of routes
that get around weather
in certain places.
And there is a whole virtual
online book of those.
You can actually
look it up yourself
if you go to the NOAA
status page on the web.
But in this case, it's
going to move possibly
hundreds of airplanes.
And the question is, what
will that do to the system?
And so on the right
is a system that
was deployed that
allows you to test that,
and it tells you how many
airplanes you're moving
from one place to another.
Without getting
into detail, this
is a tool for
determining whether you
have the right staffing
in place to handle this.
From the time that this
was developed to the time
that it was deployed
was 17 years,
which is on the long side.
Typical I think the average
time to deploy a new feature
to the NAS is about 10.
But this is what
happens when you're
working with a system that
has to work all the time.
And it's an argument I get into
with my military colleagues
all the time on the
other side of miter where
they can deploy something
in two or three years.
And the difference is ours
have to work all the time.
A military system can
work 95% of the time
and still be acceptable and
still give you an advantage.
And that's a huge
difference when you're
working in an air traffic.
The next step beyond this was
to start thinking about systems
that suggest solutions.
And this is an example
of one that we worked on,
and it employed some
NASA ideas as well.
But basically, the
idea would be instead
of having to
develop those routes
and do what-if examples to test
them and so forth, you could
actually identify for each
aircraft involved, what would be
a reasonably optimal route to
get around a weather situation,
coordinate it.
And then one of the big
problems with rerouting
is you have to collaborate
amongst facilities.
And so this would automate
that coordination.
Again, we did a bunch of
human in the loop testing
and worked through it until
they were satisfied with it
and thought it would work.
It was put into the
deployment pipeline,
and then the funding dried up.
But it is a possible
thing to do.
It's still potentially
on the list,
so maybe someday we'll
see something like this.
But to date, we don't move
aircraft one at a time.
We move them in giant groups.
So that's still the
state of the art.
And the last system I
wanted to talk about
was the problem
of strategic TFM.
The stuff that I was
talking about before,
you saw pictures of weather.
That means we had either
weather radar returns on there
or we had short-term predictions
where you could actually
draw essentially
where you thought
the weather was going to move.
But strategic TFM uses
that initial weather
picture that I saw,
which is that I have
a vague idea of where
the problem is going
to be 12 hours from now, six
hours from now, whatever it is.
And I have a bunch
of aircraft that
are going to take off and maybe
spend five hours in the air.
What do I want to do?
And there's a couple of
problems with this situation.
Number one, typically, when
humans are solving a problem,
they rely on past experience.
You never get the same weather
day twice in the past, really.
And so it's very hard to learn.
The other is you have a bunch
of stakeholders involved
that have different objectives.
The FAA folks want to
protect their controllers
so that they continue to
safely handle the aircraft.
Airlines obviously want
to meet their schedule.
DOD wants to execute their
mission, so on and so forth.
And so it's not clear
what winning looks either.
So it makes it a hard
problem to solve.
So the way we do this today
is that every two hours, there
is a teleconference
where we argue about what
the right solution ought to be
and pick some set of solutions
out of an infinite design space
and then see how they work.
And then two hours
later, we go back
and have another argument
and work on the next thing.
And so for years
and years, we've
been trying to design systems
that would solve this problem.
You're looking at a picture
here of the Air Traffic Control
Command Center in Northern
Virginia, where this--
which is where they
coordinate this argument.
And the data that they
have is the weather
forecast that you saw and
some other weather forecasts.
They have counts of
traffic around the area.
And of course, they still use
those flow evaluation areas
that I showed back then to
look at what traffic is where.
But there aren't really any
diagnostic systems to do that.
So you can't have a talk
today about aviation
without AI coming
into it someplace.
So this is where
we're trying to apply
modern artificial intelligence
to solve that specific problem.
Past attempts to solve
this problem using
previous kinds of
technologies have generally
failed due to the same reason
that it's hard for humans
to solve this problem, which
is that it's very hard to draw
conclusions about what
worked in the past
because you don't really
have great data to work from.
Modern machine learning
systems, turns out,
can piece things
together pretty well
from a whole variety of
vaguely similar situations
and draw better conclusions.
And so for the
first time, we think
we've found something that
can help people navigate
this enormous design space.
And you just look at-- to give
an example of what these kinds
of problems are--
so I'm just going to
go to this, actually.
Look at a real example.
Here's a very simple air
traffic management example.
Something's happening, in this
case, in the Atlanta area.
And you might have low
ceilings at the airport.
They'll reduce the arrival rate.
You might have weather that's
occluding the fixes that
supply that traffic to it.
And if you go through
and say, well, I
could control with a ground
delay program, the arrival rate.
Over the next, say,
four to six hours,
I have a variety start and
end times hourly rates.
I can decide which
aircraft are in there.
I can put in trail
spacing restrictions on
or the time-based
metering on those fixes.
I can decide to
ground stop traffic
into Atlanta for a while.
If I just go through and
enumerate those possible design
choices, you rapidly
get into the billions,
trillions of options.
And they do this
today, and they just
make those decisions
based on their sort
of intuition and experience.
And then you take
that against the fact
that you have variation
in the weather.
And so we actually have
forecasts now that our ensemble
forecasts that they generate a
whole series of possible weather
outcomes.
The one we use for this
happens to generate 26.
And so the question is,
over all that possible range
of outcomes, what are the
best designs for solving
that problem?
And all the things
we've tried in the past,
we've actually been able
to solve it and come up
with reasonable solutions.
But the compute
times range in weeks,
which obviously [INAUDIBLE].
But AI, with using AI methods,
actually using a method that's--
that was tested
to play StarCraft,
we adapted it to
this, and it actually
it does find a reasonable
solution for that.
So there is some promise
that we can finally
bring some science to the
traffic management process.
And it's time because
the system is now
entering a period of
change that we haven't
seen over those 31 years.
Amy mentioned new aircraft,
standard commercial aircraft.
That's been the bulk of
the concern of the FAA
and the aviation community
for all of that time.
And that's really
beginning to change.
We have small UAS at the
low end of the spectrum,
small unmanned aircraft, Amazon
package delivery type things
and, so on and so forth.
That's a new operational design,
urban air mobility or aircraft,
such as Brian's
potentially going to talk
about, eVTOLs and air
taxi type things which
are potentially
revolutionary for short range
and for regional mobility.
The tempo of space launches,
you've probably noticed,
has gone--
it's gone up radically.
We're now launching
almost every day,
and every SpaceX launch is
a challenge to the airspace.
It blocks a bunch of
airspace and so on.
And so and at high
altitude, we're
potentially going to start
having supersonic aircraft that
behave quite differently
from traditional aircraft.
And so in the face
of this, if we're
going to maintain and
achieve the economic benefits
of these new types
of aviation, we
have to really improve the
way that we handle traffic.
And not only that, the
traditional FAA model
where we talk to all the
airplanes is no longer viable.
And so some of
these operations are
going to have to be handled by
private service providers that
will have to deconflict, for
example, these small package
delivery aircraft.
And the FAA is going to have
to be comfortable enough
with those operations to certify
them and say that that's OK,
that's safe enough.
So if you're looking for
problems to solve, on this slide
are lots and lots of
problems to solve--
a lot of great thesis topics.
And I'm sure John can tell you
which ones are most important--
so not the supersonic.
No, that's good.
So just back to
what I learned as I
tried to apply those lessons.
Human-centered design is hard.
Over the course of trying
to get things deployed
and understanding how they would
work in the National Airspace
System, we've gone through a
whole bunch of experiments,
some of which were inspired by
those original experiments we
did on that iRIS 2400, which I
found a video about it where it
said it could render dozens
of polygons several times
per second, which I
thought was excellent.
We have better
tools for that now.
But it's still a challenge.
A lot of times, you're
introducing a decision support
system because you want
people to essentially do
their job differently.
And they're only
going to look at it
and say, how can I do my current
job quickly, more easily,
so on and so forth?
That's a challenging problem.
Traffic management is
governed by uncertainty
in weather and demand
and so on and so forth.
And the science of
human machine teaming--
again, perfect segue has
come a long way since 1951,
but we still don't
understand it completely.
How do we work with
AI-supported systems in a way
where the human is
still maintaining
sort of central
command of the task
and the understanding
of the task,
but is doing it much
more efficiently?
And interestingly, it's
still all about weather,
and the weather is
getting noticeably worse.
The severity of
thunderstorms is increasing.
Incidents of turbulence is
increasing significantly.
Obviously, the world
is getting hotter.
Over those 31 years,
there have been
a couple of examples
of aircraft that
had to be recertified to take
off at higher temperatures
because we now
have higher takeoff
temperatures at some airports.
And that's not going to stop
changing unless we radically
improve our consciousness.
And I'm still having
adventures in publishing.
We still do the thing
with the abstracts,
but I now am an editor
in chief of a journal,
so I get to really
appreciate some of the things
that people are doing out there.
And those adventures
now have gone
to getting texts
that are written
by AI, which isn't as
useful in application,
I think, as some of the
ones we were just talking.
But in any case,
that's what I have.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
You're not going to walk
around because this.
How do you know that?
Hi, so my dad was a
priest, my late father.
And so he always said a sermon,
you have to have three things.
So I'm going to do three things
with three different stories.
So the fun thing I want to
talk about problems where
you can trace the impact--
have big impact on the world
in the environmental space.
Second thing I'm going to do
is going to show the lineage
or how it dated back
to work with John.
And the third, because
it's my nature,
I have to rip job John just a
little bit as it wouldn't be me
otherwise.
So I start with
this, which doesn't
seem like aerospace engineering,
where it takes a pebble
to make a pearl.
And the thing about the
pebble is a foreign body.
Well, for most of us,
that's our John Hansman.
I was just on my line.
I'm not saying he
is an irritant.
However, I do say that his
demand for critical thinking
has been the pebble that
has made many a pearl.
And forgive me for focusing
on only two of these pearls
or three of these pearls.
But those are closest
to me, so I can speak
most authoritively about them.
So the first pearl
is the work that's
been done on environmental
considerations in the approach
and landing.
And I still remember the day
when I got back from JPL,
and John said, what do
you want to do for your--
after I finish my
master's thesis,
which was on quantum receivers,
definitely not aerospace.
And John said, what
do you want to do?
And we started talking about
new R&R procedures and GPS
and what you could do with that.
And we started coming up with
a concept of using GPS and R&R
procedures to change the
way we operate airplanes
to reduce noise.
So this was some earlier work
done in the late '60s, early
'70s, but they didn't have the
kind of capabilities that we had
at the time, which
compared to these days,
even baby compared to
what we have these days.
But at that time, it
was state of the art.
And so the one thing that, in
addition to critical thinking,
was a holistic view
of the problem.
It wasn't just putting something
in a numerical simulation
and running it.
It was actually bringing the
human-centered design, which
both Amy and Craig spoke about.
And so we created
this tool called
Noisome, which was basically a
lot of algorithms in one side.
And then our partner simulator,
which you've heard about before,
and we had to--
I think we've reprogrammed
the autopilot.
And I think multiple times
for different projects,
but we were able to
do human in the loop
studies looking at
flight procedures.
And so instead of
having what you
have on the bottom right, which
is the standard air traffic
control procedure where you
level off and come in based leg
and turn on final
intercept from below,
we were able to
start the descent
from much higher altitude,
keeping that throttles.
And on the top
right, you can see
what resulted from our studies.
This is the arrival
into New York.
The left image is the one
for the current procedure.
The one on the right is
the one for the procedures
that we end up
designing for New York.
As you can see, the
contours are way smaller.
That said, we still
had that somebody,
that cavemen chiseling away.
Complaining about the noise.
So noise stayed with us forever.
And I'll get back to that when
I get to the third problem.
So after that work
with John and I did,
I end up-- when I joined the
faculty here, had a student
leading Wren, and
we took that work.
And then we did some
flight tests at Louisville
in 2000, 2002, and we developed
a very rigorous simulation
that we could actually model the
wind fields and all the aircraft
dynamics, and we're
able to actually predict
how far apart you needed those
airplanes so that they could
be at idle from the top of this
end, the center of the runway,
and not run into each other.
And we did this flight
test at Louisville.
And I got to tell you
that there is something
about doing numbers and trusting
them because the first night,
I wasn't there.
And we told them we need these
airplanes 15 miles apart.
And they called me before.
You're sure 15 miles?
It's like Leling says so.
I've looked over
the calculations.
We're going with 15 miles.
Trust me.
My fingers were crossed.
My toes were crossed.
Everything was crossed.
But it worked out.
And that experiment
basically showed--
and we had a bunch
of noise monitors
around how we
could significantly
reduce the noise contour.
Again, like we did in the
numerical studies in the lab--
so we moved from the lab to
prototype and field test.
But we also found
out that there were
incredible benefits in terms of
fuel savings and time savings.
So it went from more than
just noise now become
how do we design approach and
arrival procedures to deal
with the environment?
So following on this, when
I moved to Georgia Tech,
we did it with it-- basically
took that flight trial.
We made some improvements in
how we specify procedures,
and then we end up designing
the arrival procedure, which
everybody who has flown to
LA since 2007 has flown,
which basically is the river
arrival into Los Angeles.
And this one, we
had to actually then
going now beyond just the higher
fidelity simulations and all
the modeling, we
know how to do things
like if you're going to
change the procedure,
you have to make sure that
the pilot doesn't have
more than four or
five button pushes
because if you have them down on
the screen in their mode control
panel button pushing to
change the runway from 25
left to 25 right, you're going
to have some safety issues.
So we had to incorporate
all of these things.
And again, even though I
wasn't on the safety side,
like Amy was, the lessons that
we learned in ASO, now ICAP,
basically helped us
design this procedure.
And what you can see now
at the bottom right--
and I won't go into the details
of all this-- but besides,
we were able to meter this
traffic coming out from Arizona,
and we were able to
keep these airplanes
and optimize their speeds.
And the bottom left,
you will see basically
how we all the
simulations we did
to make sure that every aircraft
type could stay in VNAV mode
from top of descent all
the way to the runway.
And on the right,
you see the savings
that we're saving about $22
billion in benefits in 2018.
And this procedure has now
spread across the world.
So from that conversation
and a concept--
from lab to prototype
to the real world--
and it continues because
my student and his student,
John's grandchild and
his great grandchild,
went on to do work and
develop some [INAUDIBLE]
algorithms-- so actually
jointly set the spacing
and the sequences for arrivals.
And this can be
executed in Excel.
Again, making it simple.
So that's a pebble that's
turned into a pearl.
Another pebble that
turned into a pearl
is in surface operations.
And this was in 1999.
And there are a
couple of people who
are in the room here Hasnie
Idris, Llenas Anagnostakis,
John Amadio, et cetera, who
were involved in this project.
This was a departure
plan of project.
It was a blue sky.
Look at how do we change
surface operations.
And much of the work
there was actually
analyzing the operations at
Logan, at different airports
and seeing and also
looking at the reports
to see where were the biggest
sources of congestion,
what were the constraints.
And everybody would say,
well, gates and their runways.
But on the bottom
left was probably
one of the most
interesting results,
that the air traffic
controllers were themselves
a constraint because there is a
flow of aircraft on the surface,
but in the air
traffic control tower,
there's a flow of flight strips.
And when an air traffic
controller is overloaded,
they're going to say, wait, I'm
not going to give that command.
So the airplane might be ready,
but the air traffic controller
isn't.
So those two flows
have to be synchronized
if you want to have a
properly functioning system.
And we're doing stuff at
electronic flight strips,
et cetera, to try
to deal with that.
But we also saw some
other interesting results.
The middle one and the
bottom shows this behavior
which became swapping.
So when you push back two
airplanes at the same time,
it's a race to an intersection.
Any uncertainty
in the taxi speed
gets magnified because
if I get in front of you,
I have a minute or 45 seconds
at the very least ahead of you
before I take off.
So for years, we
couldn't figure out
how to accurately
predict taxi time.
That's swapping behavior
allowed us to actually
be able to [INAUDIBLE]
to actually figure out
how to better predict
the taxi times.
And then, of course,
on the bottom right,
you'll see that
there's non-linearity.
The more you push on the
aircraft and out in the system
is the more congestion, the more
delay and the longer the taxi
times.
And we actually saw some
interesting behavior,
[INAUDIBLE] and
Ferran, that actually
if throughput actually went
down, it didn't just stabilize.
But when you have
too many airplanes,
it's just total chaos.
And you have blockages, and
the throughput went down.
So this led to
the work that John
went on to do with Hamza
and Tom Reynolds et al
at the pushback rate
and got this picture
courtesy of Bill Latent
via Hamza of them at Logan.
Again, from concept, two field
trials where they actually
did regulate the
pushback rate to keep
the rate of the number of
planes that are taxiing out.
And you can see top right,
all the airplanes in green
piled up at Logan.
Bottom left, basically, you'll
see a much cleaner taxiway
and a shorter queue.
And you had significant savings
in both time and fuel burn,
et cetera, from that as well.
Now that continues because
now NASA is actually
doing a much larger
field trial and actually
implementation and daily
of ATD-2, where they're
doing a technology
demonstration, where they're
actually doing this rate
control for Charlotte
and a bunch of other airports.
And Tom and Hamza are
still involved basically
doing analysis and determining
on the bottom right, basically,
what the optimum
amount of buffer
that you could-- need to put in
there to determine the answer
to manage the uncertainty--
so again, from the concept
to the prototype to
basically real world,
from a pebble to the
pearl, so two pearls.
So let me talk about
the last pearl, which
doesn't have a direct
hand-to-hand trace,
but it has through
academic lineage.
And this is looking at eVTOLs
and urban air mobility,
and how do we deal with
environmental and noise
in particular, because turns out
that FAA person is still that--
Neanderthal, is still
there, still chiseling away,
complaining to the
FAA about noise.
It's tough.
So when you look at integrating
the cool new airplanes that John
Langford and Brian are
bringing to the world
into the urban environment,
there are lots of challenges.
Of course, noise is one.
There's safety.
There's availability of
takeoff and landing areas.
There's scalability of
the air traffic control.
And Craig talked about that.
And there there's also the
ground and communication
infrastructure.
All of these things exist.
But the one thing that
when you do the analysis
and you speak to people who are
in the industry is that noise
persists no matter
what the level is.
Even if it's just one eVTOL
or one aircraft flying
over your house, people
are still annoyed.
And then you have
multiple [INAUDIBLE]
annoying more and more people.
By the way, I do want to invent
a new sport for the Olympics
called drone shooting.
And you should have one set
of programmers programming
the drone to avoid the shots
and another one program
it to be a great-- have
offense and defense.
So you heard it here on that.
So one of the things
that my postdoc and some
of my students and I have been
working on and also colleagues
at UT is basically
looking at a holistic
again, back to that
holistic viewpoint
that we were all taught
by John and looking
at how do we manage noise.
But we also have to think
about how do we manage energy.
And how do we also make sure
that we fulfill the demand
that we have?
And so we came up with
this network flow problem
where we're looking
at Austin, Texas,
because we know a
lot about Austin.
And we're right there.
And we created basically
three air routes
that basically mask
or over highways
or cut across neighborhoods
where you have
significant industrial areas.
Or you had differences that
sometimes it's easy to fly over.
Other times, it's not.
And then we looked
and said, how do we
optimize all of these
jointly for noise, energy,
and for package delivery?
And we can limit the operations.
If you can fly,
you're going to limit.
Or you can go to
a higher altitude.
It's going to cost
you more energy.
Or you can fly along
routes where there's noise,
like highways, et cetera.
And so we did this where
we had created this network
with 63 nodes, three
cruising altitudes, 270
directional links,
and 19 vertiports
for the city of Austin.
And we basically studied.
And I won't go
into the equations.
I hid that slide because it's a
nonlinear optimization problem.
But in the end,
what you get is you
can see here how the
noise and the energy usage
change as you basically give
different weighting functions
to what you want.
So if you have no noise
control, these vehicles
are going to just fly at the
lowest altitude they can,
basically from A to B, and
they'll make a lot of noise.
However, if you have more
stringent noise control,
you can see here that
the community noise
exposure is lower.
And the reaction of the
community is going to be lower,
but you won't be able to
fulfill as much demand.
And so we also looked
at prioritizing noise
and prioritizing energy and
seeing how those traded off.
And then finally,
we came up, looked
at some nice theoretical
issues of matters of fairness,
where there was
utilitarian, egalitarian,
and we showed how bad.
So we have developed a tool,
which basically can allow you
to determine how your network.
So with that-- see,
I'm saying my thing--
I want to summarize by saying
it really does take a pebble.
And that pebble, in the
form of our Jon Huntsman,
has two really, from my
mind, critical attributes,
critical thinking and
a holistic viewpoint.
And to my mind, these
skills are critical
for us going forward
in tackling the most--
the really important
problems that we have
in aviation today and tomorrow.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Stand by.
Wrong document open.
All right.
Aviation in the age
of John Hansman--
the first thing I thought
about this, especially
from the perspective
of aircraft design,
is what is the age
of John Hansman?
So John Hansman, as we
all know, 70 years old.
That's one Hansman.
And you all may be thinking,
hey, John's not going anywhere.
And it's true.
John's not going anywhere.
But MIT has a long and proud
tradition of making up units.
And so I would
refer you to Smoots.
When they were defining the
Smoot, no one said, hey,
Smoot might get taller.
They just painted the lines.
And so I'm painting the lines.
And so one Hansman is
now henceforth 70 years.
So we're going to talk about
one Hansman worth of aircraft
design.
We're actually going to
talk about two Hansmans
worth of aircraft design.
And because you all know
that I am a future thinker
and I'm actually up here
to talk about the future
at a lecture that's
about history,
we're going to talk
about three Hansmans.
So my job is to use history
in this Gardner lecture
to forecast what
the future might be.
So if we actually go a little
bit over to Hansmans ago,
the Europeans first started
thinking about flying machines,
actually the Brits,
Cayley and Hinson there
and of course, Lilienthal, very
initially successful attempts
to fly gliders, unpowered
aircraft, and of course,
Lilienthal after
thousands of flights,
ended up, unfortunately, in an
accident of his own creation
and ended up dying in flight.
Following those
in the late 1800s,
groups of engineers got together
in Europe and they started
to think about, how do we
actually power these things?
Because people had started to
realize that flying machines
were possible, but it wasn't so
obvious how do you power them.
And so that was the first
international aviation Congress.
And I found this very
interesting too is before
airplanes actually worked,
lawyers got together and figured
out in the late 1800s
how to regulate them.
That's actually true.
You could look that up.
I checked it a bunch of times.
You're going to have to-- if
you don't believe me, blame JT.
So what usually happens
when the Europeans get
thinking about
things is American
entrepreneurs showed
up and made it real.
And this is my
version of history.
And so of course, the
Wright brothers in 1903
were inside of two Hansmans now,
followed by the first autonomous
airplane during World War I.
These aircraft actually
went one direction.
They did not come home.
The first commercial aircraft,
the US Mail Service, of course,
started to fly these.
In a little bit over 20 years
following the Wright brothers,
of course, Charles Lindbergh
flew across the Atlantic
and reduced the time
to cross the Atlantic
by an order of magnitude.
And I bet you that
when they first flew,
the Wright brothers, no one
thought that was possible
20 years later.
So that's 20 years later.
Let's keep going.
1930s Frank Whittle and
the first jet engine start
to appear.
1940s-- I'm skipping
over a lot of history--
many airplanes in World War II.
Of course, we ended up
breaking the sound--
the sound barrier and the
first supersonic flight
and the X-1 in 1952, the world's
first commercial jetliner.
OK, so that's the first
of three Hansmans.
1884 through 1954 was really
defined by invention and wartime
innovation.
We went from the
Wright brothers,
through two world
wars, radial engines
tapered and tapered wings,
retractable landing gears
were invented.
Aluminum airframes
We had the first
radio navigation aids.
We had refinement of
the first flight decks.
We broke the sound barrier.
We invented jet propulsion.
We had rocket propulsion.
I can go on and on and on.
OK, what's the second Hansman?
So John Hansman
was born in 1954,
which happened to be the date of
the first flight of my favorite
airplane, the Boeing 367-80.
This was when Boeing
was incredibly bold
and bet the entire company
on the prototyping of a jet
airliner to prove to
customers and to themselves
that this was a product
that could meet what
the market needed
and would create
a whole new industry that people
had started dreaming about
around this time period.
So 1954 is the first
flight of that prototype.
1957 is the first flight of the
commercial variant, the 707,
which ends up
going into service.
Competitors start to show
up the Douglas DC 8, 1958.
The 1960s are so unbelievable.
I had to just double check
the facts here again.
Imagine living in
the age of this,
where 1963, the first
flight of the Boeing 727,
starts to cannibalize
the airplane products
that they had just created.
1967, the 787 was flown
for the first time.
1969, the first wide
body airplanes, the 747
opens up the whole world.
Global connectivity,
1969 supersonic flight.
Sorry, John, maybe a
little bit of a fool's
errand there for a little bit.
It can't all be straight
down the middle.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
So this I will recognize is
an aviation-centric talk.
I'm talking to MITR department.
A bunch of space stuff happened.
I'm not going to talk about it.
If you're interested
in this, once again,
please talk to John Telco
sitting right in the center
here.
He will answer your
questions about that.
Things happen in space.
1970s, Airbus--
Airbus shows up A300--
so widebody, 1979 MD-80.
1971 entrepreneurs
start to show up.
Herb Keller creates
this radical new idea
in Texas for a low-cost
commercial airline.
And he was trying to
figure out in that version
of the regulatory
environment, how do you even
make this thing possible?
And so he was--
look up the history
of Southwest.
It's incredible the things
that they were doing in Texas.
Only of course, followed
up by 1978, Jimmy Carter,
the signing of the
Airline Deregulation Act,
which created a whole new
world for commercial aviation.
1980s, Airbus A320-- the first
glass flight decks and digital
fly by wire airplanes, the rise
of computerized reservation
systems and revenue management.
Of course, the MIT
Department here ended up
playing a huge role in the
mathematics behind revenue
management and all the systems
that we use today for those.
The rise of turbofans-- so
turbojets are going away.
We've discovered that we can
use high bypass ratio fans.
CFM is created.
Boeing creates two
new airplane products
in that decade, the
757 and the 767.
I'm not going to keep doing that
because you'll get tired of it.
And it also turns out that
from 1990 until today,
it's actually very
difficult to continue
doing the decades there.
What ended up happening
following the '90s, of course,
the 777, the 787, the
A350, so on and so forth.
From 1990 onwards, it was
just relentless innovation
on so many fronts across
the Brigade range equation.
So if you just go back
to first principles,
it was higher bypass
ratio engines.
It was geared turbofans,
new materials,
advanced combustors, low
noise in the engine space.
In the aerospace,
it was CFD fuselage
shaping winglets, supercritical
airfoils, vortex generators,
and structures.
We created computer
aided design.
We used composites and automated
fiber placement machines.
That's just on the
Brigade technologies.
You just heard so much from
Amy and the other presenters
about the pilot support
and automation tools.
We had more fly by wire.
We had glass flight decks,
auto T casts, ETOPS.
ETOPS started to make the world
connected in a much more--
a better way.
We had Huds, GPS, wide
area augmentation systems,
precision NAV on and on,
market trends, globalization,
airline consolidation,
LCCs, I can go on.
What does it look
like in the data?
So from 1954, the year that
John was born, till now,
we went from around 0 commercial
passengers approximately--
it wasn't 0--
to over 4 billion
annual passengers.
I cut off the pandemic
there because of the big dip
but just to make the point.
Since 1954, fuel
efficiency has improved
by over 80% Since 1954,
many airlines were created.
Many airlines were consolidated.
Since 1954, all that
revenue management
work turned into much
better utilization
of the airplanes,
this load factor,
over time and now,
which is over 80%.
Since 1954, prices
have come down,
have come down substantially,
even through world events
where you would think that
prices wouldn't come down.
Since 1954, Amy just showed us
accident rates have come down.
And if you take away some of
those-- some of the other bars
there and you just
look at it from 1970,
the trend is even more
clear that accident rates
have fallen dramatically.
So during that Hansman,
what does that look like?
That looks like global
connectivity, safety,
and efficiency.
That's what that
era is all about.
It's the dawn of
commercial aviation.
It's the invention of every
single airliner happened
during that Hansman.
The scaling of a whole industry,
the optimization of all
the operations, the global
economic impact of building all
those airplanes, of
running all those airlines,
the safety improvements
that we talked about,
the relentless technology
optimizing, 9/11,
which was maybe the biggest
impulse into the system from
a safety standpoint, from
an operational standpoint,
airline consolidations,
the market maturity,
and ultimately
delivering a system,
which I still view
as a modern miracle.
It's really cool.
I still to this
day get really mad
when people close their blinds
when we're on an airplane
because I want to say--
thank you for clapping.
So I want to say,
don't you get it?
Didn't you look around?
You're paying $100 to fly across
the country in a tube in the sky
at 500 miles an hour.
It's amazing.
So that happened
during that Hansman.
What happens in
the next Hansman?
All right.
That's what I think
my job was here today,
but I needed to get
through all that first.
So I think I reflect on that,
and I say a lot can happen.
It's hard to say in one hand.
I'm going to keep laughing now.
A lot can happen in one Hansman,
and it's really, really,
really hard to predict.
If you started at
the start of that,
you would not possibly
end up at the end
of either of those
stories that I told you.
But it's a fool's errand.
It's what my job is here.
I'm a fool, and
I'm on an errand.
And I'm going to make
predictions anyway.
And so I think the next Hansman
is about these three things.
I think it's about
sustainability.
And I think that and the
way I view that as I think
that efficiency still matters.
And I'm going to talk about
what that means briefly.
But getting to zero
climate impact,
I think is going to end up
mattering more over time.
I think it's going
to be about autonomy,
both automation,
where to Amy's point,
humans and automation
are working together,
both on and off the aircraft,
including in the air traffic
control environment.
And I think that we will start
to see the rise of autonomous
aircraft, commercial
aircraft over this Hansman,
and I think we're going to see
really amazing combinations
of these things that are just
simply impossible to predict,
standing at the
start of this Hansman
and wondering what it's going
to look like at the end.
So on sustainability
today, today, 39 million
annual flights, 1.1 gigatons
of CO2 equivalent emissions,
and 2.5% is aviation
share of global emissions.
Despite all the unbelievable
miracle of science statistics
that I just showed you,
aviation's emissions
have been rising despite
the 80% fuel efficiency
improvements over time.
And that's because
growth in aviation
is outpacing our ability to make
the aircraft more efficient,
and that growth is good.
It means that people
want to travel.
We should still continue
to allow people to travel,
but we've got to
pick up the pace.
So aviation's pace share
of global emissions
is actually growing over time,
despite all those improvements
that I just mentioned.
It's not because
aviation's not improving.
Again, it's because we're flying
more than our improvements are
coming in.
And also, many other industries
are decarbonizing faster
than aviation.
So this number is
going to keep going up.
Our 2.5% today is going to
be a bigger number tomorrow,
and that's a problem.
So where are the emissions?
John and I had done quite
a lot of research in this.
When I was in ICAT, I actually
took this more recent data,
2019 from the cascade team,
which I'll give a shout out here
in a second.
But this is aircraft histogram
of flights by aircraft
type over certain missions.
And you can see that most
of the available time
kilometers in the
system are provided
by widebodies and by single
aisle aircraft, obviously.
So if you start looking at where
are the potential emissions
reduction opportunity,
I'm obviously
going to talk in
just a second here
about the opportunity
of electrification
and some other things.
And if we look in the-- call
it sub-500 nautical mile space,
it's about 14% of
the total emissions.
And so this is great.
We have a lot of
innovations that
can start to address this market
space with electrification.
There's a huge addressable
flight opportunity,
which makes it a great
business opportunity,
because and that's why you
see a lot of companies coming
into this space because man,
that's a lot of flights to go
potentially try to address.
But it has a disproportionately
limited impact.
Even if we electrify every
single one of those flights,
we've only solved
14% of the problem.
We have another 80%
of the problem to go.
So where are all those?
And I can go on and
on about this subject.
But I'll just
briefly say, if you
look at widebodies
as just one example,
they're somewhere around call
it half the fuel and about 10%
of the flights.
So if you want to
address the problem,
you've got have got to address
how this segment of the market
is powered.
And it's not just how the
emissions out of the tailpipe
of the aircraft.
One of the things that we've
been doing in especially
and what you'll see
in a second in a tool
that I'm about to show
you is that we have
to think beyond the aircraft.
We have to think about aviation
as a system of systems problem.
Where do you get the
source of the energy?
How do you carry it?
How is it transported?
How do you use it
on the airplane
and ultimately get to
the total climate impact?
So how do we do the full
life cycle accounting
of all the climate effects?
So something that the
Boeing team is now
leading that I was
really proud was really
a derivative of the work of--
I think now decades
of thinking in ICAT
is how to create tools that
bring all of that together
in a quantifiable way that.
Is truthful, that's
based on the facts.
It's not based on people's
feelings about sustainability,
but it's based on
the literal facts
of doing all the math of the
system that I just showed you.
And that's a tool
that's now online,
and you can go check it out.
And one of the
results of that is
that it's going to take
a lot of different tools.
So here's just sort
of a very simplified
view of how I think things may
play out in the next Hansman
era.
I think there's going to be
very obviously new energy
carriers on the left.
So we're going to need massive
amounts of sustainable aviation
fuel.
That's obvious.
There's no way through
the next couple of decades
unless we have tons and
tons of sustainable aviation
fuel that doesn't exist today.
And that's going to take
the form of biofuels,
and it will take
the form of e-fuels.
And there's a whole long
discussion about that.
And the lab for Aviation
and the Environment,
which John now
leads, by the way,
that lab has been pioneers in
thinking about alternative fuels
and so on.
I think there's
opportunity for things
like hydrogen, maybe
other fuels of this type,
and obviously battery
electric and electrification.
I think we're going to
see new aircraft shapes.
One of the great things that
came out of the MIT Department
over the last few decades
was the D8 program.
And that's obviously the
first aircraft on the top
there, which I'm very
passionate about,
having spent many years on.
I think that we're running out
of room on the tube and wing
aircraft to make the efficiency
improvements, which is why you
see that chart that I showed.
That marginal improvements
are getting smaller.
And so I think that there's
opportunity for new aircraft
shapes.
And I think one of
the things that I
was very passionate
about in my PhD research
was this idea of
right sizing aircraft.
And that's what John and I had
spent-- had spent quite a bit
of time thinking about.
Can you make aircraft that
are tailored specifically
for the mission that they're
intending to operate?
And I think that's
where you're starting
to see some of what people are
calling UAM or regional air
mobility or these other
somewhat tortured terms.
But what you're
seeing is aircraft
that use particular new
energy carriers to have--
to be more right
sized for the mission.
So that gets to the
point where I show you
a little bit of what that
actually looks like in practice.
There's hundreds of companies
that are doing things like this.
I'm going to talk about
the one that I lead,
which is the one that's in
the red box there called Wisk.
John and Chris Korten
is around here.
They're going to
talk to you tomorrow
about the other yellow airplane.
They're called Electra.
There are hundreds of these.
I just want to show you
a little bit about what's
going on behind the hood
or under the hood, rather,
in what are just incredibly
fun and entrepreneurial
and engineering-driven
companies and cultures
to build the things that
ultimately, I think,
will start to matter for
the view of the Hansman
that I just showed you there.
We build autonomous
electric aircraft.
There's a long history of the
company, which I don't have time
to tell you, but this is
a fifth generation of one
of the airplanes that
we built. This one
is actually flying down in New
Zealand that you can see there.
These aircraft take
off vertically.
They fly like an airplane.
And they stop, and they
land vertically again,
like a helicopter.
Our concept of operations is
autonomous with human oversight.
I'll show you what that
looks like here in a second.
These are battery
electric powered aircraft.
The safety targets
are when you get
into things doing the ARP
4754 and the VMCAs and so
on, things like
catastrophic hazards
or 10 to the minus 9 delay,
no single points of failure,
so on and so forth-- so
similar to commercial aircraft,
this aircraft.
Now the problem with
battery electric airplanes,
and what John will show you,
is an innovation tomorrow
on this is that they
can't fly very far.
So this airplane flies
less than 100 miles.
It carries four people.
And it charges quickly.
These are the kinds of
systems that are on board.
We are an incredibly
vertically integrated company.
We make every--
nearly every system
on the airplane, which
makes it very fun.
So it's a composite airframe.
It's actually a bonded
composite airframe.
We use thing things like
SQRTM and some other out
of autoclave technologies that
enable high-rate manufacturing.
We build our own computers.
We build our own software
for those computers.
We build our own battery packs.
I'll show you what
those look like.
Electric motors.
It's obviously a fully
electric fly by wire airplane,
and sensing navigation
landing, I'll
talk a little bit more
about just briefly.
For those of you that
have an electric car,
it's a pretty amazing thing
when you really look inside
of your electric car.
These systems are
unbelievably simple.
And so here I'm showing
just a little bit
of what an airplane
looks like when
there's no fuel in the wings.
This aircraft, obviously,
it doesn't have a turbine.
It doesn't have
hydraulic systems.
It doesn't have pneumatics.
All that it has in big quotes
is high voltage harnessing, low
voltage harnessing
batteries, motors.
That's it, computers.
The motors look like this.
I think they're unbelievably
impressive, what you can
create with electric machines.
This has about the
same amount of power
that you would get in a
Lycoming engine that's
on a small general
aviation aircraft.
And it has very, very few parts.
We're in the middle of
making all of that right now
out in California.
And we expect to be flying this
first version of the Gen six
airplane within the
next couple of months.
But that means that right now,
we're building all those battery
packs.
You can see up on
the top right there,
the battery cells
that we use are
similar to what's
in your cell phone.
They're pouch cells that are
almost the same form factor
as what's in your cell phone.
We put them in
aviation-safe battery packs,
which is a whole very
interesting research subject.
We make those motors
that I just showed you.
We put it all on the ground and
complex things like ironbirds
and make sure the software
works and all the rest.
We have to think way
beyond the airplane.
I hope that you understand that.
Now, from the discussions that
we just had from Craig and JP
and Amy.
So these are all
the things that we
have to pioneer in
order to advance
our autonomous operations.
Trust me, it would be it would
be many orders of magnitude
easier if we were doing
this with a pilot on board.
We're really trying to advance
all the enabling elements
of this, what the
FAA is starting
to call a super system
for autonomous operations.
That starts to look like this.
I put this up here
because I think
this is very interesting
to dovetail with what
Amy and team just showed is
that the way that aircraft
may be supervised in the future.
This is an actual picture
from how we actually
supervise the airplanes.
That's the word that
we use, that all
of the human factors for how
that's done is new work to do.
It's new research.
It needs to be done with
appropriate human factors.
So that it's safe.
It's a whole new world to go in
and derive lessons from the past
and apply them to the future.
This is the FAA tech center in
New Jersey, which was really
fun to be back to because
I think many of us
went to the JUP talks with
Jon at the same center.
And so we actually are
running simulations
with the whisk
airplanes in there now.
We take all our sensor
packages and compute
and all the software
and whatnot,
and we do things
detect and avoid
trials on surrogate
helicopters in California
using many of the
lessons learned
that John Langford taught
me while we were together
at Aurora Flight Sciences.
And so it may not stop there.
There may be things
that go beyond gen six,
so things like
cargo and logistics
and other electrified
products over time, which
is really fun to think about.
So bringing it back
to our timeline,
I guess it is a little
bit of a fool's errand
to try to predict the
future, as I mentioned.
But if I have to I
would say it's probably
the era of sustainability and
autonomy if I were guessing.
And I will leave
with this, which
is if I look back at
that history, what
I see is that most
of the products
that I showed you were
the successful ones.
But when you really
pull the thread
on the super
interesting innovations
and people and
projects and companies
and all the things that went
into creating all of those,
almost all of them failed.
And I would say that that's
probably the world that we're
in right now where
it's not obvious
what the ultimate landing place
is for all these technologies.
It's not obvious what are
the successful products
in this space.
It's not obvious what are
the successful companies
in the space.
But John taught us a
bunch of stuff, which is
thinking from first principles.
He taught us to consider
the whole system, which
I hope you heard reflected
from our completely not
coordinated talks today.
He taught us to do
the work that matters,
not just publishing papers
for publishing papers sake,
but to try to drive those
numbers that I showed you
on the slides ever
higher and lower,
based on which direction is
good, and to adapt to change.
And so I think we're
all pretty well teed up
to go after the next Hansman.
Thanks.
What do we do now?
I forgot to mention all the
slides that was [INAUDIBLE].
Well, thank you so much for
those outstanding talks.
We have a few minutes
for Q&A, so I'd
like to invite our
speakers to come up,
and we can open it
up to the audience.
You can come on.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
We have a mic here,
but John Langford
asked John Hansman, what does
the next Hansman look like?
I think Brian's on target.
And actually, this is
something I learned in Masha.
One of my students,
Masha, who's here,
is actually the person
who got me really to think
about the sustainability part.
So I think we're fundamentally
driven by sustainability
as an industry and whatever.
And the autonomy is obvious.
It's actually autonomy and
optimization, whatever.
So we're going to think
about the objective function.
Whether the airframe, I think--
I agree also with Brian that
we should build something
like the D8, that
we're in an obsolete.
We can't continue
to go the way we've
been going right now if you
get the increased bypass ratio
by making the engine bigger.
We're sort of at the point
where the additional drag
from the nacelle counteracts
the additional the improvement
from that.
So we need to take advantage
of configuration stuff there.
But I think it's existential
to the aviation industry, which
is if we don't become
more efficient,
we will become marginalized,
and it will become
socially unacceptable to fly.
And the market will go away.
So I think that's
the real driver.
Autonomy, I think,
is a technology,
but we're going to use every
technology we can get and.
We do need to think of
it as a system problem.
I also just want
to thank everybody.
I think there are themes
that I didn't realize
that I had that I've seen.
But I think the
goal has actually
been to improve the
system and to have impact.
And I think everybody here has.
So I think we've done the
first part of the job.
OK, I don't know if I
answered your question.
No, no, I'll behave.
Brian, this is a
question for you.
You mentioned that getting the
aircraft out there in the world
would be orders of
magnitude easier if it
didn't have to be autonomous.
From a business
perspective, are you
ever tempted to find autonomous
or crewed or piloted markets
for the airplane?
One of the things that I
learned, maybe from Jon
Langford, actually--
and Jon, I don't
know if this is a
lesson that I don't even
know if Jon would
agree with this now,
but my reflection from
our time at Aurora
was that the idea of
having a piloted aircraft
and trying to turn it
into an uncrewed aircraft
or an optionally
piloted aircraft
as kind of a
pressure relief valve
for the regulatory
discussion and so on
was never it never dealt
with the hard question.
It never forced
the hard question.
By really thinking holistically
about the whole concept
of operations, we think we're
able to put forth to the FAA
the hard question in a
really responsible way.
And then to just
take it head on.
So from a business
standpoint, I mean,
one of the advantages
that we've had
is that we've had two very
long-term thinkers involved
in the company.
The company was founded
by Larry Page, obviously
a very long-term
thinker, and then Boeing
came in as a joint
venture partner in 2019,
fully acquired the
company last year.
So we've been in
a position where
we can take the longer view
and we don't necessarily
have to raise the next
round every month or so.
But obviously, the
markets change.
Times change.
You could tell
Boeing's in crisis.
And so every entrepreneurial
journey is kind of we'll
have to take things
as they come.
So we'll see.
But we have no current plan to
ever go to a piloted aircraft.
We're trying to
force a hard question
and honestly succeed
or fail and just face
into that on our
ability to do it.
And if we fail, then we're
going to fail trying responsibly
to do it for the first time.
And that's the way
it's going to go.
We have time for
maybe one or two more.
So I think this is for Amy.
I was just wondering.
There was a talk about
automation versus pilot--
pilot monitoring
and all that stuff.
How often do you
think pilot actually
does take over from autopilot
in the commercial industry
right now that have saved--
made it safer, so to speak,
in the context of going
fully automatic versus not?
Yeah, we're working in the
industry to collect data,
and we're finding that
only about 10% of flights
could be conducted totally on
autonomy without some pilot
intervention.
About 26% of flights have
some system malfunction,
requiring pilot
intervention to continue
safe flight to the destination.
And why has this not
reliably been logged?
Because they're so common.
The circuit breaker presses
that the pilot does regularly
during the flight that
nobody reports it.
You say the pilot, why
didn't you tell me?
They're like, why
would I tell you.
This happens every day.
So the rest include air traffic,
running fairly quick changes
to the flight, disconnect.
Let your buddy reprogram
the flight management system
while you hand fly until
everything's reconfigured
and take over.
So we know that or
we are increasingly
learning that our deterministic
model of the nominal flight
is the mean, but the variance
around that in the flight,
the amount of
variance, disturbance,
operational disturbance, and
variation throughout any flight
is profound.
And right now, it is the
pilot who manages that.
[INAUDIBLE] I think it's
sort of counterintuitive
also why autonomous
and electric.
And one of the things we found
through doing the full safety
cases and so on is that
the fact that we can only
fly for less than an hour
is actually quite good
because we can
operationally restrict
so much of the actual complexity
of a large commercial aircraft.
So I wouldn't want to
confound the solving
the problem with our smaller
plane and then saying,
therefore it's solved for
large commercial airplanes.
I would say we are solving
such a small portion
of that big airplane problem.
We're trying to do
what I've been telling
people is the Fosbury
flop, for people that
know that term, the guy
who first jumped backwards
over a high jump bar.
We're trying to do that
for commercial passenger
carrying autonomous aircraft.
And the more we constrict
it-- restrict it
so that it looks like
a Gondola in the sky
where you take the cable
away, that's the better
off we're going to be.
I appreciate Missy Cummings,
who surveyed pilots--
this would have been
2018 time frame--
and asked them how many
minutes in your average flight
do you actually hand fly?
And for the A320, the answer
was on two to three minutes.
For the 777, it was on
average seven minutes.
This ended up a thing on Wolf
Blitzer, where Missy was going,
these airplanes
are so automated.
And I was glad that Missy
brought me in as her foil
because Wolf turns to me and
says, so we don't need pilots.
And I said, well, those
two to seven minutes
include takeoff, landing,
and every emergency.
Last question.
For Brian, but for all of you,
everyone mentioned the FAA,
but not much mention
was made of regulation.
Is the FAA, in your
opinion, as it's currently
staffed and organized,
able to adequately enable
these futures for aviation?
Well, there's a tough word
in there, which is, I guess,
adequately, or there's
adjectives in there
that are hard to describe.
I would say that we're
headed down the road.
From my perspective,
just being a developer
and seeing the kind
of front lines,
the FAA doesn't have
all the expertise
in the engineering
corps that's required
to deal with some of these
subjects because they're so new.
And it's OK.
It's not because it's
a fault of their own.
It's because they're
incredibly new.
I mean, this is a
National Academies thing
that John and Amy and others
should, I think really
think about is, how
do you get-- how
can you create an
incentive for people
to go through some of these
really innovative programs
in industry and then
come back to the FAA
so that you understand the
technologies that you're
expected to regulate.
So that's one thing.
I think from a
staffing standpoint
and so on, there's
just-- the FAA isn't
the high the highest
performing organization
in the world from just like
a responsiveness standpoint.
I'd say most applicants
would tell you
that the people that are really
running CERT programs would say,
my biggest frustration is
just the nuts and bolts
of passing paper back and
forth and other things.
I guess there's less
of a big theme there.
But there is this
talent problem that I
think is there's
something really
there for the National Academies
or somebody else to consider.
But the air traffic control
you should talk about
because I actually think
there's staffing problems.
I do think that there
are staffing problems
in the CERT side
too, in that they're
trying to run the
regular operation,
doing all the Boeing issues,
while at the same time,
you have a ton of
other new entrants.
And so even if they had the
folks, who had the-- and I
agree with you--
that the expertise.
Even they had the expertise.
They're just overwhelmed
because there's so much going on
in the traditional
certification marketplace
that when you have all these
new entrants, it's hard to get.
Basically, you join the
line and get a number.
And you would
probably say that we
saw that when I was at Universal
Hydrogen. We were doing that.
It's just hard to get
a number because people
are busy doing the Boeing and
Airbus things in the real world.
But I do think that air
traffic controllers,
they have some staffing issues.
The question is, is AI
going to be helpful,
or do you have to search
staff to basically bring
new technology in?
And I leave that to you.
OK, I'll just make a
couple of quick comments
to start with the air traffic
control staffing issue.
AI is not going to help
that particular problem.
What will help that is
that the FAA is actively
changing the rules by which
people can get into the system
and how the training is going.
And we pretty much
believe that that's
going to start turning around.
But it is a challenge right now.
The existing controller
workforce in only a few places,
but in a few very important
places is very overworked,
and that is a constraint, to
some degree, on the system.
But with respect to the
certification challenge,
just kind of two
aspects to that.
One is the way the
certification system
works is that the applicants
are bringing with them not only
this is what we want to certify,
but here's the means by which we
are going to
demonstrate compliance.
And the FAA is sort of
honor bound in this system
to not suggest how to do that.
They can evaluate whether
something that comes
is adequate, but they're not
going to prescribe how to do it.
The challenge there
is nobody knows
what's adequate for certain
kinds of systems like this.
So we're actually holding--
I think it might be next
week or a couple of weeks.
We've been holding
these symposiums
where the industry
comes and FAA comes
and experts from other firms
come and discuss this problem.
How are we going to
solve this problem?
So progress will be made.
It will be made at
a pace which ensures
safety, which is inconvenient
for venture capitalists
and so forth.
But that is what
everyone's trying.
I mean, it is a
very big challenge.
So you just have to
have to hold suit.
You have to understand that
for the past 31 years at least,
and possibly an entire
Hansman, the only thing
that the FAA has been asked
to certify essentially
looks like an airliner or
a general aviation aircraft
with slight variations
on where the engines go.
We did certify the first
electric propulsion aircraft
about a year ago.
Yeah, so that progress
has been made.
But now we're going to bring
an aircraft with eight rotors
and in some cases tilt rotor
and so on and so forth,
and then say that
that's going to be
managed by an AI-based
system [INAUDIBLE].
Wonderful.
Please, let's
thank our speakers.
[APPLAUSE]
And also Thank John for
all his contributions
at the [INAUDIBLE].
[APPLAUSE]