next speaker is Dr Lian hary uh he is a
research scientist at MIT Quantum honic
and AI group and a postdoc fellow at
Professor DK ingland laboratory and also
he is a senior scientist at NT research
physics and informatics
love his talk is about the research of
honic computing to solve the problem of
high demand of computation energy for
data center
so all right so thanks Micky for that
introduction and today I'm going to be
talking about Optical neural networks
and Computing with light so a little
background of myself before I get
started uh I actually come into this
field of applied engineering from
theoretical physics background so I was
at the other Institute in technology
Caltech where I studied theoretical
physics relativity Theory and black
holes then I went to Stanford where I uh
got to know this professor named Yoshi
Yamamoto that I worked with in Japan for
one year on these uh uh Computing
machines called coherent icing machines
and that's research that eventually
brought me back to MIT and this
interesting work in Optical Computing so
co coherent icing machines the original
vision was merge the classical in the
quantum and into and create a machine
that can solve hard optimization
problems so this is a kind of a it's a
what we call an optical parametric
oscillator you can think of this as one
part laser and one part bit it's a laser
that oscillates in one of two phase
States and that uh that phase State
encodes the bit and it has some Quant
interesting Quantum properties when the
opo is below threshold this gives you
squeezing which is a very use full
Quantum resource um but it also has
Classical properties if you go above
threshold it's just a coherent state so
that's classical and we realized you
could solve use these uh use these
parametric oscillators to solve what's
called an icing problem which is a hard
optimization problem as part of this NB
hard uh class but the thing that I that
really inspired me was uh just the fact
that Optics provides a a very strong
resource in in the efficiency of these
icing machines so we did this
benchmarking study this was my my work
when I was here in Japan uh comparing
this machine to another kind of quantum
computer or the d-wave quantum maner and
that was really Hut a couple years ago
and we found that the optical machine
does a I mean orders of magnitude better
at a large number of these icing
problems especially the ones with dense
connectivity that you can't easily embed
into the sparse d-waves hardware and so
this immediately told us that there's
something really special about the use
for Optics in a computation algorithms
and I guess at the same time there was a
lot of uh work that I was not aware of
which is related to Optical neural
networks which really got started back
in the 80s and the 70s uh but there was
a Resurgence of that uh in the late
2010s and when I saw that work I
immediately saw oh that makes a lot of
sense we knew that Optics was going to
be very useful for computing and so
that's going to be really the the story
of this talk I'm going to start with a
more of a background about why we need
Optical Computing that I'm going to talk
about three different approaches for our
research groups into using optics for
computing so the background is really
motivated by how deep learning works and
what the limits to deep learning are
going to be on the hardware side uh so
deep learning is uh based on this
fundamental block called the perceptron
this is an old idea I think this goes
back to
1958 and the first perceptron was a
physical device that was uh built at
Cornell University and basically a
perceptron it sums up a bunch of inputs
which are appropriately weighted and
then it thresholds that output and that
uh can do a pretty decent job at a lot
of simple learning tasks such as a digit
classification uh but at the same time
uh there there is a linearity in this
perceptron relation and that leads to
the perceptron not doing well at many
very trivial tasks so a great example is
here you have three different uh
classification tasks I want to sep
separate the red dots from the blue dots
and the perceptron thanks to the
linearity of this function here it can't
do these two on the right it can only do
the one on the left the so-called
linearly separable uh
problem and so that is a it's called the
exor problem because the simplest
problem that the perceptron cannot solve
is just the exor operation that's just a
gate and this is it was one of the big
uh big challenges to actually using
neural networks when these were initi
initially introduced the solution to
that was just to realize that you need
to have neurons in between your inputs
and outputs so this is called a deep
neuron Network and if each of those
neurons implements a perceptron then it
turns out that this has a lot more
expressibility than just the perceptron
alone and this is the basis for uh mod
for deep learning now now actually when
you implement these on in computer
hardware you're not just randomly uh
arranging the perceptrons like on the
right left you arrange them into regular
grids of arrays of data and that uh that
gives you a much much faster performance
in computers uh and when you do that you
realize that deep learning or running
these neural networks is really just two
things uh that are interleaved one is
linear Matrix Vector multiplication and
the other is a nonlinear function and we
just call that an activation function
and if you want to write code to do this
the simplest code would just be that on
the right so this idea combined with
with a couple of additional tools one is
gradient-based optimization or training
and additional types of layers such as
convolutional layers led to the first
successful and useful implementation of
these perceptrons which would be the
convolutional neural networks for uh
digit or character classification so
this was work that was done by Yan laon
back when he was at Bell labs and it was
very successful at this task but uh it
didn't the Tech the technique didn't
really catch catch on and the reason was
that there were many other machine
learning techniques that were a lot
easier to use uh more familiar to people
that did the same thing with almost the
same
accuracy and so that's where the field
stood for quite a while and it was only
with the Advent of much more complicated
data sets where you needed these deep
neural networks to really solve the
problems so there is this imag net data
set this was uh formulated in
and people people tried the classic
machine learning techniques to classify
the images in this data set it's a
thousand images not just let's say 30
characters and it's millions of
images and nothing worked well uh until
uh these guys from Jeff hinton's group
came along and created what's called
alexnet so Alex net is very similar to
Lynette except that it has much bigger
layers and I guess the answer is a
couple days out of date but that's when
I first gave this talk um so it uh this
really blew all all the competition out
of the water and after the ne in the
next couple of years uh this these
neural networks were doing as well as
humans at this very hard machine
learning uh Benchmark problem um and so
what's the difference between uh Lynette
or Yan laon's initial experiment and
Alex net there are a couple of
theoretical changes but the big thing is
just that Alex net is a lot bigger and
you can quantify that by looking at the
number of weights or the number of Max
at a neural network those are things
that are very easy to compute just
looking at the uh the layer Dimensions
which you can get out of any paper and
you find that in the in lyette it's
about 400 KX and 50 Kobes whereas in
Alex net it's closer to 600 megax or 60
meytes so that's a factor of 1,000
increase in the amount of Max and the
amount of Weights going from one to the
other and it was that factor of a
thousand that you needed in Hardware
capabilities that really made deep
learning take off and so that was an
inflection point in the growth of uh the
exponential growth of machine learning
models that people saw in around 2012
and after that point these models
started growing exponentially but with a
much faster uh time constant where I
think at the peak of this um the model
sizes were doubling every three months
or so uh which really let makes you
realize this is going to tax the
hardware very quickly and so if you look
at modern deep learning Hardware there
are three things that are very critical
one is that all of this Hardware is
optimized to to optimally compute these
Matrix Matrix multiplications which is
the linear
algebra second is that they're all bottl
knucked by energy consumption and most
of that energy consumption comes from
these electronic interconnects to send
data from a point A to point B on your
chip now uh there are many ways this is
done uh if the hardware to do efficient
linear algebra is not old is not new
it's quite old and uh there's this
concept called a systolic array which is
one of the most efficient ways to do
linear algebra u in digital electronics
and this is something that has people
had been developing in Academia but uh
Now with uh with this demand of deep
learning it's become a commercial
product and so the Google TPU and gpus
nowadays are all really good examples of
systolic arrays uh so this was a product
that was first introduced in
2016 and you can still use it on the
cloud um it's also used to train all of
Google's machine learning models and uh
the TPU has gone through several
iterations and I think that comparing
those iterations is also a good way of
uh illustrating the limitations we see
to electronic solutions to to this
machine learning learning problem and
how mors law probably has a limit has a
limited uh gives limited gains in the
future so if you look at uh these these
this technical chart here is just the
energy cost of different operations uh
at the 45 millimeter node or nanometer
node and so that was the first TPU and
the 7even nanometer node and the
Improvement should be a factor of 45
over7 that's about 6.5 but what they
actually find is that the Improvement
for most of these Ops is about 3 four so
there's a limited uh there's a a a
limited gains for a a large number of
the important kinds of Ops that you want
to do the especially the max but also
the reading from memor going from this
older process node to 7 nanometers and
of course that has continued to three
nanometers and 2 nanometers and however
many nanometers we expect in the future
and even if you had even if you didn't
have that limitation there are other
fundamental sounds that are digital
electronics because we've had so much
improvement in the last couple decades
are coming close to reaching so
fundamentally the lowest energy to
perform a gate is called the land hour
limit and that's KT log 2 um but there's
also a limit called the reliability
reliable Computing limit and that's
about the land hour limit times the log
of your error probability which is
around uh you would like it to be around
10 Theus 20 or lower and there are uh
there are trends that that uh people
have calculated that suggests that we
may be approaching this reliable
Computing bound with in the in the next
decade or two um and so that really
highlights the need for another Paradigm
for computing if we really want to
continue this exponential growth in
model sizes and this is potentially
where Optics comes into play now to
understand where Optics can give us an
advantage which we should look at the
differences between Optics and
electronics um they're the same in many
ways they have the same fundamental
force and we're using the same particle
to communicate data or the photon but
there's this big difference in terms of
the in terms of the uh carrier frequency
of electronic excitations versus Optical
ones a factor of 10,000 to 100,000 and
that manifests in a lot of different
ways in in terms of the photon energy as
well as its wavelength in terms of its
interaction with matter the types of
sources and detectors that you would use
and the methods in which you wire data
from A to
B and this leads to a lot of potential
advantages for using Optics over
Electronics both for communications and
for computing the related to data rates
loss Distortion cross talk the number of
modes um linearity and also potentially
but I won't talk about it as much here
but Quantum advantages and Computing at
the speed of
light so data rates is kind of a given
uh fundamentally this is because the the
optical signals are being transmitted at
this carrier frequency which is 200 300
terahertz or so and that's a orders of
magnitude higher than the carrier
frequencies of electronic excitations
and there are a lot of other practical
things that limit Optical data rates but
uh those have been engineered for a long
time to the point that we're very close
to uh that fundamental limit uh over a
single optical fiber you can transmit 50
to 200 terabits per second of data a lot
of these records get broken every every
year by Japanese companies like NDT or
institutes like
aist and uh a good way to visualize this
is that uh nowadays in your high-end
gpus you have a processor and then
there's this high bandwidth memory that
goes on top of that and there are
thousands of connections between your
processor and your hbm and you can get
the same amount of uh data throughput
through the core an optical fiber so
that's just roughly a 10 Micron uh size
um region as as on all of those
connections going from the processor to
the hbm but the fiber can carry it
hundreds of kilometers so that's one
advantage uh to you should compare this
to how data is transmitted on chip
though because there's a fundamental
limit to how you can transmit data on
chip that's related to RC circuitry so
the resistance of a wire depends on its
length and the capacitance also depends
on its length length and if you
calculate the RC time constant you'll
find that that depends on some material
constants you can't really change those
by very much uh times the aspect ratio
of your wires and this leads to uh this
leads to if you want to ask yourself how
much data can you squeeze through a
micron siiz wire uh a limit that depends
very sharply on the length of your wire
whereas in photonics it's really
independent and with state-of-the-art
technology it can be orders of magnitude
higher
now in addition electronic signals are
very sensitive to uh loss Distortion
interference and cross talk and many of
these problems just go away with
photonics this is true because
electronic signals usually have
frequency dependent frequency dependent
loss when they go down wave guides but
in fonics you're more limited by uh
group velocity dispersion which which uh
only only is relevant on much longer
length scales and cross talk can be much
lower because
the modes attenuate exponentially in the
evanescent regions outside of the wave
guide and I think I'll skip over that
for L of time but another important
question is not just communicating but
how do you compute with Optics and how
can you make Optical Computing more
efficient U and this is something where
we're not just naively trying to replace
what everything what what an electronic
processor does uh many things like
nonlinearity and memory are much better
done in electronics versus in Optics but
this linear algebra which I mentioned at
the very beginning that's a key part of
deep learning and it's actually the
bottleneck
in that's something that theoretically
can be very easily mapped to Optics and
if you map it to Optics it becomes free
because Optical propagation is just
based on Maxwell's equations which is
passive and free and so if you can make
this mapping between linear algebra and
Optics then potentially you can get a
big Advantage uh to running this part of
your neural network in l
and so there are uh there are many ways
to uh understand how this would work uh
so in a matrix Vector multiplication
you're going to have fan out you're
going to have uh multiplication and
you're going to have summation and each
one of these operations can be thought
of as being implemented in Optics um and
when you implement these in Optics you
get something that's called Optical
parallelism that's an idea that for
every active conversion step between
ronic and
optic you you are effectively doing many
operations if you have fan out an
integration in your circuit also if your
circuit has depth it's basically the
same thing and if you look at the amount
of parallelism you have in a matrix
Vector multiplication well you if it's
an M byn Matrix then you have a fan out
of N and you have a fan in of M
and you can just uh calculate the energy
per operation here and you see that it
depends inversely on both M and N which
are the sizes of your matrices now for
the trend in machine learning has bur
towards larger and larger matrices
especially in these large generative
models like
llms and so that really suggests that
the since the advantage of Optics will
go go with M and N that really suggests
uh that the advantage should should be
quite substantial
and so motivated by that our group has a
large number of we're studying a large
number of different Optical
architectures to try to get this
Advantage for computing powered by
photonics uh the first uh this was what
I worked on when I first joined MIT is
based on coherent detection which we
also implemented with with the what are
called vixel arrays uh we also have some
freespace Optical schemes based on
programmable fanout and then we have uh
some more traditional approaches based
on beam splitter meshes and some
approaches based on wavelength
multiplexing and I'll try to see how
much I can get through um starting with
I think the most standard architecture
which is the beam splitter mesh or
multiport interferometer so sorry about
the uh pixelated image here but a
multiport interferometer it's a it's
a it's a a programmable Matrix Vector
multiplier that works through Optical
interference so the idea is that if your
vector is encoded in different different
modes then a mode mixer is equivalent to
passively performing Matrix Vector
multiplication so think of things like a
directional coupler a beam splitter an
MMI all these things perform a fixed
Matrix Vector multiplication but what we
want to do here is do a programmable
Matrix Vector multiplication so we can
Implement all those matrices in in a a
deep neural network in this Hardware how
do you do that well if your Matrix has a
size of two there's a known way to do
this and it's called a MOX Ander
interferometer MOX Ander interferometer
has two beam Splitters and uh usually
one phase shifter but here you need two
and you can show that this implements a
matrix of the following form which uh
coupled with some with two phase
shifters on the output this gives you a
a universal 2x two Matrix that respects
the respects energy conservation so it's
a unitary Matrix so this can Implement
any 2x2 matrix that respects energy
conservation now the real in the real
world our neural networks need more than
two neurons and so you need to find a
way to generalize this 2 by two to an n
byn and there are ways to do that uh so
this first way was devised by wreck
Zinger and some other people back in the
90s and this is just to tile this MOX
Ender into this triangular mesh and you
can show that any in this case 4x4
Matrix can be realized as a product of 2
x two matrices uh if they're arranged in
this particular way and the reason it
needs to be arranged in this way is that
you can do some math rewrite this
equation as this and then you can show
that this is equivalent to a
diagonalization of this Matrix U so
those of you who have taken linear
algebra might know about the QR
decomposition of matrices this is just a
QR decomposition but our Matrix starts
as unitary so R is
one and there this also gives you a
prescription to find the phases the
thetas and F you need in order to imp
this desired Matrix
U
and that uh that was the first uh first
approach now this has some limitations U
the the first one that everyone mentions
is well this is a triangle and your
chips are always square or rectangular
and so you're wasting a lot of space
doing this uh but actually that problem
has been remedied so in 2016 this
postdoc William Clemens came up with
this architecture that just splits the
rect triangle in half and then it mer es
those two triangles along this the
hypotenuse and that gives you Al that's
also un Universal it's also very easy to
program um so these things
experimentally they were first used for
Quantum photonics and only later were
they you uh deployed to classical
photonics um so in Quantum photonics
there are a lot of these operations that
you have to
implement a lot of these Primitives for
to make a Quantum Optical computer these
include things like Fusion Gates the km
scheme has a particular interference
pattern and then if you want to do a
non-universal do non-universal Computing
like bz on sampling you still need a a
way of mixing modes and you want to mix
the modes in a manner that's fully
programmable U so this was originally
developed for uh Quantum photonics and
it it spun off a number of startups uh
so these two startups I know in
particular squantum and Xanadu uh their
technology is very critically dependent
on being able to Implement these uh
programmable
unitaries but at MIT we realized in 2017
or a couple years before that um that
you can also use this for classical
computation uh in particular we use this
silicon batonic programmable beam
splitter mesh uh based on Thermo optic
phase shifters up here and we realize
that this thing since it can do
programmable Matrix Vector products uh
that you could run a proof of concept uh
deep learning models on this so we we
did a proof of concept demo of a vowel
classification with this and that was
something that uh it spun off two
companies uh one was called light matter
it's still headquartered in Boston and
the bay area as well as lightelligence
that's partly in Boston but now mostly
in China and these companies were
originally founded with the intent of
taking those measures and making Optical
Computing units now that didn't happen
but largely because they discovered that
in in the near- term there were was more
customer demand for interconnects uh not
so much that the meshes wouldn't work
there are reasons that the meshes might
be hard in practice one is the need for
a nonlinearity in the Chip And so this
is something that we've been working on
uh even after they they spawn off and we
realized that this problem has a
solution is which is that you can create
a nonlinearity on a chip that has uh no
nonlinear Optics through a combination
of photo detection and modulation so you
take the you take your light you use
your light to drive a photo detector and
then it becomes a current and then that
current goes into a modulator and then
the modulator modulates the light and
that ends up giving you a nonlinear uh a
nonlinear mapping between the input
light and the output light and not only
is it nonlinear but it's programmable uh
so you can get all these different kinds
of nonlinearities just by tuning the set
point of this ring
modulator and so that coupled with a uh
novel Inu Training Method allowed us to
demonstrate for the first time U uh a
single chip um single chip photonic
coherent deep learning with a latency
that is limited not by the nonlinearity
and not by any readout but only by the
speed of light for the yeah the speed of
the light that propagates through this
chip and
also where is the yeah and this idea of
training it's something that uh many
other groups research groups are also
studying uh so there's a lot of interest
in uh doing back back propagation in
fonics and it turns out that back
propagation theoretically is very
similar to what they call uh the adjoint
method and so there have been uh there
was this Theory proposal back in 2018
about how you could physically realize
the adjoint method u in batonic hardware
and that's simp since been realized in
2023 now there there are a lot of
limitations to these meas that have to
do with uh Hardware Hardware
imperfections um I think I'll I think
I'll skip through this for a lack of
time but basically the slides I'm going
through are are about how uh there are a
lot of challenges in physically
realizing these these large MOX Zander
meshes when your Hardware is fabricated
and it's not quite uh what what your
theoretical model predicts it should be
and there are self-configuration and
error correction methods that you can
use um so that you can still use the
hardware to implement the desired
matrices even in spite of these these
imperfections but I wanted to talk about
two other approaches to Optical
Computing uh which are probably a little
bit more scalable and one is delocalized
Computing uh and so why would you want
delocalized Computing uh so there are
two Trends in the in the world right now
uh one is one is Edge Computing where we
have all these devices that are
generating data and we don't know what
to do with all that data we can't can't
send it all to the cloud for processing
that would overload the cloud and often
times there's uh there are privacy
reasons that you wouldn't want to do
that and then also uh for training a lot
of large machine learning models you run
into memory bottlenecks where you can't
store all of the weight memory and all
of the activation memory especially all
the intermediate layers that you have to
store temporarily stash the activations
for to do back propagation you can't
store all of that in a single GPU so you
have to delize your your your training
algorithms usually through a combination
of weight broadcasting and then uh
weight update reduce
steps and and so some kind of an
algorithm or some kind of a photonic
architecture uh that is suitable for
delocalized computing might be very
useful to the community and this is
something that uh we realized in late
2020 early 21 and we came up with this
architecture called ncast that I think
goes along way towards doing that the
main ideas are reported in this paper
down
here and this is motivated by a concept
called Magic State Computing something
that comes from the quantum literature
and it's this idea that uh you can in
certain cases you can create this
physical state called a magic State and
once you have that magic State you can
send that magic state to a user and the
user can combine the magic state with
some data to process uh a given
algorithm and give you a result and I
guess the magic part about this is that
the magic State lets you process the
data with much less in much less time
and with much less energy than if you
had to process it by yourself now that
uh that idea it has a very rigorous uh
definition in quantum mechanics it has
to do with performing certain Quantum
Gates like T Gates non- Clifford Gates
that are hard especially when they're
error corrected uh you can do that by
first generating a magic state for your
Tate and then once you have that state
doing the Tate is just a a set of
Clifford Gates which are easy now this
doesn't obviate the need to generate the
magic State that's still hard but once
you have the state then it becomes easy
uh netcast is a is a sort of bringing
this concept to the classical domain for
machine learning so in netcast you have
a server this is a thing that's
generating your magic States in a Time
frequency basis and then you have a
client and that's the thing that's going
to use your magic States and these can
be separated over an optical link and it
can be tens of
kilometers this the magic state has this
time frequency basis um and this is
basically a matrix it's one of the many
matrices that you're going to send from
the server to the client to perform the
uh to run the neural network and the
client drives a modulator uh and then um
and then uses some Dem multiplexing
Optics and that computes the vector y =
w * X so that's the ACT that's the
waiting section of your neural network
and then you go on to the next layer you
wait that one and and perform the
nonlinearities in the client and so
forth
so we demonstrated this um again we used
a silicon photonic technology to
demonstrate this this was a uh 48
Channel MOX Zender uh modulator array we
drove this with a laser array with 16
different wavelengths and that generated
our photonic magic State and once we
have that state we wanted to show that
you can really do de localized
computation so we decided to separate
the server and the client um over a
deployed optical fiber link connecting
MIT down here in downtown Cambridge to
Lincoln lab over here in uh Lexington
Massachusetts I don't qu I don't quite
have a map of Tokyo to superimpose on
here but I think that's something like
Tokyo to Kawasaki or
Yokohama uh the fiber takes a bit of a
longer route so it's 86 it's 43 km but
we're going there and back again so that
we can have both the server and the
client at MIT in different rooms so that
the grad student doesn't have to go back
and forth to do the
experiment so this is a a good example
of the kind of data that you'll get so
you get some weights they get mixed with
your activations like this this number
three U you they get multiplied then you
sum up the uh the multiplied data and
yeah and you record the output and this
is this is what you call a calibration
curve so this should just be a line uh
this is desired data and this is the
measure data and you get an we get an
error of about 05% so that's about eight
bits of precision which is good uh8 bits
is what most people need to do a a large
number of neuron netw Works in
practice and you can also look at the
energy consumption required the optical
energy consumption is limited by
detector noise and it ends up being on
the order of 100,000 photons or so and
if you use a Quantum loed detector it
can be even down to a single Photon uh
and we have some work about how you
could uh do this with coherent detectors
which would be Quantum limited this was
a cryogenic demo but if it's coherent it
would be U room
temperature okay so this uh it's this is
uh it's also very interesting because of
in information security uh reasons so
this is kind of an architecture with
this architecture you're never sharing
the activation data with the server so
there's privacy in that sense but you'd
also like to have privacy in the sense
that the server never fully rals its
model to the user either and we found
that there are ways to do this with
modifications to the algorithm where you
can get efficient uh deep learning
inference even when you're leaking only
a very fraction small fraction of the
weight data and a very small fraction of
the activation data um and this can be
proved using theorems related to Quantum
communication so this final thing that
I'd like to talk about in the last three
minutes I have is uh photonics for uh
dense dense or highly scalable computing
based on coherent detection and so this
is based on a question that is a as a
new architecture it's based on a
question which is if I have two Optical
waves X and each each of these Optical
signals encodes a number X and Y and
what's the most efficient way to
multiply those
signals you can't do it just by sending
the signals through each other I mean
Optics they just go straight through
each other uh interference is a linear
and so that will never produce a
nonlinear result uh you can do it
through something that's called
nonlinear Optics some frequency
generation uh but that's is very very
very challenging it's a whole field and
it usually doesn't work at low
energy and the solution to this is
actually it won the Nobel Prize and it
won the Nobel Prize back in 2020
1921 and it's this concept called the
photoelectric effect which is if you
have a light incident on uh a metal or
in our case a photod detector it
produces a a stream of electrons and the
number of electrons it's related to the
intensity of the field but the intensity
of the field is your electric field
squared or E
squared so that's a nonlinearity and you
can combine that nonlinearity with just
interference and you get something that
multiplies two numbers on a photocurrent
and this is something that we're all
familiar with in coherent Optics is
called a homine detector they have the
same thing in radio frequency uh you can
do it to multiply two numbers you can
also do it to multiply two vectors and
if you have many such detectors you can
multiply a matrix on a vector and so
this was the architecture that we
proposed back in 2019 um and in 2022 we
also realized this one um to generate
the optical signals you needed for the
weights we used an array of vixel so
these are uh these are microscale lasers
we used a fan a a phase mask to Fan out
the data appropriately and then we had a
detector array um this is just a p
picture of the pixels pixels can be very
fast they can modulate very fast and
they can be very compact uh so those are
the two things we need and this is just
an example of the fan out experiment and
uh an example of the data we didn't get
quite as good accuracy it was on the
order of 2% not 0.5% um but this was I
think there's room for improving that
and I just kind of wanted since I'm out
of time I just wanted to uh highlight
how the this approach based on coherent
detection is something that we're
looking towards spinning off a startup
on uh so our hope is that the
theoretical performance of the Prototype
that we developed in this paper already
sits uh well above what's possible with
state-of-the-art electronics and our
hope is that building on that prototype
and making this theoretical performance
and actual performance um that we can
make this into a useful product and it's
also something where I think that
there's a space in the market for this
kind of an approach uh there were a lot
of different uh uh startups that start
started out doing optical Computing that
went into Optical interconnects and so
now somebody has to carry on the idea of
optical Computing and so with that I'd
uh like to conclude and if you're
interested more uh we do have these uh
papers and I'd really like to
acknowledge all the great people who
collaborated with us on this work thank
you very
[Applause]
much all right so the first one about
the topic is is it possible to create
General Purp a general purpose computer
with photonic systems only are there any
obstacles to Achi achieving universality
or tur
completeness so possible it's certainly
possible the question is will that
computer be efficient and the answer is
probably not uh so the closest to to
this direction that I've seen is there
there are a lot of this work on
efficient photonic transistors and
transistors are very important primitive
uh to any kind of universal Computing um
there was some work out of
ntbr uh that demonstrated transistors
out of fto dual scale at around a
gigahertz speed so that's good uh the
transistors
were tens of microns in size so you're
you're immediately going to have
something that's much larger than uh a
standard chip if you implement many of
these
transistors and I don't know if there's
a fundamental way to fix that
fundamentally Optics is going to be
limited by the wavelength of light so
that's going to be microns and
transistors can go down to tens of
nanometers but I but I think that uh you
don't need full universality to make use
of make use of optics for computation I
think that the best way to use Optics is
to use optics for what it's good at and
then do the rest of the stuff in
electronics
okay so once it reaches the scaleup
point how do you envision the
integration between photonic Computing
systems and electronic ones since the
input lag can be an issue due to the
orders of magnitude Gap and so yeah this
is related to the first question which
is if you make if you have a hybrid
computer with both Optical and
electronic you have to do conversion
between the two uh so you'll need you'll
need Dax and adcs to go from Optical to
go from analog to digital and then
you'll need modulators and uh detectors
and so I think that a key point to
mention here is that the the number of
Ops you perform in a matrix Vector
product in the optical domain is much
much larger than the amount of data that
comes in and out uh so if we're talking
about a thousand by, matrix
multiplication you send in a vector of
size a thousand and you read out a
vector of a SI a thousand the number of
Ops is about a million and so you can
still get very good throughputs even
with uh uh even if you're electronically
bottlenecked uh because you're doing a
million for the cost of a thousand but
in order to get those advantages you
need really need to scale something up
where you can where you can process
those matrices of size a
thousand so let's
see okay so this question is uh when do
you expect a photonic Quantum Computing
uh system to be available for an
industrial use so there are two things
there one is when do you expect a
photonic Quantum Computing system to be
available and second when will it be
industrially relevant and these these
startups already have prototypes out
there for example zanadu has a a
particular system involving uh U
involving delay lines and interference
and I think at this point I would say
those are primarily science experiments
that they're trying to engineer very
well when it will become a universal
processor there are a bunch of uh open
questions um kind of fundamental open
questions and technologies that need to
be developed before it becomes a pro be
becomes a universal processor um if that
happens within 5 to 10 years I think
that that would be great but I I can't
guarantee that and for an industrial
use this is the applications question
and it's one that I think no one has a
good answer to to there are there are
very specific there are very few
specific applications where we know
quantum computers have an exponential
speed up and some of these are really
useful like uh U like a RSA decryption
or uh quantum chemistry simulation uh
some of them are not very have no use uh
like very specific toy problems that you
put in a paper and then there are a
bunch of problems that might have a
speed up uh especially problems related
to um optimization and so I think more
research needs to be done uh to see if
there will be industrially useful
algorithms and that's the last question
thank you