My name is Jim Flynn. I am a program
director at MIT corporate relations and
I want to welcome you back from lunch.
Uh hopefully everyone is fed and have
enough energy to uh power through this
afternoon.
uh we'll kick off our next session is uh
called chips code and people essentially
AI hardware AI software as well as AI
training. So handling our first segment,
it is my pleasure to introduce Jesus Del
Alamo who is a professor of electrical
engineering and computer science at MIT
and has also in the past served as the
director of the micros systemystems
technology lab at MIT and he will talk
to you about the current state of AI
hardware. Let's give a warm welcome for
Jesus.
Thank you. Good afternoon. Thank you for
inviting me. What an audience. This is
really this is really fantastic. I'm
delighted to be here. So yes, today I
want to share some thoughts about the
future of a hardware. Of course, it's a
it's a it's a very large topic. So I
will only be able to touch on a on a few
on a few
issues. So uh this conference is about
AI and so therefore the four key pillars
of AI are going to be discussed which
are algorithms, data sets, human talent
of course and and hardware. And this
talks this talk is about hardware and
hardware today is being is seen as the
key to enable the long-term progress in
AI that we have seen in the last few
years to continue for years to come
without burning the planet along the
way. In fact, you can see the the uh
importance of AI hardware in this chart.
It's a little bit busy, but let let me
go through it. What this chart
represents in a semi-logarithmic scale
on the y-axis is the computational
performance of the computing the
computers that have been used to train
the various models in the last uh you
know 20 years or so uh as a function of
time. So notice it's a it's a
semi-ogarithmic scale, a logarithmic
scale on the y- axis, a linear scale on
the x axis. And you can see that for the
first few years in this chart up to
about 2012, there was progress that went
about uh 2x doubling of uh twice uh
doubling every two years or so, which is
the rate of progress of mors law.
However, something happened in 2012, an
inflation point that really resulted in
a massive increase in in the progress
that went from doubling every two years
to doubling every two months. Now what
happened there was the advent of the
GPU, the graphical processing unit as
the engine to implement these algorithms
as opposed to CPU standard uh processing
units before that uh that were used uh
in the past and is this new hardware the
GPU and the massive parallelism that it
allows that resulted in this tremendous
improvement in the productivity in the
growth in the computing capabilities
that were used to train these models. So
this is to make the point that a
specialized hardware makes a huge
difference and as a result we should be
thinking into the future of AI hardware
innovating in terms of new hardware to
continue to uh introduce inflation
points of this type. Now you get a
picture of what is going on today in
this chart. It's a little bit busy
again, but this is a chart that uh maps
in this two-dimensional space of peak
performance in giga operations per
second as a function of peak power of
many AI processors and accelerators that
have been demonstrated out there. These
are also logarithmic scale. So they span
many orders of magnitude. On the bottom
left you see small um edge type uh
machines and moving towards the top
right edge you see the very big data
centers with the big engines that are
implementing the large language models
and you can see how there is a very
fundamental trade-off uh between power
and performance. If you want more
performance you really need to be
willing to to uh burn more power. It
seems it seems uh inevitable to do that.
But in fact, if you look in more detail,
you will actually see that there is a
fundamental barrier there that
essentially no demonstration has ever
crossed in terms of this trade-off of
power and u and performance which is
given by 10 terops per watt. And the
reason for that fundamental limit is
because the underlying technology that
is being used in all these accelerators
and processors is the same. It is
conventional SMOS, the mainstream micro
electronics technology which is making
progress along the way but is making
relatively slow progress. And so we are
facing this fundamental limit that we
need to find a way to
cross. And in fact if you look in more
detail you will see that we are in a
trajectory which is start which is
starting to bend over which means that
if you want much more performance as is
desirable for these very large language
models that are being introduced. you
can see that you need to burn a super
linearly more power in order to in order
to enable this. So we are truly in an
unsustainable trajectory that needs to
be corrected right and and so that is
why you have seen how in the last few
months we are hearing uh the major uh
data server companies uh talking about
you know using nuclear energy to to feed
the data centers because the amount of
energy that is going to be required to
implement all these models is really
going to be gigantic. So clearly this is
something that needs some uh some
drastic new approach. We need as
indicated in the red arrow on the on the
top left. We need a new trajectory in
which we can continue to improve the
performance and the capabilities of
computing but to do that at much modest
increases in uh in power. Now Joe Hinton
u has been telling us now for for quite
some time. He he won the Nobel Prize in
physics as you know just last year that
there is a complete new way of doing AI
computation that promises much great
efficient uh increases in the energy
efficiency and that is analog computing.
In fact he says we can use very low
power analog computation. You can have
trillion way parallelism using things
like meristers. This is the kilobytes uh
for the weights. So analog computing
based on this new approach which I'm
going to tell you a little bit about
really promises great enhancements in
energy efficiency in uh in in AI
computation. And in fact in in this
other talk this is a slide from a talk
that he gave in Cambridge uh titled two
paths to intelligence. He actually talks
specifically about the core mathematical
function that underlies uh neural
networks and deep learning which is the
vector uh matrix multiplication. And he
says that if you implement the vector
matrix multiplication in the analog
domain using a network of resistors as
it's as you can see in the diagram
resistors which conductance can be
programmed to have the weights of a
neural network then you can use the
combination of ohms law and kickoff's
law to perform the vector matrix
multiplication in the analog domain with
much greater savings in in energy as
opposed to the conventional digital
domain which is how it's being done
today. and and so so the key is is this
network of resistors with a with a value
of the resistance or a value of the
conductance which can be programmed and
can be held in memory. It is this key
device which he calls meters sometimes
is also called a synapse which is in
effect a programmable nonvolatile
resistor meaning that you can program a
value of the resistance and it will be
held in memory until a new value is
programmed. And this is the key in this
in these two dimensional arrays to um to
implement analog neural networks that
perform the vector matrix
multiplication. Now essentially the way
this works is as the diagram in the
middle shows if we look at the
conductance which is the inverse of the
resistance of the resistor. If we apply
positive voltages positive pulses uh
across the device or to a third terminal
that is acting on the device then the
conductance increases in a programmable
way as you can see in the staircase on
the right. And if you apply a series of
negative pulses then the conductance
drops again in a staircase way um as
more negative pulses arrive and and when
you stop the pulses the value of the
conductance will remain in memory until
you change it again. Now the specs that
we need for a for a device like this to
really result in the great savings in
energy efficiency of analog neural
networks are fairly well understood and
I have a summary of them in in the table
here. So we know what we want. The
problem is that today in spite of having
quite a wide range of options there
based on new materials and based on new
physical principles, there is no one
device technology that has been found
that meets all the specs that are
required to to implement these neuron
networks which is which is why folks
like me which are interested in
materials and transistors and devices
are really interested in in this
problem. And so a number of us at MIT
are working on a number of concepts. How
can we implement these membrrisers or
synaptic devices or AI transistors
however you want to call them uh with
the right uh portfolio of properties are
required to implement neural networks.
So I'm going to tell you about two
projects uh that are going on in my lab.
On the left is a project uh that is
based on devices that are based on
proton intercolation onto a
semiconductor. On the right uh devices
that are based on the federal effect
these are ongoing research projects in
my lab. So on the right I'll give you
some more details on that. There is if I
may point here there is a a thin layer
of tungsten oxide here. Tungsten oxide
is actually a semiconductor. So you can
think of it as a as a transistor channel
except that it's very easy to to
introduce ions into the tungsten oxide
and the ions will the right ion will
dope the tungsten oxide enhancing the
conductivity. If you take the ions away
then you can reduce the conductivity. So
we have two contacts uh uh on both sides
of a tungxen oxide to measure the
conductivity of the conductance of a
tungxen oxide and we are going to
introduce ions in in our case protons
from a reservoir which is this paladium
gate here through an electrolyte which
in our case is uh ph uh phosphocilicate
glass and that is one of the key
innovations of of my research group. So
essentially what you have here is a tiny
nano battery that injects protons from
this reservoir into the tungsten oxide
on demand. If we apply a positive
voltage we get protons in. If we apply a
negative voltage we get the protons out.
And if we remove the voltage the protons
will remain in place so that the device
holds the memory of the conductance that
has been set by the proton concentration
that has been introducing here.
Essentially, we can control the doping
level of a semiconductor at room
temperature simply by uh using these
tiny nano batteries. Something that we
cannot possibly do with silicon. And on
the right is a different device concept
uh where we have essentially it's a thin
transistor. If for those of you that uh
know about transistors that are used on
for displays for example, it's sort of
upside down. This is the gate. This is
the dialectric. This is the
semiconductor channel which in our case
is indium gallium zinc oxide. And then
the two contacts for the source and
drain. So we can measure the conductance
of this channel uh by putting a voltage
across the source and drain. What's
unique about this device is that this
dialectric is actually a ferroelectric
is half new siliconium oxide a material
that has been found recently to have uh
prominent ferctric characteristics and
that is also silicon compatible. And so
applying a a suitable voltage across the
havoc silicon oxide, you can program the
polarization state and that changes the
threshold voltage of the semiconductor
channel and that changes the current
through it. And once you remove that
voltage, the fer the polarization state
is held in memory in this in uh in this
ferctic material and it only can be
changed by applying the the reverse
voltage. So again we have a device in
which we can program a conductance that
is read through a semiconductor channel
and is held in memory until we change it
again. So these are two types of devices
that we are working in my lab. Now a key
requirement for any technology of this
kind is that it has to be integrated on
top of a SMOS platform because it has to
leverage the SMOS backbone that is going
to continue to make a lot of progress
along the way for years to come. Right?
So the way the technology is going to
look like this is a a cartoon schematic
is we'll have a silicon wafer with the
silicon transistors at the at the w at
the uh silicon level and then we'll have
many layers of interconnects and
somewhere in this tall interconnect
stack of uh of a modern chip there will
be a layer where the AI accelerator will
sit with these synapi synaptic devices
or memoristic devices and so it has to
be built in there in the middle of the
cos process on the back end which is the
ation that we use for to refer to these
where all the interconnects are. And as
a result, it has to be fully SIMOS
compatible. It has to be done in a SIMOS
fab. It has to use SIMOS compatible
materials, SIMO compatible processes. It
has to be able to withstand 400 degrees
centiggrades, which is the temperature
required for the rest of interconnects
that are going to come on top. And also
it has to u be able to uh to be done
everything has to be done at temperature
less than 400 degrees because you don't
want to damage anything that has been
fabricated before. So there are many
constraints that a technology of this
kind has to fulfill which we are
incorporating in in our research in in
our lab. So let me give you some more
details of this um this uh uh proton
intercalation device that we have been
investigating in my group. Here you see
a top view of one of our experimental
devices. You see the uh the source and
drain are here. This is these golden
regions. The gate is coming like this.
The active area of the device is right
there. This is the tungsten oxide
channel. So the active area is right
there where the overlap of all these
regions takes place which is in the
nanometer scale 30 nanometers long and
60 nanometers wide. So we are
emphasizing extremely uh extreme scaling
for for our transistors or for our
devices to achieve very high density.
This is a transmission electron
microraph cross-section. You can see
here the tungsten oxide channel very
very thin layer with two contacts at
both ends. You can see here the
phosphocosilic phosphocyic glass
electrolyte and the paladium gate and
also reservoir. So the protons come from
the paladium through the PSG into the
tungsten oxide and then back and we read
the conductance of the tungsten oxide by
putting a voltage between these two gold
electrons and passing current through
it. Now this device actually works quite
well. Here is some electrical
characteristics similar to what I show
you earlier that we desire. Here we are
applying uh five nancond pulses uh uh
positive and you can see how the
conductance of the device increases and
when we switch to negative pulses the
conductance of the device decreases. We
span a very large dynamic range about
20x or so in conductance. the uh the
trajectory is fairly linear and
symmetric on the way up and on the way
down and as I said it responds to uh
very very short pulses which means that
this is a technology that could really
operate at very high uh speeds something
that's important is to show that you
have retention in the end this must have
memory through the uh to withstand the
training process in a in a in a deep
learning uh system and so you can see
here how the device has been programmed
here's again conductance as a as a
function of uh pulse number we have uh
apply a pulse to program the conductance
to the next level and then we read that
conductance 100 times one per second and
you can see how the value is held in
memory quite well. This is still a
little bit of a a little bit of a drift
but uh quite limited. Uh so to show you
that this really holds uh memory quite
well and of course the device shows very
high endurance and repeatability. Here
are 10 to the five pulses over 30 hours.
You can see the device has a very very
reproducible um
characteristics and this is a benchmark
with some work that has been done uh in
industry by uh other by other
colleagues. uh the metric that we are
using here is this is all about energy
from the very beginning I've emphasized
that right so the the metric that we
using here is the energy that is
required to change the conductance of
this device by a certain amount so that
ratio is a reasonable measure of energy
efficiency that we can use different
investigators to compare different
device technologies so here I'm showing
you two designs from other folks this is
based on oxygen ions this is based on
lithium ions our work I remind you is
based on protons And we chose protons
because well the proton is the lightest
ion that exists and as a result is going
to be able to move fast. It's very small
and so it's going to be able to move
fast and responds to a very small
voltage which again is what we want to
achieve very high energy efficiency. So
you can see how by uh using a much
lighter ion that these folks and by
scaling this is the area of the device
to to nanoscale dimensions we have been
able to enhance this measure of energy
efficiency by many orders of magnitude
that that gives you a sense of of the
promise of of this technology and in
fact the um PhD student that carried out
this research then when he graduated he
went on to set up a company to try to
commercialize to commercialize this
technology which I I I found really
fantastic and in fact he was I
understand speaking earlier today and I
saw that he has a booth or uh displaying
there with some some of u some of the
ideas and and the uh where where the
company sits corporation and um and so
he's in the process of you know bringing
this technology to a maturity level that
eventually can be implemented in the
real world. So I I find that extremely
exciting. All right. So we've talked
about new devices and new based on new
materials and in some cases new physical
principles to implement anal analog
neural networks which which George
Hinton has told us is the way to achieve
greater uh efficiency enhancements. It
turns out that you can also do analog
neural networks without requiring new
devices or new materials just using
SIMOS. And so here is the work and I'm
now going to be talking about the
research of other colleagues at MIT.
This is the work of professor Anatha
Chandra Kasan and his postoc Aya Ammer
who are using SRAMM which is a static
random access memory. It's a standard
memory design uses using SIMOS to
implement analog neural networks in in a
similar way. So so now instead of a
device you've got an SRAM cell which
will contain six seven nine transistors.
So it's a much bigger creature which is
why in the end we really are going to
need new devices and new materials. But
you can really make a lot of progress uh
using SIMOS and in particular they have
demonstrated an all analog voice
activity detection with a neural network
here that contains uh three levels and
here is a chip implementation in a four
14 nanometer fined process that really
shows that this is real and that they
can make all these work with great
energy efficiency.
Some more examples on the left here I'm
showing you the work of VBNZ and Joel
Emmer other colleagues also in
electrical engineering who are also
investigating analog neural networks in
this case they are developing tools to
design these networks depending on what
specific technology you have meristers
or SRAMs or whatever it is that you have
and and other system level parameters to
optimize for throughput and to optimize
for energy efficiency. the parameter
space is vast and so therefore you need
new design tools that are going to be
able to analyze all these and find an
optimum design and on the right is a
colleague dear Kenlon who's using
photonics to do deep learning and as he
likes to say we process AI algorithms at
the speed of light so a very a very uh
cool
technology a couple more examples uh
also castan is is already examining
issues of security on these new types of
neural
networks is investing investigating what
he calls tiny ML, tiny machine learning,
essentially tiny um um inference uh
engines to be used on the edge that are
have very little memory that have used
that have very little energy and that
have very little processing capability
and yet that they can do smart things as
as a way to bring efficient AI to the to
the edge. And then at the bottom here is
also a cool project from another
colleague Ronan Han who is using uh
large language models to help on the
design of uh analog
circuits. All of this is taking place in
the context and I will finish with this
at MIT which is the MIT AI hardware
program. This is a collaboration between
the MIT school of engineering and the
Schwartzman College of Computing to
essentially explore new concepts of AI
hardware to drastically enhance the
energy efficiency of implementation of
AI in the in the future. So let me share
with you very briefly our vision which I
have already mentioned in this talk.
Essentially our vision is that sustained
progress in AI is going to demand a
specialized hardware. I show you the
difference that it made already a few
years ago and that's what we need to
continue to do forward. Energy
efficiency should be should be our
paramount goal and that is going to
require new devices, new materials,
perhaps new physical principles. I show
you some nano battery based uh devices
very different from conventional
transistors. But all of this has to
leverage the SIMOS backbone. Simos is
going to continue to be this amazing
technology extremely versatile and
powerful that is going to continue to
make progress for many years to come. We
must leverage it to the max. So this is
going to require a vertical integrated
effort. there there are no well-
definfined boundaries between the
various various levels of abstraction as
we have in conversional electronics. So
we need to be able to work up and down
the entire stack from materials all the
way to algorithms and we need to be able
to do hardware and algorithmic
co-design. And finally for this to be
successful we are convinced that we need
to do this in collaboration in close
collaboration with industry. You know in
academia we can select problems that are
fun that are interesting and we could
just immerse ourselves and and enjoy
solving them. But we at MIT also like to
work on relevant problems that if we can
fix them, if we can solve them, we can
make a contribution to humanity. And
that's what industry brings to us. If we
are in close collaboration with
industry, that awareness of what are the
problems that if we if we can uh make
progress on can really make a difference
in the world. The value proposition that
we offer to the companies that join in
this program is the ability to define
together with a principal investigator a
research project that is tailored to the
interest of your company to follow the
progress of that pro of that project
very closely over the years and at the
same time to gain awareness on all the
other projects that all companies that
participate in the program are funding
so that you get a much broader vision of
as I gave you very briefly here on on
the broader range of AI hardware
research that's going on at MIT. We do
that through an annual symposium which
actually took place yesterday and we
also do that through a full online um
update that takes place online uh in the
fall and there you see the entire the
entire portfolio and of course there are
many other many other benefits in the
program. And I finish by showing you a
picture of our secret weapon in AI
hardware, which is our beautiful uh
still very new MIT nano facility in the
Lisa Tissu building, which is this
extraordinary facility for nanop
fabrication and nanotechnology that
allows us to prototype all kinds of
novel concept based on new materials
such as I show you a few examples today.
Thank you for your interest and I'll be
happy to take some questions.
Oh, there are questions
here. I am not so knowledgeable of some
of these some of these issues that are
being asked here as as as you saw I work
at a at the materials and device level.
There is a lot of interest on quantum
hardware. In fact, yesterday at the
symposium, Dear Kangloo, who is working
on photonics was presenting a number of
concepts that were really spanning the
intersection between photonics and and
quantum computing as an area that is
really uh uh incredibly fertile for
computing but also for for
communications. So definitely that is an
area that overlaps strongly with with
the area of photonics uh AI that I think
is very worthwhile to explore and the
key person at MIT is
develop so can quantum hardware give us
that another inflection inflection point
to the progress of uh of AI well that is
that is definitely the hope uh it's
going to take a while according to what
Dangru told yesterday. But that is the
hope. We need something that will bend
the curve and also essentially increase
the rate of progress by a factor of 10
in in a
hardware. That seems to be it. Thank you
again.
[Applause]