good afternoon everyone
my name is Erica capable James I'm a
professor of medical anthropology and
urban studies at the Massachusetts
Institute of
Technology and it is my very great honor
to be able to introduce an important
topic that is critical to the world
today and that is thinking about the
future of Gaza and as specifically
healthc care in Gaza uh we are very
fortunate to have three experts who are
going to speaking about their personal
experiences and their lived experiences
both as Palestinians and as uh
individuals who have volunteered and
spent a tremendous amount of time
working in both Israel and
Palestine these issues are important not
just because of the the the current
acute phase of conflict but also because
so many countries around the world are
struggling with what to do during and
after conf conflict how to bring people
who have suffered
tremendously uh back to health back to
mental health and you know to begin re
building their lives I'm familiar with
these topics from my own research in
Haiti over the past 30 years now and I
see that the cycles of conflict and
violence sometimes recur when healing
does not take place um for individuals
families and communities there also
needs to
justice so without further Ado I'd like
to introduce uh Dr Iman Ansari who's a
personal friend and uh a physician here
in Boston and she is going to be our
moderator for the day um I I there's not
enough that I can say about how
wonderful she is as a person how much
she does as a
humanitarian and uh and she's an expert
so with no further Ado let me pass it to
you
Iman thank you so much Erica uh good
afternoon everyone so Erica asked me to
introduce myself and then give you a
little bit of a background about me and
what got me into medicine so my name is
Iman Al khadra and my husband's last
name is Ansari so I became Iman Ansari
um I am a pediatric pulmonologist
Intensive Care Unit uh physician and I
practice as an emergency medicine
physician
here in Boston um I am um also um as
Erica mentioned uh very invested in uh
social justice uh issues um and have
been working very actively in my
children's School our Hospital our
medical school um on elevating issues of
social justice not only for the
Palestinians but in general um after my
kids um grew um a bit older and I was
able to travel away I started uh going
to Palestine on medical missions um
through an NGO called uh Palestine
children Relief Fund
pcrf and um after many years of um going
on missions over there to uh
specifically to the West Bank um I
joined the board uh of directors of pcrf
and um I'm currently on their board of
directors my path into medicine is the
is not an unusual path I used to think
um whenever I I talk about my path uh to
my American friends that um you know
maybe because I'm coming from the Middle
East it's different but I think it is a
shared path um I was born and raised in
soui Arabia to uh two parents who are
Palestinians my father was born in um
safad a town um city in the north um on
the mountain in the Galilee um and my
mother was born in haa
and in 1948 uh they were forcibly
displaced to uh Syria they grew up there
and then they got married moved to Saudi
Arabia where I was born and raised very
traditional home very traditional
expectation education was super
important for my parents they wanted us
to have um University degree uh but for
the girl they preferred that I have like
English literature degree or Arabic
literature or even science but uh
ultimate goal is I'll have the degree
I'll put it in the kitchen and I'll
become the best mother ever um so for me
to ask to go to Medicine was pretty
unusual um my older brother is a
cardiologist and he preceded me in uh
going to medicine and I thought um the
smartest people go to Medicine you get
to help people you get to make a
difference I wanted to make a difference
and um I decided to go to Medicine
initially my father um did not uh did
not approve um and we tried we tried our
hardest with aunts and uncles and
grandparents to convince my dad and
eventually my brother told him you know
she's pretty headstrong so uh let her go
to Medicine she'll be busy with with
school workor and um and exams that she
will not have time for trouble and my
father you know bought that um argument
that rationale and allowed me to go to
Medicine and then forced my two sisters
after me to to pursue the same path to
keep them busy um finished medical
school in Saudi Arabia again I wanted to
come to the US uh to do postgraduate
training like my brother and my father
said no unless I was married uh so when
my um now husband asked to meet me and
get to know me I told him let's cut to
the chase do you want to marry me but
I'm on a mission I'm coming to the US
and he said fine so we got married and
came here and um I've been mostly in
Boston ever since I did residency at
Tufts and then my pulmonary and critical
care Fellowship where at children at
Children's Hospital I went to Cincinnati
briefly um and then came back to Boston
and um from there um like my work has
focused on my clinical work um I have
four children that I raised here in um
in Newton in
Massachusetts and uh over the past six
years um my humanitarian work uh became
of um serious um level of importance to
me um one thing I will say as I have one
more minute before I I turn it to our
first guest um uh when I went for the
first time to Palestine and Israel um it
was a very emotional visit I've never
been there before I've never um had
immediate family live there I don't know
what is there so when I went there I
went just like any American who's
visiting that land for the first time
and it was an
eyeopener um we'll talk more in our
conversations um about health care over
there um but um I had a sense of
responsibility to as a pediatrician to
the children over there because they
could have been me and they deserve the
same health care that my children are
getting in Boston and that gave me that
you know sense of responsibility and
commitment that I will do everything I
can to elevate the level of Health Care
over there to help people there um be
treated with the same standard of care
we have here in the US and now I would
like to introduce our first guest um my
colleague and if I can call you my
friend me H Dr
abua Dr abua is special izes in Internal
Medicine and is currently completing
both a clinical Fellowship in critical
care so she will be an intensivist like
me at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical
Center in Boston she's also doing a
research fellowship at the Middle East
initiative at the Harvard Kennedy School
she is a Palestinian bedwin um physician
um who uh practiced in Israel uh she was
one of the first respondent um at
treating incoming victims of uh October
7th on that day she lost many colleagues
friends neighbors and in the subsequent
weeks and months she lost also friends
in
RDA across the border uh during Israel's
um um devastating military campaign on
razza um throughout this traumatic
period in her life she refused to
surrender uh her sorrow or concern for
all innocent victims of violence um Yaba
um um can you tell us about um your
background and your path into Medicine
sure so uh as you as you mentioned I'm a
Palestinian citizen of Israel um many
many people are not really familiar with
this definition uh some call us Israeli
Arabs or some other definition but
actually like 20 21% of Israeli citizens
are actually Palestinians who are um
whose Heritage is Palestinian and um
they were basically not refugees after U
the n in 1948 so my ancestors um uh
stayed in the makab the the desert area
of Israel the South part um and we're
we're Palestinian uh with with an
Israeli citizenship and I grew up as a
as a a bedwin girl in in Israel um but
my parents as in a way similar to your
parents really wanted us to get good
education so I actually grew up in a in
a Jewish town in Israel um which made it
easier for me I guess to to get into um
medical school because the the education
system in Israel is very segregated so
there's like a um an education system
for Arabs and education system for
Jewish people and because I I grew up in
a Jewish town uh I I had the privilege
to go into a Jewish um Hebrew speaking
school um and I I always knew that I
wanted to go uh into medicine first
because my mother was diagnosed with
breast cancer um when I was
14 um and but also I felt like this is
the best way to to help people and
especially I wanted I always knew I
wanted to go back to my own Community
the bedwin community was very much
underserved um and and helped them and
actually after I I I went to medical
school in Jerusalem the Hebrew
University and when I graduated I I did
my internship and my residency in sooka
medical center in beleva uh which is
like the biggest biggest city in the in
the South um and and was actually
started my social activism and some
political activism as well um looking
into Health disparities and working to
promote um Better Health Care or Health
Equity for uh uh bedwin patients uh
starting with trying to prevent genetic
diseases but uh later on I had some
projects on diabetes and and uh um
trying to promote and uh advocate for
better access to
healthcare um as many of the bedwin in
this area live in um unrecognized
Villages so they're like these um places
that are not recognized by by the formal
authorities in Israel so they they're
not entitled to basic infastructure like
you know um uh electricity running water
uh shelters which is one thing that we
um we had to deal with uh as of October
7th 2023 and like 100,000 people are um
getting direct hits by Rockets but they
have nowhere to run uh because there are
no shelters um and no clinics and even
like the the a small amount of clinics
that there were that we had there
actually shut down um after October 7th
uh so that's that's how I um I knew that
I wanted always to you know help those
who are most in need uh and also that's
how I got in a way to my research Focus
which is um politics of healthcare or
the intersection between Healthcare and
politics and I guess we're going to talk
a little bit about this um later
on but mean you were able to enter Gazza
because my understanding is that um
Israelis cannot could not enter Gaza
correct for us it's illegal um so
basically what I did so on October 7th I
was uh I was an attending in sooka so in
Bersa and I woke woke up uh at 6:30 a.m
with like this the the alarms and the
sirens and the uh sounds of rockets
falling um which sadly for me as someone
who grew up in this area is we're used
to it so uh for me it was like okay
another another morning uh of yet again
hearing Sirens but then I I went to the
hospital um and the the patient started
coming so the patients from the the the
Kim the Gaza envelope the bed Villages
started coming and this is when we
figure it out that this is this is
different from what we uh we we know and
I have to say I was trained in this
Hospital uh it's the busiest emergency
room in Israel and I've never seen it um
the way I've seen it this day hundreds
of patients hundreds of bodies many
people came already you know Dead on
Arrival um even kids who were directly
hit by
Rockets um but I I I have to say I
um at some point like in the afternoon
of this of this day which was really
devastating
um I looked around and I saw that the
people around me both patients and
Physicians who were both Jewish and
Arabs or Jewish Israelis and
Palestinians
um and and I think I two things came to
my mind when I saw this the first was as
I said I we're kind of like used to the
armed conflicts or what we call military
operations right um so the one thing
that that came to my mind is like okay
now I know how War looks like looks like
and how it looks like on the other side
when the Israeli Army is bombing Gaza
because it's the again the separation is
so
um strict that I don't really get to it
is it is illegal for me to go into Gaza
even though like uh I have friends there
I family members there so we don't
really know what's going on there uh but
on October 7th I I felt like I had some
uh idea and then the second thing that I
that I've thought of is that this is we
keep saying that this is a conflict
between you know Jews and Arabs or like
Israelis and Palestinians but honestly
no this is um um at this moment in time
I figure that this is a conflict between
people who believe that violence is the
answer and we need to you know with more
violence we will try to we will solve
this conflict and people who are
actually believing in in saving lives
and in humanity and um they dropped
everything and came to the hospital that
day uh to save lives and after that in
the past in the uh three months after
that the before I moved to
Boston um we opened another unit and and
I did a lot of uh work in the community
to help people who were again directly
hit by by rockets and we did try to go
into Gaza I uh I volunteer with physics
for human rights Israel and they had
mobile clinics in Gaza but they couldn't
again it was illegal for them to go in
but uh we continued to uh stay in touch
with um um with the hospitals there and
with some uh Hospital directors and
Physicians and in the past year since
then we've also fundraised um I was um
involved with many other organizations
and we fundraised over three $3 million
um to World Central Kitchen to get into
um to give it to humanitarian aids to
gasa and specifically
food um and since then I've been
documenting um what was happening
specifically attacks on health care in
Gaza speaking to friends and colleagues
who um who are working
there um and maybe just to give some
some data uh is that and I don't know
how how um people like how
knowledgeable um the you know the
general population is about this but uh
since October
7th
um about more than 50% of the hospitals
in Gaza are are now non-functional so
they had um
36 original hospitals and now only 16
are functional uh the last one that was
um uh that was that actually collapsed
was kamarad Juan in the southern part of
Gaza that was actually evacuated on
December
28th uh and um the director was uh
detained and still like the his location
is
unknown um
the actually according to the
wh um data in the past year there was
about 1500 attacks on health care
facilities and staff in armed conflicts
around the world more than a thousand of
them uh were against um health care
facilities and and staff in Gaza
specifically um so this is kind of like
um at least for me it's a it's a it's an
obvious case of it's not either or it's
bad to you know to
um OB it's it's it's even crazy for me
that I need to say that it's bad to kill
people right and it's bad to act in
violence and I've seen it for both s
like in both sides both in Israel
against Israelis uh and against in
Palestinians in
Gaza uh and I'm I'm so glad that we're
having this conversation because I think
more people should know what's going on
there and we should actually think of
what we're going to do
next thank you thank you yes mean so um
to just um highlight something that you
said that it it for you it's not
Palestinians versus Jews or Jews versus
Palestinians in in Israel and and RZA as
much as because Palestinians were killed
as well on October 7th and Palestinians
have been killed before and after
October 7 but it's the ideology of
violence that has been constant
basically killing um and the scale of of
the killing of course like um we will
talk numbers um uh later on in our
conversation but the scale of killing is
also very disproportionate however for
us as Physicians killing is a killing
and a life is a life and each life uh
matters Jewish Palestinian non-jewish
nonp Palestinian each life matters thank
you
y um and um now I would like to
introduce our second guest um and that
is uh Dr fero sidwa um H Dr uh fose you
asked me to call you fose so I'm gonna
call you fose uh he's a humanitarian
surgeon having worked most extensively
in Palestine but also in Ukraine Haiti
Zimbabwe and borina F
he most recently volunteered at the
European Hospital in kanun in Gaz from
March 25th until
april8 um with the world uh Health
Organization uh Dr um sidwa has written
and spoken extensively about the
surgical humanitarian work um the United
States role in the Israeli Palestinian
um um I'm going to use the word conflict
even though I prefer not to use the word
conflict but this is the summary I have
and the political consequences of
medical relief work he approaches the
Israeli Palestinian issue as a secular
American and as a
humanitarian um fuse welcome so can you
initially tell us about your path to
Medicine just because some of our
attendees um may not be in medicine and
it would be important for them to know
how did you make your way um and from
medicine and and surgery how did you
make your way to Palestine
uh actually it's it's the opposite way
around so I um I uh my my uh my freshman
year of college was 2000 and that's when
the second Ina broke out so I um I
started learning a lot about the Israel
Palestine conflict uh read a lot about
it I've edited some books on the topic
at this point and um in learning about
it uh and then you know of course the
next year uh September 11th happened in
the US and so that was a also a big
politicizing time so these were the like
the Middle East was a big focus of
political activity and just everything
that was going on in the whole country
and certainly on on my college campus at
Johns Hopkins
so uh so after you know I had gone to
med school thinking I would be a doctor
just because my dad's a doctor and that
was the only profession I knew that
existed um but uh afterwards I thought
well maybe uh maybe some something else
would be better I don't I you know again
I was a young guy didn't really know
what I was thinking but I thought maybe
something else so I said I'll let me let
me go live uh near this conflict that
I've seen uh I couldn't get a
volunteering position in the West Bank
but I could I did find one in Israel so
actually I lived in hia um I think you
said your mother's from hia right but
the um the uh so I lived in hia for a
year for people who don't know hia is
the only mixed Arab Jewish city um in
Israel and um there are the the as you
can imagine the city government is
dominated by uh by Jewish Israelis and
there's a lot of uh kind of deliberate
harassment and and uh pinning down of
the Arab Community there
so uh so I worked with an Arab Jewish
Cooperative that just tried to solve
intercommunal problems in hia I mostly
just helped them communicate with the uh
with their funders at the EU um and this
doesn't exist anymore which tells you
how far to the right Israeli Society has
gone unfortunately but um uh but yeah so
while I was there I would tour around in
the West Bank um on the weekends
sometimes and I actually ended up at uh
uh in Hebron I I'm probably I'm pretty
sure I was at a hospital I just can't
remember but I ended up in Hebron and uh
and there was a Physicians for human
rights Israel delegation there um and uh
one of the guys there took me aside and
uh an an Israeli fellow Jewish Israeli
fellow and he took me aside and said you
know froze if you you said you want to
be a doctor but look at how these
Palestinian Doctors live you know they
don't get any special treatment from
anybody may maybe they have enough to
buy a used car from some settler but
they don't um they don't get any special
privileges they get beaten senseless at
checkpoints just like everybody else
they have to watch their children be
beaten not be arrested have you know
it's it's their life is just as cruel
and vicious as everybody else but they
still come to work and and still try to
help people and he said if you would do
that uh then be a doctor but otherwise
don't be a doctor and what he said made
an impact on me for sure because I I I
could see it but I hadn't been able to
articulate like what was wrong with this
picture why why aren't these people
privileged in any any way whatsoever
which You Could See Clearly um but at
the same time I thought to myself well
I'm never going to be in that situation
I'm I'm the first world doctor in the
scenario not the third world doctor so
the um so I also took his um his
presence and his attitude because like
this guy could have sat in his living
room and criticized Israeli occupation
policy all he wanted and nobody would
have cared but by coming into the
territories he's putting himself at risk
not from the Palestinians but from his
own Society uh he's taking I'm sure he's
losing social bonds he's probably losing
money losing job opportunities losing
academic opportunities um because he's
going to be seen as a traiter his his
position of oh we should go um uh the
the POs you know just to show you how
extreme his position is in Israeli
Society after October 7th about a 100
Israeli Physicians signed a letter
calling on the Israeli uh Defense Forces
to destroy hospitals in Gaza that's
pretty wild that's that's pretty unusual
this this was mind buling
yeah well I wish I have to be honest I
wish it was mindboggling but um uh I'm
sure yes me and offline would testify
that it is not um the but no and I want
to be very clear Israeli Society is not
some monolith right I mean it's it's
true that peaceful Peaceable positions
are are a minority a very small minority
position but just to just to just so
nobody thinks we're being unfair the um
I I wrote a letter to the Biden
Administration that uh 98 other American
Healthcare professionals signed and in
that letter we called for an arms
embargo well 282 Israeli Physicians have
signed a letter endorsing our letter to
the Biden Administration they didn't
bother sending it to Netanyahu they just
sent it to Biden when he was still in
office excuse me sorry I'm nursing a
cough well that's that's probably
illegal for them to do it's it's illegal
to call for any uh that that it might be
considered treason under Israeli law to
call for an arms blockade on Israel so
uh you know that that's not a small
thing but again it's it's it would be
also unfair to pretend that that's some
you know that that is a very very very
small minority of even physicians in
Israel but nevertheless it's there um
but anyway sorry so my path to Medicine
um I uh so yeah so then I uh after
living in Israel I came back I taught
Middle School in East Baltimore for a
year and then I went to went to med
school in in Texas um and uh yeah just
that's uh that's how that went so I
actually I actually decided to be a
doctor in the context of the Israel
Palestine conflict and that's why I uh
um continue to work there but I've I've
worked in plenty of other places as well
I've worked in Ukraine three times since
the Russian invasion that's where I got
this sh actually um and I've worked in
Haiti I've worked in Burkina Faso I
worked in southern Zimbabwe like I
mentioned I worked in the West Bank so
yeah yeah thank you so I've been to the
West Bank as I mentioned on medical
missions repeatedly and the um what is
most impressive I felt that the level of
um The Physician training and their
skills in medicine um was outstanding
like the physicians in in Palestine
could come and care for our children
here um in Boston and be on par with my
best colleagues and not only that they
can do even more so an orthopedic
surgeon can deliver a baby can evacuate
an intracranial bleed because of their
conditions and their limited resources
they tend to be very very skilled but
the resources are dire and the number of
Physicians per population is low um and
the Health Care System needs a lot of
support to even measure up to our basic
standard of care not even the standard
of care of Veterinary
Hospital how was the level of the Health
Care system in GZA you haven't been to
GZA before this latest attack on GZA
right no so just to um put our listeners
into like the perspective of GDA GDA
strip is in the South um the population
in GDA over 70% of them are internally
displaced from other parts of Palestine
and they live in refugee camps in razza
in addition to the indigenous people of
razza it's very uh population dense uh
the population there is upward of 2.5
million people um in a neighborhood that
is really not not that large um and
they've been under siege and under
repeated military attack um for over 17
years right now this latest escalation
is a latest escalation but it's a it's a
chronic status of being under Warfare I
would say um I'm gonna also mention a
quick thing that I think you've heard
before um for a lot of people who are
involved with um with the Palestinian uh
humanitarian work the word conflict tend
to um uh be um less favored because it
gives the impression as if the sides are
equal and they're not even the word War
as if like there are two governments
with two military um uh you know um who
are like the belligerant and fighting
each other which is not the case so this
population has been under attack for a
while despite that they have as yasine
mentioned um many
hospitals you know a a Health Care
system that seemed to be working to some
extent and it seemed to be now decimated
but you were there on the ground can you
share with us fose what did you
see yeah so um just to add a little more
context actually the uh everything so so
the Gaza has been under siege literally
a military siege for 17 years like you
like you mentioned since uh since about
2005 when uh when the the uh when Hamas
won the Palestinian legislative council
elections and um during that time the
the US Israeli Egyptian blockade of Gaza
has reached truly extreme proportions
there's nothing like it that's ever been
done in outside of like medieval Siege
history it's really quite cruel Gaza is
a strip of land that is 25 mil long and
it's at its widest it's 6 mil wide so
it's the length of a marathon and the
width of a pretty quick jum jog it's not
large at all in it is two or in it used
to be 2.2 million people uh Gaza City
had a population density higher than
that than that of New York City and of
course without the height of its
buildings without its Municipal services
and the entire strip even including the
completely unpopulated uninhabitable
parts of it had the same population
density as Boston so this is a very
crowded place like you mentioned also
70% of the strip is refugees from the
1948 and some also from the 196 7 Wars
but also uh 50% of the stripp is
children uh the 51% of people are were
under under the age of 18 I think I
think it was 40% are under the age of 15
and 15% of PE of humans in Gaza are
under the age of five that it's a that's
extremely
unusual it's a very very young place um
and the The Siege has had some very
unusual characteristics in the mo for
the modern world uh you know in the 9s
when uh Gaza and the West Bank were
still still had some contact between
each other uh you could still move uh
gaza's main export was furniture that uh
people would would build um and then
mostly would export to the West Bank uh
that uh so there were 10 there were
often 10,000 trucks a day entering and
leaving Gaza um and that's when gaza's
population was about half of what it is
now today we're talking even even I'm
talking about before October 7th now the
the number of trucks that would enter
Gaza was somewhere between 4 and 800 per
day usually about 500 um to supply all
of the needs of this population this is
also a population that since uh uh 2005
has undergone I think I I can't even I
can't remember because there's so many
uh like y me mentioned the operations
that the Israelis I shouldn't say the
Israelis I that the US and Israel keep
carrying out against Gaza um there's
been something like 13 or 14 of them uh
just to tell you just to show you how
extreme these operations are just to
maybe illustrate one point of how
extreme these operations are every time
the with with all three of the biggest
operations that's uh castled in 2008 and
N protective Edge in 2014 and now this
one called swords of iron or some crazy
name um with all three of these
operations the Israelis have spent days
literally Days running tracked Vehicles
so tanks bulldozers whatever they could
find along the eastern and Northern edge
of the Gaza Strip because that's the
only part that has any agricultural land
in it because it's on the tip of the uh
the southern aquifer um it just
destroying the soil over and over just
compacting it compacting it compacting
it and eventually the B the bulldozer
drivers are getting bored and actually
carving stars of David into the land
that are visible on satellites there
this was just reported in the Washington
Post uh yesterday or the day before that
they've done this for the third time now
so this is the the quality and extent of
Destruction that's been done to Gaza
over and over and over again for the
past nearly two decades in a population
that has almost entirely grown up in
those two decades is just absolutely
unprecedented in any other part of the
world I honestly I think in human
history if somebody can provide me a
counter example I'd love to see it so
that so you you're like well I asked you
about the Health Care System why are you
talking about this healthc care is the
very top of what a society provides to
people in in the way I think of it and
you guys are academics so you can
probably correct me but the um healthc
care is up here food and sewage and
sanitation are down here right well when
I was in Gaza uh most of the Health Care
System had already been destroyed and
and that's the way it is now
unfortunately we we often talk about you
know if you look at The Who and the OCA
the the un uh OCA um updates you'll see
that there are 36 hospitals in Gaza
that's not really true there there are
36 building that are called hospitals
but most of them don't do acute medical
care they're maternity uh hospitals
they're important things don't get me
wrong but they're not actual acute care
hospitals they're not their maternity
hospitals their Rehabilitation
Facilities their pediatric specialist
things like that um and uh is a tertiary
orc Veterinary Hospital only only shifa
only shifa and even then it just
happened to be very large it didn't it
but you know it did have a cath lab it
did have a neuro Interventional lab it
did it did have lot of that shifa did
but shiffa and that's I'm glad you
brought it up shifa was really the only
place where you could do Advanced
tertiary and qu quinary care in Gaza not
only because of the physical plant of
the building just for maybe people don't
know shiffa Hospital yes me was it in
Gaza City or was
it where was shifa hospital I think Gaza
City I I think it's in Gaza City but
anyway shifa is a 700 something bed
hospital it would actually be the
seventh biggest Hospital in California
so it's a huge place
um uh especially for a PL a territory
that only has 2.2 million people in it
it's just enormous um all of the best
physicians all of the best surgeons all
of the most advanced uh modalities of
care um and the only Trauma Center were
were for the entire Gaza Strip were at
shifa hospital shifa was raided four
times and it's been completely destroyed
uh there were 3,400 hospital beds in
Gaza before October 7th which was
already way way too low that was at the
level of in Sudan um in terms of the
perp person hospital beds that were
available when shiffa was destroyed
which the final the Israel rid shiffa
Hospital four times and the last one
ended uh on March 30th or 31st when when
I was at a European Hospital in the
South um and so we actually got a large
influx of their staff and their patients
and things like that but um when shiffa
was finally destroyed 20% of healthc
care beds in Gaza were gone and all of
the advanced modalities of of caring GS
that were gone all of them cardiac
catheterization like just anything that
you would think of as as being in a
hospital gone that that's that that was
it uh so so that so like the top tier of
of healthc care was just bulldozed off
and it's gone it's not um and in
addition to that with the destruction of
shifa came the uh The Killing and
imprisonment of a huge amount of amount
of its staff and these were the staff
that were at the top of it so um the the
heads of departments the head uh you
know the the heads of nursing
departments the Physicians that head
that head departments etc etc um and so
the the the large mass of experience
that keeps any complex system like a
healthcare system going gone uh these
most of these people are still in
Israeli detention or or murdered or
killed or yeah and you know there there
was a particularly vicious example and
I'm ashamed that I can't remember their
names um uh but there there was a a a a
woman physician I I believe she was a
pediatrician and her son I believe was a
general surgeon they were found Bound in
machine gun to the together at when the
raid was over that's what you know it
just speaks to what the isra attack is
but anyway so when I was at and Dr hus
Abu safia for example he's well Dr H
ABIA was was that was that Kamal one
like yester mentioned um and uh you know
you know his example is kind of
interesting actually uh husam Abu safia
is a pediatrician and Kamal adwan from
what I understand was mostly a
children's hospital um that Kamal edwan
basically doesn't exist anymore but
husam Abu safia really built this
Hospital up himself he was the one who
established the Departments found
competent people to lead them you he
really he poured his life into this
Hospital uh the the hospital was laid
Siege to for three months by the
Israelis this is
after after detaining Abu sfia at the
beginning of again I I I totally agree
with you Aman that a war is not the
right way to describe whatever has
happened in the past uh 15 months but
just for the sake of using some
rhetorical device I'll call it a war at
the beginning of the war or the attack
um the uh Abu safia was detained and he
was let go you can't claim now now
they're going around saying he's the
Hamas Colonel that we've been looking
all sorts of utter nonsense think man
the guy's just pediatrician um Abu safia
during this this 3mon Siege he refused
to leave the hospital his uh son was
killed during during the siege of the
hospital his son was killed his son is
buried in the courtyard of the hospital
that he created he's wounded in his leg
so uh and then finally the Israelis
demand that he give himself up before
they just destroy the entire place so he
does because he figured he's he's hoping
that by doing so at least I think he's
hoping by doing so that he'll um spare
the uh spare the hospital the worst of
it even though it didn't um just with
dignity and Grace he walks with an
injured leg in his white coat up to an
Israeli tank and they open the door and
he gets in and no one has heard a word
from him since um and then his mother
has a heart attack the next day or the
day after and dies because she just
can't can't handle it anymore you know
everybody has a limit so his example
kind of it shows you know you they
they're taking this the the pal
intelligencia not just in healthcare but
in really every possible field you can
think of uh they're either driving them
out of Gaza or just arresting them and
killing them uh and then that's just
having this multigenerational effect
that you can see all the way down the
line and again in a place that is half
children if you take away the
intelligencia I mean what are you what
are you leaving there you know but
anyway the to answer the question you
actually asked me sorry the uh the
healthc care system in Gaza even when I
was there in March which was a
relatively good time especially where I
was in in conun uh was an utter disaster
the the hospital had about 220 beds uh
and there were 1,500 people admitted to
it there was another 1,500 people lining
the hallways of the hospital who just
lived in they just lived there because
they were the ones that were lucky
enough to think well if I go live in the
hallways of the hospital I don't have to
live outside um because all these
people's homes had been destroyed most
of them were displaced from the north
but others were displaced from conun
itself the grounds of the hospital was
itself a displaced person's camp we were
told 10 to 15,000 people were Sheltering
there they were sharing four toilets and
one water spigot from what I could find
um and uh like just to give one example
of how unb this is back this is a year
ago now but uh just to give one example
of how incredibly overwhelmed this
Health Care system was uh I did wound
care rounds the first three days that I
was there just to establish a wound care
service which was obviously quite
necessary given the U the the huge
amount of exposive injuries we were
seeing yeah and uh I found about 250
people in the hospital who needed daily
operative wound care so they really they
needed to be taken to the O put under
general anesthesia have their wound de
breeded extensively packed you know
whatever but some kind of operation not
a complex one like I could teach any
teenager to do it in about 30 minutes
but the um but nevertheless it needs
these resources there are 250 such
people there's four ORS at a European
Hospital how on Earth are you going to
provide this service well I you know i i
i innovated and I started and I probably
shouldn't say this out loud but I
started stealing ketamine from the
anesthesia carts and doing this on the
floor that's is my understanding yeah
the medication limitation so the
anesthetics were limited oxygen was
limited antibiotics became you know
unavailable so even if you do the
procedure you know the risks that come
after that and we're talking about
injuries so similar to what you
mentioned before yes mean like thinking
at this from a public health perspective
and the three of us are involved with
public public health and humanitarian
work the number of people who are dying
from you know the attacks the the
violent attacks is something and the
number of people who are impacted by the
starvation the infectious diseases the
post-operative infections if they were
lucky enough to have a procedure that
all compounds the the cost the the human
cost of what was happening in gizza what
are your thoughts yes mean right so I I
actually I wanted yeah I wanted to give
some uh H context to this because also
fro mentioned the The Siege on Gaza that
started in 2007 uh because I think it's
important to know the context um it
didn't happen this like War didn't
happen in a
vacuum um and um fos was right to say
you know the basic thing is sanitation
and sewage system and actually back in
2018 the already declared Gaza unlivable
because of sanitary and um conditions uh
and part of it is because of the siege
so many people don't really know that
one of the characteristics of The Siege
meant that um the Israeli Army actually
controlled all entrances uh and exits
from uh from Gaza Strip except from
rafah uh checkpoint which was um
controlled by the Egyptians but since uh
the the Egyptians and the Israeli Army
are cooperating was basically the same
and and part of it was um part of the
restrictions was that anything that can
be perceived as um uh that has potential
for dual
use um cannot be cannot be entered to uh
to Gaza so dual use means everything
that can be possible possibly used for
like uh building um tunnels or bombs or
whatever cannot be entered so what does
that mean so all of like the the gases
that we use for anesthesia
medications because they're liquids that
cannot be
identified um electricity generators so
all these things even just you know
concrete because you can build um you
can build tunnels with that so that I I
hope explains why most of the hospitals
there cannot be tertiary um Care Centers
because you can you can't even uh get
the supplies because they're all
controlled by by thei thei military uh
so that's one thing and then second
thing again as fro mentioned is um
um the the frequency of of military
operations so almost once a year um
these things happen um and every gazin
physician that I've interviewed says we
know that the first thing that happens
that there are uh deliberate attacks
against Healthcare and one of the things
um just as an example is that during um
May 2021 21 sorry um there was another
operation that lasted I think two two
weeks it was during covid and one the
things that happened that the the only
covid clinic and covid lab uh that you
that um was used for the for all the
Hospitals and Clinics in in Gaza was
bombed um and the director was killed
together with 12 uh family members uh
and this impacted
the the the care that
gsin received in the following 6 to 12
months uh where they couldn't get covid
tests or vaccines um for about for about
12 months and and in it increased the
fatality rate um significantly so this
all happened before October 7th so once
October 7th happened and the and the War
uh in Gaza started this was they already
started from a like a from a deficit in
a way and when you think of of healthare
Public Health um I actually thought you
know on on the Israeli side we used to
treat like um soldiers in the first
month who came with these bizarre
infections because they they were you
know using the water from Gaza Strip
that are all like polluted and infected
and this is without even speaking about
you know all the poisonous uh uh things
that you get in the ground just from the
bombing which is something that we we
know it's part of like it's natural it's
like we talk about uh poisonous uh gases
after after the fires in La for example
um so all these things definitely impact
um umth Public Health there and we we
now just since the ceasefire we now
start hearing about more and more bodies
that are taken out under the rubble um
that we weren't even aware of before uh
the ceasefire so I'm I think that we'll
see the the real consequences in the
next coming months when there are
actually evacuations of all the debris
from the
bombings my understanding when I first
um started uh traveling on medical
missions to the West Bank was that um
the deficit in the West Bank was dark
like compared to um going to the
hospitals in haa and the hospitals in
Jerusalem and compared to the US the
hospitals on Israeli side are comparable
to our best hospitals here in the US um
and you just go through the border with
the challenges of going through the
checkpoints um um kendia and others um
once you cross it's like Crossing into
time as if you are in a movie or in a
nightmare like the difference is just
Stark and people don't know like when I
explain to people especially when they
say oh oh they were living fine there
was peace there was peace on October 6th
and October 5th
Etc it it didn't look peaceful to me and
while people look exactly the same like
I can't tell the difference between
someone who is Palestinian Israeli or
Jewish Israeli or Palestinian in the
West Bank or or um on the other uh side
of the fence somehow that distinction is
very um known in in for people who live
there and the lives of those two are are
not the same I wonder how can how can we
um explain and transmit that information
what you saw on the ground F what you
know yes mean and you experience on the
ground and from your your interviews how
can we Elevate the level of knowledge of
people who are here who haven't traveled
there and the West Bank is in much
better shape than gizza but it's not in
a good shape at all
so I'm just envisioning something that
is more nightmarish at Baseline than the
West Bank and right now it's even way
worse how how can we make them believe
that this is the situation on the
ground well uh I I it's it's unfortunate
because nobody likes history including
me but I think you have to look at it um
the the history is not complicated in in
any significant way
um you know the yeah just like like like
like you mentioned what was or you kind
of hinted at it what was Gaza on October
6th right well again I don't have we
don't have time to go through it in in
detail but you're you're talking about a
imprisoned child Refugee population
subjected to massive bombing attack like
yes me said almost every year uh two of
which have been so severe that they've
actually resulted in the landscape of
the gaz's strip being changed like I
mentioned uh a place where attacks on
Healthcare were already completely
normal before before October 7th it was
it's true that it's been completely just
turned up to 11 but it's it's was
complet it was totally the norm before
everybody fully understood that um and
then it's I I just I I I try to
emphasize to people what this blockade
was Yas me did mention that the Israelis
justify things in terms of dual use but
it's actually a lot more sinister than
that and it it's I don't mean to
contradict you but it's there's a
there's a far more extreme layer to it
and this has been reported on in the
American Press totally unimpeachable
sources anybody who wants to look them
up can do so um the yes exactly uh Erica
I completely agree with you I just just
said in the chat yeah so in um yes I
mean you can probably correct me about
the dates um but after I believe it was
after um uh after operation or excuse me
after the uh the Hamas election which
you corrected me sorry I thought I
thought it was too 2005 you said it was
2007 but whenever it was whenever Hamas
won the uh the Palestinian legislative
council elections in the mid 2000s um
the Israeli the US and Israel
immediately imposed a Siege on Gaza and
there was a very famous quote from a guy
who used to be the uh the special
adviser to Ariel Chiron who was the
Prime Minister at the time uh his name
was do Vice glass he was an American I
think uh at least judging by his accent
he um he's in a in a cabinet uh cabinet
discussion he famously said our new
policy is that we're going to put the
Palestinians on a diet they'll get a lot
thinner but they won't die and the
important context of that is that when
the uh when he said that apparently the
entire Israeli cabinet erupted in
laughter they thought it was the
funniest thing they'd ever heard um so
that that was the policy that he wasn't
joking um the uh and unfor you to be
fair a lot of them did die but the uh
but that that was the policy so the
Israeli government went to the
meticulous degree and people should
think about what this means it went to
the meticulous degree of calculating how
many calories does a gauen person need
to survive and then allowing
specifically that many calories into
Gaza every single day that why on Earth
does Israel have the power to do that to
an entire population just imagine if you
if that's how you lived would you accept
that for your children would you nobody
would this is outrageous you no no no
one on Earth would accept this I mean
Jews in the wars saww ghetto didn't
accept it why would they it's it's
outrageous it's totally outlandish you
know Palestinians and the Gaza GTO
weren't going to accept it either and
the the the cruelty of this policy just
escalated and escalated and escalated
and escalated and escalated um and
incidentally just people can challenge
me if they think I'm wrong it tended to
escalate when Hamas became more
reasonable not when they became more
violent that actually went the other way
when they became more violent so the um
so yeah so there there's a long history
there for sure and it's it's quite
extreme yeah and I will say I I just
want to add that one of the two
arguments that we hear so one argument
that we hear recently is that you know
we've tried a Palestinian state it was
Gaza look what happened so I think that
what for is mentioning is just a good
example that what if you don't really
have control on transfer of like food
medication just freedom of movement then
you obviously don't have sovereignty so
that's definitely not not an example of
like a Palestinian state that failed
that one thing and then the second thing
that I will say especially about the
attacks on healthare is that one of the
arguments that we we hear is that you
know it can it it is Justified because
there were um hostages um hidden there
so on a personal note I have to say I
have friends who were hostages uh and
were murdered um and colleagues who were
murdered uh on let's say the Israeli
side I had to I hate to do this division
uh and I still don't think it is
Justified to to attack a hospital
because of that just imagine that you
know I work now at Beth Israel as you
mentioned imagine that I don't know a
terrorist organization is having a
hostage um situation in the hospital no
one would even even think of uh bombing
with a bomb of like one ton uh of
explosives um bombing the the hospital
it it would be
unacceptable to anyone um but I don't
understand why in it is it is acceptable
and it is Justified I think that's a
that's a it should be uh an unacceptable
argument and as uh you know as a medical
community as an academic Community as a
you know human Community we should
definitely condemn this and make sure
that this does not happen
again mean I'm sorry about your friends
that you lost and the family members and
and people from from the south so I
think um yes it goes without saying but
I'm GNA say it every life matters like
this is our oath as Physicians every
life matters um I mourn the Jewish life
that was lost but I mourn the
Palestinian life equally the issue I
think we've been encountering over the
past 16 months is that somehow the
Palestinian life is discounted and it's
worth dispensing with 40,000 or more of
Palestinian lives because of what
happened sorry out the last count
61,000 61,000 I think the count is more
I think right now um during this semi
ceasefire um and once the UN and other
uh humanitarian organization can do more
work uh think the numbers will be will
be different um so I'm at Harvard and um
the late poor Paul Farmer used to say um
the idea that some lives matter less is
the root of all that is wrong with the
world and I think one of the challenges
for me as a physician and as a
Palestinian is that specific thing like
Palestinian lives should matter Jewish
life does matter and Palestinian life
should matter
um and that is part of what is missing
um from um a lot of the reporting that
comes out we're mentioned in numbers
like
61,000 versus you know the names of the
people each one was a life of its own um
which is really which is really part of
the dehumanization that's happening to
the Palestinian in our Western
media um one thing I want to ask you
um you're an Israeli a Palestinian
Israeli I prefer the term a Palestinian
Israeli than Arab Israeli because we're
a very specific population like we don't
say you know um Latino America like we
say you know someone from Puerto Rico
someone from Cuba so you are a
Palestinian
Israeli um how how has it been for you
over the past year speaking up for the
humanity of Palestinians GZA um as an
Israeli knowing that some of your
colleagues um back home um have lost
jobs over this yeah it is extremely
challenging uh more challenging than I
would have thought because I I expect
the at least you know my colleagues like
the medical and healthc Care Community
to understand that every life is sacred
as you just said and I was um
disappointed and and uh surprised to
learn that it wasn't as obvious uh as it
is to me uh and yes many many of my
colleagues who said that actually lost
their jobs uh I still think that at this
moment in time it is Our obligation to
um to say that and speak out uh about
the sac the the fact that every human
life is sacred and that we must stop all
violence and we must um as you said
um advocate for Palestinian lives and
how and that they they they do matter
just as much as any other lives um and
uh I have to say like on I I do want to
end on a hopeful note that there are
some um Jewish colleagues Jewish Israeli
colleagues many of them who share our
Vol our values and also speak out uh
against this and especially I have to
say in the last day after like the
president Trump said talked about you
know uh the another Force displacement
of the 2 million gazans
to other countries and that maybe the
United States will own the Gaza Strip um
um many many many speak against it and
and and plan the resistance this is our
time we have to resist this so even
though it is challenging uh and even
though it um it Demands a lot of Courage
I still think that as a Palestinian as
an Israeli citizen but as you know the
citizen of the world the human being it
is my
obligation to to resist what is
happening now and do whatever I can to
actually promote peace and um and shared
humanity and Society in the
region thank you so much yine and thank
you fuse and this is an excellent point
um to now um from it to start taking
some questions from the audience so one
of the questions that came um is asking
about housing uh giving the area size of
Gazza could there be or are there
immediate efforts to engage housing
systems that could nurture Health
efforts and food uh security um they
mentioned so many Technologies uh and or
designs that allow for Off the Grid
alternative dwelling energy gardening
efforts um these are all necessary for
health and wellness I agree with you
Ryan what do you think fuse and
Y um so obviously I mean housing is the
as we mentioned it's like the one of the
most basic things um that we're
um we're now facing when we even just
discussing Rec construction of and
rebuilding of Gaza um I think so my my
rule of thumb uh at least you know
thinking of the future is that um anyone
who can fund a bomb or like an airplane
who bombs people can fund clinics and
housing and and you know rebuilding
sewage systems and stuff like that so I
and I not at the same time
right one of the yeah yeah yeah yeah I
mean I don't it it shouldn't be at the
same time you shouldn't fund what we
have done which we which we what we have
done as Americans like we sent
humanitarian Aid and at the same time we
kept sending the bombs and um that is
just hypocritical absolutely absolutely
but but if you have the nerve to to pay
for bombs at least have the decency to
pay for you know housing and and and uh
clinics and and hospitals and
education um and that's what I expect
from from the global community uh from
us as you know as um just you know
humans uh and and yes we have we we are
so good at developing Technologies to
kill other people everyone is talking
about AI today we also there there were
a few like Publications about how AI was
used actually to kill people in Gaza and
Lebanon and the West Bank in the past 15
months we we should leverage these
Technologies for better public health
and and and better education and to
actually uh rebuild Gaza from a a place
of
trust um uh and and and invest there as
a you know as a global Community that's
how I see
it thank you yes peruse you mentioned
human rights um at what at one point I
will um I will say that this past
December uh on the 10th marked 76 years
since the adoption of the universal
Declaration of Human Rights and you're
right security and shelter precede water
and water precede food and food precedes
Health but health is one of them so one
of the questions comes um asking what
are the sectors you think are most
needed right now in healthare after we
establish the the immediate need of
security shelter food and
water um honestly I would say uh you
know trauma care but then also obstetric
and Pediatric Care I think would be
probably the most uh the most important
things to focus on
yeah yes mean what do you
think I mean I think it I I agree with
fro and he has more experience in uh in
this than me because he was there uh but
at least from what I've heard from uh
from other Physicians it seems like
everything is in you know severe um um
shortage so uh um all the all the basic
needs you Primary Care pediatricians um
um
Obstetricians um we don't talk about
mental health because this is in a way
um maybe higher on the mlo uh pyramid
but yeah it's like a luxury yeah yes but
but no it's not it's not luxury I we
need to remember that um on the average
a person in Gaza lost about 30 family
members um what does that what does that
do to your you know to your Soul mental
health um right and everyone is
traumatized everyone is traumatized
everywhere right but uh we have to keep
that in mind as
well thank you uh thank you y and fuse
zaren is asking um and it's great to see
you here Zan um she's asking that um if
she cannot physically uh go on medical
Mission as a physician here in in the US
how can she support the healthc care
sector in gizza and the West Bank
mental health would be one way right
like if we can get electricity up and
running um and have internet could we
have um mental health um appointments
with Physicians
here yeah I believe I think so first I
know of like a specific um um Venture
it's in the West Bank but it's like
digital way to uh give like deliver
mental health um um you know treatments
uh in Arabic or in English I want to say
like the Palestinians both in the West
Bank and Gaza and that's evidence-based
are the the most educated out of the
Arab world they most of them know
English so this can definitely uh help
um I also want to say I think that's a
good opportunity to speak what we
happened um I think it was last week
where uh two Palestinian patients were
uh supposed to speak speak I think at
Harvard and I feel comfortable saying it
as Harvard faculty uh and it was uh
cancelled so I think that's another
thing that we can do as uh you know as
as Physicians here uh there are
Palestinians here uh from Gaza who um
left uh ran away from you know from the
bombs looking from for Better Lives and
many of them are you know sick or
patients and they can be uh supported
here as well uh and we just need to you
know let them let them speak about their
experiences and not cancel them just
because it's I don't know
unbalanced thank you yes I can speak
actually a bit uh to that experience so
I'm the organizer of that lecture um at
uh at the medical school and um uh
complaints came over the weekend about
the event uh from uh people who I feel
um out of out of empathy I would say the
word Palestinian patients from Gaza is a
trigger for them without understanding
um how the event will happen so um it
wasn't canceled as much as it was paused
to explore what it is and to have all
the facts so once the dean have all the
facts he's actually approved reinstating
uh the patient sessions Thea patient
sessions and the lectures so um it's
actually um a success story in which you
know um reason and Common Sense and
speaking directly um to people who are
making decisions and making the argument
Works um so there you go that's
wonderful way of yeah and I think there
were also about 200 discrimination
complaints filed again about this right
like there it was there were hundreds of
complaints filed at least that's what
the Boston papers reported this morning
Boston Globe said um just because I know
the inside of that story The lectures
were approved before the knowledge about
the complaints um good I think there is
um and one of the questioners brought up
the issue of pervasive anti-palestinian
racism in the US that is a true
statement we do have pervasive
anti-palestinian racism and we do have
censorship and silencing um it's not
happening in this instance because um
they were approved to to um to be
reinstated however um permission to
narrate was an article that Edward S
wrote um that decades ago and I think I
agree wholeheartedly with you and with
fuse uh we need to speak up we need to
shed light on the facts on the ground
and um we need to elevate the humanity
of Palestinians Palestinians are humans
um and they deserve equal attention
equal Humanity equal right just like any
other people not more and but not less
definitely not less um one of the
questions that also came is um where uh
would people find um accurate resources
to learn about the situation on the
ground uh from a medical
standpoint the health
clusters yeah the the the UN The Who
Health clusters um the there's there's
plenty of resources online uh from
people on the
ground I will just say because I don't
know will probably not say but um he has
a wonderful in the New York Times that
gives uh some um Testaments from
Physicians who worked in
Gaza uh and it's a it's
a it's really it really is a painful
read but I think it's very very
important thank you thank you for
writing it h f no me too yep um one of
the questions that also came is um as
you
citizens um how can we advocate for
Palestinians and what's happening in in
Gaza so people who are not in
healthcare yeah I mean I I think uh
people in or out of healthcare should
just recognize the I I try to emphasize
it all the time there there was no
Israeli attack on Gaza there was a US
Israeli attack on Gaza that's been going
on for the past like we said 17 years um
everything the US and Israel are Israel
has been described I think accurately as
an offshore as a stationary American
aircraft carrier in the Middle East uh
there's a there there's a lot of
cooperation that the two military
systems are very very tightly
coordinated so you just have to
recognize that we are the ones that
committed these crimes that's it as soon
as you recognize that you you it's
pretty obvious what you should be doing
you should be trying to stop them um you
know how you don't like if you go set
your neighbor's house on fire you can't
walk back to your house and say yeah I
don't really care what happens when my
neighbor's house catches fire it's like
no you you're the one that set it on
fire if you commit a crime you're
responsible for the consequences of that
crime and and mitigating them and paying
people reparations for them etc etc it's
not it's not complicated how to how that
has to happen but that requires
political organization it requires
talking to people and it requires taking
some
risks talking to our politicians voting
the right politicians in that look at
humans as humans abs creating or
creating new political systems whatever
it might be I don't know that's up to
everybody else to decide I I couldn't
claim expertise in that but
yeah thank you um that question comes
back to you yes mik m is asking um what
do you think Israeli uh Jewish and
Palestinian Physicians can do to make a
difference that's a that's a wonderful
question and I and I love it because I
think we always have a choice we we can
choose choose to sign a a petition or a
letter that says it's okay to bomb a
hospital or we can choose to actually um
um cooperate with our colleagues um uh
Palestinians and Israelis and I have to
say actually in the past two years I was
working with uh two other uh colleagues
researchers on a research um qualitative
research and we studied Healthcare
initiatives that are joint uh Israeli
and Palestinians cross border or cross
culture
um some of them were you know Israelis
and Palestines from Gaza some in
Jerusalem some in West Bank and some
inside Israel and we actually showed
that um we looked at three metrics so
equality and participation and in
management in decision making um int
intensity how intense the interaction is
and intentionality how intentional the
programming is in in terms of like um
building trust and speaking about um
the traumas the the narratives the pain
and stuff like that and we show that all
these three are are associated with uh
building trust and I think that um
Healthcare the reason we chose health
care and health and Medicine in general
is because this is kind of like in a way
a a a profession in
consensus uh in which we actually see on
a daily basis Israelis and Palestinians
interact and collaborate
um because of you know the hypocritic G
and because we really uh the the
consensuses that we need we're here to
save lives no matter who our patients
are um and and this is a profession that
is based on trust uh we are trained on
how to deliver you know difficult
conversations and and we we're trained
on how to build Report with our patients
and we see that so I see that on a daily
basis that a Palestinian can treat
Jewish uh patience and vice versa and
and and they trust each other um so I do
think that um I or at least I expect my
Israeli Jewish uh colleagues to First
understand the power dynamics and how
like and their privilege and actually
leverage it to support their Palestinian
colleagues create more crossb
collaborations in you know training um
Healthcare um staff uh delivering more
equipment and medication uh advocate for
Palestinian Physicians and specifically
Palestinian patients uh and advocate for
for a better access to healthcare um
this this way we can actually build
Bridges toward hopefully some kind of
like a a solution that can scale up
Beyond Healthcare um um and I really
believe that this is it this has a great
potential I fully agree thank you thank
you so much yine thank you so um Ryan
here brings another uh comment um he's
saying just talking about this speaking
for the past hour and and 17 minutes has
been cathartic and therapeutic exercise
are there any International Zoom groups
to connect um victims of war in Gazza to
people who want to listen to them who
can just talk like the traditional pin
pal concept a weekly or monthly effort
um uh to share hope pain dreams
Etc I know a lot of us have been glued
yeah glued to the Instagram and Facebook
and we follow stories and follow
journalists from the ground but tell me
Fus no I was going to say there probably
are but I I don't honestly know where
they are or or how to how to find them
but uh um yeah yeah so I don't know
necessarily of like Zoom groups yeah um
but
um there are definitely like people uh
posting stuff on social media um there
is a great podcast called Unapologetic
then the third narrative that uh is done
by two Palestinian citizens of Israel
one is from East Jerusalem actually so
not gsin um but there again there are
like Palestinian communities um in US
cities Iman maybe also can speak about
this but we have some uh Palestinian
Community here in Boston um that has
events um and there are events in
different universities I think maybe
just getting more into these circles uh
will get you exposed I guess to
Palestinian
stories yeah there is in Boston and I
think in many cities the uh the annual
film festival and that was actually an
entry for me to learn about the
Palestinian community in Boston when I
first came in and got to know a lot of
people through the film festival and we
end up building actually communities uh
locally in um in Newton in Boston of
people who would like to to discuss uh
the Palestinian issue one suggestion I
will have I'm a book lover and a vicious
leader uh reader you can um you can
start a book club and read different
books about Palestine and um and educate
um yourself and the community around you
and that will keep the conversation
going I would say the the book um we
reviewed most recently is a book I would
highly recommend it's a 2024 Pulitzer
Prize winner uh by Nathan thr uh it's
titled A Day in the Life of Abid Salama
and um the book is about a school bus um
that um end up um getting set on fire by
um hitting another trailer and um six
people end up dying uh of burns um and
it talks about all these like circles
structural circles that contributed to
eventually the death of the four kids
you could say the fault was the driver
of the trailer but it turns out that the
fault is a whole structure that made
that road that made Access to Health
Care harder that made the access of the
parents to their kids in these hospitals
harder and it talks about the bigger
picture of occupation which actually
gets into we're all involved in public
Health the public health Parable couple
of years ago I think there was um a post
about Physicians needing to stay in
their Lane and stop talking about gun
violence but it is our lane we don't
want to be in politics but we are
Physicians and the parable in public
health is if you're seeing someone dying
and you resuscitate them drowning in a
river and you resuscitate the first the
second the third at one point you need
to go upstream and see what's causing
all the these drowning incidents you'll
find a broken bridge and you need to fix
the bridge and I think it's part of our
hypocritic oath to look Upstream while
treating the patients and figure out how
how to to basically fix the
bridge excellent I'm wondering if there
are any other questions one of the
questions that uh someone posted it's a
bit provocative but I think it's
worthwhile um
I I accept that question uh it says um
why should a US citizen care about GZA
or its
healthare in in the same vein I would
say I've heard it from so many people
there are so many wars in the world why
should we only single out
resta I don't think we should only
single out Gaza but um it's exactly what
I said before you should care because
you're the one that smashed
it I I can't I can't walk into my
neighbor my response yeah I can't walk
into my neighbor's house and set it on
fire and say h i don't care what happens
in my neighbor's house if you want to
say you don't care about what happens in
other countries we have our own problems
to deal with that's completely fine
that's a totally legitimate thing but
then you don't but you don't get to go
drop bombs on other people and at the
same time say that you don't care about
what happens to them like no no one
that's it like imagine if a Russian said
I don't care what what happens in
Ukraine we'd
all so it's so OB VI that that's an
idiotic statement because Russia is the
reason things are happening in Ukraine
we are the reason things are happening
in Gaza we are the reason that shiffa
hospital is not a functional Place
anymore we're the reason there's no Road
system we're the reason there's no
sewage system we're the reason that the
population of Gaza might now be half a
million less than it was two years
ago you don't get to just say you don't
care that that's not that when you
commit crimes you're responsible for
them that's a basic moral precept that
literally nobody has had a hard time
understanding and that's why so much
effort is taken into trying to pretend
that this is a conflict going on between
two other people over there and that
we're just this silent Observer that's
not the situation at all and I'll just
add um that you know um the
taxpayer um in the US pays funded this
war much more than I did as an Israeli
taxpayer so I this is why uh if if you
if you if you care for like what your
tax money is doing then you should care
about
this absolutely and I would say as a
pediatrician um to just think as as you
both said like more than 50% of the
population are children um it's just
horrifying to think what they've endured
and how many of them have been killed
and M um it's just unfathomable um I I
love quotes so um I'm going to say uh J
Baldwin's quote the children are always
ours every single one of them all over
the globe and I'm beginning to suspect
that whoever is incapable of recognizing
this may be incapable of
morality um I want to give Erica a
chance to uh share with us some of what
they are doing at
MIT uh
Erica can yes um please first of all uh
thank you Ima Yas and fose for such a
provocative moving and um personal uh
discussion today I truly appreciate it
and hope that future viewers will be
able to benefit from your experience and
your knowledge and expertise uh going
forward um some of the themes I think
that stood out for me and and again I
come from doing most of my professional
research in Haiti which is a country
country that has been in battled for for
different kinds of reasons but that has
also suffered with u
multigenerational uh endurance of
political conflict poverty violence of
many kinds and the long-term
psychosocial aftermath so I've I've
thought about you know several questions
in your conversation you were thinking
about how do we how do we Rank and
decide what is the best best way to uh
assist or intervene in the post quote
whatever the so-called post era will be
whether there's a period of Peace
whether it endur so that's one theme
that I think we're thinking about you
know is it basic needs first before
mental health or is it infrastructure
and my experience from Haiti in working
on the postconflict period there is it
kind of has to be all of them at the
same time but still there may not be
successes one thing that in my my
research has shown is that the the
survivors of politically motivated
violence without a future whether it was
education employment Etc became the
later gang members who are you know now
in many ways destabilizing Haiti you
know so I'm I'm hopeful that uh that
there will be you know a a sovereign um
entity that can make decisions for
itself yeah Yas mean's points about
there needing to be kind of expertise on
the ground that sort of leads the way
but then also collaborations with uh
community members across borders across
disciplines I think that's also critical
um we also talked a lot about especially
for Rose the question of um our
complicity meaning Americans complicity
with types of political action the
militarism and um intervention
overseas um as well as our own
responsibility and I think that's
something I would love um in the future
to take on to Greater degree is how how
do we understand what responsibility we
each bear individually and then expand
out and and then to think more about
then what what does the level of our own
responsibility mean in terms of how much
we should engage to try to help repair
care or to uh bring about Justice you
know for crimes or for harms however you
want to speak of it um we talked a lot
today too about the question of the
value of life and how it's it has become
normative to devalue certain populations
lives in the world and especially dazin
and and the the extent to which we spoke
about um the the calculation of you know
not only nutritional values but you know
the the categorization of whether
something has a single use or a dual use
and you know this type of mentality or
this type of um uh ideology I find I I
wonder how does one uh these are
questions for the future but how do you
move from sort of this um precautionary
position and always anticipating the the
worst um and so such that humanitarian
Aid is viewed as you know potentially it
a source of future um resistance or
protest on the part of you know Gins or
whoever I mean that that I think is is a
a broader philosophical question I did
want to also just to point out to our
viewers that the MIT libraries is going
to be hosting this webinar we are going
to be putting up full bios of all of our
speakers and
participants uh we will also have
suggestions for those of you who want to
you know either get involved locally or
you know to support some of the
international organizations and
institutions that we mentioned today we
will put all of that information and we
will put links to the article that um
ferose has written with a colleague and
other other resources uh to help you as
you begin to learn I I took very
seriously as well the question of
all of us individuals who are asking
what can we
do start locally building relation
learning about others and maybe ask how
can I be of help maybe not to we should
assume that we know or or never we are
the experts but to hopefully with
humility and a stance of um desire to be
a true Ally you know reach out in that
vein so um I supposed to be doing the
closing I want to thank you all again um
and I didn't know thank you anyone has
any last thoughts really
quick thank you for elevating our voices
uh Erica and MIT uh I'm I'm very
grateful for this
opportunity thank you be remiss if I did
not say um at MIT later this month uh
you can reach out to me Erica James
ejames mit.edu uh we were going to be
hosting a virtual reality exhibit called
The Phoenix of Gaza and it's going to be
limited in terms of how much access but
the exhibit is moving from MIT then it's
going to go to UMass ammer and it shows
images before during and after October
7th um but a lot of it is about seeing
what doesn't exist any longer
Unfortunately um one of my colleagues uh
Dr Devon atala at UMass Boston says that
all of us who are hearing these stories
and trying to be open are ourselves
embodied archives and right now with
Gaza being virtually destroyed we I
think have a responsibility to keep
alive uh the history the memories and to
the extent that we can second event um
happening at MIT and the department of
urban studies and planning there's going
to be a two-day Symposium to talk about
the role of urban planning in the
Israeli and Palestinian and specifically
gazan everyday realities I don't know
that that is going to be open to the
public but they will uh be putting some
things online in the
future ideas I I volunteer myself and um
thank you thank you all once
again thank you for having
us bye take care