So last time we talked about the sum
troder theorem and today I want to do
some digesting of what we learned. Um so
on the one hand the the summary trout
theorem was was um had a lot of impact
both the theorem and the proof and the
proof involved topology and that started
a whole thing of using topology and
combinotaurics
and um Tom Wolf learned about it the for
analyst Tom Wolf learned about it and he
he brought the cell decompositions and
those topological methods into fora
analysis um and had a lot of impact and
the theorem itself the statement is like
sharp and the proof is fairly short and
uh so it's really nice. Um
but there are some questions that are
closely related to the submar troder
theorem that the proof doesn't actually
tell us anything about um and so I
wanted to um go through them today and
and discuss why the proof doesn't tell
us much about some of these related
things and those those some of those
things will be the main topics of the
class going forward. Yeah.
Okay, so
I'm going to put in the board seam ready
trotder
theorem and proof are quite remarkable
but
they don't tell us
uh anything about some questions that
seem closely related.
Okay, so number one doesn't tell us
anything about projection theory in
finite fields.
Okay. Number two, it doesn't tell us
anything about the structure of sharp
examples.
All right.
So, we discussed a little bit last
class. I mentioned the sharp examples
for the sority trout theorem that we
know and and it's an interesting
question. If you have an example that is
close to being sharp for the summary
trer theorem can we say anything about
its structure
and it might be a little surprising but
the proof of the sad trer theorem really
gives no information about that and
we'll talk about why
okay number three so the sad tr theorem
is the sharp theorem about projection
theory for points sets of points in the
uklidian plane in R2 finite sets in R2.
Um, so you might hope that it would tell
you something helpful about projection
theory for sets of unit balls in R2. Um,
but it says rather little about that. So
it says rather little about the
projection theory
of
unit balls
in R2 um with some spacing conditions.
So I'll put here with the housedorf
spacer.
This is also a little bit surprising.
And um so Tom Wolf was really interested
in analysis problems problems like this
and he found the sired troder proof in
the cominatorics literature which at
that time were like two pretty different
groups of mathematicians.
um and he imported it and he tried to
use it to answer questions like this and
he did prove a bunch of interesting
stuff but he was not able to answer this
question. Um and so we'll talk about
what the issue is why the why the
summarated troder proof does not say all
that much about this set.
Okay, cool. and uh and then going
forward this and this maybe this are
going to be some of the main topics of
our class.
Oh yeah and so oh and Mimi also
mentioned so you know one of the big
developments that made me excited to
teach the class is that there is now a
sharp theorem about this proven by Orpin
and Schmurkin and Ren and Wong. Um and
actually it doesn't use any of the
methods from the Seamaretti Troder
proof. Um so anyway so we'll talk today
sort of to explain why something
different is needed and then we'll we'll
meet the something different starting uh
next class.
Okay.
All right. So, so why does the method
that we saw Yeah.
>> Um are there any other spaces like other
than real space where kind of a similar
uh memo to that kind of technical real
splitting memo works like I know like it
doesn't work for finite anything that's
kind of similar enough to real.
>> Yeah. Okay. So the question is the key
ingredient in the in the proof we did of
the summary troder theorem is this cell
decomposition lema. You can cut the
plane up into pieces in a way so that
each line doesn't go through too many
pieces. And the question was other than
R2 are there some other spaces where
something like this would work. Um okay
so it works to at least to some extent
in higher dimensions Rn. Um it uh it
doesn't make any sense over FP which I
was going to say in a second. Um and um
it works with some modifications in CN
um and um
and yeah and those are all the spaces
really I know where it works.
Okay. Okay. So we we just sort of
mentioned um so why why did these
methods not work over FP? Well, we had
this basic thing of like cutting a space
into pieces where like the simplest
thing would be like you take a line in
the plane and it cuts it into two
connected components, right? And um uh
that just doesn't make sense in FP2.
There's if you remove a line from FP2,
there's no sense in which what's left
over is organized into two components.
Okay, so this one is not that
surprising. Um, and these are a little
more surprising and we I think we need
to talk in some more depth to explain
why we didn't learn anything about them.
Okay.
All right. So, let's first we'll talk
about the structure of sharp examples
for the ST theorem. And let me first
remind you what the ST theorem says and
what are the sharp examples. Uh, okay.
So, the theorem was this. So I have a
set X is a set of points in the plane
and L is a set of lines in the plane
and then we're going to count the
incidences between them. Theorem says
that the number of incidences between X
and L is bounded by the number of points
plus the number of lines plus a more
complicated term.
Okay. And I will just label these terms
one and two and three.
Okay, so a situation where where term
one dominates
is easy to imagine. We just need to put
each point on a line. So I'll draw some
lines and then each point I will put on
one of these lines.
Okay. So this type of example I would
describe as not having any remarkable
structure. Um so this is uh not rigid
and there are many degrees of freedom.
So there's no so I would say no special
structure here.
It's not rigid.
Um there are many degrees of freedom.
Each one of these points I can slide
freely along this line. So I have at
least x degrees of freedom. All right.
Now, example, the situation where two
dominates,
the picture is a little bit different,
but it's similar. Um, so to have L
incences, I just need that each line
goes through a point. So there's a few
points. I put them anywhere. And then
I'm going to draw my lines. And each
line it will go through one of these
points. So it just looks like Oops.
looks like that. Sometimes called the
stars example.
Okay. And again, there's no special
structure. It's not rigid. There are
many degrees of freedom. I can rotate
this line and so
okay. And then example three when this
term dominates those are harder to come
by and they have more structure and
they're more interesting. So the known
examples
are an integer grid
integer
grid
or uh instead of the integers you could
take a ring like a ring in a number
field this time kind of grid or more
generally you could take an R grid where
R is the ring of integers.
and a number fit.
[Applause]
Okay. Um draw a little picture.
All right. So this is the scenario where
the the known examples have structure.
Um we have structure
in the known examples
and we have very few degrees of freedom
to determine these examples.
>> Cool. Okay. Were there any questions or
comments?
>> Yeah. If you embed R2 into the real
projective plane, there's like a duality
that takes lines in the real projective
plane to points and switches points with
lines and it preserves intersections.
>> And it seems to me like the first two
classes of example are kind of dual when
you do that. Is the third class of
examples like self duel if you do that
kind of uh switching lines and points?
>> Yeah. Okay. That's a great question. Let
me just repeat it for everybody. So
there's a structure called point line
duality. Um so
it's probably nicest to explain it in
the um
uh in the projector space, but let me
say it in a low brown way. In a low brow
way. So if I have a line y, I can
probably write it as y = mx + b.
In other words, um, and let me do this
is a little sound a little silly, but
I'm going to write as mx minus b. Why
not? Okay, so in other words, the line
is 0 = mx - b minus y.
Okay. So if I have a set of points it
would be you know x1 y1
xn yn points. If I have a set of lines,
they might be M1 B1
and then M um
L B L if I have L lines.
And um if I want to count incidences, I
consider a different point, different
line and I check this equation. And this
equation is actually symmetric
if you replace if you switch the role of
MB and the role of XY.
So I can turn my points into lines and
turn my lines into points.
So this is
symmetric. If I take MB and switch it
with XY.
Okay. So as student pointed out if you
take this example and then you apply
point line duality you get this example.
So this line here became that point
these points became those lines and so
on. So these two examples are dual to
each other. All right. Now the question
was if you take this example and you
apply point line duality what do you
get? Yeah. Um and um you actually do get
something different. Um so so you can
apply
point line duality
right all right so to to think about
what would happen if we did this I won't
do it in complete detail but but let's
sort of take a first step um so when I
do that each one of these lines will
become a point and the uh the point will
be labeled like m. So the the
xcoordinate of our point will be the
slope. So who were the slopes of these
lines? Well, when we constructed them,
the slopes were rational numbers with
small denominators. So those will be the
x coordinates. They'll be rational
numbers with small denominators. And
then for each x coordinate, the
y-coordinates will be the different b
values. So the different, you know, the
places where it hits the y- axis. And
you can compute that with a little work.
um and you get a set which is not a grid
actually. It's not an integer grid. So
you know the set of rationals with small
denominators that's not uh um I say it's
not um integer multiples of one number.
Uh so it is actually a genuinely
different example when you switch the
the points and the lines. Yeah. So
that's great. Um and the other thing we
mentioned last time is that we can apply
projective transformations.
Okay. Um so this list of examples is a
little bit messy. There are a few of
them but it's a little bit messy. And
that perhaps has contributed to making
it feel daunting to prove that all the
examples look like one of these.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Great.
Great question.
Okay. So, um, so next I thought that we
would go over a bit the proof of the sum
theorem with an eye towards what does it
tell us about the structure of sharp
examples and unfortunately we'll see
tells us very little but but it's good
to see it.
Okay, so the first step in the proof was
a double counting argument
and a double counting argument proved a
weaker upper bound for the number of
incidences which was this
Um and that double counting argument has
a corlary which is perhaps easier to say
and the correlary is actually the only
thing you really need to prove the
summary troder theorem. The correlary
says that if the number of lines is more
than the number of points squared
then the number of incidences is just
bounded by the number of lines which is
in other words it matches the case two
over here. The picture looks like this
where a typical line just goes through
one of the points.
Okay,
cool. Um, so actually that's I didn't
emphasize that last time, but that's a
nice thing to say because this coralary
is maybe easier to hold in our mind than
the whatever the exponents are up there.
Okay, so now the next idea was this uh
cell decomposition idea.
Um so let me draw an example for some
ready troder and then I'll draw the cell
decomposition and we'll talk about how
it's helping us.
Okay. So I'll have a set of points like
that might it might be an integer grid
and then I have some lines here. um
lines at those slopes,
lines at these slopes,
okay? Etc.
And then we will do a cell
decomposition.
Those
are our cells. It's our cell wall. And
here are our our cells. O subi.
Okay.
So let's say xi
is
x intersected with oi and li is the set
of lines so that l intersect o y is not
empty.
Okay.
And um what we what we can can do with
the cell decomposition is that we we
choose our cell decomposition fine
enough.
So the cell decomposition has a
parameter s. Um
there's a parameter s
and in terms of this parameter um x i is
like x over s^2.
So there you can think of there being s
squared cells and the points are
distributed evenly among them and li is
at most x over s
and in sharp examples this would be an
equality.
Okay. Um, so what we do is we do the
cell decomposition fine enough
so that li is bigger than xi squared and
then we use the correlate.
Okay.
Okay. So why does this not help us very
much? Uh why does this not help very
much to understand the structure? So
what what we're going to what we've done
here is we've cut our original we've cut
our space into cells and we're going to
look one cell at a time. In each cell we
see a ton of lines and not that many
points.
And then by double counting we can
deduce that in each cell we have this
bound. Um so we use our corlary it says
that the number of incidences between x
i and li is at most around l.
So within each cell uh a typical line is
only hitting one point within the cell.
Okay.
So this divide and conquer argument,
we're cutting space up into cells and
then we're thinking about them one at a
time. And doing that simplifies our life
because we have some we've broken our
problem into smaller problems and we
just think about them one at a time. And
we understand each smaller problem well
enough to bound the total number of
incidences.
But um we are not paying attention to
any possible sort of interaction between
these cells.
Um and the the structure is all about
the interaction between the cells.
Um so you know a given a given line in
our story
is actually uh appearing in many
different cells. And so there's some
relationship about between what's going
on in this cell and what's going on in
that cell. And in our proof, we're not
trying to understand or exploit that
relationship. We're just looking at the
cells one at a time.
Anyway, so the only structure that the
proof gives us is that within each cell,
you see some points and you each you see
some lines and each line only goes
through one point within the cell, which
is not yet a rigid structure at all. And
that's all that the proof gives us.
Okay. Any questions or comments about
that?
Um so so I have been wondering about
this question of uh of structure of
sharp examples and I thought of a
direction that you know that could that
pe people were interested people could
pursue as a project and I wanted to put
it out there. So take 10 or 15 minutes
to share like a project idea of um of
some I don't know sort of smaller
problems that would might build up
towards understanding this.
So here was my thought. Um okay so first
of all the the this general incidence
theorem implies a projection theorem.
The projection theorem is more
specialized and I think it might be
easier to understand the sharp examples
for the projection theorem.
Um,
okay. So, I called it a theorem last
time. We could also call it a corlary.
So, X is contained in R2 is a finite
set. D is a set of directions.
Um and then um s of xd
is the maximum over all of the
directions of the size of pi theta of x.
And um the way I've stated the theorem
before is that the number of directions
is at most 1 + s^2 over the number of
points. But algebraically it's
equivalent to say the following thing.
If the number of directions is at least
two, then s is at least x to the 12 d to
the 12.
That's just algebra.
The case where the number of directions
is just one is not very interesting. If
you're only projecting in one direction,
it could easily happen that the
projection has only one point.
Okay.
So this is a very special case of this.
In this case, what are the lines? The
set of lines are all of the lines that
are in these directions and pass through
at least one of these points. So that's
a very particular way of choosing the
lines
and there are not as many sharp
examples.
So taking one of these grids and then um
taking a a a set a set of directions
that are rational numbers with small
numerators and denominators. That's a
sharp example for this.
I think if you apply point line duality
that it it's still a sharp example for
summary trotder but I don't think it is
a projection example anymore.
Um so let's see.
So being
so being a projection example means that
for every point
all of the lines going through it have
the same set of slopes. Those are the
directions we're projecting.
So if I applied point line duality
that would mean that for every line
um
uh the set of xcoordinates where it
intersects a point would be the same and
and that's not true here.
Maybe it's better. You may have check on
your own. But so I so I claim if you if
you apply point line duality, you don't
anymore have an example with this
projection structure.
Also, if you apply a projective
transformation, then you will ruin the
fact that there were parallel lines
here. Um so that the directions the
direct you know after projective
transformation lines that used to point
in the same direction won't point in the
same direction anymore. So that won't be
a projective example either. So the
class of known sharp examples is smaller
which makes it a little more hopeful
that we could understand it. It is
actually just grids over number fields.
Okay.
Now once we set the problem up this way,
you could imagine
fixing the set D in advance
and then just for that set of
projections considering different sets X
and seeing what happens. And so you get
actually lots of different problems
depending on what set of directions you
fix.
So let's write that down.
All right. So for any set D,
S subd of N be the minimum over any set
of end points of um SXD
which remember what that is. So it's the
minimum over any set of points of the
maximum over these different projections
of pi theta of x.
Okay. So
yeah. So so in my opinion for any set d
that you write down it's interesting to
try to estimate this. So now we have
lots and lots of questions and most of
those questions have not been
investigated all that much.
Uh okay. Now in the in the sharp
examples that we know about who is D
in the known sharp examples
the set D is uh rational numbers with
small numerators and denominators.
uh or
um rational fractions in some other
ring. So this is a ring of integers in a
in a number field.
And then I'll say this just more
informally. A and b are small.
So maybe the number field are things of
the form a1 plus square of 2 a2 and
a1 and a2 are small integers.
Okay. So in all the known sharp examples
these are the sets of directions and
they have quite a lot of algebraic
structure. And so we could ask the
question if we fix a set of directions
that does not have so much algebraic
structure then can we get a better
estimate?
All right.
Okay.
Um so let's think about um you know we
we begin with the simplest problem that
we can. Um so let's take just a few
directions, two directions, three
directions, four directions. All
right. So, um remark there is some um
linear transformation symmetry in this
problem.
Right? So, if I start with the
configuration of points and some
directions, I can apply a linear change
of variables to R2. I'll get a new
configuration of points and I'll get
some new directions, but it's it'll be
the same problem just in new
coordinates.
Um so uh up to symmetry
if you take just three directions
um then you there there's only one
choice up to symmetry. So the set of
directions
ah okay actually let me say something
else. So okay so up to symmetry if there
are three directions then there's only
one choice.
Um, okay. Let me make a comment about
how to write down the directions. I
actually already was using it without uh
without explaining it properly. So, this
is the list of slopes of the directions,
right? Okay. Um, so
so let's describe our our projections
as pi t of x1 x2 is x1 + t * x2.
Right? So for this this investigation,
this t is more or less the slope of the
projection. And that is a more
convenient thing to talk about than the
angle in radians.
And and that was what we were writing up
here.
Okay. So um
uh cool. So for example, pi 0 of x1 x2
would just be x1. And the other simplest
projection would be just to take x2 and
that doesn't quite fit into this
notation. But um there's a convention
that we'll call that pi infinity. Pi
infinity of x1 x2 is just x
and then all the you know all the other
ones will be t will be a real number.
Okay. So,
so if d equals 3
um then without loss of generality d
might be 0 1 and infinity.
Okay.
And um
[Applause]
Okay.
Um, all right. So, let me copy down what
the samurai troder theorem says for
comparison. says for any set D uh S subd
of N is at least D to the 12 N to the 12
as long for as long as there are at
least two points.
Um so if D is 01 infinity or any set of
three ele three slopes because it's all
the same um this is sharp.
Um for instance that you could take an n
byn integer grid or n half by n the half
integer grid.
Okay. So there's nothing new for three
directions. Let's go to four directions.
Okay. By using our symmetry we can
arrange that the first three directions
are 0 1 and infinity. and there'll be a
fourth direction t and t could be any
real number. So we have one degree of
freedom how we would choose four
directions.
Okay.
So on and the one extreme we could
choose t to be like a half or two and
this so this would be rational with a
small size
and then the other extreme we could say
that t t might be a transcendental
number and somewhere in the middle we
would have roo2 or like a big
rational number like a thousand or
something like that.
Okay. Now in this case um uh the theorem
is sharp
that so the example that we have with
four directions the the four directions
would be these
and in this case let's question what
would happen so let me write a specific
question so question
if t so if E is 0 1 infinity and T where
T is transcendental.
Then
is it true that SD of N is bounded by N
to the 12.
So it's at least N to the 1/2. If the
theorem is sharp, it would be
approximately n to the half. But if the
theorem is not sharp and we can improve
it, it might be bigger than this.
My best guess is that it's bigger than
this. And I played around a little bit
with examples and I can show you the uh
best example that I can find.
Okay.
Okay. So example
let me say that P ks
is the set of polomials in this
transcendental number t. So a 0 + a1 t +
a k minus1 t the k minus one. So they're
degree k polomials
and the a's are integers
and they have size up to s. So let's say
so that guy is going to kind of play the
role like integers from one up to s um
in in that that would have worked well
if we had a rational slope.
Okay. So now our set s is going to be
pks times pks. K and s of course are
parameters. So we can play with them and
sort of see what's optimal.
So the size of X is S to the 2K. The
size of this thing is S to the K. We
have K choices and S S choices for each
of AI.
Okay. Now what happens when we project
X?
Pi 0 of X projection onto the first
coordinate is just PKS and pi infinity
of X is projection onto the second
coordinate that's just PKS.
Those are quite small. Best we could
hope for really.
Now what is pi one of X?
Pi one of X is I take an element of here
and I add it to an element of here. So
I'm going to add this set to itself.
When I take two of these polomials and
add them together, I get a new polomial
and I just add the coefficients. So the
new constant the old um the the constant
coefficient was between 0 and s minus
one and I add up two of those. The sum
is between zero and 2s basically. So pi
1 of x is contained in p k comma 2s
and it's pretty much equal to that.
All right.
Now what happens if I take pi t of x?
Well pi t of x means I'm going to take
x1 which is in here and I'm going to add
it to t * x2. x2 lives in here. I'm
going to multiply it by t and add it to
x1.
Right? All right. And this is it's this
is the most important one. And these
were designed to make this reasonably
small.
So what's going to happen? Um well t *
x2 is going to be a polomial like this.
But it will have degree k instead of k
minus one.
And then I will add it to x1 which is a
polomial like this. when I put them
together I'll get a polomial of degree K
and the coefficients will be up to 2s.
So this is contained in P k + 1 2s
and this one is the largest of the four
projections.
It's a bit smaller than this but I doubt
that it matters very much. So let's just
think of it as being about this big.
All right.
So s is the size of the biggest
projection. This one is the biggest
projection.
And that is roughly um 2s
to the k + one.
All right. So let me digest it a little
bit. It's 2 to the k + one. The plus one
doesn't matter very much. and then s
and then s to the k.
S to the k is the square root of x.
That's our sort of what we're shooting
for. We're trying to get as as close as
we can to the square root of x. It's 2
to the k um and there's x to the 12. And
then there's an s here. And the s is the
size of x to the 1 / 2 k.
Okay, so I want to try to get as close
to this as I can. So I want to minimize
this thing. So now we're going to choose
K to minimize it.
K should also be an integer, but that's
not a not a big issue.
Cool.
Okay. Well, if I want to minimize this
product, at least roughly, the thing to
do is to make this one equal to this
one.
So, let's set 2 the k to be equal to x^
the 1 / 2k. And now we'll solve for k.
First, I raise both sides to the 2k
power. So, I get 2 to the 2k^ 2 is x.
Now, I'll take the logarithm of both
sides. So 2 k^2 is the logarithm base 2
of x.
And now I'll solve for k. And there's
some constants that uh let's not worry
about too much. So k is k is equal to
some constant time the log of x to the
12.
Okay. So now how big was this thing?
It's uh either one of these things are
equal to each other. And this one is
maybe easier to understand. It's two to
that.
So our s uh subd of this set x is like
um e to a constant
log of x to the 12
x to the 12.
All right. So asmtoically as the size of
x goes to infinity this thing is smaller
than x to the 0.51.
But it's also you know this thing is
bigger than any constant. It is going to
infinity. So it's also not less less
some x to the 1/2.
Okay, so this was just one example.
S subd of N. Um, so this tells us that S
subd of N is less than E to a constant
log of N to the 12 N to the 12.
And this by definition is the minimum
over all the possible sets X of size N.
And this was just one of them. Um but I
think it's plausible that this is the
this is the one with smallest
projections.
Okay.
So
so plausibly that gives a sense of how
thing for for four directions how do
things change when you go from a the
from a transcendental thing on the one
side to a very nice rational slope on
the other side.
Okay, cool. And that I mean that's sort
of the beginning of an investigation. Of
course, we could have more directions.
Um,
so we have many questions.
Yeah. So, four directions is already
complicated enough to be interesting.
Um, but wow, we could also have many
directions and so we would have lots
more questions.
So, more questions.
Um, so maybe D is 0, one, and infinity.
And then a bunch more directions.
So we have r directions and the you know
the
the sharp example these guys were
rational numbers or rational numbers in
some field and with small heights. Um
the opposite of that would be um maybe
t1 up to tr are algebraically
independent over q.
So they're each transcendental but even
more than that there's no algebraic
relation among all of them. This would
be sort of the most transcendental
situation.
Um so then
how does this behave?
Um
and then there's stuff in the middle. So
maybe these guys could live in a field
extension of Q which is like pretty
complicated. And so potentially there
could be an interaction between
algebraic number theory where is a
discipline that describes like who are
the field extensions of Q. How do you
think about them? Um with projection
theory.
Cool. So people coming into the class
have different backgrounds. I'm not sure
if there's anyone who does number theory
and algebraic number theory.
Um but um anyway, so so this is a
possible project. In the weeks ahead,
we'll be talking more about different
different types of projects and
everybody can pick out something that
they want to work on for their final
project for the class.
Cool. Okay. Any other qu any questions
or comments about about this? This is my
my stab at having some warm-up questions
to that that lead towards thinking about
um the structure of sharp examples for
summary trotder.
>> From what you're saying, you expect that
you can prove something stronger for
this case where everything is
algebraically independent.
>> Yeah, if I had to guess, so I think the
question is what do I guess is true?
Um if I had to guess, I would guess that
there are um there are sorry this should
be s subd of n. There are much stronger
lower bounds for this than the than this
already trotder. If these are all trans
this is a if there are no algebraic
relations there.
Yeah. So for you know for this setup you
could make a class of examples that is
kind of like this class but instead of
having polomials in just one thing T
there would be polinomials in T1 up to
TR.
Um, and I don't know if you could count
the total degree or I'm not sure.
Anyway, so there's some some example you
could get your hands on and I think it's
plausible that that's the sharp example
and I think it's plausible the bounds
are much stronger than the general
summarity tryer bound and I would be
really interested to or I could be wrong
also but I would be really interested in
in either case.
Okay. So um let's circle back to our
class outline.
So the summarated trder proof uh doesn't
tell us much about projection theory for
finite fields. We'll talk more about
that next class. It doesn't tell us much
about the structure of sharp examples
for the semirder theorem over the reals.
We just talked about that. And it
doesn't tell us very much about
projection theory for unit balls. So
let's talk about this one. This is
perhaps the central topic in our class.
And let's see what the problem is. Why
um you know this complete elegant
solution of the projection problem for
points in R2 doesn't tell us very much
about the projection problem for unit
balls in R2.
All right. So first um let's recall what
is what is the projection problem for
unit balls and what is house spacing.
Uh all right.
So set up.
All right. Let me write.
All right. So X is now a set of unit
balls
in the ball of radius R in R2.
And D is a set of directions. So I'm
going to think of it as a subset of the
circle. Um and it their directions are 1
/ r separated because otherwise they
would be sort of equivalent from the
point of view of projecting some unit
balls in BR. All right. S of XD is the
largest projection.
All right. And this symbol is now doing
double duty. and we're thinking of it as
the length of the projection.
Okay. So,
so we, so we'd like to understand how
these things behave. Um, but besides
looking at this cardality of X and the
cardality of D, we're also going to pay
attention to their spacing.
So, n subx of r
is the maximum of x intersected with a
ball of radius little r with any center.
So it's the maximum over this center
and n subd of row is the maximum
of d intercept gamma where gamma is an
arc of length row in the circle. So this
describes how x and d are packed at
smaller scales or how they're spaced.
Um
so hidorf spacing means
that x is around r to the alpha for some
pre parameter alpha and n subx of little
r is bounded by little r to the alpha.
That's how direct spacing for x. How's
our spacing for the directions would be
the number of directions is r to the
beta and um nd of little r over big r is
bounded by little r to the beta.
Okay, so this informally says that the
balls of x are not kind of packed too
much into a smaller ball and the
directions are not kind of packed too
much into a smaller direction into a
small band of directions.
um you know these exact conditions
it's not the only conditions one might
be interested in. It's not the only
spacing condition that might be
interesting to think about, but it's one
of the most popular ones. And it has it
has sort of turned out that the most
interesting math has come up by trying
to understand these conditions.
And they come up they come up naturally
in some points of view even though
they're also I will argue that other
spacing conditions are helpful to
consider sometimes.
So that's housed door spacing. Um and um
the analog of the summary trotder
problem is going to be try to understand
this if x and d have house door spacing.
So question
if x and d
have house door spacing.
Wow. Let me put up a conjecture
which is even now a theorem.
Um then
d is less
s^2 x + one.
Okay. So this was an old conjecture and
now it's a theorem proven by orin and
merkin and red and wong. Um and it's
totally analogous to the semi troder
projection theorem for finite point
sets. But the proof of the semi rider
theorem doesn't help very much to prove
this thing.
Okay. So what goes wrong?
Um
okay.
So
um so let's try to use the cell
decomposition method.
So here's X
Actually,
let me back up a second. Um, so to see
what goes wrong, it helps to remember
how the cell decomposition method worked
for the original semir Troder theorem,
which we did go over, but let me go over
it in the context of this projection
theorem. And so you can see how it looks
there, so that we'll be able to compare.
Um,
all right.
[Applause]
I do realize that this is maybe the
third time that we have outlined the
proof of this ever troder theorem with
the cell decompositions, but well really
good pieces of math. It's okay to see a
few times.
All right. So
sketch of ST proof um ST projection
proof
using um cell decompositions.
Okay. So we have a set X of points.
So here's X and then I cut it into cells
and X I
is X intersect OI. I'm going to do my
cell decomposition
and it has a parameter
uh which I I called S before but I'm
going to call it sigma now because we
have this other letter S and uh it gets
confusing.
So the size of X I is like X over sigma
squ.
Okay. Um,
now
we're gonna draw all the so the set L
our lines are going to be all the lines
through X with a slope in D.
And when we just look at this cell,
we're still doing the projections in all
the same directions. We have the same D.
Um,
okay. Yeah, let me write down our so D.
So, DI is the same as D.
Okay. And then, um, we have a a double
counting observation.
And the double counting observation says
that if the number of directions is
bigger than the number of points, maybe
twice the number of points,
um, then s should be at least around the
number of points.
And the reason for that is that if you
have this many directions
and a typical point
for most of the directions you're
projecting it cannot hit any other
point. So in most directions when you
project a point. So we have this point
we have a handful of other points but
then we're going to project this point
in many directions.
So there
okay so we have let's say we have more
than twice as many directions as points
if I draw a lines in different in these
different directions through my base
point most of those lines won't hit any
other point so when I look at this
projection this will be the only point
over here and so in this situation
most of the time um the points don't
land on top of each other when you do
projections. And so this size of the
projection is around the same as the
size of the set.
Okay.
Um
okay, great. So now L are all of the
lines that go through X with slope in D.
And each line only goes through a small
fraction of the cells. So,
so
um so LI, so LI would be the lines
that go through OI and for a typical
cell li would be smaller than L over
sigma.
So now what we do is we cut up our
picture into small enough cells that in
each cell the number of directions is
bigger than the number of points.
So we choose sigma
so that x over sigma squared is smaller
than half of the number of directions.
Um
and so then we get that si is bigger
than xi which is x over sigma squ.
Um okay and from that we can compute um
um
so I say this so s
* d is the number of lines
and that's bigger than sigma times the
number of lines through a typical cell
which is like sigma time the number of
directions times the size of a
projection for a particular cell. So
then in in each cell the number of lines
is the number of directions times the
size of a projection.
Uh okay. And SI is bigger than XI.
So that's bigger than sigma * D * um X
over sigma^ 2.
That's X * D / sigma.
and sigma is dictated here.
So if you plug in the value of sigma,
you get that this is x to the 12 d to
the three halves and you cancel the d's
and and that's the lower bound.
Okay.
So algebra aside, what is happening is
that we do this cell decomposition and
we cut things up finely enough so that
within this cell the number of
directions is bigger than the number of
points in this cell. Then we know that a
typical line only goes through one point
and then we count everything up and some
ready troder falls out.
What goes wrong when we try to do this
for unit bus?
[Applause]
All right.
So if the set X has an alpha dimensional
spacing condition, then you should
visualize it as being something like a
caner set. So I tried to draw that here.
So now we can partition it.
We do our cell decomposition.
we have sigma squared cells. Sigma is a
parameter.
So x i is x intersected with oi. So here
it is.
And um well we'd like to think of this
as a smaller version of our original
problem. And our original problem was
about unit balls in a bigger ball. So
actually we need to know how big is this
bigger ball.
Let's call it a ball of radius little r.
Now it won't necessarily happen. We
don't know for sure that x i is
organized into one ball like this. But
that is the that could happen and it's
the most important case. So let's just
imagine that each of these xis lives in
one ball like this.
Okay. Now, we're going to think of this
as a smaller version of our original
problem. In our original problem, we had
a set of directions and we needed them
to be one over r separated
because two directions that are too
close together, they look equivalent.
And now that we have this smaller ball,
our set of directions are not one over
little r separated.
So, here's the key point.
set of directions is 1 / r separated
but it is not one over little r
separated.
All right. So if we if you think of it
in terms of the fibers of the projection
map you would see some twos.
So maybe that
maybe this is one of our directions. And
you see that the there there's a fiber
that is a tube with a lot of points in
it. And maybe there's another direction
in our projection
um
that looks something like that.
This is a different noticeably different
direction if you're looking at the big
ball and it has a different set of
points in it. But if you're looking just
within this cell, these two tubes or
these two directions are
indistinguishable.
Okay.
So, in order to
study our original problem, in order to
study what's going on within this cell,
we can't really use all of these
directions. We only have to we have to
use the inequivalent ones.
So d
is um let's say
d so
let's say that theta 1 is equivalent to
theta 2 if theta 1 minus theta 2 is less
than 1 / r and then d is going to be d
up to equivalence.
This is not exactly an equivalence
relation, but anyway, we we pick a
subset of the directions so that there's
only one of them in each one over R arc.
Maybe it's better to say that. Let me
see.
So we choose
di inside of D.
So that um
uh
so that DI intersect an arc smaller than
one
for each arc gamma in the circle of
length 1 / R.
And now we have a smaller set of
directions.
Okay.
Okay. So, double counting
double counting still helps still uh uh
works well.
If it were to happen that DI
was bigger than
Xi,
that's still true, just like before.
But the key difference between the
original problem and this version with
um unit balls is that in the original
problem when we looked at a smaller
piece of it in the cell oi we had many
fewer points but we still had the same
number of directions. So if the cell was
small enough the number of points in the
cell would drop below the number of
directions and then double counting
would give a very good bound.
But now when I go into a smaller cell, I
have fewer points, but I also have fewer
directions.
And so it's not clear whether I'm making
any progress.
Um to check whether you're making
progress, you have to write down
carefully how these things are changing.
Um and um I won't do the whole
computation, but I will tell you what
happens.
So if x and d are housedorf
and uh so x is r to the alpha so x is
alpha dimensional and d is r to the beta
d is beta dimensional then what you'll
find is that x i is little r to the
alpha so the radius little r would
depend on how much we chop things up. If
I take a finer cell decomposition,
little r will get smaller. So it's
essentially a free parameter that I can
choose. Xi will be like little r to the
alpha and d will be little r to the
beta.
So if alpha was bigger than beta
initially, so I had many more points
than directions, which is the
interesting case. After I look at a
smaller cell, alpha will still be bigger
than beta. So I still have many more
points than directions.
Um so I won't ever get to a place where
I can apply this double counting.
Okay. Now having said that I think there
are some situations where where this
method would give something new and
interesting. Uh so in particular
when we did this computation
it was predicated on having equalities
here
and if we had strong inequalities here
then something more favorable would
happen and we might get uh an
interesting estimate.
I don't think this has ever been written
down carefully. So Tom Wolf tried really
hard to understand this and I'm sure he
thought through everything that I just
presented
but I guess the answers didn't turn out
sufficiently sort of positive for him to
write it up as a paper and I don't think
anyone else has really systematically
done it. So also it could be a good
project to see how much does cell
decomposition tell us.
Okay. Now there is also an example
that's worth mentioning um why being
able to cut things into pieces
um
that doesn't necessarily let us
I should say okay so so this was so okay
so there's also an example that matches
the story that I was just telling about
how this proof would go um and the
example goes back to the beginning of
the class when we were noticing when we
were doing projection theory in finite
fields
that it makes a difference whether you
have a prime field or whether you have a
field with sub fields and that is also
true for um for this problem that's on
the board here. It's different over the
real numbers versus the complex numbers
because the complex numbers have a nice
sub field the real numbers.
So let me end by mentioning that
example.
[Applause]
Are there actually are there any
questions or comments before I before I
do that last example?
Okay.
So end the class. I'll mention this
example over the complex numbers.
Okay. So in this setup, X is a set of
unit balls
in the ball of radius R in C2.
Um so
this ball you can think of C2 for the
moment as being R4. So this ball has a
volume
which is like R 4th.
Okay. Now we're going to consider some
projections and I think a good way to
write it is pi t of z1 z2 is z1 + t z2.
So in this story z1 and z2 and t are all
complex numbers. So these are complex
projections and they're parameterized by
a complex number t which maybe we can
think of as being in the unit ball. So d
is contained in the unit ball in the
space of complex numbers
and it's 1 / r separated.
Okay. And then we can define sxd and nxr
and nd row and housedorf.
As usual,
all those definitions translate in a
straightforward way to the complex
setting.
Okay. And now the example basically is
that the set X is basically R2 the real
points and the set of directions are
going to be the real directions.
So
X is a set of unit balls
with centers
in R2
and they're sitting in the ball of
radius R. So the size of X would be like
R 2
R 2 kind of real balls among R to the
4th complex balls.
And our set of directions are going to
be um is going to be contained in the
real part of the ball and they're one
over r separated. So our set of
directions will have size r.
Okay. So now if I take a real point z1
z1 and z2 are real and I take a real
projection so t is real then that will
be real.
So the um all of the projections of all
of the centers of the balls will be
real. The balls are still complex so
they stick out a little bit in the
imaginary direction but not very much.
So if I take
uh so if t is in d
and I take pi t of x, what does it look
like? Here's the complex plane. Here's a
ball of radius R and
it will look like this.
And this height will only be one because
this will consist of lots of unit balls
whose centers are real.
So we can conclude that S of XD is
around R.
Okay, so this example badly violates
this conjecture showing that the
conjecture is not true over the complex
numbers.
Um, and this example
so and you know we had some simpler
things that we did know how to prove
over the reals. Uh, we had double
counting and we had the forier method.
Those work over the complex numbers and
this example is sharp for both of those
things.
Um
and um in this example you do kind of
have so so you could ask you know are
there cell decompositions over the
complex numbers? It's a slightly tricky
question. Um you know the way we built
cell decompositions did look special for
the real numbers because we took a
variety a real a real you know the zero
set of a polinomial and cut it out and
that decomposed space into pieces. And
here we're working over the complex
numbers. If you take the zero set of a
complex polomial and cut it out, it does
not divide space into pieces. If you
take the zero set of a real polinomial
and cut it out, it does divide space
into pieces, but it doesn't necessarily
interact well with complex projections.
Um,
but in spite of that, there is with work
a decent cell decomposition theory over
C. And the main thing is that it's easy
to see that for this particular example,
you could divide it into pieces in a
nice way by hand and the pieces would
have all the properties of the cell
decomposition uh that that you would
that you would have in R2.
Okay. So that goes to show that even
even though this theorem looks a lot
like the semi troder theorem and we have
a proof of the semi troder theorem,
we're going to need to approach this
theorem very differently.
because the cell decomposition method
applies equally well to this example
which is a counter example too you know
which is which does not match our
theorem.
Um so to make progress towards this we
have to think about the issue of whether
a seal field field has sub fields and
things like that um and try to take
advantage of that to improve the bounds
over over something like this.