[Music]
from the MIT energy initiative this is
what if it works a podcast looking at
the energy solutions for climate change
I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob
Stoner and today we talk with a material
scientist about the stuff in our
buildings our phones our cars and how
that stuff takes a toll on the
environment materials and the
manufacturer of materials are
responsible for over a third of
greenhouse gas emissions globally and so
the choices we make at every stage of
Designing materials of recycling and
Manufacturing are going to have Global
impact that's Elsa olivetti professor of
Material Science and Engineering at MIT
and Mission lead for the decarbonizing
energy and Industry mission of mit's
climate project and of course there's
long been discussion in business amongst
policy makers about emissions what
should or shouldn't be coming out of our
cars how detrimental are the emissions
from airplanes but alletti says there's
a whole other dimension to that
emissions
conversation so those cars and those
airplanes are made of stuff right and so
we've got to do a lot to make that stuff
you think about what we sometimes call
the embodied impact of the stuff that we
hold and we you know process and and
live in and and throughout our lives and
it's also surprising maybe for people
that that's dominated that impact that
oneir is dominated by a couple of key
materials that we produce at vast scales
right steel cement we make as much
cement as we use water right so the the
sort of scale of that aluminum copper so
these kind of really big bulk materials
are a big part of that impact and
remember when you turn raw materials
into say an airplane there are a ton of
steps where do we tend to expend the
most energy olivetti says it depends but
there's a lot of energy involved in the
refining process so going from an ore
and the chemical and heat and
temperature processes that are
associated with making them usable in
whatever form and so that that's when
we're talking about greenhouse gas
emissions if we're talking about land
use or the environmental impact on an
ecosystem or water quality then the
burden might be shifting to a different
stage of the life cycle more in the
mining because the significant amount of
wastes that are produced or the uh
releases to water air and soils and that
gets at an important piece of this as
significant as greenhouse gases are the
effect of materials extraction on the
planet reaches even beyond that take
tailings which exist on the sites of
mines and they're essentially just a
bunch of the stuff that people weren't
really looking for so tailings are a
processing waste from The Mining and
refining process and the thing that to
think about with tailings is it's most
frequently wet because we add a lot of
water and and solvents to try to float
up the parts of the metal and the
constituents that we actually want mines
will often have these huge ponds
containing tailings and they're filled
with chemicals and as we transition to a
cleaner Energy System we will need to do
more mining so how do you make that
Mining and refinement of raw materials
more efficient and less dirty that's
what drives alletti and she says it's
important to recognize as technology
gets more advanced our needs are
changing one thing to keep in mind as we
are thinking about transitioning to low
carbon energy infrastructures that it it
particularly um the the technologies
that are needed for that are
particularly dependent on a um a wider
variety and more of the materials that
we use so something like a a car with an
internal combustion engine may have a
couple of materials that are specialized
for that engine but if we think about a
battery electric vehicle for example
there can be upwards of of five to eight
times the quantity of more Specialty
Minerals and a much broader array so so
things like nickel and Cobalt and
lithium and graphite that are very
critical to the battery itself and we
need so we need more complexity in terms
of more Supply chains that we accessing
and then we also need more quantity as
we transition to electric vehicles does
that mean more mining has to go on to
support electric vehicles than just
internal combustion engines yeah more
mining of the of that broader set right
I mean in terms of the um so yeah so we
have significant growth associated with
with a much wider variety of minerals
okay um and you know upwards of of uh
100 you know 100% full increases in the
in the quantities that we need to be um
going after and that there are more
there's more complexity associated with
those and that's really across all the
energy technologies that Advanced
Technologies that we're interested in
right and Rob been talking about more
Specialty Minerals that are present in
in magnets for example in wind turbines
but I mentioned a couple also for
batteries and solar cells so you can
think about that that the energy low
carbon energy transition is is dependent
on a significant minerals extraction um
uh
situation dependent on us doing the
mining and beneficiation and mineral
extraction in a thoughtful sustainable
sensible way in order to have that
transition happen without a series of
unintended
consequences um that we want to make
sure that we're uh developing policies
and incentives to directionally look at
and I can talk a little bit more
specifically about one of those just as
an example uh we could dig into um
talking about uh nickel um and nickel is
interesting for a couple of different
reasons it's important to remember that
the things that are the dominant uses
for nickel now are not necessarily what
is relevant to the energy transition as
much so nickel right now is used the
majority for stainless steel something
we think about and use all the time but
it's also a critical element associated
with battery electric vehicles and and
so the transition for our vehicle Fleet
that needs to happen as part of a low
carbon energy transition is going to
mean there's a lot more nickel that will
that will'll need um and so that will
start to become the dominant use which
is pretty significant in terms of what
that means for for Supply chains and the
other thing that's interesting about the
the broader set of materials that that
we need in in part of the low carbon
energy transition is that they have
different kinds of geographic
concentrations than than we might expect
they're they could be very highly
concentrated in particular geographies
which means we're very dependent on
those
geographies um for for the mining
process um it also Downs Downstream as I
said in refining and processing so in
nickel's case the majority of of nickel
um extraction what you know one region
that nickel extraction happens is in
Indonesia it's also extracted in Russia
so the demand for nickel is growing so
rapidly that there's been a pretty
significant investment in mining
infrastructure in Indonesia both in
terms of of new uh new sources new mines
opening but also Indonesia is interested
in the economic development opportuni so
they also want to be developing
infrastructure Downstream of of
extracting it out of the ground they
want to develop that capability to
refine and beneficiate um as we've as
we've talked about so that they get to
add the value in their home country
rather than having someone else do it
and get the money for it exactly like
they have been
historically taking that ore and digging
out of the ground but then shipping it
elsewhere to be refined and majority is
actually currently refined in China
that's true of almost all of the
materials we could talk about after the
mining mining is sometimes while
geographically concentrated different
kinds of of geographic pockets for
mining but almost all of it is currently
processed and and and supply chains go
through China we're talking
Downstream um and in Indonesia in
particular what's been uh challenging is
thinking about the trade-offs of the
environmental impact of mining with the
economic development opportunity and
they and their need and interest to grow
rapidly to take advantage of this of
this opportunity yeah you know I grew up
in a mining town yeah in Northern Canada
sbur Ontario and and in those days it
was sulfite minerals that they they mind
in hard rock deep below the surface and
we were always aware that Indonesia was
coming along and and would have the
ability to mine their laterite nickel
deposits but those are surface deposits
and and as Elsa is saying I mean getting
to those deposits means you're leveling
forests and removing huge amounts of
Earth um and and there are other places
where that kind of thing exists new
calonia is another place in in the South
Pacific we were always you know feeling
very smug about our sulfites because we
didn't have to cause that sort of
Destruction we caused other kinds of
Destruction and so we were pretty sure
that that would never happen and now I
I'm seeing even looking Beyond later
rides people are talking about nickel
nodules on the ocean floor and and
they're not only talking about mining
nickel that way but you know scraping
huge amounts of ocean floor in order to
get at new minerals I I'm really kind of
uncomfortable with that and I think we
have to think about that as a society
there's a lot of discussion I feel like
anybody listening to this discussion
right now their head is kind of
exploding because we're talking about
using more nickel to facilitate the
transition to cleaner energy like have
electric vehicles not have internal
combustion engines and to do that you
need to clearcut forests potentially
scrape the ocean floor um use well use
like a ton of processing right to or or
you know ship stuff to China and process
and which we already do right and so I
guess my question is we are we sure all
this pollution and like you know
greenhouse gas emissions is worth it to
facilitate the electric vehicles like I
assume somebody has done this math right
yeah we actually just did this analysis
looking at those materials that I said
these sort of bulk high volume materials
at which are the majority of impact
right we can't forget that the the kind
of nuances and complexities of all these
Supply chains are very critical and very
important part of it and we must
transition to low carbon modes of
Transport modes of generating
electricity each of those are very
dependent on this broader portfolio of
materials I've mentioned but in terms of
the volumes it's also need we also need
vast quantities of concrete
steel copper right all of these bulk
materials as well that whole set is
necessary as part of the transition and
the production from an energy
perspective of all of those materials
that are part of the energy
transition is still about half of the
energy that would be required to
continue the fossil fuel-based
energy infrastructure that we have even
if you consider that like in Indonesia
obvious obvously it sounds like some
forests are being cut down and that has
like long-term ramifications when it
comes to right absorbing carbon sure
yeah so all the re the you know growth
as an economy is inextricably linked to
Resource use the things we do and the
the systems in which we exist are
dependent on impact on the environment
and I think the trick and the
opportunity we have in a lowc carbon
energy transition is while we're
thinking thought fully about the
technology we need about the impact
we're doing we can make sure we're not
having significant unintended
consequences and one of the things
that's interesting about the new kinds
of pressures and the new geography
shifts that's happening is it's
different kinds of pressures in
different kinds of regions and that then
lead to other challenges we need to be
tracking so in the case of of Indonesia
this fast tracking of nickel production
and processing is is an opportunity
nationally for Indonesia but we need the
right kind of signal the right kind of
investment the right kind of signals
from demand from consumers from
automobile manufacturers of let's do it
right and what are the resources in
order to do it right so that we're not
having these tradeoffs instead we're
building sustainable Supply throughout
the entire life cycle of those materials
is that happening like as as we have
more electric vehicles as the Chinese
are producing tons of electric vehicles
um are the right incentives reaching
Indonesia or are people just like go
find as much nickel as you possibly can
and we'll pay you for it and do it as
fast as you
can we can say a little bit of both or a
lot of bit of both and but we need to
try to think about what is the full
Suite of decarbonization opportunities
to apply throughout the life cycle but
also other ways in which we would
mitigate the environmental impact of of
resource use yeah so we can work with
the Indonesian government for example or
the automobile manufacturers to try to
develop sustainable Supply chains and
and demand signals that would propagate
throughout those Supply chains for more
sustainable production can also think
about ways to incend production
domestically or in where we have more
control over those Supply chains other
strategies could include in increasing
recycling so which would maybe in the
long run need mean that we need less
primary extraction so those are there
are a couple of different strategies for
for managing those tradeoffs yeah there
are some processes that are forming
around the the cop and and
unfccc um that that try to create a way
for developed countries with
money to help developing countries that
are producing these minerals get cleaner
um and and the process that's most
talked about now is called the jetp
process joint transition energy plan or
program I think it's called where we're
different wealthy countries are
contributing money but there are strings
attached you know if if you want to we
will give you money for energy
development in India for example says
the United States or Japan to Indonesia
provided that you don't develop coal
mines and instead develop these low
carbon resources like either solar or
hydro and perhaps also adopt refining
practices that are less energy intensive
or inherently less polluting and I think
I think we're at the beginning of that
uh sort of move toward those sorts of
Arrangements but but it's a possible
way um have you been either with nickel
or with any other um uh thing that is
mine for have you been on the ground at
one of those minds and can you talk
about what it's like since so few people
really have that experience what's it
like yeah I've been to a couple of of
minds and I think the part that is
consistently
shocking is the vastness of it the scale
at which things need to operate in order
to get the materials that we use and for
example I've been to the uh copper mine
in Utah kott mine that the has been
operation since 1900 it's you know
incred it's open pit incredibly you two
empire state buildings tall Pit in the
ground and you can see you know this
tiny little truck at the bottom that is
a enormous truck when you're standing
next to it you know the wheel is I can't
even see the top of the wheel if I'm
standing next to the truck but it looks
like a tiny you know Lego toy as it's
coming up you know spinning up the
spiral of the of the mine and you know
kind of rock pile after rock pile and
the vast majority of what is being
driven out of that on that you know tiny
than becoming bigger truck is rock that
doesn't contain Copp it isn't
necessarily part of this and you can see
in that site in particular you can go
from each of the stages down to even
some of the wire manufacturers are are
local uh you know within driving
distance of that to see that so that's
probably the most striking is the
vastness and how much activity goes into
each molecule that we then get to use in
our cell phones that we just you know
don't even really think about as we're
as we're living our living our daily
lives and the other thing that's
striking is we think about
decarbonizing and the trying to reduce
our Reliance on fossil fuel how much of
that process still is going to need
fossil fuels in order to transition
right that truck is using Fuel and so I
think that this this sort of importance
of moving
rapidly but but thoughtfully in what we
talked about in nickel or in G you can
think about in any of these sort of
local community conversations that need
to happen within mining it's a
particular challenge that that you know
engaging communities and thinking about
those processes as are happening locally
has to happen deliberately and rapidly
because of the scale and the need of the
transition all the way from every
battery in our vehicles to the grid but
also that truck that's driving out of
the mine that also brings you into
contact with Society more I mean some of
the easy places are easy because they're
far away from where people live and want
to be but as as you start pursuing
deposits of higher grades or any grades
that you can get access to you often
come into into contact with for example
Aboriginal groups uh in in Australia
this has been a a major factor in the
pilra area in Western Australia for
mining iron and and Rio Tinto one of the
big operators there had just a disaster
with with one of those mins where they
inadvertently destroyed major cultural
heritage site um and so those sorts of
uh complications introduce complexity
and developing the mines planning them
operating those areas and that adds to
cost as well as as just the sort of
having to move more
[Music]
rock uh rob you know you were saying you
grew up in a mining town in in Canada I
wonder if you think that the mining
industry has changed a lot in your
lifetime I know it's a lot safer now
than it used to be at least in developed
countries when I was when I was a child
we had a lot of Orphans in in my classes
typically going through Primary School
people had lost their fathers in the
minds a lot of amputees I had a I had a
cycling coach at one point who had lost
a leg in a m c lapse and the lots of
stories of Mind collapses that happens
far less nowadays um because of the the
safety culture that these companies have
developed but I don't know how well that
translates to environments like
Indonesia or or other poor countries
where people are prepared to take bigger
personal risks and maybe look the other
way in order to get stuff get get a job
or just the central government has fewer
regulations about like you have to you
know whatever they may not have an oosha
like these are hurdles that you have to
overcome to being licensed yeah and and
less automation you know they're they're
using manual labor in many situations
where we would use machines so there
people are more exposed also I don't
know if you have any thoughts there but
I also wonder if you can talk a little
bit about um when you think about cell
phones electric vehicles what are the
metals that we need more and more of
like if you had to say these are really
On The Rise Like if I if you look
forward 10 or 20 years as like these are
the things where the demand is just
really Rising because our lives are
changing like we didn't use you know
like people didn't have um cell phones
30 years ago necessarily that They
Carried with them all so what are EVS
you know yeah there are a couple
of elements that are more prominent
within the within the electrification or
low carbon
infrastructure we've talked about some
of them so uh Cobalt
copper nickel
lithium then there's also the set that
are as part of uh wind turbines and
solar so neodymium and and other Rare
Earth elements uh that are present but
things like
mbum um and the so there's a plethora of
those but another way to think about it
is when you're you're talking about cell
phones in something in the in 1980 there
was something like 11 elements that were
used used within the the circuit board
for a phone and now it's the entire
periodic table wow so you I mean
essentially you are carrying around you
know stable forms of the primary
uh periodic table in your pocket and and
so that's just from 1980 and you know in
the 2000s we added another 45 and and
you know just has grown and those
elements are there for a reason they add
a particular
functionality they you know perform
better we want that performance as
consumers we don't often think about the
trade-offs associated with the supply
chains of those but also the complexity
that it introduces in terms of trying to
do something with them when we're done
with our cell phone so it's it's
ubiquitous um and and also in addition
to
that the fact that there's many more
different types there's also just more
associated with it so silicon is another
element that we think about both
relevant for energy transition in solar
cells but also relevant in Wafers for
electronics and and and electrical
appliances are there any of those
elements where you think I'm really
worried like that I I don't think
there's enough of it when I see the
demand curve and I see what I think is
the supply I don't see it or I'm worried
that these things are going to
collide so we often say that
materials availability is not about
running out it's about risk assoc
associated with those tradeoffs so we
talked about the sort of Rapid rise in
nickel and you know what does that do
for for local um
communities because often we'll get it
at whatever price at whatever cost
another way to think about this is
the those that that kind of catalog this
so the US Geological Society for example
has this way they frame the amount that
we are uh the reserves the amount that's
economically extractable div divided by
the production the amount that we need
annually and that's kind of how much is
left right and so 40 years ago we had 40
Years of copper left based on that okay
now we have 40 Years of copper left and
that's because as the demand goes up we
have there's technology that that
increases our ability to extract them so
I don't think about it as running out
but you think about it as these these
significant shifts or volatility and
prices in in Supply chains and what does
that mean for local communities and the
in the levels at which we're willing to
go in order to extract these materials
and then what the complications are that
introduces that on one side we've talked
about the environmental impact but we
could also think about on the demand
side what are we not
doing because it's gotten too expensive
right and you know what what does that
mean for the fact that we wouldn't be
able to Electrify the vehicle Fleet at
the rate we would want to because the
prices of those materials are going up
and that's another thing that starts to
happen with the Advanced Energy
Technologies is as we get better at
doing them the manufacturing cost goes
down making the battery pack making the
solar cell but it starts to be very
dependent on then what the prices of
those materials are and so subject to
the kinds of supply chain disruptions
that mean when we have actual or
perceived risk of Supply availability
constraints rather than it running out
you talked about you used the the word
primary Metals at one point when you
were talking earlier and and that's a
that's a really important subject I
think because you know you mind for iron
you mine for nickel you would make a
nickel mine you'd make a copper mine but
you'd never make a strontium mine when
or itum mine a lot of those are
byproducts of of all that
mining as we as we use more and more of
these Advanced Technologies big magnets
strong magnets for example or even
Fusion systems that use some of these
some of these exotic materials or
materials that we don't commonly find
um do we hit a wall with those where
where the primary production no longer
keeps up with demand for these sort of
secondary metals or or co-produced
metals and does do we do we sort of stop
using them and and run into um
disasters in terms of the
other kinds of risks associated with
materials availability there's a
particular kind of risk or a particular
kind of dynamic associated with those
metals that we're not building the mine
for as you say and Cobalt which has been
talked about a lot in the press in terms
of the challenges in mining and the
geographic concentration is an example
that we don't build a mine for Cobalt we
build a mine for nickel or copper and
the Cobalt is obtained as a byproduct of
that as your saying and so what that
means is for things like Cobalt as
demand goes up it's not necessarily
having the same kind of price response
that we would have in nickel or or
copper for example so we're kind of
subject to what's happening with that
nickel mine so that introduces a
different kind of volatility in the in
the
supply sometimes the sources for these
materials are in wastes so vadium for
example is something where there's a lot
of opportunity for other way vadium
extra ction in in secondary streams that
we wouldn't normally what is vadium I've
never heard of it it's an element it's
an under the radar but it's used in
steel and a lot and very dominantly um
and it offers a lot of really important
properties in steel but it also could be
relevant to some kind of battery some
kinds of battery technologies flow
batteries vadium Lum flow batteries yeah
in it could be that's another way we
could do more uh electrification storage
on the grid for example I'm reminded of
a famous situation a couple years ago
where demand for steel increased
dramatically in China because of
subsidies for building which created
tremendous demand for vadium okay and it
wiped out all of the guys who were
trying to make vadium flow batteries and
so that was an interesting you know
crossover I see because it was like
pulled away other
use comp that's actually a really
important point to make back on our
nickel story because any we've been talk
talking about the sort of demand signals
of how do you create sustainable
supplies of nickel right because I said
earlier most of the nickel right now is
used in stainless steel we also have to
talk to the folks that are part of the
stainless steel supply chain if we're
just working with the battery
manufacturers and they're sending all
sorts of demand signals let's get
sustainable nickel but we don't talk to
the folks sending signals from the
stainless steel industry then the nickel
miners don't care because they're
answering to the stainless steel folks
now so that Dynamic of what is the
dominant use right now but then how will
that change and how fast will that
change is really important when we start
to try to think about how do we
incentivize what sorts of policies are
we going to write so let's talk about um
Solutions and you could use nickel or
anything else but maybe talk
about one element and you know how you
see kind of how you move the needle in a
way that you feel like would be a win
like how do you make it so there's fewer
greenhouse gases coming from the
extraction of that thing the processing
of that thing so we could think about
copper a little bit because copper is
interesting in that it's pretty
dependent to any kind of growth both in
terms of electrification but also just
in terms of electronic devices and our
increased demand for that and just the
need to conduct more electrons copper is
a good way to do that so it's in like
all our laptops and our and our car
dominant use is actually in buildings
and construction wiring in our buildings
and the infrastructure associated with
that so it's kind of everywhere right
right right so cities are increasing in
size which they are then you're building
buildings so copper is is Ubi so you
could think about the environmental
implications of copper if we're focused
on energy and greenhouse gas emissions
there's ways of thinking about Solutions
across the supply chain so we could
think about the production of heat to to
run the processes and can we Electrify
that but also can we change the the
chemistry of how we go from the mineral
to Copper we could look at different
kinds of of ways of uh doing that that
are more environmentally friendly so
sulfidation is an is an is a a process
being looked at here at MIT in terms of
better processing of of copper and and
to the products that we're interested in
but you could also think about reduction
of mining
overall by increasing the recycling of
copper and recycling can be challenging
to think about in all the stuff that
we've talked about before because as
we're increasing
demand it we are still growing in the
amount of material that we use and so
there isn't enough existing to be
pulling out for secondary for recycling
to meet that Demand right so recycling
offers an opportunity to displace mining
really only if we've saturated what's
being used we sometimes say in stock or
in the buildings that we're using but
some things like copper and steel as I
said because it's ubiquitous because
it's everywhere those elements those
materials offer an opportunity for more
circularity and we do that in the United
States I mean there's a lot of scrap
steel used here exactly scrap steel and
and scrap copper where in in the case of
copper at least there's still a lot of
hidden stocks that we aren't NE that we
aren't necessarily collecting or
recycling as much as we could like a
building gets torn down you mean that
kind of thing exactly construction
demolition waste where we're not
recovering all the copper that can be
used again in those applications how do
you incentivize people to do that rather
than say it's cheaper to like go to some
poor country and get new copper out of
the ground like labor isn't very
expensive it's it's
doable yeah yeah um so It's Tricky you
have to build up the infrastructure for
recycling and that is actually happening
right now in the in the copper
conversation in the US is there's
because of the growth in in demand and
the fact that there could be more of
this demand met by secondary we have to
in incent you know invest capital in
building secondary refining processes
for copper uh in the United States or
wherever or in
Europe in order to to make that happen
and then as you point out with your
question there's there's then incenting
the collection of that
material so that it can then be sent to
those to those refiners and so there's
this trade-off there between do we have
the enough capacity to process that the
secondary material and are the is the
value of copper is the price of copper
high enough that that we're interest
that there's support to set up the
collection infrastructure to do that and
most
often the will need some kind of subsidy
to incent that to to start off with and
even in countries like China there's
significant subsidies in in in making
secondary work to to kind of start it
off and often to to continue that until
we're able to have the processes
themselves be economic relative to the
primary processes how do we how do we do
in in recycling of metals I mean are a
lot of them ending up in in dumps we the
us we the US well we maybe other
countries too yes we are certainly not
doing as well as we can so the recycling
rates or is the for things like copper
is usually about 30% um of a of
consumption can is met with secondary
that could go up we've looked at that
copper in particular that could go up to
maybe about up to 60% um reasonably
economically but we need the local
capacity to to develop that
out um and so yeah generally recycling
is around 30 to 40% for most um Metals
in that in that range it's higher for
things like steel um and and you know
going down to something pretty kind of
fundamental that we all think about
something like an aluminum can even
there's just significant Headroom to
increase Recycling and there we have
pretty direct evidence that deposits on
a on an aluminum can in terms of you
know we usually
say increases the amount of collection
rate so in the US the highest is sort of
10 cents right we would think for
Redemption you have you know upwards of
of 40 50% recovery based on that but in
in Europe in some European countries
where it's where it's higher the the
bottle deposits are higher the recycling
rate is is also higher so there's some
pretty direct feedback loops there um
that that can you know we can use to
build uh Stronger policies for incenting
that as well it seems like though what
you're saying is um you know government
is extremely important if you're
thinking about um
recycling more and more of these
materials that we have floating around
versus digging them out of the ground a
new um and yes I immediately thought of
soda cans because you see people like
collecting them for the to get back that
money um and it makes complete sense
that if you have like the demolition of
a building and there's a bunch of copper
in there the more you offer to go in and
like grab that copper out the more
likely it is is like the higher that
price is the more somebody's like okay I
will do this because it's worth my time
yeah and so we you have this model where
you have to try to think about how do we
incent that and and some of the policy
schemes start to look like
responsibility going either to the
individual or to the producer so there's
a set of incentives in recycling called
extender producer responsibility where
we think about those that are
manufacturing to begin with though you
know the wire or the bottle or then you
know have a cost associated with then
managing that end of life and so then
it's where does that cost go who Bears
the the burden of that cost and being
thoughtful about architecting that
policy um is is part of the need
there Elsa olivetti is Professor of
Material Science and Engineering at MIT
she's also Mission director for mit's
climate project decarbonizing energy and
Industry Elsa olivetti thank you so much
for being here thank you for having me
thanks Elsa
what if it works is a production of the
MIT energy initiative if you like the
show please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen and remember to
subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu
podcasts and you can learn more about
the work of the energy initiative and
the energy transition at energy g.
mit.edu
[Music]
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob soner thanks for listening