Uh we'll talk about two stories today.
Uh one in context to cancer diagnostics
and thinking about how do we enhance and
improve our ability to detect residual
disease, improve therapy selection and
perhaps even enable early detection uh
to really supercharge and power the
bloodbased diagnostics that are now
emerging in the commercial sector. Uh
and the second story I'll talk about
biommanufacturing. And this has been in
the news again over the last few weeks.
And uh as Natalie mentioned, the
initiative for new manufacturing is
thinking a lot about different
strategies for how we enable uh
manufacturing across the United States.
And biology will be an important
component of this, something that's been
uh heavily uh talked about recently in
Washington as well as other parts of the
country as a tool that could help
empower the bio economy. And so talk a
little bit about a different a different
approach to thinking about production of
small uh materials uh in in
manufacturing uh that way. Uh I I'll
start up front by just saying uh a lot
of the work that you'll see here has
been funded either through uh research
awards at the Koch Institute, through
some of our programs like the Frontiers
program or through the Gates Foundation
and DARPA. Um so just get that out of
the way up front.
All right. So let's talk about cancer
diagnostics today. You know, diagnostics
using liquid biopsies is really poised
to transform how we think about care for
patients in cancer. Uh there's been
several ideas in thinking about how do
we detect analytes that we can acquire
from uh blood or from urine or from
other specimens uh that could stand in
as a proxy to the types of tissue
biopsies that we take uh in uh in kind
of standard surgical resections.
And as we think about blood-based
diagnostics, historically, you know,
people have focused on circulating tumor
cells. These are small cells that
dislodge from the tumor and move around,
often thought to be part of how
metastasis occurs. But really over the
last 10 years and you know we've done
work in that space thinking about
sequencing of those to identify cancer
genomes. But really over the last 10
years self-free DNA has become an
analyte that's critically important for
being able to identify single nucleotide
variations uh insert variations uh and
and and other defects that emerge from
the cancer as a way to detect it for
cancer screening potentially uh for
detecting recurrence. So after you've
had treatment, do I still have cancer is
an important question for patients to be
able to answer. And then ultimately also
how do we pick the right treatment? How
do we know which treatment you're likely
to respond to? Uh really amazing uh and
uh new kinds of inhibitors that have
emerged for kinases and other classes
including some we just heard about. How
do you know if you're right to receive
that treatment? Some of these uh can be
detected from genomic analyses. So it's
with this backdrop and promise that
there's now a you know multi-billion
dollar let's put on the order of $500
billion uh market for these types of
tests led by companies like Grail and
Exact uh and the Tariff.
When we think about what this looks like
from a patients vantage point there
might be uh materials that are in the
blood that could be used for this type
of monitoring that are present at some
threshold that's easy to detect. If I
have cancer and things are uh in
circulation, you know, that level is
pretty high. But when we start to and we
can see a lot of these on imaging scans,
right? So we do an MRI or a CAT scan,
you can often see these nodules. Maybe
you do surgical resection, chemotherapy,
adivant therapy, and then those go away
in the imaging scan. But we don't know,
this is sort of the inverse of the
iceberg problem or maybe it's the right
side of the iceberg problem. what the
state of the disease is in that window
where we can't detect it by imaging
scans. And the promise of liquid
biopsies has been to create that noise
floor that's below what you could detect
so that you could see through that
trough to determine if you need
additional treatment or to monitor the
state of disease.
The challenge in the field, however, has
been that the sensitivity of these
methods, while they're very good at
capturing information, has been quite
poor. And these are a number of clinical
studies that just kind of highlight this
in different settings uh in early
screening detection and recurrence uh
therapy selection across a couple of
different cancer types. These are not
very good sensitivities. In fact, these
are worse than throwing a dart
sometimes, right? Or 50/50 coin flip. Uh
this is really kind of poor sensitivity.
And the reason for this, right, is that
at some level the amount of analyte
that's present is quite low.
And so what a lot of emphasis has been
on over the last uh you know five years
or so has been in thinking about how do
we enhance our ability to improve
detection from that blood sample. So you
go to the doctor, you take a blood draw,
they isolate the plasma, it goes in a
kit and it gets shipped off somewhere.
And we detect these by next generation
sequencing which as a chemist these are
effectively just molecule counters that
allow you to detect those variations in
the genome that you ascribe back to uh
the traits that you're looking for
mutations that tell you which treatment
to select. And so this is all done uh
using next generation sequencing. So a
lot of effort has been spent in trying
to enhance our molecular biology
techniques and our sequencing techniques
to be able to improve the sensitivity in
that range.
In fact, one of my former students leads
the Gersonner Center for blood uh for
for cancer diagnostics at the Broad
Institute. uh and he and his team have
actually advanced several of these ideas
uh for enhancing the ability to where
they can now measure at the noise floor
of sematic variations within the natural
human genome. So this is as low
biologically as you can go
that the technical noise now is
basically zero.
But the problem is is that we are not
sampling very much of the total amount
of material that's available. So if I
think about what's upstream of that,
there's an additional filtration that's
occurring. The tumor cells release
cell-free DNA. Some of that has to
traffic into the blood. In the blood, it
may be degraded by a variety of
different mechanisms. Nucleuses that
chew up that cellulfree DNA. Uptake by
macrofasages or cuffer cells in the in
the liver. Uh excretion through the
kidney. All of these are mechanisms for
clearance such that by the time I
actually take that blood draw, I'm
measuring just a fraction of what I
could have seen originally.
And so the challenge is for enhancing
the sensitivity of these, it's not on
the back side. We've effectively solved
that problem where as good as we can do
biologically and molecular biology of
reading out that information. But this
front-end problem of how could we
collect more becomes a real challenge.
You say, well, okay, great. I can go in
and do a surgical resection and get the
tumor directly. Yes, in a in a primary
care setting that in in a first in a
first instance that would be usually
what's done. Uh some kind of surgical
resection, but in the context of
metastasis or minimal residual disease
settings, you're not going to perform
surgeries to find out that information.
We could hook somebody up to a diialysis
machine, but if you're already sick in
cancer, it's unlikely that you're going
to want to sit there for several hours
to collect all of that material through
there. So, we need a different way to
think about this problem.
Well, we teach uh chemical engineering
to undergraduates and one of the basic
principles that we teach about is mass
balance equations.
The body is a steady state reactor
effectively, right? We eat materials and
well, we excrete materials. Tumors are
dying and we could take out a blood draw
as an output. The materials are being
degraded at the other side. So from a
steady state balance right we can write
a kinetics of some amount of material is
being generated by the tumor some amount
is being degraded by the liver and by
nucleus activity and so at any given
time in the blood I have a steadystate
concentration of that cell-free DNA of
which a small fraction of that is
related to the tumor right a lot of
that's from normal cells and so when we
take a blood draw and you kind of see
here in the cartoon we're
substoastically sampling the molecules
that are in the bloodstream at any given
time.
So that means that in that tube of
blood, there's a nonzero chance that I
actually never pulled a molecule from
the tumor. So I can't measure what I
didn't collect.
But the good news is in chemical
engineering, we also teach how you think
about steady state reactors and how you
balance this. And the best way to do
that is to alter the kinetics of in this
case generation or degradation of the
material. If I'm a if I'm in an early
detection setting or minimal residual
disease, I don't really know how to
generate more tumor DNA. So I have to
focus on the other side of the problem
of blocking degradation. And so this is
really the concept that we thought about
in the lab. uh could we provide an agent
that would temporarily
inhibit the degradation of the cell-free
DNA long enough that we could enhance
that concentration in the blood such
that when we take the blood draw the
tumor DNA is present so this was the
thought concept right could could we do
this could we add an agent that somehow
would enhance the I'll call it contrast
of tumor DNA that's present in in the
blood sample that we
So this was a a joint effort uh with one
of my colleagues in the uh Koch
Institute Sangetta Betia and her team uh
my former student Victor Adelinson and
then uh three uh students one from or or
scientists from each lab uh Carmen
Martin uh Shervin Treezy uh and and
Jeang.
We did this experiment. This is one of
those experiments. This is this is that
fun moment as a PI when you you know you
draw it up on paper and we go yeah look
let's let's let's let's block
degradation. We went and found an
antibbody that had anti- doublestranded
DNA uh activity. We said okay if we
administer it to a mouse could we boost
the amount of cell-free DNA? And you're
sort of expecting when you do this
experiment like and I don't know Jessica
you've done this you're kind of like
hoping that maybe there's a little
difference and you like yeah we should
try it again we should totally do it.
when they came back with this result it
was like okay like there's something
fundamentally going on here that we
should take a look at and this is you
know two orders of magnitude nearly in
additional self-free DNA uh that we were
able to recover in the self-free DNA of
these these animals uh and so if then
you look at the question of the the
tumor derived DNA we see a similar boost
in this case it's 19fold uh as a
function concentration you can see there
that we get back of additional DNA so
just By adding an antibbody, injecting
it into the animal uh and then an hour
later withdrawing the blood sample, we
get a 19fold increase in this
sensitivity or in this recovery that
translates into sensitivity here where
you can see now looking at tumor derived
marks on the DNA, we're able to enhance
that sensitivity by uh you know more
than fivefold.
So we've been able to take something
that was invisible and make it visible.
If I think about this in a clinical
setting, we already have a paradigm for
how to think about this translationally.
Today, if you go in for an MRI uh scan,
a lot of times about an hour before you
get the imaging done, you'll get a
contrast ad contrast agent administered
by IV. And then you go and you do the uh
the scan. And in this case, right, you
can see that uh the the the mass is is
highlighted there with the contrast
agent. These blood-based agents that
I've just described offer a similar kind
of paradigm. Imagine now, right, you
have minimal residual disease, you've
had your cancer treatment, you're trying
to determine am I cancer-free? This is
really important for patients to know.
and you go an hour before you take your
blood test and you get an agent
administered and then you come back an
hour later and give your blood draw to
see if it's there or not. So this is the
concept and we spun out a company called
Amplifier uh that uh has uh gotten off
to a fast start. They are over here in
Kendall Square at the Bear Collabs. Uh
you see the team here. Uh Annie uh
Murphy, former foundation medicine uh
and Eric Wong uh who's worked with
several blood biopsy companies are uh
helping to to move this along. We are
now advancing the lead agents and you
know excitingly some recent data. I
asked them what what I could share and
they said you know this this is really
nice because we often talk about data
reproducibility and and challenges of
these things. uh you know sometimes
these effects you might imagine uh might
not be as real as you expect. Here
they've perfectly replicated the models
that we had uh published in the science
paper previously. Uh they're in the
process of advancing candidates for
first in human trials uh sometime in the
next year year and a half. Uh so what's
really cool about this is that the uh
effect size is so large that that first
clinical trial is going to give us some
insights into how this actually works in
humans. So as we think about efficacy
that that uh statistical difference is
so large that if that holds in humans uh
should translate nicely and so we're
looking at how we then use this uh in
partnership with other diagnostic
companies as a front end. We've done and
demonstrated this for cell-free DNA but
the principle applies to many other
analytes as well and could be used for
proteinbased diagnostics and
neurogenerative disease or in other
kinds of autoimmunity infectious disease
potentially. Uh so really excited about
where this this could head.
I'll transition here
uh to talk about a a different a
different uh technology and and and
principle. And this really has to do
with how do we think about bringing
medicines to patients. So what I've
talked about in the first story is
really about how we think about building
agents that can have an influence in in
the in in improving cancer diagnostics.
But it doesn't matter how good that
material is or how good any other cancer
treatment might be if we can't actually
make it and get it to the patient where
they need it. Um this is increasingly
important in this current moment where
geopolitical concerns and other kind
external factors are really driving a
strong uh sense of nationalization
and a a sort of walling off of economies
in various regions. And so the ability
to access things globally, we see this
in the current uh climate with tariffs
are blocking certain free trade. It may
become increasingly important to figure
out ways in which we can make materials
in distributed fashion. And so how would
you make medicines as complex as a
monoconal antibbody in a setting, you
know, like the ones that are shown here,
uh either in humanitarian aspects or in
thinking about uh rapid response in
emergent situations. uh these are these
are conditions that that uh we don't
have a current solution for how to make
things on on demand.
Um a little over 10 years ago, DARPA,
the advanced project research agency
here in the US, uh uh we had a chance to
work on a program with them where they
they they asked us, you know, could you
make a technology that would help us
manufacture biioharmaceuticals
like the antibbody agent that I just
showed you or the ones we heard about in
the last talk on demand in 24 hours in a
backpack in the field?
like all right gauntlet thrown this is a
big challenge because this is the
problem today's biio manufacturing looks
like this
it's a large plant there's lots of
people inside there's lots of manual
things you can see all the valves the
stainless steel the facility that's
shown there probably costs you know
roughly 200 million to2 billion dollars
to build and operate it's highly complex
people have to know exactly what they're
doing there's a lot of protocols to
follow. It's expensive. The capital is
expensive. The operating costs are
expensive. The sustainability cost is
expensive. These antibbody processes are
some of the like least sustainable
manufacturing processes on the planet um
by several metrics uh including water
use. So, how in the world could you
possibly take something like this and
start to make a backpack that makes
medicine somewhere? That was the
challenge that we were faced with. Um
and what that kind of looks like from a
business perspective or or from a a
value chain perspective is really this.
Today when we manufacture we manufacture
something like the drug substance the
active ingredient uh in a facility
somewhere might be centralized uh which
creates a risk. You know if something
happens at that plant you know we we
might be short in supply. This happens
every year for vaccines. Every year
vaccine targets are not met because
there's a shortage in certain childhood
vaccines that are that are required
because they're made in centralized
facilities.
We have to package that up and ship it
around the world. You know, we're
shipping a lot of water around the world
all the time. This is in a lot of
industries, but especially true in this
industry. We freeze it down and we ship
it around. So, not only are we shipping
water, but we're shipping it really
cold.
I spent my sbatical in 2015 at Biogen
and the executive vice president walk by
my desk every day and be like, "Chris,
you're a smart MIT professor. How do I
stop shipping water around the world?" I
don't know. I'm not sure we have the
answer, but we should keep thinking
about this question. What we need to do
is shorten that distance between
manufacturing and patients. And so
that's really at the heart of the
question that we were asked. If you
think about this, this kind of offers an
opportunity to think about microactories
for biology or for biio manufacturing
here where we're shortening that
distance for some medicines like cell
therapies. We know that this is really
important because the cells come out of
the patient, they have to be transformed
and put back in the patient. But there's
really no fundamental reason why we
can't do this for other types of
medicines as well. And what does this
open up? Not only does it shorten that
value chain for the producer, but it
also offers the opportunity to think
about more precision medicines, more
medicines that are tailored for rare
diseases. As we're in this current era
where AI is generating leads for new
proteins all the time, and we're
discovering the basis of disease through
genomic studies at a rapid pace. Almost
every disease is becoming a rare
disease. And as we do so, we need to
think a little differently about how we
supply. It might not be one large
factory that makes everything for the
world's supply, but actually we have a
high volume high mix low volume demand
in manufacturing. So while this program
was really focused on um the war fighter
and trying to understand how do we
provide capabilities for for the US
military, uh there's really interesting
uh implications today for thinking about
this in the context of uh of precision
medicine and uh distributed production.
So, we had an opportunity to work on
this. It took us about five years. Um,
we had to unlearn everything that we
knew, right? If you're building
something to go in a backpack, you can't
take everything with you. So, the idea
of doing a fed batch reaction that takes
several days and then doing your
downstream chromatography one step at a
time. You just can't do that. You have
to make everything smaller and tighter
and faster. Uh so you can see here the I
I affectionately call it the chewing gum
and duct tape prototype that we built uh
in the lab. You can see some standard
parts kind of off the shelf. Most of
those we actually ripped out the guts,
rebuilt them, put in new software. Very
MIT. In fact, my favorite is the uh TFF
there. The little screen on there, the
software, the company wouldn't let us
actually get into it. So we actually
built a little macro that clicked a
button all the time for us. I think it
still does that actually, but um you
know, rewired this entire thing. But you
can see, you know, really small modular
footprint. didn't quite fit in a
backpack but fits on a desk here. Um so
we built several of these and several
innovations in the manufacturing
processes themselves that kind of went
into this. Uh we developed the first in
vessel perfusion strategy for microbial
systems uh to be able to allow for a
much smaller footprint operating in
continuous. We actually showed that you
could use freeze-dried yeast as an
inoculum. So instead of having to do N
minus one reactor tanks, instead of
having to uh keep that that cell cold in
the cold chain, we could just use
freeze-dried yeast much like baker's
yeast that you use to cook with, you
could inject those in directly. The
cells would start producing and then on
the downstream side today, most uh
processes on the downstream side, you
you develop one step of purification.
You get to a certain point, then you
develop the next one and then you
develop the next one. uh with Steve
Kramer at Wensler Poly Techchnical
Institute, we actually developed some
new strategies to look at that as a
single unit operation so that we can
operate in a flowthrough mode that
allows for all of the clearance to occur
through the set of uh resins that are uh
selected there and then finally a
formulation step to be able to put it in
something to be injection ready. And so
with this system once you start it's
fully automated, hands-free and you can
walk away and it produces cyclical
batches of material coming out on the
back end uh over several days. is I
think the longest we ran it in the lab
was about uh 2 weeks, 3 weeks. Uh the
students at some point said, "Can we
just stop feeding it media? It seems
like it's just going to keep going."
Um we made several different products
with it. We made human growth hormone uh
interferon uh alpha 2b and then this is
GCSF. GCSF is used for cancer treatments
for patients that have low white blood
cell counts. Uh it's also used uh in
radiation treatment. So for medical
countermeasure, it's also very useful
and is in the US uh stockpile for
national security. We showed here that
the materials that we made in that
prototype that I showed you in a lab,
right? Not GMP, not GMP, but those
materials that we made were of the same
quality and purity as what Amgen makes
as their product, Nupagen. In fact, in
uh rat studies down in the bottom there,
uh we showed that uh over repeat dose
toxicology studies that it was
equivalent to their material and had the
same PK and PD properties. So suggesting
that you know in fairly austere
conditions you can make uh very high
quality materials.
Uh so DARPA came to us and they said
well this is really fantastic. We love
this. Can you make us a GMP version of
that system? And we said, "Yeah, that's
where the boundary at MIT kind of lies."
You know, GMP takes a lot of
documentation, as you know, quality
management. Uh, so we spun out a company
uh that that started to think about this
as well. I guess one other point here to
make uh is that the platform itself is
platformed. So that same system with
some different conditions of buffers and
such can make a range of different
molecules proteins all of which that
today would require separate facilities.
So one facility many products which is
really important for the use application
here and some of the papers there
highlight the nuances of some of the
learnings in the the the downstream
chromatography in fact to the point
where now we can actually use sequence
information and things like the single
domain antibbody to predict the process
condition. So very early machine
learning kind of ideas of how could we
use sequence information to actually
predict process.
Uh so we did spin out a company called
Sunflower and Sunflower has been
advancing this concept at a much uh
slightly larger scale. This is a system
they call the Dalia unit. Uh the Dalia
is a full endto-end drug substance
production system. You can see sort of
the footprint there. Uh you can't see
the woman standing in the back there in
the in the with the slide here, but uh
it would sit like roughly these two
tables here on the floor. Uh so very
small footprint um fully automated. So
once you set it up, you can walk away
from it. And then because it's
continuous uh and operating under these
principles, it's very uh efficient and
sustainable in its operations. Uh this
is a picture of what it actually kind of
looks like. Uh so it's uh you can see
they've replicated all of these same
protocols and and processes that we ran
here. They've also developed a monoconal
antibbody process for those that are
kind of afficionados. You know monoconal
antibodies today are a platform process
in bioprocessing.
They use protein a columns as a common
step to remove the impurities and and to
concentrate it. Uh they've actually
shown that they can get rid of that
expensive step and use uh just the same
steps that we've involved in the other
ones. So you can make a very wide range
in the apothecary of different types of
products with similar outputs and
materials. Uh they had a chance to run
this actually during uh during the
pandemic. They they used it to produce
that same GCSF that we manufactured at
MIT as well as a COVID uh vaccine
subunit in a warehouse. You can see it
there in the background uh in
California. All of it passed all of the
USP bioden tests, all of the the quality
attributes that would be sufficient and
necessary to use for clinical purpose.
They didn't use it for that. They didn't
do it under GMP, but the quality metrics
were sufficient. So, because it was
functionally closed and the way it's
automated, you can do it in very very
austere environments. I don't think the
regulators are fully ready for this yet,
but uh the ability to manufacture high
quality drug substance anywhere uh is is
within reach. um that chewing gum and
duct tape prototype. I thought I'd throw
this one in there, too. This is their
first commercial product. This is the
Daisy Pedal. It's just the Profusion
bioreactor, but you can see the design
is now very simple. In fact, it's so
easy that like anybody can do it. We've
had executives that have never been in a
lab come in and start these systems. If
you've ever used a bioreactor, that's a
big accomplishment. Um, also thinking a
lot about user interface. You can see
the the the the software that they've
built uh is very simple and intuitive to
read out. it's not complex. So they're
uh their their thought here is that this
is something that anybody should be able
to access uh these types of production
systems.
When you think about the capacity, the
Dalia unit that I showed you when we
scale it up to this this table is about
the size or capacity of a pilot plant.
Um, but what that really means is that
one of those units could make enough
vaccine doses for all the state of
California for SARS KV2 for example
or a a cancer drug like Tristamab for
countries like uh Colombia and if you
scale it up to a few units you could
offer a whole country uh capabilities
and coverage in that. So this idea that
we could now distribute production to
parts of the world that don't have it
today, if we overlap a map of where the
cancer or where the co vaccines were
deployed and where they were
manufactured, they're almost identical.
And so what it really says is proximity
to manufacturing is really important. In
fact, we see in countries that do not
have drug substance manufacturing that
the cost of drugs in those countries is
higher. So as we think about
democratization of of medicines uh the
ability to distribute manufacturing is
going to be increasingly important and
what you lose in scale you make up for
in automation and this I think is a
really key learning that the cost
modeling to build out you know scale out
versus scale up and scale up that's the
the diagonal line as I get larger in
volume per year I reduce the cost per
gram but actually this uh fixed unit
scaling allows for very efficient
scaling of cost uh all the way up until
you get to those very high volumes. So
in intermediate ranges again appropriate
for phase uh for early phase development
or for uh rare diseases and and and
certain indications. Uh this is a really
uh costefficient way to think about uh
production.
I'll finish out with just a couple of
thoughts. So we've built these uh
companies based on some of the research
we've we had developed here at MIT and
spun them out. It's been a super fun
process to get uh students involved in
those uh those those projects as they
leave or or research scientists have
been part of the lab uh kind of uh as
part of that founding team in the
technology transfer. Carmen Martin who I
mentioned earlier went to Amplifier. Uh
several folks from my lab went to to
Sunflower. And what we've been doing
since then is really thinking about
particularly on this context of
production, how do we go faster, better,
and how do we do more? So if we have a
system that could manufacture anything
if the cells produce it, we need to work
on what the cells can produce. And so to
that end, we formed the alternative host
consortia with uh several bioarm
companies uh and continue to operate it
with with the the groups that are here
um to really think about how do we
engineer the host itself uh and to be
more productive and to be faster? How do
we make a wider range of quality
attributes on the products? How do we
think about things like like oillation?
And then one direction that we've been
thinking a lot about uh in this
consortia as well has been what's the
role of computation in it uh today and
this I I took from the National Security
Commission's report on emerging
biotechnology. Uh there's this idea that
we can generate knowledge through AI and
computing and biological information.
We're seeing the beginnings of this
right with AI generated proteins and
alpha fold and some of the things that
are happening there. What we're still
not very good at is scaling up all of
that knowledge from the bench into
production. Uh but as we think about the
ability to read out biology and to build
biology, can we use computation to help
inform strategies for doing these
things? And if we're thinking about
distributed models, the ability to go
from plate to reactor is a really
critical step because we may not need to
go to 100,000 liters for some of these
things. We can simply scale out. And so
could we go from sequence to production
in a very very short time frame. Uh one
of the things that the consorcia has
started to think about is how do we
build the tools to do this? I mentioned
uh sequence to process predictions. This
is something that we had done a few
years ago in the context of nanobodies.
Uh more recently we've developed
autoenccoder models to be able to do
codon optimization in our organism of
choice here that uh consistently
outperform the the the commercial
benchmarks. Uh it's interesting the
models are learning features of the
biology that you would sort of I don't
know it took biologists a long time to
learn things like cy regulatory elements
and aspects of how it organizes genes in
the genome in the codons that it's using
it's learning that language through the
training and is replicating that in the
types of proteins that it optimizes. Uh
so I think we think a lot of times that
these are just black boxes but actually
when you kind of peek inside to see what
it's understanding it's quite
interesting. Um and then something else
that we're doing that's I think really
important for bop process is thinking
about active learning or reinforcement
learning strategies to optimize process
development. Um today most people in
boprocessing use statistical design of
experiments. These sort of assume
quadratic or linear relationships and
you typically test certain endpoints and
kind of make these response surfaces.
But we know biology is not really linear
and so how do we kind of map that out in
a more efficient way? uh these active
learning strategies using things like
Gaussian process models and basing
optimizers is a really efficient way to
do this. We're using this uh in the lab
for biorocessing. We've actually also
started to use this as a strategy to
think about uh optimizing doses of
imunotherapies. So I think it's a a
general strategy that is we think about
the kind of data we need to use for the
right AI tools. This isn't simply
scraping the literature for everything
in biology. We don't have all that
fundamental knowledge. So how do we
generate it? the most efficient way to
generate is through uh using it as a
tool to help guide the experiments.
I'll stop here and I'll just kind of
make this last point uh thinking about
these things is you know we often talk
about the
eras of industrial revolutions and you
know Steve Jobs said uh that he thought
that the most important technology of
the 21st century would be biotechnology.
Presently, if you've read the news, we
all think it's AI,
but actually AI is the opportunity to
unlock the biology. There's this idea of
abundance economics that's sometimes
thrown around politically, but the
original concept of abundance economics
is that you take things that are very
inexpensive and you spend those
resources to do things that are
expensive or hard. And so if we think
about like the industrial revolution,
the ability to make things by physical
means that led to the ability to make
things like uh chips, semiconductors,
the lasers, a little bit of physics
thrown in there too, but the ability to
make things led to be able to make
hardware
chips, computers. With computers, we can
now do computation. And we're doing AI,
we're doing ML. Like these are great,
but actually AI and ML are getting
cheaper and cheaper. Now we can spend
that resource to ask us how to unlock
biology and this is I think really where
the opportunity lies and all the things
that we've talked about here and kind of
what the next stage looks like in the
initiative for new manufacturing. We're
thinking a lot about this interface how
do we relate these two things AI and
automation with outcomes particularly in
biio manufacturing uh and other sectors.
Uh so I'll stop here happy to take any
questions if there are any. Uh but
thanks for your time and attention and
thanks for your patience with the AV
setup.
We'll start questioning from here.
>> Hi. Um, I was just wondering how in like
the backpack you guys are dealing with
wholesale protein detection. Is that I
know you touched on like regulatory and
like process control, but
>> yeah. Yeah, awesome question. Um, so, so
two things. Um, we didn't build into the
system, uh, the quality release
analytics. There's ways to sort of
automate that and we've kind of mapped
out that actually for for drug substance
release you could probably get away with
five
I'll call it pieces of kit to be able to
measure attributes that are relevant to
to to the molecule and those can all be
automated. So we didn't do that as part
of the the work here but you know I
think there's solutions for thinking
about that. That's the technical answer.
The other answer the more innovative
answer is to think about how do you not
have host cell proteins in the first
place. So one of the advantages of the
system that we chose here, so we we
chose not to use mamalian cells. We use
microbial cells. We use yeast in
particular. And mamalian cells as you
may know, right, are very hard to kind
of keep alive. They also make a lot of
host cell proteins. So for your protein,
there's 2,000 other HCPs in there. And
so if you ever look at a CHO process,
the impur, like we talk about the titers
of the product, but actually the
impurity profile is quite large as well.
For yeast, they're like 70 to 80% clean
coming out of the bioreactor. And so
you're really just doing polishing. On
top of that, we've out now mapped out
through the whole genome non-essential
genes. And so you can go in and start
knocking out serrone genes that are bad
actors. And so you can kind of clean it
up to a point where like maybe there
aren't so many or maybe we just have one
or two steps to be able to clear it.
Ultimately, you know, when you think
about distributed manufacturing, the
other opportunity is to collect data to
show over time the relationship between
process conditions and quality
attributes. And so as we think about
things like real-time release with the
right data sets at scale, you can start
to really think about how you truly
enable that in ways that we can't today.
So thanks for the question.
>> Any other questions for Chris?
>> Very interesting cases here. Uh for our
question about uh the the yeast you use
uh based on the case study, many of them
are are ye. So I uh want to understand
if you want to focus on that or did you
want to expand your application to
mleium sales like cho or hexonfree?
>> Yeah. So we're really interested in uh
thinking about how do we reduce the cost
of manufacturing and the biggest lever
and part of the learning that I actually
was able to to to to take away from my
time at Biogen where they asked me this
question. They said we want to go 10x
higher in yield and 10x lower in cost.
The best lever for this is the biology.
And if you look today, there's no
proteins uh you know at the global scale
that are produced in mamalian cells
after you get past sort of insulin,
right? So insulin is probably the
biggest protein that we make at super
large scale that's not in a mamalian
cell. Everything else like monoconal
antibodies is made in a mamleian cell.
So we're really focused on how do we use
alternative hosts and we're not wedded
to yeast per se. uh fungi, bacteria may
also provide certain advantages for
certain kinds of proteins, but we need
to learn how to intensify processes
through the biology that mamalian cells
can't offer.
>> Yeah, that makes sense. And I can see
there's uh quite quite some different
strategy we can use to intensify that
even with the mamium process.
>> The other secret of so we talked about
the host cell protein, but the other
secret of microbial systems is they go
faster. So we actually had a student
that did a a internship at Amgen and
showed that on a cost basis you could
meet CHO cost targets in a fed batch
process using yeast at half the tighters
because you're going through the
facility that much faster. So we need to
remember time as an important integral
in our estimates of productivity not
just tighter.
I think we have time for one more
question.
Otherwise, thank you Chris for
>> Thank you.