I think we'll go ahead and
get started since we're
starting a little bit late.
I'm Emery Brown, I'm from BCS,
Brain and Cognitive Sciences
Picower Institute.
I'm going to be the moderator
for this session on brains.
So why think about the brain?
It's this fantastic organ.
It only weighs 3 pounds,
but it consumes almost 20%
of the oxygen in
the cardiac output.
And studying the brain is a
challenge because almost--
but what's cool about it
is that everything we learn
can help us with new diseases
relevant to the brain.
And the critical factors,
as was mentioned earlier
in today's first session, is
that, just like the other areas
of investigation
that were discussed,
brain research and brain related
improvements in health care,
there are three things
that converge here
at MIT, advances in science,
engineering innovations,
translational applications.
And you'll hear that
today from our speakers.
So these are our speakers.
We're very happy to have
Ed Boyden from the Picower
Institute, Mark Baier, also
from the Picower Institute, Josh
McDermott from the
McGovern Institute,
and also Evelina Fedorenko
from the McGovern Institute.
And we just made a
little chart to show you
that indeed, these
three areas will
be touched throughout with the
talks that you're going to hear.
So with that, I'll turn
it over to my colleagues.
Ed.
[APPLAUSE]
All right, yeah,
thank you so much.
This is really a
fun day and it's
great to see so many
convergent fields
in this amazing, important area.
I direct a group that
tries to confront
through technology the spatial
and temporal complexity
of the brain.
And this is a great
arena for innovation.
I mean, the brain is
a gigantic object.
And brain cells are
gigantic objects.
But the wiring of the
brain is nanoscale, right?
The wiring is extremely tiny.
And the connections
between brain cells
are also very, very small.
Also, we have molecules, right?
The human genome has, what?
30,000 or so genes encoding
for countless biomolecules.
And we need to know what they
do and how they work together
and how they go wrong
in disease states.
But it's even more
complicated because there's
a time dimension, too.
If you think about Alzheimer's
disease or learning or aging
or almost any process that's
important to us as people,
there's an extended component of
time related to these functions.
Yet, the elementary
neural codes of the brain
are very, very brief,
millisecond timescale electrical
pulses.
So we build tools to try
to help neuroscientists
conquer these differences
in space and time.
Now, why is it important?
Well, lots of
technologies exist.
On the left, MRI scans,
on the right, microscopes.
But it's very hard to
image a large object
like a brain down to those
nanoscale dimensions.
So in our group, we practice a
lot of creativity skills, which
we think can be
learned and practiced,
and one idea is to do
the opposite of what
people are doing.
And for literally
300 years, the way
that biologists
magnify images of cells
is with some kind
of lensing effect.
We started wondering,
what if you
could magnify cells directly?
And so the basic idea, we
call expansion microscopy,
we chemically install a
dense, spiderweb like mesh
of, basically, baby diaper
polymer inside the brain.
Not a living brain,
but a preserved one.
And if you do it just right,
you can weave that chemical mesh
inside cells and outside
cells, around biomolecules,
in between biomolecules,
and you can
magnify the brain physically.
So in panel B here is a
piece of the mouse brain
several millimeters on the side.
Panel C, the same piece of
brain tissue about a day, day
and a half later, but we've
blown it up by 100 times
in volume.
And the polymer starts
out super dense,
like in the upper
left in that cartoon,
and ends up like
in the lower left.
Here's a little movie of a
piece of brain being expanded.
So we formed the baby
diaper polymer earlier,
and it's half an hour sped
up to about half a minute.
But we add water right there.
And I hope you can see that
this piece of brain tissue,
which is permeated by
the baby diaper polymer,
is physically growing right
before your very eyes.
That's great.
So now, we can use
imaging tools and see
tiny things that
are too small to be
seen by regular technology.
And that's important because,
again, molecules are tiny
and the wiring of the
brain is also really tiny.
And yet, you want to understand
it across an extended 3D spatial
extent.
So here's an actual
piece of brain tissue.
This is from the
mouse hippocampus,
which is involved
with many functions,
including related to memory, but
lots of other things as well.
And the brain cells are
expressing fluorescent proteins.
So these are proteins borrowed
from jellyfish, coral,
and other creatures.
And it gives you a color
code or barcode, if you will,
so you can tell the cells apart.
We deliver the genes for
these proteins using viruses.
We then preserve the brain
and expand it using the method
that I told you about.
And now, we can see the final
wiring much better than before.
So we're going to fly through
this piece of brain right now.
And I hope you can see that
these individual processes,
which have distinct colors,
are much, much easier
to see than one of my guests.
And then, of course,
we can Zoom in and out.
It's intrinsically
a multi-scale way
of visualizing the
brain circuitry.
So we're excited about
this idea and how we can
use it to map entire brains.
But of course, this doesn't
work on a living thing.
And so we have to
really switch gears here
to tackle the second
question, which is time.
How do we control these fast
electrical pulses of the brain?
If we could control
them, then you
could drive certain brain cells
and figure out what they do.
Do they trigger a
behavior or a pathology
or perhaps the remedy
of a pathology?
And so the idea that
we brought forth
is this concept that we
now call optogenetics,
because opto is about
light, and genetics,
because we use genes to
mediate light sensitivity.
The basic concept is
basically like this.
Suppose you had
solar panels that
convert light to electricity.
If you could somehow
install them on brain cells,
shine light on the solar
panels, convert to electricity,
you could control the brain.
And then, you could bring
light into the brain.
Electrodes are brought into
the brain all the time.
Because it doesn't feel pain
we can bring optical fibers
in as well.
So how do we do it?
Well, we have to make
the neurons sense
light, which means we have
to find those solar panels.
And it turns out, all
over the tree of life,
you can find molecules
that do that, right?
So here we are looking at a
single celled green algae.
And it has an eyespot in the
back there, which helps it
sense light to control
those flagella,
those tails that help it swim.
We just zoomed in
to the eyespot,
and it's chock full of these
proteins that convert light
into electrical
signals, ion fluxes.
Kind of like those solar panels
that we were just talking about.
So what we can do is take
advantage of the fact
that this is a protein.
It's genetically encoded.
It has the right temporal
and other properties.
It's a fast response to light
because you just open up a pore
and instantly get
ion flux across.
And so the idea that
we brought forth
was, let's borrow this
gene and see if we
could put it into the brain.
And so this is where we had
to count on serendipity.
We're very excited now, by
the way, to try to use AI
and other methods to do on
purpose what we did accidentally
here.
Can we go out and look for
treasure in the natural world
and not just wait around
for it to show up?
Anyway, we can
take the gene that
encodes for this light
activated protein,
we can install it using
a gene delivery method,
like a gene therapy vector
into the brain cell.
The brain cell will manufacture
the light activated protein.
And then, again,
serendipity kicked in again.
It was safe.
It worked.
It didn't have to work.
The algae could have been a
happy home for the protein
and the neuron could have
died or malfunctioned.
Anyway, it was really
surprising in a pleasant way
that when we shine light
from a laser or an LED
on these brain cells, they
fired electrical pulses,
not unlike the ones
happening in your own heads
right now as I say these words.
So there's lots of
things you can do.
You can take different
parts of the brain,
put these light activated
molecules in them,
try to see what happens.
So I'll just pick one example
because it has a nice movie.
But dopamine is a very important
neuromodulator in the brain.
In the popular press, it's
often called the pleasure center
of the brain.
Could you find out
whether reinforcing
the activity of these neurons
also reinforces behavior?
And so it's a very
simple experiment here.
Mice go and poke their
nose in a little portal.
And if they go to
the right one, they
get a pulse of light that aims
at these dopamine neurons, which
are expressing the
light activated protein.
If they go to the left
portal, nothing happens.
And so you can see the
result. Lifts its nose,
gets the pulse of light,
does it again, does it again.
And so this mouse is,
basically, working for light.
So this is very widespread.
We share all of our
tools freely, by the way.
So expansion microscopy
that I talked about before
is in use by thousands
of research groups,
almost 900 experimental
results coming out already.
Optogenetics is in use by
thousands of research groups
as well.
And interestingly,
these molecules
are starting to be
used in people as well.
So many people are blind.
They've lost their light
sensors in their eyes.
A team in Europe got
one of our molecules,
discovered here at MIT, and was
able to deliver the gene for it
into the eye of a person who
lost his normal light sensors.
And they converted the
spared cells of the eye
into, well, kind of a camera.
And so he was able to
recognize household objects.
He could see doors on a hallway.
Not perfect vision, couldn't
recognize faces very well,
struggled to read text,
so more work to be done.
But still, a very
interesting advance
in an otherwise extremely
difficult to confront condition.
Going forward, we want
to integrate these tools.
We've always shared
the tools freely,
but we want to
start combining them
towards this goal
of making computer
simulations of the brain.
If we could simulate
the brain, of course,
that'd be very interesting from
an AI perspective, potentially.
But also, we could maybe
look under the hood
and poke around in silico--
in software and
try to figure out
where in a network to intervene
to help with the disease state.
And of course, if we could
simulate brain computations
of different kinds,
it could become a tool
that we could use to probe
different scientific questions.
So in the coming years, our hope
is to start with small brains,
like fish and worms,
and start going
to larger and larger brains.
And this is sort of
a complicated slide,
but it outlines one
of our ways of trying
to put together all the
different approaches that we
take.
So the upper left, we
want to look at the brain
while it's in action,
the blue part.
In the lower left
with yellow, we're
going to use the
expansion method
to make maps of the brain.
And then, the three
blocks to the right
are ways of making different
models, machine learning
models, biophysical
models, and so forth.
So to conclude, we're very
excited about these tools
we're building to see, map,
control, and understand
the brain.
We share them all very freely.
But in the time to
come, we're very
excited to try to integrate them
into a workflow that hopefully
can help us build computational
models as well that
can be of great use for others.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Just let me grab my jacket here.
All right, sounded like an
unruly classroom earlier,
but I'm glad
everybody's calmed down.
A sad fact of life is that
diseases, deprivation,
and injuries can
impair brain function,
and it's extremely difficult
to restore brain function,
particularly in adulthood.
And a very classic
example of this
is a condition called
amblyopia, which
is a condition that is a
visual impairment that develops
in children that don't have high
quality vision during infancy.
And that's what's shown
here on the left side.
This is a child that has
a cataract in one eye.
The cataract is easily
detected and can
be surgically
removed and replaced
with an artificial lens.
But as a consequence of that
altered visual experience
during infancy, there's a
permanent visual disability.
So there's a very severe visual
disability in the amblyopic eye,
the eye that had been deprived,
and a loss of stereoscopic depth
perception that has a major
impact on the child's life.
Now, there is a treatment
for this type of disease,
it's called patch therapy.
It was introduced well
over 100 years ago
and is still the
medical standard
of care, which is something of
an embarrassment, I would say.
But patch therapy can work.
So the patching occurs
in the other eye,
which we call the fellow
eye, and it forces vision
through the eye that
had been deprived.
The limitation of patch
therapy is that it only
works very early in life.
In this case, on
the left in humans,
if the patching is not
done before the age
of four months of age, then
there is no recovery of vision.
So if the cataract was not
detected early enough in life
or-- and corrected, this is
really a very poor prognosis
for that child.
We've been modeling this for
over 50 years in animal studies,
and that's what's shown on the
right is just a similar story.
This is a cat model of
deprivation amblyopia as well.
So I didn't mention, but
the cause of amblyopia
is an impaired
synaptic development
in a part of the brain
called visual cortex.
So what we'd like
to do is to harness
the principles of experience
dependent synaptic plasticity
to promote recovery
of brain function,
particularly in adults.
So over, again, the last
half century or so, we've
learned a tremendous
amount about the mechanisms
of synaptic
plasticity, plasticity
at excitatory
synapses in the brain.
We know that synapses are
bidirectionally modifiable.
And one of the critical
triggers for this plasticity
is a neurotransmitter--
whoops, can I go back one?
A neurotransmitter receptor
called an NMDA receptor.
And what we've learned is that
activation of NMDA receptors
can trigger both
synaptic depression
and synaptic potentiation.
And the critical
variable is the level
of postsynaptic response at the
same time those receptors are
activated.
And so what you see on
the right is a function
where we can map the
consequences of NMDA receptor
activation depending on the
level of postsynaptic response.
So there's a critical site here.
Again, go back please.
My laser pointer doesn't work.
One forward.
Thank you.
So you can see strong NMDA
receptor activation can yield
a synaptic potentiation and weak
NMDA receptor activation yields
synaptic depression.
So what is controlling
this postsynaptic response?
Well, obviously, it's
how many synapses
are active at the
same time and what
the strength of those
synapses is, and also,
the concurrent level of
inhibition in the brain.
So we'd like to
understand how we
can promote the
conditions that will
lead to synaptic strengthening.
So a lot of our
work was influenced
by a theory of
synaptic plasticity
that was introduced
by Leon Cooper.
Leon was a mentor, friend,
and colleague of mine.
Sadly, he died just
a few weeks ago.
He's a very famous physicist.
He won the Nobel Prize for a
theory of superconductivity.
But after that, he
went on to become
interested in synaptic
plasticity in the brain.
And he developed a theory that
is now called the BCM theory,
or Bienenstock, Cooper,
and Monroe theory.
It's a very simple idea.
And what he proposed is
that the synaptic strength
varies as a function of the
product of the input activity
and a concurrent level
of postsynaptic response,
some function of the concurrent
level of postsynaptic response.
And that function is
shown here in the middle,
and it should bear
a close resemblance
to what I just showed you.
In fact, Leon's theory
inspired the experiments
that revealed the properties
of bidirectional synaptic
plasticity in the brain.
A critical variable
in Leon's theory
was that crossover point
between synaptic depression
and potentiation doesn't
have a fixed value.
But rather, it's free to
slide back and forth depending
on the average
activity of the cell.
So in other words, the
rules of synaptic plasticity
are themselves plastic,
and that's a property
we now call metaplasticity.
So the question is, can
we slide that threshold
to the left to promote
synaptic potentiation
and allow recovery of function?
Next slide.
I guess I can do that.
OK, so the way we
addressed this was
to take advantage
of a neurotoxin that
is derived from Puffer fish.
If you've ever had fugu,
it's a delicacy in Japan.
It's a type of sushi that is
prepared from Puffer fish,
but it can be quite dangerous.
Because in the liver and ovaries
of pufferfish is a lethal toxin
called tetrodotoxin.
The reason it's lethal is
because it blocks all action
potentials.
It blocks all nerve impulses.
It can be used in experiments
to block electrical activity
in the brain.
So the experiment
that we conceived
was to inject tetrodotoxin
into the eyes of an animal that
had been rendered
amblyopic, shut off
the activity of
the visual system,
allow that threshold
to slide to the left,
and then restore vision and ask,
do the synapses regain strength?
And I wouldn't be telling
you this if it didn't work,
and the results were
really quite dramatic.
So this is experiments
that were done
in a cat model of amblyopia.
We've done the same
thing in mice as well.
And the graph on the left
here shows the acuity
of either the
amblyopic eye in blue
or the fellow eye,
the good eye in green.
And so this animal had been
deprived of vision in one eye,
in the amblyopic eye
for a period of time.
That eye was opened.
There's no spontaneous
recovery of vision,
just as the case in the humans.
But at the time indicated with
the ttx and the downward going
arrows, this drug was
injected into the eyes.
And then, of course, that
shut off all the activity
in the fellow eye.
But now, we wait and
watch what happens.
So when the ttx wears off,
the fellow eye response
returns to normal.
But amazingly, the amblyopic
eye response comes bounding back
and goes right up
to a value that's
comparable to the fellow eye.
So a complete
reversal of amblyopia.
And this experiment was done at
an age when traditional therapy
is no longer effective.
So that's what's shown
on the right side
here, that downward going
arrow, that this is occurring
at about 14 weeks
of age, which is
well beyond that sensitive
period when patch therapy works.
So we were very excited
by these results.
It seemed it was a
theoretically inspired study.
But it really was
based on an assumption.
And the assumption was is
that ttx actually shuts off
activity in the visual system.
However, more
recently, we discovered
that if we can shut off
activity in the retinas,
that the relay nucleus
that brings information
from retinas to cortex
is not quieted at all.
In fact, the activity in
that relay nucleus, which
is called the lateral
geniculate nucleus,
that activity starts to fire off
in bursts, spontaneous bursts,
high frequency
bursting activity.
And that bursting activity
occurs both in the neurons
that are postsynaptic
to the inactivated eye
and to the other eye as well.
So it's a qualitative change
in the type of activity
that's going to the cortex.
So the question then
became was, geez,
are these bursts really
required for this recovery?
So I have a wonderful graduate
student, Matty [INAUDIBLE],
who tested this by
knocking out the gene that
was responsible for
this bursting activity
in the lateral
geniculate nucleus.
You can eliminate bursting.
And when she did so, she
eliminated the recovery
that was caused by
the ttx injection.
So we have to
really rethink what
the mechanism for
this recovery is.
And I don't have a
good answer for you.
But what we do know is that
the bursting activity sets up
a pattern of very highly
synchronous activity
in the brain and also impairs
inhibition in the cortex.
So we think we've achieved
what we hoped to achieve,
not by sliding the
threshold necessarily,
but by evoking a stronger
postsynaptic response.
So the mechanism is
still, obviously,
under intensive
investigation in the lab.
But we can already
start to think
about how we might apply this
in a therapeutic setting.
So the next step for us was
to go to a primate model
of deprivation amblyopia.
So we've repeated
these experiments now
in monkeys that were rendered
amblyopic by early life
monocular deprivation.
And the results are,
again, very dramatic.
So we can get a very
substantial improvement
in the electrophysiological
measure of visual function
in monkeys.
But this also-- there's been--
nature has provided this
experiment in humans as well.
There are amblyopic humans
that, unfortunately,
have suffered damage to their
fellow eye in adulthood.
So they have relied on
their fellow eye for vision
for their whole life.
But then, because of
injury or disease,
the fellow eye has to be
removed or is otherwise
incapable of supporting vision.
And what's observed is
that, in many cases,
there is an unexpected recovery
of vision in the amblyopic eye.
So this means that plasticity
is there in our brains.
We just need to find a
way to tap into that.
Now, losing the fellow eye
is not a therapeutic strategy
to promote recovery
from amblyopia.
But what is is temporarily
inactivating that fellow eye
and, essentially, rebooting
the visual system.
So we think this is an
exciting future ahead.
And with that,
thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
Our next speaker
is Josh McDermott.
[APPLAUSE]
Greetings, everyone.
All right, so we
rely on our senses
to perceive the world around us.
But as Mark just told you,
our senses are fragile.
So in fact, over
39 million people
worldwide are blind and
over 70 million people
worldwide are deaf.
And we would love to be
able to restore the senses
in these individuals.
Now, certainly, the treatments
for these conditions
have improved over
time, but we're
far from being able to fully
restore sight and hearing.
All right, so the
first thing you all
need to all have
receptors in your ears
called hair cells that are
responsible for turning sound
into electrical signals,
and they're shown here.
So they sit on top of
a membrane in your ear
that vibrates in
response to sound.
And the hairs on the cells
get bent when they move around
and that causes changes in
their membrane potential.
And those signals are
sent to your brain
via the auditory nerve
that's shown there.
Now, deafness is typically
caused by hair cell dysfunction.
All right, the second
thing you need to know
is that, in the last
five years, there
have been huge
advances in our ability
to build computer models
of sensory systems.
And this has been
really largely driven
by progress in artificial
neural networks.
So when we do this in
our lab, we typically
start with a model
of the ear that's
rooted in everything that
we know from biology.
And then, we put on top of that
an artificial neural network
that gets optimized
to do different kinds
of auditory tasks, like
recognizing words or localizing
sounds.
And what this long stream
of fantastic students
has shown over and
over again is that when
you build models in this way,
they reproduce human behavior
to a pretty remarkable extent
across many different domains.
And this has really
transformed our ability
to understand and
study perception.
So our goal now is to use these
models to understand and improve
bionic ears and eyes.
So our lab study is
the sense of hearing,
so we're focused on bionic ears.
But we think many
of the insights
will be equally
relevant to vision.
So the cochlear implant
is a bionic ear.
It aims to cause hearing
via electrical stimulation.
And it is the primary treatment
for deafness at present.
There are over a million of
these devices in use worldwide.
So the way this works
is there's a microphone
outside the head and that--
the sound signal
that gets recorded
gets turned into
electrical signals,
and those are sent down that
wire that goes into the cochlea
and wraps around in that
spiral, and the wire
has got a bunch of
electrodes on it.
And so the key concept is
that if you have hair cell
dysfunction that
causes deafness,
but if the auditory nerve
that would normally convey
signals from the hair cells to
your brain, if that's intact,
then that can be
electrically stimulated
and that should cause
you to hear something.
So you bypass the hair cells to
create the sensation of sound.
So ideally, the
electrical stimulation
would replicate the nerve
patterns of activity
that would normally happen
from hearing electrically.
But that's really hard to do.
And so although these devices
are in some sense miraculous,
they're still not close to
restoring normal hearing.
And so one example of
that is shown here.
So I'll show you a number of
graphs that will look like this.
So this graph plots how well
people can recognize speech
in noise.
So the y-axis is word
recognition accuracy,
and the x-axis is the
signal to noise ratio.
So as you move to
the right, the speech
gets louder relative
to the noise
and it gets easier to recognize.
So the black curve shows how
well people with normal hearing
can recognize words.
And when the speech is loud
enough, they're at ceiling.
The red curve shows
what happens in humans
that have cochlear implants.
OK, so on the one hand, the fact
that they can score about 60%
correct is amazing because
these are individuals who would
otherwise be completely deaf.
But you can also
see that there's
a large gap between the red
curve and the black curve,
and that's what we'd
really like to close.
All right, so what limits
outcomes with these devices?
Well, there's at least
three potential factors
that we know of.
One is that the device
strategies are almost surely
suboptimal.
Another is that if you
undergo a period of deafness,
the neurons in your
auditory system die.
So there's neurodegeneration,
to varying extents,
in the auditory nerve or
beyond and what we call
the central auditory system.
And there's also the potential
that your brain is suboptimally
decoding the signals that
it gets from these devices.
All right, so what
limits our research
into understanding
these factors?
Well, one is that we have
very limited access to what's
actually happening in the brain
of a human implant listener.
So it's not like you can
just look at a person
and tell whether they
have neurodegeneration
or tell whether their
brain is suboptimally
decoding those signals.
But there are two
other major obstacles.
One is that the best
outcomes typically
occur after somebody has lived
with an implant for a very
extended period of
time, months to years.
And the other issue
is that the outcomes
are highly variable
across individuals,
as I'll show you in a moment.
So it's not like you can
get a new idea for a device
and give it to one person
and then really extrapolate
much about how it
will work in general.
So this makes it very
challenging to experiment
with alternative
device strategies.
And so most of the major
implant manufacturers
have all pretty much
been doing the same thing
for the last 10, 20 years.
All right, now, what
we can do nowadays
is build very good simulations
of the nerve responses that
would result from
a cochlear implant.
And Anisha Banerjee is
a fantastic grad student
in our lab who has built
one of these simulations.
The details here
don't really matter.
It's a computer program that
predicts the nerve responses
from electrical stimulation.
And so one example
is shown here.
So the top picture shows
an example, nerve response
from a cochlear implant.
The different rows represent
different nerve fibers
and the x-axis is time, OK?
What's shown on the bottom
is an analogous simulation
from a normal ear to the
same speech utterance.
So the point is that the
cochlear implant is intended
to produce nerve responses that
look like what you would get
from the normal ear, but
you can see that they
look really different.
And that's probably
part of the issue.
All right, so how can we
understand these outcomes
with the models that
we have of the brain?
So one other
important fact to note
is that human implant users
improve pretty substantially
over time.
So this is a really cool graph
that shows word recognition
scores as a function of
the number of months post
activation.
So how long someone has lived
with their device, and each line
is a different individual.
The different
colors don't matter.
So you can see that
all the lines go up
and they go up over
a period of time.
So people are learning
to do something
with their brains
that makes them
better at decoding
the information they
get from the device.
But the other thing
to note here is
that the asymptotic performance
is really highly variable.
So some people end up doing
great and others much less so.
And so what we don't know
is whether that variation is
due to differences in
how well people can learn
or whether, for instance,
it might be differences
in neural degeneration
or some other factor
that we don't know about.
So these models that we build
using machine learning we think
can help reveal the potential
of brain plasticity.
So we can take these models
of the auditory system
and build what we call a
static model of hearing
through a cochlear
implant where you take
a model of the normal
auditory system
and you just give it input
from a cochlear implant.
But we can also
build what we would
call a plastic model, where
you completely re-optimize
the neural network to deal with
input from a cochlear implant,
simulating what would happen
if your brain could completely
readapt itself to this
altered kind of input.
We can also potentially look
at the impact of degeneration
by looking at what
happens if you just
delete a bunch of nerve fibers
in the input to the model
or delete a bunch of neurons.
All right, so what happens?
So here's one
example of a result.
Again, this is the
same kind of graph
that shows word recognition
accuracy versus the signal
to noise ratio.
The black line shows a
model of normal hearing
that is very similar
in its performance
to humans with normal hearing.
And the green
curve shows a model
that gets input from
a cochlear implant,
but that is fully plastic.
So you can see that the
green curve is actually
pretty close to the
Black curve, right?
It's a little bit worse,
but really, pretty close.
Now, the red curve
shows the results
of humans that have
cochlear implants that we
tested in our lab on the
exact same experiment.
And you can see that
they're not doing nearly
as well as the model of the
green curve that is, right?
So that suggests that,
in principle, you
could do a lot better with
the input from the implant,
if you could fully
reoptimize your brain
to process those signals.
Can we simulate the possibility
of incomplete plasticity?
Well, one thing
we can do is just
reoptimize some of the
parts of that neural network
to deal with input from
the cochlear implant.
And when you do that,
you get the blue curve,
and that's now within
striking distance
of what you see from humans.
Now, by contrast, I'm
going to show you now
what happens if you delete 50%
of the neurons in these models.
And those are the dashed lines.
And the effect of that is
actually remarkably modest.
So we see huge effects of
the extent to which you
can reoptimize your
brain for this altered
input and really modest
effects of neurodegeneration.
So it's consistent
with the idea that
plasticity is a dominant
factor underlying outcomes.
And it raises the possibility
that increasing plasticity
in the human auditory
system, doing things
like what Mark was
just talking about,
could potentially
yield big benefits.
All right, so the next steps
that we're excited about
are to use these models
to derive new device
strategies that could
potentially further improve
outcomes.
And so we think the models can
be very useful here in revealing
the best case outcomes
for candidate devices,
potentially enabling
large scale screening.
So you can try out lots
of different ideas.
And then, the most
promising options
are things that you could
potentially explore in humans.
So I think this
is a nice example
of basic science
with impact where
the models that we
build of the brain
and refining those models
will lead to better therapies
that we hope will help people.
So thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
And with that, it
is a great pleasure
to introduce the world's expert
on the neural basis of language,
my colleague, Professor
Evelina Fedorenko.
Thank you.
All right, so let's
see if this works.
So language is--
I study language,
and language is this
incredible superpower we have.
Using language, we can
build deep relationships
with each other and restore
international political order.
We can send submarines to
the bottom of the ocean,
rockets into space,
and cure diseases.
We can bring about
political and social change
and record the history of
our planet and our species.
So how do our brains achieve
this remarkable feat?
So using studies of
patients with lesions,
non-invasive imaging like fMRI
and intracranial recordings,
and patients undergoing surgery
for brain tumors or epilepsy,
we've learned that there's
a whole bunch of areas
in your brain that
help you do this.
And I assure you, all of these
areas are working in your brains
as you're listening
to me right now.
These areas look something like
this in any individual brain.
And interestingly, they
support both comprehension
and production.
This makes us think that
these areas, basically,
store our knowledge of
language, so what words mean
and how to put words together.
And of course, we need this
knowledge to both take a thought
and encode it into
a word sequence,
or process somebody
else's word sequence
and infer the meaning
that they intended.
What I just said should make
it clear to some of you who
may have heard of things like
Broca's area and Wernicke's area
that these language
areas I mentioned
are actually different from
these areas classically
discussed in the
neurobiology of language.
It turns out that these Broca's
area and Wernicke's area
are lower level areas.
So Broca's area
is an area that's
important for planning
speech motor movements,
and Wernicke's area is important
for perceiving speech sounds.
So, for example, if I now switch
to talking in a language that's
unfamiliar to you,
your Wernicke's area
will be working
just as hard as it's
working right now
because it's still
getting its preferred input,
which is speech sounds.
But your purple areas,
your language areas,
the activity in
them will plummet
because you would no
longer be able to extract
any meaningful
information from them.
These areas, the
language areas, are also
distinct from areas that
support thinking and reasoning,
as my group and a few
others have shown.
Of course, our language
system interacts closely
with our reasoning abilities,
but nevertheless, the language
areas are not the areas that are
doing thinking in your brain.
And you can lose
your language system,
as in cases of severe
aphasia, and still
be able to think and
reason in complex ways.
A couple other things.
The system seems
quite robustly similar
across diverse languages.
There is over 7,000 languages
spoken and signed across
the world.
We've tested this in
about 50 languages.
Looks similar.
For those of us who have
multiple language systems living
in our brains, like bilingual
and multilingual speakers,
they all live in that system,
and developmentally, the system
is there and shows adult like
topography by about age three.
Now, our focus
today is on health.
So losing language is an
incredibly devastating
condition.
Not having full access to
language and development
leads to all sorts of cognitive
delays and difficulties
in establishing relationships
with your caretakers
and losing language
in adulthood.
In cases of
degeneration or stroke
aphasia is life changing in
all sorts of horrible ways.
So in trying to understand
language development,
we're trying to
ask questions like,
why is the language
system sometimes
doesn't develop properly as,
for example, in cases of autism?
Can we predict language
development trajectories?
And can we intervene
in high risk cases
to ensure that the language
system give it the best
chance to develop typically?
For acquired
disorders, we're asking
questions like, in what ways
can a language system break?
Can the language system
fix itself, to some degree,
in cases when it
starts malfunctioning?
And what can we do externally
to intervene on the brain
to ensure that the language
system recovers as much as
possible?
So we work on both developmental
questions and questions
of language loss in
adulthood, and I'll
give you a glimpse of
the latter line of work.
So this is a collaboration that
we've had going for a few years
now with Swathi Kiran, who is at
BU leading the Center for Brain
Recovery, and the lead junior
scientist is [INAUDIBLE], who
is now a postdoc at Harvard.
So understanding
recovery from aphasia
has been going on for many
years, centuries really, now.
So a lot of people
have focused on trying
to understand the trajectory,
the timeline of development.
And very consistently,
a lot of groups
have shown that most
recovery happens
within the first few months.
But in many cases,
recovery does continue even
after the first year,
although at a slower pace.
Many other groups have
studied questions like,
what makes some people
recover better and worse?
And one big finding is
that the younger you are
and the better your
brain health is
at the time the stroke
happens, the better off you're
going to be.
But also, it matters
where the damage happens
and how extensive it is.
In our work, we've been
trying to understand
the recovery mechanisms that
underlie recovery from aphasia.
So to the extent that
a patient recovers,
what's happening in the
brains of those patients?
What are the changes that lead
to the restoration of some
of the linguistic function?
And there have been two big
ideas for how this might happen.
One idea is what's
referred to as homeostasis.
So it's basically the idea is
that you have some remaining
parts of your language
system and they're
trying to recover function
by somehow reorganizing
the function among
the remaining bits.
So you're trying to go back
as much as possible to the way
things were before
the stroke event.
A very different idea
is reorganization.
So this is a more drastic
takeover of function
by areas that weren't
doing language before,
but are now going to
be doing language.
And a good candidate for
this kind of takeover
is the system that many people
call the multiple demand
system or the executive
function system.
It's a very cool
system you all have.
It supports so-called
executive abilities
like working memory,
attention, inhibitory control,
and it's active across
many, many different kinds
of behaviors.
One way to think
of this system is
it's a system that evolution
gave us to be able to adapt,
right?
We have all sorts of specialized
mechanisms, like for hearing
or for vision or for
language, but we also
have resources to be
able to deal with change.
And this system, the idea was
that this system is flexible
enough so that if some
specialized mechanisms get
damaged, the system
can take over.
Why does it matter?
Well, if we know that it's
a language system that
helps you recover, the remaining
parts of the language system,
or this very
different system, we
can intervene on these systems.
We can either stimulate them
or do behavioral therapy that
targets this particular system.
So it really matters for
trying to boost the recovery
mechanisms that are in place.
So we tried to
evaluate these two
ideas in a group of patients
with chronic aphasia
and a bunch of controls.
So what we did was record
their brain activity
as they listened to
language to understand
which parts of their brain
are processing language.
And we also measured
their linguistic ability
in all sorts of ways using
standard assessments.
And so then, we're, basically
asking, OK, to the extent
that these patients vary in
how good they are in language.
What's different about how
their brains process language
so that some are doing
better than others?
And it turns out that
it's really homeostasis
that's doing this work.
So it's the same system that
was doing language in your brain
before stroke that--
whose ability, whose
activity is best predictive
of how well you're
doing after a stroke.
So now, individuals who show
most typical like patterns
in that system are
the ones that do best.
So what we're
doing now is trying
to evaluate a
range of therapies,
some based on behavior.
So for a while, people
got really excited
about this idea of
takeover of function.
And a lot of
therapies got shifted
to trying to increase general
ability, executive function
ability.
Let's make people
better at working memory
or at keeping
attention in the hope
that it helps restore
these loss functions.
It turns out that, no, you need
to really focus on language
and keep training the
language system up.
We're also doing work with
electrical stimulation
of the language
system remaining parts
to see if it boosts recovery.
We're also doing this very
hard thing of longitudinal
scanning trying to--
very little is
understood, actually,
about the acute stage of what
happens in the first few months
because most people don't want
to do research when they just
suffered a stroke.
But it's really,
really important
to understand how things change
during those first few months
after injury, so
we're trying that.
And much like what
Josh was talking about,
we're also building
computational models
based on language models
like ChatGPT, including
creating kind of aphasic
variants of these models
to get a more mechanistic
level insight into how
things can break, and
hopefully, how we can fix them.
So thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
Nice job.
Thank you.
Empty chair.
It is a big chair.
So we have time
for some questions.
Are there any that
get it started off?
Tony.
Use a mic back there.
In animal studies,
does language have
to exist for thinking to exist?
This is something you presented.
And I've read some studies that
say that animals actually think,
even if they cannot speak.
Is there a biological
reality to that?
I mean, animals certainly do
all sorts of complex cognition.
Whether their thinking
mechanisms are exactly the same
as humans, well, probably not.
But whether they're just
kind of-- whether humans
have simply bigger and better
versions of those mechanisms
is potentially likely.
And a lot of people
are working on this.
But Yeah, you can definitely
think without language,
including in animals.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
You mentioned something
about language development
with the very young.
And you said around three
years of age things change.
But previously, I've
heard a lot about much
later than that learning
a foreign language up
to age 10 or 11,
somewhere like that.
How do these two relate?
Sorry, I didn't quite
hear everything you said.
So how will we
learn later in life?
You mentioned in the
talk that around, I
believe it was the
age of three years,
that the way the language
acquisition learning was taking
place dropped off at that point.
No.
I was just saying that the
system I was talking about
is there by age three.
Of course, learning can
happen much later than three.
Yeah, it still works.
Because I'd heard like
10, 11 years old that--
Into the teenage years,
you can learn language
in a native like way.
Yeah.
I have a question.
In terms of the scope
of your research,
do you also look into
cognitive, I guess,
impact caused by other diseases
such as cancer entering
the brain, for example?
Thank you.
Good question.
I guess some of the
tools that we developed,
we do work with brain
cancer neurosurgeons.
This is not about cognition,
but our microscopy methods
if you can find brain tumor
cells more accurately.
We had a paper earlier
this year where
we showed that you could get
much more accurate counts
of aggressive brain tumor cells
with our new imaging methods
than with older ones.
So not exactly
conditioned, but the tools
can be definitely applied.
Yeah, I was more referring
to metastasis of other cancer
into the brain.
Yeah, I don't think any
of us work on that per se.
I mean, I'm very
generally interested
in what happens as people age.
We do a lot of work on the
consequences of hearing loss.
And that is also
accompanied with other kinds
of cognitive changes.
So that's one thing that's
a little bit related
to what you said.
And of course, there's things
like Alzheimer's and Parkinson's
that play into that as well.
Thank you.
So Mark, going back to your
discussion about amblyopia,
what's the best you
can do right now
for someone who has amblyopia?
Well, as I mentioned, patch
therapy is the standard of care.
The severity of amblyopia
depends on the cause.
So there are more benign causes.
More benign.
Less severe causes that can
be treated as late as age 8, 7
or 8.
So again, it's patch therapy.
But in recent years,
there's been introduction
of what's called dichoptic
therapy, which is using
binocular visual stimulation.
And they're getting
very good results.
But again, the
effects so far are
restricted to this early
developmental period.
Go ahead.
What causes a loss
of language ability
with age, hunting
for words, and so on?
And are there other ways
to recover from that?
That's a great question.
So I'm also very interested
in aging, like Josh is.
And we've just finished
a study looking
at how the language system in
the brain changes with aging.
And we can't find any
ways in which it changes.
So neurally, it
looks just as good
as a system in young brains.
It's as strongly
active, as strongly
lateralized to the
left hemisphere,
responds similarly
selective to language.
And so there is no
obvious changes there.
So I suspect a lot of the
word finding difficulties
that people report
with aging have
to do with more
general memory systems.
And of course, those
are very susceptible
to disorders like
Alzheimer's, and in general,
decay with healthy aging.
And those changes you can see
very well, even with methods
like non-invasive imaging.
I don't know if there
is more to that.
If you don't mind, I
have two questions.
One is, with the
cochlear implants,
do you find that there's more
neuroplasticity in people
who lost their hearing
at a later age as opposed
to people who never
were able to hear?
Do they adapt to a
cochlear implant better?
Yeah, it's a little
bit complicated.
So I mean, in general,
the best outcomes
happen with people who are
implanted at a very early age.
And one plausible
explanation for that
is that, in general,
the brain tends
to be more plastic at
younger ages, right?
But there are also--
there is also evidence
that there are benefits to
having some hearing experience.
And so that probably
factors in as well.
Yeah, that's a short answer.
My second question
is about language.
You talked about these
centers of the brain
are for all multi-language,
bilingual, multilingual.
When people lose language
and become aphasic,
do they always lose
all of their languages,
or can they lose one
of their languages
if they're multilingual?
And how does that play
into your studies?
That's a great question.
So in most cases, yes, you
lose multiple languages,
but there are interesting
effects where sometimes people
report that the language
that's not a native language,
you tend to preserve
a little bit better.
And we think we
just recently got
a glimpse of a possible
mechanism for that.
I always found this
really confusing.
Not making sense.
But one thing that we see
is that native languages
tend to be processed
a little more focally.
So they don't always
engage this whole system.
There is a core part
in the posterior
in the left temporal
cortex that seems
to really, really be important.
But for all of your later--
so for me, English is
a non-native language,
and English engages this whole
network very consistently.
And so if you have vocal damage
in the left temporal cortex,
it is more likely to wipe
out your native language,
and the remaining parts may
work better in the later learned
languages because it's just
more consistently recruited
in this way.
Fantastic.
Hi.
Thanks for sharing
your research.
They are fascinating.
I'd like to know if there
is any studies showing
the impacts of the use--
the early and frequent use
of technology, social media,
and generative AI by
children and teenagers
in core cognitive functions?
Because attention,
learning, memory,
because we've been hearing
a lot about the impacts
of social media and screens in
the mental health, increased
levels of anxiety and
eating disorders in girls,
but what about the
other functions?
Using technology can
harm in the long-term
our attention, language
acquisition, memory, learning.
Do we have any robust
evidence on that?
Thank you.
Yeah, to my knowledge,
there isn't, actually,
robust evidence one
way or the other.
I mean, there is a
literature that--
I mean, Ev may remember
this better than I do.
But there there were
a lot of studies
for a while showing that you
could see some advantages
from people that played
a lot of video games,
like on benefits on visual
attention, for instance.
And I'm not up to date on what
the current status of that is.
Did that stuff hold up?
I can't remember.
Yeah, and that research
program on video games
started because people thought
that video games are destroying
our children's brains.
And they started looking
at all sorts of functions
like attention, memory.
And it turns out everything
they looked at is actually
a little bit better in kids.
So that's where that went.
And yeah, I have not
heard of any research
other than the mental
health effects of exposure
to social media that it
affects attention or memory
in any negative way or language.
I still keep my kids off it.
[LAUGHTER]
Hi.
Thank you so much.
The brain is so amazing
because there's still
so much we don't know.
I've heard about how
people are trying to--
I mean, I guess all of
you guys in your own way--
but are trying to
map each circuit.
And to me, it sounds like
the kind of impossible dream
that we once thought mapping
the whole genome would be.
So do you think that's
something that we'll
see in any of our lifetimes?
I mean, just understanding how
all the different pieces fit
together.
Or is that way out there?
Thank you.
I think everybody should
take a shot at that one.
Go ahead.
Yeah, well, I think
one of the great things
about being here at MIT is
the technology collaborations.
So great engineering school,
great science school,
great cross-talk.
And the influx of everything
from nanotechnology
for neural interfacing to
new noninvasive strategies
for delivering
energy and recording
information from
the brain, I think
that's presenting a huge amount
of almost engineered serendipity
between different fields
that is opening up a of--
a bit of a Moore's law in
terms of improving our ability
to look at and control
brain circuits.
So being an engineer, maybe
it's how I think about things.
But I think being at
MIT, you're surrounded
by people who are always asking
for what the next big problem is
that they could work on.
And they may have
revolutionized one field,
and they're looking for
the next big challenge.
And for many people,
that's the brain.
Mark, any thoughts?
No thoughts.
[LAUGHTER]
No.
I mean, I think there's
value in simplification.
I'm a lumper, not a splitter.
And looking for
general principles
seems to me a lost art that
needs to be reinvigorated
and I hope to see that continue.
Yes, I think, I mean, one
thing I would say is--
I mean, I don't
know how realistic
it is to think that
we will actually
understand the human brain
fully at the circuit level.
And I'm not sure that
we will necessarily
need to for a lot of the
things that we want to do.
So for instance, if we end up
really understanding learning,
and if learning is the
key to a lot of the things
that we want to do, then
that may be sufficient.
And having really
detailed explanations
of what happens at the
circuit level, I mean,
may or may not be critical for
what we actually want to do.
So I think there will be
examples where we have really
circuit level
explanations for things,
but I'm not sure
that will generally
be the case for the human
brain just because it's
so big and so complicated.
Hello.
I'm from bioengineering
department,
and we do run the clinical trial
with the long COVID participants
and chronic Lyme participants.
And I've been always very
fascinated about the patients
complain about their
brain fog symptoms
as number one major
symptom complaints.
And that's why I'm here.
And I got very fascinated
with the language aphasia
presentation.
Thank you so much.
And I would love to-- because I
don't have much basic knowledge
in the brain science.
But I want to ask this
question for my patients
actually here that this is
all new symptoms in terms
of being lost in the
middle of the speech
when they're trying
to engage interaction
with the summoning conversation.
And the way they describe
brain fog and cognitive deficit
is oftentimes related to their
language of difficulties.
And I would love to
know your insight
in terms of the brain function
associated with the infection
triggers or source.
Not so much a stroke
issue, but perhaps,
what are the insights with
the infection triggers?
And can this kind of a brain
fog complaints description
of language difficulty
be something
to look at in the case of
Wernicke's or Broca's area,
or what are the insights
that we can look further
to expand our research?
I would love to
hear your feedback.
Thank you.
Yeah, I don't know if I have
too much to say about this.
I mean, from my understanding,
the brain fog like symptoms
in long COVID patients are not
quite specific to language.
The language may
be affected, but it
seems like it's a pretty
wide spread systemic effects
on multiple systems.
So it's possible that insights
from specific disorders,
like language or audition,
related things may be helpful,
but it seems like there is some
more global things to understand
there.
And maybe the
deficits are actually
in this very vulnerable system
to aging, which we mentioned
the system that affects
memory and is very
affected in Alzheimer's,
so the system that
has big hippocampal components.
But yeah, sorry, I don't
think I have anything
more specific than that.
Thank you so much.
So a question for
you before you leave.
So what do you measure to
document the patient's brain
fog?
What kind of tests
do you have them do?
So currently, in our study,
we do three different measures
that we add.
So typically, a day before
person comes to MIT visit
for study visit, we
assign the cognitive test
called brain check.
It's equivalent
version of a battery
that can be done remotely.
So it takes strobe and trail
making and memory function,
immediate recognition
type of testing.
And once they come to
MIT for study visit,
we do two different
neurocognitive testing.
One is called right eye, which
we add a visual sensitivity
testing.
So the person will--
we're going to look
at the eye coordination
and pursuit and saccades
and the brain reaction time
and physical reaction time
by using different images
and how quickly they react.
And the other one we also use
equivalent version of EEG called
[? Wave. ?] It's actually
a commercial testing,
but we look at the
brain activity,
look at the alpha peak wave
during the P300 testing,
we also do the flanker
testing as well
just to see the difference
in terms of reaction time.
Great, thanks.
We can learn from
the audience as well.
[LAUGHTER]
So Hi, I'm [INAUDIBLE], and I'm
a first year master's student
at Harvard.
So my question may be
a little bit naive.
So in my undergrad
study, I did projects
related to understanding
molecular mechanism of autism.
And I also have some experience
dealing with the neuroimage.
So my question
would be, well, it
is possible to have a model,
like machine learning model,
to actually predict both
the genomics and the--
I mean, the outcome of
diseases or the hearing
aid devices for both
genomics level and also
the circuit level.
So if that is possible,
so what is the challenge
that you may see in this?
So we have less
than two minutes.
You want to try that.
Josh that's you.
So, I mean, we're
definitely not there, right?
I mean, I think the means by
which genes lead to circuits,
I mean, that's a pretty big and
hard and complicated problem.
I don't know.
I mean, machine
learning could certainly
be useful probably
in understanding
that if you had enough data.
And my guess is there probably
will be lots of headway on that.
I mean, there's
definitely lots of people
who are very excited
about building
models of the entire brain
at the circuit level.
I mean, this is I think
what Ed maybe aspires to.
And where that's going to lead,
I think, we still don't know.
But it's a really
exciting direction
And, it could
become within reach.
OK, thank you.
So one last question.
Thanks.
Thanks for your talk.
I'm curious.
I have actually two
questions, if I might.
With regard to language,
are the same centers
for language processing
identical regardless
of the input via hearing,
sight, signing, et cetera?
Yes, Sorry, I didn't
explicitly say this.
They're AI model,
so it doesn't matter
if you're reading or
listening or processing
sign language if your sign.
OK, my second
question is, how broad
is the definition of language?
Does it encompass
situational awareness
when you're in traffic,
traffic lights, where
cars are, danger on the street?
Is that part of the
language function?
Well, so I certainly
wouldn't put--
I mean, language is a very
difficult construct in the sense
that it interacts with all
sorts of other systems.
But it so happens that we have
a set of these areas that are
quite specialized for language.
And then, a lot
of ongoing work is
trying to understand how
these language circuits work
with low level
audition circuits,
how they work with
memory circuits,
attention circuits.
Because, of course, we use
language in its real life
complexity where
there's a lot of systems
that come together and
have to talk to each other.
But it does seem that there
is some sense in which there
is a system that's specialized
for just this encoding decoding
aspect between thoughts
and word sequences.
I guess a follow on to that is,
if I lost my language centers,
would I lose my ability
to understand situational?
No, you would not.
In fact, there is a large body
of work with severe aphasics
and their cognition--
so it relates
to the first question as well--
their cognition is totally fine.
They can navigate the world,
they can socially reason,
they can keep their attention,
they can play chess,
they just can't express
their thoughts and language
or understand others.
Thank you.
So to be in sync with the
remaining part of the program,
let's thank our speakers.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
And I guess they're going
to reconvene over in the--
across the way
there very shortly.
OK, great.