So I'm Yaniv, CEO and founder of Alpha
Biome. Uh I'm also a researcher at MIT
and uh for the past 20 years I've been
um looking at how AI can be used in
order to find order in the chaos. Uh so
this is what we are doing at Alpha
Biome. Uh we are using um this
technology in order to revolutionize the
way biomarkers are being discovered and
uh commercialized. Um, quickly what are
biomarkers? Biomarkers are the signals
that our body leaves behind. These are
tiny genetic fragments that can be used
in order to predict the development of
diseases. They can be used to diagnose
the medical condition and they can be
used in order to determine what is going
to be the most effective treatment. Now
these less biomarkers are of extreme
importance not just to patients but also
to pharma companies who pay hundreds of
millions per each. And the reason is
that they are of immense value both for
patients of course that can benefit from
the best treatment but also they are the
key for pharma in order to both extend
the patent exclusivity for their
existing drugs uh by detecting a cohort
of likely responders as well as for
developing a new kind a new generation
of drugs And this is a $50 billion
market. There are dozens of deals every
year where biomarkers are being
purchased uh across many different
therapeutic areas from oncology uh to
degenerate nervous systems uh gastro um
and others. Now, all of these
biomarkers, there is one thing in common
to them, and that is that they are
mostly coming from the host genome, the
human DNA. Um, you're looking for a
mutation, a bad corrupt gene, and so on.
And this is what the vast majority of
the biomarkers are based on. And we do
something profoundly different. We can
detect biomarkers from the microbiome.
These trillions of creatures living
inside us. and on our bodies. And um we
have already discovered more than
100,000 novel biomarkers that can be
used to predict efficacy of drugs um
using our proprietary technology and um
these are all coming from the
microbiome. We spent two years proving
that these biomarkers are actually of
value to predict drug efficacy. We did
it on cows on animals. This was the
largest the world's largest clinical
study where we use these technology and
these biomarkers in order to predict
drug efficacy for cows. There are drugs
for cows. Uh and we demonstrated that we
can triple the effect of these
commercially available leading drugs. It
was demonstrated on 30,000 cows all
around the world. It was published in
already several uh peer-reviewed
scientific studies. And a year ago we
expanded to humans demonstrated the same
thing. We can predict efficacy for drug
uh for IBD patients Crohn's and colitis
going from 32% efficacy to 67. So
doubling the efficacy for humans real
data real patients. Um we signed an
agreement to get this IBD data but also
recently signed another agreement to get
similar data for childhood obesity and
topic dermatitis. Uh and we're looking
for partnerships with pharma companies
with um blockbusters that are looking
for biomarkers with insurance providers
and payers who look um to optimize
treatments for their patients uh
focusing mainly Europe, US uh Japan,
Korea and Singapore. So thanks