good morning everybody delighted you're
here my name is Todd Glickman I'm senior
director of The Office of corporate
relations at MIT and our industrial
liaison program I am delighted to
welcome you to our second annual
Symposium in Bangkok ILP provides
actively managed facilitated access to
the rich resources of MIT to large
corporations worldwi wide we're honored
to have 16 ILP member companies in the
aan region five of them here in
Thailand this year's theme unleashing AI
transforming Industries empowering
Futures is all about the intersection of
AI and Industry today we'll hear from
four MIT faculty researchers three MIT
connected startups and experience two
moderated panel discussions that include
representatives from industry e acemia
and
government with gratitude I would like
to thank our Symposium sponsors CP group
true digital for the Fantastic facility
today Bangkok Bank CMS group and
mapon with the representatives from
these organizations please rise and
accept our
[Applause]
thanks I'd also like to recognize our
five ILP member companies based here in
Thailand Bangkok Bank Sam Cement Group
CP group true digital cbx and the
electricity generating authority of
Thailand we appreciate your
participation in ILP and all the support
that you give to
MIT each of my colleagues joining us
today will be introduced in turn during
the program but there are two colleagues
not on the program who I'd like you to
meet first corporate relations associate
director for conferences at event Quan
Lee in the back corner there without
whom this program would not have come
together so
well working closely with Dr taret and
Mr joke from our venue sponsor true
digital Park all of the logistics have
come together superbly Quan Dr tarit Mr
joke you have our very deep
gratitude and one more introduction that
will take a moment of
explanation I have been privileged to
serve in my current role for 25 5 years
as some of you already know I have
elected to retire from MIT effective
March the 1st and I am absolutely
thrilled to introduce ILP program
director miss hongfan a graduate of the
MIT Sloan MBA program class of 2003 who
has worked with me here at ILP since
2016 supporting members in the US and
Asia I know that Hong will do a superb
job of carrying on the tradition and
building the terrific relationships that
we' have had here here for the last two
decades okay so with that let's get
started a few logistical comments at the
end of each talk there will be the
opportunity for questions from the
audience so you don't see any
microphones right we're not going to be
using microphones in the audience
instead we all know you have an iPad or
an iPhone or a laptop with you and
that's what we're going to use it's an
electronic system to submit questions
you will see a QR code and a URL the
board behind and these are the links to
a service that's called pigeon hole you
connect to pigeon hole enter your
question you can do so with attribution
or anonymously you can also vote for
others questions raising their position
in the queue for attention by the
speaker we'll have a morning break a
lunch break and an afternoon break in
addition to refreshments and networking
you'll have the opportunity to visit
with our startup companies at their
stands just outside this Hall these
startups have come a very long way to
meet you and see if there are ways that
you and they can collaborate and
bringing new air related Solutions here
to Thailand I hope you'll take the time
to visit them today then at the end of
the program we'll have a final
networking
reception okay all set let's start the
program I'm honored to introduce Dr tet
niman wudang general manager of true
digital Park the sponsor of today's
venue Dr T
good
morning um as an MIT alarm I'm so
delighted to welcome you all to the MIT
industrial song program second annual
Symposium in Bangkok this is the second
year to do
it we provide you know
the platform um to exchange knowledge
like this um I think it is an honor to
have it in Thailand because this kind of
platform this kind of Symposium is
unlike the others what are the chances
that we you know fly in MIT Professor
researcher startups to exchange you know
the no housee the Forefront technology
ideas from Boston
continue as we embark on this journey of
exploring this year
theme from banking to retails from
infrastructure sector to real estate
from chemical to Telecom Tech from
agriculture farming to food the
Symposium provides a variable platform
to learn from the expertise of MIT and
engage in insightful discussion with
these industry leaders true digital Park
is deeply honor once again to host this
pre prestigious Symposium and this
aligns perfectly with our campus core
principle of fostering Innovation and
nurturing thriving ecosystem where
startups Corporation Academia can
collaborate and flourish on behalf of
the organizing team once again I extend
our sincere gratitude to all of you who
joining us today we are proud and
thankful to be a part of this event and
last but not least to my fellow MIT
go be verse thank you and have a great
day and next to share the perspective as
a government sector representative on
this Symposium it is my pleasure to
welcome the governor of Bangkok Mr
shadan please join me for a round of
applause
[Music]
and good morning everyone I have 10
minutes so I have to be quick first I
would like to welcome you to Bangkok I'm
alni of the MIT I gradate course one for
my master degree long time ago and I
cannot remember anything there but I
think many thing I learned and I've got
experience here and I think this
Symposium very important for Bangkok why
I think I like the what iack Newton say
see further you only on the shoulder of
the Giants so I think you are all Giants
in your your own area I think we would
like to learn from you I think many
things can be used to improve uh
technology and I think another one is by
B Joy right B Joy he said the smartest
people in the world don't all work for
us most of them work for someone else
and this true for any company you know
even Google Apple IBM I think you we
need to learn from other smart people
around the world and that's why you are
gathering here for Bangkok I think we
need lots of good solution from
technology um we have two number I think
I talked about this many times but you
are first time to hear that we have two
important number about Bangkok number
one we are the most visited CI in the
world just like just now like we beat
Istanbul like we have like 33 million
people this year but number 98 we are
quite low in the liability index you
know from 140 cities around the world we
are number 98 so we are nice city to
stay for like you maybe six seven days
you know but to work and to live here
maybe not very nice so that's how how
can we improve that so that's one
challenge that Bangkok facing I think
maybe the solution from you can help
improve this you know and this is all
problem we see in Bangkok you know PR
way flooding garbage PM 2.5 traffic jam
how can we improve this by your
expertise I think we compare to our
friend you know our our neighbor
Singapore in 1980 when Liu he he was a
prime minister the first thing he
focused about Singapore is productivity
right he he like about corruption
transparency education housing for
people he he start with
transparency and then in 20 2005 he
shift the focus to exciting and
fascinating City you know but when you
are product you have good productivity
you can create exciting and fast see
quite easy right they can have like San
Bay build in I think less than eight
years right for Thailand even to have a
entertainment complex we still debating
you know is it good or bad because we
don't have trust in the government and
that's a big problem so I think we we
can summarize Bangkok at this we are
exciting and fascinating City people
want to visit us you know but we are
City with low
productivity so we have to admit that
and then we have to improve on this you
know so I think technology AI can be
part of the solution to improve our
productivity how can you use less input
to get the same or even more output can
you travel less traffic jam I think Dr
kak came here late because of the
traffic jam right so how can we reduce
that how can we improve that using Ai
and Technology you know I like the book
by Ben green I think I I mentioned him
because he was a MIT Professor I think
he wrote the book not Smart City but
smart enough City so as a government
sector you know we cannot invest a lot
on technology we have other things to
take care of like people health care
healthare and other things right so we
cannot invest too much on technology so
I I don't to be the smartest city in the
world I just want to be the smart enough
City with proper investment proper
solution for our people so I think there
are three Circle that you need to to
worry the solution should be people
decide
so you have to be like people Centric
not technology Centric and then okay
business should be viable should be good
investment and good return for your
budget and Technology should be feasible
I'm sure the the the last circle of you
will provide technology feasible
solution but don't forget another two
circles that's so important for the
government sector other why we cannot
invest we have limited budget you know
so we need the Swit spot in the middle
that is a smart in our city so I think
we use we need to use proper technology
to increase our efficiency and
sustainability so that's a key thing
that what are we are looking for AI can
be part of the solution so what have we
been using I think that we should start
with transparency you know because with
corruption and not transparent difficult
to have a productive productivity
increase so we focus first on the
transparency so we start doing like open
data open service contract policy
Innovation everything should be on
website people can come and see what you
are doing so being transparent on our
data so if you want to work with BM I
think we have lot of data set that you
can work on and then we can give it to
you openly all the budget fiscal budget
we put it on the website so people
investigate what we use money for you
know and people increase people
interested in the data of the city
before that we have like 400,000 people
visit our website now we have 3 million
to look at our data that we open for the
public you know and this can be and look
at our construction permit you know or
use in the analog you have to submit
seven copies of your blueprint you know
and people go through this by like they
use manual to to check it so we will
transform it into digital and we can use
AI to check the building permit in the
future so now we start moving from
analog approval to become a online
construction permit approval from 45
days we can use it 14 days but long ways
to go so something like that we can use
AI to improve our productivity you know
and I think we have another private
sector they call uh they call act AI so
they use AI to investigate all the
biding of our project and they can see
the discrepancies in price in something
that not is like fishy thing you know
and they can detect the problem so I
think fraud detection tool you can use
AI to go through data comparing and see
the problem so this this uh AI helps a
lot in improving transparency of our
buiding project in Bangkok right
management I think we have one
application very interesting because
traffy Fu the name mean nothing but it's
a simple app that people can use to take
picture of the problem in the city and
then comment yeah maybe comment complain
maybe like oh come and fix this problem
have been there for three years you know
and this the P the picture the GPS you
know exactly what location is it and
with a comment the AI can read and know
which department it belongs to so the
problem send directly to the people
responsible so don't go to through me
they go directly to my team and they
have to fix it because it's there I know
how long has the problem been there and
how long it has not been solved and with
this data it really improve our
management you know the first day like
20,000 complaints come to this website
and they crash over computer but now so
far we have 800,000 complaints and we
fix 100 640,000 of them without me
ordering anything so this are power of
digital and AI also help that right and
then you can know exactly what problem
are there fot Path Road Safety traffic
and then you classify and then you can
do your budget better next year because
you know what's the problem people need
to be
fixed and usually we take the first
month it take like two two months to
solve one problem and after 2 years it
took only two days now to solve one
problem so you can see productivity
improve without any budget more budget
spend because application is free and
the budget for fixing is already there
but
faster we doing some health care right
we do 1 million people heal check up
right now so we have big database of
people in Bangkok and this database can
be we can use AI to analyze the problem
and maybe do more preventive care so
this data set is now available you know
to of the health of the Bangkok people
and you can know exactly each district
what problem they have so can identify
the problem and then we can spend our
budget properly on maybe on the
preventive
thing Mobility big problem right I mean
you in Bangkok you know we are notorious
for traffic jam um but I mean in this
location not bad because you have BTS
Like connecting but that's a big problem
so we have about 500 intersection in
Bangkok oh control manually by the
police so police see okay traffic G
pushed red green yellow but now we're
going to use AI to help improve the flow
so installing like 72 intersections so
they like using adaptive control look at
the data the traffic and then put the
light on uh properly according to the
demand so this might help improve the
traffic a little bit so you can see like
10 to 30% improve by using technology
for the traffic control and then
in the future we will expand that to all
500 intersections we
have and for the safety if you walk in
Bangkok you can see many motorcycle
riding on pesan way big bad behavior you
know but that's what Ty behavior is so
we're using camera to detect AI to
detect the the license plate and then we
issue the fine to them so we we hope
that this be help improve the behavior
by using the AI technology educ we try
to cooperate with Google improving the
capacity of the classroom so I think in
the future AI I I don't think it's I
think the problem with viia you still
need people right so not artificial
intelligence but intelligent assistant
so we try to use AI as our IIA and one
one one reminder I'm not sure is there
any Supreme AI you know is there any
Democrat Ai and Republican AI get up is
what the data you feed them right for
example I ask them is a Chaat the good
governor and they can cannot provide me
answer so I think you have to be careful
too because at the end emotion and then
there are database what you train them
to you know so that I'm sure that there
are certain questions that AI cannot
answer and me people have to decide so
let them be our good tools to improve
the cities thank you very much
[Applause]