so today I would like to uh
finish the first part by saying a few
more uh words about exergies and um the
allocation problems so that it's going
to be also useful for the
homework and and remember
that one of
the things that we have touched upon is
heating bul
flow for example heating water from
condition one to condition
two which therefore requires by the
energy balance H an energy which is
given by the fluoride
times the change in the enthalpy of the
flow that
maybe uh understood that or cold heat
even if it is a bit improper because
that is a it's not really a heat
interaction or at least it is a heat
interaction at multiple temperatures as
the temperature changes from one to two
here nevertheless if
we agree on on the meaning we can call
it heat and then the the coefficient of
performance
of for example in this case a heat
pump that provides that heat by
taking the necessary entropy from the
environment because in order to heat up
and also need to provide
entropy and uh if I take it from the
environment I avoid uh uh having a
generation by
irreversibility uh the machine needs
some work to
operate and the ratio between the Heat
and the work that are provided is called
the
cop so the cop plays the role of the
first low efficiency but it can be
higher than one so we call it cop we
don't call it
efficiency it's a ratio of two energies
whereas the second low efficiency is the
ratio you can cast it as
either the actual cop over the maximum
cop which you would obtain if the
Machinery was
reversible or you can cast it as the
ratio of the
exg change uh or the exergy that you
have provided to your bulk flow over the
exergy of the resource that you have
used in this case uh
work we have also seen that this combin
if
I take H2 minus H1 * m dot outside of
the parenthesis I and I recognize that
it we called it
QA the the remainder is a is a Carno
coefficient
looking
combination that if we Define uh H2
minus H1 over S2 minus S1 as the
logarithmic mean temperature or the
equivalent heat temperature that
provides the same ratio of energy and
entropy then it's you can write it you
can write it this way
and here you recognize that QA over W is
cop so the second low efficiency is
given by cop times the car
coefficient and what is the maximum
cop well the maximum
cop is when the second low efficiency is
equal to one 100% reversible
Machinery so you set this equal to one
and therefore cop Max is the inverse of
that caral
coefficient so we also played with some
numbers because this is an important
topic and it is a way in which we
consume a lot of uh energy so if we want
to improve our uh ways of using uh fuels
or any other uh exergy
resource uh
natural
resource for example nuclear and solar
and so on we want to
um know the uh efficiencies and so here
is a we gave an example of heating water
in an industrial uh uh setup typical
numbers could be from 60 to 120°
C and then if we compare compute that
carau
ratio and remember that here also we
need we need to make explicit uh the
Assumption of the environment that we
have available when we compute that
because that makes a lot of difference
especially for small
temperatures and um temperature
differences so here for example if I
take
300K here's the number the carau ratio
is 17.2%
and it's inverse which is the maximum
cop for the heat
pump therefore is
5.8 okay so 5.8 means that I spend one
unit of one kilowatt hour of
energy and I deliver 5.8 kilowatt hours
of energy to my stream
if I go to lower temperatures like in
Residential Heating from 20 to 60° at
the same environment
300K which which is like summertime
because it's 27 degrees C uh in that
case the Caro coefficient is
4% so you take the inverse of 4% it
gives
25 right so that means that in in
principle if you had a reversible heat
pump with 1 kilow of electrical energy
you provide 25 kilowatt hours of
heat whereas in
a electric boiler for one kilowatt hour
of energy you provide one kilowatt hour
of heat or maybe a little less because
maybe some is lost to the insulation of
the
boiler okay
then we also argued that
uh the current way in which we use fuels
namely burning them in a flame and then
using the hot products of combustion to
heat up a working fluid of some uh
thermal
cycle if we want to improve of that that
the efficiency of this and go beyond the
current says 64% which is obtained as
the product of an about 75% efficiency
of the combust of the flame and an 85
perc efficiency of the thermal
cycle you need to improve on these two
efficiencies but even if you improve the
thermal cycle to 100% you still stuck to
the limit of s 75 say 80% for the
flame and we've said we've seen that
history tells us that uh we are on our
learning process heading towards higher
efficiencies than uh
80% and so the only way we can reach
them is to find alternatives to the
combustion in
Flames the oxidation of of the fuel in
flames and we also said that when we do
chemical reactions and combustion in a
little more detail we will see this
diagram and we will see that the flame
goes this way and generates entropy by
reversibility whereas if you uh are uh
like in a fuel cell or more uh um um
able to
control uh the process and while the
system spontaneously wants to go from
fuel to products of combustion you
manage to to extract also some energy
like in the fuel cell then you may
reduce the entropy produced by
reversibility and your efficiencies can
be
higher like in some examples
here okay so
usually separate production of
electricity we produce
electricity in power uh in facility
power plants that use our
fuel and remember we said that the for
the moment but also for typical
applications it is fair to um
approximate the exergy of the
fuel by its uh heating volume so energy
and exergy content are very similar of
the order of plus or minus 2% depending
on the hydrocarbons so this is a is a
fair approximation in practice so you
use this fuel you burn it you obtain
these products of combustion and then
you transfer the heat from the product
of combustion to uh
um working fluid of the thermal cycle
then of course the product combustion
must be
exhausted to the
atmosphere and as we all know we are all
concerned about uh pollution that comes
from these
exhausts U not
only the
global
uh pollutant uh CO2 carbon dioxide
um which is pollutant only in terms of
playing a role in greenhouse effect as
we all know uh but also other products
of combustion like
uh
nox so the
various oxides of
nitrogen which can produce acid rain and
other various effects
so you need to control what gets out
there and typically what gets out
there H is uh at
relatively high
temperature say maybe 110 140 de
Celsius um this is when you don't
want the water that is in the produ of
combustion to
condense that is to avoid because some
fuels have some sulfur content and uh
water with sulfur makes um sulfuric acid
and
that's uh corrosive and you want to um
avoid that
but um you can
also have condensation so you if you you
can uh use higher level
materials uh that can sustain uh
corrosion you can also uh condense part
of the water that is produced by the
combustion process in that
case you extract a little more uh
energy and then we talk instead of a
lower heating value it's actually you're
exploiting getting closer to the higher
heating value or somewhere in in between
we'll see some details about this but
here the idea is that this energy is
transferred to this to this thing and to
this working fluid and then the thermal
the thermal cycle provides uh
work and of course since you're are
extracting not only energy but also
entropy the thermal cycle must
discharge uh that entropy to the
environment which is uh at the moment
still considered a a sort of a a
free way of getting rid of of of
entropy although some some places we
talking about of course you need
authorization to do that so that is
equivalent to uh not being exactly uh um
for free not anymore in other words we
we cannot use the environment as a as a
as a thermal dump
uh for for free
anymore okay first low efficiency here
we have only one product which whose
energy content is w and only only one
uh uh energy source
which is the fuel which energy content
is
Q so that's the first low
efficiency and typical for first low
efficiencies as we said uh could be yes
the best available technology could be
maybe
65% uh but the average um the average
efficiency of like a
national um lot of of U of power plants
uh well it varies from country to
country of course for example I think
that in Italy is between 42 and
45% the second low efficiency is the
ratio of the exergy of the product to
the exergy of
your uh
fuel now considering that the exit can
be approximated to the energy of the
fuel you see that for this particular
case the second low efficiency is equal
to the first low
efficiency so indeed if you are at 65%
the 65% the margin for improvement is 35
you still have you only have 35 to go to
get
100% And remember that second low wise
100% is not impossible it's the upper
limit it's what you would have for a
reversible
Machinery okay so the message is here
that for this particular case AA 2 is
equal to AA 1
approximately now when we instead of
producing electricity we want to heat up
some something for example here simple
case of eating up
a room at some um fixed temperature or
maybe heating
up uh water to make it boil at some
temperature for
example here 120° some pressurized uh
steam production which is very common in
industrial processes for for M material
processing and so on
okay so now the first low efficiency is
the ratio of the heat that you
produce that you deliver so this is your
final
product H over the uh energy of the
fuel the second LW efficiency instead is
the ratio of the exergy of that heat so
it's the heat multiplied by the caror
coefficient
divided by the
xgy then again we use the approximation
that the XG is equal to the uh energy
content of the fuel and therefore we
recognize this ratio here is AA one so
in this case the second low efficiency
is equal to the first low efficiency
times the Cal
coefficient so for example if you want
to produce steam
120° in unit environment at
283 uh you compute and you have
a a
boiler that consumes for example natural
gas and it is
95% first flow efficient so ETA one is
95% it means that only 5% is lost to the
flu gases uh through the stack and that
means so you got 95% times the Caro
coefficient here makes about
27% so that in that
case the margin for improvement is much
higher like
73% to go to
100 in some sense we should say that if
this is a representative of
our uh typical way of heating up water
in industrial processing by using
fuels uh the fact that uh for this
technology we are only 27% whereas for
power production we are 65% means that
we are at different levels of maturity
of this uh uses of
uh natural resources for these two
different
Technologies and
products most of the times
we many times the the burner doesn't
have to heat up something at constant
temperature like when you boil something
but uh needs to heat up uh for example
water again for residential purposes
typical number numbers are from 20 to
60 and so here are these uh again we
have uh that since the temperature is
changing here we can define a
logarithmic mean
temperature which is the temperature
that enters in the Carno
coefficient and again the second low
efficiency is equal to the first low
efficiency times the caral coefficient
and uh
the typical number varies depending on
what temperature T not you uh choose so
depending on whether you
are winter or
summer so for example if you are in the
summer 255° C is 29
298k uh
residential a residential domestic um
boiler which has an efficieny Co about
85% first
LW gets a second low efficiency of just
4% winter
time if outside is at 0 degrees Celsius
freezing then it's
11% for an industrial boiler the
efficiency is a little better first low
efficiency let's say 95%
and if you go
from uh yeah okay maybe this is not to
this this should be a 60 probably these
numbers I think I did that for from 60
220 well check the numbers if you
interested and uh it it gives 12 12
12% in the summer and 19% for second low
efficiency during the winter
so there
are ample margins of
improvement and one of them is
cenation as we
said produce with that fuel electricity
and then
use your low temperature uh uh
need uh low temperature heat that is
needed uh to as a as a for
entropy and therefore this becomes a
second product or say a
byproduct the second low efficiency then
has at the numerator the exergies of the
two
products work for the exergy of the work
of the electricity and heat times its
Carno coefficient for the exergy of the
heat divided by the the
fuel and
again uh this is the same thing
uh where we highlight that the
temperature uh if the temperature of
what you're heating is changing you need
to put in the the logarithmic mean
temperature
you can also
do um the same kind of calculations for
refrigeration because often in in
industrial processes but also in air
conditioning residential air
conditioning you need
to cool down for example air
conditioning you need to cool down a
working fluid between 12 and 7 from 12
to 7° C
typical so you have you can define a
coop of the
refrigeration which is the heating load
so the heat that it takes away from the
working
fluid divided by the work that you have
spent in order to run the Machinery
typically
compression
uh cycle a refrigeration cycle but not
not
necessarily uh and then you um so this
is the cop the second low
efficiency is uh well you can view this
as minus QC times the Caro
coefficient and again the second low
efficiency therefore is the cop times
the caral
coefficient and for typical values
I mean for an industrial refrigerator
for which the cop is about five which is
relatively
High it means that you spend one
kilowatt hour and
extract 5 kilowatt hours of heat from
from from the
cooling as a cooling effect so
five you multiply by the coral
coefficient for those temperatures at a
an outside temperature of uh what is it
30°
C and you get a second low efficiency of
36% not
bad at least compared with heating it it
seems that with cooling we're doing
better in fact machinery for cooling is
a you know the same as the Machinery
that we use for heat pumps it requires
more uh investment more materials and
it's more sophisticated than just a
plain burning something and uh using a
heat
exchanger
now people have tried
also the simultaneous combined
production of power
heat and cooling it's called three
generation you have three
products and
um it's actually you can actually this
is this considers also the the fact that
you may have you that you may use as
a possible resource oh no no sorry this
is the this is the cooling effect okay
this is the cooling effect uh
and so this uses as as a resource only
the
fuel and therefore you have three um you
have three um
products and here is one of the of the
problems it's not so easy to
Define
uh first low
efficiency because you have
you have to put the
enumerator apple and or C you have to
put um heat
work and cooling so so they don't uh
they're different U uh animals and uh
they shouldn't stay together in a
numerator but you could Define separate
efficiencies provided we have have a way
to allocate the fuel
consumption and assign a fraction of
it for each of the
products which is the idea
of this uh allocation that we now
getting uh to refresh
again so
the you see
every local area that could be a nation
for example here I put some numbers and
the flag for Italy and if you're
interested in if you have a preferred
country you can do this table it would
be interesting in any case to
search
uh and to see for example for separate
production
one thing is to to consider what it is
the average uh National
efficiency uh and one is the efficiency
of the best available
technology and then you have the same
for Combined heat and
power and you can do also the same for
when you hybridize
your uh use of resources by using some
that are fossil fuels and some that are
um renewable
resources and of course each line is for
what product you are interested in so
electric
power uh residential
heat uh winter
summer industrial heat Cooling
and so
on yeah the list is is long because
energy product in you could also
consider the prod the the production of
materials for example aluminum is a very
from from the or is boyon whatever it is
you uh is is a very energy consuming uh
process and so talking about
efficiencies is important and also doing
a
cogeneration uh is also a way to save
energy so use better our natural
resources and for each one of these uh
Technologies or or or products Energy
Products we can also
study where we are in the learning curve
and as you as you be seen this is the
learning curve for power
production if we did the learning curve
for a heat we would be uh just about uh
here between 10 and
20% uh cooling is between 20 and 30 so
so the curves will be
shifted and
probably uh also
the characteristic time could be
different but in any case you see it's
not in the m in a matter of uh just a
few
years it requires many years to mature a
technology so that also as car message
that if you are in the
energy uh business or if you
want uh to listen to a politician you
have to be
careful because nobody can promise
results in short
times okay so that's another interesting
story so that brings us to the uh
problem of allocation as uh
so we have already
discussed in a CO generation
facility it amounts to defining these uh
coefficients Alpha that are the
fractions of the fuel that we think are
used for the two products that we assign
to the two products and we've seen that
uh this assignment is a
bit arbitrary there is no law of physics
that tells us how to do it
and each one has its pros and cons and
uh
um uh in particular in order to evaluate
these you it is interesting to see this
primary Energy savings because
cogeneration does uh allow you to reduce
the the overall fuel consumption then uh
if you did it in separ production
facilities so there is savings and the
problem of these Alphas is how you
allocate that those
Savings of to the two products heat and
work and once you have chosen those
Alphas you can Define the
cops uh and the partial efficiency of
your work and of your heat production
and as we said uh
this uh topic all
started when the cop of heat production
became important in determining the
Energy Efficiency of
buildings which in turn determines the
value of these
buildings so this has an economic uh
impact and uh this incremental
electricity centered allocation method
which was
uh uh assigning all the energy savings
to the production of
heat is what triggered
the
uh
the the need to do something better
because
that is
unfair with respect to uh other people
who would produce heat uh by just
burning the
fuel so typically one would uh uh Define
this
reference efficiencies for um the
separate production
facilities defined by some
Authority and then uh Define this
coefficient of allocation as the
weighted sum of what I would consume to
produce that same amount of electricity
and
in in a in separate production
facilities at least this method has the
advantage to uh
split
evenly the primary Energy savings
between the two
products so if I say 20
% I
assigned a 20% Improvement to the
efficiency of work and a 20% Improvement
to the efficiency of
heat
um the people that are really fond of
thermodynamics and would like to solve
every problem with
thermodynamics uh insisted for a while
that you should use the exergy
method which takes as
reference the reversible process because
after all that
is the ultimate Target that we should uh
be um heading
towards uh however the problem is that
as we've seen in the learning curve
heat and
work uh technologies have not the same
level of maturity and therefore we are
the the the the the distance of where we
are from where we could be with a
reversible Machinery which is the exergy
target uh is very different like maybe
35% uh for electricity and uh maybe 80%
or even more for
heat and this makes uh
uh this makes giv again gives too much
advantage to the heat because the the
weight with which uh the Energy savings
would be split between work and heat
would would be proportional to that uh
uh margin of
improvement and in
fact if we look at the numbers for this
example
here we find that uh we we you would
have a
cop of
200 which is better than the
350 of the electricity centered
method but in a more realistic uh uh
with more realistic uh
reference
efficiencies you would
have much more
reasonable numbers I mean lower numbers
like 92 maybe
96% for the cop of residential in this
District heating which which is good
because it's better than say the typical
85%
uh and also uh it gives a a a more more
fair
split uh between work and
heat now
uh the homework doesn't call you to um
to do anything about this method of
local area because that is not yet been
uh accepted or Incorporated in any of
the standards it's just an
idea and
um nevertheless it's interesting
[Music]
to to say that essentially what the
local Authority should uh uh use
according to our suggestion
is um as reference
efficiencies the average efficiencies of
the local area including the the
combined heat and power uh production
facilities that
way if your combined
uh U
facility is like in this
case uh more more
efficient than the reference
then it
deserves some incentive or at least clap
uh uh
because they're doing better than the
average in the local area so one
Criterion also
for either giving incentives or giving
authorization to to make a new uh Power
Plant is so that it meets uh higher
efficiency so it highers it has a higher
efficiency than the average and
therefore in turn it will higher the uh
average uh efficiency of the area so
that would be beneficial for
everybody the converse is when we do a
hybrid power
plants and in this
case we are we are using uh in this
paper just not a Coen generation but
just power production only Power
production and instead of using just
fuel you use fuel and integrate that
fuel with some renewable like solar
energy or vice versa instead of having
just a renewable just solar energy
heating um Power plant like those power
plants with mirrors that we have
uh said the other the other the other
day and you can look it up there are a
few prototypes in California in Spain in
Italy and probably other places too
um
nevertheless the fact that um of course
solar energy is not always available and
there for uh you need to either make
some storage in order to have it
function continuously or you could
integrate with fuel for when um to to
compensate when uh there are clouds or
or or nighttime so there is no solar
energy uh available in this way you may
have advantages both from the point of
view of efficiency
so it's more stable uh
uh input for your power plant and also
for the cost because the investment is
going to be uh diluted over more hours
of
operation so it is important in these uh
case also to determine
these fractions
the
betas the fractions of
um of the
product that can be understood as
being the product of the fossil or the
product of the renewable
part so if I could identify what
fraction of the electricity produced is
considered renewable this would be at
the same level as say
photovoltaic
uh energy because it's photovoltaic
energy is
a is a like a separate
production from solar to uh
electricity and so there is no reason
why if the country decides to um give an
incentive to photovoltaics
why there's no reason why they shouldn't
give also an incentive to a hybrid
facility at
least in uh in as far as the uh fraction
of electricity that is recognized as
renewable
because in the
end it turns out that these facilities
hybrid facilities
have higher uh slightly higher uh
efficiencies than photovoltaics so if
photovolatic is like 15%
efficient uh these facilities may may go
over
15% and so it is it may be a better way
of
using solar energy for electricity
production so also
here uh at
the
uh beginning people thought of uh
assigning all the benefit of the
hybridization to the uh renewable
aspect but then this would be
unfair
because this power facilities would
hybrid facilities would uh would get the
in incentives even if they don't deserve
it because part of the savings that is
made by the hybridization it should also
go to the U fossil line of the power
plant so also
here a reasonable way is to use a
reference
production so it it would be uh the
the waited the
um the
fraction of what
the of how
much uh electricity you would
produce with that fuel in a separate
production
facility and the other is uh how much
electricity you would use would produce
in a solar
facility and these weighted ratios are
balanced but of course somebody has to
Define what reference efficiencies to
use and
again there is this consideration of uh
the xergy method that
uh would um provide
like
100% as
the target the reversible uh
Target and 93% for the reversible Target
in uh the conversion of solar energy
into uh
electricity uh
but these targets are very far from the
actual level of uh
average efficiencies and therefore it is
dangerous to use those as uh references
it is better to use as
references something fixed or again
something based on a local area so the
average
values of the
uh partial efficiencies in the in the
local
area so that again also
here you could argue that uh who
deserves the incentives the economic
incentives are only those who improve
somewhat to the average uh usage of
those resources in in the local area
so for the
numbers here there is an
example yeah I think I skipped one uh
one I I removed one slide in which would
saying oh yeah here it is the the the
separate
production uh for
solar that is typically say average of
of today for photovolatic is
15.3% and the and here we use the 38% M
maybe we could have put also 42 maybe
also 45%
today for the separate production of
electricity from fuels okay now here's
this the the hybrid
facility and these numbers
Define the relative role of of hybrid
production in the local area for example
this says that over of the overall
electricity
45% is a hybrid and
10% is separate solar so like
photovoltaics and
then by
using this um self
tuned
average
local uh separate local production
references here's the is the numbers
it's for example it would say that this
hybrid
facility improves the efficiency of
production from solar from 15% to
18.7% the exergy method would have said
that the Improvement is to
35% giving therefore a lot of credit and
therefore very high incentives and the
the the fuel center the even
higher so
nonsense so if you happen to end up
working in one of these
agencies that
Define regulations and that keep
following um
the the evolution of local areas and the
improvements uh you have to be aware of
avoiding
uh wrong numbers that would uh uh
change the direction of uh Technologies
or
investments in
in not where you want it to be
going so because these numbers and in
particular the lows
that determine incentives based on these
numbers determine the choices of the
companies in where to invest in what
okay all right so with with this I think
I have
um said a little more about uh this
problem of allocation and uh if you
still have some questions maybe this is
the time for for the homework for
example maybe this is the time to
ask uh if it is all clear then okay in
any case if you need help I'm available
in the office just email me and we we
can set up an appointment or just uh
chat by
email
okay yeah because
now I want to move to the second part of
the
course this was an initial slide you
remember where we said uh in the second
part of the course we're going to de
deal with chemical potentials and multi
constituent uh
systems so in part we have
already
discussed uh because these are stable a
lot of of of these is is played with a
stable equilibrium States and we said a
lot about the properties of stable
equilibrium States and in
fact in the next
uh uh few slides I'll just uh which are
full of
formulas as usual
um I'll just
um review quickly what the things that
we've already said that are uh relevant
to the applications that uh then we want
to need to we want to focus
on uh next
so this part is uh divided into three
other
parts the first one is defining
properties of
mixtures
in single phase
so we'll have to talk about partial
properties Define what what they are
Define some ideal mixture and here I
should also add another uh topic which
is ideal solution U
Behavior we will talk about osmotic
pressure we will talk about the minimum
work uh from for SE separation
of a mixture into its
components or the maximum work that you
can extract from
mixing if you don't do it irreversibly
and then um yeah osmotic pressure and
the so-called blue energy and then also
the problem of
stratification uh so what's the
composition in the air at various
Heights then there will be a second part
that will will deal
with liquid Vapor equilibrium or say two
phase States for
mixtures and the third part which deals
with systems or mixtures with chemical
reactions most of it is covered is is
still covered sorry is covered by the
book here
so here is
a dense summary of things that we have
seen you remember we defined uh these
characteristic uh functions starting
from the fundamental relation of the
stable equilibrium
States and Performing the lendra
transform of some of its variables or
all of its variables we defined
alternative ways of describing the
properties of stable
equilibrium and among these we uh thisan
transforms we defined the F which is the
elol free energy G which is the Gibs
free energy H which is the enthalpy and
and the EU which is the oiler free
energy they're all
related like this of
course
uh where you
see
this that means
the summation of the products of the
various constituents so we
already set
up for dealing with
mixtures it is also this uh Oiler uh
free
energy is a function of temperature
pressure and chemical potential so that
means that you can measure it
by uh uh
appropriate Mutual equilibrium of your
mixture with an appropriate environment
of which you know the temperature the
pressure and the chemical
potentials because essentially the value
of the oil g g oil free free energy of
your uh mixture
depends only on
that
so once you fixed your Reservoir in a
completely open situation in which the
system can exchange uh energy therefore
temperature equality with the reservoir
pressure I'm sorry volume therefore
pressure in equality with the reservoir
and it can exchange also all
constituents with your Reservoir so the
all the chemical potentials of your
system for each substance must be equal
to the chemical
potential of the reservoir of the
corresponding
substance and so that provides ways to
uh do these measurements of these Oiler
function of course the oiler function is
important as we emphasized the force
systems it's also important for large
systems because for large systems it is
identically equal to zero as we as part
of the result of the uh simple system
model in which we have seen that the
um refraction effects at walls are uh
not in important and therefore for
example the work associated with to in
placing a partition into in your
system or the entropy uh prod produced
by reversibility if you remove a
partition become negligible for large
amounts and uh and so in that
case since the uh Oiler uh free energy
is related as we have seen to that work
and to that irreversibility
of uh placing or removing uh
partitions uh that that in the limit of
large number of particles that goes to
zero and G and that gives rise to the
so-called I mean the what is known as
the oiler
relation and also
if you subtract the differential of the
oiler relation from the Gibs relation
which is the differential of the
fundamental relation you get this other
relation
between differentials that is called the
Gibbs doem
relation which we already used when we
did the for example the Gibs phase rule
now the various forms the
various differentials of this of the
fundamental relation or
the or
the transforms of it elal GS enthalpy so
these expressions for the
differentials are useful in in order to
identify just by
inspection uh what are the natural
variables of these uh of these functions
so for energy the natural for the energy
form of the fundamental relation the
natural variables as we know are s
entropy volume and the amounts of
constituents and the amounts of
constituents can be written in terms of
mole fraction
this
way and
also Again by inspection you can
infer
immediately what the partial derivatives
of this function are with respect to the
various natural variables for example T
is the partial of e with respect to S
minus p is the partial of e with respect
to V the chemical potential and this is
important is when viewed this way is the
partial of e with respect to
n and
being a derivative of this function
here it is viewed as a function of s of
the same variable
svnn then you do the same also for
example for the say let's go down here
to the Gibs free
energy the Gibs free energy
has this form of the differential so you
identify its natural variable as being
temperature pressure and the
amount and the partial
derivatives minus s is the partial of G
with respect to
T volume is the partial of G with
respect to pressure the chemical
potential is the partial of G with
respect to
n and this way the chemical potential
is viewed as a function of TP
andn it's the same chemical potential we
talking about the same system in a
stable equilibrium state but you can
view the chemical potential as function
of different
variables because the game of the lendra
transformation is to change
from uh not readily measurable variables
like the entropy to more readily
variable measurable variable like
temperature pressure or for the free for
the emal free energy temperature and
volume the
enthalpy doesn't gain much because it
still has the entropy there but the
enthalpy is is important for bulk flow
interactions and that's why uh we keep
it in uh in play
now of course this is that
summation but when we have a single uh
substance so when we have a pure
substance we have this same uh set of
equations this is valid in general so
including small
systems it's the same as two slides
before only that uh we we've
written uh this as simply mu and N only
one
substance oh you could call it one one
or actually
here we are going to use the double
subscript as a convention
to um denote pure substance so if you
see a double Subs subscrip it means we
are referring to pure that
constituent okay so in the larger um
number of particle limits so the simple
system approximation applies
and we still have the oiler
relation the GS the DM relation
simplifies and can be be viewed as a
essentially the
differential of the chemical
potential of the only substance that we
have so you see that the chemical
potential is a
function of T and
P let's see uh yeah uh here I think I
made a
mistake in these
um let's see in the limit in the large n
limit uh the chemical potential
loses its dependence on the amounts like
okay here it is written
correctly
okay oh yeah okay here I did take it
away fine
uh so the chemical potential is
not an
independent property once you fix the
temperature and the pressure chemical
potential is a function of tnp so that
fixes also the chemical
potential whereas for a
mixture the phase rule depending on
uh how many phases you have coexisting
and so
on some chemical potentials can be
changed
independently not for the pure
substance and in fact if you have for a
pure substance two phases you have one
relation like this for one phase like
liquid and another relation like this
for the vapor and if if they
coexist the two must be
equal and therefore not uh uh
temperature and pressure are not even
any more uh
independently variable like when you
have a single
phase
okay we will see that chemical
potentials play an important role for
mixtures because they determine the
properties and they also play an import
important role in determining the
condition for Mutual
equilibrium so they are really our
Focus for the pure substance
notice that due to the oiler relation
the chemical potential is also
equal to the specific Gibs free energy
so the Gibs free energy per unit
mole like
see uh
G
is capital G Over
N now in
uh the uh simple system
model for a mixture so this is the
simple system
model G is equal to that
summation when you have only
one that summation becomes just one term
and therefore you see that the
uh if you take G
so it's new1 one And1 one divided by
let's let me put one one
here so that's new so that proves that
in that case that gives a free energy uh
molar so that's G11 is equal to
mu11 only for a p substance
okay so how do we measure
properties well in order to
measure we will see that we said that
the chemical potentials are Central
because they determine the for example
the
Gibs free energy which is a legan
transform of this of the fundamental
relation and therefore you can extract
all the information from from it of
course if you know it as a function so
you need to know not just one value you
need to know how it varies with
temperature pressure you need to know
all this function in order to
characterize your your your
mixture and the chemical
potentials are uh the key of the game
and the way you can measure
them is by a a manometer by measuring
the partial
pressure so you need to
develop uh rigid semi-permeable
membranes capable of keeping the
molecules all molecules in the mixture
except one
inside the mixture and allowing only
some the molecules of one type to cross
once you have identified a membrane like
that you just wait
for Mutual equilibrium to to to occur
and then measure this partial pressure
and then as you
remember the condition for Mutual
equilibrium is that the chemical
potential of constituent I in the
mixture must be equal to the chemical
potential of the constituent on the
other side of the membrane through which
that substance can be uh can
flow and we call partial pressure that
pressure at which that occurs the
pressure of the pure system that uh so
that that's the meaning of the double
I and so this
equality makes uh um
the yeah okay here I kept because for
small systems you also have this
dependence even for uh the pure
substance but for large uh
amounts that
drops and then you see that the you can
solve this equation and
evaluated the partial pressure as a
function of the other variables which is
temperature pressure and the amounts in
the
mixture uh and the amount in this uh
small syst in this pure system on the
other side of the membrane but the the
the absolute amounts drop out for large
n so that dependence is only through the
uh relative comp
position of your mixture so the
percentages of how much how many
molecules of each type I have in my uh
mixture and again
here I
use this relation which is also
important uh to remember namely that
therefore
for large gen the chemical potential of
the constituent in the mixture is equal
to the chemical potential of the pure
component evaluated at the temperature
and the partial pressure of the mixture
and the chemical potential of the pure
component is given by the Gibs free
energy and the Gibs free energy if you
remember is also written as H minus
TS so what we are saying is that can
chemical
potential of component in the mixture
can be written as
this but since this is G it can also be
written as
H
uh I'm sorry this is new i h i t at the
partial pressure minus t s i t
P
okay and
this with double I are the properties of
the pure
substances so a good part but not
all uh of the properties of the mixture
are determined by the properties of the
P the few components
in fact we will uh Define
some behaviors that we will call
Ideal which are simplified version
simplified models in which all of the
properties uh of the mixtures of the
mixture are
determined uh by the properties of the
pure
components that is a is not to say
that the most most real mixtures are not
ideal in the sense that we will try to
Define uh but the ideal mixture model or
the ideal solution
models uh are a good
start and
then the typical procedure is that to
start with ideal description then since
my actual mixture uh depart from
ideal you
describe the departure from
ideal We call we going to call those
excess uh
properties now a first step towards the
construction of properties of a mixture
from the property of the pure uh
components is to
[Music]
Define I think we already done in yeah
we defined already the partial
properties the way we did
it was to
um okay uh right
the
differential of the
expression that see this mui is
also as we said a function of
TP and the uh the
amounts so we
write the differential of that
and then we use those Maxwell
relations that allows us to for example
this partial derivative of mu with
respect to T which is the coefficient of
DT in this
differential we
recognize that except for the minus sign
is equal
to the second derivative of of of
G so of G of the capital G of the GI
free
energy with respect to T and with
respect to n because the chemical
potential is a partial of G with respect
to n so this
is the second derivative but then due to
the um reciprocity or Schwarz theorem
about second partial
derivatives this can also be viewed as
that you first do the the partial of G
with respect to T and then with respect
to n so the partial of G with respect to
T is minus S as we can see from here
partial of G with respect to T is minus
s so by writing the differentials we go
and do and
watch uh by inspection what these
partial derivatives are but also we
should
remember uh I mean we could remember uh
by heart that the this partial
derivatives at least this and
that in any
case this says how much the entropy
changes if while keeping temperature and
pressure fixed and also the various
amounts I add a little bit of one
substance this is why it takes the name
partial entropy it's the contribution of
that con of of of that constituent to uh
the uh property
of of the
mixture then we do the same we did the
same for this
other partial derivatives which is the
coefficient of the
pressure which is here it can also be
viewed as a second partial derivative of
G
therefore therefore it in this case it's
the partial of the volume with respect
to n so it says how much the volume
changes increases if I add a little bit
of substance I while keeping temperature
pressure and the other constituents
fixed that's called the partial
volume we also
here we
have the expression for the differential
I have to take care also of uh the
different the differentials of the NS
here so I have a summation because I
have many NS I have this partial
derivatives of chemical potential of one
substance with respect to the amount of
another substance
and
the
uh reciprocity of second order
derivatives tells us that there is a
reciprocity in this
relation and for short hand in what
follows I'm going to denote these
partial derivatives as Mu I comma J or
mu J comma I so the comma I
means partial with respect to ni
then
using um for example this is the Gibbs
relation differential of the fundamental
relation uh I can
compute the partial energy of
constituent
I because I can take
formally I mean don't tell the
mathematicians but if I take these
expression here for the for the and I
divide by Del partial n partial n
i uh so I divide through so I so that
becomes that d ided by dni is equal to T
* DS /
dni but that DS divided by dni is the
partial
entropy then I have d V ided by dni
that's the partial
volume and
DN ided by dni is
one dni divided by dni is one so that
leaves me with just uh the chemical
potential it's I mean it's one if the uh
if the I am dividing is the same as the
N if zero if I'm dividing one by the
other
because they are independent and so this
is how we
prove I mean you can do it better but
just this was just sort of a game
because formal sometimes proceeding
formally is helpful to go fast and do
some
checking in any case so this is the
expression for the partial
energy of constituent and you can play
the same game using the differential for
the enthalpy to express the partial
enthalpy of
constituent what is important uh here is
that all these partial properties
entropy volume energy
enthalpy
are
related to the chemical potential you
see the chemical
potential
or partial derivatives of the chemical
potential either with respect to T or
with respect to
P so that
means that if I have this expression
here I can
determine by just mathematical
manipulation all the partial properties
of the constituent in the
mixture okay so from this
one I get
si uh
VI hi I EI
and what do I do with
them
well this next slide is to show that
uh with them you can
compute the properties of the overall
properties of the mixture
so here I do it again for the general
case and then in the uh I look at the
large and
large um number of
particles
limit essentially
we can
take the expression
for the oiler one this is one way of
doing of
course many different ways of getting to
the same result for example in the
book there is no discussion about the
oiler
U free
energy and
so you find a different derivation
starting from just the valid in the
large limit large number of
particles in any
case I start from the um expression for
the oiler relation which is a function
of TP and
new and
then substitute inside the MU here
this expression
here so that it becomes a function of TP
andn and then I
take the derivatives of
um
this with
respect to these independent variables
of course we need to do some chain rule
because here we have a function of a
function so for
example the derivative of EU with
respect to
T gets one contribution from the T that
is here this T
here and that's the derivative with
respect to
T then when I think that the other
variables so so let's say loely speaking
at constant p and constant mu okay so I
put a p and a mu
here plus there is also a
contribution to changes in temperature
through the chemical potentials so that
adds the partial of EU with respect to
the chemical
potentials times the derivative of the
chemical potential with respect to
temperature
okay now it turns out that if we take if
we look at the uh expression for the
differential of the oiler uh free energy
which is this
one by inspection as usual we can
extract the values of the partial
derivatives for example minus s is equal
to partial of uh Oiler
over
temperature volume is the partial of
Oiler over
pressure the amount of
constituent is the negative of the oiler
with respect to the chemical potential
so this partial derivative partial of U
EU with respect to chemical potential of
constituent I while I keep
fixed temperature pressure and the
chemical potentials of all other
constituents is equal to the negative of
the amount of constituents I have in the
mixture so this thing
here is uh minus n
i
Okay then if I look in the previous
slide and I look at the partial of mu
respect to T at constant PN that's minus
s that's negative of uh the partial
entropy so minus and minus cancel
becomes a
plus and so I have uh the summation of
Ni *
SI whereas the first derivative
here is here
it's it's minus S capital S it's the
entropy of the
mixture okay so I just if I now take
this expression and rewrite it here it
says that the entropy
of the overall entropy of my mixture is
equal to the weighted sum of the partial
entropies weighted by the amounts with
which the constituents are present in
the
mixture minus a correcting term that has
to
do with um the oiler
free
energy but if we are not interested in
small systems the oiler free energy is
is zero and so in that limit only the
first
term uh
remains and so we
obtain that if I have these SI with them
I can
compute the properties of my mixture
so I know the entropy of my
mixture and here you can play the same
game also for the
volume me skip
this we can play the same game also with
respect when I do the partial derivative
of Oiler with respect to the amounts of
one of the constituents
if you do carefully the derivatives as
we are doing
here this becomes equal to this
summation which is written here
again and since in the large limit
uh oil is equal to Z to zero identically
it means that this summation is equal to
zero ident identically actually there
are there are as many there is there is
one for each constituent because you
see there is a summation over the
constituents I so I is a dummy index in
within the summation but then there is a
j which is a free so this has to be
equal to zero for every J this is called
the DM
margules
relation and we it will play some
role in uh making sure that when you
develop models you're doing it
consistently for the moment we leave it
there now in the next slide I'm going
to
start from these three so the first
these three lines become the first
lines uh
here
because from these relations I can
prove similar relations also for all the
other properties that we have talked
about energy elol free energy GES free
energy enalia
so that means we can for all these in
and also I can go it can go on to
F
G
H
okay uh I have relations like like
that if I want them for the mixture all
I need to do is play some derivatives of
the chemical
potentials and with the proper relation
I get to the relation to the property of
of the mixture of course I need to also
know the
amounts so I need to know the chemical
potentials how they depend on
temperature pressure and amounts and I
need to know how many I have in my
mixture
yeah I think time is up so we could stop
uh here