I make a joke
that sometimes I feel
like the Sloan Fellows
program, it's the mid-career crisis.
Most of us, we were already doing well.
We had good jobs, good salaries,
good opportunities.
there was no need to come here
to get a good job.
The reason to come here
is to actually have a stop.
To reflect on everything,
reassess, understand
who you are, where you want to be
and how you're going to get there.
During this year,
I have built up much more self-awareness.
I felt like I just didn't know
that much about myself.
You’re just, like, on the go.
You’re just like
keep going then the projects done.
You get one task done after another.
This program
just, like,
helped me to learn
so much more about myself,
my own blindspots.
I had grew
a lot in my career learning by doing.
But I felt that
there was a lot of firefighting
as opposed to a bigger perspective,
a bigger strategy around
how to do things.
MIT is not just being here
and take classes. MIT is
being here and having conversations
with all types of people,
different programs, the
entrepreneurship ecosystem,
the engineering school, the undergrad,
the events.
It's a whole thing.
Being surrounded
by people
that are actually
looking for ways
to change the world
and make the world a better place, it's
exactly what I needed.
It's not just what we’ve
learned over the last 12 months,
but how do you apply that
with the people that you do
daily life with?
How do I take what
I've learned out to my friends,
to my sphere of influence,
to my workplace, to my family?
So that, you know,
I can have an impact on people.
Being here
gave me the opportunity
to learn something I didn't know before.
Change my mindset,
how you spot opportunities,
how you understand the technology
to solve for these, let's say,
big problems in the world
and how to combine that.
Before coming here,
I would have never had that mindset.
For me it was very important
that my MBA was not just about
what I could get from the classroom,
but actually what I could get from people
that were actually more experienced
than me.
The best thing I got out of
this is people.
I have lifelong friends
that I met here that will literally be
my best friends
through the rest of my life.
They come from
such different backgrounds,
such different experience,
but yet they are all so humble
and want to work
and want to make
a good impact on the world.
When I came here
and I started to know people
from literally around the world,
it was amazing
learning how to prepare different dishes
around the world,
how to learn small words
in different languages,
but also the lifestyle
and the way of think and the way of work.
Having this experience of diversity, it’s been
meaningful and helpful for my future.
The most key takeaway
of this whole experience,
aside from the academic
and amazing experience being here at MIT,
is that building of community
and network
that you get to keep
forever, and it's yours.
No one can take that away from you.