so it's great to see everybody uh it's
unfortunate it seems like fall already
arrived here so it's
cloudy but the the river is beautiful I
hope you get a chance to go walk around
um I'm going to talk about what I'm
calling the this infinite Loop um it's
really this uh overall Journey that
we're in and trying to make medicines um
and for us we make molecules just right
right down the street right on the
campus of MIT and we try to do that
where we can make a 100 million
molecules and we can do that in a short
period of time
and the big question now is what do they
all do like can we actually start to
learn from those molecules so that we
can build machine learning models and
then eventually type in a computer and
really interact with it and not just
hallucinate ligans that we hear about
now with Alpha fold and so forth but
actually get drug molecules and the
other big part is of that is how do you
scale how do you actually manufacture
these molecules rapidly how do you get
into animal experiments and so we're
also building digital twins of machines
so that scientists can actually before
they actually go make the molecule you
can actually predict what's going to
happen with high confidence so hopefully
accelerate the pace in which we can
actually hopefully overcome some of
these medical challenges that we all
hear about or experience and so this is
the infinite Loop because it never ends
unfortunately we're never going to be
able to make the number of molecules uh
that are possible so that's 10 to the
power 60 or even greater if you speak to
a theoretician and so we're always going
to be in the cycle of trying to
understand how do the moleculars
molecules actually influence biology and
then go ahead and take that information
and iterate on that and so we just want
to use machine learning to do that in a
much faster uh way I'm also going to
show you that we're able to build
algorithms that actually do things that
humans can't and actually it translates
all the way at least into animal
experiments at this stage and so um this
is a project that emerged actually with
a collaborator uh right right down the
street uh syrea Therapeutics and so they
were one of the first companies to
create a medicine for a disease called
duchan muscular distrophy it's a disease
in young boys where there's essentially
still really no robust cure and
unfortunately they die eventually and so
we've been working on this at MIT for a
long time and a lot of roadblocks it's
just simply a delivery Challenge and so
we asked the question once we ended up
getting enough data and understanding
what's going on can we actually start to
use deep learning to design molecules
that are actually potentially medicines
and so I'm going to walk you through
what we've learned so this devastating
disease du muscular distrophy it's a
genetic disease it actually ends up in
the case that their muscle cells don't
work properly and so in in our bodies
and humans we actually if you exercise
you have more muscle tissue and so forth
um in their case it doesn't even matter
if they exercise they have necrosis
breakdown of the tissue the muscle
tissue where it's overtaken by fat tisue
tissue unfortunately in their teenage
years they simply if your muscles don't
work properly you can't survive and they
unfortunately die and really no
treatments until recently and the
current treatments are are are not very
good they're not ready to really cure
this disease and so why does this
actually happen what's going on at the
genetic level as I mentioned it's in the
DNA it's a mutation in which they don't
actually end up making this protein
called disten it's one of the largest
proteins in our muscle cells in our
bodies it allows them to actually work
and so this protein is it doesn't
function correctly so it's been a major
challenge to figure out how do you
actually come up with a therapy or a
drug gene therapy is starting to look
promising and we're going to walk walk
through that here so you have this
faulty Gene and how how how do you
actually fix it so this is the first
molecule that came online from Serta
it's actually it's it's really
interesting it's it's it's painting a
picture which I think is really really
interesting
it's a molecule called a
phosphorodiamidate morpholino aliger and
I'm showing you a picture of it here and
it's inspired by the properties of DNA
and RNA but what chemists have done is
they've designed it so you actually
can't make it with biological systems
and they did that because they really
wanted to impart more drug-like features
they wanted to remove that phosphate
that's on the backbone that negative
charge so that it's not doesn't get
cleaved rapidly they also wanted to
stabil ized the structure so they went
ahead and changed the ribos ring so that
it actually had a a morpholino what's
neat here and why I really like this
this is the future of medicine it's
going to be completely artificial
biopolymers that are designed to have
really nonimmunogenic behavior and long
lasting and that's what they did here
the challenge is it's 10 kilon so it
faces a a delivery problem it simply
will not cross your membrane of these
muscle cells so we know it's a genetic
medicine if it actually gets into the
nucleus I'll show you it actually can
restore production of this protein by
splicing mechanism and ultimately allows
these cells the function properly so I'm
showing you the dosing it's 50
milligrams per kilogram so this is a
Brute Force molecule that means you need
to give grams IV of infusion to really
get this molecule into those muscle
cells because it's large it doesn't
simply diffuse as we know small
molecules do right what I'm also showing
you here is that it actually works so
you actually if you can get it into
these uh tissues and then do
imunohistochemistry what I'm showing you
in green is someone that's actually
received this molecule and we're looking
for restoration of of that particular
protein so how can we actually improve
this how do we overcome this delivery
challenge so we said okay well let's
just look in the literature and ask the
question are there any off-the-shelf
Technologies or approaches that we at
MIT can just bring in our our our robots
and our Automation and make and try
everything just to really understand if
we can improve this property that we're
Desiring this delivery challenge so
there's a couple things that inspired us
one is that there's these materials that
are called cell penetrating peptides and
so we go ahead and attach them it's
written here as a CPP coant directly on
this anti-sense Olo so now this is in
the artart called a peptide pmo
conjugate these are actually an emerging
area of Medicine
and then we had an animal model it's
called the MDX Mouse and this actually
resembles what occurs in the DMD case
and what inspired is is that you can
actually modify this molecule and you
can go do an animal experiment first off
it doesn't die uh it's safe at least in
mice and moreover you can start to
restore levels of disten to the same
levels of a healthy animal as shown in
Red so that's looking for restoration um
of the particular uh protein um dis
so this is the challenge this is really
the unlock this is the case for mRNA
vaccines this is the case for any
genetic medicine it actually has to get
inside the cell right and so I'm showing
you how this works so in our case we're
going to take this peptide pmo it's
going to get endocytosed as I'm showing
here it has to release from that
biological barrier the endosome so it's
still inh housed within this vesicle and
then eventually even get into the
nucleus that's not as large of a
challenge and in the nucleus it's going
to actually carry out its function which
is going to alter the splicing
mechanisms at the MRNA level and
actually eventually allow you to get
this message RNA that will then produce
the protein so we're going to go ahead
and and look at this and understand if
we can improve this delivery Challenge
and we're doing it with a cell
penetrating peptide we're going to use
an engineered cell line this is one of
the gold standards to understand if
you're actually getting delivery and the
molecule is actually functional
the way it works we call this the egfp
splice correction uh cell and if we in
fact end up in the nucleus as I'm
showing you here we actually have a gene
for egfp that has a particular piece of
DNA in it that actually if we get
hybridization and the right splicing
we're going to turn on fluorescence so
it's a turn on assay so the cells are
more bright they're more green they are
the more they fluores that in theory
should be correlated with how well we
delivered this molecule into the cell so
we went ahead and made everything that
we could find in the literature we just
said we don't we we we want to actually
help solve this problem so we went ahead
and looked at over a hundred different
constructs we tested them all in this
assay and what I'm showing you is fold
change in fluorescence so a lot of those
black dots are actually close to zero so
they didn't have a large effect on
relative to this unmodified pmo to
whereas some of the winners actually
look like they're improving fluoresence
by 20 to 30 fold we thought perhaps we
had something to work with so you go
ahead and dive deep into this and we
learned that polyarginine so it's one of
your amino acids actually was the most
effective at delivering into the cell
the problem with this is from a chemist
perspective we didn't learn anything all
we learn is string together Arginine
residues the same amino acid and that
actually would give you higher
fluorescence now the problem the real
problem is that these polyart
compounds were discovered back in the
1980s and they've never helped solve the
delivery challenge because they're toxic
so what happened is they'll actually gum
up your kidney because they have this
positive charge on the side chain the
ion channels don't function properly and
they also cause Mass cell degranulation
so we had we really had nowhere to go
right we just put in years of work and
we we we didn't learn anything new um
we're still stuck and so we call this a
toxicity and SAR problem and so we said
okay how can we actually get out of this
local Minima so at this time we said
okay we're generating a lot of data we
think biologically we have some core
hypothesis of what we need to actually
go after is it time now for us to
actually use artificial intelligence to
do chemical Evolution right evolution of
drug molecules and what we need is we
need to build a data set as everyone
talks about we need to train a machine
learning model and you'll see we'll
connect it to an Optimizer and
essentially we're going to iterate over
and over again in a computer and then
eventually in the laboratory and the
hope is is that we're going to actually
have molecules that work better than
anything we could have ever designed at
MIT or even at syto
Therapeutics so as I mentioned we always
going to have a data problem so when you
go to do these types of experiments you
need a biological hypothesis that allows
you to establish your data your key
learning so you train a machine learning
model that actually makes sense so over
the years we made one real key
observation
the observation was is that we shouldn't
think about these cell penetrating
peptides in terms of their individual
amino acids but rather as modules and
that if we bring these modules together
they should function
synergistically in other words if you
take one construct and you measure its
full change in this assay as I'm showing
you there the pvec molecule shown in red
very uh small effect in terms of
delivery from that egfp assay if I take
another variant called bpep and I study
that okay it has a little bit of a
better a stronger effect but the key is
that when we cently fuse them together
to make this new cell penetrating muy
actually is not simply additive there's
a multiplier and we call that
synergistic so now the hypothesis is we
need to unlock this overall challenge by
bringing together these modules the
modules that favor endosomal release
association with membranes nuclear
localization and in some combinatoric
fashion we could perhaps have high
efficient delivery and so we went ahead
and made over 600 different designs and
we asked the question from this cell
assay what actually happens do we see
anything that works quite well so 600
different data points you can run this
even on what's called a high throughput
fax experiment so an overnight robot
will run all these egfp sell assays for
you the next day you'll be plotting out
your data and this is what you see you
see a fair spread of constructs actually
um worked okay right 10-fold Improvement
of fluorescence and others had zero
improvement over just unmodified pmo and
a few of them a number of them had
increase activity up to 20 fold so now
in this new world actually and I would
have never have done this in graduate
school 20 years ago um you actually
asked the question will this data be
powerful enough to actually predict what
would have happened in that cell assay
right and so we went ahead and buil a
machine learning model based on those
600 data points all from same conditions
in a Cell assay and then we built what's
called a Triad so we connected the
overall machine learning model that
predicts activity to a generator the
generator scrubed the entire universe of
everything we know about peptides that
may help
permeation and moreover we actually used
some of the key things that we learn to
actually build into this generator like
immunogenicity and other things that you
care about when you make a drug
molecule and lastly we connected it to a
genetic algorithm called an Optimizer in
our case and what that did is that
penalized any of the sequences that
proved to be high activity but say
strings of arginine right we penalized
it if it was very long sequence if it
didn't look like it was going to be
soluble and so forth and now the
computer just runs continuously it can
understand molecules we did Morgan
fingerprints to do this and eventually
it predicts sequences and this is why in
uate school we would work with
computational people and they would come
to us and ask us to make molecules for
them and we would say okay well if I
make that it's going to take a year of
my life how confident are you it's going
to work they're like not very confident
that's why this has all changed is
because we have all these tools now to
really get confident in the molecules
that computers predict and go actually
make them in the laboratory so computers
can understand molecules you have to do
that with a fingerprinting technology
which is called Morgan fingerprints and
essentially you're barcoding each
molecule as you design and then for our
case it's a polymer so you string them
together and you essentially get what
looks like a QR code right and so this
is the fingerprinting of molecules and
it can even be non-natural amino acids
as I'm showing you so that's how the
computer algorithm work through all
these various pieces of data and
actually built this model so it actually
uh predicts many many sequences more
than you can possibly make there
sequences you can't find anywhere here
on Earth in any of the databases they're
built from even even non-natural amino
acids they even come out circular and so
forth and so another challenge is you
got to go make and test some of them are
9.3 kilodalton so 93 amino acids or so
we refer to them as these mock proteins
so machine learning derived many
proteins and we went ahead and go went
and made a batch of them and asked the
question do they actually really work so
the ne thing here is we've actually as I
mentioned built machines that can
rapidly make molecules in this case we
could make these machine learning
derived many proteins in 15 minutes on
these robots that we have it's the
world's fastest machine to make peptides
and proteins and the way it works is you
literally um charge these instruments
usually on a weekly basis and students
and postdocs will type in these
sequences and the Machine will just run
through it you can even make proteins or
machine learning derived constructs um
and so we went ahead and and did that um
and tested a handful of them and lo and
behold the highest performing sequence
that we've ever discovered actually were
discovered with this approach they're
showing in the red box so up to 50-fold
Greater Improvement in that cell assay
better than anything that was originally
tested better than anything that was in
the data set alone and so we're quite
excited about this perhaps you can get
out of these local Minima that we're in
and really design things that at least
will teach you new aspects of delivery
so why is it that the algorithm actually
liked particular sequences over others
so this is a what's called a great
radiant activation map what we're doing
is we're color color coding the yellow
uh monomers or pieces of this polymer
that the algorithm thought was most
activating it turns out that it's
actually even non-natural amino acids so
variance that nature has really never
seen before that's an aminohexanoic acid
why do I show this is because it's not a
a Guess Game for us we can look at this
information then we can go understand
why we can do structural activity
relationship studies change that amino
acid and figure out why is it that it
turned out to be so
important so now we dive deeper we say
we're going to go do animal experiments
from these compounds that were U
discovered with this approach so we do
titrations make sure that they actually
make sense at the cell assay so do a
bunch of different concentrations I'm
showing you that on the left uh plot and
then on the right plot we're asking are
these toxic is it just that we're
permeabilizing the outer membrane and
that's why is you getting better
delivery and so you see a wide
difference in concentrations between a
toxicity and a function and so this is
how we move forward into an animal
experiment so the last big question
you're probably asking me why did we
pick this uh egfp assay turns out
there's an egfp animal so I can
translate and this is the case for
genetic medicines if you solved the
delivery problem you can translate what
you learn in the cell all the way to the
animal and so in this animal it actually
every organ has that same same egfp
construct so we can do a simple tail
vein injection we can wait seven days in
this case extract the organs you can
measure the amount of pmo present and
the amount of egfp and you can start to
understand biodistributions how well are
these molecules getting into these cells
and so forth and you can use this as a
whole another tool for
optimization so we went ahead and took
these constructs did a number of dosing
and actually took out the the tissues
that we care about for DMD quadriceps
diaphragm and heart and actually they
work right they work some of them um at
you know 30 migs per kig and even less
and so um we didn't fully predict that
this would actually translate fully but
in some ways that's why we ended up with
vaccines right from mRNA and the
shortest possible time anyone's ever
made anything that went into a human
it's because the genetic medicines with
solving the delivery problem really do
in fact work so we live in a new space
we do this for many projects all the way
from Li and design and Discovery all the
way into delivery and as I said when we
manufacture molecules even before
synthesis we take these types of
approaches and so from a discovery
perspective we make sure we have a key
biological hypothesis in our case it was
working with a modular library and then
that doesn't uh make us um in this data
limiting problem uh we need quantitative
biological assays and then we need to
understand what kind of machine learning
um are we going to use this changes so
fast even in the Sciences um you know
there's probably a thousand papers about
how to update a machine learning model
every single day now and then we
connected to these Optimizer and triad
systems to really make sure the
molecules that come out are worth going
to spend time in the laboratory and then
Chase all the way to the animal
experiment and I would say using this
approach we've now um cracked the one
Mig per kig injection at animals so
really the most potent molecule we've
ever discovered is advancing in even
into non-human primates using using this
approach so it's a lot of fun and uh
thank you for hearing about one of the
projects we have at
[Applause]
MIT thank you so much um we do have time
for questions um if anyone we're just
going to do it the oldfashioned way
raise your hand and I'll hand you the
mic any questions for
Brad thank you fantastic talk so how
about we we bring in new modalities like
positive liid particles into the CPP so
we can use machine learning and
automatic synesis pipelines to bridge
the two modality together yeah yeah
absolutely so I usually have a group
photo at this at the end if you could
flash it on there because I I just want
to show you a picture of my group
they're great I had like a hundred other
slides so I couldn't make it all the way
to that
but um along those lines yeah so we
basically on that machine I showed you
right you can program in lipidated amino
acids you can program in lipidated
proteins you could even make Polymers of
lipids so um essentially um being able
to rapidly make molecules in an
automated format is in many ways if it's
around polyamid synthesis or even some
lipid chemistry you can do what you just
ask and you can actually build machine
learning models you can do everything
I've just showed you but with completely
different approach yeah so
absolutely yeah this is the the group
these are all the people that do the
wonderful work
so thanks Brad great talk so it's
interesting now to see you're moving
into nhps to see if if there's any
potential toxicity but in parallel what
about M GMP manufacturing of some of
these um peptide constructs yeah um so I
you know one thing that we do at MIT
professors students and posts is we
actually end up launching a lot of
companies
so I do have a company called Amit
Technologies which is are building the
the robots in a GMP environment and so
they they will be made under GMP
conditions absolutely um and you know
it's not you know the peptide
manufacturing has been around for GMP
for a long time but yeah certainly yeah