we present Cleo a real time and task
driven approach to build open set 3D
scene graphs consider the problem of
building a metric semantic map of this
cluttered
cubicle what is the right granularity of
the objects to retain in the map for
instance is a single backpack an object
or is the zipper on the backpack an
object or maybe the two backpack should
be considered together as a single
object should these condiment packets be
mapped as a collective object two
objects for each type or individual
packets should this be a set of
notebooks or three
notebooks the correct scene
representation depends on the
task thus we present Cleo which creates
a task driven 3D scene graph including
task relevant objects and regions given
a set of natural language tasks
provided with these task Creo creates
the following objects for example
grouping the backpacks and condiments as
a collective
object making the task more detailed and
specific induces Cleo to split the map
into multiple objects including single
backpacks or similar types of
condiments given rgbd images Cleo's
front end forms object Primitives
Cleo's back end uses the information
bottleneck to Cluster Primitives and to
Tas relevant
objects task irrelevant objects can be
removed task relevant clusters are added
as objects to
Cleo Cleo similarly clusters places and
task relevant regions with the
information
bottleneck we provide visual results
showing Cleo mapping an office scene in
real time given the following task we
visualize the objects and regions in the
video objects are shown as cubes near
the
mesh places Primitives are shown as
Spears below the room regions they are
clustered
in we also demonstrate Cleo in an
apartment scene again in real time
to demonstrate Cleo at Large Scale we
mapped a five floor building in real
time mapped objects are shown with their
most relevant task
here we run Cleo on board spots laptop
spot first Maps a scene online in real
time then we will perform task execution
in the same session without any
postprocessing of the map
now we give spot a Target object to find
and grasp using
Cleo we run multiple object search and
grass task in total over 20
our code and data sets are open source
check out the attached link to access
them along with our paper thanks for
watching