uh great to be here I'm Dan Stack
co-founder and CEO of electri fire
thermal Solutions uh we're in MIT
spinout I was working here since 2014
under Dr Charles forsberg in the nuclear
energy department and we founded the
company to decarbonize energy uh
industry with electrified Heat and the
market pain point on its face is that if
you are an industrial of really of any
kind you're usually burning fossil fuels
and if you tried to get off of fossil
fuels to something zero carbon you will
find no affordable option um and there's
three main features to this challenge as
we see it the first one is that
electricity zero carbon electricity has
become quite cheap wind power solar
power are being deployed at record
numbers there's two counterpoints to
them however the first one is that
firming that energy is very expensive
that is storing it in a battery for
later you'll easily 10x the cost of that
energy if you want it firm and On Demand
the other challenge is that Industries
are used to heat generally speaking
their heat demands are what dominates
and even if you had a perfect battery it
doesn't put out high temperature heat
for your process it puts out electricity
so how do we take that zero carbon
electricity and make it into a firm heat
Source that's still affordable that's
what we've been doing at electrified
thermal we've been developing the jeel
hiive thermal battery and in essence it
is a box that sits on your industrial
site nearby and it takes in electricity
whenever it makes sense it could be from
solar power wind power nuclear Hydro or
just the grid with those energy sources
on it we take that electricity and we
put out high temperature 24/7 uh gas
high temperature air or other gases that
we flow into your furnace your boiler
your Kiln and we can do the job of
fossil fuels as we do that we can
deliver 1,800 Celsius we're at least
three times cheaper at least three times
cheaper than hydrogen um which
is kind of the de facto answer in a lot
of cases the less hydrogen you need the
happier you will be if you're trying to
decarbonize uh retrofittable we plug
into your process give you a pipe of
high temperature gas into your furnace
into your boiler into your Kiln so you
don't have to radically redesign what
you do to decarbonize what you do and
it's very modular we can build larger or
smaller boxes and we can put multiple on
a site and as I'll show later we also
have other form factors and our vision
is industry electrified by 2045 which is
roughly a$3 trillion Challenge and
opportunity this is what it takes to
transform our uh energy and Industrial
sectors uh this is what we spend on
fossil fuel today in these sectors and
so it's a massive undertaking but we are
aiming the juive thermal battery and the
juive technology to be the engine of the
future that has double digit um Global
percentages of energy flowing through it
by this time and what makes us different
than other approaches to electrified
Heating and thermal storage is roughly
10 years in the making mostly during my
time ATM which is the electrically
conductive fire brick and so as we got
to working on this problem back then we
came to understand that electric heaters
are the bottleneck if you want to
Electrify industry electric heaters were
never designed to replace fossil fuels
and why would they be it didn't make
sense before and so what we did was we
looked at materials that can survive you
know other heaters they oxidize they
burn out they break down they don't last
long enough and they don't go hot enough
um and what we looked at was materials
that can take the heat can run at flame
temps for decades and so we developed
electrically conductive fire bricks I
have one here if you come by my booth
and give me a business card you can hold
it um um and we run electricity straight
through these bricks and heat them up to
Flame temperatures and so what you see
on the screen here is what's inside the
jewel Hive and it's full of these bricks
and regular fire bricks and they can
heat up the flame temps and when you
want the energy back out you just flow
air or other gases straight through the
brick chamber and it comes out hot it's
very simple and there's nothing here
that oxidizes burns out it breaks down
it can run at medium and high voltages
which is better for scale compared to
electric heating Technologies and so
we've checked the major boxes that we
see as the limiters
and we've been scaling up so I was here
I think it was two years ago now we've
made some big progress uh we've gone now
our first multi-ton batches of these
bricks this year they're very similar
98% similar to existing bricks so we've
worked with existing Supply chains
existing manufacturers to produce these
now whether you want two tons or 2,000
tons we can make the E bricks to scale
up our Tech and they're very similar to
what's used in the glass industry as an
example as far as actually piloting the
system we've gone from a few hundred
Watts now to several tens of kilowatts
in our elevator size box on the right so
the left is what we used to do the right
is what we do now you can see me
standing in there with some colleagues
and we've done uh cylic heating we've
put out it's hard to see here but you
can see the faint glow of the hot gas
coming out the back we've done cylic
high temperature gas flows we've also
done uh Direct Metals melting in the
bottom right you'll see where we loaded
metal in and does direct radiative
heating for Metals um a customer wanted
to see this and so our elevator size box
here we've been running this for about a
year now and what comes next is our
megawatt scale system um and so we'll be
deploying that early next year customer
sites the year after and we're talking
to folks that want steam generation uh
calcination uh any number of uh furnaces
that we're looking to hook up to and
deep
conversations and ultimately we'll be
scaling to the hundreds of megawatts so
we go with first to kind of container
size systems and then we go to megawatt
scale systems so we can uh service the
entire industrial uh sector final quick
point on economics can this save you
money yes and we can say that because
electricity prices are getting negative
uh increasingly so as we deploy solar
and wind power near zero dollar
electricity and this is just over the
last five years in the US and I think
I'm out of time here so I'll jump to the
punchline that we can save you money is
a quick chart of just five sample
countries on the left of each of these
is our cost plus the cost of the jewel
Hive on the right is the natural gas
price and when we we run to these
different countries we can beat natural
gas prices now it's a widening envelope
of uh places where we can beat natural
gas because of these Trends so come talk
to me if you want to save money while
decarbonizing uh and reach out at uh
come to my booth or at these email
addresses and looking forward to
speaking thanks
[Applause]