my name is Terell Williams and I serve
as the associate director for diversity
equity and inclusion in the office of
admission here at M Sloan I also serve
as tonight's moderator for our panel um
I'm really excited about this
opportunity to host this uh panel um
that talks about the partners and
families of Sloan um one that I
definitely connect with as somebody who
traveled here with a significant other
and recently had a child um in the last
nine months so I'm going to check and
see if the in the chat to see if our
other panelists is here but I'll pass it
over to Amber and to kick us off all
right hi everybody um this is Amber and
Chris calling from Somerville
Massachusetts I'll start off and then
I'll hand it over to Chris so my name is
Amber I was the slony that uh brought us
out here to Massachusetts uh my parents
are immigrants from Peru I was born and
raised in California and prior to
graduate school I spent about five and a
half years in the social sector working
for a Statewide foundation in California
called the Latino Community Foundation
where I manage our Latino giving service
CC Network that's actually where Chris
and I met Chris was extremely involved
in volunteering with our organization
and we met um that way I around in 2020
was when I really got the itch to go
back to graduate school um I was really
looking
for an opportunity to go to really I
guess level up my professional toolkit
and provide and build a more data driven
approach to the work that I was doing um
and that's what ultimately brought me to
MIT for my MBA
and as TR mentioned um I'm actually also
the one that did the Dual degree program
so in my first semester at Sloan I
applied to the Dual degree program and I
did my MPA my masters in public
administration at the Harvard Kennedy
School um and so we've been here for
three years I um class of 23 for Mi MIT
Sloan and class of 24 for the Harvard
Kennedy School with my MPA I'm excited
to chat a little bit more about that for
folks that are interested um but yeah I
I loved my time at Sloan I was the class
president one of the class presidents of
and that's how much I loved it I wanted
to get back to the community and get as
involved as possible uh both working
with the student body and the faculty
and staff like trell so I'll pass it off
to Chris and I can answer my questions
later how's it going y'all Chris uh
Torres spouse uh first gentleman of
Sloan I guess for a short amount of time
um was very excited to come out to uh to
Boston for uh her program I think we
learned a ton uh excited to give you all
a little bit of the the so the
significant other experience um so if
anyone has questions or bring in
Partners uh we also recently just uh
welcomes our first uh first born into
the world so at 10 months old uh amber
also did the parent thing uh while
completing those crazy program so we can
talk a little bit about that um and then
a little bit about me I'm a product
manager at Google um so I was able to
move to the to the Boston office and
navigate the career transitions that
came with the location transfer and
everything else um but yeah looking
forward to the conversation tonight
awesome awesome so it looks like our
other panelists are not in the chat but
one thing we do well here at Sloan is
Pivot um so we can definitely have more
conversations so I can butt in as a
moderator and be able to kind of share
my experience as somebody on this staff
side that came here with a significant
other as well uh having a child within
the last year um so I do want to kick us
off with our first question um so uh
amber and Chris can you just kind of
talk about that uh thought process of
like ultimately going back to school and
what attracted you to Sloan's NBA
program yeah so I think for me I touched
on this a little bit in my in my intro
um I was hoping to I my background was
really in project management um
relationship part uh stakeholder
Partnerships and all of that and and
storytelling and what I kind of was
feeling at the end of my professional
experience with the foundation that I
was at was that I really wanted to bring
in um that more data different appro
data driven approach to my work and so
that's why the MIT Sloan MBA became very
attractive to me Char you can correct me
if I'm wrong but I believe our MBA is a
technical MBA um given the course
requirements that we have to take and I
think and that for me on one hand was
extremely scary because it was very
different from anything I had ever done
um but on the other hand that's exactly
the challenge that I wanted
uh on on a personal note you know having
been born and raised in California I did
travel a lot but um had never lived in
the east coast and so around the time
that I was applying for programs um
Chris and I get engaged were more
seriously thinking about our future um
and as we're planning out the next
couple of years in life I'm like this is
probably going to be the only time we
can live farther away from where our
families are and so that's that was
something else that attracted me to this
area and
I was interested in the Dual degree
program with with the Harvard Kennedy
School given my my previous professional
background and so the opportunity to do
that at these two amazing institutions
um for me was really attractive and
during my admit weekend I remember when
I was deciding across different programs
um I asked my M like the person who was
my facilitator the student I was like
okay so really like culture is important
to me like What's the culture like at
Sloan and he said you know well I think
that admissions team just does a really
good job of weeding out any and
I was like haha that's so funny um but
honestly being here on the campus I
think one of the things that I loved
about being at Sloan is like you have
such amazing individuals that have done
ridiculous things in their career um
really impressive things but folks that
you would meet are are genuinely really
humble um and everybody we have a saying
at Salone sonon is helping sonon and uh
that's something that you feel across
like from adamant weekend to your first
day on campus uh you genuinely feel
everybody's intent to support one
another uh and that for me is was really
important especially going back to
graduate school after being uh working
for so
long thank you for sharing that so Chris
I want to pass it over to you in terms
of like the significant other experience
so could you kind of shed some light on
like how does stone ensure that partners
and families from diverse backgrounds uh
feel included and supported as their
significant other is going through the
program uh I mean I can honestly say
like it's it's extremely welcoming um
even even more than than just any
expectations uh I think early on uh
after you know even through the whole
admit process I think we were in
sessions with other you know couples and
partners that were coming so we got a
little bit to know you know in advance
what it would be like but while we were
on campus um extremely welcoming I had
my own kind of partner ID Like official
MIT ID I got access to the libraries
Partners the gym the the partners can
access all of the clubs which to me felt
like I was getting a mini MBA because
like you know they had like what is the
crypto club and MIT doing at this time
you know you want to be on the on the
Forefront of some of the the biggest
topics out there and um you know if
you're if you get to go to some of these
talks and some of these meetings that
was huge uh I also joined the inter
mural Sports so I had uh you know join
the hockey team I have like my own Sloan
hockey jersey uh really proud of that
one um but super super inclusive uh I'm
a bit biased uh from what I like to say
is the other liberal arts school that's
that's down the way from MIT um you know
and having the the blessing of being of
her in both programs uh it's night and
day kind of the experience uh MIT
extremely open extremely collaborative
you the fact that I got access to
anything was uh was a blessing um I
think the other schools out there are
not as welcoming and and and to call out
names Harvard is is really not anywhere
near the level of openness that MIT is
so I was I was really uh
grateful thank you for sharing that uh
Kristen I have a quick followup that I
saw within the chat that I thought was
pretty relevant um you mentioned
something about uh your job um allowing
you to you know transfer locations um
somebody mentioned like they're a little
nervous about that because you so can
you kind of shed some light on like how
you navigated that process of you know
requesting that
transfer yeah um I I I can't say there's
uh really silver bullets there I think
there were a couple of Perfect Storm
items that that made it happen for us um
the fact that this was during covid
World was kind of shut down when she was
applying um you know everything went
remote you know for a hot second there
um I think that gave me an opening to be
able to move uh easily um I will say I
started conversation really early with
my manager um you know and I imagine
everyone's going through the application
process if everyone could pick M I'm
sure they would uh but you know at a
certain time we didn't know where we
could end up and so I was talking to my
manager we could end up in Boston we
could end up in you know any of these
cities in the US um I just tried to to
to get it out there early that I was
planning on moving I was planning on
kind of following Amber Where She Went
um and so I kept that kind of open
communication um Co helped out a little
bit in terms of making things a a bit
more fluid um but it did help that we
already had an office here I already had
some uh you know some of my cross
functional team stakeholders that were
in this office uh and I was able to make
that happen so um early communication
was was really big on that um a little
bit of opportunity in terms of what
other teams I was working with uh but I
was also prepared to to kind of make a
really big job switch within the company
so I was also looking at some roles uh
as it came down to to to shorter and
shorter uh School lists um to to make it
happen so glad Boston made it happen uh
but I I was prepared for a little bit
tougher conversations as well appreciate
that appreciate that so am I want to
pass it back over to you as it pertains
like the the curriculum of Sloan and the
curriculum of HKS kind of being able to
balance that but also being a
significant other can you get to talk
about the the core semester and like
that transition period for you as you're
transitioning back into school but
having a a significant other there with
you and like you know navigating that
process and maybe how you leaned on
Chris for support during that particular
time maybe outside of your cohort yeah
it was
rough I think um I really struggled my
first month and and and just learning
how to be a student again uh and again
coming from the social sector the
curriculum for me was completely
different because I just hadn't been
exposed to a lot of what for some people
were basic terms um it was like learning
a new a new language and then learning
the curriculum alongside that for me um
and but that's where I'm saying that
salon's helping salon's part was so
critical to my support I was very
transparent with my core team so that
group of like seven people that I was
paired up with about my initial
insecurities um and also my strengths
and I was like hey y'all this is what
I'm going to be really good at for our
team and this is what I'm definitely
really nervous about and I might
struggle with and I can tell you in in
the classes that I was more nervous
about like my court team members that
like they had professionally done like
statistics and data modeling they were
like oh here just sit next to me and
I'll explain everything to you while
we're while we're in class um or they
would sit after with all of us and they
would explain the model and what how
they built that and why it worked and so
that was extremely supportive in terms
of getting me the support that I needed
um within within that core that core
semester um as a core team we actually
we didn't do it super often we did it
twice I think where we met um the out of
the seven of us I think four had part
partners and three did not and so we
would have like these big dinners where
we would all come together and meet and
chat so that our partners felt like they
were a part of that also um and then on
a personal note I think once I did get
into my MBA curriculum and I into my NBA
program I knew that I was going to have
a very busy semester um in July before I
started I actually booked a trip for
Chris and I in Upstate New York like a
surprise a surprise trip I just put it
on our calendar like surprise trip it
was like the weekend of October 15th um
of my first year and I did that because
I said okay at that point I would have
been in school for two months and so I
want to make sure that I'm committing
like I have no idea what it's going to
be like Chris kept joking like you're
gonna ignore me and you're gonna you're
GNA be busy all the time with all your f
with all your new friends um but you
know I think for me it was also
important to try and create that that
one-on-one time with with each other to
make sure that we were we were involved
um but like Chris mentioned earlier I
think that the sloy community is so uh
um committed to just connect with one
another that they were very welcoming to
to him for most of the events that we
had that's great I know that that
balance is important as you're going
into a program making sure that you have
enough time for your your m home life
but also within the school life and kind
of balancing the social life here U one
thing that I share with um uh
prospective students that are you know
thinking about you know going to
business school may have a significant
other it's almost like a cheat code
going back to school with a another
person because you can explore together
um so I definitely like that aspect of
You Know Myself coming here with
somebody else and being able to kind of
explore the restaurants in the area or
being able to just kind of go to the
sporting events or being able to kind of
interact with other you know couples in
the area so I think that's pretty great
that people are considering it but just
know that there's a community here
that's pretty large for significant
others um and kind of tying into that
like the social life um so outside of
the class like you know was that hard to
manage like the partner in family life
with academics and network and I know
you just kind of touched on it you said
you know having a surprise trip but were
there other examples that you can
particularly highlight that you know
being the Senate co-president that
probably was you know a lot of time on
your hands to kind of balance that but
also being a a partner like like how was
the social life aspect uh for you and
Chris while you were in the
program yeah let me start touch I'll
touch on the the Salone presidency
because that was a lot um so I think um
as as one does when you run for office
you have to discuss with your family
and so I actually did talk about it with
Chris um beforehand more so because I
was torn between two possible
positions um but I think for me it was
important for me to to chat with Chris
about
like um what this opportunity could mean
for me what it would bring knowing that
it would take time away not just from
him but also from the other commitments
that I had made for myself during my
graduate degree program um so I think
that was that was was really critical I
think also
um but it also gave way for for new
opportunities in terms of like just new
involvements new new access to different
to just different
opportunities uh different kinds of
events and that for me was was equally
as important I I always for me like my
SL Sloan president experience was like
having a mini internship of like
executive Management in a really awesome
awesome way um and I got to work really
closely with my with my co-president who
had a very different professional
background than I did and approached
problems very differently than I did
which which also was helpful um so yeah
anything you want to add yeah I mean I
think honestly the the so experience for
me was was purely social I think like in
many ways I I got to join uh a lot of
really interesting clubs but it's not
like I could leave work at 1M for a lot
of the interesting conversations because
they usually happen like during school
hours um that said you know like I
joined the Hispanic Business Club um a
lot of that was you know networking
social and connecting um I would say the
social calendar uh for an MBA program
not only M but definitely MIT it is
packed uh if there are social things you
want to do it is constant it is every
day you can you can go to as many things
as you want um and so I think from that
perspective for us it was really a pict
pick or choose uh you know for her it
was like oh we can go to this talk this
talk uh you know this happy hour uh this
company's coming in and and you know
hosting so and so um you know and so for
me personally I I mean we were kind of
strong enough I was like if you want to
go go ahead and vice versa and vice
versa like Chris went to a lot of things
that I didn't I went to that she didn't
go to I think a big part of it is
literally we did not say yes to
everything yeah so it that that's what I
was going to say was like at a certain
point I was like I'm I'm tapped Out
actually you you can go ahead and go uh
this is a little bit easier preit of
course um but uh but yeah like I say
that to say like there is a lot going on
and um I think like you know the MIT
motto is like drinking from a fire hose
there is more than enough coming at you
whether it's academics or you know just
the social aspect of it um that you can
pick uh you know you can pick and choose
and I think you should probably start
setting boundaries yeah but I was really
big like for me coming to Boston I also
you know we came together it's not like
we came with a built-in friend group or
Social Circle yeah um so I do want to
turn back to like the core group that
first semester uh it was huge like we
had like a you know a small set of
people who she was in every class with
uh also had Partners um you know we had
those kind of dinners and so we had like
a a good little small social group that
expanded um and that kind of became my
social group so even as I was in a new
city um you you know I also had kind of
events to go to if I wanted to I
definitely started saying no more and
more but um but yeah there's a lot to it
and I think we just you know we had to
find our balance of what were the things
that we that interested us some yeah
like she said some of those things I
went to and she didn't even as a partner
so um like I said really really
welcoming for um for the partners even
in a way that I did not expect so yeah
and just quickly on the balance I think
the other thing too as a student is so
much of the time like even though you're
socializing a lot of these folks are
also balancing the same school work that
you are and so you all are there to kind
of back each other up and support each
other in the in between spaces and
there's a lot of like working on campus
that happens like getting together right
after class that provides space to to do
that work collaboratively and then also
um have more free time later awesome
awesome so I see some questions in the
chat it kind of you know focusing on on
those who are parents and I know we
mentioned earlier that you finished the
last was it last semester at HKS um and
you had just given birth yeah so I can
walk through that timeline a little bit
so I was I was pregnant my last semester
at Sloan so like my key semester as
president I was pregnant but I had an
announced and I graduated Sloan nobody
knew but I was pregnant and my son my
son walked with me um I gave birth in
November of
2023 so that was my La that was my um
ball semester of my last year at the
Harvard Kennedy School um so I gave
birth about two and a half weeks before
the end of the
semester um and then here in the
Cambridge area you don't have CL most
people don't have classes on during the
month of January um December's basically
holiday break also and so uh or winter
break and so I um had all of
December most of January off um so two
months off and then I went back to to to
to classes and finished out at HKS and
to to kind of bring it what kind of gave
us an idea and implanted a seed is her
uh one of her Court team members uh uh
Bruce he uh they they specifically tried
to time their pregnancy around this
period uh and they knew that going into
fall semester they were like into going
into fall semester they already knew
that they were going to try to um you
know try to to to to start getting
pregnant so that the baby came during
that time and at that time we were
thinking about it we were like like you
know if your families and you guys are
trying to plan out uh plan out the baby
timelines like it's always tough when's
the right time you know what are the
right factors you know what should we
consider and that was a really big part
for us was like do we wait till after
she graduates do we wait till after she
graduates plus a year and you has like
cemented herself and work a bit um but I
do think you know we had the we had one
of her Court teammate somebody super
close who was like no no no they they
had a baby already during that timeline
and so we also got to to see a bit of
their experience and to be honest I
think it gave us a little bit more of a
confidence to be able to do it ourselves
so yeah that that being said in that
case the student was the father and not
the one who actually G like had to go
through the child birthing process yeah
um I do feel like for me it worked out
because um while I don't necessarily
think two months I was ready to bounce
back it was a slow enough transition for
me that I was able to manage the units
that I had left left with having a
newborn at home um we also had our moms
that were supporting us and so all of
that
was made all of that possible in a way
that was sustainable for me a lot of
help yeah a lot of help we had a lot of
help and then when people offered were
like yes thank you
please so that was also a big part of it
and when you all were going through that
that pregnancy Journey um did you all um
take advantage of any of the resources
that MIT had to offer as it pertains to
maybe like child birth class
or just like prep to get
ready I feel like my first trimester was
a blur because it was so busy with
wrapping up um and so we didn't do any
resources at Sloan I also again had not
sh that I was pregnant so I didn't even
look to see what resources there were um
but I will say this area is fantastic um
it's a fantastic parent
Community um I did use some resources at
the Kennedy School which is where I was
like I had already you know I already
had the baby and so I used like the
nursing rooms um I used some of the
parent support systems that were there
but honestly the best system has
actually been it's called the
camberville um there a camberville
Facebook group and so there's a
camberville parents and a camberville
mom so it's Cambridge Somerville we live
in the Somerville area met for like all
basically the Boston area um and it's a
a group a Facebook group that you can
join based on your child's uh bir
there's a they have different birthing
ranges and you can ask any types of
questions we're actually about to find
our Nanny through that Avenue um I think
you also had a ton of friends who had
babies you had Bruce in them who had
babies oh I did so we as we asked a lot
of questions from current students who
already had children like one of my best
friends Stephanie has came with a
three-year-old and was pregnant her last
semester it wasn't abnormal to have a
baby and I think like that was that was
one of the bigger pieces that MIT
brought was like there were already
families around
there were groups um that organized
around parents there were like group
chats that organized around parents
organized events kids yeah like she has
a mom group specifically with other
slones you know a WhatsApp group um and
so I I think a really big part of it was
like we we had Community who were in it
together um yeah I I think we were too a
little too late for the MIT specific
resources but the community itself it
was there yeah I do want to add about
the um the the courses that MIT does
have to offer because I did take
advantage of them uh when me and my wife
were expecting so MIT does offer like um
like classes for new and expecting
parents um so we did like a six week
like prep course on like child birth
like the whole process of like
understanding what that's like so we had
a lot of MIT like students as well as
staff within the room we kind of going
through the process together and um that
was pretty cool to kind of like relieve
some of that anxiety of like okay what's
going to be like within child birth but
also that resource was great and it was
actually free for for us to do that so
um I definitely appreciated that and
also MIT did have like some virtual
classes to that you can attend if you
didn't want to be in person because of
where where you were within that
particular process so they did have some
virtual classes that pertained to like
breastfeeding and there was another
class that talks about um like there was
like four stages of like a fussy baby um
so I really like that um so that was
helpful in terms of like preparing and
then like you mentioned like trying to
time it um so my my my daughter was
actually born in December so right
before the beginning of the new year so
we were transitioning to like IP for
students so we didn't have much going on
as pertains to like student programming
so that was kind of Ideal for me to kind
of like have a month off and then U my
wife was actually able to kind of have
an extended period off with paternity
leave so Massachusetts um was you know
phenomenal I really am grateful we chose
to move here because they are very
Progressive as it pertains to maternity
leave and you know making sure that
there's also a uh paternity for for for
for those who are the non- birthing
parents as well um so in that particular
process for um I guess transitioning
with the baby um did you all know of any
resources like for on campus housing for
those who are coming in with with
children um or Those Who coming in with
significant other I know MIT does offer
housing but are you all familiar with
those particular
resources um well CHR was just saying my
my core team member Bruce he came with a
um one and a half-year-old and then they
had their child in January of our first
year and they lived in student campus
housing uh which uh so while we didn't
use it ourselves like I know that they
they used that they loved it because it
was close to a playground it was close
to campus um and that made it really
really easy for them but we don't know
much more beyond
that there was Community around that
also like cuz that's where most of the
families were and so I think that was
you know there was proximity in in the
family that we're we're going through
the similar things yeah but I will say
because I this question earlier because
somebody was worried about affordability
coming I think they were coming with two
kids and two dogs um where we live right
now
Somerville um I would say there's a lot
more space here like we have a small
backyard um we have enough space for the
three of us um and I think in this area
it gets a little bit more affordable and
a little bit bigger and so our friends
that wanted a little bit more space Bas
did come out to Somerville it's it's
about 20 to 25 minutes door too taking
the taking public transit it's even
faster if you're bold and ride your bike
like does I'm a scaredy-cat so I don't
do that but he loves riding his bike and
he gets there quick
faster um and
so yeah there's there's definitely if
you're if you're willing to go a little
bit further it get it does get a little
bit more affordable out here in this
area yeah that contested that so with
the um the public transit so being able
to kind of be on that red line will be
uh beneficial because that gets you
right to MIT slan um so if you're within
the the Kindle square area Central area
or even close to the Harvard Square um
those are some good locations for people
that have that children or you know
looking to have a shorter commute versus
living in the city which could be a
little uh uh challenging uh given the
traffic situation here in the Boston
area so um try to find something within
I guess the the respective bubble of MIT
Sloan there actually housing resources
on our um our website that gives more
students like opportunities to kind of
research where areas are a little bit
popular some of Ville is pretty popular
and then there's also some areas um in
the um Central Square area that are
pretty popular for students as well and
as Boston is a uh not a college town but
there are several uh higher in higher
education institutions here a lot of
students are moving out annually so
there's a lot of spaces that open up for
students to be able to kind of fill
those particular voids so there's always
um something available just depends on
like how close you want to be or how far
you want to be in that particular uh
time frame um I know we're getting
closer to time but I do want to kind of
uh pivot our conversation to more of the
application process um so for those
students that are you know applying or
considering applying to to graduate
school in general um could you all Just
sh kind of share any advice for a
perspective applicant as they're going
through this
process uh ask as many people for
support um I'm the first one in my
friend group to get an MBA I'm a first
generation student um no one of my
family had gotten an MBA before um and
for um first generation folks that are
from underrepresented backgrounds here
in the United States you might have
heard of programs like the Consortium
fellowship or um MLT I unfortunately was
not a part of either of those as it
relates to Sloan um but I know that
those can be very helpful I always say
Chris was my
MLT um because he actually helped
project manage my application process um
he and I'm it's where he's laughing but
it's true like he created the
spreadsheet for me um he helped me set
out deadlines for like when I needed to
submit my application to um one of my
former colleagues used to used to work
within um Stanford Admissions and so uh
she helped he helped me get stuff to all
the people that were willing to support
me in my process um on time and just do
everything on time and make sure that I
was getting everything uh out there as
quickly as possible so I think for me
the biggest piece of advice is use use
your support system as much as possible
ask folks for help I think especially
when it comes to your admissions essays
it be it can it can really easily start
to become really repetitive or you're
looking at it and you're like nothing is
wrong or like I don't know what else to
fix um so just asking pairs of fresh
eyes to look it over to support you I
think I think is extremely critical um
because it is this tunnel vision that
you kind of start getting into
especially as as the deadline start
approaching and I do want to add that
for those of you who are applying with
your significant other there are
different indicators on our application
as well where you can indicate their
name so their name in which round they
plan to apply as well um there was a
question in the chat about what what how
what percentage of students are coming
to our program with significant others
um that numbers around about 33% of our
students within our NBA program the
stone fellows program is a little higher
because those are student those are
individuals who have a little bit more
work years of work experience um and
they're you know uh about 15 years in
their career so they're coming in with
multiple children um so that number is
slightly higher so we do have a a strong
community of those who are applying with
their significant other as well as
coming in with um a significant other so
in the application like I mentioned you
can indicate if your significant other
is applying as well as which round
they're applying we'll do our best to
review you both on an individual Merit
but we'll have that you know context of
that there's two people applying with
this within this particular household so
just kind of keep that in mind as you're
going through the process um for some
odd reason most uh significant others
don't apply the same R um so um some may
apply round one and then the other one
gets the courage to apply maybe round
two or round three um so that does
happen so just let us know that on your
particular application so we are aware
that there is a significant other that
is applying also if you don't know at
the time that you submit your
application as your significant other is
applying and you ultimately get that
letter of admission you can let us know
at a later point if your significant
other does choose to apply and we can
add that that note to your particular
record as well